<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv cell-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.504668+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444558</id><title>Polarized Dishevelled dissolution and condensation drives embryonic axis specification in oocytes (198 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.505418+00:00</updated><author><name>S. Zachary Swartz</name></author><author><name>Tzer Han Tan</name></author><author><name>Margherita Perillo</name></author><author><name>Nikta Fakhri</name></author><author><name>Gary M. Wessel</name></author><author><name>Athula H. Wikramanayake</name></author><author><name>Iain M. Cheeseman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The organismal body axes that are formed during embryogenesis are intimately linked to intrinsic asymmetries established at the cellular scale in oocytes [1]. Here, we report an axis-defining event in meiotic oocytes of the sea star &lt;italic&gt;Patiria miniata&lt;/italic&gt;. Dishevelled is a cytoplasmic Wnt pathway effector required for axis development in diverse species [2-4], but the mechanisms governing its function and distribution remain poorly defined. Using time-lapse imaging, we find that Dishevelled localizes uniformly to puncta throughout the cell cortex in Prophase I-arrested oocytes, but becomes enriched at the vegetal pole following meiotic resumption through a dissolution-condensation mechanism. This process is driven by an initial disassembly phase of Dvl puncta, followed by selective reformation of Dvl assemblies at the vegetal pole. Rather than being driven by Wnt signaling, this localization behavior is coupled to meiotic cell cycle progression and influenced by Lamp1+ endosome association and Frizzled receptors pre-localized within the oocyte cortex. Our results reveal a cell cycle-linked mechanism by which maternal cellular polarity is transduced to the embryo through spatially-regulated Dishevelled dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444558" rel="alternate" title="Polarized Dishevelled dissolution and condensation drives embryonic axis specification in oocytes (198 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.445000</id><title>Functional dissection of human mitotic proteins using CRISPR-Cas9 tiling screens (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.506095+00:00</updated><author><name>Jacob A. Herman</name></author><author><name>Lucas Carter</name></author><author><name>Sonali Arora</name></author><author><name>Jun Zhu</name></author><author><name>Sue Biggins</name></author><author><name>Patrick J. Paddison</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Kinetochores are large protein assemblies that mark the centromere and bind to mitotic spindle microtubules to ensure accurate chromosome segregation. Like most protein-coding genes, the full multifunctional nature of kinetochore factors remains uncharacterized due to the limited experimental tools for unbiased dissection of human protein sequences. Here, we develop a method that leverages CRISPR-Cas9 induced mutations to comprehensively identify key functional regions within protein sequences that are required for cellular outgrowth. Our analysis of 48 human kinetochore genes revealed hundreds of regions required for cell proliferation, corresponding to known and uncharacterized protein domains. We biologically validated 15 of these regions, including amino acids 387-402 of Mad1, which when deleted compromise Mad1 kinetochore localization and chromosome segregation fidelity. Altogether, we demonstrate that CRISPR-Cas9-based tiling mutagenesis enables &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; identification of key functional domains in protein-coding genes, which elucidates separation of function mutants and allows functional annotation across the human proteome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.445000" rel="alternate" title="Functional dissection of human mitotic proteins using CRISPR-Cas9 tiling screens (19 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444797</id><title>Systematic Tuning of Rhodamine Spirocyclization for Super-Resolution Microscopy (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.506432+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicolas Lardon</name></author><author><name>Lu Wang</name></author><author><name>Aline Tschanz</name></author><author><name>Philipp Hoess</name></author><author><name>Mai Tran</name></author><author><name>Elisa D’Este</name></author><author><name>Jonas Ries</name></author><author><name>Kai Johnsson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Rhodamines are the most important class of fluorophores for applications in live-cell fluorescence microscopy. This is mainly because rhodamines exist in a dynamic equilibrium between a fluorescent zwitterion and a non-fluorescent but cell-permeable spirocyclic form. Different imaging applications require different positions of this dynamic equilibrium, which poses a challenge for the design of suitable probes. We describe here how the conversion of the &lt;italic&gt;ortho&lt;/italic&gt;-carboxy moiety of a given rhodamine into substituted acyl benzenesulfonamides and alkylamides permits the systematic tuning of the equilibrium of spirocyclization with unprecedented accuracy and over a large range. This allows to transform the same rhodamine into either a highly fluorogenic and cell-permeable probe for live-cell stimulated emission depletion (STED) microscopy, or into a spontaneously blinking dye for single molecule localization microscopy (SMLM). We used this approach to generate differently colored probes optimized for different labeling systems and imaging applications.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444797" rel="alternate" title="Systematic Tuning of Rhodamine Spirocyclization for Super-Resolution Microscopy (18 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444917</id><title>V-ATPase is a universal regulator of LC3 associated phagocytosis and non-canonical autophagy (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.506676+00:00</updated><author><name>Kirsty M. Hooper</name></author><author><name>Elise Jacquin</name></author><author><name>Taoyingnan Li</name></author><author><name>Jonathan M. Goodwin</name></author><author><name>John H. Brumell</name></author><author><name>Joanne Durgan</name></author><author><name>Oliver Florey</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Non-canonical autophagy is a key cellular pathway in immunity, cancer and neurodegeneration, characterised by &lt;underline&gt;C&lt;/underline&gt;onjugation of &lt;underline&gt;A&lt;/underline&gt;TG8 to endolysosomal &lt;underline&gt;S&lt;/underline&gt;ingle-&lt;underline&gt;M&lt;/underline&gt;embranes (CASM). CASM is activated by engulfment (endocytosis, phagocytosis), agonists (STING, TRPML1) and infection (influenza), dependent on the ATG16L1 WD40-domain, and specifically K490. However, the factor(s) associated with non-canonical ATG16L1 recruitment, and CASM induction, remain unknown. Here, we investigate a role for V-ATPase during non-canonical autophagy. We report that increased V0-V1 engagement is associated with, and sufficient for, CASM activation. Upon V0-V1 binding, V-ATPase directly recruits ATG16L1, via K490, during LC3-associated phagocytosis (LAP), STING- and drug-induced CASM, indicating a common mechanism. Furthermore, during LAP, key molecular players, including NADPH oxidase/ROS, converge on V-ATPase. Finally, we show that LAP is sensitive to &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; SopF, which disrupts the V-ATPase-ATG16L1 axis, and provide evidence that CASM contributes to the &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; host response. Together, these data identify V-ATPase as a universal regulator of CASM, and indicate that SopF evolved in part to evade non-canonical autophagy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444917" rel="alternate" title="V-ATPase is a universal regulator of LC3 associated phagocytosis and non-canonical autophagy (13 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.18.444637</id><title>A Drosophila Toolkit for Imaging of HA-tagged Proteins Unveiled a Block in Autophagy Flux in the Last Instar Larval Fat Body (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.506903+00:00</updated><author><name>Tadayoshi Murakawa</name></author><author><name>Tsuyoshi Nakamura</name></author><author><name>Kohei Kawaguchi</name></author><author><name>Futoshi Murayama</name></author><author><name>Zhao Ning</name></author><author><name>Timothy J Stasevich</name></author><author><name>Hiroshi Kimura</name></author><author><name>Naonobu Fujita</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;For &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; functional analysis of a protein of interest (POI), multiple transgenic strains with POI harboring different tags are needed but generation of these strains is still labor-intensive work. To overcome this, we developed a versatile Drosophila toolkit with a genetically encoded single-chain variable fragment for the HA epitope tag: “HA Frankenbody”. This system allows various analyses of HA-tagged POI in live tissues by simply crossing an HA Frankenbody fly with an HA-tagged POI fly. Strikingly, the GFP-mCherry tandem fluorescent-tagged HA Frankenbody revealed a block in autophagic flux and an accumulation of enlarged autolysosomes in the last instar larval and prepupal fat body. Autophagy was dispensable for the swelling of lysosomes, indicating that lysosomal activity is downregulated at this stage. Furthermore, forced activation of lysosomes by fat body-targeted overexpression of Mitf, the single MiTF/TFE family gene in Drosophila, suppressed the lysosomal swelling and resulted in pupal lethality. Collectively, we propose that downregulated lysosomal function in the fat body plays a role in the metamorphosis of Drosophila.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.18.444637" rel="alternate" title="A Drosophila Toolkit for Imaging of HA-tagged Proteins Unveiled a Block in Autophagy Flux in the Last Instar Larval Fat Body (7 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>