<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv cell-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.610433+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443921</id><title>Live-Cell Imaging of (p)ppGpp with RNA-based Fluorescent Sensors (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.610665+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhining Sun</name></author><author><name>Rigumula Wu</name></author><author><name>Bin Zhao</name></author><author><name>Rilee Zeinert</name></author><author><name>Peter Chien</name></author><author><name>Mingxu You</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Guanosine tetra- and pentaphosphate, (p)ppGpp, are important alarmone nucleotides that regulate bacterial survival in stressful environment. A direct detection of (p)ppGpp in living cells is critical for our understanding of the mechanism of bacterial stringent response. However, it is still challenging to directly image and measure cellular (p)ppGpp. Here, we report a type of RNA-based fluorescent sensors for live-cell imaging of (p)ppGpp. Our sensor is engineered by conjugating a recently identified (p)ppGpp-specific riboswitch with a fluorogenic RNA aptamer, Broccoli. These sensors can be genetically encoded and enable direct monitoring of cellular (p)ppGpp accumulation. Unprecedented information on cell-to-cell variation and cellular dynamics of (p)ppGpp levels can now be obtained under different nutritional conditions. We predict that these RNA-based sensors will be broadly adapted to study bacterial stringent response.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443921" rel="alternate" title="Live-Cell Imaging of (p)ppGpp with RNA-based Fluorescent Sensors (22 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443932</id><title>A Method for Rapid Flow-cytometric Isolation of Endothelial Nuclei and RNA from Archived Frozen Brain Tissue (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.610848+00:00</updated><author><name>Amy L. Kimble</name></author><author><name>Jordan Silva</name></author><author><name>Melissa Murphy</name></author><author><name>Jessica A. Hensel</name></author><author><name>Sarah-Anne E. Nicholas</name></author><author><name>Evan R. Jellison</name></author><author><name>Bo Reese</name></author><author><name>Patrick A. Murphy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Endothelial cells are important contributors to brain development, physiology, and disease. Although RNA sequencing has contributed to the understanding of brain endothelial cell diversity, bulk analysis and single-cell approaches have relied on fresh tissue digestion protocols for the isolation of single endothelial cells and flow cytometry-based sorting on surface markers or transgene expression. These approaches are limited in the analysis of the endothelium in human brain tissues, where fresh samples are difficult to obtain. Here, we developed an approach to examine endothelial RNA expression by using an endothelial-specific marker to isolate nuclei from abundant archived frozen brain tissues. We show that this approach rapidly and reliably extracts endothelial nuclei from frozen mouse brain samples, and importantly, from archived frozen human brain tissues. Furthermore, isolated RNA transcript levels are closely correlated with expression in whole cells from tissue digestion protocols and are enriched in endothelial markers and depleted of markers of other brain cell types. As high-quality RNA transcripts could be obtained from as few as 100 nuclei in archived frozen human brain tissues, we predict that this approach should be useful for both bulk analysis of endothelial RNA transcripts in human brain tissues as well as single-cell analysis of endothelial sub-populations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443932" rel="alternate" title="A Method for Rapid Flow-cytometric Isolation of Endothelial Nuclei and RNA from Archived Frozen Brain Tissue (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443558</id><title>Elongation factor ELOF1 drives transcription-coupled repair and prevents genome instability (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.611023+00:00</updated><author><name>Marit E Geijer</name></author><author><name>Di Zhou</name></author><author><name>Kathiresan Selvam</name></author><author><name>Barbara Steurer</name></author><author><name>Bastiaan Evers</name></author><author><name>Chirantani Mukherjee</name></author><author><name>Simona Cugusi</name></author><author><name>Marvin van Toorn</name></author><author><name>Melanie van der Woude</name></author><author><name>Wenzhi Gong</name></author><author><name>Roel Janssens</name></author><author><name>Anja Raams</name></author><author><name>Joyce HG Lebbink</name></author><author><name>Bart Geverts</name></author><author><name>Dalton A Plummer</name></author><author><name>Karel Bezstarosti</name></author><author><name>Arjan F Theil</name></author><author><name>Richard Mitter</name></author><author><name>Adriaan B Houtsmuller</name></author><author><name>Wim Vermeulen</name></author><author><name>Jeroen AA Demmers</name></author><author><name>Shisheng Li</name></author><author><name>Hannes Lans</name></author><author><name>René Bernards</name></author><author><name>Jesper Q Svejstrup</name></author><author><name>Arnab Ray Chaudhuri</name></author><author><name>John J Wyrick</name></author><author><name>Jurgen A Marteijn</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Correct transcription is crucial for life. However, DNA damage severely impedes elongating RNA Polymerase II (Pol II), causing transcription inhibition and transcription-replication conflicts. Cells are equipped with intricate mechanisms to counteract the severe consequence of these transcription-blocking lesions (TBLs). However, the exact mechanism and factors involved remain largely unknown. Here, using a genome-wide CRISPR/cas9 screen, we identified elongation factor ELOF1 as an important new factor in the transcription stress response upon DNA damage. We show that ELOF1 has an evolutionary conserved role in Transcription-Coupled Nucleotide Excision Repair (TC-NER), where it promotes recruitment of the TC-NER factors UVSSA and TFIIH to efficiently repair TBLs and resume transcription. Additionally, ELOF1 modulates transcription to protect cells from transcription-mediated replication stress, thereby preserving genome stability. Thus, ELOF1 protects the transcription machinery from DNA damage by two distinct mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443558" rel="alternate" title="Elongation factor ELOF1 drives transcription-coupled repair and prevents genome instability (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443597</id><title>The Drosophila orthologue of the primary ciliary dyskinesia-associated gene, DNAAF3, is required for axonemal dynein assembly (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.611307+00:00</updated><author><name>Petra zur Lage</name></author><author><name>Zhiyan Xi</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Lennon</name></author><author><name>Iain Hunter</name></author><author><name>Wai Kit Chan</name></author><author><name>Alfonso Bolado Carrancio</name></author><author><name>Alex von Kriegsheim</name></author><author><name>Andrew P. Jarman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ciliary motility is powered by a suite of highly conserved axoneme-specific dynein motor complexes. In humans the impairment of these motors through mutation results in the disease, Primary Ciliary Dyskinesia (PCD). Studies in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; have helped to validate several PCD genes whose products are required for cytoplasmic pre-assembly of axonemal dynein motors. Here we report the characterisation of the &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; homologue of the less known assembly factor, &lt;italic&gt;DNAAF3&lt;/italic&gt;. This gene, &lt;italic&gt;CG17669&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Dnaaf3&lt;/italic&gt;), is expressed exclusively in developing mechanosensory chordotonal (Ch) neurons and spermatocytes, the only two &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; cell types bearing motile cilia/flagella. Mutation of &lt;italic&gt;Dnaaf3&lt;/italic&gt; results in larvae that are deaf and adults that are uncoordinated, indicating defective Ch neuron function. The mutant Ch neuron cilia of the antenna specifically lack dynein arms, while Ca imaging in larvae reveals a complete loss of Ch neuron response to vibration stimulus, confirming that mechanotransduction relies on ciliary dynein motors. Mutant males are infertile with immotile sperm whose flagella lack dynein arms and show axoneme disruption. Analysis of proteomic changes suggest a reduction in heavy chains of all axonemal dynein forms, consistent with an impairment of dynein pre-assembly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SUMMARY STATEMENT&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;DNAAF3 function as a dynein assembly factor for motile cilia is conserved in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443597" rel="alternate" title="The Drosophila orthologue of the primary ciliary dyskinesia-associated gene, DNAAF3, is required for axonemal dynein assembly (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443861</id><title>Dynein light chain-dependent dimerization of Egalitarian is essential for maintaining oocyte fate in Drosophila (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.611481+00:00</updated><author><name>Hannah Neiswender</name></author><author><name>Chandler H. Goldman</name></author><author><name>Rajalakshmi Veeranan-Karmegam</name></author><author><name>Graydon B. Gonsalvez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Egalitarian (Egl) is an RNA adaptor for the Dynein motor and is thought to link numerous, perhaps hundreds, of mRNAs with Dynein. Dynein, in turn, is responsible for the transport and localization of these mRNAs. Studies have shown that efficient mRNA binding by Egl requires the protein to dimerize. We recently demonstrated that Dynein light chain (Dlc) is responsible for facilitating the dimerization of Egl. Mutations in Egl that fail to interact with Dlc do not dimerize, and as such, are defective for mRNA binding. Consequently, this mutant does not efficiently associate with BicaudalD (BicD), the factor responsible for linking the Egl/mRNA complex with Dynein. In this report, we tested whether artificially dimerizing this Dlc-binding mutant using a leucine zipper would restore mRNA binding and rescue mutant phenotypes in vivo. Interestingly, we found that although artificial dimerization of Egl restored BicD binding, it only partially restored mRNA binding. As a result, Egl-dependent phenotypes, such as oocyte specification and mRNA localization, were only partially rescued. We hypothesize that Dlc-mediated dimerization of Egl results in a three-dimensional conformation of the Egl dimer that is best suited for mRNA binding. Although the leucine zipper restores Egl dimerization, it likely does not enable Egl to assemble into the conformation required for maximal mRNA binding activity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443861" rel="alternate" title="Dynein light chain-dependent dimerization of Egalitarian is essential for maintaining oocyte fate in Drosophila (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443936</id><title>A Trio of Ubiquitin Ligases Sequentially Drive Ubiquitylation and Autophagic Degradation of Dysfunctional Yeast Proteasomes (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.611629+00:00</updated><author><name>Richard S. Marshall</name></author><author><name>Richard D. Vierstra</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;As central effectors of ubiquitin (Ub)-mediated proteolysis, proteasomes are regulated at multiple levels, including degradation of unwanted or dysfunctional particles via autophagy (termed proteaphagy). In yeast, inactive proteasomes are exported from the nucleus, sequestered into cytoplasmic aggresomes via the Hsp42 chaperone, extensively ubiquitylated, and then tethered to the expanding phagophore by the autophagy receptor Cue5. Here, we demonstrate the need for ubiquitylation driven by the trio of Ub ligases (E3s) San1, Rsp5 and Hul5, which, together with their corresponding E2s, work sequentially to promote nuclear export and Cue5 recognition. Whereas San1 functions prior to nuclear export, Rsp5 and Hul5 likely decorate aggresome-localized proteasomes in concert. Ultimately, topologically complex Ub chain(s) containing both K48 and K63 Ub-Ub linkages are assembled, mainly on the regulatory particle, to generate autophagy-competent substrates. As San1, Rsp5, Hul5, Hsp42, and Cue5 also participate in general proteostasis, proteaphagy likely engages an essential mechanism for eliminating inactive/misfolded proteins.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;HIGHLIGHTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ubiquitylation is essential for the autophagic turnover of dysfunctional proteasomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The San1, Rsp5 and Hul5 E3s act sequentially to drive proteaphagy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The E2s Ubc1, Ubc4 and Ubc5 are collectively required.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both K48- and K63-mediated Ub-Ub linkages are assembled for efficient proteaphagy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443936" rel="alternate" title="A Trio of Ubiquitin Ligases Sequentially Drive Ubiquitylation and Autophagic Degradation of Dysfunctional Yeast Proteasomes (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>