<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv cell-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.955849+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.22.449254</id><title>RNA at the surface of phase-separated condensates impacts their size and number (34 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.956241+00:00</updated><author><name>Audrey Cochard</name></author><author><name>Marina Garcia-Jove Navarro</name></author><author><name>Shunnichi Kashida</name></author><author><name>Michel Kress</name></author><author><name>Dominique Weil</name></author><author><name>Zoher Gueroui</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Membrane-less organelles, by localizing and regulating complex biochemical reactions, are ubiquitous functional subunits of intracellular organization. They include a variety of nuclear and cytoplasmic ribonucleoprotein (RNP) condensates, such as nucleoli, P-bodies, germ granules and stress granules. While is it now recognized that specific RNA and protein families are critical for the biogenesis of RNP condensates, how these molecular constituents determine condensate size and morphology is unknown. To circumvent the biochemical complexity of endogenous RNP condensates, the use of programmable tools to reconstitute condensate formation with minimal constituents can be instrumental. Here we report a methodology to form RNA-containing condensates in living cells with controlled RNA and protein composition. Our bioengineered condensates are made of ArtiGranule scaffolds undergoing liquid-liquid phase separation in cells and programmed to specifically recruit a unique RNA species. We found that RNAs localized on condensate surface, either as isolated RNA molecules or as a homogenous corona of RNA molecules around the condensate. This simplified system allowed us to demonstrate that the size of the condensates scales with RNA surface density, the higher the RNA density is, the smaller and more frequent the condensates are. Our observations suggest a mechanism based on physical constraints, provided by RNAs localized on condensate surface, that limit condensate growth and coalescence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.22.449254" rel="alternate" title="RNA at the surface of phase-separated condensates impacts their size and number (34 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.23.449608</id><title>A rare natural lipid induces neuroglobin expression to prevent amyloid oligomers toxicity and retinal neurodegeneration (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.956797+00:00</updated><author><name>Henry Patrick Oamen</name></author><author><name>Nathaly Romero Romero</name></author><author><name>Philip Knuckles</name></author><author><name>Juha Saarikangas</name></author><author><name>Yuhong Dong</name></author><author><name>Fabrice Caudron</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Most neurodegenerative diseases such as Alzheimer’s disease are proteinopathies linked to the toxicity of amyloid oligomers. Treatments to delay or cure these diseases are lacking. Using budding yeast, we report that the natural lipid tripentadecanoin induces expression of the nitric oxide oxidoreductase Yhb1 to prevent the formation of protein aggregates during aging and extends replicative lifespan. In mammals, tripentadecanoin induces expression of the Yhb1 orthologue, neuroglobin, to protect neurons against amyloid toxicity. Tripentadecanoin also rescues photoreceptors in a mouse model of retinal degeneration and retinal ganglion cells in a Rhesus monkey model of optic atrophy. Together, we propose that tripentadecanoin affects p-bodies to induce neuroglobin expression and offers a potential treatment for proteinopathies and retinal neurodegeneration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The natural lipid tripentadecanoin is cytoprotective against amyloid oligomer toxicity and retinal neurodegeneration by inducing YHBI/neuroglobin expression in yeast and mammals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.23.449608" rel="alternate" title="A rare natural lipid induces neuroglobin expression to prevent amyloid oligomers toxicity and retinal neurodegeneration (9 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-06-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.22.449474</id><title>PI(4,5)P2 controls slit diaphragm formation and endocytosis in Drosophila nephrocytes (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.957345+00:00</updated><author><name>Maximilian Gass</name></author><author><name>Sarah Borkowsky</name></author><author><name>Marie-Luise Lotz</name></author><author><name>Rita Schröter</name></author><author><name>Pavel Nedvetsky</name></author><author><name>Stefan Luschnig</name></author><author><name>Astrid Rohlmann</name></author><author><name>Markus Missler</name></author><author><name>Michael P. Krahn</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; nephrocytes are an emerging model system for mammalian podocytes and podocyte-associated diseases. Like podocytes, nephrocytes exhibit characteristics of epithelial cells, but the role of phospholipids in polarization of these cells is yet unclear. In epithelia phosphatidylinositol(4,5)bisphosphate (PI(4,5)P2) and phosphatidylinositol(3,4,5)-trisphosphate (PI(3,4,5)P3) are asymmetrically distributed in the plasma membrane and determine apical-basal polarity. Here we demonstrate that both phospholipids are present in the plasma membrane of nephrocytes, but only PI(4,5)P2 accumulates at slit diaphragms. Knockdown of Skittles, a phosphatidylinositol(4)phosphate 5-kinase, which produces PI(4,5)P2, abolished slit diaphragm formation and led to strongly reduced endocytosis. Notably, reduction in PI(3,4,5)P3 by overexpression of PTEN or expression of a dominant-negative phosphatidylinositol-3-Kinase did not affect nephrocyte function, whereas enhanced formation of PI(3,4,5)P3 by constitutively active phosphatidylinositol-3-Kinase resulted in strong slit diaphragm and endocytosis defects by ectopic activation of the Akt/mTOR pathway. Thus, PI(4,5)P2 but not PI(3,4,5)P3 is essential for slit diaphragm formation and nephrocyte function. However, PI(3,4,5)P3 has to be tightly controlled to ensure nephrocyte development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.22.449474" rel="alternate" title="PI(4,5)P2 controls slit diaphragm formation and endocytosis in Drosophila nephrocytes (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>