<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv cell-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.448486+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445468</id><title>A method for single molecule localization microscopy of tissues reveals non-random distribution of nuclear pores in Drosophila (33 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.448779+00:00</updated><author><name>Jinmei Cheng</name></author><author><name>Edward S. Allgeyer</name></author><author><name>Jennifer H. Richens</name></author><author><name>Edo Džafić</name></author><author><name>Amandine Palandri</name></author><author><name>Bohdan Lewkow</name></author><author><name>George Sirinakis</name></author><author><name>Daniel St Johnston</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single Molecule Localisation Microscopy (SMLM) can provide nanoscale resolution in thin samples but has rarely been applied to tissues, because of high background from out of focus emitters. Here we describe a line scanning microscope that provides optical sectioning for SMLM in tissues. Imaging endogenously-tagged nucleoporins and F-actin on this system using DNA- and peptide-PAINT routinely gives 30nm resolution or better at depths greater than 20 µm. This revealed that the nuclear pores are nonrandomly distributed in most &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; tissues, in contrast to cultured cells. Lamin Dm&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; shows a complementary localisation to the nuclear pores, suggesting that it corrals the pores. Furthermore, ectopic expression of the tissue-specific Lamin C distributes the nuclear pores more randomly, whereas &lt;italic&gt;lamin C&lt;/italic&gt; mutants enhance nuclear pore clustering, particularly in muscle nuclei. Since nucleoporins interact with specific chromatin domains, nuclear pore clustering could regulate chromatin organisation locally and contribute to the disease phenotypes caused by human Lamin A/C laminopathies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445468" rel="alternate" title="A method for single molecule localization microscopy of tissues reveals non-random distribution of nuclear pores in Drosophila (33 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.445599</id><title>Computational toolbox for ultrastructural quantitative analysis of filament networks in cryo-ET data (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.449024+00:00</updated><author><name>Georgi Dimchev</name></author><author><name>Behnam Amiri</name></author><author><name>Florian Fäßler</name></author><author><name>Martin Falcke</name></author><author><name>Florian KM Schur</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A precise quantitative description of the ultrastructural characteristics underlying biological mechanisms is often key to their understanding. This is particularly true for dynamic extra- and intracellular filamentous assemblies, playing a role in cell motility, cell integrity, cytokinesis, tissue formation and maintenance. For example, genetic manipulation or modulation of actin regulatory proteins frequently manifests in changes of the morphology, dynamics, and ultrastructural architecture of actin filament-rich cell peripheral structures, such as lamellipodia or filopodia. However, the observed ultrastructural effects often remain subtle and require sufficiently large datasets for appropriate quantitative analysis. The acquisition of such large datasets has been enabled by recent advances in high-throughput cryo-electron tomography (cryo-ET) methods. However, this also necessitates the development of complementary approaches to maximize the extraction of relevant biological information. We have developed a computational toolbox for the semi-automatic quantification of filamentous networks from cryo-ET datasets to facilitate the analysis and cross-comparison of multiple experimental conditions. GUI-based components simplify the manipulation of data and allow users to obtain a large number of ultrastructural parameters describing filamentous assemblies. We demonstrate the feasibility of this workflow by analyzing cryo-ET data of untreated and chemically perturbed branched actin filament networks and that of parallel actin filament arrays. In principle, the computational toolbox presented here is applicable for data analysis comprising any type of filaments in regular (i.e. parallel) or random arrangement. We show that it can ease the identification of key differences between experimental groups and facilitate the in-depth analysis of ultrastructural data in a time-efficient manner.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.445599" rel="alternate" title="Computational toolbox for ultrastructural quantitative analysis of filament networks in cryo-ET data (16 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.445490</id><title>Soft limbal niche maintains stem cell compartmentalization and function through YAP (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.449202+00:00</updated><author><name>Swarnabh Bhattacharya</name></author><author><name>Abhishek Mukherjee</name></author><author><name>Sabrina Pisano</name></author><author><name>Anna Altshuler</name></author><author><name>Waseem Nasser</name></author><author><name>Sunanda Dey</name></author><author><name>Anna Kaganovsky</name></author><author><name>Aya Amitai-Lange</name></author><author><name>Michael Mimouni</name></author><author><name>Sergiu Socea</name></author><author><name>Peleg Hasson</name></author><author><name>Chloe Feral</name></author><author><name>Haguy Wolfenson</name></author><author><name>Ruby Shalom-Feuerstein</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Stem cells’ (SCs) decision to self-renew or differentiate largely depends on the extracellular environment and elasticity of their niche. A well-described mediator of the mechanotransduction pathway is the co-transcriptional activator Yes-associated protein (YAP), known to shuttle into the nucleus of cells grown on stiff matrices. YAP is also known to be essential for stemness, but confusingly, SCs often reside in soft niches. Furthermore, the role of matrix rigidity in niche formation and SC function &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; is poorly understood. Here we report that the post-natal development of the murine corneal epithelium involves matrix stiffening and loss of YAP activity that is associated with the formation of differentiation compartment. Importantly, manipulating the matrix crosslinking enzyme, Lox, perturbed SC mark expression and resulted in loss of corneal transparency. In agreement, we found that YAP and mechanotransduction pathways are essential for stemness in the soft niche compartment, wound healing response, and dedifferentiation of committed cells into SCs following SC depletion. &lt;italic&gt;In vitro&lt;/italic&gt; experiments revealed that stiffer substrates induced cytoplasmic YAP localization through activation of LATS1/2, facilitating SMAD2/3-mediated cell differentiation. Taken together, we propose that the soft environment of the corneal SC niche maintains YAP activity to support SC regulation during morphogenesis, adult homeostasis and regeneration by the niche.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Matrix stiffening mediates the post-natal compartmentalization of SCs and differentiated cells of the corneal epithelium&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;YAP activity is indispensable for SC function, regeneration and dedifferentiation following injury&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Matrix stiffness enhances LATS1/2-mediated YAP inactivation and SMAD2/3-dependent corneal epithelial cell differentiation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Manipulation of mechanotransduction pathways influences SC growth &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.445490" rel="alternate" title="Soft limbal niche maintains stem cell compartmentalization and function through YAP (14 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>