<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv cell-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.837519+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.16.448697</id><title>Visualizing looping of two endogenous genomic loci using synthetic zinc-finger proteins with anti-FLAG and anti-HA frankenbodies in living cells (45 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.837858+00:00</updated><author><name>Yang Liu</name></author><author><name>Ning Zhao</name></author><author><name>Masato T. Kanemaki</name></author><author><name>Yotaro Yamamoto</name></author><author><name>Yoshifusa Sadamura</name></author><author><name>Timothy J. Stasevich</name></author><author><name>Hiroshi Kimura</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In eukaryotic nuclei, chromatin loops mediated through cohesin are critical structures that regulate gene expression and DNA replication. Here we demonstrate a new method to visualize endogenous genomic loci using synthetic zinc-finger proteins harboring repeat epitope tags (ZF probes) for signal amplification via binding of tag-specific intracellular antibodies, or frankenbodies, fused with fluorescent proteins. We achieve this in two steps. First, we develop an anti-FLAG frankenbody that can bind FLAG-tagged proteins in diverse live-cell environments. The anti-FLAG frankenbody complements the anti-HA frankenbody, enabling two-color signal amplification from FLAG and HA-tagged proteins. Second, we develop a pair of cell-permeable ZF probes that specifically bind two endogenous chromatin loci predicted to be involved in chromatin looping. By coupling our anti-FLAG and anti-HA frankenbodies with FLAG- and HA-tagged ZF probes, we simultaneously visualize the dynamics of the two loci in single living cells. This reveals close association between the two loci in the majority of cells, but the loci markedly separate upon the triggered degradation of the cohesin subunit RAD21. Our ability to image two endogenous genomic loci simultaneously in single living cells provides a proof-of-principle that ZF probes coupled with frankenbodies are useful new tools for exploring genome dynamics in multiple colors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.16.448697" rel="alternate" title="Visualizing looping of two endogenous genomic loci using synthetic zinc-finger proteins with anti-FLAG and anti-HA frankenbodies in living cells (45 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-06-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.13.448249</id><title>TDAExplore: quantitative image analysis through topology-based machine learning (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.838126+00:00</updated><author><name>Parker Edwards</name></author><author><name>Kristen Skruber</name></author><author><name>Nikola Milićević</name></author><author><name>James B. Heidings</name></author><author><name>Tracy-Ann Read</name></author><author><name>Peter Bubenik</name></author><author><name>Eric A. Vitriol</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Machine learning has greatly expanded the ability to classify images. However, many machine learning classifiers require thousands of images for training and lack quantitative descriptors of how images were grouped. We overcome these limitations with a machine learning approach based on topological data analysis, where a data set of 20-30 images is sufficient to accurately train the classifier. Our method quantifies differences between groups and identifies subcellular regions with the largest dissimilarities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.13.448249" rel="alternate" title="TDAExplore: quantitative image analysis through topology-based machine learning (19 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-06-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.16.448703</id><title>Analysis of conditional colocalization relationships and hierarchies from three-color microscopy images (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.838340+00:00</updated><author><name>Jesus Vega-Lugo</name></author><author><name>Bruno da Rocha-Azevedo</name></author><author><name>Aparajita Dasgupta</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Touret</name></author><author><name>Khuloud Jaqaman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Colocalization is a cornerstone approach in cell biology for the analysis of multicolor microscopy images. It provides information on the localization of molecules within various subcellular compartments and allows the interrogation of molecular interactions in their spatiotemporal cellular context. However, the overwhelming majority of colocalization analyses are designed for two-color microscopy images, which limits their applicability and the type of information that they may reveal, leading to underutilization of multicolor microscopy images. Here we describe an approach for analyzing the colocalization relationships between three molecular entities, termed “conditional colocalization analysis,” based on spatial point pattern analysis of detected objects in microscopy images. Going beyond the question of whether colocalization is present or not, it addresses the question of whether the colocalization between two molecular entities is influenced, positively or negatively, by their respective colocalization with a third entity. We showcase two applications of conditional colocalization analysis, one addressing the question of the compartmentalization of molecular interactions, and one investigating the hierarchy of molecular interactions in a multimolecular complex. The software for conditional colocalization analysis is freely accessible online at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/kjaqaman/conditionalColoc"&gt;https://github.com/kjaqaman/conditionalColoc&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.16.448703" rel="alternate" title="Analysis of conditional colocalization relationships and hierarchies from three-color microscopy images (18 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-06-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.14.447273</id><title>Negative modulation of macroautophagy by HERPUD1 is counteracted by an increased ER-lysosomal network with impact in drug-induced stress cell survival (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.838535+00:00</updated><author><name>G. Vargas</name></author><author><name>O. Cortés</name></author><author><name>E. Arias-Muñoz</name></author><author><name>S. Hernández</name></author><author><name>C. Cerda-Troncoso</name></author><author><name>L. Hernández</name></author><author><name>A. E. González</name></author><author><name>M. H. Tatham</name></author><author><name>H. Bustamante</name></author><author><name>C. Retamal</name></author><author><name>J. Cancino</name></author><author><name>M. Varas-Godoy</name></author><author><name>R. T. Hay</name></author><author><name>A. Rojas-Fernandez</name></author><author><name>V. A. Cavieres</name></author><author><name>P. V. Burgos</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Macroautophagy and the ubiquitin proteasome system work as an interconnected network in the maintenance of cellular homeostasis. Indeed, efficient activation of macroautophagy upon nutritional deprivation is sustained by degradation of preexisting proteins by the proteasome. However, the specific substrates that are degraded by the proteasome in order to activate macroautophagy are currently unknown. By quantitative proteomic analysis we identified several proteins downregulated in response to starvation but independently of ATG5 expression. Among them, the most significant was HERPUD1, an ER protein of short-half life and a well-known substrate of the proteasome. We found that increased HERPUD1 stability by deletion of its ubiquitin-like domain (UBL) plays a negative role on basal and induced macroautophagy. Moreover, we found it triggers ER expansion by reordering the ER in crystalloid structures, but in the absence of unfolded protein response activation. Surprisingly, we found ER expansion led to an increase in the number and function of lysosomes establishing a tight network with the presence of membrane-contact sites. Importantly, a phosphomimetic S59D mutation within the UBL mimics UBL deletion on its stability and the ER-lysosomal network expansion revealing an increase of cell survival under stress conditions. Altogether, we propose stabilized HERPUD1 downregulates macroautophagy favoring instead a closed interplay between the ER and lysosomes with consequences in cell stress survival.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract Figure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="447273v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.14.447273" rel="alternate" title="Negative modulation of macroautophagy by HERPUD1 is counteracted by an increased ER-lysosomal network with impact in drug-induced stress cell survival (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-06-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>