<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv cell-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.777500+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450524</id><title>Horizontal Transfer of Histone H3 by Mammalian Cells (226 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.778159+00:00</updated><author><name>Parker L. Sulkowski</name></author><author><name>Hilary E. Nicholson</name></author><author><name>Matthew Z. Li</name></author><author><name>Norbert Perrimon</name></author><author><name>Zhe Liu</name></author><author><name>William G. Kaelin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Histones are small, highly basic, nuclear proteins that serve as structural elements to condense DNA into chromatin and regulate its accessibility&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. Although histones released from dying cells can act as extracellular signaling molecules, all intracellular histone molecules are assumed to have originated from the cell in which they reside&lt;sup&gt;2–6&lt;/sup&gt;. Here we show that histone H3 is horizontally transferred between viable cells. Using an ER-targeted biotin ligase to detect secreted proteins&lt;sup&gt;7,8&lt;/sup&gt;, we serendipitously discovered that histone H3 is selectively secreted by autophagic cells relative to histones H2A, H2B, and H4. Specific H3 posttranslational modifications are enriched or depleted on secreted H3 relative to intracellular H3, suggesting that specific PTMs dictate H3’s ability to be secreted or the information it conveys to neighboring cells. Remarkably, we found that secreted H3 can enter the nuclei of recipient cells in an autophagy-independent and cell contactindependent manner ex vivo and in vivo. These findings have implications for cell-cell communication during nutrient deprivation, hypoxia, and perhaps other forms of cellular stress, and for the ability to deliver macromolecules across cell membranes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450524" rel="alternate" title="Horizontal Transfer of Histone H3 by Mammalian Cells (226 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.28.450262</id><title>Actin force generation in vesicle formation: mechanistic insights from cryo-electron tomography (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.779010+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Serwas</name></author><author><name>Matthew Akamastsu</name></author><author><name>Amir Moayed</name></author><author><name>Karthik Vegesna</name></author><author><name>Ritvik Vasan</name></author><author><name>Jennifer M Hill</name></author><author><name>Johannes Schöneberg</name></author><author><name>Karen M Davies</name></author><author><name>Padmini Rangamani</name></author><author><name>David G Drubin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Actin filament assembly provides force during clathrin-mediated endocytosis. Here, cryo-electron tomography analysis of actin filament number, organization, and orientation during clathrin-mediated endocytosis in intact human cells revealed that force generation is robust despite variance in network organization. Actin dynamics simulations incorporating a measured branch angle of 68 ± 9° indicate that sufficient force to drive endocytosis can be generated through polymerization, and that assembly is triggered from 4 ± 2 founding “mother” filaments, consistent with the tomography data. The actin-binding protein Hip1R decorates the entire endocytic invagination, including the neck region. Simulations showed that the unexpected Hip1R neck localization targets filament growth to this region, improving internalization efficiency and robustness. Actin cytoskeleton organization described here allowed direct translation of structural information to mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cryo-electron tomography-informed simulations reveal actin force generation mechanism during clathrin-mediated endocytosis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.28.450262" rel="alternate" title="Actin force generation in vesicle formation: mechanistic insights from cryo-electron tomography (37 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.02.450855</id><title>Integrated light and electron microscopy continuum resolution imaging of 3D cell cultures (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.779991+00:00</updated><author><name>Edoardo Dimprima</name></author><author><name>Marta Garcia Montero</name></author><author><name>Sylwia Gawrzak</name></author><author><name>Paolo Ronchi</name></author><author><name>Ievgeniia Zagoriy</name></author><author><name>Yannick Schwab</name></author><author><name>Martin Jechlinger</name></author><author><name>Julia Mahamid</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;3D cell cultures, in particular organoids, recapitulate tissue architectures and are emerging model systems to investigate healthy or diseased tissues and organs. Understanding the complex cellular sociology of organoids requires the integration of diverse imaging modalities covering different spatial and temporal resolutions. Here, we present an integrated multi-scale 3D imaging approach that traverses from millimeter-scale live-cell light microscopy to nanoscale volume electron microscopy. Performing the 3D cell culture in a single carrier amenable to all imaging steps provides a continuum resolution view of the same organoid. Our approach allows us to follow organoid growth, probe their morphology with fluorescent markers, identify cells of interest and analyze their ultrastructure. We demonstrate this workflow on mouse and human derived 3D cell cultures. The continuum resolution imaging pipeline is thus suited to foster both basic and translational organoid research by simultaneously exploiting the advantages of light and electron microscopy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.02.450855" rel="alternate" title="Integrated light and electron microscopy continuum resolution imaging of 3D cell cultures (30 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450416</id><title>CellProfiler 4: Improvements in Speed, Utility and Usability (25 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.780256+00:00</updated><author><name>David R. Stirling</name></author><author><name>Madison J. Swain-Bowden</name></author><author><name>Alice M. Lucas</name></author><author><name>Anne E. Carpenter</name></author><author><name>Beth A. Cimini</name></author><author><name>Allen Goodman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;CellProfiler is a free, open source image analysis program which enables researchers to generate modular pipelines with which to process microscopy images into interpretable measurements. Here we describe CellProfiler 4, a new version of this software which has been ported to the Python 3 language. Based on user feedback, we have made several user interface refinements to improve the usability of the software. We introduced new modules to expand the capabilities of the software. We also evaluated performance and made targeted optimisations to reduce the time and cost associated with running common large-scale analysis pipelines. This release will ensure that researchers will have continued access to CellProfiler’s powerful computational tools in the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450416" rel="alternate" title="CellProfiler 4: Improvements in Speed, Utility and Usability (25 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.02.450924</id><title>Mitochondrial dysfunction triggers secretion of the immunosuppressive factor α-fetoprotein (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.780473+00:00</updated><author><name>Kimberly A. Jett</name></author><author><name>Zakery N. Baker</name></author><author><name>Amzad Hossain</name></author><author><name>Aren Boulet</name></author><author><name>Paul A. Cobine</name></author><author><name>Sagnika Ghosh</name></author><author><name>Philip Ng</name></author><author><name>Orhan Yilmaz</name></author><author><name>Kris Barretto</name></author><author><name>John DeCoteau</name></author><author><name>Karen Mochoruk</name></author><author><name>George Ioannou</name></author><author><name>Christopher Savard</name></author><author><name>Sai Yuan</name></author><author><name>Christopher Lowden</name></author><author><name>Byung-Eun Kim</name></author><author><name>Hai-Ying Mary Cheng</name></author><author><name>Brendan J Battersby</name></author><author><name>Vishal M. M. Gohil</name></author><author><name>Scot C Leary</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Signaling circuits crucial to systemic physiology are widespread, yet uncovering their molecular underpinnings remains a barrier to understanding the etiology of many metabolic disorders. Here, we identify a copper-linked signaling circuit activated by disruption of mitochondrial function in the murine liver or heart that results in atrophy of the spleen and thymus and causes a peripheral white blood cell deficiency. We demonstrate that the leukopenia is caused by α-fetoprotein, which requires copper and the cell surface receptor CCR5 to promote white blood cell death. We further show that α-fetoprotein expression is upregulated in several cell types upon inhibition of oxidative phosphorylation, including a muscle cell model of Barth syndrome. Collectively, our data argue that α-fetoprotein secreted by bioenergetically stressed tissue suppresses the immune system, an effect which may explain the recurrent infections that are observed in a subset of mitochondrial diseases or in other disorders with mitochondrial involvement.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.02.450924" rel="alternate" title="Mitochondrial dysfunction triggers secretion of the immunosuppressive factor α-fetoprotein (18 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>