<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv cell-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.774073+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.451100</id><title>Nucleolar NOC1 controls protein synthesis and cell competition in Drosophila (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.774341+00:00</updated><author><name>Francesca Destefanis</name></author><author><name>Valeria Manara</name></author><author><name>Stefania Santarelli</name></author><author><name>Sheri Zola</name></author><author><name>Marco Brambilla</name></author><author><name>Giacomo Viola</name></author><author><name>Paola Maragno</name></author><author><name>Gabriella Viero</name></author><author><name>Maria Enrica Pasini</name></author><author><name>Marianna Penzo</name></author><author><name>Paola Bellosta</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;NOC1&lt;/italic&gt; is a nucleolar protein necessary in yeast for a correct transport of the large ribosomal subunit and ribosome biogenesis. Here we shown that ubiquitous downregulation of NOC1 in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; results in defective polysome formation and decreases the rate of protein synthesis. Reduction of NOC1 is detrimental for animal growth and adequate expression of NOC1 in organs, such as the prothoracic gland and in the fat body is necessary for proper organ function. In the imaginal discs downregulation of NOC1 results in small cells that die by apoptosis. This event is rescued in &lt;italic&gt;M/+&lt;/italic&gt; background suggesting that cells with reduced of NOC1 are outcompeted by wild type cells because of their reduced protein synthesis. NOC1 downregulation induces the upregulation of the pro-apoptotic eiger-JNK signaling pathway, that results in the activation of DILP8 compensatory mechanism. Our results demonstrate that NOC1 in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; plays an important role in the regulation of protein synthesis and cell survival, linking its function in the nucleolus to the control of animal growth and development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;summary statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;NOC1 is a nucleolar protein necessary for the general control of protein synthesis and cellular growth. In vivo NOC1 expression is required for the correct development of the animal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.451100" rel="alternate" title="Nucleolar NOC1 controls protein synthesis and cell competition in Drosophila (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.451306</id><title>Quantitative intracellular retention of delivered RNAs through optimized cell fixation and immuno-staining (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.774620+00:00</updated><author><name>Prasath Paramasivam</name></author><author><name>Martin Stöter</name></author><author><name>Eloina Corradi</name></author><author><name>Irene Dalla Costa</name></author><author><name>Andreas Höijer</name></author><author><name>Stefano Bartesaghi</name></author><author><name>Alan Sabirsh</name></author><author><name>Lennart Lindfors</name></author><author><name>Marianna Yanez Arteta</name></author><author><name>Peter Nordberg</name></author><author><name>Shalini Andersson</name></author><author><name>Marie-Laure Baudet</name></author><author><name>Marc Bickle</name></author><author><name>Marino Zerial</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Detection of nucleic acids within sub-cellular compartments is key to understanding their function. Determining the intracellular distribution of nucleic acids requires quantitative retention and estimation of their association with different organelles by immunofluorescence microscopy. This is important also for the delivery of nucleic acid therapeutics which depends on endocytic uptake and endosomal escape. However, the current methods fail to preserve the majority of exogenously delivered nucleic acids in the cytoplasm. To solve this problem, by monitoring Cy5-labeled mRNA delivered to primary human adipocytes via lipid nanoparticles (LNP), we optimized cell fixation, permeabilization and immuno-staining of a number of organelle markers, achieving quantitative retention of mRNA and allowing visualization of levels which escape detection using conventional procedures. Additionally, we demonstrated the protocol to be effective on exogenously delivered siRNA, miRNA, as well as endogenous miRNA. Our protocol is compatible with RNA probes of single molecule fluorescence in-situ hybridization (smFISH) and molecular beacon, thus demonstrating that it is broadly applicable to study a variety of nucleic acids.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.451306" rel="alternate" title="Quantitative intracellular retention of delivered RNAs through optimized cell fixation and immuno-staining (7 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>