<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv cell-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.617385+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.08.447593</id><title>ER-lysosome lipid transfer protein VPS13C/PARK23 prevents aberrant mtDNA-dependent STING signaling (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.617651+00:00</updated><author><name>William Hancock-Cerutti</name></author><author><name>Zheng Wu</name></author><author><name>Arun Tharkeshwar</name></author><author><name>Shawn M. Ferguson</name></author><author><name>Gerald S. Shadel</name></author><author><name>Pietro De Camilli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mutations in VPS13C cause early onset, autosomal recessive Parkinson’s Disease (PD). We have established that VPS13C encodes a lipid transfer protein localized to contact sites between the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) and late endosomes/lysosomes. In the current study, we demonstrate that depleting VPS13C in HeLa cells causes an accumulation of lysosomes with an altered lipid profile, including an accumulation of di-22:6-BMP, a biomarker of the PD-associated leucine-rich repeat kinase 2 (LRRK2) G2019S mutation. In addition, the DNA-sensing cGAS/STING pathway, which was recently implicated in PD pathogenesis, is activated in these cells. This activation results from a combination of elevated mitochondrial DNA in the cytosol and a defect in the degradation of activated STING, a lysosome-dependent process. These results suggest a link between ER-lysosome lipid transfer and innate immune activation and place VPS13C in pathways relevant to PD pathogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.08.447593" rel="alternate" title="ER-lysosome lipid transfer protein VPS13C/PARK23 prevents aberrant mtDNA-dependent STING signaling (23 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-06-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.11.448119</id><title>Structural Basis for Cytoplasmic Dynein-1 Regulation by Lis1 (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.617869+00:00</updated><author><name>John P Gillies</name></author><author><name>Janice M Reimer</name></author><author><name>Eva P Karasmanis</name></author><author><name>Indrajit Lahiri</name></author><author><name>Zaw Min Htet</name></author><author><name>Andres E Leschziner</name></author><author><name>Samara L Reck-Peterson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The lissencephaly 1 gene, &lt;italic&gt;LIS1&lt;/italic&gt;, is mutated in patients with the neurodevelopmental disease lissencephaly. The Lis1 protein is conserved from fungi to mammals and is a key regulator of cytoplasmic dynein-1, the major minus-end-directed microtubule motor in many eukaryotes. Lis1 is the only dynein regulator that binds directly to dynein's motor domain, and by doing so alters dynein's mechanochemistry. Lis1 is required for the formation of fully active dynein complexes, which also contain essential cofactors: dynactin and an activating adaptor. Here, we report the first high-resolution structure of the yeast dynein-Lis1 complex. Our 3.1Å structure reveals, in molecular detail, the major contacts between dynein and Lis1 and between Lis1's β-propellers. Structure-guided mutations in Lis1 and dynein show that these contacts are required for Lis1's ability to form fully active human dynein complexes and to regulate yeast dynein's mechanochemistry and in vivo function. We present a model for the conserved role of Lis1 in regulating dynein from yeast to humans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.11.448119" rel="alternate" title="Structural Basis for Cytoplasmic Dynein-1 Regulation by Lis1 (7 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-06-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.447875</id><title>Notch pathway is required for protection against heat-stress in spermatogonial stem cells (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.618059+00:00</updated><author><name>Omar D. Moreno Acosta</name></author><author><name>Agustín F. Boan</name></author><author><name>Ricardo S. Hattori</name></author><author><name>Juan I. Fernandino</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Environmentally favorable conditions the sustainability of spermatogenesis is brought about by a balance between two types of division, the self-renewal division for the maintenance of the stem cell pool and the differentiation division for continuous production of spermatozoa. The production of gametes under unfavorable, stressful conditions can decrease or even be interrupted, compromising fertility parameters. Thus, the survival of spermatogonial stem cells (SSCs) is crucial for the recovery of spermatogenesis after stressful situations (e.g. high temperature). Here, we show that the Notch pathway protects the spermatogonial stem cells against thermal stress, ensuring reproductive success after normal conditions are restored. First, presenilin enhancer-2 (pen-2), the catalytic subunit of γ-secretase complex, was localized in SSCs of the medaka testis. The exposure of adult males to thermal stress condition induced apoptosis in all spermatogenics cells, with the exception of SSCs. Concomitantly, the Notch pathways was up-regulated, including the &lt;italic&gt;pen-2&lt;/italic&gt;, its ligands (dll4, jag1-2) and its receptors (notch1a-3); &lt;italic&gt;pen-2&lt;/italic&gt; expression was restricted to the SSCs during thermal stress. The importance of this pathway was further supported by an &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; approach, in which the inhibition of Notch activity induced a loss of SSCs. Overall, this study demonstrates that the Notch pathways activity is necessary for the protection of SSCs under chronic thermal stress.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.447875" rel="alternate" title="Notch pathway is required for protection against heat-stress in spermatogonial stem cells (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.447841</id><title>Parkin drives pS65-Ub turnover independently of canonical autophagy in Drosophila (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.618225+00:00</updated><author><name>Joanne L. Usher</name></author><author><name>Juliette J. Lee</name></author><author><name>Alvaro Sanchez-Martinez</name></author><author><name>Alexander J. Whitworth</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Parkinson's disease-related proteins, PINK1 and parkin, act in a common pathway to maintain mitochondrial quality control. While the PINK1-parkin pathway can promote autophagic mitochondrial turnover (mitophagy) in cell culture, recent studies have questioned whether they contribute to mitophagy in vivo, and alternative PINK1- and parkin-dependent mitochondrial quality control pathways have been proposed. To determine the mechanisms by which the Pink1-parkin pathway operates in vivo, we developed methods to detect Ser65-phosphorylated ubiquitin (pS65-Ub) in Drosophila. Exposure to the oxidant paraquat led to robust, Pink1-dependent pS65-Ub production. Surprisingly, parkin-null flies displayed strikingly elevated basal levels of pS65-Ub, suggestive of disrupted flux through the Pink1-parkin pathway. Depletion of the core autophagy proteins Atg1, Atg5 and Atg8a did not cause pS65-Ub accumulation to the same extent as loss of parkin, and overexpression of parkin was able to reduce both basal and paraquat-induced pS65-Ub levels in an Atg5-null background. Taken together, these results suggest that the Pink1-parkin pathway is able to promote mitochondrial turnover independently of canonical autophagy in vivo.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.447841" rel="alternate" title="Parkin drives pS65-Ub turnover independently of canonical autophagy in Drosophila (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>