<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>BioRxiv preprints in plant_biology posted in the last week with at least 5 tweets</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.402088+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant_biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443356</id><title>Sugar units, not chilling units, control endodormancy duration in plants – potato tuber as a case study (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.421519+00:00</updated><author><name>Raz Danieli</name></author><author><name>Shmuel Assouline</name></author><author><name>Bolaji Babajide Salam</name></author><author><name>Paula Teper-Bamnolker</name></author><author><name>Eduard Belausov</name></author><author><name>Yael Friedmann</name></author><author><name>David Granot</name></author><author><name>Dani Eshel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Endodormancy (ED) is a crucial stage in the life cycle of many perennial plants, regulated by genetic and environmental factors. Chilling units, growth regulators, and nutrient supply are considered inducers of ED release, but the mechanism governing ED duration is poorly understood. The potato tuber has been used as a model system to study metabolic processes associated with ED release. Cold-induced sweetening is a well-known response of the tuber to chilling. Here, we found that cold stress induces an increase in sugar units in association with plasmodesmatal closure in the dormant bud cells. Tuber sweetening was associated with shortened ED duration after cooling. Heat exposure also caused sugar unit accumulation followed by faster ED release. A logistic function was developed to predict ED duration based on sugar unit measurements. We discovered that ED release is better correlated with the accumulation of sugar units compared to chilling units. CRISPR/Cas9 knockout of the vacuolar invertase gene (&lt;italic&gt;StVInv&lt;/italic&gt;) induced longer ED, but only in cultivars in which the mutation modified the level sugar units. Our results suggest that sugar units are better predictors of vegetative bud ED duration than chilling units.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443801</id><title>Chlorophyll fluorescence: How the quality of information about PAM instrument parameters may affect our research (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.421120+00:00</updated><author><name>Tim Nies</name></author><author><name>Yuxi Niu</name></author><author><name>Oliver Ebenhöh</name></author><author><name>Shizue Matsubara</name></author><author><name>Anna Matuszyńska</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chlorophyll &lt;italic&gt;a&lt;/italic&gt; fluorescence is a powerful indicator of photosynthetic energy conversion in plants and photosynthetic microorganisms. One of the most widely used measurement techniques is Pulse Amplitude Modulation (PAM) fluorometry. Unfortunately, parameter settings of PAM instruments are often not completely described in scientific articles although their variations, however small these may seem, can influence measurements. We show the effects of parameter settings on PAM measurements. We first simulated fluorescence signals using a previously published computational model of photosynthesis. Then, we validated our findings experimentally. Our analysis demonstrates how the kinetics of non-photochemical quenching (NPQ) induction and relaxation are affected by different settings of PAM instrument parameters. Neglecting these parameters may mislead data interpretation and derived hypotheses, hamper independent validation of the results, and cause problems for mathematical formulation of underlying processes. Given the uncertainties inflicted by this neglect, we urge PAM users to provide detailed documentation of measurement protocols. Moreover, to ensure accessibility to the required information, we advocate minimum information standards that can serve both experimental and computational biologists in our efforts to advance system-wide understanding of biological processes. Such specification will enable launching a standardized database for plant and data science communities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlight&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;PAM fluorometry measurement is sensitive to instrument settings and protocols. Yet, protocols are published incompletely. We urge to reach an agreement on minimal protocol information of PAM experiments to be shared publicly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443557</id><title>Unravelling consensus genomic regions conferring leaf rust resistance in wheat via meta-QTL analysis (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.420536+00:00</updated><author><name>Amo Aduragbemi</name></author><author><name>Jose Miguel Soriano</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Leaf rust, caused by the fungus &lt;italic&gt;Puccinia triticina&lt;/italic&gt; Erikss (Pt), is a destructive disease affecting wheat and a threat to food security. Developing resistant varieties represents a useful method of disease control, and thus, understanding the genetic basis for leaf rust resistance is required. To this end, a comprehensive bibliographic search for leaf rust resistance quantitative trait loci (QTLs) was performed, and 393 QTLs were collected from 50 QTL mapping studies. Afterwards, a consensus map with a total length of 4567 cM consisting of different types of markers (SSR, DArT, Chip-based SNP markers and SNP markers from GBS) was used for QTL projection, and meta-QTL analysis was performed on 320 QTLs. A total of 75 genetic map positions (gmQTLs) were discovered and refined to 15 high confidence mQTLs (hcmQTLs). The candidate genes discovered within the hcmQTL interval were then checked for differential expression using data from three transcriptome studies, resulting in 92 differentially expressed genes (DEGs). The expression of these genes in various leaf tissues during wheat development was explored. This study provides insight into leaf rust resistance in wheat and thereby provides an avenue for developing resistant varieties by incorporating the most important hcmQTLs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443061</id><title>Permeability profiling of all 13 Arabidopsis PIP aquaporins using a high throughput yeast approach (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.419071+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael Groszmann</name></author><author><name>Annamaria De Rosa</name></author><author><name>Weihua Chen</name></author><author><name>Jiaen Qiu</name></author><author><name>Samantha A McGaughey</name></author><author><name>Caitlin S. Byrt</name></author><author><name>John R Evans</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Plant aquaporins have many more functions than just transporting water. Within the diversity of plant aquaporins are isoforms capable of transporting signaling molecules, nutrients, metalloids and gases. It is established that aquaporin substrate discrimination depends on combinations of factors such as solute size, pore size and polarity, and post-translational protein modifications. But our understanding of the relationships between variation in aquaporin structures and the implications for permeability is limited. High-throughput yeast-based assays were developed to assess diverse substrate permeabilities to water, H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, boric acid, urea and Na&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;. All 13 plasma membrane intrinsic proteins (PIPs) from Arabidopsis (AtPIPs) were permeable to both water and H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, although their effectiveness varied, and none were permeable to urea. AtPIP2 isoforms were more permeable to water than AtPIP1s, while AtPIP1s were more efficient at transporting H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; with AtPIP1;3 and AtPIP1;4 being the most permeable. Among the AtPIP2s, AtPIP2;2 and AtPIP2;7 were also permeable to boric acid and Na&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;. Linking AtPIP substrate profiles with phylogenetics and gene expression data enabled us to align substrate preferences with known biological roles of AtPIPs and importantly guide towards unidentified roles hidden by functional redundancy at key developmental stages and within tissue types. This analysis positions us to more strategically test &lt;italic&gt;in planta&lt;/italic&gt; physiological roles of AtPIPs in order to unravel their complex contributions to the transport of important substrates, and secondly, to resolve links between aquaporin protein structure, substrate discrimination, and transport efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yeast based high throughput assays were developed to assess the permeability of each Arabidopsis PIP aquaporin isoform to water, H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, boric acid, urea and sodium.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443507</id><title>Rapid analysis of strigolactone receptor activity in a Nicotiana benthamiana dwarf14 mutant (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.418543+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexandra R.F. White</name></author><author><name>Jose A. Mendez</name></author><author><name>Aashima Khosla</name></author><author><name>David C. Nelson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;DWARF14 (D14) is an ɑ/β-hydrolase and receptor for the plant hormone strigolactone (SL) in angiosperms. Upon SL perception, D14 works with MORE AXILLARY GROWTH2 (MAX2) to trigger polyubiquitination and degradation of DWARF53(D53)-type proteins in the SUPPRESSOR OF MAX2 1-LIKE (SMXL) family. We used CRISPR-Cas9 to generate knockout alleles of the two homoeologous &lt;italic&gt;D14&lt;/italic&gt; genes in the &lt;italic&gt;Nicotiana benthamiana&lt;/italic&gt; genome. The &lt;italic&gt;Nbd14a,b&lt;/italic&gt; double mutant had several phenotypes that are consistent with the loss of SL perception in other plants, including increased axillary bud outgrowth, reduced height, shortened petioles, and smaller leaves. A ratiometric fluorescent reporter system was used to monitor degradation of SMXL7 from &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; (AtSMXL7) after transient expression in &lt;italic&gt;N. benthamiana&lt;/italic&gt; and treatment with the strigolactone analog GR24. AtSMXL7 was degraded after treatment with GR24&lt;sup&gt;5DS&lt;/sup&gt;, which has the stereochemical configuration of SLs, as well as its enantiomer GR24&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;ent&lt;/italic&gt;-5DS&lt;/sup&gt; . In &lt;italic&gt;Nbd14a,b&lt;/italic&gt; leaves, AtSMXL7 abundance was unaffected by GR24. Transient coexpression of AtD14 with the AtSMXL7 reporter in &lt;italic&gt;Nbd14a,b&lt;/italic&gt; restored the degradation response to GR24, but required an active catalytic triad. With this platform, we evaluated the ability of several AtD14 mutants that had not been characterized in plants to target AtSMXL7 for degradation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443365</id><title>Cis-regulatory divergence underpins the evolution of C3-C4 intermediate photosynthesis in Moricandia (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.418160+00:00</updated><author><name>Meng-Ying Lin</name></author><author><name>Urte Schlüter</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Stich</name></author><author><name>Andreas P.M. Weber</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Altered transcript abundances and cell specific gene expression patterns that are caused by regulatory divergence play an important role in the evolution of C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; photosynthesis. How these altered gene expression patterns are achieved and whether they are driven by &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;- or &lt;italic&gt;trans&lt;/italic&gt;-regulatory changes is mostly unknown. To address this question, we investigated the regulatory divergence between C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; and C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; intermediates, using allele specific gene expression (ASE) analyses of &lt;italic&gt;Moricandia arvensis&lt;/italic&gt; (C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;), &lt;italic&gt;M. moricandioides&lt;/italic&gt; (C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;) and their interspecific F&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; hybrids. ASE analysis on SNP-level showed similar relative proportions of regulatory effects among hybrids: 36% and 6% of SNPs were controlled by &lt;italic&gt;cis-&lt;/italic&gt;only and &lt;italic&gt;trans-&lt;/italic&gt;only changes, respectively. GO terms associated with metabolic processes and the positioning of chloroplast in cells were abundant in transcripts with &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-SNPs shared by all studied hybrids. Transcripts with &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-specificity expressed bias toward the allele from the C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; intermediate genotype. Additionally, ASE evaluated on transcript-level indicated that ∼27% of transcripts show signals of ASE in &lt;italic&gt;Moricandia&lt;/italic&gt; hybrids. Promoter-GUS assays on selected genes revealed altered spatial gene expression patterns, which likely result from regulatory divergence in their promoter regions. Assessing ASE in &lt;italic&gt;Moricandia&lt;/italic&gt; interspecific hybrids contributes to the understanding of early evolutionary steps towards C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; photosynthesis and highlights the impact and importance of altered transcriptional regulations in this process.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443788</id><title>ABA homeostasis and long-distance translocation is redundantly regulated by ABCG ABA importers (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.417530+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuqin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Himabindu Vasuki</name></author><author><name>Jie Liu</name></author><author><name>Hamutal Bar</name></author><author><name>Shani Lazary</name></author><author><name>Aiman Egbaria</name></author><author><name>Dagmar Ripper</name></author><author><name>Laurence Charrier</name></author><author><name>Zeinu Mussa Belew</name></author><author><name>Nikolai Wulff</name></author><author><name>Hussam Hassan Nour-Eldin</name></author><author><name>Asaph Aharoni</name></author><author><name>Laura Ragni</name></author><author><name>Lucia Strader</name></author><author><name>Nir Sade</name></author><author><name>Roy Weinstain</name></author><author><name>Markus Geisler</name></author><author><name>Eilon Shani</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The effects of abscisic acid (ABA) on plant growth, development and response to the environment depend on local ABA concentrations. Here, we exploited a genome-scale amiRNA screen, targeting the &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/italic&gt; transportome, to show that ABA homeostasis is regulated by two previously unknown ABA transporters. ABCG17 and ABCG18 are localized to the plasma membranes of leaf mesophyll and stem cortex cells to redundantly promote ABA import, leading to conjugated inactive ABA sinks, thus restricting stomatal closure. &lt;italic&gt;ABCG17&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;ABCG18&lt;/italic&gt; double knockdown revealed that the transporters encoded by these genes not only limit stomatal aperture size, conductance and transpiration while increasing water-use efficiency but also control ABA translocation from the shoot to the root to regulate lateral root emergence. Under abiotic stress conditions, &lt;italic&gt;ABCG17&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;ABCG18&lt;/italic&gt; are transcriptionally repressed, promoting active ABA movement and response. The transport mechanism mediated by ABCG17 and ABCG18 allows plants to maintain ABA homeostasis under normal growth conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443285</id><title>Efficient CRISPR/Cas-mediated Targeted Mutagenesis in Spring and Winter Wheat Varieties (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.406967+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Hahn</name></author><author><name>Laura Sanjurjo Loures</name></author><author><name>Caroline A. Sparks</name></author><author><name>Kostya Kanyuka</name></author><author><name>Vladimir Nekrasov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The CRISPR/Cas technology has recently become a molecular tool of choice for gene function studies in plants as well as crop improvement. Wheat is a globally important staple crop with a well annotated genome and there is plenty of scope for improving its agriculturally important traits using genome editing technologies, such as CRISPR/Cas. As part of this study we targeted three different genes in hexaploid wheat &lt;italic&gt;Triticum aestivum&lt;/italic&gt;: &lt;italic&gt;TaBAK1-2&lt;/italic&gt; in the spring cultivar Cadenza as well as &lt;italic&gt;Ta-eIF4E&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Ta-eIF(iso)4E&lt;/italic&gt; in winter cultivars Cezanne, Goncourt and Prevert. The primary transgenic lines carrying CRISPR/Cas-induced indels were successfully generated for all targeted genes. As winter wheat varieties are generally less amenable to genetic transformation, the successful experimental methodology for transformation and genome editing in winter wheat presented in this study will be of interest to the research community working with this crop.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443923</id><title>Brace root phenotypes predict root lodging susceptibility and the contribution to anchorage in maize (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.406502+00:00</updated><author><name>Ashley N. Hostetler</name></author><author><name>Lindsay Erndwein</name></author><author><name>Jonathan W. Reneau</name></author><author><name>William Cantera</name></author><author><name>Adam Stager</name></author><author><name>Herbert G. Tanner</name></author><author><name>Douglas Cook</name></author><author><name>Erin E. Sparks</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A changing global climate brings increasingly prevalent and severe storms that threaten crop production by imparting mechanical stresses. Plant failure due to mechanical stress is termed lodging and in the United States, yield loss due to lodging has been estimated at 7-25% for maize (&lt;italic&gt;Zea mays&lt;/italic&gt;). In maize, the presence of specialized aerial brace roots has been shown to increase anchorage and root lodging resistance. However, beyond scoring for presence, there have been limited attempts to define the brace root phenotypes that optimize anchorage. This study reports variable root lodging and plant biomechanics in a population of 52 maize inbred lines. To quantify the variation in brace root phenotypes within this population, a semi-automated phenotyping workflow was developed. These empirical measurements were integrated into predictive random forest models to demonstrate that brace root phenotypes can classify root lodging incidence and plant biomechanics. The prediction accuracy of these models is driven by multiple brace root phenotypes suggesting that anchorage can be optimized by the manipulation of multiple functional traits. Plant height has been previously associated with lodging susceptibility yet the inclusion of plant height as a predictor does not always improve prediction accuracy. Previously, brace root node number has been shown to be genetically linked to plant height and here we show that additional brace root phenotypes are linked to plant height but with opposing effects on root lodging susceptibility. Together these data define the important brace root phenotypes that predict root lodging resistance and demonstrate the need to uncouple the linkage between plant height and root traits for the development of climate resilient crops.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>