<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>BioRxiv preprints in plant_biology posted in the last week with at least 5 tweets</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.051904+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant_biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.05.442845</id><title>Mechanistic Insights of High Temperature-Interfered Meiosis in Autotetraploid Arabidopsis thaliana (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.053998+00:00</updated><author><name>Huiqi Fu</name></author><author><name>Ke Yang</name></author><author><name>Xiaohong Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jiayi Zhao</name></author><author><name>Ibrahim Eid Elesawi</name></author><author><name>Hong Liu</name></author><author><name>Jing Xia</name></author><author><name>Guanghui Yu</name></author><author><name>Chunli Chen</name></author><author><name>Chong Wang</name></author><author><name>Bing Liu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Environmental temperature has a huge impact on multiple meiosis processes in flowering plants. Polyploid plants derived from whole genome duplication are believed to have an enhanced abiotic stress tolerance. In this study, the impact of high temperatures on male meiosis in autotetraploid &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; was investigated. We found that autotetraploid Columbia (Col-0) plants generate a subpopulation of aberrant meiotic products under normal temperature, which is significantly increased under heat stress. Cytological studies revealed that, as the case in diploid &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt;, assembly of microtubular cytoskeleton network, pairing and segregation of homologous chromosomes, and meiotic recombination in autotetraploid Arabidopsis are compromised under the high temperatures. Immunostaining of ɤH2A.X and recombinase DMC1 suggested that heat stress inhibits formation of DNA double-strand breaks; additionally, it specifically destabilizes ASY1 and ASY4, but not SYN1 on chromosomes. The loading defects of ASY1 and ASY4 overlap in the &lt;italic&gt;syn1&lt;/italic&gt; mutant, which supports that the building of lateral element of synaptonemal complex occurs downstream of a SYN1-ASY4-ASY3 stepwise assembly of axis. Remarkably, heat-induced abnormalities of ASY1 and ASY4 co-localize on chromosomes of both diploid and autotetraploid Arabidopsis, suggesting that high temperatures interfere with ASY1-associated SC via an impacted stability of chromosome axis. Furthermore, ZYP1-dependent transverse filament of SC is disrupted by heat stress. Taken together, these findings suggest that polyploidization negatively contributes to instability of chromosome axis and meiotic recombination in &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; under heat stress.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.04.442592</id><title>Comparative meta-proteomic analysis for the identification of novel plasmodesmata proteins and regulatory cues (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.053599+00:00</updated><author><name>Philip Kirk</name></author><author><name>Sam Amsbury</name></author><author><name>Liam German</name></author><author><name>Rocio Gaudioso-Pedraza</name></author><author><name>Yoselin Benitez-Alfonso</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A major route for cell-to-cell signaling is via cell wall-embedded pores termed plasmodesmata (PD) forming the symplasm. PD regulate many aspects of plant development and responses to the environment however, our understanding of what factors affect their structure and permeability is limited. In this paper, a meta-analysis is presented as a tool for the identification of conditions affecting PD transport and &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; generation of PD proteomes for species of interest. The custom-built pipeline searches the whole genome for protein structural features and conserved domains identified on experimental proteomes and use it to predict PD candidates in 22 compatible plant species. Using the &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; proteome and microarray analysis, interactions between PD genes and conditions affecting PD function are identified. High salinity and osmotic stress affect a significant number of PD candidate genes and we provide evidence that these conditions regulate symplasmic transport of GFP. Using the pipeline, the &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; PD proteome for &lt;italic&gt;Medicago truncatula&lt;/italic&gt; was generated, as an example of a plant in which experimental data is not available. The identification of a candidate receptor like protein was experimentally validated in &lt;italic&gt;M. truncatula&lt;/italic&gt; transgenic roots expressing fluorescently tagged protein fusion. Together the results highlight the power of our newly designed tool in the identification of new factors and proteins influencing PD in diverse plant species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.03.442461</id><title>Misregulation of MYB16 causes stomatal cluster formation by disrupting polarity in asymmetric cell division (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.052584+00:00</updated><author><name>Shao-Li Yang</name></author><author><name>Ngan Tran</name></author><author><name>Meng-Ying Tsai</name></author><author><name>Chin-Min Kimmy Ho</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Stomata and leaf cuticle regulate water evaporation from the plant body and balance the trade-off between photosynthesis and water loss. We identified MYB16, a key transcription factor controlling cutin biosynthesis, from previous stomatal lineage ground cell (SLGC)-enriched transcriptome study. The preferential localization of MYB16 in SLGCs but not meristemoids suggests a link between cutin synthesis and stomatal development. Here, we showed that downregulation of MYB16 in meristemoids was directly mediated by the stomatal master transcription factor, SPEECHLESS (SPCH). The suppression of MYB16 before asymmetric division was crucial for stomatal patterning because overexpression or ectopic expression of MYB16 in meristemoids increased impermeability and elevated stomatal density and clusters. The aberrant pattern of stomata was due to reduced and disrupted establishment of polarity during asymmetric cell division. Manipulating polarity by growing seedlings on hard agar rescued stomatal clusters and polarity defects in MYB16 ectopic lines. By expressing a cutinase in MYB16 ectopic lines, stomatal clustering was reduced, which suggests that the ectopic accumulation of cuticle affects the polarity in asymmetrically dividing cells and causes clustered stomata. Taken together, inhibiting MYB16 expression by SPCH in early stomatal lineage is required to correctly place the polarity complex for proper stomatal patterning during leaf morphogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>