<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv preprints in molecular_biology posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.614940+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/molecular_biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443934</id><title>SMCHD1 has separable roles in chromatin architecture and gene silencing that could be targeted in disease (42 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.615346+00:00</updated><author><name>Andres Tapia del Fierro</name></author><author><name>Bianca den Hamer</name></author><author><name>Natasha Jansz</name></author><author><name>Kelan Chen</name></author><author><name>Tamara Beck</name></author><author><name>Hannah Vanyai</name></author><author><name>Natalia Benetti</name></author><author><name>Alexandra D Gurzau</name></author><author><name>Lucia Daxinger</name></author><author><name>Shifeng Xue</name></author><author><name>Thanh Thao Nguyen Ly</name></author><author><name>Iromi Wanigasuriya</name></author><author><name>Kelsey Breslin</name></author><author><name>Harald Oey</name></author><author><name>Yvonne Krom</name></author><author><name>Dinja van der Hoorn</name></author><author><name>Linde F Bouwman</name></author><author><name>Matthew E. Ritchie</name></author><author><name>Bruno Reversade</name></author><author><name>Fabrice Prin</name></author><author><name>Timothy Mohun</name></author><author><name>Silvère M van der Maarel</name></author><author><name>Edwina McGlinn</name></author><author><name>James M Murphy</name></author><author><name>Andrew Keniry</name></author><author><name>Jessica C de Greef</name></author><author><name>Marnie E Blewitt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The interplay between 3D chromatin architecture and gene silencing is incompletely understood. Here, we report a novel point mutation in the non-canonical SMC protein SMCHD1 that enhances its silencing capacity at endogenous developmental targets and at the facioscapulohumeral muscular dystrophy associated macro-array, D4Z4. Heightened SMCHD1 silencing perturbs developmental &lt;italic&gt;Hox&lt;/italic&gt; gene activation, causing a homeotic transformation in mice. Paradoxically, the mutant SMCHD1 appears to enhance insulation against another epigenetic regulator complex, PRC2, while depleting long range chromatin interactions akin to what is observed in the absence of SMCHD1. These data suggest that SMCHD1’s role in long range chromatin interactions is not directly linked to gene silencing or insulating the chromatin, refining the model for how the different levels of SMCHD1-mediated chromatin regulation interact to bring about gene silencing in normal development and disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443660</id><title>Engineered type six secretion systems deliver active exogenous effectors and Cre recombinase (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.615723+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven J. Hersch</name></author><author><name>Linh Lam</name></author><author><name>Tao G. Dong</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genetic editing has revolutionized biotechnology but delivery of endonuclease genes as DNA can lead to aberrant integration or overexpression, leading to off-target effects. Here we develop a mechanism to deliver Cre recombinase as a protein by engineering the bacterial type six secretion system (T6SS). Using multiple T6SS fusion proteins, &lt;italic&gt;Aeromonas dhakensis&lt;/italic&gt; or attenuated &lt;italic&gt;Vibrio cholerae&lt;/italic&gt; donor strains, and a gain-of-function cassette for detecting Cre recombination, we demonstrate successful delivery of active Cre directly into recipient cells. Most efficient transfer was achieved using a truncated version of PAAR2 from &lt;italic&gt;V. cholerae&lt;/italic&gt;, resulting in a relatively small (118 amino acid) ‘delivery tag’. We further demonstrate the versatility of this system by delivering an exogenous effector, TseC, enabling &lt;italic&gt;V. cholerae&lt;/italic&gt; to kill &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt;. This implicates that &lt;italic&gt;P. aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; is naturally resistant to all native effectors of &lt;italic&gt;V. cholerae&lt;/italic&gt; and that the TseC chaperone protein is not required for its activity. Moreover, it demonstrates that the engineered system can improve T6SS efficacy against specific pathogens, proposing future application in microbiome manipulation or as a next-generation antimicrobial. Inexpensive and easy to produce, this protein delivery system has many potential applications ranging from studying T6SS effectors to genetic editing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Delivery of protein-based drugs, antigens, and gene-editing agents has broad applications. The type VI protein secretion system (T6SS) can target both bacteria and eukaryotic cells and deliver proteins of diverse size and function. Here we harness the T6SS to successfully deliver Cre recombinase to genetically edit bacteria without requiring the introduction of exogenous DNA into the recipient cells. This demonstrates a promising advantage over current genetic editing tools that require transformation or conjugation of DNA. The engineered secretion tag can also deliver a heterologous antimicrobial toxin that kills an otherwise unsusceptible pathogen, &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt;. These results demonstrate the potential of T6SS-mediated delivery in areas including genome editing, killing drug-resistant pathogens, and studying toxin functions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443952</id><title>D-serine induces distinct transcriptomes in diverse Escherichia coli pathotypes (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.619381+00:00</updated><author><name>James P. R. Connolly</name></author><author><name>Natasha C. A. Turner</name></author><author><name>Jennifer C. Hallam</name></author><author><name>Patricia T. Rimbi</name></author><author><name>Tom Flett</name></author><author><name>Mhairi J. McCormack</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Roe</name></author><author><name>Nicky O’Boyle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Appropriate interpretation of environmental signals facilitates niche specificity in pathogenic bacteria. However, the responses of niche-specific pathogens to common host signals are poorly understood. D-serine (D-ser) is a toxic metabolite present in highly variable concentrations at different colonisation sites within the human host that we previously found is capable of inducing changes in gene expression. In this study, we made the striking observation that the global transcriptional response of three &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; pathotypes - enterohaemorrhagic &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; (EHEC), uropathogenic &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; (UPEC) and neonatal meningitis associated &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; (NMEC) - to D-ser was highly distinct. In fact, we identified no single differentially expressed gene common to all three strains. We observed the induction of ribosome-associated genes in extraintestinal pathogens UPEC and NMEC only, and the induction of purine metabolism genes in gut-restricted EHEC and UPEC indicating distinct transcriptional responses to a common signal. UPEC and NMEC encode &lt;italic&gt;dsdCXA&lt;/italic&gt; – a genetic locus required for the detoxification and hence normal growth in the presence of D-ser. Specific transcriptional responses were induced in strains accumulating D-ser (WT EHEC and UPEC/NMEC mutants lacking the D-ser-responsive transcriptional activator DsdC), corroborating the notion that D-ser is an unfavourable metabolite if not metabolized. Importantly, many of the UPEC-associated transcriptome alterations correlate with published data on the urinary transcriptome, supporting the hypothesis that D-ser sensing forms a key part of urinary niche adaptation in this pathotype. Collectively, our results demonstrate distinct pleiotropic responses to a common metabolite in diverse &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; pathotypes, with important implications for niche selectivity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pathogenic &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; comprise a group of highly specialized bacteria, some of which are capable of disseminating from the intestine and causing disease at other sites within the human host. Chemicals (metabolites) derived from the host and other microorganisms shape the behaviour of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; in different environments. Here we investigate the changes in gene expression that occur in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; strains capable (UPEC and NMEC) and incapable (EHEC) of metabolizing D-ser – a metabolite specifically enriched in the urine and in regions of the brain. We show that EHEC, UPEC and NMEC – distinct pathotypes associated with disease in the gut, bladder and brain, respectively, respond in a distinct manner to D-ser. Many of the genes affected by D-ser have been shown to be important during disease, highlighting the importance of varied responses to this common signal in host infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.443857</id><title>Transcriptomic profiling of human orbital fat and differentiating orbital fibroblasts (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.620128+00:00</updated><author><name>Dong Won Kim</name></author><author><name>Kamil Taneja</name></author><author><name>Thanh Hoang</name></author><author><name>Clayton Pio Santiago</name></author><author><name>Timothy James McCulley</name></author><author><name>Shannath Louise Merbs</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Robert Mahoney</name></author><author><name>Seth Blackshaw</name></author><author><name>Fatemeh Rajaii</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Purpose:
Orbital fat hyperplasia has a central role in the manifestations of thyroid-associated orbitopathy (TAO). To better understand the pathways involved in adipogenesis in TAO, we have used transcriptomic methods to analyze gene expression in control and TAO patients, as well as in differentiating orbital fibroblasts (OFs). 

Methods:
We performed bulk RNA sequencing (RNA-Seq) on intraconal orbital fat to compare gene expression in control and TAO patients. We treated cultured OFs derived from TAO patients with media containing dexamethasone, insulin, rosiglitazone, and isobutylmethylxanthine (IBMX) to induce adipogenesis.  We used single nuclear RNA-Seq (snRNA-Seq) profiling of treated OFs to compare gene expression over time in order to identify pathways that are involved in orbital adipogenesis in vitro and compared the dynamic patterns of gene expression identify differences in gene expression in control and TAO orbital fat.

Results:
Orbital fat from TAO and control patients segregate with principal component analysis (PCA). Numerous signaling pathways are enriched in orbital fat isolated from TAO patients.  SnRNA-Seq of orbital fibroblasts undergoing adipogenesis reveals differential expression of adipocyte-specific genes over the developmental time course. Furthermore, genes that are enriched in TAO orbital fat are also upregulated in orbital adipocytes that differentiate in vitro, while genes that are enriched in control orbital fat are enriched in orbital fibroblasts prior to differentiation.

Conclusions:
Differentiating orbital fibroblasts serve as a model to study orbital fat hyperplasia seen in TAO. We demonstrate that the insulin-like growth factor-1 receptor (IGF-1R) and Wnt signaling pathways are differentially expressed early in orbital adipogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443506</id><title>High-precision mapping of nuclear pore-chromatin interactions reveals new principles of genome organization at the nuclear envelope (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.622161+00:00</updated><author><name>Swati Tyagi</name></author><author><name>Fei Chen</name></author><author><name>Jialiang Huang</name></author><author><name>Martin W. Hetzer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The role of nuclear pore complexes (NPCs) in genome organization remains poorly characterized due to technical limitations in probing genome-wide protein-DNA interactions that are specific to the nuclear envelope. Here, we developed a sensitive method, NPC-DamID, which combines &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; reconstitution of nuclear import and DamID technology. This fixation-free method specifically identifies genomic DNA interactions at the NPCs in intact nuclei. We found that NPCs are preferentially associated with common and hierarchically arranged super-enhancers (SEs) across multiple cells and tissue types. We also uncovered phase-separated condensates at NPCs that compartmentalize and concentrate transcriptional coactivators and structural proteins at SE-regulated genes. Our results support the idea that NPCs are sites of anchoring SE regulatory hubs through their interaction with CTCF and also maintains the conformation of SEs through interaction with structural proteins of SEs like Med1 and PolII.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443880</id><title>The amino acid substitution affects cellular response to mistranslation (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.622529+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew D. Berg</name></author><author><name>Yanrui Zhu</name></author><author><name>Bianca Y. Ruiz</name></author><author><name>Raphaël Loll-Krippleber</name></author><author><name>Joshua Isaacson</name></author><author><name>Bryan-Joseph San Luis</name></author><author><name>Julie Genereaux</name></author><author><name>Charles Boone</name></author><author><name>Judit Villén</name></author><author><name>Grant W. Brown</name></author><author><name>Christopher J. Brandl</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mistranslation, the mis-incorporation of an amino acid not specified by the standard genetic code, occurs in all organisms. tRNA variants that increase mistranslation arise spontaneously and engineered tRNAs can achieve mistranslation frequencies approaching 10% in yeast and bacteria. Interestingly, human genomes contain tRNA variants with the potential to mistranslate. Cells cope with increased mistranslation through multiple mechanisms, though high levels cause proteotoxic stress. The goal of this study was to compare the genetic interactions and the impact on transcriptome and cellular growth of two tRNA variants that mistranslate at a similar frequency but create different amino acid substitutions in &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt;. One tRNA variant inserts alanine at proline codons whereas the other inserts serine for arginine. Both tRNAs decreased growth rate, with the effect being greater for arginine to serine than for proline to alanine. The tRNA that substituted serine for arginine resulted in a heat shock response. In contrast, heat shock response was minimal for proline to alanine substitution. Further demonstrating the significance of the amino acid substitution, transcriptome analysis identified unique up- and downregulated genes in response to each mistranslating tRNA. Number and extent of negative synthetic genetic interactions also differed depending upon type of mistranslation. Based on the unique responses observed for these mistranslating tRNAs, we predict that the potential of mistranslation to exacerbate diseases caused by proteotoxic stress depends on the tRNA variant. Furthermore, based on their unique transcriptomes and genetic interactions, different naturally occurring mistranslating tRNAs have the potential to negatively influence specific diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>