<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>BioRxiv preprints in molecular_biology posted in the last week with at least 5 tweets</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.439369+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/molecular_biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.01.442275</id><title>Modeling in yeast how rDNA introns slow growth and increase desiccation tolerance in lichens (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.452806+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniele Armaleo</name></author><author><name>Lilly Chiou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We define a molecular connection between ribosome biogenesis and desiccation tolerance in lichens, widespread symbioses between specialized fungi (mycobionts) and unicellular phototrophs. Our experiments test whether the introns present in the nuclear ribosomal DNA of lichen mycobionts contribute to their anhydrobiosis. Self-splicing introns are found in the rDNA of several eukaryotic microorganisms, but most introns populating lichen rDNA are unable to self-splice, being either degenerate group I introns lacking the sequences needed for catalysis, or spliceosomal introns ectopically present in rDNA. Using CRISPR, we introduced a spliceosomal intron from the rDNA of the lichen fungus &lt;italic&gt;Cladonia grayi&lt;/italic&gt; into all nuclear rDNA copies of the yeast &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt;, which lacks rDNA introns. Three intron-bearing mutants were constructed with the intron inserted either in the 18S rRNA genes, the 25S rRNA genes, or in both. The mutants removed the introns correctly but had half the rDNA genes of the wildtype strain, grew 4.4 to 6 times slower, and were 40 to 1700 times more desiccation tolerant depending on intron position and number. Intracellular trehalose, a disaccharide implicated in desiccation tolerance, was detected but not at levels compatible with the observed resistance. Extrapolating from yeast to lichen mycobionts we propose that the unique requirement for a splicing machinery by lichen rDNA introns slows down intron splicing and ribosomal assembly. This effect, and the distinctive roles played by group I &lt;italic&gt;vs&lt;/italic&gt;. spliceosomal rDNA introns, lead the environmental stress responses of lichen fungi to generate the twin lichen phenotypes of slow growth and desiccation tolerance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.04.442547</id><title>Capacity to erase gene occlusion is a defining feature distinguishing naive from primed pluripotency (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.452300+00:00</updated><author><name>Kara M. Foshay</name></author><author><name>Jae Hyun Lee</name></author><author><name>Li Zhang</name></author><author><name>Croydon J. Fernandes</name></author><author><name>Bohou Wu</name></author><author><name>Jedidiah Gaetz</name></author><author><name>Samuel W. Baker</name></author><author><name>Timothy J. Looney</name></author><author><name>Andy Peng Xiang</name></author><author><name>Guoping Fan</name></author><author><name>Bruce T. Lahn</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pluripotent stem cells can exist in either the naive state representing a developmental blank slate or the downstream primed state poised for differentiation. Currently, known differences between these two states are mostly phenomenological, and none can adequately explain why the two states should differ in developmental priming. Gene occlusion is a mode of epigenetic inactivation that renders genes unresponsive to their cognate transcriptional activators. It plays a crucial role in lineage restriction. Here, we report that a defining feature distinguishing the two pluripotent states lies in the ability of naive but not primed cells to erase occlusion. This “deocclusion” capacity requires Esrrb, a gene expressed only in the naive but not primed state. Notably, Esrrb silencing in the primed state is itself due to occlusion. Collectively, our data argue that the Esrrb-dependent deocclusion capacity in naive cells is key for sustaining naive pluripotency, and the loss of this capacity in the primed state via the occlusion of Esrrb poises cells for differentiation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.05.442738</id><title>A spoonful of disorder regulates interactions within Stress Granules and Processing Bodies (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.449915+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrea Vandelli</name></author><author><name>Fernando Cid Samper</name></author><author><name>Marc Torrent Burgas</name></author><author><name>Natalia Sanchez de Groot</name></author><author><name>Gian Gaetano Tartaglia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Condensation, or liquid-like phase separation, is a phenomenon indispensable for the spatiotemporal regulation of molecules within the cell. Recent studies indicate that the composition and molecular organization of phase-separated organelles such as Stress Granules (SGs) and Processing Bodies (PBs) are highly variable and dynamic. A dense contact network involving both RNAs and proteins controls the formation of SGs and PBs and an intricate molecular architecture, at present poorly understood, guarantees that these assemblies sense and adapt to different stresses and environmental changes. Here, we investigated the physico-chemical properties of SGs and PBs components and studied the architecture of their interaction networks. We observed that proteins and RNAs establishing the largest amount of contacts have distinct structural characteristics. More specifically, we found that structural disorder is enriched in all protein-RNA, protein-protein and RNA-RNA interactions. Intriguingly, enrichment in the disorder of proteins is linked to increased number of interactions with single-stranded regions in RNAs. Our findings support the hypothesis that SGs and PBs can quickly assemble and disassemble thanks to the activity of unfolded domains in proteins and single-stranded regions in RNAs, guaranteeing the formation of dynamic contacts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.01.442262</id><title>The potential of aquatic haematophagous, liquidosomatophagous and macrophagous leeches as a tool for iDNA characterisation (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.449503+00:00</updated><author><name>Christina Lynggaard</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Oceguera-Figueroa</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Kvist</name></author><author><name>M Thomas P Gilbert</name></author><author><name>Kristine Bohmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Leeches play important roles in food webs due to their abundance, diversity and feeding habits. Studies using invertebrate-derived DNA (iDNA) extracted from leech gut contents to target vertebrate DNA have focused on the Indo-Pacific region and mainly leveraged the leech family Haemadipsidae, composed of haematophagous terrestrial leeches, while the aquatic haematophagous, liquidosomatophagous and macrophagous counterparts have largely been disregarded. While there is general knowledge regarding the taxonomic groups that leeches prefer to feed on, detailed taxonomic resolution is still missing and therefore, their potential use for monitoring animals is not known. In this study, 116 non-haemadipsid leeches belonging to 12 species and spanning the three feeding habits were collected in Mexico and Canada. We used DNA metabarcoding to investigate their diet and assess their potential use for vertebrate monitoring. We detected vertebrate taxa from five orders including fish, turtles and birds in the diet of the aquatic haematophagous leeches; eight invertebrate orders of annelids, arthropods and molluscs in the liquidosomatophagous leeches; and ten orders of invertebrates belonging to Arthropoda and Annelida, as well as one vertebrate and one parasitic nematode, in the macrophagous leeches. These results show the potential use of iDNA from the gut content of aquatic haematophagous leeches for retrieving vertebrate taxa, and from macrophagous and liquidosomatophagous counterparts for invertebrates. Our study provides information about the dietary range of the freshwater leeches and the non-haemadipsid terrestrial leech and proof-of-concept for the use of non-haemadipsid leeches for animal monitoring, expanding our knowledge of the use of iDNA from leech gut contents to North America.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.02.442342</id><title>Cytosolic aggregation of mitochondrial proteins disrupts cellular homeostasis by stimulating other proteins aggregation (41 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.448803+00:00</updated><author><name>Urszula Nowicka</name></author><author><name>Piotr Chroscicki</name></author><author><name>Karen Stroobants</name></author><author><name>Maria Sladowska</name></author><author><name>Michal Turek</name></author><author><name>Barbara Uszczynska-Ratajczak</name></author><author><name>Rishika Kundra</name></author><author><name>Tomasz Goral</name></author><author><name>Michele Perni</name></author><author><name>Christopher M. Dobson</name></author><author><name>Michele Vendruscolo</name></author><author><name>Agnieszka Chacinska</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mitochondria are organelles with their own genomes but rely on the import of nuclear-encoded proteins synthesized by cytosolic ribosomes. Therefore, it is important to understand whether failures in the mitochondrial uptake of these nuclear-encoded proteins may cause proteotoxic stress, and to identify which response mechanisms may be in place to respond to it. Here, we report that upon mitochondrial protein import impairment, high-risk precursor and immature forms of mitochondrial proteins form aberrant deposits in the cytosol. In turn, these deposits cause further cytosolic accumulation of other mitochondrial and disease-related proteins, including α-synuclein and amyloid β. This aberrant accumulation triggers a cytosolic protein homeostasis imbalance that is accompanied by specific molecular chaperone responses, both at the transcriptomic and protein levels. Our results provide evidence that mitochondrial dysfunction, and specifically protein import defects, can contribute to protein homeostasis impairment, thus revealing a possible molecular mechanism for mitochondrial involvement in neurodegenerative diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>