<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>BioRxiv preprints in molecular_biology posted in the last week with at least 5 tweets</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.036182+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/molecular_biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.04.442547</id><title>Capacity to erase gene occlusion is a defining feature distinguishing naive from primed pluripotency (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.037104+00:00</updated><author><name>Kara M. Foshay</name></author><author><name>Jae Hyun Lee</name></author><author><name>Li Zhang</name></author><author><name>Croydon J. Fernandes</name></author><author><name>Bohou Wu</name></author><author><name>Jedidiah Gaetz</name></author><author><name>Samuel W. Baker</name></author><author><name>Timothy J. Looney</name></author><author><name>Andy Peng Xiang</name></author><author><name>Guoping Fan</name></author><author><name>Bruce T. Lahn</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pluripotent stem cells can exist in either the naive state representing a developmental blank slate or the downstream primed state poised for differentiation. Currently, known differences between these two states are mostly phenomenological, and none can adequately explain why the two states should differ in developmental priming. Gene occlusion is a mode of epigenetic inactivation that renders genes unresponsive to their cognate transcriptional activators. It plays a crucial role in lineage restriction. Here, we report that a defining feature distinguishing the two pluripotent states lies in the ability of naive but not primed cells to erase occlusion. This “deocclusion” capacity requires Esrrb, a gene expressed only in the naive but not primed state. Notably, Esrrb silencing in the primed state is itself due to occlusion. Collectively, our data argue that the Esrrb-dependent deocclusion capacity in naive cells is key for sustaining naive pluripotency, and the loss of this capacity in the primed state via the occlusion of Esrrb poises cells for differentiation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.05.442738</id><title>A spoonful of disorder regulates interactions within Stress Granules and Processing Bodies (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.036715+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrea Vandelli</name></author><author><name>Fernando Cid Samper</name></author><author><name>Marc Torrent Burgas</name></author><author><name>Natalia Sanchez de Groot</name></author><author><name>Gian Gaetano Tartaglia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Condensation, or liquid-like phase separation, is a phenomenon indispensable for the spatiotemporal regulation of molecules within the cell. Recent studies indicate that the composition and molecular organization of phase-separated organelles such as Stress Granules (SGs) and Processing Bodies (PBs) are highly variable and dynamic. A dense contact network involving both RNAs and proteins controls the formation of SGs and PBs and an intricate molecular architecture, at present poorly understood, guarantees that these assemblies sense and adapt to different stresses and environmental changes. Here, we investigated the physico-chemical properties of SGs and PBs components and studied the architecture of their interaction networks. We observed that proteins and RNAs establishing the largest amount of contacts have distinct structural characteristics. More specifically, we found that structural disorder is enriched in all protein-RNA, protein-protein and RNA-RNA interactions. Intriguingly, enrichment in the disorder of proteins is linked to increased number of interactions with single-stranded regions in RNAs. Our findings support the hypothesis that SGs and PBs can quickly assemble and disassemble thanks to the activity of unfolded domains in proteins and single-stranded regions in RNAs, guaranteeing the formation of dynamic contacts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>