<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.950545+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.21263703</id><title>AnthropoAge, a novel approach to integrate body composition into the estimation of biological age (76 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.951508+00:00</updated><author><name>Carlos A. Fermín-Martínez</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Márquez-Salinas</name></author><author><name>Enrique C. Guerra</name></author><author><name>Lilian Zavala-Romero</name></author><author><name>Neftali Eduardo Antonio-Villa</name></author><author><name>Luisa Fernández-Chirino</name></author><author><name>Eduardo Sandoval-Colin</name></author><author><name>Daphne Abigail Barquera-Guevara</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Campos Muñoz</name></author><author><name>Luis Miguel Gutiérrez-Robledo</name></author><author><name>Omar Yaxmehen Bello-Chavolla</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Methods to estimate biological age (BA) capture different aspects of aging. Here, we consider the role of changes in body composition related to aging as a starting point to incorporate anthropometry into the estimation of BA. To that end, we developed AnthropoAge, a metric to estimate 10-year mortality risk as a proxy of BA using anthropometric and linked mortality data from NHANES-III (n=11,865) and validated it in NHANES-IV (n=7,065). We identified that thigh circumference, arm circumference, body-mass index (BMI), waist-to-height ratio (WHtR) and arm length were useful to predict BA in men, whilst weight, thigh circumference, subscapular and tricipital skinfolds and WHtR in women. We also developed a simplified version of AnthropoAge (S-AnthropoAge) which used only BMI and WHtR, with strong concordance with the complete metric. Both AnthropoAge and S-AnthropoAge were useful to predict 10-year mortality independent of ethnicity, sex, and comorbidities. In comparison to PhenoAge, AnthropoAge/S-AnthropoAge were superior for prediction of cardiovascular, cerebrovascular, cancer-related and nephritis/nephrosis related mortality risk in contrast with other causes. Accelerated aging metrics AnthropoAgeAccel/S-AnthropoAgeAccel identified males with phenotypes of decreased lean and fat mass and females with phenotypes of increased fat mass and increased abdominal adiposity, which likely reflected sexual dimorphisms related to accelerated body composition aging. When jointly assessing PhenoAge and AnthropoAge/S-AnthropoAge, we identified unique aging trajectories with differential mortality risk and comorbidity clustering. AnthropoAge is a useful proxy of BA, which captures cause-specific mortality risk; assessing aging using different BA measures may be useful to better characterize the heterogeneity of the aging process.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.21263703" rel="alternate" title="AnthropoAge, a novel approach to integrate body composition into the estimation of biological age (76 tweets)"/><category term="Geriatric Medicine"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.21263680</id><title>Xylazine Spreads Across the US: A Growing Component of the Increasingly Synthetic and Polysubstance Overdose Crisis (44 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.951928+00:00</updated><author><name>Joseph Friedman</name></author><author><name>Fernando Montero Castillo</name></author><author><name>Phillippe Bourgois</name></author><author><name>Rafik Wahbi</name></author><author><name>Daniel Dye</name></author><author><name>David Goodman</name></author><author><name>Chelsea Shover</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recent sharp exacerbations of the US overdose crisis have been linked to systemic polysubstance use and potent synthetic compounds in numerous drug classes. Xylazine is a veterinary tranquilizer, long noted in the opioid supply of Puerto Rico, and more recently Philadelphia. Yet its national growth over time, geographic distribution, and potential role in the shifting US overdose risk environment are poorly characterized.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this sequential mixed methods study, xylazine was increasingly observed by our ethnographic team over many years of intensive participant observation fieldwork in Philadelphia among drug sellers and people who inject drugs (PWID). Subsequently, we systematically searched for records describing xylazine-involved overdose mortality across the US and assessed time trends and overlap with other drugs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 10 jurisdictions—representing all 4 US Census Regions—xylazine was found to be increasingly implicated in overdose mortality, rising from 0.36% of deaths in 2015 to 6.7% in 2020. The highest xylazine prevalence in the recent data was observed in Philadelphia, (25.8% of deaths), followed by Maryland (19.3%) and Connecticut (10.2%). Illicitly-manufactured-fentanyls were present in 98.4% of xylazine-involved-overdose-deaths— suggesting a strong ecological link—as well as cocaine (45.4%), benzodiazepines (28.4%), heroin (23.3%), and alcohol (19.7%). PWID in Philadelphia described xylazine as a sought-after adulterant that improves euphoria and lengthens the short duration of fentanyl injections, in particular. They also linked it to increased risk of soft tissue infection and overdose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We summarize evidence that xylazine is increasingly implicated in overdose deaths across the US and is linked to the proliferation of illicitly-manufactured-fentanyls. We document hypothesis-generating ethnographic accounts linking it to health risks for PWID. Nevertheless, many jurisdictions do not routinely test for xylazine, and it is not tracked in federal overdose statistics. Further efforts are needed to provide PWID with services that can help to minimize additional risks associated with a shifting drug supply.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.21263680" rel="alternate" title="Xylazine Spreads Across the US: A Growing Component of the Increasingly Synthetic and Polysubstance Overdose Crisis (44 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.21263987</id><title>Leveraging genomic diversity for discovery in an EHR-linked biobank: the UCLA ATLAS Community Health Initiative (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.952528+00:00</updated><author><name>Ruth Johnson</name></author><author><name>Yi Ding</name></author><author><name>Vidhya Venkateswaran</name></author><author><name>Arjun Bhattacharya</name></author><author><name>Alec Chiu</name></author><author><name>Tommer Schwarz</name></author><author><name>Malika Freund</name></author><author><name>Lingyu Zhan</name></author><author><name>Kathryn S. Burch</name></author><author><name>Christa Caggiano</name></author><author><name>Brian Hill</name></author><author><name>Nadav Rakocz</name></author><author><name>Brunilda Balliu</name></author><author><name>Jae Hoon Sul</name></author><author><name>Noah Zaitlen</name></author><author><name>Valerie A. Arboleda</name></author><author><name>Eran Halperin</name></author><author><name>Sriram Sankararaman</name></author><author><name>Manish J. Butte</name></author><author><name>Clara Lajonchere</name></author><author><name>Daniel H. Geschwind</name></author><author><name>Bogdan Pasaniuc</name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Large medical centers located in urban areas such as Los Angeles care for a diverse patient population and offer the potential to study the interplay between genomic ancestry and social determinants of health within a single medical system. Here, we introduce the UCLA ATLAS Community Health Initiative – a biobank of genomic data linked with de-identified electronic health records (EHRs) of UCLA Health patients. We leverage the unique genomic diversity of the patient population in ATLAS to explore the interplay between self-reported race/ethnicity and genetic ancestry within a disease context using phenotypes extracted from the EHR. First, we identify an extensive amount of continental and subcontinental genomic diversity within the ATLAS data that is consistent with the global diversity of Los Angeles; this includes clusters of ATLAS individuals corresponding to individuals with Korean, Japanese, Filipino, and Middle Eastern genomic ancestries. Most importantly, we find that common diseases and traits stratify across genomic ancestry clusters, thus suggesting their utility in understanding disease biology across diverse individuals. Next, we showcase the power of genetic data linked with EHR to perform ancestry-specific genome and phenome-wide scans to identify genetic factors for a variety of EHR-derived phenotypes (phecodes). For example, we find ancestry-specific associations for liver disease, and link the genetic variants with neurological and neoplastic phenotypes primarily within individuals of admixed ancestries. Overall, our results underscore the utility of studying the genomes of diverse individuals through biobank-scale genotyping efforts linked with EHR-based phenotyping.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.21263987" rel="alternate" title="Leveraging genomic diversity for discovery in an EHR-linked biobank: the UCLA ATLAS Community Health Initiative (26 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.21263909</id><title>Pervasive Downward Bias in Estimates of Liability Scale Heritability in GWAS Meta-Analysis: A Simple Solution (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.953015+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew D. Grotzinger</name></author><author><name>Javier de la Fuente</name></author><author><name>Michel G. Nivard</name></author><author><name>Elliot M. Tucker-Drob</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SNP heritability is a fundamental quantity in the genetic analysis of complex traits. For binary phenotypes, in which the continuous distribution of risk in the population is unobserved, observed-scale heritabilities must be transformed to the more interpretable liability-scale. We demonstrate here that the field standard approach for performing the liability conversion can downwardly bias estimates by as much as ∼20% in simulation and ∼30% in real data. These attenuated estimates stem from the standard approach failing to appropriately account for varying levels of ascertainment across the cohorts comprising the meta-analysis. We formally derive a simple procedure for incorporating cohort-specific ascertainment based on the summation of effective sample sizes across the contributing cohorts, and confirm via simulation that it produces unbiased estimates of liability-scale heritability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.21263909" rel="alternate" title="Pervasive Downward Bias in Estimates of Liability Scale Heritability in GWAS Meta-Analysis: A Simple Solution (24 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.21264161</id><title>A Machine Learning Approach to Predict 5-year Risk for Complications in Type 1 Diabetes (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.953281+00:00</updated><author><name>Naba Al-Sari</name></author><author><name>Svetlana Kutuzova</name></author><author><name>Tommi Suvitaival</name></author><author><name>Peter Henriksen</name></author><author><name>Flemming Pociot</name></author><author><name>Peter Rossing</name></author><author><name>Douglas McCloskey</name></author><author><name>Cristina Legido-Quigley</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;OBJECTIVE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our aim was to apply state-of-the-art machine learning algorithms to predict the risk of future progression to diabetes complications, including diabetic kidney disease (≥30% decline in eGFR) and diabetic retinopathy (mild, moderate or severe).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using data in a cohort of 537 adults with type 1 diabetes we predicted diabetes complications emerging during a median follow-up of 5.4 years. Prediction models were computed first with clinical risk factors at baseline (17 measures) and then with clinical risk factors and blood-derived metabolomics and lipidomics data (965 molecular features) at baseline. Participants were first classified into two groups: type 1 diabetes stable (n=195) or type 1 diabetes with progression to diabetes complications (n=190). Furthermore, progression of diabetic kidney disease (≥30% decline in eGFR; n=79) and diabetic retinopathy (mild, moderate or severe; n=111) were predicted in two complication-specific models. Models were compared by 5-fold cross-validated area under the receiver operating characteristic (AUROC) curves. The Shapley additive explanations algorithm was used for feature selection and for interpreting the models. Accuracy, precision, recall, and F-score were used to evaluate clinical utility.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;RESULTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;During a median follow-up of 5.4 years, 79 (21 %) of the participants (mean±SD: age 54.8 ± 13.7 years) progressed in diabetic kidney disease and 111 (29 %) of the participants progressed to diabetic retinopathy. The predictive models for diabetic kidney disease progression were highly accurate with clinical risk factors: the accuracy of 0.95 and AUROC of 0.92 (95% CI 0.857;0.995) was achieved, further improved to the accuracy of 0.98 and AUROC of 0.99 (95% CI 0.876;0.997) when omics-based predictors were included. The predictive panel composition was: albuminuria, retinopathy, estimated glomerular filtration rate, hemoglobin A&lt;sub&gt;1c&lt;/sub&gt;, and six metabolites (five identified as ribitol, ribonic acid, myo-inositol, 2,4- and 3,4-dihydroxybutanoic acids).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Models for diabetic retinopathy progression were less predictive with clinical risk predictors at, AUROC of 0.81 (95% CI 0.754;0.958) and with omics included at AUROC of 0.87 (95% CI 0.781;0.996) curve. The final retinopathy-panel included: hemoglobin A&lt;sub&gt;1c&lt;/sub&gt;, albuminuria, mild degree of retinopathy, and seven metabolites, including one ceramide and the 3,4-dihydroxybutanoic acid).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;CONCLUSIONS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we demonstrate the application of machine learning to effectively predict five-year progression of complications, in particular diabetic kidney disease, using a panel of known clinical risk factors in combination with blood small molecules. Further replication of this machine learning tool in a real-world context or a clinical trial will facilitate its implementation in the clinic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.21264161" rel="alternate" title="A Machine Learning Approach to Predict 5-year Risk for Complications in Type 1 Diabetes (15 tweets)"/><category term="Endocrinology (including Diabetes Mellitus and Metabolic Disease)"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.21264206</id><title>Enhancing the brain’s emotion regulation capacity with a randomised trial of a 5-week heart rate variability biofeedback intervention (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.953550+00:00</updated><author><name>Kaoru Nashiro</name></author><author><name>Jungwon Min</name></author><author><name>Hyun Joo Yoo</name></author><author><name>Christine Cho</name></author><author><name>Shelby L. Bachman</name></author><author><name>Shubir Dutt</name></author><author><name>Julian F. Thayer</name></author><author><name>Paul Lehrer</name></author><author><name>Tiantian Feng</name></author><author><name>Noah Mercer</name></author><author><name>Padideh Nasseri</name></author><author><name>Diana Wang</name></author><author><name>Catie Chang</name></author><author><name>Vasilis Z. Marmarelis</name></author><author><name>Shri Narayanan</name></author><author><name>Daniel A. Nation</name></author><author><name>Mara Mather</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Heart rate variability is a robust biomarker of emotional well-being, consistent with the shared brain networks regulating emotion regulation and heart rate. While high heart rate oscillatory activity clearly indicates healthy regulatory brain systems, can increasing this oscillatory activity also enhance brain function? To test this possibility, we randomly assigned 106 young adult participants to one of two 5-week interventions involving daily biofeedback that either increased heart rate oscillations (Osc+ condition) or had little effect on heart rate oscillations (Osc- condition) and examined effects on brain activity during rest and during regulating emotion. In this healthy cohort, the two conditions did not differentially affect anxiety, depression or mood. However, the Osc+ intervention increased low-frequency heart rate variability and increased brain oscillatory dynamics and functional connectivity in emotion-related resting-state networks. It also increased down-regulation of activity in somatosensory brain regions during an emotion regulation task. The Osc- intervention did not have these effects. These findings indicate that heart rate oscillatory activity not only reflects the current state of regulatory brain systems but also changes how the brain operates beyond the moments of high oscillatory activity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.21264206" rel="alternate" title="Enhancing the brain’s emotion regulation capacity with a randomised trial of a 5-week heart rate variability biofeedback intervention (13 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.17.21262268</id><title>First trimester gut microbiome induces Inflammation-dependent gestational diabetes phenotype in mice (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.953905+00:00</updated><author><name>Yishay Pinto</name></author><author><name>Sigal Frishman</name></author><author><name>Sondra Turjeman</name></author><author><name>Adi Eshel</name></author><author><name>Meital Nuriel-Ohayon</name></author><author><name>Oren Ziv</name></author><author><name>William Walters</name></author><author><name>Julie Parsonnet</name></author><author><name>Catherine Ley</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth L. Johnson</name></author><author><name>Ron Schweitzer</name></author><author><name>Soliman Khatib</name></author><author><name>Faiga Magzal</name></author><author><name>Snait Tamir</name></author><author><name>Kinneret Tenenbaum Gavish</name></author><author><name>Samuli Rautava</name></author><author><name>Seppo Salminen</name></author><author><name>Erika Isolauri</name></author><author><name>Or Yariv</name></author><author><name>Yoav Peled</name></author><author><name>Eran Poran</name></author><author><name>Joseph Pardo</name></author><author><name>Rony Chen</name></author><author><name>Moshe Hod</name></author><author><name>Ruth E. Ley</name></author><author><name>Betty Schwartz</name></author><author><name>Eran Hadar</name></author><author><name>Yoram Louzoun</name></author><author><name>Omry Koren</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gestational diabetes mellitus (GDM) is a condition in which non-diabetic women are diagnosed with glucose intolerance during pregnancy, typically in the second trimester. GDM can lead to a wide range of obstetrical and metabolic complications for both mother and neonate&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. Early identification of GDM risk, along with a better understanding of its pathophysiology during the first trimester of pregnancy, may be effective in reducing GDM incidence, as well as its associated short and long term morbidities&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. Here, we comprehensively profiled the gut microbiome, metabolome, inflammatory cytokines, nutrition and clinical records of 394 women during the first trimester of pregnancy. We found elevated levels of proinflammatory serum cytokines in those who later developed GDM. The women’s stool samples were also characterized by decreased levels of several fecal short-chain fatty acids and altered microbiome. We next tested the hypothesis that differences in GDM-associated microbial composition during the first trimester drove inflammation and insulin-resistance. Stool samples collected early in pregnancy from women from three populations who did and did not later develop GDM were transplanted to germ-free mice and confirmed that both inflammation and insulin-resistance are induced by the microbiome of pregnant women more than 10 weeks prior to GDM diagnosis. Following these observations, we used a machine-learning approach to predict GDM based on first trimester clinical, microbial and inflammatory markers. Our model showed high predictive accuracy. Overall, our results suggest that the gut microbiome of women in the first trimester plays a remarkable role in inflammation-induced GDM pathogenesis and point to dozens of GDM markers during the first trimester of pregnancy, some of which may be targets for therapeutic intervention.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.17.21262268" rel="alternate" title="First trimester gut microbiome induces Inflammation-dependent gestational diabetes phenotype in mice (12 tweets)"/><category term="Obstetrics and Gynecology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.21264208</id><title>Integration of genetic colocalizations with physiological and pharmacological perturbations identifies cardiometabolic disease genes (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.954323+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael J. Gloudemans</name></author><author><name>Brunilda Balliu</name></author><author><name>Daniel Nachun</name></author><author><name>Matthew G. Durrant</name></author><author><name>Erik Ingelsson</name></author><author><name>Martin Wabitsch</name></author><author><name>Thomas Quertermous</name></author><author><name>Stephen B. Montgomery</name></author><author><name>Joshua W. Knowles</name></author><author><name>Ivan Carcamo-Orive</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Identification of causal genes for polygenic human diseases has been extremely challenging, and our understanding of how physiological and pharmacological stimuli modulate genetic risk at disease-associated loci is limited. Specifically, insulin resistance (IR), a common feature of cardiometabolic disease, including type 2 diabetes, obesity, and dyslipidemia, lacks well-powered GWAS, and therefore few associated loci and causal genes have been identified.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we perform and integrate LD-adjusted colocalization analyses across nine cardiometabolic traits combined with eQTLs and sQTLs from five metabolically relevant human tissues (subcutaneous and visceral adipose, skeletal muscle, liver, and pancreas). We identify 470 colocalized loci and prioritize 207 loci with a single colocalized gene. To elucidate upstream regulators and functional mechanisms for these genes, we integrate their transcriptional responses to 21 physiological and pharmacological cardiometabolic regulators in human adipocytes, hepatocytes, and skeletal muscle cells, and map their protein-protein interactions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our use of transcriptional responses under metabolic perturbations to contextualize genetic associations from our state-of-the-art colocalization approach provides a list of likely causal genes and their upstream regulators in the context of IR-associated cardiometabolic risk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.21264208" rel="alternate" title="Integration of genetic colocalizations with physiological and pharmacological perturbations identifies cardiometabolic disease genes (12 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.21263381</id><title>Three month FVC change: a trial endpoint for IPF based on individual participant data meta-analysis (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.954631+00:00</updated><author><name>Fasihul A Khan</name></author><author><name>Iain Stewart</name></author><author><name>Samuel Moss</name></author><author><name>Laura Fabbri</name></author><author><name>Karen A. Robinson</name></author><author><name>Simon Johnson</name></author><author><name>R Gisli Jenkins</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Rationale&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Novel therapies for idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF) are in development, but there remains uncertainty about the optimal trial endpoint. An earlier endpoint would enable assessment of a greater number of therapies in adaptive trial designs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individual participant data (IPD) from placebo arms of interventional trials were sought to determine whether short-term changes in forced vital capacity (FVC), gas transfer for carbon monoxide (DL&lt;sub&gt;CO&lt;/sub&gt;) and six-minute walk distance (6MWD) could act as surrogate endpoints to accelerate early-phase trials in IPF.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic databases were searched on 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; December 2020, and IPD were sought and meta-analysed. The primary outcome was overall mortality according to baseline and/or three-month change in either FVC, DL&lt;sub&gt;CO&lt;/sub&gt; or 6MWD, with a secondary outcome of disease progression at 12 months, adjusted for age, sex, smoking status and baseline physiology.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Measurements and main results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;IPD was available for 10/23 eligible studies totalling 1819 participants. Baseline and three-month change in all physiological variables were independently associated with disease outcomes. A 2.5% relative decline in FVC over three months was associated with mortality (adjusted hazard ratio 1.14, 95%CI 1.06;1.24, I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 59.9%) and disease progression (adjusted odds ratio 1.29; 95%CI 1.18;1.40, I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;=67%). Optimal thresholds for three-month change in FVC for distinguishing disease outcomes were identified.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;IPD meta-analysis of trial placebo arms demonstrated three-month change in physiological variables, particularly FVC, were associated with mortality and disease progression among individuals with untreated IPF. FVC change over three months may hold potential as a surrogate endpoint in IPF interventional adaptive trials.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.21263381" rel="alternate" title="Three month FVC change: a trial endpoint for IPF based on individual participant data meta-analysis (12 tweets)"/><category term="Respiratory Medicine"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.15.21263636</id><title>Ontogeny of plasma lipid metabolism in pregnancy and early childhood: a longitudinal population study (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.954835+00:00</updated><author><name>Satvika Burugupalli</name></author><author><name>Adam Alexander T. Smith</name></author><author><name>Gavriel Olshansky</name></author><author><name>Kevin Huynh</name></author><author><name>Corey Giles</name></author><author><name>Sudip Paul</name></author><author><name>Anh Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Thy Duong</name></author><author><name>Natalie Mellett</name></author><author><name>Michelle Cinel</name></author><author><name>Sartaj Ahmad Mir</name></author><author><name>Li Chen</name></author><author><name>Markus R. Wenk</name></author><author><name>Neerja Karnani</name></author><author><name>Fiona Collier</name></author><author><name>Richard Saffery</name></author><author><name>Peter Vuillermin</name></author><author><name>Anne-Louise Ponsonby</name></author><author><name>David Burgner</name></author><author><name>Peter J. Meikle</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is mounting evidence that &lt;italic&gt;in utero&lt;/italic&gt; and early life exposures may predispose an individual to metabolic disorders in later life; and dysregulation of lipid metabolism is critical in such outcomes. However, there is limited knowledge about lipid metabolism and factors causing lipid dysregulation in early life that could result in adverse health outcomes in later life. In this study, we aim to understand the lipid metabolism in pregnancy, and from birth to four years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods and findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We performed comprehensive lipid profiling of 1074 mother-child dyads in the Barwon Infant Study (BIS), a population based pre-birth cohort and measured 776 distinct lipid species across 42 lipid classes using ultra high-performance liquid chromatography (UHPLC). We measured lipids in 1032 maternal serum samples at 28 weeks’ gestation, 893 cord serum samples at birth, 793, 735, and 511 plasma samples at six, twelve months, and four years, respectively. The lipidome differed between mother and newborn and changed markedly with increasing postnatal age. Cord serum was enriched with long chain poly-unsaturated fatty acids (LC-PUFAs), and corresponding cholesteryl esters relative to the maternal serum. Alkenyl-phosphatidylethanolamine species containing LC-PUFAs increased with postnatal age, whereas the corresponding lysophospholipids and triglycerides decreased. We performed regression analyses to investigate the associations of cord serum lipid species with birth factors: gestational age, birth weight, mode of birth and duration of labor. Majority of the cord serum lipids were strongly associated with gestational age and birth weight, with most lipids showing opposing associations. Each mode of birth showed an independent association with cord serum lipids.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There were marked changes in the plasma lipidome over the first four years of life. This study sheds light on lipid metabolism in infancy and early childhood and provide a framework to define the relationship between lipid metabolism and health outcomes in early childhood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This work was supported by the A*STAR-NHMRC joint call funding (1711624031).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.15.21263636" rel="alternate" title="Ontogeny of plasma lipid metabolism in pregnancy and early childhood: a longitudinal population study (11 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.21256632</id><title>Relative timing of RSV epidemics in summer 2021 across the US was similar to a typical RSV season (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.955407+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhe Zheng</name></author><author><name>Joshua L. Warren</name></author><author><name>Iris Artin</name></author><author><name>Virginia E. Pitzer</name></author><author><name>Daniel M. Weinberger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We evaluated the timing of respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) epidemics in 2021 using Google search data. Despite the unusual out-of-season timing, the relative timing of RSV epidemics between states in 2021 shared a similar spatial pattern with typical RSV seasons. These insights can inform prophylaxis administration and planning of clinical trials.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.21256632" rel="alternate" title="Relative timing of RSV epidemics in summer 2021 across the US was similar to a typical RSV season (11 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.21264079</id><title>Quality control and removal of technical variation of NMR metabolic biomarker data in ∼120,000 UK Biobank participants (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.956346+00:00</updated><author><name>Scott C. Ritchie</name></author><author><name>Praveen Surendran</name></author><author><name>Savita Karthikeyan</name></author><author><name>Samuel A. Lambert</name></author><author><name>Thomas Bolton</name></author><author><name>Lisa Pennells</name></author><author><name>John Danesh</name></author><author><name>Emanuele Di Angelantonio</name></author><author><name>Adam S. Butterworth</name></author><author><name>Michael Inouye</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Metabolic biomarker data quantified by nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy has recently become available in UK Biobank. Here, we describe procedures for quality control and removal of technical variation for this biomarker data, comprising 249 circulating metabolites, lipids, and lipoprotein sub-fractions on approximately 121,000 participants. We identify and characterise technical and biological factors associated with individual biomarkers and find that linear effects on individual biomarkers can combine in a non-linear fashion for 61 composite biomarkers and 81 biomarker ratios. We create an R package, ukbnmr, for extracting and normalising the metabolic biomarker data, then use ukbnmr to remove unwanted variation from the UK Biobank data. We make available code for re-deriving the 61 composite biomarkers and 81 ratios, and for further derivation of 76 additional biomarker ratios of potential biological significance. Finally, we demonstrate that removal of technical variation leads to increased signal for genetic and epidemiological studies of the NMR metabolic biomarkers in UK Biobank.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.21264079" rel="alternate" title="Quality control and removal of technical variation of NMR metabolic biomarker data in ∼120,000 UK Biobank participants (10 tweets)"/><category term="Cardiovascular Medicine"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.460915</id><title>Glucosyltransferase-dependent and independent effects of Clostridioides difficile toxins during infection (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.956787+00:00</updated><author><name>F. Christopher Peritore-Galve</name></author><author><name>John A. Shupe</name></author><author><name>Rory J. Cave</name></author><author><name>M. Kay Washington</name></author><author><name>Sarah A. Kuehne</name></author><author><name>D. Borden Lacy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Clostridioides difficile&lt;/italic&gt; infection (CDI) is the leading cause of nosocomial diarrhea and pseudomembranous colitis in the USA. In addition to these symptoms, patients with CDI can develop severe inflammation and tissue damage, resulting in life-threatening toxic megacolon. CDI is mediated by two large homologous protein toxins, TcdA and TcdB, that bind and hijack receptors to enter host cells where they use glucosyltransferase (GT) enzymes to inactivate Rho family GTPases. GT-dependent intoxication elicits cytopathic changes, cytokine production, and apoptosis. At higher concentrations TcdB induces GT-independent necrosis in cells and tissue by stimulating production of reactive oxygen species via recruitment of the NADPH oxidase complex. Although GT-independent necrosis has been observed &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, the relevance of this mechanism during CDI has remained an outstanding question in the field. In this study we generated novel &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; toxin mutants in the hypervirulent BI/NAP1/PCR-ribotype 027 R20291 strain to test the hypothesis that GT-independent epithelial damage occurs during CDI. Using the mouse model of CDI, we observed that epithelial damage occurs through a GT-independent process that is does not involve immune cell influx. The GT-activity of either toxin was sufficient to cause severe edema and inflammation, yet GT activity of both toxins was necessary to produce severe watery diarrhea. These results indicate that both TcdA and TcdB contribute to infection when present. Further, while inactivating GT activity of &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; toxins may suppress diarrhea and deleterious GT-dependent immune responses, the potential of severe GT-independent epithelial damage merits consideration when developing toxin-based therapeutics against CDI.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SIGNIFICANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Clostridioides difficile&lt;/italic&gt; is the leading cause of antibiotic-associated diarrhea in hospitals worldwide. This bacterium produces two virulence factors, TcdA and TcdB, which are large protein toxins that enter host colon cells to cause inflammation, fluid secretion, and cell death. The enzymatic domain of TcdB is a target for novel &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; infection (CDI) therapeutics since it is considered the major factor in causing severe CDI. However, necrotic cell death due to non-enzymatic TcdB-host interactions have been reported in cell culture and intoxicated tissue. Here, we generated &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; strains with enzyme-inactive toxins to evaluate the role of each toxin in an animal model of CDI. We observe an additive role for TcdA and TcdB in disease and both glucosyltransferase-dependent and independent phenotypes. These findings are expected to inform the development of toxin-based CDI therapeutics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.460915" rel="alternate" title="Glucosyltransferase-dependent and independent effects of Clostridioides difficile toxins during infection (9 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.21264038</id><title>Dissecting the Epigenomic Differences between Smoking and Nicotine Dependence in a Veteran Cohort (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.957011+00:00</updated><author><name>Sheila Tiemi Nagamatsu</name></author><author><name>Robert H Pietrzak</name></author><author><name>Ke Xu</name></author><author><name>John H Krystal</name></author><author><name>Joel Gelernter</name></author><author><name>Janitza Liz Montalvo-Ortiz</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Smoking is a serious public health issue linked to more than 8 million deaths per year worldwide. It also may lead to nicotine dependence (ND). Smoking can induce long-lasting epigenetic changes. Although epigenetic alterations related to tobacco smoke have been largely studied, few works have investigated ND and its interaction with smoking status (SS).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We investigated the peripheral epigenomic profile of SS and ND in a U.S. male veteran cohort.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;DNA from saliva was collected from 1,135 European American (EA) male U.S. military veterans. DNAm was assessed using the Illumina Infinium Human MethylationEPIC BeadChip array. SS was evaluated as: current smokers (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt;=137; 12.1%) and non-current smokers (never and former smokers; &lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt;=998; 87.9%). ND was assessed using the Fagerström Test for Nicotine Dependence (FTND). EWAS and co-methylation analyses were conducted for SS and ND.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A total of 450 and 22 genome-wide significant differentially methylated sites (DMS) were associated with SS and ND, respectively (fifteen overlapped sites). We identified 97 DMS (43 genes) in SS-EWAS previously reported in the literature, including &lt;italic&gt;AHRR&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;F2RL3&lt;/italic&gt; genes (&lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt;-value range: 1.95×10&lt;sup&gt;−83&lt;/sup&gt; to 4.5×10&lt;sup&gt;−33&lt;/sup&gt;). ND novel DMS mapped to &lt;italic&gt;NEUROG1, ANPEP&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;SLC29A1&lt;/italic&gt;. Co-methylation analysis identified 386 modules (11 SS-related and 19 ND-related). SS-related modules showed enrichment for alcoholism, chemokine signaling pathway, and neurogenesis; while ND-related modules were enriched for cellular adhesion, and nicotine addiction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study confirms previous findings and identifies novel and -potentially specific - epigenetic signatures for SS and ND in a sample of EA male veterans.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.21264038" rel="alternate" title="Dissecting the Epigenomic Differences between Smoking and Nicotine Dependence in a Veteran Cohort (8 tweets)"/><category term="Psychiatry and Clinical Psychology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.21264091</id><title>Population-scale analysis of common and rare genetic variation associated with hearing loss in adults (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.957198+00:00</updated><author><name>Kavita Praveen</name></author><author><name>Lee Dobbyn</name></author><author><name>Lauren Gurski</name></author><author><name>Ariane H. Ayer</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey Staples</name></author><author><name>Shawn Mishra</name></author><author><name>Yu Bai</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Kaufman</name></author><author><name>Arden Moscati</name></author><author><name>Christian Benner</name></author><author><name>Esteban Chen</name></author><author><name>Siying Chen</name></author><author><name>Alexander Popov</name></author><author><name>Janell Smith</name></author><author><name>Olle Melander</name></author><author><name>Marcus Jones</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Marchini</name></author><author><name>Suganthi Balasubramanian</name></author><author><name>Brian Zambrowicz</name></author><author><name>Meghan Drummond</name></author><author><name>Aris Baras</name></author><author><name>Goncalo R. Abecasis</name></author><author><name>Manuel A. Ferreira</name></author><author><name>Eli A. Stahl</name></author><author><name>Giovanni Coppola</name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the genetic underpinnings of disabling hearing loss, which affects ∼466 million people worldwide, can provide avenues for new therapeutic target development. We performed a genome-wide association meta-analysis of hearing loss with 125,749 cases and 469,497 controls across five cohorts, including UK Biobank, Geisinger DiscovEHR, the Malmö Diet and Cancer Study, Mount Sinai’s Bio&lt;italic&gt;Me&lt;/italic&gt; Personalized Medicine Cohort, and FinnGen. We identified 53 loci affecting hearing loss risk, 18 of which are novel, including coding variants in &lt;italic&gt;COL9A3&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;TMPRSS3&lt;/italic&gt;. Through exome-sequencing of 108,415 cases and 329,581 controls from the same cohorts, we identified an association with rare predicted loss-of-function variants in a gene that has been uncharacterized in hearing loss, &lt;italic&gt;KLHDC7B&lt;/italic&gt; (odds ratio [OR] = 2.14, &lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt; = 5.2 × 10&lt;sup&gt;−30&lt;/sup&gt;), and with coding variants in two genes previously implicated in animal models of hearing loss (&lt;italic&gt;SYNJ2&lt;/italic&gt;, OR = 1.31, &lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt; = 1.3 × 10&lt;sup&gt;−14&lt;/sup&gt;; &lt;italic&gt;FSCN2&lt;/italic&gt;, OR = 1.24, &lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt; = 4.1 × 10&lt;sup&gt;−15&lt;/sup&gt;). We also observed single-variant and gene-burden associations with 11 genes known to cause Mendelian forms of hearing loss, including an increased risk in heterozygous carriers of mutations in the autosomal recessive hearing loss genes &lt;italic&gt;GJB2&lt;/italic&gt; (Gly12fs; OR = 1.21, &lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt; = 4.2 × 10&lt;sup&gt;−11&lt;/sup&gt;) and &lt;italic&gt;SLC26A5&lt;/italic&gt; (gene burden; OR = 1.96, &lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt; = 2.8 × 10&lt;sup&gt;−17&lt;/sup&gt;). Our results show that Mendelian hearing loss genes contribute to the burden of hearing loss in the adult population, and suggest a shared etiology between common and rare forms of hearing loss. This work illustrates the potential of large-scale exome sequencing to elucidate the genetic architecture of common traits in which risk is modulated by both common and rare variation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.21264091" rel="alternate" title="Population-scale analysis of common and rare genetic variation associated with hearing loss in adults (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.21262316</id><title>NOVEL MANAGEMENT OF DEPRESSION USING KETAMINE IN THE INTENSIVE CARE UNIT (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.957561+00:00</updated><author><name>Nirmaljot Kaur</name></author><author><name>Siva Naga S. Yarrarapu</name></author><author><name>Abhishek R. Giri</name></author><author><name>Kathleen A. Rottman Pietrzak</name></author><author><name>Christan Santos</name></author><author><name>Philip E. Lowman</name></author><author><name>Shehzad Niaz</name></author><author><name>Pablo Moreno Franco</name></author><author><name>Devang K. Sanghavi</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ketamine, a dissociative anesthetic, induces remission of depression by antagonizing glutaminergic NMDA receptors. Ketamine has been used previously in outpatient setting for treatment-resistant depression, but we showcase its utility in depression management at the Intensive Care Unit (ICU).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Research Question&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Can ketamine be used for depression treatment in ICU patients?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Study Design and Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A retrospective chart review of ICU patients was done at a tertiary center from 2018 to 2021, to assess the ketamine usage. Among the patients reviewed, ketamine was used for depression in 12, and for analgesia &amp;amp; sedation in 2322 patients. Ketamine was administered in doses of 0.5mg/kg &amp;amp; 0.75mg/kg for depression. Each course consisted of 3 doses of ketamine administered over 3 days. 7 in 12 patients received a single course of ketamine. The rest received 3-4 courses 1 week apart.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ketamine was found to improve mood and affect in most of the patients with depression. 11 in 12 patients had a positive response with better sleep. It has a major advantage over conventional anti-depressants since it takes only a few hours to induce remission. Patients who refused to eat and follow treatment protocol, and who would otherwise succumb to death if not for the rapid remission of depression, were administered ketamine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A major drawback of ketamine is that the duration of remission is short, with the response lasting only up to 7 days after a single dose. Hence, all the patients in our study were weaned off ketamine with a supporting antidepressant. Ketamine has been documented to cause cardio-neurotoxicity; however, only one patient had worsening lethargy in our study. To conclude, ketamine has a monumental benefit in treating depression in the ICU. Although our study was associated with positive outcomes, there is a need for prospective studies with long-term follow-up assessments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.21262316" rel="alternate" title="NOVEL MANAGEMENT OF DEPRESSION USING KETAMINE IN THE INTENSIVE CARE UNIT (7 tweets)"/><category term="Intensive Care and Critical Care Medicine"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.21263954</id><title>Self-modulation of motor cortex activity after stroke alters behavior and corticospinal tract structure: a randomized controlled trial (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.957844+00:00</updated><author><name>Zeena-Britt Sanders</name></author><author><name>Melanie K. Fleming</name></author><author><name>Tom Smejka</name></author><author><name>Marilien C. Marzolla</name></author><author><name>Catharina Zich</name></author><author><name>Sebastian W. Rieger</name></author><author><name>Michael Lührs</name></author><author><name>Rainer Goebel</name></author><author><name>Cassandra Sampaio-Baptista</name></author><author><name>Heidi Johansen-Berg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Real-time functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) neurofeedback allows individuals to self-modulate their ongoing brain activity. This may be a useful tool in clinical disorders which are associated with altered brain activity patterns. Motor impairment after stroke has previously been associated with decreased laterality of motor cortex activity. Here we examined whether chronic stroke survivors were able to use real-time fMRI neurofeedback to increase laterality of motor cortex activity and assessed effects on motor performance and on brain structure and function. We carried out a randomized, double-blind, sham-controlled trial in which 24 chronic stroke survivors with mild to moderate upper limb impairment experienced three training days of either Real (n=12) or Sham (n=12) neurofeedback. Stroke survivors were able to use Real neurofeedback to increase laterality of motor cortex activity within, but not across, training days. Improvement in gross hand motor performance assessed by the Jebsen Taylor Test (JTT) was observed in the Real neurofeedback group compared to Sham. However, there were no improvements on the Action Research Arm Test (ARAT) or the Upper Extremity Fugl-Meyer (UE-FM) score. Additionally, decreased white-matter asymmetry of the corticospinal tracts was detected 1-week after neurofeedback training, indicating that the tracts become more similar with Real neurofeedback. Changes in the affected corticospinal tract was positively correlated with neurofeedback performance. Therefore, here we demonstrate that chronic stroke survivors are able to use fMRI neurofeedback to self-modulate motor cortex activity, and that training is associated with improvements in hand motor performance and with white matter structural changes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.21263954" rel="alternate" title="Self-modulation of motor cortex activity after stroke alters behavior and corticospinal tract structure: a randomized controlled trial (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.21263187</id><title>Comprehensive genetic diagnosis of tandem repeat expansion disorders with programmable targeted nanopore sequencing (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.958525+00:00</updated><author><name>Igor Stevanovski</name></author><author><name>Sanjog R. Chintalaphani</name></author><author><name>Hasindu Gamaarachchi</name></author><author><name>James M. Ferguson</name></author><author><name>Sandy S. Pineda</name></author><author><name>Carolin K. Scriba</name></author><author><name>Michel Tchan</name></author><author><name>Victor Fung</name></author><author><name>Karl Ng</name></author><author><name>Andrea Cortese</name></author><author><name>Henry Houlden</name></author><author><name>Carol Dobson-Stone</name></author><author><name>Lauren Fitzpatrick</name></author><author><name>Glenda Halliday</name></author><author><name>Gianina Ravenscroft</name></author><author><name>Mark R. Davis</name></author><author><name>Nigel G. Laing</name></author><author><name>Avi Fellner</name></author><author><name>Marina Kennerson</name></author><author><name>Kishore R. Kumar</name></author><author><name>Ira W. Deveson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Short-tandem repeat (STR) expansions are an important class of pathogenic genetic variants. Over forty neurological and neuromuscular diseases are caused by STR expansions, with 37 different genes implicated to date. Here we describe the use of programmable targeted long-read sequencing with Oxford Nanopore’s ReadUntil function for parallel genotyping of all known neuropathogenic STRs in a single, simple assay. Our approach enables accurate, haplotype-resolved assembly and DNA methylation profiling of expanded and non-expanded STR sites. In doing so, the assay correctly diagnoses all individuals in a cohort of patients (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; = 27) with various neurogenetic diseases, including Huntington’s disease, fragile X syndrome and cerebellar ataxia (CANVAS) and others. Targeted long-read sequencing solves large and complex STR expansions that confound established molecular tests and short-read sequencing, and identifies non-canonical STR motif conformations and internal sequence interruptions. Even in our relatively small cohort, we observe a wide diversity of STR alleles of known and unknown pathogenicity, suggesting that long-read sequencing will redefine the genetic landscape of STR expansion disorders. Finally, we show how the flexible inclusion of pharmacogenomics (PGx) genes as secondary ReadUntil targets can identify clinically actionable PGx genotypes to further inform patient care, at no extra cost. Our study addresses the need for improved techniques for genetic diagnosis of STR expansion disorders and illustrates the broad utility of programmable long-read sequencing for clinical genomics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study describes the development and validation of a programmable targeted nanopore sequencing assay for parallel genetic diagnosis of all known pathogenic short-tandem repeats (STRs) in a single, simple test.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.21263187" rel="alternate" title="Comprehensive genetic diagnosis of tandem repeat expansion disorders with programmable targeted nanopore sequencing (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.18.21263768</id><title>Understanding the pathways leading to socioeconomic inequalities in HIV testing uptake in 18 sub-Saharan African countries: a mediation analysis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.958981+00:00</updated><author><name>Pearl Anne Ante-Testard</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Hamidouche</name></author><author><name>Bénédicte Apouey</name></author><author><name>Rachel Baggaley</name></author><author><name>Joseph Larmarange</name></author><author><name>Tarik Benmarhnia</name></author><author><name>Laura Temime</name></author><author><name>Kévin Jean</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although socioeconomic inequalities in HIV prevention, testing and treatment services have been well documented, their drivers remain poorly understood. Understanding the different pathways between socioeconomic position and HIV testing across different countries could help designing tailored programs aimed at reducing such inequalities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We analysed data from Demographic and Health Surveys conducted between 2010 and 2018 in 18 sub-Saharan African countries (Burkina Faso, Cameroon, Côte d’Ivoire, Congo DR, Ethiopia, Guinea, Kenya, Lesotho, Liberia, Malawi, Mali, Niger, Rwanda, Senegal, Sierra Leone, Tanzania, Zambia and Zimbabwe). Using a potential outcomes framework and the product method, we decomposed the total effect linking wealth and recent (&amp;lt; 12 months) HIV testing into i) direct effects, and ii) indirect effects, via &lt;italic&gt;demand-related&lt;/italic&gt; (related to individual’s ability to perceive need for care and inclination to seek care) or &lt;italic&gt;supply-related&lt;/italic&gt; (related to individual’s ability to reach, pay for and engage in health care) mediators. Multivariable gender-specific modified Poisson models were fitted to estimate proportions mediated, while accounting for exposure-mediator interaction when present.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A total of 392,044 participants were included in the analysis. Pro-rich wealth-related inequalities were observed in a majority of countries, with nine countries with high levels of inequalities among women and 15 countries among men.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The indirect effects of each mediator varied greatly across countries. The proportion mediated tended to be higher for &lt;italic&gt;demand-related&lt;/italic&gt; than for &lt;italic&gt;supply-related&lt;/italic&gt; mediators. For instance, among women, HIV-related knowledge was estimated to mediate up to 12.1% of inequalities in Côte d’Ivoire; this proportion was up to 31.5% for positive attitudes toward people living with HIV (PLHIV) in Senegal. For the four &lt;italic&gt;supply-related&lt;/italic&gt; mediators, the proportion mediated was systematically below 7%. Similar conclusions were found when repeating analyses on men for the &lt;italic&gt;demand-related&lt;/italic&gt; mediators, with higher proportions mediated by positive attitudes toward PLHIV (up to 39.9% in Senegal).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our findings suggest that socioeconomic inequalities in HIV testing may be mediated by the &lt;italic&gt;demand-side&lt;/italic&gt; more than &lt;italic&gt;supply-side&lt;/italic&gt; characteristics, with important variability across countries. Overall, the important inter-country heterogeneity in pathways of socioeconomic inequalities in HIV testing illustrates that addressing inequalities requires tailored efforts as well as upstream interventions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A French version of the abstract is available upon request from the corresponding author.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.18.21263768" rel="alternate" title="Understanding the pathways leading to socioeconomic inequalities in HIV testing uptake in 18 sub-Saharan African countries: a mediation analysis (5 tweets)"/><category term="HIV/AIDS"/><published>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.21264084</id><title>A novel echo-parameter supersedes the Society of Thoracic Surgeons risk score in predicting 1-year mortality in patients undergoing transcatheter aortic valve replacement (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.959281+00:00</updated><author><name>Chieh-Ju Chao</name></author><author><name>Pradyumma Agasthi</name></author><author><name>Amith R Seri</name></author><author><name>Timothy Barry</name></author><author><name>Anusha Shanbhag</name></author><author><name>Yuxiang Wang</name></author><author><name>Mackram Eleid</name></author><author><name>David Fortuin</name></author><author><name>John P. Sweeney</name></author><author><name>Peter Pollak</name></author><author><name>Abdallah El Sabbagh</name></author><author><name>Steven J. Lester</name></author><author><name>William K Freeman</name></author><author><name>Tasneem Z. Naqvi</name></author><author><name>David R Holmes</name></author><author><name>Christopher P. Appleton</name></author><author><name>Reza Arsanjani</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We proposed several new echo-parameters (augmented blood pressure) derived from blood pressure and aortic valve gradient measurements and hypothesized that they can accurately predict 1-year mortality post-TAVR.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the era of transcatheter aortic valve replacement (TAVR), predicting post-procedural outcome of patients is one of the most important goals in structural heart research.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients in the Mayo Clinic National Cardiovascular Diseases Registry (NCDR)-TAVR database who underwent TAVR between January 1, 2012 and June 30, 2017 were identified to retrieve baseline demographics, STS risk score, ECG, cardiac computed tomography, echocardiographic and mortality data. Augmented blood pressure parameters and valvulo-arterial impedance were evaluated by Cox regression. After logistic model generation, receiver operating curve analysis was used to assess the model performance against STS risk score.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final cohort contained 883 patients with the mean age of 81.3±8.5 years old and 58.2% were male. The mean STS risk score was 8.1±5.1. The median follow-up duration was 353 days and one-year all-cause mortality rates was 13.3%. Multivariate Cox regression showed that augmented SBP and augmented MAP parameters were independent predictors of 1-year mortality (all p&amp;lt;0.0001). A single-parameter model based on augmented MAP1 supersedes STS risk score in predicting 1-year mortality (AUC 0.697 vs. 0.591, p=0.0055).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Augmented mean arterial pressure provides a simple but effective approach for clinicians to quickly estimate the clinical outcome of TAVR patients and should be incorporated in the assessment of TAVR candidacy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Condensed Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We proposed and validated a new echo-parameter, augmented mean arterial pressure, in a cohort contains 883 patients who underwent TAVR between January 1, 2012 and June 30, 2017. Multivariate Cox regression showed that augmented MAP parameters was independent predictors of 1-year mortality (all p&amp;lt;0.0001). A single-parameter model based on augmented MAP supersedes STS risk score in predicting 1-year mortality (AUC 0.697 vs. 0.591, p=0.0055). Augmented MAP provides a simple but effective approach for clinicians to quickly estimate the clinical outcome of TAVR patients and should be incorporated in the assessment of TAVR candidacy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.21264084" rel="alternate" title="A novel echo-parameter supersedes the Society of Thoracic Surgeons risk score in predicting 1-year mortality in patients undergoing transcatheter aortic valve replacement (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cardiovascular Medicine"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.21263935</id><title>Is annual vaccination best? A modelling study of influenza vaccination strategies in children (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.959752+00:00</updated><author><name>Kylie E. C. Ainslie</name></author><author><name>Steven Riley</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Annual vaccination of children against influenza is a key component of vaccination programs in many countries. However, past infection and vaccination may affect an individual’s susceptibility to infection. Little research has evaluated whether annual vaccination is the best strategy. Using the United Kingdom as our motivating example, we assess the impact of different childhood vaccination strategies, specifically annual and biennial (every other year), on attack rate and expected number of infections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods and Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present a multi-annual, individual-based, stochastic, force of infection model that accounts for individual exposure histories and disease/vaccine dynamics influencing susceptibility. We simulate birth cohorts that experience yearly influenza epidemics and follow them until age 18 to determine attack rates and the number of childhood infections. We perform simulations under baseline conditions, with an assumed vaccination coverage of 44%, to compare annual vaccination to no and biennial vaccination. We relax our baseline assumptions to explore how our model assumptions impact vaccination program performance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At baseline, we observed more than a 50% reduction in the number of infections between the ages 2 and 10 under annual vaccination in children who had been vaccinated at least half the time compared to no vaccination. When averaged over all ages 0-18, the number of infections under annual vaccination was 2.07 (2.06, 2.08) compared to 2.63 (2.62, 2.64) under no vaccination, and 2.38 (2.37, 2.40) under biennial vaccination. When we introduced a penalty for repeated exposures, we observed a decrease in the difference in infections between the vaccination strategies. Specifically, the difference in childhood infections under biennial compared to annual vaccination decreased from 0.31 to 0.04 as exposure penalty increased.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our results indicate that while annual vaccination averts more childhood infections than biennial vaccination, this difference is small. Our work confirms the value of annual vaccination in children, even with modest vaccination coverage, but also shows that similar benefits of vaccination can be obtained by implementing a biennial vaccination program.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many countries include annual vaccination of children against influenza in their vaccination programs. In the United Kingdom, annual vaccination of children aged of 2 to 10 against influenza is recommended. However, little research has evaluated whether annual vaccination is the best strategy, while accounting for how past infection and vaccination may affect an individual’s susceptibility to infection in the current influenza season. Prior work has suggested that there may be a negative effect of repeated vaccination. In this work we developed a stochastic, individual-based model to assess the impact of repeated vaccination strategies on childhood infections. Specifically, we first compare annual vaccination to no vaccination and then annual vaccination to biennial (every other year) vaccination. We use the UK as our motivating example. We found that an annual vaccination strategy resulted in the fewest childhood infections, followed by biennial vaccination. The difference in number of childhood infections between the different vaccination strategies decreased when we introduced a penalty for repeated exposures. Our work confirms the value of annual vaccination in children, but also shows that similar benefits of vaccination can be obtained by implementing a biennial vaccination program, particularly when there is a negative effect of repeated vaccinations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.21263935" rel="alternate" title="Is annual vaccination best? A modelling study of influenza vaccination strategies in children (5 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.21263962</id><title>Integrating genome-wide polygenic risk scores and non-genetic risk factors to develop and validate risk prediction models for colorectal cancer (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.960017+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah E. Briggs</name></author><author><name>Philip Law</name></author><author><name>James E. East</name></author><author><name>Sarah Wordsworth</name></author><author><name>Malcolm Dunlop</name></author><author><name>Richard Houlston</name></author><author><name>Julia Hippisley-Cox</name></author><author><name>Ian Tomlinson</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;While population screening programs for cancer colorectal (CRC) have proven benefit, risk-stratified approaches may improve screening outcomes further. To date, genome-wide polygenic risk scores (PRS) for CRC have not been integrated with non-genetic risk factors. We aimed to evaluate several genome-wide approaches, and the benefit of adding PRS to the QCancer-10 (colorectal cancer) non-genetic risk model, to identify those at highest risk of CRC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using UK Biobank we developed and compared six different PRS for CRC. The top-performing genome-wide and GWAS-significant PRS were then combined with QCancer-10 and performance compared to QCancer-10 alone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;PRS derived using LDpred2 software performed best, with an odds-ratio per standard deviation of 1.58, and top age- and sex-adjusted C-statistic of 0.733 in logistic regression and 0.724 in Cox regression models in the Geographic Validation Cohort. Integrated QCancer-10+PRS models out-performed QCancer-10, with C-statistics of 0.730 and 0.693, and explained variation of 28.1% and 21.0% from QCancer-10+LDpred2 and QCancer-10 respectively in men; performance improvements in women were similar. Men in the top 20% of risk accounted for 47.6% of cases, and women 42.5% using QCancer-10+LDpred2 models, with a 3.49-fold increase in risk in men and 2.75-fold increase in women in the top 5% of risk, compared to average risk. Decision curve analysis showed that adding PRS to QCancer-10 improved net-benefit and interventions avoided across most probability thresholds.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Integrated QCancer-10+PRS models out-perform existing CRC risk prediction models. Evaluation of risk stratified screening using this approach in a bowel screening population could be warranted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SUMMARY BOX&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What is already known about this subject&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Risk stratification based on genetic or environmental risk factors may improve cancer screening outcomes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many polygenic risk scores (PRS) based on a limited number of genome-wide significant SNPs have been assessed in colorectal cancer (CRC), but just two studies have examined the use of genome-wide PRS methodologies&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;No previously published study has examined integrated models combining genome-wide PRS and non-genetic risk factors beyond age&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;QCancer-10 (colorectal cancer) is the top-performing non-genetic risk prediction model for CRC&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What are the new findings?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;PRS derived using LDpred2 software outperform existing models, and other genome-wide and genome-wide significant models evaluated here&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adding either LDpred2 PRS or genome-wide significant PRS improves the performance and clinical benefit of the QCancer-10 model, with greater gain from the LDpred2 model&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;How might it impact on clinical practice in the foreseeable future?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The performance and clinical benefit of QCancer-10 is improved by adding PRS, to a level that suggests utility in stratifying CRC screening and prevention&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.21263962" rel="alternate" title="Integrating genome-wide polygenic risk scores and non-genetic risk factors to develop and validate risk prediction models for colorectal cancer (5 tweets)"/><category term="Gastroenterology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.21263942</id><title>Predicting Progression Free Survival after Systemic Therapy in Advanced Head and Neck Cancer: Bayesian regression and Model development (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.960320+00:00</updated><author><name>Paul R Barber</name></author><author><name>Fabian Flores-Borja</name></author><author><name>Giovanna Alfano</name></author><author><name>Kenrick Ng</name></author><author><name>Gregory Weitsman</name></author><author><name>Luigi Dolcetti</name></author><author><name>Rami Mustapha</name></author><author><name>Felix Wong</name></author><author><name>Jose M Vicencio</name></author><author><name>Myria Galazi</name></author><author><name>James W Opzoomer</name></author><author><name>James N Arnold</name></author><author><name>Shahram Kordasti</name></author><author><name>Jana Doyle</name></author><author><name>Jon Greenberg</name></author><author><name>Magnus T Dillon</name></author><author><name>Kevin J Harrington</name></author><author><name>Martin D Forster</name></author><author><name>Anthony C C Coolen</name></author><author><name>Tony Ng</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advanced Head and Neck Squamous Cell Cancer (HNSCC) is associated with a poor prognosis, and biomarkers that predict response to treatment are highly desirable. The primary aim was to predict Progression Free Survival (PFS) with a multivariate risk prediction model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Blood samples from 56 HNSCC patients were prospectively obtained within a Phase 2 clinical trial (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT02633800"&gt;NCT02633800&lt;/ext-link&gt;), before and after the first treatment cycle of platinum-based chemotherapy, to identify biological covariates predictive of outcome. A total of 42 baseline covariates were derived pre-treatment, which were combined with 29 covariates after one cycle of treatment. These covariates were ranked and selected by Bayesian multivariate regression to form risk scores to predict PFS, producing “baseline” and “combined” risk prediction models respectively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The baseline model comprised of CD33+CD14+ monocytes, Double Negative B cells and age, in a weighted risk signature which predicted PFS with a concordance index (C-index) of 0.661. The combined model composed of baseline CD33+CD14+ monocytes, baseline Tregs, after-treatment changes in CD8 effector memory T cells, CD8 Central memory T cells and CD3 T Cells, along with the hypopharyngeal primary tumor subsite. This weighted risk signature exhibited an improved C-index of 0.757. There was concordance between levels of CD33+CD14+ myeloid cells in tumor tissue, as demonstrated by imaging mass cytometry, and peripheral blood in the same patients. This monocyte subpopulation also had univariate predictive value (log-rank p value = 0.03) but the C-index was inferior to the combined signature.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This immune-based combined multimodality signature, obtained through longitudinal peripheral blood monitoring, presents a novel means of predicting response early on during the treatment course.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Daiichi Sankyo Inc, Cancer Research UK, EU IMI2 IMMUCAN, UK Medical Research Council, European Research Council (335326), National Institute for Health Research and The Institute of Cancer Research.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.21263942" rel="alternate" title="Predicting Progression Free Survival after Systemic Therapy in Advanced Head and Neck Cancer: Bayesian regression and Model development (5 tweets)"/><category term="Oncology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.21264011</id><title>The mathematics of erythema: Development of machine learning models for artificial intelligence assisted measurement and severity scoring of radiation induced dermatitis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.960744+00:00</updated><author><name>Rahul Ranjan</name></author><author><name>Richard Partl</name></author><author><name>Ricarda Erhart</name></author><author><name>Nithin Kurup</name></author><author><name>Harald Schnidar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Although significant advancements in computer-aided diagnostics using artificial intelligence (AI) have been made, to date, no viable method for radiation-induced skin reaction (RISR) analysis and classification is available. The objective of this single-center study was to develop machine learning and deep learning approaches using deep convolutional neural networks (CNNs) for automatic classification of RISRs according to the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) grading system. Scarletred&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; Vision, a novel and state-of-the-art digital skin imaging method capable of remote monitoring and objective assessment of acute RISRs was used to convert 2D digital skin images using the CIELAB color space and conduct SEV* measurements. A set of different machine learning and deep convolutional neural network-based algorithms has been explored for the automatic classification of RISRs. A total of 2263 distinct images from 209 patients were analyzed for training and testing the machine learning and CNN algorithms. For a 2-class problem of healthy skin (grade 0) versus erythema (grade≥ 1), all machine learning models produced an accuracy of above 70%, and the sensitivity and specificity of erythema recognition were 67-72% and 72-83%, respectively. The CNN produced a test accuracy of 74%, sensitivity of 66%, and specificity of 83% for predicting healthy and erythema cases. For the severity grade prediction of a 3-class problem (grade 0 versus 1 versus 2), the test accuracy was 60-67%, and the sensitivity and specificity were 56-82%, 35-59%, and 65-72%, respectively. For estimating the severity grade of each class, the CNN obtained an accuracy of 73%, 66%, and 82%, respectively. Ensemble learning combines several individual predictions to obtain a better generalization performance. Furthermore, we exploited ensemble learning by deploying a CNN model as a meta-learner. The ensemble CNN based on bagging and majority voting shows an accuracy, sensitivity and specificity of 87%, 90%, and 82% for a 2-class problem, respectively. For a 3-class problem, the ensemble CNN shows an overall accuracy of 66%, while for each grade (0, 1, and 2) accuracies were 0.76%, 0.69%, and 0.87%, sensitivities were 0.70%, 0.57%, and 0.71%, and specificities were 0.78%, 0.75%, and 0.95%, respectively. This study is the first to focus on erythema in radiation-dermatitis and produces benchmark results using machine learning models. The outcome of this study validates that the proposed system can act as a pre-screening and decision support tool for oncologists or patients to provide fast, reliable, and efficient assessment of erythema grading.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.21264011" rel="alternate" title="The mathematics of erythema: Development of machine learning models for artificial intelligence assisted measurement and severity scoring of radiation induced dermatitis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Dermatology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.21264368</id><title>“Jittered” Oculomotor Sensing Concomitant with Hypoactive Dorsal Parietal Systems during Live Eye-Contact in Autism Spectrum Disorder (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.961010+00:00</updated><author><name>Joy Hirsch</name></author><author><name>Xian Zhang</name></author><author><name>J. Adam Noah</name></author><author><name>Swethasri Dravida</name></author><author><name>Adam Naples</name></author><author><name>Mark Tiede</name></author><author><name>Julie M. Wolf</name></author><author><name>James C. McPartland</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Reluctant eye contact and reduced social interactions characteristic of autism spectrum disorder (ASD) are consistent with deficits in oculomotor and face processing systems. We test the hypothesis that these deficits are interrelated ASD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eye-tracking and hyperscanning with functional near-infrared spectroscopy (fNIRS) were used to acquire neuroimaging data during live, dynamic eye-to-eye contacts in 17 ASD and 19 typically-developed (TD) adults. Real eye contact conditions were contrasted with conditions where eye gaze was directed at a comparable dynamic face video. These findings were regressed with eye-contact dwell-time, i.e., times when gaze of both partners was in the eye-box of the other, to confirm the relationship between visual sensing and neural coding. Visual fixations and positional variance were also determined.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Average gaze dwell-times in the “eye-box” did not vary between ASD and TD participants but were longer for the Real Eye than Video Eye condition for both groups. However, positional gaze variability, “jitter”, was higher for ASD in both conditions. Neural findings for TD [Real Eye &amp;gt; Video Eye] were consistent with previous findings for interactive face-gaze with activity in right temporal and dorsal parietal regions. However, in ASD ventral temporal regions were observed for this contrast without evidence for dorsal parietal activity. This neural difference was enhanced when regressed by eye-contact dwell-times.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Together findings are consistent with the hypothesis that unstable bottom-up oculomotor signals contribute to deficits in live face processing and reduced dorsal stream activity in ASD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eye contact avoidance is a diagnostic feature of autism spectrum disorder (ASD). However, the underlying neural mechanisms are unknown. Using a two-person neural imaging system and a face-to-face paradigm with eye tracking, we found that the neural systems activated by live eye contact differed between typically developed (TD) and ASD groups. In ASD, the ventral occipital parietal systems were engaged, whereas in TD, the dorsal posterior parietal systems were engaged. Positional variation of eye gaze, “jitter”, was higher in ASD than TD. These findings are consistent with the hypothesis that bottom-up variations in visual sensing are components of altered interactive face processing and dorsal stream mechanisms and may contribute to the neural underpinnings of reluctant eye contact behaviors in ASD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.21264368" rel="alternate" title="“Jittered” Oculomotor Sensing Concomitant with Hypoactive Dorsal Parietal Systems during Live Eye-Contact in Autism Spectrum Disorder (4 tweets)"/><category term="Psychiatry and Clinical Psychology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.21263888</id><title>Incorporating Polygenic Risk Scores and Nongenetic Risk Factors for Breast Cancer Risk Prediction among Asian Women, Results from Asia Breast Cancer Consortium (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.961302+00:00</updated><author><name>Yaohua Yang</name></author><author><name>Ran Tao</name></author><author><name>Xiang Shu</name></author><author><name>Qiuyin Cai</name></author><author><name>Wanqing Wen</name></author><author><name>Kai Gu</name></author><author><name>Yu-Tang Gao</name></author><author><name>Ying Zheng</name></author><author><name>Sun-Seog Kweon</name></author><author><name>Min-Ho Shin</name></author><author><name>Ji-Yeob Choi</name></author><author><name>Eun-Sook Lee</name></author><author><name>Sun-Young Kong</name></author><author><name>Boyoung Park</name></author><author><name>Min Ho Park</name></author><author><name>Guochong Jia</name></author><author><name>Bingshan Li</name></author><author><name>Daehee Kang</name></author><author><name>Xiao-Ou Shu</name></author><author><name>Jirong Long</name></author><author><name>Wei Zheng</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Polygenic risk scores (PRSs) have shown promises in breast cancer risk prediction; however, limited studies have been conducted among Asian women.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To develop breast cancer risk prediction models for Asian women incorporating PRSs and nongenetic risk factors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;PRSs were developed using data from genome-wide association studies (GWAS) of breast cancer conducted among 123 041 Asian-ancestry women (including 18 650 cases) using three approaches (1) reported PRS for European-ancestry women; (2) breast cancer-associated single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) identified by fine-mapping of GWAS-identified risk loci; (3) genome-wide risk prediction algorithms. A nongenetic risk score (NgRS) was built including six well-established nongenetic risk factors using data from 1974 Asian women. Integrated risk scores (IRSs) were constructed using PRSs and the NgRS. PRSs were initially validated in an independent dataset including 1426 cases and 1323 controls and further evaluated, along with the NgRS and IRSs, in the second dataset including 368 cases and 736 controls nested withing a prospective cohort study.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Case-control and prospective cohort studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;20 444 breast cancer cases and 106 450 controls from the Asia Breast Cancer Consortium.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Outcomes and Measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Logistic regression was used to examine associations of risk scores with breast cancer risk to estimate odds ratios (ORs) with 95% confidence intervals (CIs) and area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUC).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the prospective cohort, PRS&lt;sub&gt;111,&lt;/sub&gt; a PRS with 111 SNPs, developed using the fine-mapping approach showed a prediction performance comparable to a genome-wide PRS including over 855,000 SNPs. The OR per standard deviation increase of PRS&lt;sub&gt;111&lt;/sub&gt; was 1.67 (95% CI=1.46-1.92) with an AUC of 0.639 (95% CI=0.604-0.674). The NgRS had a limited predictive ability (AUC=0.565; 95% CI=0.529-0.601); while IRS&lt;sub&gt;111&lt;/sub&gt;, the combination of PRS&lt;sub&gt;111&lt;/sub&gt; and NgRS, achieved the highest prediction accuracy (AUC=0.650; 95% CI=0.616-0.685). Compared with the average risk group (40&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;-60&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; percentile), women in the top 5% of PRS&lt;sub&gt;111&lt;/sub&gt; and IRS&lt;sub&gt;111&lt;/sub&gt; were at a 3.84-folded (95% CI=2.30-6.46) and 4.25-folded (95% CI=2.57-7.11) elevated risk of breast cancer, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions and Relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;PRSs derived using breast cancer-associated risk SNPs have similar prediction performance in Asian and European descendants. Including nongenetic risk factors in models further improved prediction accuracy. Our findings support the utility of these models in developing personalized screening and prevention strategies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key Points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Question&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;What is the performance of breast cancer risk prediction models for Asian women incorporating polygenic risk scores (PRSs) and nongenetic risk factors?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A 111-genetic-variant PRS developed using data of 125 790 Asian women was significantly associated with breast cancer risk in an independent case-control study nested within a prospective cohort, with an odd ratio (OR) per standard deviation increase of 1.67 (95% confidence interval [CI]=1.46-1.92) and an area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUC) of 0.639 (95% CI=0.604-0.674). The prediction model including this PRS and six nongenetic risk factors improved the AUC to 0.650 (95% CI=0.616-0.685).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Meaning&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our study provides strong supports for the utility of prediction models in identifying Asian women at high risk of breast cancer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.21263888" rel="alternate" title="Incorporating Polygenic Risk Scores and Nongenetic Risk Factors for Breast Cancer Risk Prediction among Asian Women, Results from Asia Breast Cancer Consortium (4 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461306</id><title>Hyperconcentrated Mucus Unifies Submucosal Gland and Superficial Airway Dysfunction in Cystic Fibrosis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.961711+00:00</updated><author><name>Takafumi Kato</name></author><author><name>Giorgia Radicioni</name></author><author><name>Micah J. Papanikolas</name></author><author><name>Georgi V. Stoychev</name></author><author><name>Matthew R. Markovetz</name></author><author><name>Kazuhiro Aoki</name></author><author><name>Mindy Porterfield</name></author><author><name>Kenichi Okuda</name></author><author><name>Selene M. Barbosa Cardenas</name></author><author><name>Rodney C. Gilmore</name></author><author><name>Cameron B. Morrison</name></author><author><name>Camille Ehre</name></author><author><name>Kimberlie A. Burns</name></author><author><name>Kristen K. White</name></author><author><name>Henry P. Goodell</name></author><author><name>Holly Thacker</name></author><author><name>Henry T. Loznev</name></author><author><name>Lawrence J. Forsberg</name></author><author><name>Takahide Nagase</name></author><author><name>Michael Rubinstein</name></author><author><name>Scott H. Randell</name></author><author><name>Michael Tiemeyer</name></author><author><name>David B. Hill</name></author><author><name>Mehmet Kesimer</name></author><author><name>Wanda K. O’Neal</name></author><author><name>Stephen T. Ballard</name></author><author><name>Ronit Freeman</name></author><author><name>Brian Button</name></author><author><name>Richard C. Boucher</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cystic fibrosis (CF) is characterized by abnormal transepithelial ion transport. However, a description of CF lung disease pathophysiology unifying superficial epithelial and submucosal gland (SMG) dysfunctions has remained elusive. We hypothesized that biophysical abnormalities associated with CF mucus hyperconcentration provide a unifying mechanism. Studies of the anion secretion-inhibited pig airway CF model revealed elevated SMG mucus concentrations, osmotic pressures, and SMG mucus accumulation. Human airway studies revealed hyperconcentrated CF SMG mucus with raised osmotic pressures and cohesive forces predicted to limit SMG mucus secretion/release. Utilizing proline-rich protein 4 (PRR4) as a biomarker of SMG secretion, proteomics analyses of CF sputum revealed markedly lower PRR4 levels compared to healthy and bronchiectasis controls, consistent with a failure of CF SMGs to secrete mucus onto airway surfaces. Raised mucus osmotic/cohesive forces, reflecting mucus hyperconcentration, provide a unifying mechanism that describes disease-initiating mucus accumulation on airway surfaces and within SMGs of the CF lung.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hyperconcentrated Mucus Unifies Submucosal Gland and Superficial Airway Dysfunction in Cystic Fibrosis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461306" rel="alternate" title="Hyperconcentrated Mucus Unifies Submucosal Gland and Superficial Airway Dysfunction in Cystic Fibrosis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.21264139</id><title>RESEARCH PROTOCOL: Large-scale evidence generation and evaluation across a network of databases for type 2 diabetes mellitus (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.962453+00:00</updated><author><name>Rohan Khera</name></author><author><name>Martijn J Scheumie</name></author><author><name>Yuan Lu</name></author><author><name>Anna Ostropolets</name></author><author><name>Ruijun Chen</name></author><author><name>George Hripcsak</name></author><author><name>Patrick B Ryan</name></author><author><name>Harlan M Krumholz</name></author><author><name>Marc A Suchard</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Therapeutic options for type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) have expanded over the last decade with the emergence of sodium-glucose co-transporter-2 (SGLT2) inhibitors and glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP1) receptor agonists, which reduced the risk of major cardiovascular events in randomized controlled trials (RCTs). Cardiovascular evidence for older second-line agents, such as sulfonylureas, and direct head-to-head comparisons, including with dipeptidyl peptidase 4 (DPP4) inhibitors, are lacking, leaving a critical gap in our understanding of the relative effects of T2DM agents on cardiovascular risk and on patient-centered safety outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods and Analysis&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Large-Scale Evidence Generations Across a Network of Databases for T2DM (LEGEND-T2DM) initiative is a series of systematic, large-scale, multinational, real-world comparative cardiovascular effectiveness and safety studies of all 4 major second-line anti-hyperglycemic agents including SGLT2 inhibitor, GLP1 receptor agonist, DPP4 inhibitor and sulfonylureas. LEGEND-T2DM will leverage the Observational Health Data Science and Informatics (OHDSI) community that provides access to a global network of administrative claims and electronic health record (EHR) data sources. Committed data partners represent 190 million patients in the US and about 50 million internationally. LEGEND-T2DM will identify all adult, T2DM patients who newly initiate a traditionally second-line T2DM agent, including individuals with and without established cardiovascular disease. Using an active comparator, new-user cohort design, LEGEND-T2DM will execute all pairwise class-vs-class and drug-vs-drug comparisons in each data source that meet a minimum patient count of 1,000 per arm and extensive study diagnostics that assess reliability and generalizability through cohort balance and equipoise to examine the relative risk of cardiovascular and safety outcomes. The primary cardiovascular outcomes include a 3-point and a 4-point composite of major adverse cardiovascular events, and series of safety outcomes. The study will pursue data-driven, large-scale propensity adjustment for measured confounding, a large set of negative control outcome experiments to address unmeasured and systematic bias.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Ethics and Dissemination&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study ensures data safety through a federated analytic approach and follows research best practices, including prespecification and full disclosure of hypotheses tested and their results. LEGEND-T2DM is dedicated to open science and transparency and will publicly share all our analytic code from reproducible cohort definitions through turn-key software, enabling other research groups to leverage our methods, data, and results in order to verify and extend our findings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.21264139" rel="alternate" title="RESEARCH PROTOCOL: Large-scale evidence generation and evaluation across a network of databases for type 2 diabetes mellitus (4 tweets)"/><category term="Endocrinology (including Diabetes Mellitus and Metabolic Disease)"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.19.21263548</id><title>Qatar Genome: Insights on Genomics from the Middle East (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.962778+00:00</updated><author><name>Hamdi Mbarek</name></author><author><name>Geethanjali Devadoss Gandhi</name></author><author><name>Senthil Selvaraj</name></author><author><name>Wadha Al-Muftah</name></author><author><name>Radja Badji</name></author><author><name>Yasser Al-Sarraj</name></author><author><name>Chadi Saad</name></author><author><name>Dima Darwish</name></author><author><name>Muhammad Alvi</name></author><author><name>Tasnim Fadl</name></author><author><name>Heba Yasin</name></author><author><name>Fatima Alkuwari</name></author><author><name>Rozaimi Razali</name></author><author><name>Waleed Aamer</name></author><author><name>Fatemeh Abbaszadeh</name></author><author><name>Ikhlak Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Younes Mokrab</name></author><author><name>Karsten Suhre</name></author><author><name>Omar Albagha</name></author><author><name>Khalid Fakhro</name></author><author><name>Ramin Badii</name></author><author><name>Said I. Ismail</name></author><author><name>Asma Althani</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite recent biomedical breakthroughs and large genomic studies growing momentum, the Middle Eastern population, home to over 400 million people, is under-represented in the human genome variation databases. Here we describe insights from phase 1 of the Qatar Genome Program which whole genome sequenced 6,045 individuals from Qatar. We identified more than 88 million variants of which 24 million are novel and 23 million are singletons. Consistent with the high consanguinity and founder effects in the region, we found that several rare deleterious variants were more common in the Qatari population while others seem to provide protection against diseases and have shaped the genetic architecture of adaptive phenotypes. Insights into the genetic structure of the Qatari population revealed five non-admixed subgroups. Based on sequence data, we also reported the heritability and genetic marker associations for 45 clinical traits. These results highlight the value of our data as a resource to advance genetic studies in the Arab and neighbouring Middle Eastern populations and will significantly boost the current efforts to improve our understanding of global patterns of human variations, human history and genetic contributions to health and diseases in diverse populations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.19.21263548" rel="alternate" title="Qatar Genome: Insights on Genomics from the Middle East (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.21263983</id><title>The COMBAT-TB Workbench: Making powerful TB bioinformatics accessible (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.963235+00:00</updated><author><name>Peter van Heusden</name></author><author><name>Ziphozakhe Mashologu</name></author><author><name>Thoba Lose</name></author><author><name>Robin Warren</name></author><author><name>Alan Christoffels</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Whole Genome Sequencing (WGS) is a powerful method for detecting drug resistance, genetic diversity and transmission dynamics of &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt;. Implementation of WGS in public health microbiology laboratories is impeded by a lack of user-friendly, automated and semi-automated pipelines. We present the COMBAT-TB workbench, a modular, easy to install application that provides a web based environment for &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; bioinformatics. The COMBAT-TB Workbench is built using two main software components: the IRIDA Platform for its web-based user interface and data management capabilities and the Galaxy bioinformatics workflow platform for workflow execution. These components are combined into a single easy to install application using Docker container technology. We implemented two workflows, for &lt;italic&gt;M. tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; sample analysis and phylogeny, in Galaxy. Building our workflows involved updating some Galaxy tools (Trimmomatic, snippy and snp-sites) and writing new Galaxy tools (snp-dists, TB-Profiler, tb_variant_filter and TB Variant Report). The irida-wf-ga2xml tool was updated to be able to work with recent versions of Galaxy and was further developed into IRIDA plugins for both workflows. In the case of the &lt;italic&gt;M. tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; sample analysis an interface was added to update the metadata stored for each sequence sample with results gleaned from the Galaxy workflow output. Data can be loaded into the COMBAT-TB Workbench via the web interface or via the command line IRIDA uploader tool. The COMBAT-TB Workbench application deploys IRIDA, the COMBAT-TB IRIDA plugins, the MariaDB database and Galaxy using Docker containers (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/COMBAT-TB/irida-galaxy-deploy"&gt;https://github.com/COMBAT-TB/irida-galaxy-deploy&lt;/ext-link&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;While the reduction in cost of WGS is making sequencing more affordable in Lower and Middle Income Countries, public health laboratories in these countries seldom have access to bioinformaticians and system support engineers adept at using the Linux command line and complex bioinformatics software. The COMBAT-TB Workbench provides an open source, modular, easy to deploy and use environment for managing and analysing &lt;italic&gt;M. tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; WGS data and thereby makes WGS usable in practice in the LMIC context.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.21263983" rel="alternate" title="The COMBAT-TB Workbench: Making powerful TB bioinformatics accessible (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.21264251</id><title>The relationships between women’s reproductive factors: a Mendelian randomization analysis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.963490+00:00</updated><author><name>Claire Prince</name></author><author><name>Gemma C Sharp</name></author><author><name>Laura D Howe</name></author><author><name>Abigail Fraser</name></author><author><name>Rebecca C Richmond</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Women’s reproductive factors include their age at menarche and menopause, the age at which they start and stop having children, and the number of children they have. Studies that have linked these factors with disease risk have largely investigated individual reproductive factors and have not considered the genetic correlation and total interplay that may occur between them. This study aimed to investigate the nature of the relationships between eight female reproductive factors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used data from the UK Biobank and genetic consortia with data available for the following reproductive factors: age at menarche, age at menopause, age at first birth, age at last birth, number of births, being parous, age at first sex and lifetime number of sexual partners. Linkage disequilibrium score regression (LDSC) was performed to investigate the genetic correlation between reproductive factors. We then applied Mendelian randomization (MR) methods to estimate the causal relationships between these factors. Sensitivity analyses were used to investigate directionality of the effects, test for evidence of pleiotropy and account for sample overlap.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;LDSC indicated that most reproductive factors are genetically correlated (r&lt;sub&gt;g&lt;/sub&gt; range: |0.06 – 0.94|), though there was little evidence for genetic correlations between lifetime number of sexual partners and age at last birth, number of births and ever being parous (r&lt;sub&gt;g&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;lt; 0.01). MR revealed potential causal relationships between many reproductive factors, including later age at menarche (1 SD increase) leading to a later age at first sexual intercourse (Beta (B)=0.09 SD, 95% confidence intervals (CI)=0.06,0.11), age at first birth (B=0.07 SD, CI=0.04,0.10), age at last birth (B=0.06 SD, CI=0.04,0.09) and age at menopause (B=0.06 SD, CI=0.03,0.10). Later age at first birth was found to lead to a later age at menopause (B=0.21 SD, CI=0.13,0.29), age at last birth (B=0.72 SD, CI=0.67,0.77) and a lower number of births (B=-0.38 SD, CI=-0.44,-0.32).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study presents evidence that women’s reproductive factors are genetically correlated and causally related. Future studies examining the health sequelae of reproductive factors should consider a woman’s entire reproductive history, including the causal interplay between reproductive factors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.21264251" rel="alternate" title="The relationships between women’s reproductive factors: a Mendelian randomization analysis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.21263912</id><title>Effect of Long-Term Caloric Restriction on DNA Methylation Measures of Biological Aging in Healthy Adults: CALERIE™ Trial Analysis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.963720+00:00</updated><author><name>R Waziry</name></author><author><name>DL Corcoran</name></author><author><name>KM Huffman</name></author><author><name>MS Kobor</name></author><author><name>M Kothari</name></author><author><name>VB Kraus</name></author><author><name>WE Kraus</name></author><author><name>DTS Lin</name></author><author><name>CF Pieper</name></author><author><name>ME Ramaker</name></author><author><name>M Bhapkar</name></author><author><name>SK Das</name></author><author><name>L Ferrucci</name></author><author><name>WJ Hastings</name></author><author><name>M Kebbe</name></author><author><name>DC Parker</name></author><author><name>SB Racette</name></author><author><name>I Shalev</name></author><author><name>B Schilling</name></author><author><name>DW Belsky</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Calorie restriction (CR) slows aging and increases healthy lifespan in model organisms. We tested if CR slowed biological aging in humans using DNA methylation analysis of blood samples from N=197 participants in the Comprehensive Assessment of Long-term Effects of Reducing Intake of Energy (CALERIE™) randomized controlled trial. We quantified CR effects on biological aging by comparing change scores for six epigenetic-clock and Pace-of-Aging measures between n=128 CR-group and n=69 ad-libitum-control-group participants at 12- and 24-month follow-ups. CR effects were strongest for DunedinPACE Pace of Aging (12-month Cohen’s d=0.3; 24-month Cohen’s d=0.2, p&amp;lt;0.01 for both), followed by DunedinPoAm and the GrimAge epigenetic clock, although effects for these measures were not statistically different from zero (p&amp;gt;0.08). CR effects for other epigenetic clocks were in the opposite direction (all p&amp;gt;0.15). CALERIE intervention slowed Pace of Aging but showed minimal effect on epigenetic clocks hypothesized to reflect longer term accumulation of aging burden.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.21263912" rel="alternate" title="Effect of Long-Term Caloric Restriction on DNA Methylation Measures of Biological Aging in Healthy Adults: CALERIE™ Trial Analysis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Nutrition"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.21262960</id><title>Genome-wide meta-analysis of iron status biomarkers and the effect of iron on all-cause mortality in HUNT (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.964111+00:00</updated><author><name>Marta R Moksnes</name></author><author><name>Ailin Falkmo Hansen</name></author><author><name>Sarah E Graham</name></author><author><name>Sarah A Gagliano Taliun</name></author><author><name>Kuan-Han Wu</name></author><author><name>Wei Zhou</name></author><author><name>Ketil Thorstensen</name></author><author><name>Lars G Fritsche</name></author><author><name>Dipender Gill</name></author><author><name>Amy Mason</name></author><author><name>Francesco Cucca</name></author><author><name>David Schlessinger</name></author><author><name>Gonçalo R. Abecasis</name></author><author><name>Stephen Burgess</name></author><author><name>Bjørn Olav Åsvold</name></author><author><name>Jonas B Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Kristian Hveem</name></author><author><name>Cristen J Willer</name></author><author><name>Ben M Brumpton</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Iron is essential for many biological processes, but iron levels must be tightly regulated to avoid harmful effects of both iron deficiency and overload. Here, we perform genome-wide association studies on four iron related biomarkers (serum iron, serum ferritin, transferrin saturation, total iron binding capacity) in the Trøndelag Health Study (HUNT), the Michigan Genomics Initiative (MGI) and the SardiNIA study, followed by their meta-analysis with publicly available summary statistics, analyzing up to 257 953 individuals. We identify 127 genetic loci associated with iron traits. Among 19 novel protein-altering variants, we observe a rare missense variant (rs367731784) in HUNT, which suggests a role for &lt;italic&gt;DNAJC13&lt;/italic&gt; in transferrin recycling. We further validate the latest genetic risk scores for each biomarker in HUNT (6% variance in serum iron explained) and present linear and non-linear Mendelian randomization analyses of the traits on all-cause mortality. We find evidence of a harmful effect of increased serum iron and transferrin saturation in linear analyses that estimate population-averaged effects. However, there was weak evidence of a protective effect of increasing serum iron at the very low end of its distribution. Our findings contribute to our understanding of the genes affecting iron status and its consequences on human health.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.21262960" rel="alternate" title="Genome-wide meta-analysis of iron status biomarkers and the effect of iron on all-cause mortality in HUNT (3 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.21263753</id><title>Detecting a History of Repetitive Head Impacts from a Short Voice Recording (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.964385+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael G. Tauro</name></author><author><name>Mirco Ravanelli</name></author><author><name>Cristian A. Droppelmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Repetitive head impacts (RHI) are associated with an increased risk of developing various neurodegenerative disorders, such as Alzheimer’s disease (AD), Parkinson’s disease (PD), and most notably, chronic traumatic encephalopathy (CTE). While the clinical presentation of AD and PD is well established, CTE can only be diagnosed post-mortem. Therefore, a distinction can be made between the pathologically defined CTE and RHI-related functional or structural brain changes (RHI-BC) which may result in CTE. Unfortunately, there are currently no accepted biomarkers of CTE nor RHI-BC, a major hurdle to achieving clinical diagnoses. Interestingly, speech has shown promise as a potential biomarker of both AD and PD, being used to accurately classify individuals with AD and PD from those without. Given the overlapping symptoms between CTE, RHI-BC, PD and AD, we aimed to determine if speech could be used to identify individuals with a history of RHI from those without. We therefore created the Verus dataset, consisting of 13 second voice recordings from 605 professional fighters (RHI group) and 605 professional athletes in non-contact sports (control group) for a total of 1210 recordings. Using a deep learning approach, we achieved 85% accuracy in detecting individuals with a history of RHI from those without. We then used our model trained on the Verus dataset to fine-tune on publicly available AD and PD speech datasets and achieved new state-of-the-art accuracies of 84.99% on the AD dataset and 89% on the PD dataset. Finding a biomarker of CTE and RHI-BC that presents early in disease progression is critical to improve risk management and patient outcome. Our study is the first we are aware of to investigate speech as such a candidate biomarker of RHI-BC.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.21263753" rel="alternate" title="Detecting a History of Repetitive Head Impacts from a Short Voice Recording (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.21263989</id><title>Update of transmission modelling and projections of gambiense human African trypanosomiasis in the Mandoul focus, Chad (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.964605+00:00</updated><author><name>Kat S Rock</name></author><author><name>Ching-I Huang</name></author><author><name>Ronald E Crump</name></author><author><name>Paul R Bessell</name></author><author><name>Paul E Brown</name></author><author><name>Inaki Tirados</name></author><author><name>Philippe Solano</name></author><author><name>Marina Antillon</name></author><author><name>Albert Picado</name></author><author><name>Severin Mbainda</name></author><author><name>Justin Darnas</name></author><author><name>Emily H Crowley</name></author><author><name>Steve J Torr</name></author><author><name>Mallaye Peka</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In recent years, an integrated programme of vector control, screening and treatment of &lt;italic&gt;gambiense&lt;/italic&gt; human African trypanosomiasis (gHAT) infections has led to a rapid decline in cases in the Mandoul disease focus of Chad. In this study, we assess whether elimination of transmission has already been achieved in the region despite low-level case reporting, quantify the role of intensified interventions in transmission reduction, and predict the trajectory of gHAT in Mandoul for the next decade under a range of control scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Method&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We utilise human case data (2000–2019) to update a previous model of transmission of gHAT in Mandoul. We also test the updated model, which now has refined assumptions on diagnostic specificity of the current algorithm and an improved fitting method, via a data censoring approach.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conclude that passive detection rates have increased due to improvements in diagnostic availability in fixed health facilities since 2015, by 2.1-fold for stage 1 detection, and by 1.5-fold for stage 2. We find that whilst the diagnostic algorithm for active screening is estimated to be highly specific (99.93%, 95% CI: 99.91–99.95%), the high screening level and limited remaining infection means that some recently reported cases might be false positives, especially the ones that were not parasitologically confirmed. We also find that the focus-wide tsetse vector reduction estimated through model fitting (99.1%, 95% CI: 96.1–99.6%) is comparable to the very high reduction previously measured by the decline in catches of tsetse from monitoring traps. In line with previous results, the model suggests that transmission was likely interrupted in 2015 as a result of intensified interventions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We recommend that additional confirmatory testing is performed in Mandoul in order that the endgame can be carefully monitored now that infection levels are so low. More specific measurement of cases would better inform when it is safe to stop active screening and vector control.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.21263989" rel="alternate" title="Update of transmission modelling and projections of gambiense human African trypanosomiasis in the Mandoul focus, Chad (3 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.21264113</id><title>Altered prefrontal signaling during inhibitory control in a salient drug context in human cocaine addiction (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.964933+00:00</updated><author><name>Ahmet O. Ceceli</name></author><author><name>Muhammad A. Parvaz</name></author><author><name>Sarah King</name></author><author><name>Matthew Schafer</name></author><author><name>Pias Malaker</name></author><author><name>Akarsh Sharma</name></author><author><name>Nelly Alia-Klein</name></author><author><name>Rita Z. Goldstein</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Drug addiction is characterized by impaired Response Inhibition and Salience Attribution (iRISA), where the salience of drug cues is postulated to overpower that of other reinforcers with a concomitant decrease in self-control. However, the neural underpinnings of the interaction between the salience of drug cues and inhibitory control in drug addiction remain unclear. We developed a novel stop-signal fMRI task where the stop-signal reaction time (SSRT—a classical inhibitory control measure) was tested under different salience conditions (modulated by drug, food, threat or neutral words) in individuals with cocaine use disorder (CUD; n=26) vs. demographically matched healthy control participants (HC; n=26). Despite similarities in drug cue-related SSRT and valence and arousal word ratings between groups, the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (dlPFC) activity was diminished during the successful inhibition of drug versus food cues in CUD, and was correlated with lower frequency of recent use, lower craving, and longer abstinence (Z &amp;gt; 3.1, &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt; &amp;lt; .05 corrected). Results suggest reduced involvement of cognitive control regions (e.g., dlPFC) during inhibitory control under a drug context, relative to an alternative reinforcer, in CUD. Supporting the iRISA model, these results elucidate the direct impact of drug-related cue-reactivity on the neural signature of inhibitory control in drug addiction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Excessive salience attribution to drugs and related cues at the expense of nondrug reinforcers and cues and inhibitory control impairments are hallmark symptoms of drug addiction. Although these neuropsychological functions have been investigated independently, brain representations of their interaction are less clear. We illustrate that, despite matched behavioral performance and valence and arousal ratings, the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex—a key node of the cognitive control network also associated with craving—exhibits decreased signaling when successfully inhibiting responses to drug compared to nondrug (food) cues (words) in cocaine-addicted individuals. Modulating salience while taxing self-control permits the study of their combined impact, an ecologically valid examination of the addiction experience. Better understanding inhibitory control under drug cue-reactivity may refine targeted neuromodulatory interventions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.21264113" rel="alternate" title="Altered prefrontal signaling during inhibitory control in a salient drug context in human cocaine addiction (3 tweets)"/><category term="Addiction Medicine"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.21263664</id><title>New insights from GWAS on longitudinal and cross-sectional BMI and related phenotypes in admixed children with Native American and European ancestries (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.965206+00:00</updated><author><name>Lucas Vicuña</name></author><author><name>Esteban Barrientos</name></author><author><name>Tomás Norambuena</name></author><author><name>Danilo Alvares</name></author><author><name>Juan Cristobal Gana</name></author><author><name>Valeria Leiva</name></author><author><name>Veronica Mericq</name></author><author><name>Cristian Meza</name></author><author><name>Ana Pereira</name></author><author><name>José L. Santos</name></author><author><name>Susana Eyheramendy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Body-mass index (BMI) is a well-known marker of adiposity across all ages. The genetic architecture of BMI has been thoroughly studied among adults. In contrast, there are a few genome-wide association studies (GWAS) on children. Further, GWAS on children have been performed almost exclusively in Europeans at single ages. We aimed to better understand the genetic architecture of BMI trajectory across ages and how BMI is affected by Native American genetic ancestry. We performed cross-sectional and longitudinal GWAS for BMI-related traits on 904 admixed Chilean children with mostly European and Mapuche Native American genetic ancestry. We focused on BMI and two traits that occur at the minimum of the childhood BMI growth trajectory, namely, age at adiposity rebound (Age-AR) and BMI at adiposity rebound (BMI-AR). We found several variants in the immune gene &lt;italic&gt;HLA-DQB3&lt;/italic&gt; that are strongly associated with BMI at ages 1.5-2.5 years old, but not at other ages. We also identified a variant in the sex-determining gene &lt;italic&gt;DMRT1&lt;/italic&gt; significantly associated with Age-AR (&lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt; = 9.8 × 10&lt;sup&gt;−9&lt;/sup&gt;). Further, BMI was significantly higher in Mapuche than in European children at all ages between 5.5 and 16.5 years old, but not before. Finally, Age-AR was significantly lower (&lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt; = 0.013) by 1.64 years in the Mapuche children compared with Europeans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.21263664" rel="alternate" title="New insights from GWAS on longitudinal and cross-sectional BMI and related phenotypes in admixed children with Native American and European ancestries (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.21263762</id><title>PathProfiler: Automated Quality Assessment of Retrospective Histopathology Whole-Slide Image Cohorts by Artificial Intelligence – A Case Study for Prostate Cancer Research (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:54.965511+00:00</updated><author><name>Maryam Haghighat</name></author><author><name>Lisa Browning</name></author><author><name>Korsuk Sirinukunwattana</name></author><author><name>Stefano Malacrino</name></author><author><name>Nasullah Khalid Alham</name></author><author><name>Richard Colling</name></author><author><name>Ying Cui</name></author><author><name>Emad Rakha</name></author><author><name>Freddie C. Hamdy</name></author><author><name>Clare Verrill</name></author><author><name>Jens Rittscher</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Research using whole slide images (WSIs) of scanned histopathology slides for the development of artificial intelligence (AI) algorithms has increased exponentially over recent years. Glass slides from large retrospective cohorts with patient follow-up data are digitised for the development and validation of AI tools. Such resources, therefore, become very important, with the need to ensure that their quality is of the standard necessary for downstream AI development. However, manual quality control of such large cohorts of WSIs by visual assessment is unfeasible, and whilst quality control AI algorithms exist, these focus on bespoke aspects of image quality, e.g. focus, or use traditional machine-learning methods such as hand-crafted features, which are unable to classify the range of potential image artefacts that should be considered.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this study, we have trained and validated a multi-task deep neural network to automate the process of quality control of a large retrospective cohort of prostate cases from which glass slides have been scanned several years after production, to determine both the usability of the images for research and the common image artefacts present.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using a two-layer approach, quality overlays of WSIs were generated from a quality assessment undertaken at patch-level at 5X magnification. From these quality overlays the slide-level quality scores were predicted and then compared to those generated by three specialist urological pathologists, with a Pearson correlation of 0.89 for overall ‘usability’ (at a diagnostic level), and 0.87 and 0.82 for focus and H&amp;amp;E staining quality scores respectively. We subsequently applied our quality assessment pipeline to the TCGA prostate cancer cohort and to a colorectal cancer cohort, for comparison.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our model, designated as PathProfiler, indicates comparable predicted usability of images from the cohorts assessed (86-90%), and perhaps more significantly is able to predicts WSIs that could benefit from re-scanning or re-staining for quality improvement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have shown in this study that AI can be used to automate the process of quality control of large retrospective cohorts to maximise research outputs and conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.21263762" rel="alternate" title="PathProfiler: Automated Quality Assessment of Retrospective Histopathology Whole-Slide Image Cohorts by Artificial Intelligence – A Case Study for Prostate Cancer Research (3 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>