<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.976759+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.22268769</id><title>Multimodal repertoire analysis unveils B cell biology in health and immune-mediated diseases (15 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.977389+00:00</updated><author><name>Mineto Ota</name></author><author><name>Masahiro Nakano</name></author><author><name>Yasuo Nagafuchi</name></author><author><name>Satomi Kobayashi</name></author><author><name>Hiroaki Hatano</name></author><author><name>Ryochi Yoshida</name></author><author><name>Yuko Akutsu</name></author><author><name>Takahiro Itamiya</name></author><author><name>Atsushi Matsuo</name></author><author><name>Yumi Tsuchida</name></author><author><name>Hirofumi Shoda</name></author><author><name>Kazuhiko Yamamoto</name></author><author><name>Kazuyoshi Ishigaki</name></author><author><name>Tomohisa Okamura</name></author><author><name>Keishi Fujio</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite involvement of B cells in the pathogenesis of immune-mediated diseases, biological mechanisms underlying their function are scarcely understood. To overcome this gap, comprehensive analysis of the B cell repertoire is essential. Here, we cataloged and investigated the repertoire of five B cell subsets from 595 cases under immune-mediated diseases and health. CDR-H3 length among naïve B cells was shortened among autoimmune diseases in an interferon signature-dependent manner. VDJ gene usage was skewed especially in plasmablasts and unswitched-memory B cells of systemic lupus erythematosus patients with frequent usage of VDJ genes used mainly in naïve B cells and not unswitched-memory B cells of healthy controls. We developed a scoring system for this skewing, and it correlated with peripheral helper T cell transcriptomic signatures and disease activity and decreased after belimumab treatment. Moreover, genetic association analysis identified three molecules possibly involved in somatic hyper-mutation processes in humans. Our multimodal repertoire analysis brings new insights to B cell biology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.22268769" rel="alternate" title="Multimodal repertoire analysis unveils B cell biology in health and immune-mediated diseases (15 tweets)"/><category term="Allergy and Immunology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.22268740</id><title>Estimation of causal effects of a time-varying exposure at multiple time points through Multivariable Mendelian randomization (13 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.977910+00:00</updated><author><name>Eleanor Sanderson</name></author><author><name>Tom G Richardson</name></author><author><name>Tim T Morris</name></author><author><name>Kate Tilling</name></author><author><name>George Davey Smith</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mendelian Randomisation (MR) is a powerful tool in epidemiology to estimate the causal effect of an exposure on an outcome in the presence of unobserved confounding, by utilising genetic variants as instrumental variables (IVs) for the exposure. The effects obtained from MR studies are often interpreted as the lifetime effect of the exposure in question. However, the causal effects of many exposures are thought to vary throughout an individual’s lifetime and there may be periods during which an exposure has more of an effect on a particular outcome. Multivariable MR (MVMR) is an extension of MR that allows for multiple, potentially highly related, exposures to be included in an MR estimation. MVMR estimates the direct effect of each exposure on the outcome conditional on all of the other exposures included in the estimation. We explore the use of MVMR to estimate the direct effect of a single exposure at different time points in an individual’s lifetime on an outcome. We use simulations to illustrate the interpretation of the results from such analyses and the key assumptions required. We show that causal effects at different time periods can be estimated through MVMR when the association between the genetic variants used as instruments and the exposure measured at those time periods varies, however this estimation will not necessarily identify exact time periods over which an exposure has the most effect on the outcome. We illustrate the method through estimation of the causal effects of childhood and adult BMI on smoking behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.22268740" rel="alternate" title="Estimation of causal effects of a time-varying exposure at multiple time points through Multivariable Mendelian randomization (13 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.22268834</id><title>Association between child sexual abuse and mid-life employment earnings (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.978318+00:00</updated><author><name>Samantha Bouchard</name></author><author><name>Rachel Langevin</name></author><author><name>Francis Vergunst</name></author><author><name>Melissa Commisso</name></author><author><name>Pascale Domond</name></author><author><name>Martine Hébert</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Ouellet-Morin</name></author><author><name>Frank Vitaro</name></author><author><name>Richard Tremblay</name></author><author><name>Sylvana M. Côté</name></author><author><name>Massimiliano Orri</name></author><author><name>Marie-Claude Geoffroy</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individuals who have been sexually abused are at a greater risk for poor health, but associations with economic outcomes in mid-life have been overlooked.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We investigated associations between child sexual abuse (≤18 years) and economic outcomes at 33-37 years, while considering type of report (official/retrospective) and characteristics of abuse (type, severity, and chronicity).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This cohort study used data collected for the Quebec Longitudinal Study of Kindergarten Children.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Quebec Longitudinal Study of Kindergarten Children is a population-based sample.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Participants were 3,020 boys and girls attending kindergarten in the Canadian Province of Quebec in 1986/88 and followed up until 2017.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main outcome/Measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Child sexual abuse (0-18 years old) was assessed using both retrospective self-report questionnaires and objective reports (notification to Child Protection Services). Information on employment earnings was obtained from government tax return records. Tobit regressions were used to test associations of sexual abuse with earnings adjusting for sex and family socioeconomic background.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of the 3,020 participants 1,320 [43.7%] self-reported no sexual abuse, 1,340 [44.3%] had no official report but were missing on the retrospective questionnaire, 340 [11.3%] reported retrospective sexual abuse, and 20 [0.7%] had official report. In the fully adjusted model, individuals who retrospectively reported being sexually abused earned US$4,031 (CI=-7,134 to -931) less per year at age 33-37 years, while those with official reports earned US$16,042 (CI=-27,465 to -4,618) less, compared to participants who were not abused. Among individuals with retrospectively reported abuse, those who experienced intra-familial abuse earned US$4,696 (CI=-9,316 to -75) less than individuals who experienced extra-familial abuse, while participants who experienced penetration earned US$6,188 (CI=-12,248 to -129) less than those who experienced non-contact abuse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion and Relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Child sexual abuse puts individuals at risk for lasting reductions in employment earnings in adulthood. Early identification and support for sexual abuse victims could help reduce the economic gap and improve long-term outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key Points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Question&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is child sexual abuse associated with lower mid-life employment earnings?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a large population-based cohort (n=3,020), children exposed to sexual abuse had lower annual employment earnings from age 33-37 years than children nonexposed, after adjustment for childhood socioeconomic circumstances. These differences were more pronounced for individuals with official Child Protection Service reports compared to those with retrospective reports, and for individuals who experienced more severe forms of sexual abuse (i.e., penetration, intra-familial).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Meaning&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Children exposed to sexual abuse are at risk of poor socioeconomic outcomes in mid-adulthood; interventions and support to improve long-term economic participation should be considered.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.22268834" rel="alternate" title="Association between child sexual abuse and mid-life employment earnings (6 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.07.22268880</id><title>The combined impact of persistent infections and human genetic variation on C-reactive protein levels (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.978751+00:00</updated><author><name>Flavia Hodel</name></author><author><name>Olivier Naret</name></author><author><name>Clara Bonnet</name></author><author><name>Nicole Brenner</name></author><author><name>Noemi Bender</name></author><author><name>Tim Waterboer</name></author><author><name>Pedro Marques-Vidal</name></author><author><name>Peter Vollenweider</name></author><author><name>Jacques Fellay</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Multiple human pathogens establish chronic, sometimes life-long infections. Even if they are often latent, these infections can trigger some degree of local or systemic immune response, resulting in chronic low-grade inflammation. There remains an incomplete understanding of the potential contribution of both persistent infections and human genetic variation on chronic low-grade inflammation. We searched for potential associations between seropositivity for 13 persistent pathogens and the plasma levels of the inflammatory biomarker C-reactive protein (CRP), using data collected in the context of the UK Biobank and the CoLaus|PsyCoLaus Study, two large population-based cohorts. We performed backward stepwise regression starting with the following potential predictors: serostatus for each pathogen, polygenic risk score for CRP, as well as demographic and clinical factors known to be associated with CRP. We found evidence for an association between &lt;italic&gt;Chlamydia trachomatis&lt;/italic&gt; (P-value = 5.04e-3) and &lt;italic&gt;Helicobacter pylori&lt;/italic&gt; (P-value = 8.63e-4) seropositivity and higher plasma levels of CRP. We also found an association between pathogen burden and CRP levels (P-value = 4.12e-4). These results improve our understanding of the relationship between persistent infections and chronic inflammation, an important determinant of long-term morbidity in humans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.07.22268880" rel="alternate" title="The combined impact of persistent infections and human genetic variation on C-reactive protein levels (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.475008</id><title>Metabolic rescue ameliorates mitochondrial encephalo-cardiomyopathy in murine and human iPSC models of Leigh syndrome (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.979118+00:00</updated><author><name>Jin-Young Yoon</name></author><author><name>Nastaran Daneshgar</name></author><author><name>Yi Chu</name></author><author><name>Biyi Chen</name></author><author><name>Marco Hefti</name></author><author><name>Kaikobad Irani</name></author><author><name>Long-Sheng Song</name></author><author><name>Charles Brenner</name></author><author><name>E. Dale Abel</name></author><author><name>Barry London</name></author><author><name>Dao-Fu Dai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mice with deletion of complex I subunit Ndufs4 develop mitochondrial encephalomyopathy resembling Leigh syndrome (LS). We report that LS mice also develop severe cardiac bradyarrhythmia and diastolic dysfunction. Human induced pluripotent stem cell-derived cardiomyocytes (iPS-CMs) with Ndufs4 deletion recapitulate LS cardiomyopathy. Mechanistically, we demonstrate a direct link between complex I deficiency, decreased intracellular NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;/ NADH and bradyarrhythmia, mediated by hyperacetylation of the cardiac sodium channel Na&lt;sub&gt;V&lt;/sub&gt;1.5, particularly at K1479 site. Neuronal apoptosis in the cerebellar and midbrain regions in LS mice was associated with hyperacetylation of p53 and activation of microglia. Targeted metabolomics revealed increases in several amino acids and citric acid cycle intermediates, likely due to impairment of NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;-dependent dehydrogenases, and a substantial decrease in reduced Glutathione (GSH). Metabolic rescue by nicotinamide riboside (NR) supplementation increased intracellular NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;/ NADH, restored metabolic derangement, reversed protein hyperacetylation through NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;-dependent Sirtuin deacetylase, and ameliorated cardiomyopathic phenotypes, concomitant with improvement of Na&lt;sub&gt;V&lt;/sub&gt;1.5 current and SERCA2a function measured by Ca2&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;- transients. NR also attenuated neuronal apoptosis and microglial activation in the LS brain and human iPS-derived neurons with Ndufs4 deletion. Our study reveals direct mechanistic explanations of the observed cardiac bradyarrhythmia, diastolic dysfunction and neuronal apoptosis in mouse and human iPSC models of LS.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.475008" rel="alternate" title="Metabolic rescue ameliorates mitochondrial encephalo-cardiomyopathy in murine and human iPSC models of Leigh syndrome (4 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.21268406</id><title>Hypothesis-free detection of gene-interaction effects on biomarker concentration in UK Biobank using variance prioritisation (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.979662+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew S. Lyon</name></author><author><name>Louise A. C. Millard</name></author><author><name>George Davey Smith</name></author><author><name>Tom R. Gaunt</name></author><author><name>Kate Tilling</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Blood biomarkers include disease intervention targets that may interact with genetic and environmental factors resulting in subgroups of individuals who respond differently to treatment. Such interactions may be observed in genetic effects on trait variance. Variance prioritisation is an approach to identify genetic loci with interaction effects by estimating their association with trait variance, even where the modifier is unknown or unmeasured. Here, we develop and evaluate a regression-based Brown-Forsythe test and variance effect estimate to detect such interactions. We provide scalable open-source software (varGWAS) for genome-wide association analysis of SNP-variance effects (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/MRCIEU/varGWAS"&gt;https://github.com/MRCIEU/varGWAS&lt;/ext-link&gt;) and apply our software to 30 blood biomarkers in UK Biobank. We find 468 variance quantitative trait loci across 24 biomarkers and follow up findings to detect 82 gene-environment and six gene-gene interactions independent of strong scale or phantom effects. Our results replicate existing findings and identify novel epistatic effects of &lt;italic&gt;TREH&lt;/italic&gt; rs12225548 x &lt;italic&gt;FUT2&lt;/italic&gt; rs281379 and &lt;italic&gt;TREH&lt;/italic&gt; rs12225548 x &lt;italic&gt;ABO&lt;/italic&gt; rs635634 on alkaline phosphatase and &lt;italic&gt;ZNF827&lt;/italic&gt; rs4835265 x &lt;italic&gt;NEDD4L&lt;/italic&gt; rs4503880 on gamma glutamyltransferase. These data could be used to discover possible subgroup effects for a given biomarker during preclinical drug development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.21268406" rel="alternate" title="Hypothesis-free detection of gene-interaction effects on biomarker concentration in UK Biobank using variance prioritisation (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.22268686</id><title>Immunological Cross-Reactivity to Dengue Virus among Persons with Neuroinvasive West Nile Virus Infection (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.980260+00:00</updated><author><name>Vanessa Raabe</name></author><author><name>Muktha S. Natrajan</name></author><author><name>Chris Huerta</name></author><author><name>Yongxian Xu</name></author><author><name>Lilin Lai</name></author><author><name>Mark J. Mulligan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antibody dependent enhancement has been well described between Zika and dengue viruses, but is poorly characterized between West Nile and dengue viruses. We demonstrate that neuroinvasive West Nile virus infection leads to the development of non-neutralizing, cross-reactive IgG antibodies to dengue and Zika viruses capable of causing antibody dependent enhancement &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; of dengue virus and leads to the formation of flavivirus cross-reactive memory B cells in some patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.22268686" rel="alternate" title="Immunological Cross-Reactivity to Dengue Virus among Persons with Neuroinvasive West Nile Virus Infection (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>