<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.362210+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21267194</id><title>Rare coding variation illuminates the allelic architecture, risk genes, cellular expression patterns, and phenotypic context of autism (116 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.362833+00:00</updated><author><name>Jack M. Fu</name></author><author><name>F. Kyle Satterstrom</name></author><author><name>Minshi Peng</name></author><author><name>Harrison Brand</name></author><author><name>Ryan L. Collins</name></author><author><name>Shan Dong</name></author><author><name>Lambertus Klei</name></author><author><name>Christine R. Stevens</name></author><author><name>Caroline Cusick</name></author><author><name>Mehrtash Babadi</name></author><author><name>Eric Banks</name></author><author><name>Brett Collins</name></author><author><name>Sheila Dodge</name></author><author><name>Stacey B. Gabriel</name></author><author><name>Laura Gauthier</name></author><author><name>Samuel K. Lee</name></author><author><name>Lindsay Liang</name></author><author><name>Alicia Ljungdahl</name></author><author><name>Behrang Mahjani</name></author><author><name>Laura Sloofman</name></author><author><name>Andrey Smirnov</name></author><author><name>Mafalda Barbosa</name></author><author><name>Alfredo Brusco</name></author><author><name>Brian H.Y. Chung</name></author><author><name>Michael L. Cuccaro</name></author><author><name>Enrico Domenici</name></author><author><name>Giovanni Battista Ferrero</name></author><author><name>Jay J. Gargus</name></author><author><name>Gail E. Herman</name></author><author><name>Irva Hertz-Picciotto</name></author><author><name>Patricia Maciel</name></author><author><name>Dara S. Manoach</name></author><author><name>Maria Rita Passos-Bueno</name></author><author><name>Antonio M. Persico</name></author><author><name>Alessandra Renieri</name></author><author><name>Flora Tassone</name></author><author><name>Elisabetta Trabetti</name></author><author><name>Gabriele Campos</name></author><author><name>Marcus C.Y. Chan</name></author><author><name>Chiara Fallerini</name></author><author><name>Elisa Giorgio</name></author><author><name>Ana Cristina Girard</name></author><author><name>Emily Hansen-Kiss</name></author><author><name>So Lun Lee</name></author><author><name>Carla Lintas</name></author><author><name>Yunin Ludena</name></author><author><name>Rachel Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Lisa Pavinato</name></author><author><name>Margaret Pericak-Vance</name></author><author><name>Isaac Pessah</name></author><author><name>Evelise Riberi</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Moyra Smith</name></author><author><name>Claudia I.C. Souza</name></author><author><name>Slavica Trajkova</name></author><author><name>Jaqueline Y.T. Wang</name></author><author><name>Mullin H.C. Yu</name></author><author><name>David J. Cutler</name></author><author><name>Silvia De Rubeis</name></author><author><name>Joseph D. Buxbaum</name></author><author><name>Mark J. Daly</name></author><author><name>Bernie Devlin</name></author><author><name>Kathryn Roeder</name></author><author><name>Stephan J. Sanders</name></author><author><name>Michael E. Talkowski</name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Individuals with autism spectrum disorder (ASD) or related neurodevelopmental disorders (NDDs) often carry disruptive mutations in genes that are depleted of functional variation in the broader population. We build upon this observation and exome sequencing from 154,842 individuals to explore the allelic diversity of rare protein-coding variation contributing risk for ASD and related NDDs. Using an integrative statistical model, we jointly analyzed rare protein-truncating variants (PTVs), damaging missense variants, and copy number variants (CNVs) derived from exome sequencing of 63,237 individuals from ASD cohorts. We discovered 71 genes associated with ASD at a false discovery rate (FDR) ≤ 0.001, a threshold approximately equivalent to exome-wide significance, and 183 genes at FDR ≤ 0.05. Associations were predominantly driven by &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; PTVs, damaging missense variants, and CNVs: 57.4%, 21.2%, and 8.32% of evidence, respectively. Though fewer in number, CNVs conferred greater relative risk than PTVs, and repeat-mediated &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; CNVs exhibited strong maternal bias in parent-of-origin (e.g., 92.3% of 16p11.2 CNVs), whereas all other CNVs showed a paternal bias. To explore how genes associated with ASD and NDD overlap or differ, we analyzed our ASD cohort alongside a developmental delay (DD) cohort from the deciphering developmental disorders study (DDD; n=91,605 samples). We first reanalyzed the DDD dataset using the same models as the ASD cohorts, then performed joint analyses of both cohorts and identified 373 genes contributing to NDD risk at FDR ≤ 0.001 and 662 NDD risk genes at FDR ≤ 0.05. Of these NDD risk genes, 54 genes (125 genes at FDR ≤ 0.05) were unique to the joint analyses and not significant in either cohort alone. Our results confirm overlap of most ASD and DD risk genes, although many differ significantly in frequency of mutation. Analyses of single-cell transcriptome datasets showed that genes associated predominantly with DD were strongly enriched for earlier neurodevelopmental cell types, whereas genes displaying stronger evidence for association in ASD cohorts were more enriched for maturing neurons. The ASD risk genes were also enriched for genes associated with schizophrenia from a separate rare coding variant analysis of 121,570 individuals, emphasizing that these neuropsychiatric disorders share common pathways to risk.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21267194" rel="alternate" title="Rare coding variation illuminates the allelic architecture, risk genes, cellular expression patterns, and phenotypic context of autism (116 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.21268159</id><title>Taiwan Biobank: a rich biomedical research database of the Taiwanese population (40 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.364366+00:00</updated><author><name>Yen-Chen Anne Feng</name></author><author><name>Chia-Yen Chen</name></author><author><name>Tzu-Ting Chen</name></author><author><name>Po-Hsiu Kuo</name></author><author><name>Yi-Hsiang Hsu</name></author><author><name>Hwai-I Yang</name></author><author><name>Wei J. Chen</name></author><author><name>Chen-Yang Shen</name></author><author><name>Tian Ge</name></author><author><name>Hailiang Huang</name></author><author><name>Yen-Feng Lin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Taiwan Biobank (TWB) is an ongoing prospective study of over 150,000 individuals aged 30-70 recruited from across Taiwan beginning in 2012. A comprehensive list of phenotypes was collected for each consented participant at recruitment and follow-up visits through structured interviews and physical measurements. Biomarkers and genetic data were also generated for all participants from blood and urine samples. We present here an overview of the genetic data quality, population structure, and familial relationship within TWB, which consists of predominantly Han Chinese-ancestry individuals, and highlight important attributes and genetic findings thus far from the biobank. A linkage to Taiwan’s National Health Insurance database of &amp;gt;25 years and other health-related registries is underway that will enrich the phenotypic spectrum of TWB and enable deep and longitudinal genetic investigations. TWB provides one of the largest biobank resources for biomedical and public health research in East Asia that will contribute to our understanding of the genetic basis of human health and disease in global populations through collaborative studies with other biobanks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.21268159" rel="alternate" title="Taiwan Biobank: a rich biomedical research database of the Taiwanese population (40 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.21267933</id><title>Protection following BNT162b2 booster substantially exceeds that of a fresh 2-dose vaccine: a quasi-experimental study (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.364824+00:00</updated><author><name>Ofra Amir</name></author><author><name>Yair Goldberg</name></author><author><name>Micha Mandel</name></author><author><name>Yinon M. Bar-On</name></author><author><name>Omri Bodenheimer</name></author><author><name>Nachman Ash</name></author><author><name>Sharon Alroy-Preis</name></author><author><name>Amit Huppert</name></author><author><name>Ron Milo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Israel began administering a BNT162b2 booster dose to restore protection following the waning of the 2-dose vaccine. Biological studies have shown that a fresh booster leads to increased antibody levels compared to a fresh 2-dose vaccine, which may suggest increased effectiveness. To compare the real-world effectiveness of a fresh booster dose with that of a fresh 2-dose vaccine, we conduct a quasi-experimental study that compares populations that were eligible to receive the vaccine at different times due to age cutoff policies. Our analysis shows that a fresh booster increases protection against confirmed infection by 3.7 (95% CI: 2.7 to 5.2) fold compared to a fresh 2-dose vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.21267933" rel="alternate" title="Protection following BNT162b2 booster substantially exceeds that of a fresh 2-dose vaccine: a quasi-experimental study (15 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21267985</id><title>Validation of Genomic and Transcriptomic Models of Homologous Recombination Deficiency in a Real-World Pan-Cancer Cohort (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.365261+00:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Leibowitz</name></author><author><name>Bonnie V Dougherty</name></author><author><name>Joshua SK Bell</name></author><author><name>Joshuah Kapilivsky</name></author><author><name>Jackson Michuda</name></author><author><name>Andrew Sedgwick</name></author><author><name>Wesley Munson</name></author><author><name>Tushar Chandra</name></author><author><name>Jonathan R Dry</name></author><author><name>Nike Beaubier</name></author><author><name>Catherine Igartua</name></author><author><name>Timothy Taxter</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the introduction of DNA-damaging therapies into standard of care cancer treatment, there is a growing need for predictive diagnostics assessing homologous recombination deficiency (HRD) status across tumor types. Following the strong clinical evidence for the utility of DNA-sequencing-based HRD testing in ovarian cancer, and growing evidence in breast cancer, we present analytical validation of the Tempus|HRD-DNA test. We further developed, validated, and explored the Tempus|HRD-RNA model, which uses gene expression data from 16,470 RNA-seq samples to predict HRD status from formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded (FFPE) tumor samples across numerous cancer types.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Genomic and transcriptomic profiling was performed using next-generation sequencing from Tempus|xT, Tempus|xO, Tempus|xE, Tempus|RS, and Tempus|RS.v2 assays on 48,843 samples. Samples were labeled based on their &lt;italic&gt;BRCA1, BRCA2&lt;/italic&gt; and selected Homologous Recombination Repair (HRR) pathway gene (&lt;italic&gt;CDK12, PALB2, RAD51B, RAD51C, RAD51D&lt;/italic&gt;) mutational status to train and validate HRD-DNA, a genome-wide loss-of-heterozygosity biomarker, and HRD-RNA, a logistic regression model trained on gene expression, using several performance metrics and statistical tests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a sample of 2,058 breast and 1,216 ovarian tumors, BRCA status was predicted by HRD-DNA with F1-scores of 0.98 and 0.96, respectively. Across an independent set of 1,363 samples across solid tumor types, the HRD-RNA model was predictive of BRCA status in prostate, pancreatic, and non-small cell lung cancer, with F1-scores of 0.88, 0.69, and 0.62, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We predict HRD-positive patients across many cancer types and believe both HRD models may generalize to other mechanisms of HRD outside of BRCA loss. HRD-RNA complements DNA-based HRD detection methods, especially for indications with low prevalence of BRCA alterations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21267985" rel="alternate" title="Validation of Genomic and Transcriptomic Models of Homologous Recombination Deficiency in a Real-World Pan-Cancer Cohort (15 tweets)"/><category term="Oncology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.21268076</id><title>Evaluating a communication aid for return of genetic results in families with hypertrophic cardiomyopathy: A randomized controlled trial (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.365702+00:00</updated><author><name>Charlotte Burns</name></author><author><name>Laura Yeates</name></author><author><name>Joanna Sweeting</name></author><author><name>Christopher Semsarian</name></author><author><name>Jodie Ingles</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Genetic testing for hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (HCM) is considered a key aspect of management. Communication of genetic test results to the proband and their family members, can be a barrier to effective uptake. We hypothesized that a communication aid would facilitate effective communication, and sought to evaluate knowledge and communication of HCM risk to at-risk relatives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was a prospective randomized controlled trial. Consecutive HCM patients attending a specialized clinic, who agreed to participate, were randomized to the intervention or current clinical practice. The intervention consisted of a genetic counselorled appointment, separate to their clinical cardiology review, and guided by a communication booklet which could be written in and taken home. Current clinical practice was defined as the return of the genetic result by a genetic counselor and cardiologist, often as part of a clinical cardiology review. The primary outcome was the ability and confidence of the individual to communicate genetic results to at-risk relatives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;italic&gt;a priori&lt;/italic&gt; outcome of improved communication amongst HCM families did not show statistically significant differences between the control and intervention group, though the majority of probands in the intervention group achieved fair communication (n=13/22) and had higher genetic knowledge scores than those in the control group (7 ± 3 versus 6 ± 3). A total of 29% of at-risk relatives were not informed of a genetic result in their family.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communication amongst HCM families remains challenging, with nearly a third of at-risk relatives not informed of a genetic result. We show a significant gap in the current approach to supporting family communication about genetics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Australian New Zealand Clinical Trials Registry: ACTRN12617000706370&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What is known about this topic&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communication between family members regarding genetic testing can be a barrier to effective uptake.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What this paper adds to the topic&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communication is a challenge in HCM families, with nearly a third of at-risk relatives not informed of a genetic result. There is a significant gap in the current approaches to supporting family communication about genetics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.21268076" rel="alternate" title="Evaluating a communication aid for return of genetic results in families with hypertrophic cardiomyopathy: A randomized controlled trial (10 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.18.21267894</id><title>Deep learning based models to study the effect of glaucoma genes on angle dysgenesis in-vivo (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.366196+00:00</updated><author><name>Viney Gupta</name></author><author><name>Shweta Birla</name></author><author><name>Toshit Varshney</name></author><author><name>Bindu I Somarajan</name></author><author><name>Shikha Gupta</name></author><author><name>Mrinalini Gupta</name></author><author><name>Karthikeyan Mahalingam</name></author><author><name>Abhishek Singh</name></author><author><name>Dinesh Gupta</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To predict the presence of Angle Dysgenesis on Anterior Segment Optical Coherence Tomography (ADoA) using deep learning and to correlate ADoA with mutations in known glaucoma genes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A cross-sectional observational study.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eight hundred, high definition anterior segment optical coherence tomography (ASOCT) B-scans were included, out of which 340 images (One scan per eye) were used to build the machine learning (ML) model and the rest were used for validation of ADoA. Out of 340 images, 170 scans included PCG (n=27), JOAG (n=86) and POAG (n=57) eyes and the rest were controls. The genetic validation dataset consisted of another 393 images of patients with known mutations compared with 320 images of healthy controls&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;ADoA was defined as the absence of Schlemm’s canal(SC), the presence of extensive hyper-reflectivity over the region of trabecular meshwork or a hyper-reflective membrane (HM) over the region of the trabecular meshwork. Deep learning was used to classify a given ASOCT image as either having angle dysgenesis or not. ADoA was then specifically looked for, on ASOCT images of patients with mutations in the known genes for glaucoma (&lt;italic&gt;MYOC, CYP1B1, FOXC1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;LTBP2&lt;/italic&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Outcome measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using Deep learning to identify ADoA in patients with known gene mutations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our three optimized deep learning models showed an accuracy &amp;gt; 95%, specificity &amp;gt;97% and sensitivity &amp;gt;96% in detecting angle dysgenesis on ASOCT in the internal test dataset. The area under receiver operating characteristic (AUROC) curve, based on the external validation cohort were 0.91 (95% CI, 0.88 to 0.95), 0.80 (95% CI, 0.75 to 0.86) and 0.86 (95% CI, 0.80 to 0.91) for the three models. Amongst the patients with known gene mutations, ADoA was observed among all the patients with &lt;italic&gt;MYOC&lt;/italic&gt; mutations, as it was also observed among those with &lt;italic&gt;CYP1B1, FOXC1&lt;/italic&gt; and with &lt;italic&gt;LTBP2&lt;/italic&gt; mutations compared to only 5% of those healthy controls (with no glaucoma mutations).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Three deep learning models were developed for a consensus-based outcome to objectively identify ADoA among glaucoma patients. All patients with &lt;italic&gt;MYOC&lt;/italic&gt; mutations had ADoA as predicted by the models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.18.21267894" rel="alternate" title="Deep learning based models to study the effect of glaucoma genes on angle dysgenesis in-vivo (6 tweets)"/><category term="Ophthalmology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.21268191</id><title>Prevalence of HIV and Syphilis and their Co-infection among Men Having Sex with Men in Asia: A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.366792+00:00</updated><author><name>Sultan Mahmud</name></author><author><name>Md Mohsin</name></author><author><name>Abdul Muyeed</name></author><author><name>Sorif Hossain</name></author><author><name>Md Mynul Islam</name></author><author><name>Ariful Islam</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Studies found that the group of men who have sex with men (MSM) is at a very high level of risk of HIV and sexually transmitted infections (STIs) in Asian regions due to multiple reasons. Although the prevalence of HIV among general people in Asia is considered low, the prevalence of HIV and Syphilis among MSM in this region was found very high and usually, it goes unnoticed. This study aimed to inspect the prevalence and trends of HIV, Syphilis, and their co-infection among MSM in Asia. 
Methods: A systematic search was performed on January 5, 2021, in PubMed, MEDLINE, and Google Scholar databases. To evaluate the heterogeneity, Q-tests and were used. To explore the publication bias, Eggers' test and funnel plot were used. The random-effect model and subgroup analysis were performed due to the significant heterogeneity.
Results: A total of 2,872 articles were identified, and 66 articles of high quality were included in the final analysis. The overall prevalence of HIV among MSM and Syphilis was estimated considering 69 estimates from 66 studies whereas 19 estimates of co-infection were found in 17 studies. The pooled HIV prevalence was 8.48% (CI: 7.01-9.95) and the pooled Syphilis prevalence was 9.86% (CI: 8.30-11.41) with significant heterogeneity and publication bias. The pooled prevalence of HIV and Syphilis co-infection was 2.99% (CI: 1.70-4.27) with significant heterogeneity and no publication bias. The HIV, Syphilis, and HIV and Syphilis co-infection prevalence estimates exhibited an upward trend during 2002-2017.
Conclusions: HIV, Syphilis, and their co-infection are quite prevalent among MSM in the Asia-Pacific region. Integrated and intensified intervention strategies, HIV testing, and improved access to antiretroviral treatment as well as increased awareness are needed to reduce HIV, Syphilis, and their co-infection among the discussed vulnerable group.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.21268191" rel="alternate" title="Prevalence of HIV and Syphilis and their Co-infection among Men Having Sex with Men in Asia: A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis (4 tweets)"/><category term="HIV/AIDS"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268114</id><title>A tractometry investigation of white matter tract network structure and relationships with cognitive function in relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.367401+00:00</updated><author><name>Danka Jandric</name></author><author><name>Geoff JM Parker</name></author><author><name>Hamied Haroon</name></author><author><name>Valentina Tomassini</name></author><author><name>Nils Muhlert</name></author><author><name>Ilona Lipp</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the brain changes underlying cognitive dysfunction is a key priority in multiple sclerosis to improve monitoring and treatment of this debilitating symptom. Functional connectivity network changes are associated with cognitive dysfunction, but it is less well understood how changes in normal appearing white matter relate to cognitive symptoms. If white matter tracts share a similar network structure it would be expected that tracts within a network are similarly affected by MS pathology. In the present study, we used a tractometry approach to explore patterns of variance in diffusion metrics across white matter (WM) tracts. We investigated whether separate networks, based on normal variation or pathology, appear, and how this relates to neuropsychological test performance across cognitive domains. A sample of 102 relapsing-remitting MS patients and 27 healthy controls underwent MRI and neuropsychological testing. Tractography was performed on diffusion MRI data to extract 40 WM tracts and microstructural measures were extracted from each tract. Principal component analysis (PCA) was used to decompose metrics from all tracts to assess the presence of any co-variance structure among the tracts. Similarly, PCA was applied to cognitive test scores to identify the main cognitive domains. Finally, we assessed the ability of tract components to predict test performance across cognitive domains. We found that a single component which captured pathology across all tracts explained the most variance and that there was little evidence for separate, smaller network patterns of pathology. WM tract components were weak, but significant, predictors of cognitive function in MS. These findings highlight the need to investigate the relationship between the normal appearing white matter and cognitive impairment further and on a more granular level, to improve the understanding of the network structure of the brain in MS.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268114" rel="alternate" title="A tractometry investigation of white matter tract network structure and relationships with cognitive function in relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>