<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.788033+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.21260947</id><title>Prospective validation of host transcriptomic biomarkers for pulmonary tuberculosis by real-time PCR (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.788717+00:00</updated><author><name>Simon C. Mendelsohn</name></author><author><name>Stanley Kimbung Mbandi</name></author><author><name>Andrew Fiore-Gartland</name></author><author><name>Adam Penn-Nicholson</name></author><author><name>Munyaradzi Musvosvi</name></author><author><name>Humphrey Mulenga</name></author><author><name>Michelle Fisher</name></author><author><name>Katie Hadley</name></author><author><name>Mzwandile Erasmus</name></author><author><name>Onke Nombida</name></author><author><name>Michèle Tameris</name></author><author><name>Gerhard Walzl</name></author><author><name>Kogieleum Naidoo</name></author><author><name>Gavin Churchyard</name></author><author><name>Mark Hatherill</name></author><author><name>Thomas J. Scriba</name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We tested performance of host-blood transcriptomic tuberculosis (TB) signatures for active case-finding. Among 20,207 HIV-uninfected and 963 HIV-infected adults screened; 2,923 and 861 were enrolled from five South African communities. Eight signatures were measured by microfluidic RT-qPCR and participants were microbiologically-investigated for pulmonary TB at baseline, and actively surveilled for incident disease through 15 months. Diagnostic AUCs for 61 HIV-uninfected (weighted-prevalence 1.1%) and 10 HIV-infected (prevalence 1.2%) prevalent TB cases for the 8 signatures were 0.63–0.79 and 0.65–0.88, respectively. Thereafter, 24 HIV-uninfected and 9 HIV-infected participants progressed to incident TB (1.1 and 1.0 per 100 person-years, respectively). Prognostic AUCs through 15-months follow-up were 0.49–0.66 and 0.54–0.81, respectively. Prognostic performance for incident TB occurring within 6-12 months in HIV-negative participants was higher for all signatures. None of the signatures met WHO Target Product Profile criteria for a triage test to diagnose asymptomatic TB; most signatures met the criteria for symptomatic TB. Prognostic accuracy of most signatures for incident TB within six months of testing met the criteria for an incipient TB test.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.21260947" rel="alternate" title="Prospective validation of host transcriptomic biomarkers for pulmonary tuberculosis by real-time PCR (16 tweets)"/><category term="Respiratory Medicine"/><published>2021-07-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21260986</id><title>A plasma metabolite score of three eicosanoids predicts incident type 2 diabetes – a prospective study in three independent cohorts (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.789436+00:00</updated><author><name>Karolina Tuomisto</name></author><author><name>Joonatan Palmu</name></author><author><name>Tao Long</name></author><author><name>Jeramie D. Watrous</name></author><author><name>Kysha Mercader</name></author><author><name>Kim A. Lagerborg</name></author><author><name>Allen Andres</name></author><author><name>Marko Salmi</name></author><author><name>Sirpa Jalkanen</name></author><author><name>Ramachandran S. Vasan</name></author><author><name>Michael Inouye</name></author><author><name>Aki S. Havulinna</name></author><author><name>Pekka Jousilahti</name></author><author><name>Teemu J. Niiranen</name></author><author><name>Susan Cheng</name></author><author><name>Mohit Jain</name></author><author><name>Veikko Salomaa</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aim&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Peptide markers of inflammation have been associated with the development of type 2 diabetes. The role of upstream, lipid-derived mediators of inflammation such as eicosanoids, remains less clear. The aim was to examine whether eicosanoids are associated with incident type 2 diabetes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the FINRISK 2002 study, a population-based sample of Finnish men and women aged 25-74 years, we used directed, non-targeted liquid chromatography – mass spectrometry to identify 545 eicosanoids and related oxylipins in the participants’ plasma samples (n=8,292). We used multivariable-adjusted Cox regression to examine associations between eicosanoids and incident type 2 diabetes. The findings were replicated in the Framingham Heart Study (FHS, n=2,886) and DILGOM 2007 (n=3,905). Together, these three cohorts had 1070 cases of incident type 2 diabetes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;76 eicosanoids were associated individually with incident type 2 diabetes. We identified three eicosanoids independently associated with incident type 2 diabetes using stepwise Cox regression with forward selection and a Bonferroni-corrected inclusion threshold. A three-eicosanoid risk score produced a hazard ratio (HR) of 1.56 (95% confidence interval 1.41-1.72) per one standard deviation (SD) increment for risk of incident diabetes. The HR for comparing the top quartile to the lowest was 2.80 (2.53-3.07). Meta-analysis of the three cohorts yielded a pooled HR per SD of 1.31 (1.05-1.56).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plasma eicosanoid profiles predict incident type 2 diabetes and the clearest signals replicate in three independent cohorts. Our findings give new information on the biology underlying type 2 diabetes and suggest opportunities for early identification of people at risk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21260986" rel="alternate" title="A plasma metabolite score of three eicosanoids predicts incident type 2 diabetes – a prospective study in three independent cohorts (6 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261034</id><title>Running related biomechanical risk factors for overuse injuries in distance runners: A systematic review considering injury specificity and the potentials for future research (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.790001+00:00</updated><author><name>Steffen Willwacher</name></author><author><name>Markus Kurz</name></author><author><name>Johanna Robbin</name></author><author><name>Matthias Thelen</name></author><author><name>Joseph Hamill</name></author><author><name>Luke Kelly</name></author><author><name>Patrick Mai</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To identify and evaluate the evidence of the most relevant running-related risk factors (RRRFs) for running-related overuse injuries (ROIs) and to suggest future research directions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Systematic review considering prospective and retrospective studies. (PROSPERO_ID: 236832)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data sources&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pubmed. Connected Papers. The search was performed in February 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Eligibility criteria&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;English language. Studies on participants whose primary sport is running addressing the risk for the seven most common ROIs and at least one kinematic, kinetic (including pressure measurements), or electromyographic RRRF. An RRRF needed to be identified in at least one prospective or two retrospective studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sixty-two articles fulfilled our eligibility criteria. Levels of evidence for specific ROIs ranged from conflicting to moderate evidence. Running populations and methods applied varied considerably between studies. While some RRRFs appeared for several ROIs, most RRRFs were specific for a particular ROI. The biomechanical measurements performed in many studies would have allowed for consideration of many more RRRFs than have been reported, highlighting a potential for more effective data usage in the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study offers a comprehensive overview of RRRFs for the most common ROIs, which might serve as a starting point to develop ROI-specific risk profiles of individual runners. Future work should use macroscopic (big data) approaches involving long-term data collections in the real world and microscopic approaches involving precise stress calculations using recent developments in biomechanical modelling. However, consensus on data collection standards (including the quantification of workload and stress tolerance variables and the reporting of injuries) is warranted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261034" rel="alternate" title="Running related biomechanical risk factors for overuse injuries in distance runners: A systematic review considering injury specificity and the potentials for future research (3 tweets)"/><category term="Orthopedics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>