<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.352046+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22268989</id><title>Network Constraints on Longitudinal Grey Matter Changes in First Episode Psychosis (38 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.352212+00:00</updated><author><name>Sidhant Chopra</name></author><author><name>Stuart Oldham</name></author><author><name>Ashlea Segal</name></author><author><name>Alexander Holmes</name></author><author><name>Kristina Sabaroedin</name></author><author><name>Edwina R. Orchard</name></author><author><name>Shona M. Francey</name></author><author><name>Brian O’Donoghue</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Cropley</name></author><author><name>Barnaby Nelson</name></author><author><name>Jessica Graham</name></author><author><name>Lara Baldwin</name></author><author><name>Jeggan Tiego</name></author><author><name>Hok Pan Yuen</name></author><author><name>Kelly Allott</name></author><author><name>Mario Alvarez-Jimenez</name></author><author><name>Susy Harrigan</name></author><author><name>Christos Pantelis</name></author><author><name>Stephen J Wood</name></author><author><name>Mark Bellgrove</name></author><author><name>Patrick McGorry</name></author><author><name>Alex Fornito</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Different regions of the brain’s grey matter are connected by a complex structural network of white matter fibres, which are responsible for the propagation of action potentials and the transport of trophic and other molecules. In neurodegenerative disease, these connections constrain the way in which grey matter volume loss progresses. Here, we investigated whether connectome architecture also shapes the spatial pattern of longitudinal grey matter volume changes attributable to illness and antipsychotic medication in first episode psychosis (FEP).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted a triple-blind randomised placebo-control MRI study where 62 young adults with first episode psychosis received either an atypical antipsychotic or placebo over 6-months. A healthy control group was also recruited. Anatomical MRI scans were acquired at baseline, 3-months and 12-months. Deformation-based morphometry was used to estimate illness-related and antipsychotic-related grey matter volume changes over time. Representative functional and structural brain connectivity patterns were derived from an independent healthy control group using resting-state functional MRI and diffusion-weighted imaging. We used neighbourhood deformation models to predict the extent of brain change in a given area by the changes observed in areas to which it is either structurally connected or functionally coupled.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;At baseline, we found that empirical illness-related regional volume differences were strongly correlated with predicted differences using a model constrained by structural connectivity weights (r = .541; p &amp;lt; .001). At 3-months and 12-months, we also found a strong correlation between longitudinal regional illness-related (r &amp;gt; .516; p &amp;lt; .001) and antipsychotic-related volume change (r &amp;gt; .591; p &amp;lt; .001) with volumetric changes in structurally connected areas. These correlations were significantly greater than those observed across various null models accounting for lower-order spatial and network properties of the data. Associations between empirical and predicted volume change estimates were much lower for models that only considered binary structural connectivity (all r &amp;lt; .376), or which were constrained by inter-regional functional coupling (all r &amp;lt; .436). Finally, we found that potential epicentres of volume change emerged posteriorly early in the illness and shifted to the prefrontal cortex by later illness stages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Psychosis- and antipsychotic-related grey matter volume changes are strongly shaped by anatomical brain connectivity. This result is consistent with findings in other neurological disorders and implies that such connections may constrain pathological processes causing brain dysfunction in FEP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22268989" rel="alternate" title="Network Constraints on Longitudinal Grey Matter Changes in First Episode Psychosis (38 tweets)"/><category term="Psychiatry and Clinical Psychology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.22269328</id><title>Estimating body fat distribution - a driver of cardiometabolic health - from silhouette images (15 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.352363+00:00</updated><author><name>Marcus D.R. Klarqvist</name></author><author><name>Saaket Agrawal</name></author><author><name>Nathaniel Diamant</name></author><author><name>Patrick T. Ellinor</name></author><author><name>Anthony Philippakis</name></author><author><name>Kenney Ng</name></author><author><name>Puneet Batra</name></author><author><name>Amit V. Khera</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Inter-individual variation in fat distribution is increasingly recognized as clinically important but is not routinely assessed in clinical practice because quantification requires medical imaging.

Objectives: We hypothesized that a deep learning model trained on an individual's body shape outline - or silhouette - would enable accurate estimation of specific fat depots, including visceral (VAT), abdominal subcutaneous (ASAT), and gluteofemoral (GFAT) adipose tissue volumes, and VAT/ASAT ratio. We additionally set out to study whether silhouette-estimated VAT/ASAT ratio may stratify risk of cardiometabolic diseases independent of body mass index (BMI) and waist circumference.

Methods: Two-dimensional coronal and sagittal silhouettes were constructed from whole-body magnetic resonance images in 40,032 participants of the UK Biobank and used to train a convolutional neural network to predict VAT, ASAT, and GFAT volumes, and VAT/ASAT ratio. Logistic and Cox regressions were used to determine the independent association of silhouette-predicted VAT/ASAT ratio with type 2 diabetes and coronary artery disease.

Results: Mean age of the study participants was 65 years and 51% were female. A deep learning model trained on silhouettes enabled accurate estimation of VAT, ASAT, and GFAT volumes (R2: 0.88, 0.93, and 0.93, respectively), outperforming a comparator model combining anthropometric and bioimpedance measures (ΔR2 = 0.05-0.13). Next, we studied VAT/ASAT ratio, a nearly BMI- and waist circumference-independent marker of unhealthy fat distribution. While the comparator model poorly predicted VAT/ASAT ratio (R2: 0.17-0.26), a silhouette-based model enabled significant improvement (R2: 0.50-0.55). Silhouette-predicted VAT/ASAT ratio was associated with increased prevalence of type 2 diabetes and coronary artery disease.

Conclusions: Body silhouette images can estimate important measures of fat distribution, laying the scientific foundation for population-based assessment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.22269328" rel="alternate" title="Estimating body fat distribution - a driver of cardiometabolic health - from silhouette images (15 tweets)"/><category term="Endocrinology (including Diabetes Mellitus and Metabolic Disease)"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22269005</id><title>Identifying the potential role of insomnia on multimorbidity: A Mendelian randomization phenome-wide association study in UK Biobank (15 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.352445+00:00</updated><author><name>Mark J Gibson</name></author><author><name>Deborah A Lawlor</name></author><author><name>Louise AC Millard</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Objectives: To identify the breadth of potential causal effects of insomnia on health outcomes and hence its possible role in multimorbidity.
Design: Mendelian randomisation (MR) Phenome-wide association study (MR-PheWAS) with two-sample Mendelian randomisation follow-up.
Setting: Individual data from UK Biobank and summary data from a number of genome-wide association studies.
Participants: 336,975 unrelated white-British UK Biobank participants.
Exposures: Standardised genetic risk of insomnia for the MR-PheWAS and genetically predicted insomnia for the two-sample MR follow-up, with insomnia instrumented by a genetic risk score (GRS) created from 129 single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs).
Main outcomes measures: 11,409 outcomes from UK Biobank extracted and processed by an automated pipeline (PHESANT). Potential causal effects (i.e., those passing a Bonferroni-corrected significance threshold) were followed up with two-sample MR in MR-Base, where possible.
Results: 437 potential causal effects of insomnia were observed for a number of traits, including anxiety, stress, depression, mania, addiction, pain, body composition, immune, respiratory, endocrine, dental, musculoskeletal, cardiovascular and reproductive traits, as well as socioeconomic and behavioural traits. We were able to undertake two-sample MR for 71 of these 437 and found evidence of causal effects (with directionally concordant effect estimates across all analyses) for 25 of these. These included, for example, risk of anxiety disorders (OR=1.55 [95% confidence interval (CI): 1.30, 1.86] per category increase in insomnia), diseases of the oesophagus/stomach/duodenum (OR=1.32 [95% CI: 1.14, 1.53]) and spondylosis (OR=1.57 [95% CI: 1.22, 2.01]). 
Conclusion: Insomnia potentially causes a wide range of adverse health outcomes and behaviours. This has implications for developing interventions to prevent and treat a number of diseases in order to reduce multimorbidity and associated polypharmacy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22269005" rel="alternate" title="Identifying the potential role of insomnia on multimorbidity: A Mendelian randomization phenome-wide association study in UK Biobank (15 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.22269176</id><title>ExPRSweb - An Online Repository with Polygenic Risk Scores for Common Health-related Exposures (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.352506+00:00</updated><author><name>Ying Ma</name></author><author><name>Snehal Patil</name></author><author><name>Xiang Zhou</name></author><author><name>Bhramar Mukherjee</name></author><author><name>Lars G. Fritsche</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Complex traits are influenced by genetic risk factors, lifestyle, and environmental variables, so called exposures. Some exposures, e.g., smoking or lipid levels, have common genetic modifiers identified in genome-wide association studies. Since measurements are often unfeasible, Exposure Polygenic Risk Scores (ExPRSs) offer an alternative to study the influence of exposures on various phenotypes. Here, we collected publicly available summary statistics for 28 exposures and applied four common PRS methods to generate ExPRSs in two large biobanks, the Michigan Genomics Initiative and the UK Biobank. We established ExPRS for 27 exposures and demonstrated their applicability in phenome-wide association studies and as predictors for common chronic conditions. Especially, the addition of multiple ExPRSs showed, for several chronic conditions, an improvement compared prediction models that only included traditional, disease-focused PRSs. To facilitate follow-up studies, we share all ExPRS constructs and generated results via an online repository called ExPRSweb.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.22269176" rel="alternate" title="ExPRSweb - An Online Repository with Polygenic Risk Scores for Common Health-related Exposures (11 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.22269229</id><title>The impact of depression diagnosis on diabetes and lifetime hyperglycaemia (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.352573+00:00</updated><author><name>Saskia P Hagenaars</name></author><author><name>Alexandra C Gillett</name></author><author><name>Francesco Casanova</name></author><author><name>Katherine G Young</name></author><author><name>Harry Green</name></author><author><name>Cathryn M Lewis</name></author><author><name>Jess Tyrrell</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aims&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The aim of this study was to evaluate longitudinal associations between the mean and variability of HbA1c levels in individuals with type 2 diabetes (T2D) and major depressive disorder (MDD).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individuals with T2D from the UK Biobank with linked primary care records were analysed. An HbA1c measurement within +/- 6-months of T2D diagnosis was taken as baseline, with subsequent HbA1c measurements used as the outcome in generalised least squares regression to evaluate longitudinal associations with a three-level MDD diagnosis variable (MDD controls, pre-T2D MDD cases and post-T2D MDD cases).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using 7,968 T2D individuals, we show that MDD has utility in explaining mean HbA1c levels (p=6.53E-08). This is attributable to MDD diagnosis interacting with baseline T2D medication (p=3.36E-04) and baseline HbA1c (p=2.66E-05), but not with time-when all else is equal, the temporal trend in expected HbA1c did not differ by MDD diagnosis. However, joint consideration with baseline T2D medication showed that each additional medication prescribed was associated with a +4 mmol/mol (2.5%) increase in expected HbA1c across follow up for post-T2D MDD cases, relative to pre-T2D MDD cases and MDD controls. Furthermore, variability in HbA1c increased across time for post-T2D MDD cases but decreased for MDD controls and pre-T2D MDD cases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;These findings suggest closer monitoring of individuals with both T2D and MDD is essential to improve their diabetic control, particularly for those who develop MDD after T2D diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Novelty statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What is already known?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Comorbid T2D and MDD is associated with poorer diabetic control and worse prognosis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What this study has found?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We demonstrate a strong complex relationship between MDD and diabetic control, influenced by diabetic medication and baseline HbA1c levels. We showed that individuals who develop MDD after their T2D diagnosis have greater variability in HbA1c levels over time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What are the implications of the study?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study shows the importance of closer monitoring of HbA1c in individuals with both T2D and MDD, particularly those who develop MDD after diabetes, to improve diabetic control and reduce complications associated comorbid T2D and MDD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.22269229" rel="alternate" title="The impact of depression diagnosis on diabetes and lifetime hyperglycaemia (11 tweets)"/><category term="Endocrinology (including Diabetes Mellitus and Metabolic Disease)"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.22269287</id><title>Pramipexole Enhances Reward Learning by Preserving Value Estimates (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.352648+00:00</updated><author><name>Don Chamith Halahakoon</name></author><author><name>Alexander Kaltenboeck</name></author><author><name>Marieke Martens</name></author><author><name>John G. Geddes</name></author><author><name>Catherine J. Harmer</name></author><author><name>Philip Cowen</name></author><author><name>Michael Browning</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dopamine D2-like receptor agonists show promise as treatments for depression. They are thought to act by altering how individuals learn from rewarding experiences. However, the nature of these reward learning alterations, and the mechanisms by which they are produced is not clear. Reinforcement learning accounts describe three distinct processes that may produce similar changes in reward learning behaviour; increased reward sensitivity, increased inverse decision temperature and decreased value decay. As these processes produce equivalent effects on behaviour, arbitrating between them requires measurement of how expectations and prediction errors are altered. In the present study, we characterised the behavioural effects of a sustained 2-week course of the D2/3/4 receptor agonist pramipexole on reward learning and used fMRI measures of expectation and prediction error to assess which of these three mechanistic processes were responsible for the behavioural effects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;40 healthy volunteers (Age: 18-43, 50% female) were randomly allocated to receive either two weeks of pramipexole (titrated to 1mg/day) or placebo in a double-blind, between subject design. Participants completed a probabilistic instrumental learning task, in which stimuli were associated with either rewards or losses, before the pharmacological intervention and twice between days 12-15 of the intervention (once with and once without fMRI). Both asymptotic choice accuracy, and a reinforcement learning model, were used to assess reward learning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Behaviourally, pramipexole specifically increased choice accuracy in the reward condition, with no effect in the loss condition. Pramipexole increased the BOLD response in the orbital frontal cortex during the expectation of win trials but decreased the BOLD response to reward prediction errors in the ventromedial prefrontal cortex. This pattern of results indicates that pramipexole enhances choice accuracy by reducing the decay of estimated values during reward learning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The D2-like receptor agonist pramipexole enhances reward learning by preserving learned values. This is a plausible candidate mechanism for pramipexole’s observed anti-depressant effect.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.22269287" rel="alternate" title="Pramipexole Enhances Reward Learning by Preserving Value Estimates (11 tweets)"/><category term="Psychiatry and Clinical Psychology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.22269035</id><title>Whole genome analysis reveals the genomic complexity in metastatic cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.352722+00:00</updated><author><name>Amarinder S. Thind</name></author><author><name>Bruce Ashford</name></author><author><name>Dario Strbenac</name></author><author><name>Ruta Gupta</name></author><author><name>Jonathan R Clark</name></author><author><name>N. Gopalakrishna Iyer</name></author><author><name>Jenny Mitchell</name></author><author><name>Jenny Lee</name></author><author><name>Simon A Mueller</name></author><author><name>Elahe Minaei</name></author><author><name>Jay Perry</name></author><author><name>Marie Ranson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Metastatic cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma (cSCC) is associated with a high risk of recurrence and poor prognosis. There is limited published data exploring whole genome sequencing (WGS). The aim of this project was to provide the first comprehensive genomic understanding of the state of metastatic cSCC. In this study, we used WGS on matched tumor and blood DNA to detect somatic genetic alterations from 25 patients with regional metastases of head and neck cSCC. Our computational analyses interrogate clinical impacts of these genetic alterations on metastatic cSCC across the cohort for both the coding and non-coding genome.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the non-coding genome, 3’UTR regions of &lt;italic&gt;EVC&lt;/italic&gt; (48%), &lt;italic&gt;PPP1R1A&lt;/italic&gt; (48%) and &lt;italic&gt;LUM&lt;/italic&gt; (16%) were significantly functionally altered (Q-value &amp;lt; 0.05). Further, significant functional alterations are observed in the tumor suppressing lncRNA LINC01003 (68% of specimens, Q-value: 0.0158). In addition, significant recurrent copy number loss in tumor suppressor genes &lt;italic&gt;KANSL1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;PTPRD&lt;/italic&gt; and gain in &lt;italic&gt;CALR, CCND1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;FGF3&lt;/italic&gt; was observed for coding regions. SNV’s driver analyses predicted &lt;italic&gt;TP53, CDKN2A&lt;/italic&gt;, as potential drivers of the metastasis cSCC (using 3 different tools). Indel signature analysis highlight dominance of ID signature 13 followed by ID8 &amp;amp; ID9. Interestingly, ID 9 has previously been shown to have no association with skin melanoma, unlike ID 13 and 8, suggesting some point of difference between these two skin-based diseases. The overall landscape of variation in metastatic cSCC is dominated by cell cycle and DNA repair disruption.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.22269035" rel="alternate" title="Whole genome analysis reveals the genomic complexity in metastatic cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma (10 tweets)"/><category term="Oncology"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.22269323</id><title>Cerebrospinal fluid neurofilament light chain differentiates behavioural variant frontotemporal dementia progressors from phenocopy non-progressors (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.352821+00:00</updated><author><name>Dhamidhu Eratne</name></author><author><name>Michael Keem</name></author><author><name>Courtney Lewis</name></author><author><name>Matthew Kang</name></author><author><name>Mark Walterfang</name></author><author><name>Samantha M Loi</name></author><author><name>Wendy Kelso</name></author><author><name>Claire Cadwallader</name></author><author><name>Samuel F Berkovic</name></author><author><name>Qiao-Xin Li</name></author><author><name>Colin L Masters</name></author><author><name>Steven Collins</name></author><author><name>Alexander Santillo</name></author><author><name>Dennis Velakoulis</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: 
Distinguishing behavioural variant frontotemporal dementia (bvFTD) from non-neurodegenerative non-progressor, phenocopy mimics of frontal lobe dysfunction, can be one of the most challenging clinical dilemmas. A biomarker of neuronal injury, neurofilament light chain (NfL), could reduce misdiagnosis and delay.

Methods: 
Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) NfL, amyloid beta 1-42 (AB42), total and phosphorylated tau (T-tau, P-tau) levels were examined in patients with an initial diagnosis of bvFTD. Based on follow up information, patients were categorised as Progressors. Non-Progressors were subtyped in to Phenocopy Non-Progressors (non-neurological/neurodegenerative final diagnosis), and Static Non-Progressors (static deficits, not fully explained by non-neurological/neurodegenerative causes).

Results: 
Forty-three patients were included: 20 Progressors, 23 Non-Progressors (15 Phenocopy, 8 Static), 20 controls. NfL concentrations were lower in Non-Progressors (Non-Progressors Mean, M=554pg/mL, 95%CI:[461, 675], Phenocopy Non-Progressors M=459pg/mL, 95%CI:[385, 539], Static Non-Progressors M=730pg/mL, 95%CI:[516, 940]), compared to bvFTD Progressors (M=2397pg/mL, 95%CI:[1607, 3332]).  NfL distinguished Progressors from Non-Progressors with the highest accuracy (area under the curve 0.92, 90%/87% sensitivity/specificity, 86%/91% positive/negative predictive value, 88% accuracy). Static Non-Progressors tended to have higher T-tau and P-tau levels compared to Phenocopy Non-Progressors.  

Conclusion: 
This study demonstrated strong diagnostic utility of CSF NfL to distinguish bvFTD from phenocopy non-progressor variants, at baseline, with high accuracy, in a real-world clinical setting. This has important clinical implications, to improve outcomes for patients and clinicians facing this challenging clinical dilemma, as well as for healthcare services, and clinical trials. Further research is required to investigate heterogeneity within the non-progressor group and potential diagnostic algorithms, and prospective studies are underway assessing plasma NfL&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.22269323" rel="alternate" title="Cerebrospinal fluid neurofilament light chain differentiates behavioural variant frontotemporal dementia progressors from phenocopy non-progressors (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.22268812</id><title>Independent morphological variables correlate with Aging, Mild Cognitive Impairment, and Alzheimer’s Disease (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.352928+00:00</updated><author><name>Fernanda Hansen Pacheco de Moraes</name></author><author><name>Felipe Sudo</name></author><author><name>Marina Monteiro Carneiro</name></author><author><name>Bruno R. P. de Melo</name></author><author><name>Paulo Mattos</name></author><author><name>Bruno Mota</name></author><author><name>Fernanda Tovar-Moll</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This manuscript presents a study with recruited volunteers that comprehends three sorts of events present in Alzheimer’s Disease (AD) evolution (structural, biochemical, and cognitive) to propose an update in neurodegeneration biomarkers for AD. The novel variables, K, I, and S, suggested based on physics properties and empirical evidence, are defined by power-law relations between cortical thickness, exposed and total area, and natural descriptors of brain morphology. Our central hypothesis is that variable K, almost constant in healthy human subjects, is a better discriminator of a diseased brain than the current morphological biomarker, Cortical Thickness, due to its aggregated information. We extracted morphological features from 3T MRI T1w images of 123 elderly subjects: 77 Healthy Cognitive Unimpaired Controls (CTL), 33 Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI) patients, and 13 Alzheimer’s Disease (AD) patients. Moreover, Cerebrospinal Fluid (CSF) biomarkers and clinical data scores were correlated with K, intending to characterize health and disease in the cortex with morphological criteria and cognitive-behavioral profiles. K distinguishes Alzheimer’s Disease, Mild Cognitive Impairment, and Healthy Cognitive Unimpaired Controls globally and locally with reasonable accuracy (CTL-AD, 0.82; CTL-MCI, 0.58). Correlations were found between global and local K associated with clinical behavioral data (executive function and memory assessments) and CSF biomarkers (t-Tau, A&lt;italic&gt;β&lt;/italic&gt;-40, and A&lt;italic&gt;β&lt;/italic&gt;-42). The results suggest that the cortical folding component, K, is a premature discriminator of healthy aging, Mild Cognitive Impairment, and Alzheimer’s Disease, with significant differences within diagnostics. Despite the non-concomitant events, we found correlations between brain structural degeneration (K), cognitive tasks, and biochemical markers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.22268812" rel="alternate" title="Independent morphological variables correlate with Aging, Mild Cognitive Impairment, and Alzheimer’s Disease (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.22269108</id><title>Novel Application of a Force Sensor during Sit-to-Stands to Measure Dynamic Cerebral Autoregulation Onset (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.353008+00:00</updated><author><name>Alicen A Whitaker</name></author><author><name>Eric D. Vidoni</name></author><author><name>Stacey E. Aaron</name></author><author><name>Adam G. Rouse</name></author><author><name>Sandra A Billinger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Purpose: Current sit-to-stand methods measuring dynamic cerebral autoregulation (dCA) do not capture the precise onset of the time delay (TD) response. Reduced sit-to-stand reactions in older adults and individuals post-stroke could inadvertently introduce variability, error, and imprecise timing. We applied a force sensor during a sit-to-stand task to more accurately determine how TD before dCA onset may be altered. 
Methods: Middle cerebral artery blood velocity (MCAv) and mean arterial pressure (MAP) were measured during two sit-to-stands separated by 15 minutes. Recordings started with participants sitting on a force-sensitive resistor for 60 seconds, then asked to stand for two minutes. Upon standing, the force sensor voltage immediately dropped and marked the exact moment of arise-and-off (AO). Time from AO until an increase in cerebrovascular conductance (CVC = MCAv/MAP) was calculated as TD. 
Results: We tested the sensor in 4 healthy young adults, 2 older adults, and 2 individuals post-stroke. Healthy young adults stood quickly and the force sensor detected a small change in TD  compared to classically estimated AO, from verbal command to stand. When compared to the estimated AO, older adults had a delayed measured AO and TD decreased  up to ~50% while individuals post-stroke had an early AO and TD increased up to ~14%.
Conclusion: The transition reaction speed during the sit to stand has the potential to influence dCA metrics. As observed in the older adults and participants with stroke, this response may drastically vary and influence TD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.22269108" rel="alternate" title="Novel Application of a Force Sensor during Sit-to-Stands to Measure Dynamic Cerebral Autoregulation Onset (6 tweets)"/><category term="Rehabilitation Medicine and Physical Therapy"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476283</id><title>Ehrlichia SLiM ligand mimetic activates Notch signaling in human monocytes (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.353078+00:00</updated><author><name>LaNisha L. Patterson</name></author><author><name>Thangam Sudha Velayutham</name></author><author><name>Caitlan D. Byerly</name></author><author><name>Duc Cuong Bui</name></author><author><name>Jignesh Patel</name></author><author><name>Veljko Veljkovic</name></author><author><name>Slobodan Paessler</name></author><author><name>Jere W. McBride</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Ehrlichia chaffeensis&lt;/italic&gt; evades innate host defenses by reprogramming the mononuclear phagocyte through mechanisms that involve exploitation of multiple evolutionarily conserved cellular signaling pathways including Notch. This immune evasion strategy is directed in part by tandem repeat protein (TRP) effectors. Specifically, the TRP120 effector activates and regulates Notch signaling through interactions with the Notch receptor and the negative regulator, F-Box and WD repeat domain-containing 7 (FBW7). However, the specific molecular interactions and motifs required for E. chaffeensis TRP120-Notch receptor interaction and activation have not been defined. To investigate the molecular basis of TRP120 Notch activation, we compared TRP120 with endogenous canonical/non-canonical Notch ligands and identified a short region of sequence homology within the tandem repeat (TR) domain. TRP120 was predicted to share biological function with Notch ligands, and a function-associated sequence in the TR domain was identified. To investigate TRP120-Notch receptor interactions, colocalization between TRP120 and endogenous Notch-1 was observed. Moreover, direct interactions between full length TRP120, the TRP120 TR domain containing the putative Notch ligand sequence, and the Notch receptor LBR were demonstrated. To molecularly define the TRP120 Notch activation motif, peptide mapping was used to identify an 11-amino acid short linear motif (SLiM) located within the TRP120 TR that activated Notch signaling and downstream gene expression. Peptide mutants of the Notch SLiM or anti-Notch SLiM antibody reduced or eliminated Notch activation and NICD nuclear translocation. This investigation reveals a novel molecularly defined pathogen encoded Notch SLiM mimetic that activates Notch signaling consistent with endogenous ligands.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476283" rel="alternate" title="Ehrlichia SLiM ligand mimetic activates Notch signaling in human monocytes (5 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.22269000</id><title>Development of a screening tool for pelvic floor dysfunction in female athletes: protocol of a Delphi consensus (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.353159+00:00</updated><author><name>Silvia Giagio</name></author><author><name>Andrea Turolla</name></author><author><name>Tiziano Innocenti</name></author><author><name>Stefano Salvioli</name></author><author><name>Giulia Gava</name></author><author><name>Paolo Pillastrini</name></author><author><name>Marco Vecchiato</name></author><author><name>Jodie Dakic</name></author><author><name>Helena Catherine Frawley</name></author><author><name>Kari Bo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background/aim: Several epidemiological studies have found a high prevalence of Pelvic Floor Dysfunction (PFD) among female athletes. However, according to several authors, these data could even be underestimated, both in research and clinical practice. Screening for potential PFD is often delayed and risk factors are not often evaluated. As a consequence, withdrawal from sport, negative influence on performance, worsening symptoms and unrecognized diagnosis may occur. 
The aim of our research is to develop a screening tool for pelvic floor dysfunction in female athletes useful for clinicians (musculoskeletal/sport physiotherapists, sports medicine physicians, team physicians) to guide referral to a PFD expert (e.g. pelvic floor/women's health physiotherapist, gynecologist, uro-gynecologist, urologist).
Methods: A 2-round modified Delphi study will be conducted to ascertain expert opinion on which combination of variables and risk factors should be included in the screening tool. 
Conclusion: The implementation of the present screening tool into clinical practice may facilitate the referral to a PFD expert for further assessment of the pelvic floor and therefore, to identify potential dysfunction and, eventually, the related treatment pathway.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.22269000" rel="alternate" title="Development of a screening tool for pelvic floor dysfunction in female athletes: protocol of a Delphi consensus (5 tweets)"/><category term="Obstetrics and Gynecology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.22269137</id><title>Cell-type-specific transcriptome architecture underlying the establishment and exacerbation of systemic lupus erythematosus (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.353245+00:00</updated><author><name>Masahiro Nakano</name></author><author><name>Mineto Ota</name></author><author><name>Yusuke Takeshima</name></author><author><name>Yukiko Iwasaki</name></author><author><name>Hiroaki Hatano</name></author><author><name>Yasuo Nagafuchi</name></author><author><name>Takahiro Itamiya</name></author><author><name>Junko Maeda</name></author><author><name>Ryochi Yoshida</name></author><author><name>Saeko Yamada</name></author><author><name>Aya Nishiwaki</name></author><author><name>Haruka Takahashi</name></author><author><name>Hideyuki Takahashi</name></author><author><name>Yuko Akutsu</name></author><author><name>Takeshi Kusuda</name></author><author><name>Hiroyuki Suetsugu</name></author><author><name>Lu Liu</name></author><author><name>Kwangwoo Kim</name></author><author><name>Xianyong Yin</name></author><author><name>So-Young Bang</name></author><author><name>Yong Cui</name></author><author><name>Hye-Soon Lee</name></author><author><name>Hirofumi Shoda</name></author><author><name>Xuejun Zhang</name></author><author><name>Sang-Cheol Bae</name></author><author><name>Chikashi Terao</name></author><author><name>Kazuhiko Yamamoto</name></author><author><name>Tomohisa Okamura</name></author><author><name>Kazuyoshi Ishigaki</name></author><author><name>Keishi Fujio</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) is a complex and heterogeneous autoimmune disease involving multiple immune cells. A major hurdle to the elucidation of SLE pathogenesis is our limited understanding of dysregulated gene expression linked to various clinical statuses with a high cellular resolution. Here, we conducted a large-scale transcriptome study with 6,386 RNA sequencing data covering 27 immune cell types from 159 SLE and 89 healthy donors. We first profiled two distinct cell-type-specific transcriptomic signatures: disease-state and disease-activity signatures, reflecting disease establishment and exacerbation, respectively. We next identified candidate biological processes unique to each signature. This study suggested the clinical value of disease-activity signatures, which were associated with organ involvement and responses to therapeutic agents such as belimumab. However, disease-activity signatures were less enriched around SLE risk variants than disease-state signatures, suggesting that the genetic studies to date may not well capture clinically vital biology in SLE. Together, we identified comprehensive gene signatures of SLE, which will provide essential foundations for future genomic, genetic, and clinical studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.22269137" rel="alternate" title="Cell-type-specific transcriptome architecture underlying the establishment and exacerbation of systemic lupus erythematosus (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22269032</id><title>Spatial clustering in vaccination hesitancy: the role of social influence and social selection (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.353398+00:00</updated><author><name>Lucila Gisele Alvarez Zuzek</name></author><author><name>Casey M Zipfel</name></author><author><name>Shweta Bansal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The phenomenon of vaccine hesitancy behavior has gained ground over the last three decades, jeopardizing the maintenance of herd immunity. This behavior tends to cluster spatially, creating pockets of unprotected sub-populations that can be hotspots for outbreak emergence. What remains less understood are the social mechanisms that can give rise to spatial clustering in vaccination behavior, particularly at the landscape scale. We focus on the presence of spatial clustering, and aim to mechanistically understand how different social processes can give rise to this phenomenon. In particular, we propose two hypotheses to explain the presence of spatial clustering: (i) social selection, in which vaccine-hesitant individuals share socio-demographic traits, and clustering of these traits generates spatial clustering in vaccine hesitancy; and (ii) social influence, in which hesitant behavior is contagious and spreads through neighboring societies, leading to hesitant clusters. Adopting a theoretical spatial network approach, we explore the role of these two processes in generating patterns of spatial clustering in vaccination behaviors under a range of spatial structures. We find that both processes are independently capable of generating spatial clustering, and the more spatially structured the social dynamics in a society are, the higher spatial clustering in vaccine-hesitant behavior it realizes. Together, we demonstrate that these processes result in unique spatial configurations of hesitant clusters, and we validate our models on both processes with fine-grain empirical data on vaccine hesitancy, social determinants, and social connectivity in the US. Finally, we propose, and evaluate the effectiveness of, two novel intervention strategies to diminish hesitant behavior. Our generative modeling approach informed by unique empirical data provides insights on the role of complex social processes in driving spatial heterogeneity in vaccine hesitancy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22269032" rel="alternate" title="Spatial clustering in vaccination hesitancy: the role of social influence and social selection (4 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.22269024</id><title>IMU-derived kinematics detect gait differences with age or knee osteoarthritis but differ from marker-derived inverse kinematics (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.353457+00:00</updated><author><name>Jocelyn F. Hafer</name></author><author><name>Julien A. Mihy</name></author><author><name>Andrew Hunt</name></author><author><name>Ronald F. Zernicke</name></author><author><name>Russell T. Johnson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Common in-lab, marker-based gait analyses may not represent daily, real-world gait. Real-world gait analyses may be feasible using inertial measurement units (IMUs), especially with recent advancements in open-source methods (e.g., OpenSense). Before using OpenSense to study real-world gait, we must determine whether these methods: (1) estimate joint kinematics similarly to traditional marker-based motion capture (MoCap) and (2) differentiate groups with clinically different gait mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Healthy young and older adults and older adults with knee osteoarthritis completed this study. We captured MoCap and IMU data during overground walking at participants’ self-selected and faster speeds. MoCap and IMU kinematics were computed with appropriate OpenSim workflows. We tested whether sagittal kinematics differed between MoCap- and IMU-derived data, whether tools detected between-group differences similarly, and whether kinematics differed between tools by speed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;MoCap data showed more flexion than IMU data (hip: 0-47 and 65-100% stride, knee: 0-38 and 58-91% stride, ankle: 18-100% stride). Group kinematics differed at the hip (young extension &amp;gt; knee osteoarthritis at 30-47% stride) and ankle (young plantar flexion &amp;gt; older healthy at 62-65% stride). Group-by-tool interactions occurred at the hip (61-63% stride). Significant tool-by-speed interactions were found, with hip and knee flexion increasing more for MoCap than IMU data with speed (hip: 12-15% stride, knee: 60-63% stride).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While MoCap- and IMU-derived kinematics differed, our results suggested that the tools similarly detected clinically meaningful differences in gait. Results of the current study suggest that IMU-derived kinematics with OpenSense may enable the valid and reliable evaluation of gait in real-world, unobserved settings.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.22269024" rel="alternate" title="IMU-derived kinematics detect gait differences with age or knee osteoarthritis but differ from marker-derived inverse kinematics (4 tweets)"/><category term="Orthopedics"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.07.22268907</id><title>A Computational Framework for Identifying Age Risks in Drug-Adverse Event Pairs (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.353522+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhizhen Zhao</name></author><author><name>Ruoqi Liu</name></author><author><name>Lei Wang</name></author><author><name>Lang Li</name></author><author><name>Chi Song</name></author><author><name>Ping Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The identification of associations between drugs and adverse drug events (ADEs) is crucial for drug safety surveil-lance. An increasing number of studies have revealed that children and seniors are susceptible to ADEs at the population level. However, the comprehensive explorations of age risks in drug-ADE pairs are still limited. The FDA Adverse Event Reporting System (FAERS) provides individual case reports, which can be used for quantifying different age risks. In this study, we developed a statistical computational framework to detect age group of patients who are susceptible to some ADEs after taking specific drugs. We adopted different Chi-squared tests and conducted disproportionality analysis to detect drug-ADE pairs with age differences. We analyzed 4,580,113 drug-ADE pairs in FAERS (2004 to 2018Q3) and identified 2,523 pairs with the highest age risk. Furthermore, we conducted a case study on statin-induced ADE in children and youth. The code and results are available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Zhizhen-Zhao/Age-Risk-Identification"&gt;https://github.com/Zhizhen-Zhao/Age-Risk-Identification&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.07.22268907" rel="alternate" title="A Computational Framework for Identifying Age Risks in Drug-Adverse Event Pairs (3 tweets)"/><category term="Health Informatics"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.22269267</id><title>Rapid detection of single nucleotide polymorphisms using the MinION nanopore sequencer: a feasibility study for perioperative precision medicine (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.353592+00:00</updated><author><name>Yoshiteru Tabata</name></author><author><name>Yoshiyuki Matsuo</name></author><author><name>Yosuke Fujii</name></author><author><name>Atsufumi Ohta</name></author><author><name>Kiichi Hirota</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Precision medicine is a phrase used to describe personalized medical care tailored to specific patients based on their clinical presentation and genetic makeup. However, despite the fact that several single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) have been reported to be associated with increased susceptibility to particular anesthetic agents and the occurrence of perioperative complications, genomic profiling and thus precision medicine has not been widely applied in perioperative management.
Methods: We validated six SNP loci known to affect perioperative outcomes in Japanese patients using genomic DNA from saliva specimens and nanopore sequencing of each SNP loci to facilitate allele frequency calculations and then compared the nanopore results to those produced using the conventional dideoxy sequencing method.
Results: Nanopore sequencing reads clustered into the expected genotypes in both homozygous and heterozygous cases. In addition, the nanopore sequencing results were consistent with those obtained using conventional dideoxy sequencing and the workflow provided reliable allele frequency estimation, with a total analysis time of less than 4 h.
Conclusion: Thus, our results suggest that nanopore sequencing may be a promising and versatile tool for SNP genotyping, allowing for rapid and feasible risk prediction of perioperative outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.22269267" rel="alternate" title="Rapid detection of single nucleotide polymorphisms using the MinION nanopore sequencer: a feasibility study for perioperative precision medicine (3 tweets)"/><category term="Anesthesia"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.22269272</id><title>Association of Retinal Age Gap with Arterial Stiffness and Incident Cardiovascular Disease (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.353658+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhuoting Zhu</name></author><author><name>Yifan Chen</name></author><author><name>Wei Wang</name></author><author><name>Yueye Wang</name></author><author><name>Wenyi Hu</name></author><author><name>Xianwen Shang</name></author><author><name>Huan Liao</name></author><author><name>Danli Shi</name></author><author><name>Yu Huang</name></author><author><name>Jason Ha</name></author><author><name>Zachary Tan</name></author><author><name>Katerina Kiburg</name></author><author><name>Xueli Zhang</name></author><author><name>Shulin Tang</name></author><author><name>Honghua Yu</name></author><author><name>Xiaohong Yang</name></author><author><name>Mingguang He</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Retinal parameters could reflect systemic vascular changes. With the advances of deep learning technology, we have recently developed an algorithm to predict retinal age based on fundus images, which could be a novel biomarker for ageing and mortality.
Objective: To investigate associations of retinal age gap with arterial stiffness index (ASI) and incident cardiovascular disease (CVD). 
Methods: A deep learning (DL) model was trained based on 19,200 fundus images of 11,052 participants without any past medical history at baseline to predict the retinal age. Retinal age gap (retinal age predicted minus chronological age) was generated for the remaining 35,917 participants. Regression models were used to assess the association between retinal age gap and ASI. Cox proportional hazards regression models and restricted cubic splines were used to explore the association between retinal age gap and incident CVD. 
Results: We found each one-year increase in retinal age gap was associated with increased ASI (β=0.002, 95% confidence interval [CI]: 0.001-0.003, P&amp;lt;0.001). After a median follow-up of 5.83 years (interquartile range [IQR]: 5.73-5.97), 675 (2.00%) developed CVD. In the fully adjusted model, each one-year increase in retinal age gap was associated with a 3% increase in the risk of incident CVD (hazard ratio [HR]=1.03, 95% CI: 1.01-1.06, P=0.012). In the restricted cubic splines analysis, the risk of incident CVD increased significantly when retinal age gap reached 1.21 (HR=1.05; 95% CI, 1.00-1.10; P-overall &amp;lt;0.0001; P-nonlinear=0.0681).
Conclusion: We found that retinal age gap was significantly associated with ASI and incident CVD events, supporting the potential of this novel biomarker in identifying individuals at high risk of future CVD events.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.22269272" rel="alternate" title="Association of Retinal Age Gap with Arterial Stiffness and Incident Cardiovascular Disease (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cardiovascular Medicine"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22269075</id><title>Genome-wide association study of chronic sputum production implicates loci involved in mucus production and infection (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.353765+00:00</updated><author><name>R Packer</name></author><author><name>N Shrine</name></author><author><name>R Hall</name></author><author><name>C Melbourne</name></author><author><name>R Thompson</name></author><author><name>AT Williams</name></author><author><name>ML Paynton</name></author><author><name>J Davitte</name></author><author><name>E Hessel</name></author><author><name>D Michalovich</name></author><author><name>JC Betts</name></author><author><name>I Sayers</name></author><author><name>A Yeo</name></author><author><name>IP Hall</name></author><author><name>MD Tobin</name></author><author><name>LV Wain</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chronic sputum production impacts on quality of life and is a feature of many respiratory diseases. Identification of the genetic variants associated with chronic sputum production in a disease agnostic sample could improve understanding of its causes and identify new molecular targets for treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted a genome-wide association study (GWAS) of chronic sputum production in UK Biobank. Signals meeting genome-wide significance (P&amp;lt;5×10&lt;sup&gt;−8&lt;/sup&gt;) were fine-mapped and putative causal genes identified by gene expression analysis. GWAS of respiratory traits were interrogated to identify whether the signals were driven by existing respiratory disease amongst the cases and variants were further investigated for wider pleiotropic effects using phenome-wide association studies (PheWAS).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;From a GWAS of 9,714 cases and 48,471 controls, we identified six novel genome-wide significant signals for chronic sputum production including the Human Leukocyte Antigen (HLA) locus, chromosome 11 mucin locus (containing &lt;italic&gt;MUC2, MUC5AC&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;MUC5B&lt;/italic&gt;) and the &lt;italic&gt;FUT2&lt;/italic&gt; locus. The mucin locus signal had previously been reported for association with moderate-to-severe asthma. The HLA signal was fine-mapped to an amino-acid change of threonine to arginine (frequency 36.8%) in HLA-DRB1 (HLA-&lt;italic&gt;DRB1&lt;/italic&gt;*03:147). The signal near &lt;italic&gt;FUT2&lt;/italic&gt; was associated with expression of several genes including &lt;italic&gt;FUT2&lt;/italic&gt;, for which the direction of effect was tissue dependent. Our PheWAS identified a wide range of associations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Novel signals at the &lt;italic&gt;FUT2&lt;/italic&gt; and mucin loci highlight mucin flucosylation as a driver of chronic sputum production even in the absence of diagnosed respiratory disease and provide genetic support for this pathway as a target for therapeutic intervention.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22269075" rel="alternate" title="Genome-wide association study of chronic sputum production implicates loci involved in mucus production and infection (3 tweets)"/><category term="Respiratory Medicine"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>