<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.232113+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266651</id><title>The Frequency, Penetrance and Variable Expressivity of Dilated Cardiomyopathy-Associated Putative Pathogenic Gene Variants in UK Biobank Participants (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.232708+00:00</updated><author><name>Ravi Shah</name></author><author><name>Babken Asatryan</name></author><author><name>Ghaith Sharaf Dabbagh</name></author><author><name>Nay Aung</name></author><author><name>Mohammed Y Khanji</name></author><author><name>Luis R. Lopes</name></author><author><name>Stefan van Duijvenboden</name></author><author><name>Anthony Holmes</name></author><author><name>Daniele Muser</name></author><author><name>Andrew P. Landstrom</name></author><author><name>Aaron Mark Lee</name></author><author><name>Pankaj Arora</name></author><author><name>Christopher Semsarian</name></author><author><name>Virend K. Somers</name></author><author><name>Anjali Owens</name></author><author><name>Patricia B Munroe</name></author><author><name>Steffen E. Petersen</name></author><author><name>C. Anwar A. Chahal</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a paucity of data regarding the phenotype of dilated cardiomyopathy (DCM) gene variants in the general population. We aimed to determine the frequency and penetrance of DCM-associated putative pathogenic gene variants in a general, adult population, with a focus on the expression of clinical and subclinical phenotype, including structural, functional and arrhythmic disease features.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;UK Biobank participants who had undergone whole exome sequencing (WES), ECG and cardiovascular magnetic resonance (CMR) imaging were selected for study. Three different variant calling strategies (one primary and two secondary) were used to identify subjects with putative pathogenic variants in 44 DCM genes. The observed phenotype was graded to either 1) DCM (clinical or CMR diagnosis); 2) early DCM features, including arrhythmia and/or conduction disease, isolated ventricular dilation, and hypokinetic non-dilated cardiomyopathy; or 3) phenotype-negative.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among 18,665 individuals included in the study, 1,463 (7.8%) subjects possessed ≥1 putative pathogenic variant in 44 DCM genes by the main variant calling strategy. A clinical diagnosis of DCM was present in 0.34% and early DCM features in 5.7% of individuals with putative pathogenic variants. ECG and CMR analysis revealed evidence of subclinical DCM in an additional 1.6% and early DCM features in 15.9% of individuals with putative pathogenic variants. Arrhythmias and/or conduction disease (15.2%) were the most common early DCM features, followed by hypokinetic non-dilated cardiomyopathy (4%). The combined clinical/subclinical penetrance was ≤30% with all three variant filtering strategies. Clinical DCM was slightly more prevalent among participants with putative pathogenic variants in definitive/strong evidence genes, as compared to those with variants in moderate/limited evidence genes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the UK Biobank, approximately 1/6 of adults with putative pathogenic variants in DCM genes exhibited a subclinical phenotype based on ECG and/or CMR, most commonly manifesting with arrhythmias in the absence of substantial ventricular dilation/dysfunction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Clinical Perspective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What is new?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among individuals with putative pathogenic DCM gene variants, subclinical DCM and early DCM features, detected by ECG and/or CMR, were nearly four times more common than clinically manifest DCM or early features (23.7% vs. 6.1%).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over 90% of subjects with a putative pathogenic variant in DCM-associated genes did not have a prior history of DCM.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clinical DCM was slightly more prevalent among participants with putative pathogenic variants in definitive/strong evidence genes (13.9% for clinical and subclinical), as compared to those with variants in moderate/limited evidence genes, but there was no significant difference in combined clinical/subclinical phenotype by cluster.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The overall clinical/subclinical penetrance of DCM-associated single putative pathogenic variants was highly variable between genes, ranging from 0 to 66.7%.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What are the clinical implications?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arrhythmias and cardiac conduction disease are the most common early manifestation of putative pathogenic variants implicated in DCM, mostly occurring prior to the development of structural/functional abnormalities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;A genotype-first screening approach for DCM using a large genetic panel is currently not suitable in the general population due to incomplete understanding of DCM genetic architecture and reduced penetrance of DCM-associated putative pathogenic variants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Journal Subject Terms&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cardiomyopathy; Genetics; Sudden Cardiac Death&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266651" rel="alternate" title="The Frequency, Penetrance and Variable Expressivity of Dilated Cardiomyopathy-Associated Putative Pathogenic Gene Variants in UK Biobank Participants (24 tweets)"/><category term="Cardiovascular Medicine"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469715</id><title>Contractile force of transplanted cardiomyocytes contributes to heart function after injury (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.232982+00:00</updated><author><name>Tim Stüdemann</name></author><author><name>Judith Rössinger</name></author><author><name>Christoph Manthey</name></author><author><name>Birgit Geertz</name></author><author><name>Rajiven Srikantharajah</name></author><author><name>Constantin von Bibra</name></author><author><name>Aya Shibamiya</name></author><author><name>Maria Köhne</name></author><author><name>Antonius Wiehler</name></author><author><name>J. Simon Wiegert</name></author><author><name>Thomas Eschenhagen</name></author><author><name>Florian Weinberger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Transplantation of pluripotent stem cell-derived cardiomyocytes represents an innovative therapeutic strategy for heart failure. Studies in small and large animals have demonstrated functional recovery of left ventricular function after cardiomyocyte transplantation&lt;sup&gt;1–4&lt;/sup&gt;, and first clinical studies are currently underway&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;. Yet, the mechanism of action underlying graft-induced benefit is unknown&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;. Here we demonstrate that transplanted cardiomyocytes actively contribute to heart function. We transplanted cardiomyocytes with an optogenetic off-on switch in a guinea pig cardiac injury model. Light-induced inhibition of engrafted cardiomyocyte contractility resulted in a rapid decrease of left ventricular function that was fully reversible with the offset of photostimulation. Hence, our optogenetic approach demonstrated that transplanted cardiomyocytes actively participate in heart function, supporting the hypothesis that the delivery of new force-generating myocardium can serve as a regenerative therapeutic strategy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469715" rel="alternate" title="Contractile force of transplanted cardiomyocytes contributes to heart function after injury (17 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.21266740</id><title>Smoking-dependent expression alterations in nasal epithelium reveal immune impairment linked to germline variation and lung cancer risk (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.233165+00:00</updated><author><name>Maria Stella de Biase</name></author><author><name>Florian Massip</name></author><author><name>Tzu-Ting Wei</name></author><author><name>Federico M. Giorgi</name></author><author><name>Rory Stark</name></author><author><name>Amanda Stone</name></author><author><name>Amy Gladwell</name></author><author><name>Martin O’Reilly</name></author><author><name>Ines de Santiago</name></author><author><name>Kerstin Meyer</name></author><author><name>Florian Markowetz</name></author><author><name>Bruce A J Ponder</name></author><author><name>Robert C Rintoul</name></author><author><name>Roland F Schwarz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Lung cancer is the leading cause of cancer-related death in the world. In contrast to many other cancers, a direct connection to lifestyle risk in the form of cigarette smoke has long been established. More than 50% of all smoking-related lung cancers occur in former smokers, often many years after smoking cessation. Despite extensive research, the molecular processes for persistent lung cancer risk are unclear. CT screening of current and former smokers has been shown to reduce lung cancer mortality by up to 26%.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To examine whether clinical risk stratification can be improved upon by the addition of genetic data, and to explore the mechanisms of the persisting risk in former smokers, we have analyzed transcriptomic data from accessible airway tissues of 487 subjects. We developed a model to assess smoking associated gene expression changes and their reversibility after smoking is stopped, in both healthy subjects and clinic patients. We find persistent smoking-associated immune alterations to be a hallmark of the clinic patients. Integrating previous GWAS data using a transcriptional network approach, we demonstrate that the same immune and interferon related pathways are strongly enriched for genes linked to known genetic risk factors, demonstrating a causal relationship between immune alteration and lung cancer risk. Finally, we used accessible airway transcriptomic data to derive a non-invasive lung cancer risk classifier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our results provide initial evidence for germline-mediated personalised smoke injury response and risk in the general population, with potential implications for managing long-term lung cancer incidence and mortality.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.21266740" rel="alternate" title="Smoking-dependent expression alterations in nasal epithelium reveal immune impairment linked to germline variation and lung cancer risk (16 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.21266863</id><title>Predicting Post-operative Pain in Lung Cancer Patients using Pre-operative Peak Alpha Frequency (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.233349+00:00</updated><author><name>Samantha K. Millard</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Furman</name></author><author><name>Amy Kerr</name></author><author><name>David A. Seminowicz</name></author><author><name>Fang Gao-Smith</name></author><author><name>Babu V. Naidu</name></author><author><name>Ali Mazaheri</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aims and Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Experimental models of neuropathic pain suggest that individual peak alpha frequency (PAF), measured using electroencephalography (EEG), can predict future pain sensitivity in experimental settings. Here, we tested whether PAF could predict future pain severity in a clinical setting in patients undergoing thoracotomy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recorded using wearable around the ear electrodes (cEEGrids), the feasibility and efficacy of pre-operative PAF as a neuro-marker for post-operative pain was assessed in 16 patients undergoing thoracic surgery for lung cancer (age = 67.53 ± 4.38 [SD]). Patients also provided numerical ratings (0-10) of current, average, and worst pain pre-operatively as well as within three days post-operatively&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results and Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pre-operative PAF of less than 9 Hz was highly sensitive (1.0) and specific (0.86) in identifying patients who would go on to experience severe (&amp;gt;7/10) worst pain. Moreover, PAF was negatively correlated with patients’ current, average, and worst post-operative pain. PAF was significantly higher for those reporting lower pain severity compared to those reporting higher pain severity in the immediate post-operative period. This suggests that PAF is a promising neuro-marker to pre-operatively assess individual susceptibility to severe pain in the immediate post-operative period, possibly enabling more informed assessment of an individual’s suitability for surgery.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.21266863" rel="alternate" title="Predicting Post-operative Pain in Lung Cancer Patients using Pre-operative Peak Alpha Frequency (16 tweets)"/><category term="Pain Medicine"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.21266768</id><title>Insights from an autism imaging biomarker challenge: promises and threats to biomarker discovery (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.233493+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicolas Traut</name></author><author><name>Katja Heuer</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Lemaître</name></author><author><name>Anita Beggiato</name></author><author><name>David Germanaud</name></author><author><name>Monique Elmaleh</name></author><author><name>Alban Bethegnies</name></author><author><name>Laurent Bonnasse-Gahot</name></author><author><name>Weidong Cai</name></author><author><name>Stanislas Chambon</name></author><author><name>Freddy Cliquet</name></author><author><name>Ayoub Ghriss</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Guigui</name></author><author><name>Amicie de Pierrefeu</name></author><author><name>Meng Wang</name></author><author><name>Valentina Zantedeschi</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Boucaud</name></author><author><name>Joris van den Bossche</name></author><author><name>Balázs Kegl</name></author><author><name>Richard Delorme</name></author><author><name>Thomas Bourgeron</name></author><author><name>Roberto Toro</name></author><author><name>Gaël Varoquaux</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;MRI has been extensively used to identify anatomical and functional differences in Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD). Yet, many of these findings have proven difficult to replicate because studies rely on small cohorts and are built on many complex, undisclosed, analytic choices. We conducted an international challenge to predict ASD diagnosis from MRI data, where we provided preprocessed anatomical and functional MRI data from &amp;gt; 2,000 individuals. Evaluation of the predictions was rigorously blinded. 146 challengers submitted prediction algorithms, which were evaluated at the end of the challenge using unseen data and an additional acquisition site. On the best algorithms, we studied the importance of MRI modalities, brain regions, and sample size. We found evidence that MRI could predict ASD diagnosis: the 10 best algorithms reliably predicted diagnosis with AUC∼0.80 – far superior to what can be currently obtained using genotyping data in cohorts 20-times larger. We observed that functional MRI was more important for prediction than anatomical MRI, and that increasing sample size steadily increased prediction accuracy, providing an efficient strategy to improve biomarkers. We also observed that despite a strong incentive to generalise to unseen data, model development on a given dataset faces the risk of overfitting: performing well in cross-validation on the data at hand, but not generalising. Finally, we were able to predict ASD diagnosis on an external sample added after the end of the challenge (EU-AIMS), although with a lower prediction accuracy (AUC=0.72). This indicates that despite being based on a large multisite cohort, our challenge still produced biomarkers fragile in the face of dataset shifts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;MRI can provide reliable biomarkers for ASD&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because of overfitting, models with excellent apparent performance on public data failed to generalise&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 10 best algorithms used classic machine learning methods&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Biomarker development needs blinded evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prediction performance should reach AUC=0.83 on samples with 10k subjects&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.21266768" rel="alternate" title="Insights from an autism imaging biomarker challenge: promises and threats to biomarker discovery (10 tweets)"/><category term="Radiology and Imaging"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266731</id><title>In vivo myelin imaging and tissue microstructure in white matter hyperintensities and perilesional white matter (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.233727+00:00</updated><author><name>Jennifer K. Ferris</name></author><author><name>Brian Greeley</name></author><author><name>Irene M. Vavasour</name></author><author><name>Sarah N. Kraeutner</name></author><author><name>Shie Rinat</name></author><author><name>Joel Ramirez</name></author><author><name>Sandra E. Black</name></author><author><name>Lara A. Boyd</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;White Matter hyperintensities (WMHs) relate to cognitive decline in aging, due to their deleterious effect on white matter structure. Diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) detects changes to white matter microstructure, both within the WMH and extending in a penumbra-like pattern in surrounding (perilesional) normal appearing white matter (NAWM). However, DTI markers are not specific to tissue components, complicating interpretation of previous DTI findings. Myelin water imaging is a novel imaging technique that provides specific markers of myelin content (myelin water fraction: MWF) and interstitial fluid (geometric mean T2: GMT2). Here we combined DTI and myelin water imaging to examine tissue characteristics in WMHs and perilesional NAWM. Our goal was to establish a multimodal neuroimaging approach to track WMH progression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;80 individuals (47 older adults and 33 individuals with chronic stroke) underwent neuroimaging and tissue segmentation. To measure perilesional NAWM, WMH masks were dilated in 2mm segments up to 10mm in distance from the WMH to measure perilesional NAWM. Fractional anisotropy (FA), mean diffusivity (MD), MWF, and GMT2 were extracted from WMHs and perilesional NAWM. We examined whether white matter metrics showed a spatial gradient of effects in perilesional NAWM, as a function of Distance from the WMH, and Group. We tested whether white matter metrics in the WMH lesion related to severity of cerebrovascular disease across the whole sample, indexed by whole brain WMH volume.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We observed a spatial gradient of higher MD and GMT2, and lower FA, in perilesional NAWM and the WMH. In the chronic stroke group, MWF was reduced in the WMH lesion but did not show a spatial gradient in perilesional NAWM. Across the whole sample, white matter metrics within the WMH lesion related to whole-brain WMH volume; MD and GMT2 increased, and MWF decreased, with increasing WMH volume.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;NAWM adjacent to WMHs exhibits characteristics of a transitional stage between healthy NAWM tissue and WMH lesions. This was observed in markers sensitive to interstitial fluid, but not in the specific marker of myelin concentration (MWF). Within the WMH, interstitial fluid was higher and myelin concentration was lower in individuals with more severe cerebrovascular disease. Our data suggests that fluid-sensitive imaging metrics (such as DTI) can identify NAWM at high risk of conversion to a WMH. In contrast, specific markers of myelin concentration (e.g., MWF) can be used to measure levels of demyelination in the WMH itself, which may be a useful marker for disease staging of advanced WMHs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266731" rel="alternate" title="In vivo myelin imaging and tissue microstructure in white matter hyperintensities and perilesional white matter (9 tweets)"/><category term="Radiology and Imaging"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266717</id><title>Identifying high-risk comorbidities of short and long-term opioid prescription use (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.234034+00:00</updated><author><name>Mariela V Jennings</name></author><author><name>Hyunjoon Lee</name></author><author><name>Daniel B Rocha</name></author><author><name>Sevim B Bianchi</name></author><author><name>Brandon J Coombes</name></author><author><name>Richard C Crist</name></author><author><name>Annika Faucon</name></author><author><name>Yirui Hu</name></author><author><name>Rachel L Kember</name></author><author><name>Travis T Mallard</name></author><author><name>Maria Niarchou</name></author><author><name>Melissa N Poulsen</name></author><author><name>Peter Straub</name></author><author><name>Richard D Urman</name></author><author><name>Colin G Walsh</name></author><author><name>Lea K Davis</name></author><author><name>Jordan W Smoller</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Troiani</name></author><author><name>Sandra Sanchez-Roige</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic health records (EHR) are useful tools for understanding complex medical phenotypes, but they have been underutilized for opioid use disorders (OUD). Patterns of prescription opioid use might provide an objective measure of OUD risk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We extracted data for over 2.6 million patients across three health registries (Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Mass General Brigham, Geisinger) between 2005 and 2018. We defined three groups based on levels of opioid exposure: No Prescription, Minimal Exposure (2 prescriptions within 90 days at least once, but never 3 prescriptions &amp;lt;90 days apart), and Chronic Exposure (≥10 opioid prescriptions in a year), and compared them to the full registries and to patients with OUD diagnostic codes. We extracted demographic and clinical characteristics known to co-occur with OUD, including psychiatric and substance use disorders, pain-related diagnoses, HIV, and hepatitis C.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The prevalence of substance (alcohol, tobacco, cannabis) use disorders was higher in patients with OUD and Chronic Exposure than those with No Prescription or Minimal Exposure. Patients in the OUD and Chronic Exposure groups had more psychiatric (anxiety, depression, schizophrenia, bipolar disorder) and medical comorbidities (pain, hepatitis C, HIV) than those in the Minimal Exposure group. Notably, patients in the Minimal Exposure group had different comorbidity profiles (higher rates of substance use and psychiatric disorders, more pain conditions) than those in the Unscreened or No Prescription groups, highlighting the value of including opioid exposure in studies of OUD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Long-term opioid prescription use may serve as an additional tool to characterize OUD risk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266717" rel="alternate" title="Identifying high-risk comorbidities of short and long-term opioid prescription use (7 tweets)"/><category term="Addiction Medicine"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.21266320</id><title>Measure by Measure: Resting Heart Rate Across the 24 Hour Cycle. (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.234500+00:00</updated><author><name>Cathy A Speed</name></author><author><name>Tom Arneil</name></author><author><name>Robert K Harle</name></author><author><name>Alex Wilson</name></author><author><name>Alan Karthikesalingam</name></author><author><name>Michael V McConnell</name></author><author><name>Justin P Phillips</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;Background:&lt;/bold&gt; Photoplethysmography (PPG) sensors, typically found in wrist-worn devices, can continuously monitor heart rate (HR) in large populations in real-world settings. Resting heart rate (RHR) is an important biomarker of morbidities and mortality, but no universally accepted definition nor measurement criteria exist. In this study, we provide a working definition of RHR and describe a method for measurement of RHR recorded using PPG derived from wristband measurement across a 24-hour cycle.
&lt;bold&gt;Methods:&lt;/bold&gt; 433 healthy subjects wore a wrist device that measured activity and HR for up to 3 months. HR during inactivity was recorded and the duration of inactivity needed for HR to stabilise was ascertained. We identified the lowest HR during each 24-hour cycle (true RHR) and examined the time of day or night this occurred. The variation of HR during inactivity through the 24-hour cycle was also assessed. The sample was also subdivided according to daily activity levels for subset analysis. 
&lt;bold&gt;Findings:&lt;/bold&gt; Adequate data was obtained for 19,242 days and 18,520 nights. HR stabilised in most subjects after 4 minutes of inactivity. Mean (SD) RHR for the sample was 54.5 (8.0) bpm (day) and 50.5 (7.6) bpm (night). RHR values were highest in the least active group (lowest MET quartile) . A circadian variation of HR during inactivity was confirmed, with the lowest values being between 0300 and 0700 hours for most subjects.
&lt;bold&gt;Interpretation:&lt;/bold&gt; RHR measured using a PPG-based wrist-worn device is significantly lower at night than in the day, and a circadian rhythm of HR during inactivity was confirmed.  Since RHR is such an important health metric, clarity on the definition and measurement methodology used is important. A minimum rest time of 4 minutes provides a reliable measurement of HR during inactivity and true RHR in a 24-hour cycle is best measured between 0300 and 0700 hours. 
&lt;bold&gt;Funding:&lt;/bold&gt; This study was funded by Google.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.21266320" rel="alternate" title="Measure by Measure: Resting Heart Rate Across the 24 Hour Cycle. (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cardiovascular Medicine"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266487</id><title>Intersecting single-cell transcriptomics and genome-wide association studies identifies crucial cell populations and candidate genes for atherosclerosis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.234833+00:00</updated><author><name>Lotte Slenders</name></author><author><name>Lennart P. L. Landsmeer</name></author><author><name>Kai Cui</name></author><author><name>Marie A.C. Depuydt</name></author><author><name>Maarten Verwer</name></author><author><name>Joost Mekke</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Timmerman</name></author><author><name>Noortje A.M. van den Dungen</name></author><author><name>Johan Kuiper</name></author><author><name>Menno P.J. Winther</name></author><author><name>Koen H.M. Prange</name></author><author><name>Wei Feng Ma</name></author><author><name>Clint L. Miller</name></author><author><name>Redouane Aherrahrou</name></author><author><name>Mete Civelek</name></author><author><name>Gert J. de Borst</name></author><author><name>Dominique P.V. de Kleijn</name></author><author><name>Folkert W. Asselbergs</name></author><author><name>Hester M. den Ruijter</name></author><author><name>Arjan Boltjes</name></author><author><name>Gerard Pasterkamp</name></author><author><name>Sander W. van der Laan</name></author><author><name>Michal Mokry</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Genome-wide association studies have discovered hundreds of common genetic variants for atherosclerotic disease and cardiovascular risk factors. The translation of susceptibility loci into biological mechanisms and targets for drug discovery remains challenging. Intersecting genetic and gene expression data has led to the identification of candidate genes. However, previously studied tissues are often non-diseased and heterogeneous in cell composition, hindering accurate candidate prioritization. Therefore, we analyzed single-cell transcriptomics from atherosclerotic plaques for cell-type-specific expression to identify atherosclerosis-associated candidate gene-cell pairs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods and Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To identify disease-associated genes, we applied gene-based analyses using GWAS summary statistics from 46 atherosclerotic and cardiovascular disease, risk factors, and other traits. We then intersected these candidates with scRNA-seq data to identify genes specific for individual cell (sub)populations in atherosclerotic plaques. The coronary artery disease loci demonstrated a prominent signal in plaque smooth muscle cells (&lt;italic&gt;SKI&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;KANK2&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;SORT1&lt;/italic&gt;) p-adj. = 0.0012, and endothelial cells (&lt;italic&gt;SLC44A1&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;ATP2B1&lt;/italic&gt;) p-adj. = 0.0011. Further sub clustering revealed genes in risk loci for coronary calcification specifically enriched in a synthetic smooth muscle cell population. Finally, we used liver-derived scRNA-seq data and showed hepatocyte-specific enrichment of genes involved in serum lipid levels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We discovered novel gene-cell pairs, on top of known pairs, pointing to new biological mechanisms of atherosclerotic disease. We highlight that loci associated with coronary artery disease reveal prominent association levels in mainly plaque smooth muscle and endothelial cell populations. We present an intuitive single-cell transcriptomics-driven workflow rooted in human large-scale genetic studies to identify putative candidate genes and affected cells associated with cardiovascular traits. Collectively, our workflow allows for the identification of cell-specific targets relevant for atherosclerosis and can be universally applied to other complex genetic diseases and traits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Translational perspective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;GWAS identified a large number of genomic loci associated with atherosclerotic disease. The translation of these results into drug development and faster diagnostics remains challenging. With our approach, we cross-reference the GWAS findings for atherosclerotic disease with scRNA-seq data of disease-relevant tissue and bring the GWAS findings closer to the functional and mechanistic studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract Figure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="21266487v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266487" rel="alternate" title="Intersecting single-cell transcriptomics and genome-wide association studies identifies crucial cell populations and candidate genes for atherosclerosis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cardiovascular Medicine"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470055</id><title>Bagaza virus in wild birds, Portugal, 2021 (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.235235+00:00</updated><author><name>Joao Queiros</name></author><author><name>Silvia Barros</name></author><author><name>Alberto Sanchez-Cano</name></author><author><name>Margarida Henriques</name></author><author><name>Teresa Fagulha</name></author><author><name>Fabio Abade dos Santos</name></author><author><name>Margarida Duarte</name></author><author><name>Catarina Goncalves</name></author><author><name>David Goncalves</name></author><author><name>Marisa Rodrigues</name></author><author><name>Teresa Cardona Cabrera</name></author><author><name>Isabel G. Fernandez de Mera</name></author><author><name>Christian Gortazar</name></author><author><name>Ursula Hofle</name></author><author><name>Paulo Celio Alves</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bagaza virus (BAGV) emerged in Spain, in 2010. Since then, BAGV was not reported in other European countries until September 2021, when BAGV was diagnosed by molecular methods in one corn bunting and several red-legged partridges, after abnormal mortality in Southern Portugal. Sequencing revealed high similarity with strains reported previously.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470055" rel="alternate" title="Bagaza virus in wild birds, Portugal, 2021 (3 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.21266534</id><title>Determination of NK cell immunophenotype and cytokine profile in patients with Rocky Mountain spotted fever (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.235431+00:00</updated><author><name>Carolina Maynez-Prieto</name></author><author><name>Jaime R. Adame-Gallegos</name></author><author><name>Moisés Ramírez-López</name></author><author><name>Estefanía Quintana-Mendías</name></author><author><name>Blanca E. Estrada-Aguirre</name></author><author><name>Maribel Baquera-Arteaga</name></author><author><name>Diana Manzanera-Ornelas</name></author><author><name>Enrique Guevara-Macías</name></author><author><name>Gerardo P. Espino-Solís</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The intracellular pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Rickettsia rickettsii&lt;/italic&gt; causes tick-borne spotted fever (also called Rocky Mountain spotted fever (RMSF) and is increasingly recognized as an emerging cause of febrile illness in Mexico. However, little is known about the early immune responses to infection. Four RMSF pediatric patients on acute phase and eight healthy controls from Chihuahua, Mexico were recruited. The natural killer cell (NK) immunophenotype and the cytokine profile in peripheral blood were characterized by flow cytometry. The population of cytotoxic NK cells expressing NKG2D was significantly decreased in patients on 3rd day of hospitalization compared to the first sampling on admission. Interleukins IL-6, IL-8, and IL-10 levels were significantly increased in patients upon admission compared to controls. This study shows that circulating NK cells are numerically decreased, while cytokines induce a pro-inflammatory process in patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.21266534" rel="alternate" title="Determination of NK cell immunophenotype and cytokine profile in patients with Rocky Mountain spotted fever (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266755</id><title>Genome sequencing in the Parkinson’s disease clinic (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.235589+00:00</updated><author><name>Emily J. Hill</name></author><author><name>Laurie A. Robak</name></author><author><name>Rami Al-Ouran</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Deger</name></author><author><name>Jamie C. Fong</name></author><author><name>Paul Jerrod Vandeventer</name></author><author><name>Emily Schulman</name></author><author><name>Sindhu Rao</name></author><author><name>Hiba Saade</name></author><author><name>Rainer von Coelln</name></author><author><name>Harshavardhan Doddapaneni</name></author><author><name>Sejal Salvi</name></author><author><name>Shannon Dugan-Perez</name></author><author><name>Donna M. Muzny</name></author><author><name>Amy McGuire</name></author><author><name>Zhandong Liu</name></author><author><name>Richard Gibbs</name></author><author><name>Chad Shaw</name></author><author><name>Joseph Jankovic</name></author><author><name>Lisa M. Shulman</name></author><author><name>Joshua M. Shulman</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background and Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Genetic variants impact both Parkinson’s disease (PD) risk and manifestations. While genetic information is of potential interest to patients and clinicians, genetic testing is rarely performed during routine PD clinical care. The goal of this study was to perform genome sequencing and examine patient interest in comprehensive genetic testing for PD in 2 academic movement disorder clinics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 208 subjects with PD (age=63 years, 67% male), genome sequencing was performed and filtered using a custom panel, including 49 genes associated with PD, parkinsonism, or related disorders, as well as a 90-variant PD genetic risk score. Separately, 231 patients (age=67 years, 63% male) were surveyed on interest in genetic testing at baseline and in response to vignettes covering (i) familial risk of PD (&lt;italic&gt;LRRK2&lt;/italic&gt;); (ii) risk of PD dementia (&lt;italic&gt;GBA&lt;/italic&gt;); (iii) PD genetic risk score; and (iv) secondary, medically-actionable variants (&lt;italic&gt;BRCA1&lt;/italic&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Genome sequencing revealed a &lt;italic&gt;LRRK2&lt;/italic&gt; variant in 3.4% and a &lt;italic&gt;GBA&lt;/italic&gt; risk variant in 10.1% of our clinical sample. The genetic risk score was normally distributed, identifying 42 subjects with high risk of PD. Medically-actionable findings were discovered in 2 subjects (1%). In our survey, the majority (82%) responded they would share a &lt;italic&gt;LRRK2&lt;/italic&gt; variant with relatives. Most registered unchanged or increased interest in testing when confronted with potential risk for dementia or medically- actionable findings, and most (75%) expressed interest in learning their PD genetic risk score.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Discussion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our results highlight broad interest in comprehensive genetic testing among patients with PD and may facilitate integration of genome sequencing in clinical practice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266755" rel="alternate" title="Genome sequencing in the Parkinson’s disease clinic (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21265452</id><title>Deep learning to estimate gestational age from blind ultrasound sweeps of the gravid abdomen (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.235807+00:00</updated><author><name>Teeranan Pokaprakarn</name></author><author><name>Juan C. Prieto</name></author><author><name>Joan T. Price</name></author><author><name>Margaret P. Kasaro</name></author><author><name>Ntazana Sindano</name></author><author><name>Hina R. Shah</name></author><author><name>Marc Peterson</name></author><author><name>Mutinta M. Akapelwa</name></author><author><name>Filson M. Kapilya</name></author><author><name>Yuri V. Sebastião</name></author><author><name>William Goodnight</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth M. Stringer</name></author><author><name>Bethany L. Freeman</name></author><author><name>Lina M. Montoya</name></author><author><name>Benjamin H. Chi</name></author><author><name>Dwight J. Rouse</name></author><author><name>Stephen R. Cole</name></author><author><name>Bellington Vwalika</name></author><author><name>Michael R. Kosorok</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey S. A. Stringer</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ultrasound is indispensable to gestational age estimation, and thus to quality obstetric care, yet high equipment cost and need for trained sonographers limit its use in low-resource settings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;From September 2018 through June 2021, we recruited 4,695 pregnant volunteers in North Carolina and Zambia and obtained blind ultrasound sweeps (cineloops) of the gravid abdomen alongside standard fetal biometry. We trained a neural network to estimate gestational age from the sweeps and, in three test sets, assessed performance of the model and biometry against previously established gestational age.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In our main test set, model mean absolute error (MAE) was 3.9 days (standard error [SE] 0.12) vs. 4.7 days (SE 0.15) for biometry (difference -0.8 days; 95% CI -1.1, -0.5; p&amp;lt;0.001). Results were similar in North Carolina (difference -0.6 days, 95% CI -0.9, -0.2) and Zambia (−1.0 days, 95% CI -1.5, -0.5). Findings were supported in the test set of women who conceived by in vitro fertilization (model MAE 2.8 days [SE 0.28] vs. 3.6 days [SE 0.53] for biometry; difference -0.8 days, 95% CI -1.7, 0.2), and in the set of women from whom sweeps were collected by untrained users with low-cost, battery-powered devices (model MAE 4.9 days [SE 0.29] vs. 5.4 days [SE 0.28] for biometry; difference -0.6, 95% CI -1.3, 0.1).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our model estimated gestational age more accurately from blindly obtained ultrasound sweeps than did trained sonographers performing fetal biometry. These results presage a future where all pregnant people – not just those in rich countries – can access the diagnostic benefits of sonography.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21265452" rel="alternate" title="Deep learning to estimate gestational age from blind ultrasound sweeps of the gravid abdomen (3 tweets)"/><category term="Obstetrics and Gynecology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>