<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.708294+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.01.21262607</id><title>ADataViewer: Exploring Semantically Harmonized Alzheimer’s Disease Cohort Datasets (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.712083+00:00</updated><author><name>Yasamin Salimi</name></author><author><name>Daniel Domingo-Fernándéz</name></author><author><name>Carlos Bobis-Álvarez</name></author><author><name>Martin Hofmann-Apitius</name></author><author><name>Colin Birkenbihl</name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Currently, AD cohort datasets are difficult to find, lack across-cohort interoperability, and the content of the shared datasets often only becomes clear to third-party researchers once data access has been granted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;METHODS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We accessed and systematically investigated the content of 20 major AD cohort datasets on data-level. A medical professional and a data specialist manually curated and semantically harmonized the acquired datasets. We developed a platform that facilitates data exploration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;RESULTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present ADataViewer, an interactive platform that facilitates the exploration of 20 cohort datasets with respect to longitudinal follow-up, demographics, ethnoracial diversity, measured modalities, and statistical properties of individual variables. Additionally, we publish a variable mapping catalog harmonizing 1,196 variables across the 20 cohorts. The platform is available under &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://adata.scai.fraunhofer.de/"&gt;https://adata.scai.fraunhofer.de/&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;DISCUSSION&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;ADataViewer supports robust data-driven research by transparently displaying cohort dataset content and suggesting datasets suited for discovery and validation studies based on selected variables of interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.01.21262607" rel="alternate" title="ADataViewer: Exploring Semantically Harmonized Alzheimer’s Disease Cohort Datasets (31 tweets)"/><category term="Health Informatics"/><published>2021-09-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.21263499</id><title>The natural history of TB disease-a synthesis of data to quantify progression and regression across the spectrum (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.712714+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexandra S Richards</name></author><author><name>Bianca Sossen</name></author><author><name>Jon C Emery</name></author><author><name>Katherine C Horton</name></author><author><name>Torben Heinsohn</name></author><author><name>Beatrice Frascella</name></author><author><name>Federica Balzarini</name></author><author><name>Aurea Oradini-Alacreu</name></author><author><name>Brit Hacker</name></author><author><name>Anna Odone</name></author><author><name>Nicky McCreesh</name></author><author><name>Alison D Grant</name></author><author><name>Katharina Kranzer</name></author><author><name>Frank Cobelens</name></author><author><name>Hanif Esmail</name></author><author><name>Rein MGJ Houben</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prevalence surveys have found a substantial burden of subclinical (asymptomatic but infectious) TB, from which individuals can progress, regress or even persist in a chronic disease state. We aimed to quantify these pathways across the spectrum of TB disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We created deterministic framework of TB disease with progression and regression between three states of pulmonary TB disease: minimal (non-infectious), subclinical, and clinical (symptomatic and infectious) disease. We estimated ranges for each parameter by considering all data from a systematic review in a Bayesian framework, enabling quantitative estimation of TB disease pathways.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Twenty-four studies contributed data from 6030 individuals. Results suggested that, after five years, 24.7%(95% uncertainty interval, UI, 21.3%-28.6%) of individuals with prevalent subclinical disease at baseline had either progressed to clinical disease or died from TB, whereas 16.1%(95%UI, 13.8%-18.5%) had recovered after regressing to minimal disease. Over the course of five years 30% (95%UI, 27.2%-32.6%) of the subclinial cohort never developed symptoms. For those with clinical disease at baseline, 39%(95%UI, 35.8%-41.9%) and 10.3%(95%UI, 8.5%-12.4%) had died or recovered from TB, with the remainder in, or undulating between, the three disease states. The ten-year mortality of people with untreated prevalent infectious disease was 38%.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our results show that for people with subclinical disease, classic clinical disease is neither inevitable nor an irreversible outcome. As such, reliance on symptom-based screening means a large proportion of people with infectious disease may never be detected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;TB Modelling and Analysis Consortium and European Research Council&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Research in Context&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Evidence before this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In recent years the existence of a spectrum of TB disease has been re-accepted. The classic paradigm of disease is one active state of symptomatic presentation with bacteriologically positive sputum, now referred to as clinical disease. Within the spectrum, a subclinical phase (where people do not report symptoms but have bacteriologically positive sputum) has been widely accepted, due to prevalence surveys using chest radiography screening in addition to symptom screening. On average these prevalence surveys have found around 50% of people with prevalent infectious TB had subclinical disease. There is also another state of minimal disease, or non-infectious disease, that is the earliest point on the disease spectrum after progression from infection. The likelihood or speed of natural progression, regression, or persistence of individuals across this spectrum remains unknown. As a consequence, the ability to accurately predict the impact of interventions has been limited. As individuals with bacteriologically-positive TB now receive treatment, contemporary data to inform the required transitions is highly limited. However, a large number of cohorts of patients were described in the pre-chemotherapy era. Until now, these data have not been synthesised to inform parameters to describe the natural history of TB disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Added value of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We synthesised data from historical and contemporary literature to explore the expected trajectories of individuals across the spectrum of TB disease. We considered a cohort of people with prevalent bacteriologically positive disease, with a 50/50 split of people with subclinical and clinical disease at baseline. We found that within five years, 13.3% of people recover from TB, with no chance of progressing to active disease without reinfection. However, we also find that 26.3% are still spending time infectious at the end of the five years. Our estimates for 10 year mortality and duration of symptoms before treatment aligned with the known and accepted values.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We also show that regression from subclinical disease results in a large reservoir of people with minimal disease, from which they can permanently recover, but can also progress again to subclinical disease. The undulating pathways that lead to regression and progression mean that 30% (27.2%-32.6%) of individuals with prevalent subclinical disease do not experience symptoms over the course of five years. This shows that clinical disease is neither a rapid, nor inevitable outcome of subclinical disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Implications of the available evidence&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;With these data-driven estimates of parameters, informed projections of the relative value of addressing minimal, subclinical, or clinical disease can now be provided. Given the known reservoir of prevalent subclinical disease and its contribution to transmission, efforts to diagnose and treat people with “earlier” stages of TB are likely to have a larger impact than strategies targeting clinical disease, particularly on individuals who never would have progressed to clinical disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.21263499" rel="alternate" title="The natural history of TB disease-a synthesis of data to quantify progression and regression across the spectrum (30 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.11.21263146</id><title>Causal effect of C-reactive protein and vitamin D on human cerebral anatomy observed among genetically correlated biomarkers in blood (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.713254+00:00</updated><author><name>Dylan J. Kiltschewskij</name></author><author><name>William R. Reay</name></author><author><name>Murray J. Cairns</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Psychiatric disorders such as schizophrenia are commonly associated with structural brain alterations affecting the cortex, which frequently vary with clinically relevant factors including antipsychotic treatment, duration of illness and age of onset. While the underlying variables mediating these structural changes are poorly understood, recent genetic evidence suggests circulating metabolites and other biochemical traits play a causal role in a number of psychiatric disorders which could be mediated by changes in the cerebral cortex. In the current study, we leveraged publicly available genome-wide association study (GWAS) data to explore shared genetic architecture and evidence for causal relationships between a panel of 50 biochemical traits and measures of cortical thickness and surface area at both the global and regional levels. Linkage disequilibrium score regression identified a total of 20 significant and 156 suggestive genetically correlated biochemical-cortical trait pairings, of which six exhibited strong evidence for causality in a latent causal variable model. Interestingly, a negative causal relationship was identified between a unit increase in serum C-reactive protein levels and thickness of the lingual and lateral occipital regions that was also supported by Mendelian randomisation, while circulating vitamin D (25-hydroxyvitamin D) levels exhibited a positive causal effect on temporal pole thickness. Taken together, our findings suggest a subset of biochemical traits exhibit shared genetic architecture and potentially causal relationships with cortical thickness in functionally distinct regions, which may contribute to alteration of cortical structure in psychiatric disorders.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.11.21263146" rel="alternate" title="Causal effect of C-reactive protein and vitamin D on human cerebral anatomy observed among genetically correlated biomarkers in blood (14 tweets)"/><category term="Psychiatry and Clinical Psychology"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.11.21256274</id><title>The Morbidity Costs of Air Pollution through the Lens of Health Spending in China (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.714689+00:00</updated><author><name>Xin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xun Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xi Chen</name></author><author><name>Yuehua Liu</name></author><author><name>Xintong Zhao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This study offers one of the first causal evidence on the morbidity costs of fine particulates (PM2.5) for all age cohorts in a developing country, using individual-level healthcare spending data from the basic medical insurance program in Wuhan, China. Our instrumental variable (IV) approach uses thermal inversion to address potential endogeneity in PM2.5 concentrations and shows that PM2.5 imposes a significant impact on medical expenditures. The IV estimate suggests that a 10 μg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; reduction in monthly average PM2.5 leads to a 2.79% decrease in the value of health spending and a 0.70% decline in the number of transactions in pharmacies and health facilities. The effect is more salient for males, children, and older adults. Moreover, our estimates provide a lower bound of people’s willingness-to-pay, which amounts to CNY 51.85 (or USD 8.38) per capita per year for a 10 μg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; reduction in PM2.5.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;JEL Codes&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Q51, Q53, I11, I31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conflict of interest&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.11.21256274" rel="alternate" title="The Morbidity Costs of Air Pollution through the Lens of Health Spending in China (4 tweets)"/><category term="Health Policy"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460266</id><title>Investigation of a derived adverse outcome pathway (AOP) network for endocrine-mediated perturbations (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.730151+00:00</updated><author><name>Janani Ravichandran</name></author><author><name>Bagavathy Shanmugam Karthikeyan</name></author><author><name>Areejit Samal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;An adverse outcome pathway (AOP) is a compact representation of the available mechanistic information on observed adverse effects upon environmental exposure. Sharing of events across individual AOPs has led to the emergence of AOP networks. Since AOP networks are expected to be functional units of toxicity prediction, there is current interest in their development tailored to specific research question or regulatory problem. To this end, we have developed a detailed workflow to construct a comprehensive endocrine-specific AOP (ED-AOP) network. Connectivity analysis of the ED-AOP network comprising 48 AOPs reveals 7 connected components and 12 isolated AOPs. Subsequently, we apply standard network measures to perform an in-depth analysis of the two largest connected components of the ED-AOP network. Notably, the graph-theoretic analyses led to the identification of important events including points of convergence or divergence in the ED-AOP network. Detailed analysis of the largest component in the ED-AOP network gives insights on the systems-level perturbations caused by endocrine disruption, emergent paths, and stressor-event associations. In sum, the derived ED-AOP network can be used to address the current knowledge gaps in the existing regulatory framework and aid in better risk assessment of environmental chemicals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460266" rel="alternate" title="Investigation of a derived adverse outcome pathway (AOP) network for endocrine-mediated perturbations (3 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460053</id><title>Dysregulation of the Tweak/Fn14 pathway in skeletal muscle of spinal muscular atrophy mice (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.730663+00:00</updated><author><name>Katharina E. Meijboom</name></author><author><name>Emily McFall</name></author><author><name>Daniel Anthony</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Edwards</name></author><author><name>Sabrina Kubinski</name></author><author><name>Gareth Hazell</name></author><author><name>Nina Ahlskog</name></author><author><name>Peter Claus</name></author><author><name>Kay E. Davies</name></author><author><name>Rashmi Kothary</name></author><author><name>Matthew J.A. Wood</name></author><author><name>Melissa Bowerman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spinal muscular atrophy (SMA) is a childhood neuromuscular disorder caused by depletion of the survival motor neuron (SMN) protein. SMA is characterized by the selective death of spinal cord motor neurons, leading to progressive muscle wasting. Loss of skeletal muscle in SMA is a combination of denervation-induced muscle atrophy and intrinsic muscle pathologies. Elucidation of the pathways involved is essential to identify the key molecules that contribute to and sustain muscle pathology. The tumor necrosis factor-like weak inducer of apoptosis (TWEAK)/TNF receptor superfamily member fibroblast growth factor inducible 14 (Fn14) pathway has been shown to play a critical role in the regulation of denervation-induced muscle atrophy as well as muscle proliferation, differentiation and metabolism in adults. However, it is not clear whether this pathway would be important in highly dynamic and developing muscle. We thus investigated the potential role of the TWEAK/Fn14 pathway in SMA muscle pathology, using the severe Taiwanese &lt;italic&gt;Smn&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;;SMN2&lt;/italic&gt; and the less severe &lt;italic&gt;Smn&lt;sup&gt;2B/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; SMA mice, which undergo a progressive neuromuscular decline in the first three post-natal weeks. Here, we report significantly dysregulated expression of the TWEAK/Fn14 pathway during disease progression in skeletal muscle of the two SMA mouse models. In addition, siRNA-mediated &lt;italic&gt;Smn&lt;/italic&gt; knockdown in C2C12 myoblasts suggests a genetic interaction between Smn and the TWEAK/Fn14 pathway. Further analyses of SMA, &lt;italic&gt;Tweak&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Fn14&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice revealed dysregulated myopathy, myogenesis and glucose metabolism pathways as a common skeletal muscle feature, and providing further evidence in support of a relationship between the TWEAK/Fn14 pathway and Smn. Finally, a pharmacological intervention (Fc-TWEAK) to upregulate the activity of the TWEAK/Fn14 pathway improved disease phenotypes in the two SMA mouse models. Our study provides novel mechanistic insights into the molecular players that contribute to muscle pathology in SMA and into the role of the TWEAK/Fn14 pathway in developing muscle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460053" rel="alternate" title="Dysregulation of the Tweak/Fn14 pathway in skeletal muscle of spinal muscular atrophy mice (3 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>