<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.643985+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.21268179</id><title>An online atlas of human plasma metabolite signatures of gut microbiome composition (44 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.644756+00:00</updated><author><name>Koen F. Dekkers</name></author><author><name>Sergi Sayols-Baixeras</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Baldanzi</name></author><author><name>Christoph Nowak</name></author><author><name>Ulf Hammar</name></author><author><name>Diem Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Georgios Varotsis</name></author><author><name>Louise Brunkwall</name></author><author><name>Nynne Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Aron C. Eklund</name></author><author><name>Jacob Bak Holm</name></author><author><name>H. Bjørn Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Filip Ottosson</name></author><author><name>Yi-Ting Lin</name></author><author><name>Shafqat Ahmad</name></author><author><name>Lars Lind</name></author><author><name>Johan Sundström</name></author><author><name>Gunnar Engström</name></author><author><name>J. Gustav Smith</name></author><author><name>Johan Ärnlöv</name></author><author><name>Marju Orho-Melander</name></author><author><name>Tove Fall</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The human gut microbiota produces a variety of small compounds, some of which enter the bloodstream and impact host health. Conversely, various exogenous nutritional and pharmaceutical compounds affect the gut microbiome composition before entering circulation. Characterization of the gut microbiota—host plasma metabolite interactions is an important step towards understanding the effects of the gut microbiota on human health. However, studies involving large and deeply phenotyped cohorts that would reveal such meaningful interactions are scarce. Here, we used deep metagenomic sequencing and ultra-high-performance liquid chromatography linked to mass spectrometry for detailed characterization of the fecal microbiota and plasma metabolome, respectively, of 8,584 participants invited at age 50 to 64 of the Swedish CArdioPulmonary bioImage Study (SCAPIS). After adjusting for multiple comparisons, we identified 1,008 associations between species alpha diversity and plasma metabolites, and 318,944 associations between specific gut metagenomic species and plasma metabolites. The gut microbiota explained up to 50% of the variance of individual plasma metabolites (mean of 4.7%). We present all results as the searchable association atlas "GUTSY" as a rich resource for mining associations, and exemplify the potential of the atlas by presenting novel associations between oral medication and the gut microbiome, and microbiota species strongly associated with levels of the uremic toxin p-cresol sulfate. The association atlas can be used as the basis for targeted studies of perturbation of specific bacteria and for identification of candidate plasma biomarkers of gut flora composition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.21268179" rel="alternate" title="An online atlas of human plasma metabolite signatures of gut microbiome composition (44 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.24.21268385</id><title>Schizophrenia-associated somatic copy number variants from 12,834 cases reveal contribution to risk and recurrent, isoform-specific NRXN1 disruptions (20 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.645566+00:00</updated><author><name>Eduardo A Maury</name></author><author><name>Maxwell A Sherman</name></author><author><name>Giulio Genovese</name></author><author><name>Thomas G. Gilgenast</name></author><author><name>Prashanth Rajarajan</name></author><author><name>Erin Flaherty</name></author><author><name>Schahram Akbarian</name></author><author><name>Andrew Chess</name></author><author><name>Steven A. McCarroll</name></author><author><name>Po-Ru Loh</name></author><author><name>Jennifer E. Philips-Cremins</name></author><author><name>Kristen J. Brennand</name></author><author><name>James T.R . Walters</name></author><author><name>Michael O'Donovan</name></author><author><name>Patrick Sullivan</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Sebat</name></author><author><name>Eunjung A. Lee</name></author><author><name>Christopher A. Walsh</name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;While inherited and de novo copy number variants (CNV) have been implicated in the genetic architecture of schizophrenia (SCZ), the contribution of somatic CNVs (sCNVs), present in some but not all cells of the body, remains unknown. Here we explore the role of sCNVs in SCZ by analyzing blood-derived genotype arrays from 12,834 SCZ cases and 11,648 controls. sCNVs were more common in cases (0.91%) than in controls (0.51%, p = 2.68e-4). We observed recurrent somatic deletions of exons 1-5 of the NRXN1 gene in 5 SCZ cases. Allele-specific Hi-C maps revealed ectopic, allele-specific loops forming between a potential novel cryptic promoter and non-coding cis regulatory elements upon deletions in the 5' region of NRXN1. We also observed recurrent intragenic deletions of ABCB11, a gene associated with anti-psychotic response, in 5 treatment-resistant SCZ cases. Taken together our results indicate an important role of sCNVs to SCZ risk and treatment-responsiveness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.24.21268385" rel="alternate" title="Schizophrenia-associated somatic copy number variants from 12,834 cases reveal contribution to risk and recurrent, isoform-specific NRXN1 disruptions (20 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.27.21268442</id><title>Brain atrophy in prodromal synucleinopathy is shaped by structural connectivity and gene expression (15 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.646033+00:00</updated><author><name>Shady Rahayel</name></author><author><name>Christina Tremblay</name></author><author><name>Andrew Vo</name></author><author><name>Ying-Qiu Zheng</name></author><author><name>Stéphane Lehéricy</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Arnulf</name></author><author><name>Marie Vidailhet</name></author><author><name>Jean-Christophe Corvol</name></author><author><name>Jean-François Gagnon</name></author><author><name>Ronald B Postuma</name></author><author><name>Jacques Montplaisir</name></author><author><name>Simon Lewis</name></author><author><name>Elie Matar</name></author><author><name>Kaylena Ehgoetz Martens</name></author><author><name>Per Borghammer</name></author><author><name>Karoline Knudsen</name></author><author><name>Allan Hansen</name></author><author><name>Oury Monchi</name></author><author><name>Bratislav Misic</name></author><author><name>Alain Dagher</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Isolated REM sleep behaviour disorder (iRBD) is a synucleinopathy characterized by abnormal behaviours and vocalizations during REM sleep. Most iRBD patients develop dementia with Lewy bodies, Parkinson's disease, or multiple system atrophy over time. Patients with iRBD exhibit brain atrophy patterns that are reminiscent of those observed in overt synucleinopathies. However, the mechanisms linking brain atrophy to the underlying alpha-synuclein pathophysiology are poorly understood. Our objective was to investigate how the prion-like and regional vulnerability hypotheses of alpha-synuclein might explain brain atrophy in iRBD.

Using a multicentric cohort of 182 polysomnography-confirmed iRBD patients who underwent T1-weighted MRI, we performed vertex-based cortical surface and deformation-based morphometry analyses to quantify brain atrophy in patients (67.8 years, 84% men) and 261 healthy controls (66.2 years, 75%) and investigated the morphological correlates of motor and cognitive functioning in iRBD. Next, we applied the agent-based Susceptible-Infected-Removed model (i.e., a computational model that simulates in silico the spread of pathologic alpha-synuclein based on structural connectivity and gene expression) and tested if it recreated atrophy in iRBD by statistically comparing simulated regional brain atrophy to the atrophy observed in patients. The impact of SNCA and GBA gene expression and brain connectivity was then evaluated by comparing the model fit to the one obtained in null models where either gene expression or connectivity was randomized.

The results showed that iRBD patients present with cortical thinning and tissue deformation, which correlated with motor and cognitive functioning. Next, we found that the atrophy simulated based on brain connectivity and gene expression recreated cortical thinning (r=0.51, p=0.0007) and tissue deformation (r=0.52, p=0.0005) in patients, and that the connectome's architecture along with SNCA and GBA gene expression contributed to shaping atrophy in iRBD. We further demonstrated that the full agent-based model performed better than network measures or gene expression alone in recreating the atrophy pattern in iRBD.

In summary, atrophy in iRBD is extensive, correlates with motor and cognitive functioning, and can be recreated using the dynamics of agent-based modelling, structural connectivity, and gene expression. These findings support the concepts that both prion-like spread and regional susceptibility account for the atrophy observed in prodromal synucleinopathies. Therefore, the agent-based Susceptible-Infected-Removed model may be a useful tool for testing hypotheses underlying neurodegenerative diseases and new therapies aimed at slowing or stopping the spread of alpha-synuclein pathology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.27.21268442" rel="alternate" title="Brain atrophy in prodromal synucleinopathy is shaped by structural connectivity and gene expression (15 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.21268413</id><title>Increased persuadability and credulity in people with corpus callosum dysgenesis (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.646445+00:00</updated><author><name>Linda J Richards</name></author><author><name>Joseph Barnby</name></author><author><name>Ryan Dean</name></author><author><name>Henry Burgess</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey Kim</name></author><author><name>Alessa Teunisse</name></author><author><name>Lisa Mackenzie</name></author><author><name>Gail Robinson</name></author><author><name>Peter Dayan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Corpus callosum dysgenesis is one of the most common congenital neurological malformations. Despite being a clear and identifiable structural alteration of the brains white matter connectivity, the impact of corpus callosum dysgenesis on cognition and behavior has remained unclear. Here we build upon past clinical observations in the literature to define the clinical phenotype of corpus callosum dysgenesis better using unadjusted and adjusted group differences compared with a neurotypical sample on a range of social and cognitive measures that have been previously reported to be impacted by a corpus callosum dysgenesis diagnosis. Those with a diagnosis of corpus callosum dysgenesis (n = 22) demonstrated significantly higher persuadability, credulity, and insensitivity to social trickery than neurotypical (n = 86) participants, after controlling for age, sex, education, autistic-like traits, social intelligence, and general cognition. To explore this further, machine learning, utilizing a set neurotypical sample for training the normative covariance structure of our psychometric variables, was used to test whether these dimensions possessed the capability to discriminate between a test-set of neurotypical and corpus callosum dysgenesis participants. We found that participants with a diagnosis of corpus callosum dysgenesis were best classed within dimension space along the same axis as persuadability, credulity, and insensitivity to social trickery after controlling for age and sex, with Leave-One-Out-Cross-Validation across 250 training-set permutations providing a mean accuracy of 71.7 percent. These results have wide-reaching implications for a) the characterization of corpus callosum dysgenesis, and b) the role of the corpus callosum in social inference.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.21268413" rel="alternate" title="Increased persuadability and credulity in people with corpus callosum dysgenesis (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2021-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.21268161</id><title>Predicting risk of pancreatic cancer in individuals with new-onset type-2 diabetes in primary care: protocol for the development and validation of a clinical prediction model (QPancreasD) (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.646852+00:00</updated><author><name>Pui San Tan</name></author><author><name>Ashley Kieran Clift</name></author><author><name>Weiqi Liao</name></author><author><name>Martina Patone</name></author><author><name>Carol Coupland</name></author><author><name>Rachael Bashford-Rogers</name></author><author><name>Shivan Sivakumar</name></author><author><name>David Clifton</name></author><author><name>Stephen P Pereira</name></author><author><name>Julia Hippisley-Cox</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pancreatic cancer continues to have an extremely poor prognosis in part due to late diagnosis. 25% of pancreatic cancer patients have a prior diagnosis of diabetes, and hence identifying individuals at risk of pancreatic cancer in those with recently diagnosed type 2 diabetes may be a useful opportunity to identify candidates for screening and early detection. In this study, we will comparatively evaluate regression and machine learning-based clinical prediction models for estimating individual risk of developing pancreatic cancer two years after type 2 diabetes diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the development dataset, we will include adults aged 30-84 years with incident type-2 diabetes registered with QResearch primary care database. Patients will be followed up from type-2 diabetes diagnosis to first diagnosis of pancreatic cancer as recorded in any one of primary care records, hospital episode statistics, cancer registry data, or death records. Cox-proportional hazards models will be used to develop a risk prediction model for estimating individual risk of developing pancreatic cancer during up to 2 years of follow-up. We will perform variable selection using a combination of clinical and statistical significance approach i.e. HR &amp;lt;0.9 or &amp;gt;1.1 and p&amp;lt;0.01. Linear predictors and baseline survivor function at 2 years will be used to compute absolute risk predictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Internal-external cross-validation (IECV) framework across geographical regions within England will be used to assess performance and pooled using random effects meta-analysis using: (i) model fit in terms of variation explained by the model Royston &amp;amp; Sauerbrei’s R2D, (ii) calibration slope and calibration-in-the-large, and (iii) discrimination measured in terms of Harrell’s C and Royston &amp;amp; Sauerbrei’s D-statistic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further, we will evaluate machine learning (ML) approaches for the clinical prediction model using neural networks (NN) and XGBoost. The model predictors and performance of these will be compared with the results of those derived from the regression-based strategy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Discussion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The proposed study will develop and validate a novel risk prediction model to aid early diagnosis of pancreatic cancer in patients with new-onset diabetes in primary care. With an enhanced decision-risk tool for use at point-of care by general practitioners to assess pancreatic cancer risk, it may improve decision-making so that at-risk patients are rapidly prioritised to aid early diagnosis of pancreatic cancer in patients with newly diagnosed diabetes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.21268161" rel="alternate" title="Predicting risk of pancreatic cancer in individuals with new-onset type-2 diabetes in primary care: protocol for the development and validation of a clinical prediction model (QPancreasD) (3 tweets)"/><category term="Primary Care Research"/><published>2021-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>