<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.464143+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.18.21259977</id><title>Altered functional connectome hierarchy with gene expression signatures in newly-diagnosed focal epilepsy (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.464728+00:00</updated><author><name>Christophe E de Bézenac</name></author><author><name>Lorenzo Caciagli</name></author><author><name>Batil K Alonazi</name></author><author><name>Boris C Bernhardt</name></author><author><name>Anthony G Marson</name></author><author><name>Simon S Keller</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neuroimaging research is providing insights into epilepsy as a disorder of brain connectivity linked to functional impairments which may have an identifiable genetic component. This case-control study aims to identify imbalances in a functional connectome dimension spanning from unimodal to transmodal networks and explore the potential genetic basis of such alterations in patients with newly diagnosed focal epilepsy (NDfE).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used gradient-based analysis of resting-sate fMRI data comparing cortical gradient maps in patients with NDfE (n = 27) to age and sex-matched controls (n = 36). Using a brain-wide gene expression dataset, gene combinations associated with altered brain regions were then entered into an enrichment analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found an increased differentiation of connectivity profiles between unimodal and transmodal networks in NDfE, which was particularly pronounced in the patients with persistent seizures at 12-months follow-up (n=10). Differences corresponded to gradient score reductions in a visual network and increases in limbic and default mode systems which subserve higher-level cognition. Cortical difference maps were spatially correlated with regional expression of a weighted gene combination. These genes were enriched for disease and ontology terms and pathways previously associated with epilepsy and seizure susceptibility.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretations&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Large-scale functional hierarchy may be altered from in focal epilepsy from diagnosis and correlate with response to treatment. Combining functional neuroimaging and transcriptional data analysis may provide a framework for understanding the wide-ranging impairments associated with the disorder and mechanistic insight into how gene processes may drive alterations in brain function mediating the genetic risk of epilepsy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.18.21259977" rel="alternate" title="Altered functional connectome hierarchy with gene expression signatures in newly-diagnosed focal epilepsy (12 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2021-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.21260947</id><title>Prospective validation of host transcriptomic biomarkers for pulmonary tuberculosis by real-time PCR (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.465312+00:00</updated><author><name>Simon C Mendelsohn</name></author><author><name>Stanley Kimbung Mbandi</name></author><author><name>Andrew Fiore-Gartland</name></author><author><name>Adam Penn-Nicholson</name></author><author><name>Munyaradzi Musvosvi</name></author><author><name>Humphrey Mulenga</name></author><author><name>Michelle Fisher</name></author><author><name>Katie Hadley</name></author><author><name>Mzwandile Erasmus</name></author><author><name>Onke Nombida</name></author><author><name>Michele Tameris</name></author><author><name>Gerhard Walzl</name></author><author><name>Kogielium Naidoo</name></author><author><name>Gavin Chruchyard</name></author><author><name>Mark Hatherill</name></author><author><name>Thomas Scriba</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We tested performance of host-blood transcriptomic tuberculosis (TB) signatures for active case-finding. Among 20,207 HIV-uninfected and 963 HIV-infected adults screened; 2,923 and 861 were enrolled from five South African communities. Eight signatures were measured by microfluidic RT-qPCR and participants were microbiologically-investigated for pulmonary TB at baseline, and actively surveilled for incident disease through 15 months. Diagnostic AUCs for 61 HIV-uninfected (weighted-prevalence 1.1%) and 10 HIV-infected (prevalence 1.2%) prevalent TB cases for the 8 signatures were 0.63-0.79 and 0.65-0.88, respectively. Thereafter, 24 HIV-uninfected and 9 HIV-infected participants progressed to incident TB (1.1 and 1.0 per 100 person-years, respectively). Prognostic AUCs through 15-months follow-up were 0.49-0.66 and 0.54-0.81, respectively. Prognostic performance for incident TB occurring within 6-12 months in HIV-negative participants was higher for all signatures. None of the signatures met WHO Target Product Profile criteria for a triage test to diagnose asymptomatic TB; most signatures met the criteria for symptomatic TB. Prognostic accuracy of most signatures for incident TB within six months of testing met the criteria for an incipient TB test.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.21260947" rel="alternate" title="Prospective validation of host transcriptomic biomarkers for pulmonary tuberculosis by real-time PCR (6 tweets)"/><category term="Respiratory Medicine"/><published>2021-07-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.21260946</id><title>Association between prenatal alcohol exposure and children's facial shape. A prospective population-based cohort study (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.466291+00:00</updated><author><name>Xianjing Liu</name></author><author><name>Manfred Kayser</name></author><author><name>Steven A. Kushner</name></author><author><name>Henning Tiemeier</name></author><author><name>Fernando Rivadeneira</name></author><author><name>Vincent W. V. Jaddoe</name></author><author><name>Wiro Niessen</name></author><author><name>Eppo B. Wolvius</name></author><author><name>Gennady V. Roshchupkin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;IMPORTANCE: Children exposed to a high level of prenatal alcohol exposure (PAE) are more likely to develop fetal alcohol spectrum disorder with adverse phenotypes on their faces. However, it is still poorly understood, which level of PAE is associated with facial manifestation and if such associations persist during childhood. 
OBJECTIVE: To examine the association between PAE and children facial phenotype in a prospective multi-ethnic population-based study.
DESIGN, SETTING, AND PARTICIPANTS: This study was based on the Generation R Study, a prospective cohort from fetal life onwards with maternal and offspring data. Children had a 3D facial image taken at ages 9 (n=3160) and 13 years (n=2492). 
EXPOSURES: We defined 6 levels of PAE based on the frequency and dose of alcohol consumption, and defined three tiers based on the timing of alcohol exposure of the unborn child.
MAIN OUTCOMES AND MEASURES:  For image analysis, we used 3D graph convolutional networks for non-linear dimensionality reduction, which compressed the high-dimensional images into 200 endophenotypes representing facial morphology. These facial endophenotypes were used as dependent variables in a linear regression analysis to search for associations with PAE. Finally, to detect specific facial components associated with PAE, we mapped statistically significant endophenotypes back to the 3D facial shape. We generated heatmaps to display the facial changes associated with PAE. PAE prediction based on facial shape was also performed; the prediction accuracy was estimated by area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUC).
RESULTS: A significant association between PAE and facial shape was found in the 9-year-old children, at all levels of alcohol exposure: the higher the level of exposure, the stronger the association. Moreover, PAE before and during pregnancy was associated with facial shape. The most common detected facial phenotypes included turned-up nose tip, shortened nose, turned-out jaw and turned-in lower-eyelid-related regions. For the 13-year-old children, the associations were weaker and the AUCs lower than those of the 9-years-old children.
CONCLUSIONS AND RELEVANCE: PAE before and during pregnancy, even at low level, is associated with the facial shape of children, and these associations become weaker as children grow older.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.21260946" rel="alternate" title="Association between prenatal alcohol exposure and children's facial shape. A prospective population-based cohort study (4 tweets)"/><category term="Pediatrics"/><published>2021-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.21.21251509</id><title>Incidence of Lyme disease in the United Kingdom and association with fatigue: a population-based, historical cohort study (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.466651+00:00</updated><author><name>Florence Brellier</name></author><author><name>Mar Pujades-Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Emma Powell</name></author><author><name>Kathleen Mudie</name></author><author><name>Eliana Lacerda</name></author><author><name>Luis Nacul</name></author><author><name>Kevin Wing</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To evaluate incidence rates of Lyme disease in the UK and to investigate a possible association with subsequent fatigue&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Population-based historical cohort study with a comparator cohort matched by age, sex, and general practice&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients treated in UK general practices contributing to IQVIA Medical Research Data&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;2,130 patients with a first diagnosis of Lyme disease between 2000 and 2018, and 8,510 randomly-sampled matched comparators, followed-up for a median time of 3 years and 8 months.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main outcome measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Time from Lyme disease diagnosis to consultation for any fatigue-related symptoms or diagnosis and for myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome (ME/CFS). Adjusted hazard ratios (HRs) were estimated from Cox models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Average incidence rate for Lyme disease across the UK was 5.18 per 100,000 py between 2000 and 2018, increasing from 2.55 in 2000 to 9.33 in 2018. In total 929 events of any types of fatigue were observed, i.e. an incidence rate of 307.90 per 10,000 py in the Lyme cohort (282 events) and 165.60 in the comparator cohort (647 events). Effect of Lyme disease on any subsequent fatigue varied by index season with highest adjusted HRs in autumn [3.14 (95%CI: 1.92 to 5.13)] and winter [2.23 (1.21 to 4.11)]. Incidence rates of ME/CFS were 11.16 per 10,000 py in Lyme patients (12 events) and 1.20 in comparators (5 events), corresponding to an adjusted HR of 16.95 (5.17 to 55.60). Effect on any types of fatigue and ME/CFS was attenuated 6 months after diagnosis but still clearly visible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;UK primary care records provided strong evidence that Lyme disease was associated with acute and chronic fatigue. Albeit weaker, these effects persisted beyond 6 months, suggesting that patients and healthcare providers should remain alert to fatigue symptoms months to years following Lyme disease diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key messages box&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What is already known on this topic&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Incidence rates of Lyme disease in the UK are increasing but estimations vary according to data sources used.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reports investigating the association between Lyme disease and long-term fatigue are contradictory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What this study adds&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Average incidence rate for Lyme disease across the UK was estimated at 5.18 per 100,000 py between 2000 and 2018, and followed an increasing trend.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In patients with Lyme disease, a 2- and 3-fold increase in any subsequent fatigue was observed in winter and autumn, respectively, and a 16-fold increase in ME/CFS (all seasons combined), compared to a non-Lyme cohort matched by sex, age, and general practice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.21.21251509" rel="alternate" title="Incidence of Lyme disease in the United Kingdom and association with fatigue: a population-based, historical cohort study (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21260986</id><title>A plasma metabolite score of three eicosanoids predicts incident type 2 diabetes – a prospective study in three independent cohorts (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.466954+00:00</updated><author><name>Karolina Tuomisto</name></author><author><name>Joonatan Palmu</name></author><author><name>Tao Long</name></author><author><name>Jeramie D. Watrous</name></author><author><name>Kysha Mercader</name></author><author><name>Kim A. Lagerborg</name></author><author><name>Allen Andres</name></author><author><name>Marko Salmi</name></author><author><name>Sirpa Jalkanen</name></author><author><name>Ramachandran S. Vasan</name></author><author><name>Michael Inouye</name></author><author><name>Aki S. Havulinna</name></author><author><name>Pekka Jousilahti</name></author><author><name>Teemu J. Niiranen</name></author><author><name>Susan Cheng</name></author><author><name>Mohit Jain</name></author><author><name>Veikko Salomaa</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aim&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Peptide markers of inflammation have been associated with the development of type 2 diabetes. The role of upstream, lipid-derived mediators of inflammation such as eicosanoids, remains less clear. The aim was to examine whether eicosanoids are associated with incident type 2 diabetes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the FINRISK 2002 study, a population-based sample of Finnish men and women aged 25-74 years, we used directed, non-targeted liquid chromatography – mass spectrometry to identify 545 eicosanoids and related oxylipins in the participants’ plasma samples (n=8,292). We used multivariable-adjusted Cox regression to examine associations between eicosanoids and incident type 2 diabetes. The findings were replicated in the Framingham Heart Study (FHS, n=2,886) and DILGOM 2007 (n=3,905). Together, these three cohorts had 1070 cases of incident type 2 diabetes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;76 eicosanoids were associated individually with incident type 2 diabetes. We identified three eicosanoids independently associated with incident type 2 diabetes using stepwise Cox regression with forward selection and a Bonferroni-corrected inclusion threshold. A three-eicosanoid risk score produced a hazard ratio (HR) of 1.56 (95% confidence interval 1.41-1.72) per one standard deviation (SD) increment for risk of incident diabetes. The HR for comparing the top quartile to the lowest was 2.80 (2.53-3.07). Meta-analysis of the three cohorts yielded a pooled HR per SD of 1.31 (1.05-1.56).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plasma eicosanoid profiles predict incident type 2 diabetes and the clearest signals replicate in three independent cohorts. Our findings give new information on the biology underlying type 2 diabetes and suggest opportunities for early identification of people at risk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21260986" rel="alternate" title="A plasma metabolite score of three eicosanoids predicts incident type 2 diabetes – a prospective study in three independent cohorts (3 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261034</id><title>Running related biomechanical risk factors for overuse injuries in distance runners: A systematic review considering injury specificity and the potentials for future research (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.467359+00:00</updated><author><name>Steffen Willwacher</name></author><author><name>Markus Kurz</name></author><author><name>Johanna Robbin</name></author><author><name>Matthias Thelen</name></author><author><name>Joseph Hamill</name></author><author><name>Luke Kelly</name></author><author><name>Patrick Mai</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To identify and evaluate the evidence of the most relevant running-related risk factors (RRRFs) for running-related overuse injuries (ROIs) and to suggest future research directions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Systematic review considering prospective and retrospective studies. (PROSPERO_ID: 236832)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data sources&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pubmed. Connected Papers. The search was performed in February 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Eligibility criteria&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;English language. Studies on participants whose primary sport is running addressing the risk for the seven most common ROIs and at least one kinematic, kinetic (including pressure measurements), or electromyographic RRRF. An RRRF needed to be identified in at least one prospective or two retrospective studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sixty-two articles fulfilled our eligibility criteria. Levels of evidence for specific ROIs ranged from conflicting to moderate evidence. Running populations and methods applied varied considerably between studies. While some RRRFs appeared for several ROIs, most RRRFs were specific for a particular ROI. The biomechanical measurements performed in many studies would have allowed for consideration of many more RRRFs than have been reported, highlighting a potential for more effective data usage in the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study offers a comprehensive overview of RRRFs for the most common ROIs, which might serve as a starting point to develop ROI-specific risk profiles of individual runners. Future work should use macroscopic (big data) approaches involving long-term data collections in the real world and microscopic approaches involving precise stress calculations using recent developments in biomechanical modelling. However, consensus on data collection standards (including the quantification of workload and stress tolerance variables and the reporting of injuries) is warranted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261034" rel="alternate" title="Running related biomechanical risk factors for overuse injuries in distance runners: A systematic review considering injury specificity and the potentials for future research (3 tweets)"/><category term="Orthopedics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>