<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.401383+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.21267169</id><title>The DIAMONDS intervention to support self-management of type 2 diabetes in people with severe mental illness: study protocol for a single-group feasibility study (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.402288+00:00</updated><author><name>Jennifer V E Brown</name></author><author><name>Ramzi Ajjan</name></author><author><name>Sarah Alderson</name></author><author><name>Jan R Böhnke</name></author><author><name>Claire Carswell</name></author><author><name>Patrick Doherty</name></author><author><name>Keith Double</name></author><author><name>Simon Gilbody</name></author><author><name>Michelle Hadjiconstantinou</name></author><author><name>Catherine Hewitt</name></author><author><name>Richard I G Holt</name></author><author><name>Rowena Jacobs</name></author><author><name>Vicki Johnson</name></author><author><name>Ian Kellar</name></author><author><name>David Osborn</name></author><author><name>Steve Parrott</name></author><author><name>David Shiers</name></author><author><name>Johanna Taylor</name></author><author><name>Jacqui Troughton</name></author><author><name>Judith Watson</name></author><author><name>Najma Siddiqi</name></author><author><name>Peter A Coventry</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The DIAMONDS programme aims to evaluate a novel supported diabetes self-management intervention for people with severe mental illness (the “DIAMONDS intervention”). The purpose of this study is to test the feasibility of intervention delivery and data collection procedures to inform a definitive randomised controlled trial (RCT).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adults aged 18 years or over with a diagnosis of type 2 diabetes and severe mental illness (schizophrenia, schizoaffective disorder, or bipolar disorder) will be eligible for inclusion. Individuals with other types of diabetes or non-psychotic mental illness and those lacking capacity to consent will not be eligible. Participants will be recruited from NHS mental health trusts and general practices across the North of England. All participants will receive the DIAMONDS intervention: weekly one-to-one sessions with a trained facilitator (“DIAMONDS Coach”) to support goal setting, action planning, and diabetes education; ongoing self-management supported by a paper-based workbook and optional digital application (app); and monthly peer-support group sessions with other participants. The primary outcomes are: 1. Recruitment rate, measured as proportion of the recruitment target (N=30) achieved at 5 months from start of recruitment, 2. Attrition measured as the proportion of missing outcomes data at the end of the recruitment period (5 months from start of recruitment) for physiological and self-reported data items, 3. Intervention delivery rate recorded as the proportion of planned sessions delivered (measured by the number of completed intervention session logs per participant within 15 weeks of the first intervention session). Secondary outcomes include completeness of data collection at baseline and of process evaluation data at follow-up as well as the feasibility and acceptability of the intervention and of wearing a blinded continuous glucose monitoring device. An intervention fidelity framework will also be developed. Recruitment started in July 2021. The study was prospectively registered: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="isrctn" xlink:href="15328700"&gt;ISRCTN15328700&lt;/ext-link&gt; (12&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; March 2021).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Discussion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The results of this feasibility study will inform the refinement of the content and delivery of the DIAMONDS intervention, as well as research procedures, including recruitment and data collection, in preparation for the main DIAMONDS RCT.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.21267169" rel="alternate" title="The DIAMONDS intervention to support self-management of type 2 diabetes in people with severe mental illness: study protocol for a single-group feasibility study (23 tweets)"/><category term="Psychiatry and Clinical Psychology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.21266509</id><title>Genome-wide association study across five cohorts identifies five novel loci associated with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.404452+00:00</updated><author><name>Richard J Allen</name></author><author><name>Amy Stockwell</name></author><author><name>Justin M Oldham</name></author><author><name>Beatriz Guillen-Guio</name></author><author><name>Carlos Flores</name></author><author><name>Imre Noth</name></author><author><name>Brian L Yaspan</name></author><author><name>R Gisli Jenkins</name></author><author><name>Louise V Wain</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF) is a chronic lung condition with poor survival times. We previously published a genome-wide meta-analysis of IPF risk across three studies with independent replication of associated variants in two additional studies. To maximise power and to generate more accurate effect size estimates, we performed a genome-wide meta-analysis across all five studies included in the previous IPF risk GWAS. We utilised the distribution of effect sizes across the five studies to assess the replicability of the results and identified five robust novel genetic association signals implicating mTOR signalling, telomere maintenance and spindle assembly genes in IPF risk.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.21266509" rel="alternate" title="Genome-wide association study across five cohorts identifies five novel loci associated with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (13 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471790</id><title>Functional modulation of PTH1R activation and signalling by RAMP2 (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.405090+00:00</updated><author><name>Katarina Nemec</name></author><author><name>Hannes Schihada</name></author><author><name>Gunnar Kleinau</name></author><author><name>Ulrike Zabel</name></author><author><name>Eugene O. Grushevskyi</name></author><author><name>Patrick Scheerer</name></author><author><name>Martin J. Lohse</name></author><author><name>Isabella Maiellaro</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Receptor-activity-modifying proteins (RAMPs) are ubiquitously expressed membrane proteins that associate with different G protein-coupled receptors (GPCRs) including the parathyroid hormone 1 receptor (PTH1R), a class B GPCR, and an important modulator of mineral ion homeostasis and bone metabolism. However, it is unknown whether and how RAMP proteins may affect PTH1R function. Using different optical biosensors to measure the activation of PTH1R and its downstream signalling, we describe here that RAMP2 acts as a specific allosteric modulator of PTH1R, shifting PTH1R to a unique pre-activated state that permits faster activation in a ligand-specific manner. Moreover, RAMP2 modulates PTH1R downstream signalling in an agonist-dependent manner, most notably increasing the PTH-mediated Gi3 signalling sensitivity. Additionally, RAMP2 increases both PTH- and PTHrP-triggered β-arrestin2 recruitment to PTH1R. Employing homology modelling we describe the putative structural molecular basis underlying our functional findings. These data uncover a critical role of RAMPs in the activation and signalling of a GPCR that may provide a new venue for highly specific modulation of GPCR function and advanced drug design.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471790" rel="alternate" title="Functional modulation of PTH1R activation and signalling by RAMP2 (12 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.21266984</id><title>Assessing the causal role of epigenetic clocks in the development of multiple cancers: a Mendelian randomization study (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.409947+00:00</updated><author><name>Fernanda Morales-Berstein</name></author><author><name>Daniel L McCartney</name></author><author><name>Ake T Lu</name></author><author><name>Konstantinos K Tsilidis</name></author><author><name>Emmanouil Bouras</name></author><author><name>Philip Haycock</name></author><author><name>Kimberley Burrows</name></author><author><name>Amanda I Phipps</name></author><author><name>Daniel D Buchanan</name></author><author><name>Iona Cheng</name></author><author><name>Richard M Martin</name></author><author><name>George Davey Smith</name></author><author><name>Caroline L Relton</name></author><author><name>Steve Horvath</name></author><author><name>Riccardo E Marioni</name></author><author><name>Tom G Richardson</name></author><author><name>Rebecca C Richmond</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Epigenetic clocks have been associated with cancer risk in several observational studies. Nevertheless, it is unclear whether they play a causal role in cancer risk or if they act as a non-causal biomarker.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted a two-sample Mendelian randomization (MR) study to examine the genetically predicted effects of epigenetic age acceleration as measured by HannumAge (9 single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs)), Horvath Intrinsic Age (24 SNPs), PhenoAge (11 SNPs) and GrimAge (4 SNPs) on multiple cancers (i.e., breast, prostate, colorectal, ovarian and lung cancer). We obtained genome-wide association data for biological ageing from a meta-analysis (N=34,710), and for cancer from the UK Biobank (N cases=2,671–13,879; N controls=173,493–372,016), FinnGen (N cases=719–8,401; N controls=74,685–174,006) and several international cancer genetic consortia (N cases=11,348–122,977; N controls=15,861–105,974). Main analyses were performed using multiplicative random effects inverse variance weighted (IVW) MR. Individual study estimates were pooled using fixed effect meta-analysis. Sensitivity analyses included MR-Egger, weighted median, weighted mode and Causal Analysis using Summary Effect Estimates (CAUSE) methods, which are robust to some of the assumptions of the IVW approach.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meta-analysed IVW MR findings suggested that higher GrimAge acceleration increased the risk of colorectal cancer (OR=1.12 per year increase in GrimAge acceleration, 95%CI 1.04–1.20, &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt;=0.002). The direction of the genetically predicted effects was consistent across main and sensitivity MR analyses. Among subtypes, the genetically predicted effect of GrimAge acceleration was greater for colon cancer (IVW OR=1.15, 95%CI 1.09–1.21, &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt;=0.006), than rectal cancer (IVW OR=1.05, 95%CI 0.97–1.13, &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt;=0.24). We also found evidence that higher GrimAge acceleration decreased the risk of prostate cancer (pooled IVW OR=0.93 per year increase in GrimAge acceleration, 95%CI 0.87–0.99, &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt;=0.02). This was supported by MR sensitivity analyses, but did not replicate in MR analyses using data on parental history of prostate cancer in UK Biobank (IVW OR=1.00, 95%CI 0.96–1.04, &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt;=1.00). Results were less consistent for associations between other epigenetic clocks and cancers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;GrimAge acceleration may increase the risk of colorectal cancer. Additionally, there is more limited evidence that it may be protective against prostate cancer. Findings for other clocks and cancers were inconsistent. Further work is required to investigate the potential mechanisms underlying the results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;FMB was supported by a Wellcome Trust PhD studentship in Molecular, Genetic and Lifecourse Epidemiology (218495/Z/19/Z). KKT was supported by a Cancer Research UK (C18281/A29019) programme grant (the Integrative Cancer Epidemiology Programme) and by the Hellenic Republic’s Operational Programme “Competitiveness, Entrepreneurship &amp;amp; Innovation” (OΠΣ 5047228). PH was supported by Cancer Research UK (C18281/A29019).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;RMM was supported by the NIHR Biomedical Research Centre at University Hospitals Bristol and Weston NHS Foundation Trust and the University of Bristol and by a Cancer Research UK (C18281/A29019) programme grant (the Integrative Cancer Epidemiology Programme). The views expressed are those of the author(s) and not necessarily those of the NIHR or the Department of Health and Social Care. GDS and CLR were supported by the Medical Research Council (MC_UU_00011/1 and MC_UU_00011/5) and by a Cancer Research UK (C18281/A29019) programme grant (the Integrative Cancer Epidemiology Programme). REM was supported by an Alzheimer’s Society project grant (AS-PG-19b-010) and NIH grant (U01 AG-18-018, PI: Steve Horvath). RCR is a de Pass Vice Chancellor’s Research Fellow at the University of Bristol.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.21266984" rel="alternate" title="Assessing the causal role of epigenetic clocks in the development of multiple cancers: a Mendelian randomization study (9 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.21266935</id><title>Treatment of Recurrent Glioblastoma by Chronic Convection-Enhanced Delivery of Topotecan (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.410922+00:00</updated><author><name>Eleonora F. Spinazzi</name></author><author><name>Michael G. Argenziano</name></author><author><name>Pavan S. Upadhyayula</name></author><author><name>Matei A. Banu</name></author><author><name>Justin A. Neira</name></author><author><name>Dominique M.O. Higgins</name></author><author><name>Peter B. Wu</name></author><author><name>Brianna Pereira</name></author><author><name>Aayushi Mahajan</name></author><author><name>Nelson Humala</name></author><author><name>Osama Al-Dalahmah</name></author><author><name>Wenting Zhao</name></author><author><name>Akshay V. Save</name></author><author><name>Deborah M. Boyett</name></author><author><name>Tamara Marie</name></author><author><name>Julia L Furnari</name></author><author><name>Tejaswi D. Sudhakar</name></author><author><name>Sylwia A. Stopka</name></author><author><name>Michael S. Regan</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Catania</name></author><author><name>Laura Good</name></author><author><name>Meenu Behl</name></author><author><name>Sachin Jambawalikar</name></author><author><name>Akiva Mintz</name></author><author><name>Angela Lignelli</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Y.R. Agar</name></author><author><name>Peter A. Sims</name></author><author><name>Mary Welch</name></author><author><name>Andrew Lassman</name></author><author><name>Fabio Iwamoto</name></author><author><name>Randy S. D’Amico</name></author><author><name>Jack Grinband</name></author><author><name>Peter Canoll</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey N. Bruce</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glioblastoma, the most common primary brain malignancy, is invariably fatal. Systemic chemotherapy is ineffective mostly because of drug delivery limitations. To overcome this, we devised an internalized pump-catheter system for direct chronic convection-enhanced delivery (CED) into peritumoral brain tissue. Topotecan (TPT) by chronic CED in 5 patients with refractory glioblastoma selectively eliminated tumor cells without toxicity to normal brain. Large, stable drug distribution volumes were non-invasively monitored with MRI of co-infused gadolinium. Analysis of multiple radiographically localized biopsies taken before and after treatment showed a decreased proliferative tumor signature resulting in a shift to a slow-cycling mesenchymal/astrocytic-like population. Tumor microenvironment analysis showed an inflammatory response and preservation of neurons. This novel drug delivery strategy and innovative clinical trial paradigm overcomes current limitations in delivery and treatment response assessment as shown here for glioblastoma and is potentially applicable for other anti-glioma agents as well as other CNS diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.21266935" rel="alternate" title="Treatment of Recurrent Glioblastoma by Chronic Convection-Enhanced Delivery of Topotecan (9 tweets)"/><category term="Oncology"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.21267312</id><title>Maternal Fc-mediated non-neutralizing antibody responses correlate with protection against congenital human cytomegalovirus infection (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.411559+00:00</updated><author><name>Eleanor C. Semmes</name></author><author><name>Itzayana G. Miller</name></author><author><name>Jennifer A. Jenks</name></author><author><name>Courtney E. Wimberly</name></author><author><name>Stella J. Berendam</name></author><author><name>Melissa J. Harnois</name></author><author><name>Helen Webster</name></author><author><name>Jillian H. Hurst</name></author><author><name>Joanne Kurtzberg</name></author><author><name>Genevieve G Fouda</name></author><author><name>Kyle M. Walsh</name></author><author><name>Sallie R. Permar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human cytomegalovirus (HCMV) is the most common congenital infection and a leading cause of stillbirth, neurodevelopmental impairment, and pediatric hearing loss worldwide. Development of a maternal vaccine or therapeutic to prevent congenital infection has been hindered by limited knowledge of the immune responses that protect against placental HCMV transmission in maternal primary and nonprimary infection. To identify protective antibody responses, we measured anti-HCMV IgG binding and anti-viral functions in maternal and cord blood sera from HCMV transmitting (n=41) and non- transmitting (n=40) mother-infant dyads identified via a large U.S.-based public cord blood bank. In a predefined immune correlate analysis, maternal monocyte-mediated antibody-dependent cellular phagocytosis (ADCP) and high avidity IgG binding to HCMV envelope glycoproteins were associated with decreased risk of congenital HCMV infection. Moreover, HCMV-specific IgG engagement of FcγRI and FcγRIIA, which mediate non-neutralizing antibody responses, was enhanced in non-transmitting mother-infant dyads and strongly correlated with ADCP. These findings suggest that Fc effector functions including ADCP protect against placental HCMV transmission. Taken together, our data indicate that future active and passive immunization strategies to prevent congenital HCMV infection should target Fc-mediated non-neutralizing antibody responses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.21267312" rel="alternate" title="Maternal Fc-mediated non-neutralizing antibody responses correlate with protection against congenital human cytomegalovirus infection (8 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.21267508</id><title>Enterovirus D68 epidemic, UK, 2018, was caused by subclades B3 and D1, predominantly in children and adults respectively, with both subclades exhibiting extensive genetic diversity (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.411924+00:00</updated><author><name>Hannah C. Howson-Wells</name></author><author><name>Theocharis Tsoleridis</name></author><author><name>Izzah Zainuddin</name></author><author><name>Alexander W. Tarr</name></author><author><name>William L. Irving</name></author><author><name>Jonathan K. Ball</name></author><author><name>Louise Berry</name></author><author><name>Gemma Clark</name></author><author><name>C. Patrick McClure</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Enterovirus D68 (EV-D68) has been recently identified in biennial epidemics coinciding with diagnoses of non-polio acute flaccid paralysis/myelitis (AFP/AFM). We investigated the prevalence, genetic relatedness and associated clinical features of EV-D68 in 194 known EV positive samples from late 2018, UK. EV-D68 was detected in 83 (58%) of the 143 EV positive samples. Sequencing and phylogenetic analysis revealed an extensive genetic diversity, split between subclades B3 (n=50) and D1 (n=33), suggesting epidemiologically unrelated infections. B3 predominated in children and younger adults, and D1 in older adults and the elderly (p=0.0009). Clinical presentation indicated causation or exacerbation of respiratory distress in 91.4% of EV-D68-positive individuals, principally: cough (75.3%), shortness of breath (56.8%), coryza (48.1%), wheeze (46.9%), supplemental oxygen required (46.9%) and fever (38.9%). Clinical features were not distinguished by subclade. Two cases of AFM were observed, one with EV-D68 detectable in the cerebrospinal fluid, otherwise neurological symptoms were rarely reported (n=4).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.21267508" rel="alternate" title="Enterovirus D68 epidemic, UK, 2018, was caused by subclades B3 and D1, predominantly in children and adults respectively, with both subclades exhibiting extensive genetic diversity (8 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.21267511</id><title>Data-driven identification of previously unrecognized communities with alarming levels of tuberculosis infection in the Democratic Republic of Congo (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.412533+00:00</updated><author><name>Mauro Faccin</name></author><author><name>Olivier Rusumba</name></author><author><name>Alfred Ushindi</name></author><author><name>Mireille Riziki</name></author><author><name>Tresor Habiragi</name></author><author><name>Fairouz Boutachkourt</name></author><author><name>Emmanuel André</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;When access to diagnosis and treatment of tuberculosis is disrupted by poverty or unequal access to health services, marginalized communities not only endorse the burden of preventable deaths, but also suffer from the dramatic consequences of a disease which impacts one’s ability to access education and minimal financial incomes. Unfortunately, these pockets are often left unrecognized in the flow of data collected National tuberculosis reports, as localized hotspots are diluted in aggregated reports focusing on notified cases. Such system is therefore profoundly inadequate for identifying these marginalized groups, which urgently require adapted interventions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We computed an estimated incidence-rate map for the South-Kivu province of the Democratic Republic of Congo, a province of 6.3 million inhabitants, leveraging available data including notified incidence, level of access to health care and exposition to identifiable risk factors. These estimations were validated in a prospective multi-centric study.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We could demonstrate that combining different sources of openly-available data allows to precisely identify pockets of the population which endorses the biggest part of the burden of disease. We could precisely identify areas with a predicted annual incidence of &lt;italic&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/italic&gt; 1%, a value three times higher than the national estimates. While hosting only 2.5% of the total population, we estimated that these areas were responsible for 23.5% of the actual tuberculosis cases of the province. The bacteriological results obtained from systematic screenings strongly correlated with the estimated incidence (r=0.86), and much less with the incidence reported from epidemiological reports (r=0.77), highlighting the inadequacy of these reports when used alone to guide disease control programs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.21267511" rel="alternate" title="Data-driven identification of previously unrecognized communities with alarming levels of tuberculosis infection in the Democratic Republic of Congo (7 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.21267399</id><title>Current state of the evidence on community treatments for people with complex emotional needs: a scoping review (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.412826+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah Ledden</name></author><author><name>Luke Sheridan Rains</name></author><author><name>Merle Schlief</name></author><author><name>Phoebe Barnett</name></author><author><name>Brian Chi Fung Ching</name></author><author><name>Brendan Hallam</name></author><author><name>Mia Maria Günak</name></author><author><name>Thomas Steare</name></author><author><name>Jennie Parker</name></author><author><name>Sarah Labovitch</name></author><author><name>Sian Oram</name></author><author><name>Steve Pilling</name></author><author><name>Sonia Johnson</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improving the quality of care in community settings for people with ‘Complex Emotional Needs’ (CEN - our preferred working term for services for people with a “personality disorder” diagnosis or comparable needs) is recognised internationally as a priority. Plans to improve care should be rooted as far as possible in evidence. We aimed to take stock of the current state of such evidence, and identify significant gaps through a scoping review of published investigations of outcomes of community-based psychosocial interventions designed for CEN.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted a scoping review with systematic searches. We searched six bibliographic databases, including forward and backward citation searching, and reference searching of relevant systematic reviews. We included studies using quantitative methods to test for effects on any clinical, social, and functioning outcomes from community-based interventions for people with CEN.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We included 226 papers in all (209 studies). Little relevant literature was published before 2000. Since then, publications per year and sample sizes have gradually increased, but most studies are relatively small, including many pilot or uncontrolled studies. Most studies focus on symptom and self-harm outcomes of various forms of specialist psychotherapy: most result in outcomes better than from inactive controls and similar to other specialist psychotherapies. We found large evidence gaps.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adaptation and testing of therapies for significant groups (e.g. people with comorbid psychosis, bipolar disorder, post-traumatic stress disorder or substance misuse; older and younger groups; parents) have for the most part only reached a feasibility testing stage. We found little evidence regarding interventions to improve social aspects of people’s lives, peer support or ways of designing effective services.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compared with other longer term mental health problems that significantly impair functioning, the evidence base on how to provide high quality care for people with CEN is very limited. There is good evidence that people with CEN can be effectively helped when specialist therapies are available and they are able to engage with them. However, a much more methodologically robust and substantial literature addressing a much wider range of research questions is urgently needed to optimise treatment and support across this group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.21267399" rel="alternate" title="Current state of the evidence on community treatments for people with complex emotional needs: a scoping review (7 tweets)"/><category term="Psychiatry and Clinical Psychology"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.21267319</id><title>Beyond well-mixed: a simple probabilistic model of airborne disease transmission in indoor spaces (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.413219+00:00</updated><author><name>Sijian Tan</name></author><author><name>Zhihang Zhang</name></author><author><name>Kevin Maki</name></author><author><name>Krzysztof J. Fidkowski</name></author><author><name>Jesse Capecelatro</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We develop a simple model for assessing risk of airborne disease transmission that accounts for non-uniform mixing in indoor spaces and is compatible with existing epidemiological models. A database containing 174 high-resolution simulations of airflow in classrooms, lecture halls, and buses is generated and used to quantify the spatial distribution of expiratory droplet nuclei for a wide range of ventilation rates, exposure times, and room configurations. Imperfect mixing due to obstructions, buoyancy, and turbulent dispersion results in concentration fields with significant variance. The spatial non-uniformity is found to be accurately described by a shifted lognormal distribution. A well-mixed mass balance model is used to predict the mean, and the standard deviation is parameterized based on ventilation rate and room geometry. When employed in a dose-response function risk model, infection probability can be estimated considering spatial heterogeneity that contributes to both short- and long-range transmission.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.21267319" rel="alternate" title="Beyond well-mixed: a simple probabilistic model of airborne disease transmission in indoor spaces (6 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.21267161</id><title>Genomic dissection of the bacterial population underlying Klebsiella pneumoniae infections in hospital patients: insights into an opportunistic pathogen (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.413514+00:00</updated><author><name>Claire L. Gorrie</name></author><author><name>Mirjana Mirceta</name></author><author><name>Ryan R. Wick</name></author><author><name>Louise M. Judd</name></author><author><name>Margaret M. C. Lam</name></author><author><name>Ryota Gomi</name></author><author><name>Iain J. Abbott</name></author><author><name>Nicholas R. Thomson</name></author><author><name>Richard A. Strugnell</name></author><author><name>Nigel F. Pratt</name></author><author><name>Jill S. Garlick</name></author><author><name>Kerrie M. Watson</name></author><author><name>Peter C. Hunter</name></author><author><name>David V. Pilcher</name></author><author><name>Steve A. McGloughlin</name></author><author><name>Denis W. Spelman</name></author><author><name>Kelly L. Wyres</name></author><author><name>Adam W. J. Jenney</name></author><author><name>Kathryn E. Holt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; is a major cause of opportunistic healthcare-associated infections, which are increasingly complicated by the presence of extended-spectrum beta-lactamases (ESBLs) and carbapenem resistance. We conducted a year-long prospective surveillance study of &lt;italic&gt;K. pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; clinical isolates identified in a hospital microbiological diagnostic laboratory. Disease burden was two-thirds urinary tract infections (UTI; associated with female sex and age), followed by pneumonia (15%), wound (10%) and disseminated infections/sepsis (10%). Whole-genome sequencing (WGS) revealed a diverse pathogen population, including other species within the &lt;italic&gt;K. pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; complex (18%). Several infections were caused by &lt;italic&gt;K. variicola/K. pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; species hybrids, one of which showed evidence of nosocomial transmission, indicating fitness to transmit and cause disease despite a lack of acquired antimicrobial resistance (AMR). A wide range of AMR phenotypes were observed and, in most cases, corresponding mechanisms were identified in the genomes, mainly in the form of plasmid-borne genes. ESBLs were correlated with presence of other acquired AMR genes (median 10). Bacterial genomic features associated with nosocomial onset of disease were ESBL genes (OR 2.34, p=0.015) and rhamnose-positive capsules (OR 3.12, p&amp;lt;0.001). Virulence plasmid-encoded features (aerobactin, hypermucoidy) were rare (&amp;lt;3%), and mostly present in community-onset cases. WGS-confirmed nosocomial transmission was rare (10% of cases) but strongly associated with ESBLs (OR 21, p&amp;lt;1×10&lt;sup&gt;-11&lt;/sup&gt;). We estimate 28% risk of onward nosocomial transmission for ESBL-positive strains vs 1.7% for ESBL-negative strains. These data indicate the underlying burden of &lt;italic&gt;K. pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; disease in hospitalised patients is due largely to opportunistic infections with diverse strains. However, we also identified several successful lineages that were overrepresented but not due to nosocomial transmission. These lineages were associated with ESBL, yersiniabactin, mannose+ K loci and rhamnose- K loci; most are also common in public clinical genome collections, suggesting enhanced propensity for colonisation and spread in the human population.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.21267161" rel="alternate" title="Genomic dissection of the bacterial population underlying Klebsiella pneumoniae infections in hospital patients: insights into an opportunistic pathogen (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.21267419</id><title>Microbiota composition in the lower respiratory tract is associated with severity in patients with acute respiratory distress by influenza (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.413965+00:00</updated><author><name>Alejandra Hernández-Terán</name></author><author><name>Angel E. Vega-Sánchez</name></author><author><name>Fidencio Mejía-Nepomuceno</name></author><author><name>Ricardo Serna-Muñoz</name></author><author><name>Sebastián Rodríguez-Llamazares</name></author><author><name>Iván Salido-Guadarrama</name></author><author><name>Jose A. Romero-Espinoza</name></author><author><name>Cristobal Guadarrama-Pérez</name></author><author><name>JL Sandoval</name></author><author><name>Fernando Campos</name></author><author><name>Erika N. Mondragón-Rivero</name></author><author><name>Alejandra Ramírez-Venegas</name></author><author><name>Manuel Castillejos-López</name></author><author><name>Norma A. Téllez-Navarrete</name></author><author><name>Christopher E. Ormsby</name></author><author><name>Rogelio Pérez- Padilla</name></author><author><name>Joel A. Vázquez-Pérez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Several factors are associated with the severity of the respiratory disease caused by the influenza virus. Although viral factors are one of the most studied, in recent years the role of the microbiota and co-infections in severe and fatal outcomes has been recognized. However, most of the work has focused on the microbiota of the upper respiratory tract (URT), hindering potential insights from the lower respiratory tract (LRT) that may help to understand the role of the microbiota in Influenza disease. In this work, we characterized the microbiota of the LRT of patients with Influenza A using 16S rRNA sequencing. We tested if patients with different outcomes (deceased/recovered), use of antibiotics, and different days of symptoms onset differ in their microbial community composition. We found striking differences in the diversity and composition of the microbiota depending on the days of symptoms onset and with mortality of the studied patients. We detected a high abundance of opportunistic pathogens such as &lt;italic&gt;Enterococcus, Granulicatella&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus&lt;/italic&gt; in patients either deceased or with antibiotic treatment. Also, we found that antibiotic treatment deeply perturbs the microbial communities in the LRT and affect the probability of survival in Influenza A patients. Altogether, the loss of microbial diversity could, in turn, generate a disequilibrium in the community, potentially compromising the immune response increasing viral infectivity, promoting the growth of potentially pathogenic bacteria that, together with altered biochemical parameters, can be leading to severe forms of the disease. Overall, the present study gives one of the first characterizations of the diversity and composition of microbial communities in the LRT of Influenza patients and its relationship with clinical variables and disease severity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.21267419" rel="alternate" title="Microbiota composition in the lower respiratory tract is associated with severity in patients with acute respiratory distress by influenza (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.21267379</id><title>Age-specific effects of body size on fracture risk in later life: A lifecourse Mendelian randomization study (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.414392+00:00</updated><author><name>Grace M. Power</name></author><author><name>Jon H. Tobias</name></author><author><name>Timothy M. Frayling</name></author><author><name>Jess Tyrrell</name></author><author><name>April Hartley</name></author><author><name>Jon Heron</name></author><author><name>George Davey Smith</name></author><author><name>Tom G. Richardson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Musculoskeletal conditions, including fractures, can have severe and long-lasting consequences. Higher body mass index in adulthood is widely acknowledged to be protective for most fracture sites, indicated through previous clinical and epidemiological observational research. However, the association between weight and bone health is complex and sources of bias, induced by confounding factors, may have distorted earlier findings. Employing a lifecourse Mendelian randomization (MR) approach by using genetic instruments to separate effects at different life stages, this investigation aims to explore how prepubertal and adult body size independently influence fracture risk in later life.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using data from a large UK-based prospective cohort, univariable and multivariable MR with inverse variance weighted meta-analysis were conducted to simultaneously estimate the effects of age-specific genetic proxies for body size (n=453,169) on the odds of fracture in later life (n=416,795). A two-step MR framework was additionally applied to elucidate potential mediators. Univariable and multivariable MR indicated strong evidence that higher body size in childhood reduced fracture risk in later life (OR, 95% CI: 0.89, 0.82 to 0.96, P=0.005 and OR, 95% CI: 0.76, 0.69 to 0.85, P=1×10&lt;sup&gt;−6&lt;/sup&gt;, respectively). Conversely, higher body size in adulthood increased fracture risk (OR, 95% CI: 1.08, 1.01 to 1.16, P=0.023 and OR, 95% CI: 1.26, 1.14 to 1.38, P=2×10&lt;sup&gt;−6&lt;/sup&gt;, respectively). Two-step MR analyses suggested that the effect of higher body size in childhood on reduced fracture risk was mediated by its influence on higher estimated bone mineral density (eBMD) in adulthood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This investigation provides novel evidence that higher body size in childhood has a direct effect on reduced fracture risk in later life through its influence on increased eBMD. Results indicate that higher body size in adulthood is a risk factor for fractures, opposing findings from earlier research. Protective effect estimates previously observed are likely attributed to childhood effects.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.21267379" rel="alternate" title="Age-specific effects of body size on fracture risk in later life: A lifecourse Mendelian randomization study (4 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.21266787</id><title>Association of Egg Consumption, Metabolic Markers, and Risk of Cardiovascular Diseases (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.414690+00:00</updated><author><name>Lang Pan</name></author><author><name>Lu Chen</name></author><author><name>Jun Lv</name></author><author><name>Yuanjie Pang</name></author><author><name>Yu Guo</name></author><author><name>Pei Pei</name></author><author><name>Huaidong Du</name></author><author><name>Ling Yang</name></author><author><name>Iona Y. Millwood</name></author><author><name>Robin G. Walters</name></author><author><name>Yiping Chen</name></author><author><name>Weiwei Gong</name></author><author><name>Junshi Chen</name></author><author><name>Canqing Yu</name></author><author><name>Zhengming Chen</name></author><author><name>Liming Li</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To simultaneously explore the associations of self-reported egg consumption with plasma metabolic markers and these markers with CVD risk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Totally 4,778 participants (3,401 CVD cases subdivided into subtypes and 1,377 controls) aged 30-79 were selected from a nested case-control study based on the China Kadoorie Biobank. Targeted nuclear magnetic resonance was used to quantify 225 metabolites and derived traits in baseline plasma samples. Linear regression was conducted to assess associations between self-reported egg consumption and metabolic markers, which were further compared with associations between metabolic markers and CVD risk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Egg consumption was associated with 24 out of 225 markers, including positive associations for apolipoprotein A1, acetate, mean HDL diameter, and lipid profiles of very large and large HDL, and inverse associations for total cholesterol and cholesterol esters in small VLDL. Among these 24 markers, 14 of them were associated with CVD risk. In general, the associations of metabolic markers with egg consumption and of metabolic markers with CVD risk showed opposite patterns.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the Chinese population, egg consumption is associated with several metabolic markers, which may partially explain the protective effect of egg consumption on CVD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.21266787" rel="alternate" title="Association of Egg Consumption, Metabolic Markers, and Risk of Cardiovascular Diseases (3 tweets)"/><category term="Nutrition"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>