<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.107848+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459250</id><title>GPCR-G protein selectivity – a unified meta-analysis (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.108185+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander S. Hauser</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Avet</name></author><author><name>Claire Normand</name></author><author><name>Arturo Mancini</name></author><author><name>Asuka Inoue</name></author><author><name>Michel Bouvier</name></author><author><name>David E. Gloriam</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Two-thirds of human hormones and one-third of clinical drugs act on membrane receptors that couple to G proteins to achieve appropriate functional responses. While G protein transducers from literature are annotated in the Guide to Pharmacology database, two recent large-scale datasets now expand the receptor-G protein ‘couplome’. However, these three datasets differ in scope and reported G protein couplings giving different coverage and conclusions on GPCR-G protein signaling. Here, we report a meta-analysis unifying GPCR-G protein coupling, by standardized normalization and consensus support, into a common coupling map. This unravels novel consensus couplings for receptors supported by two independent sources and insights on coupling selectivity of GPCRs and classification of co-coupling G proteins. The coupling protocol, map and selectivity resources will promote advances in receptor research and cellular signaling towards the exploitation of G protein signaling specificity in design of safer drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459250" rel="alternate" title="GPCR-G protein selectivity – a unified meta-analysis (8 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-09-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>