<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:02.975784+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.21264442</id><title>Hi-C detects genomic structural variants in peripheral blood of pediatric leukemia patients (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:02.976316+00:00</updated><author><name>Claire Mallard</name></author><author><name>Michael J Johnston</name></author><author><name>Anna Bobyn</name></author><author><name>Ana Nikolic</name></author><author><name>Bob Argiropoulos</name></author><author><name>Jennifer A Chan</name></author><author><name>Gregory MT Guilcher</name></author><author><name>Marco Gallo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;B-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia (B-ALL) is often driven by chromosome translocations that result in recurrent and well-studied gene fusions. Currently, fluorescent in-situ hybridization probes are employed to detect candidate translocations in bone marrow samples from B-ALL patients. Recently Hi-C, a sequencing-based technique originally designed to reconstruct the three-dimensional architecture of the nuclear genome, was shown to effectively recognize structural variants. Here, we demonstrate that Hi-C can be used as a genome-wide assay to detect translocations and other structural variants of potential clinical interest. Structural variants were identified in both bone marrow and peripheral blood samples, including an &lt;italic&gt;ETV6-RUNX1&lt;/italic&gt; translocation present in one pediatric B-ALL patient. Our report provides proof-of-principle that Hi-C could be an effective strategy to globally detect driver structural variants in B-ALL peripheral blood specimens, reducing the need for invasive bone marrow biopsies and candidate-based clinical tests.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.21264442" rel="alternate" title="Hi-C detects genomic structural variants in peripheral blood of pediatric leukemia patients (10 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-10-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.04.21264162</id><title>Inherited variants in CHD3 demonstrate variable expressivity in Snijders Blok-Campeau syndrome (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:02.976645+00:00</updated><author><name>Jet van der Spek</name></author><author><name>Joery den Hoed</name></author><author><name>Lot Snijders Blok</name></author><author><name>Alexander J. M. Dingemans</name></author><author><name>Dick Schijven</name></author><author><name>Christoffer Nellaker</name></author><author><name>Hanka Venselaar</name></author><author><name>Tahsin Stefan Barakat</name></author><author><name>E. Martina Bebin</name></author><author><name>Stefanie Beck-Wödl</name></author><author><name>Gea Beunders</name></author><author><name>Natasha J. Brown</name></author><author><name>Theresa Brunet</name></author><author><name>Han G. Brunner</name></author><author><name>Philippe M. Campeau</name></author><author><name>Goran Čuturilo</name></author><author><name>Christian Gilissen</name></author><author><name>Tobias B. Haack</name></author><author><name>Ralf A. Husain</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Kamien</name></author><author><name>Sze Chern Lim</name></author><author><name>Luca Lovrecic</name></author><author><name>Janine Magg</name></author><author><name>Ales Maver</name></author><author><name>Valancy Miranda</name></author><author><name>Danielle C. Monteil</name></author><author><name>Charlotte W. Ockeloen</name></author><author><name>Lynn S. Pais</name></author><author><name>Vasilica Plaiasu</name></author><author><name>Laura Raiti</name></author><author><name>Christopher Richmond</name></author><author><name>Angelika Rieß</name></author><author><name>Eva M. C. Schwaibold</name></author><author><name>Marleen E. H. Simon</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Spranger</name></author><author><name>Tiong Yang Tan</name></author><author><name>Michelle L. Thompson</name></author><author><name>Bert B.A. de Vries</name></author><author><name>Ella J. Wilkins</name></author><author><name>Marjolein H. Willemsen</name></author><author><name>Clyde Francks</name></author><author><name>Lisenka E. L. M. Vissers</name></author><author><name>Simon E. Fisher</name></author><author><name>Tjitske Kleefstra</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Interpretation of next-generation sequencing data of individuals with an apparent sporadic neurodevelopmental disorder (NDD) often focusses on pathogenic variants in genes associated with NDD, assuming full clinical penetrance with limited variable expressivity. Consequently, inherited variants in genes associated with dominant disorders may be overlooked when the transmitting parent is clinically unaffected. While &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; variants explain a substantial proportion of cases with NDDs, a significant number remains undiagnosed possibly explained by coding variants associated with reduced penetrance and variable expressivity. We characterized twenty families with inherited heterozygous missense or protein-truncating variants (PTVs) in &lt;italic&gt;CHD3&lt;/italic&gt;, a gene in which &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; variants cause Snijders Blok-Campeau syndrome, characterized by intellectual disability, speech delay and recognizable facial features (SNIBCPS). Notably, the majority of the inherited &lt;italic&gt;CHD3&lt;/italic&gt; variants were maternally transmitted. Computational facial and human phenotype ontology-based comparisons demonstrated that the phenotypic features of probands with inherited &lt;italic&gt;CHD3&lt;/italic&gt; variants overlap with the phenotype previously associated with &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; variants in the gene, while carrier parents are mildly or not affected, suggesting variable expressivity. Additionally, similarly reduced expression levels of CHD3 protein in cells of an affected proband and of related healthy carriers with a &lt;italic&gt;CHD3&lt;/italic&gt; PTV, suggested that compensation of expression from the wildtype allele is unlikely to be an underlying mechanism. Our results point to a significant role of inherited variation in SNIBCPS, a finding that is critical for correct variant interpretation and genetic counseling and warrants further investigation towards understanding the broader contributions of such variation to the landscape of human disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.04.21264162" rel="alternate" title="Inherited variants in CHD3 demonstrate variable expressivity in Snijders Blok-Campeau syndrome (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-10-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>