<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.853169+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261888</id><title>Genetic risk estimates for offspring of patients with Stargardt disease (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.853864+00:00</updated><author><name>Stéphanie S. Cornelis</name></author><author><name>Esmee H. Runhart</name></author><author><name>Miriam Bauwens</name></author><author><name>Zelia Corradi</name></author><author><name>Elfride de Baere</name></author><author><name>Susanne Roosing</name></author><author><name>Lonneke Haer-Wigman</name></author><author><name>Claire-Marie Dhaenens</name></author><author><name>Anneke T. Vulto-van Silfhout</name></author><author><name>Frans P.M. Cremers</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Genetic counseling in autosomal recessive Stargardt disease (STGD1) is complicated because of unknown frequencies of pathogenic &lt;italic&gt;ABCA4&lt;/italic&gt; alleles across populations, variable and unknown severity of &lt;italic&gt;ABCA4&lt;/italic&gt; alleles, and incomplete penetrance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;METHODS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this cross-sectional study, published &lt;italic&gt;ABCA4&lt;/italic&gt; variants were categorized by severity based on previous functional and clinical studies and current statistical comparisons of their frequencies in patients versus the general population, their observed versus expected homozygous occurrence in patients, and their occurrence in combination with established mild alleles in patients. The sum allele frequencies of these severity categories were used to estimate inheritance risks for offspring of STGD1 patients and carriers of pathogenic &lt;italic&gt;ABCA4&lt;/italic&gt; variants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;RESULTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The risk for offspring of a STGD1 patient with the ‘severe|severe’ genotype or a ‘severe|mild with complete penetrance’ genotype to develop STGD1 at some moment in life was estimated at 2.8-3.1% (1 in 35-32 individuals) and 1.6-1.8% (1 in 62-57 individuals), respectively. The risk to develop STGD1 in childhood was estimated to be 2 to 4-fold lower: 0.7-0.8% (1 in 148-124) and 0.3-0.4% (1 in 295-248), respectively. For offspring of an unaffected &lt;italic&gt;ABCA4&lt;/italic&gt; variant carrier from a STGD1 family who carries one severe or one mild &lt;italic&gt;ABCA4&lt;/italic&gt; variant with complete penetrance, the risk to develop STGD1 throughout life is 1.4-1.6% (1 in 71-64) and 0.19-0.21% (1 in 516-487), respectively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We propose a genotype-based personalized counseling approach to appreciate the large differences in inheritance risk between individuals. We advocate considering the lower risk of early-onset STGD1 compared with the total STGD1 risk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261888" rel="alternate" title="Genetic risk estimates for offspring of patients with Stargardt disease (16 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.21261568</id><title>A randomised controlled trial to test the effects of fish aggregating devices and SBC activities promoting fish consumption in Timor-Leste: A study protocol (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.854492+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Tilley</name></author><author><name>Kendra A Byrd</name></author><author><name>Lauren Pincus</name></author><author><name>Katherine Klumpyan</name></author><author><name>Katherine Dobson</name></author><author><name>Joctan do Reis Lopes</name></author><author><name>Kelvin Mashisia Shikuku</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Timor-Leste is one of the world’s most malnourished nations where micronutrient-deficient diets are a contributing factor to the prevalence of child stunting, currently estimated to be 45.6% of children under five. Fish are an important source of micronutrients and one that may assist the country’s predominantly rural population of agriculturalists to exit poverty and malnutrition. However, a small national fishing fleet producing low catch volumes place fish out of reach of most inland and upland populations where it is needed most. Fish consumption is very low in rural areas compared to coastal, regional, and global averages. This trial is a one-year, cluster-randomized, partially masked, controlled trial among families living in rural, inland Timor-Leste. This trial aims to test and compare the effects of two treatments, alone and in combination, on the frequency and volume of household fish consumption in upland areas as a proxy for improved dietary diversity and micronutrient intake. Treatment 1 is the installation of nearshore, moored fish aggregating devices (FADs) to improve catch rates with existing fishing gears. Treatment 2 is social and behaviour change (SBC) activities to promote fish consumption. Villages in inland communities will be randomized to receive treatment 1, treatment 2, both treatments, or neither treatment. Some households with one child under five will be recruited, and data will be collected at baseline (prior to the rollout of the treatments) and endline. Our study will determine the impact of an improved supply of fish, along with nutrition-oriented SBC activities, on the fish purchasing and consumption practices of rural, inland households. Findings from this study are urgently needed by small island developing states in order to make policy and investment decisions on how best to improve households’ diets using locally available, nutrient-dense foods such as fish. Investments such as these are needed to break the cycle of malnutrition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.21261568" rel="alternate" title="A randomised controlled trial to test the effects of fish aggregating devices and SBC activities promoting fish consumption in Timor-Leste: A study protocol (7 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.21261747</id><title>Drug repurposing of metformin for Alzheimer’s disease: Combining causal inference in medical records data and systems pharmacology for biomarker identification (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.854706+00:00</updated><author><name>Marie-Laure Charpignon</name></author><author><name>Bella Vakulenko-Lagun</name></author><author><name>Bang Zheng</name></author><author><name>Colin Magdamo</name></author><author><name>Bowen Su</name></author><author><name>Kyle Evans</name></author><author><name>Steve Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Artem Sokolov</name></author><author><name>Sarah Boswell</name></author><author><name>Yi-Han Sheu</name></author><author><name>Melek Somai</name></author><author><name>Lefkos Middleton</name></author><author><name>Bradley T. Hyman</name></author><author><name>Rebecca A. Betensky</name></author><author><name>Stan N. Finkelstein</name></author><author><name>Roy E. Welsch</name></author><author><name>Ioanna Tzoulaki</name></author><author><name>Deborah Blacker</name></author><author><name>Sudeshna Das</name></author><author><name>Mark W. Albers</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Metformin, an antidiabetic drug, triggers anti-aging cellular responses. Aging is the principal risk factor for dementia, but previous observational studies of the diabetes drugs metformin vs. sulfonylureas have been mixed. We tested the hypotheses that metformin improves survival and reduces the risk of dementia, relative to the sulfonylureas, by emulating target trials in electronic health records of diabetic patients at an academic-centered healthcare system in the US and a wide-ranging group of primary care practices in the UK. To address metformin’s potentially dual influences on dementia risk—that it might reduce the hazard of death and put more people at risk of developing dementia while reducing the hazard of dementia by slowing biological aging, we used a competing risks approach and carefully grounded that within a causal inference emulated trial framework. To identify candidate biomarkers of metformin’s actions in the brain that might mediate reduced dementia risk, we conducted an in-vitro systems pharmacology evaluation of metformin and glyburide on differentiated human neural cells through differential gene expression. We named our multi-dimensional approach DRIAD-EHR (Drug Repurposing in Alzheimer’s Disease-Electronic Health Records). In intention-to-treat analyses, metformin was associated with a lower hazard of all-cause mortality than sulfonylureas in both cohorts. In competing risks analyses, there was also a lower cause-specific hazard of dementia onset among metformin initiators. In in-vitro studies, metformin reduced human neural cell expression of &lt;italic&gt;SPP1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;APOE&lt;/italic&gt;, two secreted proteins that have been implicated in Alzheimer’s disease pathogenesis and whose levels can be quantified in the CSF. Together, our findings suggest that metformin might prevent dementia in patients &lt;italic&gt;without&lt;/italic&gt; type II diabetes. In addition, our results inform the design of clinical trials of metformin in non-diabetics and suggest a pharmacodynamic CSF biomarker, SPP1, for metformin’s action in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.21261747" rel="alternate" title="Drug repurposing of metformin for Alzheimer’s disease: Combining causal inference in medical records data and systems pharmacology for biomarker identification (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.21261690</id><title>Relationship between astrocyte reactivity, using novel 11C-BU99008 PET, and glucose metabolism, grey matter volume and amyloid load in cognitively impaired individuals (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.855131+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas R Livingston</name></author><author><name>Valeria Calsolaro</name></author><author><name>Rainer Hinz</name></author><author><name>Joseph Nowell</name></author><author><name>Sanara Raza</name></author><author><name>Steve Gentleman</name></author><author><name>Robin J Tyacke</name></author><author><name>Jim Myers</name></author><author><name>Ashwin V Venkataraman</name></author><author><name>Robert Perneczky</name></author><author><name>Roger N Gunn</name></author><author><name>Eugenii A Rabiner</name></author><author><name>Christine A Parker</name></author><author><name>Philip S Murphy</name></author><author><name>Paul B Wren</name></author><author><name>David J Nutt</name></author><author><name>Paul M Matthews</name></author><author><name>Paul Edison</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Post mortem&lt;/italic&gt; neuropathology suggests that astrocyte reactivity may play a significant role in neurodegeneration in Alzheimer’s disease. We explored this &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; using multimodal PET and MRI imaging. Twenty subjects (11 older, cognitively impaired subjects and 9 age-matched healthy controls) underwent brain scanning using the novel reactive astrocyte PET tracer &lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;C-BU99008, &lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;F-FDG and &lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;F-florbetaben PET, and T1-weighted MRI. Differences between cognitively impaired subjects and healthy controls in voxel-wise levels of astrocyte reactivity, glucose metabolism and grey matter volume were explored, and their relationship to each other was assessed using Biological Parametric Mapping (BPM). Aβ-positive cognitively impaired subjects showed greater brain astrocyte reactivity, except in the temporal lobe, with further increased astrocyte reactivity in Mild Cognitive Impairment compared to Alzheimer’s subjects in the cingulate cortices. BPM correlations revealed regions which showed reduced &lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;C-BU99008 uptake in Aβ-positive cognitively impaired subjects, such as the temporal lobe, also showed reduced &lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;F-FDG uptake and grey matter volume. BPM analysis also revealed a regionally-dynamic relationship between astrocyte reactivity and amyloid uptake: increased amyloid load in cortical association areas of the temporal lobe and cingulate cortices was associated with &lt;italic&gt;reduced&lt;/italic&gt; astrocyte reactivity, whilst increased amyloid uptake in primary motor and sensory areas (in which amyloid load occurs later) was associated with &lt;italic&gt;increased&lt;/italic&gt; astrocyte reactivity. These novel observations add to the hypothesis that while astrocyte reactivity may be triggered by early Aβ-deposition, sustained pro-inflammatory astrocyte reactivity with greater amyloid deposition may lead to astrocyte dystrophy and amyloid-associated neuropathology such as grey matter atrophy and glucose hypometabolism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.21261690" rel="alternate" title="Relationship between astrocyte reactivity, using novel 11C-BU99008 PET, and glucose metabolism, grey matter volume and amyloid load in cognitively impaired individuals (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261907</id><title>Refined characterization of circulating tumor DNA through biological feature integration (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.855387+00:00</updated><author><name>Havell Markus</name></author><author><name>Dineika Chandrananda</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Moore</name></author><author><name>Florent Mouliere</name></author><author><name>James Morris</name></author><author><name>James Brenton</name></author><author><name>Christopher G. Smith</name></author><author><name>Nitzan Rosenfeld</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) in blood plasma is present at very low concentrations compared to cell-free DNA (cfDNA) of non-tumor origin. To enhance ctDNA detection, recent studies have been focused on understanding the non-random fragmentation pattern of cfDNA. These studies have investigated fragment sizes, genomic position of fragment end points, and fragment end motifs. Although these features have been described and shown to be aberrant in cancer patients, there is a lack of understanding of how the individual and integrated analysis of these features enrich ctDNA fraction and enhance ctDNA detection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using whole genome sequencing and copy number analysis of plasma samples from 5 high grade serious ovarian cancer patients, we observed that 1) ctDNA is enriched not only in fragments shorter than mono-nucleosomes (∼167bp), but also in those shorter than di-nucleosomes (∼240-330bp) (28-159% enrichment). 2) fragments that start and end at the border or within the nucleosome core are enriched in ctDNA (5-46% enrichment). 3) certain DNA motifs conserved in regions 10bp up- and down-stream of fragment ends (i.e. cleavage sites) could be used to detect tumor-derived fragments (10-44% enrichment). We further show that the integrated analysis of these three features resulted in a higher enrichment of ctDNA when compared to using fragment size alone (additional 7-25% enrichment after fragment size selection).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We believe these genome wide features, which are independent of genetic mutational changes, could allow new ways to analyze and interpret cfDNA data, as significant aberrations of these features from a healthy state could improve its utility as a diagnostic biomarker.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In recent years circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) has received much attention, and investment, as a biomarker that could transform the clinical care of cancer patients. Despite this, there is much that is not known about this biomarker. Recently, it has been demonstrated that the biological properties of ctDNA can be leveraged to improve ctDNA based assays. Here we build on this by carrying out an in-depth analysis of three genome wide fragmentation patterns of cell-free DNA; specifically fragment size, positioning of fragment end points with respect to nucleosome occupancy, and fragment end motifs. Whilst previous studies have described these features in an individual manner and used them as point statistics for comparison between healthy individuals and cancer patients, our study is the first to show that the individual and integrative analysis of these features can be used to enrich for ctDNA and enable enhanced ctDNA detection. The features described are independent of specific genomic alterations, with signal integrated across the breadth of the genome. This allows informative analysis that leverages a larger proportion of sequencing reads, further building the case for the use of cost-effective approaches like shallow whole genome sequencing for cancer diagnostics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261907" rel="alternate" title="Refined characterization of circulating tumor DNA through biological feature integration (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>