<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.358088+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.21265342</id><title>Linking common and rare disease genetics through gene regulatory networks (78 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.358729+00:00</updated><author><name>Olivier B. Bakker</name></author><author><name>Annique Claringbould</name></author><author><name>Harm-Jan Westra</name></author><author><name>Henry Wiersma</name></author><author><name>Floranne Boulogne</name></author><author><name>Urmo Võsa</name></author><author><name>Sophie Mulcahy Symmons</name></author><author><name>Iris H. Jonkers</name></author><author><name>Lude Franke</name></author><author><name>Patrick Deelen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genetic variants identified through genome-wide association studies (GWAS) are typically non-coding and exert small regulatory effects on downstream genes, but which downstream genes are ultimately impacted and how they confer risk remains mostly unclear. Conversely, variants that cause rare Mendelian diseases are often coding and have a more direct impact on disease development. We demonstrate that common and rare genetic diseases can be linked by studying the gene regulatory networks impacted by common disease-associated variants. We implemented this in the ‘Downstreamer’ method and applied it to 44 GWAS traits and find that predicted downstream “key genes” are enriched with Mendelian disease genes, e.g. key genes for height are enriched for genes that cause skeletal abnormalities and Ehlers-Danlos syndromes. We find that 82% of these key genes are located outside of GWAS loci, suggesting that they result from complex &lt;italic&gt;trans&lt;/italic&gt; regulation rather than being impacted by disease-associated variants in &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;. Finally, we discuss the challenges in reconstructing gene regulatory networks and provide a roadmap to improve identification of these highly connected genes for common traits and diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.21265342" rel="alternate" title="Linking common and rare disease genetics through gene regulatory networks (78 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.23.21265427</id><title>Performance of Valved Respirators to Reduce Respiratory Particles Generated by Speaking (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.359072+00:00</updated><author><name>Jessica M. Hazard</name></author><author><name>Christopher D. Cappa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Wearing of face coverings serves two purposes: reducing the concentration of ambient particles inhaled and reducing the emission of respiratory particles generated by the wearer. The efficiency of different face coverings depends on the material, design, and fit. Face coverings such as N95 respirators, when worn properly, are highly efficient at filtering ambient particles during inhalation. Some N95 respirators, as well as other face covering types, include a one-way valve to allow easier exhalation while still maintaining high filtration efficiency towards ambient particles. The extent to which these valves decrease filtration of emitted respiratory particles is, however, not well established. Here, we show that different valved N95s exhibit highly variable filtration efficiencies for exhaled respiratory particles. As such, valved N95s do not provide reliable source control of respired particles and their use should be discouraged in situations where such source control is needed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.23.21265427" rel="alternate" title="Performance of Valved Respirators to Reduce Respiratory Particles Generated by Speaking (13 tweets)"/><category term="Occupational and Environmental Health"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.21265472</id><title>Prediction of recessive inheritance for missense variants in human disease (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.359293+00:00</updated><author><name>Ben O. Petrazzini</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Balick</name></author><author><name>Iain S. Forrest</name></author><author><name>Judy Cho</name></author><author><name>Ghislain Rocheleau</name></author><author><name>Daniel M. Jordan</name></author><author><name>Ron Do</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The prediction of pathogenic human missense variants has improved in recent years, but a more granular level of variant characterization is required. Further axes of information need to be incorporated in order to advance the genotype-to-phenotype map. Recent efforts have developed mode of inheritance prediction tools; however, these lack robust validation and their discrimination performance does not support clinical utility, with evidence of them being fundamentally insensitive to recessive acting diseases. Here, we present MOI-Pred, a three-way variant-level mode of inheritance prediction tool aimed at recessive identification for missense variants. MOI-Pred shows strong ability to discriminate missense variants causing autosomal recessive disease (area under the receiver operating characteristic (AUROC)=0.99 and sensitivity=0.85) in an external validation set. Additionally, we introduce an electronic health record (EHR)-based validation approach using real-world clinical data and show that our recessive predictions are enriched for recessive associations with human diseases, demonstrating utility of our method. Mode of inheritance predictions - pathogenic for autosomal recessive (AR) disease, pathogenic for autosomal dominant (AD) disease, or benign – for all possible missense variants in the human genome are available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/rondolab/MOI-Pred/"&gt;https://github.com/rondolab/MOI-Pred/&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.21265472" rel="alternate" title="Prediction of recessive inheritance for missense variants in human disease (9 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.21265507</id><title>Phenotypic and genetic factors associated with differential consent to record linkage for prescription history in the Australian Genetics of Depression Study (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.364454+00:00</updated><author><name>Lina Gomez</name></author><author><name>Santiago Díaz-Torres</name></author><author><name>Lucía Colodro-Conde</name></author><author><name>Luis M. Garcia-Marin</name></author><author><name>Chloe Yap</name></author><author><name>Enda M. Byrne</name></author><author><name>Loic Yengo</name></author><author><name>Penelope A. Lind</name></author><author><name>Naomi R. Wray</name></author><author><name>Sarah E. Medland</name></author><author><name>Ian B. Hickie</name></author><author><name>Michelle K. Lupton</name></author><author><name>Miguel E. Rentería</name></author><author><name>Nicholas G. Martin</name></author><author><name>Adrian I. Campos</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Samples can be prone to ascertainment and attrition biases.The Australian Genetics of Depression Study is a large publicly recruited cohort (n=20,689) established to increase the understanding of depression and antidepressant treatment response. As part of the recruitment, participants donated a saliva sample and were given the option to consent to linkage of prescription records for research purposes. This study investigates differences between participants who donated a saliva sample or agreed to linkage of their records compared to those who did not. We observed that older, male participants with a higher education were more likely to donate a saliva sample. Self-reported bipolar disorder, ADHD, panic disorder, PTSD, substance use disorder and social anxiety disorder were associated with lower odds of donating a saliva sample whereas anorexia was associated with higher odds of donation. Male and younger participants showed higher odds of agreeing to record linkage. Participants with higher neuroticism scores and those with a history of bipolar disorder were also more likely to agree to record linkage whereas participants with a diagnosis of anorexia were less likely to agree. Increased likelihood of consent was also associated with increased genetic susceptibility to anorexia and reduced genetic risk for depression, and schizophrenia whereas there was no significant genetic effect for neuroticism. Overall, our results show moderate differences among these subsamples. Most current epidemiological studies do not adjust, nor search, for attrition biases at the genetic level. The possibility to do so is a strength of samples such as the AGDS. Our results suggest that analyses can be made more robust by identifying attrition biases both on the phenotypic and genetic level, and either contextualising them as a potential limitation or performing sensitivity analyses adjusting for them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.21265507" rel="alternate" title="Phenotypic and genetic factors associated with differential consent to record linkage for prescription history in the Australian Genetics of Depression Study (9 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.21265424</id><title>Intrahost-diversity of influenza A virus in upper and lower respiratory tract derived samples from a college community (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.364898+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicolae Sapoval</name></author><author><name>P. Jacob Bueno de Mesquita</name></author><author><name>Yunxi Liu</name></author><author><name>Roger Wang</name></author><author><name>Tian Rui Liu</name></author><author><name>Josie Garza</name></author><author><name>Torrey Williams</name></author><author><name>Carmelli Cadiz</name></author><author><name>Gene S. Tan</name></author><author><name>Harm Van Bakel</name></author><author><name>R. A. Leo Elworth</name></author><author><name>Donald K. Milton</name></author><author><name>Todd J. Treangen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Motivation. Influenza is a rapidly mutating RNA virus responsible for annual epidemics causing substantial morbidity, mortality, and economic loss. Characterizing influenza virus mutational diversity and evolutionary processes within and between human hosts can provide tools to help track and understand transmission events. In this study we investigated possible differences between the intrahost genomic content of influenza virus in upper respiratory swabs and exhaled aerosols thought to be enriched for virus from the lower respiratory tract. 

Results. We examined the sequences of specimens collected from influenza A virus (IAV) infected college community members from December 2012 through May 2013. We analyzed four types of IAV samples μm aerosols (N=38), coarse &amp;gt;5μm aerosols (N=27), nasopharyngeal (N=53), and oropharyngeal swabs (N=47)) collected from 42 study participants with 60 sampling instances. Eighteen (42.9%) participants had data from four sample types (nasopharyngeal swab, oropharyngeal swab, coarse aerosol, fine aerosol) included in the analysis, 10 (23.8%) had data from 3 sample types, 10 (23.8%) had data from 2 sample types, and 4 (9.5%) had data from one type of sample included in the analysis. We found that 481 (53.3%) consensus single nucleotide polymorphisms are shared by all sample types and 600 (66.5%) are shared by at least three different sample types. We observed that within a single patient consensus and non-consensus single nucleotide variants are shared across all sample types. Finally, we inferred a phylogenetic tree using consensus sequences and found that samples derived from a single patient are monophyletic. 
 
Conclusions. Single nucleotide polymorphisms did not differentiate between samples with varying origin along the respiratory tree. We found that signatures of variation in non-consensus intrahost single nucleotide variants are host and sample, but not site-specific. We conclude that the genomic information available does not allow us to discern a transmission route. Future investigation into whether any site-specific mutational signatures emerge over a longer period of infection, for example in immunocompromised hosts, can be interesting from the virus evolution perspective.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.21265424" rel="alternate" title="Intrahost-diversity of influenza A virus in upper and lower respiratory tract derived samples from a college community (9 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466210</id><title>Selective inhibition of PfATP6 by artemisinins and identification of new classes of inhibitors after expression in yeast (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.365439+00:00</updated><author><name>Catherine M. Moore</name></author><author><name>Jigang Wang</name></author><author><name>Qingsong Lin</name></author><author><name>Pedro Ferreira</name></author><author><name>Mitchell A. Avery</name></author><author><name>Khaled Elokely</name></author><author><name>Henry M. Staines</name></author><author><name>Sanjeev Krishna</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Treatment failures with artemisinin combination therapies (ACTs) threaten global efforts to eradicate malaria. They highlight the importance of identifying drug targets and new inhibitors and of studying how existing antimalarial classes work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Herein we report the successful development of an heterologous expression-based compound screening tool. Validated drug target &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; calcium ATPase6 (PfATP6) and a mammalian ortholog (SERCA1a) were functionally expressed in yeast providing a robust, sensitive, and specific screening tool. Whole-cell and &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; assays consistently demonstrated inhibition and labelling of PfATP6 by artemisinins. Mutations in PfATP6 resulted in fitness costs that were ameliorated in the presence of artemisinin derivatives when studied in the yeast model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As previously hypothesised, PfATP6 is a target of artemisinins. Mammalian SERCA1a can be mutated to become more susceptible to artemisinins. The inexpensive, low technology yeast screening platform has identified unrelated classes of druggable PfATP6 inhibitors. Resistance to artemisinins may depend on mechanisms that can concomitantly address multi-targeting by artemisinins and fitness costs of mutations that reduce artemisinin susceptibility.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466210" rel="alternate" title="Selective inhibition of PfATP6 by artemisinins and identification of new classes of inhibitors after expression in yeast (8 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.21265156</id><title>Acute Pain Pathways: protocol for a prospective cohort study (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.366339+00:00</updated><author><name>Molly Moore Jeffery</name></author><author><name>Mitra Ahadpour</name></author><author><name>Summer Allen</name></author><author><name>Richardae Araojo</name></author><author><name>Fernanda Bellolio</name></author><author><name>Nancy Chang</name></author><author><name>Laura Ciaccio</name></author><author><name>Lindsay Emanuel</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Fillmore</name></author><author><name>Gregg H. Gilbert</name></author><author><name>Patricia Koussis</name></author><author><name>Christine Lee</name></author><author><name>Heather Lipkind</name></author><author><name>Celeste Mallama</name></author><author><name>Tamra Meyer</name></author><author><name>Megan Moncur</name></author><author><name>Teryl K. Nuckols</name></author><author><name>Michael A. Pacanowski</name></author><author><name>David B. Page</name></author><author><name>Elektra Papadopoulos</name></author><author><name>Jessica D. Ritchie</name></author><author><name>Joseph S. Ross</name></author><author><name>Nilay D. Shah</name></author><author><name>Mat Soukup</name></author><author><name>Christopher O. St. Clair</name></author><author><name>Stephen Tamang</name></author><author><name>Sam S. Torbati</name></author><author><name>Douglas W. Wallace</name></author><author><name>Yueqin Zhao</name></author><author><name>Rebekah Heckmann</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Opioid analgesics are often used to treat moderate-to-severe acute non-cancer pain; however, there is little high-quality evidence to guide clinician prescribing. An essential element to developing evidence-based guidelines is a better understanding of pain management and pain control among individuals experiencing acute pain for various common diagnoses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods and analysis&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This multi-center prospective observational study will recruit 1,550 opioid-naïve participants with acute pain seen in diverse clinical settings including primary/urgent care, emergency departments, and dental clinics. Participants will be followed for 6 months with the aid of a patient-centered health data aggregating platform that consolidates data from study questionnaires, electronic health record data on health care services received, prescription fill data from pharmacies, and activity and sleep data from a Fitbit activity tracker. Participants will be enrolled to represent diverse races and ethnicities and pain conditions, as well as geographical diversity. Data analysis will focus on assessing patients’ patterns of pain and opioid analgesic use, along with other pain treatments; associations between patient and condition characteristics and patient-centered outcomes including resolution of pain, satisfaction with care, and long-term use of opioid analgesics; and descriptive analyses of patient management of leftover opioids.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Ethics and dissemination&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study has received approval from IRBs at each site. Results will be made available to participants, funders, the research community, and the public.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Trial registration number&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;NCT04509115&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Strengths and limitations of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study addresses a key knowledge gap by recruiting a large and diverse group of patients with acute pain, following them for 6 months, and prospectively assessing their pain experience and acute pain treatment&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients will be recruited from multiple treatment settings that are important in the treatment of acute pain, including emergency departments, primary care, dental settings, and surgical settings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;A patient-centered health data aggregating platform reduces the patient burden of participating in the trial by allowing participants to complete questionnaires when it is convenient and by automatically collecting data on physical activity, healthcare service use, and prescription fills&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;All participants will have been offered an opioid prescription, reducing the ability to compare outcomes across opioid and non-opioid pain medications&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite a large sample size, there may be limited numbers of specific acute pain diagnoses with a sufficient sample to analyze and compare by condition/diagnosis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.21265156" rel="alternate" title="Acute Pain Pathways: protocol for a prospective cohort study (7 tweets)"/><category term="Pain Medicine"/><published>2021-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.21265127</id><title>Genome-wide association study of liver fat, iron, and extracellular fluid fraction in the UK Biobank (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.367089+00:00</updated><author><name>Colm O’Dushlaine</name></author><author><name>Mary Germino</name></author><author><name>Niek Verweij</name></author><author><name>Jonas B. Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Ashish Yadav</name></author><author><name>Christian Benner</name></author><author><name>Joshua D. Backman</name></author><author><name>Nan Lin</name></author><author><name>Gonçalo R. Abecasis</name></author><author><name>Aris Baras</name></author><author><name>Manuel A. Ferreira</name></author><author><name>Luca A. Lotta</name></author><author><name>Johnathon R. Walls</name></author><author><name>Prodromos Parasoglou</name></author><author><name>Jonathan L. Marchini</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Abdominal magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) represents a non-invasive approach allowing the extraction of clinically informative phenotypes. We developed an automated pipeline to segment liver pixels from abdominal MRI images and apply published models to approximate fat fraction, extracellular fluid fraction and iron content in 40,058 MRIs from the UK Biobank. We then conducted a genome-wide association of these traits using imputed variants (N=37,250 individuals, 11,914,698 variants) and exome sequence data (N=35,274 individuals, 8,287,315 variants). For liver fat we identified 8 novel loci in or near genes MARC1, GCKR, ADH1B, MTTP, TRIB1, GPAM, PNPLA2 and APOH. For liver iron we identified 1 novel locus between the genes ASNSD1 and SLC40A1, an iron transporter involved in hemochromatosis. For extracellular fluid fraction we identified 6 novel loci in or near genes AGMAT, NAT2, MRPL4-S1PR2, FADS1, ABO and HFE, with almost all having prior associations to obesity, liver, iron, or lipid traits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.21265127" rel="alternate" title="Genome-wide association study of liver fat, iron, and extracellular fluid fraction in the UK Biobank (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265491</id><title>Loss-of-Function FLNC Variants are Associated with Arrhythmogenic Cardiomyopathy Phenotypes when Identified through Exome Sequencing of a General Clinical Population (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.367728+00:00</updated><author><name>Eric D Carruth</name></author><author><name>Maria Qureshi</name></author><author><name>Amro Alsaid</name></author><author><name>Melissa A Kelly</name></author><author><name>Hugh Calkins</name></author><author><name>Brittney Murray</name></author><author><name>Crystal Tichnell</name></author><author><name>Amy C Sturm</name></author><author><name>Aris Baras</name></author><author><name>H Lester Kirchner</name></author><author><name>Brandon K Fornwalt</name></author><author><name>Cynthia A James</name></author><author><name>Christopher M Haggerty</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;Background&lt;/bold&gt;
The FLNC gene has recently garnered attention as a likely cause of arrhythmogenic cardiomyopathy (ACM), which is considered an actionable genetic condition. However, the association with disease in an unselected clinical population is unknown. We hypothesized that individuals with loss-of-function variants in FLNC (FLNC&lt;sub&gt;LOF&lt;/sub&gt;) would have increased odds for ACM-associated phenotypes versus variant-negative controls in the Geisinger MyCode cohort.
&lt;bold&gt;Methods&lt;/bold&gt;
We identified rare, putative FLNC&lt;sub&gt;LOF&lt;/sub&gt; among 171,948 individuals with exome sequencing linked to health records. Associations with ACM phenotypes from available diagnoses and cardiac evaluations were investigated.
&lt;bold&gt;Results&lt;/bold&gt;
Sixty individuals (0.03%; median age 58 years [47 — 70 IQR], 43% male) harbored 27 unique FLNC&lt;sub&gt;LOF&lt;/sub&gt;. These individuals had significantly increased odds ratios (OR) for dilated cardiomyopathy (OR:4.9, [95% confidence interval: 2.6 — 7.6]; p&amp;lt;0.001), supraventricular tachycardia (OR:3.2, [1.1 — 5.6]; p=0.01), defibrillator implantation (OR:4.6, [1.9 — 8.4]; p&amp;lt;0.001), and left-dominant ACM (OR:4.2, [1.4 — 7.9]; p=0.003). Echocardiography revealed reduced left ventricular ejection fraction (52 ± 13% vs. 57 ± 9%; p=0.001) associated with FLNC&lt;sub&gt;LOF&lt;/sub&gt;. Overall, at least 9% of FLNC&lt;sub&gt;LOF&lt;/sub&gt; carriers demonstrated evidence of penetrant disease.
&lt;bold&gt;Conclusions&lt;/bold&gt;
FLNC&lt;sub&gt;LOF&lt;/sub&gt; variants are associated with increased odds of ventricular arrhythmia and dysfunction in an unselected clinical population. These findings support genomic screening of FLNC for actionable secondary findings.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265491" rel="alternate" title="Loss-of-Function FLNC Variants are Associated with Arrhythmogenic Cardiomyopathy Phenotypes when Identified through Exome Sequencing of a General Clinical Population (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265606</id><title>Rapid health evaluation in migrant peoples in transit through Darien, Panama: Protocol for a multi-method qualitative and quantitative study (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.368114+00:00</updated><author><name>Amanda Gabster</name></author><author><name>Monica Jhanigmal</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Toller Erausquin</name></author><author><name>Jose Antonio Suarez</name></author><author><name>Justo Emilio Pinzon-Espinosa</name></author><author><name>Madeline Baird</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Katz</name></author><author><name>Davis Beltran Henriquez</name></author><author><name>Gonzalo Cabezas Talavero</name></author><author><name>Andres Henao Martinez</name></author><author><name>Carlos Franco-Paredes</name></author><author><name>Nelson Agudelo-Higuita</name></author><author><name>Monica Pachar</name></author><author><name>Jose Anel Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Juan Miguel Pascale</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Abstract

Background:
The world is currently unprepared to deal with a the drastic increase in global migration. There is an urgent need to develop programs to protect the well being and health of migrant peoples. Increased population movement is already evident throughout the Americas as exemplified by the rising number of migrant peoples that pass through the Darien neotropical moist broadleaf forest along the border region between Panama and Colombia. The transit of migrant peoples through this area has an increase in the last years. In 2021 an average of 9,400 people entered the region per month compared to 2,000-3,500 people monthly in 2019. Along this trail, there is no access to healthcare, food provision, potable water, or housing. To date, much of what is known about health needs and barriers to healthcare within this population is based on journalistic reports and anecdotes. There is a need for a comprehensive approach to assess the healthcare needs migrant peoples in transit.  This study aims to describe demographic characteristics, mental and physical health status and needs, and experiences of host communities, and to identify opportunities to improve healthcare provision to migrant peoples in transit in Panama. 

Study design and methods: 
This multi-method study will include qualitative (n=70) and quantitative (n=520) components.  The qualitative component includes interviews with migrant peoples in transit, national and international non-governmental organizations and agencies based in Panama. The quantitative component is a rapid epidemiological study which includes a questionnaire and four clinical screenings: mental health, sexual and reproductive health, general and tropical medicine, and nutrition. 

Conclusion:
This study will contribute to a better understanding of the health status and needs of migrant peoples in transit through Darien, Panama. Findings will be used to allocate resources and provide  targeted healthcare interventions for migrant peoples in transit through Darien, Panama.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265606" rel="alternate" title="Rapid health evaluation in migrant peoples in transit through Darien, Panama: Protocol for a multi-method qualitative and quantitative study (5 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.21265321</id><title>Accuracy of computer-aided chest X-ray screening in the Kenya National Tuberculosis Prevalence Survey (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.368568+00:00</updated><author><name>Brenda Mungai</name></author><author><name>Jane Ong'ang'o</name></author><author><name>Chu Chang Ku</name></author><author><name>Marc YR Henrion</name></author><author><name>Ben Morton</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Joekes</name></author><author><name>Richard Kiplimo</name></author><author><name>Dickson Kirathe</name></author><author><name>Enos Masini</name></author><author><name>Joseph Sitienei</name></author><author><name>Veronica Manduku</name></author><author><name>Beatrice Mugi</name></author><author><name>Stephen Bertel Squire</name></author><author><name>Peter MacPherson</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Community–based screening for tuberculosis (TB) could improve detection but is resource intensive. We set out to evaluate the accuracy of computer–aided TB screening using digital chest X-ray (CXR) to determine if this approach met target product profiles (TPP) for community–based screening.

Methods: CXR images from participants in the 2016 Kenya National TB Prevalence Survey were evaluated using CAD4TBv6 (Delft Imaging), giving a probabilistic score for pulmonary TB ranging from 0 (low probability) to 99 (high probability). We constructed a Bayesian latent class model to estimate the accuracy of CAD4TBv6 screening compared to bacteriologically–confirmed TB across CAD4TBv6 threshold cut–offs, incorporating data on Clinical Officer CXR interpretation, participant demographics (age, sex, TB symptoms, previous TB history), and sputum results. We compared model–estimated sensitivity and specificity of CAD4TBv6 to optimum and minimum TPPs.

Results: Of 63,050 prevalence survey participants, 61,848 (98%) had analysable CXR images, and 8,966 (14.5%) underwent sputum bacteriological testing; 298 had bacteriologically–confirmed pulmonary TB. Median CAD4TBv6 scores for participants with bacteriologically–confirmed TB were significantly higher (72, IQR: 58–82.75) compared to participants with bacteriologically–negative sputum results (49, IQR: 44–57, p&amp;lt;0.0001). CAD4TBv6 met the optimum TPP; with the threshold set to achieve a mean sensitivity of 95% (optimum TPP), specificity was 83.3%, (95% credible interval [CrI]: 83.0%–83.7%, CAD4TBv6 threshold: 55). There was considerable variation in accuracy by participant characteristics, with older individuals and those with previous TB having lowest specificity. 

Conclusions: CAD4TBv6 met the optimal TPP for TB community screening. To optimise screening accuracy and efficiency of confirmatory sputum testing, we recommend that an adaptive approach to threshold setting is adopted based on participant characteristics.
 &lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.21265321" rel="alternate" title="Accuracy of computer-aided chest X-ray screening in the Kenya National Tuberculosis Prevalence Survey (5 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.24.21265348</id><title>Factors Associated with Medicine Timing Effects: A Meta-analysis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.368962+00:00</updated><author><name>Marc D. Ruben</name></author><author><name>Lauren J. Francey</name></author><author><name>Gang Wu</name></author><author><name>David F. Smith</name></author><author><name>Garret A. FitzGerald</name></author><author><name>Jacob J. Hughey</name></author><author><name>John B. Hogenesch</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clinical evidence suggests that the time of day of treatment can affect outcomes in many different diseases, but this information is dispersed, imprecise, and heterogeneous. Consequently, practice guidelines and clinical care recommendations seldom specify intervention time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To understand the sources of variability and summarize clinical findings on the time of day effects of medicine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data Sources&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A systematic search of Pubmed, Google Scholar, and &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov"&gt;ClinicalTrials.gov&lt;/ext-link&gt; for “chronotherapy” OR “time of administration”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Study Selection&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Any clinical study since 2000, randomized or observational, that compared the effects of treatment at different times of day. We included pharmacologic or surgical interventions having at least one continuous outcome.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data Extraction and Synthesis&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;For selected studies, we extracted the mean and variance of each time-of-day treatment group. From these, we computed the standardized mean difference (SMD) as the measure of timing effect. Where a study reported multiple outcomes, we selected a single outcome based on a defined order of priority.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Outcomes and Measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We estimated overall pooled effect size and heterogeneity by a random effects model, followed by outlier detection and subgroup analyses to evaluate how study factors, including drug, design, outcome, and source, associate with timing effect.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;78 studies met the inclusion criteria, comprising 48 distinct interventions over many therapeutic areas. We found an overall effect of time on clinical outcomes but with substantial heterogeneity between studies. Predicted effects range from none to large depending on the study context. Study size, registration status, and source are associated with the magnitude of effect. Larger trials and those that were pre-registered have markedly smaller effects, suggesting that the published record overstates the effects of the timing of medicine on clinical outcomes. In particular, the notion that antihypertensives are more effective if taken at bedtime draws disproportionately from one source in the field, which consistently detects larger effects than the community average. Lastly, among the most highly studied drug timing relationships, aspirin’s anti-clotting effect stands out, consistently favoring evening over morning dosing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions and Relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;While accounts of drug timing effects have focused on &lt;italic&gt;yes/no&lt;/italic&gt;, appreciating the range of probable effects may help clarify where ‘circadian medicine’ meets the threshold for clinical benefit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.24.21265348" rel="alternate" title="Factors Associated with Medicine Timing Effects: A Meta-analysis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cardiovascular Medicine"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.23.21265407</id><title>Relationship among work–treatment balance, job stress, and work engagement in Japan: A cross-sectional study (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.369248+00:00</updated><author><name>Kazunori Ikegami</name></author><author><name>Hajime Ando</name></author><author><name>Hisashi Eguchi</name></author><author><name>Mayumi Tsuji</name></author><author><name>Seiichiro Tateishi</name></author><author><name>Koji Mori</name></author><author><name>Keiji Muramatsu</name></author><author><name>Yoshihisa Fujino</name></author><author><name>Akira Ogami</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;There is a drive to support workers undergoing medical treatment who wish to continue working in Japan, known as the work–treatment balance. It is hoped that this support for the work–treatment balance could boost their mental health. This study examines the relationship among the work–treatment balance, job stress, and work engagement. This study was conducted in December 2020 in Japan, with 27,036 participants. We divided the participants into three groups by the receipt state of support for the work–treatment balance: control group (no need the support), unsupported group, and supported group. The scores of the parameters of the job content questionnaire and the Utrecht Work Engagement Scale (UWES-3) were compared among groups using a multilevel regression with age-sex or multivariate-adjusted models. In the two models, the job control score of the unsupported group was significantly lower than that of the control group. The two social support scores of the supported group were significantly higher than those of the control group. The scores of the UWES-3 of the unsupported group were significantly lower than those of the control group. The support of work–treatment balance for workers could have a positive impact on their mental health.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.23.21265407" rel="alternate" title="Relationship among work–treatment balance, job stress, and work engagement in Japan: A cross-sectional study (3 tweets)"/><category term="Occupational and Environmental Health"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466295</id><title>Repeated exposure to chlorpyrifos is associated with a dose-dependent chronic neurobehavioral deficit in adult rats (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.369995+00:00</updated><author><name>Ana CR Ribeiro</name></author><author><name>Elisa H Hawkins</name></author><author><name>Fay M Jahr</name></author><author><name>Joseph L McClay</name></author><author><name>Laxmikant S Deshpande</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Organophosphate (OP) chemicals include commonly used pesticides and also chemical warfare agents, and mechanistically they are potent inhibitors of the cholinesterase (ChE) enzyme. While a chronic low-dose OP exposure does not produce acute cholinergic crises, epidemiological studies report long-term neuropsychiatric issues including depression and cognitive impairments in OP-exposed individuals. Chlorpyrifos (CPF) is one of the most widely used pesticides worldwide. Multiple laboratory studies have reported on either the long-term behavioral effect of a single, high-dose CPF or studied sub-chronic behavioral effects particularly the motor and cognitive effects of repeated low-dose CPF exposure. However, studies on chronic mood and depression-related morbidities following repeated sub-threshold CPF doses that would mimic occupationally-relevant OP exposures are lacking. Here, adult male rats were injected with CPF (1, 3, 5, or 10 mg/kg/d, s.c.) for 21-days. Dependent on the CPF dose, ChE activity was inhibited approximately 60-80% in the blood and about 20-50% in the hippocampus at 2-days after the end of CPF exposures. Following an 11-week washout period, CPF-treated rats exhibited a dose-dependent increase in signs of anhedonia (sucrose preference test), anxiety (open-field and elevated plus-maze), and despair (forced swim test) despite a complete recovery of ChE activity at this stage. We speculate that both cholinergic and non-cholinergic mechanisms could play a role in the development of chronic OP-related depressive outcomes. The proposed CPF exposure paradigm could provide an ideal model to further study molecular mechanisms underlying cause and effect relationships between environmental OP exposures and the development of chronic behavioral deficits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466295" rel="alternate" title="Repeated exposure to chlorpyrifos is associated with a dose-dependent chronic neurobehavioral deficit in adult rats (3 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.21265667</id><title>Female football specific energy availability questionnaire and menstrual cycle hormone monitoring (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.370362+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicola Keay</name></author><author><name>Eddie Craghill</name></author><author><name>Gavin Francis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Abstract

Objectives
The purpose of this study was to assess the energy availability status of professional female football players with an online Female Football Energy Availability Questionnaire (FFEAQ), combined with the clinical tool to model menstrual cycle hormones using artificial intelligence (AI) techniques. 
Methods
The Female Football Energy Availability (FFEAQ) was developed based on published questionnaires, with a weighted scoring system to assess risk of Relative Energy Deficiency in Sport (RED-S). For menstrual cycle hormones AI techniques modelled hormone variation over a cycle, using the results from capillary blood samples taken at two time points.
Results
21 female footballers of professional club level participated in this study, with mean age 22 years [range 16 to 30]. 20 athletes recorded positive scores on the FFEAQ, suggesting a low risk of Relative Energy Deficiency in Sport (RED-S). No players had experienced primary amenorrhoea. 5 athletes reported previous history of secondary amenorrhoea. Amongst the 15 players not taking hormonal contraception, 2 reported current oligomenorrhoea. 
The application of AI techniques to model menstrual cycle hormones found that in 1 of the 3 players, subclinical hormone disruption was occurring with this player reporting variable flow of menstruation. Although the other 2 players showed expected menstrual hormone variation, 1 player reported variable flow according to training load, suggestive of subclinical anovulation. At the time of testing training load was low due to pandemic lock down. 
Conclusions
The professional female football athletes in this study were found to be at low risk of RED-S from the FFEAQ. Modelling menstrual cycle hormones using AI techniques indicated that this has the potential to be an effective clinical tool in identifying subtle hormone dysfunction such as subclinical anovulatory cycles in female athletes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.21265667" rel="alternate" title="Female football specific energy availability questionnaire and menstrual cycle hormone monitoring (3 tweets)"/><category term="Sports Medicine"/><published>2021-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>