<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.198470+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.19.21264255</id><title>Metabolic Dysfunction Related Liver Disease as a Risk Factor for Cancer (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.198892+00:00</updated><author><name>Alasdair Taylor</name></author><author><name>Moneeza K Siddiqui</name></author><author><name>Philip Ambery</name></author><author><name>Javier Armisen</name></author><author><name>Benjamin G. Challis</name></author><author><name>Carolina Haefliger</name></author><author><name>Ewan R. Pearson</name></author><author><name>Alex S.F. Doney</name></author><author><name>John F. Dillon</name></author><author><name>Colin N.A. Palmer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The aim of this study was to investigate the association with obesity, diabetes and related liver dysfunction and the incidence of cancer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study was conducted with health record data available from the National Health Service in Tayside and Fife. GoDARTS, SHARE and Tayside and Fife diabetics, three Scottish cohorts of 13,695, 62,438, and 16,312 patients respectively were analysed in this study. Participants in GoDARTS were a volunteer sample, with half having T2DM. SHARE were a volunteer sample. Tayside and Fife diabetics was a population level cohort. Metabolic dysfunction-related liver disease (MDLD) was defined using ALT measurements, and individuals with alternative causes of liver disease (alcohol abuse, viruses etc) were excluded from the analysis. Other indicators of liver disease were analysed including the Fatty Liver Index, Fibrosis Score(FIB-4) and hospital admissions for NASH. The main outcomes were cancer incidence and cancer death.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;MDLD associated with increased cancer incidence with a hazard ratio of 1.31 in a cox proportional hazards model adjusted for sex, type 2 diabetes, BMI, and smoking status (95% CI = 1.27 – 1.35, p &amp;lt; 0.0001). This was replicated in two further cohorts, and similar associations with cancer incidence were found for Fatty Liver Index (FLI), FIB-4 and NASH. Homozygous carriers of the common NAFLD risk variant PNPLA3 rs738409 had increased risk of cancer. (HR = 1.27 (1.02-1.58), p = 3.1×10&lt;sup&gt;−2&lt;/sup&gt;). BMI was not independently associated with cancer incidence when MDLD was included as a covariate. MDLD was associated with increased risk of cancer death (HR = 1.40, 95% CI =1.33 - 1.47, p &amp;lt; 0.0001).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;MDLD, FLI, FIB-4 and NASH associated with increased risk of cancer incidence and death. Further, we found evidence of a causal association between NAFLD and cancer using the established causal risk allele of PNPLA3 as a genetic instrument. NAFLD may be a major component of the relationship between obesity and cancer incidence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Lay Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found that individuals with metabolic dysfunction-related liver disease (MDLD) have higher overall cancer risk than healthy individuals, as well as increased risk of specific cancers such as colon, breast and lung. We also show that when MDLD is accounted for, obesity does not significantly increase overall cancer risk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.19.21264255" rel="alternate" title="Metabolic Dysfunction Related Liver Disease as a Risk Factor for Cancer (3 tweets)"/><category term="Gastroenterology"/><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>