<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.029109+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.21264206</id><title>Enhancing the brain’s emotion regulation capacity with a randomised trial of a 5-week heart rate variability biofeedback intervention (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.029655+00:00</updated><author><name>Kaoru Nashiro</name></author><author><name>Jungwon Min</name></author><author><name>Hyun Joo Yoo</name></author><author><name>Christine Cho</name></author><author><name>Shelby L. Bachman</name></author><author><name>Shubir Dutt</name></author><author><name>Julian F. Thayer</name></author><author><name>Paul Lehrer</name></author><author><name>Tiantian Feng</name></author><author><name>Noah Mercer</name></author><author><name>Padideh Nasseri</name></author><author><name>Diana Wang</name></author><author><name>Catie Chang</name></author><author><name>Vasilis Z. Marmarelis</name></author><author><name>Shri Narayanan</name></author><author><name>Daniel A. Nation</name></author><author><name>Mara Mather</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Heart rate variability is a robust biomarker of emotional well-being, consistent with the shared brain networks regulating emotion regulation and heart rate. While high heart rate oscillatory activity clearly indicates healthy regulatory brain systems, can increasing this oscillatory activity also enhance brain function? To test this possibility, we randomly assigned 106 young adult participants to one of two 5-week interventions involving daily biofeedback that either increased heart rate oscillations (Osc+ condition) or had little effect on heart rate oscillations (Osc- condition) and examined effects on brain activity during rest and during regulating emotion. In this healthy cohort, the two conditions did not differentially affect anxiety, depression or mood. However, the Osc+ intervention increased low-frequency heart rate variability and increased brain oscillatory dynamics and functional connectivity in emotion-related resting-state networks. It also increased down-regulation of activity in somatosensory brain regions during an emotion regulation task. The Osc- intervention did not have these effects. These findings indicate that heart rate oscillatory activity not only reflects the current state of regulatory brain systems but also changes how the brain operates beyond the moments of high oscillatory activity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.21264206" rel="alternate" title="Enhancing the brain’s emotion regulation capacity with a randomised trial of a 5-week heart rate variability biofeedback intervention (12 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.21264208</id><title>Integration of genetic colocalizations with physiological and pharmacological perturbations identifies cardiometabolic disease genes (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.030255+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael J. Gloudemans</name></author><author><name>Brunilda Balliu</name></author><author><name>Daniel Nachun</name></author><author><name>Matthew G. Durrant</name></author><author><name>Erik Ingelsson</name></author><author><name>Martin Wabitsch</name></author><author><name>Thomas Quertermous</name></author><author><name>Stephen B. Montgomery</name></author><author><name>Joshua W. Knowles</name></author><author><name>Ivan Carcamo-Orive</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Identification of causal genes for polygenic human diseases has been extremely challenging, and our understanding of how physiological and pharmacological stimuli modulate genetic risk at disease-associated loci is limited. Specifically, insulin resistance (IR), a common feature of cardiometabolic disease, including type 2 diabetes, obesity, and dyslipidemia, lacks well-powered GWAS, and therefore few associated loci and causal genes have been identified.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we perform and integrate LD-adjusted colocalization analyses across nine cardiometabolic traits combined with eQTLs and sQTLs from five metabolically relevant human tissues (subcutaneous and visceral adipose, skeletal muscle, liver, and pancreas). We identify 470 colocalized loci and prioritize 207 loci with a single colocalized gene. To elucidate upstream regulators and functional mechanisms for these genes, we integrate their transcriptional responses to 21 physiological and pharmacological cardiometabolic regulators in human adipocytes, hepatocytes, and skeletal muscle cells, and map their protein-protein interactions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our use of transcriptional responses under metabolic perturbations to contextualize genetic associations from our state-of-the-art colocalization approach provides a list of likely causal genes and their upstream regulators in the context of IR-associated cardiometabolic risk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.21264208" rel="alternate" title="Integration of genetic colocalizations with physiological and pharmacological perturbations identifies cardiometabolic disease genes (10 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.21263187</id><title>Comprehensive genetic diagnosis of tandem repeat expansion disorders with programmable targeted nanopore sequencing (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.030636+00:00</updated><author><name>Igor Stevanovski</name></author><author><name>Sanjog R. Chintalaphani</name></author><author><name>Hasindu Gamaarachchi</name></author><author><name>James M. Ferguson</name></author><author><name>Sandy S. Pineda</name></author><author><name>Carolin K. Scriba</name></author><author><name>Michel Tchan</name></author><author><name>Victor Fung</name></author><author><name>Karl Ng</name></author><author><name>Andrea Cortese</name></author><author><name>Henry Houlden</name></author><author><name>Carol Dobson-Stone</name></author><author><name>Lauren Fitzpatrick</name></author><author><name>Glenda Halliday</name></author><author><name>Gianina Ravenscroft</name></author><author><name>Mark R. Davis</name></author><author><name>Nigel G. Laing</name></author><author><name>Avi Fellner</name></author><author><name>Marina Kennerson</name></author><author><name>Kishore R. Kumar</name></author><author><name>Ira W. Deveson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Short-tandem repeat (STR) expansions are an important class of pathogenic genetic variants. Over forty neurological and neuromuscular diseases are caused by STR expansions, with 37 different genes implicated to date. Here we describe the use of programmable targeted long-read sequencing with Oxford Nanopore’s ReadUntil function for parallel genotyping of all known neuropathogenic STRs in a single, simple assay. Our approach enables accurate, haplotype-resolved assembly and DNA methylation profiling of expanded and non-expanded STR sites. In doing so, the assay correctly diagnoses all individuals in a cohort of patients (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; = 27) with various neurogenetic diseases, including Huntington’s disease, fragile X syndrome and cerebellar ataxia (CANVAS) and others. Targeted long-read sequencing solves large and complex STR expansions that confound established molecular tests and short-read sequencing, and identifies non-canonical STR motif conformations and internal sequence interruptions. Even in our relatively small cohort, we observe a wide diversity of STR alleles of known and unknown pathogenicity, suggesting that long-read sequencing will redefine the genetic landscape of STR expansion disorders. Finally, we show how the flexible inclusion of pharmacogenomics (PGx) genes as secondary ReadUntil targets can identify clinically actionable PGx genotypes to further inform patient care, at no extra cost. Our study addresses the need for improved techniques for genetic diagnosis of STR expansion disorders and illustrates the broad utility of programmable long-read sequencing for clinical genomics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study describes the development and validation of a programmable targeted nanopore sequencing assay for parallel genetic diagnosis of all known pathogenic short-tandem repeats (STRs) in a single, simple test.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.21263187" rel="alternate" title="Comprehensive genetic diagnosis of tandem repeat expansion disorders with programmable targeted nanopore sequencing (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.21264368</id><title>“Jittered” Oculomotor Sensing Concomitant with Hypoactive Dorsal Parietal Systems during Live Eye-Contact in Autism Spectrum Disorder (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.031049+00:00</updated><author><name>Joy Hirsch</name></author><author><name>Xian Zhang</name></author><author><name>J. Adam Noah</name></author><author><name>Swethasri Dravida</name></author><author><name>Adam Naples</name></author><author><name>Mark Tiede</name></author><author><name>Julie M. Wolf</name></author><author><name>James C. McPartland</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Reluctant eye contact and reduced social interactions characteristic of autism spectrum disorder (ASD) are consistent with deficits in oculomotor and face processing systems. We test the hypothesis that these deficits are interrelated ASD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eye-tracking and hyperscanning with functional near-infrared spectroscopy (fNIRS) were used to acquire neuroimaging data during live, dynamic eye-to-eye contacts in 17 ASD and 19 typically-developed (TD) adults. Real eye contact conditions were contrasted with conditions where eye gaze was directed at a comparable dynamic face video. These findings were regressed with eye-contact dwell-time, i.e., times when gaze of both partners was in the eye-box of the other, to confirm the relationship between visual sensing and neural coding. Visual fixations and positional variance were also determined.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Average gaze dwell-times in the “eye-box” did not vary between ASD and TD participants but were longer for the Real Eye than Video Eye condition for both groups. However, positional gaze variability, “jitter”, was higher for ASD in both conditions. Neural findings for TD [Real Eye &amp;gt; Video Eye] were consistent with previous findings for interactive face-gaze with activity in right temporal and dorsal parietal regions. However, in ASD ventral temporal regions were observed for this contrast without evidence for dorsal parietal activity. This neural difference was enhanced when regressed by eye-contact dwell-times.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Together findings are consistent with the hypothesis that unstable bottom-up oculomotor signals contribute to deficits in live face processing and reduced dorsal stream activity in ASD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eye contact avoidance is a diagnostic feature of autism spectrum disorder (ASD). However, the underlying neural mechanisms are unknown. Using a two-person neural imaging system and a face-to-face paradigm with eye tracking, we found that the neural systems activated by live eye contact differed between typically developed (TD) and ASD groups. In ASD, the ventral occipital parietal systems were engaged, whereas in TD, the dorsal posterior parietal systems were engaged. Positional variation of eye gaze, “jitter”, was higher in ASD than TD. These findings are consistent with the hypothesis that bottom-up variations in visual sensing are components of altered interactive face processing and dorsal stream mechanisms and may contribute to the neural underpinnings of reluctant eye contact behaviors in ASD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.21264368" rel="alternate" title="“Jittered” Oculomotor Sensing Concomitant with Hypoactive Dorsal Parietal Systems during Live Eye-Contact in Autism Spectrum Disorder (3 tweets)"/><category term="Psychiatry and Clinical Psychology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>