<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.496349+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.31.21262937</id><title>Impairments in goal-directed action and reversal learning in a proportion of individuals with psychosis: evidence for differential phenotypes in early and persistent psychosis (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.498717+00:00</updated><author><name>Shuichi Suetani</name></author><author><name>Andrea Baker</name></author><author><name>Kelly Garner</name></author><author><name>Peter Cosgrove</name></author><author><name>Matilda Mackay-Sim</name></author><author><name>Dan Siskind</name></author><author><name>Graham K Murray</name></author><author><name>James G Scott</name></author><author><name>James P Kesby</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cognitive impairments in psychosis are one of the strongest predictors of functional decline. Cortico-striatal dysfunction may contribute to both psychosis and cognitive impairment in psychotic illnesses. The decision-making processes underlying goal-directed action and serial reversal learning can be measured and are sensitive to changes reflecting cortico-striatal dysfunction. As such, changes in decision-making performance may assist with predicting functional decline in people with psychosis. We assessed decision-making processes in healthy controls (N=34), and those with early psychosis (N=15) and persistent psychosis (N=45). We subclassified subjects based on intact/impaired goal-directed action. Compared with healthy controls (&amp;lt;20%), a large proportion (58%) of those with persistent psychosis displayed impaired goal-directed action, predicting poor serial reversal learning performance. Computational approaches indicated that those with persistent psychosis were less deterministic in their decision-making. Those with impaired goal-directed action had a decreased capacity to rapidly update their prior beliefs in the face of changing contingencies. In contrast, the early psychosis group included a lower proportion of individuals with impaired goal-directed action (20%) and displayed a different cognitive phenotype from those with persistent psychosis. These findings suggest prominent decision-making deficits, indicative of cortico-striatal dysfunction, are present in a large proportion of people with persistent psychosis while those with early psychosis have relatively intact decision-making processes compared to healthy controls. It is unclear if there is a progressive decline in decision-making processes in some individuals with psychosis or if the presence of decision-making processes in early psychosis is predictive of a persistent trajectory of illness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.31.21262937" rel="alternate" title="Impairments in goal-directed action and reversal learning in a proportion of individuals with psychosis: evidence for differential phenotypes in early and persistent psychosis (6 tweets)"/><category term="Psychiatry and Clinical Psychology"/><published>2021-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>