<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.194351+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.21267677</id><title>Artificial intelligence for diagnosis and prognosis in neuroimaging for dementia; a systematic review (51 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.195960+00:00</updated><author><name>R Borchert</name></author><author><name>T Azevedo</name></author><author><name>A Badhwar</name></author><author><name>J Bernal</name></author><author><name>M Betts</name></author><author><name>R Bruffaerts</name></author><author><name>MC Burkhart</name></author><author><name>I Dewachter</name></author><author><name>HM Gellersen</name></author><author><name>A Low</name></author><author><name>L Machado</name></author><author><name>CR Madan</name></author><author><name>M Malpetti</name></author><author><name>J Mejia</name></author><author><name>S Michopoulou</name></author><author><name>C Muñoz-Neira</name></author><author><name>M Peres</name></author><author><name>V Phillips</name></author><author><name>S Ramanan</name></author><author><name>S Tamburin</name></author><author><name>H Tantiangco</name></author><author><name>L Thakur</name></author><author><name>A Tomassini</name></author><author><name>A Vipin</name></author><author><name>E Tang</name></author><author><name>D Newby</name></author><author><name>J Ranson</name></author><author><name>D.J. Llewellyn</name></author><author><name>M Veldsman</name></author><author><name>T Rittman</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recent developments in artificial intelligence (AI) and neuroimaging offer new opportunities for improving diagnosis and prognosis of dementia. To synthesise the available literature, we performed a systematic review.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We systematically reviewed primary research publications up to January 2021, using AI for neuroimaging to predict diagnosis and/or prognosis in cognitive neurodegenerative diseases. After initial screening, data from each study was extracted, including: demographic information, AI methods, neuroimaging features, and results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found 2709 reports, with 252 eligible papers remaining following screening. Most studies relied on the Alzheimer’s Disease Neuroimaging Initiative (ADNI) dataset (n=178) with no other individual dataset used more than 5 times. Algorithmic classifiers, such as support vector machine (SVM), were the most commonly used AI method (47%) followed by discriminative (32%) and generative (11%) classifiers. Structural MRI was used in 71% of studies with a wide range of accuracies for the diagnosis of neurodegenerative diseases and predicting prognosis. Lower accuracy was found in studies using a multi-class classifier or an external cohort as the validation group. There was improvement in accuracy when neuroimaging modalities were combined, e.g. PET and structural MRI. Only 17 papers studied non-Alzheimer’s disease dementias.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The use of AI with neuroimaging for diagnosis and prognosis in dementia is a rapidly emerging field. We make a number of recommendations addressing the definition of key clinical questions, heterogeneity of AI methods, and the availability of appropriate and representative data. We anticipate that addressing these issues will enable the field to move towards meaningful clinical translation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.21267677" rel="alternate" title="Artificial intelligence for diagnosis and prognosis in neuroimaging for dementia; a systematic review (51 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267756</id><title>A spectrum of recessiveness among Mendelian disease variants in UK Biobank (32 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.197434+00:00</updated><author><name>Alison R. Barton</name></author><author><name>Margaux L.A. Hujoel</name></author><author><name>Ronen E. Mukamel</name></author><author><name>Maxwell A. Sherman</name></author><author><name>Po-Ru Loh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent work has found increasing evidence of mitigated, incompletely penetrant phenotypes in heterozygous carriers of recessive Mendelian disease variants. We leveraged whole-exome imputation within the full UK Biobank cohort (&lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;∼500K) to extend such analyses to 3,481 rare variants curated from ClinVar and OMIM. Testing these variants for association with 57 quantitative traits yielded 103 significant associations involving variants previously implicated in 35 different diseases. Notable examples included a &lt;italic&gt;POR&lt;/italic&gt; missense variant implicated in Antley-Bixler syndrome that associated with a 1.76 (s.e. 0.27) cm increase in height, and an &lt;italic&gt;ABCA3&lt;/italic&gt; missense variant implicated in interstitial lung disease that associated with reduced FEV1/FVC ratio. Association analyses with 1,257 disease traits yielded five additional variant-disease associations. We also observed contrasting levels of recessiveness between two more-common, classical Mendelian diseases. Carriers of cystic fibrosis variants exhibited increased risk of several mitigated disease phenotypes, whereas carriers of spinal muscular atrophy alleles showed no evidence of altered phenotypes. Incomplete penetrance of cystic fibrosis carrier phenotypes did not appear to be mediated by common allelic variation on the functional haplotype. Our results show that many disease-associated recessive variants can produce mitigated phenotypes in heterozygous carriers and motivate further work exploring penetrance mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267756" rel="alternate" title="A spectrum of recessiveness among Mendelian disease variants in UK Biobank (32 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472674</id><title>Qualifying a human Liver-Chip for predictive toxicology: Performance assessment and economic implications (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.197950+00:00</updated><author><name>Lorna Ewart</name></author><author><name>Athanasia Apostolou</name></author><author><name>Skyler A. Briggs</name></author><author><name>Christopher V. Carman</name></author><author><name>Jake T. Chaff</name></author><author><name>Anthony R. Heng</name></author><author><name>Sushma Jadalannagari</name></author><author><name>Jeshina Janardhanan</name></author><author><name>Kyung-Jin Jang</name></author><author><name>Sannidhi R. Joshipura</name></author><author><name>Mahika Kadam</name></author><author><name>Marianne Kanellias</name></author><author><name>Ville J. Kujala</name></author><author><name>Gauri Kulkarni</name></author><author><name>Christopher Y. Le</name></author><author><name>Carolina Lucchesi</name></author><author><name>Dimitris V. Manatakis</name></author><author><name>Kairav K. Maniar</name></author><author><name>Meaghan E. Quinn</name></author><author><name>Joseph S. Ravan</name></author><author><name>Ann Catherine Rizos</name></author><author><name>John F.K. Sauld</name></author><author><name>Josiah Sliz</name></author><author><name>William Tien-Street</name></author><author><name>Dennis Ramos Trinidad</name></author><author><name>James Velez</name></author><author><name>Max Wendell</name></author><author><name>Prathap Kumar Mahalingaiah</name></author><author><name>Donald E. Ingber</name></author><author><name>Daniel Levner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human organ-on-a-chip (Organ-Chip) technology has the potential to disrupt preclinical drug discovery and improve success in drug development pipelines as it can recapitulate organ-level pathophysiology and clinical responses. The Innovation and Quality (IQ) consortium formed by multiple pharmaceutical and biotechnology companies, however, systematic and quantitative evaluation of the predictive value of Organ-Chips has not yet been reported. Here, 780 Liver-Chips were analyzed to determine their ability to predict drug-induced liver injury (DILI) caused by small molecules identified as benchmarks by the IQ consortium. The Liver-Chip met the qualification guidelines across a blinded set of 27 known hepatotoxic and non-toxic drugs with a sensitivity of 80% and a specificity of 100%. With this performance, a computational economic value analysis suggests that the Liver-Chip could generate $3 billion annually for the pharmaceutical industry due to increased R&amp;amp;D productivity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472674" rel="alternate" title="Qualifying a human Liver-Chip for predictive toxicology: Performance assessment and economic implications (20 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.21266792</id><title>Rapid fluoroquinolone resistance detection in Pseudomonas aeruginosa using mismatch amplification mutation assay-based real-time PCR (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.198759+00:00</updated><author><name>Danielle E. Madden</name></author><author><name>Kate L. McCarthy</name></author><author><name>Scott C. Bell</name></author><author><name>Olusola Olagoke</name></author><author><name>Timothy Baird</name></author><author><name>Jane Neill</name></author><author><name>Kay A. Ramsay</name></author><author><name>Timothy J. Kidd</name></author><author><name>Adam G. Stewart</name></author><author><name>Shradha Subedi</name></author><author><name>Keat Choong</name></author><author><name>Tamieka A. Fraser</name></author><author><name>Derek S. Sarovich</name></author><author><name>Erin P. Price</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antimicrobial resistance (AMR) is an ever-increasing global health concern. Here, we developed two SYBR Green-based mismatch amplification mutation assays (SYBR-MAMAs) targeting GyrA T83I, D87N, D87Y, and D87H, the predominant causes of fluoroquinolone AMR in &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt;. SYBR-MAMAs were tested on 85 isolates, 45 with intermediate/full ciprofloxacin resistance. Assays identified the correct phenotype in 84% intermediate/full resistant and 100% sensitive strains. Clinical implementation of our rapid SYBR-MAMAs will permit timely treatment alterations to improve patient outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.21266792" rel="alternate" title="Rapid fluoroquinolone resistance detection in Pseudomonas aeruginosa using mismatch amplification mutation assay-based real-time PCR (14 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267798</id><title>The association between midwifery staffing levels and the experiences of mothers on postnatal wards: cross sectional analysis of routine data (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.199260+00:00</updated><author><name>Lesley Turner</name></author><author><name>David Culliford</name></author><author><name>Jane Ball</name></author><author><name>Ellen Kitson-Reynolds</name></author><author><name>Peter Griffiths</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Women have consistently reported lower satisfaction with postnatal care compared with antenatal and labour care. The aim of this research was to examine whether women’s experience of inpatient postnatal care in England is associated with variation in midwifery staffing levels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Analysis of data from the National Maternity Survey in 2018 including 17,611 women from 129 organisations. This was linked to hospital midwifery staffing numbers from the National Health Service (NHS) Workforce Statistics and the number of births from Hospital Episode Statistics. A two-level logistic regression model was created to examine the association of midwifery staffing levels and experiences in post-natal care.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The median full time equivalent midwives per 100 births was 3.55 (interquartile range 3.26 to 3.78). Higher staffing levels were associated with less likelihood of women reporting delay in discharge (adjusted odds ratio [aOR] 0.849, 95% CI 0.753 to 0.959, p=0.008), increased chances of women reporting that staff always helped in a reasonable time aOR1.200 (95% CI 1.052, 1.369, p=0.007) and that they always had the information or explanations they needed aOR 1.150 (95% CI 1.040, 1.271, p=0.006). Women were more likely to report being treated with kindness and understanding with higher staffing, but the difference was small and not statistically significant aOR 1.059 (0.949, 1.181, p=0.306).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Negative experiences for women on postnatal wards were more likely to occur in trusts with fewer midwives. Low staffing could be contributing to discharge delays and lack of support and information, which may in turn have implications for longer term outcomes for maternal and infant wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Explanation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;While we recognise that not all gestational parents identify as women; this term was chosen as it has been used in the data source which was accessed for this study and represents most people having maternities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Statement of significance (problem)&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Women report negative experiences of postnatal care compared with antenatal care and birth. There is a recognised shortage of midwives in maternity services, and this may be impacting on the quality of postnatal care.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What is already known?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is evidence that midwifery staffing levels are associated with birth outcomes but little empirical evidence on the impact of midwifery staffing levels in postnatal care&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What this paper adds?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This analysis of survey data supports previous findings that increased midwifery staffing is associated with benefits. This is the first study to examine the effects of staffing on women’s experience of postnatal care.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267798" rel="alternate" title="The association between midwifery staffing levels and the experiences of mothers on postnatal wards: cross sectional analysis of routine data (10 tweets)"/><category term="Obstetrics and Gynecology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267743</id><title>HIV Phylogenetics Reveals Overlapping Transmission Networks among Cities and Key Populations in Pakistan (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.199448+00:00</updated><author><name>Adriano de Bernardi Schneider</name></author><author><name>François Cholette</name></author><author><name>Yann Pelcat</name></author><author><name>Aaron G. Lim</name></author><author><name>Peter T. Vickerman</name></author><author><name>Adiba Hassan</name></author><author><name>Laura H. Thompson</name></author><author><name>James F. Blanchard</name></author><author><name>Faran Emmanuel</name></author><author><name>Tahira Reza</name></author><author><name>Nosheen Dar</name></author><author><name>Nadeem Ikram</name></author><author><name>Richard Pilon</name></author><author><name>Chris Archibald</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey B. Joy</name></author><author><name>Paul Sandstrom</name></author><author><name>Joel O. Wertheim</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The first case of HIV in Pakistan was documented in 1987, with multiple subtypes and circulating recombinant forms being introduced and currently circulating in the country. Since then, there has been a shift in the country from a low prevalence/high risk to a high-risk concentrated epidemic. Pakistan’s epidemic is concentrated among key populations at greater risk of HIV infection including people who inject drugs (PWID), Hijra sex workers (HSW), female sex workers (FSW), male sex workers (MSW), and men who have sex with men (MSM). This study focused on the geographical aspect as well as on the interactions between key populations at higher risk of contracting HIV. We aimed at understanding the behavior of these key populations at a molecular level with high granularity as well as investigating the possibility of multiple HIV-1 introductions in Pakistan. In this cross-sectional biological and behavioral survey, we collected dried blood spots (DBS) for the purposes of seroprevalence estimates and molecular epidemiology from individuals in 17 cities in Pakistan representing four key populations: PWID, HSW, MSW, and FSW. A total of 1153 envelope sequences (reference positions in HXB2: 7860-8274) of HIV were sequenced using a Sanger-based sequencing approach. To identify clusters based on the introduction of the virus in Pakistan from foreign countries we added 3623 publicly available HIV envelope sequences to our dataset. Phylogeographic inference suggests at least 15 independent introductions of the virus into Pakistan, with a total of 12 clusters ranging from 3 to 675 sequences in size containing sequences from Pakistan and neighboring countries exclusively. Our phylogenetic analysis shows a significant degree of connectivity and directionality suggesting broad and overlapping networks of HIV-1 transmission among cities and key populations in Pakistan.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267743" rel="alternate" title="HIV Phylogenetics Reveals Overlapping Transmission Networks among Cities and Key Populations in Pakistan (9 tweets)"/><category term="HIV/AIDS"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267714</id><title>Hepatitis C subtyping assay failure in UK patients born in Sub-Saharan Africa: implications for global treatment and elimination (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.199726+00:00</updated><author><name>Kazeem Adeboyejo</name></author><author><name>Barnabas J. King</name></author><author><name>Theocharis Tsoleridis</name></author><author><name>Alexander W. Tarr</name></author><author><name>John McLauchlan</name></author><author><name>William L. Irving</name></author><author><name>Jonathan K. Ball</name></author><author><name>C. Patrick McClure</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The newly developed direct-acting antivirals (DAAs) have revolutionised the treatment of chronic hepatitis C virus (HCV), where cohort studies have shown that cure rates as high as 98% can be achieved. Whilst genome sequencing has demonstrated that some subtypes of HCV naturally harbour drug resistance associated substitutions (RAS), these have not been considered important as previous molecular epidemiological studies have suggested that such difficult-to-treat subtypes are rare. Therefore, to optimise and streamline molecular detection and sequence-based typing of diverse RAS-containing subtypes, a novel panel of single round PCR assays was applied to HCV derived from 146 individuals, whose likely source of infection was from regions of sub-Saharan Africa (SSA). Partial NS5A and NS5B sequences were obtained from 135 HCV-positive patients born in 19 different countries from SSA but attending clinics in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Virus subtype assignments were determined by pairwise-distance analysis and compared to both diagnostic laboratory assignments and free-to-use online typing tools. We determined that routine clinical diagnostic methods incorrectly subtyped 59.0% of samples, with a further 6.8% incorrectly genotyped. Of five commonly used online tools, Geno2Pheno performed most effectively in determining a subtype in agreement with pairwise distance analysis. Considering the estimated number of HCV infections to have occurred in across Africa, this study provides a simple low-cost pathway to guide regional therapeutic choice and assist global eradication programmes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267714" rel="alternate" title="Hepatitis C subtyping assay failure in UK patients born in Sub-Saharan Africa: implications for global treatment and elimination (6 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.21267943</id><title>The quorum sensing com system regulates pneumococcal colonisation and invasive disease in a pseudo-stratified airway tissue model (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.199940+00:00</updated><author><name>Christian R. Kahlert</name></author><author><name>Susanne Nigg</name></author><author><name>Lucas Onder</name></author><author><name>Ronald Dijkman</name></author><author><name>Liliane Diener</name></author><author><name>Regulo Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Pietro Vernazza</name></author><author><name>Volker Thiel</name></author><author><name>Jorge E. Vidal</name></author><author><name>Werner C. Albrich</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Streptococcus pneumoniae (Spn) colonises respiratory epithelia but can also invade lung cells causing pneumonia. We developed an ex vivo model with human airway epithelial (HAE) cells harvested from lung biopsies to study Spn colonisation and translocation. Flow-cytometry, confocal imaging and electron microscopy studies identified the epithelial lineage with signs of differentiation (beating cilia, mucus, and tight junctions). HAE cells were challenged with Spn wild-type TIGR4 (wtSpn) or its isogenic ΔcomC quorum sensing-deficient mutant. ΔcomC mutant colonised significantly less than wtSpn at 6 h post-inoculation but at significantly higher levels at 19 h and 30 h. Translocation correlated inversely with colonisation density. Transepithelial electric resistance (TEER) decreased after pneumococcal infection and correlated with increased translocation for both strains.
Confocal imaging illustrated colocalisation of intracellular Spn with both cilia and zonulin-1 and prominent microcolony formation with wtSpn but disintegration of microcolony structures over time with ΔcomC mutant. ΔcomC caused a more pronounced release of both zonulin-1 and lactate dehydrogenase into the supernatant at later time points than wtSpn, suggesting that cytotoxicity is likely not the mechanism leading to translocation. There was a density- and time-dependent increase of inflammatory cytokines from human HAE cells infected with ΔcomC compared with wtSpn, including increased levels of the NLRP3 inflammasome-related IL-18. 
In conclusion, our experiments indicate that ComC system allows a higher organisational level of population structure resulting in microcolony formation, increased early colonisation and subsequent translocation. We propose that ComC inactivation unleashes a very different and possibly more virulent phenotype that merits further investigation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.21267943" rel="alternate" title="The quorum sensing com system regulates pneumococcal colonisation and invasive disease in a pseudo-stratified airway tissue model (6 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.21267630</id><title>Polygenic adaptation is not a major driver of disparities in disease mortality across global populations (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.200278+00:00</updated><author><name>Ujani Hazra</name></author><author><name>Joseph Lachance</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background and objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Health disparities are due to a range of socioeconomic and biological causes, and many common diseases have a genetic basis. Divergent evolutionary histories cause allele frequencies at disease-associated loci to differ across global populations. To what extent are differences in disease risks due to natural selection?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methodology&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Examining a panel of nine global populations, we identified which of the 20 most common causes of death have the largest health disparities. Polygenic risk scores were computed and compared for 11 common diseases for the same nine populations. We then used &lt;italic&gt;PolyGraph&lt;/italic&gt; to test whether differences in disease risk can be attributed to polygenic adaptation. Finally, we compared human development index statistics and polygenic risk scores to mortality rates for each population.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among common causes of death, HIV/AIDS and tuberculosis exhibited the greatest disparities in mortality rates. Focusing on common polygenic diseases, we found that genetic predictions of disease risk varied across global populations (including elevated risks of lung cancer in Europeans). However, polygenic adaptation tests largely yielded negative results when applied to common diseases. Our analyses revealed that natural selection was not a major cause of differences in disease risks across global populations. We also found that correlations between mortality rates and human development index statistics were stronger than correlations between mortality rates and polygenic predictions of disease risks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions and implications&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although evolutionary history contributes to differences in disease risks, health disparities are largely due to socioeconomic and other environmental factors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.21267630" rel="alternate" title="Polygenic adaptation is not a major driver of disparities in disease mortality across global populations (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267561</id><title>Identification of Genetic Loci Simultaneously Associated with Multiple Cardiometabolic Traits (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.200488+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexis C. Wood</name></author><author><name>Amit Arora</name></author><author><name>Michelle Newell</name></author><author><name>Victoria L. Bland</name></author><author><name>Jin Zhou</name></author><author><name>Nicola Pirastu</name></author><author><name>Jose M. Ordovas</name></author><author><name>Yann C. Klimentidis</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background and Aims&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cardiometabolic disorders (CMD) arise from a constellation of features such as increased adiposity, hyperlipidemia, hypertension and compromised glucose control. Many genetic loci have shown associations with individual CMD-related traits, but no investigations have focused on simultaneously identifying loci showing associations across all domains. We therefore sought to identify loci associated with risk across seven continuous CMD-related traits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods and Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted separate genome-wide association studies (GWAS) for systolic and diastolic blood pressure (SBP/DBP), hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c), low- and high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-C/HDL-C), waist-to-hip-ratio (WHR), and triglycerides (TGs) in the UK Biobank (N=356,574–456,823). Multiple loci reached genome-wide levels of significance (N=145-333) for each trait, but only four loci (in/near &lt;italic&gt;VEGFA, GRB14-COBLL1, KLF14&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;RGS19-OPRL1)&lt;/italic&gt; were associated with risk across all seven traits (P&amp;lt;5×10&lt;sup&gt;−8&lt;/sup&gt;). We sought replication of these four loci in an independent set of seven trait-specific GWAS meta-analyses. &lt;italic&gt;GRB14-COBLL1&lt;/italic&gt; showed the most consistent replication, revealing nominally significant associations (P&amp;lt;0.05) with all traits except DBP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our analyses suggest that very few loci are associated in the same direction of risk with traits representing the full spectrum of CMD features. We identified four such loci, and an understanding of the pathways between these loci and CMD risk may eventually identify factors that can be used to identify pathologic disturbances that represent broadly beneficial therapeutic targets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267561" rel="alternate" title="Identification of Genetic Loci Simultaneously Associated with Multiple Cardiometabolic Traits (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267748</id><title>A meta-analysis of Early Results to predict Vaccine efficacy against Omicron (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.201023+00:00</updated><author><name>David S Khoury</name></author><author><name>Megan Steain</name></author><author><name>James Triccas</name></author><author><name>Alex Sigal</name></author><author><name>Miles Philip Davenport</name></author><author><name>Deborah Cromer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the studies to date, the estimated fold-drop in neutralisation titre against Omicron ranges from 2- to over 20-fold depending on the study and serum tested. Collating data from the first four of these studies results in a combined estimate of the drop in neutralisation titre against Omicron of 9.7-fold (95% CI 5.5-17.1). We use our previously established model to predict that six months after primary immunisation with an mRNA vaccine, efficacy for Omicron is estimated to have waned to around 40% against symptomatic and 80% against severe disease. A booster dose with an existing mRNA vaccine (even though it targets the ancestral spike) has the potential to raise efficacy for Omicron to 86.2% (95% CI: 72.6-94) against symptomatic infection and 98.2% (95% CI: 90.2-99.7) against severe infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267748" rel="alternate" title="A meta-analysis of Early Results to predict Vaccine efficacy against Omicron (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267787</id><title>Social isolation and the aging brain Social isolation is linked to declining grey matter structure and cognitive functions in the LIFE-Adult panel study (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.201472+00:00</updated><author><name>L Lammer</name></author><author><name>F Beyer</name></author><author><name>M Luppa</name></author><author><name>C Sander</name></author><author><name>R Baber</name></author><author><name>C Engel</name></author><author><name>K Wirkner</name></author><author><name>M Loeffler</name></author><author><name>SG Riedel-Heller</name></author><author><name>A Villringer</name></author><author><name>AV Witte</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Social isolation is a risk factor for dementia, a devastating disease with a rapidly growing global prevalence. However, the link between social isolation and changes in brain structure and function is poorly understood, as studies are scarce in number, methodologically inconsistent and small in size. In this pre-registered analysis of a large population-based panel study, we aimed to determine the impact of social isolation on brain structures and cognitive functions central to age associated decline and dementia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods and findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We analysed data of 1992 cognitively healthy participants of the LIFE-Adult study at baseline (age range: 50-82 years) and of 1409 particpants at follow-up (average change in age: 5.89 years). We measured social isolation using the 30-point Lubben Social Network Scale (LSNS) and derived measures of grey matter structure from anatomical 3T MRIs. We employed covariate adjusted linear mixed models to test the associations of baseline social isolation and change in social isolation with hippocampal volume, cognitive functions (executive functions, memory, processing speed) and cortical thickness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found stronger baseline social isolation to be significantly associated with smaller hippocampal volumes (β = −5.5 mm&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;/LSNS point(pt), FDR q = 0.004, BF = 14.6) and lower cognitive functions (all β &amp;lt; −0.014 SD/pt, FDR q &amp;lt; 0.003, BF &amp;gt; 49). Increases in social isolation over time were linked to hippocampal volume decline (β = −4.9 mm&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;/pt, FDR q = 0.01, BF = 2.9) and worse memory performance (β = −0.013 SD/pt, FDR q = 0.04, BF = 1.1). Furthermore, we detected a significant interaction of baseline social isolation with change in age on hippocampal volume (β = −0.556 mm&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;/pt*a, q = 0.04, BF = 0.5), indicating accelerated brain aging in more isolated individuals. Moreover, social isolation cross-sectionally and longitudinally correlated with lower cortical thickness in multiple clusters in the orbitofrontal cortex, precuneus and other areas (FDR q &amp;lt; 0.05).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we provide evidence that social isolation contributes to hippocampal and cortical atrophy and subtle cognitive decline in non-demented mid-to late-life adults. Importantly, within-subject effects of social isolation were similar to between-subject effects, indicating an opportunity for targeting social isolation to reduce dementia risk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267787" rel="alternate" title="Social isolation and the aging brain Social isolation is linked to declining grey matter structure and cognitive functions in the LIFE-Adult panel study (4 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21266784</id><title>Pre-Operative Kidney Biomarkers and Risks for Death, Cardiovascular and Chronic Kidney Disease Events: The TRIBE-AKI Study (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.201824+00:00</updated><author><name>George Vasquez-Rios</name></author><author><name>Dennis G. Moledina</name></author><author><name>Yaqi Jia</name></author><author><name>Eric McArthur</name></author><author><name>Sherry G. Mansour</name></author><author><name>Heather Thiessen-Philbrook</name></author><author><name>Michael G. Shlipak</name></author><author><name>Jay L. Koyner</name></author><author><name>Amit X. Garg</name></author><author><name>Chirag R. Parikh</name></author><author><name>Steven G. Coca</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Soluble tumor necrosis factor receptor (sTNFR)1, sTNFR2, and plasma kidney injury molecule-1 (KIM-1) are associated with kidney events in patients with and without diabetes. However, their associations with clinical outcomes when obtained pre-operatively have not been explored.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The TRIBE-AKI cohort study is a prospective, multicenter, cohort study of high-risk adults undergoing cardiac surgery. We assessed the associations between pre-operative concentrations of plasma sTNFR1, sTNFR2, and KIM-1 and post-operative long-term outcomes including mortality, cardiovascular events, and chronic kidney disease (CKD) incidence or progression, ascertained after discharge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among 1378 participants included in the analysis with a median follow-up period was 6.7 (IQR 4.0-7.9), 434 (31%) patients died, 256 (19%) experienced cardiovascular events and out of 837 with available long-term kidney function data, 30% developed CKD. After adjustment for clinical covariates, each log increase in biomarker concentration was independently associated with mortality with 95%CI adjusted hazard ratios (aHRs) of 3.0 (2.3-4.0), 2.3 (1.8-2.9) and 2.0 (CI 1.6-2.4) for sTNFR1, sTNFR2 and KIM-1, respectively. For cardiovascular events, the 95%CI aHRs were 2.1 (1.5 – 3.1), 1.9 (1.4 – 2.6) and 1.6 (1.2 – 2.1) for sTNFR1, sTNFR2 and KIM-1, respectively. For CKD events, the aHRs were 2.2 (1.5 – 3.1) for sTNFR1, 1.9 (1.3 – 2.7) for sTNFR2, and 1.7 (1.3 – 2.3) for KIM-1. Despite the associations, each of the biomarkers alone or in combination failed to result in robust discrimination on an absolute basis or compared to a clinical model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;sTNFR1, sTNFR2, and KIM-1 were independently associated with longitudinal outcomes after discharge from a cardiac surgery hospitalization including death, cardiovascular and CKD events when obtained pre-operatively in high-risk individuals. Pre-operative plasma biomarkers could serve to assist during the evaluation of patients in whom cardiac surgery is planned.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21266784" rel="alternate" title="Pre-Operative Kidney Biomarkers and Risks for Death, Cardiovascular and Chronic Kidney Disease Events: The TRIBE-AKI Study (3 tweets)"/><category term="Nephrology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>