<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.784917+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.21265571</id><title>Age and disc degeneration in low back pain: automated analysis enables a magnetic resonance imaging comparison of large cross-sectional cohorts of symptomatic and asymptomatic subjects (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.785445+00:00</updated><author><name>A Jamaludin</name></author><author><name>T Kadir</name></author><author><name>A Zisserman</name></author><author><name>I McCall</name></author><author><name>FMK Williams</name></author><author><name>H Lang</name></author><author><name>E Buchanan</name></author><author><name>JP Urban</name></author><author><name>J Fairbank</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We aimed to improve understanding of the role of imaging in diagnosis of low back pain by determining the prevalence of age-related disc degeneration in asymptomatic and symptomatic subjects. Spinal MRIs of symptomatic and asymptomatic subjects were re-annotated onto the same objective grading system and prevalence of degenerative changes compared.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an exploratory cross-sectional study, we compared the prevalence of disc degeneration between two large groups of anonymised females, 30-80yrs, viz a symptomatic group with chronic back pain (724) and an asymptomatic (701) group. We used a verified automated MRI annotation system to re-annotate their spinal MRIs and report degeneration on the Pfirrmann (1-5) scale, and other degenerative changes (herniation, endplate defects, marrow signs, spinal stenosis) as binary present/absent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Severe degenerative changes were significantly more prevalent in discs of symptomatics than asymptomatics in the lower (L4-S1) but not the upper (L1-L3) lumbar discs in subjects &amp;lt;60years. We found high co-existence of several degenerative features in both populations. Degeneration was minimal in around 30% of symptomatics &amp;lt; 50years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Automated MRI provides a valuable means of rapidly comparing large MRI datasets. Here, through directly comparing MRI annotations on the same objective scales it enabled us to detect significant age and spinal-level related differences in the prevalence of degenerative features between asymptomatic and symptomatic populations. By distinguishing between symptomatics whose discs have structural defects, and symptomatics with minimal degenerative changes, MRI could provide a means of clinical stratification, and provide a useful pathway to investigate possible pain sources.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key messages&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What is already known about this subject?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even though intervertebral disc degeneration, and degenerative changes such as disc herniations, are strongly associated with low back pain, the importance of disc degeneration in development of low back pain is questioned because these degenerative changes are seen in both those with and those without low back pain; spinal MRIs are thus thought to be of little clinical value.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What does this study add?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study provides the first data on age-related degeneration in those without pain and shows the significant differences in prevalence between age-related and symptom-related disc degeneration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study provides definitive data showing that severe disc degeneration is directly implicated in a significant proportion of those with chronic low back pain, with the association with pain strongly dependent on age and spinal level&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;How might this impact on clinical practice or future developments?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study shows that even though severe disc degeneration is strongly associated with low back pain, 30% of younger (&amp;lt;50yrs) chronic low back pain patients have no evident disc degeneration detected by MRI, which is important information (currently not used) for clinicians in directing treatments (and perhaps a clearer reason for the proper use of scans).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study provides important information for those working on mechanisms, as it enables stratification between pathways of pain arising from structural defects in the disc, and those pain pathways in discs with no such structural change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.21265571" rel="alternate" title="Age and disc degeneration in low back pain: automated analysis enables a magnetic resonance imaging comparison of large cross-sectional cohorts of symptomatic and asymptomatic subjects (16 tweets)"/><category term="Orthopedics"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.21265956</id><title>Effect of electroMagnetic Interference from smartPHone On cardiac implaNtable Electronic device (EMI-PHONE study) (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.785871+00:00</updated><author><name>Sanatcha Apakuppakul</name></author><author><name>Nilubon Methachittiphan</name></author><author><name>Sirin Apiyasawat</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Smartphone can emit two types of electromagnetic waves, static field from magnet and dynamic field from calling. Previous evidence showed the interference effects from old generation of mobile phones to cardiac implantable electronic device (CIEDs). The current generation of smartphones and CIEDS are reportedly better designed to reduce electromagnetic interference (EMI). We seek to find the presence and the magnitude of EMI from the current generation of smartphones.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A total of 80 consecutive subjects with CIEDs (Included pacemaker, ICD, CRT-D, CRT-P) were recruited from our CIEDs clinic and were tested for EMI. Each subject was tested with three different smartphones (Nokia 3310, Iphone 7, and Samsung 9S). Each phone was attached to chest wall at 0 cm at pulse generator site, at atrial lead, and at ventricular lead site. During the tests, real-time interrogations were performed to detect any EMI from smartphone in stand-by mode, and during calling-in and out for 30 seconds. After the tests, post-test interrogation was performed to detect any parameters changes. Adverse events including pacemaker inhibition, false ICD shock, CIEDs device malfunction, and urgent electrophysiologist consultations were recorded.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of all 80 subjects (Mean age 70.5±12.9 year-old, 50% male) recruited in the study, all completed the tests according to our protocol. The most common type of CIEDs tested was pacemaker (N=56, 70%), followed by ICD (N=16, 20%), and CRT (N=8, 10%). Most patients (N=62, 77.5%) had more than one lead implanted. The mean year of implantation was 5.2±2.8 (Devices were implanted since 2008-2019). Of all the tests performed, there was no EMI or adverse events observed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Current generation of smartphones have no EMI effect to CIEDs and can be used safely without any adverse events including pacemaker inhibition, false ICD shock and CIEDs device malfunction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.21265956" rel="alternate" title="Effect of electroMagnetic Interference from smartPHone On cardiac implaNtable Electronic device (EMI-PHONE study) (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cardiovascular Medicine"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467852</id><title>Glomerular function and urinary biomarker changes between vancomycin and vancomycin plus piperacillin-tazobactam in a translational rat model (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.786172+00:00</updated><author><name>Jack Chang</name></author><author><name>Gwendolyn Pais</name></author><author><name>Kimberly Valdez</name></author><author><name>Sylwia Marianski</name></author><author><name>Erin F. Barreto</name></author><author><name>Marc H. Scheetz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Clinical studies have reported additive nephrotoxicity associated with the combination of vancomycin (VAN) and piperacillin-tazobactam (TZP). This study assessed differences in glomerular filtration rate (GFR) and urinary biomarkers between rats receiving VAN and those receiving VAN+TZP. Male Sprague-Dawley rats (n=26) were randomized to receive 96 hours of intravenous VAN at 150mg/kg/day, intraperitoneal TZP at 1400 mg/kg/day, or VAN+TZP. Kidney function was evaluated using fluorescein-isothiocyanate sinistrin and a transdermal sensor to estimate real-time glomerular filtration rate (GFR). Kidney injury was evaluated via urinary biomarkers including kidney injury molecule-1 (KIM-1), clusterin, and osteopontin. Compared to a saline control, only rats in the VAN group showed significant declines in GFR by day 4 (−0.39 mL/min/100 g body weight, 95% CI: -0.68 to -0.10, p=0.008). When the VAN+TZP and VAN alone treatment groups were compared, significantly higher urinary KIM-1 was observed in the VAN alone group on day 1 (18.4 ng, 95% CI: 1.4 to 35.3, p=0.03), day 2 (27.4 ng, 95% CI: 10.4 to 44.3, p=0.002), day 3 (18.8 ng, 95% CI: 1.9 to 35.8, p=0.03), and day 4 (23.2 ng, 95% CI: 6.3 to 40.2, p=0.007). KIM-1 was the urinary biomarker that most correlated with decreasing GFR on day 3 (Spearman’s rho: -0.45, p = 0.022) and day 4 (Spearman’s rho: - 0.41, p = 0.036). Kidney function decline and increased KIM-1 were observed among rats that received VAN only, but not TZP or VAN+TZP. Addition of TZP to VAN does not worsen kidney function or injury in a validated translational rat model.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467852" rel="alternate" title="Glomerular function and urinary biomarker changes between vancomycin and vancomycin plus piperacillin-tazobactam in a translational rat model (5 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467799</id><title>Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor Inhibition Prevents Caveolin-1-dependent Calcifying Extracellular Vesicle Biogenesis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.786428+00:00</updated><author><name>Amirala Bakhshian Nik</name></author><author><name>Hooi Hooi Ng</name></author><author><name>Patrick Sun</name></author><author><name>Francesco Iacoviello</name></author><author><name>Paul R. Shearing</name></author><author><name>Sergio Bertazzo</name></author><author><name>Deniel Mero</name></author><author><name>Bohdan B. Khomtchouk</name></author><author><name>Joshua D. Hutcheson</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chronic kidney disease (CKD) increases the risk of cardiovascular disease, including vascular calcification, leading to higher mortality. Release of calcifying extracellular vesicles (EVs) by vascular smooth muscle cells (VSMCs) promotes the ectopic mineralization of vessel walls. Caveolin-1 (CAV1) protein plays a key role in formation of calcifying EVs in VSMCs. Epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) co-localizes with and influences the intracellular trafficking of CAV1.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We computationally analyzed 7651 individuals in the Multi-Ethnic Study of Atherosclerosis (MESA) and Framingham cohorts to assess potential correlations between coronary artery calcium and single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) associated with elevated serum levels of EGFR. Using a diet-induced mouse model of CKD, we measured serum EGFR and assessed the potential of EGFR inhibition to prevent vascular calcification.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individuals in the MESA and Framingham cohorts with SNPs associated with increased serum EGFR exhibit elevated coronary artery calcium. Mice with CKD developed widespread vascular calcification, which associated with increased serum levels of EGFR. In both the CKD mice and human VSMC culture, EGFR inhibition significantly reduced vascular calcification by mitigating the release of CAV1-positive calcifying EVs. EGFR inhibition also increased bone mineral density in CKD mice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given that EGFR inhibitors exhibit clinical safety and efficacy in other pathologies, the current data suggest that EGFR may be an ideal target to prevent pathological vascular calcification.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Subject terms&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Growth Factors, Vascular Biology, Vascular Disease, Translational Study&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467799" rel="alternate" title="Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor Inhibition Prevents Caveolin-1-dependent Calcifying Extracellular Vesicle Biogenesis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.21265997</id><title>Hyperconnectivity and altered dynamic interactions of a nucleus accumbens network in post-stroke depression (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.786711+00:00</updated><author><name>Lena KL Oestreich</name></author><author><name>Paul Wright</name></author><author><name>Michael J O’Sullivan</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Post-stroke depression (PSD) is a common complication after stroke. To date, no consistent locus of injury is associated with this complication. Here, we probed network dynamics in four functional circuits tightly linked to major depressive disorder and investigated structural alterations within these networks in PSD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Forty-four participants with recent stroke and 16 healthy volunteers were imaged with 3T structural, diffusion and resting-state functional MRI and completed the Geriatric Depression Scale (GDS). Associations between GDS and functional connectivity were investigated within networks seeded from nucleus accumbens (NAc), amygdala and dorsolateral prefrontal cortex. In addition, the default mode network (DMN) was identified by connectivity with medial prefrontal cortex (mPFC) and posterior cingulate cortex (PCC). Circuits that exhibited altered activity associated with GDS were further investigated by extracting within-network volumetric and microstructural measures from structural images.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Functional connectivity within the NAc-seeded network and DMN correlated positively with depressive symptoms. Normal anticorrelations between these two networks were absent in patients with PSD. PCC grey matter volume as well as microstructural measures in mPFC and the medial forebrain bundle, a major projection pathway interconnecting the NAc-seeded network and links to mPFC, were associated with GDS scores.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Depression after stroke is marked by reduced mutual inhibition between functional circuits involving NAc and DMN as well as volumetric and microstructural changes within these networks. Aberrant network dynamics present in patients with PSD are therefore likely to be influenced by secondary, pervasive alterations in grey and white matter, remote from the site of injury.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.21265997" rel="alternate" title="Hyperconnectivity and altered dynamic interactions of a nucleus accumbens network in post-stroke depression (5 tweets)"/><category term="Radiology and Imaging"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.21265082</id><title>Polygenic risk prediction and SNCA haplotype analysis in a Latino Parkinson’s disease cohort (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.786930+00:00</updated><author><name>Douglas Loesch</name></author><author><name>Andrea R. V. R. Horimoto</name></author><author><name>Elif Irem Sarihan</name></author><author><name>Miguel Inca-Martinez</name></author><author><name>Emily Mason</name></author><author><name>Mario Cornejo-Olivas</name></author><author><name>Luis Torres</name></author><author><name>Pilar Mazzetti</name></author><author><name>Carlos Cosentino</name></author><author><name>Elison Sarapura-Castro</name></author><author><name>Andrea Rivera-Valdivia</name></author><author><name>Angel C. Medina</name></author><author><name>Elena Dieguez</name></author><author><name>Victor Raggio</name></author><author><name>Andres Lescano</name></author><author><name>Vitor Tumas</name></author><author><name>Vanderci Borges</name></author><author><name>Henrique B. Ferraz</name></author><author><name>Carlos R. Rieder</name></author><author><name>Artur Schumacher-Schuh</name></author><author><name>Bruno L. Santos-Lobato</name></author><author><name>Carlos Velez-Pardo</name></author><author><name>Marlene Jimenez-Del-Rio</name></author><author><name>Francisco Lopera</name></author><author><name>Sonia Moreno</name></author><author><name>Pedro Chana-Cuevas</name></author><author><name>William Fernandez</name></author><author><name>Gonzalo Arboleda</name></author><author><name>Humberto Arboleda</name></author><author><name>Carlos E. Arboleda-Bustos</name></author><author><name>Dora Yearout</name></author><author><name>Cyrus P. Zabetian</name></author><author><name>Timothy A. Thornton</name></author><author><name>Ignacio F. Mata</name></author><author><name>Timothy D. O’Connor</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Large-scale Parkinson’s disease (PD) genome-wide association studies (GWAS) and meta-analyses have, until recently, only been conducted on subjects with European-ancestry. Consequently, polygenic risk scores (PRS) constructed using PD GWAS data are likely to be less predictive when applied to non-European cohorts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using GWAS data from Nalls et al. 2019, we constructed a PD PRS for a Latino PD cohort (LARGE-PD) and tested it for association with PD status. We validated the PRS performance through testing the PD PRS in an independent cohort of Latino PD patients and by repeating the PRS analysis in LARGE-PD with the addition of 440 external Peruvian controls. To explore the global distribution of PD PRS, we utilized 1000 Genomes Project (1KGP) and Peruvian Genome Project (PGP) data to estimate PD risk allele frequencies. We also tested &lt;italic&gt;SNCA&lt;/italic&gt; haplotypes for association with PD risk using logistic regression in LARGE-PD and a European-ancestry PD cohort from the International Parkinson Disease Genomics Consortium (IPDGC).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The GWAS-significant PD PRS had an area under the receiver-operator curve (AUC) of 0.668 (95% CI: 0.640-0.695) and explained 2.2% of the phenotypic variance on the liability scale in LARGE-PD. The inclusion of external Peruvian data as controls mitigated this result, dropping the AUC 0.632 (95% CI: 0.607-0.657). In 1KGP Latinos, we found the PD PRS to exhibit a bias by ancestry. At the &lt;italic&gt;SNCA&lt;/italic&gt; locus, haplotypes differ by ancestry. Ancestry-specific &lt;italic&gt;SNCA&lt;/italic&gt; haplotypes were associated with PD status in both LARGE-PD and the IPDGC cohort (p-value &amp;lt; 0.05). Apart from rs356182, these haplotypes share as little as 14% of their variants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The PD PRS has potential for PD risk prediction in Latinos, but variability caused by admixture patterns and bias in the PD PRS calculated using only European-ancestry data limits its utility. The inclusion of diverse subjects can help elucidate PD risk loci and improve risk prediction in non-European cohorts. In the case of the &lt;italic&gt;SNCA&lt;/italic&gt; locus, by leveraging a Latino cohort, we provide orthogonal evidence for rs356182 causality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.21265082" rel="alternate" title="Polygenic risk prediction and SNCA haplotype analysis in a Latino Parkinson’s disease cohort (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.21266096</id><title>No Evidence that Ongoing HIV-Specific Immune Responses Contribute to Persistent Inflammation and Immune Activation in Persons on Long-Term ART (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.787683+00:00</updated><author><name>Adam R. Ward</name></author><author><name>Allison S. Thomas</name></author><author><name>Eva M. Stevenson</name></author><author><name>Szu-Han Huang</name></author><author><name>Sheila M. Keating</name></author><author><name>Rajesh T. Gandhi</name></author><author><name>Deborah K. McMahon</name></author><author><name>Ronald J. Bosch</name></author><author><name>Bernard J. Macatangay</name></author><author><name>Joshua C. Cyktor</name></author><author><name>Joseph J. Eron</name></author><author><name>John W. Mellors</name></author><author><name>R. Brad Jones</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;People with HIV (PWH) have persistently elevated levels of inflammation and immune activation despite suppressive antiretroviral therapy (ART), with specific biomarkers showing associations with non-AIDS-defining morbidities and mortality. We investigated the potential role of the HIV-specific adaptive immune response, which also persists under ART, in driving levels of these clinically relevant biomarkers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;HIV-specific T-cell responses and antibody concentrations were measured at study entry in the ACTG A5321 cohort, following a median of 7 years of suppressive ART. HIV persistence measures including cell-associated (CA)-DNA, CA-RNA, and plasma HIV RNA (single-copy assay) were also assessed. Plasma inflammatory biomarkers and T-cell activation and cycling were measured at a pre-ART time point and at study entry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neither the magnitudes of HIV-specific T-cell responses nor HIV antibody levels were correlated with levels of the inflammatory or immune activation biomarkers, including hs-CRP, IL-6, neopterin, sCD14, sCD163, %CD38&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;HLA-DR&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; cells, and %Ki67&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; cells – including after adjustment for pre-ART biomarker level. Magnitudes of T-cell responses to HIV-Pol were correlated with TNF-α levels, but this was confounded by several factors. Plasma HIV RNA levels were correlated with CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T-cell activation (r = 0.25, p = 0.027), but other HIV persistence parameters were not associated with these biomarkers. In mediation analysis, relationships between HIV persistence parameters and inflammatory biomarkers were not influenced by either HIV-specific T-cell responses or antibody levels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adaptive HIV-specific immune responses do not appear to contribute to the elevated inflammatory and immune activation profile associated with morbidity and mortality under long-term ART.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;HIV-specific T-cell and antibody responses persist over years of suppressive ART, but there is no evidence that these ongoing immune responses contribute to elevated levels of inflammation and immune activation in people living with HIV on long-term ART.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.21266096" rel="alternate" title="No Evidence that Ongoing HIV-Specific Immune Responses Contribute to Persistent Inflammation and Immune Activation in Persons on Long-Term ART (4 tweets)"/><category term="HIV/AIDS"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.21266020</id><title>NREM sleep signatures of memory disruption and psychiatric symptoms in young people with 22q11.2 deletion syndrome (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.788061+00:00</updated><author><name>NA Donnelly</name></author><author><name>U Bartsch</name></author><author><name>HA Moulding</name></author><author><name>C Eaton</name></author><author><name>H Marston</name></author><author><name>JE Hall</name></author><author><name>J Hall</name></author><author><name>MJ Owen</name></author><author><name>MBM van den Bree</name></author><author><name>MW Jones</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Young people with 22q11.2 Deletion Syndrome (22q11.2DS) are at increased risk of schizophrenia, intellectual disability, Attention-Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) and autism spectrum disorder. In common with these conditions, 22q11.2DS is also associated with sleep problems. We investigated whether abnormal sleep or sleep-dependent network activity in 22q11.2DS may reflect convergent, early signatures of neural circuit disruption also evident in associated neurodevelopmental conditions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We recorded high-density sleep EEG in young people (6-20 years) with 22q11.2DS (n=28) and their unaffected siblings (n=17), quantifying the associations between sleep architecture, EEG oscillations (spindles and slow-waves) and psychiatric symptoms. We also measured performance on a memory task before and after sleep.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;22q11.2DS was associated with significant alterations in sleep architecture, including a greater proportion of N3 sleep and lower proportions of N1 and REM sleep than in siblings. During NREM sleep, deletion carriers showed increased power in slow delta and sigma oscillations, increased slow-wave and spindle amplitudes, and altered coupling between spindles and slow-waves. Spindle and slow-wave amplitudes correlated positively with overnight memory in controls, but negatively in 22q11.2DS. Mediation analyses indicated that increased slow-wave amplitude in 22q11.2DS was statistically mediated via ADHD symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This first study of sleep EEG in 22q11.2DS highlights several alterations in EEG signatures of NREM sleep, some of which were associated with ADHD symptoms. ADHD symptoms have previously been associated with incident psychotic symptoms in 22q11.2DS; our findings may therefore reflect delayed or compromised neurodevelopmental processes which precede, and may be biomarkers for, psychotic disorders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.21266020" rel="alternate" title="NREM sleep signatures of memory disruption and psychiatric symptoms in young people with 22q11.2 deletion syndrome (4 tweets)"/><category term="Psychiatry and Clinical Psychology"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.21266056</id><title>Atypical action updating in a dynamic environment associated with adolescent obsessive-compulsive disorder (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.788368+00:00</updated><author><name>Aleya A. Marzuki</name></author><author><name>Matilde M. Vaghi</name></author><author><name>Anna Conway-Morris</name></author><author><name>Muzaffer Kaser</name></author><author><name>Akeem Sule</name></author><author><name>Annemieke Apergis-Schoute</name></author><author><name>Barbara J. Sahakian</name></author><author><name>Trevor W. Robbins</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Computational research had determined that adults with obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD) display heightened action updating in response to noise in the environment and neglect meta-cognitive information (such as confidence) when making decisions. These features are proposed to underlie patients’ compulsions despite knowledge they are irrational. Nonetheless, it is unclear whether this extends to adolescents with OCD as research in this population is lacking. Thus, this study aimed to investigate the interplay between action and confidence in adolescents with OCD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Twenty-seven adolescents with OCD and 46 controls completed a predictive-inference task, designed to probe how subjects’ actions and confidence ratings fluctuate in response to unexpected outcomes. We investigated how subjects update actions in response to prediction errors (indexing mismatches between expectations and outcomes) and used parameters from a Bayesian model to predict how confidence and action evolve over time. Confidence-action association strength was assessed using a regression model. We also investigated the effects of serotonergic medication.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adolescents with OCD showed significantly increased learning rates, particularly following small prediction errors. Results were driven primarily by unmedicated patients. Confidence ratings appeared equivalent between groups, although model-based analysis revealed that patients’ confidence was less affected by prediction errors compared to controls. Patients and controls did not differ in the extent to which they updated actions and confidence in tandem.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adolescents with OCD showed enhanced action adjustments, especially in the face of small prediction errors, consistent with previous research establishing ‘just-right’ compulsions, enhanced error-related negativity, and greater decision-uncertainty in paediatric-OCD. These tendencies were ameliorated in patients receiving serotonergic medication, emphasising the importance of early intervention in preventing disorder-related cognitive deficits. Confidence ratings were equivalent between young patients and controls, mirroring findings in adults OCD research.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.21266056" rel="alternate" title="Atypical action updating in a dynamic environment associated with adolescent obsessive-compulsive disorder (3 tweets)"/><category term="Psychiatry and Clinical Psychology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468191</id><title>A novel non-genetic murine model of hyperglycemia and hyperlipidemia-associated accelerated atherosclerosis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.788837+00:00</updated><author><name>Susanne Gaul</name></author><author><name>Khurrum Shahzad</name></author><author><name>Rebekka Medert</name></author><author><name>Ishan Gadi</name></author><author><name>Christina Meader</name></author><author><name>Dagmar Schumacher</name></author><author><name>Angela Wirth</name></author><author><name>Saira Ambreen</name></author><author><name>Sameen Fatima</name></author><author><name>Jes-Niels Boeckel</name></author><author><name>Hamzah Khawaja</name></author><author><name>Jan Haas</name></author><author><name>Maik Brune</name></author><author><name>Peter Paul Nawroth</name></author><author><name>Berend Isermann</name></author><author><name>Ulrich Laufs</name></author><author><name>Marc Freichel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Objective: Atherosclerosis, the main pathology underlying cardiovascular diseases is accelerated in diabetic patients. Genetic mouse models require breeding efforts which are time-consuming and costly. To establish a new non-genetic model of inducible metabolic risk factors mimicking hyperlipidemia, hyperglycemia, or both and allowing to detect phenotypic differences dependent on the metabolic stressor(s). Methods and Results: Wild type mice were injected with gain-of-function PCSK9D377Y (proprotein convertase subtilisin/kexin type 9) mutant adeno-associated viral particles (AAV) and streptozotocin and fed either a high-fat diet (HFD) or high-cholesterol/high fat-diet (Paigen diet, PD). Combined hyperlipidemic and hyperglycemic (HGHCi) mice, but not hyperlipidemia (HCi) alone, display characteristic features of accelerated atherosclerosis. Atherosclerotic plaques of HGHCi animals were larger, showed a less stable phenotype, contained more macrophages and less smooth muscle cells. These findings were observed both at early (12 weeks) and late (20 weeks) time points on both HFD or PD diet. Differences between the HGHCi and HCi model were confirmed using RNAseq analysis revealing that significantly more genes are dysregulated in mice with combined hyperlipidemia and hyperglycemia as compared to the hyperlipidemia only group. The HGHCi-associated genes were related to pathways regulating inflammation, cellular metabolism and collagen degradation. PD accelerates atherosclerosis in mice and shows plaque formation already after 8 weeks, therefore, representing a fast direct inducible hyperglycemic atherosclerosis model. Conclusion: We established a non-genetic inducible mouse model allowing comparative analyses of atherosclerosis in HCi and HGHCi conditions and its modification by diet, allowing analyses of multiple metabolic hits in mice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468191" rel="alternate" title="A novel non-genetic murine model of hyperglycemia and hyperlipidemia-associated accelerated atherosclerosis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>