<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.707546+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265881</id><title>Fidaxomicin as first line: What will it cost in the USA and Canada? (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.709365+00:00</updated><author><name>Devangi Patel</name></author><author><name>Julien Senecal</name></author><author><name>Brad Spellberg</name></author><author><name>Andrew M. Morris</name></author><author><name>Lynora Saxinger</name></author><author><name>Brent W. Footer</name></author><author><name>Emily G. McDonald</name></author><author><name>Todd C. Lee</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recent changes in the Infectious Diseases and Healthcare Epidemiology Societies of America (IDSA-SHEA) guidelines for managing &lt;italic&gt;Clostridioides difficile&lt;/italic&gt; infections (CDI) have placed fidaxomicin as first-line treatment for CDI.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To estimate the net cost of first line fidaxomicin as compared to vancomycin in the American and Canadian healthcare systems and to estimate the price points at which fidaxomicin would become cost saving.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data sources&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We identified all randomized controlled trials comparing fidaxomicin with vancomycin through the 2021 IDSA-SHEA guideline update. Medication costs were obtained from wholesale prices (US) and the Quebec drug formulary (Canada). The average cost of a CDI recurrence was established through two systematic reviews using PubMed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Study selection&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;For fidaxomicin efficacy, we included double-blind and placebo-controlled trials. For the systematic review of recurrence costs, studies were included if they were primary research articles, had a cost-analysis of CDI, included cases of recurrent CDI, and were calculated with cost parameters from American or Canadian healthcare systems. Studies were excluded if the population was solely pediatric or hospitalized.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data extraction and Synthesis&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the efficacy meta-analysis, data was pooled using a random effects model. For the costs review, literature screening was performed by 2 independent reviewers. The mean cost across identified studies was adjusted to 2021 dollars.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Outcomes and Measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The primary outcome of the meta-analysis was CDI recurrence at day 40. The primary outcome of the systematic review was the average cost of a CDI recurrence in the American and Canadian healthcare systems. The objective was to estimate the net cost per recurrence prevented and the price point below which fidaxomicin would be cost saving.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;At current drug pricing, the estimated additional cost of a 10-day course of fidaxomicin compared to vancomycin in order to prevent one recurrence was $46,178USD (95%CI $36,942-$69,267) and $13,760CAD (95%CI $11,008-$20,640), respectively. The estimated mean systemic cost of a CDI recurrence was $14,506USD and $8,588CAD, respectively. When priced below $1550USD and $800CAD, fidaxomicin was likely to become cost saving.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions and Relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The increased drug expenditure on fidaxomicin will not be offset through recurrence prevention unless fidaxomicin price is re-negotiated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key Points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Question&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;At what price point does new guideline recommendations for changing from vancomycin to fidaxomicin for first line &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; infection (CDI) therapy become cost saving?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a 10-day course, we estimated that compared to vancomycin, treatment with fidaxomicin costs an additional $46,178USD to prevent one CDI recurrence and that treating one recurrence costs $14,506USD. The current cost of fidaxomicin is only partially offset through prevention of recurrences. Upfront therapy with fidaxomicin would be cost saving if the price were reduced below $1550USD per treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Meaning&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;New guideline updates could add billions in additional drug costs for CDI treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265881" rel="alternate" title="Fidaxomicin as first line: What will it cost in the USA and Canada? (10 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.21265717</id><title>A multi-ethnic polygenic risk score is associated with hypertension prevalence and progression throughout adulthood (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.710023+00:00</updated><author><name>Nuzulul Kurniansyah</name></author><author><name>Matthew O Goodman</name></author><author><name>Tanika Kelly</name></author><author><name>Tali Elfassi</name></author><author><name>Kerri L Wiggins</name></author><author><name>Joshua C Bis</name></author><author><name>Xiuqing Guo</name></author><author><name>Walter Palmas</name></author><author><name>Kent D Taylor</name></author><author><name>Henry J Lin</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey Haessler</name></author><author><name>Yan Gao</name></author><author><name>Daichi Shimbo</name></author><author><name>Jennifer A Smith</name></author><author><name>Bing Yu</name></author><author><name>Elena Feofanova</name></author><author><name>Roelof Smit</name></author><author><name>Zhe Wang</name></author><author><name>Shih-Jen Hwang</name></author><author><name>Simin Liu</name></author><author><name>Sylvia Wassertheil-Smoller</name></author><author><name>JoAnn E Manson</name></author><author><name>Donald M Lloyd-Jones</name></author><author><name>Stephen S Rich</name></author><author><name>Ruth JF Loos</name></author><author><name>Susan Redline</name></author><author><name>Adolfo Correa</name></author><author><name>Charles Kooperberg</name></author><author><name>Myriam Fornage</name></author><author><name>Robert C Kaplan</name></author><author><name>Bruce M Psaty</name></author><author><name>Jerome I Rotter</name></author><author><name>Donna K Arnett</name></author><author><name>Alanna C Morrison</name></author><author><name>Nora Franceschini</name></author><author><name>Daniel Levy</name></author><author><name>Tamar Sofer</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used summary statistics from previously-published GWAS of systolic and diastolic BP and of hypertension to construct Polygenic Risk Scores (PRS) to predict hypertension across diverse populations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used 10,314 participants of diverse ancestry from BioMe to train trait-specific PRS. We implemented a novel approach to select one of multiple potential PRS based on the same GWAS, by optimizing the coefficient of variation across estimated PRS effect sizes in independent subsets of the training dataset. We combined the 3 selected trait-specific PRS as their unweighted sum, called “PRSsum”. We evaluated PRS associations in an independent dataset of 39,035 individuals from eight cohort studies, to select the final, multi-ethnic, HTN-PRS. We estimated its association with prevalent and incident hypertension 4-6 years later. We studied hypertension development within HTN-PRS strata in a longitudinal, six-visit, longitudinal dataset of 3,087 self-identified Black and White participants from the CARDIA study. Finally, we evaluated the HTN-PRS association with clinical outcomes in 40,201 individuals from the MGB Biobank.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compared to other race/ethnic backgrounds, African-Americans had higher average values of the HTN-PRS. The HTN-PRS was associated with prevalent hypertension (OR=2.10, 95% CI [1.99, 2.21], per one standard deviation (SD) of the PRS) across all participants, and in each race/ethnic background, with heterogeneity by background (p-value &amp;lt; 1.0×10&lt;sup&gt;-4&lt;/sup&gt;). The lowest estimated effect size was in African Americans (OR=1.53, 95% CI [1.38, 1.69]). The HTN-PRS was associated with new onset hypertension among individuals with normal (respectively, elevated) BP at baseline: OR=1.71, 95% CI [1.55, 1.91] (OR=1.48, 95% CI [1.27, 1.71]). Association was further observed in age-stratified analysis. In CARDIA, Black participants with high HTN-PRS percentiles developed hypertension earlier than White participants with high HTN-PRS percentiles. The HTN-PRS was significantly associated with increased risk of coronary artery disease (OR=1.12), ischemic stroke (OR=1.15), type 2 diabetes (OR=1.19), and chronic kidney disease (OR=1.12), in the MGB Biobank.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The multi-ethnic HTN-PRS is associated with both prevalent and incident hypertension at 4-6 years of follow up across adulthood and is associated with clinical outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.21265717" rel="alternate" title="A multi-ethnic polygenic risk score is associated with hypertension prevalence and progression throughout adulthood (10 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.21265839</id><title>Effects of non-invasive brain stimulation in dystonia: a systematic review and meta-analysis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.710572+00:00</updated><author><name>Jordan Morrison-Ham</name></author><author><name>Gillian M. Clark</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth G. Ellis</name></author><author><name>Andris Cerins</name></author><author><name>Juho Joutsa</name></author><author><name>Peter G. Enticott</name></author><author><name>Daniel T. Corp</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deep brain stimulation is a highly effective treatment of dystonia, but is invasive and associated with risks, such as intraoperative bleeding and infections. Previous research has used non-invasive brain stimulation (NIBS) in an attempt to alleviate symptoms of dystonia. The results of these studies, however, have been variable, leaving efficacy unclear. This study aimed to evaluate the effects of NIBS on symptoms of dystonia and determine whether methodological characteristics are associated with variability in effect size.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Embase and MEDLINE Complete databases were searched for articles using any type of NIBS as an intervention in dystonia patients, with changes in dystonia symptoms the primary outcome of interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meta-analysis of 26 studies demonstrated a small effect size for NIBS in reducing symptoms of dystonia (random-effects Hedges’ g = 0.21, p = .002). Differences in the type of NIBS, type of dystonia, and brain region stimulated had a significant effect on dystonia symptoms. Meta-regression revealed that 10 sessions of active stimulation, and the application of concurrent motor training programs resulted in significantly larger mean effect sizes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;NIBS has yielded small improvements to dystonic symptoms, but effect sizes depended on methodological characteristics, with more sessions of stimulation producing a larger response. Future research should further investigate the application of NIBS parallel to motor training, in addition to providing a greater quantity of sessions, to help define optimal parameters for NIBS protocols in dystonia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Registration&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;PROSPERO 2020, CRD42020175944.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.21265839" rel="alternate" title="Effects of non-invasive brain stimulation in dystonia: a systematic review and meta-analysis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265869</id><title>Phase-locked transcranial electrical brain stimulation for tremor suppression in dystonic tremor syndromes (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.711013+00:00</updated><author><name>Freek Nieuwhof</name></author><author><name>Ivan Toni</name></author><author><name>Arthur W.G. Buijink</name></author><author><name>Anne-Fleur van Rootselaar</name></author><author><name>Bart P.C. van de Warrenburg</name></author><author><name>Rick C. Helmich</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tremor is a common and burdensome symptom in patients with dystonia, which is clinically heterogeneous and often resistant to treatment. The pathophysiology is suggested to involve abnormal activity in the cerebellum and motor cortex, but the causal role of these brain regions remains to be established. Transcranial alternating current stimulaton (TACS) can suppress rhytmic cerebral activity in other tremor disorders when phase-locked to the ongoing arm tremor, but the effect on dystonic tremor syndromes is unknown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective/Hypothesis&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We aimed to establish the causal role of the cerebellum and motor cortex in dystonic tremor syndromes, and explore the therapeutic efficacy of phase-locked TACS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We applied phase-locked TACS over the ipsilateral cerebellum (N=14) and contralateral motor cortex (N=17) in dystonic tremor syndrome patients, while patients assumed a tremor-evoking posture. We measured tremor power using accelerometery during 30s stimulation periods at 10 different phase-lags (36-degrees increments) between tremor and TACS for each target. Post-hoc, TACS-effects were related to a key clinical feature: the jerkiness (regularity) of tremor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cerebellar TACS modulated tremor amplitude in a phase-dependent manner, such that tremor amplitude was suppressed or enhanced at opposite sides of the phase-cycle. This effect was specific for patients with non-jerky (sinusoidal) tremor (n=10), but absent in patients with jerky (irregular) tremor (n=4). Phase-locked stimulation over the motor cortex did not modulate tremor amplitude.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study indicates that the cerebellum plays a causal role in the generation of (non-jerky) dystonic tremor syndrome. Our findings suggest pathophysiologic heterogeneity between patients with dystonic tremor syndrome, which mirrors clinical variability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265869" rel="alternate" title="Phase-locked transcranial electrical brain stimulation for tremor suppression in dystonic tremor syndromes (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265803</id><title>Cerebello-thalamic activity drives an abnormal motor network into dystonic tremor (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.717126+00:00</updated><author><name>Freek Nieuwhof</name></author><author><name>Ivan Toni</name></author><author><name>Michiel F. Dirkx</name></author><author><name>Cecile Gallea</name></author><author><name>Marie Vidailhet</name></author><author><name>Arthur W.G. Buijink</name></author><author><name>Anne-Fleur van Rootselaar</name></author><author><name>Bart P.C. van de Warrenburg</name></author><author><name>Rick C. Helmich</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Dystonic tremor syndromes are highly burdensome and treatment is often inadequate. This is partly due to poor understanding of the underlying pathophysiology. Several lines of research suggest involvement of the cerebello-thalamo-cortical circuit and the basal ganglia in dystonic tremor syndromes, but their role is unclear. Here we aimed to investigate the contribution of the cerebello-thalamo-cortical circuit and the basal ganglia to the pathophysiology of dystonic tremor syndrome, by directly linking tremor fluctuations to cerebral activity during scanning. In 27 patients with dystonic tremor syndrome (dystonic tremor: &lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt;=23; tremor associated with dystonia: &lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt;=4), we used concurrent accelerometery and functional MRI during a posture holding task that evoked tremor, alternated with rest. Using multiple regression analyses, we separated tremor-related activity from brain activity related to (voluntary) posture holding. Using dynamic causal modelling, we tested for altered effective connectivity between tremor-related brain regions as a function of tremor amplitude fluctuations. Finally, we compared grey matter volume between patients (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt;=27) and matched controls (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt;=27).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found tremor-related activity in sensorimotor regions of the bilateral cerebellum, contralateral ventral intermediate (VIM) and ventro-oralis posterior nuclei (VOp) of the thalamus, contralateral primary motor cortex (hand area), contralateral pallidum, and the bilateral frontal cortex (laterality with respect to the tremor). Grey matter volume was increased in patients compared to controls in the portion of contralateral thalamus also showing tremor-related activity, as well as in bilateral medial and left lateral primary motor cortex, where no tremor-related activity was present. Effective connectivity analyses showed that inter-regional coupling in the cerebello-thalamic pathway, as well as the thalamic self-connection, were strengthened as a function of increasing tremor power.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These findings indicate that the pathophysiology of dystonic tremor syndromes involves functional and structural changes in the cerebello-thalamo-cortical circuit and pallidum. Deficient input from the cerebellum towards the thalamo-cortical circuit, together with hypertrophy of the thalamus, may play a key role in the generation of dystonic tremor syndrome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265803" rel="alternate" title="Cerebello-thalamic activity drives an abnormal motor network into dystonic tremor (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265744</id><title>Metabolome-defined obesity and the risk of future diabetes and mortality (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.717366+00:00</updated><author><name>Filip Ottosson</name></author><author><name>Einar Smith</name></author><author><name>Ulrika Ericson</name></author><author><name>Salvatore Di Somma</name></author><author><name>Paola Antonini</name></author><author><name>Peter M Nilsson</name></author><author><name>Céline Fernandez</name></author><author><name>Olle Melander</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Obesity is a key risk factor for type 2 diabetes, however, up to 20% of patients are normal weight. Our aim was to identify metabolite patterns reproducibly predictive of BMI, and subsequently to test if lean individuals who carry an obese metabolome are at hidden high risk of obesity related diseases, such as diabetes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We measured 109 metabolites in fasted plasma samples of 7663 individuals from two Swedish and one Italian population-based cohort. Ridge regression models were used to predict BMI using the plasma metabolites. Individuals with a predicted BMI either more than 5 kg/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; higher (overestimated) or lower (underestimated) than their actual BMI were characterized as outliers and further investigated for obesity related risk factors and future risk of diabetes and mortality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The plasma metabolome could predict BMI in all cohorts (r&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 0.48, 0.26 and 0.19). The overestimated group had a BMI similar to individuals correctly predicted as normal weight, similar waist circumference, were not more likely to change weight over time but had a 2 times higher risk of future diabetes and an 80 % increased risk of all-cause mortality. These associations remained after adjustments for obesity-related risk factors and lifestyle parameters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found that lean individuals with an obese metabolome, have an increased risk for diabetes and all-cause mortality compared to lean individuals with a healthy metabolome. Metabolomics may be used to identify hidden high-risk individuals, in order to initiate lifestyle and pharmacological interventions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265744" rel="alternate" title="Metabolome-defined obesity and the risk of future diabetes and mortality (4 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467225</id><title>Spread of Xanthomonas vasicola pv. musacearum within banana mats: implications for Xanthomonas wilt management (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.717555+00:00</updated><author><name>Walter Ocimati</name></author><author><name>Anthony F Tazuba</name></author><author><name>Guy Blomme</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Xanthomonas wilt (XW) of banana caused by Xanthomonas vasicola pv. musacearum (Xvm) does not spread to all plants physically interconnected through the rhizome when one or a few are diseased. However, the factors behind this incomplete systemic spread of Xvm are not fully known yet could inform XW management. This study explored the effect of Xvm inoculum amounts, number and size of suckers, sucker positioning on mother plant corms and other mother plant corm attributes on sucker colonization. A shorter (p &amp;lt;0.05) incubation period (17.9 vs 21.1 days) and higher (p&amp;lt;.001) cumulative number of symptomatic leaves (5.2 vs 1.6 leaves) was observed when all (high inoculum) compared to two leaves (low inoculum) were inoculated. Xvm was recovered in corms at 29 days post inoculation (dpi) in both treatments with no differences (p &amp;gt;0.05) in proportions of corms with Xvm between the treatments. However, Xvm was recovered earlier and at a higher frequency in suckers when all leaves were inoculated. Lower Xvm recoveries occurred in the lower corm sections to which most suckers were attached relative to the middle and upper corm sections. Xvm incidence in corms increased with the number of attached maiden suckers, and the dpi while it declined with increasing mother plant and corm height. Thus, Xvm spread within mats is influenced by the amount of inoculum and the physiological stage (e.g., height) of the plant and attached suckers. The position of suckers, predominantly at the bottom of corms also protects them from infection. Measures that reduce Xvm inoculum build-up in mats are thus crucial for minimizing within mat XW spread.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467225" rel="alternate" title="Spread of Xanthomonas vasicola pv. musacearum within banana mats: implications for Xanthomonas wilt management (4 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467322</id><title>AlphaFold Models Illuminate Half of Dark Human Proteins (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.717706+00:00</updated><author><name>Jessica L Binder</name></author><author><name>Joel Berendzen</name></author><author><name>Amy O Stevens</name></author><author><name>Yi He</name></author><author><name>Jian Wang</name></author><author><name>Nikolay V Dokholyan</name></author><author><name>Tudor I Oprea</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We investigate the use of confidence scores to predict the accuracy of a given AlphaFold model for drug discovery. Predicted accuracy is improved by eliminating confidence scores below 80, due to effects of disorder. 95% of models corresponding to a set of recent crystal structures are accurate at the fold level. Conformational discordance in the training set has a more significant effect on accuracy than sequence divergence. We propose criteria for models and residues that are possibly useful for virtual screening, by which AlphaFold provides models for half of understudied (dark) human proteins and two-thirds of residues in those models.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467322" rel="alternate" title="AlphaFold Models Illuminate Half of Dark Human Proteins (3 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.21265926</id><title>Whole Exome Sequencing in dense families suggests genetic pleiotropy amongst Mendelian and complex neuropsychiatric syndromes (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.717880+00:00</updated><author><name>Suhas Ganesh</name></author><author><name>Alekhya Vemula</name></author><author><name>Samsiddhi Bhattacharjee</name></author><author><name>Kezia Mathew</name></author><author><name>Dhruva Ithal</name></author><author><name>Karthick Navin</name></author><author><name>Ravi Kumar Nadella</name></author><author><name>Biju Viswanath</name></author><author><name>Sanjeev Jain</name></author><author><name>Meera Purushottam</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Whole Exome Sequencing (WES) studies have provided important insights into the genetic architecture of neuropsychiatric syndromes identifying rare and novel variants in the protein-coding sequence of the genome that impact function. Variants and genes that are central to the shared biology of these clinical syndromes may be identified by WES in families with multiple affected individuals with serious mental illnesses (F-SMI). Methods: We performed WES in 250 individuals (affected = 186, family-control = 64) from 100 families, each with 2 or more members with SMI, and 60 unrelated population-controls. Within pedigree prioritization employed criteria of 1. rarity (Minor Allele Frequency &amp;lt;0.1%, GnomAD South-Asian sample, 15308 exomes); 2. functional consequence (Loss of Function or missense deleterious in 4/5 in silico predictions). 3. sharing by 3 or more affected members within a family. Across the sample, gene-set-wide case-control association analysis was performed with Sequence Kernel Association Test, accounting for kinship. Results: In 17 families with 3 or more exome samples, we identified 79 rare predicted deleterious variants in 79 unique genes shared by 3 or more affected members and absent in 60 unrelated controls. Twenty (25.32%) genes were implicated in monogenic neurodevelopmental syndromes in Online Mendelian Inheritance in Man representing a statistically significant overrepresentation (Fishers Exact test OR = 2.47, p = 0.001). In gene-set wise SKAT, statistically significant association was noted for genes related to synaptic function (SKAT-p = 0.017). Discussion: In F-SMI based WES study, we identify private, rare, protein altering variants in genes previously implicated in monogenic Mendelian neuropsychiatric syndromes; suggesting pleotropic influences in neurodevelopment between complex and monogenic syndromes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.21265926" rel="alternate" title="Whole Exome Sequencing in dense families suggests genetic pleiotropy amongst Mendelian and complex neuropsychiatric syndromes (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265854</id><title>WOMEN’S BIRTH PREPAREDNESS AND COMPLICATION READINESS IN NIGERIA: A SYSTEMATIC REVIEW AND META-ANALYSIS (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.718075+00:00</updated><author><name>Margaret O. Akinwaare</name></author><author><name>Abimbola Oluwatosin</name></author><author><name>Olakekan Uthman</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Ike</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Globally, efforts are being made to reduce the menace of maternal death in order to achieve the sustainable development goal. Maternal death has been associated with inadequate birth preparedness and complication readiness especially in the low and middle-income countries. Therefore, this review assessed birth preparedness and complication readiness in Nigeria.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A systematic review and meta-analysis of published research articles on birth preparedness and complication readiness in Nigeria was done using PubMed, EMBASE and MEDLINE databases. All published articles from inception to November, 2018 were included in the review. A total of 8913 published articles were identified from electronic search, a total of 4440 studies were included in this review, while only 12 articles met the inclusion criteria and were included in the meta-analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pooled prevalence of ‘Good BPCR’ for all studies yielded an estimate of 58.7% (95% CI 43.9 to 72.7%). The &lt;italic&gt;I&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; statistic was 98%, indicating statistically significant heterogeneity among the studies. The percentage of women with good birth preparedness and complication readiness increases with increasing year of publication, such that women tended to be more aware good birth preparedness and complication readiness in recent years. More than half of the women had knowledge of obstetric danger signs (52.0%, 95% CI 39.5 to 64.4%, 10 studies), arranged for transportation (59.5%, 95% CI 36.2 to 80.7, 11 studies) or saved money (63.4%, 95% CI 44.7 to 80.2%, 11 studies) as part of the BPCR.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Women in Nigeria are better prepared for birth preparedness and complication readiness in recent years. Therefore, interventions to promote more adequate birth preparedness and complication readiness among women is recommended.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;PROSPERO registration number&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study protocol was registered with PROSPERO number, CRD42019123220&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key questions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What is already known?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Globally, birth preparedness and complication readiness is a concept which has been proven to be effective at increasing skilled birth attendance. It is a strategy for reducing maternal death especially in middle and lo-income countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What are the new findings?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;More pregnant women and recently delivered mothers in the Southern part of Nigeria have a better birth preparedness and complication readiness compared to their counterpart in the Northern part of the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Number of pregnant women and recently delivered mothers with good birth preparedness and complication readiness increases with increasing year of publication.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What do the new findings imply?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;This review provides data about women’s birth preparedness and complication readiness across different regions of Nigeria. Having a poorer BPCR in the Northern region of the country could be responsible for higher maternal death in the region.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;This could be used to plan interventions to improve birth preparedness and complication readiness in different regions of the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data availability statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;No data are available.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265854" rel="alternate" title="WOMEN’S BIRTH PREPAREDNESS AND COMPLICATION READINESS IN NIGERIA: A SYSTEMATIC REVIEW AND META-ANALYSIS (3 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265077</id><title>Predicting Melanoma Staging using Targeted RNA Sequencing data using Machine Learning. (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.718230+00:00</updated><author><name>Fahad Shabbir Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Furqan Bin Irfan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The aim of this study is to use machine learning to predict tumor staging and metastasis in melanoma with differentially expressed genes. Machine has been used in different clinical setting to predict different outcomes. However, it has not been used to look at predicting the diagnostic aspect of tumor staging. We used the TCGA RNA-Sequencing data on melanomas to predict tumor staging nodal and/or metastasis using deep neural networks (DNN) and random forest classifier (RF). Results: We were able to predict tumor staging (lower vs higher stage, i.e. Tis / T1 / T2 vs T3 and higher), nodal metastasis and combined nodal or distant metastasis in patients with melanomas with high accuracies. However, we need to further validate these results.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265077" rel="alternate" title="Predicting Melanoma Staging using Targeted RNA Sequencing data using Machine Learning. (3 tweets)"/><category term="Oncology"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>