<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular medical and health sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.470351+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/medical_health-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.21261912</id><title>Genomic profiles of Covishield and Covaxin breakthrough SARS-CoV-2 strains from Odisha, India (190 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.471056+00:00</updated><author><name>Arup Ghosh</name></author><author><name>Safal Walia</name></author><author><name>Roma Rattan</name></author><author><name>Amol Kanampalliwar</name></author><author><name>Atimukta Jha</name></author><author><name>Shifu Aggarwal</name></author><author><name>Sana Fatma</name></author><author><name>Niyati Das</name></author><author><name>Nirupama Chayani</name></author><author><name>Punit Prasad</name></author><author><name>Sunil K. Raghav</name></author><author><name>Ajay Parida</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Vaccine breakthrough infections pose a vast challenge in the eradication of the COVID pandemic situation. Emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern infecting the immunized individuals indicate an ongoing battle between host immunity and natural selection of the pathogen. Our report sheds light on the prominent SARS-CoV-2 variations observed in the isolates from AZD1222/Covishield and BBV152/Covaxin vaccinated subjects.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.21261912" rel="alternate" title="Genomic profiles of Covishield and Covaxin breakthrough SARS-CoV-2 strains from Odisha, India (190 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.15.21262067</id><title>Significant reduction in humoral immunity among healthcare workers and nursing home residents 6 months after COVID-19 BNT162b2 mRNA vaccination (102 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.471548+00:00</updated><author><name>David H. Canaday</name></author><author><name>Oladayo A. Oyebanji</name></author><author><name>Debbie Keresztesy</name></author><author><name>Michael Payne</name></author><author><name>Dennis Wilk</name></author><author><name>Lenore Carias</name></author><author><name>Htin Aung</name></author><author><name>Kerri St. Denis</name></author><author><name>Evan C. Lam</name></author><author><name>Christopher F. Rowley</name></author><author><name>Sarah D. Berry</name></author><author><name>Cheryl M. Cameron</name></author><author><name>Mark J. Cameron</name></author><author><name>Brigid Wilson</name></author><author><name>Alejandro B. Balazs</name></author><author><name>Christopher L. King</name></author><author><name>Stefan Gravenstein</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;High COVID-19 mortality among nursing home (NH) residents led to their prioritization for SARS-CoV-2 vaccination; most NH residents received BNT162b2 mRNA vaccination under the Emergency Use Authorization due to first to market and its availability. With NH residents’ poor initial vaccine response, the rise of NH breakthrough infections and outbreaks, characterization of the durability of immunity to inform public health policy on the need for boosting is needed. We report on humoral immunity from 2 weeks to 6-months post-vaccination in 120 NH residents and 92 ambulatory healthcare worker controls with and without pre-vaccination SARS-CoV-2 infection. Anti-spike and anti-receptor binding domain (RBD) IgG, and serum neutralization titers, were assessed using a bead-based ELISA method and pseudovirus neutralization assay. Anti-spike, anti-RBD and neutralization levels dropped more than 80% over 6 months’ time in all groups irrespective of prior SARS-CoV-2 infection. At 6 months post-vaccine, 72% of the infection-naive NH residents had neutralization titers at or below the lower limit of detection compared to 16% at 2 weeks after full vaccination. These data demonstrate a significant reduction in levels of antibody in all groups. In particular, those infection-naive NH residents had lower initial post-vaccination humoral immunity immediately and exhibited the greatest declines 6 months later. Healthcare workers, given their younger age and relative good-health, achieved higher initial antibody levels and better maintained them, yet also experienced significant declines in humoral immunity. Based on the rapid spread of the delta variant and reports of vaccine breakthrough in NH and among younger community populations, boosting NH residents may be warranted.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.15.21262067" rel="alternate" title="Significant reduction in humoral immunity among healthcare workers and nursing home residents 6 months after COVID-19 BNT162b2 mRNA vaccination (102 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.17.21262195</id><title>COVID-19 Incidence and Hospitalization Rates are Inversely Related to Vaccination Coverage Among the 112 Most Populous Counties in the United States (41 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.472206+00:00</updated><author><name>Jeffrey E Harris</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We tested whether COVID-19 incidence and hospitalization rates were inversely related to vaccination coverage among the 112 most populous counties in the United States, each with a population exceeding 600,000, and together with a combined total population of 147 million persons. We measured vaccination coverage as the percent of the total population fully vaccinated as of July 15, 2021, with the exception of 11 Texas counties, where the cutoff date was July 14, 2021. We measured COVID-19 incidence as the number of confirmed cases per 100,000 population during the 14-day period ending August 12, 2021. We measured hospitalization rates as the number of confirmed COVID-19 admissions per 100,000 population during the same 14-day period. COVID-19 incidence was significantly higher among counties in the lower half of the distribution of vaccination coverage (incidence 543.8 per 100,000 among 56 counties with mean coverage 42.61%) than among counties in the upper half of the distribution of coverage (incidence 280.7 per 100,000 among 56 counties with mean coverage 57.37%, p &amp;lt; 0.0001). Hospital admissions were also significantly higher among counties in the lower half of the distribution (55.37 per 100,000) than in the upper half of the distribution (20.48 per 100,000, p &amp;lt; 0.0001). In log-linear regression models, a 10-percentage-point increase in vaccination coverage was associated with a 28.3% decrease in COVID-19 incidence (95% confidence interval, 16.8 - 39.7%), a 44.9 percent decrease in the rate of COVID-19 hospitalization (95% CI, 28.8 - 61.0%), and a 16.6% decrease in COVID-19 hospitalizations per 100 cases (95% CI, 8.4 - 24.8%). Higher vaccination coverage is associated not only with significantly lower COVID-19 incidence, but also significantly less severe cases of the disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.17.21262195" rel="alternate" title="COVID-19 Incidence and Hospitalization Rates are Inversely Related to Vaccination Coverage Among the 112 Most Populous Counties in the United States (41 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.17.21262177</id><title>Do Covid-19 patients needing ICU admission have worse 6 months follow up outcomes when compared with hospitalized non-ICU patients? A prospective cohort study (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.472663+00:00</updated><author><name>Suleyman Yildirim</name></author><author><name>Seher Susam</name></author><author><name>Pinar Cimen</name></author><author><name>Sena Yapicioglu</name></author><author><name>Onur Sunecli</name></author><author><name>Ozlem Ediboglu</name></author><author><name>Cenk Kirakli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Introduction 
Studies focus on pathogenesis, clinical manifestations, and complications during the early phase of the coronavirus disease-19 (COVID-19). Long-term outcomes of COVID-19 patients who discharge intensive care unit (ICU) are unclear. 
Objectives
We investigated the effect of COVID-19 on lung structure, pulmonary functional, exercise capacity and quality of life in patients discharge from ICU and medical ward.
Methods
A prospective single-centre study conducted in PCR confirmed COVID-19 patients who has been discharged from University of Health Sciences, Dr. Suat Seren Chest Disease and Thoracic Surgery Teaching and Research Hospital between 15 January and 5 March 2021. Patients who followed up for more than 48 hours in ICU and more than 72 hours in medical ward were included the study. Computed tomography scores, pulmonary functional tests (PFT), 6-min walking distance and health related quality of life by SF-36 were compared between ICU and medical ward patients at 6 months after discharge.
Results	
	Seventy patients were included final analyses and 31 of them discharged from ICU. ICU patients had higher CT scores than non-ICU patients at admission (17 vs 11) and follow up visit (6 vs 0). Two-three of ICU patients had at least one abnormal finding at control CT. Advanced age (OR 1.08, 95% CI 1.02-1.15) and higher CT score at admission (OR 1.13, 95% CI 1.01-1.27) were risk factors for having radiological abnormalities at control CT.  
Conclusion
	A number of COVID-19 survivors especially with severe disease could not fully recover after 6 months of hospital discharge.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.17.21262177" rel="alternate" title="Do Covid-19 patients needing ICU admission have worse 6 months follow up outcomes when compared with hospitalized non-ICU patients? A prospective cohort study (8 tweets)"/><category term="Intensive Care and Critical Care Medicine"/><published>2021-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.21262314</id><title>Inhaled nitric oxide use in COVID19-induced hypoxemic respiratory failure. (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.473016+00:00</updated><author><name>Abhishek R. Giri</name></author><author><name>Siva Naga S. Yarrarapu</name></author><author><name>Nirmaljot Kaur</name></author><author><name>Alexander P. Hochwald</name></author><author><name>Julia Crook</name></author><author><name>Scott Helgeson</name></author><author><name>Michael F. Harrison</name></author><author><name>Neal Patel</name></author><author><name>Pramod K. Guru</name></author><author><name>Philip Lowman</name></author><author><name>Pablo Moreno-Franco</name></author><author><name>Augustine Lee</name></author><author><name>Devang K. Sanghavi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Nitric Oxide (NO) is an endogenous vasodilator that is synthesized by the vascular endothelium.  Due to its vasodilatory effect and short half-life, the use of NO as an exogenous inhaled medication (iNO) to target the pulmonary vasculature, in conditions with increased pulmonary vascular resistance, has been studied. 
The use of iNO in patients with ARDS secondary to COVID-19 has therapeutic importance in improving oxygenation. It also has potential anti-viral, anti-inflammatory, and anti-thrombotic properties.
Herein, we want to share our experience of use of iNO in hypoxemic respiratory failure secondary to COVID 19 pneumonia. We hypothesized that iNO may be beneficial at preventing intubation, decreasing invasive mechanical ventilation duration, and consequently improve outcomes including hospital mortality.

Methods: This is a descriptive hypothesis generating study of patients admitted for COVID-19 pneumonia who received iNO for hypoxemic respiratory failure, at a single tertiary care center. We collected information on patient demographics, co-morbidities, iNO treatment, need for intubation, arterial blood gas analysis, laboratory values, hospital length of stay, and mortality. Patients were divided into two groups based on the timing of iNO administration: group 1 - pre-intubation (i.e. iNO started at least 1 day prior to endotracheal intubation, if any) and group 2 - post-intubation (i.e. iNO started on the same day as or after endotracheal intubation and mechanical ventilation). 

Result: A total of 45 (group 1, n=26 [57.8%] vs group2, n=19 [42.2%]) COVID 19 patients who had iNO use. The mean time from hospital admission to iNO administration(days) in group 1 was 2.1 (1.8, SD) vs 4.2 (5.9, SD) in group 2. The mean hospital length of stay from the beginning of iNO treatment until discharge or death was 18.3 vs 26.2 days, with 8 deaths (30.8%) vs 9 deaths (47.4%) in group 1 vs group 2, respectively. 
Discussion:
Our study is unable to demonstrate comparably outcomes benefit of iNO. Although there was a trend towards decreased  need for  invasive mechanical ventilation in group 1[Only 11 (42.3 %) patients were intubated out of 26 who received iNO early after hospital admission (2.3 days)], no statistical significance could be achieved because of small sample size. 
Our study demonstrated that iNO administration pre-intubation did not appear harmful and appears to be safe, complementary to HFNC,  signalling the domain where systematic investigation is required to confirm or not the potential for iNO to improve patient outcomes in the management of COVID  19-induced hypoxemic respiratory failure.
Conclusion:
This study showcases the potential benefit of early pre-intubation use of iNO in COVID patients with hypoxemic respiratory failure. This study could conclusively form the basis for a prospective trial and could have a tremendous impact in improving patient outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.21262314" rel="alternate" title="Inhaled nitric oxide use in COVID19-induced hypoxemic respiratory failure. (7 tweets)"/><category term="Intensive Care and Critical Care Medicine"/><published>2021-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.17.21262170</id><title>The Rapid Assessment of Aggregated Wastewater Samples for Genomic Surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 on a City-Wide Scale (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.473466+00:00</updated><author><name>Eric Christian Rouchka</name></author><author><name>Julia H. Chariker</name></author><author><name>Kumar Saurabh</name></author><author><name>Sabine Waigel</name></author><author><name>Wolfgang Zacharias</name></author><author><name>Mei Zhang</name></author><author><name>Daymond Talley</name></author><author><name>Ian Santisteban</name></author><author><name>Madeline Puccio</name></author><author><name>Sarah Moyer</name></author><author><name>Rochelle Holm</name></author><author><name>Ray Yeager</name></author><author><name>Kevin J Sokoloski</name></author><author><name>Joshua Fuqua</name></author><author><name>Aruni Bhatnagar</name></author><author><name>Ted Smith</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Throughout the course of the ongoing SARS-CoV-2 pandemic there has been a need for approaches that enable rapid monitoring of public health using an unbiased and minimally invasive means. A major way this has been accomplished is through the regular assessment of wastewater samples by qRT-PCR to detect the prevalence of viral nucleic acid with respect to time and location. Further expansion of SARS-CoV-2 wastewater monitoring efforts to include the detection of variants of interest / concern through next-generation sequencing have enhanced the understanding of the SARS-CoV-2 outbreak. In this report we detail the results of a collaborative effort between public health and metropolitan wastewater management authorities and the University of Louisville to monitor the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic through the monitoring of aggregate wastewater samples over a period of 28 weeks. Our data indicates that wastewater monitoring of water quality treatment centers and smaller neighborhood-scale catchment areas is a viable means by which the prevalence and genetic variation of SARS-CoV-2 within a metropolitan community of approximately one million individuals may be monitored. Importantly, these efforts confirm that regional emergence and spread of variants of interest / concern may be detected as readily in aggregate wastewater samples as compared to the individual wastewater sheds.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.17.21262170" rel="alternate" title="The Rapid Assessment of Aggregated Wastewater Samples for Genomic Surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 on a City-Wide Scale (6 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.21262116</id><title>To share or not to share – What the general public thinks about global COVID-19 vaccine distribution (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.473860+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthias Klumpp</name></author><author><name>Ida G. Monfared</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Vollmer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We conducted representative surveys among the adult population in Germany (n=1,003) and the United States (n=1,000) with discrete choice experiments and analytical hierarchy process items to elicit opinions about global COVID-19 vaccine distribution. Results unveil a high consent towards utilitarian or egalitarian distribution principles, prioritizing countries with weak health care systems and high numbers of current cases or deaths. This implies that the public in Germany and the United States has very well understood the global nature of the pandemic and how important sharing of resources and vaccines really is.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The people in Germany and the United States favor utilitarian or egalitarian distribution principles for global COVID-19 vaccine distribution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.21262116" rel="alternate" title="To share or not to share – What the general public thinks about global COVID-19 vaccine distribution (6 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.17.21262183</id><title>The association between immunosuppressants use and COVID-19 adverse outcome: National COVID-19 cohort in South Korea (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.474183+00:00</updated><author><name>Hyun Joon Shin</name></author><author><name>Ronald Chow</name></author><author><name>Hyerim Noh</name></author><author><name>Jongseong Lee</name></author><author><name>Jihui Lee</name></author><author><name>Young-Geun Choi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: There is uncertainty of the effect of immunosuppression, including corticosteroids, before COVID-19 infection on COVID-19 outcomes. The aim of this study was to investigate the relationship between prehospitalization immunosuppressants use (exposure), and COVID-19 patient outcomes. 

Methods: We conducted a population-based retrospective cohort study using a nationwide healthcare claims database of South Korea as of May 15, 2020. Confirmed COVID-19 infection in hospitalized individuals aged 40 years or older were included for analysis. We defined exposure variable by using inpatient and outpatient prescription records of immunosuppressants from the database. Our primary outcome was a composite endpoint of all-cause death, intensive care unit (ICU) admission, and mechanical ventilation use. Inverse probability of treatment weighting (IPTW)-adjusted logistic regression analyses were used, to estimate odds ratio (OR) and 95% confidence intervals, comparing immunosuppressants users and non-users.
 
Findings: We identified 4,349 patients, for which 1,356 were immunosuppressants users and 2,903 were non-users. Patients who used immunosuppressants were at increased odds of the primary outcome of all-cause death, ICU admission and mechanical ventilation use (IPTW OR 1.32; 95% CI: 1.06 - 1.63). Patients who used corticosteroids were at increased odds of the primary outcome (IPTW OR 1.33; 95% CI: 1.07 - 1.64). 

Interpretation: We support the latest guidelines from the CDC, that people on immunosuppressants are at high risk of severe COVID-19 and immunocompromised people may need booster COVID-19 vaccinations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.17.21262183" rel="alternate" title="The association between immunosuppressants use and COVID-19 adverse outcome: National COVID-19 cohort in South Korea (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>