<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv genomics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.488008+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genomics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444077</id><title>Comparative and systems analyses of Leishmania spp. non-coding RNAs through developmental stages (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.488348+00:00</updated><author><name>J. Eduardo Martinez-Hernandez</name></author><author><name>Victor Aliaga-Tobar</name></author><author><name>Carolina González</name></author><author><name>Rubens Monte-Neto</name></author><author><name>Alberto J. M. Martin</name></author><author><name>Vinicius Maracaja-Coutinho</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; spp. is the causal agent of several diseases called leishmaniases, neglected diseases that seek to be eradicated in the coming years. We aimed to study the genomic structure and function of non-coding RNAs (ncRNAs) from &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; spp. and to get insights into its RNAome. We studied 26 strains corresponding to 16 different species of &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; genus. RNAome analysis revealed the presence of several ncRNAs that are shared through different species, allowing us to differentiate between subgenus and as well as species that are canonically related to visceral leishmaniasis. We found coexpression relationships within coding genes and ncRNAs, thus suggesting possible functional relationships between different coding genes-ncRNAs. Expression analysis in the metacyclic developmental stage comparison for &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania braziliensis&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania major&lt;/italic&gt; reveals the presence of shared coexpressed ncRNAs to several other coding genes in both species involved in chromatin structure and host interaction. This work constitutes the first effort to characterize the &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; RNAome, supporting further approaches to better understand the role of ncRNAs in the gene regulation, infective process and host-parasite interaction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;AUTHOR SUMMARY&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leishmaniasis is a worldwide tropical neglected disease, which is endemic in several countries of America, Africa, Asia and Europe. &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; parasites are transmitted to mammal hosts by the bite of female sandflies. Currently, more than one million of the new infections are reported mainly in the Americas, the Mediterranean basin, the Middle East and Central Asia. The genomic knowledge of these parasites have increased since the first draft genome was published in 2005, however the role of non-coding RNAs in pathogenesis and development is still an open avenue. Here we use a system and comparative genomic approach to characterize and predict the function of the whole ncRNA repertoire in &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; parasites. Although &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; presents a large amount of ncRNA, there is a low conservation rate, however it is directly proportional to phylogenetic relationships. We also found that this conserved ncRNA was related to histone regulation and proteophosphoglycan ppg3 co-expression. Our study provides new insights in our knowledge about function and expression patterns of ncRNA and their relationship with &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; chromatin regulation and virulence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444077" rel="alternate" title="Comparative and systems analyses of Leishmania spp. non-coding RNAs through developmental stages (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.444856</id><title>Transcriptomics of improved fruit retention by hexanal in ‘Honeycrisp’ reveals hormonal crosstalk and reduced cell-wall remodelling in the fruit-abscission zone (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.488677+00:00</updated><author><name>Karthika Sriskantharajah</name></author><author><name>Walid El Kayal</name></author><author><name>Davoud Torkamaneh</name></author><author><name>Murali Mohan Ayyanath</name></author><author><name>Praveen Saxena</name></author><author><name>Alan J Sullivan</name></author><author><name>Gopinadhan Paliyath</name></author><author><name>Jayasankar Subramanian</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Apples (&lt;italic&gt;Malus domestica&lt;/italic&gt; Borkh) are prone to pre-harvest fruit drop which is more pronounced in ‘Honeycrisp’. Using a transcriptomic approach, we analyzed the molecular mechanisms of fruit retention in ‘Honeycrisp’. A total of 726 differentially expressed genes (DEGs) were identified in the abscission zone of hexanal-treated and untreated fruit (FAZ). Hexanal down-regulated the genes involved in ethylene biosynthesis, such as S-adenosylmethionine synthase (&lt;italic&gt;SAM2&lt;/italic&gt;) and 1-aminocyclopropane-1carboxylic acid oxidases (&lt;italic&gt;ACO3&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;ACO4&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;ACO4&lt;/italic&gt;-&lt;italic&gt;like&lt;/italic&gt;). Genes related to ABA biosynthesis (&lt;italic&gt;FDPS&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;CLE25&lt;/italic&gt;) were also down-regulated. On the contrary, gibberellic acid (GA) biosynthesis genes, gibberellin 20 oxidase1-like (&lt;italic&gt;GA20OX&lt;/italic&gt;-&lt;italic&gt;like&lt;/italic&gt;) and ent-kaurene oxidase (&lt;italic&gt;KO&lt;/italic&gt;) were up-regulated. Further, hexanal down-regulated the expression of genes related to cell-wall remodelling enzymes such as polygalacturonase (&lt;italic&gt;PG1&lt;/italic&gt;), glucanases (endo-β-1,4-glucanase; EG) and expansins (&lt;italic&gt;EXPA1&lt;/italic&gt;-&lt;italic&gt;like, EXPA6, EXPA8, EXPA10&lt;/italic&gt;-&lt;italic&gt;like, EXPA16&lt;/italic&gt;-&lt;italic&gt;like&lt;/italic&gt;). Hexanal also reduced ethylene, and abscisic acid (ABA) production at commercial harvest stage. Hexanal reduced ethylene production in fruits and thus reduced the sensitivity of FAZ cells to ethylene and ABA. Simultaneously, hexanal maintained the cell-wall integrity of FAZ cells by regulating genes involved in cell-wall modifications. Our findings show that fruit abscission is delayed by hexanal, by down regulating ABA through an ethylene-dependent mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlight&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hexanal, a naturally occurring plant compound, increased fruit retention in apples by decreasing ethylene and ABA production and maintaining the cell-wall integrity in the fruit abscission zone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.444856" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptomics of improved fruit retention by hexanal in ‘Honeycrisp’ reveals hormonal crosstalk and reduced cell-wall remodelling in the fruit-abscission zone (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>