<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv genomics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.427764+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genomics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.29.446263</id><title>Genome of the giant panda roundworm illuminates its host shift and parasitic adaptation (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.428421+00:00</updated><author><name>Yue Xie</name></author><author><name>Sen Wang</name></author><author><name>Shuangyang Wu</name></author><author><name>Shenghan Gao</name></author><author><name>Qingshu Meng</name></author><author><name>Chengdong Wang</name></author><author><name>Jingchao Lai</name></author><author><name>Li Luo</name></author><author><name>Xuan Zhou</name></author><author><name>Jing Xu</name></author><author><name>Xiaobin Gu</name></author><author><name>Ran He</name></author><author><name>Zijiang Yang</name></author><author><name>Xuerong Peng</name></author><author><name>Songnian Hu</name></author><author><name>Guangyou Yang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Baylisascaris schroederi, a bamboo-feeding giant panda (Ailuropoda melanoleuca)-specific roundworm (ascaridoid) parasite, is the causative agent of baylisascariasis, which represents a leading reason for the mortality of wild giant panda populations and therefore poses a significant threat to giant panda conservation. Here we present a 293-Mb chromosome-level genome assembly of B. schroederi to inform its biology, including host adaptations. Comparative genomics revealed an evolutionary trajectory accompanied by host-shift events in ascaridoid parasite lineages after host separations, suggesting their potential transmissions and fast adaptations to hosts. Genomic and anatomical lines of evidence, including expansion and positive selection of genes related to cuticle and basal metabolisms, indicates that B. schroederi undergoes specific adaptations to survive in the sharp-edged bamboo enriched gut of giant panda by structurally increasing its cuticle thickness and efficiently utilizing host nutrients during gut parasitism. Also, we characterized the secretome and predicted potential drug and vaccine targets for new interventions. Overall, this genome resource provides new insights into the host adaptation of B. schroederi to giant panda as well as the host-shift events in ascaridoid parasite lineages. These findings also add to our knowledge on the unique biology of the giant panda roundworm and aid the development of much-needed novel strategies for the control of baylisascariasis and thus the protection of giant panda populations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.29.446263" rel="alternate" title="Genome of the giant panda roundworm illuminates its host shift and parasitic adaptation (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.446128</id><title>Comparative chromatin accessibility upon BDNF-induced neuronal activity delineates neuronal regulatory elements (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.429050+00:00</updated><author><name>Ignacio L. Ibarra</name></author><author><name>Vikram S. Ratnu</name></author><author><name>Lucia Gordillo</name></author><author><name>In-Young Hwang</name></author><author><name>Luca Mariani</name></author><author><name>Kathryn Weinand</name></author><author><name>Henrik M. Hammaren</name></author><author><name>Martha L. Bulyk</name></author><author><name>Mikhail M. Savitski</name></author><author><name>Judith B Zaugg</name></author><author><name>Kyung-Min Noh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neuronal activity induced by brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF) triggers gene expression, which is crucial for neuronal survival, differentiation, synaptic plasticity, memory formation, and neurocognitive health. However, its role in chromatin regulation is unclear. Here, using temporal profiling of chromatin accessibility and transcription in mouse primary cortical neurons upon either BDNF stimulation or depolarization (KCl), we identify features that define BDNF-specific chromatin-to-gene expression programs. Enhancer activation is an early event in the regulatory control of BDNF-treated neurons, where the bZIP motif-binding Fos protein pioneered chromatin opening and cooperated with co-regulatory transcription factors (Homeobox, EGRs, and CTCF) to induce transcription. Deleting cis-regulatory sequences decreased BDNF-mediated Arc expression, a regulator of synaptic plasticity. BDNF-induced accessible regions are linked to preferential exon usage by neurodevelopmental disorder-related genes and heritability of neuronal complex traits, which were validated in human iPSC-derived neurons. Thus, we provide a comprehensive view of BDNF-mediated genome regulatory features using comparative genomic approaches to dissect mammalian neuronal activity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.446128" rel="alternate" title="Comparative chromatin accessibility upon BDNF-induced neuronal activity delineates neuronal regulatory elements (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>