<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv genomics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.759001+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genomics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450255</id><title>SLOW5: a new file format enables massive acceleration of nanopore sequencing data analysis (113 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.759455+00:00</updated><author><name>Hasindu Gamaarachchi</name></author><author><name>Hiruna Samarakoon</name></author><author><name>Sasha P. Jenner</name></author><author><name>James M. Ferguson</name></author><author><name>Timothy G. Amos</name></author><author><name>Jillian M. Hammond</name></author><author><name>Hassaan Saadat</name></author><author><name>Martin A. Smith</name></author><author><name>Sri Parameswaran</name></author><author><name>Ira W. Deveson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nanopore sequencing is an emerging genomic technology with great potential. However, the storage and analysis of nanopore sequencing data have become major bottlenecks preventing more widespread adoption in research and clinical genomics. Here, we elucidate an inherent limitation in the file format used to store raw nanopore data – known as FAST5 – that prevents efficient analysis on high-performance computing (HPC) systems. To overcome this, we have developed SLOW5, an alternative file format that permits efficient parallelisation and, thereby, acceleration of nanopore data analysis. For example, we show that using SLOW5 format, instead of FAST5, reduces the time and cost of genome-wide DNA methylation profiling by an order of magnitude on common HPC systems, and delivers consistent improvements on a wide range of different architectures. With a simple, accessible file structure and a &lt;sup&gt;~&lt;/sup&gt;25% reduction in size compared to FAST5, SLOW5 format will deliver substantial benefits to all areas of the nanopore community.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450255" rel="alternate" title="SLOW5: a new file format enables massive acceleration of nanopore sequencing data analysis (113 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.03.450759</id><title>Genomic evolution of the globally disseminated multidrug-resistant Klebsiella pneumoniae clonal group 147 (40 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.759872+00:00</updated><author><name>Carla Rodrigues</name></author><author><name>Siddhi Desai</name></author><author><name>Virginie Passet</name></author><author><name>Devarshi Gajjar</name></author><author><name>Sylvain Brisse</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: The rapid emergence of multidrug-resistant Klebsiella pneumoniae (Kp) is largely driven by the spread of specific clonal groups (CG). Of these, CG147 includes 7-gene MLST sequence types ST147, ST273 and ST392. CG147 has caused nosocomial outbreaks across the world, but its global population dynamics remain unknown. Here, we report a pandrug-resistant ST147 clinical isolate from India (strain DJ) and define the evolution and global emergence of CG147. Methods: Antimicrobial susceptibility testing (EUCAST guidelines) and genome sequencing (Illumina and Oxford Nanopore technologies, Unicycler assembly) were performed on strain DJ. Additionally, we collated 217 publicly available CG147 genomes (NCBI, May 2019). CG147 evolution was inferred within a temporal phylogenetic framework (BEAST) based on a recombination-free sequence alignment (Roary/Gubbins). Comparative genomic analyses focused on resistance and virulence genes and other genetic elements (BIGSdb, Kleborate, PlasmidFinder, PHASTER, ICEFinder and CRISPRCasFinder). Results: Strain DJ had a pandrug resistance phenotype. Its genome comprised 7 plasmids and 1 linear phage-plasmid. Four carbapenemase genes were detected: blaNDM-5 and 2 copies of blaOXA-181 in the chromosome, and a second copy of blaNDM-5 on an 84 kb IncFII plasmid. CG147 genomes carried a mean of 13 acquired resistance genes or mutations; 63% carried a carbapenemase gene and 83% harbored blaCTX-M. All CG147 genomes presented GyrA and ParC mutations and a common subtype IV-E CRISPR-Cas system. ST392 and ST273 emerged in 2005 and 1995, respectively. ST147, the most represented phylogenetic branch, was itself divided into two main clades with distinct capsular loci: KL64 (74%, DJ included, emerged in 1994 and disseminated worldwide, with carbapenemases varying among world regions) and KL10 (20%, 2002, predominantly found in Asian countries, associated with carbapenemases NDM and OXA-48-like). Further, subclades within ST147-KL64 differed in the yersiniabactin locus, OmpK35/K36 mutations, plasmid replicons and prophages. The absence of IncF plasmids in some subclades was associated with a possible activity of a CRISPR-Cas system. Conclusions: K. pneumoniae clonal group CG147 comprises pandrug- or extensively-resistant isolates and carries multiple and diverse resistance genes and mobile genetic elements, including chromosomal blaNDM-5. Its emergence is driven by the spread of several phylogenetic clades marked by their own genomic features and specific temporo-spatial dynamics. These findings highlight the need for precision surveillance strategies to limit the spread of particularly concerning CG147 subsets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.03.450759" rel="alternate" title="Genomic evolution of the globally disseminated multidrug-resistant Klebsiella pneumoniae clonal group 147 (40 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.02.450803</id><title>Chasing perfection: validation and polishing strategies for telomere-to-telomere genome assemblies (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.760155+00:00</updated><author><name>Ann M Mc Cartney</name></author><author><name>Kishwar Shafin</name></author><author><name>Michael Alonge</name></author><author><name>Andrey V Bzikadze</name></author><author><name>Giulio Formenti</name></author><author><name>Arkarachai Fungtammasan</name></author><author><name>Kerstin Howe</name></author><author><name>Chirag Jain</name></author><author><name>Sergey Koren</name></author><author><name>Glennis A Logsdon</name></author><author><name>Karen H Miga</name></author><author><name>Alla Mikheenko</name></author><author><name>Benedict Paten</name></author><author><name>Alaina Shumate</name></author><author><name>Daniela C Soto</name></author><author><name>Ivan Sovic</name></author><author><name>Jonathon MD Wood</name></author><author><name>Justin M Zook</name></author><author><name>Adam M. Phillippy</name></author><author><name>Arang Rhie</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Advances in long-read sequencing technologies and genome assembly methods have enabled the recent completion of the first Telomere-to-Telomere (T2T) human genome assembly, which resolves complex segmental duplications and large tandem repeats, including centromeric satellite arrays in a complete hydatidiform mole (CHM13). Though derived from highly accurate sequencing, evaluation revealed that the initial T2T draft assembly had evidence of small errors and structural misassemblies. To correct these errors, we designed a novel repeat-aware polishing strategy that made accurate assembly corrections in large repeats without overcorrection, ultimately fixing 51% of the existing errors and improving the assembly QV to 73.9. By comparing our results to standard automated polishing tools, we outline common polishing errors and offer practical suggestions for genome projects with limited resources. We also show how sequencing biases in both PacBio HiFi and Oxford Nanopore Technologies reads cause signature assembly errors that can be corrected with a diverse panel of sequencing technologies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.02.450803" rel="alternate" title="Chasing perfection: validation and polishing strategies for telomere-to-telomere genome assemblies (24 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450365</id><title>Single Cell T Cell Receptor Repertoire Profiling for Dogs (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.760595+00:00</updated><author><name>Zachary L. Skidmore</name></author><author><name>Hans Rindt</name></author><author><name>Shirley Chu</name></author><author><name>Bryan Fisk</name></author><author><name>Catrina Fronick</name></author><author><name>Robert Fulton</name></author><author><name>Mingyi Zhou</name></author><author><name>Nathan J. Bivens</name></author><author><name>Carol N. Reinero</name></author><author><name>Malachi Griffith</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey N. Bryan</name></author><author><name>Obi L. Griffith</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spontaneous cancers in companion dogs are increasingly recognized as robust models of human disease. This recognition has led to translational clinical trials in companion dogs with osteosarcoma, lymphoma, melanoma, squamous cell carcinoma, and soft tissue sarcoma. The ability to precisely track tumor-specific immune responses in such clinical trials would benefit from reagents to perform species-specific single cell T cell receptor sequencing (scTCRseq). This technology defines clones of T cells reacting to immune interventions and can help identify the specific epitope of response. Single cell gene expression data give insights into the activity and polarization of the T cell. To date, scTCRseq has not been demonstrated for canine samples.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Samples from two responding dogs in a trial of an autologous deglycosylated melanoma vaccine were selected to demonstrate applicability of scTCRseq in a cancer immunotherapy setting. A single-cell suspension of cryopreserved peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) was prepared for 10X single cell sequencing. Full length 10X cDNA was amplified using a custom-designed nested PCR of the alpha/beta V(D)J region. A library made from this enriched product (scTCRseq) and a 10X gene expression (GEX) library (scRNAseq) were sequenced on the NovaSeq 6000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;1,850-2,172 estimated V(D)J-expressing cells yielded 87-103.7 million reads with 73.8%-75.8% mapped to a V(D)J gene (beta/alpha chains ratio 1.5:1). 43 TRAJ, 29 TRAV, 12 TRBJ, and 22 TRBV gene segments were observed representing 72.9%, 51.8%, 100%, and 62.9% of all known V and J gene segments respectively. A large diversity of clonotypes was captured with 966-1,253 TRA/TRB clonotypes identified. Both dogs also exhibited a small number of highly abundant T cell clonotypes suggesting the presence of an anti-tumor T cell population. GEX enriched libraries successfully defined large clusters of CD8+ and CD4+ T cells that overlapped with V(D)J-expressing cells.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Discussion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The developed reagents successfully generated scTCRseq data, for the first time, which allowed the T cell repertoire to be surveyed in dogs responding to anti-tumor immunotherapy. These reagents will allow longitudinal tracking of anti-tumor T cell dynamics in canine cancer immunotherapy trials.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450365" rel="alternate" title="Single Cell T Cell Receptor Repertoire Profiling for Dogs (12 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450414</id><title>Probing molecular specificity with deep sequencing and biophysically interpretable machine learning (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.760882+00:00</updated><author><name>H. Tomas Rube</name></author><author><name>Chaitanya Rastogi</name></author><author><name>Siqian Feng</name></author><author><name>Judith F. Kribelbauer</name></author><author><name>Allyson Li</name></author><author><name>Basheer Becerra</name></author><author><name>Lucas A. N. Melo</name></author><author><name>Bach Viet Do</name></author><author><name>Xiaoting Li</name></author><author><name>Hammaad H. Adam</name></author><author><name>Neel H. Shah</name></author><author><name>Richard S. Mann</name></author><author><name>Harmen J. Bussemaker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Quantifying sequence-specific protein-ligand interactions is critical for understanding and exploiting numerous cellular processes, including gene regulation and signal transduction. Next-generation sequencing (NGS) based assays are increasingly being used to profile these interactions with high-throughput. However, these assays do not provide the biophysical parameters that have long been used to uncover the quantitative rules underlying sequence recognition. We developed a highly flexible machine learning framework, called ProBound, to define sequence recognition in terms of biophysical parameters based on NGS data. ProBound quantifies transcription factor (TF) behavior with models that accurately predict binding affinity over a range exceeding that of previous resources, captures the impact of DNA modifications and conformational flexibility of multi-TF complexes, and infers specificity directly from &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; data such as ChIP-seq without peak calling. When coupled with a new assay called Kd-seq, it determines the absolute affinity of protein-ligand interactions. It can also profile the kinetics of kinase-substrate interactions. By constructing a biophysically robust foundation for profiling sequence recognition, ProBound opens up new avenues for decoding biological networks and rationally engineering protein-ligand interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450414" rel="alternate" title="Probing molecular specificity with deep sequencing and biophysically interpretable machine learning (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>