<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv genomics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.608840+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genomics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.12.448184</id><title>Improved SNV discovery in barcode-stratified scRNA-seq alignments (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.609207+00:00</updated><author><name>NM Prashant</name></author><author><name>Hongyu Liu</name></author><author><name>Christian Dillard</name></author><author><name>Helen Ibeawuchi</name></author><author><name>Turkey Alsaeedy</name></author><author><name>Kwan Hang Chan</name></author><author><name>Anelia Horvath</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single cell SNV analysis is an emerging and promising strategy to connect cell-level genetic variation to cell phenotypes. At the present, SNV detection from 10x Genomics scRNA-seq data is typically performed on the pooled sequencing reads across all cells in a sample. Here, we assess the gain of information of SNV assessments from individual cell scRNA-seq data, where the alignments are split by barcode prior to the variant call. For our analyses we use publicly available sequencing da-ta on the human breast cancer cell line MCF7 cell line generated at consequent time-points during anticancer treatment. We analysed SNV calls by three popular variant callers, GATK, Strelka2 and Mutect2, in combination with a method for cell-level tabulation of the sequencing read counts bearing SNV alleles, SCReadCounts. Our analysis shows that variant calls on individual cell alignments identify at least two-fold higher number of SNVs as compared to the pooled scRNA-seq. We demonstrate that scSNVs exclusively called in the single cell alignments (scSNVs) are substantially enriched in novel genetic variants and in coding functional annotations, in particular, stop-codon and missense substitutions. Furthermore, we find that the expression of some scSNVs correlates with the expression of their harbouring gene (cis-scReQTLs). Overall, our study indicates an immense potential of SNV calls from individual cell scRNA-seq data and emphasizes on the need of cell-level variant detection approaches and tools. Given the growing accumulation of scRNA-seq datasets, cell-level variant assessments are likely to significantly contribute to the understanding of the cellular heterogeneity and the relationship between genetics variants and functional phenotypes. In addition, cell-level variant assessments from scRNA-seq can be highly informative in cancer where they can help elucidate somatic mutations evolution and functionality.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.12.448184" rel="alternate" title="Improved SNV discovery in barcode-stratified scRNA-seq alignments (17 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>