<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv genomics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.822378+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genomics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.14.448344</id><title>Mapping the Genetic Landscape of DNA Double-strand Break Repair (160 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.823394+00:00</updated><author><name>Jeffrey A. Hussmann</name></author><author><name>Jia Ling</name></author><author><name>Purnima Ravisankar</name></author><author><name>Jun Yan</name></author><author><name>Ann Cirincione</name></author><author><name>Albert Xu</name></author><author><name>Danny Simpson</name></author><author><name>Dian Yang</name></author><author><name>Anne Bothmer</name></author><author><name>Cecilia Cotta-Ramusino</name></author><author><name>Jonathan S. Weissman</name></author><author><name>Britt Adamson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cells repair DNA double-strand breaks (DSBs) through a complex set of pathways that are critical for maintaining genomic integrity. Here we present Repair-seq, a high-throughput screening approach that measures the effects of thousands of genetic perturbations on the distribution of mutations introduced at targeted DNA lesions. Using Repair-seq, we profiled DSB repair outcomes induced by two programmable nucleases (Cas9 and Cas12a) after knockdown of 476 genes involved in DSB repair or associated processes in the presence or absence of oligonucleotides for homology-directed repair (HDR). The resulting data enabled principled, data-driven inference of DSB end joining and HDR pathways and demonstrated that repair outcomes with superficially similar sequence architectures can have markedly different genetic dependencies. Systematic interrogation of these dependencies then uncovered unexpected relationships among DSB repair genes and isolated incompletely characterized repair mechanisms. This work provides a foundation for understanding the complex pathways of DSB repair and for optimizing genome editing across modalities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.14.448344" rel="alternate" title="Mapping the Genetic Landscape of DNA Double-strand Break Repair (160 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-06-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.17.448907</id><title>Whole-genome sequencing and analysis of two azaleas, Rhododendron ripense and Rhododendron kiyosumense (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.823893+00:00</updated><author><name>Kenta Shirasawa</name></author><author><name>Nobuo Kobayashi</name></author><author><name>Akira Nakatsuka</name></author><author><name>Hideya Ohta</name></author><author><name>Sachiko Isobe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To enhance the genomics and genetics of azalea, the whole-genome sequences of two species of &lt;italic&gt;Rhododendron&lt;/italic&gt; were determined and analyzed in this study: &lt;italic&gt;Rhododendron ripense&lt;/italic&gt;, the cytoplasmic donor and ancestral species of large-flowered and evergreen azalea cultivars, respectively; and &lt;italic&gt;Rhododendron kiyosumense&lt;/italic&gt;, a native of Chiba prefecture (Japan) seldomly bred and cultivated. A chromosome-level genome sequence assembly of &lt;italic&gt;R. ripense&lt;/italic&gt; was constructed by single-molecule real-time (SMRT) sequencing and genetic mapping, while the genome sequence of &lt;italic&gt;R. kiyosumense&lt;/italic&gt; was assembled using the single-tube long fragment read (stLFR) sequencing technology. The &lt;italic&gt;R. ripense&lt;/italic&gt; genome assembly contained 319 contigs (506.7 Mb; N50 length: 2.5 Mb) and was assigned to the genetic map to establish 13 pseudomolecule sequences. On the other hand, the genome of &lt;italic&gt;R. kiyosumense&lt;/italic&gt; was assembled into 32,308 contigs (601.9 Mb; N50 length: 245.7 kb). A total of 34,606 genes were predicted in the &lt;italic&gt;R. ripense&lt;/italic&gt; genome, while 35,785 flower and 48,041 leaf transcript isoforms were identified in &lt;italic&gt;R. kiyosumense&lt;/italic&gt; through Iso-Seq analysis. Overall, the genome sequence information generated in this study enhances our understanding of genome evolution in the Ericales and reveals the phylogenetic relationship of closely-related species. This information will also facilitate the development of phenotypically attractive azalea cultivars.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.17.448907" rel="alternate" title="Whole-genome sequencing and analysis of two azaleas, Rhododendron ripense and Rhododendron kiyosumense (10 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.18.449053</id><title>A compendium of novel genomics technologies provides a chromosome-scale assembly and insights into the sex determining system of the Greenland Halibut (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.824247+00:00</updated><author><name>Anne-Laure Ferchaud</name></author><author><name>Claire Merot</name></author><author><name>Eric Normandeau</name></author><author><name>Ioannis Ragoussis</name></author><author><name>Charles Babin</name></author><author><name>Haig Djambazian</name></author><author><name>Pierre Bérubé</name></author><author><name>Celine Audet</name></author><author><name>Wocjciech Walkusz</name></author><author><name>Margaret Treble</name></author><author><name>Louis Bernatchez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite the commercial importance of Greenland Halibut (&lt;italic&gt;Reinhardtius hippoglossoides)&lt;/italic&gt;, important gaps still persist in our knowledge of this species, including its reproductive biology and sex determination mechanism. In this study, we combined single molecule sequencing of long reads (Pacific Sciences) with Chromatin Conformation Capture sequencing (Hi-C) data to provide the first chromosome-level genome reference for this species. The high-quality assembly encompassed more than 598 Megabases (Mb) assigned to 1 594 scaffolds (scaffold N50 = 25 Mb) with 96 % of its total length distributed among 24 chromosomes. The investigation of its syntenic relationships with other economically important flatfish species revealed a high conservation of synteny blocks among members of this phylogenetic clade. Sex determination analysis revealed that flatfishes do not escape the rule applied to other teleost fish and exhibit a high level of plasticity and turnover in sex-determination mechanisms. A whole-genome sequence analysis of 198 individuals allowed us to draw a full picture of the molecular sex determination (SD) system for Greenland Halibut, revealing that this species possesses a very nascent male heterogametic XY system, with a putative major effect of the sox2 gene, also described as the main SD driver in two other flatfishes. Interestingly, our study also suggested for the first time in flatfishes that a putative Y-autosomal fusion could be associated with a reduction of recombination typical of early steps of sex chromosome evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.18.449053" rel="alternate" title="A compendium of novel genomics technologies provides a chromosome-scale assembly and insights into the sex determining system of the Greenland Halibut (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.18.449059</id><title>LD-CNV: rapid and simple discovery of chromosomal translocations using linkage disequilibrium between copy number variable loci (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.824693+00:00</updated><author><name>Luca Comai</name></author><author><name>Kirk R Amundson</name></author><author><name>Benny Ordonez</name></author><author><name>Xin Zhao</name></author><author><name>Guilherme Tomaz Braz</name></author><author><name>Jiming Jiang</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Marie Henry</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Large scale structural variations, such as chromosomal translocations, can have profound effects on fitness and phenotype, but are difficult to identify and characterize. Here, we describe a simple and effective method aimed at identifying translocations using only the dosage of sequence reads mapped on the reference genome. We binned reads on genomic segments sized according to sequencing coverage and identified instances when copy number segregated in populations. For each dosage-polymorphic 1Mb bin, we tested linkage disequilibrium (LD) with other variable bins. In nine potato (Solanum tuberosum) dihaploid families translocations affecting pericentromeric regions were common and in two cases were due to genomic misassembly. In two populations, we found evidence for translocation affecting euchromatic arms. In cv. PI 310467, a non-reciprocal translocation between chromosome 7 and 8 resulted in a 5-3 copy number change affecting several Mb at the respective chromosome tips. In cv. Alca Tarma, the terminal arm of chromosome 4 translocated to the tip of chromosome 1. Using oligonucleotide-based fluorescent in situ hybridization painting probes (oligo-FISH), we tested and confirmed the predicted arrangement in PI 310467. In 192 natural accessions of Arabidopsis thaliana, dosage haplotypes tended to vary continuously and resulted in higher noise, while LD between pericentromeric regions suggested the effect of repeats. This method should be useful in species where translocations are suspected because it tests linkage without the need for genotyping.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.18.449059" rel="alternate" title="LD-CNV: rapid and simple discovery of chromosomal translocations using linkage disequilibrium between copy number variable loci (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.17.448889</id><title>Fast and powerful statistical method for context-specific QTL mapping in multi-context genomic studies (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.825078+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew Lu</name></author><author><name>Mike Thompson</name></author><author><name>M Grace Gordon</name></author><author><name>Andy Dahl</name></author><author><name>Chun Jimmie Ye</name></author><author><name>Noah Zaitlen</name></author><author><name>Brunilda Balliu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent studies suggest that context-specific eQTLs underlie genetic risk factors for complex diseases. However, methods for identifying them are still nascent, limiting their comprehensive characterization and downstream interpretation of disease-associated variants. Here, we introduce FastGxC, a method to efficiently and powerfully map context-specific eQTLs by leveraging the correlation structure of multi-context studies. We first show via simulations that FastGxC is orders of magnitude more powerful and computationally efficient than previous approaches, making previously year-long computations possible in minutes. We next apply FastGxC to bulk multi-tissue and single-cell RNA-seq data sets to produce the most comprehensive tissue- and cell-type-specific eQTL maps to date. We then validate these maps by establishing that context-specific eQTLs are enriched in corresponding functional genomic annotations. Finally, we examine the relationship between context-specific eQTLs and human disease and show that FastGxC context-specific eQTLs provide a three-fold increase in precision to identify relevant tissues and cell types for GWAS variants than standard eQTLs. In summary, FastGxC enables the construction of context-specific eQTL maps that can be used to understand the context-specific gene regulatory mechanisms underlying complex human diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.17.448889" rel="alternate" title="Fast and powerful statistical method for context-specific QTL mapping in multi-context genomic studies (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>