<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>BioRxiv preprints in genomics posted in the last week with at least 5 tweets</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.354137+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genomics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443499</id><title>Accuracies of genomic predictions for disease resistance of striped catfish to Edwardsiella ictaluri using artificial intelligence algorithms (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.378341+00:00</updated><author><name>Nguyen Thanh Vu</name></author><author><name>Tran Huu Phuc</name></author><author><name>Kim Thi Phuong Oanh</name></author><author><name>Nguyen Van Sang</name></author><author><name>Trinh Thi Trang</name></author><author><name>Nguyen Hong Nguyen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Assessments of genomic prediction accuracies using machine and deep learning methods are currently not available or very limited in aquaculture species. The principal aim of this study was to examine the predictive performance of these new methods for disease resistance to &lt;italic&gt;Edwardsiella ictaluri&lt;/italic&gt; in a population of striped catfish &lt;italic&gt;Pangasianodon hypophthalmus&lt;/italic&gt; and to make comparisons with four common methods, i.e., pedigree-based best linear unbiased prediction (PBLUP), genomic-based best linear unbiased prediction (GBLUP), single-step GBLUP (ssGBLUP) and a non-linear Bayesian approach (notably BayesR). Our analyses using machine learning (i.e., KAML) and deep learning (i.e., DeepGP) together with the four common methods (PBLUP, GBLUP, ssGBLUP and BayesR) were conducted for two main disease resistance traits (i.e., survival status coded as 0 and 1 and survival time, i.e., days that the animals were still alive after the challenge test) in a pedigree consisting of 560 individual animals (490 offspring and 70 parents) genotyped for 14,154 Single Nucleotide Polymorphism (SNPs). The results showed that KAML outperformed GBLUP and ssGBLUP, with the increases in the prediction accuracies for both traits by 5.1 – 47.7%. However, the prediction accuracies obtained from KAML were comparable to those estimated using BayesR. Imputation of missing genotypes using AlphaFamImpute increased the prediction accuracies by 0.2 – 33.2% in all the methods used. On the other hand, there were no significant increases in the prediction accuracies for both survival status and survival time when multivariate models were used in comparison to univariate analyses. Interestingly, the genomic prediction accuracies based on only highly significant SNPs (P &amp;lt; 0.00001) were not largely different from those obtained from the whole set of 14,154 SNPs. In all our analyses, the accuracies of genomic prediction were somewhat higher for survival time than survival status (0/1 data). It is concluded that there are prospects for the application of genomic selection to increase disease resistance to &lt;italic&gt;Edwardsiella ictaluri&lt;/italic&gt; in striped catfish breeding programs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443887</id><title>TAD-like single-cell domain structures exist on both active and inactive X chromosomes and persist under epigenetic perturbations (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.377903+00:00</updated><author><name>Yubao Cheng</name></author><author><name>Miao Liu</name></author><author><name>Mengwei Hu</name></author><author><name>Siyuan Wang</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Topologically associating domains (TADs) are important building blocks of three-dimensional genome architectures. The formation of TADs was shown to depend on cohesin in a loop-extrusion mechanism. Recently, advances in an image-based spatial genomics technique known as chromatin tracing led to the discovery of cohesin-independent TAD-like structures, also known as single-cell domains — highly variant self-interacting chromatin domains with boundaries that occasionally overlap with TAD boundaries but tend to differ among single cells and among single chromosome copies. Several recent computational modeling studies suggest that single-cell variations of epigenetic profiles may underlie the formation of the single-cell domains.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we use chromatin tracing to visualize in female human cells the fine-scale chromatin folding of inactive and active X chromosomes, which are known to have distinct global epigenetic landscapes and distinct population-averaged TAD profiles, with inactive X chromosomes largely devoid of TADs and cohesin. We show that both inactive and active X chromosomes possess highly variant single-cell domains across the same genomic region despite the fact that only active X chromosomes show clear TAD structures at the population level. These X chromosome single-cell domains exist in distinct cell lines. Perturbations of major epigenetic components did not significantly affect the frequency or strength of the single-cell domains. Increased chromatin compaction of inactive X chromosomes occurs at a length scale above that of the single-cell domains.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In sum, this study suggests that single-cell domains are genome architecture building blocks independent of variations in major epigenetic landscapes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443567</id><title>Chromatin landscape dynamics in development of the plant parasitic nematode Meloidogyne incognita (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.376414+00:00</updated><author><name>Rahim Hassanaly-Goulamhoussen</name></author><author><name>Ronaldo De Carvalho Augusto</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Marteu-Garello</name></author><author><name>Arthur Péré</name></author><author><name>Bruno Favery</name></author><author><name>Martine Da Rocha</name></author><author><name>Etienne G.J. Danchin</name></author><author><name>Pierre Abad</name></author><author><name>Christoph Grunau</name></author><author><name>Laetitia Perfus-Barbeoch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In model organisms, epigenome dynamics underlies a plethora of biological processes. The role of epigenetic modifications in development and parasitism in nematode pests remains unknown. The root-knot nematode &lt;italic&gt;Meloidogyne incognita&lt;/italic&gt; adapts rapidly to unfavorable conditions, despite its asexual reproduction. However, the mechanisms underlying this remarkable plasticity and their potential impact on gene expression remain unknown. This study provides the first insight into contribution of epigenetic mechanisms to this plasticity, by studying histone modifications in &lt;italic&gt;M. incognita&lt;/italic&gt;. The distribution of five histone modifications revealed the existence of strong epigenetic signatures, similar to those found in the model nematode &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/italic&gt;. We investigated their impact on chromatin structure and their distribution relative to transposable elements (TE) loci. We assessed the influence of the chromatin landscape on gene expression at two developmental stages: eggs, and pre-parasitic juveniles. H3K4me3 histone modification was strongly correlated with high levels of expression for protein-coding genes implicated in stage-specific processes during &lt;italic&gt;M. incognita&lt;/italic&gt; development. We provided new insights in the dynamic regulation of parasitism genes kept under histone modifications silencing. In this pioneering study, we establish a comprehensive framework for the importance of epigenetic mechanisms in the regulation of the genome expression and its stability in plant-parasitic nematodes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nematode &lt;italic&gt;Meloidogyne incognita&lt;/italic&gt; is one of the most destructive plant parasites worldwide. Its ability to infect a wide range of hosts and its high adaptability contribute to its parasitic success. We investigated the role of epigenetic mechanisms — specifically post-translational histone modifications — in the parasitic life cycle. We showed these modifications are linked to gene expression regulation and likely contribute to nematode development and pathogenicity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443472</id><title>A burst of transposon expression accompanies the activation of Y chromosome fertility genes during Drosophila spermatogenesis (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.375929+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew A. Lawlor</name></author><author><name>Weihuan Cao</name></author><author><name>Christopher E. Ellison</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Transposable elements (TEs) must replicate in germline cells to pass novel insertions to offspring. In &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; ovaries, TEs can exploit specific developmental windows of opportunity to evade host silencing and increase their copy numbers. However, TE activity and host silencing in the distinct cell types of the &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; testis are not well understood. We reanalyzed publicly available single-cell RNA-seq datasets to quantify TE expression in the distinct cell types of the &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; testis. We developed a novel method for identification of TE and host gene expression programs and find that a distinct population of early spermatocytes expresses a large number of TEs at much higher levels than other germline and somatic components of the testes. This burst of TE expression coincides with the activation of Y chromosome fertility factors and spermatocyte-specific transcriptional regulators, as well as downregulation of many components of the piRNA pathway. The TEs expressed by this cell population are enriched on the Y chromosome and depleted on the X chromosome relative to other active TEs. These data suggest that some TEs may achieve high insertional activity in males by exploiting a window of opportunity for mobilization created by the activation of spermatocyte-specific and Y-chromosome-specific transcriptional programs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443707</id><title>Novel Interpretable Tissue-Specific and Multi-Tissue Transcriptomic Clocks to Infer Aging Mechanisms (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.375508+00:00</updated><author><name>Aayush Gupta</name></author><author><name>Mindren Lu</name></author><author><name>Jessica Sun</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1.&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aging is characterized as a progressive decline in fitness that ultimately results in death. We set out to build both tissue-specific and multi-tissue transcriptomic clocks to make global tissue age predictions in individuals from GTEx. Existing work in the field primarily uses epigenetic clocks as predictors of age, but these models have known issues and are significantly less interpretable than their transcriptomic counterparts. Due to their transcriptomic nature, we can use these models to directly infer mechanisms of aging from their features. Linear regression remains the current standard analysis technique, but we improved upon its baseline performance with modern techniques, exploring both XGBoost and MLPs. We also experimented with using deconvolved cell data for predictions, which account for cellular composition and reduce signal distortion from rare cell types. Since it is known that the heterogeneity of cell types in particular tissues can lead to noise in these models, we proposed using deconvolution as a potential remedy for this problem.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our results found that MLPs are not well suited for the task due to a lack of training data, but the use of XGBoost is effective at improving the baseline performance of predictions of existing tissue-specific clocks. These models allowed us to directly compute genes most important to age prediction in our models, and we showed that multiple genes found have been independently identified elsewhere to show evidence of correlation with age. Given the small size of our datasets, we were unable to make conclusive determinations about multi-tissue predictors, but preliminary results suggest that the technique shows promise and is worthy of future investigation. Likewise, given our limited deconvolved cell data, we did not currently observe strong results, but we again note that this is an area in need of further investigation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By improving upon the performance of existing models, we demonstrated that a novel machine learning technique, XGBoost, can be an effective technique to further our understanding of aging mechanisms by extraction of the most relevant genes found in those models. This is significant because the genetic causes of aging are still not fully understood, and research in the field of aging is lacking in comparison to other domains. As the problem of identifying tissues that age at different rates is of specific interest, our tissue-specific models potentially have other applications in this domain, including informing pathologies in tissues that are found to be aging faster, or analyzing how people with similar ages can have vastly different tissue ages. An extended technical presentation of this work can be found here, and a highly simplified non-technical overview presentation can be found here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443255</id><title>Ariadne: Barcoded Linked-Read Deconvolution Using de Bruijn Graphs (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.374862+00:00</updated><author><name>Lauren Mak</name></author><author><name>Dmitry Meleshko</name></author><author><name>David C. Danko</name></author><author><name>Waris N. Barakzai</name></author><author><name>Natan Belchikov</name></author><author><name>Iman Hajirasouliha</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;De novo&lt;/italic&gt; assemblies are critical for capturing the genetic composition of complex samples. Linked-read sequencing techniques such as 10x Genomics’ Linked-Reads, UST’s TELL-Seq, Loop Genomics’ LoopSeq, and BGI’s Long Fragment Read combines 3′ barcoding with standard short-read sequencing to expand the range of linkage resolution from hundreds to tens of thousands of base-pairs. The application of linked-read sequencing to genome assembly has demonstrated that barcoding-based technologies balance the tradeoffs between long-range linkage, per-base coverage, and costs. Linked-reads come with their own challenges, chief among them the association of multiple long fragments with the same 3′ barcode. The lack of a unique correspondence between a long fragment and a barcode, in conjunction with low sequencing depth, confounds the assignment of linkage between short-reads.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We introduce Ariadne, a novel linked-read deconvolution algorithm based on assembly graphs, that can be used to extract single-species read-sets from a large linked-read dataset. Ariadne deconvolution of linked-read clouds increases the proportion of read clouds containing only reads from a single fragment by up to 37.5-fold. Using these enhanced read clouds in &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; assembly significantly improves assembly contiguity and the size of the largest aligned blocks in comparison to the non-deconvolved read clouds. Integrating barcode deconvolution tools, such as Ariadne, into the postprocessing pipeline for linked-read technologies increases the quality of &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; assembly for complex populations, such as microbiomes. Ariadne is intuitive, computationally efficient, and scalable to other large-scale linked-read problems, such as human genome phasing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The source code is available on GitHub: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/lauren-mak/Ariadne"&gt;https://github.com/lauren-mak/Ariadne&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443095</id><title>Clone expansion of mutation-driven clonal hematopoiesis is associated with aging and metabolic dysfunction in individuals with obesity (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.374329+00:00</updated><author><name>Rosanne C. van Deuren</name></author><author><name>Johanna C. Andersson-Assarsson</name></author><author><name>Felipe M. Kristensson</name></author><author><name>Marloes Steehouwer</name></author><author><name>Kajsa Sjöholm</name></author><author><name>Per-Arne Svensson</name></author><author><name>Marc Pieterse</name></author><author><name>Christian Gilissen</name></author><author><name>Magdalena Taube</name></author><author><name>Peter Jacobson</name></author><author><name>Rosie Perkins</name></author><author><name>Han G. Brunner</name></author><author><name>Mihai G. Netea</name></author><author><name>Markku Peltonen</name></author><author><name>Björn Carlsson</name></author><author><name>Alexander Hoischen</name></author><author><name>Lena M.S. Carlsson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aging is associated with clonal hematopoiesis (CH) caused by somatic mutations in blood cell progenitors. Mutations with ≥2% variant allele frequency (VAF), known as clonal hematopoiesis of indeterminate potential (CHIP) mutations, have been linked to risk of hematological malignancies and cardiovascular disease. Using an ultrasensitive single-molecule molecular inversion probe (smMIP) sequencing assay, we identified clonal hematopoiesis driver mutations (CHDMs) in a set of established CH driver genes in individuals with obesity from the Swedish Obese Subjects study. In cross-sectional setting, with samples from 1050 individuals, we identified 273 candidate CHDMs in 216 individuals, with a VAF ranging from 0.01% to 31.15% and with clone sizes and prevalence increasing with age. Longitudinal analysis over 20 years in 40 individuals showed that small clones may grow over time and become CHIP. Greater speed of clone growth was associated with insulin resistance (R=0.04, P=0.025) and low circulating levels of high-density lipoprotein-cholesterol (R=-0.68, P=1.74E&lt;sup&gt;-05&lt;/sup&gt;), suggesting that dysfunctional metabolism may accelerate expansion of CH.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443570</id><title>Convergent loss of chemoreceptors across independent origins of slave-making in ants (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.364552+00:00</updated><author><name>Evelien Jongepier</name></author><author><name>Alice Séguret</name></author><author><name>Anton Labutin</name></author><author><name>Barbara Feldmeyer</name></author><author><name>Claudia Gstöttl</name></author><author><name>Susanne Foitzik</name></author><author><name>Jürgen Heinze</name></author><author><name>Erich Bornberg-Bauer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The evolution of an obligate parasitic lifestyle often leads to the reduction of morphological and physiological traits, which may be accompanied by loss of genes and functions. Slave-maker ants are social parasites that exploit the work force of closely related ant species for social behaviours such as brood care and foraging. Recent divergence between these social parasites and their hosts enables comparative studies of gene family evolution. We sequenced the genomes of eight ant species, representing three independent origins of ant slavery. During the evolution of eusociality, chemoreceptor genes multiplied due to the importance of chemical communication in societies. We investigated evolutionary patterns of chemoreceptors in relation to slave-making in ants. We found that slave-maker ant genomes harboured only half as many gustatory receptors as their hosts, potentially mirroring the outsourcing of foraging tasks to host workers. In addition, parasites had fewer odorant receptors and their loss shows patterns of convergence across origins of parasitism, representing a rare case of convergent molecular evolution. This convergent loss of specific odorant receptors suggests that selective deprivation of receptors is adaptive. The 9-exon odorant receptor subfamily, previously linked to social evolution in insects, was significantly enriched for convergent loss across the three origins of slavery in our study, indicating that the transition to social parasitism in ants is accompanied by the loss of receptors that are likely important for mediating eusocial behaviour. Overall, gene loss in slave-maker ants suggests that a switch to a parasitic lifestyle accompanies relaxed selection on chemical perception.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.443962</id><title>The First High-Quality Reference Genome of Sika Deer Provides Insights for High-Tannin Adaptation (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.358600+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiumei Xing</name></author><author><name>Cheng Ai</name></author><author><name>Tianjiao Wang</name></author><author><name>Yang LI</name></author><author><name>Huitao Liu</name></author><author><name>Pengfei Hu</name></author><author><name>Guiwu Wang</name></author><author><name>Huamiao Liu</name></author><author><name>Hongliang Wang</name></author><author><name>Ranran Zhang</name></author><author><name>Junjun Zheng</name></author><author><name>Xiaobo Wang</name></author><author><name>Lei Wang</name></author><author><name>Yuxiao Chang</name></author><author><name>Qian Qian</name></author><author><name>Jinghua Yu</name></author><author><name>Lixin Tang</name></author><author><name>Shigang Wu</name></author><author><name>Xiujuan Shao</name></author><author><name>Alun Li</name></author><author><name>Peng Cui</name></author><author><name>Wei Zhan</name></author><author><name>Sheng Zhao</name></author><author><name>Zhichao Wu</name></author><author><name>Xiqun Shao</name></author><author><name>Yimeng Dong</name></author><author><name>Min Rong</name></author><author><name>Yihong Tan</name></author><author><name>Xuezhe Cui</name></author><author><name>Shuzhuo Chang</name></author><author><name>Xingchao Song</name></author><author><name>Tongao Yang</name></author><author><name>Limin Sun</name></author><author><name>Yan Ju</name></author><author><name>Pei Zhao</name></author><author><name>Huanhuan Fan</name></author><author><name>Ying Liu</name></author><author><name>Xinhui Wang</name></author><author><name>Wanyun Yang</name></author><author><name>Min Yang</name></author><author><name>Tao Wei</name></author><author><name>Shanshan Song</name></author><author><name>Jiaping Xu</name></author><author><name>Zhigang Yue</name></author><author><name>Qiqi Liang</name></author><author><name>Chunyi Li</name></author><author><name>Jue Ruan</name></author><author><name>Fuhe Yang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sika deer are known to prefer oak leaves, which are rich in tannins and toxic to most mammals; however, the genetic mechanisms underlying their unique ability to adapt to living in the jungle are still unclear. In identifying the mechanism responsible for the tolerance of a highly toxic diet, we have made a major advancement in the elucidation of the genomics of sika deer. We generated the first high-quality, chromosome-level genome assembly of sika deer and measured the correlation between tannin intake and RNA expression in 15 tissues through 180 experiments. Comparative genome analyses showed that the UGT and CYP gene families are functionally involved in the adaptation of sika deer to high-tannin food, especially the expansion of UGT genes in a subfamily. The first chromosome-level assembly and genetic characterization of the tolerance toa highly toxic diet suggest that the sika deer genome will serve as an essential resource for understanding evolutionary events and tannin adaptation. Our study provides a paradigm of comparative expressive genomics that can be applied to the study of unique biological features in non-model animals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443369</id><title>Integrated phospho-proteogenomic and single-cell transcriptomic analysis of meningiomas establishes robust subtyping and reveals subtype-specific immune invasion (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.356676+00:00</updated><author><name>Christina Blume</name></author><author><name>Helin Dogan</name></author><author><name>Lisa Schweizer</name></author><author><name>Matthieu Peyre</name></author><author><name>Sophia Doll</name></author><author><name>Daniel Picard</name></author><author><name>Roman Sankowski</name></author><author><name>Volker Hovestadt</name></author><author><name>Konstantin Okonechnikov</name></author><author><name>Philipp Sievers</name></author><author><name>Areeba Patel</name></author><author><name>David Reuss</name></author><author><name>Mirco Friedrich</name></author><author><name>Damian Stichel</name></author><author><name>Daniel Schrimpf</name></author><author><name>Katja Beck</name></author><author><name>Hans-Georg Wirsching</name></author><author><name>Gerhard Jungwirth</name></author><author><name>C Oliver Hanemann</name></author><author><name>Katrin Lamszus</name></author><author><name>Manfred Westphal</name></author><author><name>Nima Etminan</name></author><author><name>Andreas Unterberg</name></author><author><name>Christian Mawrin</name></author><author><name>Marc Remke</name></author><author><name>Olivier Ayrault</name></author><author><name>Peter Lichter</name></author><author><name>Stefan M Pfister</name></author><author><name>Guido Reifenberger</name></author><author><name>Michael Platten</name></author><author><name>Till Milde</name></author><author><name>David TW Jones</name></author><author><name>Rachel Grossmann</name></author><author><name>Zvi Ram</name></author><author><name>Miriam Ratliff</name></author><author><name>Christel Herold-Mende</name></author><author><name>Jan-Philipp Mallm</name></author><author><name>Marian C Neidert</name></author><author><name>Wolfgang Wick</name></author><author><name>Marco Prinz</name></author><author><name>Michael Weller</name></author><author><name>Matthias Mann</name></author><author><name>Michel Kalamarides</name></author><author><name>Andreas von Deimling</name></author><author><name>Matthias Schlesner</name></author><author><name>Felix Sahm</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Meningiomas are the most frequent primary intracranial tumors. They can follow a wide clinical spectrum from benign to highly aggressive clinical course. No specific therapy exists for refractory cases or cases not amenable to resection and radiotherapy. Identification of risk of recurrence and malignant transformation for the individual patients is challenging. However, promising molecular markers and prognostic subgrouping by DNA methylation are emerging. Still, the biological underpinnings of these diagnostic subgroups are elusive, and, consequently, no novel therapeutic options arise thereof. Here we establish robust subgroups across the full landscape of meningiomas, consistent through DNA methylation, mutations, the transcriptomic, proteomic and phospho-proteomic level. Pronounced proliferative stress and DNA damage repair signals in malignant cells and in clusters exclusive to recurrent tumors are in line with their higher mitotic activity, but also provide an explanation for the accumulation of genomic instability in anaplastic meningiomas. Although homozygous deletion of &lt;italic&gt;CDKN2A/B&lt;/italic&gt; is a diagnostic marker of high-grade meningioma, the expression of its gene product increased from low to non-deleted high-grade cases. Differences between subgroups in lymphocyte and myeloid cell infiltration, representing a majority of tumor mass in low-grade NF2 tumors, could be assigned to cluster-specific interaction with tumor cells. Activation to a more proinflammatory phenotype and decreased infiltration of myeloid cells in high-grade cases correlated with lower expression of &lt;italic&gt;CSF1&lt;/italic&gt;, located on chromosome arm 1p, whose deletion is known as prognostic marker, with no proposed mechanism before. Our results demonstrate a robust molecular subclassification of a tumor type across multiple layers, provide insight into heterogeneous growth dynamics despite shared pathognomonic mutations, and highlight immune infiltration modulation as a novel target for meningioma therapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443777</id><title>Single-cell epigenomic tracing of lifelong endothelial cell plasticity across mouse organs (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.356450+00:00</updated><author><name>Xianhong Yu</name></author><author><name>Yaxi Liu</name></author><author><name>Xiaoge Liu</name></author><author><name>Haiqing Xiong</name></author><author><name>Aibin He</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Endothelial cells (ECs) across ages and tissues are highly heterogeneous in developmental origins, structures, functions, and cellular plasticity. Here, we applied CoBATCH for single-cell epigenomic tracing of dynamic EC lineage histories in five mouse organs from development to ageing. Our analyses showed that epigenomic memory reflects both developmental origins and tissue-restricted specialization of EC sublineages but with varying time lengths across organs. To gain insights into cellular plasticity of ECs, we identified bivalent chromatin occupancy of otherwise mutually exclusive EC- (ERG) and mesenchymal-specific (TWIST1/SNAI1) transcription factors promoting endothelial-to-mesenchymal transition. We further revealed that pseudotime trajectories by histone modifications H3K36me3 and H3K27ac faithfully recapitulate short- and long-range EC fate change over senescence, respectively. Together, our data provide a unique exploration of chromatin-level cell fate regulation of organotypic EC lineages across the lifespan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Single-cell chromatin binding is examined for tracing endothelial cell lineages in mouse organs across the lifespan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443814</id><title>One Cell At a Time: A Unified Framework to Integrate and Analyze Single-cell RNA-seq Data (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.356243+00:00</updated><author><name>Chloe Wang</name></author><author><name>Lin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Bo Wang</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The surge of single-cell RNA sequencing technologies enables the accessibility to large single-cell RNA-seq datasets at the scale of hundreds of thousands of single cells. Integrative analysis of large-scale scRNA-seq datasets has the potential of revealing &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; cell types as well as aggregating biological information. However, most existing methods fail to integrate multiple large-scale scRNA-seq datasets in a computational and memory efficient way. We hereby propose OCAT, &lt;bold&gt;O&lt;/bold&gt;ne &lt;bold&gt;C&lt;/bold&gt;ell &lt;bold&gt;A&lt;/bold&gt;t a &lt;bold&gt;T&lt;/bold&gt;ime, a graph-based method that sparsely encodes single-cell gene expressions to integrate data from multiple sources without most variable gene selection or explicit batch effect correction. We demonstrate that OCAT efficiently integrates multiple scRNA-seq datasets and achieves the state-of-the-art performance in cell-type clustering, especially in challenging scenarios of non-overlapping cell types. In addition, OCAT facilitates a variety of downstream analyses, such as gene prioritization, trajectory inference, pseudotime inference and cell inference. OCAT is a unifying tool to simplify and expedite single-cell data analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443907</id><title>HASTER is a transcriptional stabilizer of HNF1A (39 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.355929+00:00</updated><author><name>Anthony Beucher</name></author><author><name>Irene Miguel-Escalada</name></author><author><name>Diego Balboa Alonso</name></author><author><name>Matias G De Vas</name></author><author><name>Miguel Angel Maestro</name></author><author><name>Javier Garcia-Hurtado</name></author><author><name>Aina Bernal</name></author><author><name>Holger Heyn</name></author><author><name>Roser Gonzalez Franco</name></author><author><name>Pierfrancesco Vargiu</name></author><author><name>Sagrario Ortega</name></author><author><name>Philippe Ravassard</name></author><author><name>Jorge Ferrer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The biological purpose and disease relevance of long noncoding RNAs (lncRNAs) is poorly understood. We examined &lt;italic&gt;HASTER&lt;/italic&gt;, a lncRNA antisense to &lt;italic&gt;HNF1A&lt;/italic&gt;. Haploinsufficient mutations in &lt;italic&gt;HNF1A&lt;/italic&gt;, encoding a homeodomain transcription factor, cause diabetes mellitus. Using mouse and human models, we show that &lt;italic&gt;HASTER&lt;/italic&gt; maintains HNF1A at cell-specific physiological concentrations through positive and negative feedback loops. &lt;italic&gt;Haster&lt;/italic&gt; mutant pancreatic β cells thus showed variegated HNF1A overexpression or silencing, causing insulin-deficiency and diabetes. We demonstrate that the &lt;italic&gt;HASTER&lt;/italic&gt; promoter acts in cis to prevent HNF1A overexpression and silencing, and link &lt;italic&gt;HASTER&lt;/italic&gt;-dependent inhibition to local remodelling of 3D chromatin architecture. We further show that &lt;italic&gt;HASTER&lt;/italic&gt; negative feedback ensures that HNF1A creates open chromatin at appropriate cell-specific genome regions. Our studies expose a cis-regulatory element that is unlike enhancers or silencers, and instead stabilizes expression levels of a pioneer transcription factor. They also show that disruption of a mammalian lncRNA can cause diabetes mellitus.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.08.443158</id><title>Resource Profile and User Guide of the Polygenic Index Repository (49 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.355289+00:00</updated><author><name>Joel Becker</name></author><author><name>Casper A.P. Burik</name></author><author><name>Grant Goldman</name></author><author><name>Nancy Wang</name></author><author><name>Hariharan Jayashankar</name></author><author><name>Michael Bennett</name></author><author><name>Daniel W. Belsky</name></author><author><name>Richard Karlsson Linnér</name></author><author><name>Rafael Ahlskog</name></author><author><name>Aaron Kleinman</name></author><author><name>David A. Hinds</name></author><author><name>Avshalom Caspi</name></author><author><name>David L. Corcoran</name></author><author><name>Terrie E. Moffitt</name></author><author><name>Richie Poulton</name></author><author><name>Karen Sugden</name></author><author><name>Benjamin S. Williams</name></author><author><name>Kathleen Mullan Harris</name></author><author><name>Andrew Steptoe</name></author><author><name>Olesya Ajnakina</name></author><author><name>Lili Milani</name></author><author><name>Tõnu Esko</name></author><author><name>William G. Iacono</name></author><author><name>Matt McGue</name></author><author><name>Patrik K.E. Magnusson</name></author><author><name>Travis T. Mallard</name></author><author><name>K. Paige Harden</name></author><author><name>Elliot M. Tucker-Drob</name></author><author><name>Pamela Herd</name></author><author><name>Jeremy Freese</name></author><author><name>Alexander Young</name></author><author><name>Jonathan P. Beauchamp</name></author><author><name>Philipp Koellinger</name></author><author><name>Sven Oskarsson</name></author><author><name>Magnus Johannesson</name></author><author><name>Peter M. Visscher</name></author><author><name>Michelle N. Meyer</name></author><author><name>David Laibson</name></author><author><name>David Cesarini</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Benjamin</name></author><author><name>Patrick Turley</name></author><author><name>Aysu Okbay</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Polygenic indexes (PGIs) are DNA-based predictors. Their value for research in many scientific disciplines is rapidly growing. As a resource for researchers, we used a consistent methodology to construct PGIs for 47 phenotypes in 11 datasets. To maximize the PGIs’ prediction accuracies, we constructed them using genome-wide association studies—some of which are novel—from multiple data sources, including 23andMe and UK Biobank. We present a theoretical framework to help interpret analyses involving PGIs. A key insight is that a PGI can be understood as an unbiased but noisy measure of a latent variable we call the “additive SNP factor.” Regressions in which the true regressor is the additive SNP factor but the PGI is used as its proxy therefore suffer from errors-in-variables bias. We derive an estimator that corrects for the bias, illustrate the correction, and make a Python tool for implementing it publicly available.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443890</id><title>A catalog of transcription start sites across 115 human tissue and cell types (52 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.354979+00:00</updated><author><name>Jill E. Moore</name></author><author><name>Xiao-Ou Zhang</name></author><author><name>Shaimae I. Elhajjajy</name></author><author><name>Kaili Fan</name></author><author><name>Fairlie Reese</name></author><author><name>Ali Mortazavi</name></author><author><name>Zhiping Weng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Accurate transcription start site (TSS) annotations are essential for understanding transcriptional regulation and its role in human disease. Gene collections such as GENCODE contain annotations for tens of thousands of TSSs, but not all of these annotations are experimentally validated nor do they contain information on cell type-specific usage. Therefore, we sought to generate a collection of experimentally validated TSSs by integrating &lt;italic&gt;RNA Annotation and Mapping of Promoters for the Analysis of Gene Expression&lt;/italic&gt; (RAMPAGE) data from 115 cell and tissue types, which resulted in a collection of approximately 50 thousand representative RAMPAGE peaks. These peaks were primarily proximal to GENCODE-annotated TSSs and were concordant with other transcription assays. Because RAMPAGE uses paired-end reads, we were then able to connect peaks to transcripts by analyzing the genomic positions of the 3’ ends of read mates. Using this paired-end information, we classified the vast majority (37 thousand) of our RAMPAGE peaks as verified TSSs, updating TSS annotations for 20% of GENCODE genes. We also found that these updated TSS annotations were supported by epigenomic and other transcriptomic datasets. To demonstrate the utility of this RAMPAGE rPeak collection, we intersected it with the NHGRI/EBI GWAS catalog and identified new candidate GWAS genes. Overall, our work demonstrates the importance of integrating experimental data to further refine TSS annotations and provides a valuable resource for the biological community.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>