<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv genomics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.934366+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genomics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.23.449602</id><title>Factors Driving DNA Methylation Variation in Human Blood (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.935013+00:00</updated><author><name>Jacob Bergstedt</name></author><author><name>Sadoune Ait Kaci Azzou</name></author><author><name>Kristin Tsuo</name></author><author><name>Anthony Jaquaniello</name></author><author><name>Alejandra Urrutia</name></author><author><name>Maxime Rotival</name></author><author><name>David T. S. Lin</name></author><author><name>Julia L. MacIsaac</name></author><author><name>Michael S. Kobor</name></author><author><name>Matthew L. Albert</name></author><author><name>Darragh Duffy</name></author><author><name>Etienne Patin</name></author><author><name>Lluís Quintana-Murci</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Epigenetic changes are required for normal development and health, and can also underlie disease states; yet, the nature and respective contribution of factors that drive epigenetic variation in humans remain to be fully characterized. Here, we assessed how the blood DNA methylome of 958 adults is affected by genetic variation, aging, sex and 139 diverse environmental exposures, and investigated whether these effects are direct or mediated by changes in cellular composition, measured by deep immunophenotyping. We show that cellular heterogeneity and DNA sequence variation are the strongest predictors of DNA methylation levels. We identify latent cytomegalovirus infection as a major driver of DNA methylation variation and delineate three distinct effects of aging on DNA methylation, including increased dispersion consistent with epigenetic drift. Our rich dataset provides a unique resource for the design and interpretation of epigenetic studies and highlight critical factors in medical epigenomics studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.23.449602" rel="alternate" title="Factors Driving DNA Methylation Variation in Human Blood (11 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.22.448967</id><title>Rapid Genomic Characterization and Global Surveillance of Klebsiella Using Pathogenwatch (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.936134+00:00</updated><author><name>Silvia Argimón</name></author><author><name>Sophia David</name></author><author><name>Anthony Underwood</name></author><author><name>Monica Abrudan</name></author><author><name>Nicole E. Wheeler</name></author><author><name>Mihir Kekre</name></author><author><name>Khalil Abudahab</name></author><author><name>Corin A. Yeats</name></author><author><name>Richard Goater</name></author><author><name>Ben Taylor</name></author><author><name>Harry Harste</name></author><author><name>Dawn Muddyman</name></author><author><name>Edward J. Feil</name></author><author><name>Sylvain Brisse</name></author><author><name>Kathryn Holt</name></author><author><name>Pilar Donado-Godoy</name></author><author><name>KL Ravikumar</name></author><author><name>Iruka N. Okeke</name></author><author><name>Celia Carlos</name></author><author><name>David M. Aanensen</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella&lt;/italic&gt; species, including the notable pathogen &lt;italic&gt;K. pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt;, are increasingly associated with antimicrobial resistance (AMR). Genome-based surveillance can inform interventions aimed at controlling AMR. However, its widespread implementation requires tools to streamline bioinformatic analyses and public health reporting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We developed the web application Pathogenwatch, which implements analytics tailored to &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella&lt;/italic&gt; species for integration and visualization of genomic and epidemiological data. We populated Pathogenwatch with 16,537 public &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella&lt;/italic&gt; genomes to enable contextualization of user genomes. We demonstrated its features with 1,636 genomes from four low- and middle-income countries (LMICs) participating in the NIHR Global Health Research Unit (GHRU) on AMR.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using Pathogenwatch, we found that GHRU genomes were dominated by a small number of epidemic drug-resistant clones of &lt;italic&gt;K. pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt;. However, differences in their distribution were observed (e.g. ST258/512 dominated in Colombia, ST231 in India, ST307 in Nigeria, ST147 in the Philippines). Phylogenetic analyses including public genomes for contextualization enabled retrospective monitoring of their spread. In particular, we identified hospital outbreaks, detected introductions from abroad, and uncovered clonal expansions associated with resistance and virulence genes. Assessment of loci encoding O-antigens and capsule in &lt;italic&gt;K. pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt;, which represent possible vaccine candidates, showed that three O-types (O1-O3) represented 88.9% of all genomes, whereas capsule types were much more diverse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pathogenwatch provides a free, accessible platform for real-time analysis of &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella&lt;/italic&gt; genomes to aid surveillance at local, national and global levels. We have improved representation of genomes from GHRU participant countries, further facilitating ongoing surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;40-word summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pathogenwatch is a free web-application for analysis of &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella&lt;/italic&gt; genomes to aid surveillance at local, national and global levels. We improved the representation of genomes from middle-income countries through the Global Health Research Unit on AMR, further facilitating ongoing surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;FUNDING&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This work was supported by Official Development Assistance (ODA) funding from the National Institute of Health Research [grant number 16_136_111].&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This research was commissioned by the National Institute of Health Research using Official Development Assistance (ODA) funding. The views expressed in this publication are those of the authors and not necessarily those of the NHS, the National Institute for Health Research or the Department of Health.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;CONFLICT OF INTEREST&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The authors: No reported conflicts of interest. All authors have submitted the ICMJE Form for Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.22.448967" rel="alternate" title="Rapid Genomic Characterization and Global Surveillance of Klebsiella Using Pathogenwatch (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>