<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.576283+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary_biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443470</id><title>RevGadgets: an R Package for visualizing Bayesian phylogenetic analyses from RevBayes (64 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.576990+00:00</updated><author><name>Carrie M. Tribble</name></author><author><name>William A. Freyman</name></author><author><name>Michael J. Landis</name></author><author><name>Jun Ying Lim</name></author><author><name>Joëlle Barido-Sottani</name></author><author><name>Bjørn Tore Kopperud</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Höhna</name></author><author><name>Michael R. May</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Statistical phylogenetic methods are the foundation for a wide range of evolutionary and epidemiological studies. However, as these methods grow increasingly complex, users often encounter significant challenges with summarizing, visualizing, and communicating their key results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present &lt;monospace&gt;RevGadgets&lt;/monospace&gt;, an R package for creating publication-quality figures from the results of a large variety of phylogenetic analyses performed in &lt;monospace&gt;RevBayes&lt;/monospace&gt; (and other phylogenetic software packages).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We demonstrate how to use &lt;monospace&gt;RevGadgets&lt;/monospace&gt; through a set of vignettes that cover the most common use cases that researchers will encounter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;monospace&gt;RevGadgets&lt;/monospace&gt; is an open-source, extensible package that will continue to evolve in parallel with &lt;monospace&gt;RevBayes&lt;/monospace&gt;, helping researchers to make sense of and communicate the results of a diverse array of analyses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443470" rel="alternate" title="RevGadgets: an R Package for visualizing Bayesian phylogenetic analyses from RevBayes (64 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443235</id><title>Molecular and cellular architecture of the larval sensory organ in the cnidarian Nematostella vectensis (41 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.577296+00:00</updated><author><name>Callum Teeling</name></author><author><name>Eleanor Gilbert</name></author><author><name>Siffreya Pedersen</name></author><author><name>Nathan Chrismas</name></author><author><name>Vengamanaidu Modepalli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The apical pole of eumetazoan ciliated larvae acts as a neurosensory structure and is principally composed of sensory-secretory cells. Cnidarians like the sea anemone &lt;italic&gt;Nematostella vectensis&lt;/italic&gt; are the only non-bilaterian group to evolve ciliated larvae with a neural integrated sensory organ that is likely homologous to bilaterians. Here, we uncovered the molecular signature of the larval sensory organ in &lt;italic&gt;Nematostella&lt;/italic&gt; by generating a transcriptome of the apical tissue. We characterised the cellular identity of the apical domain by integrating larval single-cell data with the apical transcriptome and further validated this through in-situ hybridisation. We discovered that the apical domain comprises a minimum of 6 distinct cell types, including apical cells, neurons, peripheral flask-shaped gland/secretory cells, and undifferentiated cells. By profiling the spatial expression of neuronal genes, we showed that the apical region has a unique neuronal signature distinct from the rest of the body. By combining the planula cilia proteome with the apical transcriptome data, we revealed the sheer complexity of the non-motile apical tuft. Overall, we present comprehensive spatial/molecular data on the &lt;italic&gt;Nematostella&lt;/italic&gt; larval sensory organ and open new directions for elucidating the functional role of the apical organ and larval nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443235" rel="alternate" title="Molecular and cellular architecture of the larval sensory organ in the cnidarian Nematostella vectensis (41 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443886</id><title>Complex introgression among three diverged largemouth bass lineages (35 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.577590+00:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Silliman</name></author><author><name>Honggang Zhao</name></author><author><name>Megan Justice</name></author><author><name>Wilawan Thongda</name></author><author><name>Bryant Bowen</name></author><author><name>Eric Peatman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hybrid zones between diverged lineages offer an unique opportunity to study evolutionary processes related to speciation. Natural and anthropogenic hybridization in the black basses (&lt;italic&gt;Micropterus&lt;/italic&gt; spp.) is well documented, including an extensive intergrade zone between the widespread northern Largemouth Bass (&lt;italic&gt;M. salmoides&lt;/italic&gt;) and the Florida Bass (&lt;italic&gt;M. floridanus&lt;/italic&gt;). Phenotypic surveys have identified an estuarine population of Largemouth Bass (&lt;italic&gt;M. salmoides&lt;/italic&gt;) in the Mobile-Tensaw Delta, with larger relative weight and smaller adult size compared to inland populations, suggesting a potential third lineage of largemouth bass. To determine the evolutionary relationships between these Mobile Delta bass populations, &lt;italic&gt;M. salmoides&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;M. floridanus&lt;/italic&gt;, putative pure and intergrade populations of all three groups were sampled across the eastern United States. Phylogenetic analyses of 8,582 nuclear SNPs derived from genotype-by-sequencing and the ND2 mitochondrial gene determined that Delta bass populations stem from a recently diverged lineage of Largemouth Bass. Using a novel quantitative pipeline, a panel of 73 diagnostic SNPs was developed for the three lineages, evaluated for accuracy, and then used to screen 881 samples from 52 sites for genetic integrity and hybridization on the Agena MassARRAY platform. These results strongly support a redrawing of native ranges for both the intergrade zone and &lt;italic&gt;M. floridanus&lt;/italic&gt;, which has significant implications for current fisheries management. Furthermore, Delta bass ancestry was shown to contribute significantly to the previously described intergrade zone between northern Largemouth Bass and Florida Bass, suggesting a more complex pattern of secondary contact and introgression among these diverged &lt;italic&gt;Micropterus&lt;/italic&gt; lineages.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443886" rel="alternate" title="Complex introgression among three diverged largemouth bass lineages (35 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443711</id><title>Multiple ancestral and a plethora of recent gene duplications during the evolution of the green sensitive opsin genes (RH2) in teleost fishes (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.577796+00:00</updated><author><name>Zuzana Musilova</name></author><author><name>Fabio Cortesi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Vertebrates have four visual cone opsin classes that, together with a light-sensitive chromophore, provide sensitivity from the ultraviolet to the red wavelengths of light. The rhodopsin-like 2 (RH2) opsin is sensitive to the centre blue-green part of the spectrum, which is the most prevalent light underwater. While various vertebrate groups such as mammals and sharks have lost the &lt;italic&gt;RH2&lt;/italic&gt; gene, in teleost fishes this opsin has continued to proliferate. By investigating the genomes of 115 teleost species, we find that &lt;italic&gt;RH2&lt;/italic&gt; shows an extremely dynamic evolutionary history with repeated gene duplications, gene losses and gene conversion affecting entire orders, families and species. At least four ancestral duplications provided the substrate for today’s &lt;italic&gt;RH2&lt;/italic&gt; diversity with duplications occurring in the common ancestors of Clupeocephala, Neoteleostei, and Acanthopterygii. Following these events, &lt;italic&gt;RH2&lt;/italic&gt; has continued to duplicate both in tandem and during lineage specific genome duplications. However, it has also been lost many times over so that in the genomes of extant teleosts, we find between zero to eight &lt;italic&gt;RH2&lt;/italic&gt; copies. Using retinal transcriptomes in a phylogenetic representative dataset of 30 species, we show that &lt;italic&gt;RH2&lt;/italic&gt; is expressed as the dominant green-sensitive opsin in almost all fish lineages. The exceptions are the Osteoglossomorpha (bony tongues and mooneyes) and several characin species that have lost &lt;italic&gt;RH2&lt;/italic&gt;, and tarpons, other characins and gobies which do not or only lowly express the gene. These fishes instead express a green-shifted long-wavelength-sensitive &lt;italic&gt;LWS&lt;/italic&gt; opsin. Our study highlights the strength of using modern genomic tools within a comparative framework to elucidate the detailed evolutionary history of gene families.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443711" rel="alternate" title="Multiple ancestral and a plethora of recent gene duplications during the evolution of the green sensitive opsin genes (RH2) in teleost fishes (13 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443318</id><title>Morph-specific investment in testes mass in a trimorphic beetle, Proagoderus watanabei (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.577937+00:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan M. Parrett</name></author><author><name>Eleanor M. Slade</name></author><author><name>Robert J. Knell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;When competition between males for mates is intense it is common to find that some males will adopt alternative tactics for acquiring fertilisations, often involving the use of ‘sneak’ tactics whereby males avoid contests. These alternative tactics are sometimes associated with discrete differences in male morphology, with sneak males investing less in weaponry but more in traits such as testes which will give an advantage in sperm competition. In some cases it appears that males develop into more than two morphs, with a number of examples of tri- and even tetramorphic arthropod species being described. Here we analyse the scaling relations of the dung beetle species &lt;italic&gt;Proagoderus watanabei&lt;/italic&gt;, which expresses two distinct weapon traits: paired head horns and a pronotal horn. We find that males of this species are trimorphic, with alpha males expressing long head horns and a pronotal horn, beta males with long head horns but no pronotal horn, and gamma males with short head horns only. We also find that alpha males invest less in testes than do beta or gamma males, indicating that beta and gamma males in this species probably experience higher risks of sperm competition than do alphas.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443318" rel="alternate" title="Morph-specific investment in testes mass in a trimorphic beetle, Proagoderus watanabei (12 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443825</id><title>A spatially aware likelihood test to detect sweeps from haplotype distributions (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.578281+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael DeGiorgio</name></author><author><name>Zachary A. Szpiech</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The inference of positive selection in genomes is a problem of great interest in evolutionary genomics. By identifying putative regions of the genome that contain adaptive mutations, we are able to learn about the biology of organisms and their evolutionary history. Here we introduce a composite likelihood method that identifies recently completed or ongoing positive selection by searching for extreme distortions in the spatial distribution of the haplotype frequency spectrum relative to the genome-wide expectation taken as neutrality. Furthermore, the method simultaneously infers two parameters of the sweep: the number of sweeping haplotypes and the “width” of the sweep, which is related to the strength and timing of selection. We demonstrate that this method outperforms the leading haplotype-based selection statistics. Then, as a positive control, we apply it to two well-studied human populations from the 1000 Genomes Project and examine haplotype frequency spectrum patterns at the &lt;italic&gt;LCT&lt;/italic&gt; and MHC loci. To facilitate use of this method, we have implemented it in user-friendly open source software.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443825" rel="alternate" title="A spatially aware likelihood test to detect sweeps from haplotype distributions (12 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.444039</id><title>Fitness effects of CRISPR endonucleases in Drosophila melanogaster populations (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.578459+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna M. Langmüller</name></author><author><name>Jackson Champer</name></author><author><name>Sandra Lapinska</name></author><author><name>Lin Xie</name></author><author><name>Matthew Metzloff</name></author><author><name>Jingxian Liu</name></author><author><name>Yineng Xu</name></author><author><name>Andrew G. Clark</name></author><author><name>Philipp W. Messer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;CRISPR/Cas9 systems provide a highly efficient and flexible genome editing technology with numerous potential applications in areas ranging from gene therapy to population control. Some proposed applications involve CRISPR/Cas9 endonucleases integrated into an organism’s genome, which raises questions about potentially harmful effects to the transgenic individuals. One application where this is particularly relevant are CRISPR-based gene drives, which promise a mechanism for rapid genetic alteration of entire populations. The performance of such drives can strongly depend on fitness costs experienced by drive carriers, yet relatively little is known about the magnitude and causes of these costs. Here, we assess the fitness effects of genomic CRISPR/Cas9 expression in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; cage populations by tracking allele frequencies of four different transgenic constructs, designed to disentangle direct fitness costs due to the integration, expression, and target-site activity of Cas9 from costs due to potential off-target cleavage. Using a maximum likelihood framework, we find a moderate level of fitness costs due to off-target effects but do not detect significant direct costs. Costs of off-target effects are minimized for a construct with Cas9HF1, a high-fidelity version of Cas9. We further demonstrate that using Cas9HF1 instead of standard Cas9 in a homing drive achieves similar drive conversion efficiency. Our results suggest that gene drives should be designed with high-fidelity endonucleases and may have implications for other applications that involve genomic integration of CRISPR endonucleases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.444039" rel="alternate" title="Fitness effects of CRISPR endonucleases in Drosophila melanogaster populations (8 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443771</id><title>Social selection within aggregative multicellular development drives morphological evolution (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.578753+00:00</updated><author><name>Marco La Fortezza</name></author><author><name>Gregory J. Velicer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The evolution of developmental systems might be shaped by both historical differences in developmental features and social selection, among other factors. In aggregative multicellularity, development is itself a social process in which unicellular organisms cooperate in carrying out complex developmental programs. In some aggregative systems, development culminates in the construction of spore-packed fruiting bodies. Fruiting body development in myxobacteria often unfolds within genetically and behaviorally diverse conspecific cellular environments that can include social defection and warfare. Here we use the bacterium &lt;italic&gt;Myxococcus xanthus&lt;/italic&gt; to test whether the character of the cellular environment during aggregative development shapes morphological evolution. We manipulated the cellular composition of &lt;italic&gt;Myxococcus&lt;/italic&gt; development in an experiment in which evolving populations initiated from a single ancestor repeatedly co-developed with one of several non-evolving partners - a benign cooperator, one of three cheaters or one of three antagonists. Fruiting body morphology was found to diversify as a function of developmental partners, revealing adaptation specific to distinct cellular environments. Collectively, antagonistic partners selected for higher levels of robust fruiting body formation than did cheaters or the benign cooperator. Moreover, even small degrees of genetic divergence between the distinct cheater partners were sufficient to drive treatment-level morphological divergence. Co-developmental partners not only shaped mean trait evolution but also determined the magnitude and dynamics of stochastic morphological diversification and subsequent convergence. In sum, we find that even few genetic differences affecting developmental and social features can greatly impact the morphological evolution of multicellular bodies and experimentally demonstrate that microbial warfare can promote cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443771" rel="alternate" title="Social selection within aggregative multicellular development drives morphological evolution (6 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>