<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>BioRxiv preprints in evolutionary_biology posted in the last week with at least 5 tweets</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.056124+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary_biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.05.442740</id><title>Factors that affect the rates of adaptive and non-adaptive evolution at the gene level in humans and chimpanzees (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.057207+00:00</updated><author><name>Vivak Soni</name></author><author><name>Adam Eyre-Walker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The rate of amino acid substitution has been shown to be correlated to a number of factors including the rate of recombination, the age of the gene, the length of the protein, mean expression level and gene function. However, the extent to which these correlations are due to adaptive and non-adaptive evolution has not been studied in detail, at least not in hominids. We find that the rate of adaptive evolution is significantly positively correlated to the rate of recombination, protein length and gene expression level, and negatively correlated to gene age. The correlations remain significant when each factor is controlled for in turn, except when controlling for expression in an analysis of protein length; and they also remain significant, or marginally significant, when biased gene conversion is controlled for. However, the positive correlations could be an artefact of population size contraction. We also find that the rate of non-adaptive evolution is negatively correlated to each factor, and all these correlations survive controlling for each other and biased gene conversion. Finally, we examine the effect of gene function on rates of adaptive and non-adaptive evolution; we confirm that virus interacting proteins (VIPs) have higher rates of adaptive and lower rates of non-adaptive evolution, but we also demonstrate that there is significant variation in the rate of adaptive and non-adaptive evolution between GO categories when removing VIPs. We estimate that the VIP/non-VIP axis explains about 5-8x more of the variance in evolutionary rate than GO categories.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.03.442498</id><title>Global Gene Expression Divergence in Spontaneous Mutation Accumulation Lines of Caenorhabditis elegans under Varying Efficiency of Selection (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.056690+00:00</updated><author><name>Thaddeus C. Deiss</name></author><author><name>Anke Konrad</name></author><author><name>Ulfar Bergthorsson</name></author><author><name>Vaishali Katju</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To ascertain the effect of relaxation of selection on global gene expression, &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/italic&gt; mutation accumulation (MA) lines were propagated under varying degrees of efficiency of selection determined by their different population sizes (&lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt; = 1, 10 and 100). Both the mutational variance (&lt;italic&gt;V&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;italic&gt;m&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;), and the residual variance (&lt;italic&gt;V&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;italic&gt;r&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;) were greatest in MA lines with the lowest efficiency of natural selection. The results suggest that gene expression is under strong balancing selection. Furthermore, mutations resulting in increased transcriptional noise or sensitivity to microenvironmental variation accumulate most under extreme genetic drift. In contrast, the &lt;italic&gt;V&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;italic&gt;m&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;/&lt;italic&gt;V&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;italic&gt;r&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; ratio was lowest in the &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt; =1 lines. Chromatin domains associated with broad gene silencing and active transcription exhibited the greatest and the smallest increase in transcriptional variation, respectively. Furthermore, the preponderance of overexpressed genes was especially pronounced in mitochondrial respiration, stress response, and immune system pathways, especially in low fitness &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt; = 1 lines.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>