<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular zoology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.134593+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/zoology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462241</id><title>Using TrackMate to Analyze Drosophila Larval and Adult Locomotion (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.139856+00:00</updated><author><name>Alisa A. Omelchenko</name></author><author><name>Ainul Huda</name></author><author><name>Allison N. Castaneda</name></author><author><name>Thomas J. Vaden</name></author><author><name>Lina Ni</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; adult and larvae exhibit sophisticated behaviors that are widely used in development, synaptic transmission, sensory physiology, and learning and memory research. Many of these behaviors depend on locomotion, the ability of an animal to move. However, the statistical analysis of locomotion is not trivial. Here we use an open-source Fiji plugin TrackMate to track the locomotion of &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; adults and larvae. We build optimal experimental setups to rapidly process recordings by Fiji and analyze by TrackMate. We also provide tips for analyzing non-optimal recordings. TrackMate extracts the X and Y positions of an animal on each frame of an image sequence or a video. This information allows for generating moving trajectories, calculating moving distances, and determining preference indices in two-choice assays. Notably, this free-cost analysis method does not require programming skills.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study uses an open-source Fiji plugin TrackMate to computationally analyze &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; adult and larval behavioral assays, which does not require programming skills.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462241" rel="alternate" title="Using TrackMate to Analyze Drosophila Larval and Adult Locomotion (3 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>