<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular zoology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.509975+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/zoology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.18.456772</id><title>Multiple parasitism promotes facultative host acceptance of cuckoo eggs and rejection of cuckoo chicks (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.510299+00:00</updated><author><name>Hee-Jin Noh</name></author><author><name>Ros Gloag</name></author><author><name>Naomi E. Langmore</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many hosts of brood parasitic cuckoos reject foreign eggs from the nest. Yet where nests commonly receive more than one cuckoo egg, hosts might benefit by instead accepting parasite eggs. This is because cuckoos remove an egg from the nest before adding their own, and keeping cuckoo eggs in the nest reduces the odds that further host eggs are removed by subsequent cuckoos. This ‘clutch dilution effect’ has been proposed as a precondition for the evolution of cuckoo nestling eviction by hosts, but no previous studies have tested this in a host that rejects cuckoo nestlings. We tested the clutch dilution hypothesis in large-billed gerygones (&lt;italic&gt;Gerygone magnirostris&lt;/italic&gt;), which are multiply parasitized by little bronze-cuckoos (&lt;italic&gt;Chalcites minutillus&lt;/italic&gt;). Gerygones evict cuckoo nestlings but accept cuckoo eggs. Consistent with multiple parasitism favouring egg acceptance, we found gerygone egg survival was higher under scenarios of cuckoo egg acceptance than rejection. Yet gerygones were also flexible in their egg acceptance, with 35% abandoning cuckoo-egg-only clutches. This novel demonstration of adaptive clutch dilution suggests that multiple parasitism can favour a facultative response to brood parasite eggs, whereby hosts accept or reject parasite eggs depending on clutch composition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.18.456772" rel="alternate" title="Multiple parasitism promotes facultative host acceptance of cuckoo eggs and rejection of cuckoo chicks (4 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>