<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular zoology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.921503+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/zoology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466512</id><title>Sex and Estrous Cycle in Memory for Sequences of Events in Rats (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.922613+00:00</updated><author><name>M. Jayachandran</name></author><author><name>P. Langius</name></author><author><name>F. Pazos Rego</name></author><author><name>R. P. Vertes</name></author><author><name>T. A. Allen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ability to remember sequences of events is fundamental to episodic memory. While rodent studies have examined sex and estrous cycle in episodic-like spatial memory tasks, little is known about these biological variables in memory for sequences of events that depend on representations of temporal context. We investigated the role of sex and estrous cycle in rats during all training and testing stages of a cross-species validated sequence memory task (Jayachandran et al., 2019). Rats were trained on a task composed of two sequences, each with four unique odors delivered on opposite ends of a linear track. Training occurred in six successive stages starting with learning to poke in a nose port for ≥1.2s; eventually demonstrating sequence memory by holding their nose in the port for ≥1s for in-sequence odors and &amp;lt;1s for out-of-sequence odors in order to receive a water reward. Performance was analyzed across sex and estrous cycle (proestrus, estrus, metestrus, and diestrus), the latter being determined by the cellular composition of a daily vaginal lavage. We found no evidence of sex differences in asymptotic sequence memory performance, similar to published data in humans performing the analogous task (Reeders et al., 2021). Likewise, we found no differences in performance across the estrous cycle. One minor difference was that female rats tended to have slightly longer poke times, while males had slightly more short poke times but this did not affect their decisions. These results suggest sex and estrous cycle are not major factors in sequence memory capacities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466512" rel="alternate" title="Sex and Estrous Cycle in Memory for Sequences of Events in Rats (26 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466806</id><title>Decision-Making in Rats is Sensitive to Rare and Extreme Events: the Black Swan Avoidance (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.923306+00:00</updated><author><name>Mickaël Degoulet</name></author><author><name>Louis-Matis Willem</name></author><author><name>Christelle Baunez</name></author><author><name>Stéphane Luchini</name></author><author><name>Patrick A. Pintus</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Most studies assessing decision-making under uncertainty use events with probabilities that are above 10-20 %. Here, to study decision-making in radical uncertainty conditions, Degoulet, Willem, Baunez, Luchini and Pintus provide a novel experimental design that aims at measuring the extent to which rats are sensitive - and how they respond - to extremely rare (below 1% of probability) but extreme events in a four-armed bandit task. Gains (sugar pellets) and losses (time-out punishments) are such that large - but rare - values materialize or not depending on the option chosen. The results show that all rats diversify their choices across options. However, most rats exhibit sensitivity to rare and extreme events despite their sparse occurrence, by combining more often options with extreme gains (Jackpots) and/or avoidance of extreme losses (Black Swans). In general, most rats’ choices feature one-sided sensitivity in favor of trying more often to avoid extreme losses than to seek extreme gains - that is, they feature Black Swan Avoidance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="simple"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;-&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;A novel experiment is proposed to measure whether rats are sensitive - and how they respond - to radical uncertainty materialized by extremely rare and extreme events in a four-armed bandit task;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;-&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most rats exhibit sensitivity to rare and extreme events;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;-&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most rats opt more often to avoid rare and extreme losses than to seek rare and extreme gains: they feature Black Swan avoidance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466806" rel="alternate" title="Decision-Making in Rats is Sensitive to Rare and Extreme Events: the Black Swan Avoidance (5 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>