<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular zoology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.467068+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/zoology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473475</id><title>Δ9-tetrahydrocannabinol (THC) vapor exposure produces conditioned rewarding effects in male and female rats (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.467598+00:00</updated><author><name>Catherine F. Moore</name></author><author><name>Catherine M. Davis</name></author><author><name>Elise M. Weerts</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vaping of cannabis and cannabis extracts containing Δ9-tetrahydrocannabinol (THC, the primary psychoactive constituent of cannabis) is on the rise. Development of animal models using vapor exposure is important for increasing our understanding of the rewarding and aversive effects of vaped cannabinoids. Currently there are limited data on the conditioned rewarding effects of THC vapor in rats, and no studies to date examining sex differences.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Male and female Sprague-Dawley rats (N=96; 12 per sex/group) underwent place conditioning after exposure to vaporized THC or vehicle (propylene glycol, PG). THC vapor-conditioned rats received one of three THC vapor exposure amounts (THC Group 1: 5 puffs of 100 mg/ml THC, THC Group 2: 5 puffs of 200 mg/ml THC, or THC Group 3: 10 puffs of 200 mg/ml THC) and matched vehicle vapor (PG) exposure and on alternate days for two sets of 8 daily sessions (16 days total). Vehicle-conditioned rats (Veh Group 0) received only PG vapor exposure each day. Rats were passively administered vapor for 30-min immediately before daily, 30-min conditioning sessions. Untreated rats completed place preference tests after the 8th and 16th conditioning sessions and then testing continued daily until extinction occurred. Following extinction, rats underwent a THC vapor-primed reinstatement session.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Male and female rats showed an exposure-dependent preference for the THC vapor-paired chamber, though sex differences were observed. The lowest THC vapor exposure group tested (THC Group 1) did not produce CPP in males or females. Exposure to the middle condition tested (THC Group 2) resulted in preference for the THC vapor-paired chamber in males, but not females. The highest THC vapor exposure condition tested (THC Group 3) produced place preference in both males and females. Preference for the THC-paired chamber extinguished more quickly in males than in females. Following extinction, THC vapor re-exposure (i.e., drug-prime) did not result in reinstatement of place preference for either sex.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study demonstrated conditioned rewarding effects of THC vapor in both male and female rats, and provides evidence for sex differences in doses of THC vapor that produce CPP and in time to extinction. Conditioned place aversion was not observed at any of the THC vapor exposure amounts tested. These data provide a foundation for future exploration of the conditioned rewarding effects vaporized THC, cannabis and its constituents in preclinical models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473475" rel="alternate" title="Δ9-tetrahydrocannabinol (THC) vapor exposure produces conditioned rewarding effects in male and female rats (14 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473935</id><title>Failure to account for behavioral variability overestimates bonobo populations and compromises accuracy in population monitoring (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.468094+00:00</updated><author><name>Erin G Wessling</name></author><author><name>Martin Surbeck</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Wildlife population monitoring depends on accurate counts of individual animals or artefacts of behavior (e.g., nests or dung). In indirect surveying, which depends largely upon artefacts of behavior, likelihood to encounter indirect signs of a species is derived from both artefact production and decay, although variability in behaviors relevant to artefact abundance is rarely considered in population estimation. Here we demonstrate how ignoring behavioral variability contributes to overestimation of population size of an endangered ape endemic to the Democratic Republic of the Congo, the bonobo (&lt;italic&gt;Pan paniscus&lt;/italic&gt;). Commonly, a single metric of sign production (i.e., nest construction) is used to estimate bonobo density, assumed to be representative of bonobo nest behavior across all contexts. We estimated nest construction rates from three bonobo groups within the Kokolopori Bonobo Reserve and found that nest construction rates in bonobos to be highly variable across populations as well as seasonal within populations. Failure to account for behavioral variability in nest construction leads to potentially severe degradation in accuracy of bonobo population estimates of abundance, accounting for a likely overestimation of bonobo numbers by 34%, and in the worst cases as high as 80% overestimation. Using bonobo nesting as an example, we demonstrate that failure to account for inter- and intra-population behavioral variation compromises our ability to monitor population change or reliably compare contributors to population decline or persistence. We argue that variation in sign production is but one of several potential ways that behavioral variability can affect conservation monitoring, should be measured across contexts whenever possible, and must be considered in population estimation confidence intervals. With increasing attention to behavioral variability as a potential tool for conservation, conservationists must also account for the impact that behavioral variability across time, space, individuals, and populations can play upon precision and accuracy of wildlife population estimation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473935" rel="alternate" title="Failure to account for behavioral variability overestimates bonobo populations and compromises accuracy in population monitoring (6 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473249</id><title>Confidence as a noisy decision reliability estimate (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.468319+00:00</updated><author><name>Zoe M. Boundy-Singer</name></author><author><name>Corey M. Ziemba</name></author><author><name>Robbe L. T. Goris</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Decisions vary in difficulty. Humans know this and typically report more confidence in easy than in difficult decisions. However, confidence reports do not perfectly track decision accuracy, but also reflect response biases and difficulty misjudgments. To isolate the quality of confidence reports, we developed a model of the decision-making process underlying choice-confidence data. In this model, confidence reflects a subject’s estimate of the reliability of their decision. The quality of this estimate is limited by the subject’s uncertainty about the uncertainty of the variable that informs their decision (“meta-uncertainty”). This model provides an accurate account of choice-confidence data across a broad range of perceptual and cognitive tasks, revealing that meta-uncertainty varies across subjects, is stable over time, generalizes across some domains, and can be manipulated experimentally. The model offers a parsimonious explanation for the computational processes that underlie and constrain the sense of confidence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473249" rel="alternate" title="Confidence as a noisy decision reliability estimate (6 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473828</id><title>Cultural diffusion dynamics depend on behavioural production rules (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.468514+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael Chimento</name></author><author><name>Brendan J. Barrett</name></author><author><name>Anne Kandler</name></author><author><name>Lucy M. Aplin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Culture is an outcome of the acquisition of knowledge about behaviour through social transmission, and its subsequent production. Transmission and production are often discussed interchangeably or modeled separately, yet to date, no study has accounted for both processes and explored their interaction. We present a generative model that integrates the two in order to explore how variation in either might shape cultural diffusion dynamics. Agents make behavioural choices that change as they learn from their behavioural productions. Their repertoires also change over time, and the social transmission of behaviours depends on their frequency. We diffuse a novel behaviour through social networks across a large parameter space to demonstrate how accounting for both transmission and production reveals dependencies between individual-level behavioural production rules and population-level diffusion dynamics. We then investigate how such dependencies might affect the performance of two commonly used inferential models for social learning; Network-based Diffusion Analysis (NBDA), and Experienced Weighted Attraction models (EWA). By clarifying the distinction between acquisition and usage, we illuminate often-overlooked theoretical differences between social learning and social influence. These distinctions yield consequences and new considerations for how inferential methods are applied to empirical studies of culture.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473828" rel="alternate" title="Cultural diffusion dynamics depend on behavioural production rules (5 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473541</id><title>BISoN: A Bayesian Framework for Inference of Social Networks (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.468697+00:00</updated><author><name>Jordan D. A. Hart</name></author><author><name>Michael N. Weiss</name></author><author><name>Daniel W. Franks</name></author><author><name>Lauren J. N. Brent</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Social networks are often constructed from point estimates of edge weights. In many contexts, edge weights are inferred from observational data, and the uncertainty around point estimates can be affected by various factors. Though this has been acknowledged in previous work, methods that explicitly quantify uncertainty in edge weights have not yet been widely adopted, and remain undeveloped for common types of data. Furthermore, existing methods are unable to cope with some of the complexities often found in observational data, and do not propagate uncertainty in edge weights to subsequent analyses. We introduce a unified Bayesian framework for modelling social networks based on observational data. This framework, which we call &lt;italic&gt;BISoN&lt;/italic&gt;, can accommodate many common types of observational social data, can capture confounds and model effects at the level of observations, and is fully compatible with popular methods of social network analysis. We show how the framework can be applied to common types of data and how various types of downstream analyses can be performed, including non-random association tests and regressions on network properties. Our framework opens up the opportunity to test new types of hypotheses, make full use of observational datasets, and increase the reliability of scientific inferences. We have made example R code available to enable adoption of the framework.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473541" rel="alternate" title="BISoN: A Bayesian Framework for Inference of Social Networks (4 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>