<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular zoology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.281034+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/zoology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472556</id><title>Simulated visual hallucinations in virtual reality enhance cognitive flexibility (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.281277+00:00</updated><author><name>Clara Rastelli</name></author><author><name>Antonino Greco</name></author><author><name>Yoed N. Kenett</name></author><author><name>Chiara Finocchiaro</name></author><author><name>Nicola De Pisapia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Historically, psychedelic drugs are known to modulate cognitive flexibility, a central aspect of cognition permitting adaptation to changing environmental demands. Despite proof suggesting phenomenological similarities between artificially-induced and actual psychedelic altered perception, experimental evidence is still lacking about whether the former is also able to modulate cognitive flexibility. To address this, we measure participants’ cognitive flexibility through behavioral tasks after the exposure to virtual reality panoramic videos and their hallucinatory-like counterparts generated by the DeepDream algorithm. Results show that the estimated semantic network has a flexible structure when preceded by altered videos. Crucially, following the simulated psychedelic exposure, individuals also show an attenuated contribution of the automatic process and chaotic dynamics underlying the decision process. This suggests that simulated altered perceptual phenomenology enhances cognitive flexibility, presumably due to a reorganization in the cognitive dynamics that facilitates the exploration of uncommon decision strategies and inhibits automated choices.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472556" rel="alternate" title="Simulated visual hallucinations in virtual reality enhance cognitive flexibility (26 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472386</id><title>Acute and chronic physical activity improve spatial pattern separation in humans (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.281454+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniela Ramirez Butavand</name></author><author><name>María F. Rodríguez</name></author><author><name>María V. Cifuentes</name></author><author><name>Magdalena Miranda</name></author><author><name>Cristian García Bauza</name></author><author><name>Pedro Bekinschtein</name></author><author><name>Fabricio Ballarini</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Physical activity benefits both fitness and cognition. However, its effect on long-term memory is unclear. Successful memory involves not only remembering information over time but also keeping memories distinct and less confusing. The ability to separate similar experiences into distinct memories is one of the main features of episodic memory. In this work, we evaluated the effect of acute and chronic physical activity on a new task to assess spatial pattern separation in a 3D virtual reality environment. We manipulated the load of memory similarity and found that 25 minutes of cycling after encoding - but not before retrieval - was sufficient to improve similar, but not dissimilar memories, 24 hours after encoding. Furthermore, we found that participants who engaged in regular physical activity, but not sedentary subjects, showed memory for the similar condition the next day. Thus, physical activity could be a simple way to improve discrimination of spatial memories in humans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472386" rel="alternate" title="Acute and chronic physical activity improve spatial pattern separation in humans (17 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472640</id><title>Role of immigrants and muzzle contacts in the uptake of a novel food by wild vervet monkeys (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.281608+00:00</updated><author><name>Pooja Dongre</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Canteloup</name></author><author><name>Gaëlle Lanté</name></author><author><name>Mathieu Cantat</name></author><author><name>Erica van de Waal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The entry into and uptake of information in social groups is critical for behavioural adaptation by long-lived species in rapidly changing environments. We exposed five groups of wild vervet monkeys to a novel food to investigate innovation of processing and consuming it. We observed whether dispersing males could introduce this innovation into groups and compare uptake between groups. We report that immigrant males innovated in two groups, and an infant innovated in one group. In two other groups, immigrant males imported the innovation from another group. Uptake of the novel food was fastest in groups where immigrant males ate first and younger individuals were most likely to acquire the novel food. We also investigated the role of muzzle contact behaviour in information seeking around the novel food. Muzzle contacts decreased in frequency over repeated exposures to the novel food, were targeted towards knowledgeable adults the most, and juveniles and naïve individuals initiated the most. Knowledgeable adult males were targeted but rarely initiated muzzle contacts, whereas knowledgeable adult females were targeted and initiated them, emphasising an adult sex difference in seeking social information. We highlight the potential of immigrants as vectors of information, enabling rapid behavioural adaptation and population level culture.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472640" rel="alternate" title="Role of immigrants and muzzle contacts in the uptake of a novel food by wild vervet monkeys (12 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472422</id><title>Gross anatomy of the gluteal and posterior thigh muscles in koalas based on their innervations (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.281743+00:00</updated><author><name>Sayaka Tojima</name></author><author><name>Hidaka Anetai</name></author><author><name>Kaito Koike</name></author><author><name>Saori Anetai</name></author><author><name>Kounosuke Tokita</name></author><author><name>Chris Leigh</name></author><author><name>Jaliya Kumaratilake</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;There are not many descriptions of the muscle morphology of marsupials, despite the fact that they should show diversity according to the adaptation and dispersal to a variety of environments. Most of the previous studies regarding the gross anatomy of marsupials were conducted in the 1800 - 1900’s, and many issues still remain that need to be reexamined. For instance, the muscle identification had been performed based only on their attachments and thus, muscle descriptions are often inconsistent among the studies. These classic studies often do not include figures or photographs, so the discrepancies in the descriptions of the muscles could only be verified by performing the muscle identification again with a more reliable method. This problem can be solved by performing muscle identification by innervation. This method, which focuses on the ontogenic origin of the muscle as opposed to the attachment site, is prone to individual and interspecies variation and is a common technique in recent anatomical research. This technique is more reliable than previous methods and is suitable for comparison with other taxa (i.e., eutherians). In this study, we first conducted muscle identification based on innervation in the gluteal and posterior thighs of koalas in order to reorganize the anatomical knowledge of marsupials. This is because the gluteus and posterior thighs of koalas are the areas where previous studies have been particularly inconsistent. We dissected five individual koalas and clarified discrepancies in previous studies, as well as investigated the unique muscle morphology and their function in koalas. Specifically, the koala’s gluteal muscle group is suitable for abduction, while the posterior thigh muscles are particularly suitable for flexion. In the future, we will update the anatomical findings of marsupials in the same way to clarify the adaptive dissipation process of marsupials, as well as to contribute to the understanding of the evolutionary morphology of mammals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472422" rel="alternate" title="Gross anatomy of the gluteal and posterior thigh muscles in koalas based on their innervations (4 tweets)"/><category term="Zoology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>