<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular zoology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.025897+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/zoology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.05.463216</id><title>Tales of schizomid tails: patterns in schizomid flagellum shape from elliptical Fourier analysis (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.026140+00:00</updated><author><name>Robert J. Kallal</name></author><author><name>Gustavo Silva de Miranda</name></author><author><name>Erika L. Garcia</name></author><author><name>Hannah M. Wood</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The arachnid order Schizomida is a relatively understudied group of soil-dwelling predators found on all continents except Antarctica. While efforts to understand their biology are growing, there is still much to know about them. A curious aspect of their morphology is the male flagellum, a sexually dimorphic, tail-like structure which differs in shape across the order and functions in their courtship rituals. The flagellar shape is important for taxonomic classification, yet few efforts have been made to examine shape diversity across the group. Using elliptical Fourier analysis, a type of geometric morphometrics based on outline shape, we quantified shape differences across a combined nearly 550 outlines in the dorsal and lateral views, categorizing them based on genus, family, biogeographic realm, and habitat, with special emphasis on Caribbean and Cuban fauna. We tested for allometric relationships, differences in disparity based on locations and sizes in morphospace among these categories, and for clusters of shapes in morphospace. We found multiple differences in all categories despite apparent overlaps in morphospace, evolutionary allometry, and evidence for discrete clusters in some flagellum shapes. This study can serve as a foundation for further study on the evolution, diversification, and taxonomic utility of the male flagellum.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.05.463216" rel="alternate" title="Tales of schizomid tails: patterns in schizomid flagellum shape from elliptical Fourier analysis (7 tweets)"/><category term="Zoology"/><published>2021-10-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463704</id><title>Wind and route choice affect performance of bees flying above versus within a cluttered obstacle field (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.026357+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas Burnett</name></author><author><name>Marc Badger</name></author><author><name>Stacey Combes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bees flying through natural landscapes encounter physical challenges, such as wind and cluttered vegetation. The influence of these factors on the flight performance of bees remains unknown. We analyzed 548 videos of wild-caught honeybees (&lt;italic&gt;Apis mellifera&lt;/italic&gt;) flying through an enclosure containing a field of vertical obstacles that bees could fly within (through open corridors, without maneuvering) or above. We examined how obstacle field height, wind presence and direction (headwinds or tailwinds) affected altitude, ground speed, and side-to-side casting (lateral excursions) of bees. When obstacle fields were short, bees flew at altitudes near the midpoint between the tunnel floor and ceiling. When obstacle fields approached or exceeded this midpoint, bees typically, but not always, increased their altitudes to fly over the obstacles. Bees that flew above the obstacle fields exhibited 40% faster ground speeds and 36% larger lateral excursions than bees that flew within the obstacle fields, likely due to the visual feedback from obstacles and narrow space available within the obstacle field. Wind had a strong effect on ground speed and lateral excursions, but not altitude. Bees flew 12-19% faster in tailwinds than in the other wind conditions, but their lateral excursions were 19% larger in any wind, regardless of its direction, than in still air. Our results show that bees flying through complex environments display flexible flight behaviors (e.g., flying above versus within obstacles), which affect flight performance. Similar choices in natural landscapes could have broad implications for foraging efficiency, pollination, and mortality in wild bees.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463704" rel="alternate" title="Wind and route choice affect performance of bees flying above versus within a cluttered obstacle field (4 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>