<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular zoology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.515975+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/zoology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471747</id><title>Can pyrethroid-piperonyl butoxide (PBO) nets reduce the efficacy of indoor residual spraying with pirimiphos-methyl against pyrethroid-resistant malaria vectors? (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.516273+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas Syme</name></author><author><name>Martial Gbegbo</name></author><author><name>Dorothy Obuobi</name></author><author><name>Augustin Fongnikin</name></author><author><name>Abel Agbevo</name></author><author><name>Damien Todjinou</name></author><author><name>Corine Ngufor</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;As the uptake of pyrethroid-PBO ITNs increases, their combination with IRS insecticides could become an operational reality in many malaria-endemic communities. Pirimiphos-methyl is a pro-insecticide requiring activation by mosquito cytochrome P450 enzymes to induce toxicity while PBO blocks activation of these enzymes in pyrethroid-resistant vector mosquitoes. PBO may thus antagonise the toxicity of pirimiphos-methyl IRS when combined with pyrethroid-PBO ITNs. The impact of combining two major brands of pyrethroid-PBO ITNs (Olyset&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; Plus, PermaNet&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; 3.0) with pirimiphos-methyl IRS (Actellic&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; 300CS) was evaluated against pyrethroid-resistant &lt;italic&gt;Anopheles gambiae&lt;/italic&gt; sl in two parallel experimental hut trials in southern Benin in comparison to bendiocarb IRS and each intervention alone. The wild vector population was resistant to pyrethroids but susceptible to pirimiphos-methyl and bendiocarb. PBO pre-exposure partially restored deltamethrin toxicity but not permethrin. Mosquito mortality in experimental huts was significantly improved in the combinations of bendiocarb IRS with Olyset&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; Plus (33%) and PermaNet&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; 3.0 (38%) compared to bendiocarb IRS alone (14–16%, p&amp;lt;0.001), demonstrating an additive effect. Conversely, mortality was significantly reduced in the combinations of pirimiphos-methyl IRS with Olyset&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; Plus (59%) and PermaNet&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; 3.0 (55%) compared to pirimiphos-methyl IRS alone (77–78%, p&amp;lt;0.001), demonstrating an antagonistic effect. Combining pirimiphos-methyl IRS with the pyrethroid-PBO ITNs provided significantly improved mosquito mortality (55-59%) compared to the pyrethroid-PBO ITNs alone (22-26%) and improved blood-feeding inhibition relative to the IRS alone. This study provided evidence of an antagonistic effect when pyrethroid-PBO ITNs were combined with pirimiphos-methyl IRS in the same household resulting in lower levels of vector mosquito mortality compared to the IRS alone. Pirimiphos-methyl IRS also showed potential to significantly enhance malaria control when deployed to complement pyrethroid-PBO ITNs in an area where PBO fails to fully restore susceptibility to pyrethroids.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471747" rel="alternate" title="Can pyrethroid-piperonyl butoxide (PBO) nets reduce the efficacy of indoor residual spraying with pirimiphos-methyl against pyrethroid-resistant malaria vectors? (5 tweets)"/><category term="Zoology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471462</id><title>Dairy vs. beef production – expert views on welfare (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.516477+00:00</updated><author><name>Roi Mandel</name></author><author><name>Marc B.M. Bracke</name></author><author><name>Christine J. Nicol</name></author><author><name>John A. Webster</name></author><author><name>Lorenz Gygax</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Consumers’ views and concerns about the welfare of farm animals may play an important role in their decision to consume dairy, meat and/or plants as their primary protein source. As animals are killed prematurely in both dairy and beef industries, it is important to quantify and compare welfare compromise in these two sectors before the point of death. Seventy world-leading bovine welfare experts based in 23 countries, were asked to evaluate the likelihood of a bovine to experience 12 states of potential welfare concern, inspired by the Welfare Quality® protocol. The evaluation focused on the most common beef and dairy production systems in the experts’ country, and was carried out separately for dairy/beef calves raised for red-meat, dairy/beef calves raised for veal, dairy/beef calves raised as replacement, and for dairy/beef cows. The results show experts rated the overall likelihood of a negative welfare state (i.e. welfare risk) to be higher in animals from dairy herds than from beef herds, for all animal categories, regardless of whether they were used to produce milk, red-meat or veal. These findings suggest that consuming food products derived from common dairy production systems (dairy or meat), may be more harmful to the welfare of animals than consuming products derived from common beef production systems (i.e. from animals solely raised for their meat). Raising awareness about the linkage between dairy and meat production, and the toll of milk production on the welfare state of animals in the dairy industry, may encourage a more sustainable and responsible food consumption.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471462" rel="alternate" title="Dairy vs. beef production – expert views on welfare (5 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471264</id><title>Improving replicability using interaction with laboratories: a multi-lab experimental assessment (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.516617+00:00</updated><author><name>Iman Jaljuli</name></author><author><name>Neri Kafkafi</name></author><author><name>Eliezer Giladi</name></author><author><name>Ilan Golani</name></author><author><name>Illana Gozes</name></author><author><name>Elissa Chesler</name></author><author><name>Molly A. Bogue</name></author><author><name>Yoav Benjamini</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Phenotyping inbred and genetically-engineered mouse lines has become a central strategy for discovering mammalian gene function and evaluating pharmacological treatment. Yet the utility of any findings critically depends on their replicability in other laboratories. In previous publications we proposed a statistical approach for estimating the inter-laboratory replicability of novel discoveries in a single laboratory, and demonstrated that previous phenotyping results from multi-lab databases can be used to derive a Genotype-by-Lab (GxL) adjustment factor to ensure the replicability of single-lab results, for similarly measured phenotypes, even before making the effort of replicating the new finding in additional laboratories.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The demonstration above, however, still raised several important questions that could only be answered by an additional large-scale prospective experiment: Does GxL-adjustment works in single-lab experiments that were not intended to be standardized across laboratories? With genotypes that were not included in the previous experiments? And can it be used to adjust the results of pharmacological treatment experiments? We replicated results from five studies in the Mouse Phenome Database (MPD), in three behavioral tests, across three laboratories, offering 212 comparisons including 60 involving a pharmacological treatment: 18 mg/kg/day fluoxetine. In addition, we define and use a dimensionless GxL factor, derived from dividing the GxL variance by the standard deviation between animals within groups, as the more robust vehicle to transfer the adjustment from the multi-lab analysis to very different labs and genotypes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For genotype comparisons, GxL-adjustment reduced the rate of non-replicable discoveries from 60% to 12%, for the price of reducing the power to make replicable discoveries from 87% to 66%. Another way to look at these results is noting that the adjustment could have prevented 23 failures to replicate, for the price of missing only three replicated ones. The tools and data needed for deployment of this method across other mouse experiments are publicly available in the Mouse Phenome Database.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our results further point at some phenotypes as more prone to produce non-replicable results, while others, known to be more difficult to measure, are as likely to produce replicable results (once adjusted) as the physiological body weight is.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471264" rel="alternate" title="Improving replicability using interaction with laboratories: a multi-lab experimental assessment (5 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>