<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular zoology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.321017+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/zoology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469585</id><title>Improving behavior monitoring of free moving dairy cows using non invasive wireless EEG approach and digital signal processing techniques (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.321300+00:00</updated><author><name>Ana Carolina de Sousa Silva</name></author><author><name>Aldo Ivan Céspedes Arce</name></author><author><name>Hubert Luzdemio Arteaga Miñano</name></author><author><name>Gustavo Voltani von Atzingen</name></author><author><name>Valeria Cristina Rodrigues Sarnighausen</name></author><author><name>Ernane José Xavier Costa</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electroencephalography (EEG) is the most common method to access brain information. Techniques to monitor and to extract brain signal characteristics in farm animals are not as developed as in humans and laboratory animals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;New method&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The method comprised two steps. In the first step, the signals were acquired after the telemetric equipment was developed, the electrodes were positioned and fixed, the sample frequency was defined, the equipment was positioned, and artifacts and other acquisition problems were dealt with. Brain signals from six Holstein heifers that could move freely in free stalls were acquired. The control group consisted in the same number of bovines, contained in a climatic chamber (restrained group). In the second step, the signals were characterized by Power Spectral Density, Short-Time Fourier Transform, and Lempel-Ziv complexity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The results indicated that there was an ideal position to attach the electrodes to the front of the bovine’s head, so that longer artifact-free signal sections were acquired. The signals showed typical EEG frequency bands, like the bands found in humans. The Lempel-Ziv complexity values indicated that the bovine brain signals contained random and chaotic components. As expected, the signals acquired from the retained bovine group displayed sections with a larger number of artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Comparison with existing methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present the first method that helps to monitor and to extract brain signal features in unrestrained bovines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The method could be applied to investigate changes in brain electrical activity during animal farming, to monitor brain activity related with animal behavior.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;A method that allows brain signals to be monitored in freely moving dairy cows is described&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The method uses noninvasive electrodes to minimize stress during EEG monitoring and allows bovines to behave normally during the process&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The method establishes the frequency sampling rate, electrodes positioning and fixation, equipment holding, artifact extraction, and signal characterization&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The brain signals are characterized by PSD, STFT, and Lempel-Ziv normalized complexity&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The method can be applied to relate EEG to animal behavior under normal handling conditions&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469585" rel="alternate" title="Improving behavior monitoring of free moving dairy cows using non invasive wireless EEG approach and digital signal processing techniques (13 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469808</id><title>Viral dynamics and immune responses to foot-and-mouth disease virus in African buffalo (Syncerus caffer). (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.321512+00:00</updated><author><name>Eva Perez-Martin</name></author><author><name>Brianna Beechler</name></author><author><name>Katherine Scott</name></author><author><name>Lin-Mari de Klerk-Lorist</name></author><author><name>Fuquan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Georgina Limon</name></author><author><name>Brian Dugovich</name></author><author><name>Simon Gubbins</name></author><author><name>Arista Botha</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Juleff</name></author><author><name>Robyn Hetem</name></author><author><name>Louis van Schalkwyk</name></author><author><name>Francois Maree</name></author><author><name>Anna Jolles</name></author><author><name>Bryan Charleston</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Foot-and-mouth disease (FMD) is one of the most important livestock diseases restricting international trade. While it is clear that African buffalo (Syncerus caffer) act as the main wildlife reservoir, viral and immune response dynamics during FMD virus acute infection have not been described before in this species. We used experimental needle inoculation and contact infections with three Southern African Territories serotypes to assess clinical, virological and immunological dynamics for thirty days post infection. Clinical FMD in the needle inoculated buffaloes was mild and characterised by pyrexia. Despite the absence of generalised vesicles, all contact animals were readily infected with their respective serotypes within the first 2-9 days after being mixed with needle challenged buffaloes. Irrespective of the route of infection or serotype there were positive associations between the viral loads in blood and the induction of host innate pro-inflammatory cytokines and acute phase proteins. Viral loads in blood and tonsils were tightly correlated during the acute phase of the infection, however, viraemia significantly declined after a peak at 4 days post infection (dpi), which correlated with the presence of detectable neutralising antibodies. In contrast, infectious virus was isolated in the tonsils until the last sampling point (30 dpi) in most animals. The pattern of virus detection in serum and tonsil swabs was similar for all three serotypes in the direct challenged and contact challenged animals. We have demonstrated for the first time, that African buffalo are indeed systemically affected by FMD virus and clinical FMD in buffalo is characterized by a transient pyrexia.  Despite the lack of FMD lesions, infection of African buffalo was characterised by high viral loads in blood and oropharynx, rapid and strong host innate and adaptive immune responses and high transmissibility.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469808" rel="alternate" title="Viral dynamics and immune responses to foot-and-mouth disease virus in African buffalo (Syncerus caffer). (3 tweets)"/><category term="Zoology"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>