<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular zoology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:34:31.389810+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/zoology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453525</id><title>Insights on the historical biogeography of Philippine native pigs and its relationship with Continental domestic and wild boars (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:34:31.390375+00:00</updated><author><name>John King N. Layos</name></author><author><name>Ronel N. Geromo</name></author><author><name>Dinah M. Espina</name></author><author><name>Masahide Nishibori</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Philippine archipelago was believed to have never been connected to the Asian continent even during the severe Quaternary sea-level drops. As a result, the history of pig dispersal in the Philippines remains controversial and must have some anthropogenic origin associated with some human migration events. In this study, the context of origin, dispersal, and the level of genetic introgression in Philippine native pigs were deduced using mitochondrial DNA D-loop analysis altogether with domestic pigs and wild boars corresponding to their geographic origin. Results revealed a considerable genetic diversity (0.900±0.016), and a widespread Asian pig-ancestry (94.60%) were revealed in the phylogenetic analysis with admixed European pig-origin (5.10%) harboring various fractions of ancestry from Berkshire and Landrace. The close genetic connection between the continental wild boars and domestic pigs present in the Philippine pigs corroborates our hypothesis of a genetic signal that could potentially be associated with the recently reported multiple waves of human migrations to the Philippines during the last 50,000 years. The high frequency of haplotypes (54.08%) that collapsed in the D7 haplogroup represent an interesting challenge as its distribution does not coincide with the hypothesized migratory route of the Neolithic Austronesian-speaking populations. We detected the first Pacific Clade signature and ubiquitously distributed D2 haplotypes which postulate the legitimate dispersal of pigs associated with the multiple waves of human migrations involving the Philippines. The multimodal mismatch and neutrality test statistics both Fu’s F&lt;italic&gt;s&lt;/italic&gt; and Tajima’s D correlates the long stationary period of effective population size revealed in the Bayesian skyline plot. While the sudden decrease in population was consistent with the pronounced population bottleneck of Asian and European pigs during the interglacial periods of the Pleistocene.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453525" rel="alternate" title="Insights on the historical biogeography of Philippine native pigs and its relationship with Continental domestic and wild boars (5 tweets)"/><category term="Zoology"/><published>2021-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>