<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular zoology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.067954+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/zoology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467047</id><title>The evolution of color naming reflects pressure for efficiency: Evidence from the recent past (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.068178+00:00</updated><author><name>Noga Zaslavsky</name></author><author><name>Karee Garvin</name></author><author><name>Charles Kemp</name></author><author><name>Naftali Tishby</name></author><author><name>Terry Regier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It has been proposed that semantic systems evolve under pressure for efficiency. This hypothesis has so far been supported largely indirectly, by synchronic cross-language comparison, rather than directly by diachronic data. Here, we directly test this hypothesis in the domain of color naming, by analyzing recent diachronic data from Nafaanra, a language of Ghana and Côte d’Ivoire, and comparing it with quantitative predictions derived from the mathematical theory of efficient data compression. We show that color naming in Nafaanra has changed over the past four decades while remaining near-optimally efficient, and that this outcome would be unlikely under a random drift process that maintains structured color categories without pressure for efficiency. To our knowledge, this finding provides the first direct evidence that color naming evolves under pressure for efficiency, supporting the hypothesis that efficiency shapes the evolution of the lexicon.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467047" rel="alternate" title="The evolution of color naming reflects pressure for efficiency: Evidence from the recent past (5 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468986</id><title>Morpholino-mediated knockdown of the brain mineralocorticoid receptor affects glucocorticoid signaling and neuroplasticity in wild ocellated wrasse (Symphodus ocellatus) (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.068348+00:00</updated><author><name>Bridget M. Nugent</name></author><author><name>Kelly A. Stiver</name></author><author><name>Jiawei Han</name></author><author><name>Holly K Kindsvater</name></author><author><name>Susan E. Marsh-Rollo</name></author><author><name>Hans A. Hofmann</name></author><author><name>Suzanne H. Alonzo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Uncovering the genetic, physiological, and developmental mechanisms underlying phenotypic variation is necessary for understanding how genetic and genomic variation shape phenotypic variation and for discovering possible targets of selection. Although the neural and endocrine mechanisms underlying social behavior are evolutionarily ancient, we lack an understanding of the proximate causes and evolutionary consequences of variation in these mechanisms. Here, we examine in the natural environment the behavioral, neuromolecular, and fitness consequences of a morpholino-mediated knockdown of the mineralocorticoid receptor (MR) in the brain of nesting males of the ocellated wrasse, Symphodus ocellatus, a species with male alternative reproductive tactics. Even though MR knockdown did not significantly change male behavior directly, this experimental manipulation strongly altered glucocorticoid signaling and neuroplasticity in the preoptic area, the putative hippocampus homolog, and the putative basolateral amygdala homolog. We also found that individual variation in stress axis gene expression and neuroplasticity is strongly associated with variation in male behavior and fitness-related traits. The brain region-specific effects of MR knockdown on phenotypic integration in the wild reported here suggest specific neuroendocrine and neuroplasticity pathways that may be targets of selection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468986" rel="alternate" title="Morpholino-mediated knockdown of the brain mineralocorticoid receptor affects glucocorticoid signaling and neuroplasticity in wild ocellated wrasse (Symphodus ocellatus) (4 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.464426</id><title>Parental control: ecology drives plasticity in parental response to offspring signals (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.068497+00:00</updated><author><name>Shana Caro</name></author><author><name>Adara C Velasco</name></author><author><name>Tjomme van Mastrigt</name></author><author><name>Kees van Oers</name></author><author><name>Ashleigh S Griffin</name></author><author><name>Stuart A West</name></author><author><name>Camilla A Hinde</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Different bird species have completely different parent-offspring interactions. When food is plentiful, the chicks that are begging the loudest are fed the most. When food is scarce, bird species instead feed the largest offspring. While this variation could be due to parents responding to signalling differently based on food availability, it could equally be due to offspring adjusting their behaviour, or to variation in information availability. We tested between these competing explanations experimentally, by manipulating food availability in a population of wild great tits, Parus major, while standardising offspring behaviour and size. We found that when food was more plentiful, parents were: (1) more likely to preferentially feed the chicks that were begging the most; and (2) less likely to preferentially feed larger chicks. In addition, we consistently found these same patterns, in a meta-analysis across 57 bird species. Overall, our results suggest that parents have more control over food distribution than offspring do, and that they flexibly adjust how they respond to both offspring signals and cues of offspring quality in response to food availability. Consequently, depending upon environmental conditions, predictably different signalling systems are favoured.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.464426" rel="alternate" title="Parental control: ecology drives plasticity in parental response to offspring signals (3 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468751</id><title>Transcription Factor Gene Pea3 Regulates Erectile Function in Mice (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.068644+00:00</updated><author><name>Jarret A.P. Weinrich</name></author><author><name>Aanchal Tyagi</name></author><author><name>Megan C. Kenney</name></author><author><name>Richard J. DiCasoli</name></author><author><name>Julia A. Kaltschmidt</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Male mice with homozygous loss of function mutations of the &lt;italic&gt;ETS&lt;/italic&gt; transcription factor gene &lt;italic&gt;Pea3&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Pea3&lt;/italic&gt; null) are infertile due to their inability to deposit semen plugs, however the specific deficits in male sexual behaviors that drive this phenotype are unknown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aim&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To investigate the regulatory role of the &lt;italic&gt;Pea3&lt;/italic&gt; gene in organizing gross sexual behaviors and erectile functioning during active copulation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The copulatory behavior of male mice (&lt;italic&gt;Pea3&lt;/italic&gt; null and control) with hormonally primed ovariectomized females was monitored via high-speed and high-resolution digital videography to assess for differences in female-directed social behaviors, gross sexual behaviors (mounting, thrusting), and erectile and ejaculatory function.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Outcomes&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Pea3&lt;/italic&gt; null male mice have dramatically reduced erectile function during sexual intercourse, however other aspects of male sexual behaviors are largely intact.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Pea3&lt;/italic&gt; null male mice exhibit greatly reduced erectile function, with 44% of males displaying no visible erections during mounting behaviors, and none achieving sustained erections. As such, &lt;italic&gt;Pea3&lt;/italic&gt; null males are incapable of intromission, and semen plug deposition, despite displaying largely normal female-directed social behaviors, mounting behaviors, and ejaculatory grasping behavior. Additionally, the coordination of the timing of thrusting trains is impaired in &lt;italic&gt;Pea3&lt;/italic&gt; null males.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Clinical Implications&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The identification of the transcription factor &lt;italic&gt;Pea3&lt;/italic&gt; in regulating erectile function in mice may provide a useful target for understanding the genetics of male sexual dysfunction in human patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Strengths and Limitations&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;High-speed and high-resolution videography allows for a detailed analysis of male sexual behaviors and erectile functioning in &lt;italic&gt;Pea3&lt;/italic&gt; null and control mice. How disruption of the &lt;italic&gt;Pea3&lt;/italic&gt; gene translates to erectile dysfunction is still unknown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The transcription factor gene &lt;italic&gt;Pea3&lt;/italic&gt; regulates the ability to achieve and maintain erections in male mice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468751" rel="alternate" title="Transcription Factor Gene Pea3 Regulates Erectile Function in Mice (3 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468665</id><title>Random attention can explain apparent object choice behavior in free-walking blowflies (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.068777+00:00</updated><author><name>José Monteagudo</name></author><author><name>Martin Egelhaaf</name></author><author><name>Jens Peter Lindemann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Flies are often observed to approach dark objects. To a naïve observer they seem to pay selective attention to one out of several objects although previous research identified a reflex-like fixation behavior integrating responses to all objects as possible underlying mechanism. In a combination of behavioral experiments and computational modelling, we investigate the choice behavior of flies freely walking towards an arrangement of two objects placed at a variable distance from each other. The walking trajectories are oriented towards one of the objects much earlier than predicted by a simple reactive model. We show that object choice can be explained by a continuous control scheme in combination with a mechanism randomly responding to the position of each object according to a stochastic process. Although this may be viewed as a special form of an attention-like mechanism, the model does not require an explicit decision mechanism or a memory for the drawn decision.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Walking blowflies apparently choose one of two objects to approach. In model simulations, a fixation scheme combined with random attention replicates this behavior without an explicit decision mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468665" rel="alternate" title="Random attention can explain apparent object choice behavior in free-walking blowflies (3 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>