<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular zoology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.207750+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/zoology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470558</id><title>An experimental test of chronic traffic noise exposure on parental behaviour and reproduction in zebra finches (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.208222+00:00</updated><author><name>Quanxiao Liu</name></author><author><name>Esther Gelok</name></author><author><name>Kiki Fontein</name></author><author><name>Hans Slabbekoorn</name></author><author><name>Katharina Riebel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chronic traffic noise is increasingly recognised as a potential hazard to wildlife. Various songbird species, for example, have been shown to breed poorly in traffic noise exposed habitats. However, identifying whether noise is causal in this requires experimental approaches. We here tested whether experimental exposure to chronic traffic noise affected parental behaviour and reproductive success in offspring number and growth in an important model of avian development, the zebra finch (&lt;italic&gt;Taeniopygia guttata&lt;/italic&gt;). In a counterbalanced repeated-measures design, breeding pairs experienced continuous playbacks of one of two types of highway noise that previous spatial choice tests had shown to be neutral (control) or aversive. We monitored offspring development and parental feeding rates and nest attendance. Parental nest attendance was positively correlated with feeding effort and was higher in the aversive than in the control sound treatment and this effect was more pronounced for parents attending larger broods. However, neither noise condition affected offspring number, growth or body mass. There was also an absence of an effect of noisy conditions on these reproductive parameters when we combined our data with two other comparable studies in the same species in a meta-analysis. We discuss whether the increased parental engagement is a potential compensatory strategy that alleviated direct noise effects on the chicks. However, impaired parent-offspring or within-pair communication could also have increased parents’ nest attendance time. Future work is required to test these possible explanations and investigate potential long-term costs of increased parental engagement.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470558" rel="alternate" title="An experimental test of chronic traffic noise exposure on parental behaviour and reproduction in zebra finches (4 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470324</id><title>Ambiguous Body Ownership Experience Caused by Feeling–judgement Conflict: Evidence from Subjective Measurement in Rubber Hand Illusion using Integrated Information Theory (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.208537+00:00</updated><author><name>Takayuki Niizato</name></author><author><name>Yuta Nishiyama</name></author><author><name>Kotaro Sakamoto</name></author><author><name>Takumi Kazama</name></author><author><name>Tatsuya Okabayashi</name></author><author><name>Taiki Yamaguchi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human body awareness is malleable and adaptive to changing contexts. The illusory sense of body-ownership has been studied since the publication of the rubber hand illusion, where ambiguous body ownership feeling, expressed as “the dummy hand is my hand even though that is not true”, was first defined. Phenomenologically, the ambiguous body ownership is attributed to a conflict between feeling and judgement; in other words, it characterises a discrepancy between first-person (i.e. bottom-up) and third-person (i.e. top-down) processes. Although Bayesian inference can explain this malleability of body image sufficiently, the theory does not provide a good illustration of why we have different experiences to the same stimuli – the difficulty lies in the uncertainty regarding the concept of judgement in their theory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study attempts to explain subjective experience during rubber hand illusions using integrated information theory (IIT). The integrated information Φ in IIT measures the difference between the entire system and its subsystems. This concept agrees with the phenomenological interpretation – that is, there is conflict between judgement and feeling. By analysing the seven nodes of a small body– brain system, we demonstrate that the integrity of the entire system during the illusion decreases with increasing integrity of its subsystems. These general tendencies agree well with many brain-image analyses and subjective reports; furthermore, we found that subjective ratings were associated with the Φs. Our result suggests that IIT can explain the general tendency of the sense of ownership illusions and individual differences in subjective experience during the illusions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470324" rel="alternate" title="Ambiguous Body Ownership Experience Caused by Feeling–judgement Conflict: Evidence from Subjective Measurement in Rubber Hand Illusion using Integrated Information Theory (3 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471164</id><title>Social migratory connectivity: do birds that socialize in winter breed together? (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.208977+00:00</updated><author><name>Theadora A Block</name></author><author><name>bruce E. Lyon</name></author><author><name>Zachary Mikalonis</name></author><author><name>Alexis S Chaine</name></author><author><name>Daizaburo Shizuka</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Researching the complete life cycles of migratory animals is essential for understanding conservation and population dynamics. Many studies focus on the breeding season, but surviving winter is equally important. Living in groups during winter can play a vital role as social connections within groups can provide many benefits such as protection from predators and increased access to resources. However, it is often unknown how social connections change across seasons in migratory animals. We focus on social connections in a migratory bird and ask whether social connections in winter continue during breeding. Golden-crowned sparrows have distinct, stable winter communities which include both site and group fidelity across years: birds almost always rejoin the same social community each year. If these birds have social connectivity across migration, we would expect individuals that associate in winter would also associate together on their breeding grounds. Our small-scale GPS tagging study combined with intensive social behavior data revealed that sparrows in the same tightly-knit winter community migrated to highly disparate locations during summer, showing that social connections in winter do not continue in summer. This suggests that golden-crowned sparrows have entirely separate social structures across seasons and that long-term social memories allow them to reform stable groups each winter.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471164" rel="alternate" title="Social migratory connectivity: do birds that socialize in winter breed together? (3 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>