<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular zoology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.382917+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/zoology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476116</id><title>Impaired spatial memory in adult vitamin D deficient BALB/c mice is associated with reductions in spine density, nitric oxide, and neural nitric oxide synthase in the hippocampus (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.383052+00:00</updated><author><name>Md. Mamun Al-Amin</name></author><author><name>Robert K. P. Sullivan</name></author><author><name>Suzy. Alexander</name></author><author><name>David A. Carter</name></author><author><name>DanaKai. Bradford</name></author><author><name>Thomas H. J. Burne</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Vitamin D deficiency is prevalent in adults and is associated with cognitive impairment. However, the mechanism by which adult vitamin D (AVD) deficiency affects cognitive function remains unclear. We examined spatial memory impairment in AVD-deficient BALB/c mice and its underlying mechanism by measuring spine density, long term potentiation (LTP), nitric oxide (NO), neuronal nitric oxide synthase (nNOS) and endothelial NOS (eNOS) in the hippocampus. Adult male BALB/c mice were fed a control or vitamin D deficient diet for 20 weeks. Spatial memory performance was measured using an active place avoidance (APA) task, where AVD-deficient mice had reduced latency entering the shock zone compared to controls. We characterised hippocampal spine morphology in the CA1 and dentate gyrus (DG) and made electrophysiological recordings in the hippocampus of behaviourally naïve mice to measure LTP. We next measured NO, as well as glutathione, lipid peroxidation and oxidation of protein products and quantified hippocampal immunoreactivity for nNOS and eNOS. Spine morphology analysis revealed a significant reduction in the number of mushroom spines in the CA1 dendrites but not in the DG. There was no effect of diet on LTP. However, hippocampal NO levels were depleted whereas other oxidation markers were unaltered by AVD deficiency. We also showed a reduced nNOS, but not eNOS, immunoreactivity. Finally, vitamin D supplementation for 10 weeks to AVD-deficient mice restored nNOS immunoreactivity to that seen in in control mice. Our results suggest that lower levels of NO, reduced nNOS immunostaining contribute to hippocampal-dependent spatial learning deficits in AVD-deficient mice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476116" rel="alternate" title="Impaired spatial memory in adult vitamin D deficient BALB/c mice is associated with reductions in spine density, nitric oxide, and neural nitric oxide synthase in the hippocampus (10 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475627</id><title>Head Removal Enhances Planarian Electrotaxis (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.383142+00:00</updated><author><name>Ziad Sabry</name></author><author><name>Rui Wang</name></author><author><name>Aryo Jahromi</name></author><author><name>Christina Rabeler</name></author><author><name>William B. Kristan</name></author><author><name>Eva-Maria S. Collins</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sensing electric fields is an ability that certain animal species utilize for communication, hunting, and spatial orientation. Freshwater planarians move toward the cathode in a static electric field (cathodic electrotaxis). First described by Raymond Pearl more than a century ago, planarian electrotaxis has received little attention and the underlying mechanisms and evolutionary significance remain unknown. We developed an apparatus and scoring metrics for automated quantitative and mechanistic studies of planarian behavior upon exposure to a static electric field. Using this automated setup, we characterized electrotaxis in the planarian &lt;italic&gt;Dugesia japonica&lt;/italic&gt; and found that this species responds to voltage instead of to current, in contrast to results from previous studies using other species. Because longer planarians exhibited more robust electrotaxis than shorter planarians, we hypothesized that signals from the head impede cathodic electrotaxis. To test this hypothesis, we took advantage of the regenerative abilities of planarians and compared electrotaxis in head and tail fragments of various lengths. We found that tail and trunk fragments electrotaxed while head fragments did not, regardless of size. However, we could restore cathodic electrotaxis in head fragments via decapitation, demonstrating that the presence of the head impaired cathodic electrotaxis. This result is in stark contrast to other stimulated behaviors such as phototaxis, thermotaxis or chemotaxis, which are weaker or absent in headless fragments. Thus, electrotaxis may be an important ability of headless planarian fragments to support survival prior to head regeneration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present a new method for quantitative studies of planarian electrotaxis and show that &lt;italic&gt;Dugesia japonica&lt;/italic&gt; move toward the cathode. This behavior is enhanced by removal of the head.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475627" rel="alternate" title="Head Removal Enhances Planarian Electrotaxis (6 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475834</id><title>House sparrows do not exhibit a preference for the scent of potential partners with different MHC-I allele numbers and genetic distances (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.383218+00:00</updated><author><name>Luisa Amo</name></author><author><name>Guillermo Amo de Paz</name></author><author><name>Johanna Kabbert</name></author><author><name>Annie Machordom</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;MHC genes play a fundamental role in immune recognition of pathogens and parasites. Therefore, females may increase offspring heterozygosity and genetic diversity by selecting MHC genetically compatible or heterozygous males. In birds, several studies suggest that MHC genes play a role in mate choice, and recent evidence suggest that olfaction may play a role in such discrimination. Previous studies indicated that house sparrow females with low allelic diversity prefer males with higher diversity in MHC-I alleles. Here, we directly explored whether both house sparrow females and males could estimate by scent the number in MHC amino acid and functional variants as well as the level of MHC-I similarity or dissimilarity of potential partners. Our results show that neither females nor males exhibit a preference related to the number of MHC-I amino acid variants or functional variants or in relation to MHC amino acid or functional similarity of potential partners, suggesting that MHC-I is not detected through olfaction. Further studies are needed to understand the mechanisms responsible for MHC-I based mate discrimination in birds.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475834" rel="alternate" title="House sparrows do not exhibit a preference for the scent of potential partners with different MHC-I allele numbers and genetic distances (5 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>