<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular zoology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.912306+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/zoology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455910</id><title>Hippocampal place cells as a cryptographic tool that enables animals to secretly cache and retrieve their food (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.912698+00:00</updated><author><name>Oren Forkosh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;For animals, the ability to hide and retrieve valuable information, such as the location of food, can mean the difference between life and death. Here, we propose that to achieve this, their brain uses spatial cells similarly to how we utilize encryption for data security. Some animals are able to cache hundreds of thousands of food items annually by each individual and later retrieve most of what they themselves stashed. Rather than memorizing their cache locations as previously suggested, we propose that they use a single cryptographic-like mechanism during both caching and retrieval. The model we developed is based on hippocampal spatial cells, which respond to an animal’s positional attention, such as when the animal enters a specific region (place-cells) or gazes at a particular location (spatial-view-cells). We know that the region that activates each spatial cell remains consistent across subsequent visits to the same area but not between areas. This remapping, combined with the uniqueness of cognitive maps, produces a persistent crypto-hash function for both food caching and retrieval. We also show that the model stores temporal information that helps animals in food caching order preference as previously observed. This behavior, which we refer to as crypto-taxis, might also explain consistent differences in decision-making when animals are faced with a large number of alternatives such as in foraging.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455910" rel="alternate" title="Hippocampal place cells as a cryptographic tool that enables animals to secretly cache and retrieve their food (9 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455968</id><title>Forgetting Enhances Episodic Control with Structured Memories (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.912873+00:00</updated><author><name>Annik Yalnizyan-Carson</name></author><author><name>Blake A. Richards</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Forgetting is a normal process in healthy brains, and evidence suggests that the mammalian brain forgets more than is required based on limitations of mnemonic capacity. Episodic memories, in particular, are liable to be forgotten over time. Researchers have hypothesized that it may be beneficial for decision making to forget episodic memories over time. Reinforcement learning offers a normative framework in which to test such hypotheses. Here, we show that a reinforcement learning agent that uses an episodic memory cache to find rewards in maze environments can forget a large percentage of older memories without any performance impairments, if they utilize mnemonic representations that contain structural information about space. Moreover, we show that some forgetting can actually provide a benefit in performance compared to agents with unbounded memories. Our analyses of the agents show that forgetting reduces the influence of outdated information and states which are not frequently visited on the policies produced by the episodic control system. These results support the hypothesis that some degree of forgetting can be beneficial for decision making, which can help to explain why the brain forgets more than is required by capacity limitations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455968" rel="alternate" title="Forgetting Enhances Episodic Control with Structured Memories (6 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456071</id><title>Uncertainty avoidance versus conditioned reinforcement: exploring paradoxical choice in rats (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.913017+00:00</updated><author><name>Victor Ajuwon</name></author><author><name>Andrés Ojeda</name></author><author><name>Robin A. Murphy</name></author><author><name>Tiago Monteiro</name></author><author><name>Alex Kacelnik</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Paying a cost to reduce uncertainty can be adaptive, because better informed decision-makers can align their preferences to opportunities. However, birds and mammals display an appetite for information that they cannot use to functionally alter behaviour or its outcomes. We explore two putative motivational mechanisms for this paradoxical behaviour. The information hypothesis proposes that reducing uncertainty is reinforcing &lt;italic&gt;per se&lt;/italic&gt;, consistent with the concept of curiosity: a motivation to know, in the absence of instrumental benefits. In contrast, the conditioned reinforcement hypothesis sees information-seeking as a consequence of asymmetries in secondarily acquired reinforcement: responding increments caused by post-choice stimuli announcing positive outcomes (S&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;) exceed decrements caused by stimuli signalling absence of reward (S&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt;). We contrast these hypotheses experimentally. Rats chose between two equally profitable options delivering food probabilistically after a fixed delay. In the informative option (&lt;italic&gt;Info&lt;/italic&gt;), the outcome (food/no food) was signalled immediately after choice, whereas in the non-informative option (&lt;italic&gt;NoInfo&lt;/italic&gt;) outcomes were uncertain until the delay lapsed. Subjects preferred (&lt;italic&gt;Info&lt;/italic&gt;) when (1) outcomes were signalled by salient auditory cues, (2) only the absence of reward was signalled, and (3) only reward was signalled, though acquisition was slower when rewards were not explicitly signalled. Our results show that a salient good news signal is not required as a conditioned reinforcer to generate paradoxical preferences. Terminal preferences support the information hypothesis but the slower acquisition of (&lt;italic&gt;Info&lt;/italic&gt;) preference when S&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; is not present is consistent with the conditioning account. We conclude that both uncertainty reduction and conditioned reinforcement influence choice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456071" rel="alternate" title="Uncertainty avoidance versus conditioned reinforcement: exploring paradoxical choice in rats (6 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456046</id><title>Escaping from multiple visual threats: Modulation of escape responses in Pacific staghorn sculpin (Leptocottus armatus). (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.913176+00:00</updated><author><name>Hibiki Kimura</name></author><author><name>Tilo Pfalzgraff</name></author><author><name>Marie Levet</name></author><author><name>Yuuki Kawabata</name></author><author><name>John F Steffensen</name></author><author><name>Jacob L Johansen</name></author><author><name>Paolo Domenici</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fish perform rapid escape responses to avoid sudden predatory attacks. During escape responses, fish bend their bodies into a C-shape and quickly turn away from the predator and accelerate. The escape trajectory is determined by the initial turn (Stage 1) and a contralateral bend (Stage 2). Previous studies have used a single threat or model predator as a stimulus. In nature, however, multiple predators may attack from different directions simultaneously or in close succession. It is unknown whether fish are able to change the course of their escape response when startled by multiple stimuli at various time intervals. Pacific staghorn sculpin (&lt;italic&gt;Leptocottus armatus&lt;/italic&gt;) were startled with a left and right visual stimulus in close succession. By varying the timing of the second stimulus, we were able to determine when and how a second stimulus could affect the escape response direction. Four treatments were used: a single visual stimulus (control); or two stimuli coming from opposite sides separated by a 0 ms (simultaneous treatment); a 33 ms; or a 83 ms time interval. The 33 ms and 83 ms time intervals were chosen to occur shortly before and after a predicted 60 ms visual escape latency (i.e. during Stage 1). The 0 ms and 33 ms treatments influenced both the escape trajectory and the Stage 1 turning angle, compared to a single stimulation, whereas the 83 ms treatment had no effect on the escape response. We conclude that Pacific staghorn sculpin can modulate their escape response only between stimulation and the onset of the response, but that escape responses are ballistic after the body motion has started.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456046" rel="alternate" title="Escaping from multiple visual threats: Modulation of escape responses in Pacific staghorn sculpin (Leptocottus armatus). (6 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455992</id><title>Experimental evidence that chronic outgroup conflict reduces reproductive success in a cooperatively breeding fish (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.913341+00:00</updated><author><name>Ines Braga Goncalves</name></author><author><name>Andrew N. Radford</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Conflicts with conspecific outsiders are common in group-living species, from ants to primates, and are argued to be an important selective force in social evolution. However, whilst an extensive empirical literature exists on the behaviour exhibited during and immediately after interactions with rivals, only very few observational studies have considered the cumulative fitness consequences of outgroup conflict. Using a cooperatively breeding fish, the daffodil cichlid (&lt;italic&gt;Neolamprologus pulcher&lt;/italic&gt;), we conducted the first experimental test of the effects of chronic outgroup conflict on reproductive investment and output. ‘Intruded’ groups received long-term simulated territorial intrusions by neighbours that generated consistent group-defence behaviour; matched ‘Control’ groups (each the same size and with the same neighbours as an Intruded group) received no intrusions in the same period. Intruded groups had longer inter-clutch intervals and produced eggs with less protein than Control groups. Despite this lower egg investment, Intruded groups provided more parental care, achieving similar hatching success to Control groups. Ultimately, however, Intruded groups had fewer and smaller surviving offspring than Control groups at 1-month post-hatching. We therefore provide experimental evidence that outgroup conflict can decrease fitness via cumulative effects on reproductive success, confirming the selective potential of this empirically neglected aspect of sociality.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455992" rel="alternate" title="Experimental evidence that chronic outgroup conflict reduces reproductive success in a cooperatively breeding fish (5 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456159</id><title>How big should this object be? Perceptual influences on viewing-size preferences (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.913475+00:00</updated><author><name>Yi-Chia Chen</name></author><author><name>Arturo Deza</name></author><author><name>Talia Konkle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;When viewing objects depicted in a frame, observers prefer to view large objects like cars in larger sizes and smaller objects like cups in smaller sizes. That is, the visual size of an object that "looks best" is linked to its typical physical size in the world. Why is this the case? One intuitive possibility is that these preferences are driven by semantic knowledge: For example, when we recognize a sofa, we access our knowledge about its real-world size, and this influences what size we prefer to view the sofa within a frame. However, might visual processing play a role in this phenomenon--that is, do visual features that are related to big and small objects look better at big and small visual sizes, respectively, even when observers do not have explicit access to semantic knowledge about the objects? To test this possibility, we used "texform" images, which are synthesized versions of recognizable objects, which critically retain local perceptual texture and coarse form information, but are no longer explicitly recognizable. To test for visual size preferences, we used a two-interval forced choice task, in which each texform was presented at the preferred visual size of its corresponding original image, and a visual size slightly bigger or smaller. Observers consistently selected the texform presented at the canonical visual size as the more aesthetically pleasing one. These results suggest that the preferred visual size of an object depends not only on explicit knowledge of its real-world size, but also can be evoked by mid-level visual features that systematically covary with an object's real-world size.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456159" rel="alternate" title="How big should this object be? Perceptual influences on viewing-size preferences (4 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456206</id><title>“Playing mysterious”: occurrence of Bio-duck calls in Brazil reveals a complex acoustic behaviour for the Antarctic minke whale (Balaenoptera bonaerensis) (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.913615+00:00</updated><author><name>Marcos Rossi-Santos</name></author><author><name>Diego Filun</name></author><author><name>William Soares-Filho</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Paro</name></author><author><name>Leonardo Wedekin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Acoustic methods can provide important data on the occurrence and distribution of migratory species. Information about Antarctic Minke whale (Balaenoptera bonaerensis) occurrence in the winter breeding grounds is scarce, mostly limited to old records from whaling stations before 1960’s international moratory, such as Costinha Station in Northeastern Brazil (6° S / 34° W). This work describes the occurrence of the Antarctic minke whale (AMW) through Bio-duck acoustic detections in the Santos Basin, South-Southeastern Brazil (22º and 28º S / 42º and 48º W), registered between November 12 and December 19, 2015. AMW calls were detected for 12 days. We detected and classified 9 different Bio-duck calls in Brazilian coast waters, evidencing a high diverse acoustic behaviour for the minke whale breeding ground. This is the first study to describe the acoustic diversity of AMW vocalizations in lower latitudes, constituting important information to the conservation and management of cetaceans and their habitat. Therefore, our study presents the foremost acoustic evidence of the Antarctic minke whale in Brazil, utilizing high technological passive acoustic methods, such as autonomous underwater vehicle (SeaGlider) sampling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456206" rel="alternate" title="“Playing mysterious”: occurrence of Bio-duck calls in Brazil reveals a complex acoustic behaviour for the Antarctic minke whale (Balaenoptera bonaerensis) (3 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>