<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular zoology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.974324+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/zoology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468077</id><title>Acoustic and postural displays in a miniature and transparent teleost fish, Danionella dracula (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.974514+00:00</updated><author><name>Rose L. Tatarsky</name></author><author><name>Zilin Guo</name></author><author><name>Sarah C. Campbell</name></author><author><name>Helena Kim</name></author><author><name>Wenxuan Fang</name></author><author><name>Jonathan T. Perelmuter</name></author><author><name>Eric R. Schuppe</name></author><author><name>Hudson K. Reeve</name></author><author><name>Andrew H. Bass</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Individuals can reveal their relative competitive ability or mate quality through acoustic communication, varying signals in form and frequency to mediate adaptive interactions including competitive aggression. We report robust acoustic displays during aggressive interactions for a laboratory colony of &lt;italic&gt;Danionella dracula&lt;/italic&gt;, a recently discovered miniature and transparent species of teleost fish closely related to zebrafish (&lt;italic&gt;Danio rerio&lt;/italic&gt;). Males produce bursts of pulsatile, click-like sounds and a distinct postural display, extension of a hypertrophied lower jaw, during resident-intruder dyad interactions. Females lack a hypertrophied lower jaw and show no evidence of sound production or jaw extension under such conditions. Novel pairs of size-matched or mismatched males were combined in resident-intruder assays where sound production and jaw extension could be linked to individuals. Resident males produce significantly more sound pulses than intruders in both dyad contexts; larger males are consistently more sonic in size-mismatched pairs. For both conditions, males show a similar pattern of increased jaw extension that frequently coincided with acoustic displays during periods of heightened sonic activity. These studies firmly establish &lt;italic&gt;D. dracula&lt;/italic&gt; as a sound-producing species that modulates both acoustic and postural displays during social interactions based on either residency or body size, thus providing a foundation for investigating the role of these displays in a new model clade for neurogenomic studies of aggression, courtship and other social interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468077" rel="alternate" title="Acoustic and postural displays in a miniature and transparent teleost fish, Danionella dracula (27 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.07.467581</id><title>Ecological validity of masking release with speech-like stimuli (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.974713+00:00</updated><author><name>Hyojin Kim</name></author><author><name>Viktorija Ratkute</name></author><author><name>Bastian Epp</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Comodulated masking noise and binaural cues can facilitate detecting a target sound from noise. These cues can induce a decrease in detection thresholds, quantified as comodulation masking release (CMR) and binaural masking level difference (BMLD), respectively. However, their relevance to speech perception is unclear as most studies have used artificial stimuli different from speech. Here, we investigated their ecological validity using sounds with speech-like spectro-temporal dynamics. We evaluated the ecological validity of such grouping effect with stimuli reflecting formant changes in speech. We set three masker bands at formant frequencies F1, F2, and F3 based on CV combination: /gu/, /fu/, and /pu/. We found that the CMR was little (&lt;italic&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/italic&gt; 3 dB) while BMLD was comparable to previous findings (∼ 9 dB). In conclusion, we suggest that other features may play a role in facilitating frequency grouping by comodulation such as the spectral proximity and the number of masker bands.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.07.467581" rel="alternate" title="Ecological validity of masking release with speech-like stimuli (4 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>