<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular zoology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.554238+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/zoology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461196</id><title>What is unique about the human eye? Comparative image analysis on the external eye morphology of human and nonhuman great apes (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.554760+00:00</updated><author><name>Fumihiro Kano</name></author><author><name>Takeshi Furuichi</name></author><author><name>Chie Hashimoto</name></author><author><name>Christopher Krupenye</name></author><author><name>Jesse G. Leinwand</name></author><author><name>Lydia M. Hopper</name></author><author><name>Christopher F. Martin</name></author><author><name>Ryoma Otsuka</name></author><author><name>Tomoyuki Tajima</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The gaze-signaling hypothesis and the related cooperative-eye hypothesis posit that humans have evolved special external eye morphology, including exposed white sclera (the white of the eye), to enhance the visibility of eye-gaze direction and thereby facilitate conspecific communication through joint-attentional interaction and ostensive communication. However, recent quantitative studies questioned these hypotheses based on new findings that humans are not necessarily unique in certain eye features compared to other great ape species. Therefore, there is currently a heated debate on whether external eye features of humans are distinguished from those of other apes and how such distinguished features contribute to the visibility of eye-gaze direction. This study leveraged updated image analysis techniques to test the uniqueness of human eye features in facial images of great apes. Although many eye features were similar between humans and other species, a key difference was that humans have uniformly white sclera which creates clear visibility of both eye outline and iris –the two essential features contributing to the visibility of eye-gaze direction. We then tested the robustness of the visibility of these features against visual noises such as darkening and distancing and found that both eye features remain detectable in the human eye, while eye outline becomes barely detectable in other species under these visually challenging conditions. Overall, we identified that humans have distinguished external eye morphology among other great apes, which ensures robustness of eye-gaze signal against various visual conditions. Our results support and also critically update the central premises of the gaze-signaling hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461196" rel="alternate" title="What is unique about the human eye? Comparative image analysis on the external eye morphology of human and nonhuman great apes (11 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-09-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461752</id><title>Unsupervised deep learning reveals a stimulative effect of dopamine D3 receptor agonists on zebrafish sociality (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.556133+00:00</updated><author><name>Yijie Geng</name></author><author><name>Randall T. Peterson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Although some pharmacological agents are known to alter social behaviors, precise description and quantification of such effects have proven difficult. The complexity of brain functions regulating sociality makes it challenging to predict drug effects on social behavior without testing in live animals, and most existing behavioral assays are low-throughput and provide only unidimensional readouts of social function. To achieve richer characterization of drug effects on sociality, we developed a scalable social behavioral assay for zebrafish named ZeChat based on unsupervised deep learning. High-dimensional and dynamic social behavioral phenotypes are automatically classified using this method. By screening a neuroactive compound library, we found that different classes of chemicals evoke distinct patterns of social behavioral fingerprints. By examining these patterns, we discovered that dopamine D3 agonists possess a social stimulative effect on zebrafish. The D3 agonists pramipexole, piribedil, and 7-hydroxy-DPAT-HBr rescued social deficits in a valproic acid-induced zebrafish autism model. The ZeChat platform provides a promising approach for dissecting the pharmacology of social behavior and discovering novel social-modulatory compounds.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461752" rel="alternate" title="Unsupervised deep learning reveals a stimulative effect of dopamine D3 receptor agonists on zebrafish sociality (7 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461476</id><title>An innovative optical context to make honeybees crash repeatedly (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.556500+00:00</updated><author><name>Julien R. Serres</name></author><author><name>Antoine H.P. Morice</name></author><author><name>Constance Blary</name></author><author><name>Romain Miot</name></author><author><name>Gilles Montagne</name></author><author><name>Franck Ruffier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To investigate altitude control in honeybees, an optical context was designed to make honeybees crash. It has been widely accepted that honeybees rely on the optic flow generated by the ground to control their altitude. However, identifying an optical context capable of uncorrelating forward speed from altitude in honeybees’ flight was the first step towards enhancing the optical context to better understand altitude control in honeybees. This optical context aims to put honeybees in the same flight conditions as an open sky flight above mirror-smooth water. An optical manipulation, based on a pair of opposed horizontal mirrors, was designed to remove any visual information coming from the floor and ceiling. Such an optical manipulation reproduced quantitatively the seminal experiment of Heran &amp;amp; Lindauer (1963), and revealed that honeybees control their altitude by detecting the optic flow with a visual field that extends to approximately 165°.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461476" rel="alternate" title="An innovative optical context to make honeybees crash repeatedly (7 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461160</id><title>A report on a characteristic vocalization in Corvus macrorhynchos osai with an indication of vocal learning (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.556785+00:00</updated><author><name>Noriko Kondo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the process of vocal learning, animals give immature vocalization, such as babbling and subsong. Here I report a characteristic vocalization given by a subspecies of large-billed crow, &lt;italic&gt;Corvus macrorhynchos osai&lt;/italic&gt;, that live in Kuroshima Island, Okinawa, Japan. This vocalization (type-K) is characterized by very rapid bill movements (ca. 13 times/sec). The type-K was heard throughout the island, indicating that the population of the Kuroshima Island share this call type. In addition, a juvenile crow was observed giving immature type-K repeatedly. This observation suggests that this call type is not innate but acquired through vocal learning.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461160" rel="alternate" title="A report on a characteristic vocalization in Corvus macrorhynchos osai with an indication of vocal learning (6 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461518</id><title>Early life sleep disruption drives lasting sex-specific changes in behavior in genetically vulnerable Shank3 heterozygous autism model mice (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.556991+00:00</updated><author><name>Julia S. Lord</name></author><author><name>Sean M. Gay</name></author><author><name>Kathryn M. Harper</name></author><author><name>Viktoriya D. Nikolova</name></author><author><name>Kirsten M. Smith</name></author><author><name>Sheryl S. Moy</name></author><author><name>Graham H. Diering</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sleep disruption is a common comorbidity in patients with autism spectrum disorder (ASD), a condition diagnosed with a striking male bias of ∼4:1. It is unclear how sleep disruption contributes to ASD susceptibility, and the sex biased vulnerability. We examined sleep behavior and the effects of early life sleep disruption (ELSD) in developing mice bearing C-terminal truncation (ΔC) in ASD risk gene &lt;italic&gt;Shank3&lt;/italic&gt;. Male and female &lt;italic&gt;Shank3&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;ΔC/ΔC&lt;/sup&gt; homozygotes showed clear sleep disruption early in postnatal life, compared to &lt;italic&gt;Shank3&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;WT/ΔC&lt;/sup&gt; heterozygotes and wild-type littermates, suggesting that sleep disruption may be an early symptom in the expression of ASD. We find that ELSD interacts with genetic vulnerability in &lt;italic&gt;Shank3&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;WT/ΔC&lt;/sup&gt; heterozygotes to drive lasting and sex-specific changes in behavior. Our results clearly show that sleep disruption during sensitive periods of postnatal development is causative of lasting changes in behavior in genetically vulnerable individuals, but in a striking sex-specific manner.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461518" rel="alternate" title="Early life sleep disruption drives lasting sex-specific changes in behavior in genetically vulnerable Shank3 heterozygous autism model mice (6 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461403</id><title>Prolactin and the regulation of parental care and helping behavior in cooperatively breeding white-browed sparrow weaver societies (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.557328+00:00</updated><author><name>Lindsay A. Walker</name></author><author><name>Linda Tschirren</name></author><author><name>Jennifer E. York</name></author><author><name>Peter J. Sharp</name></author><author><name>Simone L. Meddle</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Young</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In many cooperatively breeding societies non-breeding individuals help to rear the offspring of breeders. The physiological mechanisms that regulate such cooperative helping behavior are poorly understood, but may have been co-opted, during the evolution of cooperative breeding, from pre-existing mechanisms that regulated parental care. Key among these may be a role for prolactin. Here we investigate whether natural variation in circulating prolactin levels predicts both parental and helper contributions to nestling provisioning in cooperatively breeding white-browed sparrow weavers, &lt;italic&gt;Plocepasser mahali&lt;/italic&gt;. In sparrow weaver groups, a single dominant pair monopolize reproduction and non-breeding subordinates help with nestling feeding. We show that: (i) among parents, dominant females feed nestlings at higher rates, make longer provisioning visits and have higher prolactin levels than dominant males; and (ii) among subordinates, engaged in cooperative helping behavior, those within their natal groups feed nestlings at higher rates and have higher prolactin levels than immigrants. Moreover, continuous variation in prolactin levels positively predicts nestling-provisioning rates and mean provisioning visit durations when all bird classes are combined. These relationships are principally driven by differences among bird classes in both circulating prolactin levels and provisioning traits; the more limited within-class variation in prolactin and provisioning traits were not evidently correlated, highlighting a likely role for additional mechanisms in the fine-scale regulation of care. Our findings broadly support the hypothesis that parental care and cooperative helping behavior are regulated by a common underlying mechanism and highlight the need for experimentation to now establish the causality of any role for prolactin.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461403" rel="alternate" title="Prolactin and the regulation of parental care and helping behavior in cooperatively breeding white-browed sparrow weaver societies (5 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461524</id><title>A Discrete Formulation of Two Alternative Forced Choice Decision Dynamics Derived from a Double-Well Quantum Landscape (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.557630+00:00</updated><author><name>Morgan Rosendahl</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Cohen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tools from quantum theory have been effectively leveraged in modeling otherwise poorly understood effects in decision-making such as apparent fallacies in probability judgments and context effects. This approach has described the dynamics of two alternative forced choice (2AFC) decisions in terms of the path of a single quantum particle evolving in a single potential well. Here, we present a variant on that approach, which we name the Multi-Particle and Multi-Well (MPMW) quantum cognitive framework, in which decisions among N alternatives are treated by the sum of positional measurements of many independent quantum particles representing stimulus information, acted on by an N-well landscape that defines the decision alternatives. In this article, we apply the MPMW model to the simplest and most common case of N-alternative decision making, 2AFC dynamics. This application calls for a multi-particle double-well implementation, which allows us to construct a simple, analytically tractable discrete drift diffusion model (DDM), in the form of a Markov chain, wherein the parameters of the attractor wells reflect bottom-up (automatic) and top-down (control-dependent) influences on the integration of external information. We first analyze this Markov chain in its simplest form, as a single integrator with a generative process arising from a static quantum landscape and fixed thresholds, and then consider the case of multi-integrator processing under the same conditions. Within this system, stochasticity arises directly from the double-well quantum attractor landscape as a function of the dimensions of its wells, rather than as an external parameter requiring independent fitting. The simplicity of the Markov chain component of this model allows for easy analytical computation of closed forms for response time distributions and response probabilities that match qualitative properties of the accuracies and reaction times of humans performing 2AFC tasks. The MPMW framework produces response time distributions following inverse gaussian curves familiar from previous DDM models and empirical data, including the common observation that mean response times are faster for incorrect than for correct responses. The work presented in this paper serves as a proof of concept, based on which the MPMW framework can be extended to address more complex decision-making processes, (e.g., N-alternative forced choice, dynamic control allocation, and nesting quantum landscapes to allow for modeling at both the task and stimulus levels of processing) that we discuss as future directions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461524" rel="alternate" title="A Discrete Formulation of Two Alternative Forced Choice Decision Dynamics Derived from a Double-Well Quantum Landscape (4 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462066</id><title>A machine vision based frailty index for mice (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.557868+00:00</updated><author><name>Leinani E. Hession</name></author><author><name>Gautam S. Sabnis</name></author><author><name>Gary A. Churchill</name></author><author><name>Vivek Kumar</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chronological aging is uniform, but biological aging is heterogeneous. Clinically, this heterogeneity manifests itself in health status and mortality, and it distinguishes healthy from unhealthy aging. Clinical frailty indexes (FIs) serve as an important tool in gerontology to capture health status. FIs have been adapted for use in mice and are an effective predictor of mortality risk. To accelerate our understanding of biological aging, high-throughput approaches to pre-clinical studies are necessary. Currently, however, mouse frailty indexing is manual and relies on trained scorers, which imposes limits on scalability and reliability. Here, we introduce a machine learning based visual frailty index (vFI) for mice that operates on video data from an open field assay. We generate a large mouse FI datasets comprising 256 males and 195 females. From video data on these same mice, we use neural networks to extract morphometric, gait, and other behavioral features that correlate with manual FI score and age. We use these features to train a regression model that accurately predicts frailty within 1.03 ± 0.08 (3.9% ± 0.3%) of the pre-normalized FI score in terms of median absolute error. We show that features of biological aging are encoded in open-field video data and can be used to construct a vFI that can complement or replace current manual FI methods. We use the vFI data to examine sex-specific aspects of aging in mice. This vFI provides increased accuracy, reproducibility, and scalability, that will enable large scale mechanistic and interventional studies of aging in mice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462066" rel="alternate" title="A machine vision based frailty index for mice (4 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462036</id><title>Cis-regulatory changes in locomotor genes are associated with the evolution of burrowing behavior (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.558180+00:00</updated><author><name>Caroline K. Hu</name></author><author><name>Ryan A. York</name></author><author><name>Hillery C. Metz</name></author><author><name>Nicole L. Bedford</name></author><author><name>Hunter B. Fraser</name></author><author><name>Hopi E. Hoekstra</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;How evolution modifies complex, innate behaviors is largely unknown. Divergence in many morphological traits has been linked, at least in part, to &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-regulatory changes in gene expression, a pattern also observed in some behaviors of recently diverged populations. Given this, we compared the gene expression in the brains of two interfertile sister species of &lt;italic&gt;Peromyscus&lt;/italic&gt; mice, including allele-specific expression (ASE) of their F&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; hybrids, that show large and heritable differences in burrowing behavior. Because &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-regulation may contribute to constitutive as well as activity-dependent gene expression, we also captured a molecular signature of burrowing circuit divergence by quantifying gene expression in mice shortly after burrowing. We found that several thousand genes were differentially expressed between the two sister species regardless of behavioral context, with several thousand more showing behavior-dependent differences. Allele-specific expression in F&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; hybrids showed a similar pattern, suggesting that much of the differential expression is driven by &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-regulatory divergence. Genes related to locomotor coordination showed the strongest signals of lineage-specific selection on burrowing-induced &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-regulatory changes. By comparing these candidate genes to independent quantitative trait locus (QTL) mapping data, we found that the closest QTL markers to these candidate genes are associated with variation in burrow shape, demonstrating an enrichment for candidate locomotor genes near segregating causal loci. Together, our results provide insight into how &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-regulated gene expression can depend on behavioral context as well as how this dynamic regulatory divergence between species can be integrated with forward genetics to enrich our understanding of the genetic basis of behavioral evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462036" rel="alternate" title="Cis-regulatory changes in locomotor genes are associated with the evolution of burrowing behavior (4 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462241</id><title>Using TrackMate to Analyze Drosophila Larval and Adult Locomotion (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.558415+00:00</updated><author><name>Alisa A. Omelchenko</name></author><author><name>Ainul Huda</name></author><author><name>Allison N. Castaneda</name></author><author><name>Thomas J. Vaden</name></author><author><name>Lina Ni</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; adult and larvae exhibit sophisticated behaviors that are widely used in development, synaptic transmission, sensory physiology, and learning and memory research. Many of these behaviors depend on locomotion, the ability of an animal to move. However, the statistical analysis of locomotion is not trivial. Here we use an open-source Fiji plugin TrackMate to track the locomotion of &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; adults and larvae. We build optimal experimental setups to rapidly process recordings by Fiji and analyze by TrackMate. We also provide tips for analyzing non-optimal recordings. TrackMate extracts the X and Y positions of an animal on each frame of an image sequence or a video. This information allows for generating moving trajectories, calculating moving distances, and determining preference indices in two-choice assays. Notably, this free-cost analysis method does not require programming skills.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study uses an open-source Fiji plugin TrackMate to computationally analyze &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; adult and larval behavioral assays, which does not require programming skills.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462241" rel="alternate" title="Using TrackMate to Analyze Drosophila Larval and Adult Locomotion (4 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461071</id><title>The anterior paired lateral neuron normalizes odour-evoked activity at the mushroom body calyx (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.558712+00:00</updated><author><name>Luigi Prisco</name></author><author><name>Stephan Hubertus Deimel</name></author><author><name>Hanna Yeliseyeva</name></author><author><name>André Fiala</name></author><author><name>Gaia Tavosanis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To identify and memorize discrete but similar environmental inputs, the brain needs to distinguish between subtle differences of activity patterns in defined neuronal populations. The Kenyon cells of the &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; adult mushroom body (MB) respond sparsely to complex olfactory input, a property that is thought to support stimuli discrimination in the MB. To understand how this property emerges, we investigated the role of the inhibitory anterior paired lateral neuron (APL) in the input circuit of the MB, the calyx. Within the calyx, presynaptic boutons of projection neurons (PNs) form large synaptic microglomeruli (MGs) with dendrites of postsynaptic Kenyon cells (KCs). Combining EM data analysis and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; calcium imaging, we show that APL, via inhibitory and reciprocal synapses targeting both PN boutons and KC dendrites, normalizes odour-evoked representations in MGs of the calyx. APL response scales with the PN input strength and is regionalized around PN input distribution. Our data indicate that the formation of a sparse code by the Kenyon cells requires APL-driven normalization of their MG postsynaptic responses. This work provides experimental insights on how inhibition shapes sensory information representation in a higher brain centre, thereby supporting stimuli discrimination and allowing for efficient associative memory formation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461071" rel="alternate" title="The anterior paired lateral neuron normalizes odour-evoked activity at the mushroom body calyx (3 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461543</id><title>Aversive View Memory and Navigational Risk Sensitivity in the Desert Ant, Cataglyphis Velox (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.559017+00:00</updated><author><name>Cody A Freas</name></author><author><name>Antoine Wystrach</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Schwarz</name></author><author><name>Marcia L Spetch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many ants establish foraging routes through learning views of the visual panorama. Route models have focused primarily on attractive view use, which experienced foragers orient towards to return to known sites. However, aversive views have recently been uncovered as a key component of route learning. Here, &lt;italic&gt;Cataglyphis velox&lt;/italic&gt; rapidly learned aversive views, when associated with a negative outcome, a period of captivity in brush, triggering an increase in hesitation behavior. These memories were based on the accumulation of experiences over multiple trips with each new experience regulating forager’s hesitancy. Foragers were also sensitive to captivity time differences, suggesting they possess some mechanism to quantify duration. Finally, we analyzed foragers’ perception of risky (i.e. variable) versus stable aversive outcomes by associating two sites along the route with distinct captivity schedules, a fixed or variable duration, with the same mean across training. Foragers exhibited significantly less hesitation to the risky outcome compared to the fixed, indicating they perceived risky outcomes as less severe. Results align with a logarithmic relationship between captivity duration and hesitations, suggesting that aversive stimulus perception is a logarithm of its actual value. We conclude by characterizing how these behaviors can be executed within the mushroom bodies’ neural circuitry.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461543" rel="alternate" title="Aversive View Memory and Navigational Risk Sensitivity in the Desert Ant, Cataglyphis Velox (3 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461870</id><title>Ecological and social pressures interfere with homeostatic sleep regulation in the wild (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.559299+00:00</updated><author><name>JC Loftus</name></author><author><name>R Harel</name></author><author><name>CL Nuñez</name></author><author><name>MC Crofoot</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sleep is fundamental to the health and fitness of all animals. The physiological importance of sleep is underscored by the central role of homeostasis in determining sleep investment – following periods of sleep deprivation, individuals experience longer and more intense sleep bouts. Yet, most studies of sleep have been conducted in highly controlled settings, disconnected from the ecological and social context that may exert pressures on sleep patterns in conflict with homeostatic regulation. Using tri-axial accelerometry and GPS to track the sleep patterns of a group of wild baboons (&lt;italic&gt;Papio anubis&lt;/italic&gt;) at multiple temporal and spatial scales, we found that ecological and social pressures indeed interfere with homeostatic sleep regulation. Baboons sacrificed time spent sleeping when in less familiar locations and when sleeping in proximity to more group-mates, regardless of how much they had slept the prior night or how much they had physically exerted themselves the preceding day. Moreover, we found that the collective dynamics characteristic of social animal groups persist into the sleep period, as baboons exhibited synchronized patterns of waking throughout the night, particularly with nearby group-mates. Thus, for animals whose fitness depends critically on avoiding predation and developing social relationships, maintaining sleep homeostasis may be only secondary to remaining vigilant when sleeping in risky habitats and interacting with group-mates during the night. Our results highlight the importance of studying sleep in ecologically relevant contexts, where the adaptive function of sleep patterns directly reflect the complex trade-offs that have guided its evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461870" rel="alternate" title="Ecological and social pressures interfere with homeostatic sleep regulation in the wild (3 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>