<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.448948+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471493</id><title>Gap genes are involved in inviability in hybrids between Drosophila melanogaster and D. santomea (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.449435+00:00</updated><author><name>Wenhan Chang</name></author><author><name>Martin Kreitman</name></author><author><name>Daniel R. Matute</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Evolved changes within species lead to the inevitable loss of viability in hybrids. Inviability is also a convenient phenotype to genetically map and validate functionally divergent genes and pathways differentiating closely related species. Here we identify the &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; form of the highly conserved essential gap gene &lt;italic&gt;giant&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;gt&lt;/italic&gt;) as a key genetic determinant of hybrid inviability in crosses with &lt;italic&gt;D. santomea&lt;/italic&gt;. We show that the coding region of this allele in &lt;italic&gt;D. melanogaster/D. santomea&lt;/italic&gt; hybrids is sufficient to cause embryonic inviability not seen in either pure species. Further genetic analysis indicates that &lt;italic&gt;tailless&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;tll&lt;/italic&gt;), another gap gene, is also involved in the hybrid defects. &lt;italic&gt;giant&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;tll&lt;/italic&gt; are both members of the gap gene network of transcription factors that participate in establishing anterior-posterior specification of the dipteran embryo, a highly conserved developmental process. Genes whose outputs in this process are functionally conserved nevertheless evolve over short timescales to cause inviability in hybrids.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471493" rel="alternate" title="Gap genes are involved in inviability in hybrids between Drosophila melanogaster and D. santomea (20 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471732</id><title>Lessons on fruiting body morphogenesis from genomes and transcriptomes of Agaricomycetes (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.449655+00:00</updated><author><name>Laszlo G Nagy</name></author><author><name>Peter Jan Vonk</name></author><author><name>Markus Kunzler</name></author><author><name>Csenge Foldi</name></author><author><name>Mate Viragh</name></author><author><name>Robin A. Ohm</name></author><author><name>Florian Hennicke</name></author><author><name>Balazs Balint</name></author><author><name>Arpad Csernetics</name></author><author><name>Botond Hegedus</name></author><author><name>Zhihao Hou</name></author><author><name>Xiao-bin Liu</name></author><author><name>Shen Nan</name></author><author><name>Manish Pareek</name></author><author><name>Neha Sahu</name></author><author><name>Benedek Szathmari</name></author><author><name>Torda Varga</name></author><author><name>Hongli Wu</name></author><author><name>Xiao Yang</name></author><author><name>Zsolt Merenyi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fruiting bodies of mushroom-forming fungi (Agaricomycetes) are among the most complex structures produced by fungi. Unlike vegetative hyphae, fruiting bodies grow determinately and follow a genetically encoded developmental program that orchestrates tissue differentiation, growth and sexual sporulation. In spite of more than a century of research, our understanding of the molecular details of fruiting body morphogenesis is limited and a general synthesis on the genetics of this complex process is lacking. In this paper, we aim to comprehensively identify conserved genes related to fruiting body morphogenesis and distill novel functional hypotheses for functionally poorly characterized genes. As a result of this analysis, we report 921 conserved developmentally expressed gene families, only a few dozens of which have previously been reported in fruiting body development. Based on literature data, conserved expression patterns and functional annotations, we provide informed hypotheses on the potential role of these gene families in fruiting body development, yielding the most complete description of molecular processes in fruiting body morphogenesis to date. We discuss genes related to the initiation of fruiting, differentiation, growth, cell surface and cell wall, defense, transcriptional regulation as well as signal transduction. Based on these data we derive a general model of fruiting body development, which includes an early, proliferative phase that is mostly concerned with laying out the mushroom body plan (via cell division and differentiation), and a second phase of growth via cell expansion as well as meiotic events and sporulation. Altogether, our discussions cover 1480 genes of Coprinopsis cinerea, and their orthologs in Agaricus bisporus, Cyclocybe aegerita, Armillaria ostoyae, Auriculariopsis ampla, Laccaria bicolor, Lentinula edodes, Lentinus tigrinus, Mycena kentingensis, Phanerochaete chrysosporium, Pleurotus ostreatus, and Schizophyllum commune, providing functional hypotheses for ~10% of genes in the genomes of these species. Although experimental evidence for the role of these genes will need to be established in the future, our data provide a roadmap for guiding functional analyses of fruiting related genes in the Agaricomycetes. We anticipate that the gene compendium presented here, combined with developments in functional genomics approaches will contribute to uncovering the genetic bases of one of the most spectacular multicellular developmental processes in fungi. Key words: functional annotation; comparative genomics; cell wall remodeling; development; fruiting body morphogenesis; mushroom; transcriptome&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471732" rel="alternate" title="Lessons on fruiting body morphogenesis from genomes and transcriptomes of Agaricomycetes (15 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471977</id><title>Macroevolutionary dynamics of climatic niche space (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.449901+00:00</updated><author><name>Ignacio Quintero</name></author><author><name>Marc A. Suchard</name></author><author><name>Walter Jetz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;How and why lineages evolve along niche space as they diversify and adapt to different environments is fundamental to evolution. Progress has been hampered by the difficulties of linking a comprehensive empirical characterization of species niches with flexible evolutionary models that describe their evolution. Consequently, the relative influence of external episodic and biotic factors remains poorly understood. Here we characterize species’ two-dimensional temperature and precipitation niche space occupied (i.e., species niche envelope) as complex geometries and assess their evolution across a large vertebrate radiation (all Aves) using a model that captures heterogeneous evolutionary rates on time-calibrated phylogenies. We find that extant birds coevolved from warm, mesic climatic niches into colder and drier environments and responded to the K-Pg boundary with a dramatic increase in disparity. Contrary to expectations of subsiding rates of niche evolution as lineages diversify, our results show that overall rates have increased steadily, with some lineages experiencing exceptionally high evolutionary rates, associated with colonization of novel niche spaces, and others showing niche stasis. Both competition- and environmental change-driven niche evolution transpire and result in highly heterogeneous rates near the present. Our findings share the limitations of all work based purely on extant taxa but highlight the growing ecological and conservation insights arising from the model-based integration of increasingly comprehensive and robust environmental and phylogenetic information.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471977" rel="alternate" title="Macroevolutionary dynamics of climatic niche space (7 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471407</id><title>Floral evolution and pollinator diversification in Hedychium J.Koenig (Zingiberaceae): one of Mr. Darwin’s tropical fantasies (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.450036+00:00</updated><author><name>Ajith Ashokan</name></author><author><name>Piyakaset Suksathan</name></author><author><name>Jana Leong-Škorničková</name></author><author><name>Mark Newman</name></author><author><name>W. John Kress</name></author><author><name>Vinita Gowda</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;PREMISE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Hedychium&lt;/italic&gt; J.Koenig (ginger lilies: Zingiberaceae) is endemic to the Indo-Malayan Realm (IMR) and is known for its fragrant flowers. Two different pollination syndromes characterize the genus: diurnal or bird pollination and nocturnal or moth pollination systems. To date, no attempt has been undertaken to understand the evolution of floral traits in this genus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;METHODS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We estimated ancestral character-states, phylogenetic signals, and character correlations for thirteen discrete and eight continuous floral traits representing 75% species diversity of &lt;italic&gt;Hedychium&lt;/italic&gt;. Diversification rate estimation analyses were also employed to understand trait-dependent diversification in the genus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;RESULTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Inflorescence structure, cincinnus capacity, and curvature of floral tubes revealed strong phylogenetic dependence, whereas number of open flowers per inflorescence per day, color of the labellum, and exertion of the stigma characterized higher ecological effects. Diversification rate estimations suggested that the labellum width, floral tube length, and labellum color played a major role in the evolutionary diversification of &lt;italic&gt;Hedychium&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;CONCLUSIONS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We identified bract type and cincinnus capacity as synapomorphies for &lt;italic&gt;Hedychium&lt;/italic&gt;, while the island-specific clade III was characterized by slender cylindrical inflorescence, coiling of floral tubes, and longer bract to calyx ratio. The circum-Himalayan clade IV is the most speciose, derived, and with most variable floral traits. Although floral color and size lacked any association with pollinator-specific traits (moth and bird pollination), pale colored flowers were most common in the early diverging clades (clade I, II-el., and II-de.), indicating their ancestral nature, when compared to brightly colored flowers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471407" rel="alternate" title="Floral evolution and pollinator diversification in Hedychium J.Koenig (Zingiberaceae): one of Mr. Darwin’s tropical fantasies (6 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471243</id><title>Evaluating the role of coevolution in a horizontally transmitted mutualism (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.450185+00:00</updated><author><name>Kayla Stoy</name></author><author><name>Joselyne Chavez</name></author><author><name>Valeria De Las Casas</name></author><author><name>Venkat Talla</name></author><author><name>Aileen Berasategui</name></author><author><name>Levi Morran</name></author><author><name>Nicole Gerardo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mutualism depends on the alignment of host and symbiont fitness. Horizontal transmission can readily decouple fitness interests, yet horizontally transmitted mutualisms are common in nature. We hypothesized that pairwise coevolution and specialization in host-symbiont interactions underlies the maintenance of cooperation in a horizontally transmitted mutualism. Alternatively, we predicted selection by multiple host species may select for cooperative traits in a generalist symbiont through diffuse coevolution. We tested for signatures of pairwise coevolutionary change between the squash bug &lt;italic&gt;Anasa tristis&lt;/italic&gt; and its horizontally acquired bacterial symbiont &lt;italic&gt;Caballeronia spp&lt;/italic&gt;. by measuring local adaptation. We found no evidence for local adaptation between sympatric combinations of &lt;italic&gt;A. tristis&lt;/italic&gt; squash bugs and &lt;italic&gt;Caballeronia spp.&lt;/italic&gt; across their native geographic range. To test for diffuse coevolution, we performed reciprocal inoculations to test for specialization between three &lt;italic&gt;Anasa&lt;/italic&gt; host species and &lt;italic&gt;Caballeronia spp.&lt;/italic&gt; symbionts isolated from conspecific hosts. We observed no evidence of specialization across host species. Our results demonstrate generalist dynamics underlie the interaction between &lt;italic&gt;Anasa&lt;/italic&gt; insect hosts and their &lt;italic&gt;Caballeronia spp.&lt;/italic&gt; symbionts. Specifically, diffuse coevolution between multiple host species with a shared generalist symbiont may maintain cooperative traits despite horizontal transmission.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471243" rel="alternate" title="Evaluating the role of coevolution in a horizontally transmitted mutualism (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471459</id><title>Sexual and developmental variations of ecto-parasitism in damselflies (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.450337+00:00</updated><author><name>Shatabdi Paul</name></author><author><name>Md Kawsar Khan</name></author><author><name>Marie E. Herberstein</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The prevalence and intensity of parasitism can have different fitness costs between sexes, and across species and developmental stages. This variation could arise because of species specific sexual and developmental differences in body condition, immunity, and resistance. Theory predicts that the prevalence of parasitism will be greater in individuals with poor body condition and the intensity of parasitism will be greater in individuals with larger body size. These predictions have been tested and verified in vertebrates. In insects, however, contradictory evidence has been found in different taxa. Here, we tested these predictions on two species of &lt;italic&gt;Agriocnemis&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Agriocnemis femina&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Agriocnemis pygmaea&lt;/italic&gt;) damselflies, which are parasitized by &lt;italic&gt;Arrenurus&lt;/italic&gt; water mite ectoparasites. We measured body weight, total body length, abdomen area and thorax area of non-parasitized damselflies and found body condition varied between males and females, between immature females and mature females and between &lt;italic&gt;A. femina&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;A. pygmaea&lt;/italic&gt;. Then, we calculated the parasite prevalence, i.e., the frequency of parasitism and intensity, i.e., the number of parasites per infected damselfly in eleven natural populations of both species. In line to our predictions, we observed greater prevalence in immature females than mature females but found no difference in parasite prevalence between males and females. Furthermore, we found that parasite load was higher in females than males and in immature females than mature females. Our result also showed that the frequency and intensity of parasitism varied between the two studied species, being higher in &lt;italic&gt;A. pygmaea&lt;/italic&gt; than &lt;italic&gt;A. femina&lt;/italic&gt;. Our study provides evidence that parasitism impacts sexes, developmental stages and species differentially and suggests that variation may occur due to sex, developmental stage, and species-specific resistance and tolerance mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471459" rel="alternate" title="Sexual and developmental variations of ecto-parasitism in damselflies (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471908</id><title>No support for a meiosis suppressor in Daphnia pulex: Comparison of linkage maps reveals normal recombination in males of obligate parthenogenetic lineages. (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.450464+00:00</updated><author><name>Cécile Molinier</name></author><author><name>Thomas Lenormand</name></author><author><name>Christoph R Haag</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It is often assumed that obligate parthenogenesis (OP) evolves by a disruption of meiosis and recombination. One emblematic example that appears to support this view is the crustacean &lt;italic&gt;Daphnia pulex&lt;/italic&gt;. Here, by constructing high-density linkage maps, we estimate genome-wide recombination rates in males that are occasionally produced by OP lineages, as well as in males and females of cyclical parthenogenetic (CP) lineages. The results show no significant differences in recombination rates and patterns between CP and OP males nor between CP males and CP females. The observation that recombination is not suppressed in OP males invalidates the hypothesis of a general meiosis suppressor responsible for OP. Rather, our findings suggest that in &lt;italic&gt;D. pulex&lt;/italic&gt;, as in other species where OP evolves from CP ancestors, the CP to OP transition evolves through a re-use of the parthenogenesis pathways already present in CP and through their extension to the entire life cycle, at least in females. In addition to the implications for the evolution of OP, the genetic maps produced by this study constitute an important genomic resource for the model species &lt;italic&gt;Daphnia&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471908" rel="alternate" title="No support for a meiosis suppressor in Daphnia pulex: Comparison of linkage maps reveals normal recombination in males of obligate parthenogenetic lineages. (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471400</id><title>The price of defence: toxins, visual signals and oxidative state in an aposematic butterfly (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.450590+00:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan D Blount</name></author><author><name>Hannah M Rowland</name></author><author><name>Christopher Mitchell</name></author><author><name>Michael P Speed</name></author><author><name>Graeme D Ruxton</name></author><author><name>John A Endler</name></author><author><name>Lincoln P Brower</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In a variety of aposematic species, the conspicuousness of an individual's warning signal and the quantity of its chemical defence are positively correlated. This apparent honest signalling in aposematism is predicted by resource competition models which assume that the production and maintenance of aposematic defences compete for access to antioxidant molecules that have dual functions as pigments directly responsible for colouration and in protecting against oxidative lipid damage. Here we study a model aposematic system - the monarch butterfly (Danaus plexippus) and make use of the variable phytochemistry of its larval host-plant, milkweeds (Asclepiadaceae), to manipulate the concentration of sequestered cardenolides. We test two fundamental assumptions of resource competition models: that (1) the possession of secondary defences is associated with costs in the form of oxidative lipid damage and reduced antioxidant defences; and (2) that oxidative damage or decreases in antioxidant defences can reduce the capacity of individuals to produce aposematic displays. Monarch caterpillars that sequestered the highest concentrations of cardenolides exhibited higher levels of oxidative lipid damage as adults. The relationship between warning signals, cardenolide concentrations and oxidative damage differed between the sexes. In male monarchs conspicuousness was explained by an interaction between oxidative damage and sequestration: as males sequester more cardenolides, those with high levels of oxidative damage become less conspicuous, while those that sequester lower levels of cardenolides equally invest in conspicuous with increasing oxidative damage. There was no significant effect of oxidative damage or concentration of sequestered cardenolides on female conspicuousness. Our results demonstrate physiological linkage between the production of coloration and protection from autotoxicity, that warning signals can be honest indicators of defensive capability, and that the relationships are different between the sexes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471400" rel="alternate" title="The price of defence: toxins, visual signals and oxidative state in an aposematic butterfly (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471536</id><title>A single nucleotide variant in the PPARγ-homolog Eip75B affects fecundity in Drosophila (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.450936+00:00</updated><author><name>Katja M Hoedjes</name></author><author><name>Hristina Kostic</name></author><author><name>Thomas Flatt</name></author><author><name>Laurent Keller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Still little is understood about the nucleotide changes that underlie variation in complex phenotypes. Variation in the PPARγ-homolog &lt;italic&gt;Eip75B&lt;/italic&gt; has previously been suggested to be associated with longevity and life-history differences in the fruit fly &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt;. Using RNAi knockdown, we first demonstrate that reduced expression of &lt;italic&gt;Eip75B&lt;/italic&gt; in adults affects lifespan, egg laying rate and egg volume. To then test the effect of a naturally occurring SNP variant within a cis-regulatory domain of &lt;italic&gt;Eip75B&lt;/italic&gt;, we screened wildtype lines with alternative alleles and conducted precise genome editing using CRISPR/Cas9. These experiments revealed that this natural polymorphism has a significant effect on fecundity and egg-to-adult viability, but not on longevity or other life-history traits. These results provide a rare functional validation for the role of a natural allelic variant in adaptation of life-history traits directly linked to fitness at the single nucleotide level.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471536" rel="alternate" title="A single nucleotide variant in the PPARγ-homolog Eip75B affects fecundity in Drosophila (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>