<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.005046+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463705</id><title>Inferring the mode and strength of ongoing selection (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.006473+00:00</updated><author><name>Gustavo Valadares Barroso</name></author><author><name>Kirk Lohmueller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genome sequence data is no longer scarce. The UK Biobank alone comprises 200,000 individual genomes, with more on the way, leading the field of human genetics towards sequencing entire populations. Within the next decades, other model organisms will follow suit, especially domesticated species such as crops and livestock. Having sequences from most individuals in a population will present new challenges for using these data to improve health and agriculture in the pursuit of a sustainable future. Existing population genetic methods are designed to model hundreds of randomly sampled sequences, but are not optimized for extracting the information contained in the larger and richer datasets that are beginning to emerge, with thousands of closely related individuals. Here we develop a new method called TIDES (Trio-based Inference of Dominance and Selection) that uses data from tens of thousands of family trios to make inferences about natural selection acting in a single generation. TIDES further improves on the state-of-the-art by making no assumptions regarding demography, linkage or dominance. We discuss how our method paves the way for studying natural selection from new angles.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463705" rel="alternate" title="Inferring the mode and strength of ongoing selection (6 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463474</id><title>Population genetic bottleneck has only marginal effects on fitness evolution and its repeatability in dioecious C. elegans (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.007000+00:00</updated><author><name>Karen Bisschop</name></author><author><name>Thomas Blankers</name></author><author><name>Janine Mariën</name></author><author><name>Meike T Wortel</name></author><author><name>Martijn Egas</name></author><author><name>Astrid T. Groot</name></author><author><name>Marcel Visser</name></author><author><name>Jacintha Ellers</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Evolution is a key process by which populations can adapt to novel conditions, but it is not well understood how predictable this process is. Predictability is expected to depend on the ratio of deterministic and stochastic processes that contribute to evolutionary change and this ratio is modulated by the effective population size. Smaller effective populations harbor less genetic diversity and stochastic processes are generally expected to play a larger role, leading to less repeatable evolutionary trajectories. Empirical insight into the relationship between effective population size and repeatability is limited and biased towards asexual unicellular organisms. Here, we used populations of obligately outcrossing &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/italic&gt; to test whether fitness increase and selection response were more heterogeneous after a moderate or strong population bottleneck compared to a scenario without bottleneck. Nematodes were exposed to a novel bacterial prey and lower temperature. Population sizes after one week of growth (as a proxy of fitness) were measured before and after 15 generations of evolution. We found that replicates across all (no/moderate/strong bottleneck) treatments evolved higher fitness and no significant difference in average or maximum fitness was found among treatments. Partitioning fitness variance among effects from selection and effects from chance showed that a strong (but not a moderate) bottleneck reduced the relative contribution of selection effects to fitness variation. However, the reduced contribution from selection did not translate to a significant reduction in the repeatability of fitness evolution. Thus, although a strong bottleneck reduced the contribution of deterministic evolutionary change, we found only marginal effects on quantitative measurements of repeatability in evolution. We conclude that the extent to which evolution is predictable may not universally depend on effective population size.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463474" rel="alternate" title="Population genetic bottleneck has only marginal effects on fitness evolution and its repeatability in dioecious C. elegans (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463691</id><title>Convergent evolution of polyploid genomes from across the eukaryotic tree of life (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.007557+00:00</updated><author><name>Yue Hao</name></author><author><name>Jonathon Fleming</name></author><author><name>Joanna Petterson</name></author><author><name>Eric Lyons</name></author><author><name>Patrick P. Edger</name></author><author><name>Chris Pires</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey L. Thorne</name></author><author><name>Gavin C. Conant</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;By modeling the homoeologous gene losses that occurred in fifty genomes deriving from ten distinct polyploidy events, we show that the evolutionary forces acting on polyploids are remarkably similar, regardless of whether they occur in flowering plants, ciliates, fishes or yeasts. The models suggest these events were nearly all allopolyploidies, with two distinct progenitors contributing to the modern species. We show that many of the events show a relative rate of duplicate gene loss prior to the first post-polyploidy speciation that is significantly higher than in later phases of their evolution. The relatively low selective constraint seen for the single-copy genes these losses produced lead us to suggest that most of the purely selectively neutral duplicate gene losses occur in the immediate post-polyploid period. We also find ongoing and extensive reciprocal gene losses (RGL; alternative losses of duplicated ancestral genes) between these genomes. With the exception of a handful of closely related taxa, all of these polyploid organisms are separated from each other by tens to thousands of reciprocal gene losses. As a result, it is very unlikely that viable diploid hybrid species could form between these taxa, since matings between such hybrids would tend to produce offspring lacking essential genes. It is therefore possible that the relatively high frequency of recurrent polyploidies in some lineages may be due to the ability of new polyploidies to bypass RGL barriers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463691" rel="alternate" title="Convergent evolution of polyploid genomes from across the eukaryotic tree of life (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>