<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.411449+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473443</id><title>Cellular development and evolution of the mammalian cerebellum (114 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.412028+00:00</updated><author><name>Mari Sepp</name></author><author><name>Kevin Leiss</name></author><author><name>Ioannis Sarropoulos</name></author><author><name>Florent Murat</name></author><author><name>Konstantin Okonechnikov</name></author><author><name>Piyush Joshi</name></author><author><name>Evgeny Leushkin</name></author><author><name>Noe Mbengue</name></author><author><name>Céline Schneider</name></author><author><name>Julia Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Nils Trost</name></author><author><name>Lisa Spänig</name></author><author><name>Peter Giere</name></author><author><name>Philipp Khaitovich</name></author><author><name>Steven Lisgo</name></author><author><name>Miklós Palkovits</name></author><author><name>Lena M. Kutscher</name></author><author><name>Simon Anders</name></author><author><name>Margarida Cardoso-Moreira</name></author><author><name>Stefan M. Pfister</name></author><author><name>Henrik Kaessmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The expansion of the neocortex, one of the hallmarks of mammalian evolution&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt;, was accompanied by an increase in the number of cerebellar neurons&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;. However, little is known about the evolution of the cellular programs underlying cerebellum development in mammals. In this study, we generated single-nucleus RNA-sequencing data for ∼400,000 cells to trace the development of the cerebellum from early neurogenesis to adulthood in human, mouse, and the marsupial opossum. Our cross-species analyses revealed that the cellular composition and differentiation dynamics throughout cerebellum development are largely conserved, except for human Purkinje cells. Global transcriptome profiles, conserved cell state markers, and gene expression trajectories across neuronal differentiation show that the cerebellar cell type-defining programs have been overall preserved for at least 160 million years. However, we also discovered differences. We identified 3,586 genes that either gained or lost expression in cerebellar cells in one of the species, and 541 genes that evolved new expression trajectories during neuronal differentiation. The potential functional relevance of these cross-species differences is highlighted by the diverged expression patterns of several human disease-associated genes. Altogether, our study reveals shared and lineage-specific programs governing the cellular development of the mammalian cerebellum, and expands our understanding of the evolution of mammalian organ development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473443" rel="alternate" title="Cellular development and evolution of the mammalian cerebellum (114 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473549</id><title>Background selection under evolving recombination rates (38 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.412760+00:00</updated><author><name>Tom R. Booker</name></author><author><name>Bret A. Payseur</name></author><author><name>Anna Tigano</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background selection (BGS), the effect that purifying selection exerts on sites linked to deleterious alleles, is expected to be ubiquitous across eukaryotic genomes. The effects of BGS reflect the interplay of the rates and fitness effects of deleterious mutations with recombination. A fundamental assumption of BGS models is that recombination rates are invariant over time. However, in some lineages recombination rates evolve rapidly, violating this central assumption. Here, we investigate how recombination rate evolution affects genetic variation under BGS. We show that recombination rate evolution modifies the effects of BGS in a manner similar to a localised change in the effective population size, potentially leading to an underestimation of the genome-wide effects of selection. Furthermore, we find evidence that recombination rate evolution in the ancestors of modern house mice may have impacted inferences of the genome-wide effects of selection in that species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473549" rel="alternate" title="Background selection under evolving recombination rates (38 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473185</id><title>Mutational robustness changes during long-term adaptation in laboratory budding yeast populations (33 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.413145+00:00</updated><author><name>Milo S. Johnson</name></author><author><name>Michael M. Desai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;As an adapting population traverses the fitness landscape, its local neighborhood (i.e., the collection of fitness effects of single-step mutations) can change shape because of interactions with mutations acquired during evolution. These changes to the distribution of fitness effects can affect both the rate of adaptation and the accumulation of deleterious mutations. However, while numerous models of fitness landscapes have been proposed in the literature, empirical data on how this distribution changes during evolution remains limited. In this study, we directly measure how the fitness landscape neighborhood changes during laboratory adaptation. Using a barcode-based mutagenesis system, we measure the fitness effects of 91 specific gene disruption mutations in genetic backgrounds spanning 8,000-10,000 generations of evolution in two constant environments. We find that the mean of the distribution of fitness effects decreases in one environment, indicating a reduction in mutational robustness, but does not change in the other. We show that these distribution-level patterns result from biases in variable patterns of epistasis at the level of individual mutations, including fitness-correlated and idiosyncratic epistasis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473185" rel="alternate" title="Mutational robustness changes during long-term adaptation in laboratory budding yeast populations (33 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473617</id><title>Multiscale selection in spatially structured populations (25 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.413325+00:00</updated><author><name>Hilje M. Doekes</name></author><author><name>Rutger Hermsen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The spatial structure of natural populations is key to many of their evolutionary processes. Formal theories analysing the interplay between natural selection and spatial structure have mostly focused on populations divided into distinct, non-overlapping groups. Most populations, however, are not structured in this way, but rather (self-)organise into dynamic patterns unfolding at various spatial scales. Here, we present a mathematical framework that quantifies how patterns and processes at different spatial scales contribute to natural selection in such populations. To that end, we define the Local Selection Differential (LSD): a measure of the selection acting on a trait within a given local environment. Based on the LSD, natural selection in a population can be decomposed into two parts: the contribution of local selection, acting &lt;italic&gt;within&lt;/italic&gt; local environments, and the contribution of interlocal selection, acting &lt;italic&gt;among&lt;/italic&gt; them. Varying the size of the local environments subsequently allows one to measure the contribution of each length scale. To illustrate the use of this new &lt;italic&gt;multiscale&lt;/italic&gt; selection framework, we apply it to two simulation models of the evolution of traits known to be affected by spatial population structure: altruism and pathogen transmissibility. In both models, the spatial decomposition of selection reveals that local and interlocal selection can have opposite signs, thus providing a mathematically rigorous underpinning to intuitive explanations of how processes at different spatial scales may compete. It furthermore identifies which length scales—and hence which patterns—are relevant for natural selection. The multiscale selection framework can thus be used to address complex questions on evolution in spatially structured populations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473617" rel="alternate" title="Multiscale selection in spatially structured populations (25 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473882</id><title>Recombination suppression and selection affect local ancestries in genomes of a migratory songbird (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.413610+00:00</updated><author><name>Jun Ishigohoka</name></author><author><name>Karen Bascón-Cardozo</name></author><author><name>Andrea Bours</name></author><author><name>Janina Fuß</name></author><author><name>Arang Rhie</name></author><author><name>Jacquelyn Mountcastle</name></author><author><name>Bettina Haase</name></author><author><name>William Chow</name></author><author><name>Joanna Collins</name></author><author><name>Kerstin Howe</name></author><author><name>Marcela Uliano-Silva</name></author><author><name>Olivier Fedrigo</name></author><author><name>Erich D. Jarvis</name></author><author><name>Javier Pérez-Tris</name></author><author><name>Juan Carlos Illera</name></author><author><name>Miriam Liedvogel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The patterns of genetic relatedness among individuals vary along the genome, representing fluctuation of local ancestry. The factors responsible for this variation have not been well studied in wild animals with ecological and behavioural relevance. Here, we characterise the genomic architecture of genetic relatedness in the Eurasian blackcap, an iconic songbird species in ecology and quantitative genetics of migratory behaviour. We identify 23 genomic regions with deviated local relatedness patterns, using a chromosome-level de novo assembly of the blackcap genome and whole-genome resequencing data of 179 individuals from nine populations with diverse migratory phenotypes. Five genomic regions show local relatedness patterns of polymorphic inversions, three of which are syntenic to polymorphic inversions known in the zebra finch. Phylogenetic analysis reveals these three polymorphic inversions evolved independently in the blackcap and zebra finch indicating convergence of polymorphic inversions. Population genetic analyses in these three inversions in the blackcap suggest balancing selection between two haplotypes in one locus and background selection in the other two loci. One genomic region with deviated local relatedness is under selection against gene flow by population-specific reduction in recombination rate. Other genomic islands including 11 pericentromeric regions consist of evolutionarily conserved and non-conserved recombination cold-spots under background selection. Two of these regions with non-conserved recombination suppression are known to be associated with population-specific migratory phenotypes, where local relatedness patterns support additional effects of population-specific selection. These results highlight how different forms of recombination suppression and selection jointly affect heterogeneous genomic landscape of local ancestries.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473882" rel="alternate" title="Recombination suppression and selection affect local ancestries in genomes of a migratory songbird (24 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473503</id><title>The origin and evolution of loqs2: a gene encoding an antiviral dsRNA binding protein in Aedes mosquitoes (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.413969+00:00</updated><author><name>Carlos F. Estevez-Castro</name></author><author><name>Murillo F. Rodrigues</name></author><author><name>Antinéa Babarit</name></author><author><name>Flávia Viana Ferreira</name></author><author><name>Eric Marois</name></author><author><name>Rodrigo Cogni</name></author><author><name>João Trindade Marques</name></author><author><name>Roenick Proveti Olmo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mosquito borne viruses such as dengue, Zika, yellow fever and Chikungunya cause millions of infections every year. These viruses are mostly transmitted by two urban-adapted mosquito species, &lt;italic&gt;Aedes aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Aedes albopictus&lt;/italic&gt;, that appear to be more permissive to arbovirus infections compared to closely related species, although mechanistic understanding remains unknown. &lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; mosquitoes may have evolved specialized antiviral mechanisms that potentially contribute to the low impact of viral infection. Recently, we reported the identification of an &lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; specific double-stranded RNA binding protein (dsRBP), named Loqs2, that is involved in the control of infection by dengue and Zika viruses in &lt;italic&gt;Ae. aegypti&lt;/italic&gt;. Loqs2 interacts with two important co-factors of the RNA interference (RNAi) pathway, Loquacious (Loqs) and R2D2, and seems to be a strong regulator of the antiviral defense. However, the origin and evolution of &lt;italic&gt;loqs2&lt;/italic&gt; remains unclear. Here, we describe that &lt;italic&gt;loqs2&lt;/italic&gt; likely originated from two independent duplications of the first dsRNA binding domain (dsRBD) of &lt;italic&gt;loquacious&lt;/italic&gt; that occurred before the radiation of the &lt;italic&gt;Aedes Stegomyia&lt;/italic&gt; subgenus. After its origin, our analyses suggest that &lt;italic&gt;loqs2&lt;/italic&gt; evolved by relaxed positive selection towards neofunctionalization. In fact, &lt;italic&gt;loqs2&lt;/italic&gt; is evolving at a faster pace compared to other RNAi components such as &lt;italic&gt;loquacious, r2d2&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Dicer-2&lt;/italic&gt; in &lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; mosquitoes. Unlike &lt;italic&gt;loquacious&lt;/italic&gt;, transcriptomic analysis showed that &lt;italic&gt;loqs2&lt;/italic&gt; expression is tightly regulated, almost restricted to reproductive tissues in &lt;italic&gt;Ae. aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Ae. albopictus&lt;/italic&gt;. Transgenic mosquitoes engineered to ubiquitously express &lt;italic&gt;loqs2&lt;/italic&gt; show massive dysregulation of stress response genes and undergo developmental arrest at larval stages. Overall, our results uncover the possible origin and neofunctionalization of a novel antiviral gene, &lt;italic&gt;loqs2&lt;/italic&gt;, in &lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; mosquitoes that ultimately may contribute to their effectiveness as vectors for arboviruses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473503" rel="alternate" title="The origin and evolution of loqs2: a gene encoding an antiviral dsRNA binding protein in Aedes mosquitoes (14 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473645</id><title>Genome sequences hot and cold: a database of organisms with defined optimal growth temperatures (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.414392+00:00</updated><author><name>Karla Helena-Bueno</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Rebecca Brown</name></author><author><name>Egor Konyk</name></author><author><name>Sergey Melnikov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite the rapidly increasing number of organisms with sequenced genomes, there is no existing resource that simultaneously contains information about genome sequences and the optimal growth conditions for a given species. In the absence of such a resource, we cannot immediately sort genomic sequences by growth conditions, making it difficult to study how organisms and biological molecules adapt to distinct environments. To address this problem, we have created a database called GSHC (Genome Sequences: Hot, Cold, and everything in between). This database, available at http://melnikovlab.com/gshc, brings together information about the genomic sequences and optimal growth temperatures for 25,324 species, including ~89% of the bacterial species with known genome sequences. Using this database, it is now possible to readily compare genomic sequences from thousands of species and correlate variations in genes and genomes with optimal growth temperatures, at the scale of the entire tree of life. The database interface allows users to retrieve protein sequences sorted by optimal growth temperature for their corresponding species, providing a tool to explore how organisms, genomes, and individual proteins and nucleic acids adapt to certain temperatures. We hope that this database will contribute to medicine and biotechnology by helping to create a better understanding of molecular adaptations to heat and cold, leading to new ways to preserve biological samples, engineer useful enzymes, and develop new biological materials and organisms with the desired tolerance to heat and cold.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473645" rel="alternate" title="Genome sequences hot and cold: a database of organisms with defined optimal growth temperatures (11 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473794</id><title>Prenatal thyroid hormones accelerate postnatal growth and telomere shortening in wild great tits (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.414854+00:00</updated><author><name>Bin-Yan Hsu</name></author><author><name>Nina Cossin-Sevrin</name></author><author><name>Antoine Stier</name></author><author><name>Suvi Ruuskanen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Early-life environment is known to affect later-life health and disease, which could be mediated by the early-life programming of telomere length, a key hallmark of ageing. According to the &lt;italic&gt;fetal programming of telomere biology hypothesis&lt;/italic&gt;, variation in prenatal exposure to hormones is likely to influence telomere length. Yet the contribution of key metabolic hormones, &lt;italic&gt;i.e.&lt;/italic&gt; thyroid hormones (THs), has been largely ignored. We recently showed that in contrast to predictions, exposure to elevated prenatal THs increased postnatal telomere length in wild collared flycatchers, but the generality of such effect, its underlying proximate mechanisms and consequences on survival have not been investigated. We therefore conducted a comprehensive study evaluating the impact of THs on potential drivers of telomere dynamics (growth, post-natal THs, mitochondria and oxidative stress), telomere length and medium-term survival using wild great tits as a model system. While prenatal THs did not significantly affect telomere length after hatching (&lt;italic&gt;i.e.&lt;/italic&gt; day 7), they influenced postnatal telomere shortening (&lt;italic&gt;i.e.&lt;/italic&gt; shorter telomeres at day 14 and the following winter) but not apparent survival. Circulating THs, mitochondrial density or oxidative stress biomarkers were not significantly influenced, whereas TH-supplemented group showed accelerated growth, which may explain the observed delayed effect on telomeres. We discuss several alternative hypotheses that may explain the contrast with our previous findings in flycatchers. Given that shorter telomeres in early life tend to be carried until adulthood and are often associated with decreased survival prospects, the effects of prenatal THs on telomeres may have long-lasting effects on senescence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473794" rel="alternate" title="Prenatal thyroid hormones accelerate postnatal growth and telomere shortening in wild great tits (10 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473661</id><title>Copy number variation of the putative speciation genes in the European house mouse hybrid zone (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.415062+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexey Yanchukov</name></author><author><name>Zusana Hiadlovska</name></author><author><name>Zeljka Pezer</name></author><author><name>Milos Macholan</name></author><author><name>Jaroslav Pialek</name></author><author><name>Stuart J.E. Baird</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hybrid zones have long been described as "windows on the evolutionary process", and studying them has become even more important since the advance in the genome analysis tools. The hybrid zone between two subspecies of the house mouse (Mus musculus musculus and Mus m. domesticus) is a unique model speciation system to study fine scale interactions of recently diverged genomes. Here, we explore the role of gene Copy Number Variation in shaping the barrier to introgression in the hybrid zone within a previously established transect in Central Europe. The CNV of seven pre-selected candidate genes was determined via droplet-digital PCR and analyzed in the context of ~500k SNPs, with the ancestral population (i.e. musculus or domesticus) of every SNP allele previously inferred in the admixed individuals (Baird et al., in prep.). The copy numbers of five genes were clearly associated with the prevalence of either musculus or domesticus genomes across the hybrid zone. In three cases, the highest and/or outlying levels of association were observed at or very close to the annotated positions of the respective gene amplicons, demonstrating the power of our approach in confirming the reference locations of copy number variants. Notably, several other reference locations were recognized as positive outliers in the association with particular CNV genes, possibly representing the extra gene copies and/or their epistatic interaction sites.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473661" rel="alternate" title="Copy number variation of the putative speciation genes in the European house mouse hybrid zone (9 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473695</id><title>Intrinsic apoptosis is evolutionary divergent among metazoans (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.415268+00:00</updated><author><name>Gabriel Krasovec</name></author><author><name>Eric Qeinnec</name></author><author><name>Jean-Philippe Chambon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Apoptosis is characterised by an analogous set of morphological features1 that depend on a proteolytic multigenic family, the caspases. Each apoptotic signalling pathway involves a specific initiator caspase, upstream of the pathway regulation, which finally converges to common executioner caspases. Intrinsic apoptosis, previously known as the mitochondrial apoptotic pathway, is often considered as ancestral and evolutionary conserved among animals. First identified in the nematode Caenorhabditis elegans, intrinsic apoptosis was next characterised in fruit fly Drosophila melanogaster and mammals. Intrinsic apoptosis depends on the key initiator caspase-9 (named Ced-3 and Dronc in Caenorhabditis and Drosophila, respectively), the activator Apaf-1 and the Bcl-2 multigenic family. Many functional studies have led to a deep characterisation of intrinsic apoptosis based on those classical models. Nevertheless, the biochemical role of mitochondria, the pivotal function of cytochrome c and the modality of caspases activation remain highly heterogeneous and hide profound molecular divergences among apoptotic pathways in animals. Independent of functional approaches, the phylogenetic history of the signal transduction actors, mostly the caspase family, is the Rosetta Stone to shed light on intrinsic apoptosis evolution. Here, after exhaustive research on CARD-caspases, we demonstrate by phylogenetic analysis that the caspase-9, the fundamental key of intrinsic apoptosis, is deuterostomes-specific, while it is the caspase-2 which is ancestral and common to bilaterians. Our analysis of Bcl-2 family and Apaf-1 confirm the high heterogeneity in apoptotic pathways elaboration in animals. Taken together, our results support convergent emergence of distinct intrinsic apoptotic pathways during metazoan evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473695" rel="alternate" title="Intrinsic apoptosis is evolutionary divergent among metazoans (8 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473502</id><title>Transcriptome of the synganglion and characterization of the cys-loop ligand-gated ion channel gene family in the tick Ixodes ricinus (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.415863+00:00</updated><author><name>Claude Rispe</name></author><author><name>Caroline Hervet</name></author><author><name>Nathalie de la Cotte</name></author><author><name>Romain Daveu</name></author><author><name>Karine Labadie</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Noël</name></author><author><name>Jean-Marc Aury</name></author><author><name>Steeve Thany</name></author><author><name>Emiliane Taillebois</name></author><author><name>Alison Cartereau</name></author><author><name>Anaïs Le Mauff</name></author><author><name>Claude L. Charvet</name></author><author><name>Clément Auger</name></author><author><name>Cédric Neveu</name></author><author><name>Olivier Plantard</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ticks represent a major health issue for humans and domesticated animals. Assessing the expression patterns of the tick’s central nervous system, known as the synganglion, is an important step in understanding tick physiology and in managing tick-borne diseases. Neuron-specific genes like the cys-loop ligand-gated ion channels (cys-loop LGICs) are important pharmacological targets of acaricides. Here, we carried out the sequencing of transcriptomes of the &lt;italic&gt;I. ricinus&lt;/italic&gt; synganglion, for adult ticks in different conditions (unfed males, unfed females, and partially-fed females). The &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; assembly of these transcriptomes allowed us to obtain a large collection of cys-loop LGICs sequences. A reference meta-transcriptome based on synganglion and whole body transcriptomes was then produced, showing high completeness and allowing differential expression analyses between synganglion and whole body. Many of the genes upregulated in the synganglion were related to biological processes or functions associated with neurotransmission and located in neurones or the synaptic membrane, including most of the cys-loop LGICs. As a first step of a functional study of cysLGICs, we cloned the predicted sequence of the resistance to dieldrin (RDL) subunit homologue, and functionally reconstituted the first GABA-gated receptor of &lt;italic&gt;Ixodes ricinus&lt;/italic&gt; using a hetrologous expression approach. A phylogenetic study was performed for the nicotinic acetylcholine receptors (nAChRs) and for other cys-loop LGICs respectively, showing tick-specific expansions of some types of receptors (Histamine-gated, GluCls).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473502" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptome of the synganglion and characterization of the cys-loop ligand-gated ion channel gene family in the tick Ixodes ricinus (7 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.470191</id><title>Parental provisioning drives brain size in birds (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.416204+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael Griesser</name></author><author><name>Szymon M. Drobniak</name></author><author><name>Sereina M. Graber</name></author><author><name>Carel P. van Schaik</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Larger brains should be adaptive because they support numerous eco- and socio-cognitive benefits, but these benefits explain only a modest part of the interspecific variation in brain size. Notably underexplored are the high energetic costs of developing brains, and thus the possible role of parental provisioning in the evolution of adult brain size. We explore this idea in birds, which show considerable variation in both socio-ecological traits and the energy transfer from parents to offspring. Comparative analyses of 1,176 bird species show that the combination of adult body mass, mode of development at hatching, relative egg mass, and the time spent provisioning the young in combination strongly predict relative brain size across species. Adding adult eco- and socio-cognitive predictors only marginally adds explanatory value. We therefore conclude that parental provisioning enabled bird species to evolve into skill-intensive niches, reducing interspecific competition and consequently promoting survival prospects and population stability. Critically, parental provisioning also explains why precocial bird species have smaller brains than altricial ones. Finally, these results suggest that the cognitive adaptations that provide the behavioral flexibility to improve reproductive success and survival are intrinsically linked to successful parental provisioning. Our findings also suggest that the traditionally assessed cognitive abilities may not predict relative brain size.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Species vary substantially in their brain size, and the idea that larger-brained species are those with a complex social life or enhanced technological skills has generated much interest. Here we explore another explanation. Because the cognitive benefits provided by brains materialize after a long delay, and constructing them independently involves a major bootstrapping problem for the young, parental inputs may be critical for a species’ brain size. Comparative analyses of a large sample of bird species show that parental provisioning strongly predicts relative brain size across species, swamping the effects of previously considered social or technological cognitive abilities. Thus, cognitive adaptations in birds that enable successful parental provisioning also provide the behavioral flexibility to improve survival and reproductive success.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.470191" rel="alternate" title="Parental provisioning drives brain size in birds (6 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473648</id><title>Molecular and morphological analyses support recognition of Prostanthera volucris (Lamiaceae), a new species from the Central Tablelands of New South Wales (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.416818+00:00</updated><author><name>Ryan P. O’Donnell</name></author><author><name>Jeremy J. Bruhl</name></author><author><name>Ian R.H. Telford</name></author><author><name>Trevor C. Wilson</name></author><author><name>Heidi C. Zimmer</name></author><author><name>Guy M. Taseski</name></author><author><name>Rose L. Andrew</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Research into the systematics of &lt;italic&gt;Prostanthera&lt;/italic&gt; has recently revealed a close evolutionary relationship among &lt;italic&gt;P. phylicifolia s. str.&lt;/italic&gt;, the critically endangered &lt;italic&gt;P. gilesii&lt;/italic&gt;, and a population of uncertain identity from the Central Tablelands of New South Wales, Australia. Previous analyses were unable to establish whether genetic boundaries separated these taxa. This study aimed to assess the species boundaries among these three taxa using a combination of single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNP) sampled at the population-scale and multivariate analysis of morphological characters. Non-parametric and parametric statistics, neighbour-network analysis, phylogenetic analysis, and ancestry coefficient estimates all provided support for discrete genetic differences between the three taxa. Morphological phenetic analysis identified a suite of characters that distinguished each of these taxa. This corroboration of evidence supports the presence of three independently evolving lineages. &lt;italic&gt;Prostanthera gilesii&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;P. phylicifolia s. str.&lt;/italic&gt; are distinct species independent from the third taxon which is described here as &lt;italic&gt;P. volucris&lt;/italic&gt; R.P.O’Donnell. A detailed description, diagnostic line drawings and photographs are provided. We evaluate &lt;italic&gt;P. volucris&lt;/italic&gt; as satisfying criteria to be considered Critically Endangered.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473648" rel="alternate" title="Molecular and morphological analyses support recognition of Prostanthera volucris (Lamiaceae), a new species from the Central Tablelands of New South Wales (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473928</id><title>Applying a Modified Metabarcoding Approach for the Sequencing of Macrofungal Specimens from Fungarium Collections (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.417366+00:00</updated><author><name>C. Gary Olds</name></author><author><name>Jessie W. Berta-Thompson</name></author><author><name>Justin J. Loucks</name></author><author><name>Richard A. Levy</name></author><author><name>Andrew W. Wilson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Premise: Fungaria are a largely untapped source for understanding fungal biodiversity. The effort and cost in producing DNA barcode sequence data for large numbers of fungal specimens can be prohibitive. This study applies a modified metabarcoding approach that provides a labor and cost-effective solution for sequencing the fungal DNA barcode from hundreds of specimens at once. Methods: A two-step PCR approach uses nested barcoded primers to nrITS2 sequence data. We applied this to 766 macrofungal specimens that represent a broad taxonomic sampling of the Dikarya, of which 382 Lactarius specimens are used to identify molecular operational taxonomic units (MOTUs) through a phylogenetic approach. Scripts in Python and R were used to organize sequence data and execute packages CutAdapt and DADA2 were used for primer removal and assessing sequence quality. Sequences were compared to NCBI and UNITE databases and Sanger-produced sequences. Results: Specimen taxonomic identities from nrITS2 sequence data are &amp;gt;90% accurate across all specimens sampled. Phylogenetic analysis of Lactarius sequences identified 20 MOTUs. Discussion: The results demonstrate the capacity of these methods to produce nrITS2 sequences from large numbers of fungarium specimens. This provides an opportunity to more effectively use fungarium collections in advancing fungal diversity identification and documentation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473928" rel="alternate" title="Applying a Modified Metabarcoding Approach for the Sequencing of Macrofungal Specimens from Fungarium Collections (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.24.474119</id><title>Size-structured mating niche differentiation in the male-polyphenic mite Rhizoglyphus robini (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.417754+00:00</updated><author><name>Flor T. Rhebergen</name></author><author><name>Maarten Wijstma</name></author><author><name>Isabel M. Smallegange</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Condition-dependent expression of alternative male morphs evolves when males of different sizes experience different mating niches, requiring different morphologies. Such mating niche differentiation can be due to competitive asymmetry between large and small males in contests over mating opportunities. Here, we tested the hypothesis that aggressive interactions among males cause size-structured mating niches in an acarid mite with condition-dependent male polyphenism: the bulb mite Rhizoglyphus robini. In this species, large males mature as armed fighters with enlarged legs, and small males as scramblers without modified legs. We staged experimental dyadic contests over a mating opportunity between either a pair of fighter males, or a fighter and a scrambler male. We predicted that the larger male would have a higher likelihood of mating first in contests among fighters, that the fighter male would have a higher likelihood of mating first in fighter-scrambler contests, that fighters would have a higher likelihood of interrupting ongoing copulations if they are larger than their mating rival, and that copulations in the presence of a fighter rival therefore last shorter than copulations with a scrambler rival present. We found that in contests among fighters, the larger male had a higher probability of mating first. In contests among a fighter and scrambler, the fighter male was more likely to mate first regardless of the body size difference between the contestants. Ongoing copulations were only rarely interrupted by the rival male (always by a fighter), and the probability of interruption did not depend on the body size difference between the mating male and its rival. Copulations lasted shorter in the presence of a rival fighter, but this effect was not attributable to interruption of copulations. We conclude that the fighting niche is particularly accessible for large males, as larger males have a higher probability of winning pre-copulatory contests. Such mating niche differentiation likely contributes to evolutionary maintenance of condition-dependent male polyphenism, where small males are forced to adopt an alternative mating tactic and hence develop a dedicated morphology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.24.474119" rel="alternate" title="Size-structured mating niche differentiation in the male-polyphenic mite Rhizoglyphus robini (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>