<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.665658+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474457</id><title>Effects of periodic bottlenecks on the dynamics of adaptive evolution in microbial populations (59 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.666232+00:00</updated><author><name>Minako Izutsu</name></author><author><name>Devin M. Lake</name></author><author><name>Zachary W. D. Matson</name></author><author><name>Jack P. Dodson</name></author><author><name>Richard E. Lenski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Population bottlenecks are common in nature, and they can impact the rate of adaptation in evolving populations. On the one hand, each bottleneck reduces the genetic variation that fuels adaptation. On the other hand, fewer founders can undergo more generations and leave more descendants in a resource-limited environment, which allows surviving beneficial mutations to spread more quickly. Here we investigate the impact of repeated bottlenecks on the dynamics of adaptation in experimental populations of &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt;. We propagated 48 populations under four dilution regimes (2-, 8-, 100-, and 1000-fold), all reaching the same final size each day, for 150 days. A simple model in which adaptation is limited by the supply rate of beneficial mutations predicts that fitness gains should be maximized with ~8-fold dilutions. The model also assumes that selection acts only on the overall growth rate and is otherwise identical across dilution regimes. However, we found that selection in the 2-fold regime was qualitatively different from the other treatments. Moreover, we observed earlier and greater fitness gains in the populations subjected to 100- and 1000-fold dilutions than in those that evolved in the 8 fold regime. We also ran simulations using parameters estimated independently from a long-term experiment using the same ancestral strain and environment. The simulations produced dynamics similar to our empirical results under these regimes, and they indicate that the simple model fails owing to the assumption that the supply of beneficial mutations limits adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474457" rel="alternate" title="Effects of periodic bottlenecks on the dynamics of adaptive evolution in microbial populations (59 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474483</id><title>Retrovirus-derived acquired genes, RTL5 and RTL6, are novel constituents of the innate immune system in the eutherian brain. (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.666572+00:00</updated><author><name>Masahito Irie</name></author><author><name>Johbu Itoh</name></author><author><name>Ayumi Matsuzawa</name></author><author><name>Masahito Ikawa</name></author><author><name>Toru Suzuki</name></author><author><name>Yuichi Hiraoka</name></author><author><name>Fumitoshi Ishino</name></author><author><name>Tomoko Kaneko-Ishino</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Retrotransposon Gag-like 5 (RTL5, also known as sushi-ichi-related retrotransposon homolog 8 (SIRH8)) and RTL6 (aka SIRH3) are eutherian-specific genes presumably derived from a retrovirus and phylogenetically related to each other. RTL5 encodes a strongly acidic protein while RTL6 encodes an extremely basic protein, and the former is well conserved and the latter extremely well conserved among the eutherians, indicating their unique and critically important roles as acquired genes. Here we report that RTL5 and RTL6 are microglial genes playing roles in the front line of brain innate immune responses against distinct pathogens. Venus and mCherry knock-in mice exhibited expression of RTL5-mCherry and RTL6-Venus fusion proteins in microglia and as extracellular granules in the central nervus system (CNS), and displayed a rapid response to pathogens such as lipopolysaccharide (LPS), double-stranded (ds) RNA analog and non-methylated CpG DNA. These proteins trapped pathogens in microglia in a variety of RTL-pathogen complexes depending on the pathogens. These results demonstrate that RTL5 and RTL6 exert functional effects against different hazardous substances cooperatively and/or independently to protect the developing and/or mature brain. This provides the first evidence that retrovirus-derived genes play a role in the innate immune system of the eutherian brain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474483" rel="alternate" title="Retrovirus-derived acquired genes, RTL5 and RTL6, are novel constituents of the innate immune system in the eutherian brain. (6 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474527</id><title>Gut mélange à trois: fluctuating selection modulated by microbiota, host immune system, and antibiotics (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.667000+00:00</updated><author><name>Hugo Condessa Barreto</name></author><author><name>Beatriz Abreu</name></author><author><name>Isabel Gordo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Iron is critical in host-microbe interactions, and its availability is under tight regulation in the mammalian gut. Antibiotics and inflammation are known to perturb iron availability in the gut, which could subsequently alter host-microbe interactions. Here, we show that an adaptive allele of &lt;italic&gt;iscR&lt;/italic&gt;, encoding a major regulator of iron homeostasis of &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt;, is under fluctuating selection in the mouse gut. &lt;italic&gt;In vivo&lt;/italic&gt; competitions in immune-competent, immune-compromised, and germ-free mice reveal that the selective pressure on an &lt;italic&gt;iscR&lt;/italic&gt; mutant &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; is modulated by the presence of antibiotics, other members of the microbiota, and the immune system. &lt;italic&gt;In vitro&lt;/italic&gt; assays show that iron availability is an important mediator of the &lt;italic&gt;iscR&lt;/italic&gt; allele fitness benefits or costs.  We identify Lipocalin-2, a host's innate immune system protein that prevents bacterial iron acquisition, as a major host mechanism underlying fluctuating selection of the &lt;italic&gt;iscR allele&lt;/italic&gt;. Our results provide a remarkable example of strong fluctuating selection acting on bacterial iron regulation in the mammalian gut.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474527" rel="alternate" title="Gut mélange à trois: fluctuating selection modulated by microbiota, host immune system, and antibiotics (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.27.474232</id><title>Discovery of a class of giant virus relatives displaying unusual functional traits and prevalent within plankton: the Mirusviricetes (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.667224+00:00</updated><author><name>Morgan Gaia</name></author><author><name>Lingjie Meng</name></author><author><name>Eric Pelletier</name></author><author><name>Patrick Forterre</name></author><author><name>Chiara Vanni</name></author><author><name>Antonio Fernendez-Guerra</name></author><author><name>Olivier Jaillon</name></author><author><name>Patrick Wincker</name></author><author><name>Hiroyuki Ogata</name></author><author><name>Tom O. Delmont</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Large and giant DNA viruses of the phylum Nucleocytoviricota have a profound influence on the ecology and evolution of planktonic eukaryotes. Recently, various Nucleocytoviricota genomes have been characterized from environmental metagenomes based on the occurrence of hallmark genes identified from cultures. However, lineages diverging from the culture genomics functional principles have been overlooked thus far. Here, we developed a phylogeny-guided genome-resolved metagenomic framework using a single hallmark gene as compass, a subunit of DNA-dependent RNA polymerase encoded by most Nucleocytoviricota. We applied this method to large metagenomic data sets from the surface of five oceans and two seas and characterized 697 non-redundant Nucleocytoviricota genomes up to 1.45 Mbp in length. This database expands the known diversity of the class Megaviricetes and revealed two additional putative classes we named Proculviricetes and Mirusviricetes. Critically, the diverse and prevalent Mirusviricetes population genomes seemingly lack several hallmark genes, in particular those related to viral particle morphogenesis. Instead, they share various genes of known (e.g., TATA-binding proteins, histones, proteases and viral rhodopsins) and unknown functions rarely detected if not entirely missing in all other characterized Nucleocytoviricota lineages. Phylogenomics, comparative genomics, functional trends and the signal among planktonic cellular size fractions point to Mirusviricetes being a major, functionally divergent class of large DNA viruses that actively infect eukaryotes in the sunlit ocean using an enigmatic functional life style. Finally, we built a comprehensive marine genomic database for Nucleocytoviricota by combining multiple environmental surveys that might contribute to future endeavors exploring the ecology and evolution of plankton.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.27.474232" rel="alternate" title="Discovery of a class of giant virus relatives displaying unusual functional traits and prevalent within plankton: the Mirusviricetes (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>