<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv evolutionary-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.612872+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.08.447400</id><title>Convergent loss of the necroptosis pathway in disparate mammalian lineages shapes virus countermeasures (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.613349+00:00</updated><author><name>Ana Águeda-Pinto</name></author><author><name>Luís Q. Alves</name></author><author><name>Fabiana Neves</name></author><author><name>Grant McFadden</name></author><author><name>Bertram L Jacobs</name></author><author><name>L. Filipe C. Castro</name></author><author><name>Masmudur M. Rahman</name></author><author><name>Pedro J. Esteves</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Programmed cell death is a vital process in the life cycle of an organism. Necroptosis, an evolutionary restricted form of programmed necrosis, contributes to the innate immune response by killing pathogen-infected cells. This virus-host interaction pathway is organized around two key components: the receptor-interacting protein kinase 3 (RIPK3), which recruits and phosphorylates the mixed lineage kinase-like protein (MLKL), thus inducing cellular plasma membrane rupture and cell death. Critically, the presence of necroptotic inhibitors in viral genomes validates necroptosis as an important host defense mechanism. Here, we show, counterintuitively, that in different mammalian lineages of mammalian, central components of the necroptotic pathway, such as &lt;italic&gt;RIPK3&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;MLKL&lt;/italic&gt; genes, are deleted or display inactivating mutations. Frameshifts or premature stop codons are observed in all the studied species of cetaceans and leporids. In carnivores’ genomes, the &lt;italic&gt;MLKL&lt;/italic&gt; gene is deleted, while in a small number of species from afrotheria and rodentia premature stop codons are observed in &lt;italic&gt;RIPK3&lt;/italic&gt; and/or &lt;italic&gt;MLKL&lt;/italic&gt;. Interestingly, we also found a strong correlation between the disruption of necroptosis in leporids and cetaceans and the absence of the C-terminal domain of E3-like homologs (responsible for necroptosis inhibition) in their naturally infecting poxviruses. Overall, our study provides the first comprehensive picture of the molecular evolution of necroptosis in mammals. The loss of necroptosis multiple times during mammalian evolution highlights the importance of gene/pathway loss for species adaptation and suggests that necroptosis is not required for normal mammalian development. Moreover, this study highlights a co-evolutionary relationship between poxviruses and their hosts, emphasizing the role of host adaptation in shaping virus evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.08.447400" rel="alternate" title="Convergent loss of the necroptosis pathway in disparate mammalian lineages shapes virus countermeasures (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-06-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>