<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.514772+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.30.457919</id><title>Beyond RuBisCO: Convergent molecular evolution of multiple chloroplast genes in C4 plants (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.515344+00:00</updated><author><name>Claudio Casola</name></author><author><name>Jingjia Li</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The recurrent evolution of the C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; photosynthetic pathway in angiosperms represents one of the most extraordinary examples of convergent evolution of a complex trait. Comparative genomic analyses have unveiled some of the molecular changes associated with the C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; pathway. For instance, several key enzymes involved in the transition from C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; to C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; photosynthesis have been found to share convergent amino acid replacements along C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; lineages. However, the extent of convergent replacements potentially associated with the emergence of C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; plants remains to be fully assessed. Here, we introduced a robust empirical approach to test molecular convergence along a phylogeny including multiple C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; and C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; taxa. By analyzing proteins encoded by chloroplast genes, we tested if convergent replacements occurred more frequently than expected in C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; lineages compared to C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; lineages. Furthermore, we sought to determine if convergent evolution occurred in multiple chloroplast proteins beside the well-known case of the large RuBisCO subunit encoded by the chloroplast gene &lt;italic&gt;rbcL&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our study was based on the comparative analysis of 43 C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; and 21 C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; grass species belonging to the PACMAD clade, a focal taxonomic group in many investigations of C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; evolution. We first used protein sequences of 67 orthologous chloroplast genes to build an accurate phylogeny of these species. Then, we inferred amino acid replacements along 13 C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; lineages and 9 C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; lineages using reconstructed protein sequences of their ancestral branches, corresponding to the most recent common ancestor of each lineage. Pairwise comparisons between ancestral branches allowed us to identify both convergent and divergent amino acid replacements between C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;, C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; and C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; lineages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reconstructed phylogenetic tree of 64 PACMAD grasses was characterized by strong supports in all nodes used for analyses of convergence. We identified 217 convergent replacements and 201 divergent replacements in 45/67 chloroplast proteins in both C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; and C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; ancestral branches. Pairs of C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; ancestral branches showed higher levels of convergent replacements than C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; and C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; pairs. Furthermore, we found that more proteins shared unique convergent replacements in C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; lineages, with both RbcL and RpoC1 (the RNA polymerase beta’ subunit 1) showing a significantly higher convergent/divergent replacements ratio in C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; branches. Notably, significantly more C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; pairs of ancestral branches showed higher numbers of convergent vs. divergent replacements than C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; and C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; pairs. Our results demonstrated that, in the PACMAD clade, C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; grasses experienced higher levels of molecular convergence than C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; species across multiple chloroplast genes. These findings have important implications for both our understanding of the evolution of photosynthesis and the goal of engineering improved crop varieties that integrates components of the C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; pathway.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.30.457919" rel="alternate" title="Beyond RuBisCO: Convergent molecular evolution of multiple chloroplast genes in C4 plants (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.30.458162</id><title>Mutationathon: towards standardization in estimates of pedigree-based germline mutation rates (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.515823+00:00</updated><author><name>Lucie A. Bergeron</name></author><author><name>Søren Besenbacher</name></author><author><name>Tychele N. Turner</name></author><author><name>Cyril J. Versoza</name></author><author><name>Richard J. Wang</name></author><author><name>Alivia Lee Price</name></author><author><name>Ellie Armstrong</name></author><author><name>Meritxell Riera</name></author><author><name>Jedidiah Carlson</name></author><author><name>Hwei-yen Chen</name></author><author><name>Matthew W. Hahn</name></author><author><name>Kelley Harris</name></author><author><name>April Snøfrid Lo Natalie M Kleppe</name></author><author><name>Elora H. López-Nandam</name></author><author><name>Priya Moorjani</name></author><author><name>Susanne P. Pfeifer</name></author><author><name>George P. Tiley</name></author><author><name>Anne D. Yoder</name></author><author><name>Guojie Zhang</name></author><author><name>Mikkel H. Schierup</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the past decade, several studies have estimated the human per-generation germline mutation rate using large pedigrees. More recently, estimates for various non-human species have been published. However, methodological differences among studies in detecting germline mutations and estimating mutation rates make direct comparisons difficult. Here, we describe the many different steps involved in estimating pedigree-based mutation rates, including sampling, sequencing, mapping, variant calling, filtering, and how to appropriately account for false-positive and false-negative rates. For each step, we review the different methods and parameter choices that have been used in the recent literature. Additionally, we present the results from a “Mutationathon”, a competition organized among five research labs to compare germline mutation rate estimates for a single pedigree of rhesus macaques. We report almost a two-fold variation in the final estimated rate among groups using different post-alignment processing, calling, and filtering criteria and provide details into the sources of variation across studies. Though the difference among estimates is not statistically significant, this discrepancy emphasizes the need for standardized methods in mutation rate estimations and the difficulty in comparing rates from different studies. Finally, this work aims to provide guidelines for computational and statistical benchmarks for future studies interested in identifying germline mutations from pedigrees.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.30.458162" rel="alternate" title="Mutationathon: towards standardization in estimates of pedigree-based germline mutation rates (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>