<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.239393+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472438</id><title>Artificial selection of communities drives the emergence of structured interactions (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.239783+00:00</updated><author><name>Jules Fraboul</name></author><author><name>Giulio Biroli</name></author><author><name>Silvia De Monte</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Species-rich communities, such as the microbiota or environmental microbial assemblages, provide key functions for human health and ecological resilience. Increasing effort is being dedicated to design experimental protocols for selecting community-level functions of interest. These experiments typically involve selection acting on populations of communities, each of which is composed of multiple species. Numerical explorations allowed to link the evolutionary dynamics to the multiple parameters involved in this complex, multi-scale evolutionary process. However, a comprehensive theoretical understanding of artificial selection of communities is still lacking. Here, we propose a general model for the evolutionary dynamics of species-rich communities, each described by disordered generalized Lotka-Volterra equations, that we study analytically and by numerical simulations. Our results reveal that a generic response to selection for larger total community abundance is the emergence of an isolated eigenvalue of the interaction matrix that can be understood as an effective cross-feeding term. In this way, selection imprints a structure on the community, which results in a global increase of both the level of mutualism and the diversity of interactions. Our approach moreover allows to disentangle the role of intraspecific competition, interspecific interactions symmetry and number of selected communities in the evolutionary process, and can thus be used as a guidance in optimizing artificial selection protocols.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472438" rel="alternate" title="Artificial selection of communities drives the emergence of structured interactions (30 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472698</id><title>Evolution of stickleback spines through independent cis-regulatory changes at HOXDB (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.240018+00:00</updated><author><name>Julia I. Wucherpfennig</name></author><author><name>Timothy R. Howes</name></author><author><name>Jessica N. Au</name></author><author><name>Eric H. Au</name></author><author><name>Garrett A. Roberts Kingman</name></author><author><name>Shannon D. Brady</name></author><author><name>Amy L. Herbert</name></author><author><name>Thomas E. Reimchen</name></author><author><name>Michael A. Bell</name></author><author><name>Craig B. Lowe</name></author><author><name>Anne C. Dalziel</name></author><author><name>David M. Kingsley</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the genetic mechanisms leading to new traits is a fundamental goal of evolutionary biology. We show that &lt;italic&gt;HOXDB&lt;/italic&gt; regulatory changes have been used repeatedly in different stickleback fish species to alter the length and number of bony dorsal spines. In &lt;italic&gt;Gasterosteus aculeatus&lt;/italic&gt;, a variant &lt;italic&gt;HOXDB&lt;/italic&gt; allele is genetically linked to shortening an existing spine and adding a spine. In &lt;italic&gt;Apeltes quadracus&lt;/italic&gt;, a variant allele is associated with lengthening an existing spine and adding a spine. The alleles alter the same conserved non-coding &lt;italic&gt;HOXDB&lt;/italic&gt; enhancer by diverse molecular mechanisms, including SNPs, deletions, and transposable element insertions. The independent &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-acting regulatory changes are linked to anterior expansion or contraction of &lt;italic&gt;HOXDB&lt;/italic&gt; expression. Our findings support the long-standing hypothesis that natural &lt;italic&gt;Hox&lt;/italic&gt; gene variation underlies key morphological patterning changes in wild populations and illustrate how different mutational mechanisms affecting the same region may produce opposite gene expression changes with similar phenotypic outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract Figure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="472698v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472698" rel="alternate" title="Evolution of stickleback spines through independent cis-regulatory changes at HOXDB (21 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472416</id><title>Ecology drives the degree of convergence in the gene expression of extremophile fishes (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.240321+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael Tobler</name></author><author><name>Ryan Greenway</name></author><author><name>Joanna L. Kelley</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Convergent evolution, where independent lineages evolve similar traits when adapting to similar habitats, is a common phenomenon and testament to the repeatability of evolutionary processes. Still, non-convergence is also common, and a major question is whether apparently idiosyncratic, lineage-specific evolutionary changes are reflective of chance events inherent to evolutionary processes, or whether they are also influenced by deterministic genetic or ecological factors. To address this question, we quantified the degree of convergence in genome-wide patterns of gene expression across lineages of livebearing fishes (family Poeciliidae) that span 40 million years of evolution and have colonized extreme environments in the form of toxic, hydrogen-sulfide-rich springs. We specifically asked whether the degree of convergence across lineage pairs was related to their phylogenetic relatedness or the ecological similarity of the habitats they inhabit. Using phylogenetic comparative analyses, we showed that the degree of convergence was highly variable across lineage pairs residing in sulfide springs. While closely related lineages did not exhibit higher degrees of convergence than distantly related ones, we uncovered a strong relationship between degree of convergence and ecological similarity. Our results indicate that variation in the degree of convergence is not merely noise associated with evolutionary contingency. Rather, cryptic environmental variation that is frequently ignored when we employ reductionist approaches can significantly contribute to adaptive evolution. This study highlights the importance of multivariate approaches that capture the complexities of both selective regimes and organismal design when assessing the roles of determinism and contingency in evolution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;When different species adapt to similar environmental conditions, we frequently observe a mix between shared (convergent) and lineage-specific (nonconvergent) evolutionary changes. Shared changes provide evidence for the repeatability and predictability of evolution. However, it remains unclear whether lineage-specific changes are caused by random forces that limit the predictability of evolution, or whether they reflect deterministic processes shaped by unidentified genetic and environmental factors. By analyzing patterns of gene expression across fishes in extreme environments, we show that the degree of convergence between lineages is related to ecology, indicating that lineage-specific evolutionary changes are not just noise caused by random processes. Thus, acknowledging the complexity of nature in empirical research is critical if we want to predict evolution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472416" rel="alternate" title="Ecology drives the degree of convergence in the gene expression of extremophile fishes (20 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473006</id><title>The probability of joint monophyly of all species in an arbitrary species tree. (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.240514+00:00</updated><author><name>Rohan S Mehta</name></author><author><name>Mike Steel</name></author><author><name>Noah A Rosenberg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Monophyly is a feature of a set of genetic lineages in which every lineage in the set is more closely related to all other members of the set than it is to any lineage outside the set. Multiple sets of lineages that are separately monophyletic are said to be reciprocally monophyletic, or jointly monophyletic. The prevalence of reciprocal monophyly, or joint monophyly, has been used to evaluate phylogenetic and phylogeographic hypotheses, as well as to delimit species. These applications often make use of a probability of joint monophyly under models of gene lineage evolution. Studies in coalescent theory have computed this joint monophyly probability for small numbers of separate groups in arbitrary species trees, and for arbitrary numbers of separate groups in trivial species trees. Here, generalizing existing results on monophyly probabilities under the multispecies coalescent, we derive the probability of joint monophyly for arbitrary numbers of separate groups in arbitrary species trees. We illustrate how our result collapses to previously examined cases. We also study the effect of tree height, sample size, and number of species on the probability of joint monophyly. The result also enables computation of relatively simple lower and upper bounds on the joint monophyly probability. Our results expand the scope of joint monophyly calculations beyond small numbers of species, subsuming past formulas that have been used in simpler cases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473006" rel="alternate" title="The probability of joint monophyly of all species in an arbitrary species tree. (17 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472906</id><title>The genome sequence of the lesser marbled fritillary, Brenthis ino, and evidence for a segregating neo-Z chromosome (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.240735+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Mackintosh</name></author><author><name>Dominik Laetsch</name></author><author><name>Tobias Baril</name></author><author><name>Robert Foster</name></author><author><name>Vlad Dincă</name></author><author><name>Roger Vila</name></author><author><name>Alex Hayward</name></author><author><name>Konrad Lohse</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The lesser marbled fritillary, &lt;italic&gt;Brenthis ino&lt;/italic&gt; (Rottemburg, 1775), is a species of Palearctic butterfly. Male &lt;italic&gt;B. ino&lt;/italic&gt; individuals have been reported to have between 12 and 14 pairs of chromosomes, a much reduced chromosome number than is typical in butterflies. Here we present a chromosome-level genome assembly for &lt;italic&gt;B. ino&lt;/italic&gt;, as well as gene and transposable element annotations. The assembly is 411.8 Mb in span with contig and scaffold N50s of 9.6 and 29.5 Mb respectively. We also show evidence that the male individual from which we generated HiC data was heterozygous for a neo-Z chromosome, consistent with inheriting 14 chromosomes from one parent and 13 from the other. This genome assembly will be a valuable resource for studying chromosome evolution in Lepidoptera, as well as for comparative and population genomics more generally.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472906" rel="alternate" title="The genome sequence of the lesser marbled fritillary, Brenthis ino, and evidence for a segregating neo-Z chromosome (9 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473019</id><title>Evolutionary traits of Tick-borne encephalitis virus: Pervasive non-coding RNA structure conservation and molecular epidemiology (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.241034+00:00</updated><author><name>Lena S. Kutschera</name></author><author><name>Michael T. Wolfinger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tick-borne encephalitis virus (TBEV) is the etiological agent of tick-borne encephalitis, an infectious disease of the central nervous system that is often associated with severe sequelae in humans. While TBEV is typically classified into three subtypes, recent evidence suggests a more varied range of TBEV subtypes and lineages that differ substantially in their 3'UTR architecture. Building on comparative genomics approaches and thermodynamic modeling, we characterize the TBEV 3'UTR structureome diversity and propose a unified picture of pervasive non-coding RNA (ncRNA) structure conservation. Moreover, we provide an updated phylogeny of TBEV, building on more than 220 publicly available complete genomes, and investigate the molecular epidemiology and phylodynamics with Nextstrain, a web-based visualization framework for real-time pathogen evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473019" rel="alternate" title="Evolutionary traits of Tick-borne encephalitis virus: Pervasive non-coding RNA structure conservation and molecular epidemiology (7 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472951</id><title>The costs and benefits of dispersal in small populations (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.241354+00:00</updated><author><name>Jitka Polechova</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Dispersal has three major effects on adaptation. First, the gene flow mixes alleles adapted to different environments, potentially hindering (swamping) adaptation. Second, it inflates genetic variance: this aids adaptation to spatially (and temporally) varying environments but if selection is hard, it lowers the mean fitness of the population. Third, neighbourhood size, which determines how weak genetic drift is, increases with dispersal -- when genetic drift is strong, increase of neighbourhood size with dispersal aids adaptation. In this note I focus on the role of dispersal in environments which change smoothly across space, and when local populations are quite small such that genetic drift has a significant effect. Using individual-based simulations, I show that in small populations, even leptokurtic dispersal benefits adaptation, by reducing the power of genetic drift. This has implications for management of small marginal populations: increased gene flow appears beneficial as long as adaptations involves a quantitative, rather than a discrete, trait. However, heavily leptokurtic dispersal will swamp continuous adaptation along steep environmental gradients so that only patches of locally adapted subpopulations remain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472951" rel="alternate" title="The costs and benefits of dispersal in small populations (7 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.470823</id><title>Stressed out underground?: Transcriptomics illuminates the genome-wide response to heat stress in surface and subterranean diving beetles (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.241660+00:00</updated><author><name>Perry G. Beasley-Hall</name></author><author><name>Terry Bertozzi</name></author><author><name>Tessa M. Bradford</name></author><author><name>Charles S. P. Foster</name></author><author><name>Karl Jones</name></author><author><name>Simon M. Tierney</name></author><author><name>William F. Humphreys</name></author><author><name>Andrew D. Austin</name></author><author><name>Steven J. B. Cooper</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Subterranean habitats are environmentally stable with respect to temperature, humidity, and the absence of light. The transition to a subterranean lifestyle might therefore be expected to cause considerable shifts in an organism’s physiology; here, we investigate how subterranean colonisation affects thermal tolerance. Subterranean organisms might be at an increased risk of decline in the face of global temperature rises, but robust data on the fauna is lacking, particularly at the molecular level. In this study we compare the heat shock response of two species of diving beetle in the genus &lt;italic&gt;Paroster&lt;/italic&gt;: one surface-dwelling (&lt;italic&gt;P. nigroadumbratus&lt;/italic&gt;), the other restricted to a single aquifer (&lt;italic&gt;P. macrosturtensis&lt;/italic&gt;). &lt;italic&gt;P. macrosturtensis&lt;/italic&gt; has been previously established as having a lower thermal tolerance compared to surface-dwelling relatives, but the genomic basis of this difference is unknown. By sequencing transcriptomes of experimentally heat-shocked individuals and performing differential expression analysis, we demonstrate both species can mount a heat shock response at high temperatures (35C), in agreement with past survival experiments. However, the genes involved in these responses differ between species, and far greater genes are differentially expressed in the surface species, which may explain its more robust response to heat stress. In contrast, the subterranean species significantly upregulated the heat shock protein gene &lt;italic&gt;Hsp68&lt;/italic&gt; in the experimental setup under conditions it would likely encounter in nature (25C), suggesting it may be more sensitive to ambient stressors, e.g. handling. The results presented here contribute to an emerging narrative concerning weakened thermal tolerances in obligate subterranean organisms at the molecular level.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.470823" rel="alternate" title="Stressed out underground?: Transcriptomics illuminates the genome-wide response to heat stress in surface and subterranean diving beetles (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>