<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.019686+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475250</id><title>Assessing Bayesian Phylogenetic Information Content of Morphological Data Using Knowledge from Anatomy Ontologies (41 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.020039+00:00</updated><author><name>Diego Sasso Porto</name></author><author><name>Wasila Dahdul</name></author><author><name>Hilmar Lapp</name></author><author><name>James Balhoff</name></author><author><name>Todd Vision</name></author><author><name>Paula Mabee</name></author><author><name>Josef Uyeda</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Morphology remains a primary source of phylogenetic information for many groups of organisms, and the only one for most fossil taxa. Organismal anatomy is not a collection of randomly assembled and independent "parts", but instead a set of dependent and hierarchically nested entities resulting from ontogeny and phylogeny. How do we make sense of these dependent and at times redundant characters? One promising approach is using ontologies---structured controlled vocabularies that summarize knowledge about different properties of anatomical entities, including developmental and structural dependencies. Here we assess whether the proximity of ontology-annotated characters within an ontology predicts evolutionary patterns. To do so, we measure phylogenetic information across characters and evaluate if it is hierarchically structured by ontological knowledge---in much the same way as phylogeny structures across-species diversity. We implement an approach to evaluate the Bayesian phylogenetic information (BPI) content and phylogenetic dissonance among ontology-annotated anatomical data subsets. We applied this to datasets representing two disparate animal groups: bees (Hexapoda: Hymenoptera: Apoidea, 209 chars) and characiform fishes (Actinopterygii: Ostariophysi: Characiformes, 463 chars). For bees, we find that BPI is not substantially structured by anatomy since dissonance is often high among morphologically related anatomical entities. For fishes, we find substantial information for two clusters of anatomical entities instantiating concepts from the jaws and branchial arch bones, but among-subset information decreases and dissonance increases substantially moving to higher-level subsets in the ontology. We further applied our approach to addressing particular evolutionary hypotheses with an example of morphological evolution in miniature fishes. While we show that ontology does indeed structure phylogenetic information, additional relationships and processes, such as convergence, likely play a substantial role in explaining BPI and dissonance, and merit future investigation. Our work demonstrates how complex morphological datasets can be interrogated with ontologies by allowing one to access how information is spread hierarchically across anatomical concepts, how congruent this information is, and what sorts of processes may structure it: phylogeny, development, or convergence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475250" rel="alternate" title="Assessing Bayesian Phylogenetic Information Content of Morphological Data Using Knowledge from Anatomy Ontologies (41 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475101</id><title>Liver-derived cell lines from cavefish Astyanax mexicanus as an in vitro model for studying metabolic adaptation (31 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.020312+00:00</updated><author><name>Jaya Krishnan</name></author><author><name>Yan Wang</name></author><author><name>Olga Kenzior</name></author><author><name>Huzaifa Hassan</name></author><author><name>Luke Olsen</name></author><author><name>Dai Tsuchiya</name></author><author><name>Yongfu Wang</name></author><author><name>Chongbei Zhao</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Rohner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cell lines have become an integral resource and tool for conducting biological experiments ever since the Hela cell line was first developed (1). They not only allow detailed investigation of molecular pathways but are faster and more cost-effective than most in vivo approaches. The last decade saw many emerging model systems strengthening basic science research. However, lack of genetic and molecular tools in these newer systems pose many obstacles. Astyanax mexicanus is proving to be an interesting new model system for understanding metabolic adaptation. To further enhance the utility of this system, we developed liver-derived cell lines from both surface-dwelling and cave-dwelling morphotypes. In this study, we provide detailed methodology of the derivation process along with a comprehensive biochemical and molecular characterization of the cell lines, which reflects key metabolic traits of cavefish adaptation. We anticipate these cell lines to become a useful resource for the Astyanax community as well as researchers investigating fish biology, comparative physiology, and metabolism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475101" rel="alternate" title="Liver-derived cell lines from cavefish Astyanax mexicanus as an in vitro model for studying metabolic adaptation (31 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475184</id><title>Ghost lineages invalidate or reverse several results on gene flow (26 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.020547+00:00</updated><author><name>Theo Tricou</name></author><author><name>Eric Tannier</name></author><author><name>Damien M de Vienne</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Introgression, endosymbiosis and gene transfer, i.e. Horizontal Gene Flow (HGF), are primordial sources of innovation in all domains of life. Our knowledge on HGF relies on detection methods that exploit some of its signatures left on extant genomes. One of them is the effect of HGF on branch lengths of constructed phylogenies. This signature has been formalized in statistical tests for HGF detection, and used for example to detect massive adaptive gene flows in malaria vectors or to order evolutionary events involved in eukaryogenesis. However these studies rely on the assumption that ghost lineages (all unsampled extant and extinct taxa) have little influence. We demonstrate here with simulations and data re-analysis, that when considering the more realistic condition that unsampled taxa are legion compared to sampled ones, the conclusion of these studies become unfounded or even reversed. This illustrates the necessity to recognize the existence of ghosts in evolutionary studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475184" rel="alternate" title="Ghost lineages invalidate or reverse several results on gene flow (26 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474967</id><title>Automated Landmarking via Multiple Templates (20 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.020722+00:00</updated><author><name>Chi Zhang</name></author><author><name>Arthur Porto</name></author><author><name>Sara Rolfe</name></author><author><name>Altan Kocatulum</name></author><author><name>A. Murat Maga</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Geometric morphometrics based on landmark data has been increasingly used in biomedical and biological researchers for quantifying complex phenotypes. However, manual landmarking can be laborious and subject to intra and interobserver errors. This has motivated the development of automated landmarking methods. We have recently introduced ALPACA (Automated Landmarking through Point cloud Alignment and Correspondence), a fast method to automatically annotate landmarks via use of a landmark template as part of the SlicerMorph toolkit. Yet, using a single template may not consistently perform well for large study samples, especially when the sample consists of specimen with highly variable morphology, as it is common evolutionary studies. In this study, we introduce a variation on our ALPACA pipeline that supports multiple specimen templates, which we call MALPACA. We show that MALPACA outperforms ALPACA consistently by testing on two different datasets. We also introduce a method of choosing the templates that can be used in conjunction with MALPACA, when no prior information is available. This K-means method uses an approximation of the total morphological variation in the dataset to suggest samples within the population to be used as landmark templates. While we advise investigators to pay careful attention to the template selection process in any of the template-based automated landmarking approaches, our analyses show that the introduced K-means based method of templates selection is better than randomly choosing the templates. In summary, MALPACA can accommodate larger morphological disparity commonly found in evolutionary studies with performance comparable to human observer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474967" rel="alternate" title="Automated Landmarking via Multiple Templates (20 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475150</id><title>Function and constraint in enhancers with multiple evolutionary origins (16 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.020909+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah L Fong</name></author><author><name>John Anthony Capra</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Motivation: Thousands of human gene regulatory enhancers are composed of sequences with multiple evolutionary origins. These evolutionarily "complex" enhancers consist of older "core" sequences and younger "derived" sequences. However, the functional relationship between the sequences of different evolutionary origins within complex enhancers is poorly understood. Results: We evaluated the function, selective pressures, and sequence variation across core and derived components of human complex enhancers. We find that both components are older than expected from the genomic background, and cores are enriched for derived sequences of similar evolutionary ages. Both components show strong evidence of biochemical activity in massively parallel report assays (MPRAs). However, core and derived sequences have distinct transcription factor (TF) binding preferences that are largely stable across evolutionary origins. Given these signatures of function, both core and derived sequences have substantial evidence of purifying selection. Nonetheless, derived sequences exhibit weaker purifying selection than adjacent cores. Derived sequences also tolerate more common genetic variation and are enriched compared to cores for eQTL associated with gene expression variability in human populations. Conclusions: Both core and derived sequences have strong evidence of gene regulatory function, but derived sequences have distinct constraint profiles, TF binding preferences, and tolerance to variation compared with cores. We propose that the step-wise integration of younger derived and older core sequences has generated regulatory substrates with robust activity and the potential for functional variation. Our analyses demonstrate that synthesizing study of enhancer evolution and function can aid interpretation of regulatory sequence activity and functional variation across human populations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475150" rel="alternate" title="Function and constraint in enhancers with multiple evolutionary origins (16 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475277</id><title>Acquisition of cross-azole tolerance and aneuploidy in Candida albicans strains evolved to posaconazole (15 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.021071+00:00</updated><author><name>Rebekah J Kukurudz</name></author><author><name>Madison Chapel</name></author><author><name>Quinn Wonitowy</name></author><author><name>Abdul-Rahman Adamu Bukari</name></author><author><name>Brooke Sidney</name></author><author><name>Riley Sierhuis</name></author><author><name>Aleeza Gerstein</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A number of in vitro studies have examined the acquisition of drug resistance to the triazole fluconazole, a first-line treatment for many Candida infections. Much less is known about posaconazole, a newer triazole. We conducted the first in vitro experimental evolution of replicates from eight diverse strains of C. albicans in a high level of the fungistatic drug posaconazole. Approximately half of the 132 evolved replicates survived 50 generations of evolution, biased towards some of the strain backgrounds. We found that although increases in drug resistance were rare, increases in drug tolerance (the slow growth of a subpopulation of cells in a level of drug above the resistance level) were common across strains. We also found that adaptation to posaconazole resulted in widespread cross-tolerance to other azole drugs. Widespread aneuploidy variation was also observed in evolved replicates from some strain backgrounds. Trisomy of chromosomes 3, 6, and R was identified in 11 of 12 whole-genome sequenced evolved SC5314 replicates. These findings document rampant evolved cross-tolerance among triazoles and highlight that increases in drug tolerance can evolve independently of drug resistance in a diversity of C. albicans strain backgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475277" rel="alternate" title="Acquisition of cross-azole tolerance and aneuploidy in Candida albicans strains evolved to posaconazole (15 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.475009</id><title>Three amphioxus reference genomes reveal gene and chromosome evolution of chordates (12 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.021276+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhen Huang</name></author><author><name>Luohao Xu</name></author><author><name>Cheng Cai</name></author><author><name>Yitao Zhou</name></author><author><name>Jing Liu</name></author><author><name>Zexian Zhu</name></author><author><name>Wen Kang</name></author><author><name>Duo Chen</name></author><author><name>Surui Pei</name></author><author><name>Ting Xue</name></author><author><name>Wan Cen</name></author><author><name>Chenggang Shi</name></author><author><name>Xiaotong Wu</name></author><author><name>Yongji Huang</name></author><author><name>Chaohua Xu</name></author><author><name>Yanan Yan</name></author><author><name>Ying Yang</name></author><author><name>Wenjing He</name></author><author><name>Xuefeng Hu</name></author><author><name>Yanding Zhang</name></author><author><name>Youqiang Chen</name></author><author><name>Changwei Bi</name></author><author><name>Chunpeng He</name></author><author><name>Lingzhan Xue</name></author><author><name>Shijun Xiao</name></author><author><name>Zhicao Yue</name></author><author><name>Yu Jiang</name></author><author><name>Jr-Kai Yu</name></author><author><name>Erich D. Jarvis</name></author><author><name>Guang Li</name></author><author><name>Gang Lin</name></author><author><name>Qiujin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Qi Zhou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The slow-evolving invertebrate amphioxus has an irreplaceable role in advancing our understanding into the vertebrate origin and innovations. Here we resolve the nearly complete chromosomal genomes of three amphioxus species, one of which best recapitulates the 17 chordate ancestor linkage groups. We reconstruct the fusions, retention or rearrangements between descendants of whole genome duplications (WGDs), which gave rise to the extant microchromosomes likely existed in the vertebrate ancestor. Similar to vertebrates, the amphioxus genome gradually establishes its 3D chromatin architecture at the onset of zygotic activation, and forms two topologically associated domains at the &lt;italic&gt;Hox&lt;/italic&gt; gene cluster. We find that all three amphioxus species have ZW sex chromosomes with little sequence differentiation, and their putative sex-determining regions are nonhomologous to each other. Our results illuminate the unappreciated interspecific diversity and developmental dynamics of amphioxus genomes, and provide high-quality references for understanding the mechanisms of chordate functional genome evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.475009" rel="alternate" title="Three amphioxus reference genomes reveal gene and chromosome evolution of chordates (12 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475093</id><title>Plant peptidoglycan precursor biosynthesis: Conservation between moss chloroplasts and Gram negative bacteria (12 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.021842+00:00</updated><author><name>Amanda Jane Dowson</name></author><author><name>Adrian J Lloyd</name></author><author><name>Andrew C. Cuming</name></author><author><name>David I Roper</name></author><author><name>Lorenzo Frigerio</name></author><author><name>Christopher G Dowson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;An accumulation of evidence suggests that peptidoglycan, consistent with a bacterial cell wall, is synthesised around the chloroplasts of many photosynthetic eukaryotes, from glaucophyte algae to land plants at least as evolved as pteridophyte ferns, but the biosynthetic pathway has not been demonstrated. We employed mass spectrometry and enzymology in a two fold approach to characterize the synthesis of peptidoglycan in chloroplasts of the moss Physcomitrium (Physcomitrella) patens. To drive the accumulation of peptidoglycan pathway intermediates, P.patens was cultured with the antibiotics phosphomycin, D-cycloserine and carbenicillin, which inhibit key peptidoglycan pathway proteins in bacteria. Mass spectrometry of the TCA-extracted moss metabolome revealed elevated levels of five of the predicted intermediates from UDP-GlcNAc through to the UDP-MurNAc-D,L-diaminopimelate (DAP)-pentapeptide. Most Gram negative bacteria, including cyanobacteria, incorporate meso-diaminopimelate (D,L-DAP) into the third residue of the stem peptide of peptidoglycan, as opposed to L-Lysine, typical of most Gram positive bacteria. To establish the specificity of D,L-DAP incorporation into the P.patens precursors, we analysed the recombinant protein that appends the third stem peptide amino acid, UDP-MurNAc-tripeptide ligase (MurE), from both P.patens and the cyanobacterium Anabaena sp. strain PCC 7120. Both ligases incorporated D,L-DAP in almost complete preference to L-Lys, consistent with the mass spectrophotometric data, with catalytic efficiencies similar to previously documented Gram negative bacterial MurE ligases. We discuss how these data accord with the conservation of active site residues common to DL-DAP-incorporating bacterial MurE ligases and of the probability of a horizontal gene transfer event within the plant peptidoglycan pathway.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475093" rel="alternate" title="Plant peptidoglycan precursor biosynthesis: Conservation between moss chloroplasts and Gram negative bacteria (12 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475294</id><title>High homozygosity of inversions in sunflower species largely averts accumulation of deleterious mutations (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.022098+00:00</updated><author><name>Kaichi Huang</name></author><author><name>Kate L Ostevik</name></author><author><name>Cassandra Elphinstone</name></author><author><name>Marco Todesco</name></author><author><name>Natalia Bercovich</name></author><author><name>Gregory L. Owens</name></author><author><name>Loren H. Rieseberg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recombination is critical both for accelerating adaptation and for the purging of deleterious mutations. Chromosomal inversions can act as recombination modifiers that suppress local recombination and, thus, are predicted to accumulate such mutations. In this study, we investigated patterns of recombination, transposable element abundance and coding sequence evolution across the genomes of 1,445 individuals from three sunflower species, as well as within nine inversions segregating within species. We also analyzed the effects of inversion genotypes on 87 phenotypic traits to test for overdominance. We found significant negative correlations of long terminal repeat retrotransposon abundance and deleterious mutations with recombination rates across the genome in all three species. However, we failed to detect an increase in these features in the inversions, except for a modest increase in the proportion of stop codon mutations in several very large or rare inversions. Moreover, there was little evidence of phenotypic overdominance in inversion heterozygotes, consistent with observations of minimal deleterious load. On the other hand, significantly greater load was observed for inversions in populations polymorphic for a given inversion compared to populations monomorphic for one of the arrangements, suggesting that the local state of inversion polymorphism affects deleterious load. These seemingly contradictory results can be explained by the geographic structuring and consequent excess homozygosity of inversions in wild sunflowers. Inversions contributing to local adaptation often exhibit geographic structure; such inversions represent ideal recombination modifiers, acting to facilitate adaptive divergence with gene flow, while largely averting the accumulation of deleterious mutations due to recombination suppression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475294" rel="alternate" title="High homozygosity of inversions in sunflower species largely averts accumulation of deleterious mutations (11 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474937</id><title>Increased opposite sex association is linked with fitness benefits, otherwise sociality is subject to stabilising selection in a wild passerine (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.022310+00:00</updated><author><name>Jamie Dunning</name></author><author><name>Terry Burke</name></author><author><name>Alex Hoi Hang Chan</name></author><author><name>Heung Ying Janet Chik</name></author><author><name>Tim Evans</name></author><author><name>Julia Schroeder</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Animal sociality, an individuals propensity to association with others, has consequences for fitness, and particularly mate choice. For example, directly, by increasing the pool of prospective partners, and indirectly through increased survival. Individuals benefit from both over the short-term as these benefits are associated with mating status and subsequent fecundity, but whether animal sociality also translates into fitness is unknown. Here, we quantified social associations and their link with annual and lifetime fitness, measured as the number of recruits and in de-lifed fitness. We measured this in birds visiting a feeding station over two non-breeding periods, using social network analysis and a multi-generational genetic pedigree. We find high individual repeatability in sociality. We found that individuals with an average sociality had the highest fitness, and that birds with more opposite-sex associates had higher fitness, but this did not translate to improved lifetime fitness. For lifetime fitness, we found evidence for stabilizing selection on between sex sociality measures, suggesting that such benefits are only short-lived in a wild population.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474937" rel="alternate" title="Increased opposite sex association is linked with fitness benefits, otherwise sociality is subject to stabilising selection in a wild passerine (7 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474909</id><title>The bounded coalescent model: conditioning a genealogy on a minimum root date (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.022508+00:00</updated><author><name>Jake Carson</name></author><author><name>Alice Ledda</name></author><author><name>Luca Ferretti</name></author><author><name>Matt Keeling</name></author><author><name>Xavier Didelot</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The coalescent model represents how individuals sampled from a population may have originated from a last common ancestor. The bounded coalescent model is obtained by conditioning the coalescent model such that the last common ancestor must have existed after a certain date. This conditioned model arises in a variety of applications, such as speciation, horizontal gene transfer or transmission analysis, and yet the bounded coalescent model has not been previously analysed in detail. Here we describe a new algorithm to simulate from this model directly, without resorting to rejection sampling. We show that this direct simulation algorithm is more computationally efficient than the rejection sampling approach. We also show how to calculate the probability of the last common ancestor occurring after a given date, which is required to compute the probability of realisations under the bounded coalescent model. Our results are applicable in both the isochronous (when all samples have the same date) and heterochronous (where samples can have different dates) settings. We explore the effect of setting a bound on the date of the last common ancestor, and show that it affects a number of properties of the resulting phylogenies. All our methods are implemented in a new R package called BoundedCoalescent which is freely available online.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474909" rel="alternate" title="The bounded coalescent model: conditioning a genealogy on a minimum root date (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475057</id><title>Maternal investment evolves with larger body size and higher diversification rate in sharks and rays (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.022709+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher G Mull</name></author><author><name>Matthew W Pennell</name></author><author><name>Kara E Yopak</name></author><author><name>Nicholas K Dulvy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Across vertebrates, live-bearing has evolved at least 150 times from the ancestral state of egg-laying into a diverse array of forms and degrees of prepartum maternal investment. A key question is how this diversity of reproductive modes arose and whether reproductive diversification underlies species diversification? To test these questions, we evaluate the most basal jawed vertebrates, Chondrichthyans, which have one of the greatest ranges of reproductive and ecological diversity among vertebrates. We reconstructed the sequence of reproductive mode evolution across a time-calibrated molecular phylogeny of 610 chondrichthyans. We find that egg-laying is ancestral, and that live-bearing evolved at least seven times. Matrotrophy (i.e. additional maternal contributions) evolved at least 15 times, with evidence of one reversal. In sharks, transitions to live-bearing and matrotrophy are more prevalent in larger-bodied species in the tropics. Further, the evolution of live-bearing is associated with a near-doubling of the diversification rate, but, there is only a small increase in diversification associated with the appearance of matrotrophy. The chondrichthyan diversification and radiation, particularly throughout the shallow tropical shelf seas and oceanic pelagic habitats, appears to be associated with the evolution of live-bearing and the proliferation of a wide range of maternal investment in their developing offspring.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475057" rel="alternate" title="Maternal investment evolves with larger body size and higher diversification rate in sharks and rays (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474956</id><title>Deterministic approximation for population dynamics in the presence of advantageous mutants (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.022885+00:00</updated><author><name>Ignacio Rodriguez-Brenes</name></author><author><name>Dominik Wodarz</name></author><author><name>Natalia Komarova</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spatial stochastic simulations of evolutionary processes are computationally expensive. Here, based on spatially explicit decoupling approximations (SEDA) introduced by us earlier,  we derive a deterministic approximation  to a spatial stochastic birth-death process in the presence of two types: the less advantageous resident type and a more advantageous mutant. At the core of this technique are two essential steps: (1) a system of ODEs that approximate spatial interactions among neighboring individuals must be solved; (2)  the time-variable has to be rescaled with a factor (called "alpha") that depends on the kinetic parameters of the wild type and mutant individuals. An explicit formula for alpha is derived, which is a power law of division and death rates of the two types. The method is relatively fast and provides excellent time-series agreement with the stochastic simulation results for the spatial agent-based model. The methodology can be used to describe hard selective sweep events, including the expansion of driver mutations in carcinogenesis, bacterial evolution, and aspects of resistance dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474956" rel="alternate" title="Deterministic approximation for population dynamics in the presence of advantageous mutants (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.475003</id><title>Recurrent co-option and recombination of cytokine and three finger proteins in multiple reproductive tissues throughout salamander evolution (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.023064+00:00</updated><author><name>Damien B. Wilburn</name></author><author><name>Christy L. Kunkel</name></author><author><name>Richard C. Feldhoff</name></author><author><name>Pamela W. Feldhoff</name></author><author><name>Brian C. Searle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The proteomic composition of amphibian gametes is largely a molecular mystery, particularly for Urodeles (salamanders and newts) which have few genomic-scale resources. Lungless salamanders (family Plethodontidae) include approximately two thirds of all extant salamander species and are classic models of vertebrate mating behavior. As part of an extended, multi-stage courtship ritual, male plethodontid salamanders deliver rapidly evolving protein pheromones that modify female behavior and improve male reproductive success. Despite great interest in this set of pre-mating reproductive barriers, limited characterization of plethodontid gametes has prohibited investigation of post-mating pre-zygotic barriers such as sperm-egg recognition. In this study, we performed transcriptomic analyses of testis and ovary using long-read PacBio sequencing and proteomic analyses of sperm using mass spectrometry for two evolutionary divergent plethodontid species, &lt;italic&gt;Plethodon shermani&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Desmognathus ocoee&lt;/italic&gt;. In both species, many of the most abundant sperm proteins were paralogs of the courtship pheromones Plethodontid Receptivity Factor (PRF), Plethodontid Modulating Factor (PMF), and Sodefrin Precursor-like Factor (SPF). Sperm-specific paralogs of PMF and SPF are likely the most abundant secreted proteins in &lt;italic&gt;P. shermani&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;D. ocoee&lt;/italic&gt;, respectively. In contrast, sperm PRF lacks a signal peptide and may be expressed in cytoplasm. PRF pheromone genes evolved independently multiple times through repeated gene duplication of sperm PRF genes and signal peptides recovered by recombination with PMF genes. Phylogenetic analysis of courtship pheromones and their sperm paralogs support that each protein family evolved for these two reproductive contexts at distinct evolutionary time points between 17 and 360 million years ago. As the first molecular characterization of salamander gametes, this study expands our knowledge of amphibian fertilization beyond frogs and provides novel insight into the evolutionary processes by which new, rapidly evolving reproductive proteins may evolve.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.475003" rel="alternate" title="Recurrent co-option and recombination of cytokine and three finger proteins in multiple reproductive tissues throughout salamander evolution (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475123</id><title>Effects of recombination on the evolvability, genetic diversity and mutational robustness of neutrally evolving populations (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.023252+00:00</updated><author><name>Joachim Krug</name></author><author><name>Alexander Klug</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many effects attributed to recombination have been invoked to explain the advantage of sex. The most prominent arguments focus on either evolvability, genetic diversity, or mutational robustness to justify why the benefit of recombination overcomes its costs, with partially contradicting results. As a consequence, understanding which aspects of recombination are most important in a given situation remains an open problem for theoretical and experimental research. In this study, we focus on finite populations evolving on neutral networks, which already display remarkably complex behavior. We aim to provide a comprehensive overview of the effects of recombination by jointly considering different measures of evolvability, genetic diversity, and mutational robustness over a broad parameter range, such that many evolutionary regimes are covered. We find that several of these measures vary non-monotonically with the rates of mutation and recombination. Moreover, the presence of lethal genotypes that introduce inhomogeneities in the network of viable states qualitatively alters the effects of recombination. We conclude that conflicting trends induced by recombination can be explained by an emerging trade-off between evolvability and genetic diversity on the one hand, and mutational robustness and fitness on the other. Finally, we discuss how different implementations of the recombination scheme in theoretical models can affect the observed dependence on recombination rate through a coupling between recombination and genetic drift.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475123" rel="alternate" title="Effects of recombination on the evolvability, genetic diversity and mutational robustness of neutrally evolving populations (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474931</id><title>The Metaxin Mitochondrial Import Proteins: Multiple Metaxin-like Proteins in Fungi (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.023413+00:00</updated><author><name>Kenneth W. Adolph</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Multiple metaxin-like proteins are shown to exist in fungi, as also found for the metaxin proteins of vertebrates and invertebrates. In vertebrates, metaxins 1 and 2 are mitochondrial membrane proteins that function in the import of proteins into mitochondria. Fungal metaxin-like proteins were identified by criteria including their homology with human metaxins and the presence of characteristic GST_N_Metaxin, GST_C_Metaxin, and Tom37 protein domains. Fungi in different taxonomic divisions (phyla) were found to possess multiple metaxin-like proteins. These include the Ascomycota, Basidiomycota, Blastocladiomycota, Chytridiomycota, Mucoromycota, Neocallimastigomycota, and Zoopagomycota divisions. Most fungi with multiple metaxin-like proteins contain two proteins, designated MTXa and MTXb. Amino acid sequence alignments show a high degree of homology among MTXa proteins, with over 60% amino acid identities, and also among MTXb proteins of fungi in the same division. But very little homology is observed in aligning MTXa with MTXb proteins of the same or different fungi. Both the MTXa proteins and MTXb proteins have the protein domains that characterize the metaxins and metaxin-like proteins: GST_N_Metaxin, GST_C_Metaxin, and Tom37. The metaxins and metaxin-like proteins of vertebrates, invertebrates, plants, protists, and bacteria all possess these domains. The secondary structures of MTXa and MTXb proteins are both dominated by similar patterns of α-helical segments, but extensive β-strand segments are absent. Nine highly conserved α-helical segments are present, the same as other metaxins and metaxin-like proteins. Phylogenetic analysis reveals that MTXa and MTXb proteins of fungi form two separate and distinct groups. These groups are also separate from the groups of vertebrate metaxins, metaxin-related Sam37 proteins of yeasts, and metaxin-like FAXC proteins.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474931" rel="alternate" title="The Metaxin Mitochondrial Import Proteins: Multiple Metaxin-like Proteins in Fungi (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>