<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.144443+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.459833</id><title>Population differentiation of polygenic score predictions under stabilizing selection (49 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.144688+00:00</updated><author><name>Sivan Yair</name></author><author><name>Graham Coop</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Given the many loci uncovered by genome-wide association studies (GWAS), polygenic scores have become central to the drive for genomic medicine and have spread into various areas including evolutionary studies of adaptation. While promising, these scores are fraught with issues of portability across populations, due to the misestimation of effect sizes and missing causal loci across populations not represented in large-scale GWAS. The poor portability of polygenic scores at first seems at odds with the view that much of common genetic variation is shared among populations (Lewontin 1972). Here we investigate one potential cause of this discrepancy: phenotypic stabilizing selection drives the turnover of genetic variation shared between populations at causal loci. Somewhat counter-intuitively, while stabilizing selection to the same optimum phenotype leads to lower phenotypic differentiation among populations, it increases genetic differentiation at GWAS loci and reduces the portability of polygenic scores constructed for unrepresented populations. We also find that stabilizing selection can lead to potentially misleading signals of the differentiation of average polygenic scores among populations. We extend our baseline model to investigate the impact of pleiotropy, gene-by-environment interactions, and directional selection on polygenic score predictions. Our work emphasizes stabilizing selection as a null evolutionary model to understand patterns of allele frequency differentiation and its impact on polygenic score portability and differentiation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.459833" rel="alternate" title="Population differentiation of polygenic score predictions under stabilizing selection (49 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459309</id><title>Mutation, selection, and quantitative genetic architecture of susceptibility to bacterial pathogens in C. elegans (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.144898+00:00</updated><author><name>Lindsay M. Johnson</name></author><author><name>Sayran Saber</name></author><author><name>Md. Monjurul Islam Rifat</name></author><author><name>Sydney Rouse</name></author><author><name>Charles F. Baer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the evolutionary and genetic underpinnings of susceptibility to pathogens is of fundamental importance across a wide swathe of biology. Much theoretical and empirical effort has focused on genetic variants of large effect, but pathogen susceptibility often appears to be a polygenic complex trait. Here we investigate the quantitative genetics of survival over 120 hours of exposure (“susceptibility”) of &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; to three bacterial pathogens of varying virulence, along with the non-pathogenic OP50 strain of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;. We compare the genetic (co)variance input by spontaneous mutations accumulated under minimal selection to the standing genetic (co)variance in a set of ∼50 wild isolates. Three conclusions emerge. First, with one exception, mutations increase susceptibility to pathogens, and susceptibility is uncorrelated with fitness in the absence of pathogens. Second, the orientation in trait space of the heritable (co)variance of wild isolates is sufficiently explained by mutation. However, pathogen susceptibility is clearly under purifying, apparently directional, selection of magnitude similar to that of competitive fitness in the MA conditions. The results provide no evidence for fitness tradeoffs between pathogen susceptibility and fitness in the absence of pathogens, nor that balancing selection is important in maintaining genetic variation for susceptibility to these bacterial pathogens.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459309" rel="alternate" title="Mutation, selection, and quantitative genetic architecture of susceptibility to bacterial pathogens in C. elegans (9 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.459621</id><title>Reassortment Network of Influenza A Virus (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.145107+00:00</updated><author><name>Xingfei Gong</name></author><author><name>Mingda Hu</name></author><author><name>Wei Chen</name></author><author><name>Haoyi Yang</name></author><author><name>Boqian Wang</name></author><author><name>Junjie Yue</name></author><author><name>Yuan Jin</name></author><author><name>Long Liang</name></author><author><name>Hongguang Ren</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Influenza A virus (IAV) genomes are composed of eight single-stranded RNA segments. Genetic exchange through reassortment of the segmented genomes often endows IAVs with new genetic characteristics, which may affect transmissibility and pathogenicity. However, a comprehensive understood of the reassortment history of IAVs remains poorly studied. To this end, we assembled 40296 whole-genome sequences of IAVs for analysis. Using a new clustering method based on Mean Pairwise Distances in the phylogenetic trees, we classified each segment of IAVs into clades. Correspondingly, reassortment events among IAVs were detected by checking the segment clade compositions of related genomes under specific environment factors and time period. We systematically identified 1927 possible reassortment events of IAVs and constructed their reassortment network. Interestingly, minimum spanning tree of the reassortment network reproved that swine act as an intermediate host in the reassortment history of IAVs between avian and human. Moreover, reassortment patterns among related subtypes constructed in this study are consistent with previous studies. Taken together, our genome-wide reassorment analysis of all the IAVs offers an overview of the leaping evolution of the virus and a comprehensive network representing the relationships of IAVs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.459621" rel="alternate" title="Reassortment Network of Influenza A Virus (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>