<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.007996+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469161</id><title>Indirect effects of parental conflict on conspecific offspring development (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.008369+00:00</updated><author><name>Jenn M Coughlan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hybrid Seed Inviability (HSI) is a common barrier in angiosperms. Recent work suggests that the rapid evolution of HSI may, in part, be due to conflict between maternal and paternal optima for resource allocation to developing offspring (i.e. parental conflict). However, parental conflict requires that paternally-derived resource acquiring alleles impose a maternal cost. I test this requirement using three closely related species in the Mimulus guttatus species complex that exhibit significant HSI and differ in their inferred histories of parental conflict. I show that the presence of hybrid seeds significantly affects conspecific seed size for almost all crosses, such that conspecific seeds are smaller after developing with hybrids from fathers with a stronger history of conflict, and larger after developing with hybrids from fathers with a weaker history of conflict. This work demonstrates a cost of paternally-derived alleles, and also has implications for species fitness in secondary contact.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469161" rel="alternate" title="Indirect effects of parental conflict on conspecific offspring development (22 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468709</id><title>Recent zoonotic spillover and tropism shift of a Canine Coronavirus is associated with relaxed selection and putative loss of function in NTD subdomain of spike protein (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.008691+00:00</updated><author><name>Jordan D. Zehr</name></author><author><name>Sergei L. Kosakovsky Pond</name></author><author><name>Darren P. Martin</name></author><author><name>Kristina Ceres</name></author><author><name>Gary R. Whittaker</name></author><author><name>Laura B. Goodman</name></author><author><name>Michael J. Stanhope</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A recent study reported the occurrence of Canine Coronavirus (CCoV) in nasopharyngeal swabs from a small number of patients hospitalized with pneumonia during a 2017-18 period in Sarawak, Malaysia. Because the genome sequence for one of these isolates is available, we conducted comparative evolutionary analyses of the spike gene of this strain (CCoV-HuPn-2018), with other available &lt;italic&gt;Alphacoronavirus&lt;/italic&gt; 1 spike sequences. The most N-terminus subdomain (0-domain) of the CCoV-HuPn-2018 spike protein has sequence similarity to Transmissible Gastroenteritis Virus (TGEV) and CCoV2b strains, but not to other members of the type II Alphacoronaviruses (i.e., CCoV2a and Feline CoV2-FCoV2). This 0-domain in CCoV-HuPn-2018 has evidence for relaxed selection pressure, an increased rate of molecular evolution, and a number of unique amino acid substitutions relative to CCoV2b and TGEV sequences. A region of the 0-domain determined to be key to sialic acid binding and pathogenesis in TGEV had clear differences in amino acid sequences in CCoV-HuPn-2018 relative to both CCoV2b (enteric) and TGEV (enteric and respiratory). The 0-domain of CCoV-HuPn-2018 also had several sites inferred to be under positive diversifying selection, including sites within the signal peptide. Downstream of the 0-domain, FCoV2 shared sequence similarity to the CCoV2b and TGEV sequences, with analyses of this larger alignment identifying positively selected sites in the putative Receptor Binding Domain (RBD) and Connector Domain (CD). Recombination analyses strongly implicated a particular FCoV2 strain in the recombinant history of CCoV-HuPn-2018 with molecular divergence times estimated at around 60 years ago. We hypothesize that CCoV-HuPn-2018 had an enteric origin, but that it has lost that particular tropism, because of mutations in the sialic acid binding region of the spike 0-domain. As selection pressure on this region was reduced, the virus evolved a respiratory tropism, analogous to other &lt;italic&gt;Alphacoronavirus&lt;/italic&gt; 1, such as Porcine Respiratory Coronavirus (PRCV), that have lost this region entirely. We also suggest that signals of positive selection in the signal peptide as well as other changes in the 0-domain of CCoV-HuPn-2018 could represent an adaptive role in this new host and that this could be in part due to the different spatial distribution of the N-linked glycan repertoire for this strain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468709" rel="alternate" title="Recent zoonotic spillover and tropism shift of a Canine Coronavirus is associated with relaxed selection and putative loss of function in NTD subdomain of spike protein (16 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468996</id><title>Phylogenomic analyses using genomes and transcriptomes do not resolve relationships among major clades in Phrymaceae (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.008858+00:00</updated><author><name>Diego F. Morales-Briones</name></author><author><name>Nan Lin</name></author><author><name>Eileen Y. Huang</name></author><author><name>Dena L. Grossenbacher</name></author><author><name>James M. Sobel</name></author><author><name>Caroline D. Gilmore</name></author><author><name>David C. Tank</name></author><author><name>Ya Yang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Premise of the study: Phylogenomic datasets using genomes and transcriptomes provide rich opportunities beyond resolving bifurcating phylogenetic relationships. Monkeyflower (Phrymaceae) is a model system for evolutionary ecology. However, it lacks a well-supported phylogeny for a stable taxonomy and for macroevolutionary comparisons.
Methods: We sampled 24 genomes and transcriptomes in Phrymaceae and closely related families, including eight newly sequenced transcriptomes. We reconstructed the phylogeny using IQ-TREE and ASTRAL, evaluated gene tree discordance using PhyParts, Quartet Sampling, and cloudogram, and carried out phylogenetic network analyses using PhyloNet and HyDe. We searched for whole genome duplication (WGD) events using chromosome numbers, synonymous distance, and gene duplication events. 
Key results: Most gene trees support the monophyly of Phrymaceae and each of its tribes. Most gene trees also support the tribe Mimuleae being sister to Phrymeae + Diplaceae + Leucocarpeae, with extensive gene tree discordance among the latter three. Despite the discordance, polyphyly of Mimulus s.l. is strongly supported, and no particular reticulation event among the Phrymaceae tribes is well supported. Reticulation likely occurred among Erythranthe bicolor and close relatives. No ancient WGD event was detected in Phrymaceae. Instead, small-scale duplications are among potential drivers of macroevolutionary diversification of Phrymaceae.
Conclusions: We show that analysis of reticulate evolution is sensitive to taxon sampling and methods used. We also demonstrate that genome-scale data do not always fully "resolve" phylogenetic relationships. They present rich opportunities to investigate reticulate evolution, and gene and genome evolution involved in lineage diversification and adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468996" rel="alternate" title="Phylogenomic analyses using genomes and transcriptomes do not resolve relationships among major clades in Phrymaceae (16 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469253</id><title>Improved resolution of recalcitrant nodes in the animal phylogeny through the analysis of genome gene content and morphology (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.009116+00:00</updated><author><name>Ksenia Juravel</name></author><author><name>Luis Porras</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Hoehna</name></author><author><name>Davide Pisani</name></author><author><name>Gert Wörheide</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;An accurate phylogeny of animals is needed to clarify their evolution, ecology, and impact on shaping the biosphere. Although multi-gene alignments of up to several hundred thousand amino acids are nowadays routinely used to test hypotheses of animal relationships, some nodes towards the root of the animal phylogeny are proving hard to resolve. While the relationships of the non-bilaterian lineages, primarily sponges (Porifera) and comb jellies (Ctenophora), have received much attention since more than a decade, controversies about the phylogenetic position of the worm-like bilaterian lineage Xenacoelomorpha and the monophyly of the "Superphylum" Deuterostomia have more recently emerged. Here we independently analyse novel genome gene content and morphological datasets to assess patterns of phylogenetic congruence with previous amino-acid derived phylogenetic hypotheses. Using statistical hypothesis testing, we show that both our datasets very strongly support sponges as the sister group of all the other animals, Xenoacoelomorpha as the sister group of the other Bilateria, and largely support monophyletic Deuterostomia. Based on these results, we conclude that the last common animal ancestor may have been a simple, filter-feeding organism without a nervous system and muscles, while the last common ancestor of Bilateria might have been a small, acoelomate-like worm without a through gut.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469253" rel="alternate" title="Improved resolution of recalcitrant nodes in the animal phylogeny through the analysis of genome gene content and morphology (15 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468757</id><title>Impacts of Taxon-Sampling Schemes on Bayesian Molecular Dating under the Unresolved Fossilized Birth-Death Process (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.009394+00:00</updated><author><name>Arong Luo</name></author><author><name>Chi Zhang</name></author><author><name>Qing-Song Zhou</name></author><author><name>Simon Y.W. Ho</name></author><author><name>Chao-Dong Zhu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Evolutionary timescales can be estimated using a combination of genetic data and fossil evidence based on the molecular clock. Bayesian phylogenetic methods such as tip dating and total-evidence dating provide a powerful framework for inferring evolutionary timescales, but the most widely used priors for tree topologies and node times often assume that present-day taxa have been sampled randomly or exhaustively. In practice, taxon sampling is often carried out so as to include representatives of major lineages, such as orders or families. We examined the impacts of these diversified sampling schemes on Bayesian molecular dating under the unresolved fossilized birth-death (FBD) process, in which fossil taxa are topologically constrained but their exact placements are not inferred. We used synthetic data generated by simulation of nucleotide sequence evolution, fossil occurrences, and diversified taxon sampling. Our analyses show that increasing sampling density does not substantially improve divergence-time estimates under benign conditions. However, when the tree topologies were fixed to those used for simulation or when evolutionary rates varied among lineages, the performance of Bayesian tip dating improves with sampling density. By exploring three situations of model mismatches, we find that including all relevant fossils without pruning off those inappropriate for the FBD process can lead to underestimation of divergence times. Our reanalysis of a eutherian mammal data set confirms some of the findings from our simulation study, and reveals the complexity of diversified taxon sampling in phylogenomic data sets. In highlighting the interplay of taxon-sampling density and other factors, the results of our study have useful implications for Bayesian molecular dating in the era of phylogenomics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468757" rel="alternate" title="Impacts of Taxon-Sampling Schemes on Bayesian Molecular Dating under the Unresolved Fossilized Birth-Death Process (13 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469027</id><title>Monophyly of Diverse Bigyromonadea and their Impact on Phylogenomic Relationships Within Stramenopiles (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.009664+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna Cho</name></author><author><name>Denis V. Tikhonenkov</name></author><author><name>Elisabeth Hehenberger</name></author><author><name>Anna Karnkowska</name></author><author><name>Patrick J. Keeling</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Stramenopiles are a diverse but relatively well-studied eukaryotic supergroup with considerable genomic information available (Sibbald and Archibald, 2017). Nevertheless, the relationships between major stramenopile subgroups remain unresolved, in part due to a lack of data from small nanoflagellates that make up a lot of the genetic diversity of the group. This is most obvious in Bigyromonadea, which is one of four major stramenopile subgroups but represented by a single transcriptome. To examine the diversity of Bigyromonadea and how the lack of data affects the tree, we generated transcriptomes from seven novel bigyromonada species described in this study: Develocauda condao, Develocanicus komovi, Develocanicus vyazemskyi, Cubaremonas variflagellatum, Pirsonia chemainus, Feodosia pseudopoda, and Koktebelia satura. Both maximum likelihood and Bayesian phylogenomic trees based on a 247 gene-matrix recovered a monophyletic Bigyromonadea that includes two diverse subgroups, Developea and Pirsoniales, that were not previously related based on single gene trees. Maximum likelihood analyses show Bigyromonadea related to oomycetes, whereas Bayesian analyses and topology testing were inconclusive. We observed similarities between the novel bigyromonad species and motile zoospores of oomycetes in morphology and the ability to self-aggregate. Rare formation of pseudopods and fused cells were also observed, traits that are also found in members of labyrinthulomycetes, another osmotrophic stramenopiles. Furthermore, we report the first case of eukaryovory in the flagellated stages of Pirsoniales. These analyses reveal new diversity of Bigyromonadea, and altogether suggest their monophyly with oomycetes, collectively known as Pseudofungi, is the most likely topology of the stramenopile tree.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469027" rel="alternate" title="Monophyly of Diverse Bigyromonadea and their Impact on Phylogenomic Relationships Within Stramenopiles (12 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468838</id><title>A genome in flux: homoeologous exchanges, subgenome dominance, and gene dosage balance constraints in resynthesized allopolyploid Brassica napus (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.009867+00:00</updated><author><name>Kevin A. Bird</name></author><author><name>J. Chris Pires</name></author><author><name>Robert VanBuren</name></author><author><name>Zhiyong Xiong</name></author><author><name>Patrick P. Edger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Allopolyploidy involves the hybridization of two evolutionary diverged species and the doubling of genomic material. Frequently, allopolyploids exhibit genomic rearrangements that recombine, duplicate, or delete homoeologous regions of the newly formed genome. While decades of investigation have focused on how genome duplication leads to systematic differences in the retention and expression of duplicate genes, the impact of genomic rearrangements on genome evolution has received less attention. We used genomic and transcriptomic data for six independently resynthesized, isogenic &lt;italic&gt;Brassica napus&lt;/italic&gt; lines in the first, fifth, and tenth generation to identify genomic rearrangements and assess their impact on gene expression dynamics related to subgenome dominance and gene dosage constraint. We find that dosage constraints on the gene expression response to polyploidy begin to loosen within the first ten generations of evolution and systematically differ between dominant and non-dominant subgenomes. We also show that genomic rearrangements can bias estimation of homoeolog expression bias, but fail to fully obscure which subgenome is dominantly expressed. Finally, we demonstrate that dosage-sensitive genes exhibit the same kind of coordinated response to homoeologous exchange as they do for genome duplication, suggesting constraint on dosage balance also acts on these changes to gene dosage.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468838" rel="alternate" title="A genome in flux: homoeologous exchanges, subgenome dominance, and gene dosage balance constraints in resynthesized allopolyploid Brassica napus (12 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469195</id><title>A Time-calibrated Firefly (Coleoptera: Lampyridae) Phylogeny: Using Genomic Data for Divergence Time Estimation (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.010092+00:00</updated><author><name>Sebastian Hoehna</name></author><author><name>Sarah E Lower</name></author><author><name>Pablo Duchen</name></author><author><name>Ana Catalan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fireflies (Coleoptera: Lampyridae) consist of over 2,000 described extant species. A well-resolved phylogeny of fireflies is important for the study of their bioluminescence, evolution, and conservation. We used a recently published anchored hybrid enrichment dataset (AHE; 436 loci for 88 Lampyridae species and 10 outgroup species) and state-of-the-art statistical methods (the fossilized birth-death-range process implemented in a Bayesian framework) to estimate a time-calibrated phylogeny of Lampyridae. Unfortunately, estimating calibrated phylogenies using AHE and the latest and most robust time-calibration strategies is not possible because of computational constraints. As a solution, we subset the full dataset and applied three different strategies: using the most complete loci, the most homogeneous loci, and the loci with the highest accuracy to infer the well established Photinus clade. The estimated topology using the three data subsets agreed on almost all major clades and only showed minor discordance with less supported nodes. The estimated divergence times overlapped for all nodes that are shared between the topologies. Thus, divergence time estimation is robust as long as the topology inference is robust and any well selected data subset suffices. Additionally, we observed an unexpected amount of gene tree discordance between the 436 AHE loci. Our assessment of model adequacy showed that standard phylogenetic substitution models are not adequate for any of the 436 AHE loci which is likely to bias phylogenetic inferences. We performed a simulation study to explore the impact of (a) incomplete lineage sorting, (b) uniformly distributed and systematic missing data, and (c) systematic bias in the position of highly variable and conserved sites. For our simulated data, we observed less gene tree variation and hence the empirically observed amount of gene tree discordance for the AHE dataset is unexpected.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469195" rel="alternate" title="A Time-calibrated Firefly (Coleoptera: Lampyridae) Phylogeny: Using Genomic Data for Divergence Time Estimation (11 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.469375</id><title>Balancing selection and the crossing of fitness valleys in structured populations: diversification in the gametophytic self-incompatibility system (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.011027+00:00</updated><author><name>Roman Stetsenko</name></author><author><name>Thomas Brom</name></author><author><name>Vincent Castric</name></author><author><name>Sylvain Billiard</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The self-incompatibility locus (S-locus) of flowering plants displays a striking allelic diversity. How such a diversity has emerged remains unclear. In this paper, we performed numerical simulations in a finite island population genetics model to investigate how population subdivision affects the diversification process at a S-locus, given that the two-genes architecture typical of S-loci involves the crossing of a fitness valley. We show that population structure increases the number of self-incompatibility haplotypes (S-haplotypes) maintained in the whole metapopulation, but at the same time also slightly reduces the parameter range allowing for their diversification. This increase is partly due to a reinforcement of the diversification and replacement dynamics of S-haplotypes within and among demes. We also show that the two-genes architecture leads to a higher diversity compared with a simpler genetic architecture where new S-haplotypes appear in a single mutation step. We conclude that population structure helps explain the large allelic diversity at the self-incompatibility locus. Overall, our results suggest that population subdivision can act in two opposite directions: it makes easier S-haplotypes diversification but increases the risk that the SI system is lost.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.469375" rel="alternate" title="Balancing selection and the crossing of fitness valleys in structured populations: diversification in the gametophytic self-incompatibility system (10 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469099</id><title>Multiple adaptive solutions to face climatic constraints: novel insights in the debate over the role of convergence in local adaptation (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.011474+00:00</updated><author><name>Badr Benjelloun</name></author><author><name>Kevin Leempoel</name></author><author><name>Frédéric Boyer</name></author><author><name>Sylvie Stucki</name></author><author><name>Ian Streeter</name></author><author><name>Pablo Orozco-terWengel</name></author><author><name>Florian J. Alberto</name></author><author><name>Bertrand Servin</name></author><author><name>Filippo Biscarini</name></author><author><name>Adriana Alberti</name></author><author><name>Stefan Engelen</name></author><author><name>Alessandra Stella</name></author><author><name>Licia Colli</name></author><author><name>Eric Coissac</name></author><author><name>Michael W. Bruford</name></author><author><name>Paolo Ajmone-Marsan</name></author><author><name>Riccardo Negrini</name></author><author><name>Laura Clarke</name></author><author><name>Paul Flicek</name></author><author><name>Abdelkader Chikhi</name></author><author><name>Stéphane Joost</name></author><author><name>Pierre Taberlet</name></author><author><name>François Pompanon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The extent to which genomic convergence shapes locally adapted phenotypes in different species remains a fundamental question in evolutionary biology. To bring new insights to this debate we set up a framework which aimed to compare the adaptive trajectories of two domesticated mammal species co-distributed in diversified landscapes. We sequenced the genomes of 160 sheep and 161 goats extensively managed along environmental gradients, including temperature, rainfall, seasonality and altitude, to identify genes and biological processes shaping local adaptation. Allele frequencies at adaptive loci were rarely found to vary gradually along environmental gradients, but rather displayed a discontinuous shift at the extremities of environmental clines. Of the more than 430 adaptive genes identified, only 6 were orthologous between sheep and goats and those responded differently to environmental pressures, suggesting different adaptive mechanisms in these two closely related species. Such diversity of adaptive pathways may result from a high number of biological functions involved in adaptation to multiple eco-climatic gradients, and provides more arguments for the role of contingency and stochasticity in adaptation rather than repeatability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469099" rel="alternate" title="Multiple adaptive solutions to face climatic constraints: novel insights in the debate over the role of convergence in local adaptation (6 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.467373</id><title>Integrating transcriptomes to investigate genes associated with adaptation to aquatic environments, and assess phylogenetic conflict and whole-genome duplications in Alismatales (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.012396+00:00</updated><author><name>Ling-Yun Chen</name></author><author><name>Bei Lu</name></author><author><name>Diego F. Morales-Briones</name></author><author><name>Michael L. Moody</name></author><author><name>Fan Liu</name></author><author><name>Guang-Wan Hu</name></author><author><name>Chien-Hsun Huang</name></author><author><name>Jin-Ming Chen</name></author><author><name>Qing-Feng Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Land plants first evolved from freshwater algae, and flowering plants returned to water as early as the Cretaceous and multiple times beyond. Alismatales is the largest clade of aquatic angiosperms including all marine angiosperms, as well as terrestrial plants. We used Alismatales to explore plant adaptation to aquatic environments by including 95 samples (89 Alismatales species) covering four genomes and 91 transcriptomes (59 generated in this study). To provide a basis for investigating adaptation, we assessed phylogenetic conflict and whole-genome duplication (WGD) events in Alismatales. We recovered a relationship for the three main clades in Alismatales as ((Tofieldiaceae, Araceae), core Alismatids). There is phylogenetic conflict among the backbone of the three main clades that could be due to incomplete lineage sorting and introgression. We identified 18 putative WGD events. One of them had occurred at the most recent common ancestor of core Alismatids, and four occurred at seagrass lineages. Other events are distributed in terrestrial, emergent, and submersed life-forms and seagrasses across Alismatales. We also found that lineage and life-form were each important for different evolutionary patterns for the genes related to freshwater/marine adaptation. For example, some light or ethylene-related genes were lost in the seagrass Zosteraceae, but present in other seagrasses and freshwater species. Stomata-related genes were lost in both submersed freshwater species and seagrasses. Nicotianamine synthase genes, which are important in iron intake, expanded in both submersed freshwater species and seagrasses. Our results advance the understanding of the adaptation to aquatic environments, phylogeny, and whole-genome duplication of Alismatales.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.467373" rel="alternate" title="Integrating transcriptomes to investigate genes associated with adaptation to aquatic environments, and assess phylogenetic conflict and whole-genome duplications in Alismatales (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468966</id><title>A new lineage of non-photosynthetic green algae with extreme organellar genomes (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.013013+00:00</updated><author><name>Tomáš Pánek</name></author><author><name>Dovilė Barcytė</name></author><author><name>Sebastian C. Treitli</name></author><author><name>Kristína Záhonová</name></author><author><name>Martin Sokol</name></author><author><name>Tereza Ševčíková</name></author><author><name>Eliška Zadrobílková</name></author><author><name>Karin Jaške</name></author><author><name>Naoji Yubuki</name></author><author><name>Ivan Čepička</name></author><author><name>Marek Eliáš</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: The plastid genomes of the green algal order Chlamydomonadales tend to expand their non-coding regions, but this phenomenon is poorly understood. Here we shed new light on organellar genome evolution in Chlamydomonadales by studying a previously unknown non-photosynthetic lineage. We established cultures of two new Polytoma-like flagellates, defined their basic characteristics and phylogenetic position, and obtained complete organellar genome sequences and a transcriptome assembly for one of them.
Results: We discovered a novel deeply diverged chlamydomonadalean lineage that has no close photosynthetic relatives and represents an independent case of photosynthesis loss. To accommodate these organisms, we establish a new genus, Leontynka, with two species L. pallida and L. elongata distinguished by both morphological and molecular characteristics. Notable features of the colourless plastid of L. pallida deduced from the plastid genome (plastome) sequence and transcriptome assembly include the retention of ATP synthase, thylakoid-associated proteins, carotenoid biosynthesis pathway, and plastoquinone-based electron transport chain, the latter two modules having an obvious functional link to the eyespot present in Leontynka. Most strikingly, the L. pallida plastome with its ~362 kbp is by far the largest among non-photosynthetic eukaryotes investigated to date. Instead of a high gene content, its size reflects extreme proliferation of sequence repeats. These are present also in coding sequences, with one repeat type found in exons of 11 out of 34 protein-coding genes and up to 36 copies per gene, affecting thus the encoded proteins. The mitochondrial genome of L. pallida is likewise exceptionally large, with its &amp;gt;104 kbp surpassed only by the mitogenome of Haematococcus lacustris among all members of Chlamydomonadales studied so far. It is also bloated with repeats, yet completely different from those in the L. pallida plastome, which contrasts with the situation in H. lacustris where both organellar genomes have accumulated related repeats. Furthermore, the L. pallida mitogenome exhibits an extremely high GC content in both coding and non-coding regions and, strikingly, a high number of predicted G-quadruplexes.
Conclusions: With the unprecedented combination of plastid and mitochondrial genome characteristics, Leontynka pushes the frontiers of organellar genome diversity and becomes an interesting model for studying organellar genome evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468966" rel="alternate" title="A new lineage of non-photosynthetic green algae with extreme organellar genomes (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468897</id><title>Effect of RNA preservation methods on RNA quantity and quality of field collected avian whole blood (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.013387+00:00</updated><author><name>Johanna A Harvey</name></author><author><name>Sarah A Knutie</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A limitation of comparative transcriptomic studies of wild avian populations continues to be sample acquisition and preservation to achieve resulting high-quality RNA (i.e., ribonucleic acids that transfers, translates, and regulates the genetic code from DNA into proteins). Field sampling of wild bird samples provides challenges as RNA degradation progresses quickly and because cryopreservation is often not feasible at remote locations. We collected blood samples from songbirds, as avian blood is nucleated and provides sufficient transcriptionally active material in a small and non-lethal sample, to compare the efficacy of widely available RNA stabilizing buffers, RNAlater (Ambion) and DNA/RNA Shield (Zymo) at differing concentrations along with a dry ice-based flash freezing method (Isopropanol 99% and dry ice mixture, -109°C). Each blood sample was divided among five different preservation treatments (dry ice-based flash freezing, RNAlater with 1:5 or 1:10 dilution, or DNA/RNA Shield with 1:2 or 1:3 dilution). A new protocol was optimized for total RNA extraction from avian blood samples with small starting volumes enabling sampling of small passerines. We quantified quality measures, RNA integrity numbers (RINe), rRNA ratios, and total RNA concentrations. We found that RNA preservation buffers, RNAlater and DNA/RNA Shield at all concentrations, provide sample protection from RNA degradation. We suggest caution against using dry ice-based flash-freezing alone for samples preservation as these samples resulted in lower quality measures then samples in preservation buffer. Total RNA concentration was generally not affected by preservation treatment and may vary due to differences in initial samples volumes and carryover across processing steps.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468897" rel="alternate" title="Effect of RNA preservation methods on RNA quantity and quality of field collected avian whole blood (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468889</id><title>MAPR origins reveal a new class of prokaryotic cytochrome b5 proteins and possible role in eukaryogenesis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.013611+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Tamarit</name></author><author><name>Sarah Teakel</name></author><author><name>Michealla Marama</name></author><author><name>David Aragão</name></author><author><name>Svetlana Y. Gerdes</name></author><author><name>Jade K. Forwood</name></author><author><name>Thijs J. G. Ettema</name></author><author><name>Michael A. Cahill</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The multiple functions of PGRMC1, the archetypal heme-binding eukaryotic MAPR family member, include steroidogenic regulation, membrane trafficking, and steroid responsiveness. The interrelationships between these functions are currently poorly understood. Previous work has shown that different MAPR subclasses were present early in eukaryotic evolution, and that tyrosine phosphorylated residues appeared in the eumetazoan ancestor, coincident with a gastrulation organizer. Here we show that MAPR proteins are related to a newly recognized class of prokaryotic cytochrome-b&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt; domain proteins. Our first solved structure of this new class exhibits shared MAPR-like folded architecture and heme-binding orientation. We also report that a protein subgroup from Candidate Phyla Radiation bacteria shares MAPR-like heme-interacting tyrosines. Our results support bacterial origins for both PGRMC1 and CYP51A, that catalyze the meiosis-associated 14-demethylation of the first sterol lanosterol from yeast to humans. We propose that eukaryotic acquisition of a membrane-trafficking function related to sterol metabolism was associated with the appearance of MAPR genes early in eukaryotic evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468889" rel="alternate" title="MAPR origins reveal a new class of prokaryotic cytochrome b5 proteins and possible role in eukaryogenesis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>