<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.137074+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470311</id><title>Comparative proteogenomics deciphers the origin and evolution of eukaryotic chromatin (112 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.138091+00:00</updated><author><name>Xavier Grau-Bové</name></author><author><name>Cristina Navarrete</name></author><author><name>Cristina Chiva</name></author><author><name>Thomas Pribasnig</name></author><author><name>Meritxell Antó</name></author><author><name>Guifré Torruella</name></author><author><name>Luis Javier Galindo</name></author><author><name>Bernd Franz Lang</name></author><author><name>David Moreira</name></author><author><name>Purificación López-Garcia</name></author><author><name>Iñaki Ruiz-Trillo</name></author><author><name>Christa Schleper</name></author><author><name>Eduard Sabidó</name></author><author><name>Arnau Sebé-Pedrós</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Histones and associated chromatin proteins have essential functions in eukaryotic genome organization and regulation. Despite this fundamental role in eukaryotic cell biology, we lack a phylogenetically-comprehensive understanding of chromatin evolution. Here, we combine comparative proteomics and genomics analysis of chromatin in eukaryotes and archaea. Proteomics uncovers the existence of histone post-translational modifications in Archaea. However, archaeal histone modifications are scarce, in contrast with the highly conserved and abundant marks we identify across eukaryotes. Phylogenetic analysis reveals that chromatin-associated catalytic functions (e.g., methyltransferases) have pre-eukaryotic origins, whereas histone mark readers and chaperones are eukaryotic innovations. We show that further chromatin evolution is characterized by expansion of readers, including capture by transposable elements and viruses. Overall, our study infers detailed evolutionary history of eukaryotic chromatin: from its archaeal roots, through the emergence of nucleosome-based regulation in the eukaryotic ancestor, to the diversification of chromatin regulators and their hijacking by genomic parasites.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470311" rel="alternate" title="Comparative proteogenomics deciphers the origin and evolution of eukaryotic chromatin (112 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470630</id><title>Repeated genetic adaptation to high altitude in two tropical butterflies (47 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.138886+00:00</updated><author><name>Gabriela Montejo-Kovacevich</name></author><author><name>Joana I. Meier</name></author><author><name>Caroline N. Bacquet</name></author><author><name>Ian A. Warren</name></author><author><name>Yingguang Frank Chan</name></author><author><name>Marek Kucka</name></author><author><name>Camilo Salazar</name></author><author><name>Nicol Rueda</name></author><author><name>Stephen H. Montgomery</name></author><author><name>W. Owen McMillan</name></author><author><name>Krzysztof M. Kozak</name></author><author><name>Nicola J. Nadeau</name></author><author><name>Simon Martin</name></author><author><name>Chris D. Jiggins</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Repeated evolution can provide insight into the mechanisms that facilitate adaptation to novel or changing environments. Here we study adaptation to high altitude in two divergent tropical butterflies, &lt;italic&gt;H. erato&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;H. melpomene&lt;/italic&gt;, which have repeatedly and independently adapted to high elevations on either side of the Andean mountains. We sequenced 518 whole genomes from elevational transects and found many regions under selection at high altitude, with repeated genetic differentiation across multiple replicates, including allopatric comparisons. In contrast, there is little ‘molecular parallelism’ between &lt;italic&gt;H. erato&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;H. melpomene&lt;/italic&gt;. With a further 85 whole genomes of five close relatives, we find that a large proportion divergent regions have arisen from standing variation and putative adaptive introgression from high-altitude specialist species. Taken together our study supports a key role of standing genetic variation and gene flow from pre-adapted species in promoting parallel genetic local adaptation to the environment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470630" rel="alternate" title="Repeated genetic adaptation to high altitude in two tropical butterflies (47 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470343</id><title>Epistasis is not a strong constraint on the recurrent evolution of toxin-resistant Na+,K+-ATPases among tetrapods (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.139239+00:00</updated><author><name>Shabnam Mohammadi</name></author><author><name>Lu Yang</name></author><author><name>Santiago Herrera-Álvarez</name></author><author><name>María del Pilar Rodríguez-Ordoñez</name></author><author><name>Karen Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jay F. Storz</name></author><author><name>Susanne Dobler</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Crawford</name></author><author><name>Peter Andolfatto</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Comparative genomic studies reveal a global decline in rates of convergent amino acid substitution as a function of evolutionary distance. This pattern has been attributed to epistatic constraints on protein evolution, the idea being that mutations tend to confer the same fitness effects on more similar genetic backgrounds, so convergent substitutions are more likely to occur in closely related species. However, this hypothesis lacks experimental validation. We tested this model in the context of the recurrent evolution of resistance to cardiotonic steroids (CTS) across diverse groups of tetrapods, which occurs via specific amino acid substitutions to the α-subunit family of Na&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;,K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;-ATPases (ATP1A). After identifying a series of recurrent substitutions at two key sites of ATP1A1 predicted to confer CTS resistance, we performed protein engineering experiments to test the functional consequences of introducing these substitutions onto divergent species backgrounds. While we find that substitutions at these sites can have substantial background-dependent effects on CTS resistance, we also find no evidence for background-dependent effects on protein activity. We further show that the magnitude of a substitution’s effect on activity does not depend on the overall extent of ATP1A1 sequence divergence between species. More generally, a global analysis of substitution patterns across ATP1A orthologs and paralogs reveals that the probability of convergent substitution protein-wide is not predicted by sequence divergence. Together, these findings suggest that intramolecular epistasis is not an important constraint on the evolution of ATP1A CTS resistance in tetrapods.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individual amino acid residues within a protein work in concert to produce a functionally coherent structure that must be maintained even as orthologous proteins in different species diverge over time. Given this dependence, we expect identical mutations to have more similar effects on protein function in more closely related species. We tested this hypothesis by performing protein-engineering experiments on ATP1A, an enzyme mediating target-site insensitivity to cardiotonic steroids (CTS) in diverse animals. These experiments reveal that although the phenotypic effects of substitutions can sometimes be background-dependent, the magnitude of these effects does not correlate with ATP1A1 sequence divergence. This implies that the genetic background across the ATP1A protein does not strongly limit the evolution of CTS resistance in animals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470343" rel="alternate" title="Epistasis is not a strong constraint on the recurrent evolution of toxin-resistant Na+,K+-ATPases among tetrapods (20 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470556</id><title>Interpreting dN/dS under different selective regimes in cancer evolution (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.139527+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrés Pérez-Figueroa</name></author><author><name>David Posada</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The standard relationship between the &lt;italic&gt;dN/dS&lt;/italic&gt; statistic and the selection coefficient is contingent upon the computation of the rate of fixation of non-synonymous and synonymous mutations among divergent lineages (substitutions). In cancer genomics, however, &lt;italic&gt;dN/dS&lt;/italic&gt; is typically calculated by including mutations that are still segregating in the cell population. The interpretation of &lt;italic&gt;dN/dS&lt;/italic&gt; within sexual populations has been shown to be problematic. Here we used a simple model of somatic evolution to study the relationship between &lt;italic&gt;dN/dS&lt;/italic&gt; and the selection coefficient in the presence of deleterious, neutral, and beneficial mutations in cancer. We found that &lt;italic&gt;dN/dS&lt;/italic&gt; can be used to distinguish cancer genes under positive or negative selection, but it is not always informative about the magnitude of the selection coefficient. In particular, under the asexual scenario simulated, &lt;italic&gt;dN/dS&lt;/italic&gt; is insensitive to negative selection strength. Furthermore, the relationship between &lt;italic&gt;dN/dS&lt;/italic&gt; and the positive selection coefficient depends on the mutation detection threshold, and, in particular scenarios, it can become non-linear. Our results warn about the necessary caution when interpreting the results drawn from &lt;italic&gt;dN/dS&lt;/italic&gt; estimates in cancer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470556" rel="alternate" title="Interpreting dN/dS under different selective regimes in cancer evolution (17 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470933</id><title>UG/Abi: a highly diverse family of prokaryotic reverse transcriptases associated with defense functions (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.139735+00:00</updated><author><name>Mario Rodriguez Mestre</name></author><author><name>Linyi Gao</name></author><author><name>Shiraz A. Shah</name></author><author><name>Adrian Lopez-Beltran</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Gonzalez-Delgado</name></author><author><name>Francisco Martinez-Abarca</name></author><author><name>Jaime Iranzo</name></author><author><name>Modesto Redrejo-Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Feng Zhang</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Toro</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Reverse transcriptases (RTs) are enzymes capable of synthesizing DNA using RNA as a template. Within the last few years, a burst of research has led to the discovery of novel prokaryotic RTs with diverse antiviral properties, such as DRTs (Defense-associated RTs), which belong to the so-called group of unknown RTs (UG) and are closely related to the Abortive Infection system (Abi) RTs. In this work, we performed a systematic analysis of UG and Abi RTs, increasing the number of UG/Abi members up to 42 highly diverse groups, most of which are predicted to be functionally associated with other gene(s) or domain(s). Based on this information, we classified these systems into three major classes. In addition, we reveal that most of these groups are associated with defense functions and/or mobile genetic elements, and demonstrate the antiphage role of four novel groups. Besides, we highlight the presence of one of these systems in novel families of human gut viruses infecting members of the Bacteroidetes and Firmicutes phyla. This work lays the foundation for a comprehensive and unified understanding of these highly diverse RTs with enormous biotechnological potential.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470933" rel="alternate" title="UG/Abi: a highly diverse family of prokaryotic reverse transcriptases associated with defense functions (10 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470771</id><title>Demographic feedbacks can hamper the spatial spread of a gene drive (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.140384+00:00</updated><author><name>Léo Girardin</name></author><author><name>Florence Débarre</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This paper is concerned with a reaction–diffusion system modeling the fixation and the invasion in a population of a gene drive (an allele biasing inheritance, increasing its own transmission to offspring). In our model, the gene drive has a negative effect on the fitness of individuals carrying it, and is therefore susceptible of decreasing the total carrying capacity of the population locally in space. This tends to generate an opposing demographic advection that the gene drive has to overcome in order to invade. While previous reaction–diffusion models neglected this aspect, here we focus on it and try to predict the sign of the traveling wave speed. It turns out to be an analytical challenge, only partial results being within reach, and we complete our theoretical analysis by numerical simulations. Our results indicate that taking into account the interplay between population dynamics and population genetics might actually be crucial, as it can effectively reverse the direction of the invasion and lead to failure. Our findings can be extended to other bistable systems, such as the spread of cytoplasmic incompatibilities caused by Wolbachia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470771" rel="alternate" title="Demographic feedbacks can hamper the spatial spread of a gene drive (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470797</id><title>Fitness and mating consequences of variation in male allocation in a wind pollinated plant (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.140611+00:00</updated><author><name>Abrar A Aljiboury</name></author><author><name>Jannice Friedman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In hermaphrodites, the allocation of resources to each sex function can influence fitness through reproductive success and mating success. In wind pollinated plants, sex allocation theory predicts that male fitness increases linearly with investment of resources into male function. However, there have been few empirical tests of this prediction. We experimentally manipulated allocation to male function in Ambrosia artemisiifolia (common ragweed) in a field experiment and measured mating success using genetic assays. We investigated the effects of various morphological traits and flowering phenology on male fitness, and on male and female mate diversity. Our results provide evidence for a linear relation between allocation to male function and fitness. We find earlier onset of male flowering time increases reproductive success, while later onset flowering time increases the probability of mating with diverse individuals. This research is among the first empirical studies testing the prediction of linear male fitness returns in wind pollinated plants. Our results provide insight into the large investment into male function by wind pollinated plants and temporal variation in sex allocation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470797" rel="alternate" title="Fitness and mating consequences of variation in male allocation in a wind pollinated plant (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470853</id><title>The Evolutionary Dynamics of Hyperparasites (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.142875+00:00</updated><author><name>Graham R Northrup</name></author><author><name>Steven R Parratt</name></author><author><name>Carly Rozins</name></author><author><name>Anna-Liisa Laine</name></author><author><name>Mike Boots</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Evolutionary theory has typically focused on pairwise interactions, such as those between hosts and parasites, with relatively little work on more complex interactions including hyperparasites: parasites of parasites. Hyperparasites are common in nature, with the chestnut blight fungus virus CHV-1 a well-known natural example, but also notably include the phages of important human bacterial diseases. Theory on hyperparasitism has mostly focused on their impact on the evolution of virulence of their parasite host and relatively little is known about evolutionary trajectories of hyperparasites themselves. Our general modeling framework highlights the central role the that ability of a hyperparasite to be transmitted with its parasite plays in their evolution. Hyperparasites which transmit with their parasite hosts (hitchhike) will be selected for lower virulence, trending towards hypermutualism or hypercommensalism and select against causing a reduction in parasite virulence (hypovirulence). We examine the impact on the evolution of hyperparasite systems a of a wide range of host and parasite traits showing, for example, that high parasite virulence selects for higher hyperparasite virulence feeding back into selection for hypovirulence in the parasite. Our results have implications for hyperparasite research, both as biocontrol agents and for understanding of how hyperparasites shape community ecology and evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470853" rel="alternate" title="The Evolutionary Dynamics of Hyperparasites (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471152</id><title>Duplication of NRAMP3 gene in poplars generated two homologous transporters with distinct functions (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.143462+00:00</updated><author><name>Mathieu Pottier</name></author><author><name>Van Anh Le Thi</name></author><author><name>Catherine Primard-Brisset</name></author><author><name>Jessica Marion</name></author><author><name>Michele Bianchi</name></author><author><name>Cindy Victor</name></author><author><name>Annabelle Déjardin</name></author><author><name>Gilles Pilate</name></author><author><name>Sébastien Thomine</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Transition metals are essential for a wealth of metabolic reactions, but their concentrations need to be tightly controlled across cells and cell compartments, as metal excess or imbalance has deleterious effects. Metal homeostasis is achieved by a combination of metal transport across membranes and metal binding to a variety of molecules. Gene duplication is a key process in evolution, as emergence of advantageous mutations on one of the copies can confer a new function. Here, we report that the poplar genome contains two paralogues encoding NRAMP3 metal transporters localized in tandem. All Populus species analyzed had two copies of NRAMP3, whereas only one could be identified in Salix species indicating that duplication occurred when the two genera separated. Both copies are under purifying selection and encode functional transporters, as shown by expression in the yeast heterologous expression system. However, genetic complementation revealed that only one of the paralogues has retained the original function in release of metals stored in the vacuole previously characterized in A. thaliana. Confocal imaging showed that the other copy has acquired a distinct localization to the Trans Golgi Network (TGN). Expression in poplar indicated that the copy of NRAMP3 localized on the TGN has a novel function in the control of cell-to-cell transport of manganese. This work provides a clear case of neo-functionalization through change in the subcellular localization of a metal transporter as well evidence for the involvement of the secretory pathway in cell-to-cell transport of manganese.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471152" rel="alternate" title="Duplication of NRAMP3 gene in poplars generated two homologous transporters with distinct functions (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470985</id><title>A chromosomal inversion may facilitate adaptation despite periodic gene flow in a freshwater fish (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.143835+00:00</updated><author><name>Matt J Thorstensen</name></author><author><name>Peter T Euclide</name></author><author><name>Jennifer D Jeffrey</name></author><author><name>Yue Shi</name></author><author><name>Jason R Treberg</name></author><author><name>Douglas A Watkinson</name></author><author><name>Eva C Enders</name></author><author><name>Wesley A Larson</name></author><author><name>Yasuhiro Kobayashi</name></author><author><name>Ken Jeffries</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genomic architecture, such as chromosomal inversions, may play an important role in facilitating adaptation despite opportunities for gene flow. One system where chromosomal inversions may be important for eco-evolutionary dynamics are in freshwater fish, which often live in heterogenous environments characterized by varying levels of connectivity and varying opportunities for gene flow. In the present study, reduced representation sequencing was used to study possible adaptation in n=345 walleye (&lt;italic&gt;Sander vitreus&lt;/italic&gt;) from three North American waterbodies: Cedar Bluff Reservoir (Kansas, USA), Lake Manitoba (Manitoba, Canada), and Lake Winnipeg (Manitoba, Canada). Haplotype and outlier-based tests revealed a putative chromosomal inversion that contained three expressed genes and was nearly fixed for alternate genotypes in each Canadian lake. These patterns exist despite several opportunities for gene flow between these proximate Canadian lakes, suggesting that the inversion may be important for facilitating adaptative divergence between the two lakes despite gene flow. Our study illuminates the importance of genomic architecture for facilitating local adaptation in freshwater fish and provides additional evidence that inversions may facilitate local adaptation in many organisms that inhabit connected but heterogenous environments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470985" rel="alternate" title="A chromosomal inversion may facilitate adaptation despite periodic gene flow in a freshwater fish (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470672</id><title>Evolutionary history of sexual differentiation mechanism in insects (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.144245+00:00</updated><author><name>Yasuhiko Chikami</name></author><author><name>Miki Okuno</name></author><author><name>Atsushi Toyoda</name></author><author><name>Takehiko Itoh</name></author><author><name>Teruyuki Niimi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gain of alternative splicing gives rise to functional diversity in proteins and underlies the complexity and diversity of biological aspects. However, it is still not fully understood how alternatively spliced genes develop the functional novelty. To this end, we infer the evolutionary history of the &lt;italic&gt;doublesex&lt;/italic&gt; gene, the key transcriptional factor in the sexual differentiation of arthropods. &lt;italic&gt;doublesex&lt;/italic&gt; is controlled by sex-specific splicing and promotes both male and female differentiation in some holometabolan insects. In contrast, &lt;italic&gt;doublesex&lt;/italic&gt; promotes only male differentiation in some hemimetabolan insects. Here, we investigate ancestral states of &lt;italic&gt;doublesex&lt;/italic&gt; using &lt;italic&gt;Thermobia domestica&lt;/italic&gt; belonging to Zygentoma, the sister group of winged insects. We find that &lt;italic&gt;doublesex&lt;/italic&gt; of &lt;italic&gt;T. domestica&lt;/italic&gt; expresses sex-specific isoforms but is only necessary for male differentiation of sexual morphology. This result ensures the hypothesis that &lt;italic&gt;doublesex&lt;/italic&gt; was initially only used to promote male differentiation during insect evolution. However, &lt;italic&gt;T. domestica doublesex&lt;/italic&gt; has a short female-specific region and upregulates the expression of &lt;italic&gt;vitellogenin&lt;/italic&gt; homologs in females, suggesting that &lt;italic&gt;doublesex&lt;/italic&gt; may have already controlled some aspects of feminization in the common ancestor of winged insects. Reconstruction of the ancestral sequence and prediction of the protein structure show that the female-specific isoform of &lt;italic&gt;doublesex&lt;/italic&gt; has a long C-terminal disordered region in holometabolan insects, but not in non-holometabolan species. We propose that &lt;italic&gt;doublesex&lt;/italic&gt; acquired a female-specific isoform and then underwent a change in the protein motif structure, which became essential for female differentiation in sexual dimorphisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470672" rel="alternate" title="Evolutionary history of sexual differentiation mechanism in insects (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470932</id><title>Genetic architecture of dispersal and local adaptation drives accelerating range expansions (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.144564+00:00</updated><author><name>Jhelam N. Deshpande</name></author><author><name>Emanuel A. Fronhofer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Contemporary evolution has the potential to significantly alter biotic responses to global change, including range expansion dynamics and biological invasions. However, predictive models often make highly simplifying assumptions about the genetic architecture underlying relevant traits. This can be problematic since genetic architecture defines evolvability, that is, evolutionary rates, and higher order evolutionary processes, which determine whether evolution will be able to keep up with environmental change or not. Therefore, we here study the impact of the genetic architecture of dispersal and local adaptation, two central traits of high relevance for range expansion dynamics, on the speed and variability of range expansions into an environmental gradient, such as temperature. In our theoretical model we assume that dispersal and local adaptation traits result from the products of two non-interacting gene-regulatory networks (GRNs). We compare our model to simpler quantitative genetics models and show that in the GRN model, range expansions are accelerated, faster and more variable. Increased variability implies that these evolutionary changes reduce predictability. We further find that acceleration in the GRN model is primarily driven by an increase in the rate of local adaptation to novel habitats which results from greater sensitivity to mutation (decreased robustness) and increased gene expression. Our results highlight how processes at microscopic scales, here, within genomes, can impact the predictions of large scale, macroscopic phenomena, such as range expansions, by modulating the rate of evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470932" rel="alternate" title="Genetic architecture of dispersal and local adaptation drives accelerating range expansions (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>