<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.365702+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475641</id><title>The genetic structure of a wild wheat population has remained associated with microhabitats over 36 years (63 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.365811+00:00</updated><author><name>Tal Dahan-Meir</name></author><author><name>Thomas James Ellis</name></author><author><name>Fabrizio Mafessoni</name></author><author><name>Hanan Sela</name></author><author><name>Jacob Manisterski</name></author><author><name>Naomi Avivi-Ragolsky</name></author><author><name>Amir Raz</name></author><author><name>Moshe Feldman</name></author><author><name>Yehoshua Anikster</name></author><author><name>Magnus Nordborg</name></author><author><name>Avraham A. Levy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Wild progenitors of major crops can help us understand domestication, and may also provide the genetic resources needed for ensuring food security in the face of climate change. We examined the genetic structure of a wild emmer wheat population, sampled over 36 years while both temperature and CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; concentration increased significantly. The genotypes of 832 individuals revealed high genetic diversity over scales of tens of meters and were clustered spatially into ecological microhabitats. This pattern was remarkably stable over time. Simulations indicate that neutral processes alone are unlikely to fully explain the spatial and temporal stability of the population. These results are consistent with a role for local adaptation in shaping the fine-scale structure of plant populations, which is relevant for &lt;italic&gt;in-situ&lt;/italic&gt; conservation strategies of biodiversity in nature.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475641" rel="alternate" title="The genetic structure of a wild wheat population has remained associated with microhabitats over 36 years (63 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475860</id><title>Two modes of evolution shape bacterial strain diversity in the gut for thousands of generations (57 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.365917+00:00</updated><author><name>N. Frazão</name></author><author><name>A. Konrad</name></author><author><name>D. Güleresi</name></author><author><name>M. Lässig</name></author><author><name>I. Gordo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;How and at what pace bacteria evolve when colonizing healthy hosts remains unclear. Here, by monitoring evolution for more than six thousand generations in the mouse gut, we show that the successful colonization of an invader &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; depends on the diversity of the existing microbiota and the presence of a closely related strain. Following colonization, two modes of evolution were observed: one in which diversifying selection leads to long-term coexistence of ecotypes and a second in which directional selection propels selective sweeps. These modes can be quantitatively distinguished by the statistics of mutation trajectories. In our experiments, diversifying selection was marked by the emergence of metabolic mutations, and directional selection by acquisition of prophages, which bring their own benefits and costs. In both modes, we observed parallel evolution, with mutation accumulation rates comparable to those typically observed &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; on similar time scales. Our results show that gut environments can rapidly generate diversifying selection and ecotype formation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475860" rel="alternate" title="Two modes of evolution shape bacterial strain diversity in the gut for thousands of generations (57 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475830</id><title>Loss of plastid developmental genes coincides with a reversion to monoplastidy in hornworts (26 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.365988+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander I. MacLeod</name></author><author><name>Parth K. Raval</name></author><author><name>Simon Stockhorst</name></author><author><name>Michael R. Knopp</name></author><author><name>Eftychios Frangedakis</name></author><author><name>Sven B. Gould</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The first plastid evolved from an endosymbiotic cyanobacterium in the common ancestor of the Archaeplastida. The transformative steps from cyanobacterium to organelle included the transfer of control over developmental processes; a necessity for the host to orchestrate, for example, the fission of the organelle. The plastids of almost all embryophytes divide independent from nuclear division, leading to cells housing multiple plastids. Hornworts, however, are monoplastidic (or near-monoplastidic) and their photosynthetic organelles are a curious exception among embryophytes for reasons such as the occasional presence of pyrenoids. Here we screened genomic and transcriptomic data of eleven hornworts for components of plastid developmental pathways. We find intriguing differences among hornworts and specifically highlight that pathway components involved in regulating plastid development and biogenesis were differentially lost in this group of bryophytes. In combination with ancestral state reconstruction, our data suggest that hornworts have reverted back to a monoplastidic phenotype due to the combined loss of two plastid division-associated genes: ARC3 and FtsZ2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475830" rel="alternate" title="Loss of plastid developmental genes coincides with a reversion to monoplastidy in hornworts (26 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475913</id><title>Background selection theory overestimates effective population size for high mutation rates (13 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.366059+00:00</updated><author><name>Joseph Matheson</name></author><author><name>Joanna Masel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Simple models from the neutral theory of molecular evolution are claimed to be flexible enough to incorporate the complex effects of background selection against linked deleterious mutations. Complexities are collapsed into an “effective” population size that specifies neutral genetic diversity. To achieve this, current background selection theory assumes linkage equilibrium among deleterious variants. Data do not support this assumption, nor do theoretical considerations when the genome-wide deleterious mutation is realistically high. We simulate genomes evolving under background selection, allowing the emergence of linkage disequilibria. With realistically high deleterious mutation rates, neutral diversity is much lower than predicted from previous analytical theory.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475913" rel="alternate" title="Background selection theory overestimates effective population size for high mutation rates (13 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476347</id><title>Evolution of assortative mating following selective introgression of pigmentation genes between two Drosophila species (13 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.366115+00:00</updated><author><name>Jean R David</name></author><author><name>Erina A Ferreira</name></author><author><name>Laure Jabaud</name></author><author><name>David Ogereau</name></author><author><name>Héloïse Bastide</name></author><author><name>Amir Yassin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Adaptive introgression is ubiquitous in animals but experimental support for its role in driving speciation remains scarce. In the absence of conscious selection, admixed laboratory strains of Drosophila asymmetrically and progressively lose alleles from one parental species and reproductive isolation against the predominant parent ceases after 10 generations. Here, we selectively introgressed during one year light pigmentation genes of D. santomea into the genome of its dark sibling D. yakuba, and vice versa. We found that the pace of phenotypic change differed between the species and the sexes, and identified through genome sequencing common as well as distinct introgressed loci in each species. Mating assays showed that assortative mating between introgressed flies and both parental species persisted even after four years (~ 60 generations) from the end of the selection. Those results indicate that selective introgression of as low as 0.5% of the genome can beget morphologically-distinct and reproductively-isolated strains, two prerequisites for the delimitation of new species. Our findings hence represent a significant step towards understanding the genome-wide dynamics of speciation-through-introgression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476347" rel="alternate" title="Evolution of assortative mating following selective introgression of pigmentation genes between two Drosophila species (13 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475832</id><title>Divergence and introgression among the virilis group of Drosophila (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.366192+00:00</updated><author><name>Leeban H. Yusuf</name></author><author><name>Venera Tyukmaeva</name></author><author><name>Anneli Hoikkala</name></author><author><name>Michael G. Ritchie</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Speciation with gene flow is now widely regarded as common. However, the frequency of introgression between recently diverged species and the evolutionary consequences of gene flow are still poorly understood. The &lt;italic&gt;virilis&lt;/italic&gt; group of &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; contains around a dozen species that are geographically widespread and show varying levels of pre-zygotic and post-zygotic isolation. Here, we utilize de novo genome assemblies and whole-genome sequencing data to resolve phylogenetic relationships and describe patterns of introgression and divergence across the group. We suggest that the &lt;italic&gt;virilis&lt;/italic&gt; group consists of three, rather than the traditional two, subgroups. We found evidence of pervasive phylogenetic discordance caused by ancient introgression events between distant lineages within the group, and much more recent gene flow between closely-related species. When assessing patterns of genome-wide divergence in species pairs across the group, we found no consistent genomic evidence of a disproportionate role for the X chromosome. Some genes undergoing rapid sequence divergence across the group were involved in chemical communication and may be related to the evolution of sexual isolation. We suggest that gene flow between closely-related species has potentially had an impact on lineage-specific adaptation and the evolution of reproductive barriers. Our results show how ancient and recent introgression confuse phylogenetic reconstruction, and suggest that shared variation can facilitate adaptation and speciation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475832" rel="alternate" title="Divergence and introgression among the virilis group of Drosophila (6 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476463</id><title>Genome assembly, structural variants, and genetic differentiation between Lake Whitefish young species pairs (Coregonus sp.) with long and short reads (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.366261+00:00</updated><author><name>Claire M&amp;eacuterot</name></author><author><name>Kristina S R Stenl&amp;oslashkk</name></author><author><name>Clare Venney</name></author><author><name>Martin Laporte</name></author><author><name>Michel Moser</name></author><author><name>Eric Normandeau</name></author><author><name>Mariann &amp;Agravernyasi</name></author><author><name>Matthew Kent</name></author><author><name>Cl&amp;eacutement Rougeux</name></author><author><name>Jullien M Flynn</name></author><author><name>Sigbjorn Lien</name></author><author><name>Louis Bernatchez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The parallel evolution of nascent pairs of ecologically differentiated species offers an opportunity to get a better glimpse at the genetic architecture of speciation. Of particular interest is our recent ability to consider a wider range of genomic variants, not only single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs), thanks to long-read sequencing technology. We can now identify structural variants (SVs) like insertions, deletions, and other structural rearrangements, allowing further insights into the genetic architecture of speciation and how different variants are involved in species differentiation. Here, we investigated genomic patterns of differentiation between sympatric species pairs (Dwarf and Normal) belonging to the Lake Whitefish (Coregonus clupeaformis) species complex. We assembled the first reference genomes for both Dwarf and Normal Lake Whitefish, annotated the transposable elements, and analysed the genome in the light of related coregonid species. Next, we used a combination of long-read and short-read sequencing to characterize SVs and genotype them at population-scale using genome-graph approaches, showing that SVs cover five times more of the genome than SNPs. We then integrated both SNPs and SVs to investigate the genetic architecture of species differentiation in two different lakes and highlighted an excess of shared outliers of differentiation. In particular, a large fraction of SVs differentiating the two species was driven by transposable elements (TEs), suggesting that TE accumulation during a period of allopatry predating secondary contact may have been a key process in the speciation of the Dwarf and Normal Whitefish. Altogether, our results suggest that SVs play an important role in speciation and that by combining second and third generation sequencing we now have the ability to integrate SVs into speciation genomics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476463" rel="alternate" title="Genome assembly, structural variants, and genetic differentiation between Lake Whitefish young species pairs (Coregonus sp.) with long and short reads (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475787</id><title>Impact of Ghost Introgression on Coalescent-based Species Tree Inference and Estimation of Divergence Time (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.366353+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiao-Xu Pang</name></author><author><name>Da-Yong Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The species studied in any evolutionary investigation generally constitute a very small proportion of all the species currently existing or that have gone extinct. It is therefore likely that introgression, which is widespread across the tree of life, involves “ghosts,” i.e., unsampled, unknown, or extinct lineages. However, the impact of ghost introgression on estimations of species trees has been rarely studied and is thus poorly understood. In this study, we use mathematical analysis and simulations to examine the robustness of species tree methods based on a multispecies coalescent model under gene flow sourcing from an extant or ghost lineage. We found that very low levels of extant or ghost introgression can result in anomalous gene trees (AGTs) on three-taxon rooted trees if accompanied by strong incomplete lineage sorting (ILS). In contrast, even massive introgression, with more than half of the recipient genome descending from the donor lineage, may not necessarily lead to AGTs. In cases involving an ingroup lineage (defined as one that diverged no earlier than the most basal species under investigation) acting as the donor of introgression, the time of root divergence among the investigated species was either underestimated or remained unaffected, but for the cases of outgroup ghost lineages acting as donors, the divergence time was generally overestimated. Under many conditions of ingroup introgression, the stronger the ILS was, the higher was the accuracy of estimating the time of root divergence, although the topology of the species tree is more prone to be biased by the effect of introgression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475787" rel="alternate" title="Impact of Ghost Introgression on Coalescent-based Species Tree Inference and Estimation of Divergence Time (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476360</id><title>Partial sex linkage and linkage disequilibrium on the guppy sex chromosome (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.366410+00:00</updated><author><name>Suo Qiu</name></author><author><name>Lenxob Yong</name></author><author><name>Alstair Wilson</name></author><author><name>Darrren P Croft</name></author><author><name>Chay Graham</name></author><author><name>Deborah Charlesworth</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The guppy Y chromosome has been considered a model system for the evolution of suppressed recombination between sex chromosomes, and it has been proposed that complete sex-linkage has evolved across about 3 Mb surrounding the sex-determining locus of this fish, followed by recombination suppression across a further 7 Mb of the 23 Mb XY pair, forming younger evolutionary strata. Sequences of the guppy genome show that Y is very similar to the X chromosome, making it important to understand which parts of the Y are completely non-recombining, and whether there is indeed a large completely non-recombining region. Here, we describe new evidence that supports a different interpretation of the data that suggested the presence of such a region. We analysed PoolSeq data in samples from multiple natural populations from Trinidad. This yields evidence for linkage disequilibrium (LD) between sequence variants and the sex-determining locus. Downstream populations have higher diversity than upstream ones (which display the expected signs of bottlenecks). The associations we observe conform to predictions for a genome region with infrequent recombination that carries one or more sexually antagonistic polymorphisms. They also suggest the region in which the sex-determining locus must be located. However, no consistently male-specific variants were found, supporting the suggestion that any completely sex-linked region may be very small.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476360" rel="alternate" title="Partial sex linkage and linkage disequilibrium on the guppy sex chromosome (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476421</id><title>Gene regulatory evolution in cold-adapted fly populations neutralizes plasticity and may undermine genetic canalization (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.366479+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuheng Huang</name></author><author><name>Justin Lack</name></author><author><name>Grant Hoppel</name></author><author><name>John E Pool</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The relationships between adaptive evolution, phenotypic plasticity, and canalization remain incompletely understood. Theoretical and empirical studies have made conflicting arguments on whether adaptive evolution may enhance or oppose the plastic response. Gene regulatory traits offer excellent potential to study the relationship between plasticity and adaptation, and they can now be studied at the transcriptomic level. Here we take advantage of three closely-related pairs of natural populations of Drosophila melanogaster from contrasting thermal environments that reflect three separate instances of cold tolerance evolution. We measure the transcriptome-wide plasticity in gene expression levels and alternative splicing (intron usage) between warm and cold laboratory environments. We find that suspected adaptive changes in both gene expression and alternative splicing tend to neutralize the ancestral plastic response. Further, we investigate the hypothesis that adaptive evolution can lead to decanalization of selected gene regulatory traits. We find strong evidence that suspected adaptive gene expression (but not splicing) changes in cold-adapted populations are more vulnerable to the genetic perturbation of inbreeding than putatively neutral changes. We find some evidence that these patterns may reflect a loss of genetic canalization accompanying adaptation, although other processes including hitchhiking recessive deleterious variants may contribute as well. Our findings augment our understanding of genetic and environmental effects on gene regulation in the context of adaptive evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476421" rel="alternate" title="Gene regulatory evolution in cold-adapted fly populations neutralizes plasticity and may undermine genetic canalization (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475639</id><title>Maternal transmission as a symbiont sieve, and the absence of lactation in male mammals (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.366541+00:00</updated><author><name>George W. A. Constable</name></author><author><name>Brennen Fagan</name></author><author><name>Richard Law</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gut microbiomes of humans carry a complex symbiotic assemblage of microorganisms. As in all mammals, the special mode of feeding newborn infants through milk from the mammary gland enhances the opportunity for vertical transmission of elements of this microbiome. This has potential benefits, but it also brings with it some hazards for the host. We point out here that vertical transmission from both parents would allow host populations to be invaded by elements that are deleterious. In contrast, vertical transmission, when restricted to one parent, acts as a sieve preventing the spread of such elements. Because some transmission from mother to infant is unavoidable in placental mammals, uniparental transmission of symbionts, if it were to be selected, would require some separation of the father from the newborn infant. This paper therefore puts forward the hypothesis that the asymmetry in roles of mother and father, together with the hazards that come with biparental transmission, generate a selection pressure against male lactation in humans, and in mammals in general.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475639" rel="alternate" title="Maternal transmission as a symbiont sieve, and the absence of lactation in male mammals (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476414</id><title>Ancestral sequence reconstructions evaluated by extant sequence cross-validation (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.366600+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael Sennett</name></author><author><name>Douglas Theobald</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ancestral sequence reconstruction (ASR) has become widely used to analyze the properties of ancient biomolecules and to elucidate the mechanisms of molecular evolution.  By recapitulating the structural, mechanistic, and functional changes of proteins during their evolution, ASR has been able to address many fundamental and challenging evolutionary questions where more traditional methods have failed.  Despite the tangible successes of ASR, the accuracy of its reconstructions is currently unknown, because it is generally impossible to compare resurrected proteins to the true ancient ancestors that are now extinct. Which evolutionary models are the best for ASR?  How accurate are the resulting inferences? Here we answer these questions by applying cross-validation (CV) to sets of aligned extant sequences. To assess the adequacy of a chosen evolutionary model for predicting extant sequence data, our column-wise CV method iteratively cross-validates each column in an alignment. Unlike other phylogenetic model selection criteria, this method does not require bias correction and does not make  restrictive assumptions commonly violated by phylogenetic data. We find that column-wise CV generally provides a more conservative criterion than the AIC by preferring less complex models. To validate ASR methods, we also apply cross-validation to each sequence in an alignment by reconstructing the extant sequences using ASR methodology, a method we term extant sequence reconstruction (ESR). We can thus quantify the accuracy of ASR methodology by comparing ESR reconstructions to the corresponding true sequences. We find that a common measure of the quality of a reconstructed sequence, the average probability of the sequence, is indeed a good estimate of the fraction of the sequence that is correct when the evolutionary model is accurate or overparameterized. However, the average probability is a poor measure for comparing reconstructions, because more accurate phylogenetic models typically result in reconstructions with lower average probabilities.  In contrast, the entropy of the reconstructed distribution is a reliable indicator of the quality of a reconstruction, as the entropy provides an accurate estimate of the log-probability of the true sequence. Both column-wise CV and ESR are useful methods to validate evolutionary models used for ASR and can be applied in practice to any phylogenetic analysis of real biological sequences.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476414" rel="alternate" title="Ancestral sequence reconstructions evaluated by extant sequence cross-validation (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475794</id><title>Teasing apart the joint effect of demography and natural selection in the birth of a contact zone (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.366654+00:00</updated><author><name>Lili Li</name></author><author><name>Pascal Milesi</name></author><author><name>Mathieu Tiret</name></author><author><name>Jun Chen</name></author><author><name>Janek Sendrowski</name></author><author><name>John Baison</name></author><author><name>Zhiqiang Chen</name></author><author><name>Linghua Zhou</name></author><author><name>Bo Karlsson</name></author><author><name>Mats Berlin</name></author><author><name>Johan Westin</name></author><author><name>Rosario Garcia-Gil</name></author><author><name>Harry Wu</name></author><author><name>Martin Lascoux</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Vast population movements induced by recurrent climatic cycles have shaped the genetic structure of plant species. This is especially true in Scandinavia that was repeatedly glaciated. During glacial periods trees were confined to refugia, south and east of the ice sheet, from which they recolonized Scandinavia as the ice melted away. This multi-pronged recolonization led to large contact zones in most species. We leverage large genomic data from 5000 trees to reconstruct the demographic history of Norway spruce (&lt;italic&gt;Picea abies&lt;/italic&gt;) and test for the presence of natural selection during the recolonization process and the establishment of the contact zone. Sweden is today made up of two large genetic clusters, a southern one originating from the Baltics and a Northern one originating from Northern Russia. The contact zone delineating these two clusters closely matches the limit between two major climatic regions. This suggests that natural selection contributed to the establishment and the maintenance of the contact zone. To test this hypothesis we first used Approximate Bayesian Computation; an Isolation-with migration model with genome-wide linked selection fits the data better than a purely neutral one. Secondly, we identified loci characterized by both extreme allele frequency differences between geographic regions and association to the variables defining the climatic zones. These loci, many of which are related to phenology, form clusters present on all linkage groups. Altogether, the current genetic structure reflects the joint effect of climatic cycles, recolonization and selection on the establishment of strong local adaptation and contact zones.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Understanding how past climatic events, human actions and evolutionary forces contributed to the present distribution of genetic diversity is crucial to predict their reaction to the current climate crisis. Vast distribution shifts induced by past environmental changes, local ecological processes, natural selection and human transfers contributed to the current distribution of Norway spruce across Northern Europe. Genome-wide polymorphisms from thousands of individuals show that Scandinavia was recolonized after the Last Glacial from both south and north. This two-pronged recolonization established a contact zone between two genetic clusters that matches the limit between two major climate zones. The contact zone is shaped and maintained by natural selection on a large number of loci that form blocks of co-adapted loci spread genome-wide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475794" rel="alternate" title="Teasing apart the joint effect of demography and natural selection in the birth of a contact zone (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475896</id><title>Evolution under juvenile malnutrition impacts adult metabolism and fitness (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.366756+00:00</updated><author><name>Berra Erkosar</name></author><author><name>Cindy Dupuis</name></author><author><name>Fanny Cavigliasso</name></author><author><name>Loriane Savary</name></author><author><name>Laurent Kremmer</name></author><author><name>Hector Gallart-Ayala</name></author><author><name>Julijana Ivanisevic</name></author><author><name>Tadeusz J. Kawecki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Juveniles are often first to suffer from nutrient shortage, and juvenile undernutrition is likely an important force of natural selection shaping animal physiology, with consequences potentially extending into adulthood. We combined RNAseq, targeted metabolomics and genomics to study the consequences of experimental evolution under juvenile undernutrition for metabolism of reproductively active adult females of &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt;. Compared to six Control populations maintained on standard diet, six Selected populations evolved for over 230 generations on a nutrient-poor larval diet showed major changes in adult gene expression and metabolite abundance. In particular, Selected flies were relatively deficient in essential amino acids and purine nucleotides, but showed overabundance of several non-essential amino-acids involved in purine synthesis and overexpression of multiple enzymes catalyzing this pathway. Selected flies also accumulated medium-chain acylcarnitines suggestive of congestion in beta-oxidation, possibly linked to deficiency of electron transporters. Some aspects of the metabolic profile of Selected flies resembled that of flies subject to starvation. Furthermore, differences between Selected and Control populations in adult gene expression were in general positively correlated with differences in larval expression, consistent with pleiotropy in gene regulation between the life stages. Finally, Selected flies were less fit in terms of fecundity than Controls even when both were raised under the conditions under which the Selected populations evolved. These results suggest that evolutionary adaptation to juvenile undernutrition has large pleiotropic consequences for adult metabolism, and that they are costly rather than adaptive for adult fitness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475896" rel="alternate" title="Evolution under juvenile malnutrition impacts adult metabolism and fitness (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>