<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv evolutionary-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.767750+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.05.451163</id><title>The crucial role of genome-wide genetic variation in conservation (199 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.769129+00:00</updated><author><name>Marty Kardos</name></author><author><name>Ellie Armstrong</name></author><author><name>Sarah Fitzpatrick</name></author><author><name>Samantha Hauser</name></author><author><name>Phil Hedrick</name></author><author><name>Josh Miller</name></author><author><name>David A. Tallmon</name></author><author><name>W. Chris Funk</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The unprecedented rate of extinction calls for efficient use of genetics to help conserve biodiversity. Several recent genomic and simulation-based studies have argued that the field of conservation biology has placed too much focus on the conservation of genome-wide genetic variation, and that this approach should be replaced with another that focuses instead on managing the subset of functional genetic variation that is thought to affect fitness. Here, we critically evaluate the feasibility and likely benefits of this approach in conservation. We find that population genetics theory and empirical results show that the conserving genome-wide genetic variation is generally the best approach to prevent inbreeding depression and loss of adaptive potential from driving populations towards extinction. Focusing conservation efforts on presumably functional genetic variation will only be feasible occasionally, often misleading, and counterproductive when prioritized over genome-wide genetic variation. Given the increasing rate of habitat loss and other environmental changes, failure to recognize the detrimental effects of lost genome-wide variation on long-term population viability will only worsen the biodiversity crisis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.05.451163" rel="alternate" title="The crucial role of genome-wide genetic variation in conservation (199 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.09.451712</id><title>Global patterns of subgenome evolution in organelle-targeted genes of six allotetraploid angiosperms (65 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.769520+00:00</updated><author><name>Joel Sharbrough</name></author><author><name>Justin Conover</name></author><author><name>Matheus Fernandes Gyorfy</name></author><author><name>Corrinne Grover</name></author><author><name>Emma R Miller</name></author><author><name>Jonathan F Wendel</name></author><author><name>Daniel B Sloan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Whole-genome duplications (WGDs), in which the number of nuclear genome copies is elevated as a result of autopolyploidy or allopolyploidy, are a prominent process of diversification in eukaryotes. The genetic and evolutionary forces that WGD imposes upon cytoplasmic genomes are not well understood, despite the central role that cytonuclear interactions play in eukaryotic function and fitness. Cellular respiration and photosynthesis depend upon successful interaction between the 3000+ nuclear-encoded proteins destined for the mitochondria or plastids and the gene products of cytoplasmic genomes in multi-subunit complexes such as OXPHOS, organellar ribosomes, Photosystems I and II, and Rubisco. Allopolyploids are thus faced with the critical task of coordinating interactions between nuclear and cytoplasmic genes that were inherited from different species. Because cytoplasmic genomes share a more recent history of common descent with the maternal nuclear subgenome than the paternal subgenome, evolutionary "mismatches" between the paternal subgenome and the cytoplasmic genomes in allopolyploids might lead to accelerated rates of evolution in the paternal homoeologs of allopolyploids, either through relaxed purifying selection or strong directional selection to rectify these mismatches. We tested this hypothesis in maternal vs. paternal copies of organelle-targeted genes in six allotetraploids: Brachypodium hybridum, Chenopodium quinoa, Coffea arabica, Gossypium hirsutum, Nicotiana tabacum, and Triticum dicoccoides. We report evidence that allopolyploid subgenomes exhibit unequal rates of protein-sequence evolution, but we did not observe global effects of cytonuclear incompatibilities on paternal homoeologs of organelle-targeted genes. Analyses of gene content revealed mixed evidence for whether organelle-targeted genes re-diploidize more rapidly than non-organelle-targeted genes. Together, these global analyses provide insights into the complex evolutionary dynamics of allopolyploids, showing that allopolyploid subgenomes have separate evolutionary trajectories despite sharing the same nucleus, generation time, and ecological context.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.09.451712" rel="alternate" title="Global patterns of subgenome evolution in organelle-targeted genes of six allotetraploid angiosperms (65 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.07.451547</id><title>Early adaptation in a microbial community is dominated by mutualism-enhancing mutations (64 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.769744+00:00</updated><author><name>Sandeep Venkataram</name></author><author><name>Huan-Yu Kuo</name></author><author><name>Erik F. Y. Hom</name></author><author><name>Sergey Kryazhimskiy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Evolutionary dynamics in ecological communities are often repeatable, but how species interactions affect the distribution of evolutionary outcomes at different levels of biological organization is unclear. Here, we use barcode lineage tracking to experimentally address this gap in a facultatively mutualistic community formed by the alga &lt;italic&gt;Chlamydomonas reinhardtii&lt;/italic&gt; and the yeast &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt;. We find that interactions with the alga alter the magnitude but not the sign of the fitness effects of adaptive mutations in yeast, changing the distribution of mutants contending for fixation. In the presence of alga, most contending mutants reinforce the mutualism and make evolution more repeatable at the community level. Thus, ecological interactions not only alter the trajectory of evolution but also dictate its repeatability at multiple levels of biological organization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.07.451547" rel="alternate" title="Early adaptation in a microbial community is dominated by mutualism-enhancing mutations (64 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.451348</id><title>Rapid speciation and karyotype evolution in Orthoptera (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.769937+00:00</updated><author><name>Octavio M. Palacios-Gimenez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To test the hypothesis that high speciation rate in groups is coupled with high rate of karyotype evolution but also that younger groups having a higher rate of karyotypic diversity, I estimated rates of speciation and rates of karyotype evolution in 1,177 species belonging to 26 families in the insect order Orthoptera. Rates of karyotype evolution were estimated using the diploid number and the number of chromosome arms (fundamental number) from published karyotypes of Orthoptera. Rates of speciation were quantified considering the number of species examined karyotypically in each family, the most recent common ancestor of each family and the information about extinction rate. The rate of speciation was strongly correlated with rate of karyotype evolution and the average rates of speciation was nearly ~177 times higher than the background rate estimated for Orthoptera based on acoustic communication using phylogenomic data, as well as 8.4 and 35.6 times higher than the estimated speciation rate in vertebrates and bivalve mollusks respectively, indicating that Orthoptera has evolved very fast at chromosomal level. The findings supported the hypothesis of a high speciation rate in lineages with high rate of chromosomal evolution but there were not evidences that younger groups tended to have higher rate of karyotypic diversity. Furthermore, rates of karyotype evolution most closely fitted the punctuational evolutionary model indicating the existence of long periods of stasis of karyotype change with most karyotype change occurring quickly over short evolutionary times. I discussed genetic drift, divergent selection and meiotic drive as potential biological mechanisms to explain karyotype evolution allowing or impeding for the fixation of chromosomal rearrangements and in turn speciation in orthopterans lineages.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.451348" rel="alternate" title="Rapid speciation and karyotype evolution in Orthoptera (14 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>