<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.160177+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461741</id><title>FSTruct: an FST -based tool for measuring ancestry variation in inference of population structure (45 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.163311+00:00</updated><author><name>Maike L. Morrison</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Alcala</name></author><author><name>Noah A. Rosenberg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In model-based inference of population structure from individual-level genetic data, individuals are assigned membership coefficients in a series of statistical clusters generated by clustering algorithms. Distinct patterns of variability in membership coefficients can be produced for different groups of individuals, for example, representing different predefined populations, sampling sites, or time periods. Such variability can be difficult to capture in a single numerical value; membership coefficient vectors are multivariate and potentially incommensurable across groups, as the number of clusters over which individuals are distributed can vary among groups of interest. Further, two groups might share few clusters in common, so that membership coefficient vectors are concentrated on different clusters. We introduce a method for measuring the variability of membership coefficients of individuals in a predefined group, making use of an analogy between variability across individuals in membership coefficient vectors and variation across populations in allele frequency vectors. We show that in a model in which membership coefficient vectors in a population follow a Dirichlet distribution, the measure increases linearly with a parameter describing the variance of a specified component of the membership vector. We apply the approach, which makes use of a normalized &lt;italic&gt;F&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;italic&gt;ST&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; statistic, to data on inferred population structure in three example scenarios. We also introduce a bootstrap test for equivalence of two or more groups in their level of membership coefficient variability. Our methods are implemented in the R package FSTruct.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461741" rel="alternate" title="FSTruct: an FST -based tool for measuring ancestry variation in inference of population structure (45 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461980</id><title>Gene expression phylogenies and ancestral transcriptome reconstruction resolves major transitions in the origins of pregnancy (33 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.163900+00:00</updated><author><name>Katie Mika</name></author><author><name>Camilla M. Whittington</name></author><author><name>Bronwyn M. McAllan</name></author><author><name>Vincent J. Lynch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Structural and physiological changes in the female reproductive system underlie the origins of pregnancy in multiple vertebrate lineages. In mammals, for example, the glandular portion of the lower reproductive tract has transformed into a structure specialized for supporting fetal development. These specializations range from relatively simple maternal provisioning in egg-laying monotremes to an elaborate suite of traits that support intimate maternal-fetal interactions in Eutherians. Among these traits are the maternal decidua and fetal component of the placenta, but there is considerable uncertainty about how these structures evolved. We identified the origins of pregnancy utilizing ancestral transcriptome reconstruction to infer functional evolution of the maternal-fetal interface. Remarkably, we found that maternal gene expression profiles are correlated with degree of placental invasion. These results indicate that an epitheliochorial-like placenta evolved early in the mammalian stem-lineage and that the ancestor of Eutherians had a hemochorial placenta, and suggest maternal control of placental invasiveness. Collectively, these data resolve major transitions in the evolution of pregnancy and indicate that ancestral transcriptome reconstruction can be used to study the function of ancestral cell, tissue, and organ systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461980" rel="alternate" title="Gene expression phylogenies and ancestral transcriptome reconstruction resolves major transitions in the origins of pregnancy (33 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461419</id><title>Deleterious Mutations Accumulate Faster in Allopolyploid than Diploid Cotton (Gossypium) and Unequally Between Subgenomes (33 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.164688+00:00</updated><author><name>Justin L. Conover</name></author><author><name>Jonathan F. Wendel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Whole genome duplication (polyploidization) is among the most dramatic mutational processes in nature, so understanding how natural selection differs in polyploids relative to diploids is an important goal. Population genetics theory predicts that recessive deleterious mutations accumulate faster in allopolyploids than diploids due to the masking effect of redundant gene copies, but this prediction is hitherto unconfirmed. Here, we use the cotton genus (&lt;italic&gt;Gossypium&lt;/italic&gt;), which contains seven allopolyploids derived from a single polyploidization event 1-2 million years ago, to investigate deleterious mutation accumulation. We use two methods of identifying deleterious mutations at the nucleotide and amino acid level, along with whole-genome resequencing of 43 individuals spanning six allopolyploid species and their two diploid progenitors, to demonstrate that deleterious mutations accumulate faster in allopolyploids than in their diploid progenitors. We find that, unlike what would be expected under models of demographic changes alone, strongly deleterious mutations show the biggest difference between ploidy levels, and this effect diminishes for moderately and mildly deleterious mutations. We further show that the proportion of nonsynonymous mutations that are deleterious differs between the two co-resident subgenomes in the allopolyploids, suggesting that homoeologous masking acts unequally between subgenomes. Our results provide a genome-wide perspective on classic notions of the significance of gene duplication that likely are broadly applicable to allopolyploids, with implications for our understanding of the evolutionary fate of deleterious mutations. Finally, we note that some measures of selection (e.g. dN/dS, &lt;bold&gt;π&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;/&lt;bold&gt;π&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;sub&gt;S&lt;/sub&gt;) may be biased when species of different ploidy levels are compared.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461419" rel="alternate" title="Deleterious Mutations Accumulate Faster in Allopolyploid than Diploid Cotton (Gossypium) and Unequally Between Subgenomes (33 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461856</id><title>Rapid evolution and strain turnover in the infant gut microbiome (32 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.165213+00:00</updated><author><name>Daisy W. Chen</name></author><author><name>Nandita R. Garud</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;While the ecological dynamics of the infant gut microbiome have been intensely studied, relatively little is known about the evolutionary dynamics in the infant gut microbiome. Here we analyze longitudinal fecal metagenomic data from &amp;gt;700 infants and their mothers over the first year of life and find that the evolutionary dynamics in infant gut microbiomes are distinct from that of adults. We find evidence for almost 100-fold increase in the rate of evolution and strain turnover in the infant gut compared to healthy adults, with the mother-infant transition at delivery being a particularly dynamic period in which gene loss dominates. Within a few months after birth, these dynamics stabilize, and gene gains become increasingly frequent as the microbiome matures. We furthermore find that evolutionary changes in infants show signatures of being seeded by a mixture of &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; mutations and transmissions of pre-evolved lineages from the broader family. Several of these evolutionary changes occur in parallel in multiple infants, highlighting candidate genes that may play important roles in the development of the infant gut microbiome. Our results point to a picture of a volatile infant gut microbiome characterized by rapid evolutionary and ecological change in the early days of life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461856" rel="alternate" title="Rapid evolution and strain turnover in the infant gut microbiome (32 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461846</id><title>Gene flow biases population genetic inference of recombination rate (32 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.165670+00:00</updated><author><name>K. Samuk</name></author><author><name>M.A.F. Noor</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Accurate estimates of the rate of recombination are key to understanding a host of evolutionary processes as well as the evolution of recombination rate itself. Model-based population genetic methods that infer recombination rates from patterns of linkage disequilibrium (LD) in the genome have become a popular method to estimate rates of recombination. However, these LD-based methods make a variety of simplifying assumptions about the populations of interest that are often not met in natural populations. One such assumption is the absence of gene flow from other populations. Here, we use forward-time population genetic simulations of isolation-with-migration scenarios to explore how gene flow affects the accuracy of LD-based estimators of recombination rate. We find that moderate levels of gene flow can result in either the overestimation or underestimation of recombination rates by up to 20-50% depending on the timing of divergence. We also find that these biases can affect the detection of interpopulation differences in recombination rate, causing both false positive and false negatives depending on the scenario. We discuss future possibilities for mitigating these biases and recommend that investigators exercise caution and confirm that their study populations meet assumptions before deploying these methods.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461846" rel="alternate" title="Gene flow biases population genetic inference of recombination rate (32 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.19.460991</id><title>Odorant receptor copy number change, co-expression, and positive selection establish peripheral coding differences between fly species (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.165977+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas O. Auer</name></author><author><name>Raquel Álvarez-Ocaña</name></author><author><name>Steeve Cruchet</name></author><author><name>Richard Benton</name></author><author><name>J. Roman Arguello</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1.&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Animals sample their chemical environment using sensory neurons that express diverse chemosensory receptors, which trigger responses when they bind environmental molecules [1–7]. In addition to modifications in the ligand binding properties of receptors, chemosensory receptor evolution is characterized by copy number changes, often resulting in large gene family size differences between species [8–13]. Though chemosensory receptor expansions and contractions are frequently described, it is unknown how this is accompanied by changes in the neural circuitry in which they are expressed. Among &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt;’s chemosensory receptor families, the Odorant receptors (Ors) are ideal for addressing this question because, other than an essential co-receptor (Orco [14]), a large majority of Ors are uniquely expressed in single olfactory sensory neuron (OSN) populations. Between-species changes in Or copy number, therefore, may indicate diversification or reduction of peripheral sensory neuron populations. To test this possibility, we focused on a rapidly duplicated/deleted Or subfamily - named &lt;italic&gt;Or67a&lt;/italic&gt; - within &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; and its most closely-related sister species (&lt;italic&gt;D. simulans, D. sechellia&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;D. mauritiana&lt;/italic&gt;). Evolutionary genetic analyses and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; physiological assays demonstrate that the common ancestor of these four species possessed three &lt;italic&gt;Or67a&lt;/italic&gt; paralogs that had already diverged adaptively in their odor-evoked responses. Following the group’s speciation events, two &lt;italic&gt;Or67a&lt;/italic&gt; paralogs were independently lost in &lt;italic&gt;D. melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;D. sechellia&lt;/italic&gt;, with positive selection continuing to act on the intact genes. Instead of the expected singular expression of each of the functionally diverged Ors in different neurons, we found that the three &lt;italic&gt;D. simulans Or67a&lt;/italic&gt; paralogs are co-expressed in the same cells. Thus, while neuroanatomy is conserved between these species, independent selection on co-expressed receptors has contributed to species-specific peripheral coding of olfactory information. This work reveals a model of adaptive change previously not considered for olfactory evolution and raises the possibility that similar processes may be operating among the largely uninvestigated cases of Or co-expression [2, 15–18].&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.19.460991" rel="alternate" title="Odorant receptor copy number change, co-expression, and positive selection establish peripheral coding differences between fly species (21 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.460855</id><title>Anti-Bat Ultrasound Production in Moths is Globally and Phylogenetically Widespread (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.170331+00:00</updated><author><name>JR Barber</name></author><author><name>D Plotkin</name></author><author><name>JJ Rubin</name></author><author><name>NT Homziak</name></author><author><name>BC Leavell</name></author><author><name>P Houlihan</name></author><author><name>KA Miner</name></author><author><name>JW Breinholt</name></author><author><name>B Quirk-Royal</name></author><author><name>PS Padrón</name></author><author><name>M Nunez</name></author><author><name>AY Kawahara</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Warning signals are well known in the visual system, but rare in other modalities. Some moths produce ultrasonic sounds to warn bats of noxious taste or to mimic unpalatable models. Here we report results from a long-term study across the globe, assaying moth response to playback of bat echolocation. We tested 252 genera, spanning most families of large-bodied moths, and outline anti-bat ultrasound production in 52 genera, with eight new subfamily origins described. Based on acoustic analysis of ultrasonic emissions and palatability experiments with bats, it seems that acoustic warning and mimicry are the &lt;italic&gt;raison d’etre&lt;/italic&gt; for sound production in most moths. However, some moths use high-density ultrasound capable of jamming bat sonar. In fact, we find preliminary evidence of independent origins of sonar jamming in at least six subfamilies. Palatability data indicates that jamming and warning are not mutually exclusive strategies. To explore the possible organization of anti-bat warning sounds into acoustic mimicry rings, we intensively studied a community of moths in Ecuador and found five distinct acoustic clusters using machine learning algorithms. While these data represent an early understanding of acoustic aposematism and mimicry across this megadiverse insect order, it is likely that ultrasonically-signaling moths comprise one of the largest mimicry complexes on earth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.460855" rel="alternate" title="Anti-Bat Ultrasound Production in Moths is Globally and Phylogenetically Widespread (12 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461667</id><title>Transoceanic voyages of drywood termites (Isoptera: Kalotermitidae) inferred from extant and extinct species (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.171336+00:00</updated><author><name>A. Buček</name></author><author><name>M. Wang</name></author><author><name>J. Šobotník</name></author><author><name>D Sillam-Dussès</name></author><author><name>N. Mizumoto</name></author><author><name>P. Stiblík</name></author><author><name>C. Clitheroe</name></author><author><name>T. Lu</name></author><author><name>J. J. González Plaza</name></author><author><name>A. Mohagan</name></author><author><name>J. J. Rafanomezantsoa</name></author><author><name>B. Fisher</name></author><author><name>M. S Engel</name></author><author><name>Y. Roisin</name></author><author><name>T. A. Evans</name></author><author><name>R. Scheffrahn</name></author><author><name>T. Bourguignon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Termites are major decomposers of organic matter in terrestrial ecosystems and the second most diverse lineage of social insects. The Kalotermitidae, the second-largest termite family, are widely distributed across tropical and subtropical ecosystems, where they typically live in small colonies confined to single wood items inhabited by individuals with no foraging abilities. How the Kalotermitidae have acquired their global distribution patterns remains unresolved. Similarly, it is unclear whether foraging is ancestral to Kalotermitidae or was secondarily acquired in a few species. These questions can be addressed in a phylogenetic framework. We inferred time-calibrated phylogenetic trees of Kalotermitidae using mitochondrial genomes and nuclear ribosomal RNA genes of ∼120 species, about 27% of kalotermitid diversity, including representatives of 22 of the 23 kalotermitid genera. We found that extant kalotermitids shared a common ancestor 81 Mya (72–91 Mya 95% HPD), indicating that a few disjunctions among early-diverging kalotermitid lineages may predate Gondwana breakup. However, most of the ∼40 disjunctions among biogeographic realms were dated at less than 50 Mya, indicating that transoceanic dispersals, and more recently human-mediated dispersals, have been the major drivers of the global distribution of Kalotermitidae. Our phylogeny also revealed that the capacity to forage is often found in early-diverging kalotermitid lineages, implying that the ancestors of Kalotermitidae were able to forage among multiple wood pieces. Our phylogenetic estimates provide a platform for a critical taxonomic revision of the family and for future comparative analyses of Kalotermitidae.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461667" rel="alternate" title="Transoceanic voyages of drywood termites (Isoptera: Kalotermitidae) inferred from extant and extinct species (12 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461617</id><title>Genetic studies of human-chimpanzee divergence using stem cell fusions (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.172403+00:00</updated><author><name>Janet H.T. Song</name></author><author><name>Rachel L. Grant</name></author><author><name>Veronica C. Behrens</name></author><author><name>Marek Kucka</name></author><author><name>Garrett A. Roberts Kingman</name></author><author><name>Volker Soltys</name></author><author><name>Yingguang Frank Chan</name></author><author><name>David M. Kingsley</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Complete genome sequencing has identified millions of DNA changes that differ between humans and chimpanzees. Although a subset of these changes likely underlies important phenotypic differences between humans and chimpanzees, it is currently difficult to distinguish causal from incidental changes and to map specific phenotypes to particular genome locations. To facilitate further genetic study of human-chimpanzee divergence, we have generated human and chimpanzee auto-tetraploids and allo-tetraploids by fusing induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs) of each species. The resulting tetraploid iPSCs can be stably maintained and retain the ability to differentiate along ectoderm, mesoderm, and endoderm lineages. RNA sequencing identifies thousands of genes whose expression differs between humans and chimpanzees when assessed in single-species diploid or auto-tetraploid iPSCs. Analysis of gene expression patterns in inter-specific allo-tetraploid iPSCs shows that human-chimpanzee expression differences arise from substantial contributions of both &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-acting changes linked to the genes themselves, and &lt;italic&gt;trans&lt;/italic&gt;-acting changes elsewhere in the genome. To enable further genetic mapping of species differences, we tested chemical treatments for stimulating genome-wide mitotic recombination between human and chimpanzee chromosomes, and CRISPR methods for inducing species-specific changes on particular chromosomes in allo-tetraploid cells. We successfully generated derivative cells with nested deletions or inter-specific recombination on the X chromosome. These studies identify a long distance &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-regulatory domain of the Fragile X-associated gene (&lt;italic&gt;FMR1&lt;/italic&gt;), confirm an important role for the X chromosome in trans-regulation of other expression differences, and illustrate the potential of this system for more detailed mapping of the molecular basis of human and chimpanzee evolution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Comparative studies of humans and chimpanzees have revealed many anatomical, physiological, behavioral, and molecular differences. However, it has been challenging to map these differences to particular chromosome regions. Here, we develop a genetic approach in fused stem cell lines that makes it possible to map human-chimpanzee molecular and cellular differences to specific regions of the genome. We illustrate this approach by mapping chromosome regions responsible for species-specific gene expression differences in fused tetraploid cells. This approach is general, and could be used in the future to map the genomic changes that control many other humanchimpanzee differences in various cell types or organoids &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461617" rel="alternate" title="Genetic studies of human-chimpanzee divergence using stem cell fusions (11 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462250</id><title>Long-term experimental evolution decouples size and production costs in Escherichia coli (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.172923+00:00</updated><author><name>Dustin J. Marshall</name></author><author><name>Martino Malerba</name></author><author><name>Thomas Lines</name></author><author><name>Aysha L. Sezmis</name></author><author><name>Chowdhury M. Hasan</name></author><author><name>Richard E. Lenski</name></author><author><name>Michael J. McDonald</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Body size covaries with population dynamics across life’s domains. Theory holds that metabolism imposes fundamental constraints on the coevolution of size and demography. However, studies of interspecific patterns are confounded by other factors that covary with size and demography, and experimental tests of the causal links remain elusive. Here we leverage a 60,000-generation experiment in which &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; populations evolved larger cells to examine intraspecific metabolic scaling and correlations with demographic parameters. Metabolic theory successfully predicted the relations among size, metabolism, and maximum population density, with strong support for Damuth’s law of energy equivalence in this experiment. In contrast, populations of larger cells grew faster than those of smaller cells, contradicting the fundamental assumption that costs of production should increase proportionately with size. The finding that the costs of production are substantially decoupled from size requires re-examining the evolutionary drivers and ecological consequences of biological size more generally.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462250" rel="alternate" title="Long-term experimental evolution decouples size and production costs in Escherichia coli (11 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461574</id><title>Negative regulation of IMD contributes to disease tolerance during systemic bacterial infection in Drosophila (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.173258+00:00</updated><author><name>Arun Prakash</name></author><author><name>Katy M. Monteith</name></author><author><name>Pedro F. Vale</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Disease tolerance is an infection phenotype where hosts show relatively high health despite harbouring elevated pathogen loads. Compared to the mechanisms of immune clearance our knowledge of the mechanisms underlying increased tolerance remains incomplete. Variation in the ability to reduce immunopathology may explain why some hosts can tolerate higher pathogen burdens with reduced pathology. Negative immune regulation would therefore appear to be a clear candidate for a mechanism underlying disease tolerance but this has not been tested directly for bacterial infections. Here, we examined how the negative regulation of the immune deficiency (IMD) pathway affects disease tolerance in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; when infected with the gram-negative bacterial pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas entomophila&lt;/italic&gt;. We find that UAS&lt;sup&gt;RNAi&lt;/sup&gt;-mediated reduced expression of the negative regulators of IMD (&lt;italic&gt;pirk&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;caudal&lt;/italic&gt;) severely reduced the ability to tolerate infection in both males and females across a wide range of infectious doses. While flies unable to regulate the IMD response exhibited higher expression of antimicrobial peptides and lower bacterial loads as expected, this was not accompanied by a proportional reduction in mortality. Instead, tolerance (measured as fly survival relative to its microbe load) was drastically reduced, likely due to the combination of increased immunopathology and cytotoxicity of elevated AMP expression. Our results therefore highlight that in addition to regulating an efficient pathogen clearance response, negative regulators of IMD also contribute to disease tolerance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461574" rel="alternate" title="Negative regulation of IMD contributes to disease tolerance during systemic bacterial infection in Drosophila (10 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461914</id><title>Fitness landscape analysis reveals that the wild type allele is sub-optimal and mutationally robust (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.173517+00:00</updated><author><name>Tzahi Gabzi</name></author><author><name>Yitzhak Pilpel</name></author><author><name>Tamar Friedlander</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fitness landscape mapping and the prediction of evolutionary trajectories on these landscapes are major tasks in evolutionary biology research. Evolutionary dynamics is tightly linked to the landscape topography, but this relation is not straightforward. Models predict different evolutionary outcomes depending on mutation rates: high-fitness genotypes should dominate the population under low mutation rates and lower-fitness, mutationally robust (also called ‘flat’) genotypes - at higher mutation rates. Yet, so far, flat genotypes have been demonstrated in very few cases, particularly in viruses. The quantitative conditions for their emergence were studied only in simplified single-locus, two-peak landscapes. In particular, it is unclear whether within the same genome some genes can be flat while the remaining ones are fit. Here, we analyze a previously measured fitness landscape of a yeast tRNA gene. We found that the wild type allele is sub-optimal, but is mutationally robust (‘flat’). Using computer simulations, we estimated the critical mutation rate in which transition from fit to flat allele should occur for a gene with such characteristics. We then used a scaling argument to extrapolate this critical mutation rate for a full genome, assuming the same mutation rate for all genes. Finally, we propose that while the majority of genes are still selected to be fittest, there are a few mutation hot-spots like the tRNA, for which the mutationally robust flat allele is favored by selection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461914" rel="alternate" title="Fitness landscape analysis reveals that the wild type allele is sub-optimal and mutationally robust (10 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461604</id><title>Gene identification and genome annotation in Caenorhabditis briggsae by high throughput 5’ RNA end determination (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.173764+00:00</updated><author><name>Nikita Jhaveri</name></author><author><name>Wouter van den Berg</name></author><author><name>Byung Joon Hwang</name></author><author><name>Hans-Michael Muller</name></author><author><name>Paul W. Sternberg</name></author><author><name>Bhagwati P. Gupta</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The nematode &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis briggsae&lt;/italic&gt; is routinely used in comparative and evolutionary studies involving its well-known cousin &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt;. The &lt;italic&gt;C. briggsae&lt;/italic&gt; genome sequence has accelerated research by facilitating the generation of new resources, tools, and functional studies of genes. While substantial progress has been made in predicting genes and start sites, experimental evidence is still lacking in many cases. Here, we report an improved annotation of the &lt;italic&gt;C. briggsae&lt;/italic&gt; genome using the Trans-spliced Exon Coupled RNA End Determination (TEC-RED) technique. In addition to identifying 5’ ends of expressed genes, the technique has enabled the discovery of operons and paralogs. Application of TEC-RED yielded 10,243 unique 5’ end sequences with matches in the &lt;italic&gt;C. briggsae&lt;/italic&gt; genome. Of these, 6,395 were found to represent 4,252 unique genes along with 362 paralogs and 52 previously unknown exons. The method also identified 493 operons, including 334 that are fully supported by tags. Additionally, two SL1-type operons were discovered. Comparisons with &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; revealed that 40% of operons are conserved. Further, we identified 73 novel operons, including 12 that entirely lack orthologs in &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt;. Among other results, we found that 14 genes are trans-spliced exclusively in &lt;italic&gt;C. briggsae&lt;/italic&gt; compared with &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt;. Altogether, the data presented here serves as a rich resource to aid biological studies involving &lt;italic&gt;C. briggsae&lt;/italic&gt;. Additionally, this work demonstrates the use of TEC-RED for the first time in a non-&lt;italic&gt;elegans&lt;/italic&gt; nematode and suggests that it could apply to other organisms with a trans-splicing reaction from spliced leader RNA.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461604" rel="alternate" title="Gene identification and genome annotation in Caenorhabditis briggsae by high throughput 5’ RNA end determination (9 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461382</id><title>Idiosyncratic epistasis leads to global fitness-correlated trends (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.174055+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher W. Bakerlee</name></author><author><name>Alex N. Nguyen Ba</name></author><author><name>Yekaterina Shulgina</name></author><author><name>Jose I. Rojas Echenique</name></author><author><name>Michael M. Desai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Epistasis can dramatically affect evolutionary trajectories. In recent decades, protein-level fitness landscapes have revealed pervasive idiosyncratic epistasis among specific mutations. In contrast, other work has found ubiquitous and apparently non-specific patterns of global diminishing-returns and increasing-costs epistasis among mutations across the genome. Here, we use a hierarchical CRISPR gene drive system to construct all combinations of 10 missense mutations from across the genome in budding yeast, and measure their fitness in six environments. We show that the resulting fitness landscapes exhibit global fitness-correlated trends, but that these trends emerge from specific idiosyncratic interactions. This provides the first experimental validation of recent theoretical work that has argued that fitness-correlated trends are the generic consequence of idiosyncratic epistasis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A genome-spanning fitness landscape reveals how idiosyncratic genetic interactions lead to global epistatic patterns.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461382" rel="alternate" title="Idiosyncratic epistasis leads to global fitness-correlated trends (8 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461822</id><title>Stochastic modeling uncovers a novel mechanism underlying the evolution of mutation rates in sexually reproducing populations (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.174336+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrii Rozhok</name></author><author><name>Niles Eldredge</name></author><author><name>James DeGregori</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Natural selection is believed to universally work to lower mutation rates (MR) due to the negative impact of mutations on individual fitness. Mutator alleles have only been found to be co-selected by genetic linkage with adaptive alleles in prokaryotes. Sexual reproduction substantially reduces genetic linkage, allowing selection to effectively eradicate mutator alleles. The current understanding, therefore, is that in sexually reproducing populations selection always works to lower MR, limited by the effective population size that determines the overall selection efficiency. In the present paper, we apply a Monte Carlo model of a sexually reproducing population and demonstrate that selection acting on MR does not universally favor lower MR but depends on the mode of selection acting on adaptive phenotypic traits. We demonstrate a unique previously unreported co-selective process that can drive the evolution of higher MR in sexually reproducing populations. Our results show that MR evolution is significantly influenced by multigenic inheritance of both MR and adaptive traits that are under selection. Our results also show that, contrary to the generally accepted axiom, population size appears not to affect the strength of selection uniformly but likely forms an intra-population gradient that generates a “biased sampling” process that has an opposite effect on selection strength and thus modulates or even negates the effect of population size on MR evolution. Based on our results, we propose an expanded population genetics theory of the evolution of mutation rates in sexually reproducing organisms. Our results have potential implications for understanding processes underlying rapid adaptive change in speciation and related macroevolutionary patterns.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461822" rel="alternate" title="Stochastic modeling uncovers a novel mechanism underlying the evolution of mutation rates in sexually reproducing populations (8 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461796</id><title>The chromosomal distribution of sex-biased microRNAs in Drosophila is non-adaptive (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.174580+00:00</updated><author><name>Antonio Marco</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genes are often differentially expressed between males and females. In &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt;, the analysis of sex-biased microRNAs (short non-coding regulatory molecules) has revealed striking differences with protein-coding genes. Mainly, the X chromosome is enriched in male-biased microRNA genes, although it is depleted of male-biased protein-coding genes. The paucity of male-biased genes in the X chromosome is generally explained by an evolutionary process called demasculinization. I suggest that the excess of male-biased microRNAs in the X chromosome is due to high-rates of de novo emergence of microRNAs, a tendency of novel microRNAs in the X chromosome to be expressed in testis, and to a lack of a demasculinization process. To test this hypothesis I analysed the expression profile of microRNAs in males, females and gonads in &lt;italic&gt;D. pseudoobscura&lt;/italic&gt;, in which an autosome translocated into the X chromosome effectively becoming part of a sex chromosome (neo-X). I found that the pattern of sex-biased expression is generally conserved between &lt;italic&gt;D. melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;D. pseudoobscura&lt;/italic&gt;. Also, orthologous microRNAs in both species conserve their chromosomal location, indicating that there is no evidence of demasculinization or other inter-chromosomal movement of microRNAs. &lt;italic&gt;D. pseudoobscura&lt;/italic&gt;-specific microRNAs in the neo-X chromosome tend to be male-biased and particularly expressed in testis. In summary, the apparent paradox resulting from male-biased protein-coding genes depleted in the X chromosome and an enrichment in male-biased microRNAs is a consequence of different evolutionary dynamics between coding genes and short RNAs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461796" rel="alternate" title="The chromosomal distribution of sex-biased microRNAs in Drosophila is non-adaptive (8 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461867</id><title>Involvement of non-LTR retrotransposons in the cancer incidence and lifespan of mammals (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.174796+00:00</updated><author><name>Marco Ricci</name></author><author><name>Valentina Peona</name></author><author><name>Cristian Taccioli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The natural occurrence of closely related species that show drastic differences in lifespan and cancer incidence raised the interest in finding the particular adaptations and genomic characteristics underlying the evolution of long lifespans. Studies on transposable elements (TEs) have more and more linked them to ageing and cancer development. In this study, we compared the TE content and dynamics in the genomes of four Rodent and six Chiroptera species that show very different lifespans and cancer susceptibility including the long-lived and refractory to cancer naked mole rat (&lt;italic&gt;Heterocephalus glaber&lt;/italic&gt;), the long-lived fruit bats (&lt;italic&gt;Pteropus vampyrus&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;Rousettus aegypticaus&lt;/italic&gt;) and the short-lived velvety free-tailed bat (&lt;italic&gt;Molossus molossus&lt;/italic&gt;). By analysing the patterns of recent TE accumulation (TEs that are potentially currently active) in high-quality genome assemblies, we found that the shared genomic characteristics between long-lived species that are refractory to cancer, is the strong suppression, or negative selection against the accumulation, of non-LTR retrotransposons. All the short-lived species did show a recent accumulation of these TEs. Non-LTR retrotransposons have been often found to take part in the immune response of the host against viral infections, but their dysregulation can lead to phenomena of “sterile inflammation” and “inflammageing”. Therefore, we hypothesise that the uncontrolled non-LTR retrotransposon activity is an important factor explaining the evolution of shorter lifespans in both Rodents and Chiroptera species and potentially in all mammals. Finally, these results suggest that non-LTR retrotransposons can be agents promoting cancer and ageing in mammals thus they may be targets of future oncological therapies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461867" rel="alternate" title="Involvement of non-LTR retrotransposons in the cancer incidence and lifespan of mammals (8 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461377</id><title>Drivers of an epic radiation: the role of climate and islands in species diversification and reproductive-mode evolution of Old-World tree frogs (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.175130+00:00</updated><author><name>Gajaba Ellepola</name></author><author><name>Marcio R. Pie</name></author><author><name>Rohan Pethiyagoda</name></author><author><name>James Hanken</name></author><author><name>Madhava Meegaskumbura</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Although large diversifications of species occur unevenly across space and evolutionary lineages, the relative importance of their driving mechanisms, such as climate, ecological opportunity and key innovations, remains poorly understood. Here, we explore the remarkable diversification of rhacophorid frogs, which represent six percent of global amphibian diversity, utilize four distinct reproductive modes, and span a climatically variable area across mainland Asia, associated continental islands, and Africa. Using a complete species-level phylogeny, we find near-constant diversification rates but a highly uneven distribution of species richness. Montane regions on islands and some mainland regions have higher phylogenetic diversity and unique assemblages of taxa; we identify these as cool-wet refugia. Starting from a centre of origin, rhacophorids reached these distant refugia by adapting to new climatic conditions (‘niche evolution’-dominant), especially following the origin of key innovations such as terrestrial reproduction (in the Late Eocene) or by dispersal during periods of favourable climate (‘niche conservatism’-dominant).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461377" rel="alternate" title="Drivers of an epic radiation: the role of climate and islands in species diversification and reproductive-mode evolution of Old-World tree frogs (7 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461217</id><title>Means, motive, and opportunity for biological invasions: genetic introgression in a fungal pathogen (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.175427+00:00</updated><author><name>Flávia Rogério</name></author><author><name>Cock Van Oosterhout</name></author><author><name>Maisa Ciampi-Guillardi</name></author><author><name>Fernando Henrique Correr</name></author><author><name>Guilherme Kenichi Hosaka</name></author><author><name>Sandrine Cros-Arteil</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Rodrigues Alves Margarido</name></author><author><name>Nelson S. Massola</name></author><author><name>Pierre Gladieux</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Invasions by fungal plant pathogens pose a significant threat to the health of agriculture ecosystems. Despite limited standing genetic variation, many invasive fungal species can adapt and spread rapidly, resulting in significant losses in crop yields. Here, we report on the population genomics of &lt;italic&gt;Colletotrichum truncatum&lt;/italic&gt;, a polyphagous pathogen that can infect more than 460 plant species, and an invasive pathogen on soybean in Brazil. We study the whole-genome sequences of 18 isolates representing 10 fields from two major regions of soybean production. We show that Brazilian &lt;italic&gt;C. truncatum&lt;/italic&gt; is subdivided into three phylogenetically distinct lineages that exchange genetic variation through hybridization. Introgression affects 2 to 30% of the nucleotides of genomes and varies widely between the lineages. We find that introgressed regions comprise secreted protein-encoding genes, suggesting possible co-evolutionary targets for selection in those regions. We highlight the inherent vulnerability of genetically uniform crops in the agro-ecological environment, particularly when faced with pathogens that can take full advantage of the opportunities offered by an increasingly globalized world. Finally, we discuss “The Means, Motive, and Opportunity” of fungal pathogens and how they can become invasive species of crops. We call for more population genomic studies because such analyses can help identify geographic areas and pathogens that pose a risk, thereby helping to inform control strategies to better protect crops in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461217" rel="alternate" title="Means, motive, and opportunity for biological invasions: genetic introgression in a fungal pathogen (6 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.19.460969</id><title>The Siberian wild apple, Malus baccata (L.) Borkh., is an additional contributor to the genomes of cultivated European and Chinese apples (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.177778+00:00</updated><author><name>Xilong Chen</name></author><author><name>Amandine Cornille</name></author><author><name>Na An</name></author><author><name>Libo Xing</name></author><author><name>Juanjuan Ma</name></author><author><name>Caiping Zhao</name></author><author><name>Yibin Wang</name></author><author><name>Mingyu Han</name></author><author><name>Dong Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It is crucial to understand domestication to unravel the evolutionary processes that shape the divergence of populations. Differences in life-history traits have probably led to marked differences in the mode and speed of evolution between trees and annuals, particularly the extent of crop-wild gene flow during domestication. Apple is an iconic tree and major fruit crop grown worldwide. The contribution of wild apple species to the genetic makeup of the cultivated apple genome remains a topic of intense investigations. We used population genomics in combination with SNPs to investigate the contributions of the two known wild apple relatives, &lt;italic&gt;Malus sylvestris&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Malus sieversii&lt;/italic&gt;, and a supposed contributor, &lt;italic&gt;Malus baccata&lt;/italic&gt;, to European and Chinese rootstock and dessert genomes, with a focus on the extent of wild-crop gene flow during apple domestication. We showed that the European dessert and rootstock apples form a specific gene pool, whereas the Chinese dessert and rootstock apples were a mixture of three wild gene pools. Coalescent-based inferences and gene flow estimates indicated that &lt;italic&gt;M. baccata&lt;/italic&gt; is an additional contributor to the genome of both European and Chinese cultivated apples through wild-to-crop introgressions. We also confirmed previous results on the contribution of &lt;italic&gt;M. sylvestris&lt;/italic&gt; to the cultivated apple genome, and provided insights into the origin of the apple rootstock. This study further demonstrates the role of gene flow during apple domestication, as seen in other woody perennials, and show that domestication of the apple tree involved several wild apple species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.19.460969" rel="alternate" title="The Siberian wild apple, Malus baccata (L.) Borkh., is an additional contributor to the genomes of cultivated European and Chinese apples (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461223</id><title>Genetic barriers to gene flow separate divergent substitution rates across a butterfly hybrid zone (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.178666+00:00</updated><author><name>Tianzhu Xiong</name></author><author><name>Xueyan Li</name></author><author><name>Masaya Yago</name></author><author><name>James Mallet</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Substitution rate defines the fundamental timescale of molecular evolution which often varies in a species-specific manner. However, it is unknown under what conditions lineage-specific rates can be preserved between natural populations with frequent hybridization. Here, we show in a hybrid zone between two butterflies &lt;italic&gt;Papilio syfanius&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Papilio maackii&lt;/italic&gt; that genome-wide barriers to gene flow can effectively separate different rates of molecular evolution in linked regions. The increased substitution rate in the lowland lineage can be largely explained by temperature-induced changes to the spontaneous mutation rate. A novel method based on entropy is developed to test for the existence of barrier loci using a minimal number of samples from the hybrid zone, a robust framework when system complexity far exceeds sample information. Overall, our results suggest that during the process of speciation, the separation of substitution rates can occur locally in the genome in parallel to the separation of gene pools.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461223" rel="alternate" title="Genetic barriers to gene flow separate divergent substitution rates across a butterfly hybrid zone (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461578</id><title>The Jak/Stat pathway mediates disease tolerance during systemic bacterial infection in Drosophila (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.185150+00:00</updated><author><name>Arun Prakash</name></author><author><name>Mickael Bonnet</name></author><author><name>Katy M. Monteith</name></author><author><name>Pedro F. Vale</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Disease tolerance describes a host’s ability to maintain health independently of the ability to clear microbe loads. However, we currently know little about the mechanisms that underlie disease tolerance or how known mechanisms of tissue damage signalling and repair may contribute to variation in tolerance. The Jak/Stat pathway plays a pivotal role in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; humoral innate immunity, signalling tissue damage and triggering cellular renewal, making it a potential mechanism underlying the disease tolerance phenotype. Here, we show that disrupting the Jak/Stat pathway in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; alters disease tolerance during &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas entomophila&lt;/italic&gt; systemic infection. Overall, flies with disrupted Jak/Stat show variation in survival that is not explained by variation in pathogen loads. For instance, mutations disrupting the function of &lt;italic&gt;ROS&lt;/italic&gt;-producing &lt;italic&gt;dual oxidase (duox&lt;/italic&gt;) or the negative regulator of Jak/Stat, &lt;italic&gt;Socs36E&lt;/italic&gt; render males less tolerant to systemic bacterial infection but not females. We also investigated whether the negative regulator of Jak/Stat, &lt;italic&gt;G9a&lt;/italic&gt; -which has previously been associated with tolerance of viral infections – is also implicated in tolerance of bacterial infection. While female flies lacking &lt;italic&gt;G9a&lt;/italic&gt; showed higher mortality and reduced bacterial clearance, disease tolerance did not differ between &lt;italic&gt;G9a&lt;/italic&gt; mutants and the wildtype. This suggests that &lt;italic&gt;G9a&lt;/italic&gt; does not affect tolerance during systemic bacterial infection as it appears to do with viral infection. Overall, our findings highlight that Jak/Stat signalling mediates disease tolerance during systemic bacterial infection and that this response differs between males and females. Our work therefore suggests that differences in Jak/Stat mediated disease tolerance may be a potential source of sexually dimorphic response to infection in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461578" rel="alternate" title="The Jak/Stat pathway mediates disease tolerance during systemic bacterial infection in Drosophila (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462139</id><title>The spread of the first introns in proto-eukaryotic paralogs (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.185579+00:00</updated><author><name>Julian Vosseberg</name></author><author><name>Michelle Schinkel</name></author><author><name>Sjoerd Gremmen</name></author><author><name>Berend Snel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spliceosomal introns are a unique feature of eukaryotic genes. Previous studies have established that many introns were present in the protein-coding genes of the last eukaryotic common ancestor (LECA). Intron positions shared between genes that duplicated before LECA could in principle provide insight into the emergence of the first introns. In this study we use ancestral intron position reconstructions in two large sets of duplicated families to systematically identify these ancient paralogous intron positions. We found that 20-35% of introns inferred to have been present in LECA were shared between paralogs. These shared introns, which likely preceded ancient duplications, were widespread across different functions, with the notable exception of nuclear transport. Since we observed a clear signal of pervasive intron loss prior to LECA, it is likely that substantially more introns were shared at the time of duplication than we can detect in LECA. The large extent of shared introns indicates an early origin of introns during eukaryogenesis and suggests an early origin of a nuclear structure, before most of the other complex eukaryotic features were established.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462139" rel="alternate" title="The spread of the first introns in proto-eukaryotic paralogs (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462138</id><title>The extended Price equation: migration and sex (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.186586+00:00</updated><author><name>Jake Brown</name></author><author><name>Jared M. Field</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Price equation provides a general partition of evolutionary change into two components. The first is usually thought to represent natural selection and the second, transmission bias. Here, we provide a new derivation of the generalised equation, which contains a largely ignored third term. Unlike the original Price equation, this extension can account for migration and mixed asexual and sexual reproduction. The notation used here expresses the generalised equation explicitly in terms of fitness, rendering this otherwise difficult third term more open to biological interpretation and use. This re-derivation also permits fundamental results, derived from the Price equation, to be more easily generalised. We take Hamilton’s rule as a case study, and provide an exact, total expression that allows for population structures like haplodiploidy. Our analysis, more generally, makes clear the previously hidden assumptions in similar fundamental results, highlighting the caution that must be taken when interpreting them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462138" rel="alternate" title="The extended Price equation: migration and sex (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461264</id><title>Origin of electroneutrality in living system (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.186884+00:00</updated><author><name>Amir Akbari</name></author><author><name>Bernhard O. Palsson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Identifying the first chemical transformations, from which life emerged is a central problem in the theories of life’s origins. These reactions would likely have been self-sustaining and self-reproductive before the advent of complex biochemical pathways found in modern organisms to synthesize lipid membranes, enzymes, or nucleic acids. Without lipid membranes and enzymes, exceedingly low concentrations of the organic intermediates of early metabolic cycles in protocells would have significantly hindered evolvability. To address this problem, we propose a mechanism, where a positive membrane potential elevates the concentration of the organic intermediates. In this mechanism, positively charged surfaces of protocell membranes due to accumulation of transition metals generate positive membrane potentials. We compute steady-state ion distributions and determine their stability in a protocell model to identify the key factors constraining achievable membrane potentials. We find that (i) violation of electroneutrality is necessary to induce nonzero membrane potentials; (ii) strategies that generate larger membrane potentials can destabilize ion distributions; and (iii) violation of electroneutrality enhances osmotic pressure and diminishes reaction efficiency, thereby driving the evolution of lipid membranes, specialized ion channels, and active transport systems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The building blocks of life are constantly synthesized and broken down through concurrent cycles of chemical transformations. Tracing these reactions back 4 billion years to their origins has been a long-standing goal of evolutionary biology. The first metabolic cycles at the origin of life must have overcome several obstacles to spontaneously start and sustain their nonequilibrium states. Notably, maintaining the concentration of organic intermediates at high levels needed to support their continued operation and subsequent evolution would have been particularly challenging in primitive cells lacking evolutionarily tuned lipid membranes and enzymes. Here, we propose a mechanism, in which the concentration of organic intermediates could have been elevated to drive early metabolic cycles forward in primitive cells with ion-permeable porous membranes under prebiotic conditions and demonstrate its feasibility in a protocell model from first principles.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461264" rel="alternate" title="Origin of electroneutrality in living system (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462072</id><title>Gigantic Genomes of Salamanders Indicate Body Temperature, not Genome Size, is the Driver of Global Methylation and 5-Methylcytosine Deamination in Vertebrates (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.187116+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Nichols Adams</name></author><author><name>Robert Daniel Denton</name></author><author><name>Rachel Lockridge Mueller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Methylation of cytosines at CpG dinucleotide sites silences transposable elements (TEs), sequences that replicate and move throughout genomes. TE abundance drives differences in genome size, but TE silencing variation across genomes of different sizes remains largely unexplored. Salamanders include most of the largest C-values — 9 to 120 Gb. We measured CpG methylation levels in salamanders with genomes ranging from 2N = ~58 Gb to 4N = ~116 Gb. We compared these levels to results from endo- and ectothermic vertebrates with more typical genomes. Salamander methylation levels are ~90%, higher than all endotherms. However, salamander methylation does not differ from the other ectotherms, despite a ~100-fold difference in nuclear DNA content. Because methylation affects the nucleotide compositional landscape through 5-methylcytosine deamination to thymine, we quantified salamander CpG dinucleotide levels and compared them to other vertebrates. Salamanders have comparable CpG levels to other ectotherms, and ectotherm levels are higher than endotherms. These data show no shift in global methylation at the base of salamanders, despite a dramatic increase in TE load and genome size. This result is reconcilable with previous studies by considering endothermy and ectothermy, which may be more important drivers of methylation in vertebrates than genome size.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462072" rel="alternate" title="Gigantic Genomes of Salamanders Indicate Body Temperature, not Genome Size, is the Driver of Global Methylation and 5-Methylcytosine Deamination in Vertebrates (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461503</id><title>On the hybrid origin of the C2Salsola divaricata agg. (Amaranthaceae) from C3 and C4 parental lineages (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.187345+00:00</updated><author><name>Delphine T. Tefarikis</name></author><author><name>Diego F. Morales-Briones</name></author><author><name>Ya Yang</name></author><author><name>Gerald Edwards</name></author><author><name>Gudrun Kadereit</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;C&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; photosynthesis is characterized by recapturing photorespiratory CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; by RuBisCO in Kranz-like cells and is therefore physiologically intermediate between C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; and C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; photosynthesis. C&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; is either interpreted as an evolutionary precursor of C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; or as the result of hybridization between a C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; and C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; lineage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We compared the expression of photosynthetic traits among populations of the &lt;italic&gt;Salsola divaricata&lt;/italic&gt; agg. (C&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) from humid subtropical to arid habitats on the coasts of the Canary Islands and Morocco, and subjected them to salt and drought treatments. We screened for enhanced C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-like expression of traits related to habitat or treatment. We estimated species trees with a transcriptome dataset of Salsoleae and explored patterns of gene tree discordance. With phylogenetic networks and hybridization analyses we tested for hybrid origin of the &lt;italic&gt;Salsola divaricata&lt;/italic&gt; agg.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We observed independent variation of photosynthetic traits within and among populations and no clear evidence for selection towards C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-like trait expression in more stressful habitats or treatments. We found reticulation and gene tree incongruencies in the Salsoleae supporting a putative hybrid origin of the &lt;italic&gt;Salsola divaricata&lt;/italic&gt; agg.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;C&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; photosynthesis in the &lt;italic&gt;Salsola divaricata&lt;/italic&gt; agg. combines traits inherited from its C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; and C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; parental lineages and seems well adapted to a wide climatic amplitude.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461503" rel="alternate" title="On the hybrid origin of the C2Salsola divaricata agg. (Amaranthaceae) from C3 and C4 parental lineages (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461657</id><title>Local and temporal adaptation to climatic change in a wild tomato species via selective sweeps (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.187639+00:00</updated><author><name>Kai Wei</name></author><author><name>Gustavo A Silva-Arias</name></author><author><name>Aurélien Tellier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Positive Darwinian selection is the driving force underpinning local (in space) and temporal (in time) adaptation, and leaves footprints of selective sweeps at the underlying major genes. These two adaptive processes are classically considered independently, so that most genomic selection scans uncover only recent sweeps underpinning spatial adaptation. However, understanding if these adaptive processes are intermingled and share common genetic bases is crucial to predict a species’ evolutionary potential, for example in response to changing environmental conditions. We use whole genome data from six populations across three different habitats of the wild tomato species &lt;italic&gt;Solanum chilense&lt;/italic&gt;, to 1) infer the past demographic history, and 2) search for genes under strong positive selection. We then correlate the demographic history, allele frequencies in space and time, the age of selection events and the reconstructed historical ecological distribution of the species over five main climatic periods spanning 150,000 years. We find evidence for several selective sweeps targeting regulatory networks involved in root hair development in low altitude, and response to photoperiod and vernalization in high altitude populations. These sweeps occur in a concerted fashion in a given regulatory gene network and only at particular time periods, thereby underpinning temporal local adaptation. These genes under positive selection provide subsequently the basis for spatial local adaptation to novel habitats when new ecological niches become available. Our results reveal the importance of jointly studying spatial and temporal adaptations in species during habitat colonization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461657" rel="alternate" title="Local and temporal adaptation to climatic change in a wild tomato species via selective sweeps (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461985</id><title>The transcriptomic signature of cyclical parthenogenesis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.187935+00:00</updated><author><name>Trung Viet Huynh</name></author><author><name>Alexander S. Hall</name></author><author><name>Sen Xu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cyclical parthenogenesis, where females can engage in sexual or asexual reproduction depending on environmental conditions, represents a novel reproductive phenotype that emerged during eukaryotic evolution. The fact that environmental conditions can trigger cyclically parthenogens to engage in distinct reproductive modes strongly suggests that gene expression plays a key role in the origin of cyclical parthenogenesis. However, the genetic basis underlying cyclical parthenogenesis remains understudied. In this study we characterize the female transcriptomic signature of sexual vs. asexual reproduction in the cyclically parthenogenetic microcrustacean &lt;italic&gt;Daphnia pulex&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;D. pulicaria&lt;/italic&gt;. Our analyses of differentially expressed genes, pathway enrichment, and GO term enrichment clearly show that compared to sexual reproduction the asexual reproductive stage is characterized by both the under-regulation of meiosis and cell-cycle genes and the up-regulation of metabolic genes. We suggest that the under-regulation of meiosis and cell-cycle genes is responsible for the origin of parthenogenesis from meiosis, whereas differentially expressed metabolic genes may mediate choice of asexual vs. sexual reproductive pathway. Furthermore, our analyses identify some cases of divergent expression among gene family members (e.g., doublesex, NOTCH2) associated with asexual or sexual reproductive stage, suggesting potential functional divergence among gene family members.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461985" rel="alternate" title="The transcriptomic signature of cyclical parthenogenesis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462554</id><title>Isotopic evidence for population dynamics in the Central Italian Copper Age and Bronze Age (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.188294+00:00</updated><author><name>Marco Romboni</name></author><author><name>Ilenia Arienzo</name></author><author><name>Mauro Antonio Di Vito</name></author><author><name>Carmine Lubritto</name></author><author><name>Monica Piochi</name></author><author><name>Maria Rosa Di Cicco</name></author><author><name>Olga Rickards</name></author><author><name>Mario Federico Rolfo</name></author><author><name>Jan Sevink</name></author><author><name>Flavio De Angelis</name></author><author><name>Luca Alessandri</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mobility patterns in the Italian peninsula during prehistory are still relatively unknown. The excavation of the Copper Age and Bronze Age deposits in La Sassa cave (Sonnino, Italy) allowed to broaden the knowledge about some local and regional dynamics. We employed a multi-disciplinary approach, including stable (carbon and nitrogen – C and N, respectively) and radiogenic (strontium-Sr) isotopes analyses and the identification of the cultural traits in the material culture to identify mobility patterns that took place in the region. The Sr isotopic analyses on the human bones show that in the Copper Age and at the beginning of the Bronze Age, the cave was used as a burial place by different villages, perhaps spread in a radius of no more than 5 km. Stable isotopes analyses suggest the introduction of C4 plants in the diet of the Middle Bronze Age (MBA) communities in the area. Remarkably, in the same period, the material culture shows increasing influxes coming from the North. This evidence is consistent with the recent genomic findings tracing the arrival of people carrying a Steppe-related ancestry in Central Italy in MBA.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462554" rel="alternate" title="Isotopic evidence for population dynamics in the Central Italian Copper Age and Bronze Age (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461092</id><title>Algebraic theorem of selection by spatial sorting (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.188762+00:00</updated><author><name>Nikunj Goel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Heritable variation in traits that enhance dispersal rates can accumulate at population margins by spatial sorting. This mechanism of selection differs from natural selection as evolutionary change can ensue even in the absence of differential lifetime reproductive success. Although evidence suggests that populations are rapidly evolving at margins due to global change pressures, such as invasions and range shifts, we lack a mathematical theory of spatial sorting to understand these evolutionary patterns. To this end, we present an algebraic theorem, or the sorting theorem, to elucidate the nature of selection at margins, which can, in turn, facilitate axiomatic development of spatial sorting theory. The role of the sorting theorem in guiding research in this context is analogous to that of Price's theorem in natural selection theory.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461092" rel="alternate" title="Algebraic theorem of selection by spatial sorting (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461151</id><title>Seeing the Forest for the trees: Assessing genetic offset predictions with Gradient Forest (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.189234+00:00</updated><author><name>Áki Jarl Láruson</name></author><author><name>Matthew C. Fitzpatrick</name></author><author><name>Stephen R. Keller</name></author><author><name>Benjamin C. Haller</name></author><author><name>Katie E. Lotterhos</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gradient Forest (GF) is increasingly being used to forecast climate change impacts, but remains mostly untested for this purpose. We explore its robustness to assumption violations, and relationship to measures of fitness, using SLiM simulations with explicit genome architecture and a spatial metapopulation. We evaluate measures of GF offset in: (1) a neutral model with no environmental adaptation; (2) a monogenic “population genetic” model with a single environmentally adapted locus; and (3) a polygenic “quantitative genetic” model with two adaptive traits, each adapting to a different environment. Although we found GF Offset to be broadly correlated with fitness offsets under both single locus and polygenic architectures. It could also be confounded by neutral demography, genomic architecture, and the nature of the adaptive environment. GF Offset is a promising tool, but it is important to understand its limitations and underlying assumptions, especially when used in the context of forecasting maladaptation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461151" rel="alternate" title="Seeing the Forest for the trees: Assessing genetic offset predictions with Gradient Forest (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461085</id><title>Origin of the type I antifreeze gene in flounders in response to Cenozoic climate change (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.189682+00:00</updated><author><name>Laurie A. Graham</name></author><author><name>Sherry Y. Gauthier</name></author><author><name>Peter L. Davies</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antifreeze proteins (AFPs) inhibit ice growth within fish and protect them from freezing in icy seawater. Alanine-rich, alpha-helical AFPs (type I) have independently (convergently) evolved in four branches of fishes, one of which is a subsection of the righteye flounders. The origin of this gene family has been elucidated by sequencing two loci from a starry flounder, &lt;italic&gt;Platichthys stellatus&lt;/italic&gt;, collected off Vancouver Island, British Columbia. The first locus had two alleles that demonstrated the plasticity of the &lt;italic&gt;AFP&lt;/italic&gt; gene family, one encoding 33 AFPs and the other allele only four. In the closely related Pacific halibut, this locus encodes multiple Gig2 (antiviral) proteins, but in the starry flounder, the &lt;italic&gt;Gig2&lt;/italic&gt; genes were found at a second locus due to a lineage-specific duplication event. An ancestral &lt;italic&gt;Gig2&lt;/italic&gt; gave rise to a 3-kDa “skin” &lt;italic&gt;AFP&lt;/italic&gt; isoform, encoding three Ala-rich 11-a.a. repeats, that is expressed in skin and other peripheral tissues. Subsequent gene duplications, followed by internal duplications of the 11 a.a. repeat and the gain of a signal sequence, gave rise to circulating AFP isoforms. One of these, the “hyperactive” 32-kDa Maxi likely underwent a contraction to a shorter 3.3-kDa “liver” isoform. Present day starry flounders found in Pacific Rim coastal waters from California to Alaska show a positive correlation between latitude and &lt;italic&gt;AFP&lt;/italic&gt; gene dosage, with the shorter allele being more prevalent at lower latitudes. This study conclusively demonstrates that the flounder &lt;italic&gt;AFP&lt;/italic&gt; arose from the &lt;italic&gt;Gig2&lt;/italic&gt; gene, so it is evolutionarily unrelated to the three other classes of type I AFPs from non-flounders. Additionally, this gene arose and underwent amplification coincident with the onset of ocean cooling during the Cenozoic ice ages.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461085" rel="alternate" title="Origin of the type I antifreeze gene in flounders in response to Cenozoic climate change (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462233</id><title>Convergent mosaic brain evolution is associated with the evolution of novel electrosensory systems in teleost fishes (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.189912+00:00</updated><author><name>Erika L. Schumacher</name></author><author><name>Bruce A. Carlson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Brain region size generally scales allometrically with total brain size, but mosaic shifts in brain region size independent of brain size have been found in several lineages and may be related to the evolution of behavioral novelty. African weakly electric fishes (Mormyroidea) evolved a mosaically enlarged cerebellum and hindbrain, yet the relationship to their behaviorally novel electrosensory system remains unclear. We addressed this by studying South American weakly electric fishes (Gymnotiformes) and weakly electric catfishes (&lt;italic&gt;Synodontis&lt;/italic&gt; spp.), which evolved varying aspects of electrosensory systems, independent of mormyroids. If the mormyroid mosaic increases are related to evolving an electrosensory system, we should find similar mosaic shifts in gymnotiforms and &lt;italic&gt;Synodontis&lt;/italic&gt;. Using micro-computed tomography scans, we quantified brain region scaling for multiple electrogenic, electroreceptive, and non-electrosensing species. We found mosaic increases in cerebellum in all three electrogenic lineages relative to non-electric lineages and mosaic increases in torus semicircularis and hindbrain associated with the evolution of electrogenesis and electroreceptor type. These results show that evolving novel electrosensory systems is repeatedly and independently associated with changes in the sizes of individual brain regions independent of brain size, which suggests that selection can impact structural brain composition to favor specific regions involved in novel behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462233" rel="alternate" title="Convergent mosaic brain evolution is associated with the evolution of novel electrosensory systems in teleost fishes (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462724</id><title>Whale shark rhodopsin adapted to its vertically wide-ranging lifestyle (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.190078+00:00</updated><author><name>Kazuaki Yamaguchi</name></author><author><name>Mitsumasa Koyanagi</name></author><author><name>Keiichi Sato</name></author><author><name>Akihisa Terakita</name></author><author><name>Shigehiro Kuraku</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spectral tuning of visual pigments often facilitates adaptation to new environments, and it is intriguing to study the visual ecology of pelagic sharks with expanded habitats. The whale shark, which dives into the deep sea of nearly 2,000 meters besides near-surface filter-feeding, was previously shown to possesses the ‘blue-shifted’ rhodopsin (RHO). In this study, our spectroscopy of recombinant whale shark RHO mutants revealed the dominant effect of the novel spectral tuning amino acid site 94, which is implicated in congenital stationary night blindness of humans, accounting for the blue shift. Thermal decay profiling revealed the reduction of the thermal stability of whale shark RHO, as typically observed for cone opsins, which was experimentally shown to be achieved by the site 178, as well as 94. The results suggest that these two sites cooperatively enhance the visual capacity in both the deep sea and the sea surface, enabling exceptionally wide vertical migration of this species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462724" rel="alternate" title="Whale shark rhodopsin adapted to its vertically wide-ranging lifestyle (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461498</id><title>A global meta-analysis reveals more variable life histories in urban birds compared to their non-urban neighbours (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.190244+00:00</updated><author><name>Pablo Capilla-Lasheras</name></author><author><name>Megan J. Thompson</name></author><author><name>Alfredo Sánchez-Tójar</name></author><author><name>Yacob Haddou</name></author><author><name>Claire J. Branston</name></author><author><name>Denis Réale</name></author><author><name>Anne Charmantier</name></author><author><name>Davide M. Dominoni</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cities pose a major ecological challenge for wildlife worldwide. Phenotypic variation is a pivotal metric to predict evolutionary potential in response to environmental change. Recent work suggests that urban populations might have higher levels of phenotypic variation than non-urban counterparts. This prediction, however, has never been tested across taxa nor over a broad geographical range. Here, we conduct a meta-analysis of the urban avian literature to compare urban &lt;italic&gt;versus&lt;/italic&gt; non-urban means and variances for phenology and reproductive performance. First, we show that urban birds reproduce earlier and have smaller broods than non-urban ones. Second, we demonstrate that urban populations have a more variable phenology than non-urban populations. Our analyses reveal that the latter pattern arises from differences in phenological variation between individuals within breeding seasons, likely because of higher heterogeneity in the urban study areas. These findings suggest that the opportunity for selection on phenology may be stronger in urban bird populations and that the patterns of phenotypic variation in urban and non-urban avian populations may consistently differ.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461498" rel="alternate" title="A global meta-analysis reveals more variable life histories in urban birds compared to their non-urban neighbours (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461719</id><title>Coding sequence-independent homology search identifies highly divergent homopteran putative effector gene family (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.190438+00:00</updated><author><name>David L. Stern</name></author><author><name>Clair Han</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many genomes contain rapidly evolving and highly divergent genes whose homology to genes of known function often cannot be determined from sequence similarity alone. However, coding sequence-independent features of genes, such as intron-exon boundaries, often evolve more slowly than coding sequences and can provide complementary evidence for homology. We found that a linear logistic regression classifier using only structural features of rapidly evolving &lt;italic&gt;bicycle&lt;/italic&gt; aphid effector genes identified many putative &lt;italic&gt;bicycle&lt;/italic&gt; homologs in aphids, phylloxerids, and scale insects, whereas sequence similarity search methods yielded few homologs in most aphids and no homologs in phylloxerids and scale insects. Subsequent examination of sequence features and intron locations supported homology assignments. Differential expression studies of newly-identified &lt;italic&gt;bicycle&lt;/italic&gt; homologs, together with prior proteomic studies, support the hypothesis that BICYCLE proteins act as plant effector proteins in many aphid species and perhaps also in phylloxerids and scale insects.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461719" rel="alternate" title="Coding sequence-independent homology search identifies highly divergent homopteran putative effector gene family (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>