<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.835595+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.10.463851</id><title>The Japanese wolf is most closely related to modern dogs and its ancestral genome has been widely inherited by dogs throughout East Eurasia (95 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.836198+00:00</updated><author><name>Jun Gojobori</name></author><author><name>Nami Arakawa</name></author><author><name>Xiaokaiti Xiayire</name></author><author><name>Yuki Matsumoto</name></author><author><name>Shuichi Matsumura</name></author><author><name>Hitomi Hongo</name></author><author><name>Naotaka Ishiguro</name></author><author><name>Yohey Terai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Japanese wolf (&lt;italic&gt;Canis lupus hodophilax&lt;/italic&gt; Temminck, 1839) was a subspecies of the gray wolf that inhabited the Japanese Archipelago and became extinct 100-120 years ago. In this study, we determined the whole genomes of nine Japanese wolves from the 19&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;- early 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; centuries and 11 Japanese dogs and analyzed them along with both modern and ancient wolves and dogs. Genomic analyses indicate that the Japanese wolf was a unique subspecies of the gray wolf that was genetically distinct from both modern and ancient gray wolves, lacking gene flow with other gray wolves. A Phylogenetic tree that minimizes the effects of introgression shows that Japanese wolves are closest to the dog monophyletic group among the gray wolves. Moreover, Japanese wolves show significant genetic affinities with East Eurasian dogs. We estimated the level of introgression from the ancestor of the Japanese wolves to the ancestor of East Eurasian dogs that had occurred in the transitional period from the Pleistocene to the Holocene, at an early stage after divergence from West Eurasian dog lineages. Because of this introgression, Japanese wolf ancestry has been inherited by many dogs through admixture between East Eurasian dog lineages. As a result of this heredity, up to 5.5% of modern dog genomes throughout East Eurasia are derived from Japanese wolf ancestry.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.10.463851" rel="alternate" title="The Japanese wolf is most closely related to modern dogs and its ancestral genome has been widely inherited by dogs throughout East Eurasia (95 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-10-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>