<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv evolutionary-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.832856+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.16.448734</id><title>Parallel shifts of visual sensitivity and body colouration in replicate populations of extremophile fish (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.834353+00:00</updated><author><name>Gregory L. Owens</name></author><author><name>Thor Veen</name></author><author><name>Dylan R. Moxley</name></author><author><name>Lenin Arias-Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Michael Tobler</name></author><author><name>Diana J. Rennison</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Visual sensitivity and body pigmentation are often shaped by both natural selection from the environment and sexual selection from mate choice. One way of quantifying the impact of the environment is by measuring how traits have changed after colonization of a novel habitat. To do this, we studied &lt;italic&gt;Poecilia mexicana&lt;/italic&gt; populations that have repeatedly adapted to extreme sulphidic (H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;S containing) environments. We measured visual sensitivity using opsin gene expression, as well as body pigmentation and water transmission for populations in four independent drainages. Both visual sensitivity and body pigmentation showed significant parallel shifts towards greater medium wavelength sensitivity and reflectance in sulphidic populations. The light spectrum was only subtly different between environments and overall, we found no significant correlations between the light environment and visual sensitivity or body pigmentation. Altogether we found that sulphidic habitats select for differences in visual sensitivity and pigmentation; our data suggest that this effect is unlikely to be driven purely by the water’s spectral properties and may instead be from other correlated ecological changes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.16.448734" rel="alternate" title="Parallel shifts of visual sensitivity and body colouration in replicate populations of extremophile fish (6 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-06-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>