<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.079403+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462138</id><title>The extended Price equation: migration and sex (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.079875+00:00</updated><author><name>Jake Brown</name></author><author><name>Jared M. Field</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Price equation provides a general partition of evolutionary change into two components. The first is usually thought to represent natural selection and the second, transmission bias. Here, we provide a new derivation of the generalised equation, which contains a largely ignored third term. Unlike the original Price equation, this extension can account for migration and mixed asexual and sexual reproduction. The notation used here expresses the generalised equation explicitly in terms of fitness, rendering this otherwise difficult third term more open to biological interpretation and use. This re-derivation also permits fundamental results, derived from the Price equation, to be more easily generalised. We take Hamilton’s rule as a case study, and provide an exact, total expression that allows for population structures like haplodiploidy. Our analysis, more generally, makes clear the previously hidden assumptions in similar fundamental results, highlighting the caution that must be taken when interpreting them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462138" rel="alternate" title="The extended Price equation: migration and sex (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462139</id><title>The spread of the first introns in proto-eukaryotic paralogs (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.080207+00:00</updated><author><name>Julian Vosseberg</name></author><author><name>Michelle Schinkel</name></author><author><name>Sjoerd Gremmen</name></author><author><name>Berend Snel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spliceosomal introns are a unique feature of eukaryotic genes. Previous studies have established that many introns were present in the protein-coding genes of the last eukaryotic common ancestor (LECA). Intron positions shared between genes that duplicated before LECA could in principle provide insight into the emergence of the first introns. In this study we use ancestral intron position reconstructions in two large sets of duplicated families to systematically identify these ancient paralogous intron positions. We found that 20-35% of introns inferred to have been present in LECA were shared between paralogs. These shared introns, which likely preceded ancient duplications, were widespread across different functions, with the notable exception of nuclear transport. Since we observed a clear signal of pervasive intron loss prior to LECA, it is likely that substantially more introns were shared at the time of duplication than we can detect in LECA. The large extent of shared introns indicates an early origin of introns during eukaryogenesis and suggests an early origin of a nuclear structure, before most of the other complex eukaryotic features were established.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462139" rel="alternate" title="The spread of the first introns in proto-eukaryotic paralogs (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462233</id><title>Convergent mosaic brain evolution is associated with the evolution of novel electrosensory systems in teleost fishes (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.080509+00:00</updated><author><name>Erika L. Schumacher</name></author><author><name>Bruce A. Carlson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Brain region size generally scales allometrically with total brain size, but mosaic shifts in brain region size independent of brain size have been found in several lineages and may be related to the evolution of behavioral novelty. African weakly electric fishes (Mormyroidea) evolved a mosaically enlarged cerebellum and hindbrain, yet the relationship to their behaviorally novel electrosensory system remains unclear. We addressed this by studying South American weakly electric fishes (Gymnotiformes) and weakly electric catfishes (&lt;italic&gt;Synodontis&lt;/italic&gt; spp.), which evolved varying aspects of electrosensory systems, independent of mormyroids. If the mormyroid mosaic increases are related to evolving an electrosensory system, we should find similar mosaic shifts in gymnotiforms and &lt;italic&gt;Synodontis&lt;/italic&gt;. Using micro-computed tomography scans, we quantified brain region scaling for multiple electrogenic, electroreceptive, and non-electrosensing species. We found mosaic increases in cerebellum in all three electrogenic lineages relative to non-electric lineages and mosaic increases in torus semicircularis and hindbrain associated with the evolution of electrogenesis and electroreceptor type. These results show that evolving novel electrosensory systems is repeatedly and independently associated with changes in the sizes of individual brain regions independent of brain size, which suggests that selection can impact structural brain composition to favor specific regions involved in novel behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462233" rel="alternate" title="Convergent mosaic brain evolution is associated with the evolution of novel electrosensory systems in teleost fishes (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462724</id><title>Whale shark rhodopsin adapted to its vertically wide-ranging lifestyle (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.080948+00:00</updated><author><name>Kazuaki Yamaguchi</name></author><author><name>Mitsumasa Koyanagi</name></author><author><name>Keiichi Sato</name></author><author><name>Akihisa Terakita</name></author><author><name>Shigehiro Kuraku</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spectral tuning of visual pigments often facilitates adaptation to new environments, and it is intriguing to study the visual ecology of pelagic sharks with expanded habitats. The whale shark, which dives into the deep sea of nearly 2,000 meters besides near-surface filter-feeding, was previously shown to possesses the ‘blue-shifted’ rhodopsin (RHO). In this study, our spectroscopy of recombinant whale shark RHO mutants revealed the dominant effect of the novel spectral tuning amino acid site 94, which is implicated in congenital stationary night blindness of humans, accounting for the blue shift. Thermal decay profiling revealed the reduction of the thermal stability of whale shark RHO, as typically observed for cone opsins, which was experimentally shown to be achieved by the site 178, as well as 94. The results suggest that these two sites cooperatively enhance the visual capacity in both the deep sea and the sea surface, enabling exceptionally wide vertical migration of this species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462724" rel="alternate" title="Whale shark rhodopsin adapted to its vertically wide-ranging lifestyle (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462554</id><title>Isotopic evidence for population dynamics in the Central Italian Copper Age and Bronze Age (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.081292+00:00</updated><author><name>Marco Romboni</name></author><author><name>Ilenia Arienzo</name></author><author><name>Mauro Antonio Di Vito</name></author><author><name>Carmine Lubritto</name></author><author><name>Monica Piochi</name></author><author><name>Maria Rosa Di Cicco</name></author><author><name>Olga Rickards</name></author><author><name>Mario Federico Rolfo</name></author><author><name>Jan Sevink</name></author><author><name>Flavio De Angelis</name></author><author><name>Luca Alessandri</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mobility patterns in the Italian peninsula during prehistory are still relatively unknown. The excavation of the Copper Age and Bronze Age deposits in La Sassa cave (Sonnino, Italy) allowed to broaden the knowledge about some local and regional dynamics. We employed a multi-disciplinary approach, including stable (carbon and nitrogen – C and N, respectively) and radiogenic (strontium-Sr) isotopes analyses and the identification of the cultural traits in the material culture to identify mobility patterns that took place in the region. The Sr isotopic analyses on the human bones show that in the Copper Age and at the beginning of the Bronze Age, the cave was used as a burial place by different villages, perhaps spread in a radius of no more than 5 km. Stable isotopes analyses suggest the introduction of C4 plants in the diet of the Middle Bronze Age (MBA) communities in the area. Remarkably, in the same period, the material culture shows increasing influxes coming from the North. This evidence is consistent with the recent genomic findings tracing the arrival of people carrying a Steppe-related ancestry in Central Italy in MBA.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462554" rel="alternate" title="Isotopic evidence for population dynamics in the Central Italian Copper Age and Bronze Age (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>