<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.495681+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.21.457186</id><title>Evidence of long-term purging of mutation load in killer whale genomes (40 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.496056+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew D Foote</name></author><author><name>Thomas P Gilbert</name></author><author><name>Shyam Gopalakrishnan</name></author><author><name>Marie Louis</name></author><author><name>Michael Martin</name></author><author><name>Phillip A. Morin</name></author><author><name>Milaja Nykanen</name></author><author><name>Camilla Scharff-Olsen</name></author><author><name>Laurent A. Excoffier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genomes of high latitude killer whales harbour signatures of post-glacial founding and expansion. Here, we investigate whether reduced efficacy of selection increased mutation load in founder populations, or whether recessive deleterious mutations exposed to selection in homozygous genotypes were purged. Comparing the accumulation of synonymous and non-synonymous mutations across pairs of globally sampled genomes reveals that the most significant outliers are high latitude North Atlantic genomes, which have accumulated significantly fewer non-synonymous mutations than all other populations. Comparisons with the genome of a 7.5-Kyr-old North Atlantic killer whale, inferred to be closely related to the population directly ancestral to present-day Icelandic and Norwegian populations, calibrates the timing of the action of selection on non-synonymous mutations predominantly to the mid-late Holocene. Non-synonymous mutations purged in modern Norwegian killer whale genomes are found as globally shared standing variation in heterozygote genotypes more often than expected, suggesting overdominance. Taken together, our findings are consistent with purging of recessive non-synonymous mutations exposed to selection in founder-associated homozygous genotypes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.21.457186" rel="alternate" title="Evidence of long-term purging of mutation load in killer whale genomes (40 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>