<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv evolutionary-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.660767+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453070</id><title>Regulation of sedimentation rate shapes the evolution of multicellularity in a unicellular relative of animals (49 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.661442+00:00</updated><author><name>Omaya Dudin</name></author><author><name>Sébastien Wielgoss</name></author><author><name>Aaron M. New</name></author><author><name>Iñaki Ruiz-Trillo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Significant increases in sedimentation rate accompany the evolution of multicellularity. These increases should lead to rapid changes in ecological distribution, thereby affecting the costs and benefits of multicellularity and its likelihood to evolve. However, how genetic and cellular traits which control this process, their likelihood of emergence over evolutionary timescales, and the variation in these traits as multicellularity evolves, are still poorly understood. Here, using isolates of the ichthyosporean &lt;italic&gt;Sphaeroforma&lt;/italic&gt; genus - close unicellular relatives of animals with brief transient multicellular life stages - we demonstrate that sedimentation rate is a highly variable and evolvable trait affected by at least two distinct physical mechanisms. We first find a dramatic &amp;gt;300x variation in sedimentation rate for different &lt;italic&gt;Sphaeroforma&lt;/italic&gt; species, mainly driven by size and density during the unicellular-to-multicellular life cycle transition. Using experimental evolution with sedimentation rate as a focal trait, we readily obtained fast settling &lt;italic&gt;S. arctica&lt;/italic&gt; isolates. Quantitative microscopy showed that increased sedimentation rates most often arose by incomplete cellular separation after cell division, leading to clonal “clumping” multicellular variants with increased size and density. Additionally, density increases arose by an acceleration of the nuclear doubling time relative to cell size. Similar size- and density-affecting phenotypes were observed in four additional species from the &lt;italic&gt;Sphaeroforma&lt;/italic&gt; genus, suggesting variation in these traits might be widespread in the marine habitat. By sequencing evolved isolates, we identified mutations in regulators of cytokinesis, plasma membrane remodelling, and chromatin condensation that may contribute to both clump formation and the increase in the nuclear number-to-volume ratio. Taken together, this study illustrates how extensive cellular control of density and size drive sedimentation rate variation, likely shaping the evolution of multicellularity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453070" rel="alternate" title="Regulation of sedimentation rate shapes the evolution of multicellularity in a unicellular relative of animals (49 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.19.453013</id><title>Phylogenomic analyses of echinoid diversification prompt a re-evaluation of their fossil record (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.661965+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicolas Mongiardino Koch</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey R Thompson</name></author><author><name>Avery S Hatch</name></author><author><name>Marina F McCowin</name></author><author><name>Frances Armstrong</name></author><author><name>Simon E Coppard</name></author><author><name>Felipe Aguilera</name></author><author><name>Omri Bronstein</name></author><author><name>Andreas Kroh</name></author><author><name>Rich Mooi</name></author><author><name>Greg W Rouse</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Echinoids are key components of modern marine ecosystems. Despite a remarkable fossil record, the emergence of their crown group is documented by few specimens of unclear affinities, rendering much of their early history uncertain. The origin of sand dollars, one of its most distinctive clades, is also unclear due to an unstable phylogenetic context and discrepancies between molecular divergence times and fossil evidence. We employ seventeen novel genomes and transcriptomes to build a phylogenomic dataset with a near-complete sampling of major lineages. With it, we revise the phylogeny and divergence times of echinoids, and place their history within the broader context of echinoderm evolution. We also introduce the concept of a chronospace - a multidimensional representation of node ages - and use it to explore the effects of using alternative gene samples, models of molecular evolution, and clock priors. We find the choice of clock model to have the strongest impact on divergence times, while the use of site-heterogeneous models shows little effects. The choice of loci shows an intermediate impact, affecting mostly deep Paleozoic nodes, for which clock-like genes recover dates more congruent with fossil evidence. Our results reveal that crown group echinoids originated in the Permian and diversified rapidly in the Triassic, despite the relative lack of fossil evidence for this early diversification. We also clarify the relationships among sand dollars and their close relatives, showing that the genus Apatopygus represents a relict lineage with a deep Jurassic origin. Surprisingly, the origin of sand dollars is confidently dated to the Cretaceous, implying ghost ranges spanning approximately 50 million years, a remarkable discrepancy with their rich fossil record.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.19.453013" rel="alternate" title="Phylogenomic analyses of echinoid diversification prompt a re-evaluation of their fossil record (27 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-07-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453507</id><title>Toxin breakdown does not preclude the potential for defensive toxin use in a fruit fly (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.662538+00:00</updated><author><name>Tyler E. Douglas</name></author><author><name>Sofia G. Beskid</name></author><author><name>Callie E. Gernand</name></author><author><name>Brianna E. Nirtaut</name></author><author><name>Kristen E. Tamsil</name></author><author><name>Richard W. Fitch</name></author><author><name>Rebecca D. Tarvin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Animals that ingest toxins can themselves become toxic or unpalatable to predators and parasites. Because most animals rapidly eliminate toxins to survive toxin ingestion, it is unclear how species transition from susceptibility and toxin elimination to tolerance and accumulation as chemical defense emerges. Studies of chemical defense have generally focused on species that display active toxin sequestration and target-site insensitivity mutations that permit survival without necessitating toxin metabolism. Here we investigate whether animals that presumably rely on toxin elimination for survival can also utilize ingested toxins for defense. We use the A4 and A3 &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; fly strains from the Drosophila Synthetic Population Resource (DSPR), which respectively possess elevated and reduced metabolic resistance to nicotine. We find that ingesting nicotine increased the survival of A4 but not of A3 flies against &lt;italic&gt;Leptopilina heterotoma&lt;/italic&gt; wasp parasitism. Further, we find that despite possessing enhanced toxin clearance mechanisms, A4 flies accrued more nicotine than A3 individuals. Our results suggest that enhanced metabolic detoxification can allow for greater toxin intake by offsetting the cost of toxin ingestion. Passive toxin accumulation that accompanies increased toxin intake may underlie the early origins of chemical defense.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453507" rel="alternate" title="Toxin breakdown does not preclude the potential for defensive toxin use in a fruit fly (6 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453597</id><title>Generalizing Bayesian phylogenetics to infer shared evolutionary events (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.662835+00:00</updated><author><name>Jamie R Oaks</name></author><author><name>Perry L Wood</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many processes of biological diversification can affect multiple evolutionary lineages. Examples include multiple members of a gene family diverging when a region of a chromosome is duplicated, multiple viral strains diverging at a "super-spreading" event, and a geological event fragmenting whole communities of species. It is difficult to test for patterns predicted by such processes, because all phylogenetic methods assume that lineages diverge independently. We introduce a general Bayesian framework to relax the assumption of independent divergences during phylogenetic inference, and test for patterns predicted by processes of diversification that affect multiple evolutionary lineages. Using simulations, we find our new method accurately infers shared divergence events when they occur, and performs as well as current methods when divergnces are independent. We apply our new approach to genomic data from two genera of geckos from across the Philippines to test if past changes to the islands' landscape caused bursts of speciation. Unlike previous analyses restricted to only pairs of populations, we find evidence for patterns of shared divergences. By generalizing the space of phylogenetic trees in a way that is independent from the likelihood model, our approach opens many avenues for future research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453597" rel="alternate" title="Generalizing Bayesian phylogenetics to infer shared evolutionary events (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.453339</id><title>Segmenting biological specimens from photos to understand the evolution of UV plumage in passerine birds (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.663023+00:00</updated><author><name>Yichen He</name></author><author><name>Christopher R Cooney</name></author><author><name>Zoe K Varley</name></author><author><name>Lara O Nouri</name></author><author><name>Christopher J. A. Moody</name></author><author><name>Michael D Jardine</name></author><author><name>Steve Maddock</name></author><author><name>Gavin H Thomas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ultraviolet (UV) colouration is thought to be an important signalling mechanism in many bird species, yet broad insights regarding the prevalence of UV plumage colouration and the factors promoting its evolution are currently lacking. Here, we develop a novel image segmentation pipeline based on deep learning that considerably outperforms classical (i.e. non-deep learning) segmentation methods, and use this to extract accurate information on whole-body plumage colouration from photographs of &amp;gt;24,000 museum specimens covering &amp;gt;4,500 species of passerine birds. Our results demonstrate that UV reflectance, particularly as a component of other colours, is widespread across the passerine radiation but is strongly phylogenetically conserved. We also find clear evidence in support of the role of light environment in promoting the evolution of UV plumage colouration, and a weak trend towards higher UV plumage reflectance among bird species with ultraviolet rather than violet-sensitive visual systems. Overall, our study provides important broad-scale insight into an enigmatic component of avian colouration, as well as demonstrating that deep learning has considerable promise for allowing new data to be bought to bare on long-standing questions in ecology and evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.453339" rel="alternate" title="Segmenting biological specimens from photos to understand the evolution of UV plumage in passerine birds (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>