<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv evolutionary-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.498023+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444989</id><title>Taxon-specific or universal? Using target capture to study the evolutionary history of a rapid radiation (42 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.498331+00:00</updated><author><name>Gil Yardeni</name></author><author><name>Juan Viruel</name></author><author><name>Margot Paris</name></author><author><name>Jaqueline Hess</name></author><author><name>Clara Groot Crego</name></author><author><name>Marylaure de La Harpe</name></author><author><name>Norma Rivera</name></author><author><name>Michael H. J. Barfuss</name></author><author><name>Walter Till</name></author><author><name>Valeria Guzman-Jacob</name></author><author><name>Thorsten Kroemer</name></author><author><name>Christian Lexer</name></author><author><name>Ovidiu Paun</name></author><author><name>Thibault Leroy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Target capture emerged as an important tool for phylogenetics and population genetics in non-model taxa. Whereas developing taxon-specific capture probes requires sustained efforts, available universal kits may have a lower power to reconstruct relationships at shallow phylogenetic scales and within rapidly radiating clades. We present here a newly-developed target capture set for Bromeliaceae, a large and ecologically-diverse plant family with highly variable diversification rates. The set targets 1,776 coding regions, including genes putatively involved in key innovations, with the aim to empower testing of a wide range of evolutionary hypotheses. We compare the relative power of this taxon-specific set, Bromeliad1776, to the universal Angiosperms353 kit. The taxon-specific set results in higher enrichment success across the entire family. However, the overall performance of both kits to reconstruct phylogenetic trees is relatively comparable, highlighting the vast potential of universal kits for resolving evolutionary relationships. For more detailed phylogenetic or population genetic analyses, e.g. the exploration of gene tree concordance, nucleotide diversity or population structure, the taxon-specific capture set presents clear benefits. We discuss the potential lessons that this comparative study provides for future phylogenetic and population genetic investigations, in particular for the study of evolutionary radiations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444989" rel="alternate" title="Taxon-specific or universal? Using target capture to study the evolutionary history of a rapid radiation (42 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.445023</id><title>A complex interplay between balancing selection and introgression maintains a genus-wide alternative life history strategy (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.498596+00:00</updated><author><name>Kalle Tunström</name></author><author><name>Alyssa Woronik</name></author><author><name>Joseph J. Hanly</name></author><author><name>Pasi Rastas</name></author><author><name>Anton Chichvarkhin</name></author><author><name>Andrew D Warren</name></author><author><name>Akito Kawahara</name></author><author><name>Sean D. Schoville</name></author><author><name>Vincent Ficarrotta</name></author><author><name>Adam H. Porter</name></author><author><name>Ward B. Watt</name></author><author><name>Arnaud Martin</name></author><author><name>Christopher W. Wheat</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Alternative life-history strategies (ALHS) are genetic polymorphisms generating phenotypes differing in life histories that generally arise due to metabolic resource allocation tradeoffs. Althouigh ALHS are often be limited to a single sex or populations of a species, they can, in rare cases, be found among several species across a genus. In the butterfly genus &lt;italic&gt;Colias&lt;/italic&gt;, at least a third of the species have a female limited ALHS called Alba. While many females develop brightly pigmented wings, Alba females reallocate nitrogen resources used in pigment synthesis to reproductive development, producing white-winged, more fecund females. Whether this ALHS evolved once or many times, and whether it has moved among species via introgression or been maintained via long-term balancing selection, has not been established. Answering these questions presents an opportunity to investigate the genetic basis and evolutionary forces acting upon ALHS, which have rarely been studied at a genus level. Here we identify the genetic locus of &lt;italic&gt;Alba&lt;/italic&gt; in a second &lt;italic&gt;Colias&lt;/italic&gt; species, allowing us to compare this with previous results in a larger phylogenetic context. Our findings suggest &lt;italic&gt;Alba&lt;/italic&gt; has a singular origin and has been maintained in &lt;italic&gt;Colias&lt;/italic&gt; through a combination of balancing selection and introgression for nearly one million years and at least as many generations. Finally, using CRISPR/Cas9 deletions in the cis-regulatory region of the &lt;italic&gt;Alba&lt;/italic&gt; allele, we demonstrate that the &lt;italic&gt;Alba&lt;/italic&gt; allele is a modular enhancer for the &lt;italic&gt;BarH1&lt;/italic&gt; gene and is necessary for the induction of the ALHS, which potentially facilitates its long-term persistence in the genus.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.445023" rel="alternate" title="A complex interplay between balancing selection and introgression maintains a genus-wide alternative life history strategy (12 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.16.444351</id><title>Genomic inference of a human super bottleneck in the Early Stone Age (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.498814+00:00</updated><author><name>Wangjie Hu</name></author><author><name>Ziqian Hao</name></author><author><name>Pengyuan Du</name></author><author><name>Yi-Hsuan Pan</name></author><author><name>Haipeng Li</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The demographic history has been a foundation of human evolutionary studies for more than a century. In this study, we developed a novel method referred to as the fast infinitesimal time coalescent (FitCoal) process. This method allows the accurate calculation of the composite likelihood of a site frequency spectrum and provides the precise inference of recent and ancient demographic history. Genomic sequences of the 1000 Genomes Project and the Human Genome Diversity Project – Centre d’Etude du Polymorphisme Humain panel were analyzed. Results showed that all ten African populations had a population super bottleneck, a small effective size of approximately 1,280 breeding individuals between 813 and 930 thousand years ago, and a 20-fold rapid growth at the end of the bottleneck. The super bottleneck caused a loss of 65.85% in current human genetic diversity, but it may have separated our ancestors from other hominins. Further analysis confirmed the existence of the super bottleneck in all 40 non-African populations. Our results provide new insights into human evolution in the Early Stone Age.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.16.444351" rel="alternate" title="Genomic inference of a human super bottleneck in the Early Stone Age (11 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444135</id><title>Anaerobic derivates of mitochondria and peroxisomes in the free-living amoeba Pelomyxa schiedti revealed by single-cell genomics (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.498978+00:00</updated><author><name>Kristína Záhonová</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Cristian Treitli</name></author><author><name>Tien Le</name></author><author><name>Ingrid Škodová-Sveráková</name></author><author><name>Pavla Hanousková</name></author><author><name>Ivan Čepička</name></author><author><name>Jan Tachezy</name></author><author><name>Vladimír Hampl</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Pelomyxa schiedti&lt;/italic&gt; is a free-living amoeba belonging to the group Archamoebae, which encompasses anaerobes bearing mitochondrion-related organelles (MROs) - hydrogenosomes in free-living &lt;italic&gt;Mastigamoeba balamuthi&lt;/italic&gt; and mitosomes in the human pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Entamoeba histolytica&lt;/italic&gt;. Anaerobic peroxisomes, another adaptation to anaerobic lifestyle, were identified only recently in &lt;italic&gt;M. balamuthi&lt;/italic&gt;. We found evidence for both these organelles in the single-cell-derived genome and transcriptome of &lt;italic&gt;P. schiedti&lt;/italic&gt;, and corresponding vesicles were tentatively revealed in electron micrographs. &lt;italic&gt;In silico&lt;/italic&gt; reconstructed MRO metabolism seems similar to that of &lt;italic&gt;M. balamuthi&lt;/italic&gt; harboring respiratory complex II, electron-transferring flavoprotein, partial TCA cycle running presumably in reductive direction, pyruvate:ferredoxin oxidoreductase, [FeFe]-hydrogenases, glycine cleavage system, and sulfate activation pathway. The cell disposes with an expanded set of NIF enzymes for iron sulfur cluster assembly, but their localization remains unclear. Quite contrary, out of 67 predicted peroxisomal enzymes, only four were reported also in &lt;italic&gt;M. balamuthi&lt;/italic&gt;, namely peroxisomal processing peptidase, nudix hydrolase, inositol 2-dehydrogenase, and D-lactate dehydrogenase. Other putative functions of peroxisomes could be pyridoxal 5′-phosphate biosynthesis, amino acid and carbohydrate metabolism, and hydrolase activities. Future experimental evidence is necessary to define functions of this surprisingly enzyme-rich anaerobic peroxisome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444135" rel="alternate" title="Anaerobic derivates of mitochondria and peroxisomes in the free-living amoeba Pelomyxa schiedti revealed by single-cell genomics (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>