<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.425584+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465984</id><title>A cautionary tale on proper use of branch-site models to detect convergent positive selection (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.426809+00:00</updated><author><name>Amanda Kowalczyk</name></author><author><name>Maria Chikina</name></author><author><name>Nathan L Clark</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Comparative genomics has become a powerful tool to elucidate genotype-phenotype relationships, particularly through the study of convergently acquired phenotypes. By identifying genes under positive selection specifically on branches with the convergent phenotype we can potentially link genes to that phenotype. Such gene scans are often done using branch-site codon models. However, we have observed a recent troubling trend of misinterpretation of branch-site models in which phylogeny-wide positive selection is not distinguished from positive selection specific to convergent branches. Here, we use simulations and real data to demonstrate how failing to discern between these two cases leads to false inferences of positive selection associated with a convergent trait. We then present a “ drop-out” test solution to distinguish the two cases and thereby truly capture positive selection events associated with convergent phenotypes, thus allowing for further insights into both genetic and phenotypic evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465984" rel="alternate" title="A cautionary tale on proper use of branch-site models to detect convergent positive selection (15 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466308</id><title>Divergent evolutionary trajectories of bryophytes and tracheophytes from a complex common ancestor of land plants (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.428805+00:00</updated><author><name>Brogan J Harris</name></author><author><name>James W Clark</name></author><author><name>Dominik Schrempf</name></author><author><name>Gergely J Szöllősi</name></author><author><name>Philip Donoghue</name></author><author><name>Alistair M Hetherington</name></author><author><name>Tom A Williams</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The origin of plants and their colonization of land resulted in the transformation of the terrestrial environment. Here we investigate the evolution of the land plants (embryophytes) and their two main lineages, the tracheophytes (vascular plants) and bryophytes (non vascular plants). We used new fossil calibrations, relative lineage dating implied by horizontal gene transfer, and new phylogenomic methods for mapping gene family origins. Distinct rooting strategies resolve tracheophytes and bryophytes as monophyletic sister groups that diverged in the Cambrian, 515-494 Ma. The embryophyte stem is characterised by a burst of gene innovation, while bryophytes subsequently experienced a no less dramatic episode of reductive genome evolution in which they lost genes associated with the elaboration of vasculature and the stomatal complex. Overall, our analyses confirm that extant tracheophytes and bryophytes are both highly derived; as a result, understanding the origin of land plants requires tracing character evolution across the diversity of modern lineages.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466308" rel="alternate" title="Divergent evolutionary trajectories of bryophytes and tracheophytes from a complex common ancestor of land plants (15 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466320</id><title>Allele frequency dynamics under sex-biased demography and sex-specific inheritance in a pedigreed population (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.433073+00:00</updated><author><name>Rose M.H. Driscoll</name></author><author><name>Felix E.G. Beaudry</name></author><author><name>Elissa J Cosgrove</name></author><author><name>Reed Bowman</name></author><author><name>John W Fitzpatrick</name></author><author><name>Stephan J Schoech</name></author><author><name>Nancy Chen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sex-biased demography, including sex-biased survival or migration, can impact allele frequency changes across the genome. In particular, we can expect different patterns of genetic variation on autosomes and sex chromosomes due to sex-specific differences in life histories, as well as differences in effective population size, transmission modes, and the strength and mode of selection. Here, we demonstrate the role that sex differences in life history played in shaping short-term evolutionary dynamics across the genome. We used a 25-year pedigree and genomic dataset from a long-studied population of Florida Scrub-Jays (Aphelocoma coerulescens) to directly characterize the relative roles of sex-biased demography and inheritance in shaping genome-wide allele frequency trajectories. We used gene dropping simulations to estimate individual genetic contributions to future generations and to model drift and immigration on the known pedigree. We quantified differential expected genetic contributions of males and females over time, showing the impact of sex-biased dispersal in a monogamous system. Due to female-biased dispersal, more autosomal variation is introduced by female immigrants. However, due to male-biased transmission, more Z variation is introduced by male immigrants. Finally, we partitioned the proportion of variance in allele frequency change through time due to male and female contributions. Overall, most allele frequency change is due to variance in survival and births. Males and females have similar contributions to autosomal allele frequency change, but males have higher contributions to allele frequency change on the Z chromosome. Our work shows the importance of understanding sex-specific demographic processes in accounting for genome-wide allele frequency change in wild populations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466320" rel="alternate" title="Allele frequency dynamics under sex-biased demography and sex-specific inheritance in a pedigreed population (12 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466315</id><title>Coloring inside the lines: genomic architecture and evolution of a widespread color pattern in frogs (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.433442+00:00</updated><author><name>Sandra Goutte</name></author><author><name>Imtiyaz Hariyani</name></author><author><name>Kole Deroy Utzinger</name></author><author><name>Yann Bourgeois</name></author><author><name>Stephane Boissinot</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Traits shared among distantly related lineages are indicators of common evolutionary constraints, at the ecological, physiological or molecular level. The vertebral stripe is a color pattern that is widespread across the anuran phylogeny. Despite its prevalence in the order, surprisingly little is known about the genetic basis and evolutionary dynamic of this color pattern. Here we combine histology, genome- and transcriptome-wide analyses with order-scale phylogenetic comparative analyses to investigate this common phenotype. We show that the vertebral stripe has evolved hundreds of times in the evolutionary history of anurans and is selected for in terrestrial habitats. Using the Ethiopian Ptychadena radiation as a model system, we demonstrate that variation at the ASIP gene is responsible for the different vertebral stripe phenotypes. Alleles associated to these phenotypes are younger than the split between closely related Ptychadena species, thus indicating that the vertebral stripe results from parallel evolution within the group. Our findings demonstrate that this widespread color pattern evolves rapidly and recurrently in terrestrial anurans, and therefore constitute an ideal system to study repeated evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466315" rel="alternate" title="Coloring inside the lines: genomic architecture and evolution of a widespread color pattern in frogs (11 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466359</id><title>Evolution of maternal and early zygotic transcript regulation across Drosophila (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.434507+00:00</updated><author><name>Charles Omura</name></author><author><name>Susan Lott</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The complements of mRNAs in early embryonic development are crucial for setting up developmental trajectories in animals. The earliest stages of development are regulated by mRNAs deposited into the egg by the mother, until the zygote can become competent to transcribe its own genome. Previously, we showed that the set of maternally deposited and early transcribed zygotic mRNAs in Drosophila are generally conserved across species, but with some notable variation. We also showed that a majority of regulators of these two types of transcripts are shared. In this study, we examine the differences in regulatory motifs associated with maternal deposition and early zygotic transcription across species of Drosophila. For maternal transcripts, while the regulators are mostly conserved, we find the Drosophila pseudoobscura species subgroup appears to contain numerous novel regulatory motifs unique to these species. These novel motifs are enriched in transposable elements exclusive to this group. As this species group had been previously identified as having the largest divergence in early embryonic transcripts given their divergence time, this change in regulation may be responsible. However, transcripts that are present at the maternal stage only in these species are equally enriched in novel (group-specific) and conserved binding sites, so the novel regulation is not the sole cause of regulatory divergence in these species. At the zygotic stage, we observe a wide variety of species-specific motifs. Additionally, at both stages we observe motifs conserved across species having different effects on gene expression in different species, and regulating different sets of genes in different species. By examining changes in motif content across species, we find that changes in motif content alone is generally insufficient to drive gene expression changes across species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466359" rel="alternate" title="Evolution of maternal and early zygotic transcript regulation across Drosophila (6 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465918</id><title>Extensive sequence divergence of non-coding regions between Aspergillus fumigatus, a major fungal pathogen of humans, and its relatives (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.434775+00:00</updated><author><name>Alec Brown</name></author><author><name>Matthew E. Mead</name></author><author><name>Jacob L. Steenwyk</name></author><author><name>Gustavo H. Goldman</name></author><author><name>Antonis Rokas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Invasive aspergillosis is a deadly fungal disease; more than 400,000 patients are infected worldwide each year and the mortality rate can be as high as 50-95%. Of the ∼450 species in the genus &lt;italic&gt;Aspergillus&lt;/italic&gt; only a few are known to be clinically relevant, with the major pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Aspergillus fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt; being responsible for ∼50% of all invasive mold infections. Genomic comparisons of &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt; to other &lt;italic&gt;Aspergillus&lt;/italic&gt; species have historically focused on protein-coding regions. However, most &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt; genes, including those that modulate its virulence, are also present in non-pathogenic close relatives of &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt;. Our hypothesis is that differential gene regulation – mediated through the non-coding regions upstream of genes’ transcription start sites – contributes to &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt; pathogenicity. To begin testing this, we compared non-coding regions up to 500 base pairs upstream of the first codon of single-copy orthologous genes from the two &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt; reference strains Af293 and A1163 and eight closely related &lt;italic&gt;Aspergillus&lt;/italic&gt; section &lt;italic&gt;Fumigati&lt;/italic&gt; species. We found that non-coding regions showed extensive sequence variation and lack of homology across species. By examining the evolutionary rates of both protein-coding and non-coding regions in a subset of orthologous genes with highly conserved non-coding regions across the phylogeny, we identified 418 genes, including 25 genes known to modulate &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt; virulence, whose non-coding regions exhibit a different rate of evolution in &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt;. Examination of sequence alignments of these non-coding regions revealed numerous instances of insertions, deletions, and other types of mutations of at least a few nucleotides in &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt; compared to its close relatives. These results show that closely related &lt;italic&gt;Aspergillus&lt;/italic&gt; species that vary greatly in their pathogenicity exhibit extensive non-coding sequence variation and identify numerous changes in non-coding regions of &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt; genes known to contribute to virulence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465918" rel="alternate" title="Extensive sequence divergence of non-coding regions between Aspergillus fumigatus, a major fungal pathogen of humans, and its relatives (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.466679</id><title>Dimensionality and modularity of adaptive variation: Divergence in threespine stickleback from diverse environments (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.435498+00:00</updated><author><name>Grant E. Haines</name></author><author><name>Louis Moisan</name></author><author><name>Alison M. Derry</name></author><author><name>Andrew P. Hendry</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In nature, populations are subjected to a wide variety of environmental conditions that affect fitness and induce adaptive or plastic responses in traits, resulting in phenotypic divergence between populations. The dimensionality of that divergence, however, remains contentious. At the extremes, some contend that populations diverge along a single axis of trait covariance with greatest availability of heritable variation, even if this does not lead a population directly to its fitness optimum. Those at the other extreme argue that selection can push populations towards their fitness optima along multiple phenotype axes simultaneously, resulting in divergence in numerous dimensions. Here, we address this debate using populations of threespine stickleback (&lt;italic&gt;Gasterosteus aculeatus&lt;/italic&gt;) in the Cook Inlet region of southern Alaska from lakes with contrasting ecological conditions. We calculated effective dimensionality of divergence in several trait suites (defensive, swimming, and trophic) thought to be under correlated selection pressures, as well as across all traits. We also tested for integration among the trait suites and between each trait suite and the environment. We found that populations in the Cook Inlet radiation exhibit dimensionality of phenotype high enough to preclude a single axis of divergence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.466679" rel="alternate" title="Dimensionality and modularity of adaptive variation: Divergence in threespine stickleback from diverse environments (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466223</id><title>Onset and stepwise extensions of recombination suppression are common in mating-type chromosomes of Microbotryum anther-smut fungi (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.435815+00:00</updated><author><name>Marine Duhamel</name></author><author><name>Fantin Carpentier</name></author><author><name>Dominik Begerow</name></author><author><name>Michael Hood</name></author><author><name>Ricardo C Rodriguez de la Vega</name></author><author><name>Tatiana Giraud</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sex chromosomes and mating-type chromosomes can display large genomic regions without recombination. Recombination suppression often extended stepwise with time away from the sex- or mating-type-determining genes, generating evolutionary strata of differentiation between alternative sex or mating-type chromosomes. In anther-smut fungi of the &lt;italic&gt;Microbotryum&lt;/italic&gt; genus, recombination suppression evolved repeatedly, linking the two mating-type loci and extended multiple times in regions distal to the mating-type genes. Here, we obtained high-quality genome assemblies of alternative mating types for four &lt;italic&gt;Microbotryum&lt;/italic&gt; fungi. We found an additional event of independent chromosomal rearrangements bringing the two mating-type loci on the same chromosome followed by recombination suppression linking them. We also found, in a new clade analysed here, that recombination suppression between the two mating-type loci occurred in several steps, with first an ancestral recombination suppression between one of the mating-type locus and its centromere; later, completion of recombination suppression up to the second mating-type locus occurred independently in three species. The estimated dates of recombination suppression between the mating-type loci ranged from 0.15 to 3.58 million years ago. In total, this makes at least nine independent events of linkage between the mating-type loci across the &lt;italic&gt;Microbotryum&lt;/italic&gt; genus. Several mating-type locus linkage events occurred through the same types of chromosomal rearrangements, where similar chromosome fissions at centromeres represent convergence in the genomic changes leading to the phenotypic convergence. These findings further highlight &lt;italic&gt;Microbotryum&lt;/italic&gt; fungi as excellent models to study the evolution of recombination suppression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466223" rel="alternate" title="Onset and stepwise extensions of recombination suppression are common in mating-type chromosomes of Microbotryum anther-smut fungi (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>