<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv evolutionary-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.768774+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450565</id><title>Evolution of a minimal cell (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.769024+00:00</updated><author><name>RZ Moger-Reischer</name></author><author><name>JI Glass</name></author><author><name>KS Wise</name></author><author><name>L Sun</name></author><author><name>D Bittencourt</name></author><author><name>M Lynch</name></author><author><name>JT Lennon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Possessing only essential genes, a minimal cell can reveal mechanisms and processes that are critical for the persistence and stability of life. Here, we report on how a synthetically constructed minimal cell contends with the forces of evolution compared to a non-minimized cell from which it was derived. Genome streamlining was costly, but 80% of fitness was regained in 2000 generations. Although selection acted upon divergent sets of mutations, the rates of adaption in the minimal and non-minimal cell were equivalent. The only apparent constraint of minimization involved epistatic interactions that inhibited the evolution of cell size. Together, our findings demonstrate the power of natural selection to rapidly optimize fitness in the simplest autonomous organism, with implications for the evolution of cellular complexity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450565" rel="alternate" title="Evolution of a minimal cell (21 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450391</id><title>Fin Shape, Asymmetry, and Evolutionary Ecomorphology in Triggerfishes and Filefishes (Superfamily: Balistoidea) (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.769265+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew B. George</name></author><author><name>Mark W. Westneat</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Triggerfishes and filefishes exhibit a wide range of fin and body morphologies, inhabit many marine habitats, and feed on a variety of benthic and pelagic organisms. Particular morphologies are predicted to provide functional advantages for swimming behaviors that facilitate life in diverse habitats and feeding guilds. Ecomorphological relationships can, in turn, inform evolutionary patterns of morphological convergence. We quantified morphological diversity of 80 balistoid species using geometric morphometrics and assigned each species a primary habitat and feeding mode. Results revealed strong evidence for evolutionary integration among body and fin shapes as well as widespread convergence of both high and low aspect ratio (AR) dorsal and anal fins, the fins that power steady locomotion in these fishes. Dorsal and anal fins were determined to be moderately to highly asymmetrical in most species. Families exhibited considerable overlap in fin and body shapes, but triggerfishes generally exhibited higher AR and more asymmetrical fins than filefishes. Fin asymmetry was not strongly associated with ecology. Planktivorous and offshore-pelagic species exhibited high AR dorsal and anal fins suitable for high endurance swimming performance, while benthic grazing and structured reef species exhibited convergence on low AR median fins more suitable for facilitating maneuverability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450391" rel="alternate" title="Fin Shape, Asymmetry, and Evolutionary Ecomorphology in Triggerfishes and Filefishes (Superfamily: Balistoidea) (17 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.02.450762</id><title>Broad-scale variation in human genetic diversity levels is predicted by purifying selection on coding and non-coding elements (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.769445+00:00</updated><author><name>David Murphy</name></author><author><name>Eyal Elyashiv</name></author><author><name>Guy Amster</name></author><author><name>Guy Sella</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Analyses of genetic variation in many taxa have established that neutral genetic diversity is shaped by natural selection at linked sites. Whether the source of selection is primarily the fixation of strongly beneficial alleles (selective sweeps) or purifying selection on deleterious mutations (background selection) remains unknown, however. We address this question in humans by fitting a model of the joint effects of selective sweeps and background selection to autosomal polymorphism data from the 1000 Genomes Project. After controlling for variation in mutation rates along the genome, a model of background selection alone explains ~60% of the variance in diversity levels at the megabase scale. Adding the effects of selective sweeps driven by adaptive substitutions to the model does not improve the fit, and when both modes of selection are considered jointly, selective sweeps are estimated to have had little or no effect on linked neutral diversity. The regions under purifying selection are best predicted by phylogenetic conservation, with ~80% of the deleterious mutations affecting neutral diversity occurring in non-exonic regions. Thus, background selection is the dominant mode of linked selection in humans, with marked effects on diversity levels throughout autosomes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.02.450762" rel="alternate" title="Broad-scale variation in human genetic diversity levels is predicted by purifying selection on coding and non-coding elements (14 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.01.450666</id><title>Adaptive introgression and de novo mutations increase access to novel fitness peaks on the fitness landscape during a vertebrate adaptive radiation (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.769640+00:00</updated><author><name>Austin H. Patton</name></author><author><name>Emilie J. Richards</name></author><author><name>Katelyn J. Gould</name></author><author><name>Logan K. Buie</name></author><author><name>Christopher H. Martin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Estimating the complex relationship between fitness and genotype or phenotype (i.e. the adaptive landscape) is one of the central goals of evolutionary biology. Empirical fitness landscapes have now been estimated for numerous systems, from phage to proteins to finches. However, the nature of adaptive walks connecting genotypes to organismal fitness, speciation, and novel ecological niches are still poorly understood. One outstanding system for addressing these connections is a recent adaptive radiation of ecologically and morphologically distinct pupfishes (a generalist, molluscivore, and scale-eater) endemic to San Salvador Island, Bahamas. Here, we leveraged whole-genome sequencing of 139 hybrids from two independent field fitness experiments to identify the genomic basis of fitness, visualize the first genotypic fitness networks in a vertebrate system, and infer the contributions of different sources of genetic variation to the accessibility of the fitness landscape. We identified 132 SNPs that were significantly associated with fitness in field enclosures, including six associated genes that were differentially expressed between specialists, and one gene (protein-lysine methyltransferase: METTL21E) misexpressed in hybrids, suggesting a potential intrinsic genetic incompatibility. We then constructed genotypic fitness networks from adaptive alleles and show that only introgressed and &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; variants, not standing genetic variation, increased the accessibility of genotypic fitness paths from generalist to specialists. Our results suggest that adaptive introgression and &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; variants provided key connections in adaptive walks necessary for crossing fitness valleys and triggering the evolution of novelty during adaptive radiation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fitness landscape describes the complex relationship between genotype or phenotype and fitness and is the conceptual bridge between micro- and macro-evolution. There are many studies of the phenotypic fitness landscapes across a range of systems from microbes to vertebrates, but studies of the genotypic fitness landscape remain limited to microbial systems and the fitness of individual proteins. Here, we conduct the first study investigating the genotypic fitness landscape for organismal fitness in an exceptionally young vertebrate adaptive radiation including a generalist algivore, molluscivore, and scale-eating pupfish. We show that genetic variation originating from adaptive introgression and de novo mutations exert a disproportionate influence on the fitness landscape, enabling the crossing of adaptive valleys and the evolution of novelty.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.01.450666" rel="alternate" title="Adaptive introgression and de novo mutations increase access to novel fitness peaks on the fitness landscape during a vertebrate adaptive radiation (13 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450466</id><title>Protracted speciation under the state-dependent speciation and extinction approach (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.769833+00:00</updated><author><name>Xia Hua</name></author><author><name>Tyara Herdha</name></author><author><name>Conrad Burden</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;How long does speciation take? What are the speciation processes that generated a species group? The answers to these important questions in evolutionary biology lie in the genetic difference not only among species, but also among lineages within each species. With the advance of genome sequencing in non-model organisms and the statistical tools to improve accuracy in inferring evolutionary histories among recently diverged lineages, we now have the lineage-level trees to answer these questions. However, we do not yet have an analytical tool for inferring speciation processes from these trees. What is needed is a model of speciation processes that generates both the trees and species identities of extant lineages. The model should allow calculation of the probability that certain lineages belong to certain species and have an evolutionary history consistent with the tree. Here we propose such a model and test the model performance on both simulated data and real data. We show that maximum likelihood estimates of the model are highly accurate and give estimates from real data that generate patterns consistent with observations. We discuss how to extend the model to account for different rates and types of speciation processes across lineages in a species group. By linking evolutionary processes on lineage level to species level, the model provides a new phylogenetic approach to study not just when speciation happened, but how speciation happened.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450466" rel="alternate" title="Protracted speciation under the state-dependent speciation and extinction approach (7 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>