<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.210265+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.22.465484</id><title>Genomic insights into variation in thermotolerance between hybridizing swordtail fishes (25 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.210905+00:00</updated><author><name>Cheyenne Payne</name></author><author><name>Stephen Bovio</name></author><author><name>Dan Powell</name></author><author><name>Theresa Gunn</name></author><author><name>Shreya Banerjee</name></author><author><name>Victoria Grant</name></author><author><name>Gil Rosenthal</name></author><author><name>Molly Schumer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding how organisms adapt to changing environments is a core focus of research in evolutionary biology. One common mechanism is adaptive introgression, which has received increasing attention as a potential route to rapid adaptation in populations struggling in the face of ecological change, particularly global climate change. However, hybridization can also result in deleterious genetic interactions that may limit the benefits of adaptive introgression. Here, we used a combination of genome-wide quantitative trait locus mapping and differential gene expression analyses between the swordtail fish species Xiphophorus malinche and X. birchmanni to study the consequences of hybridization on thermotolerance. While these two species are adapted to different thermal environments, we document a complicated architecture of thermotolerance in hybrids. We identify a region of the genome that contributes to reduced thermotolerance in individuals heterozygous for X. malinche and X. birchmanni ancestry, as well as widespread misexpression in hybrids of genes that respond to thermal stress in the parental species, particularly in the circadian clock pathway. We also show that a previously mapped hybrid incompatibility between X. malinche and X. birchmanni contributes to reduced thermotolerance in hybrids. Together, our results highlight the challenges of understanding the impact of hybridization on complex ecological traits and its potential impact on adaptive introgression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.22.465484" rel="alternate" title="Genomic insights into variation in thermotolerance between hybridizing swordtail fishes (25 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-10-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>