<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.883607+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.455988</id><title>Cross-species incompatibility between a DNA satellite and a chromatin protein poisons germline genome integrity (81 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.883866+00:00</updated><author><name>Cara L Brand</name></author><author><name>Mia T Levine</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Satellite DNA spans megabases of eukaryotic genome sequence. These vast stretches of tandem DNA repeats undergo high rates of sequence turnover, resulting in radically different satellite DNA landscapes between closely related species. Such extreme evolutionary plasticity suggests that satellite DNA accumulates mutations with no functional consequence. Paradoxically, satellite-rich genomic regions support essential, conserved nuclear processes, including chromosome segregation, dosage compensation, and nuclear structure. A leading resolution to this paradox is that deleterious alterations to satellite DNA trigger adaptive evolution of chromatin proteins to preserve these essential functions. Here we experimentally test this model of coevolution between chromatin proteins and DNA satellites by conducting an evolution-guided manipulation of both protein and satellite. We focused on an adaptively evolving, ovary-enriched chromatin protein, called Maternal Haploid (MH) from Drosophila. MH co-localizes with an 11 Mb 359-bp satellite array present in Drosophila melanogaster but absent in its sister species, D. simulans. Using CRISPR/Cas9-mediated transgenesis, we swapped the D. simulans version of MH into D. melanogaster. We discovered that D. melanogaster females encoding only the D. simulans mh (mh[sim]) do not phenocopy the mh null mutation. Instead, MH[sim] is toxic to D. melanogaster ovaries: we observed elevated ovarian cell death, reduced ovary size, and subfertility in mh[sim] females. Using both cell biological and genetic approaches, we demonstrate that MH[sim] poisons oogenesis through a DNA damage pathway. Remarkably, deleting the D. melanogaster-specific 359 satellite array from mh[sim] females completely restores female germline genome integrity and fertility. This genetic rescue offers experimental evidence that rapid evolution resulted in a cross-species incompatibility between the 359 satellite and MH. These data suggest that coevolution between ostensibly inert repetitive DNA and essential chromatin proteins preserves germline genome integrity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.455988" rel="alternate" title="Cross-species incompatibility between a DNA satellite and a chromatin protein poisons germline genome integrity (81 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456260</id><title>The first chromosome-level gecko genome reveals dynamic sex chromosomes in Neotropical leaf-litter geckos (Sphaerodactylidae: Sphaerodactylus) (50 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.884063+00:00</updated><author><name>Brendan J. Pinto</name></author><author><name>Shannon E Keating</name></author><author><name>Stuart V Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Daniel P Scantlebury</name></author><author><name>Juan D Daza</name></author><author><name>Tony Gamble</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sex chromosomes have evolved many times across eukaryotes, indicating both their importance and their evolutionary flexibility. Some vertebrate groups, such as mammals and birds, have maintained a single, conserved sex chromosome system across long evolutionary time periods. By contrast, many reptiles, amphibians, and fish have undergone frequent sex chromosome transitions, most of which remain to be catalogued. Among reptiles, gecko lizards (infraorder Gekkota) have shown an exceptional lability with regard to sex chromosome transitions and may possess the majority of transitions within squamates (lizards and snakes). However—across geckos—information about sex chromosome linkage is expressly lacking, leaving large gaps in our understanding of the evolutionary processes at play in this system. To address this gap, we assembled the first chromosome-level genome for a gecko and use this linkage information to survey six Sphaerodactylus species using a variety of genomic data, including whole-genome re-sequencing, RADseq, and RNAseq. Previous work has identified XY systems in two species of Sphaerodactylus geckos. We expand upon that work to identify between two and four sex chromosome cis-transitions (XY to XY) within the genus. Interestingly, we confirmed two linkage groups as XY sex chromosome systems that were previously unknown to act as sex chromosomes in tetrapods (syntenic with Gallus 3 and Gallus 18/30/33). We highlight the increasing evidence that most (if not all) linkage groups will likely be identified as a sex chromosome in future studies given thorough enough sampling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456260" rel="alternate" title="The first chromosome-level gecko genome reveals dynamic sex chromosomes in Neotropical leaf-litter geckos (Sphaerodactylidae: Sphaerodactylus) (50 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-08-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455826</id><title>Nucleated Fish Erythrocyte Extracellular Traps (FEETs) release is an evolutionary conserved immune defence process (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.884228+00:00</updated><author><name>Giulia Rinaldi</name></author><author><name>Neila Álvarez de Haro</name></author><author><name>Andrew P. Desbois</name></author><author><name>Calum T. Robb</name></author><author><name>Adriano G. Rossi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fish erythrocytes remain nucleated for their life-span, unlike mammalian erythrocytes which undergo enucleation. Asides transportation of oxygen, fish erythrocytes are capable of several immune defence processes. Nucleated fish erythrocytes represent prime candidates for carrying out ETotic responses. ETosis is an evolutionary conserved innate immune defence process found in both vertebrates and invertebrates, which involves the extrusion of DNA studded with antimicrobial proteins into the extracellular space serving to trap and kill microorganisms. In this report, we demonstrate that fish erythrocytes isolated from &lt;italic&gt;Danio rerio&lt;/italic&gt; (zebrafish) produce ETotic-like responses when exposed to chemical and physiological stimuli. &lt;italic&gt;Salmo salar&lt;/italic&gt; (Atlantic salmon) erythrocytes produce similar ETotic responses. We have termed these ET-like formations Fish Erythrocyte Extracellular Traps (FEETs). Interestingly, we discovered that mammalian inducers of NETosis, such as the protein kinase C (PKC) activator phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate and the calcium ionophore ionomycin induced FEETs. Moreover, we found that FEETs are dependent upon activation of PKC and generation of mitochondrial reactive oxygen species. Thus, this brief report represents the first demonstration that fish erythrocytes can exhibit ETotic-like responses, unveiling a previously unknown function of nucleated erythrocytes, and sheds new light on the innate immune arsenal of erythrocytes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455826" rel="alternate" title="Nucleated Fish Erythrocyte Extracellular Traps (FEETs) release is an evolutionary conserved immune defence process (15 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455723</id><title>Deterministic shifts in molecular evolution correlate with convergence to annualism in killifishes (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.884381+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew W. Thompson</name></author><author><name>Amanda C. Black</name></author><author><name>Yu Huang</name></author><author><name>Qiong Shi</name></author><author><name>Andrew I. Furness</name></author><author><name>Ingo Braasch</name></author><author><name>Federico G. Hoffmann</name></author><author><name>Guillermo Ortí</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The repeated evolution of novel life histories correlating with ecological variables offer opportunities to test scenarios of convergence and determinism in genetic, developmental, and metabolic features. Here we leverage the diversity of aplocheiloid killifishes, a clade of teleost fishes that contains over 750 species on three continents. Nearly half of these are “annual” or seasonal species that inhabit bodies of water that desiccate and are unfeasible for growth, reproduction, or survival for weeks to months at a time. We present a large-scale phylogenomic reconstruction of aplocheiloid killifish evolution using newly sequenced transcriptomes from all major clades. We show that developmental dormancy (diapause) and annualism have up to seven independent origins in Africa and America. We then measure evolutionary rates of orthologous genes and show that annual life history is correlated with higher d&lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;/d&lt;italic&gt;S&lt;/italic&gt; ratios. Many of these fast-evolving genes in annual species constitute key developmental genes and nuclear-encoded metabolic genes that control oxidative phosphorylation. Lastly, we compare these fast-evolving genes to genes associated with developmental dormancy and metabolic shifts in killifishes and other vertebrates and thereby identify molecular evolutionary signatures of repeated evolutionary transitions to extreme environments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455723" rel="alternate" title="Deterministic shifts in molecular evolution correlate with convergence to annualism in killifishes (13 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456016</id><title>Maternal and paternal sugar consumption interact to modify offspring life history and physiology (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.884549+00:00</updated><author><name>Tara-Lyn Camilleri-Carter</name></author><author><name>Matthew D.W. Piper</name></author><author><name>Rebecca L. Robker</name></author><author><name>Damian K. Dowling</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Intergenerational effects on offspring phenotypes occur in response to variation in both maternal and paternal nutrition. Because the combined maternal and paternal effects are rarely considered together however, their relative contributions, and the capacity for interactions between parental diets to shape offspring life history and physiology are not understood. To address this, we altered sucrose levels of adult fruit flies (&lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt;) prior to mating, across two generations, producing parent-parent and parent-offspring combinations that were either matched or mismatched in dietary sucrose. We then measured lifespan, fecundity, body mass, and triglyceride levels in parents and offspring. We reveal complex non-additive interactions, that involve diets of each parent and offspring to shape offspring phenotypes, but the effects were generally not consistent with an adaptive response to parental diet. Notably, we find that interacting parental flies (sires and dams) lived longer when their sucrose treatments were matched, but they produced shorter-lived offspring.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456016" rel="alternate" title="Maternal and paternal sugar consumption interact to modify offspring life history and physiology (8 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455804</id><title>Evolutionary dynamics of sex-biased gene expression in a young XY system: Insights from the brown algae (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.884694+00:00</updated><author><name>William J Hatchett</name></author><author><name>Alexander O Jueterbock</name></author><author><name>Martina Kopp</name></author><author><name>James A Coyer</name></author><author><name>Susana M Coelho</name></author><author><name>Galice G Hoarau</name></author><author><name>Agnieszka P Lipinska</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The sex-dependent regulation of gene expression is considered to be  the underlying cause of often extensive, sexually dimorphic traits between males and females. Although the nature and degree of sex-biased gene expression has been well-documented in several animal and plant systems,  far less is known about the commonality, conservation, recruitment mechanisms and evolution of sex-biased genes in  more distant eukaryotic groups. Brown algae are of particular interest for empirical studies on the evolution of sex-biased gene expression, as they have been evolving independently from animals and plants for over one billion years. Here we focus on two brown algal dioecious species, Fucus serratus and Fucus vesiculosus, where male heterogamety (XX/XY) has recently emerged.  Using RNA-seq, we study sex-biased gene expression and discuss different evolutionary forces responsible for the evolution of sex-biased genes. We find that both species evolved masculinized transcriptomes, with sex-biased genes allocated mainly to male reproductive tissue, but  virtually absent in vegetative tissues. Conserved male-biased genes were enriched in functions related to gamete production, along with sperm competition and include two flagellar proteins under positive selection. In contrast to female-biased genes, which show high turnover rates, male-biased genes reveal remarkable conservation of bias and expression levels between the two species. As observed in other XY systems, male-biased genes also display accelerated rates of coding sequence evolution compared to female-biased or unbiased genes. Our results imply that evolutionary forces affect male and female sex-biased genes differently on structural and regulatory levels. Similarly to evolutionary distant plant and animal lineages,  sex-biased gene expression in Fucus evolved during the transition to dioecy to resolve intra-locus sexual conflict arising from anisogamy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455804" rel="alternate" title="Evolutionary dynamics of sex-biased gene expression in a young XY system: Insights from the brown algae (8 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456216</id><title>Accounting for heterogeneity in wild adult samples to measure insecticide resistance in Anopheles malaria vectors (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.884855+00:00</updated><author><name>Inga E. Holmdahl</name></author><author><name>Caroline O. Buckee</name></author><author><name>Lauren M. Childs</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background

Systematic, long-term, and spatially representative monitoring of insecticide resistance in mosquito populations is urgently needed to quantify its impact on malaria transmission, and to combat failing interventions when resistance emerges. Resistance assays on wild-caught adult mosquitoes (known as adult-capture) offer an alternative to the current protocols, and can be done cheaply, in a shorter time frame, and in the absence of an insectary. However, quantitative assessments of the performance of these assays relative to the gold standard, which involves rearing larvae in an insectary, are lacking.

Methodology/Principal findings

We developed a discrete-time deterministic mosquito lifecycle model to simulate insecticide resistance assays from adult-captured mosquito collection in a heterogeneous environment compared to the gold standard larval capture methods, and to quantify possible biases in the results. We incorporated non-lethal effects of insecticide exposure that have been demonstrated in laboratory experiments, spatial structure, and the impact of multiple exposure to insecticides and natural ageing on mosquito death rates during the assay. Using output from this model, we compared the results of these assays to true resistance as measured by the presence of the resistance allele. In simulated samples of 100 test mosquitoes, reflecting WHO-recommended sample sizes, we found that compared to adult-captured assays (MSE = 0.0059), larval-captured assays were a better measure of true resistance (MSE = 0.0018). Using a correction model, we were able to improve the accuracy of the adult-captured assay results (MSE = 0.0038). Bias in the adult-capture assays was dependent on the level of insecticide resistance rather than coverage of bed nets or spatial structure.

Conclusions/Significance

Using adult-captured mosquitoes for resistance assays has logistical advantages over the standard larval-capture collection, and may be a more accurate sample of the mosquito population. These results show that adult-captured assays can be improved using a simple mathematical approach and used to inform resistance monitoring programs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456216" rel="alternate" title="Accounting for heterogeneity in wild adult samples to measure insecticide resistance in Anopheles malaria vectors (8 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456076</id><title>Analysis of wild plant pathogen populations reveals a signal of adaptation in genes evolving for survival in agriculture in the beet rust pathogen (Uromyces beticola) (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.884994+00:00</updated><author><name>Mark McMullan</name></author><author><name>Lawrence Percival-Alwyn</name></author><author><name>Kevin Sawford</name></author><author><name>Gemy Kaithakottil</name></author><author><name>Michelle Grey</name></author><author><name>Helene Yvanne</name></author><author><name>Ross Low</name></author><author><name>Sally Warring</name></author><author><name>Darren Heavens</name></author><author><name>Ned Peel</name></author><author><name>Jakob Kroboth</name></author><author><name>Mark Stevens</name></author><author><name>David Swarbreck</name></author><author><name>Matt Clark</name></author><author><name>Neil Hall</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Improvements in crop resistance to pathogens can reduce yield losses and address global malnourishment today. Gene-for-gene -type interactions can identify new sources of resistance but genetic resistance is often short lived. Ultimately an understanding of how pathogens rapidly adapt will allow us to both increase resistance gene durability and more effectively target chemical treatments. Until recently all agricultural pathogens were living on wild hosts. To understand crop pathogen evolution, we compared genetic diversity in agricultural and wild populations. Wild reservoirs may be the source of emergent pathogen lineages, but here we outline a strategy for comparison of wild and agricultural pathogen populations to highlight genes adapting to agriculture. To address this, we have selected and developed the beet rust system (Beta vulgaris, Uromyces beticola, respectively) as our wild-agricultural model. Our hypothesis is that pathogen adaptation to agricultural crops will be evident as divergence in comparisons of wild and agricultural plant pathogen populations. We sampled isolates in both the wild and agriculture, sequenced and assembled and annotated a large fungal genome and analysed genetic diversity in 42 re-sequenced rust isolates. We found population differentiation between isolates in the wild compared to a predominantly agricultural group. Fungal effector genes are co-evolving with host resistance and are important for successful colonisation. We predicted (and found) that these exhibit a greater signal of diversification and adaptation and more importantly displayed increased wild agricultural divergence. Finding a signal of adaptation in these genes highlights this as an important strategy to identify genes which are key to pathogen success, that analysis of agricultural isolates alone cannot.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456076" rel="alternate" title="Analysis of wild plant pathogen populations reveals a signal of adaptation in genes evolving for survival in agriculture in the beet rust pathogen (Uromyces beticola) (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.14.456331</id><title>Estimation of Cross-Species Introgression Rates using Genomic Data Despite Model Unidentifiability (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.885199+00:00</updated><author><name>Ziheng Yang</name></author><author><name>Thomas Flouris</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The multispecies coalescent with introgression (MSci) model accommodates both the coalescent process and cross-species introgression/ hybridization events, two major processes that create genealogical fluctuations across the genome and gene-tree-species-tree discordance.  Full likelihood implementations of the MSci model take such fluctuations as a major source of information about the history of species divergence and gene flow, and provide a powerful tool for estimating the direction, timing and strength of cross-species introgression using multilocus sequence data.  However, introgression models, in particular those that accommodate bidirectional introgression (BDI), are known to cause unidentifiability issues of the label-switching type, whereby different models or parameters make the same predictions about the genomic data and thus cannot be distinguished by the data.  Nevertheless, there has been no systematic study of unidentifiability when full likelihood methods are applied.  Here we characterize the unidentifiability of arbitrary BDI models and derive simple rules for its identification.  In general, an MSci model with k BDI events has 2^k unidentifiable towers in the posterior, with each BDI event between sister species creating within-model unidentifiability and each BDI between non-sister species creating cross-model unidentifiability.  We develop novel algorithms for processing Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) samples to remove label switching and implement them in the BPP  program.  We analyze genomic sequence data from Heliconius butterflies as well as synthetic data to illustrate the utility of the BDI models and the new algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.14.456331" rel="alternate" title="Estimation of Cross-Species Introgression Rates using Genomic Data Despite Model Unidentifiability (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.453080</id><title>Masculinization of the X-chromosome in aphid soma and gonads (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.885334+00:00</updated><author><name>Julie Jaquiery</name></author><author><name>Jean-Christophe Simon</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Robin</name></author><author><name>Gautier Richard</name></author><author><name>Jean Peccoud</name></author><author><name>Helene Boulain</name></author><author><name>Fabrice Legeai</name></author><author><name>Sylvie Tanguy</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Prunier-Leterme</name></author><author><name>Gael Letrionnaire</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Males and females share essentially the same genome but differ in their optimal values for many phenotypic traits, which can result in intra-locus conflict between the sexes. Aphids display XX/X0 sex chromosomes and combine unusual X chromosome inheritance with cyclical parthenogenesis. Theoretical and empirical works support the hypothesis that the large excess of male-biased genes observed on the aphid X chromosome compared to autosomes has evolved in response to sexual conflicts, by restricting the product of a sexually antagonistic allele to the sex it benefits. However, whether such masculinization of the X affects all tissues (as expected if it evolved in response to sexual conflicts) or reflects tissue specificities (which would contradict the sexual conflict hypothesis) remains an open question. To address it, we measured gene expression in different somatic and gonadic tissues of males, sexual females and parthenogenetic females of the pea aphid. We observed a masculinization of the X at the tissue-level, with male-biased genes being 2.5 to 3.5 more frequent on the X than expected. We also tested the hypothesis that gene duplication can facilitate the attenuation of conflicts by allowing gene copies to neo- or sub-functionalize and reach sex-specific optima. As predicted, X-linked copies of duplicated genes having their other copies on autosomes were more frequently male-biased (40.5% of the genes) than duplicated autosomal genes (6.6%) or X-linked single-copy genes (32.5%). These results highlight a peculiar pattern of expression of X-linked genes in aphids at the tissue level and provides further support for sex-biased expression as a mechanism to attenuate intra-locus sexual conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.453080" rel="alternate" title="Masculinization of the X-chromosome in aphid soma and gonads (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>