<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.821114+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466765</id><title>Global patterns and rates of habitat transitions across the eukaryotic tree of life (88 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.822004+00:00</updated><author><name>Mahwash Jamy</name></author><author><name>Charlie Biwer</name></author><author><name>Daniel Vaulot</name></author><author><name>Aleix Obiol</name></author><author><name>Homgmei Jing</name></author><author><name>Sari Peura</name></author><author><name>Ramon Massana</name></author><author><name>Fabien Burki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The successful colonisation of new habitats has played a fundamental role during the evolution of life. Salinity is one of the strongest barriers for organisms to cross, which has resulted in the evolution of distinct marine and terrestrial (including both freshwater and soil) communities. Although microbes represent by far the vast majority of eukaryote diversity, the role of the salt barrier in shaping the diversity across the eukaryotic tree is poorly known. Traditional views suggest rare and ancient marine-terrestrial transitions, but this view is being challenged by the discovery of several recently transitioned lineages. Here, we investigate habitat evolution across the tree of eukaryotes using a unique set of taxon-rich environmental phylogenies inferred from a combination of long-read and short-read metabarcoding data spanning the ribosomal DNA operon. Our results show that overall marine and terrestrial microbial communities are phylogenetically distinct, but transitions have occurred in both directions in almost all major eukaryotic lineages, with at least 350 transition events detected. Some groups have experienced relatively high rates of transitions, most notably fungi for which crossing the salt barrier has most likely been an important aspect of their successful diversification. At the deepest phylogenetic levels, ancestral habitat reconstruction analyses suggest that eukaryotes may have first evolved in non-saline habitats, and that the two largest known eukaryotic assemblages (TSAR and Amorphea) arose in different habitats. Overall, our findings indicate that crossing the salt barrier has played an important role in eukaryotic evolution by providing new ecological niches to fill.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466765" rel="alternate" title="Global patterns and rates of habitat transitions across the eukaryotic tree of life (88 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466728</id><title>Haldane’s cost of selection imposes a mild constraint on adaptation, with a high proportion of deaths in A. thaliana being selective (43 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.822526+00:00</updated><author><name>Joseph Matheson</name></author><author><name>Moises Exposito-Alonso</name></author><author><name>Joanna Masel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Haldane’s Dilemma refers to the concern that the need for many “selective deaths” to complete a substitution creates a speed limit to adaptation. However, discussion of this concern has been marked by confusion over which features of substitutions produce limits to the speed of adaptation, what those limits are, and the consequences of violating speed limits. The term ‘substitution load’ has been particularly unhelpful in this regard. Here we distinguish different lines of reasoning that lead to speed limits, including one line of reasoning which has not yet been fully addressed. We then apply these lines of reasoning to a dataset measuring survival and fecundity of 517 different genotypes of &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; grown in eight different environmental conditions. We estimate highly permissive limits to the speed of adaptation in all environmental conditions. We also estimate that much higher proportions of deaths contribute to adaptation than were anticipated during historical discussions of speed limits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466728" rel="alternate" title="Haldane’s cost of selection imposes a mild constraint on adaptation, with a high proportion of deaths in A. thaliana being selective (43 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467349</id><title>Sexual reproduction contributes to the evolution of resistance breaking isolates of the spinach pathogen Peronospora effusa (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.823061+00:00</updated><author><name>Petros Skiadas</name></author><author><name>Joel Klein</name></author><author><name>Thomas Quiroz Monnens</name></author><author><name>Joyce Elberse</name></author><author><name>Ronnie de Jonge</name></author><author><name>Guido Van den Ackerveken</name></author><author><name>Michael F. Seidl</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Peronospora effusa causes downy mildew, the economically most important disease of cultivated spinach worldwide. To date, 19 P. effusa races have been denominated based on their capacity to break spinach resistances, but their genetic diversity and the evolutionary processes that contribute to race emergence are unknown. Here, we performed the first systematic analysis of P. effusa races showing that those emerge by both asexual and sexual reproduction. Specifically, we studied the diversity of 26 P. effusa isolates from 16 denominated races based on mitochondrial and nuclear comparative genomics. Mitochondrial genomes based on long-read sequencing coupled with diversity assessment based on short-read sequencing uncovered two mitochondrial haplogroups, each with distinct genome organization. Nuclear genome-wide comparisons of the 26 isolates revealed that ten isolates from six races could clearly be divided into three asexually evolving groups, in concordance with their mitochondrial phylogeny. The remaining isolates showed signals of reticulated evolution and discordance between nuclear and mitochondrial phylogenies, suggesting that these evolved through sexual reproduction. Increased understanding of this pathogen's reproductive modes will provide the framework for future studies into the molecular mechanisms underlying race emergence and into the P. effusa-spinach interaction, thus assisting in sustainable production of spinach through knowledge-driven resistance breeding.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467349" rel="alternate" title="Sexual reproduction contributes to the evolution of resistance breaking isolates of the spinach pathogen Peronospora effusa (13 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466881</id><title>Demographic history shapes genomic variation in an intracellular parasite with a wide geographic distribution (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.824164+00:00</updated><author><name>Pascal Angst</name></author><author><name>Dieter Ebert</name></author><author><name>Peter D. Fields</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Analyzing variation in a species’ genomic diversity can provide insights into its historical demography, biogeography and population structure, and thus, its ecology and evolution. Although such studies are rarely undertaken for parasites, they can be highly revealing because of the parasite’s coevolutionary relationships with hosts. Modes of reproduction and transmission are thought to be strong determinants of genomic diversity for parasites and vary widely among microsporidia (fungal-related intracellular parasites), which are known to have high intraspecific genetic diversity and interspecific variation in genome architecture. Here we explore genomic variation in the microsporidium &lt;italic&gt;Hamiltosporidium&lt;/italic&gt;, a parasite of the freshwater crustacean &lt;italic&gt;Daphnia magna&lt;/italic&gt;, looking especially at which factors contribute to nucleotide variation. Genomic samples from 18 Eurasian populations and a new, long-read based reference genome were used to determine the roles that reproduction mode, transmission mode and geography play in determining population structure and demographic history. We demonstrate two main &lt;italic&gt;H. tvaerminnensis&lt;/italic&gt; lineages and a pattern of isolation-by-distance, but note an absence of congruence between these two parasite lineages and the two Eurasian host lineages. We suggest a comparatively recent parasite spread through Northern Eurasian host populations after a change from vertical to mixed-mode transmission and the loss of sexual reproduction. While gaining knowledge about the ecology and evolution of this focal parasite, we also identify common features that shape variation in genomic diversity for many parasites, e.g., distinct modes of reproduction and the intertwining of host–parasite demographies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466881" rel="alternate" title="Demographic history shapes genomic variation in an intracellular parasite with a wide geographic distribution (9 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466935</id><title>Multiple hybridization events punctuate the evolutionary trajectory of Malassezia furfur (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.824621+00:00</updated><author><name>Bart Theelen</name></author><author><name>Veronica Mixao</name></author><author><name>Giuseppe Ianiri</name></author><author><name>Joleen P.Z. Goh</name></author><author><name>Jan Dijksterhuis</name></author><author><name>Joe Heitman</name></author><author><name>Thomas L. Dawson</name></author><author><name>Toni Gabaldon</name></author><author><name>Teun Boekhout</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Malassezia species are important fungal skin commensals and are part of the normal microbiota of humans and other animals. However, under certain circumstances these fungi can also display a pathogenic behaviour. For example, Malassezia furfur is a common commensal of human skin, and yet is often responsible for skin disorders but also systemic infections. Comparative genomics analysis of M. furfur revealed that some isolates have a hybrid origin, similar to several other recently described hybrid fungal pathogens. Because hybrid species exhibit genomic plasticity that can impact phenotypes, we sought to elucidate the genomic evolution and phenotypic characteristics of M. furfur hybrids in comparison to their parental lineages. To this end, we performed a comparative genomics analysis between hybrid strains and their presumptive parental lineages, and assessed phenotypic characteristics. Our results provide evidence that at least two distinct hybridization events occurred between the same parental lineages, and that the parental strains may have originally been hybrids themselves. Analysis of the mating-type locus reveals that M. furfur has a pseudobipolar mating system, and provides evidence that hybridization involved sexual liaisons resulting in cell-cell fusion leading to a diploid/aneuploid state. This study provides new insights into the evolutionary trajectory of M. furfur and contributes valuable genomic resources for future pathogenicity studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466935" rel="alternate" title="Multiple hybridization events punctuate the evolutionary trajectory of Malassezia furfur (9 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466760</id><title>Natural variation in the maternal and zygotic mRNA complements of the early embryo in Drosophila melanogaster (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.824993+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna A. Feitzinger</name></author><author><name>Anthony Le</name></author><author><name>Ammon Thompson</name></author><author><name>Mehnoor Haseeb</name></author><author><name>Mohan K. Murugesan</name></author><author><name>Austin M. Tang</name></author><author><name>Susan E. Lott</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Maternal gene products supplied to the egg during oogenesis drive the earliest events of development in all metazoans. After the initial stages of embryogenesis, maternal transcripts are degraded as zygotic transcription is activated, this is known as the maternal to zygotic transition (MZT). Altering the abundances of maternally deposited factors in the laboratory can have a dramatic effect on development, adult phenotypes and ultimately fitness. Zygotic transcription activation is a tightly regulated process, where the zygotic genome takes over control of development from the maternal genome, and is required for the viability of the organism. Recently, it has been shown that the expression of maternal and zygotic transcripts have evolved in the Drosophila genus over the course of 50 million years of evolution. However, the extent of natural variation of maternal and zygotic transcripts within a species has yet to be determined. We asked how the maternal and zygotic pools of mRNA vary within and between populations of &lt;italic&gt;D. melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt;. In order to maximize sampling of genetic diversity, African lines of &lt;italic&gt;D. melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; originating from Zambia as well as DGRP lines originating from North America were chosen for transcriptomic analysis. Single embryo RNA-seq was performed at a stage before and a stage after zygotic genome activation in order to determine which transcripts are maternally deposited and which are zygotically expressed within and between these populations. Differential gene expression analysis has been used to quantify quantitative changes in RNA levels within populations as well as fixed expression differences between populations at both stages. Generally, we find that maternal transcripts are more highly conserved, and zygotic transcripts evolve at a higher rate. We find that there is more within population variation in transcript abundance than between populations and that expression variation is highest post-MZT between African lines. Determining the natural variation of gene expression surrounding the MZT in natural populations of &lt;italic&gt;D. melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; gives insight into the extent of how a tightly regulated process may vary within a species, the extent of developmental constraint at both stages and on both the maternal and zygotic genomes, and reveals expression changes allowing this species to adapt as it spread across the world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466760" rel="alternate" title="Natural variation in the maternal and zygotic mRNA complements of the early embryo in Drosophila melanogaster (8 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466376</id><title>Riding into the future on a fly: toward a better understanding of phoresy and avian lice evolution (Phthiraptera) by screening bird carcasses for phoretic lice on hippoboscid flies (Diptera) (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.825297+00:00</updated><author><name>Leshon Lee</name></author><author><name>David J.X. Tan</name></author><author><name>Jozef Oboňa</name></author><author><name>Daniel R. Gustafsson</name></author><author><name>Ang Yuchen</name></author><author><name>Rudolf Meier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many phoretic relationships between insects are understudied because of taxonomic impediments. We here illustrate for avian lice riding on hippoboscid flies how new natural history data on phoretic relationships can be acquired quickly with NGS barcoding. Most avian lice are host-specific, but some can arrive on new hosts by riding hippoboscid flies that feed on bird blood. Our summary of the literature yielded 254 published records which we here show to belong to two large and 13 small interaction networks for birds, flies, and lice. In order to generate new records, we then developed a new protocol based on screening bird carcasses sourced by citizen scientists. The inspection of 131 carcasses from Singapore lead to the first record of a &lt;italic&gt;Guimaraesiella&lt;/italic&gt; louse species riding on &lt;italic&gt;Ornithoica momiyamai&lt;/italic&gt; flies collected from a pitta carcass. Phoresy may explain why this louse species is now known from three phylogenetically disparate hosts (&lt;italic&gt;Pitta moluccensis&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;Ficedula zanthopygia&lt;/italic&gt;; &lt;italic&gt;Pardaliparus elegans&lt;/italic&gt;). A second new case of phoresy enhances a large interaction network dominated by &lt;italic&gt;Ornithophila metallica&lt;/italic&gt;, a cosmopolitan and polyphagous hippoboscid fly species. Overall, we argue that many other two- and three-way phoretic relationships between arthropods (e.g., mites, pseudoscorpiones, beetles, flies) can be resolved using cost-effective large-scale NGS barcoding, which can be used to pre-sort specimens for taxonomic revision and thus partially overcome some taxonomic impediments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466376" rel="alternate" title="Riding into the future on a fly: toward a better understanding of phoresy and avian lice evolution (Phthiraptera) by screening bird carcasses for phoretic lice on hippoboscid flies (Diptera) (7 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467149</id><title>Genomes contain relics of a triplet code connecting the origins of primordial RNA synthesis to the origins of genetically coded protein synthesis (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.825692+00:00</updated><author><name>Geoffrey H. Siwo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Life on earth relies on three types of information polymers-DNA, RNA and proteins. In all organisms and viruses, these molecules are synthesized by the copying of pre-existing templates. A triplet-based code known as the genetic code guides the synthesis of proteins by complex enzymatic machines that decode genetic information in RNA sequences. The origin of the genetic code is one of the most fundamental questions in biology. In this study, computational analysis of about 5,000 species level metagenomes using techniques for the analysis of human language suggests that the genomes of extant organisms contain relics of a distinct triplet code that potentially predates the genetic code. This code defines the relationship between adjacent triplets in DNA/RNA sequences, whereby these triplets predominantly differ by a single base. Furthermore, adjacent triplets encode amino acids that are thought to have emerged around the same period in the earth’s early history. The results suggest that the order of triplets in primordial RNA sequences was associated with the availability of specific amino acids, perhaps due to a coupling of a triplet-based primordial RNA synthesis mechanism to a primitive mechanism of peptide bond formation. Together, this coupling could have given rise to early nucleic acid sequences and a system for encoding amino acid sequences in RNA, i.e. the genetic code. Thus, the central role of triplets in biology potentially extends to the primordial world, contributing to both the origins of genomes and the origins of genetically coded protein synthesis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the most intriguing discoveries in biology is that the order of amino acids in each protein is determined by the order of nucleotides (commonly represented by the letters A, U, G, C) in a biological molecule known as RNA. The genetic code serves as a dictionary that maps each of the 64 triplets ‘words’ in RNA to the 20 amino acids, thereby specifying how information encoded in RNA is decoded into sequences of amino acids (i.e., proteins). The deciphering of the genetic code was one of the greatest discoveries of the 20th century (1968 Nobel Prize in Medicine and Physiology) and is central to modern molecular biology. Yet, how it came to be that the order of triplets in RNA encodes the sequence of the protein synthesized remains one of the most important enigmas of biology. Paradoxically, in all life forms proteins cannot be synthesized without RNA and RNA itself cannot also be synthesized without proteins, presenting a chicken and egg dilemma. By analyzing thousands of microbial genomes using approaches drawn from the field of natural language processing, this study finds that the order of triplets across genomes contains relics of an ancient triplet code, distinct from but closely connected to the genetic code. Unlike the genetic code which specifies the relationship between information in RNA and the sequence of proteins, this ancient code describes the relationship between adjacent triplets in extant genome sequences, whereby such triplets are often different from each other by a single letter. Triplets that are closely related by this ancient code encode amino acids that are thought to have emerged around the same period in the earth’s early history. In other words, a fossil record of the chronological order of appearance of amino acids on early earth appears written in genome sequences. This potentially demonstrates that the process by which RNA sequences were synthesized in the primordial world relied on triplets and was coupled to amino acids available at the time. Hence, the connections between primordial RNA synthesis and a primitive mechanism for linking amino acids to form peptides could have enabled one type of molecule (RNA) to code for the other (protein), facilitating the emergence of the genetic code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467149" rel="alternate" title="Genomes contain relics of a triplet code connecting the origins of primordial RNA synthesis to the origins of genetically coded protein synthesis (6 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.466494</id><title>Towards a Theory of Evolution as Multilevel Learning (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.826032+00:00</updated><author><name>Vitaly Vanchurin</name></author><author><name>Yuri I. Wolf</name></author><author><name>Mikhail Katsnelson</name></author><author><name>Eugene V. Koonin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We apply the theory of learning to physically renormalizable systems in an attempt to develop a theory of biological evolution, including the origin of life, as multilevel learning. We formulate seven fundamental principles of evolution that appear to be necessary and sufficient to render a universe observable and show that they entail the major features of biological evolution, including replication and natural selection. These principles also follow naturally from the theory of learning. We formulate the theory of evolution using the mathematical framework of neural networks, which provides for detailed analysis of evolutionary phenomena. To demonstrate the potential of the proposed theoretical framework, we derive a generalized version of the Central Dogma of molecular biology by analyzing the flow of information during learning (back-propagation) and predicting (forward-propagation) the environment by evolving organisms. The more complex evolutionary phenomena, such as major transitions in evolution, in particular, the origin of life, have to be analyzed in the thermodynamic limit, which is described in detail in the accompanying paper.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.466494" rel="alternate" title="Towards a Theory of Evolution as Multilevel Learning (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466436</id><title>Evolution of warfare by resource raiding favors polymorphism in belligerence and bravery (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.826485+00:00</updated><author><name>Charles Mullon</name></author><author><name>Laurent Lehmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;From protists to primates, intergroup aggression and warfare over resources has been observed in several taxa whose populations typically consist of groups connected by limited genetic mixing. Here, we model the co-evolution between four traits relevant to this setting: (i) investment into common-pool resource production within groups (“helping”); (ii) proclivity to raid other groups to appropriate their resources (“bel-ligerence”); and investments into (iii) defense and (iv) offense of group contests (“defensive and offensive bravery”). We show that when traits co-evolve, the population often experiences disruptive selection favouring two morphs: “Hawks”, who express high levels of both belligerence and offensive bravery; and “Doves”, who express neither. This social polymorphism involves further among-traits associations when the fitness costs of helping and bravery interact. In particular if helping is antagonistic with both forms of bravery, co-evolution leads to the coexistence of individuals that either: (i) do not participate into common-pool resource production but only in its defense and appropriation (“Scrounger Hawks”); or (ii) only invest into common pool resource production (“Producer Doves”). Provided groups are not randomly mixed, these findings are robust to several modelling assumptions. This suggests that inter-group aggression is a potent mechanism in favoring within-group social diversity and behavioural syndromes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466436" rel="alternate" title="Evolution of warfare by resource raiding favors polymorphism in belligerence and bravery (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.463867</id><title>Reconstructing the Origins of a Neuropeptide Signaling System Using the Accelerated Evolution of Biodiverse Cone Snail Venoms (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.826750+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas Lund Koch</name></author><author><name>Iris Bea L Ramiro</name></author><author><name>Paula Flórez-Salcedo</name></author><author><name>Ebbe Engholm</name></author><author><name>Knud Jørgen Jensen</name></author><author><name>Kevin Chase</name></author><author><name>Baldomero M Olivera</name></author><author><name>Walden Emil Bjørn-Yoshimoto</name></author><author><name>Helena Safavi-Hemami</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Somatostatin and its related peptides (SSRPs) form a family of hormones with diverse physiological roles. The ubiquitous presence of SSRPs in vertebrates and several invertebrate deuterostomes suggests an ancient origin of the SSRP signaling system. However, the existence of SSRP genes outside of deuterostomes has not been established and the evolutionary history of this signaling system remains poorly understood. Our recent discovery of SSRP-like toxins (consomatins) in venomous marine cone snails (Conus) suggested the presence of a homologous signaling system in mollusks and potentially other protostomes. Here we identify the molluscan SSRP-like signaling gene that gave rise to the consomatin family. Following recruitment into venom, consomatin genes experience strong positive selection and repeated gene duplications resulting in the formation of a hyper-diverse family of venom peptides. Intriguingly, the largest number of consomatins was found in worm-hunting species (&amp;gt; 400 sequences), indicating a homologous system in annelids, another large protostome phylum. Comprehensive sequence mining enabled the identification of orthologous SSRP-like sequences (and their corresponding orphan receptor) in annelids and several other protostome phyla. These results establish the existence of SSRP-like sequences in many major branches of bilaterians, including xenacoelomorphs, a phylum believed to have emerged before the divergence of protostomes and deuterostomes, ~ 600 My ago. Finally, having a large set of predator-prey SSRP sequences available, we show that while the cone snail's signaling SSRP-like genes are under purifying selection, in striking contrast, the consomatin genes experience rapid directional selection to target receptors in a changing mix of prey.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.463867" rel="alternate" title="Reconstructing the Origins of a Neuropeptide Signaling System Using the Accelerated Evolution of Biodiverse Cone Snail Venoms (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>