<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.762602+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.15.460445</id><title>Physical geography, isolation by distance and environmental variables shape genomic variation of wild barley (Hordeum vulgare L. ssp. spontaneum) in the Southern Levant (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.763120+00:00</updated><author><name>Che-Wei Chang</name></author><author><name>Eyal Fridman</name></author><author><name>Martin Mascher</name></author><author><name>Axel Himmelbach</name></author><author><name>Karl Schmid</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Determining the extent of genetic variation that reflects local adaptation in crop wild relatives is of interest to discovering useful genetic diversity for plant breeding. We investigated the association of genomic variation with geographical and environmental factors in wild barley (&lt;italic&gt;Hordeum vulgare L. ssp. spontaneum&lt;/italic&gt;) populations of the Southern Levant using genotyping-by-sequencing (GBS) of 244 accessions of the Barley1K+ collection. Inference of population structure resulted in four genetic clusters that corresponded to eco-geographical habitats and a significant association of lower gene flow rates with geographical barriers, e.g. the Judaean Mountains and the Sea of Galilee. Redundancy analysis (RDA) revealed that spatial autocorrelation explained 45% and environmental variables explained 15% of total genomic variation. Only 4.5% of genomic variation was exclusively attributed to environmental variation if the component confounded with spatial autocorrelation was excluded. A synthetic environmental variable combining latitude, solar radiation, and accumulated precipitation explained the highest proportion of genomic variation (3.9%). After correcting for population structure, soil water capacity was the most important environmental variable explaining 1.18% of genomic variation. Genome scans with outlier analysis and genome-environment association studies were conducted to identify signatures of adaptation. RDA and outlier methods jointly detected selection signatures in the pericentromeric regions of chromosome 3H, 4H, and 5H, but they mostly disappeared after correction for population structure. In conclusion, adaptation to the highly diverse environments of the Southern Levant over short geographical ranges has a small effect on the genomic diversity of wild barley highlighting the importance of non-selective forces in genetic differentiation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.15.460445" rel="alternate" title="Physical geography, isolation by distance and environmental variables shape genomic variation of wild barley (Hordeum vulgare L. ssp. spontaneum) in the Southern Levant (9 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460362</id><title>Testing for heterogeneous rates of discrete character evolution on phylogenies (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.763352+00:00</updated><author><name>Liam J. Revell</name></author><author><name>Klaus P. Schliep</name></author><author><name>D. Luke Mahler</name></author><author><name>Travis Ingram</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many hypotheses in the field of phylogenetic comparative biology involve specific changes in the rate or process of trait evolution. We present a method designed to test whether the rate of evolution of a discrete character has changed in one or more clades, lineages, or time periods. This method differs from other related approaches (such as the ‘covarion’ model) in that the ‘regimes’ in which the rate or process is postulated to have changed are specified a priori by the user, rather than inferred from the data. Similarly, it differs from methods designed to model a correlation between two binary traits in that the regimes mapped onto the tree are fixed. We apply our method to investigate the rate of dewlap color and/or caudal vertebra number evolution in Caribbean and mainland clades of the diverse lizard genus &lt;italic&gt;Anolis&lt;/italic&gt;. We find little evidence to support any difference between mainland and island evolution in either character. We also examine the statistical properties of the method more generally and show that it has acceptable type I error, parameter estimation, and power. Finally, we discuss the relationship of our method to existing models of heterogeneity in the rate of discrete character evolution on phylogenies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460362" rel="alternate" title="Testing for heterogeneous rates of discrete character evolution on phylogenies (6 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.15.460086</id><title>Little hope for the polyploid endemic Pyrenean Larkspur (Delphinium montanum): evidences from population genomics and Ecological Niche Modelling (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.763523+00:00</updated><author><name>Pascaline Salvado</name></author><author><name>Pere Aymerich Boixader</name></author><author><name>Josep Parera</name></author><author><name>Albert Vila Bonfill</name></author><author><name>Maria Martin</name></author><author><name>Céline Quelennec</name></author><author><name>Jean-Marc Lewin</name></author><author><name>Valérie Hinoux</name></author><author><name>Joris A. M. Bertrand</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Species endemic to restricted geographical ranges represent a particular conservation issue, be it for their heritage interest. In a context of global change, this is particularly the case for plants which belong to high-mountain ecosystems and, because of their ecological requirements, are doomed to survive or disappear on their ‘sky islands’. The Pyrenean Larkspur (&lt;italic&gt;Delphinium montanum&lt;/italic&gt;, Ranunculaceae) is endemic to the Eastern part of the Pyrenees (France and Spain). It is now only observable at a dozen of localities and some populations show signs of decline, such as a recurrent lack of flowering. Implementing population genomic approach (e.g. RAD-seq like) is particularly useful to understand genomic patterns of diversity and differentiation in order to provide recommendations in term of conservation. However, it remains challenging for species such as &lt;italic&gt;D. montanum&lt;/italic&gt; that are autotetraploid with a large genome size (1C-value &amp;gt; 10 pg) as most methods currently available were developed for diploid species. A Bayesian framework able to call genotypes with uncertainty allowed us to assess genetic diversity and population structure in this system. Our results show evidence for inbreeding (mean &lt;italic&gt;G&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;IS&lt;/sub&gt; = 0.361) within all the populations and substantial population structure (mean &lt;italic&gt;G&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;ST&lt;/sub&gt; = 0.403) at the metapopulation level. In addition to a lack of connectivity between populations, spatial projections of Ecological Niche Modelling analyses under different climatic scenarios predict a dramatic decrease of suitable habitat for &lt;italic&gt;D. montanum&lt;/italic&gt; in the future. Based on these results, we discuss the relevance and feasibility of different conservation measures.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.15.460086" rel="alternate" title="Little hope for the polyploid endemic Pyrenean Larkspur (Delphinium montanum): evidences from population genomics and Ecological Niche Modelling (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460260</id><title>Community diversity determines the evolution of synthetic bacterial communities under artificial selection (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.763754+00:00</updated><author><name>Tiffany Raynaud</name></author><author><name>Marion Devers</name></author><author><name>Aymé Spor</name></author><author><name>Manuel Blouin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Artificial selection can be conducted at the community level in the laboratory through a differential propagation of the communities according to their level of expression of a targeted function (i.e. community phenotype). Working with communities instead of individuals as selection units brings in additional sources of variation in the considered phenotype that can arise through changes in community structure and influence the outcome of the artificial selection. These sources of variation could even be increased by manipulating species diversity. In this study, we wanted to assess the effect of manipulating initial community richness on artificial selection efficiency, defined as the change in the targeted function over time as compared to a control treatment without artificial selection. We applied artificial selection for a high productivity on synthetic bacterial communities varying for their initial richness level (from one to 16 strains). Our results showed that, overall, the communities that were artificially selected were 16% more productive than the control communities. Community richness positively influenced community productivity and metabolic capacities and was a strong determinant of the dynamics of community evolution. Our results suggested that community richness could influence artificial selection efficiency but a convergence of the community composition might have limited the effect of diversity on artificial selection efficiency. We propose that applying artificial selection on communities varying for their diversity could allow to find communities differing for their level of expression of a function but also for their responsiveness to artificial selection, provided that their initial composition is different enough.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460260" rel="alternate" title="Community diversity determines the evolution of synthetic bacterial communities under artificial selection (3 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>