<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.266105+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469478</id><title>Real-time and remote MCMC trace inspection with Beastiary (32 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.266371+00:00</updated><author><name>Wytamma Wirth</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Duchene</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bayesian phylogenetic methods have gained substantial popularity in the last decade, due to their ability to incorporate independent information and fit complex models. Most Bayesian implementations rely on Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC), which in turn requires careful interpretation of the output to assess the statistical validity of any resulting inferences. Here we describe Beastiary, a package for real-time and remote inspection of log flies generated by MCMC analysis commonly utilised in Bayesian phylogenetic analysis. Beastiary is an easily deployed web-sever that can be used to summarise and visualise the output of many popular software packages including BEAST, BEAST2, RevBayes, and MrBayes. We describe the overall design and implementation of Beastiary and some typical use cases, with a particular focus on the capability of monitoring analyses from remote servers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469478" rel="alternate" title="Real-time and remote MCMC trace inspection with Beastiary (32 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469546</id><title>Long distance migration is a major factor driving local adaptation at continental scale in Coho Salmon (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.266537+00:00</updated><author><name>Quentin Rougemont</name></author><author><name>Amanda Xuereb</name></author><author><name>Xavier Dallaire</name></author><author><name>Jean-Sebastien Moore</name></author><author><name>Eric Normandeau</name></author><author><name>Eric B Rondeau</name></author><author><name>Ruth Withler</name></author><author><name>Donald Van Doornik</name></author><author><name>Penelope Crane</name></author><author><name>Kerry Naish</name></author><author><name>John-Carlos Garza</name></author><author><name>Terry Beacham</name></author><author><name>Ben F. Koop</name></author><author><name>Louis Bernatchez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Inferring the genomic basis of local adaptation is a long-standing goal of evolutionary biology. Beyond its fundamental evolutionary implications, such knowledge can guide conservation decisions for populations of conservation and management concern. Here, we investigated the genomic basis of local adaptation in the Coho salmon (Oncorhynchus kisutch) across its entire North American range. We hypothesized that extensive spatial variation in environmental conditions and the species homing behavior may promote the establishment of local adaptation. We genotyped 7,829 individuals representing 217 sampling locations at more than 100,000 high-quality RADseq loci to investigate how recombination might affect the detection of loci putatively under selection and took advantage of the precise description of the demographic history of the species from our previous work to draw accurate population genomic inferences about local adaptation. Results indicated that genetic differentiation scans and genetic-environment association analyses were both significantly affected by variation in recombination rate as low recombination regions displayed an increased number of outliers. By taking these confounding factors into consideration, we revealed that migration distance was the primary selective factor driving local adaptation and partial parallel divergence among distant populations. Moreover, we identified several candidates SNP associated with long distance migration and altitude including a gene known to be involved in adaptation to altitude in other species. The evolutionary implications of our findings are discussed along with conservation applications.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469546" rel="alternate" title="Long distance migration is a major factor driving local adaptation at continental scale in Coho Salmon (27 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470139</id><title>Recurrent evolution of cross-resistance in response to selection for improved post-infection survival in Drosophila melanogaster (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.266732+00:00</updated><author><name>Aparajita Singh</name></author><author><name>Aabeer Basu</name></author><author><name>Biswajit Shit</name></author><author><name>Tejashwini Hegde</name></author><author><name>Nitin Bansal</name></author><author><name>Nagaraj Guru Prasad</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The host susceptibility to one pathogen can decrease, increase, or remain unaffected by virtue of the host evolving resistance towards a second pathogen. Negative correlations between a host susceptibility to different pathogens is an often-cited explanation for maintenance of genetic variation in immune function determining traits in a host population. In this study, we investigated the change in susceptibility of Drosophila melanogaster flies to various novel bacterial pathogens after being experimentally selected for increased resistance to one particular bacterial pathogen. We independently selected flies to become more resistant towards Enterococcus faecalis and Pseudomonas entomophila, and baring a few exceptions the evolved populations exhibited cross-resistance against the range of pathogens tested in the study. Neither the identity of the native pathogen nor the host sex was major determining factors in predicting the pattern of cross-resistance exhibited by the selected populations. We therefore report that a generalized cross-resistance to novel pathogens can repeatedly evolve in response to selection for resistance against a single pathogen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470139" rel="alternate" title="Recurrent evolution of cross-resistance in response to selection for improved post-infection survival in Drosophila melanogaster (26 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469925</id><title>Evolutionary features of a prolific subtype of avian influenza A virus in European waterfowl (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.266872+00:00</updated><author><name>Michelle Wille</name></author><author><name>Conny Tolf</name></author><author><name>Neus Latorre-Margalef</name></author><author><name>Ron A. M. Fouchier</name></author><author><name>Rebecca A. Halpin</name></author><author><name>David E. Wentworth</name></author><author><name>Jayna Ragwani</name></author><author><name>Oliver G. Pybus</name></author><author><name>Björn Olsen</name></author><author><name>Jonas Waldenström</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Avian influenza A virus (AIV) is ubiquitous in waterfowl, and detected annually at high prevalence in waterfowl during the Northern Hemipshere autumn. Some AIV subtypes are globally common in waterfowl, such as H3N8, H4N6, and H6N2, and are detected in the same populations at high frequency, annually. In order to investigate genetic features associated to the long-term maintenance of common subtypes in migratory ducks, we sequenced 248 H4 viruses isolated across 8 years (2002-2009) from Mallards (&lt;italic&gt;Anas platyrhynchos&lt;/italic&gt;) sampled in southeast Sweden. Phylogenetic analyses showed that both H4 and N6 sequences fell into in three distinct lineages, structured by year of isolation. Specifically, across the eight years of the study, we observed lineage replacement, whereby a different HA lineage circulated in the population each year. Analysis of deduced amino acid sequences of the HA lineages illustrated key differences in regions of the globular head of hemagglutinin that overlap with established antigentic sites in homologous hemagglutinin H3, suggesting the possibility of antigenic differences among these HA lineages. Beyond HA, lineage replacement was common to all segments, such that novel genome constellations were detected across years. A dominant genome constellation would rapidly amplify in the duck population, followed by unlinking of gene segments as a result of reassortment within 2-3 weeks following introduction. These data help reveal the evolutionary dynamics exhibited by AIV on both annual and decadal scales in an important reservoir host.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469925" rel="alternate" title="Evolutionary features of a prolific subtype of avian influenza A virus in European waterfowl (18 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469565</id><title>Transcriptional and mutational signatures of the aging germline (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.267035+00:00</updated><author><name>Evan Witt</name></author><author><name>Christopher B Langer</name></author><author><name>Li Zhao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aging is a complex biological process which is accompanied by changes in gene expression and mutational load. In many species including humans, old fathers pass on more paternally-derived &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; mutations, however, the cellular basis and cell types driving this pattern are still unclear. To understand the root causes of this phenomenon, we performed single-cell RNA-sequencing (scRNA-seq) on testes from young and old male &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt;, as well as genomic sequencing (DNA-seq) on somatic tissue from the same flies. We found that early germ cells from old and young flies have similar mutational loads, but older flies are less able to remove mutations during spermatogenesis. This indicates that germline mutations arise from primarily non-replicative factors, and that the increased mutational load of older males is due to differences in genome maintenance activities such as repairs to DNA damage. We also found that T&amp;gt;A mutations are enriched in older flies, and transcription-related enrichment terms are depleted in older males. Early spermatogenesis-enriched genes have lower dN/dS than late spermatogenesis-enriched genes, supporting the hypothesis that late spermatogenesis is the source of evolutionary innovation. This transcriptional disruption is reflected in the decreased expression of genome maintenance genes in early germ cells of older flies, as well as potentially aberrant transcription of transposable elements in the aging germline. Our results provide novel insights into the transcriptional and mutational signatures of the male germline.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469565" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptional and mutational signatures of the aging germline (18 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469564</id><title>Effects of the expression of random sequence clones on growth and transcriptome regulation in Escherichia coli (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.267154+00:00</updated><author><name>Devika Bhave</name></author><author><name>Diethard Tautz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Comparative genomic analyses have provided evidence that new genetic functions can emerge out of random nucleotide sequences. Here, we apply a direct experimental approach to study the effects of plasmids harbouring random sequence inserts under the control of an inducible promoter. Based on data from previously described experiments dealing with the growth of clones within whole libraries, we extracted specific clones that had shown either negative or positive effects on relative cell growth. We analysed these individually with respect to growth characteristics and impact on the transcriptome. We find that candidate clones for negative peptides lead to growth arrest by eliciting a general stress response. Overexpression of positive clones, on the other hand, does not change the exponential growth rates of hosts, but they show a growth advantage over a neutral candidate clone when tested in direct competition experiments. Transcriptomic changes in positive clones are relatively moderate and specific to each clone. We conclude from our experiments that random sequence peptides are indeed a suitable source for the &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; evolution of genetic functions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469564" rel="alternate" title="Effects of the expression of random sequence clones on growth and transcriptome regulation in Escherichia coli (14 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470088</id><title>Evolution of Human-specific Alleles Protecting Cognitive Function of Grandmothers (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.267266+00:00</updated><author><name>Sudeshna Saha</name></author><author><name>Naazneen Khan</name></author><author><name>Troy Comi</name></author><author><name>Andrea Verhagen</name></author><author><name>Aniruddha Sasmal</name></author><author><name>Sandra Diaz</name></author><author><name>Hai Yu</name></author><author><name>Xi Chen</name></author><author><name>Joshua M. Akey</name></author><author><name>Martin Frank</name></author><author><name>Pascal Gagneux</name></author><author><name>Ajit Varki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Late-onset Alzheimers Disease (LOAD) pathology is rare in our closest living evolutionary relatives (chimpanzees), which also express much lower microglial levels of CD33(Siglec-3), a myelomonocytic receptor inhibiting innate immune reactivity by extracellular V-set domain recognition of sialic acid(Sia)-containing self-associated molecular patterns (SAMPs). We earlier showed that V-set domain-deficient CD33-variant allele, protective against LOAD, is derived and specific to hominin-lineage. We now report that CD33 also harbors multiple hominin-specific V-set domain mutations and explore selection forces that may have favored such genomic changes. N-glycolylneuraminic acid (Neu5Gc), the preferred Sia-ligand of ancestral CD33 is absent in humans, due to hominin-specific, fixed loss-of-function mutation in CMAH, which generates CMP-Neu5Gc from its precursor, CMP-N-acetylneuraminic acid (Neu5Ac). Extensive mutational analysis and MD-simulations indicate that fixed change in amino acid 21 of hominin V-set domain and conformational changes related to His45 corrected for Neu5Gc-loss by switching to Neu5Ac-recognition. Considering immune-evasive molecular mimicry of SAMPs by pathogens, we found that human-specific pathogens &lt;italic&gt;Neisseria gonorrhoeae&lt;/italic&gt; and Group B &lt;italic&gt;Streptococcus&lt;/italic&gt; (affecting fertility and fetuses/neonates respectively) selectively bind huCD33 and this binding is significantly impacted by amino acid 21 modification. Alongside LOAD-protective CD33 alleles, humans harbor additional, derived, population-universal, cognition-protective variants absent in great ape genomes. Interestingly, 11 of 13 SNPs in these human genes (including CD33), that protect the cognitive health of elderly populations, are not shared by genomes of archaic hominins: Neanderthals and Denisovans. Finally, we present a plausible evolutionary scenario to compile, correlate and comprehend existing knowledge about huCD33 evolution and suggest that grandmothering emerged in humans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470088" rel="alternate" title="Evolution of Human-specific Alleles Protecting Cognitive Function of Grandmothers (12 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469516</id><title>CyanoHABs: unavoidable evolutionary ecological consequence for low nutrient-requiring cyanobacteria in eutrophic water (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.267436+00:00</updated><author><name>Wenduo Cheng</name></author><author><name>Somin Hwang</name></author><author><name>Qisen Guo</name></author><author><name>Haibei Zhang</name></author><author><name>Leyuan Qian</name></author><author><name>Weile Liu</name></author><author><name>Yang Yu</name></author><author><name>Yi Tao</name></author><author><name>Huansheng Cao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mechanism of cyanobacterial harmful algal blooms (CyanoHABs) is complicated and confusing. One major reason is they are studied primarily from an ecological perspective and on bloom-forming species only. This narrow angle loses a broader evolutionary and ecological context in which CyanoHABs occur and fails to provide information on relevant components to achieve a wholistic understanding. To derive a comprehensive mechanism of CyanoHABs, we examine CyanoHABs through the overlooked evolutionary and ecological lenses: evolutionary radiation, ecological comparison with co-living algae, and recently identified genomic functional repertoire between blooming and non-blooming species. We found key factors: (1) elaborate diverse functional repertoire and low nutrient requirement in cyanobacteria molded by early adaptive evolution, (2) cyanobacteria having lower nutrient requirements than green algae indeed, (3) there is no directed evolution in biological functions toward water eutrophication in cyanobacteria, (4) the CyanoHAB-associated functional repertoire are more abundant and complete in blooming than non-blooming species. These factors lead us to postulate a preliminary mechanism of CyanoHABs as a synergistic quad: superior functional repertoire, established with long adaptive radiation under nutrient-deficient conditions and not evolved toward eutrophic conditions, enables cyanobacteria to efficiently utilize elevated nutrients under current eutrophic regime for excess growth and CyanoHABs thereof, due to their lower nutrient requirements than co-living algae. This preliminary synthesis without doubt needs further empirical testing, which can be undertaken with more comparative studies of multiple species using integrated systems biology approaches.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469516" rel="alternate" title="CyanoHABs: unavoidable evolutionary ecological consequence for low nutrient-requiring cyanobacteria in eutrophic water (10 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.27.470071</id><title>Archaic introgression and variation in pharmacogenes and implications for local adaptation (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.267586+00:00</updated><author><name>Tadeusz H Wroblewski</name></author><author><name>Kelsey E Witt</name></author><author><name>Seung-been Lee</name></author><author><name>Ripan S Malhi</name></author><author><name>Emilia Huerta-Sanchez</name></author><author><name>Fernando Villanea</name></author><author><name>Katrina G Claw</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Modern humans carry Neanderthal and Denisovan (archaic) genome elements which may have been a result of environmental adaptation. These effects may be particularly evident in pharmacogenes - genes responsible for the processing of exogenous substances such as food, pollutants, and medications. However, the health implications and contribution of archaic ancestry in pharmacogenes of modern humans remains understudied. We characterize eleven key cytochrome P450 (CYP450) genes involved in drug metabolizing reactions in three Neanderthal and one Denisovan individuals and examine archaic introgression in modern human populations. We infer the metabolizing efficiency of these eleven genes in archaic individuals and show important genetic differences relative to modern human variants. We identify archaic-specific SNVs in each CYP450 gene, including some that are potentially damaging, which may result in altered metabolism in modern human people carrying these variants. We highlight four genes which display interesting patterns of archaic variation: CYP2B6 - we find a large number of unique variants in the Vindija Neanderthal, some of which are shared with a small subset of African modern humans; CYP2C9 - containing multiple variants that are shared between Europeans and Neanderthals; CYP2A6*12 - a variant defined by a hybridization event that was found in humans and Neanderthals, suggesting the recombination event predates both species; and CYP2J2 - in which we hypothesize a Neanderthal variant was re-introduced in non-African populations by archaic admixture. The genetic variation identified in archaic individuals imply environmental pressures that may have driven CYP450 gene evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.27.470071" rel="alternate" title="Archaic introgression and variation in pharmacogenes and implications for local adaptation (7 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469607</id><title>Local adaptation mediated niche expansion in correlation with genetic richness (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.267726+00:00</updated><author><name>Masaomi Kurokawa</name></author><author><name>Issei Nishimura</name></author><author><name>Bei-Wen Ying</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;As a central issue in evolution and ecology, the quantitative relationship among the genome, adaptation and the niche was investigated. Local adaptation of five &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; strains carrying either the wild-type genome or reduced genomes was achieved by experimental evolution. A high-throughput fitness assay of the ancestor and evolved populations across an environmental gradient of eight niches resulted in a total of 80 fitness curves generated from 2,220 growth curves. Further analyses showed that the increases in both local adaptiveness and niche broadness were negatively correlated with genetic richness. Local adaptation caused common niche expansion, whereas niche expansion for generality or speciality was decided by genetic richness. The order of the mutations accumulated stepwise was correlated with the magnitude of the fitness increase attributed to mutation accumulation. Pre-adaptation probably participated in coordination among genetic richness, local adaptation and niche expansion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469607" rel="alternate" title="Local adaptation mediated niche expansion in correlation with genetic richness (6 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469605</id><title>Firefly bioluminescence outshines aerial predators (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.267842+00:00</updated><author><name>Gareth S. Powell</name></author><author><name>Natalie A. Saxton</name></author><author><name>Yelena M. Pacheco</name></author><author><name>Kathrin F. Stanger-Hall</name></author><author><name>Gavin J. Martin</name></author><author><name>Dominik Kusy</name></author><author><name>Ladislav Bocak</name></author><author><name>Marc A. Branham</name></author><author><name>Seth M. Bybee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bioluminescence is found across life and has many functions. Yet we understand very little about its timing and origins, particularly as a predator avoidance strategy. Understanding the timing between bioluminescence and predator origins has yet to be examined and can help elucidate the evolution of the ecologically important signal aposematism. Using the most prevalent bioluminescent group, fireflies, where bioluminescence primarily functions as aposematic and sexual signals, the timing for the origins of both potential predators of fireflies and bioluminescence is explored. Divergence time estimations were performed using a genomic-scale phylogenetic reconstruction Lampyridae, and multiple fossil calibration points, allowing for a robust estimate for the origin of beetle bioluminescence as both a terrestrial and aerial signal. Our results recover the origins of terrestrial beetle bioluminescence at 141 mya and aerial bioluminescence at 133 mya. These ages predate the origins of all known extant aerial predators (i.e., bats and birds) and support the much older terrestrial predators (frogs, ground beetles, lizards, snakes, and hunting spiders) as the most likely drivers of bioluminescence in beetles.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469605" rel="alternate" title="Firefly bioluminescence outshines aerial predators (6 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469544</id><title>The role of indirect effects in coevolution as mutualism transitions into antagonism (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.267992+00:00</updated><author><name>Fernando Pedraza</name></author><author><name>Hanlun Liu</name></author><author><name>Klementyna A. Gawecka</name></author><author><name>Jordi Bascompte</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Species interactions have evolved from antagonistic to mutualistic and back several times throughout life’s history. Yet, it is unclear how changes in the type of interaction between species alter the coevolutionary dynamics of entire communities. This is a pressing matter, as transitions from mutualisms to antagonisms may be becoming more common with human-induced global change. Here, we combine network and evolutionary theory to simulate how shifts in interaction types alter the coevolution of empirical communities. We show that as mutualistic networks shift to antagonistic, selection imposed by direct partners begins to outweigh that imposed by indirect partners. This weakening of indirect effects is associated with communities losing their tight integration of traits and increasing their rate of adaptation. The above changes are more pronounced when specialist consumers are the first species to switch to antagonism. A shift in the outcome of species’ interactions may therefore reverberate across communities and alter the direction and speed of coevolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469544" rel="alternate" title="The role of indirect effects in coevolution as mutualism transitions into antagonism (6 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470265</id><title>X chromosomes show a faster evolutionary rate and complete somatic dosage compensation across Timema stick insect species (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.268115+00:00</updated><author><name>Darren J Parker</name></author><author><name>Kamil S Jaron</name></author><author><name>Zoé Dumas</name></author><author><name>Marc Robinson-Rechavi</name></author><author><name>Tanja Schwander</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sex chromosomes have evolved repeatedly across the tree of life. As they are present in different copy numbers in males and females, they are expected to experience different selection pressures than the autosomes, with consequences including a faster rate of evolution, increased accumulation of sexually antagonistic alleles, and the evolution of dosage compensation. Whether these consequences are general or linked to idiosyncrasies of specific taxa is not clear as relatively few taxa have been studied thus far. Here we use whole-genome sequencing to identify and characterize the evolution of the X chromosome in five species of Timema stick insects with XX:X0 sex determination. The X chromosome had a similar size (approximately 11% of the genome) and gene content across all five species, suggesting that the X chromosome originated prior to the diversification of the genus. Genes on the X showed evidence of a faster evolutionary rate than genes on the autosomes, likely due to less effective purifying selection. Genes on the X also showed almost complete dosage compensation in somatic tissues (heads and legs), but dosage compensation was absent in the reproductive tracts. Contrary to prediction, sex-biased genes showed little enrichment on the X, suggesting that the advantage X-linkage provides to the accumulation of sexually antagonistic alleles is weak. Overall, we found the consequences of X-linkage on gene sequences and expression to be similar across Timema species, showing the characteristics of the X chromosome are surprisingly consistent over 30 million years of evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470265" rel="alternate" title="X chromosomes show a faster evolutionary rate and complete somatic dosage compensation across Timema stick insect species (6 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469450</id><title>Reduction in population size and not a shift in parasite community affect evolution of immune genes in island birds (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.268242+00:00</updated><author><name>Mathilde Barthe</name></author><author><name>Claire Doutrelant</name></author><author><name>Rita Covas</name></author><author><name>Martim Melo</name></author><author><name>Juan Carlos Illera</name></author><author><name>Marie-Ka Tilak</name></author><author><name>Constance Colombier</name></author><author><name>Thibault Leroy</name></author><author><name>Claire Loiseau</name></author><author><name>Benoit Nabholz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Shared ecological conditions encountered by species that colonize islands often lead to the evolution of convergent phenotypes, commonly referred to as “island syndrome”. Reduced immune functions have been previously proposed to be part of the island syndrome, as a consequence of the reduced diversity of pathogens on island ecosystems. According to this hypothesis, immune genes are expected to exhibit genomic signatures of relaxed selection pressure in island species. In this study, we used comparative genomic methods to study immune genes in island species (N = 20) and their mainland relatives (N = 14). We gathered public data as well as generated new data on innate (Toll-Like Receptors, Beta Defensins) and acquired immune genes (Major Histocompatibility Complex classes I and II), but also on hundreds of genes annotated as involved in various immune functions. As a control, we used a set of 97 genes not involved in immune functions, to account for the lower effective population sizes in island species. We used synonymous and non-synonymous variations to estimate the selection pressure acting on immune genes. For the genes evolving under balancing selection, we used simulation to estimate the impact of population size variation. We found a significant effect of drift on immune genes of island species leading to a reduction in genetic diversity and efficacy of selection. However, the intensity of relaxed selection was not significantly different from control genes, except for MHC class II genes. These genes exhibit a significantly higher level of non-synonymous loss of polymorphism than expected assuming only drift and an evolution under frequency dependent selection, possibly due to a reduction of extracellular parasite communities on islands. Overall, our results showed that demographic effects lead to a decrease in the immune functions of island species, but the relaxed selection caused by a reduced parasite pressure may only occur in some immune genes categories.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469450" rel="alternate" title="Reduction in population size and not a shift in parasite community affect evolution of immune genes in island birds (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469825</id><title>Global non-random abundance of short tandem repeats in rodents and primates (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.268398+00:00</updated><author><name>Masoud Arabfard</name></author><author><name>Mahmood Salesi</name></author><author><name>Yazdan Hassani Nourian</name></author><author><name>Iman Arabipour</name></author><author><name>Ali Mohammad Ali Maddi</name></author><author><name>Kaveh Kavousi</name></author><author><name>Mina Ohadi</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;While of predominant abundance across vertebrate genomes and significant biological implications, the relevance of short tandem repeat (STR) abundance to speciation remains largely elusive and attributed to random coincidence for the most part. In a model study, here we collected whole-genome abundance of mono-, di-, and trinucleotide STRs in nine species, encompassing rodents and primates, including rat, mouse, olive baboon, gelada, macaque, gorilla, chimpanzee, bonobo, and human. The obtained unnormalized and normalized data were used to analyze hierarchical clustering of the STR abundances in the selected species.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found massive differential abundances between the rodent and primate orders. In addition, while numerous STRs had random abundance across the nine selected species, the global abundance conformed to three consistent &amp;lt;clusters&amp;gt;, as follows: &amp;lt;rat, mouse&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;gelada, macaque, olive baboon&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;gorilla, chimpanzee, bonobo, human&amp;gt;, which coincided with the phylogenetic distances of the selected species (p&amp;lt; 4E-05). Exceptionally, in the trinucleotide STR compartment, human was significantly distant from all other species.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We propose that the global abundance of STRs is non-random in rodents and primates, and probably had a determining impact on the speciation of the two orders. We also propose the STRs and STR lengths which specifically coincided with the phylogeny of the selected species.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469825" rel="alternate" title="Global non-random abundance of short tandem repeats in rodents and primates (4 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>