<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular evolutionary biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.922822+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/evolutionary-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467712</id><title>The molecular evolution of spermatogenesis across mammals (254 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.923320+00:00</updated><author><name>Florent Murat</name></author><author><name>Noe Mbengue</name></author><author><name>Sofia Boeg Winge</name></author><author><name>Timo Trefzer</name></author><author><name>Evgeny Leushkin</name></author><author><name>Mari Sepp</name></author><author><name>Margarida Cardoso-Moreira</name></author><author><name>Julia Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Celine Schneider</name></author><author><name>Katharina Mößinger</name></author><author><name>Thoomke Brüning</name></author><author><name>Francesco Lamanna</name></author><author><name>Meritxell Riera Belles</name></author><author><name>Christian Conrad</name></author><author><name>Ivanela Kondova</name></author><author><name>Ronald Bontrop</name></author><author><name>Rüdiger Behr</name></author><author><name>Philipp Khaitovich</name></author><author><name>Svante Pääbo</name></author><author><name>Tomas Marques-Bonet</name></author><author><name>Frank Grützner</name></author><author><name>Kristian Almstrup</name></author><author><name>Mikkel Heide Schierup</name></author><author><name>Henrik Kaessmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The testis is a key male reproductive organ that produces gametes through the process of spermatogenesis. Testis morphologies and spermatogenesis evolve rapidly in mammals, presumably due to the evolutionary pressure on males to be reproductively successful&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt;. The rapid evolution of the testis was shown to be reflected at the molecular level based on bulk-tissue work&lt;sup&gt;3-8&lt;/sup&gt;, but the molecular evolution of individual spermatogenic cell types across mammalian lineages remains largely uncharacterized. Here we report evolutionary analyses of single-nucleus transcriptome data for testes from eleven species that cover the three major mammalian lineages (eutherians, marsupials, egg-laying monotremes) and birds (the evolutionary outgroup), and include seven key primates. Our analyses reveal that the rapid evolution of the testis is driven by accelerated fixation rates of gene expression changes, amino acid altering substitutions, and newly emerged genes in late spermatogenic stages – likely facilitated by reduced pleiotropic constraints, haploid selection, and a transcriptionally permissive chromatin environment. We identify temporal expression changes of individual genes across species, which may have contributed to the emergence of species-specific phenotypes, but also conserved expression programs underlying ancestral spermatogenic processes. Sex chromosome analyses show that genes predominantly expressed in spermatogonia (i.e., germ cells fueling spermatogenesis) and Sertoli cells (i.e., somatic supporting cells) independently accumulated on X chromosomes across mammals during evolution, presumably due to male-beneficial selective forces. Further work uncovered that the process of meiotic sex chromosome inactivation (MSCI) also occurs in monotremes and hence is common to the different mammalian sex chromosome systems, contrary to previous inferences&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;. Thus, the general mechanism of meiotic silencing of unsynapsed chromatin (MSUC), which underlies MSCI, represents an ancestral mammalian feature. Together, our study illuminates the cellular and molecular evolution of mammalian spermatogenesis and associated selective forces, and provides a resource for investigating the biology of the testis across mammals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467712" rel="alternate" title="The molecular evolution of spermatogenesis across mammals (254 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468220</id><title>The chromatin-regulating CoREST complex is animal specific and essential for development in the cnidarian Nematostella vectensis (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.924058+00:00</updated><author><name>James M Gahan</name></author><author><name>Maria Hernandez-Valladares</name></author><author><name>Fabian Rentzsch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chromatin-modifying proteins are key players in the regulation of development and cell differentiation in animals. Many individual chromatin modifiers, however, predate the evolution of animal multicellularity and how they became integrated into the regulatory networks underlying development is unclear. Here we show that CoREST is an animal-specific protein that assembles a conserved, vertebrate-like histone-modifying complex including Lsd1 and HDAC1/2 in the sea anemone Nematostella vectensis. We further show that NvCoREST expression overlaps fully with that of NvLsd1 throughout development. NvCoREST mutants, generated using CRISPR-Cas9, reveal essential roles during development and for the differentiation of cnidocytes, thereby phenocopying NvLsd1 mutants. We also show that this requirement is cell autonomous using a cell-type-specific rescue approach. Together, this shows that the evolution of CoREST allowed the formation of a chromatin-modifying complex that was present before the last common cnidarian-bilaterian ancestor and thus represents an ancient component of the animal developmental toolkit.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468220" rel="alternate" title="The chromatin-regulating CoREST complex is animal specific and essential for development in the cnidarian Nematostella vectensis (16 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.467240</id><title>Interacting host modifier systems control Wolbachia-induced cytoplasmic incompatibility in a haplodiploid mite (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.925070+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicky Wybouw</name></author><author><name>Frederik Mortier</name></author><author><name>Dries Bonte</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many reproductive parasites such as &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; spread within host populations by inducing cytoplasmic incompatibility (CI). CI occurs when parasite-modified sperm fertilizes uninfected eggs. In haplodiploid hosts, CI can lead to different phenotypes depending on whether the fertilized eggs die or develop into males. Genetic conflict theories predict the evolution of host modulation of CI, which in turn strongly influences the stability of reproductive parasitism. Yet, despite the ubiquity of CI-inducing parasites in nature, there is no conclusive evidence for strong intraspecific host modulation of CI strength and phenotype. Here, we tested for intraspecific host modulation of &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt;-induced CI in haplodiploid &lt;italic&gt;Tetranychus&lt;/italic&gt; spider mites. Using a single CI-inducing &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; variant and mitochondrion, a &lt;italic&gt;Tetranychus urticae&lt;/italic&gt; nuclear panel was created that consisted of infected and cured near-isogenic lines. We performed a highly replicated age-synchronized full diallel cross comprised of incompatible and compatible control crosses. We uncovered host modifier systems that strongly suppress CI strength when carried by infected &lt;italic&gt;T. urticae&lt;/italic&gt; males. Interspecific crosses showed that the male modifier systems suppress CI strength across species boundaries. We also observed a continuum of CI phenotypes in our crosses and identified strong intraspecific female modulation of CI phenotype when paired with a specific male genotype. Crosses established a recessive genetic basis for the maternal effect and were consistent with polygenic Mendelian inheritance. Our findings identify spermatogenesis as an important target of selection for host suppression of CI strength and underscore the importance of maternal genetic effects for the CI phenotype. Both mechanisms interacted with the genotype of the mating partner, revealing that intraspecific host modulation of CI strength and phenotype is underpinned by complex genetic architectures.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.467240" rel="alternate" title="Interacting host modifier systems control Wolbachia-induced cytoplasmic incompatibility in a haplodiploid mite (12 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467730</id><title>Lack of Fe(II) transporters in basal Cyanobacteria complicates iron uptake in ferruginous Archean oceans (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.932976+00:00</updated><author><name>Tristan C. Enzingmüller-Bleyl</name></author><author><name>Joanne S. Boden</name></author><author><name>Achim J. Herrmann</name></author><author><name>Katharina W. Ebel</name></author><author><name>Patricia Sánchez-Baracaldo</name></author><author><name>Nicole Frankenberg-Dinkel</name></author><author><name>Michelle M. Gehringer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cyanobacteria oxygenated Earth’s atmosphere during the Great Oxygenation Event (GOE) through oxygenic photosynthesis. Their high iron requirement was presumed met by high levels of Fe(II) in the anoxic Archean ocean. &lt;bold&gt;Here we show that&lt;/bold&gt; most basal Cyanobacteria cannot synthesize the primary Fe(II) transporter, FeoB. Relaxed molecular clock analyses estimate the arrival of FeoB, as well as the Fe(III) transporters, cFTR1 and FutB, in the Cyanobacteria after the GOE. Furthermore &lt;italic&gt;Pseudanabaena&lt;/italic&gt; sp. PCC7367, a basal marine, benthic strain grown under simulated Archean conditions, constitutively expressed &lt;italic&gt;cftr1&lt;/italic&gt;, even after the addition of Fe(II). By utilizing gene expression studies under a simulated Archean atmosphere, as well as comparative genomics, phylogenetics and molecular clock analyses, this study identified a need to reappraise iron uptake in ancestral Cyanobacteria, as genetic profiling suggests that scavenging of siderophore bound Fe(III), rather than Fe(II), appears to have been the means of iron acquisition prior to the GOE.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467730" rel="alternate" title="Lack of Fe(II) transporters in basal Cyanobacteria complicates iron uptake in ferruginous Archean oceans (10 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467935</id><title>Genome-wide selection signatures reveal widespread synergistic effects of culture conditions and temperature stress in Drosophila melanogaster (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.933272+00:00</updated><author><name>Burny Claire</name></author><author><name>Nolte Viola</name></author><author><name>Dolezal Marlies</name></author><author><name>Schlötterer Christian</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Experimental evolution combined with whole-genome sequencing is a powerful approach to study the adaptive architecture of selected traits, in particular when replicated experimental populations evolving in opposite selective conditions (e.g. hot vs. cold temperature) are compared. Nevertheless, such comparisons could be affected by environmental effects shared between selective regimes (e.g. laboratory adaptation), which complicate the interpretation of selection signatures. Here, we used an experimental design, which takes advantage of the simplicity of selection signatures from founder populations with reduced variation, to study the fitness consequences of the laboratory environment (culture conditions) at two temperature regimes. After 20 generations of adaptation at 18°C and 29°C, strong genome-wide selection signatures were observed. About one third of the selection signatures can be either attributed to temperature effects, laboratory adaptation or the joint effects of both. The fitness consequences reflecting the combined effects of temperature and laboratory adaptation were more extreme in the hot environment for 83% of the affected genomic regions, fitting the pattern of larger expression differences between founders at 29°C. We propose that evolve and resequence (E&amp;amp;R) with reduced genetic variation allows to study genome-wide fitness consequences driven by the interaction of multiple environmental factors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467935" rel="alternate" title="Genome-wide selection signatures reveal widespread synergistic effects of culture conditions and temperature stress in Drosophila melanogaster (10 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467735</id><title>TreeSearch: morphological phylogenetic analysis in R (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.933421+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin R. Smith</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;TreeSearch is an R package for phylogenetic analysis, optimized for morphological datasets. Tree search may be conducted using under equal or implied step weights with an explicit (albeit inexact) allowance for inapplicable character entries, avoiding some of the pitfalls inherent in standard parsimony methods. Profile parsimony and user-specified optimality criteria are supported.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A graphical interface, which requires no familiarity with R, is designed to help a user to improve the quality of datasets through critical review of underpinning character codings; and to obtain additional information from results by identifying and summarising clusters of similar trees, mapping the distribution of trees, and removing ‘rogue’ taxa that obscure underlying relationships.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Taken together, the package aims to support methodological rigour at each step of data collection, analysis, and the exploration of phylogenetic results.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467735" rel="alternate" title="TreeSearch: morphological phylogenetic analysis in R (7 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.466920</id><title>Long-term evolution of quantitative traits in the Drosophila melanogaster species subgroup (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.933535+00:00</updated><author><name>Amir Yassin</name></author><author><name>Nelly Gidaszewski</name></author><author><name>Vincent Debat</name></author><author><name>Jean R. David</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Quantitative genetics aims at untangling the genetic and environmental effects on phenotypic variation. Trait heritability, which summarizes the relative importance of genetic effects, is estimated at the intraspecific level, but theory predicts that heritability could influence long-term evolution of quantitative traits. The phylogenetic signal concept bears resemblance to heritability and it has often been called species-level heritability. Under certain conditions, such as trait neutrality or contribution to phylogenesis, within-species heritability and between-species phylogenetic signal should be correlated. Here, we investigate the potential relationship between these two concepts by examining the evolution of multiple morphological traits for which heritability has been estimated in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt;. Specifically, we analysed 42 morphological traits in both sexes on a phylogeny inferred from 22 nuclear genes for nine species of the &lt;italic&gt;melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; subgroup. We used Pagel’s λ as a measurement of phylogenetic signal because it is the least influenced by the number of analysed taxa. Pigmentation traits showed the strongest concordance with the phylogeny, but no correlation was found between phylogenetic signal and heritability estimates mined from the literature. We obtained data for multiple climatic variables inferred from the geographical distribution of each species. Phylogenetic regression of quantitative traits on climatic variables showed a significantly positive correlation with heritability. Convergent selection, the response to which depends on the trait heritability, may have led to the null association between phylogenetic signal and heritability for morphological traits in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt;. We discuss the possible causes of discrepancy between both statistics and caution against their confusion in evolutionary biology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.466920" rel="alternate" title="Long-term evolution of quantitative traits in the Drosophila melanogaster species subgroup (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468115</id><title>Phylogenetic diversity of two common Trypanosoma cruzi lineages in the Southwestern United States (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.933666+00:00</updated><author><name>Carlos A Flores-Lopez</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth A Mitchell</name></author><author><name>Carolina E Reisenman</name></author><author><name>Sahotra Sarkar</name></author><author><name>Philip C Williamson</name></author><author><name>Carlos A Machado</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Trypanosoma cruzi is the causative agent of Chagas disease, a devastating parasitic disease endemic to Central and South America, Mexico, and the USA. We characterized the genetic diversity of T. cruzi circulating in five triatomine species (Triatoma gerstaeckeri, T. lecticularia, T. indictiva, T. sanguisuga and T. recurva) collected in Texas and Southern Arizona using nucleotide sequences from four single-copy loci (COII-ND1, MSH2, DHFR-TS, TcCLB.506529.310). All T. cruzi variants fall in two main genetic lineages: 75% of the samples corresponded to T. cruzi Discrete Typing Unit (DTU) I (TcI), and 25% to a North American specific lineage previously labelled TcIV-USA. Phylogenetic and sequence divergence analyses of our new data plus all previously published sequence data from those 4 genes collected in the USA, show that TcIV-USA is significantly different from any other previously defined T. cruzi DTUs. The significant level of genetic divergence between TcIV-USA and other T. cruzi lineages should lead to an increased focus on understanding the epidemiological importance of this lineage, as well as its geographical range and pathogenicity in humans and domestic animals. Our findings further corroborate the fact that there is a high genetic diversity of the parasite in North America and emphasize the need for appropriate surveillance and vector control programs for Chagas disease in southern USA and Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468115" rel="alternate" title="Phylogenetic diversity of two common Trypanosoma cruzi lineages in the Southwestern United States (5 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>