<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv neuroscience preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.408838+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neuroscience/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.27.446063</id><title>Distinct threat and valence signals in rat nucleus accumbens core (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.409377+00:00</updated><author><name>Madelyn H. Ray</name></author><author><name>Mahsa Moaddab</name></author><author><name>Michael A. McDannald</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Appropriate responding to threat and reward is essential to survival. The nucleus accumbens core (NAcc) is known to support and organize reward behavior. More recently our laboratory has shown the NAcc is necessary to discriminate cues for threat and safety. To directly reveal NAcc threat responding, we recorded single-unit activity from 7 female rats undergoing Pavlovian fear discrimination. Rats fully discriminated cues for danger, uncertainty, and safety. Demonstrating direct threat responding, most NAcc neurons showed greatest firing changes to danger and uncertainty. Heterogeneity in cue and reward firing led to the detection of multiple, functional populations. One NAcc population specifically decreased firing to threat (danger and uncertainty). A separate population bi-directionally signaled valence through firing decreases to negative valence events (danger and uncertainty) and opposing firing increases to positive valence events (reward and safety onset). The findings point to the NAcc as a neural source of threat information and a more general valence hub.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.27.446063" rel="alternate" title="Distinct threat and valence signals in rat nucleus accumbens core (29 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.446153</id><title>Mild traumatic brain injury/ concussion initiates an atypical astrocyte response caused by blood-brain barrier dysfunction (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.409702+00:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin P Heithoff</name></author><author><name>Kijana K George</name></author><author><name>Oleksii Shandra</name></author><author><name>Stefanie Robel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mild traumatic brain injury/ concussion (mTBI) account for 70-90% of all reported TBI cases and cause long lasting neurological consequences in 10 to 40% of patients. Recent clinical studies revealed increased blood-brain barrier (BBB) permeability in mTBI patients, which correlated with secondary damage after mTBI. However, the cascade of cellular events initiated by exposure to blood-borne factors resulting in sustained damage are not fully resolved. We previously reported that astrocytes respond atypically to mTBI rapidly downregulating many proteins essential to their homeostatic function while classic scar formation does not occur. Here, we tested the hypothesis that mTBI -induced BBB damage causes atypical astrocytes through exposure to blood-borne factors. Using a mTBI mouse model, 2-photon imaging, an endothelial cell-specific genetic ablation approach, and serum-free primary astrocyte cultures, we demonstrated that areas with atypical astrocytes coincide with BBB damage and that exposure of astrocytes to plasma proteins is sufficient to initiate downregulation of astrocyte homeostatic proteins. While mTBI resulted in frequent impairment of both physical and metabolic BBB properties and leakage of small-sized blood-borne factors, deposition of the coagulation factor fibrinogen or vessel rupture were rare. Surprisingly, even months after mTBI BBB repair did not occur in areas with atypical astrocytes. Together, these findings implicate that even relatively small BBB disturbances are sustained long-term and render nearby astrocytes dysfunctional, likely at the cost of neuronal health and function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.446153" rel="alternate" title="Mild traumatic brain injury/ concussion initiates an atypical astrocyte response caused by blood-brain barrier dysfunction (16 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.445554</id><title>Midfrontal theta tACS facilitates motor coordination in dyadic human-avatar motor interactions (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.409895+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah Boukarras</name></author><author><name>Duru Gun Özkan</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Era</name></author><author><name>Quentin Moreau</name></author><author><name>Gaetano Tieri</name></author><author><name>Matteo Candidi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Synchronous interpersonal motor interactions require moment-to-moment predictions and proactive monitoring of the partner’s actions. Neurophysiologically, this is highlighted by an enhancement of midfrontal theta activity. In the present study we explored the causal role of midfrontal theta for interpersonal motor interactions employing transcranial alternating current stimulation (tACS). We implemented a realistic human-avatar interaction task in immersive virtual reality (IVR) where participants controlled a virtual arm and hand to press a button synchronously with a virtual partner. Participants completed the task while receiving theta (Experiment 1) or beta (control frequency, Experiment 2) EEG-informed tACS over the frontal midline, as well as sham stimulation as a control. Results showed that frontal theta tACS significantly improved behavioural performance (by reducing interpersonal asynchrony) and participants’ motor strategies (by increasing movement times and reducing reaction times), while beta tACS had no effect on these measures. These results suggest that theta tACS over frontal areas facilitates action monitoring and motor abilities supporting interpersonal interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.445554" rel="alternate" title="Midfrontal theta tACS facilitates motor coordination in dyadic human-avatar motor interactions (13 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.27.445993</id><title>Additive Effects of Cognitive Load, Motor Demand, and Environmental Complexity on Attention: A Real-World EEG-study (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.410115+00:00</updated><author><name>Magnus Liebherr</name></author><author><name>Andrew W. Corcoran</name></author><author><name>Phillip M. Alday</name></author><author><name>Scott Coussens</name></author><author><name>Valeria Bellan</name></author><author><name>Caitlin A. Howlett</name></author><author><name>Maarten A. Immink</name></author><author><name>Mark Kohler</name></author><author><name>Matthias Schlesewsky</name></author><author><name>Ina Bornkessel-Schlesewsky</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The capacity to regulate one’s attention in accordance with fluctuating task demands and environmental contexts is an essential feature of adaptive behavior. Although the electrophysiological correlates of attentional processing have been extensively studied in the laboratory, relatively little is known about the way they unfold under more variable, ecologically-valid conditions. Accordingly, this study employed a ‘real-world’ EEG design to investigate how attentional processing varies under increasing levels of cognitive, motor, and environmental demand. Forty-four participants were exposed to an auditory oddball task while (1) sitting in a quiet room inside the lab, (2) walking around a sports field, and (3) wayfinding across a university campus. In each condition, participants were instructed to either attend to (i.e., count) or ignore oddball stimuli. While behavioral performance was similar across the lab and field conditions, oddball count accuracy was significantly reduced in the campus condition. Moreover, event-related potential components (mismatch negativity and P3) elicited in both ‘real-world’ settings differed significantly from those obtained under laboratory conditions. These findings demonstrate the impact of environmental factors on attentional processing during simultaneously-performed motor and cognitive tasks, highlighting the value of incorporating dynamic and unpredictable contexts within naturalistic designs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.27.445993" rel="alternate" title="Additive Effects of Cognitive Load, Motor Demand, and Environmental Complexity on Attention: A Real-World EEG-study (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.29.445964</id><title>Effect sizes and test-retest reliability of the fMRI-based Neurologic Pain Signature (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.410477+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaochun Han</name></author><author><name>Yoni K. Ashar</name></author><author><name>Philip Kragel</name></author><author><name>Bogdan Petre</name></author><author><name>Victoria Schelkun</name></author><author><name>Lauren Atlas</name></author><author><name>Luke J. Chang</name></author><author><name>Marieke Jepma</name></author><author><name>Leonie Koban</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Reynolds Losin</name></author><author><name>Mathieu Roy</name></author><author><name>Choong-Wan Woo</name></author><author><name>Tor D. Wager</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Identifying biomarkers that predict mental states with large effect sizes and high test-retest reliability is a growing priority for fMRI research. We examined a well-established multivariate brain measure that tracks pain induced by nociceptive input, the Neurologic Pain Signature (NPS). In N = 295 participants across eight studies, NPS responses showed a very large effect size in predicting within-person single-trial pain reports (d = 1.45) and medium effect size in predicting individual differences in pain reports (d = 0.49, average r = 0.20). The NPS showed excellent short-term (within-day) test-retest reliability (ICC = 0.84, with average 69.5 trials/person). Reliability scaled with the number of trials within-person, with ≥60 trials required for excellent test-retest reliability. Reliability was comparable in two additional studies across 5-day (N = 29, ICC = 0.74, 30 trials/person) and 1-month (N = 40, ICC = 0.46, 5 trials/person) test-retest intervals. The combination of strong within-person correlations and only modest between-person correlations between the NPS and pain reports indicates that the two measures have different sources of between-person variance. The NPS is not a surrogate for individual differences in pain reports, but can serve as a reliable measure of pain-related physiology and mechanistic target for interventions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.29.445964" rel="alternate" title="Effect sizes and test-retest reliability of the fMRI-based Neurologic Pain Signature (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445394</id><title>Quantifying brain state transition cost via Schrödinger’s bridge (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.411345+00:00</updated><author><name>Genji Kawakita</name></author><author><name>Shunsuke Kamiya</name></author><author><name>Shuntaro Sasai</name></author><author><name>Jun Kitazono</name></author><author><name>Masafumi Oizumi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Quantifying brain state transition cost is a fundamental problem in systems neuroscience. Previous studies utilized network control theory to measure the cost by considering a neural system as a deterministic dynamical system. However, this approach does not capture the stochasticity of neural systems, which is important for accurately quantifying brain state transition cost. Here, we propose a novel framework based on optimal control in stochastic systems. In our framework, we quantify the transition cost as the Kullback-Leibler divergence from an uncontrolled transition path to the optimally controlled path, which is known as Schrödinger’s bridge. To test its utility, we applied this framework to functional magnetic resonance imaging data from the Human Connectome Project and computed the brain state transition cost in cognitive tasks. We demonstrate correspondence between brain state transition cost and the difficulty of tasks. The results suggest that our framework provides a general theoretical tool for investigating cognitive functions from the viewpoint of transition cost.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445394" rel="alternate" title="Quantifying brain state transition cost via Schrödinger’s bridge (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445057</id><title>A Promising Chemical Series of Positive Allosteric Modulators of the μ-Opioid Receptor that Enhance the Antinociceptive Efficacy of Opioids but not their Adverse Effects (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.411828+00:00</updated><author><name>Kerri D. Pryce</name></author><author><name>Hye Jin Kang</name></author><author><name>Farhana Sakloth</name></author><author><name>Yongfeng Liu</name></author><author><name>Susan Khan</name></author><author><name>Katalin Toth</name></author><author><name>Abhijeet Kapoor</name></author><author><name>Andrew Nicolais</name></author><author><name>Tao Che</name></author><author><name>Lihuai Qin</name></author><author><name>Feodora Bertherat</name></author><author><name>H. Ümit Kaniskan</name></author><author><name>Jian Jin</name></author><author><name>Michael D. Cameron</name></author><author><name>Bryan L. Roth</name></author><author><name>Venetia Zachariou</name></author><author><name>Marta Filizola</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Positive allosteric modulators (PAMs) of the µ-opioid receptor (MOR) have been proposed to exhibit therapeutic potential by maximizing the analgesic properties of clinically used opioid drugs while limiting their adverse effects or risk of overdose as a result of using lower drug doses. We herein report &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; characterization of two small molecules from a chemical series of MOR PAMs that exhibit: (i) MOR PAM activity and receptor subtype selectivity &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, (ii) a differential potentiation of the antinociceptive effect of oxycodone, morphine, and methadone in mouse models of pain that roughly correlates with &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; activity, and (iii) a lack of potentiation of adverse effects associated with opioid administration, such as somatic withdrawal, respiratory depression, and analgesic tolerance. This series of MOR PAMs holds promise for the development of adjuncts to opioid therapy to mitigate against overdose and opioid use disorders.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445057" rel="alternate" title="A Promising Chemical Series of Positive Allosteric Modulators of the μ-Opioid Receptor that Enhance the Antinociceptive Efficacy of Opioids but not their Adverse Effects (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.445123</id><title>Fast photoswitchable molecular prosthetics control neuronal activity in the cochlea (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.412371+00:00</updated><author><name>Aida Garrido-Charles</name></author><author><name>Antoine Huet</name></author><author><name>Carlo Matera</name></author><author><name>Anupriya Thirumalai</name></author><author><name>Amadeu Llebaria</name></author><author><name>Tobias Moser</name></author><author><name>Pau Gorostiza</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Artificial control of neuronal activity enables studies of neural circuits and restoration of neural function. Direct, rapid, and sustained photocontrol of intact neurons could overcome shortcomings of established electrical stimulation such as poor selectivity. We have developed fast photoswitchable ligands of glutamate receptors to establish such control in the auditory system. The new photoswitchable ligands produced photocurrents in untransfected neurons upon covalently tethering to endogenous glutamate receptors and activating them reversibly with visible light pulses of few milliseconds. As a proof of concept of these molecular prostheses, we apply them to the ultrafast synapses of auditory neurons of the cochlea that encode sound and provide auditory input to the brain. This drug-based method affords kilohertz rate stimulation of auditory neurons of adult gerbils without genetic manipulation that would be required for their optogenetic control. The new photoswitchable ligands are also broadly applicable to spatiotemporally control fast spiking interneurons in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.445123" rel="alternate" title="Fast photoswitchable molecular prosthetics control neuronal activity in the cochlea (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445378</id><title>Temporal characteristics of functional connectome reconfigurations are heritable and related to cognition (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.412697+00:00</updated><author><name>Suhnyoung Jun</name></author><author><name>Thomas H. Alderson</name></author><author><name>Andre Altmann</name></author><author><name>Sepideh Sadaghiani</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The brain’s functional connectivity architecture (functional connectome) is dynamic, constantly reconfiguring in an individual-specific manner and contributing to inter-individual variability in cognitive performances. However, to what extent genetic effects shape the dynamic reconfigurations of the functional connectome is largely unknown. This paper assesses whether dynamic connectome features are heritable, quantifies their heritability, and explores their association with cognitive phenotypes. We identified discrete connectome states from resting-state fMRI data (n = 1003 including twins and non-twin siblings) and obtained multivariate features, each describing temporal or spatial characteristics of connectome dynamics. We found strong evidence that the temporal features, particularly fractional occupancy (FO) and transition probability (TP), were heritable. Importantly, a substantial proportion of phenotypic variance of these features (35% of FO and 41% of TP) was explained by genetic effects. The effect was stable after adjusting for head motion, independent of global signal regression and the chosen number of states, and absent in surrogate data. Contrarily, the data did not provide robust support for heritability of spatial features suggesting that genetic effects primarily contribute to how the connectome &lt;italic&gt;transitions&lt;/italic&gt; across states, rather than the precise way in which the states are spatially instantiated. Notably, temporal phenotypes also captured variability in cognitive performance. Overall, our findings demonstrate a link between genetic makeup and temporal reconfigurations of the functional connectome, suggesting that dynamic features may act as endophenotypes for cognitive abilities. In conclusion, we propose that connectome dynamics offer considerable potential as a theoretical, conceptual, and practical framework for linking genetics to behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445378" rel="alternate" title="Temporal characteristics of functional connectome reconfigurations are heritable and related to cognition (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.445598</id><title>Long lasting anxiety following early life stress is dependent on glucocorticoid signaling in zebrafish (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.412895+00:00</updated><author><name>Jacqueline S.R. Chin</name></author><author><name>Tram-Anh N. Phan</name></author><author><name>Lydia T. Albert</name></author><author><name>Alex C. Keene</name></author><author><name>Erik R. Duboué</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chronic adversity in early childhood is associated with increased anxiety and a propensity for substance abuse later in adulthood, yet the effects of early life stress (ELS) on brain development remains poorly understood. The zebrafish, &lt;italic&gt;Danio&lt;/italic&gt; rerio, is a powerful model for studying neurodevelopment and stress. Here, we describe a zebrafish model of ELS and identify a role for glucocorticoid signaling during a critical window in development that leads to long-term changes in brain function. Larval fish subjected to chronic stress in early development exhibited increased anxiety-like behavior and elevated glucocorticoid levels later in life. Increased stress-like behavior was only observed when fish were subjected to ELS within a precise time window in early development, revealing a temporal critical window of sensitivity. Moreover, enhanced anxiety-like behavior only emerges after two months post-ELS, revealing a developmentally specified delay in the effects of ELS. ELS leads to increased levels of baseline cortisol, and resulted in a dysregulation of cortisol receptors, suggesting long-term effects on cortisol signaling. Together, these findings reveal a ‘critical window’ for ELS to affect developmental reprogramming of the glucocorticoid receptor pathway, resulting in chronic elevated stress.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.445598" rel="alternate" title="Long lasting anxiety following early life stress is dependent on glucocorticoid signaling in zebrafish (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>