<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv neuroscience preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.601011+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neuroscience/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.09.447807</id><title>Imaging of the pial arterial vasculature of the human brain in vivo using high-resolution 7T time-of-flight angiography (40 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.601374+00:00</updated><author><name>Saskia Bollmann</name></author><author><name>Hendrik Mattern</name></author><author><name>Michaël Bernier</name></author><author><name>Simon R. Robinson</name></author><author><name>Daniel Park</name></author><author><name>Oliver Speck</name></author><author><name>Jonathan R. Polimeni</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The pial arterial vasculature of the human brain is the only blood supply to the neocortex, but quantitative data on the morphology and topology of these mesoscopic vessels (diameter 50–300 μm) remains scarce. Because it is commonly assumed that blood flow velocities in these vessels are prohibitively slow, non-invasive time-of-flight MRI angiography (TOF-MRA)—which is well-suited to high 3D imaging resolutions—has not been applied to imaging the pial arteries. Here, we provide a theoretical framework that outlines how TOF-MRA can visualize small pial arteries &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, by employing extremely small voxels at the size of individual vessels. We then provide evidence for this theory by imaging the pial arteries at 140-μm isotropic resolution using a 7T MRI scanner and prospective motion correction, and show that pial arteries one voxel-width in diameter can be detected. We conclude that imaging pial arteries is not limited by slow blood flow, but instead by achievable image resolution. This study represents the first targeted, comprehensive account of imaging pial arteries &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; in the human brain. This ultra-high-resolution angiography will enable the characterization of pial vascular anatomy across the brain to investigate patterns of blood supply and relationships between vascular and functional architecture.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.09.447807" rel="alternate" title="Imaging of the pial arterial vasculature of the human brain in vivo using high-resolution 7T time-of-flight angiography (40 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.09.447813</id><title>Toward a More Accurate 3D Atlas of C. elegans Neurons (35 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.601687+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael Skuhersky</name></author><author><name>Tailin Wu</name></author><author><name>Eviatar Yemini</name></author><author><name>Edward Boyden</name></author><author><name>Max Tegmark</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Determining cell identity in volumetric images of tagged neuronal nuclei is an ongoing challenge in contemporary neuroscience. Frequently, cell identity is determined by aligning and matching tags to an “atlas” of labeled neuronal positions and other identifying characteristics. Previous analyses of such &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; datasets have been hampered by the limited accuracy of such atlases, especially for neurons present in the ventral nerve cord, and also by time-consuming manual elements of the alignment process. We present a novel automated alignment method for sparse and incomplete point clouds of the sort resulting from typical &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; fluorescence microscopy datasets. This method involves a tunable learning parameter and a kernel that enforces biologically realistic deformation. We also present a pipeline for creating alignment atlases from datasets of the recently developed NeuroPAL transgene. In combination, these advances allow us to label neurons in volumetric images with confidence much higher than previous methods. We release, to the best of our knowledge, the most complete &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; 3D positional neuron atlas, encapsulating positional variability derived from 7 animals, for the purposes of cell-type identity prediction for myriad applications (e.g., imaging neuronal activity, gene expression, and cell-fate).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.09.447813" rel="alternate" title="Toward a More Accurate 3D Atlas of C. elegans Neurons (35 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.11.448148</id><title>Developmental Regulation of Homeostatic Plasticity in Mouse Primary Visual Cortex (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.601918+00:00</updated><author><name>Wei Wen</name></author><author><name>Gina Turrigiano</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Homeostatic plasticity maintains network stability by adjusting excitation, inhibition, or the intrinsic excitability of neurons, but the developmental regulation and coordination of these distinct forms of homeostatic plasticity remains poorly understood. A major contributor to this information gap is the lack of a uniform paradigm for chronically manipulating activity at different developmental stages. To overcome this limitation, we utilized Designer Receptors Exclusively Activated by Designer Drugs (DREADDs) to directly suppress neuronal activity in layer (L) 2/3 of mouse primary visual cortex (V1) at two important developmental timepoints: the classic visual system critical period (CP, P24-29), and adulthood (P45-55). We show that 24 hours of DREADD-mediated activity suppression simultaneously induces excitatory synaptic scaling up and intrinsic homeostatic plasticity in L2/3 pyramidal neurons during the CP, consistent with previous observations using prolonged visual deprivation. Importantly, manipulations known to block these forms of homeostatic plasticity when induced pharmacologically or via visual deprivation also prevented DREADD-induced homeostatic plasticity. We next used the same paradigm to suppress activity in adult animals. Surprisingly, while excitatory synaptic scaling persisted into adulthood, intrinsic homeostatic plasticity was completely absent. Finally, we found that homeostatic changes in quantal inhibitory input onto L2/3 pyramidal neurons were absent during the CP but present in adults. Thus, the same population of neurons can express distinct sets of homeostatic plasticity mechanisms at different development stages. Our findings suggest that homeostatic forms of plasticity can be recruited in a modular manner according to the evolving needs of a developing neural circuit.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.11.448148" rel="alternate" title="Developmental Regulation of Homeostatic Plasticity in Mouse Primary Visual Cortex (30 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.447903</id><title>Meditation-induced effects on whole-brain structural and effective connectivity (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.602107+00:00</updated><author><name>Eleonora De Filippi</name></author><author><name>Anira Escrichs</name></author><author><name>Estela Càmara</name></author><author><name>César Garrido</name></author><author><name>Marti Sánchez-Fibla</name></author><author><name>Matthieu Gilson</name></author><author><name>Gustavo Deco</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the past decades, there has been a growing scientific interest in characterizing neural correlates of meditation training. Nonetheless, the mechanisms underlying meditation remain elusive. In the present work, we investigated meditation-related changes in structural and functional connectivities (SC and FC, respectively). For this purpose, we scanned experienced meditators and control (naive) subjects using magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) to acquire structural and functional data during two conditions, resting-state and meditation (focused attention on breathing). In this way, we aimed to characterize and distinguish both short-term and long-term modifications in the brain’s structure and function. First, we performed a network-based analysis of anatomical connectivity. Then, to analyze the fMRI data, we calculated whole-brain effective connectivity (EC) estimates, relying on a dynamical network model to replicate BOLD signals’ spatio-temporal structure, akin to FC with lagged correlations. We compared the estimated EC, FC, and SC links as features to train classifiers to predict behavioral conditions and group identity. The whole-brain SC analysis revealed strengthened anatomical connectivity across large-scale networks for meditators compared to controls. We found that differences in SC were reflected in the functional domain as well. We demonstrated through a machine-learning approach that EC features were more informative than FC and SC solely. Using EC features we reached high performance for the condition-based classification within each group and moderately high accuracies when comparing the two groups in each condition. Moreover, we showed that the most informative EC links that discriminated between meditators and controls involved the same large-scale networks previously found to have increased anatomical connectivity. Overall, the results of our whole-brain model-based approach revealed a mechanism underlying meditation by providing causal relationships at the structure-function level.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.447903" rel="alternate" title="Meditation-induced effects on whole-brain structural and effective connectivity (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.09.447698</id><title>Frontal cortical functional connectivity is impacted by anaesthesia in macaques (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.602335+00:00</updated><author><name>C Giacometti</name></author><author><name>A Dureux</name></author><author><name>D Autran-Clavagnier</name></author><author><name>C. R. E. Wilson</name></author><author><name>J Sallet</name></author><author><name>M. Dirheimer</name></author><author><name>E Procyk</name></author><author><name>F Hadj-Bouziane</name></author><author><name>C Amiez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A critical aspect of neuroscience is to establish whether and how brain networks evolved across primates. To date, most comparative studies have used resting-state functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (rs-fMRI) in anaesthetized non-human primates and in awake humans. However, anaesthesia strongly affects rs-fMRI signals. The present study investigated the impact of the awareness state (anaesthesia vs. awake) within the same group of macaque monkeys on the rs-fMRI functional connectivity (FC) organization of a well characterized network in the human brain, the cingulo-frontal lateral network. Results in awake macaques revealed a similar FC pattern to that previously uncovered in the human brain. Rostral seeds in the cingulate sulcus exhibited stronger correlation strength with rostral compared to caudal lateral frontal cortical areas while caudal seeds in the cingulate sulcus displayed stronger correlation strength with caudal compared to anterior lateral frontal cortical areas. Critically, this inverse rostro-caudal functional gradient was abolished under anaesthesia. This study demonstrates that the FC pattern of cingulo-frontal cortical networks is preserved from macaque to human but some of its properties can only be observed in the awake state, warranting significant caution when comparing FC patterns across species under different states.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.09.447698" rel="alternate" title="Frontal cortical functional connectivity is impacted by anaesthesia in macaques (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.447855</id><title>Point-estimating observer models for latent cause detection (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.602582+00:00</updated><author><name>Jennifer Laura Lee</name></author><author><name>Wei Ji Ma</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The spatial distribution of visual items allows us to infer the presence of latent causes in the world. For instance, a spatial cluster of ants allows us to infer the presence of a common food source. However, optimal inference requires the integration of a computationally intractable number of world states in real world situations. For example, optimal inference about whether a common cause exists based on &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt; spatially distributed visual items requires marginalizing over both the location of the latent cause and 2&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; possible affiliation patterns (where each item may be affiliated or non-affiliated with the latent cause). How might the brain approximate this inference? We show that subject behaviour deviates qualitatively from Bayes-optimal, in particular showing an unexpected positive effect of &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt; (the number of visual items) on the false-alarm rate. We propose several “point-estimating” observer models that fit subject behaviour better than the Bayesian model. They each avoid a costly computational marginalization over at least one of the variables of the generative model by “committing” to a point estimate of at least one of the two generative model variables. These findings suggest that the brain may implement partially committal variants of Bayesian models when detecting latent causes based on complex real world data.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.447855" rel="alternate" title="Point-estimating observer models for latent cause detection (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.09.447672</id><title>Spatiotemporally flexible subnetworks reveal the quasi-cyclic nature of integration and segregation in the human brain (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.602874+00:00</updated><author><name>Marika Strindberg</name></author><author><name>Peter Fransson</name></author><author><name>Joana Cabral</name></author><author><name>Ulrika Ådén</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Though the organization of functional brain networks is modular at its core, modularity does not capture the full range of dynamic interactions between individual brain areas nor at the level of subnetworks. In this paper we present a hierarchical model that represents both flexible and modular aspects of intrinsic brain organization across time by constructing spatiotemporally flexible subnetworks. We also demonstrate that segregation and integration are complementary and simultaneous events. The method is based on combining the instantaneous phase synchrony analysis (IPSA) framework with community detection to identify a small, yet representative set of subnetwork components at the finest level of spatial granularity. At the next level, subnetwork components are combined into spatiotemporally flexibly subnetworks where temporal lag in the recruitment of areas within subnetworks is captured. Since individual brain areas are permitted to be part of multiple interleaved subnetworks, both modularity as well as more flexible tendencies of connectivity are accommodated for in the model. Importantly, we show that assignment of subnetworks to the same community (integration) corresponds to positive phase coherence within and between subnetworks, while assignment to different communities (segregation) corresponds to negative phase coherence or orthogonality. Together with disintegration, i.e. the breakdown of internal coupling within subnetwork components, orthogonality facilitates reorganization between subnetworks. In addition, we show that the duration of periods of integration is a function of the coupling strength within subnetworks and subnetwork components which indicates an underlying metastable dynamical regime. Based on the main tendencies for either integration or segregation, subnetworks are further clustered into larger meta-networks that are shown to correspond to combinations of core resting-state networks. We also demonstrate that subnetworks and meta-networks are coarse graining strategies that captures the quasi-cyclic recurrence of global patterns of integration and segregation in the brain. Finally, the method allows us to estimate in broad terms the spectrum of flexible and/or modular tendencies for individual brain areas.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.09.447672" rel="alternate" title="Spatiotemporally flexible subnetworks reveal the quasi-cyclic nature of integration and segregation in the human brain (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.09.447772</id><title>Normal Aging in Mice is Associated with a Global Reduction in Cortical Power and Network-Specific Declines in Functional Connectivity (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.603246+00:00</updated><author><name>Asher J. Albertson</name></author><author><name>Eric C. Landsness</name></author><author><name>Michelle J. Tang</name></author><author><name>Ping Yan</name></author><author><name>Hanyang Miao</name></author><author><name>Zachary P. Rosenthal</name></author><author><name>Byungchan Kim</name></author><author><name>Joseph C. Culver</name></author><author><name>Adam Q Bauer</name></author><author><name>Jin-Moo Lee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Normal aging is associated with a variety of neurologic changes including declines in cognition, memory, and motor activity. These declines correlate with neuronal changes in synaptic structure and function. Degradation of brain network activity and connectivity represents a likely mediator of age-related functional deterioration resulting from these neuronal changes. Human studies have demonstrated both general decreases in spontaneous cortical activity and disruption of cortical networks with aging. Current techniques used to study cerebral network activity are hampered either by limited spatial resolution (e.g. electroencephalography, EEG) or limited temporal resolution (e.g., functional magnetic resonance imaging, fMRI). Here we utilize mesoscale imaging of neuronal activity in &lt;italic&gt;Thy1-&lt;/italic&gt;GCaMP6f mice to characterize neuronal network changes in aging with high spatial resolution across a wide frequency range. We show that while evoked activity is unchanged with aging, spontaneous neuronal activity decreases across a wide frequency range (0.01-4Hz) involving all regions of the cortex. In contrast to this global reduction in cortical power, we found that aging is associated with functional connectivity (FC) deterioration of select networks including somatomotor, cingulate, and retrosplenial nodes. These changes are corroborated by reductions in homotopic FC and node degree within somatomotor and visual cortices. Finally, we found that whole cortex delta power and delta band node degree correlate with exploratory activity in young but not aged animals. Together these data suggest that aging is associated with global declines in spontaneous cortical activity and focal deterioration of network connectivity, and that these reductions may be associated with age-related behavioral declines.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.09.447772" rel="alternate" title="Normal Aging in Mice is Associated with a Global Reduction in Cortical Power and Network-Specific Declines in Functional Connectivity (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.09.447804</id><title>Multiscale dynamics underlying neocortical slow oscillations (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.604776+00:00</updated><author><name>Maurizio Mattia</name></author><author><name>Maria Perez-Zabalza</name></author><author><name>Núria Tort-Colet</name></author><author><name>Miguel Dasilva</name></author><author><name>Alberto Muñoz</name></author><author><name>Maria V. Sanchez-Vives</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Slow oscillations in the sleeping and anesthetized brain invariantly emerge as an alternation between Up (high firing) and Down (almost quiescent) states. In cortex, they occur simultaneously in cell assemblies in different layers and propagate as traveling waves, a concerted activity at multiple scales whose interplay and role is still under debate. Slow oscillations have been reported to start in deep layers, more specifically in layer 5. Here, we studied the laminar organization of slow oscillations in the anesthetized rat cortex and we found that the activity leading to Up states actually initiates in layer 6, then spreads towards upper layers. Layer 5 cell assemblies have a threshold-like activation that can persist after layer 6 inactivation, giving rise to hysteresis loops like in “flip-flop” computational units. We found that such hysteresis is finely tuned by the columnar circuitry depending on the recent history of the local ongoing activity. Furthermore, thalamic inactivation reduced infragranular excitability without affecting the columnar activation pattern. We propose a role for layer 6 acting as a hub unraveling a hierarchy of cortical loops.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.09.447804" rel="alternate" title="Multiscale dynamics underlying neocortical slow oscillations (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>