<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv neuroscience preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.637082+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neuroscience/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453573</id><title>Strong and opponent contributions of dorsomedial striatal pathways to behavior depends on cognitive demands and task strategy (34 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.638985+00:00</updated><author><name>Scott Bolkan</name></author><author><name>Iris Stone</name></author><author><name>Lucas Pinto</name></author><author><name>Zoe Ashwood</name></author><author><name>Jorge Garcia</name></author><author><name>Alison Herman</name></author><author><name>Priyanka Singh</name></author><author><name>Akhil Bandi</name></author><author><name>Julia Cox</name></author><author><name>Christopher Zimmerman</name></author><author><name>Jounhong Cho</name></author><author><name>Ben Engelhard</name></author><author><name>Sue Koay</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Pillow</name></author><author><name>Ilana Witten</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A classic view of the striatum holds that activity in direct and indirect pathways oppositely modulates motor output. Whether this involves direct control of movement, or reflects a cognitive process underlying movement, has remained unresolved. Here we find that strong, opponent control of behavior by the two pathways of the dorsomedial striatum (DMS) depends on a task's cognitive demands. Furthermore, a latent state model (a hidden markov model with generalized linear model observations) reveals that - even within a single task - the contribution of the two pathways to behavior is state-dependent. Specifically, the two pathways have large contributions in one of two states associated with a strategy of evidence accumulation, compared to a state associated with a strategy of repeating previous choices. Thus, both the cognitive demands imposed by a task, as well as the strategy that mice pursue within a task, determine whether DMS pathways provide strong and opponent control of behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453573" rel="alternate" title="Strong and opponent contributions of dorsomedial striatal pathways to behavior depends on cognitive demands and task strategy (34 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.21.453258</id><title>Retrosplenial cortex is necessary for spatial and non-spatial latent learning in mice (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.639716+00:00</updated><author><name>Ana Carolina Bottura de Barros</name></author><author><name>Liad J. Baruchin</name></author><author><name>Marios C. Panayi</name></author><author><name>Nils Nyberg</name></author><author><name>Veronika Samborska</name></author><author><name>Mitchell T. Mealing</name></author><author><name>Thomas Akam</name></author><author><name>Jeehyun Kwag</name></author><author><name>David M. Bannerman</name></author><author><name>Michael M. Kohl</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Latent learning occurs when associations are formed between stimuli in the absence of explicit reinforcement. Traditionally, latent learning in rodents has been associated with the creation internal models of space. However, increasing evidence points to roles of internal models also in non-spatial decision making. Whether the same brain structures and processes support the creation of spatially-anchored or non-spatial internal models via latent learning, is an open question. To address this question, we developed a novel operant box task that allows to test spatial and non-spatial versions of a flavour-based sensory preconditioning paradigm. We probed the role of the retrosplenial cortex, a brain area associated with spatial cognition and subjective value representation, in this task using precise, closed-loop optogenetic silencing during different task phases. We show that the retrosplenial cortex is necessary for both spatial and non-spatial latent learning in mice. We further demonstrate that the requirement of retrosplenial cortex is limited to the preconditioning phase of the task. Our results provide insight into the specific role of the retrosplenial cortex in latent learning, demonstrate that latent learning plays a general part in the creation of internal models, independent of spatial anchors, and provide a novel avenue for studying model-based decision making.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.21.453258" rel="alternate" title="Retrosplenial cortex is necessary for spatial and non-spatial latent learning in mice (13 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.19.453008</id><title>Don't think, feel: basal ganglia-cortical connectivity underlies self-regulation of brain oscillations in humans (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.640443+00:00</updated><author><name>Kazumi Kasahara</name></author><author><name>Charles Sayo DaSalla</name></author><author><name>Manabu Honda</name></author><author><name>Takashi Hanakawa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Brain-computer interfaces (BCIs) provide an artificial link by which the brain can directly interact with the environment. To achieve fine BCI control, participants must modulate the patterns of the cortical oscillations generated from the motor and somatosensory cortices. However, it remains unclear how humans regulate cortical oscillations, the controllability of which substantially varies across individuals. Here, we performed simultaneous electroencephalography (to assess BCI control) and functional magnetic resonance imaging (to measure brain activity) in healthy participants. Self-regulation of cortical oscillations induced activity in the basal ganglia-cortical network (BgCN) and the neurofeedback control network (NfCN). Successful self-regulation correlated with striatal activity in the BgCN, through which patterns of cortical oscillations were likely modulated. Moreover, BgCN and NfCN connectivity correlated with strong and weak self-regulation, respectively. The findings indicate that the BgCN is important for self-regulation, the understanding of which should help advance BCI technology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.19.453008" rel="alternate" title="Don't think, feel: basal ganglia-cortical connectivity underlies self-regulation of brain oscillations in humans (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>