<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv neuroscience preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.472040+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neuroscience/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444537</id><title>Attentional modulation of intrinsic timescales in visual cortex and spatial networks (76 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.472561+00:00</updated><author><name>Roxana Zeraati</name></author><author><name>Yan-Liang Shi</name></author><author><name>Nicholas A. Steinmetz</name></author><author><name>Marc A. Gieselmann</name></author><author><name>Alexander Thiele</name></author><author><name>Tirin Moore</name></author><author><name>Anna Levina</name></author><author><name>Tatiana A. Engel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neural activity fluctuates endogenously on timescales varying across the neocortex. The variation in these intrinsic timescales relates to the functional specialization of cortical areas and their involvement in the temporal integration of information. Yet, it is unknown whether the timescales can adjust rapidly and selectively to the demands of a cognitive task. We measured intrinsic timescales of local spiking activity within columns of area V4 while monkeys performed spatial attention tasks. The ongoing spiking activity unfolded across at least two distinct timescales—fast and slow—and the slow timescale increased when monkeys attended to the receptive fields location. A recurrent network model shows that multiple timescales in local dynamics arise from spatial connectivity mimicking vertical and horizontal interactions in visual cortex and that slow timescales increase with the efficacy of recurrent interactions. Our results reveal that targeted neural populations integrate information over variable timescales following the demands of a cognitive task and propose an underlying network mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444537" rel="alternate" title="Attentional modulation of intrinsic timescales in visual cortex and spatial networks (76 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.444703</id><title>A Developmental Reduction of the Excitation:Inhibition Ratio in Association Cortex during Adolescence (49 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.474107+00:00</updated><author><name>Bart Larsen</name></author><author><name>Zaixu Cui</name></author><author><name>Azeez Adebimpe</name></author><author><name>Adam Pines</name></author><author><name>Aaron Alexander-Bloch</name></author><author><name>Max Bertolero</name></author><author><name>Monica E. Calkins</name></author><author><name>Raquel E. Gur</name></author><author><name>Ruben C. Gur</name></author><author><name>Arun S. Mahadevan</name></author><author><name>Tyler M. Moore</name></author><author><name>David R. Roalf</name></author><author><name>Jakob Seidlitz</name></author><author><name>Valerie J. Sydnor</name></author><author><name>Daniel H. Wolf</name></author><author><name>Theodore D. Satterthwaite</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Adolescence is hypothesized to be a critical period for the development of association cortex. A reduction of the excitation:inhibition (E:I) ratio is a hallmark of critical period development; however it has been unclear how to measure the development of the E:I ratio using non-invasive neuroimaging techniques. Here, we used pharmacological fMRI with a GABAergic benzodiazepine challenge to empirically generate a model of E:I ratio based on multivariate patterns of functional connectivity. In an independent sample of 879 youth (ages 8-22 years), this model predicted reductions in the E:I ratio during adolescence, which were specific to association cortex and related to psychopathology. These findings support hypothesized shifts in E:I balance of association cortices during a neurodevelopmental critical period in adolescence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.444703" rel="alternate" title="A Developmental Reduction of the Excitation:Inhibition Ratio in Association Cortex during Adolescence (49 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444462</id><title>Deconstructing the Cortical Sources of Frequency Following Responses to Speech: A Cross-species Approach (39 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.474706+00:00</updated><author><name>G. Nike Gnanateja</name></author><author><name>Kyle Rupp</name></author><author><name>Fernando Llanos</name></author><author><name>Madison Remick</name></author><author><name>Marianny Pernia</name></author><author><name>Srivatsun Sadagopan</name></author><author><name>Tobias Teichert</name></author><author><name>Taylor Abel</name></author><author><name>Bharath Chandrasekaran</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Time-varying pitch is a vital cue in the processing of speech signals. Neural processing of time-varying pitch cues in speech has been extensively assayed using scalp-recorded frequency-following responses (FFRs), which are thought to reflect integrated phase-locked activity from neural ensembles exclusively along the subcortical auditory pathway. Emerging evidence however suggests that the auditory cortex contributes to the FFRs as well. However, the response properties and the relative cortical contribution to the scalp-recorded FFR are only beginning to be explored. Here we used direct intracortical recordings from human subjects and animal models (macaque, guinea pig) to deconstruct the cortical sources of FFRs and leveraged representational similarity analysis as a translational bridge to characterize similarities between the human and animal models. We found robust FFRs in the auditory cortex that emerged from the thalamorecepient layers of the auditory cortex and contributed to the scalp-recorded FFRs via volume conduction.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444462" rel="alternate" title="Deconstructing the Cortical Sources of Frequency Following Responses to Speech: A Cross-species Approach (39 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444979</id><title>VIP neurons desynchronize cortical assemblies (38 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.475083+00:00</updated><author><name>Julia Veit</name></author><author><name>Daniel P. Mossing</name></author><author><name>Hillel Adesnik</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neural synchronization on fast timescales has been linked to critical aspects of sensation, cognition and action, and impairments in synchronization are associated with neurological disease. Although the strength and spatial scale of neural synchronization varies dramatically with sensory and behavioral context, the circuit mechanisms that regulate the magnitude and spatial spread of neural oscillations are largely unknown. As in humans, monkeys, and cats, we found that in the mouse primary visual cortex (V1) the stimulus properties and behavioral state powerfully modulate gamma band synchronization. To reveal the underlying circuit that mediates this dependence, we used multi-site multi-electrode electrophysiology and cell type specific optogenetic suppression of vasoactive intestinal peptide (VIP) interneurons in awake mice. Our results show that VIP neurons potently control the gain and behavioral state-dependence of gamma band network synchronization by desynchronizing local and global networks on fine time scales. Importantly, VIP neurons preferentially decouple spatially separated cortical ensembles when they are processing non-matched stimulus features. Based on these data, we propose that cortical disinhibition by VIP interneurons fine-tunes the strength and spatial architecture of gamma-oscillating neural assemblies, which may facilitate the downstream generation of coherent visual percepts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444979" rel="alternate" title="VIP neurons desynchronize cortical assemblies (38 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.18.444672</id><title>Contactless recordings of retinal activity using optically pumped magnetometers (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.475254+00:00</updated><author><name>Britta U. Westner</name></author><author><name>James I. Lubell</name></author><author><name>Mads Jensen</name></author><author><name>Sigbjørn Hokland</name></author><author><name>Sarang S. Dalal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Optically pumped magnetometers (OPMs) have been adopted for the recording of brain activity. Without the need to be cooled to cryogenic temperatures, an array of these sensors can be placed more flexibly, which allows for the recording of neuronal structures other than neocortex. Here we use eight OPM sensors to record human retinal activity following flash stimulation. We compare this magnetoretinographic (MRG) activity to the simultaneously recorded electroretinogram of the eight participants. The MRG shows the familiar flash-evoked potentials (a-wave and b-wave) and shares a highly significant amount of information with the electroretinogram recording (both in a simultaneous and separate recording). We conclude that OPM sensors have the potential to become a contactless alternative to fiber electrodes for the recording of retinal activity. Such a contactless solution can benefit both clinical and neuroscientific settings.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.18.444672" rel="alternate" title="Contactless recordings of retinal activity using optically pumped magnetometers (30 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444460</id><title>Cortical Oscillatory Dysrhythmias in Visual Snow Syndrome: A MEG Study (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.475434+00:00</updated><author><name>Jenny L. Hepschke</name></author><author><name>Robert A Seymour</name></author><author><name>Wei He</name></author><author><name>Andrew Etchell</name></author><author><name>Paul F Sowman</name></author><author><name>Clare L Fraser</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Visual Snow (VS) refers to the persistent visual experience of static in the whole visual field of both eyes. It is often reported by patients with migraine and co-occurs with conditions like tinnitus and tremor. The underlying pathophysiology of the condition is poorly understood. Previously we hypothesised, that VSS may be characterised by disruptions to rhythmical activity within the visual system&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To test this, data from 18 patients diagnosed with visual snow syndrome (VSS), and 16 matched controls, were acquired using Magnetoencephalography (MEG). Participants were presented with visual grating stimuli, known to elicit decreases in alpha-band (8-13Hz) power and increases in gamma-band power (40-70Hz).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Data were mapped to source-space using a beamformer. Across both groups, decreased alpha power and increased gamma power localised to early visual cortex. Data from primary visual cortex (V1) were compared between groups. No differences were found in either alpha or gamma peak frequency or the magnitude of alpha power, p&amp;gt;.05. However, compared with controls, our VSS cohort displayed significantly increased V1 gamma power, p=.035. This new electromagnetic finding concurs with previous fMRI and PET findings suggesting that in VSS, the visual cortex is hyper-excitable. The coupling of alpha-phase to gamma amplitude (i.e., phase-amplitude coupling, PAC) within V1 was also quantified. Compared with controls, the VSS group had significantly reduced alpha-gamma PAC, p&amp;lt;.05, indicating a potential excitation-inhibition imbalance in VSS, as well as a potential disruption to top-down “noise-cancellation” mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overall, these results suggest that rhythmical brain activity in primary visual cortex is both hyperexcitable and disorganised in VSS, consistent with visual snow being a condition of thalamocortical dysrhythmia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444460" rel="alternate" title="Cortical Oscillatory Dysrhythmias in Visual Snow Syndrome: A MEG Study (26 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.444778</id><title>Neuronal mitochondria transport Pink1 mRNA via Synaptojanin 2 to support local mitophagy (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.475615+00:00</updated><author><name>Angelika B. Harbauer</name></author><author><name>Simone Wanderoy</name></author><author><name>J. Tabitha Hees</name></author><author><name>Whitney Gibbs</name></author><author><name>Martha Ordonez</name></author><author><name>Zerong Cai</name></author><author><name>Romain Cartoni</name></author><author><name>Ghazaleh Ashrafi</name></author><author><name>Chen Wang</name></author><author><name>Zhigang He</name></author><author><name>Thomas L. Schwarz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;PTEN-induced kinase 1 (PINK1) is a very short-lived protein that is required for the removal of damaged mitochondria through Parkin translocation and mitophagy. Because the short half-life of PINK1 limits its ability to be trafficked into neurites, local translation is required for this mitophagy pathway to be active far from the soma. The &lt;italic&gt;Pink1&lt;/italic&gt; transcript is associated with and cotransported with neuronal mitochondria. In concert with translation, the mitochondrial outer membrane protein Synaptojanin 2 binding protein (SYNJ2BP) and Synaptojanin 2 (SYNJ2) are required for tethering &lt;italic&gt;Pink1&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA to mitochondria via an RNA-binding domain in SYNJ2. This neuron-specific adaptation for local translation of PINK1 provides distal mitochondria with a continuous supply of PINK1 for activation of mitophagy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.444778" rel="alternate" title="Neuronal mitochondria transport Pink1 mRNA via Synaptojanin 2 to support local mitophagy (26 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.16.444253</id><title>Beyond BOLD: in search of genuine diffusion fMRI contrast in human brain (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.475872+00:00</updated><author><name>Wiktor Olszowy</name></author><author><name>Yujian Diao</name></author><author><name>Ileana O. Jelescu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI) is an essential method to measure brain activity non-invasively. While fMRI almost systematically relies on the blood oxygenation level-dependent (BOLD) contrast, there is an increasing interest in alternative methods that would not rely on neurovascular coupling. A promising but controversial such alternative is diffusion fMRI (dfMRI), which relies instead on dynamic fluctuations in apparent diffusion coefficient (ADC) due to microstructural changes underlying neuronal activity. However, it is unclear whether genuine dfMRI contrast, distinct from BOLD contamination, can be detected in the human brain in physiological conditions. Here, we present the first dfMRI study in humans attempting to minimize all BOLD contamination sources and comparing functional responses at two field strengths (3T and 7T), both for task and resting-state (RS) fMRI. Our study benefits from unprecedented high spatiotemporal resolution and harnesses novel denoising strategies. We report task-induced decrease in ADC with temporal and spatial features distinct from the BOLD response and yielding more specific activation maps. Furthermore, we report dfMRI RS connectivity which, compared to its BOLD counterpart, is essentially free from physiological artifacts and preserves positive correlations but preferentially suppresses anti-correlations, which are likely of vascular origin. A careful acquisition and processing design thus enable the detection of genuine dfMRI contrast on clinical MRI systems. As opposed to BOLD, diffusion functional contrast could be particularly well suited for low-field MRI.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.16.444253" rel="alternate" title="Beyond BOLD: in search of genuine diffusion fMRI contrast in human brain (20 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.21.445204</id><title>Met is required for oligodendrocyte progenitor cell migration in Danio rerio (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.476035+00:00</updated><author><name>Maria F Ali</name></author><author><name>Andrew J Latimer</name></author><author><name>Yinxue Wang</name></author><author><name>Leah Hogenmiller</name></author><author><name>Laura Fontenas</name></author><author><name>Adam J Isabella</name></author><author><name>Cecilia B Moens</name></author><author><name>Guoqiang Yu</name></author><author><name>Sarah Kucenas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During vertebrate central nervous system development, most oligodendrocyte progenitor cells (OPCs) are specified in the ventral spinal cord and must migrate throughout the neural tube until they become evenly distributed, occupying non-overlapping domains. While this process of developmental OPC migration is well characterized, the nature of the molecular mediators that govern it remain largely unknown. Here, using zebrafish as a model, we demonstrate that Met signaling is required for initial developmental migration of OPCs, and, using cell-specific knock-down of Met signaling, show that Met acts cell-autonomously in OPCs. Taken together, these findings demonstrate &lt;italic&gt;in vivo,&lt;/italic&gt; the role of Met signaling in OPC migration and provide new insight into how OPC migration is regulated during development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.21.445204" rel="alternate" title="Met is required for oligodendrocyte progenitor cell migration in Danio rerio (20 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.444193</id><title>LSD flattens the brain’s energy landscape: evidence from receptor-informed network control theory (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.476232+00:00</updated><author><name>S. Parker Singleton</name></author><author><name>Andrea I. Luppi</name></author><author><name>Robin L. Carhart-Harris</name></author><author><name>Josephine Cruzat</name></author><author><name>Leor Roseman</name></author><author><name>Gustavo Deco</name></author><author><name>Morten L. Kringelbach</name></author><author><name>Emmanuel A. Stamatakis</name></author><author><name>Amy Kuceyeski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Psychedelics like lysergic acid diethylamide (LSD) offer a powerful window into the function of the human brain and mind, by temporarily altering subjective experience through their neurochemical effects. The RElaxed Beliefs Under Psychedelics (REBUS) model postulates that 5-HT2a receptor agonism allows the brain to explore its dynamic landscape more readily, as suggested by more diverse (entropic) brain activity. Formally, this effect is theorized to correspond to a reduction in the energy required to transition between different brain-states, i.e. a “flattening of the energy landscape.” However, this hypothesis remains thus far untested. Here, we leverage network control theory to map the brain’s energy landscape, by quantifying the energy required to transition between recurrent brain states. In accordance with the REBUS model, we show that LSD reduces the energy required for brain-state transitions, and, furthermore, that this reduction in energy correlates with more frequent state transitions and increased entropy of brain-state dynamics. Through network control analysis that incorporates the spatial distribution of 5-HT2a receptors, we demonstrate the specific role of this receptor in flattening the brain’s energy landscape. Also, in accordance with REBUS, we show that the occupancy of bottom-up states is increased by LSD. In addition to validating fundamental predictions of the REBUS model of psychedelic action, this work highlights the potential of receptor-informed network control theory to provide mechanistic insights into pharmacological modulation of brain dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present a multi-modal framework for quantifying the effects of a psychedelic drug (LSD) on brain dynamics by combining functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI), diffusion MRI (dMRI), positron emission tomography (PET) and network control theory. Our findings provide support for a fundamental theory of the mechanism of action of psychedelics by showing that LSD flattens the brain’s energy landscape, allowing for more facile and frequent state transitions and more temporally diverse brain activity. We also demonstrate that the spatial distribution of serotonin 2a receptors - the main target of LSD - is key for generating these effects. This approach could be used to understand how drugs act on different receptors in the brain to influence brain function.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.444193" rel="alternate" title="LSD flattens the brain’s energy landscape: evidence from receptor-informed network control theory (19 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.442947</id><title>A Meta-Analysis of fMRI Studies of Semantic Cognition in Children (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.476566+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Enge</name></author><author><name>Rasha Abdel Rahman</name></author><author><name>Michael A. Skeide</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Our capacity to derive meaning from things that we see and words that we hear is unparalleled in other animal species and current AI systems. Despite a wealth of functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) studies on where different semantic features are processed in the adult brain, the development of these systems in children is poorly understood. Here we conducted an extensive database search and identified 50 fMRI experiments investigating semantic world knowledge, semantic relatedness judgments, and the differentiation of visual semantic object categories in children (total &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt; = 1,018, mean age = 10.1 years, range 4–15 years). Synthesizing the results of these experiments, we found consistent activation in the bilateral inferior frontal gyri (IFG), fusiform gyri (FG), and supplementary motor areas (SMA), as well as in the left middle and superior temporal gyri (MTG/STG). Within this system, we found little evidence for age-related changes across childhood and high overlap with the adult semantic system. In sum, the identification of these cortical areas provides the starting point for further research on the mechanisms by which the developing brain learns to make sense of its environment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.442947" rel="alternate" title="A Meta-Analysis of fMRI Studies of Semantic Cognition in Children (17 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.16.444349</id><title>Mind the gap: performance metric evaluation in brain-age prediction (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.476754+00:00</updated><author><name>Ann-Marie G. de Lange</name></author><author><name>Melis Anatürk</name></author><author><name>Jaroslav Rokicki</name></author><author><name>Laura K.M. Han</name></author><author><name>Katja Franke</name></author><author><name>Dag Alnæs</name></author><author><name>Klaus P. Ebmeier</name></author><author><name>Bogdan Draganski</name></author><author><name>Tobias Kaufmann</name></author><author><name>Lars T. Westlye</name></author><author><name>Tim Hahn</name></author><author><name>James H. Cole</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Estimating age based on neuroimaging-derived data has become a popular approach to developing markers for brain integrity and health. While a variety of machine-learning algorithms can provide accurate predictions of age based on brain characteristics, there is significant variation in model accuracy reported across studies. We predicted age based on neuroimaging data in two population-based datasets, and assessed the effects of age range, sample size, and age-bias correction on the model performance metrics &lt;italic&gt;r, R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, Root Mean Squared Error (RMSE), and Mean Absolute Error (MAE). The results showed that these metrics vary considerably depending on cohort age range; &lt;italic&gt;r&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; values are lower when measured in samples with a narrower age range. RMSE and MAE are also lower in samples with a narrower age range due to smaller errors/brain age delta values when predictions are closer to the mean age of the group. Across subsets with different age ranges, performance metrics improve with increasing sample size. Performance metrics further vary depending on prediction variance as well as mean age difference between training and test sets, and age-bias corrected metrics indicate high accuracy - also for models showing poor initial performance. In conclusion, performance metrics used for evaluating age prediction models depend on cohort and study-specific data characteristics, and cannot be directly compared across different studies. Since age-bias corrected metrics in general indicate high accuracy, even for poorly performing models, inspection of uncorrected model results provides important information about underlying model attributes such as prediction variance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.16.444349" rel="alternate" title="Mind the gap: performance metric evaluation in brain-age prediction (16 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444509</id><title>Synaptic Plasticity in the Agranular Insular Cortex Predicts Escalated Ethanol Consumption (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.477201+00:00</updated><author><name>Joel E. Shillinglaw</name></author><author><name>Heather C. Aziz</name></author><author><name>Daniela G. Carrizales</name></author><author><name>Richard A. Morrisett</name></author><author><name>Regina A. Mangieri</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Agranular Insular Cortex (AIC) is implicated in alcohol use disorder and pharmacologically relevant concentrations of acute ethanol inhibit N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor (NMDAR)-mediated glutamatergic synaptic transmission and plasticity onto layer 2/3 AIC pyramidal neurons. However, it is not known whether the actions of ethanol on glutamatergic synapses are means by which chronic ethanol alters mechanisms of learning and memory in AIC as alcohol drinking transitions from controlled to problematic. We utilized the chronic intermittent ethanol (CIE) vapor model of ethanol exposure in adult male mice, alone or in combination with voluntary ethanol consumption, to determine whether glutamatergic synapses on layer 2/3 AIC pyramidal neurons are differentially regulated by different durations and intensities of chronic ethanol exposure. We observed evidence of both ethanol- and age-related metaplasticity of AIC layer 2/3 glutamatergic synapses, as only young adult, ethanol-naïve mice exhibited NMDAR-dependent long term depression ex vivo. Our findings also indicated that voluntary ethanol consumption alone can elicit glutamatergic plasticity in vivo. We found that the ratio of NMDAR- to AMPAR-mediated postsynaptic currents was reduced not only in CIE-treated, but also in air-treated, chronically drinking mice relative to ethanol-naïve controls. Furthermore, lower NMDA/AMPA ratios were predictive of greater escalation of ethanol consumption. These findings suggest that even moderate exposure to ethanol may elicit plasticity in the agranular insular cortex that contributes to the progression toward uncontrolled drinking.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444509" rel="alternate" title="Synaptic Plasticity in the Agranular Insular Cortex Predicts Escalated Ethanol Consumption (15 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.443847</id><title>Impaired α-tubulin re-tyrosination leads to synaptic dysfunction and is a feature of Alzheimer’s disease (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.477415+00:00</updated><author><name>Leticia Peris</name></author><author><name>Xiaoyi Qu</name></author><author><name>Jean-Marc Soleilhac</name></author><author><name>Julie Parato</name></author><author><name>Fabien Lanté</name></author><author><name>Atul Kumar</name></author><author><name>Maria Elena Pero</name></author><author><name>José Martínez-Hernández</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Corrao</name></author><author><name>Giulia Falivelli</name></author><author><name>Floriane Payet</name></author><author><name>Sylvie Gory-Fauré</name></author><author><name>Christophe Bosc</name></author><author><name>Marian Blanca Ramírez</name></author><author><name>Andrew Sproul</name></author><author><name>Jacques Brocard</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Di Cara</name></author><author><name>Philippe Delagrange</name></author><author><name>Alain Buisson</name></author><author><name>Yves Goldberg</name></author><author><name>Marie-Jo Moutin</name></author><author><name>Francesca Bartolini</name></author><author><name>Annie Andrieux</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In neurons, dynamic microtubules play regulatory roles in neurotransmission and synaptic plasticity. While stable microtubules contain detyrosinated tubulin, dynamic microtubules are composed of tyrosinated tubulin, suggesting that the tubulin tyrosination/detyrosination (Tyr/deTyr) cycle modulates microtubule dynamics and synaptic function. In the Tyr/deTyr cycle, the C-terminal tyrosine of α-tubulin is re-added by tubulin-tyrosine-ligase (TTL). Here we show that TTL&lt;sup&gt;+/−&lt;/sup&gt; mice exhibit decreased tyrosinated microtubules, synaptic plasticity and memory deficits, and that reduced TTL expression is a feature of sporadic and familial Alzheimer’s disease (AD), with human APPV717I neurons having less dynamic microtubules. We find that spines visited by dynamic microtubules are more resistant to Amyloidβ&lt;sub&gt;1-42&lt;/sub&gt; and that TTL, by promoting microtubule entry into spines, prevents Aβ&lt;sub&gt;1-42&lt;/sub&gt;-induced spine pruning. Our results demonstrate that the Tyr/deTyr cycle regulates synaptic plasticity, is protective against spine injury, and that tubulin re-tyrosination is lost in AD, providing evidence that a defective Tyr/deTyr cycle may contribute to neurodegeneration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.443847" rel="alternate" title="Impaired α-tubulin re-tyrosination leads to synaptic dysfunction and is a feature of Alzheimer’s disease (14 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.444187</id><title>The structure of hippocampal trisynaptic pathway relates to rapid category learning in humans (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.477831+00:00</updated><author><name>Margaret L. Schlichting</name></author><author><name>Melisa Gumus</name></author><author><name>Teresa Zhu</name></author><author><name>Michael L. Mack</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Prior work suggests that complementary white matter pathways within the hippocampus differentially support learning of specific versus general information. In particular, while the trisynaptic pathway (TSP) rapidly forms memories for specific experiences, the monosynaptic pathway (MSP) slowly learns generalities. However, despite the theorized significance of such circuitry, characterizing how information flows within hippocampus (HPC) to support learning in humans remains a challenge. We leveraged diffusion-weighted imaging as a proxy for individual differences in TSP and MSP white matter structure and related it to category learning ability. We hypothesized that learning to categorize the “exception” items that deviated from category rules would benefit from TSP-supported mnemonic specificity. Participant-level estimates of TSP and MSP integrity were constructed from HPC subfield connectomes of white matter streamline density. Consistent with theories of TSP-supported learning mechanisms, we found a specific association between TSP integrity and exception learning. These results highlight the significant role of HPC circuitry in complex human learning.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.444187" rel="alternate" title="The structure of hippocampal trisynaptic pathway relates to rapid category learning in humans (13 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444577</id><title>Customizing Multifunctional Neural Interfaces through Thermal Drawing Process (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.478122+00:00</updated><author><name>Marc-Joseph Antonini</name></author><author><name>Atharva Sahasrabudhe</name></author><author><name>Anthony Tabet</name></author><author><name>Miriam Schwalm</name></author><author><name>Dekel Rosenfeld</name></author><author><name>Indie Garwood</name></author><author><name>Jimin Park</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Loke</name></author><author><name>Tural Khudiyev</name></author><author><name>Mehmet Kanik</name></author><author><name>Nathan Corbin</name></author><author><name>Andres Canales</name></author><author><name>Alan Jasanoff</name></author><author><name>Yoel Fink</name></author><author><name>Polina Anikeeva</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fiber drawing enables scalable fabrication of multifunctional flexible fibers that integrate electrical, optical and microfluidic modalities to record and modulate neural activity. Constraints on thermomechanical properties of materials, however, have prevented integrated drawing of metal electrodes with low-loss polymer waveguides for concurrent electrical recording and optical neuromodulation. Here we introduce two fabrication approaches: (1) an iterative thermal drawing with a soft, low melting temperature (T&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt;) metal indium, and (2) a metal convergence drawing with traditionally non-drawable high T&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt; metal tungsten. Both approaches deliver multifunctional flexible neural interfaces with low-impedance metallic electrodes and low-loss waveguides, capable of recording optically-evoked and spontaneous neural activity in mice over several weeks. We couple these fibers with a light-weight mechanical microdrive (1g) that enables depth-specific interrogation of neural circuits in mice following chronic implantation. Finally, we demonstrate the compatibility of these fibers with magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and apply them to visualize the delivery of chemical payloads through the integrated channels in real time. Together, these advances expand the domains of application of the fiber-based neural probes in neuroscience and neuroengineering.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444577" rel="alternate" title="Customizing Multifunctional Neural Interfaces through Thermal Drawing Process (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.444857</id><title>Neuroimaging Measures of Iron and Gliosis Explain Memory Performance in Aging (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.478378+00:00</updated><author><name>Anu Venkatesh</name></author><author><name>Ana M Daugherty</name></author><author><name>Ilana J Bennett</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Evidence from animal and histological studies have indicated that accumulation of iron in the brain results in reactive gliosis that contributes to cognitive deficits. The current study extends these findings to human cognitive aging and suggests that magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) techniques like quantitative relaxometry can be used to study iron and its effects in vivo. The effects of iron on microstructure and memory performance were examined using a combination of quantitative relaxometry and multi-compartment diffusion imaging in 35 young (21.06 +/- 2.18 years) and 28 older (72.58 +/- 6.47 years) adults, who also completed a memory task. Replicating past work, results revealed age-related increases in iron content (R2*) and diffusion, and decreases in memory performance. Independent of age group, iron content was significantly related to restricted (intracellular) diffusion in regions with low-moderate iron (hippocampus, caudate) and to all diffusion metrics in regions with moderate-high iron (putamen, globus pallidus). This pattern is consistent with different stages of iron-related gliosis, ranging from astrogliosis that may influence intracellular diffusion to microglial proliferation and increased vascular permeability that may influence all sources of diffusion. Further, hippocampal restricted diffusion was significantly related to memory performance, with a third of this effect related to iron content; consistent with the hypothesis that higher iron-related astrogliosis in the hippocampus is associated with poorer memory performance. These results demonstrate the sensitivity of MRI to iron-related gliosis and extends our understanding of its impact on cognition by showing that this relationship also explains individual differences in memory performance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.444857" rel="alternate" title="Neuroimaging Measures of Iron and Gliosis Explain Memory Performance in Aging (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444568</id><title>Mobile Footprinting: Linking Individual Distinctiveness in Mobility Patterns to Mood, Sleep, and Brain Functional Connectivity (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.478540+00:00</updated><author><name>Cedric Huchuan Xia</name></author><author><name>Ian Barnett</name></author><author><name>Tinashe M. Tapera</name></author><author><name>Zaixu Cui</name></author><author><name>Tyler M. Moore</name></author><author><name>Azeez Adebimpe</name></author><author><name>Sage Rush-Goebel</name></author><author><name>Kayla Piiwaa</name></author><author><name>Kristin Murtha</name></author><author><name>Sophia Linguiti</name></author><author><name>Ellen Leibenluft</name></author><author><name>Melissa A. Brotman</name></author><author><name>Melissa Lynne Martin</name></author><author><name>Monica E. Calkins</name></author><author><name>David R. Roalf</name></author><author><name>Daniel H. Wolf</name></author><author><name>Danielle S. Bassett</name></author><author><name>David M. Lydon-Staley</name></author><author><name>Justin T. Baker</name></author><author><name>Lyle Ungar</name></author><author><name>Theodore D. Satterthwaite</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mapping individual differences in behavior is fundamental to personalized neuroscience. Here, we establish that statistical patterns of smartphone-based mobility features represent unique “footprints” that allow individual identification. Critically, mobility footprints exhibit varying levels of person-specific distinctiveness and are associated with individual differences in affective instability, circadian irregularity, and brain functional connectivity. Together, this work suggests that real-world mobility patterns may provide an individual-specific signature linking brain, behavior, and mood.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444568" rel="alternate" title="Mobile Footprinting: Linking Individual Distinctiveness in Mobility Patterns to Mood, Sleep, and Brain Functional Connectivity (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444541</id><title>Spatiotemporal context modulates encoding and retrieval of overlapping events (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.478817+00:00</updated><author><name>Devyn E. Smith</name></author><author><name>Isabelle L. Moore</name></author><author><name>Nicole M. Long</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Overlap between events can lead to interference due to a tradeoff between encoding the present event and retrieving the past event. Temporal context information – ‘when’ something occurred, a defining feature of episodic memory – can cue retrieval of a past event. However, the influence of temporal overlap, or proximity in time, on the mechanisms of interference are unclear. Here, by identifying brain states using scalp electroencephalography (EEG) from male and female human subjects, we show the extent to which temporal overlap promotes interference and induces retrieval. In this experiment, subjects were explicitly directed to either encode the present event or retrieve a past, overlapping event while perceptual input was held constant. We find that the degree of temporal overlap between events leads to selective interference. Specifically, greater temporal overlap between two events leads to impaired memory for the past event selectively when the top-down goal is to encode the present event. Using pattern classification analyses to measure neural evidence for a retrieval state, we find that greater temporal overlap leads to automatic retrieval of a past event, independent of top-down goals. Critically, the retrieval evidence we observe likely reflects a general retrieval mode, rather than retrieval success or effort. Collectively, our findings provide insight into the role of temporal overlap on interference and memory formation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444541" rel="alternate" title="Spatiotemporal context modulates encoding and retrieval of overlapping events (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.16.444387</id><title>Slow Cortical Waves via Cyclicity (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.479080+00:00</updated><author><name>Ivan Abraham</name></author><author><name>Somayeh Shahsavarani</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Zimmerman</name></author><author><name>Fatima Husain</name></author><author><name>Yuliy Baryshnikov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fine-grained information about dynamic structure of cortical networks is crucial in unpacking brain function. Here, we introduced a novel analytical method to characterize the dynamic interaction between distant brain regions, based on cyclicity analysis, and applied it to data from the Human Connectome Project. Resting-state fMRI time series are aperiodic and, hence, lack a base frequency. Cyclicity analysis, which is time-reparametrization invariant, is effective in recovering dynamic temporal ordering of such time series along a circular trajectory without assuming any time scale. Our analysis detected the propagation of slow cortical waves across the brain with consistent shifts in lead-lag relationships between specific brain regions. We also observed short bursts of strong temporal ordering that dominated overall lead-lag relationships between pairs of regions in the brain, which were modulated by tasks. Our results suggest the possible role played by slow waves of ordered information between brain regions that underlie emergent cognitive function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.16.444387" rel="alternate" title="Slow Cortical Waves via Cyclicity (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.18.440679</id><title>Evidence for PKD2L1-positive neurons present distant from the central canal in the ventromedial spinal cord and Medulla of the adult mouse (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.479454+00:00</updated><author><name>Nina Jurčić</name></author><author><name>Caroline Michelle</name></author><author><name>Jérôme Trouslard</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Wanaverbecq</name></author><author><name>Anne Kastner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neurons in contact with the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) are found around the medullo-spinal central canal (CC) in adult mice. These neurons (CSF-cNs), located within or below the ependymal cell layer known as the stem cell niche, present a characteristic morphology with a dendrite projecting to the CC and ending with a protrusion. They are GABAergic, characterized by an immature neuronal phenotype and selectively express PKD2L1, a channel member of the TRP channel superfamily with properties of sensory receptor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using immunohistological techniques in mice, we characterize a new population of PKD2L1 positive cells that is observed around embryonic day 16 (E16), is present distant from the CC in a zone enriched with astrocytes and ependymal fibers of the ventro-medial spinal cord and medulla. With development, their number appears stable although smaller than that of CSF-cNs and they progressively become more distant from the CC with the reorganization of the CC region. These neurons share both functional and phenotypical properties with CSF-cNs, but they appear subdivided in two groups. One, present along the midline, has a bipolar morphology and extend a long dendrite along ependymal fibers and towards the CC. The second group, localized in more ventro-lateral regions, has a multipolar morphology and no apparent projection to the CC&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Altogether, we describe a novel population of PKD2L1&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; neurons distant from the CC but with properties similar to CSF-cNs that might serve to sense modification in the composition of either CSF or interstitial liquid, a function that will need to be confirmed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.18.440679" rel="alternate" title="Evidence for PKD2L1-positive neurons present distant from the central canal in the ventromedial spinal cord and Medulla of the adult mouse (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>