<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv neuroscience preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.716902+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neuroscience/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450543</id><title>Optogenetic stimulation of medial amygdala GABA neurons with kinetically different channelrhodopsin variants yield opposite behavioral outcomes (245 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.717655+00:00</updated><author><name>Aiste Baleisyte</name></author><author><name>Ralf Schneggenburger</name></author><author><name>Olexiy Kochubey</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Optogenetic manipulation of genetically-specified neuron populations has become a key tool in circuit neuroscience. The medial amygdala (MeA) receives pheromone information about conspecifics and has crucial functions in social behaviors; interestingly, this amygdalar structure contains a majority of GABAergic projection neurons. A previous study showed that optogenetic activation of MeA GABA neurons with channelrhodopsin-2&lt;sup&gt;H134R&lt;/sup&gt; (ChR2) strongly enhanced inter-male aggression (Hong et al. 2014, Cell). When we attempted to reproduce these findings, accidentally using a faster channelrhodopsin variant (channelrhodopsin-2&lt;sup&gt;H134R,E123T&lt;/sup&gt; or ChETA), we found the opposite results. We therefore systematically compared the behavioral outcome of optogenetic stimulation of MeApd GABA neurons with ChETA versus ChR2, employing two widely used AAV serotypes. This revealed that optogenetic stimulation with ChETA &lt;italic&gt;suppressed&lt;/italic&gt; aggression, whereas optogenetic stimulation with ChR2 &lt;italic&gt;increased&lt;/italic&gt; aggression. Recordings of membrane potential changes following optogenetic stimulation with ChETA versus ChR2 revealed larger plateau depolarizations, smaller action potential amplitudes, and larger local inhibition of neighboring inhibitory neurons with ChR2 as compared to ChETA. Our study shows that channelrhodopsin variants have to be chosen with care for &lt;italic&gt;in-vivo&lt;/italic&gt; optogenetic experiments. Furthermore, the role of MeApd GABA neurons in aggression control should be re- evaluated.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450543" rel="alternate" title="Optogenetic stimulation of medial amygdala GABA neurons with kinetically different channelrhodopsin variants yield opposite behavioral outcomes (245 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450332</id><title>Cherry-picking information: humans actively sample evidence to support prior beliefs (51 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.717971+00:00</updated><author><name>Paula Kaanders</name></author><author><name>Pradyumna Sepulveda</name></author><author><name>Tomas Folke</name></author><author><name>Pietro Ortoleva</name></author><author><name>Benedetto De Martino</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;No one likes to be wrong. Previous research has shown that participants may underweight information incompatible with previous choices, a phenomenon called confirmation bias. In this paper we argue that a similar bias exists in the way information is actively sought. We investigate how choice influences information gathering using a perceptual choice task and find that participants sample more information from a previously chosen alternative. Furthermore, the higher the confidence in the initial choice, the more biased information sampling becomes. As a consequence, when faced with the possibility of revising an earlier decision, participants are more likely to stick with their original choice, even when incorrect. Critically, we show that agency controls this phenomenon. The effect disappears in a fixed sampling condition where presentation of evidence is controlled by the experimenter, suggesting that the way in which confirmatory evidence is acquired critically impacts the decision process. These results suggest active information acquisition plays a critical role in the propagation of strongly held beliefs over time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450332" rel="alternate" title="Cherry-picking information: humans actively sample evidence to support prior beliefs (51 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.02.450779</id><title>Wild lab: A naturalistic free viewing experiment reveals previously unknown EEG signatures of face processing. (47 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.718315+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna L. Gert</name></author><author><name>Benedikt V. Ehinger</name></author><author><name>Silja Timm</name></author><author><name>Tim C Kietzmann</name></author><author><name>Peter Koenig</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neural mechanisms of face perception are predominantly studied in well-controlled experimental settings that involve random stimulus sequences and fixed eye positions. While powerful, the employed paradigms are far from what constitutes natural vision. Here, we demonstrate the feasibility of ecologically more valid experimental paradigms using natural viewing behavior, by combining a free viewing paradigm on natural scenes, free of photographer bias, with advanced data processing techniques that correct for overlap effects and co-varying nonlinear dependencies of multiple eye movement parameters. We validate this approach by replicating classic N170 effects in neural responses, triggered by fixation onsets (fERPs). Importantly, our more natural stimulus paradigm yielded smaller variability between subjects than the classic setup. Moving beyond classic temporal and spatial effect locations, our experiment furthermore revealed previously unknown signatures of face processing. This includes modulation of early fERP components, as well as category-specific adaptation effects across subsequent fixations that emerge even before fixation onset.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.02.450779" rel="alternate" title="Wild lab: A naturalistic free viewing experiment reveals previously unknown EEG signatures of face processing. (47 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.01.447872</id><title>On the topochronic map of the human brain dynamics (38 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.718687+00:00</updated><author><name>P. Sorrentino</name></author><author><name>S. Petkoski</name></author><author><name>M. Sparaco</name></author><author><name>E. Troisi Lopez</name></author><author><name>R. Rucco</name></author><author><name>E. Signoriello</name></author><author><name>F. Baselice</name></author><author><name>S. Bonavita</name></author><author><name>M.A. Pirozzi</name></author><author><name>M. Quarantelli</name></author><author><name>G. Sorrentino</name></author><author><name>V. Jirsa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Large-scale brain activity evolves dynamically over time across multiple time-scales. The structural connectome imposes a spatial network constraint since two structurally connected brain regions are more likely to coordinate their activity. It also imposes a temporal network constraint by virtue of time delays via signal transmission, which has modulatory effects on oscillatory signals. Specifically, the lengths of the structural bundles, their widths, myelination, and the topology of the structural connectome influence the timing of the interactions across the brain network. Together, they define a space-time structure (topochronic map) spanned by connection strengths (space) and signal transmission delays (time), which together establish the deterministic scaffold underlying the evolution of brain dynamics. We introduce a novel in vivo approach for directly measuring functional delays across the whole brain using magneto/electroencephalography and integrating them with the structural connectome derived from magnetic resonance imaging. We developed a map of the functional delays characterizing the connections across the human brain and a map of the corresponding functional velocities. This yields a topochronic map of the human brain dynamics. The functional delays are tightly regulated, with a trend showing, as expected, that larger structural bundles had faster velocities, with the delays varying much less than expected if they only depended upon distance. Then, we estimated the delays from magnetoencephalography (MEG) data in a cohort of multiple sclerosis patients, who have damaged myelin sheaths, and demonstrated that patients showed greater delays across the whole network than a matched control group. Furthermore, within each patient, individual lesioned connections were slowed down more than unaffected ones. Our technique provides a practical approach for estimating functional transmission delays in vivo at the single-subject and single-fiber level and, thus, opens the possibility for novel diagnostic and curative interventions as well as providing empirical, subject-specific constraints to tailor brain models.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.01.447872" rel="alternate" title="On the topochronic map of the human brain dynamics (38 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450548</id><title>Combination and competition between path integration and landmark navigation in the estimation of heading direction (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.719347+00:00</updated><author><name>Sevan K. Harootonian</name></author><author><name>Arne D. Ekstrom</name></author><author><name>Robert C. Wilson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Successful navigation requires the ability to compute one’s location and heading from incoming multisensory information. Previous work has shown that this multisensory input comes in two forms: body-based idiothetic cues, from one’s own rotations and translations, and visual allothetic cues, from the environment (usually visual landmarks). However, exactly how these two streams of information are integrated is unclear, with some models suggesting the body-based idiothetic and visual allothetic cues are combined, while others suggest they compete. In this paper we investigated the integration of body-based idiothetic and visual allothetic cues in the computation of heading using virtual reality. In our experiment, participants performed a series of body turns of up to 360 degrees in the dark with only a brief flash (300ms) of visual feedback &lt;italic&gt;en route&lt;/italic&gt;. Because the environment was virtual, we had full control over the visual feedback and were able to vary the offset between this feedback and the true heading angle. By measuring the effect of the feedback offset on the angle participants turned, we were able to determine the extent to which they incorporated visual feedback as a function of the offset error. By further modeling this behavior we were able to quantify the computations people used. While there were considerable individual differences in &lt;italic&gt;performance&lt;/italic&gt; on our task, with some participants mostly ignoring the visual feedback and others relying on it almost entirely, our modeling results suggest that almost all participants used the same &lt;italic&gt;strategy&lt;/italic&gt; in which idiothetic and allothetic cues are combined when the mismatch between them is small, but compete when the mismatch is large. These findings suggest that participants update their estimate of heading using a hybrid strategy that mixes the combination and competition of cues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Successful navigation requires us to combine visual information about our environment with body-based cues about our own rotations and translations. In this work we investigated how these disparate sources of information work together to compute an estimate of heading. Using a novel virtual reality task we measured how humans integrate visual and body-based cues when there is mismatch between them — that is, when the estimate of heading from visual information is different from body-based cues. By building computational models of different strategies, we reveal that humans use a hybrid strategy for integrating visual and body-based cues — combining them when the mismatch between them is small and picking one or the other when the mismatch is large.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450548" rel="alternate" title="Combination and competition between path integration and landmark navigation in the estimation of heading direction (22 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450616</id><title>TMEM120A/TACAN inhibits mechanically activated Piezo2 channels (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.719947+00:00</updated><author><name>John Smith Del Rosario</name></author><author><name>Matthew Gabrielle</name></author><author><name>Yevgen Yudin</name></author><author><name>Tibor Rohacs</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mechanically activated Piezo2 channels are key mediators of light touch and proprioception in mice and humans. Relatively little is known about what other proteins regulate Piezo2 activity in a cellular context. TACAN (TMEM120A) was proposed to act as a high threshold mechanically activated ion channel in nociceptive dorsal root ganglion (DRG) neurons. Here we find that TACAN co-expression robustly reduced mechanically activated Piezo2 currents, but did not inhibit mechanically activated Piezo1 and TREK1 currents. TACAN co-expression did not affect cell surface expression of either Piezo1 or Piezo2 and did not have major effects on the cortical actin or tubulin cytoskeleton. TACAN expression alone did not result in the appearance of mechanically activated currents above background. In addition, TACAN and Piezo2 expression in DRG neurons overlapped, and siRNA mediated knockdown of TACAN did not decrease the proportion of slowly adapting mechanically activated currents, but resulted in an increased proportion of rapidly adapting currents. Our data do not support TACAN being a mechanically activated ion channel, and identify it as a negative modulator of Piezo2 channel activity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450616" rel="alternate" title="TMEM120A/TACAN inhibits mechanically activated Piezo2 channels (21 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450296</id><title>Transcriptional profiling of sequentially generated septal neuron fates (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.720550+00:00</updated><author><name>Miguel Turrero García</name></author><author><name>Sarah K Stegmann</name></author><author><name>Tiara E Lacey</name></author><author><name>Christopher M Reid</name></author><author><name>Sinisa Hrvatin</name></author><author><name>Caleb Weinreb</name></author><author><name>Manal A Adam</name></author><author><name>M Aurel Nagy</name></author><author><name>Corey C Harwell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The septum is a ventral forebrain structure known to regulate innate behaviors. During embryonic development, septal neurons are produced in multiple proliferative areas from neural progenitors following transcriptional programs that are still largely unknown. Here, we use a combination of single cell RNA sequencing, histology and genetic models to address how septal neuron diversity is established during neurogenesis. We find that the transcriptional profiles of septal progenitors change along neurogenesis, coinciding with the generation of distinct neuron types. We characterize the septal eminence, a spatially distinct and transient proliferative zone composed of progenitors with distinctive molecular profiles, proliferative capacity and fate potential compared to the rostral septal progenitor zone. We show that &lt;italic&gt;Nkx2.1&lt;/italic&gt;-expressing septal eminence progenitors give rise to neurons belonging to at least three morphological classes, born in temporal cohorts that are distributed across different septal nuclei in a sequential fountain-like pattern. Our study provides insight into the molecular programs that control the sequential production of different neuronal types in the septum, a structure with important roles in regulating mood and motivation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450296" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptional profiling of sequentially generated septal neuron fates (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450628</id><title>Activity-dependent LTP in the dentate gyrus promotes epileptic seizures (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.721091+00:00</updated><author><name>Kaoutsar Nasrallah</name></author><author><name>M. Agustina Frechou</name></author><author><name>Young J. Yoon</name></author><author><name>Subrina Persaud</name></author><author><name>Tiago Gonçalves</name></author><author><name>Pablo E. Castillo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Epilepsy is a devastating brain disorder whose cellular mechanisms remain poorly understood. Excitatory mossy cells (MCs) in the dentate gyrus of the hippocampus are implicated in temporal lobe epilepsy, the most common form of focal epilepsy in adults. However, the role of MCs during initial seizures, before MC loss occurs, is unclear. Here, we show that initial seizures induced with kainic acid (KA) intraperitoneal injection in adult mice, a well-established model of experimental epilepsy, not only increased MC and granule cell (GC) activity &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, but also triggered a BDNF-dependent long-term potentiation at MC-GC synapses (MC-GC LTP). &lt;italic&gt;In vivo&lt;/italic&gt; induction of MC-GC LTP worsened KA-induced seizures, whereas selective MC silencing and &lt;italic&gt;Bdnf&lt;/italic&gt; genetic removal from GCs, which abolishes LTP, were both anti-epileptic. Thus, initial seizures strengthen MC-GC synaptic transmission, thereby promoting epileptic activity. Our findings reveal a potential mechanism of epileptogenesis that may help develop therapeutic strategies for early intervention.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450628" rel="alternate" title="Activity-dependent LTP in the dentate gyrus promotes epileptic seizures (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450574</id><title>Rapid synaptic plasticity contributes to a learned conjunctive code of position and choice-related information in the hippocampus (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.721918+00:00</updated><author><name>Xinyu Zhao</name></author><author><name>Ching-Lung Hsu</name></author><author><name>Nelson Spruston</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To successfully perform goal-directed navigation, animals must know where they are and what they are doing—e.g., looking for water, bringing food back to the nest, or escaping from a predator. Hippocampal neurons code for these critical variables conjunctively, but little is known about how this where/what code is formed or flexibly routed to other brain regions. To address these questions, we performed intracellular whole-cell recordings in mouse CA1 during a cued, two-choice virtual navigation task. We demonstrate that plateau potentials in CA1 pyramidal neurons rapidly strengthen synaptic inputs carrying conjunctive information about position and choice. Plasticity-induced response fields were modulated by cues only in animals previously trained to collect rewards based on these cues. Thus, we reveal that gradual learning is required for the formation of a conjunctive population code, upstream of CA1, while plateau-potential-induced synaptic plasticity in CA1 enables flexible routing of the code to downstream brain regions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450574" rel="alternate" title="Rapid synaptic plasticity contributes to a learned conjunctive code of position and choice-related information in the hippocampus (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.02.450916</id><title>The role of feedback in the production of skilled finger sequences (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.722512+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicola J Popp</name></author><author><name>Carlos R Hernandez-Castillo</name></author><author><name>Paul L Gribble</name></author><author><name>Joern Diedrichsen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Actions involving fine control of the hand, for example grasping an object, rely heavily on sensory information from the fingertips. While the integration of feedback during execution of individual movements is well understood, less is known about the use of sensory feedback in the control of skilled movement sequences. To address this gap, we trained participants to produce sequences of finger movements on a keyboard-like device over a four-day training period. Participants received haptic, visual, and auditory feedback indicating the occurrence of each finger press. We then either transiently delayed or advanced the feedback for a single press by a small amount of time (30 or 60 ms). We observed that participants rapidly adjusted their ongoing finger press by either accelerating or prolonging the ongoing press, in accordance with the direction of the perturbation. Furthermore, we could show that this rapid behavioural modulation was driven by haptic feedback. While these feedback-driven adjustments reduced in size with practice, they were still clearly present at the end of training. In contrast to the directionally-specific effect we observed on the perturbed press, a feedback perturbation resulted in a delayed onset of the subsequent presses irrespective of perturbation direction or feedback modality. This observation is consistent with a hierarchical organization of skilled movement sequences, with different levels reacting distinctly to sensory perturbations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.02.450916" rel="alternate" title="The role of feedback in the production of skilled finger sequences (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.02.450445</id><title>Network diffusion model predicts neurodegeneration in limb-onset amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.723029+00:00</updated><author><name>Anjan Bhattarai</name></author><author><name>Zhaolin Chen</name></author><author><name>Phyllis Chua</name></author><author><name>Paul Talman</name></author><author><name>Susan Mathers</name></author><author><name>Caron Chapman</name></author><author><name>James Howe</name></author><author><name>CM Sarah Lee</name></author><author><name>Yenni Lie</name></author><author><name>Govinda R Poudel</name></author><author><name>Gary F Egan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The trans-neural propagation of phosphorylated 43-kDa transactive response DNA-binding protein (pTDP-43) contributes to neurodegeneration in Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis (ALS). We investigated whether Network Diffusion Model (NDM), a biophysical model of spread of pathology via the brain connectome, could capture the severity and progression of neurodegeneration (atrophy) in ALS. We measured degeneration in limb-onset ALS patients (n=14 at baseline, 12 at 6-months, and 9 at 12 months) and controls (n=12 at baseline) using FreeSurfer analysis on the structural T1-weighted Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) data. The NDM was simulated on the canonical structural connectome from the IIT Human Brain Atlas. To determine whether NDM could predict the atrophy pattern in ALS, the accumulation of pathology modelled by NDM was correlated against atrophy measured using MRI. The cross-sectional analyses revealed that the network diffusion seeded from the inferior frontal gyrus (pars triangularis and pars orbitalis) significantly predicts the atrophy pattern in ALS compared to controls. Whereas, atrophy over time with-in the ALS group was best predicted by seeding the network diffusion process from the inferior temporal gyrus at 6-month and caudal middle frontal gyrus at 12-month. Our findings suggest the involvement of extra-motor regions in seeding the spread of pathology in ALS. Importantly, NDM was able to recapitulate the dynamics of pathological progression in ALS. Understanding the spatial shifts in the seeds of degeneration over time can potentially inform further research in the design of disease modifying therapeutic interventions in ALS.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.02.450445" rel="alternate" title="Network diffusion model predicts neurodegeneration in limb-onset amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>