<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv neuroscience preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.559947+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neuroscience/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443151</id><title>Evaluating brain parcellations using the distance controlled boundary coefficient (203 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.560714+00:00</updated><author><name>Da Zhi</name></author><author><name>Maedbh King</name></author><author><name>Jörn Diedrichsen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;An important goal of human brain mapping is to define a set of distinct regions that can be linked to unique functions. Numerous brain parcellations have been proposed, using cytoarchitectonic data, structural or functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI). The intrinsic smoothness of the brain data, however, poses a problem for current methods seeking to compare different parcellations to each other. For example, criteria that simply compare within-parcel to between-parcel similarity provide even random parcellations with a high value. Furthermore, the evaluation is biased by the spatial scale of the parcellation. To address this problem, we propose the Distance Controlled Boundary Coefficient (DCBC), an unbiased criterion to evaluate discrete parcellations. We employ this new criterion to evaluate whether existing parcellations of the human neocortex can predict functional boundaries on a rich multi-domain task battery. We find that common anatomical parcellations do not perform better than chance, suggesting that task-based functional boundaries do not align well with sulcal landmarks. Parcellations based on resting-state fMRI data perform well; in some cases, as well as a parcellation defined on the evaluation data itself. Finally, multi-modal parcellations that combine functional and anatomical criteria perform substantially worse than those based on functional data alone, indicating that functionally homogeneous regions often span major anatomical landmarks. Overall, the DCBC advances the field of functional brain mapping by providing an unbiased metric that compares the predictive ability of different brain parcellations to define functionally and anatomically homogeneous brain regions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443151" rel="alternate" title="Evaluating brain parcellations using the distance controlled boundary coefficient (203 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443799</id><title>Scale-free behavioral dynamics directly linked with scale-free cortical dynamics (51 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.561146+00:00</updated><author><name>Sabrina A. Jones</name></author><author><name>Jacob H. Barfield</name></author><author><name>Woodrow L. Shew</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Naturally occurring body movements and collective neural activity both exhibit complex dynamics, often with scale-free, fractal spatiotemporal structure, thought to confer functional benefits to the organism. Despite their similarities, scale-free brain activity and scale-free behavior have been studied separately, without a unified explanation. Here we show that scale-free dynamics of behavior and certain subsets of cortical neurons are one-to-one related. Surprisingly, the scale-free neural subsets exhibit stochastic winner-take-all competition with other neural subsets, inconsistent with prevailing theory of scale-free neural systems. We develop a computational model which accounts for known cell-type-specific circuit structure and explains our findings. Our results establish neural underpinnings of scale-free behavior and clear behavioral relevance of scale-free neural activity, which was previously thought to represent background noise in cerebral cortex.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Winner-take-all competition among cortical neurons underpins shared fractal spatiotemporal dynamics of behavior and brain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443799" rel="alternate" title="Scale-free behavioral dynamics directly linked with scale-free cortical dynamics (51 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443836</id><title>cAMP controls a trafficking mechanism that directs the neuron specificity and subcellular placement of electrical synapses (42 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.561416+00:00</updated><author><name>Sierra Palumbos</name></author><author><name>Rachel Skelton</name></author><author><name>Rebecca McWhirter</name></author><author><name>Amanda Mitchell</name></author><author><name>Isaiah Swann</name></author><author><name>Sydney Heifner</name></author><author><name>Steve Von Stetina</name></author><author><name>David M Miller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Electrical synapses are established between specific neurons and within distinct subcellular compartments, but the mechanisms that direct gap junction assembly in the nervous system are largely unknown. Here we show that a transcriptional program tunes cAMP signaling to direct the neuron-specific assembly and placement of electrical synapses in the &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; motor circuit. For these studies, we use live cell imaging to visualize electrical synapses in vivo and a novel optogenetic assay to confirm that they are functional. In VA motor neurons, the UNC-4 transcription factor blocks expression of cAMP antagonists that promote gap junction miswiring. In &lt;italic&gt;unc-4&lt;/italic&gt; mutants, VA electrical synapses are established with an alternative synaptic partner and are repositioned from the VA axon to soma. We show that cAMP counters these effects by driving gap junction trafficking into the VA axon for electrical synapse assembly. Thus, our experiments in an intact nervous system establish that cAMP regulates gap junction trafficking for the biogenesis of electrical synapses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443836" rel="alternate" title="cAMP controls a trafficking mechanism that directs the neuron specificity and subcellular placement of electrical synapses (42 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.443762</id><title>Altered cerebellar response to somatosensory stimuli in the Cntnap2 mouse model of autism (34 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.561816+00:00</updated><author><name>Marta Fernández</name></author><author><name>Carlos A. Sánchez-León</name></author><author><name>Javier Llorente</name></author><author><name>Teresa Sierra-Arregui</name></author><author><name>Shira Knafo</name></author><author><name>Javier Márquez-Ruiz</name></author><author><name>Olga Peñagarikano</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Atypical sensory processing is currently included within the diagnostic criteria of autism. The cerebellum is known to integrate sensory inputs of different modalities through its connectivity to the cerebral cortex. Interestingly, cerebellar malformations are among the most replicated features found in postmortem brain of individuals with autism. We studied cerebellar integration of sensory information in a mouse model of autism, knockout for the &lt;italic&gt;Cntnap2&lt;/italic&gt; gene. &lt;italic&gt;Cntnap2&lt;/italic&gt; is widely expressed in Purkinje cells and has been recently reported to regulate their morphology. Further, individuals with &lt;italic&gt;CNTNAP2&lt;/italic&gt; mutations display cerebellar malformations and CNTNAP2 antibodies are associated with a mild form of cerebellar ataxia. Previous studies in the &lt;italic&gt;Cntnap2&lt;/italic&gt; mouse model show an altered cerebellar sensory learning. However, a physiological analysis of cerebellar function has not been performed yet. We studied sensory evoked potentials in cerebellar Crus I/II region upon electrical stimulation of the whisker pad in alert mice and found striking differences between WT and &lt;italic&gt;Cntnap2&lt;/italic&gt; KO mice. In addition, single-cell recordings identified alterations in both sensory-evoked and spontaneous firing patterns of Purkinje cells. These changes were accompanied by altered intrinsic properties and morphological features of these neurons. Together, these results indicate that the &lt;italic&gt;Cntnap2&lt;/italic&gt; mouse model could provide novel insight into the pathophysiological mechanisms of ASD core sensory deficits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.443762" rel="alternate" title="Altered cerebellar response to somatosensory stimuli in the Cntnap2 mouse model of autism (34 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443860</id><title>Variable brain wiring through scalable and relative synapse formation in Drosophila (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.562067+00:00</updated><author><name>F. Ridvan Kiral</name></author><author><name>Suchetana B. Dutta</name></author><author><name>Gerit Arne Linneweber</name></author><author><name>Caroline Poppa</name></author><author><name>Max von Kleist</name></author><author><name>Bassem A. Hassan</name></author><author><name>Peter Robin Hiesinger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Variability of synapse numbers and partners despite identical genes reveals limits of genetic determinism. Non-genetic perturbation of brain wiring can therefore reveal to what extent synapse formation is precise and absolute, or promiscuous and relative. Here, we show the role of relative partner availability for synapse formation in the fly brain through perturbation of developmental temperature. Unexpectedly, slower development at lower temperatures substantially increases axo-dendritic branching, synapse numbers and non-canonical synaptic partnerships of various neurons, while maintaining robust ratios of canonical synapses. Using R7 photoreceptors as a model, we further show that scalability of synapse numbers and ratios is preserved when relative availability of synaptic partners is changed in a DIPγ mutant that ablates R7’s preferred synaptic partner. Behaviorally, movement activity scales inversely with synapse numbers, while movement precision and relative connectivity are congruently robust. Hence, the fly genome encodes scalable relative connectivity to develop functional, but not identical, brains.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Non-identical connectivity and behavior result from temperature-dependent synaptic partner availability in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443860" rel="alternate" title="Variable brain wiring through scalable and relative synapse formation in Drosophila (31 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443328</id><title>Kinesin-3 mediated delivery of presynaptic neurexin stabilizes growing dendritic spines and postsynaptic components in vivo (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.563504+00:00</updated><author><name>Devyn Oliver</name></author><author><name>Shankar Ramachandran</name></author><author><name>Alison Philbrook</name></author><author><name>Christopher M. Lambert</name></author><author><name>Ken C. Q. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>David H. Hall</name></author><author><name>Michael M. Francis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A high degree of cell and circuit-specific regulation has complicated efforts to precisely define roles for synaptic adhesion proteins in establishing circuit connectivity. Here, we take advantage of the strengths of &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; for cell-specific analyses to investigate molecular coordination of pre- and postsynaptic development. We show that developing dendritic spines emerge from the dendrites of wild type GABAergic motor neurons following the localization of active zone proteins and the formation of immature synaptic vesicle assemblies in presynaptic terminals. Similarly, clusters of postsynaptic receptors and F-actin are visible in GABAergic dendrites prior to spine outgrowth. Surprisingly, these developmental processes occur without a requirement for synaptic activity. Likewise, the initial stages of spine outgrowth and receptor clustering are not altered by deletion of the &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; ortholog of the transsynaptic adhesion protein, neurexin/NRX-1. Over time, however, dendritic spines and postsynaptic receptor clusters are destabilized in the absence of presynaptic NRX-1/neurexin and collapse prior to adulthood. The kinesin-3 family member, UNC-104, delivers NRX-1 to presynaptic terminals and ongoing UNC-104 delivery is required into adulthood for the maintenance of postsynaptic structure. Our findings provide novel insights into the temporal order of synapse formation events &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and demonstrate a requirement for transsynaptic adhesion in stabilizing mature circuit connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contributions Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;D.O. generated strains, transgenic lines, molecular constructs, confocal and electron microscopy images, and data analysis. S.R. performed all calcium imaging experiments and analysis. C.M.L. generated destination vectors and &lt;italic&gt;nrx-1&lt;/italic&gt; constructs. D.H.H. and K.C.Q.N. aided in electron microscopy experiments and analysis. M.M.F and D.O designed and interpreted results of all experiments and wrote the manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443328" rel="alternate" title="Kinesin-3 mediated delivery of presynaptic neurexin stabilizes growing dendritic spines and postsynaptic components in vivo (23 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443909</id><title>Mice lacking the cAMP effector protein POPDC1 show enhanced hippocampal synaptic plasticity (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.563928+00:00</updated><author><name>Mahesh Shivarama Shetty</name></author><author><name>Laurence Ris</name></author><author><name>Roland F. R. Schindler</name></author><author><name>Keiko Mizuno</name></author><author><name>Laura Fedele</name></author><author><name>Karl Peter Giese</name></author><author><name>Thomas Brand</name></author><author><name>Ted Abel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Extensive research has uncovered diverse forms of synaptic plasticity and a wide array of molecular signaling mechanisms that act as positive or negative regulators. Specifically, cAMP-dependent signaling pathways have been crucially implicated in long-lasting synaptic plasticity. In this study, we examine the role of POPDC1 (or BVES), a cAMP effector protein expressed in brain, in modulating hippocampal synaptic plasticity. Unlike other cAMP effectors, such as PKA and EPAC, POPDC1 is membrane-bound and the sequence of the cAMP-binding cassette differs from canonical cAMP-binding domains. These properties suggest that POPDC1 may have a unique role in cAMP-mediated signaling underlying synaptic plasticity. Our results show that POPDC1 is enriched in hippocampal synaptoneurosomes. Acute hippocampal slices from &lt;italic&gt;Popdc1&lt;/italic&gt; knockout (KO) mice exhibit enhanced long-term potentiation (LTP) induced by a variety of stimulation paradigms, particularly in response to weak stimulation paradigms that in slices from wildtype mice induce only transient LTP. Furthermore, &lt;italic&gt;Popdc1&lt;/italic&gt; KO mice did not display any further enhancement in forskolin-induced LTP observed following inhibition of phosphodiesterases (PDEs), suggesting a possible modulation of cAMP-PDE signaling by POPDC1. Taken together, these data reveal POPDC1 as a novel player in the regulation of hippocampal synaptic plasticity and as a potential target for cognitive enhancement strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443909" rel="alternate" title="Mice lacking the cAMP effector protein POPDC1 show enhanced hippocampal synaptic plasticity (14 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443911</id><title>Structural and cellular transcriptome foundations of human brain disease (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.564117+00:00</updated><author><name>Yashar Zeighami</name></author><author><name>Trygve Bakken</name></author><author><name>Thomas Nickl-Jockschat</name></author><author><name>Jeremy Miller</name></author><author><name>Alan C. Evans</name></author><author><name>Ed Lein</name></author><author><name>Michael Hawrylycz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The intersection of human genetics and brain transcriptomics promises to reveal the structural and cellular locus of brain diseases via selective co-expression of risk genes. We find that adult brain-wide transcriptomic profiles of 40 human brain diseases identify four major transcriptional patterns, represented by tumor-related, neurodegenerative, psychiatric and substance abuse, and a mixed group of diseases, with some unexpected disease associations. Based on differential co-expression using bulk transcriptomics, the majority of brain diseases exhibit unique regional transcriptomic signatures that strongly reflect neuronal versus non-neuronal divisions and variation in excitatory and inhibitory neurons across the brain. Single cell transcriptomic data confirms and refines the relationship of different diseases to specific neuronal and non-neuronal subclasses. Disease signatures are largely conserved between mouse and human at the higher cell class level, but with significant species differences emerging at the finer subclass level that may help explain human-specific disease susceptibility.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443911" rel="alternate" title="Structural and cellular transcriptome foundations of human brain disease (14 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443637</id><title>Cortical ripples provide the conditions for consolidation during NREM sleep in humans (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.564285+00:00</updated><author><name>Charles W. Dickey</name></author><author><name>Ilya A. Verzhbinsky</name></author><author><name>Xi Jiang</name></author><author><name>Burke Q. Rosen</name></author><author><name>Sophie Kajfez</name></author><author><name>Emad N. Eskandar</name></author><author><name>Jorge Gonzalez-Martinez</name></author><author><name>Sydney S. Cash</name></author><author><name>Eric Halgren</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hippocampal ripples index the reconstruction of spatiotemporal neuronal firing patterns essential for the consolidation of memories in the cortex during non-rapid eye movement (NREM) sleep. However, it is not known whether ripples are generated in the human cortex during sleep. Here, using human intracranial recordings, we show that ∼70ms long ∼80Hz ripples are ubiquitous in all regions of the cortex during NREM sleep as well as waking. During waking, cortical ripples occur on local high frequency activity peaks. During sleep, cortical ripples occur during spindles on the down-to-upstate transition, with unit-firing patterns consistent with generation by pyramidal-interneuron feedback. Cortical ripples mark the recurrence of spatiotemporal activity patterns from preceding waking, and they group co-firing within the window of spike-timing-dependent plasticity. Thus, cortical ripples guided by sequential sleep waves may facilitate memory consolidation during NREM sleep in humans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443637" rel="alternate" title="Cortical ripples provide the conditions for consolidation during NREM sleep in humans (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443898</id><title>Dual origin and multiple neuropeptidergic trajectories of hypothalamic POMC progenitors revealed by developmental single-cell transcriptomics (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.564470+00:00</updated><author><name>Hui Yu</name></author><author><name>Marcelo Rubinstein</name></author><author><name>Malcolm J Low</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Proopiomelanocortin (POMC) neurons of the hypothalamic arcuate nucleus are essential to regulate food intake and energy balance. However, the ontogenetic transcriptional programs that specify the identity and functioning of these neurons are poorly understood. Here, we use scRNAseq to define the transcriptomes characterizing POMC progenitors in the developing hypothalamus and their transition into mature neurons. Our data show that &lt;italic&gt;Pomc&lt;/italic&gt;-expressing neurons originate from two independent developmental pathways expressing distinct combinations of transcription factors. The predominant cluster, featured by high levels of &lt;italic&gt;Pomc&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Prdm12&lt;/italic&gt; transcripts represents the precursors of canonical arcuate POMC neurons. Additional clusters of progenitors expressing lower levels of &lt;italic&gt;Pomc&lt;/italic&gt; mature into different neuronal phenotypes characterized by distinct combinations of transcription factors, neuropeptides, processing enzymes, cell surface and nuclear receptors. We conclude that the genetic programs specifying the identity and differentiation of arcuate POMC neurons are diverse and generate a heterogeneous repertoire of neuronal phenotypes early in development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443898" rel="alternate" title="Dual origin and multiple neuropeptidergic trajectories of hypothalamic POMC progenitors revealed by developmental single-cell transcriptomics (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443894</id><title>A behavioral screen for mediators of age-dependent TDP-43 neurodegeneration identifies SF2/SRSF1 among a group of potent suppressors in both neurons and glia (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.564613+00:00</updated><author><name>Jorge Azpurua</name></author><author><name>Enas Gad El-Karim</name></author><author><name>Marvel Tranquille</name></author><author><name>Josh Dubnau</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cytoplasmic aggregation of Tar-DNA/RNA binding protein 43 (TDP-43) occurs in 97 percent of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS), about 40 percent of frontotemporal dementia (FTD) and in many cases of Alzheimer’s disease (AD). Cytoplasmic TDP-43 inclusions are seen in both sporadic and familial forms of these disorders, including those cases that are caused by repeat expansion mutations in the &lt;italic&gt;C9orf72&lt;/italic&gt; gene. To identify downstream mediators of TDP-43 toxicity, we expressed human TDP-43 in a subset of &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; motor neurons. Such expression causes age-dependent deficits in negative geotaxis behavior. Using this behavioral readout of locomotion, we conducted an shRNA suppressor screen and identified 32 transcripts whose knockdown was sufficient to ameliorate the neurological phenotype. The majority of these suppressors also substantially suppressed the negative effects on lifespan seen with glial TDP-43 expression. In addition to identification of a number of genes whose roles in neurodegeneration were not previously known, our screen also yielded genes involved in chromatin regulation and nuclear/import export-pathways that were previously identified in the context of cell based or neurodevelopmental suppressor screens. A notable example is &lt;italic&gt;SF2&lt;/italic&gt;, a conserved orthologue of mammalian &lt;italic&gt;SRSF1&lt;/italic&gt;, an RNA binding protein with roles in splicing and nuclear export. Our identification &lt;italic&gt;SF2/SRSF1&lt;/italic&gt; as a potent suppressor of both neuronal and glial TDP-43 toxicity also provides a convergence with &lt;italic&gt;C9orf72&lt;/italic&gt; expansion repeat mediated neurodegeneration, where this gene also acts as a downstream mediator.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Loss of nuclear function of TDP-43 and its mislocalization into cytoplasmic inclusions are central features to a suite of neurodegenerative disorders. We screened 2700 &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; genes to identify downstream mediators that suppress an age-dependent motor dysfunction phenotype when they are knocked down by RNA interference. We identified both previously implicated pathways and several novel genes whose knock down is sufficient to dramatically and robustly rescue TDP-43 toxicity both in neuronal and glial contexts. Notably, we report that &lt;italic&gt;SF2/SRSF1&lt;/italic&gt;, which was previously reported as a suppressor of &lt;italic&gt;C9orf72&lt;/italic&gt; hexanucleotide expansion repeat toxicity, also is a potent suppressor of TDP-43 mediated neurodegeneration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443894" rel="alternate" title="A behavioral screen for mediators of age-dependent TDP-43 neurodegeneration identifies SF2/SRSF1 among a group of potent suppressors in both neurons and glia (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443804</id><title>Common neural bases for processing speech prosody and music: An integrated model (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.564783+00:00</updated><author><name>Alice Mado Proverbio</name></author><author><name>Elisabetta Piotti</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It is shared notion that speech and music processing share some commonalities. Brain bioelectrical activity was recorded in healthy participants listening to music obtained by digitally transforming real speech into melodies played by viola. Sentences were originally pronounced with a positive or negative affective prosody. The research’s aim was to investigate if the emotional content of music was extracted similarly to how the affective prosody of speech is processed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;EEG was recorded from 128 electrodes in 20 healthy students. Participants had to detect rare neutral piano sounds while ignoring viola melodies. Stimulus negative valence increased the amplitude of frontal P300 and N400 ERP components while a late inferior frontal positivity was enhanced in response to positive melodies. Similar ERP markers were previously found for processing positive and negative music, vocalizations and speech. Source reconstruction applied to N400 showed that negative melodies engaged the right superior temporal gyrus and right anterior cingulate cortex, while positive melodies engaged the left middle and inferior temporal gyrus and the inferior frontal cortex. An integrated model is proposed depicting a possible common circuit for processing the emotional content of music, vocalizations and speech, which might explain some universal and relatively innate brain reaction to music.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443804" rel="alternate" title="Common neural bases for processing speech prosody and music: An integrated model (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.443904</id><title>Truncating Tau Reveals Different Pathophysiological Actions of Oligomers in Single Neurons (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.565013+00:00</updated><author><name>Emily Hill</name></author><author><name>Thomas K. Karikari</name></author><author><name>Juan Lantero Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Henrik Zetterberg</name></author><author><name>Kaj Blennow</name></author><author><name>Magnus J Richardson</name></author><author><name>Mark J Wall</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tau protein is involved in maintaining the structural integrity of neurons. In tauopathies, including Alzheimer’s disease, tau forms oligomers, which can modulate neuronal function. Previously the introduction of oligomeric full-length human tau (aa 1-441; FL-oTau) into pyramidal neurons decreased whole-cell conductance, increased excitability and changed the action potential (AP) waveform. Introducing N-terminally truncated tau (aa 124-441; C&lt;sup&gt;FRAG&lt;/sup&gt;) removed the effects on the AP waveform and input resistance but the increase in excitability remained. A hyperpolarising shift in spike threshold underlies this increase in excitability. The N-terminal fragment (aa 1-123; N&lt;sup&gt;FRAG&lt;/sup&gt;) markedly increased input resistance and changed the AP waveform. Lower concentrations of N&lt;sup&gt;FRAG&lt;/sup&gt; only changed the AP waveform. Thus the two truncations can recapitulate the effects of FL-oTau. To investigate underlying mechanisms, we recorded sodium currents and found that FL-oTau lowers the activation voltage and reduced the maximal conductance, consistent with the lower spike threshold and reduction in AP amplitude&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphic abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="443904v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.443904" rel="alternate" title="Truncating Tau Reveals Different Pathophysiological Actions of Oligomers in Single Neurons (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.15.444029</id><title>Evidence of wiring development processes from the connectome of adult Drosophila (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.565379+00:00</updated><author><name>Louis K Scheffer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;How is the brain wired during development? Here we look at some of the characteristics of the adult Drosophila brain, a result of this development process. From this we can speculate on at least some aspects of how the wiring was done. A common hypothesis is that surface proteins direct synapse formation among touching neurons. Assuming that surface proteins are specific to cell types, we find support for this hypothesis. The brain in general supports a wide variety of connections of different degrees of reciprocity, with ratios up to a thousand to one in the two directions of synapses between types. However, contacts between cells of the same type are always bi-directional and nearly equal strength. Furthermore, among similar cell types, at least in the mushroom body, the closer the cell type by morphology, the closer the inter-type contacts are to symmetrical. These findings are all consistent with the hypothesis that surface proteins specific to cell types determine the directivity of connections. Next we look at synapses per area, and find this varies widely and is roughly log-normally distributed. In most cases, the number of synapses saturates at higher areas, though other forms are seen - linear, flat, or decreasing with increasing area. Evidence suggests that at least some of this distinction is post-synaptic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.15.444029" rel="alternate" title="Evidence of wiring development processes from the connectome of adult Drosophila (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443512</id><title>Prodromal dysfunction of α5GABA-A receptor modulated hippocampal ripples in Alzheimer’s disease (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.565831+00:00</updated><author><name>Marcia H. Ratner</name></author><author><name>Scott S. Downing</name></author><author><name>Ouyang Guo</name></author><author><name>KathrynAnn E. Odamah</name></author><author><name>Tara M. Stewart</name></author><author><name>Vidhya Kumaresan</name></author><author><name>R. Jonathan Robitsek</name></author><author><name>Weiming Xia</name></author><author><name>David H. Farb</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Decades of research attempting to slow the onset of Alzheimer’s disease (AD) indicates that a better understanding of memory will be key to the discovery of effective therapeutic approaches. Here, we ask whether prodromal neural network dysfunction might occur in the hippocampal trisynaptic circuit by using α5IA as a selective negative modulator of extrasynaptic α5GABA-A receptors in TgF344-AD transgenic rats, a model for early onset AD. The results demonstrate that orally bioavailable α5IA, an established memory enhancer, increases CA1 pyramidal cell mean firing rates and peak CA1 ripple amplitude during wakeful immobility in &lt;italic&gt;wild type&lt;/italic&gt; F344 rats resting in a familiar environment. We show that TgF344-AD rats, which express human amyloid-beta precursor protein (with the Swedish mutation) and human presenilin-1 (with a Δ exon 9 mutation), exhibit high serum Aβ42 and Aβ40 levels by 3 months of age. By 9 months of age, CA1 ripples in young adult TgF344-AD rats are nonresponsive to α5IA indicating network dysfunction prior to the onset of AD pathology and memory dysfunction. These results demonstrate, to the best of our knowledge, the first evidence for prodromal α5GABA-A receptor dysfunction in the AD hippocampal trisynaptic circuit. Moreover, as α5GABA-A receptors are located extrasynaptically and subserve the function of tonic inhibition we posit that an early stage of memory dysfunction involves the disruption of tonic inhibition in the hippocampus.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443512" rel="alternate" title="Prodromal dysfunction of α5GABA-A receptor modulated hippocampal ripples in Alzheimer’s disease (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443522</id><title>Exosomal transmission of α-synuclein initiates Parkinson’s disease-like pathology (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.566390+00:00</updated><author><name>Jason Howitt</name></author><author><name>Ley Hian Low</name></author><author><name>Michelle Bouman</name></author><author><name>Jeremy Yang</name></author><author><name>Sarah Gordon</name></author><author><name>Andrew Hill</name></author><author><name>Seong-Seng Tan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The intercellular transmission of α-synuclein is proposed to be involved in the pathogenesis of Parkinson’s disease (PD)&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. Supporting this transmission hypothesis, α-synuclein has been identified to act as a prion&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; and has been found in cerebrospinal fluid (CSF), blood, and saliva&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;. However, the mechanism required to initiate the pathogenic spread of α-synuclein in the body that results in PD remains unclear. Here we identify a mechanism for the loading of α-synuclein into exosomes, resulting in prion-like transmission that is mediated by the ubiquitin ligase activator, Ndfip1. Risk factors associated with PD, including metal toxicity, lysosome dysfunction and pesticide exposure,&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; stimulate the upregulation of Ndfip1 and increase the loading of α-synuclein into exosomes. We used this pathway to promote the loading of endogenous α-synuclein into exosomes, that when intranasally delivered to either wild type or M83 transgenic mice, resulted in Parkinson’s-like pathology including motor impairments and brain amyloids. Recipient cells require α-synuclein for pathogenesis, as delivery of exosomes containing α-synuclein to Snca knockout mice did not generate brain amyloids or Parkinson’s-like motor impairments. Our results demonstrate a novel mechanism to initiate the prion-like spread of α-synuclein in exosomes, following exposure to risk factors for PD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443522" rel="alternate" title="Exosomal transmission of α-synuclein initiates Parkinson’s disease-like pathology (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.16.444253</id><title>Beyond BOLD: in search of genuine diffusion fMRI contrast in human brain (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.566747+00:00</updated><author><name>Wiktor Olszowy</name></author><author><name>Yujian Diao</name></author><author><name>Ileana O Jelescu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI) is an essential method to measure brain activity non-invasively. While fMRI almost systematically relies on the blood oxygenation level-dependent (BOLD) contrast, there is an increasing interest in alternative methods that would not rely on neurovascular coupling. A promising but controversial such alternative is diffusion fMRI (dfMRI), which relies instead on dynamic fluctuations in apparent diffusion coefficient (ADC) due to microstructural changes underlying neuronal activity. However, it is unclear whether genuine dfMRI contrast, distinct from BOLD contamination, can be detected in the human brain in physiological conditions. Here, we present the first dfMRI study in humans attempting to minimize all BOLD contamination sources and comparing functional responses at two field strengths (3T and 7T), both for task and resting-state (RS) fMRI. Our study benefits from unprecedented high spatiotemporal resolution and harnesses novel denoising strategies. We report task-induced decrease in ADC with temporal and spatial features distinct from the BOLD response and yielding more specific activation maps. Furthermore, we report dfMRI RS connectivity which, compared to its BOLD counterpart, is essentially free from physiological artifacts and preserves positive correlations but preferentially suppresses anti-correlations, which are likely of vascular origin. A careful acquisition and processing design thus enable the detection of genuine dfMRI contrast on clinical MRI systems. As opposed to BOLD, diffusion functional contrast could be particularly well suited for low-field MRI.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.16.444253" rel="alternate" title="Beyond BOLD: in search of genuine diffusion fMRI contrast in human brain (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443839</id><title>Spatiotemporal 3D image registration for mesoscale studies of brain development (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.567098+00:00</updated><author><name>Sergey Shuvaev</name></author><author><name>Alexander Lazutkin</name></author><author><name>Roman Kiryanov</name></author><author><name>Konstantin Anokhin</name></author><author><name>Grigori Enikolopov</name></author><author><name>Alexei A. Koulakov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Comparison of brain samples representing different developmental stages often necessitates registering the samples to common coordinates. Although the available software tools are successful in registering 3D images of adult brains, registration of perinatal brains remains challenging due to rapid growth-dependent morphological changes and variations in developmental pace between animals. To address these challenges, we propose a multi-step algorithm for the registration of perinatal brains. First, we optimized image preprocessing to increase the algorithm’s sensitivity to mismatches in registered images. Second, we developed an attention-gated simulated annealing (Monte Carlo) procedure capable of focusing on the differences between perinatal brains. Third, we applied classical multidimensional scaling (CMDS) to align (“synchronize”) brain samples in time, accounting for individual development paces. We tested this multi-step algorithm on 28 samples of whole-mounted perinatal mouse brains (P0 – P9) and observed accurate registration results. Our computational pipeline offers a runtime of several minutes per brain on a personal computer and automates brain registration tasks including mapping brain data to atlases, comparison of averaged experimental groups, and monitoring brain development dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443839" rel="alternate" title="Spatiotemporal 3D image registration for mesoscale studies of brain development (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443573</id><title>microRNA-138 controls hippocampal interneuron function and short-term memory (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.568057+00:00</updated><author><name>R. Daswani</name></author><author><name>C. Gilardi</name></author><author><name>M. Soutschek</name></author><author><name>K. Weiss</name></author><author><name>S. Bicker</name></author><author><name>R. Fiore</name></author><author><name>C. Dieterich</name></author><author><name>P.L. Germain</name></author><author><name>J Winterer</name></author><author><name>G Schratt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A tightly regulated balance between excitatory and inhibitory (E/I) synaptic transmission is critical for neural circuit assembly and function. microRNAs control excitatory neuron function, but their role in inhibitory interneurons is unknown. Here, we show that miR-138-5p regulates the expression of presynaptic genes in hippocampal parvalbumin-expressing inhibitory interneurons to control short-term memory. Our finding suggests a critical role for miR-138-5p in disorders of impaired E/I balance, such as autism and schizophrenia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443573" rel="alternate" title="microRNA-138 controls hippocampal interneuron function and short-term memory (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443607</id><title>Dysfunctions of the paraventricular hypothalamic nucleus induce hypersomnia in human and mice (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.568962+00:00</updated><author><name>Chang-Rui Chen</name></author><author><name>Yu-Heng Zhong</name></author><author><name>Shan Jiang</name></author><author><name>Wei Xu</name></author><author><name>Zan Wang</name></author><author><name>Lei Xiao</name></author><author><name>Wei-Min Qu</name></author><author><name>Zhi-Li Huang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hypersomnolence disorder (HD) is characterized by excessive sleep, which is a common sequela following stroke, infections or tumorigenesis. HD was traditionally thought to be associated with lesions of wake-promoting nuclei. However, lesion of a single, even two or more wake-promoting nucleuses simultaneously did not exert serious HD. The specific nucleus and neural circuitry for HD remain unknown. Here, we observed that three patients with lesions around the paraventricular nucleus of the hypothalamus (PVH) showed hypersomnolence lasting more than 20 h per day and their excessive sleep decreased with the recovery of the PVH area. Therefore, we hypothesized that the PVH might play an essential role in the occurrence of HD. Using multichannel electrophysiological recording and fiber photometry, we found that PVH&lt;sup&gt;vglut2&lt;/sup&gt; neurons were preferentially active during wakefulness. Chemogenetic activation of PVH&lt;sup&gt;vglut2&lt;/sup&gt; neurons potently induced 9-h wakefulness, and PVH&lt;sup&gt;CRH&lt;/sup&gt;, PVH&lt;sup&gt;PDYN&lt;/sup&gt; and PVH&lt;sup&gt;OT&lt;/sup&gt; neuronal activation also exerted wakefulness. Most importantly, ablation of PVH&lt;sup&gt;vglut2&lt;/sup&gt; neurons drastically induced hypersomnia-like behaviors (30.6% reduction in wakefulness). These results indicate that dysfunctions of the PVH is crucial for physiological arousal and pathogenesis underlying HD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443607" rel="alternate" title="Dysfunctions of the paraventricular hypothalamic nucleus induce hypersomnia in human and mice (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443598</id><title>Parallel processing of olfactory and mechanosensory information in the honeybee antennal lobe (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.569896+00:00</updated><author><name>Ettore Tiraboschi</name></author><author><name>Luana Leonardelli</name></author><author><name>Gianluca Segata</name></author><author><name>Elisa Rigosi</name></author><author><name>Albrecht Haase</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We report that airflow produces a complex activation pattern in the antennal lobes of the honeybee &lt;italic&gt;Apis mellifera&lt;/italic&gt;. Glomerular response maps provide a stereotypical code for the intensity and the dynamics of mechanical stimuli that is superimposed on the olfactory code. We show responses to modulated stimuli suggesting that this combinatorial code could provide information about the intensity, direction, and dynamics of the airflow during flight and waggle dance communication.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443598" rel="alternate" title="Parallel processing of olfactory and mechanosensory information in the honeybee antennal lobe (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443802</id><title>Fluid intelligence and naturalistic task impairments after focal brain lesions (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.570538+00:00</updated><author><name>Verity Smith</name></author><author><name>Clara Pinasco</name></author><author><name>Jascha Achterberg</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Mitchell</name></author><author><name>Tilak Das</name></author><author><name>Maria Roca</name></author><author><name>John Duncan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Classical executive tasks, such as Wisconsin card-sorting and verbal fluency, are widely used as tests of frontal lobe control functions. Since the pioneering work of Shallice and Burgess (1991), it has been known that complex, naturalistic tasks can capture deficits that are missed in these classical tests. Matching this finding, deficits in several classical tasks are predicted by loss of fluid intelligence, linked to damage in a specific cortical “multiple-demand” (MD) network, while deficits in a more naturalistic task are not. To expand on these previous results, we examined the effect of focal brain lesions on three new tests – a modification of the previously-used Hotel task, a new test of task switching after extended delays, and a test of decision-making in imagined real-life scenarios. As potential predictors of impairment we measured volume of damage to &lt;italic&gt;a priori&lt;/italic&gt; MD and default mode (DMN) networks, as well as cortical damage outside these networks. Deficits in the three new tasks were substantial, but were not explained by loss of fluid intelligence, or by volume of damage to either MD or DMN networks. Instead, deficits were associated with diverse lesions, and not strongly correlated with one another. The results confirm that naturalistic tasks capture cognitive deficits beyond those measured by fluid intelligence. We suggest, however, that these deficits may not arise from specific control operations required by complex behaviour. Instead, like everyday activities, complex tasks combine a rich variety of interacting cognitive components, bringing many opportunities for processing to be disturbed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443802" rel="alternate" title="Fluid intelligence and naturalistic task impairments after focal brain lesions (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443755</id><title>Visuo-proprioceptive integration and recalibration with multiple visual stimuli (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.571003+00:00</updated><author><name>Nienke B Debats</name></author><author><name>Herbert Heuer</name></author><author><name>Christoph Kayser</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To organize the plethora of sensory signals from our environment into a coherent percept, our brain relies on the processes of multisensory integration and sensory recalibration. We here asked how visuo-proprioceptive integration and recalibration are shaped by the presence of more than one potentially relevant visual stimulus, hence paving the way to studying multisensory perception under more naturalistic settings with multiple signals per sensory modality. By manipulating the spatio-temporal correspondence between the hand position and two visual stimuli during a cursor-control task, we contrasted two alternative accounts: that only the temporally more proximal signal enters integration and recalibration similar to a winner-takes-all process, or that the influences of both visual signals superpose. Our results show that integration - and likely also recalibration - are shaped by the superposed contributions of multiple stimuli rather than by only individual ones.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443755" rel="alternate" title="Visuo-proprioceptive integration and recalibration with multiple visual stimuli (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>