<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>BioRxiv preprints in neuroscience posted in the last week with at least 5 tweets</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.431862+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neuroscience/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.07.443011</id><title>Dynamic behavioral and molecular changes induced by chronic stress exposure in mice (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.435995+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas Damien Prevot</name></author><author><name>Dipashree Chatterjee</name></author><author><name>Jaime Knoch</name></author><author><name>Sierra Codeluppi</name></author><author><name>Keith A Misquitta</name></author><author><name>Corey Fee</name></author><author><name>Dwight Newton</name></author><author><name>Hyunjung Oh</name></author><author><name>Etienne Sibille</name></author><author><name>Mounira Banasr</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Depression is a leading cause of disabilities around the world, and the underlying mechanisms involved in its pathophysiology are broad and complex. Exposure to chronic stress is a risk factor for developing depressive-symptoms and contributes to cellular and molecular changes precipitating the emergence of symptoms. In the brain, excitatory neurons, inhibitory interneurons and supporting astroglial cells are all sensitive to chronic stress exposure and are known to be impaired in depression. Using an animal model of chronic stress, we assessed the impact of variable durations of chronic stress on the emergence of behavioral deficits and associated molecular changes in the prefrontal cortex (PFC), brain region highly sensitive to stress and impaired in depression. Mice were exposed to up to 35 days of chronic restraint stress and were assessed weekly on behavioral tests measuring anxiety and anhedonia. PFC Protein and RNA levels of specific markers of excitatory, inhibitory synapses and astroglia were quantified using western blot and qPCR, respectively. Correlation and integrative network analyses were used to investigated the impact of chronic stress on the different compartments. Results showed that chronic stress induces anxiety-like behaviors within 7 days, while anhedonia-like behaviors were observed only after 35 days. At the molecular level, alterations of many markers were observed, in particular with longer exposure to chronic stress. Finally, correlation analyses and integrative network analyses revealed that male and female mice react differently to chronic stress exposure and that some markers seem to be more correlated to behaviors deficits in males than in females. Our study demonstrate that chronic induces a dynamic changes that can be observed at the behavioral and molecular levels, and that male and female mice, while exhibiting similar symptoms, have different underlying pathologies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.02.442349</id><title>Differential contributions of ventral striatum subregions to the motivational and hedonic components of the affective processing of the reward (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.435175+00:00</updated><author><name>Eva R. Pool</name></author><author><name>David Munoz Tord</name></author><author><name>Sylvain Delplanque</name></author><author><name>Yoann Stussi</name></author><author><name>Donato Cereghetti</name></author><author><name>Patrik Vuilleumier</name></author><author><name>David Sander</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ventral striatum is implicated in the affective processing of the reward, which can be divided into a motivational and a hedonic component. Here, we examined whether these two components rely on distinct neural substrates within the ventral striatum in humans. We used a high-resolution fMRI protocol targeting the ventral striatum combined with a Pavlovian-instrumental task and a hedonic reactivity task. Both tasks involved an olfactory reward, thereby allowing us to measure Pavlovian-triggered motivation and sensory pleasure for the same reward within the same participants. Our findings show that different subregions of the ventral striatum are dissociable in their contributions to the motivational and the hedonic component of the affective processing of the reward. Parsing the neural mechanisms and the interplay between Pavlovian incentive processes and hedonic processes might have important implications for understanding compulsive reward-seeking behaviors such as addiction, binge eating, or gambling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.04.442660</id><title>Metamodal Coupling of Vibrotactile and Auditory Speech Processing Systems Through Matched Stimulus Representations (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.434902+00:00</updated><author><name>Srikanth R. Damera</name></author><author><name>Patrick S. Malone</name></author><author><name>Benson W. Stevens</name></author><author><name>Richard Klein</name></author><author><name>Silvio P. Eberhardt</name></author><author><name>Edward T. Auer</name></author><author><name>Lynne E. Bernstein</name></author><author><name>Maximilian Riesenhuber</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It has been postulated the brain is organized by “metamodal”, sensory-independent cortical modules implementing particular computations. Yet, evidence for this theory has been variable. We hypothesized that effective metamodal engagement requires not only an abstract, “cognitive” congruence between cross-modal stimuli but also a congruence between neural representations. To test this hypothesis, we trained participants to recognize vibrotactile versions of auditory words using two encoding schemes. The vocoded approach preserved the dynamics and representational similarities of auditory speech while the token-based approach used an abstract phoneme-based code. Although both groups learned the vibrotactile word recognition task, only in the vocoded group did trained vibrotactile stimuli recruit the auditory speech network and lead to increased coupling between somatosensory and auditory speech areas. In contrast, the token-based encoding appeared to rely on paired-associate learning. Thus, matching neural input representations is a critical factor for assessing and leveraging the metamodal potential of cortical modules.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.02.442289</id><title>Effects of short-term plasticity in early olfactory information processing in Drosophila (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.434439+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuxuan Liu</name></author><author><name>Qianyi Li</name></author><author><name>Chao Tang</name></author><author><name>Shanshan Qin</name></author><author><name>Yuhai Tu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt;, olfactory information received by the olfactory receptor neurons (ORNs) is first processed by an incoherent feed forward neural circuit in the antennal lobe (AL) that consists of ORNs (input), the inhibitory local neurons (LNs), and projection neurons (PNs). This “early” olfactory information process has two important characteristics. First, response of a PN to its cognate ORN is normalized by the overall activity of other ORNs, a phenomenon termed “divisive normalization”. Second, PNs respond strongly to the onset of ORN activities, but they adapt to prolonged or continuously increasing inputs. Despite the importance of these characteristics for learning and memory, their underlying mechanism remains not fully understood. Here, we develop a circuit model for describing the ORN-LN-PN dynamics by including key features of neuron-neuron interactions, in particular short-term plasticity (STP) and presynaptic inhibition (PI). Our model shows that STP is critical in shaping PN’s steady-state response properties. By fitting our model to experimental data quantitatively, we found that strong and balanced short-term facilitation (STF) and short-term depression (STD) in STP is crucial for the observed nonlinear divisive normalization in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt;. By comparing our model with the observed adaptive response to time-varying signals quantitatively, we find that both STP and PI contribute to the highly adaptive response with the latter being the dominant factor for a better fit with experimental data. Our model not only helps reveal the mechanisms underlying two main characteristics of the early olfactory process, it can also be used to predict the PN responses to arbitrary time-dependent signals and to infer microscopic properties of the circuit (such as the strengths of STF and STD) from the measured input-output relation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.02.442327</id><title>Effects of gestational age at birth on perinatal structural brain development in healthy term-born babies (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.433677+00:00</updated><author><name>Oliver Gale-Grant</name></author><author><name>Sunniva Fenn-Moltu</name></author><author><name>Lucas França</name></author><author><name>Ralica Dimitrova</name></author><author><name>Daan Christaens</name></author><author><name>Lucilio Cordero-Grande</name></author><author><name>Andrew Chew</name></author><author><name>Shona Falconer</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Harper</name></author><author><name>Anthony N Price</name></author><author><name>Jana Hutter</name></author><author><name>Emer Hughes</name></author><author><name>Jonathan O’Muircheartaigh</name></author><author><name>Mary Rutherford</name></author><author><name>Serena J Counsell</name></author><author><name>Daniel Rueckert</name></author><author><name>Chiara Nosarti</name></author><author><name>Joseph V Hajnal</name></author><author><name>Grainne McAlonan</name></author><author><name>Tomoki Arichi</name></author><author><name>A David Edwards</name></author><author><name>Dafnis Batalle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Multiple studies have demonstrated less favourable childhood outcomes in infants born in early term (37-38 weeks gestation) compared to those born at full term (40-41 weeks gestation). While this could be due to lower birthweight and greater perinatal morbidity, gestational age at birth may also have a direct effect on the brain and subsequent neurodevelopment in term-born babies. Here we characterise structural brain correlates of gestational age at birth in healthy term-born neonates and their relationship to later neurodevelopmental outcome. We used T2 and diffusion weighted Magnetic Resonance Images acquired in the neonatal period from a cohort (n=454) of healthy babies born at term age (&amp;gt;37 weeks gestation) and scanned between 1 and 41 days after birth. Images were analysed using tensor based morphometry (TBM) and tract based spatial statistics (TBSS). Neurodevelopment was subsequently assessed at age 18 months using the Bayley-III Scales of Infant and Toddler Development (n=281), and the effects of gestational age at birth and related neuroimaging findings on outcome were analysed with linear regression. Infants born earlier had areas of higher relative ventricular volume, and lower relative brain volume in the basal ganglia, cerebellum and brainstem. Earlier birth was also associated with lower fractional anisotropy, higher mean, axial and radial diffusivity in major white matter tracts. Gestational age at birth was positively associated with all Bayley-III subscales at age 18 months. Linear regression models predicting outcome from gestational age at birth were significantly improved by adding neuroimaging features associated with gestational age at birth. This work adds to the growing body of evidence of the impact of early term birth and highlights the importance of considering the effect of gestational age at birth in future neuroimaging studies including term-born babies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.02.442364</id><title>Basal forebrain cholinergic neurons are part of the threat memory engram (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.433384+00:00</updated><author><name>Prithviraj Rajebhosale</name></author><author><name>Mala Ananth</name></author><author><name>Richard Crouse</name></author><author><name>Li Jiang</name></author><author><name>Gretchen López- Hernández</name></author><author><name>Christian Arty</name></author><author><name>Shaohua Wang</name></author><author><name>Alice Jone</name></author><author><name>Chongbo Zhong</name></author><author><name>Niraj S. Desai</name></author><author><name>Yulong Li</name></author><author><name>Marina R. Picciotto</name></author><author><name>Lorna W. Role</name></author><author><name>David A. Talmage</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Although the engagement of cholinergic signaling in threat memory is well established (Knox, 2016a), our finding that specific cholinergic neurons are requisite partners in a threat memory engram is likely to surprise many. Neurons of the basal forebrain nucleus basalis and substantia innominata (NBM/SI&lt;sub&gt;p&lt;/sub&gt;) comprise the major source of cholinergic input to the basolateral amygdala (BLA), whose activation are required for both the acquisition and retrieval of cued threat memory and innate threat response behavior. The retrieval of threat memory by the presentation of the conditioning tone alone elicits acetylcholine (ACh) release in the BLA and the BLA-projecting cholinergic neurons manifest immediate early gene responses and display increased intrinsic excitability for 2-5 hours following the cue-elicited memory response to the conditioned stimulus. Silencing cue-associated engram-enrolled cholinergic neurons prevents the expression of the defensive response and the subset of cholinergic neurons activated by cue is distinct from those engaged by innate threat. Taken together we find that distinct populations of cholinergic neurons are recruited to signal distinct aversive stimuli via the BLA, demonstrating exquisite, functionally refined organization of specific types of memory within the cholinergic basal forebrain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.04.442674</id><title>Functional and ultrastructural analysis of reafferent mechanosensation in larval zebrafish (28 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.433113+00:00</updated><author><name>Iris Odstrcil</name></author><author><name>Mariela D. Petkova</name></author><author><name>Martin Haesemeyer</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Boulanger-Weill</name></author><author><name>Maxim Nikitchenko</name></author><author><name>James A. Gagnon</name></author><author><name>Pablo Oteiza</name></author><author><name>Richard Schalek</name></author><author><name>Adi Peleg</name></author><author><name>Ruben Portugues</name></author><author><name>Jeff Lichtman</name></author><author><name>Florian Engert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;All animals need to differentiate between exafferent stimuli, which are caused by the environment, and reafferent stimuli, which are caused by their own movement. In the case of mechanosensation in aquatic animals, the exafferent inputs are water vibrations in the animal’s proximity, which need to be distinguished from the reafferent inputs arising from fluid drag due to locomotion. Both of these inputs are detected by the lateral line, a collection of mechanosensory organs distributed along the surface of the body.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this study, we characterize in detail how the hair cells, which are the receptor cells of the lateral line, discriminate between such reafferent and exafferent signals in zebrafish larvae. Using dye labeling of the lateral line nerve, we visualize two parallel descending inputs that can influence lateral line sensitivity. We combine functional imaging with ultra-structural EM circuit reconstruction to show that cholinergic signals originating from the hindbrain transmit efference copies that cancel out self-generated reafferent stimulation during locomotion, and that dopaminergic signals from the hypothalamus may have a role in threshold modulation both in response to locomotion and salient stimuli. We further gain direct mechanistic insight into the core components of this circuit by loss-of-function perturbations using targeted ablations and gene knockouts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We propose that this simple circuit is the core implementation of mechanosensory reafferent suppression in these young animals and that it might form the first instantiation of state-dependent modulation found at later stages in development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.01.441648</id><title>A multisensory circuit for gating intense aversive experiences (41 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.432670+00:00</updated><author><name>Arun Asok</name></author><author><name>Félix Leroy</name></author><author><name>Cameron Parro</name></author><author><name>Christopher A. de Solis</name></author><author><name>Lenzie Ford</name></author><author><name>Michelle N. Fitzpatrick</name></author><author><name>Abigail Kalmbach</name></author><author><name>Rachael Neve</name></author><author><name>Joseph B Rayman</name></author><author><name>Eric R. Kandel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ventral hippocampus (vHPC) is critical for both learned and innate fear, but how discrete projections control different types of fear is poorly understood. Here, we report a novel excitatory circuit from a subpopulation of the ventral hippocampus CA1 subfield (vCA1) to the inhibitory peri-paraventricular nucleus of the hypothalamus (pPVN) which then routes to the periaqueductal grey (PAG). We find that vCA1→pPVN projections modulate &lt;italic&gt;both&lt;/italic&gt; learned and innate fear. Fiber photometric calcium recordings reveal that activity in vCA1→pPVN projections increases during the first moments of exposure to an unconditioned threat. Chemogenetic or optogenetic silencing of vCA1→pPVN cell bodies or vCA1→pPVN axon terminals in the pPVN enhances the initial magnitude of both active and passive unconditioned defensive responses, irrespective of the sensory modalities engaged by a particular innate threat. Moreover, silencing produces a dramatic impact on learned fear without affecting milder anxiety-like behaviors. We also show that vCA1→pPVN projections monosynaptically route to the PAG, a key brain region that orchestrates the fear response. Surprisingly, optogenetic silencing of vCA1 terminals in the pPVN titrates the level of c-Fos neural activity in the PAG differently for learned versus innate threats. Together, our results show how a novel vCA1→pPVN circuit modulates neuronal activity in the PAG to regulate both learned and innate fear. These findings have implications for how initial trauma processing may influence maladaptive defensive behaviors across fear and trauma-related disorders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A multisensory gate for high intensity aversive experiences.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>