<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv neuroscience preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.683185+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neuroscience/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.01.446439</id><title>The human language system does not support music processing (101 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.683731+00:00</updated><author><name>Xuanyi Chen</name></author><author><name>Josef Affourtit</name></author><author><name>Rachel Ryskin</name></author><author><name>Tamar I. Regev</name></author><author><name>Samuel Norman-Haignere</name></author><author><name>Olessia Jouravlev</name></author><author><name>Saima Malik-Moraleda</name></author><author><name>Hope Kean</name></author><author><name>Rosemary Varley</name></author><author><name>Evelina Fedorenko</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Language and music are two human-unique capacities whose relationship remains debated. Some argue for overlap in processing mechanisms, especially for structure processing, but others fail to find overlap. Using fMRI, we examined the responses of language brain regions to diverse music stimuli, and also probed the musical abilities of individuals with severe aphasia. Across four experiments, we obtained a clear answer: music does not recruit nor requires the language system. The language regions’ responses to music are generally low and never exceed responses elicited by non-music auditory conditions, like animal sounds. Further, the language regions are not sensitive to music structure: they show low responses to both intact and scrambled music, and to melodies with vs. without structural violations. Finally, individuals with aphasia who cannot judge sentence grammaticality perform well on melody well-formedness judgments. Thus the mechanisms that process structure in language do not appear to support music processing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.01.446439" rel="alternate" title="The human language system does not support music processing (101 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.445775</id><title>Mediobasal hypothalamic FKBP51 acts as a molecular switch linking autophagy to whole-body metabolism (52 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.684558+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander S. Häusl</name></author><author><name>Lea M. Brix</name></author><author><name>Thomas Bajaj</name></author><author><name>Max L. Pöhlmann</name></author><author><name>Kathrin Hafner</name></author><author><name>Meri De Angelis</name></author><author><name>Joachim Nagler</name></author><author><name>Georgia Balsevich</name></author><author><name>Karl-Werner Schramm</name></author><author><name>Patrick Giavalisco</name></author><author><name>Alon Chen</name></author><author><name>Mathias V. Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Nils C. Gassen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mediobasal hypothalamus (MBH) is the central region in the physiological response to metabolic stress. The FK506-binding protein 51 (FKBP51) is a major modulator of the stress response and has recently emerged as a scaffolder regulating metabolic and autophagy pathways. However, the detailed protein-protein interactions linking FKBP51 to autophagy upon metabolic challenges remain elusive. We performed mass spectrometry-based metabolomics of FKBP51 knockout (KO) cells revealing an increased amino acid and polyamine metabolism. We identified FKBP51 as a central nexus for the recruitment of the LKB1/AMPK complex to WIPI4 and TSC2 to WIPI3, thereby regulating the balance between autophagy and mTOR signaling in response to metabolic challenges. Furthermore, we demonstrated that MBH FKBP51 deletion strongly induces obesity, while its overexpression protects against high-fat diet (HFD) induced obesity. Our study provides an important novel regulatory function of MBH FKBP51 within the stress-adapted autophagy response to metabolic challenges.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.445775" rel="alternate" title="Mediobasal hypothalamic FKBP51 acts as a molecular switch linking autophagy to whole-body metabolism (52 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.446423</id><title>Spatial regulation of coordinated excitatory and inhibitory synaptic plasticity at dendritic synapses (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.685583+00:00</updated><author><name>Tiziana Ravasenga</name></author><author><name>Massimo Ruben</name></author><author><name>Alice Polenghi</name></author><author><name>Enrica Maria Petrini</name></author><author><name>Andrea Barberis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The induction of synaptic plasticity at an individual dendritic glutamatergic spine can affect neighboring spines. This local modulation generates dendritic plasticity microdomains believed to expand the neuronal computational capacity. Here, we investigate whether local modulation of plasticity can also occur between glutamatergic synapses and adjacent GABAergic synapses. Using MNI-glutamate and DPNI-GABA double uncaging combined with electrophysiology, live-cell imaging and single-particle tracking, we find that the induction of LTP at an individual glutamatergic spine causes the depression of nearby GABAergic inhibitory synapses (within 3 microns), whereas more distant ones are potentiated. Notably, L-type calcium channels and calpain are required for this plasticity spreading. Overall, our data support a model whereby input-specific glutamatergic postsynaptic potentiation induces a spatially-regulated rearrangement of inhibitory synaptic strength in the surrounding area through short-range heterosynaptic interactions. Such local coordination of excitatory and inhibitory synaptic plasticity is expected to profoundly influence dendritic information processing and integration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.446423" rel="alternate" title="Spatial regulation of coordinated excitatory and inhibitory synaptic plasticity at dendritic synapses (24 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.02.446653</id><title>Single-Cell Transcriptional Profiling of the Adult Corticospinal Tract Reveals Forelimb and Hindlimb Molecular Specialization (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.685967+00:00</updated><author><name>Noa Golan</name></author><author><name>Sierra Kauer</name></author><author><name>Daniel B Ehrlich</name></author><author><name>Neal Ravindra</name></author><author><name>David van Dijk</name></author><author><name>William BJ Cafferty</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The corticospinal tract (CST) is refractory to repair after CNS trauma, resulting in chronic debilitating functional motor deficits after spinal cord injury. While novel pro-axon growth activators have stimulated plasticity and regeneration of corticospinal neurons (CSNs) after injury, robust functional recovery remains elusive. These repair strategies are sub-optimal in part due to underexplored molecular heterogeneity within the developing and adult CST. In this study, we combine retrograde CST tracing with single-cell RNA sequencing to build a comprehensive atlas of CSN subtypes. By comparing CSNs to non-spinally projecting neurons in layer Vb, we identify pan-CSN markers including &lt;italic&gt;Wnt7b&lt;/italic&gt;. By leveraging retrograde tracing, we are able to compare forelimb and hindlimb projecting CSNs, identifying subtype-specific markers, including &lt;italic&gt;Cacng7&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Slc16a2&lt;/italic&gt; respectively. These markers are expressed in embryonic and neonatal CSNs and can be used to study early postnatal patterning of the CST. Our results provide molecular insight into the differences between anatomically distinct CSN subtypes and provide a resource for future screening and exploitation of these subtypes to repair the damaged CST after injury and disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.02.446653" rel="alternate" title="Single-Cell Transcriptional Profiling of the Adult Corticospinal Tract Reveals Forelimb and Hindlimb Molecular Specialization (13 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.03.446869</id><title>Stimulus features that elicit activity in object-vector cells (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.686364+00:00</updated><author><name>Sebastian O. Andersson</name></author><author><name>Edvard I. Moser</name></author><author><name>May-Britt Moser</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Object-vector (OV) cells are cells in the medial entorhinal cortex (MEC) that track an animal’s distance and direction to objects in the environment. Their firing fields are defined by vectorial relationships to free-standing 3-dimensional (3D) objects of a variety of identities and shapes. However, the natural world contains a panorama of objects, ranging from discrete 3D items to flat two-dimensional (2D) surfaces, and it remains unclear what are the most fundamental features of objects that drive vectorial responses. Here we address this question by systematically changing features of experimental objects. Using an algorithm that robustly identifies OV firing fields, we show that the cells respond to a variety of 2D surfaces, with visual contrast as the most basic visual feature to elicit neural responses. The findings suggest that OV cells use plain visual features as vectorial anchoring points, allowing vector-guided navigation to proceed in environments with few free-standing landmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.03.446869" rel="alternate" title="Stimulus features that elicit activity in object-vector cells (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.446375</id><title>Co-expression patterns of microglia markers Iba1, TMEM119 and P2RY12 in Alzheimer’s disease (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.686679+00:00</updated><author><name>Boyd Kenkhuis</name></author><author><name>Antonios Somarakis</name></author><author><name>Lynn RT Kleindouwel</name></author><author><name>Willeke MC van Roon-Mom</name></author><author><name>Thomas Höllt</name></author><author><name>Louise van der Weerd</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microglia have been identified as key players in Alzheimer’s disease pathogenesis, and other neurodegenerative diseases. Iba1, and more specifically TMEM119 and P2RY12 are gaining ground as presumedly more specific microglia markers, but comprehensive characterization of the expression of these three markers individually as well as combined is currently missing. Here we used a multispectral immunofluorescence dataset, in which over seventy thousand microglia from both aged controls and Alzheimer patients have been analysed for expression of Iba1, TMEM119 and P2RY12 on a single-cell level. For all markers, we studied the overlap and differences in expression patterns and the effect of proximity to β-amyloid plaques. We found no difference in absolute microglia numbers between control and Alzheimer subjects, but the prevalence of specific combinations of markers (phenotypes) differed greatly. In controls, the majority of microglia expressed all three markers. In Alzheimer patients, a significant loss of TMEM119&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;-phenotypes was observed, independent of the presence of β-amyloid plaques in its proximity. Contrary, phenotypes showing loss of P2RY12, but consistent Iba1 expression were increasingly prevalent around β-amyloid plaques. No morphological features were conclusively associated with loss or gain of any of the markers or any of the identified phenotypes. All in all, none of the three markers were expressed by all microglia, nor can be wholly regarded as a pan- or homeostatic marker, and preferential phenotypes were observed depending on the surrounding pathological or homeostatic environment. This work could help select and interpret microglia markers in previous and future studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.446375" rel="alternate" title="Co-expression patterns of microglia markers Iba1, TMEM119 and P2RY12 in Alzheimer’s disease (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.30.446334</id><title>U-RISC: An Ultra-high Resolution EM Dataset Challenging Existing Deep Learning Algorithms (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.686997+00:00</updated><author><name>Ruohua Shi</name></author><author><name>Wenyao Wang</name></author><author><name>Zhixuan Li</name></author><author><name>Liuyuan He</name></author><author><name>Kaiwen Sheng</name></author><author><name>Lei Ma</name></author><author><name>Kai Du</name></author><author><name>Tingting Jiang</name></author><author><name>Tiejun Huang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Connectomics is a developing field aiming at reconstructing the connection of the neural system at nanometer scale. Computer vision technology, especially deep learning methods used in image processing, has promoted connectomic data analysis to a new era. However, the performance of the state-of-the-art methods still falls behind the demand of scientific research. Inspired by the success of ImageNet, we present the U-RISC, an annotated Ultra-high Resolution Image Segmentation dataset for Cell membrane, which is the largest cell membrane annotated Electron Microscopy (EM) dataset with a resolution of 2.18nm/pixel. Multiple iterative annotations ensured the quality of the dataset. Through an open competition, we reveal that the performance of current deep learning methods still has a considerable gap with human-level, different from ISBI 2012, on which the performance of deep learning is close to human. To explore the causes of this discrepancy, we analyze the neural networks with a visualization method, attribution analysis. We find that in U-RISC, it requires a larger area around a pixel to predict whether the pixel belongs to the cell membrane or not. Finally, we integrate currently available methods to provide a new benchmark (0.67, 10% higher than the leader of competition, 0.61) for cell membrane segmentation on U-RISC and propose some suggestions in developing deep learning algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.30.446334" rel="alternate" title="U-RISC: An Ultra-high Resolution EM Dataset Challenging Existing Deep Learning Algorithms (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.30.445761</id><title>Pre-therapeutic Microglia Activation and Sex Determine Therapy Effects of Chronic Immunomodulation (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.687441+00:00</updated><author><name>Gloria Biechele</name></author><author><name>Tanja Blume</name></author><author><name>Maximilian Deussing</name></author><author><name>Benedikt Zott</name></author><author><name>Yuan Shi</name></author><author><name>Xianyuan Xiang</name></author><author><name>Nicolai Franzmeier</name></author><author><name>Gernot Kleinberger</name></author><author><name>Finn Peters</name></author><author><name>Katharina Ochs</name></author><author><name>Carola Focke</name></author><author><name>Christian Sacher</name></author><author><name>Karin Wind</name></author><author><name>Claudio Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Simon Lindner</name></author><author><name>Franz-Josef Gildehaus</name></author><author><name>Florian Eckenweber</name></author><author><name>Leonie Beyer</name></author><author><name>Barbara von Ungern-Sternberg</name></author><author><name>Peter Bartenstein</name></author><author><name>Karlheinz Baumann</name></author><author><name>Mario M. Dorostkar</name></author><author><name>Axel Rominger</name></author><author><name>Paul Cumming</name></author><author><name>Michael Willem</name></author><author><name>Helmuth Adelsberger</name></author><author><name>Jochen Herms</name></author><author><name>Matthias Brendel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Modulation of the innate immune system is emerging as a promising therapeutic strategy against Alzheimer’s disease (AD). However, determinants of a beneficial therapeutic effect are ill-understood. Thus, we investigated the potential of 18 kDa translocator protein positron-emission-tomography (TSPO-PET) for assessment of microglial activation in mouse brain before and during chronic immunomodulation. Serial TSPO-PET was performed during five months of chronic microglia modulation by stimulation of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor (PPAR)-γ with pioglitazone in two different mouse models of AD (PS2APP, &lt;italic&gt;App&lt;sup&gt;NL-G-F&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt;). Using mixed statistical models on longitudinal TSPO-PET data, we tested for effects of therapy and sex on treatment response. We tested correlations of baseline with longitudinal measures of TSPO-PET, and correlations between PET results with spatial learning performance and β-amyloid accumulation of individual mice. Immunohistochemistry was used to determine the molecular source of the TSPO-PET signal. Pioglitazone-treated female PS2APP and &lt;italic&gt;App&lt;sup&gt;NL-G-F&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice showed attenuation of the longitudinal increases in TSPO-PET signal when compared to vehicle controls, whereas treated male &lt;italic&gt;App&lt;sup&gt;NL-G-F&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice showed the opposite effect. Baseline TSPO-PET strongly predicted changes in microglial activation in treated mice (R=−0.874, p&amp;lt;0.0001) but not in vehicle controls (R=−0.356, p=0.081). Reduced TSPO-PET signal upon treatment was associated with better spatial learning and higher fibrillar β-amyloid accumulation. Immunohistochemistry confirmed activated microglia to be the source of the TSPO-PET signal (R=0.952, p&amp;lt;0.0001). TSPO-PET represents a sensitive biomarker for monitoring of immunomodulation and closely reflects activated microglia. Pre-therapeutic assessment of baseline microglial activation and sex are strong predictors of individual immunomodulation effects and could serve for responder stratification.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.30.445761" rel="alternate" title="Pre-therapeutic Microglia Activation and Sex Determine Therapy Effects of Chronic Immunomodulation (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.01.446490</id><title>Plasticity in intrinsic excitability of hypothalamic magnocellular neurosecretory neurons in late-pregnant and lactating rats (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.688490+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael R. Perkinson</name></author><author><name>Rachael A. Augustine</name></author><author><name>Gregory T. Bouwer</name></author><author><name>Emily F. Brown</name></author><author><name>Isaiah Cheong</name></author><author><name>Alexander J. Seymour</name></author><author><name>Martin Fronius</name></author><author><name>Colin H. Brown</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Oxytocin and vasopressin secretion from the posterior pituitary gland are required for normal pregnancy and lactation. Oxytocin secretion is relatively low and constant under basal conditions but becomes pulsatile during birth and lactation to stimulate episodic contraction of the uterus for delivery of the fetus and milk ejection during suckling. Vasopressin secretion is maintained in pregnancy and lactation despite reduced osmolality (the principal stimulus for vasopressin secretion) to increase water retention to cope with the cardiovascular demands of pregnancy and lactation. Oxytocin and vasopressin secretion are determined by the action potential (spike) firing of magnocellular neurosecretory neurons of the hypothalamic supraoptic and paraventricular nucleus. In addition to synaptic input activity, spike firing depends on intrinsic excitability conferred by the suite of channels expressed by the neurons. Therefore, we analysed oxytocin and vasopressin neuron activity in anaesthetised non-pregnant, late-pregnant and lactating rats to test the hypothesis that intrinsic excitability of oxytocin and vasopressin neurons is increased in late pregnancy and lactation to promote oxytocin and vasopressin secretion required for successful pregnancy and lactation. Hazard analysis of spike firing revealed a higher incidence of post-spike hyperexcitability immediately following each spike in oxytocin neurons, but not in vasopressin neurons, in late pregnancy and lactation, which is expected to facilitate high frequency firing during bursts. Despite lower osmolality in late-pregnant and lactating rats, vasopressin neuron activity was not different between non-pregnant, late-pregnant and lactating rats, and blockade of osmosensitive ΔN-TRPV1 channels inhibited vasopressin neurons to a similar extent in non-pregnant, late-pregnant and lactating rats. Furthermore, supraoptic nucleus ΔN-TRPV1 mRNA expression was not different between non-pregnant and late-pregnant rats, suggesting that enhanced activity of ΔN-TRPV1 channels might maintain vasopressin neuron activity to increase water retention during pregnancy and lactation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.01.446490" rel="alternate" title="Plasticity in intrinsic excitability of hypothalamic magnocellular neurosecretory neurons in late-pregnant and lactating rats (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>