<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv neuroscience preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.738474+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neuroscience/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.04.451074</id><title>Towards a Neurometric-based Construct Validity of Trust (73 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.739186+00:00</updated><author><name>Pin-Hao A. Chen</name></author><author><name>Dominic Fareri</name></author><author><name>Berna Güroğlu</name></author><author><name>Mauricio R. Delgado</name></author><author><name>Luke J. Chang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Trust is a nebulous construct central to successful cooperative exchanges and interpersonal relationships. In this study, we introduce a new approach to establishing construct validity of trust using “neurometrics”. We develop a whole-brain multivariate pattern capable of classifying whether new participants will trust a relationship partner in the context of a cooperative interpersonal investment game (n=40) with 90% accuracy and find that it also generalizes to a variant of the same task collected in a different country with 82% accuracy (n=17). Moreover, we establish the convergent and discriminant validity by testing the pattern on eleven separate datasets (n=496) and find that trust is reliably related to beliefs of safety, inversely related to negative affect, but unrelated to reward, cognitive control, social perception, and self-referential processing. Together these results provide support for the notion that the psychological experience of trust contains elements of beliefs of reciprocation and fear of betrayal aversion. Contrary to our predictions, we found no evidence that trust is related to anticipated reward. This work demonstrates how “neurometrics” can be used to characterize the psychological processes associated with brain-based multivariate representations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.04.451074" rel="alternate" title="Towards a Neurometric-based Construct Validity of Trust (73 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.05.451142</id><title>Synaptic Encoding of Vestibular Sensation Regulates Movement Timing and Coordination (71 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.740376+00:00</updated><author><name>Kyla R. Hamling</name></author><author><name>Katherine Harmon</name></author><author><name>Marie Greaney</name></author><author><name>Zoë Dobler</name></author><author><name>Yukiko Kimura</name></author><author><name>Shin-ichi Higashijima</name></author><author><name>David Schoppik</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Vertebrate vestibular circuits use sensory signals derived from the inner ear to guide both corrective and volitional movements. A major challenge in the neuroscience of balance is to link the synaptic and cellular substrates that encode body tilts to specific behaviors that stabilize posture and enable efficient locomotion. Here we address this problem by measuring the development, synaptic architecture, and behavioral contributions of vestibulospinal neurons in the larval zebrafish. First, we find that vestibulospinal neurons are born and are functionally mature before larvae swim freely, allowing them to act as a substrate for postural regulation. Next, we map the synaptic inputs to vestibulospinal neurons that allow them to encode posture. Further, we find that this synaptic architecture allows them to respond to linear acceleration in a directionally-tuned and utricle-dependent manner; they are thus poised to guide corrective movements. After loss of vestibulospinal neurons, larvae adopted eccentric postures with disrupted movement timing and weaker corrective kinematics. We used a generative model of swimming to demonstrate that together these disruptions can account for the increased postural variability. Finally, we observed that lesions disrupt vestibular-dependent coordination between the fins and trunk during vertical swimming, linking vestibulospinal neurons to navigation. We conclude that vestibulospinal neurons turn synaptic representations of body tilt into defined corrective behaviors and coordinated movements. As the need for stable locomotion is common and the vestibulospinal circuit is highly conserved our findings reveal general mechanisms for neuronal control of balance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.05.451142" rel="alternate" title="Synaptic Encoding of Vestibular Sensation Regulates Movement Timing and Coordination (71 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.08.451624</id><title>Cerebellar Control of a Unitary Head Direction Sense (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.741631+00:00</updated><author><name>Mehdi Fallahnezhad</name></author><author><name>Julia Le Mero</name></author><author><name>Xhensjana Zenelaj</name></author><author><name>Jean Vincent</name></author><author><name>Christelle Rochefort</name></author><author><name>Laure Rondi-Reig</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Head direction (HD) cells, key neuronal elements in the mammalian's navigation system, are hypothesized to act as a continuous attractor network, in which temporal coordination between cell members is maintained under different brain states or external sensory conditions, resembling a unitary neural representation of direction. Whether and how multiple identified HD signals in anatomically separate HD cell structures are part of a single and unique attractor network is currently unknown. By manipulating the cerebellum, we identified pairs of thalamic and retrosplenial HD cells that lose their temporal coordination in the absence of external sensory drive, while the neuronal coordination within each of these brain regions remained intact. Further, we show that distinct cerebellar mechanisms are involved in the stability of direction representation depending on external sensory conditions. These results put forward a new role for the cerebellum in mediating stable and coordinated HD neuronal activity toward a unitary thalamocortical representation of direction.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.08.451624" rel="alternate" title="Cerebellar Control of a Unitary Head Direction Sense (27 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.451305</id><title>The EEG spectral fingerprints of meditation and mind wandering differ between experienced meditators and novices (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.743132+00:00</updated><author><name>Julio Rodriguez-Larios</name></author><author><name>Eduardo A. Bracho Montes de Oca</name></author><author><name>Kaat Alaerts</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Previous literature suggests that meditation training is associated with changes in participants’ experience during meditation practice. In this study, we assess whether putative differences in the experience of meditation between meditators and non-meditators are reflected in EEG spectral modulations. For this purpose, we recorded electroencephalography (EEG) during rest and two breath focus meditations (with and without experience sampling) in a group of 29 adult participants with more than 3 years of meditation experience and a control group of 29 participants without any meditation experience. Experience sampling in one of the meditation conditions allowed us to disentangle periods of breath focus from mind wandering (i.e. moments of distraction driven by task-irrelevant thoughts) during meditation practice. Overall, meditators reported a greater level of focus and reduced mind wandering during meditation practice than controls. In line with these reports, EEG spectral modulations associated to meditation and mind wandering also differed significantly between meditators and controls. While meditators (but not controls) showed a significant decrease in individual alpha frequency and amplitude and a steeper 1/f slope during meditation relative to rest, controls (but not meditators) showed a relative increase in individual alpha amplitude during mind wandering relative to breath focus periods. Together, our results show that the experience of meditation changes with training and that this is reflected in oscillatory and non-oscillatory components of brain activity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.451305" rel="alternate" title="The EEG spectral fingerprints of meditation and mind wandering differ between experienced meditators and novices (17 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.07.451278</id><title>Ultrastructural readout of in vivo synaptic activity for functional connectomics (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.743793+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna Simon</name></author><author><name>Arnd Roth</name></author><author><name>Arlo Sheridan</name></author><author><name>Mehmet Fişek</name></author><author><name>Vincenzo Marra</name></author><author><name>Claudia Racca</name></author><author><name>Jan Funke</name></author><author><name>Kevin Staras</name></author><author><name>Michael Häusser</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Large-volume ultrastructural mapping approaches yield detailed circuit wiring diagrams but lack an integrated synaptic activity readout which is essential for functional interpretation of the connectome. Here we resolve this limitation by combining functional synaptic labelling &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; with focused ion-beam scanning electron microscopy (FIBSEM) and machine learning-based segmentation. Our approach generates high-resolution near-isotropic three-dimensional readouts of activated vesicle pools across large populations of individual synapses in a volume of tissue, opening the way for detailed functional connectomics studies. We apply this method to measure presynaptic activity in an ultrastructural context in synapses activated by sensory input in primary visual cortex in awake head-fixed mice, showing that the numbers of recycling and non-recycling vesicles approximate to a lognormal distribution across a large number of synapses. We also demonstrate that neighbouring boutons of the same axon, which share the same spiking activity, can differ greatly in their presynaptic release probability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.07.451278" rel="alternate" title="Ultrastructural readout of in vivo synaptic activity for functional connectomics (15 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.451256</id><title>Parafoveal words can modulate sentence meaning: Electrophysiological evidence from an RSVP-with-flanker task (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.744546+00:00</updated><author><name>Nan Li</name></author><author><name>Olaf Dimigen</name></author><author><name>Werner Sommer</name></author><author><name>Suiping Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During natural reading, readers also take up some visual information from not-yet-fixated words to the right of the current fixation and it is well-established that this parafoveal preview facilitates the subsequent foveal processing of the word. However, the extraction and integration of word meaning from the parafoveal word and its possible influence on the semantic sentence context are controversial. In the current study, we recorded event-related potentials (ERPs) in the RSVP-with-flankers paradigm to test whether and how updates of sentential meaning that are based only on parafoveal information influence the subsequent foveal processing. Using Chinese sentences, the sentence congruency of parafoveal and foveal target words were orthogonally manipulated. In contrast to previous research, we also controlled for potentially confounding effects of parafoveal-to-foveal repetition priming (identity preview effects) on the N400. Crucially, we found that the classic effect of foveal congruency on the N400 component only appeared when the word in preview had been congruent with sentence meaning; in contrast, there was no N400 when the preview word had been incongruent. These results indicate that sentence meaning rapidly adapts to parafoveal preview, which already changes the context for the then fixated word. We also show that a correct parafoveal preview generally attenuates the N400 once a word is fixated, regardless of congruency. Taken together, our findings underline the highly generative and adaptive framework of language comprehension.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.451256" rel="alternate" title="Parafoveal words can modulate sentence meaning: Electrophysiological evidence from an RSVP-with-flanker task (12 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.451245</id><title>Automatic decomposition of electrophysiological data into distinct non-sinusoidal oscillatory modes (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.744965+00:00</updated><author><name>Marco S. Fabus</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Quinn</name></author><author><name>Catherine E. Warnaby</name></author><author><name>Mark W. Woolrich</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neurophysiological signals are often noisy, non-sinusoidal, and consist of transient bursts. Extraction and analysis of oscillatory features (such as waveform shape and cross-frequency coupling) in such datasets remains difficult. This limits our understanding of brain dynamics and its functional importance. Here, we develop Iterated Masking Empirical Mode Decomposition (itEMD), a method designed to decompose noisy and transient single channel data into relevant oscillatory modes in a flexible, fully data-driven way without the need for manual tuning. Based on Empirical Mode Decomposition (EMD), this technique can extract single-cycle waveform dynamics through phase-aligned instantaneous frequency. We test our method by extensive simulations across different noise, sparsity, and non-sinusoidality conditions. We find itEMD significantly improves the separation of data into distinct non-sinusoidal oscillatory components and robustly reproduces waveform shape across a wide range of relevant parameters. We further validate the technique on multi-modal, multi-species electrophysiological data. Our itEMD extracts known rat hippocampal theta waveform asymmetry and identifies subject-specific human occipital alpha without any prior assumptions about the frequencies contained in the signal. Notably, it does so with significantly less mode mixing compared to existing EMD-based methods. By reducing mode mixing and simplifying interpretation of EMD results, itEMD will enable new analyses into functional roles of neural signals in behaviour and disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;New &amp;amp; Noteworthy&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We introduce a novel, data-driven method to identify oscillations in neural recordings. This approach is based on Empirical Mode Decomposition and reduces mixing of components, one of its main problems. The technique is validated and compared with existing methods using simulations and real data. We show our method better extracts oscillations and their properties in highly noisy and non-sinusoidal datasets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Running Head&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Decomposition of data into non-sinusoidal oscillatory modes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.451245" rel="alternate" title="Automatic decomposition of electrophysiological data into distinct non-sinusoidal oscillatory modes (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.05.451170</id><title>All-trans retinoic acid induces synaptopodin-dependent metaplasticity in mouse dentate granule cells (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.745810+00:00</updated><author><name>Maximilian Lenz</name></author><author><name>Amelie Eichler</name></author><author><name>Pia Kruse</name></author><author><name>Julia Muellerleile</name></author><author><name>Thomas Deller</name></author><author><name>Peter Jedlicka</name></author><author><name>Andreas Vlachos</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The vitamin A derivative all-trans retinoic acid (atRA) is a key mediator of synaptic plasticity. Depending on the brain region studied, distinct effects of atRA on excitatory and inhibitory neurotransmission have been reported. However, it remains unclear how atRA mediates brain region-specific effects on synaptic transmission and plasticity. Here, we used intraperitoneal injections of atRA (10 mg/kg) in adult male C57BL/6J mice to study the effects of atRA on excitatory and inhibitory neurotransmission in the mouse fascia dentata. In contrast to what has been reported in other brain regions, no major changes in synaptic transmission were observed in the ventral and dorsal hippocampus 6 hours after atRA administration. Likewise, no evidence for changes in the intrinsic properties of hippocampal dentate granule cells was obtained in the atRA-treated group. Moreover, hippocampal transcriptome analysis revealed no essential changes upon atRA treatment. In light of these findings, we tested for the metaplastic effects of atRA, i.e., for its ability to modulate synaptic plasticity expression in the absence of major changes in baseline synaptic transmission. Indeed, &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; long-term potentiation (LTP) experiments demonstrated that systemic atRA treatment improves the ability of dentate granule cells to express LTP. The plasticity-promoting effects of atRA were not observed in synaptopodin-deficient mice, thus extending our previous results on the relevance of synaptopodin in atRA-mediated synaptic strengthening in the mouse prefrontal cortex. Taken together, our data show that atRA mediates synaptopodin-dependent metaplasticity in mouse dentate granule cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.05.451170" rel="alternate" title="All-trans retinoic acid induces synaptopodin-dependent metaplasticity in mouse dentate granule cells (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.09.451725</id><title>A novel imaging ligand as a biomarker for mutant huntingtin-lowering in Huntington's disease (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.746298+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniele Bertoglio</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Bard</name></author><author><name>Manuela Hessmann</name></author><author><name>Longbin Liu</name></author><author><name>Annette Gaertner</name></author><author><name>Stef De Lombaerde</name></author><author><name>Britta Huscher</name></author><author><name>Franziska Zajicek</name></author><author><name>Alan Miranda</name></author><author><name>Finn Peters</name></author><author><name>Frank Herrmann</name></author><author><name>Sabine Schaertl</name></author><author><name>Tamara Vasilkovska</name></author><author><name>Christopher J Brown</name></author><author><name>Peter D Johnson</name></author><author><name>Michael E Prime</name></author><author><name>Matthew R Mills</name></author><author><name>Annemie Van der Linden</name></author><author><name>Ladislav Mrzljak</name></author><author><name>Vinod Khetarpal</name></author><author><name>Yuchuan Wang</name></author><author><name>Deanna M Marchionini</name></author><author><name>Mette Skinbjerg</name></author><author><name>Jeroen Verhaeghe</name></author><author><name>Celia Dominguez</name></author><author><name>Steven Staelens</name></author><author><name>Ignacio Munoz-Sanjuan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Huntington's disease (HD) is a dominantly inherited neurodegenerative disorder caused by a CAG trinucleotide expansion in the huntingtin (HTT) gene that encodes the pathologic mutant HTT (mHTT) protein with an expanded polyglutamine (PolyQ) tract. While several therapeutic programs targeting mHTT expression have advanced to clinical evaluation, no method is currently available to visualize mHTT levels in the living brain. Here we demonstrate the development of a positron emission tomography (PET) imaging radioligand with high affinity and selectivity for mHTT aggregates. This small molecule radiolabeled with 11C ([11C]CHDI-180R) enables non-invasive monitoring of mHTT pathology in the brain and can track region- and time-dependent suppression of mHTT in response to therapeutic interventions targeting mHTT expression. We further show that therapeutic agents that lower mHTT in the striatum have a functional restorative effect that can be measured by preservation of striatal imaging markers, enabling a translational path to assess the functional effect of mHTT lowering.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.09.451725" rel="alternate" title="A novel imaging ligand as a biomarker for mutant huntingtin-lowering in Huntington's disease (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.07.451374</id><title>Single-cell profiling of the human primary motor cortex in ALS and FTLD (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.746971+00:00</updated><author><name>Sergio Sebastian Pineda</name></author><author><name>Hyeseung Lee</name></author><author><name>Brent Eugene Fitzwalter</name></author><author><name>Shahin Mohammadi</name></author><author><name>Luc J Pregent</name></author><author><name>Mahammad E Gardashli</name></author><author><name>Julio Mantero</name></author><author><name>Erica Engelberg-Cook</name></author><author><name>Mariely DeJesus-Hernandez</name></author><author><name>Marka van Blitterswijk</name></author><author><name>Cyril Pottier</name></author><author><name>Rosa Rademakers</name></author><author><name>Bjorn Oskarsson</name></author><author><name>Jaimin S Shah</name></author><author><name>Ronald C Petersen</name></author><author><name>Neill R Graff-Radford</name></author><author><name>Bradley F Boeve</name></author><author><name>David S Knopman</name></author><author><name>Keith A Josephs</name></author><author><name>Michael DeTure</name></author><author><name>Melissa E Murray</name></author><author><name>Dennis W Dickson</name></author><author><name>Myriam Heiman</name></author><author><name>Veronique V Belzil</name></author><author><name>Manolis Kellis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) and frontotemporal lobar degeneration (FTLD) are two devastating and fatal neurodegenerative conditions. While distinct, they share many clinical, genetic, and pathological characteristics, and both show selective vulnerability of layer 5b extratelencephalic-projecting cortical populations, including Betz cells in ALS and von Economo neurons (VENs) in FTLD. Here, we report the first high resolution single-cell atlas of the human primary motor cortex (MCX) and its transcriptional alterations in ALS and FTLD across ~380,000 nuclei from 64 individuals, including 17 control samples and 47 sporadic and &lt;italic&gt;C9orf72&lt;/italic&gt;-associated ALS and FTLD patient samples. We identify 46 transcriptionally distinct cellular subtypes including two Betz-cell subtypes, and we observe a previously unappreciated molecular similarity between Betz cells and VENs of the prefrontal cortex (PFC) and frontal insula. Many of the dysregulated genes and pathways are shared across excitatory neurons, including stress response, ribosome function, oxidative phosphorylation, synaptic vesicle cycle, endoplasmic reticulum protein processing, and autophagy. Betz cells and &lt;italic&gt;SCN4B&lt;/italic&gt;+ long-range projecting L3/L5 cells are the most transcriptionally affected in both ALS and FTLD. Lastly, we find that the VEN/Betz cell-enriched transcription factor, POU3F1, has altered subcellular localization, co-localizes with TDP-43 aggregates, and may represent a cell type-specific vulnerability factor in the Betz cells of ALS and FTLD patient tissues.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.07.451374" rel="alternate" title="Single-cell profiling of the human primary motor cortex in ALS and FTLD (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.451330</id><title>Global Effects of a PD Risk-SNP at the Alpha-Synuclein Locus (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.747557+00:00</updated><author><name>Jordan Prahl</name></author><author><name>Steven E. Pierce</name></author><author><name>Edwin JC van der Schans</name></author><author><name>Gerhard A. Coetzee</name></author><author><name>Trevor Tyson</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the most significant Parkinson’s disease (PD) risk variants, rs356182, is located at the PD-associated locus near the alpha-synuclein encoding gene, &lt;italic&gt;SNCA&lt;/italic&gt;. &lt;italic&gt;SNCA&lt;/italic&gt;-proximal variants, including rs356182, are thought to function in PD via allele-specific regulatory effects on SNCA expression. However, this interpretation discounts the complex activity of genetic enhancers and possible nonconical effects of alpha-synuclein. Here we investigate a novel risk mechanism for rs356182. We use CRISPR-Cas9 in LUHMES cells, a model for dopaminergic neurons, to generate precise hemizygous lesions at rs356182. The PD-protective (A/-), PD-risk (G/-), and WT (A/G) strains are differentiated into dopaminergic neurons then compared transcriptionally and morphologically. We observe effects not typically ascribed to &lt;italic&gt;SNCA&lt;/italic&gt;; hundreds of differentially expressed genes associated with neuronal differentiation and axonogenesis. Together, the data implicate a risk mechanism for rs356182 in which the risk-allele (G) is associated with abnormal neuronal differentiation. We speculate the disease-relevant effect originates as a diminished population of DA neurons leading to the predisposition for PD later in life.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.451330" rel="alternate" title="Global Effects of a PD Risk-SNP at the Alpha-Synuclein Locus (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>