<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv neuroscience preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.469746+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neuroscience/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443151</id><title>Evaluating brain parcellations using the distance controlled boundary coefficient (200 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.474214+00:00</updated><author><name>Da Zhi</name></author><author><name>Maedbh King</name></author><author><name>Jörn Diedrichsen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;An important goal of human brain mapping is to define a set of distinct regions that can be linked to unique functions. Numerous brain parcellations have been proposed, using cytoarchitectonic data, structural or functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI). The intrinsic smoothness of the brain data, however, poses a problem for current methods seeking to compare different parcellations to each other. For example, criteria that simply compare within-parcel to between-parcel similarity provide even random parcellations with a high value. Furthermore, the evaluation is biased by the spatial scale of the parcellation. To address this problem, we propose the Distance Controlled Boundary Coefficient (DCBC), an unbiased criterion to evaluate discrete parcellations. We employ this new criterion to evaluate whether existing parcellations of the human neocortex can predict functional boundaries on a rich multi-domain task battery. We find that common anatomical parcellations do not perform better than chance, suggesting that task-based functional boundaries do not align well with sulcal landmarks. Parcellations based on resting-state fMRI data perform well; in some cases, as well as a parcellation defined on the evaluation data itself. Finally, multi-modal parcellations that combine functional and anatomical criteria perform substantially worse than those based on functional data alone, indicating that functionally homogeneous regions often span major anatomical landmarks. Overall, the DCBC advances the field of functional brain mapping by providing an unbiased metric that compares the predictive ability of different brain parcellations to define functionally and anatomically homogeneous brain regions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443151" rel="alternate" title="Evaluating brain parcellations using the distance controlled boundary coefficient (200 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443308</id><title>Minimal functional alignment of ventromedial prefrontal cortex intracranial EEG signals during naturalistic viewing (40 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.474525+00:00</updated><author><name>Tiankang Xie</name></author><author><name>Jin Hyun Cheong</name></author><author><name>Jeremy R. Manning</name></author><author><name>Amanda M. Brandt</name></author><author><name>Joshua P. Aronson</name></author><author><name>Barbara C. Jobst</name></author><author><name>Krzysztof A. Bujarski</name></author><author><name>Luke J. Chang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ventromedial prefrontal cortex (vmPFC) has been thought to play an important role in processing endogenous information such as generating subjective affective meaning. Unlike sensory cortex, which processes exogenous information about the external world similarly across individuals, prior work has posited that vmPFC activity may be idiosyncratic to each individual, even when exposed to the same external stimulus. In this study, we recorded local field potentials (LFPs) from intracranial stereo electrodes implanted in patients with intractable epilepsy while they watched an emotionally engaging television show episode and evaluated temporal synchronization of these signals across participants in auditory cortex and vmPFC. Overall, we observed markedly lower intersubject synchronization of signals recorded from electrodes implanted in vmPFC compared to auditory cortex. A subset of patients, however, appeared to share similar vmPFC states during the more emotionally salient scenes. This work suggests that the vmPFC is involved in processing affective responses to ongoing experience in a state-like manner, but the specific states and temporal sequences are idiosyncratic to each individual, even when viewing the same television episode.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443308" rel="alternate" title="Minimal functional alignment of ventromedial prefrontal cortex intracranial EEG signals during naturalistic viewing (40 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443836</id><title>cAMP controls a trafficking mechanism that directs the neuron specificity and subcellular placement of electrical synapses (38 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.474791+00:00</updated><author><name>Sierra Palumbos</name></author><author><name>Rachel Skelton</name></author><author><name>Rebecca McWhirter</name></author><author><name>Amanda Mitchell</name></author><author><name>Isaiah Swann</name></author><author><name>Sydney Heifner</name></author><author><name>Steve Von Stetina</name></author><author><name>David M Miller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Electrical synapses are established between specific neurons and within distinct subcellular compartments, but the mechanisms that direct gap junction assembly in the nervous system are largely unknown. Here we show that a transcriptional program tunes cAMP signaling to direct the neuron-specific assembly and placement of electrical synapses in the &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; motor circuit. For these studies, we use live cell imaging to visualize electrical synapses in vivo and a novel optogenetic assay to confirm that they are functional. In VA motor neurons, the UNC-4 transcription factor blocks expression of cAMP antagonists that promote gap junction miswiring. In &lt;italic&gt;unc-4&lt;/italic&gt; mutants, VA electrical synapses are established with an alternative synaptic partner and are repositioned from the VA axon to soma. We show that cAMP counters these effects by driving gap junction trafficking into the VA axon for electrical synapse assembly. Thus, our experiments in an intact nervous system establish that cAMP regulates gap junction trafficking for the biogenesis of electrical synapses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443836" rel="alternate" title="cAMP controls a trafficking mechanism that directs the neuron specificity and subcellular placement of electrical synapses (38 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443860</id><title>Variable brain wiring through scalable and relative synapse formation in Drosophila (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.484973+00:00</updated><author><name>F. Ridvan Kiral</name></author><author><name>Suchetana B. Dutta</name></author><author><name>Gerit Arne Linneweber</name></author><author><name>Caroline Poppa</name></author><author><name>Max von Kleist</name></author><author><name>Bassem A. Hassan</name></author><author><name>Peter Robin Hiesinger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Variability of synapse numbers and partners despite identical genes reveals limits of genetic determinism. Non-genetic perturbation of brain wiring can therefore reveal to what extent synapse formation is precise and absolute, or promiscuous and relative. Here, we show the role of relative partner availability for synapse formation in the fly brain through perturbation of developmental temperature. Unexpectedly, slower development at lower temperatures substantially increases axo-dendritic branching, synapse numbers and non-canonical synaptic partnerships of various neurons, while maintaining robust ratios of canonical synapses. Using R7 photoreceptors as a model, we further show that scalability of synapse numbers and ratios is preserved when relative availability of synaptic partners is changed in a DIPγ mutant that ablates R7’s preferred synaptic partner. Behaviorally, movement activity scales inversely with synapse numbers, while movement precision and relative connectivity are congruently robust. Hence, the fly genome encodes scalable relative connectivity to develop functional, but not identical, brains.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Non-identical connectivity and behavior result from temperature-dependent synaptic partner availability in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443860" rel="alternate" title="Variable brain wiring through scalable and relative synapse formation in Drosophila (31 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443330</id><title>Rapid generation of conditional knockout mice using the CRISPR-CAS9 system and electroporation for neuroscience research (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.485613+00:00</updated><author><name>Hirofumi Nishizono</name></author><author><name>Yuki Hayano</name></author><author><name>Yoshihisa Nakahata</name></author><author><name>Yasuhito Ishigaki</name></author><author><name>Ryohei Yasuda</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Cre/Loxp-based conditional knockout technology is a powerful tool for gene function analyses by allowing region-time-specific gene manipulation. However, inserting a pair of LoxP cassettes for generating conditional knock-out can be technically challenging and thus time- and resource-consuming. This study proposes an efficient, low-cost method to generate floxed mice using the in vitro fertilization and the CRISPR-Cas9 system over two consecutive generations. This method allowed us to produce floxed mice targeting exon 5 to exon 6 of CaMK1 in a short period, 125 days, using only 16 mice. The efficiency of generating floxed mice was 10%, significantly higher than the conventional ES cell-based method. We directly edited the genome of C57BL/6N fertilized eggs, our target genetic background, to eliminate additional backcrossing steps. We confirmed that the genome of this floxed mouse is responsive to Cre protein. This low-cost, highly efficient method for generating conditional knock-out will facilitate comprehensive, tissue-specific genome analyses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443330" rel="alternate" title="Rapid generation of conditional knockout mice using the CRISPR-CAS9 system and electroporation for neuroscience research (26 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443323</id><title>A novel approach to the functional classification of retinal ganglion cells (25 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.485976+00:00</updated><author><name>Gerrit Hilgen</name></author><author><name>Evgenia Kartsaki</name></author><author><name>Viktoriia Kartysh</name></author><author><name>Bruno Cessac</name></author><author><name>Evelyne Sernagor</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Retinal neurons come in remarkable diversity based on structure, function and genetic identity. Classifying these cells is a challenging task, requiring multimodal methodology. Here, we introduce a novel approach for retinal ganglion cell (RGC) classification, based on pharmacogenetics combined with immunohistochemistry and large-scale retinal electrophysiology. Our novel strategy allows grouping of cells sharing gene expression and understanding how these cell classes respond to basic and complex visual scenes. Our approach consists of increasing the firing level of RGCs co-expressing a certain gene (&lt;italic&gt;Scnn1a&lt;/italic&gt; or &lt;italic&gt;Grik4&lt;/italic&gt;) using excitatory DREADDs (Designer Receptors Exclusively Activated by Designer Drugs) and then correlate the location of these cells with &lt;italic&gt;post hoc&lt;/italic&gt; immunostaining, to unequivocally characterize anatomical and functional features of these two groups. We grouped these isolated RGC responses into multiple clusters based on the similarity of the spike trains. With our approach, and accompanied by immunohistochemistry, we were able to extend the pre-existing list of Grik4 expressing RGC types to a total of 8 RGC types and, for the first time, we provide a phenotypical description of 14 Scnn1a-expressing RGCs. The insights and methods gained here can guide RGC classification but also neuronal classification challenges in other brain regions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443323" rel="alternate" title="A novel approach to the functional classification of retinal ganglion cells (25 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.443762</id><title>Altered cerebellar response to somatosensory stimuli in the Cntnap2 mouse model of autism (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.486303+00:00</updated><author><name>Marta Fernandez</name></author><author><name>Carlos A Sanchez-Leon</name></author><author><name>Javier Llorente</name></author><author><name>Teresa Sierra-Arregui</name></author><author><name>Shira Knafo</name></author><author><name>Javier Marquez-Ruiz</name></author><author><name>Olga Penagarikano</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Atypical sensory processing is currently included within the diagnostic criteria of autism. The cerebellum is known to integrate sensory inputs of different modalities through its connectivity to the cerebral cortex. Interestingly, cerebellar malformations are among the most replicated features found in postmortem brain of individuals with autism. We studied cerebellar integration of sensory information in a mouse model of autism, knockout for the Cntnap2 gene. Cntnap2 is widely expressed in Purkinje cells and has been recently reported to regulate their morphology. Further, individuals with CNTNAP2 mutations display cerebellar malformations and CNTNAP2 antibodies are associated with a mild form of cerebellar ataxia. Previous studies in this mouse model show an altered cerebellar sensory learning. However, a physiological analysis of cerebellar function has not been performed yet. We studied sensory evoked potentials in cerebellar Crus I/II region upon electrical stimulation of the whisker pad in alert mice and found striking differences between WT and Cntnap2 KO mice. In addition, single-cell recordings identified alterations in both sensory-evoked and spontaneous firing patterns of Purkinje cells. These alterations were accompanied by altered intrinsic properties and morphological features of these neurons. Together, these results indicate that the Cntnap2 mouse model could provide novel insight into the pathophysiological mechanisms of ASD core sensory deficits. &lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.443762" rel="alternate" title="Altered cerebellar response to somatosensory stimuli in the Cntnap2 mouse model of autism (23 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443328</id><title>Kinesin-3 mediated delivery of presynaptic neurexin stabilizes growing dendritic spines and postsynaptic components in vivo (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.486998+00:00</updated><author><name>Devyn Oliver</name></author><author><name>Shankar Ramachandran</name></author><author><name>Alison Philbrook</name></author><author><name>Christopher M. Lambert</name></author><author><name>Ken C. Q. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>David H. Hall</name></author><author><name>Michael M. Francis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A high degree of cell and circuit-specific regulation has complicated efforts to precisely define roles for synaptic adhesion proteins in establishing circuit connectivity. Here, we take advantage of the strengths of &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; for cell-specific analyses to investigate molecular coordination of pre- and postsynaptic development. We show that developing dendritic spines emerge from the dendrites of wild type GABAergic motor neurons following the localization of active zone proteins and the formation of immature synaptic vesicle assemblies in presynaptic terminals. Similarly, clusters of postsynaptic receptors and F-actin are visible in GABAergic dendrites prior to spine outgrowth. Surprisingly, these developmental processes occur without a requirement for synaptic activity. Likewise, the initial stages of spine outgrowth and receptor clustering are not altered by deletion of the &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; ortholog of the transsynaptic adhesion protein, neurexin/NRX-1. Over time, however, dendritic spines and postsynaptic receptor clusters are destabilized in the absence of presynaptic NRX-1/neurexin and collapse prior to adulthood. The kinesin-3 family member, UNC-104, delivers NRX-1 to presynaptic terminals and ongoing UNC-104 delivery is required into adulthood for the maintenance of postsynaptic structure. Our findings provide novel insights into the temporal order of synapse formation events &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and demonstrate a requirement for transsynaptic adhesion in stabilizing mature circuit connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contributions Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;D.O. generated strains, transgenic lines, molecular constructs, confocal and electron microscopy images, and data analysis. S.R. performed all calcium imaging experiments and analysis. C.M.L. generated destination vectors and &lt;italic&gt;nrx-1&lt;/italic&gt; constructs. D.H.H. and K.C.Q.N. aided in electron microscopy experiments and analysis. M.M.F and D.O designed and interpreted results of all experiments and wrote the manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443328" rel="alternate" title="Kinesin-3 mediated delivery of presynaptic neurexin stabilizes growing dendritic spines and postsynaptic components in vivo (23 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.08.443276</id><title>Uncovering long-term existence of a silent short-term memory trace (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.487763+00:00</updated><author><name>Maha E. Wally</name></author><author><name>Masanori Nomoto</name></author><author><name>Kareem Abdou</name></author><author><name>Kaoru Inokuchi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Active recall of short-term memory (STM) is known to last for a few hours, but whether STM has long-term functions is unknown. Here we show that, STM can be optogenetically retrieved at a time point during which natural recall is not possible, uncovering the long-term existence of a silent STM engram. Moreover, re-training within 3 days led to natural long-term recall, indicating facilitated consolidation. Calcium imaging revealed hippocampal CA1 reactivations of the STM trace during post-learning sleep. Inhibiting offline CA1 activity, N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor activity, or protein synthesis after first exposure to the STM-forming event impaired the future re-exposure-facilitated consolidation, which highlights a role of protein synthesis and sleep in storing a silent STM trace. These results provide evidence that STM is not completely lost within hours and demonstrates a possible two-step STM consolidation, first storage as a silent engram, then transformation into an active state by recurrence within 3 days.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.08.443276" rel="alternate" title="Uncovering long-term existence of a silent short-term memory trace (20 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443246</id><title>Dichotomous thinking and informational waste in neuroimaging (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.488405+00:00</updated><author><name>Gang Chen</name></author><author><name>Paul A. Taylor</name></author><author><name>Joel Stoddard</name></author><author><name>Robert W. Cox</name></author><author><name>Peter A. Bandettini</name></author><author><name>Luiz Pessoa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neuroimaging relies on separate statistical inferences at tens of thousands of spatial locations. Such massively univariate analysis typically requires adjustment for multiple testing in an attempt to maintain the family-wise error rate at a nominal level of 5%. We discuss how this approach is associated with substantial information loss because of an implicit but questionable assumption about the effect distribution across spatial units. To improve inference efficiency, predictive accuracy, and generalizability, we propose a Bayesian multilevel modeling framework. In addition, we make four actionable suggestions to alleviate information waste and to improve reproducibility: (1) abandon strict dichotomization; (2) report full results; (3) quantify effects, and (4) model data hierarchy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443246" rel="alternate" title="Dichotomous thinking and informational waste in neuroimaging (17 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443911</id><title>Structural and cellular transcriptome foundations of human brain disease (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.488755+00:00</updated><author><name>Yashar Zeighami</name></author><author><name>Trygve Bakken</name></author><author><name>Thomas Nickl-Jockschat</name></author><author><name>Jeremy Miller</name></author><author><name>Alan C. Evans</name></author><author><name>Ed Lein</name></author><author><name>Michael Hawrylycz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The intersection of human genetics and brain transcriptomics promises to reveal the structural and cellular locus of brain diseases via selective co-expression of risk genes. We find that adult brain-wide transcriptomic profiles of 40 human brain diseases identify four major transcriptional patterns, represented by tumor-related, neurodegenerative, psychiatric and substance abuse, and a mixed group of diseases, with some unexpected disease associations. Based on differential co-expression using bulk transcriptomics, the majority of brain diseases exhibit unique regional transcriptomic signatures that strongly reflect neuronal versus non-neuronal divisions and variation in excitatory and inhibitory neurons across the brain. Single cell transcriptomic data confirms and refines the relationship of different diseases to specific neuronal and non-neuronal subclasses. Disease signatures are largely conserved between mouse and human at the higher cell class level, but with significant species differences emerging at the finer subclass level that may help explain human-specific disease susceptibility.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443911" rel="alternate" title="Structural and cellular transcriptome foundations of human brain disease (14 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443909</id><title>Mice lacking the cAMP effector protein POPDC1 show enhanced hippocampal synaptic plasticity (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.489730+00:00</updated><author><name>Mahesh Shivarama Shetty</name></author><author><name>Laurence Ris</name></author><author><name>Roland F. R. Schindler</name></author><author><name>Keiko Mizuno</name></author><author><name>Laura Fedele</name></author><author><name>Karl Peter Giese</name></author><author><name>Thomas Brand</name></author><author><name>Ted Abel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Extensive research has uncovered diverse forms of synaptic plasticity and a wide array of molecular signaling mechanisms that act as positive or negative regulators. Specifically, cAMP-dependent signaling pathways have been crucially implicated in long-lasting synaptic plasticity. In this study, we examine the role of POPDC1 (or BVES), a cAMP effector protein expressed in brain, in modulating hippocampal synaptic plasticity. Unlike other cAMP effectors, such as PKA and EPAC, POPDC1 is membrane-bound and the sequence of the cAMP-binding cassette differs from canonical cAMP-binding domains. These properties suggest that POPDC1 may have a unique role in cAMP-mediated signaling underlying synaptic plasticity. Our results show that POPDC1 is enriched in hippocampal synaptoneurosomes. Acute hippocampal slices from &lt;italic&gt;Popdc1&lt;/italic&gt; knockout (KO) mice exhibit enhanced long-term potentiation (LTP) induced by a variety of stimulation paradigms, particularly in response to weak stimulation paradigms that in slices from wildtype mice induce only transient LTP. Furthermore, &lt;italic&gt;Popdc1&lt;/italic&gt; KO mice did not display any further enhancement in forskolin-induced LTP observed following inhibition of phosphodiesterases (PDEs), suggesting a possible modulation of cAMP-PDE signaling by POPDC1. Taken together, these data reveal POPDC1 as a novel player in the regulation of hippocampal synaptic plasticity and as a potential target for cognitive enhancement strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443909" rel="alternate" title="Mice lacking the cAMP effector protein POPDC1 show enhanced hippocampal synaptic plasticity (14 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.08.443234</id><title>Estimating the glutamate transporter surface density in mouse hippocampal astrocytes (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.490323+00:00</updated><author><name>Anca R. Rădulescu</name></author><author><name>Cassandra L. Williams</name></author><author><name>Gabrielle C. Todd</name></author><author><name>Alex A. Lemus</name></author><author><name>Haley E. Chesbro</name></author><author><name>Annalisa Scimemi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glutamate transporters preserve the spatial specificity of synaptic transmission by limiting gluta-mate diffusion away from the synaptic cleft, and prevent excitotoxicity by keeping the extracellular concentration of glutamate at low nanomolar levels. Glutamate transporters are abundantly expressed in astrocytes. Previous estimates in the rat hippocampus suggest that the surface density of glutamate transporters in astrocytic membranes is ~ 10, 800 &lt;italic&gt;μ&lt;/italic&gt;m&lt;sup&gt;−2&lt;/sup&gt;. Here, we estimate their surface density in astrocytic membranes of the mouse hippocampus, at different ages. By using realistic 3D Monte Carlo reaction-diffusion models, we show that varying the local glutamate transporter expression in astrocytes can alter profoundly the activation of extrasynaptic AMPA and NMDA receptors. Our findings show that the average density of astrocyte membranes and their surface density of glutamate transporters is higher in mice compared to rats, and increases with mouse age. There are stark differences in the density of expression of these molecules in different sub-cellular compartments, indicating that the extent to which astrocytes limit extrasynaptic glutamate diffusion depends not only on the level of astrocytic coverage, but also on the identity of the astrocyte compartment in contact with the synapse. Together, these findings provide information on the spatial distribution of glutamate transporters in the mouse hippocampus, which can be used in mathematical models of the spatiotemporal profile of extracellular glutamate after synaptic release.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The astrocyte membrane density in the hippocampal neuropil is higher than in rats.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The surface density of glutamate transporters in mouse astrocytes is higher than in rats and varies widely across different sub-cellular compartments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The identify of the astrocyte compartment in contact with a synapse, not only the extent of astrocytic coverage, is a main determinant of glutamate spillover and extrasynaptic receptor activation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Table of Contents Image&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="443234v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.08.443234" rel="alternate" title="Estimating the glutamate transporter surface density in mouse hippocampal astrocytes (12 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443637</id><title>Cortical ripples provide the conditions for consolidation during NREM sleep in humans (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.491007+00:00</updated><author><name>Charles W. Dickey</name></author><author><name>Ilya A. Verzhbinsky</name></author><author><name>Xi Jiang</name></author><author><name>Burke Q. Rosen</name></author><author><name>Sophie Kajfez</name></author><author><name>Emad N. Eskandar</name></author><author><name>Jorge Gonzalez-Martinez</name></author><author><name>Sydney S. Cash</name></author><author><name>Eric Halgren</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hippocampal ripples index the reconstruction of spatiotemporal neuronal firing patterns essential for the consolidation of memories in the cortex during non-rapid eye movement (NREM) sleep. However, it is not known whether ripples are generated in the human cortex during sleep. Here, using human intracranial recordings, we show that ∼70ms long ∼80Hz ripples are ubiquitous in all regions of the cortex during NREM sleep as well as waking. During waking, cortical ripples occur on local high frequency activity peaks. During sleep, cortical ripples occur during spindles on the down-to-upstate transition, with unit-firing patterns consistent with generation by pyramidal-interneuron feedback. Cortical ripples mark the recurrence of spatiotemporal activity patterns from preceding waking, and they group co-firing within the window of spike-timing-dependent plasticity. Thus, cortical ripples guided by sequential sleep waves may facilitate memory consolidation during NREM sleep in humans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443637" rel="alternate" title="Cortical ripples provide the conditions for consolidation during NREM sleep in humans (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443799</id><title>Scale-free behavioral dynamics directly linked with scale-free cortical dynamics (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.492927+00:00</updated><author><name>Sabrina A. Jones</name></author><author><name>Jacob H. Barfield</name></author><author><name>Woodrow L. Shew</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Naturally occurring body movements and collective neural activity both exhibit complex dynamics, often with scale-free, fractal spatiotemporal structure, thought to confer functional benefits to the organism. Despite their similarities, scale-free brain activity and scale-free behavior have been studied separately, without a unified explanation. Here we show that scale-free dynamics of behavior and certain subsets of cortical neurons are one-to-one related. Surprisingly, the scale-free neural subsets exhibit stochastic winner-take-all competition with other neural subsets, inconsistent with prevailing theory of scale-free neural systems. We develop a computational model which accounts for known cell-type-specific circuit structure and explains our findings. Our results establish neural underpinnings of scale-free behavior and clear behavioral relevance of scale-free neural activity, which was previously thought to represent background noise in cerebral cortex.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Winner-take-all competition among cortical neurons underpins shared fractal spatiotemporal dynamics of behavior and brain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443799" rel="alternate" title="Scale-free behavioral dynamics directly linked with scale-free cortical dynamics (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.08.443268</id><title>In situ and transcriptomic identification of synapse-associated microglia in the developing zebrafish brain (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.493255+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas J. Silva</name></author><author><name>Leah C. Dorman</name></author><author><name>Ilia D. Vainchtein</name></author><author><name>Nadine C. Horneck</name></author><author><name>Anna V. Molofsky</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microglia are brain resident macrophages that play vital roles in central nervous system (CNS) development, homeostasis, and pathology. Microglia both remodel synapses and engulf apoptotic cell corpses during development, but whether unique molecular programs regulate these distinct phagocytic functions is unknown. Here we identify a molecularly distinct synapse-associated microglial subset in the zebrafish (&lt;italic&gt;Danio rerio&lt;/italic&gt;). We found that ramified microglia populated synapse-rich regions of the midbrain and hindbrain between 7 and 28 days post fertilization. In contrast, microglia in the optic tectum were ameboid and clustered around neurogenic zones. Using single-cell mRNA sequencing combined with metadata from regional bulk sequencing, we identified synapse-associated microglia (SAMs) that were highly enriched in the hindbrain, expressed known synapse modulating genes as well as novel candidates, and engulfed synaptic proteins. In contrast, neurogenic-associated microglia (NAMs) were enriched in optic tectum, had active cathepsin activity, and preferentially engulfed neuronal corpses. These data yielded a functionally annotated atlas of zebrafish microglia (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.annamolofskylab.org/microglia-sequencing"&gt;https://www.annamolofskylab.org/microglia-sequencing&lt;/ext-link&gt;). Furthermore, they reveal that molecularly distinct phagocytic programs mediate synaptic remodeling and cell engulfment, and establish zebrafish hindbrain as a model circuit for investigating microglial-synapse interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.08.443268" rel="alternate" title="In situ and transcriptomic identification of synapse-associated microglia in the developing zebrafish brain (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443127</id><title>Disrupted microglial iron homeostasis in progressive multiple sclerosis (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.493552+00:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan D. Proto</name></author><author><name>Mindy Zhang</name></author><author><name>Sean Ryan</name></author><author><name>Xinting Yao</name></author><author><name>Yinyin Huang</name></author><author><name>Yi-Chien Chang</name></author><author><name>Michael R. Dufault</name></author><author><name>Emilie Christie</name></author><author><name>Anthony Chomyk</name></author><author><name>Jackie Saleh</name></author><author><name>Jose Sancho</name></author><author><name>Timothy Hammond</name></author><author><name>Bruce Trapp</name></author><author><name>Dimitry Ofengeim</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Multiple Sclerosis (MS) is a chronic autoimmune disease affecting the central nervous system (CNS). Despite therapies that reduce relapses, many patients eventually develop secondary progressive MS (SPMS), characterized by ongoing and irreversible neurodegeneration and worsening clinical symptoms. Microglia are the resident innate immune cells of the CNS. While the cellular and molecular determinants of disability progression in MS remain incompletely understood, they are thought to include non-resolving microglial activation and chronic oxidative injury. In this study, our aim was to better characterize microglia in SPMS tissues to identify disease-related changes at the single cell level. We performed single nucleus RNA-seq (snRNA-seq) on cryopreserved post-mortem brain cortex and identified disease associated changes in multiple cell types and in particular distinct SPMS-enriched microglia subsets. When compared to the cluster most enriched in healthy controls (i.e. homeostatic microglia), we found a number of SPMS-enriched clusters with transcriptional profiles reflecting increased oxidative stress and perturbed iron homeostasis. Using histology and RNA-scope, we confirmed the presence of iron accumulating, ferritin-light chain (&lt;italic&gt;FTL&lt;/italic&gt;)-expressing microglia &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt;. Among disease-enriched clusters, we found evidence for divergent responses to iron accumulation and identified the antioxidant enzyme GPX4 as a key fate determinant. These data help elucidate processes that occur in progressive MS brains, and highlight novel nodes for therapeutic intervention.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443127" rel="alternate" title="Disrupted microglial iron homeostasis in progressive multiple sclerosis (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443403</id><title>Neuropsychological evidence of multi-domain network hubs in the human thalamus (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.497981+00:00</updated><author><name>Kai Hwang</name></author><author><name>James M. Shine</name></author><author><name>Joel Bruss</name></author><author><name>Daniel Tranel</name></author><author><name>Aaron D. Boes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hubs in the human brain support behaviors that arise from brain network interactions. Previous studies have identified hub regions in the human thalamus that are connected with multiple functional networks. However, the behavioral significance of thalamic hubs has yet to be established. Our framework predicts that thalamic subregions with strong hub properties are broadly involved in functions across multiple cognitive domains. To test this prediction, we studied human patients with focal thalamic lesions in conjunction with network analyses of the human thalamocortical functional connectome. In support of our prediction, lesions to thalamic subregions with stronger hub properties were associated with widespread deficits in executive, language, and memory functions, whereas lesions to thalamic subregions with weaker hub properties were associated with more limited deficits. These results highlight how a large-scale network model can broaden our understanding of thalamic function for human cognition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443403" rel="alternate" title="Neuropsychological evidence of multi-domain network hubs in the human thalamus (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443898</id><title>Dual origin and multiple neuropeptidergic trajectories of hypothalamic POMC progenitors revealed by developmental single-cell transcriptomics (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.498359+00:00</updated><author><name>Hui Yu</name></author><author><name>Marcelo Rubinstein</name></author><author><name>Malcolm J Low</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Proopiomelanocortin (POMC) neurons of the hypothalamic arcuate nucleus are essential to regulate food intake and energy balance. However, the ontogenetic transcriptional programs that specify the identity and functioning of these neurons are poorly understood. Here, we use scRNAseq to define the transcriptomes characterizing POMC progenitors in the developing hypothalamus and their transition into mature neurons. Our data show that &lt;italic&gt;Pomc&lt;/italic&gt;-expressing neurons originate from two independent developmental pathways expressing distinct combinations of transcription factors. The predominant cluster, featured by high levels of &lt;italic&gt;Pomc&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Prdm12&lt;/italic&gt; transcripts represents the precursors of canonical arcuate POMC neurons. Additional clusters of progenitors expressing lower levels of &lt;italic&gt;Pomc&lt;/italic&gt; mature into different neuronal phenotypes characterized by distinct combinations of transcription factors, neuropeptides, processing enzymes, cell surface and nuclear receptors. We conclude that the genetic programs specifying the identity and differentiation of arcuate POMC neurons are diverse and generate a heterogeneous repertoire of neuronal phenotypes early in development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443898" rel="alternate" title="Dual origin and multiple neuropeptidergic trajectories of hypothalamic POMC progenitors revealed by developmental single-cell transcriptomics (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.08.443259</id><title>Astrocyte plasticity ensures continued endfoot coverage of cerebral blood vessels and integrity of the blood brain barrier, with plasticity declining with normal aging (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.498819+00:00</updated><author><name>William A. Mills</name></author><author><name>Shan Jiang</name></author><author><name>Joelle Martin</name></author><author><name>AnnaLin M. Woo</name></author><author><name>Matthew Bergstresser</name></author><author><name>Ian F. Kimbrough</name></author><author><name>Harald Sontheimer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Astrocytes extend endfeet that enwrap the vasculature. Disruptions to this association in disease coincide with breaches in blood-brain barrier (BBB) integrity, so we asked if the focal ablation of an astrocyte is sufficient to disrupt the BBB. 2Phatal ablation of astrocytes induced a plasticity response whereby surrounding astrocytes extended processes to cover vascular vacancies. This occurred prior to endfoot retraction in young mice yet occurred with significant delay in aged animals. Laser-stimulating replacement astrocytes showed them to induce constrictions in pre-capillary arterioles indicating that replacement astrocytes are functional. Inhibition of EGFR and pSTAT3 significantly reduced astrocyte replacement post-ablation yet without perturbations to BBB integrity. Identical endfoot replacement following astrocyte cell death due to reperfusion post-stroke supports the conclusion that astrocyte plasticity ensures continual vascular coverage so as to retain the BBB. Together, these studies uncover the ability of astrocytes to maintain cerebrovascular coverage via substitution from nearby cells and may represent a novel therapeutic target for vessel recovery post-stroke.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.08.443259" rel="alternate" title="Astrocyte plasticity ensures continued endfoot coverage of cerebral blood vessels and integrity of the blood brain barrier, with plasticity declining with normal aging (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443894</id><title>A behavioral screen for mediators of age-dependent TDP-43 neurodegeneration identifies SF2/SRSF1 among a group of potent suppressors in both neurons and glia (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.499264+00:00</updated><author><name>Jorge Azpurua</name></author><author><name>Enas Gad El-Karim</name></author><author><name>Marvel Tranquille</name></author><author><name>Josh Dubnau</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cytoplasmic aggregation of Tar-DNA/RNA binding protein 43 (TDP-43) occurs in 97 percent of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS), about 40 percent of frontotemporal dementia (FTD) and in many cases of Alzheimer’s disease (AD). Cytoplasmic TDP-43 inclusions are seen in both sporadic and familial forms of these disorders, including those cases that are caused by repeat expansion mutations in the &lt;italic&gt;C9orf72&lt;/italic&gt; gene. To identify downstream mediators of TDP-43 toxicity, we expressed human TDP-43 in a subset of &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; motor neurons. Such expression causes age-dependent deficits in negative geotaxis behavior. Using this behavioral readout of locomotion, we conducted an shRNA suppressor screen and identified 32 transcripts whose knockdown was sufficient to ameliorate the neurological phenotype. The majority of these suppressors also substantially suppressed the negative effects on lifespan seen with glial TDP-43 expression. In addition to identification of a number of genes whose roles in neurodegeneration were not previously known, our screen also yielded genes involved in chromatin regulation and nuclear/import export-pathways that were previously identified in the context of cell based or neurodevelopmental suppressor screens. A notable example is &lt;italic&gt;SF2&lt;/italic&gt;, a conserved orthologue of mammalian &lt;italic&gt;SRSF1&lt;/italic&gt;, an RNA binding protein with roles in splicing and nuclear export. Our identification &lt;italic&gt;SF2/SRSF1&lt;/italic&gt; as a potent suppressor of both neuronal and glial TDP-43 toxicity also provides a convergence with &lt;italic&gt;C9orf72&lt;/italic&gt; expansion repeat mediated neurodegeneration, where this gene also acts as a downstream mediator.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Loss of nuclear function of TDP-43 and its mislocalization into cytoplasmic inclusions are central features to a suite of neurodegenerative disorders. We screened 2700 &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; genes to identify downstream mediators that suppress an age-dependent motor dysfunction phenotype when they are knocked down by RNA interference. We identified both previously implicated pathways and several novel genes whose knock down is sufficient to dramatically and robustly rescue TDP-43 toxicity both in neuronal and glial contexts. Notably, we report that &lt;italic&gt;SF2/SRSF1&lt;/italic&gt;, which was previously reported as a suppressor of &lt;italic&gt;C9orf72&lt;/italic&gt; hexanucleotide expansion repeat toxicity, also is a potent suppressor of TDP-43 mediated neurodegeneration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443894" rel="alternate" title="A behavioral screen for mediators of age-dependent TDP-43 neurodegeneration identifies SF2/SRSF1 among a group of potent suppressors in both neurons and glia (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443804</id><title>Common neural bases for processing speech prosody and music: An integrated model (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.499621+00:00</updated><author><name>Alice Mado Proverbio</name></author><author><name>Elisabetta Piotti</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It is shared notion that speech and music processing share some commonalities. Brain bioelectrical activity was recorded in healthy participants listening to music obtained by digitally transforming real speech into melodies played by viola. Sentences were originally pronounced with a positive or negative affective prosody. The research’s aim was to investigate if the emotional content of music was extracted similarly to how the affective prosody of speech is processed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;EEG was recorded from 128 electrodes in 20 healthy students. Participants had to detect rare neutral piano sounds while ignoring viola melodies. Stimulus negative valence increased the amplitude of frontal P300 and N400 ERP components while a late inferior frontal positivity was enhanced in response to positive melodies. Similar ERP markers were previously found for processing positive and negative music, vocalizations and speech. Source reconstruction applied to N400 showed that negative melodies engaged the right superior temporal gyrus and right anterior cingulate cortex, while positive melodies engaged the left middle and inferior temporal gyrus and the inferior frontal cortex. An integrated model is proposed depicting a possible common circuit for processing the emotional content of music, vocalizations and speech, which might explain some universal and relatively innate brain reaction to music.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443804" rel="alternate" title="Common neural bases for processing speech prosody and music: An integrated model (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443325</id><title>Edaravone activates the GDNF/RET neurotrophic signaling pathway and protects mRNA-induced motor neurons from iPS cells (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.499898+00:00</updated><author><name>Qian Li</name></author><author><name>Yi Feng</name></author><author><name>Yingchao Xue</name></author><author><name>Xiping Zhan</name></author><author><name>Yi Fu</name></author><author><name>Gege Gui</name></author><author><name>Jean-Philippe Richard</name></author><author><name>Arens Taga</name></author><author><name>Xiaobo Mao</name></author><author><name>Nicholas J. Maragakis</name></author><author><name>Mingyao Ying</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spinal cord motor neurons (MNs) from human iPS cells (iPSCs) have wide applications in disease modeling and therapeutic development for amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) and other MN-associated neurodegenerative diseases. We need highly efficient MN differentiation strategies for generating iPSC-derived disease models that closely recapitulate the genetic and phenotypic complexity of ALS. An important application of these models is to understand molecular mechanisms of action of FDA-approved ALS drugs that only show modest clinical efficacy. Novel mechanistic insights will help us design optimal therapeutic strategies together with predictive biomarkers to achieve better efficacy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We induce efficient MN differentiation from iPSCs in 4 days using synthetic mRNAs coding two transcription factors (Ngn2 and Olig2) with phosphosite modification. These MNs after extensive characterization were applied in electrophysiological and neurotoxicity assays as well as transcriptomic analysis, to study the neuroprotective effect and molecular mechanisms of edaravone, an FDA-approved drug for ALS, for improving its clinical efficacy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We generate highly pure and functional mRNA-induced MNs (miMNs) from normal and ALS iPSCs, as well as embryonic stem cells. Edaravone alleviates H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-induced neurotoxicity and electrophysiological dysfunction in miMNs, demonstrating its neuroprotective effect. Guided by the transcriptomic analysis, we show a previously unrecognized effect of edaravone to induce the GDNF receptor RET and the GDNF/RET neurotrophic signaling &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, suggesting a clinically translatable strategy to activate this key neuroprotective signaling. Notably, edaravone can replace required neurotrophic factors (BDNF and GDNF) to support long-term miMN survival and maturation, further supporting the neurotrophic function of edaravone-activated signaling. Furthermore, we show that edaravone and GDNF combined treatment more effectively protects miMNs from H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-induced neurotoxicity than single treatment, suggesting a potential combination strategy for ALS treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study provides methodology to facilitate iPSC differentiation and disease modeling. Our discoveries will facilitate the development of optimal edaravone-based therapies for ALS and potentially other neurodegenerative diseases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphic Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="443325v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443325" rel="alternate" title="Edaravone activates the GDNF/RET neurotrophic signaling pathway and protects mRNA-induced motor neurons from iPS cells (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.443904</id><title>Truncating Tau Reveals Different Pathophysiological Actions of Oligomers in Single Neurons (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.500786+00:00</updated><author><name>Emily Hill</name></author><author><name>Thomas K. Karikari</name></author><author><name>Juan Lantero Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Henrik Zetterberg</name></author><author><name>Kaj Blennow</name></author><author><name>Magnus J Richardson</name></author><author><name>Mark J Wall</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tau protein is involved in maintaining the structural integrity of neurons. In tauopathies, including Alzheimer’s disease, tau forms oligomers, which can modulate neuronal function. Previously the introduction of oligomeric full-length human tau (aa 1-441; FL-oTau) into pyramidal neurons decreased whole-cell conductance, increased excitability and changed the action potential (AP) waveform. Introducing N-terminally truncated tau (aa 124-441; C&lt;sup&gt;FRAG&lt;/sup&gt;) removed the effects on the AP waveform and input resistance but the increase in excitability remained. A hyperpolarising shift in spike threshold underlies this increase in excitability. The N-terminal fragment (aa 1-123; N&lt;sup&gt;FRAG&lt;/sup&gt;) markedly increased input resistance and changed the AP waveform. Lower concentrations of N&lt;sup&gt;FRAG&lt;/sup&gt; only changed the AP waveform. Thus the two truncations can recapitulate the effects of FL-oTau. To investigate underlying mechanisms, we recorded sodium currents and found that FL-oTau lowers the activation voltage and reduced the maximal conductance, consistent with the lower spike threshold and reduction in AP amplitude&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphic abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="443904v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.443904" rel="alternate" title="Truncating Tau Reveals Different Pathophysiological Actions of Oligomers in Single Neurons (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443512</id><title>Prodromal dysfunction of α5GABA-A receptor modulated hippocampal ripples in Alzheimer’s disease (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.501198+00:00</updated><author><name>Marcia H. Ratner</name></author><author><name>Scott S. Downing</name></author><author><name>Ouyang Guo</name></author><author><name>KathrynAnn E. Odamah</name></author><author><name>Tara M. Stewart</name></author><author><name>Vidhya Kumaresan</name></author><author><name>R. Jonathan Robitsek</name></author><author><name>Weiming Xia</name></author><author><name>David H. Farb</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Decades of research attempting to slow the onset of Alzheimer’s disease (AD) indicates that a better understanding of memory will be key to the discovery of effective therapeutic approaches. Here, we ask whether prodromal neural network dysfunction might occur in the hippocampal trisynaptic circuit by using α5IA as a selective negative modulator of extrasynaptic α5GABA-A receptors in TgF344-AD transgenic rats, a model for early onset AD. The results demonstrate that orally bioavailable α5IA, an established memory enhancer, increases CA1 pyramidal cell mean firing rates and peak CA1 ripple amplitude during wakeful immobility in &lt;italic&gt;wild type&lt;/italic&gt; F344 rats resting in a familiar environment. We show that TgF344-AD rats, which express human amyloid-beta precursor protein (with the Swedish mutation) and human presenilin-1 (with a Δ exon 9 mutation), exhibit high serum Aβ42 and Aβ40 levels by 3 months of age. By 9 months of age, CA1 ripples in young adult TgF344-AD rats are nonresponsive to α5IA indicating network dysfunction prior to the onset of AD pathology and memory dysfunction. These results demonstrate, to the best of our knowledge, the first evidence for prodromal α5GABA-A receptor dysfunction in the AD hippocampal trisynaptic circuit. Moreover, as α5GABA-A receptors are located extrasynaptically and subserve the function of tonic inhibition we posit that an early stage of memory dysfunction involves the disruption of tonic inhibition in the hippocampus.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443512" rel="alternate" title="Prodromal dysfunction of α5GABA-A receptor modulated hippocampal ripples in Alzheimer’s disease (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443522</id><title>Exosomal transmission of α-synuclein initiates Parkinson’s disease-like pathology (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.501839+00:00</updated><author><name>Jason Howitt</name></author><author><name>Ley Hian Low</name></author><author><name>Michelle Bouman</name></author><author><name>Jeremy Yang</name></author><author><name>Sarah Gordon</name></author><author><name>Andrew Hill</name></author><author><name>Seong-Seng Tan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The intercellular transmission of α-synuclein is proposed to be involved in the pathogenesis of Parkinson’s disease (PD)&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. Supporting this transmission hypothesis, α-synuclein has been identified to act as a prion&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; and has been found in cerebrospinal fluid (CSF), blood, and saliva&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;. However, the mechanism required to initiate the pathogenic spread of α-synuclein in the body that results in PD remains unclear. Here we identify a mechanism for the loading of α-synuclein into exosomes, resulting in prion-like transmission that is mediated by the ubiquitin ligase activator, Ndfip1. Risk factors associated with PD, including metal toxicity, lysosome dysfunction and pesticide exposure,&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; stimulate the upregulation of Ndfip1 and increase the loading of α-synuclein into exosomes. We used this pathway to promote the loading of endogenous α-synuclein into exosomes, that when intranasally delivered to either wild type or M83 transgenic mice, resulted in Parkinson’s-like pathology including motor impairments and brain amyloids. Recipient cells require α-synuclein for pathogenesis, as delivery of exosomes containing α-synuclein to Snca knockout mice did not generate brain amyloids or Parkinson’s-like motor impairments. Our results demonstrate a novel mechanism to initiate the prion-like spread of α-synuclein in exosomes, following exposure to risk factors for PD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443522" rel="alternate" title="Exosomal transmission of α-synuclein initiates Parkinson’s disease-like pathology (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443096</id><title>Two functionally distinct Purkinje cell populations implement an internal model within a single olivo-cerebellar loop (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.503618+00:00</updated><author><name>Dora E. Angelaki</name></author><author><name>Jean Laurens</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Olivo-cerebellar loops, where anatomical patches of the cerebellar cortex and inferior olive project one onto the other, form an anatomical unit of cerebellar computation. Here, we investigated how successive computational steps map onto olivo-cerebellar loops. Lobules IX-X of the cerebellar vermis, i.e. the nodulus and uvula, implement an internal model of the inner ear’s graviceptor, the otolith organs. We have previously identified two populations of Purkinje cells that participate in this computation: Tilt-selective cells transform egocentric rotation signals into allocentric tilt velocity signals, to track head motion relative to gravity, and translation-selective cells encode otolith prediction error. Here we show that, despite very distinct simple spike response properties, both types of Purkinje cells emit complex spikes that are proportional to sensory prediction error. This indicates that both cell populations comprise a single olivo-cerebellar loop, in which only translation-selective cells project to the inferior olive. We propose a neural network model where sensory prediction errors computed by translation-selective cells are used as a teaching signal for both populations, and demonstrate that this network can learn to implement an internal model of the otoliths.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443096" rel="alternate" title="Two functionally distinct Purkinje cell populations implement an internal model within a single olivo-cerebellar loop (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443485</id><title>Cortical alpha-synuclein preformed fibrils do not affect interval timing in mice (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.503947+00:00</updated><author><name>Qiang Zhang</name></author><author><name>Hisham Abdelmotilib</name></author><author><name>Travis Larson</name></author><author><name>Cameron Keomanivong</name></author><author><name>Mackenzie Conlon</name></author><author><name>Georgina M. Aldridge</name></author><author><name>Nandakumar S. Narayanan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;One hallmark feature of Parkinson’s disease (PD) is Lewy body pathology associated with misfolded alpha-synuclein. Previous studies have shown that striatal injection of alpha-synuclein preformed fibrils (PFF) can induce misfolding and aggregation of native alpha-synuclein in a prion-like manner, leading to cell death and motor dysfunction in mouse models. Here, we tested whether alpha-synuclein PFFs injected into the medial prefrontal cortex results in cognitive deficits in mouse models as measured by interval timing, which is reliably disrupted in PD patients and in rodent models. We injected human alpha-synuclein PFF or monomers in the medial prefrontal cortex pre-injected with adeno-associated virus (AAV) overexpressing human alpha-synuclein. Despite notable medial prefrontal cortical synucleinopathy, we did not observe consistent deficits in fixed-interval timing. These results suggest that cortical alpha-synuclein does not reliably disrupt interval timing in rodent models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cortical injection of alpha-synuclein preformed fibrils (PFF) induces diffuse synucleinopathy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cortical injection of PFFs does not affect interval timing in mice&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Medial prefrontal cortical synucleinopathy does not reliably disrupt interval timing&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443485" rel="alternate" title="Cortical alpha-synuclein preformed fibrils do not affect interval timing in mice (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443607</id><title>Dysfunctions of the paraventricular hypothalamic nucleus induce hypersomnia in human and mice (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.504260+00:00</updated><author><name>Chang-Rui Chen</name></author><author><name>Yu-Heng Zhong</name></author><author><name>Shan Jiang</name></author><author><name>Wei Xu</name></author><author><name>Zan Wang</name></author><author><name>Lei Xiao</name></author><author><name>Wei-Min Qu</name></author><author><name>Zhi-Li Huang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hypersomnolence disorder (HD) is characterized by excessive sleep, which is a common sequela following stroke, infections or tumorigenesis. HD was traditionally thought to be associated with lesions of wake-promoting nuclei. However, lesion of a single, even two or more wake-promoting nucleuses simultaneously did not exert serious HD. The specific nucleus and neural circuitry for HD remain unknown. Here, we observed that three patients with lesions around the paraventricular nucleus of the hypothalamus (PVH) showed hypersomnolence lasting more than 20 h per day and their excessive sleep decreased with the recovery of the PVH area. Therefore, we hypothesized that the PVH might play an essential role in the occurrence of HD. Using multichannel electrophysiological recording and fiber photometry, we found that PVH&lt;sup&gt;vglut2&lt;/sup&gt; neurons were preferentially active during wakefulness. Chemogenetic activation of PVH&lt;sup&gt;vglut2&lt;/sup&gt; neurons potently induced 9-h wakefulness, and PVH&lt;sup&gt;CRH&lt;/sup&gt;, PVH&lt;sup&gt;PDYN&lt;/sup&gt; and PVH&lt;sup&gt;OT&lt;/sup&gt; neuronal activation also exerted wakefulness. Most importantly, ablation of PVH&lt;sup&gt;vglut2&lt;/sup&gt; neurons drastically induced hypersomnia-like behaviors (30.6% reduction in wakefulness). These results indicate that dysfunctions of the PVH is crucial for physiological arousal and pathogenesis underlying HD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443607" rel="alternate" title="Dysfunctions of the paraventricular hypothalamic nucleus induce hypersomnia in human and mice (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443839</id><title>Spatiotemporal 3D image registration for mesoscale studies of brain development (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.504485+00:00</updated><author><name>Sergey Shuvaev</name></author><author><name>Alexander Lazutkin</name></author><author><name>Roman Kiryanov</name></author><author><name>Konstantin Anokhin</name></author><author><name>Grigori Enikolopov</name></author><author><name>Alexei A. Koulakov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Comparison of brain samples representing different developmental stages often necessitates registering the samples to common coordinates. Although the available software tools are successful in registering 3D images of adult brains, registration of perinatal brains remains challenging due to rapid growth-dependent morphological changes and variations in developmental pace between animals. To address these challenges, we propose a multi-step algorithm for the registration of perinatal brains. First, we optimized image preprocessing to increase the algorithm’s sensitivity to mismatches in registered images. Second, we developed an attention-gated simulated annealing (Monte Carlo) procedure capable of focusing on the differences between perinatal brains. Third, we applied classical multidimensional scaling (CMDS) to align (“synchronize”) brain samples in time, accounting for individual development paces. We tested this multi-step algorithm on 28 samples of whole-mounted perinatal mouse brains (P0 – P9) and observed accurate registration results. Our computational pipeline offers a runtime of several minutes per brain on a personal computer and automates brain registration tasks including mapping brain data to atlases, comparison of averaged experimental groups, and monitoring brain development dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443839" rel="alternate" title="Spatiotemporal 3D image registration for mesoscale studies of brain development (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443802</id><title>Fluid intelligence and naturalistic task impairments after focal brain lesions (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.504758+00:00</updated><author><name>Verity Smith</name></author><author><name>Clara Pinasco</name></author><author><name>Jascha Achterberg</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Mitchell</name></author><author><name>Tilak Das</name></author><author><name>Maria Roca</name></author><author><name>John Duncan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Classical executive tasks, such as Wisconsin card-sorting and verbal fluency, are widely used as tests of frontal lobe control functions. Since the pioneering work of Shallice and Burgess (1991), it has been known that complex, naturalistic tasks can capture deficits that are missed in these classical tests. Matching this finding, deficits in several classical tasks are predicted by loss of fluid intelligence, linked to damage in a specific cortical “multiple-demand” (MD) network, while deficits in a more naturalistic task are not. To expand on these previous results, we examined the effect of focal brain lesions on three new tests – a modification of the previously-used Hotel task, a new test of task switching after extended delays, and a test of decision-making in imagined real-life scenarios. As potential predictors of impairment we measured volume of damage to &lt;italic&gt;a priori&lt;/italic&gt; MD and default mode (DMN) networks, as well as cortical damage outside these networks. Deficits in the three new tasks were substantial, but were not explained by loss of fluid intelligence, or by volume of damage to either MD or DMN networks. Instead, deficits were associated with diverse lesions, and not strongly correlated with one another. The results confirm that naturalistic tasks capture cognitive deficits beyond those measured by fluid intelligence. We suggest, however, that these deficits may not arise from specific control operations required by complex behaviour. Instead, like everyday activities, complex tasks combine a rich variety of interacting cognitive components, bringing many opportunities for processing to be disturbed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443802" rel="alternate" title="Fluid intelligence and naturalistic task impairments after focal brain lesions (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443755</id><title>Visuo-proprioceptive integration and recalibration with multiple visual stimuli (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.504938+00:00</updated><author><name>Nienke B Debats</name></author><author><name>Herbert Heuer</name></author><author><name>Christoph Kayser</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To organize the plethora of sensory signals from our environment into a coherent percept, our brain relies on the processes of multisensory integration and sensory recalibration. We here asked how visuo-proprioceptive integration and recalibration are shaped by the presence of more than one potentially relevant visual stimulus, hence paving the way to studying multisensory perception under more naturalistic settings with multiple signals per sensory modality. By manipulating the spatio-temporal correspondence between the hand position and two visual stimuli during a cursor-control task, we contrasted two alternative accounts: that only the temporally more proximal signal enters integration and recalibration similar to a winner-takes-all process, or that the influences of both visual signals superpose. Our results show that integration - and likely also recalibration - are shaped by the superposed contributions of multiple stimuli rather than by only individual ones.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443755" rel="alternate" title="Visuo-proprioceptive integration and recalibration with multiple visual stimuli (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443573</id><title>microRNA-138 controls hippocampal interneuron function and short-term memory (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.505111+00:00</updated><author><name>R. Daswani</name></author><author><name>C. Gilardi</name></author><author><name>M. Soutschek</name></author><author><name>K. Weiss</name></author><author><name>S. Bicker</name></author><author><name>R. Fiore</name></author><author><name>C. Dieterich</name></author><author><name>P.L. Germain</name></author><author><name>J Winterer</name></author><author><name>G Schratt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A tightly regulated balance between excitatory and inhibitory (E/I) synaptic transmission is critical for neural circuit assembly and function. microRNAs control excitatory neuron function, but their role in inhibitory interneurons is unknown. Here, we show that miR-138-5p regulates the expression of presynaptic genes in hippocampal parvalbumin-expressing inhibitory interneurons to control short-term memory. Our finding suggests a critical role for miR-138-5p in disorders of impaired E/I balance, such as autism and schizophrenia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443573" rel="alternate" title="microRNA-138 controls hippocampal interneuron function and short-term memory (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443598</id><title>Parallel processing of olfactory and mechanosensory information in the honeybee antennal lobe (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.505396+00:00</updated><author><name>Ettore Tiraboschi</name></author><author><name>Luana Leonardelli</name></author><author><name>Gianluca Segata</name></author><author><name>Elisa Rigosi</name></author><author><name>Albrecht Haase</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We report that airflow produces a complex activation pattern in the antennal lobes of the honeybee &lt;italic&gt;Apis mellifera&lt;/italic&gt;. Glomerular response maps provide a stereotypical code for the intensity and the dynamics of mechanical stimuli that is superimposed on the olfactory code. We show responses to modulated stimuli suggesting that this combinatorial code could provide information about the intensity, direction, and dynamics of the airflow during flight and waggle dance communication.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443598" rel="alternate" title="Parallel processing of olfactory and mechanosensory information in the honeybee antennal lobe (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>