<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>BioRxiv preprints in neuroscience posted in the last week with at least 5 tweets</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.031991+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neuroscience/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.04.442660</id><title>Metamodal Coupling of Vibrotactile and Auditory Speech Processing Systems Through Matched Stimulus Representations (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.034148+00:00</updated><author><name>Srikanth R. Damera</name></author><author><name>Patrick S. Malone</name></author><author><name>Benson W. Stevens</name></author><author><name>Richard Klein</name></author><author><name>Silvio P. Eberhardt</name></author><author><name>Edward T. Auer</name></author><author><name>Lynne E. Bernstein</name></author><author><name>Maximilian Riesenhuber</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It has been postulated the brain is organized by “metamodal”, sensory-independent cortical modules implementing particular computations. Yet, evidence for this theory has been variable. We hypothesized that effective metamodal engagement requires not only an abstract, “cognitive” congruence between cross-modal stimuli but also a congruence between neural representations. To test this hypothesis, we trained participants to recognize vibrotactile versions of auditory words using two encoding schemes. The vocoded approach preserved the dynamics and representational similarities of auditory speech while the token-based approach used an abstract phoneme-based code. Although both groups learned the vibrotactile word recognition task, only in the vocoded group did trained vibrotactile stimuli recruit the auditory speech network and lead to increased coupling between somatosensory and auditory speech areas. In contrast, the token-based encoding appeared to rely on paired-associate learning. Thus, matching neural input representations is a critical factor for assessing and leveraging the metamodal potential of cortical modules.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.07.443011</id><title>Dynamic behavioral and molecular changes induced by chronic stress exposure in mice (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.033646+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas Damien Prevot</name></author><author><name>Dipashree Chatterjee</name></author><author><name>Jaime Knoch</name></author><author><name>Sierra Codeluppi</name></author><author><name>Keith A Misquitta</name></author><author><name>Corey Fee</name></author><author><name>Dwight Newton</name></author><author><name>Hyunjung Oh</name></author><author><name>Etienne Sibille</name></author><author><name>Mounira Banasr</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Depression is a leading cause of disabilities around the world, and the underlying mechanisms involved in its pathophysiology are broad and complex. Exposure to chronic stress is a risk factor for developing depressive-symptoms and contributes to cellular and molecular changes precipitating the emergence of symptoms. In the brain, excitatory neurons, inhibitory interneurons and supporting astroglial cells are all sensitive to chronic stress exposure and are known to be impaired in depression. Using an animal model of chronic stress, we assessed the impact of variable durations of chronic stress on the emergence of behavioral deficits and associated molecular changes in the prefrontal cortex (PFC), brain region highly sensitive to stress and impaired in depression. Mice were exposed to up to 35 days of chronic restraint stress and were assessed weekly on behavioral tests measuring anxiety and anhedonia. PFC Protein and RNA levels of specific markers of excitatory, inhibitory synapses and astroglia were quantified using western blot and qPCR, respectively. Correlation and integrative network analyses were used to investigated the impact of chronic stress on the different compartments. Results showed that chronic stress induces anxiety-like behaviors within 7 days, while anhedonia-like behaviors were observed only after 35 days. At the molecular level, alterations of many markers were observed, in particular with longer exposure to chronic stress. Finally, correlation analyses and integrative network analyses revealed that male and female mice react differently to chronic stress exposure and that some markers seem to be more correlated to behaviors deficits in males than in females. Our study demonstrate that chronic induces a dynamic changes that can be observed at the behavioral and molecular levels, and that male and female mice, while exhibiting similar symptoms, have different underlying pathologies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.02.442364</id><title>Basal forebrain cholinergic neurons are part of the threat memory engram (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.033211+00:00</updated><author><name>Prithviraj Rajebhosale</name></author><author><name>Mala Ananth</name></author><author><name>Richard Crouse</name></author><author><name>Li Jiang</name></author><author><name>Gretchen López- Hernández</name></author><author><name>Christian Arty</name></author><author><name>Shaohua Wang</name></author><author><name>Alice Jone</name></author><author><name>Chongbo Zhong</name></author><author><name>Niraj S. Desai</name></author><author><name>Yulong Li</name></author><author><name>Marina R. Picciotto</name></author><author><name>Lorna W. Role</name></author><author><name>David A. Talmage</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Although the engagement of cholinergic signaling in threat memory is well established (Knox, 2016a), our finding that specific cholinergic neurons are requisite partners in a threat memory engram is likely to surprise many. Neurons of the basal forebrain nucleus basalis and substantia innominata (NBM/SI&lt;sub&gt;p&lt;/sub&gt;) comprise the major source of cholinergic input to the basolateral amygdala (BLA), whose activation are required for both the acquisition and retrieval of cued threat memory and innate threat response behavior. The retrieval of threat memory by the presentation of the conditioning tone alone elicits acetylcholine (ACh) release in the BLA and the BLA-projecting cholinergic neurons manifest immediate early gene responses and display increased intrinsic excitability for 2-5 hours following the cue-elicited memory response to the conditioned stimulus. Silencing cue-associated engram-enrolled cholinergic neurons prevents the expression of the defensive response and the subset of cholinergic neurons activated by cue is distinct from those engaged by innate threat. Taken together we find that distinct populations of cholinergic neurons are recruited to signal distinct aversive stimuli via the BLA, demonstrating exquisite, functionally refined organization of specific types of memory within the cholinergic basal forebrain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.04.442674</id><title>Functional and ultrastructural analysis of reafferent mechanosensation in larval zebrafish (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.032614+00:00</updated><author><name>Iris Odstrcil</name></author><author><name>Mariela D. Petkova</name></author><author><name>Martin Haesemeyer</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Boulanger-Weill</name></author><author><name>Maxim Nikitchenko</name></author><author><name>James A. Gagnon</name></author><author><name>Pablo Oteiza</name></author><author><name>Richard Schalek</name></author><author><name>Adi Peleg</name></author><author><name>Ruben Portugues</name></author><author><name>Jeff Lichtman</name></author><author><name>Florian Engert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;All animals need to differentiate between exafferent stimuli, which are caused by the environment, and reafferent stimuli, which are caused by their own movement. In the case of mechanosensation in aquatic animals, the exafferent inputs are water vibrations in the animal’s proximity, which need to be distinguished from the reafferent inputs arising from fluid drag due to locomotion. Both of these inputs are detected by the lateral line, a collection of mechanosensory organs distributed along the surface of the body.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this study, we characterize in detail how the hair cells, which are the receptor cells of the lateral line, discriminate between such reafferent and exafferent signals in zebrafish larvae. Using dye labeling of the lateral line nerve, we visualize two parallel descending inputs that can influence lateral line sensitivity. We combine functional imaging with ultra-structural EM circuit reconstruction to show that cholinergic signals originating from the hindbrain transmit efference copies that cancel out self-generated reafferent stimulation during locomotion, and that dopaminergic signals from the hypothalamus may have a role in threshold modulation both in response to locomotion and salient stimuli. We further gain direct mechanistic insight into the core components of this circuit by loss-of-function perturbations using targeted ablations and gene knockouts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We propose that this simple circuit is the core implementation of mechanosensory reafferent suppression in these young animals and that it might form the first instantiation of state-dependent modulation found at later stages in development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>