<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.211322+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466401</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 spike protein as a bacterial lipopolysaccharide delivery system in an overzealous inflammatory cascade (58 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.222312+00:00</updated><author><name>Firdaus Samsudin</name></author><author><name>Palur Raghuvamsi</name></author><author><name>Ganna Petruk</name></author><author><name>Manoj Puthia</name></author><author><name>Jitka Petrlova</name></author><author><name>Paul MacAry</name></author><author><name>Ganesh S Anand</name></author><author><name>Artur Schmidtchen</name></author><author><name>Peter J Bond</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Accumulating evidence indicates a potential role for bacterial lipopolysaccharide (LPS) in the overactivation of the immune response during SARS-CoV-2 infection. LPS is recognised by Toll-like receptor 4 (TLR4) in innate immunity. Here, we showed that LPS binds to multiple hydrophobic pockets spanning both the S1 and S2 subunits of the SARS-CoV-2 spike (S) protein. LPS binds to the S2 pocket with a lower affinity compared to S1, suggesting its possible role as an intermediate in the TLR4 cascade. Congruently, nuclear factor-kappa B (NF-κB) activation in vitro is strongly boosted by S2. In vivo, however, a boosting effect is observed for both S1 and S2, with the former potentially facilitated by proteolysis. Collectively, our study suggests the S protein may act as a delivery system for LPS in host innate immune pathways. The LPS binding pockets are highly conserved across different SARS-CoV-2 variants and therefore represent potential therapeutic targets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466401" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 spike protein as a bacterial lipopolysaccharide delivery system in an overzealous inflammatory cascade (58 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.21265525</id><title>COVCOG 1: Factors predicting Cognitive Symptoms in Long COVID. A First Publication from the COVID and Cognition Study (58 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.222883+00:00</updated><author><name>Panyuan Guo</name></author><author><name>Alvaro Benito Ballesteros</name></author><author><name>Sabine P Yeung</name></author><author><name>Ruby Liu</name></author><author><name>Arka Saha</name></author><author><name>Lyn Curtis</name></author><author><name>Muzaffer Kaser</name></author><author><name>Mark P Haggard</name></author><author><name>Lucy G Cheke</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Since its first emergence in December 2019, coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), has evolved into a global pandemic. Whilst often considered a respiratory disease, a large proportion of COVID-19 patients report neurological symptoms, and there is accumulating evidence for neural damage in some individuals, with recent studies suggesting loss of gray matter in multiple regions, particularly in the left hemisphere. There are a number of mechanisms by which COVID-19 infection may lead to neurological symptoms and structural and functional changes in the brain, and it is reasonable to expect that many of these may translate into cognitive problems. Indeed, cognitive problems are one of the most commonly reported symptoms in those suffering from “Long COVID”—the chronic illness following COVID-19 infection that affects between 10–25% of sufferers. The COVID and Cognition Study is a part cross-sectional, part longitudinal, study documenting and aiming to understand the cognitive problems in Long COVID. In this first paper from the study, we document the characteristics of our sample of 181 individuals who had suffered COVID-19 infection, and 185 who had not. We explore which factors may be predictive of ongoing symptoms and their severity, as well as conducting an in-depth analysis of symptom profiles. Finally, we explore which factors predict the presence and severity of cognitive symptoms, both throughout the ongoing illness and at the time of testing. The main finding from this first analysis is that that severity of initial illness is a significant predictor of the presence and severity of ongoing symptoms, and that some symptoms during the acute illness—particularly limb weakness—may be more common in those that have more severe ongoing symptoms. Symptom profiles can be well described in terms of 5 or 6 factors, reflecting the variety of this highly heterogenous condition suffered by the individual. Specifically, we found that neurological and fatigue symptoms during the initial illness, and that neurological, gastro-intestinal, and cardiopulmonary symptoms during the ongoing illness, predicted experience of cognitive symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.21265525" rel="alternate" title="COVCOG 1: Factors predicting Cognitive Symptoms in Long COVID. A First Publication from the COVID and Cognition Study (58 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466055</id><title>Phylogenetic analysis and in silico studies link spike Q675H mutation to SARS-CoV-2 adaptive evolution (54 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.223584+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna Bertelli</name></author><author><name>Pasqualina D'Ursi</name></author><author><name>Giovanni Campisi</name></author><author><name>Serena Messali</name></author><author><name>Maria Milanesi</name></author><author><name>Marta Giovanetti</name></author><author><name>Massimo Ciccozzi</name></author><author><name>Francesca Caccuri</name></author><author><name>Arnaldo Caruso</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genotype screening was implemented in Italy and showed a significant prevalence of new SARS-CoV-2 mutants carrying Q675H mutation, near the furin cleavage site of spike protein. Currently, this mutation, which is expressed on different SARS-CoV-2 lineages circulating worldwide, has not been thoughtfully investigated. Therefore, we performed phylogenetic and biocomputational analysis to better understand SARS-CoV-2 Q675H mutants evolutionary relationships with other circulating lineages and Q675H function in its molecular context. Our studies reveal that Q675H spike mutation is the result of parallel evolution because it arose independently in separate evolutionary clades. In silico data show that the Q675H mutation gives rise to a hydrogen-bonds network in the spike polar region delimiting the conformational space of the highly flexible loop containing the furin cleavage site. This results in an optimized directionality of arginine residues involved in interaction of spike with the furin binding pocket, thus improving proteolytic exposure of the viral protein. Furin was found to have a greater affinity for Q675H than Q675 substrate conformations. As a consequence, Q675H mutation is likely to confer a fitness advantage to SARS-CoV-2 by promoting a more efficient viral entry. Interestingly, here we show an ongoing increase in the occurrence of Q675H spike mutation in the most common SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (VOC). This finding highlights that, VOC are still evolving and start acquiring the Q675H mutation. At the same time, it suggests that our hypothesis of fitness advantage prompted by Q675H could be concrete.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466055" rel="alternate" title="Phylogenetic analysis and in silico studies link spike Q675H mutation to SARS-CoV-2 adaptive evolution (54 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.21265511</id><title>Blood cytokine analysis suggests that SARS-CoV-2 infection results in a sustained tumour promoting environment in cancer patients (53 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.224866+00:00</updated><author><name>Fien HR De Winter</name></author><author><name>An Hotterbeekx</name></author><author><name>Manon Huizing</name></author><author><name>Angelina Konnova</name></author><author><name>Erik Fransen</name></author><author><name>Bart 's Jongers</name></author><author><name>Ravi Kumar Jairam</name></author><author><name>Vincent Van averbeke</name></author><author><name>Pieter Moons</name></author><author><name>Ella Roelant</name></author><author><name>Debbie Le Blon</name></author><author><name>Wim Vanden Berghe</name></author><author><name>Annelies Janssens</name></author><author><name>Willem Lybaert</name></author><author><name>Lieselot Croes</name></author><author><name>Christof Vulsteke</name></author><author><name>Surbhi Malhotra-Kumar</name></author><author><name>Herman Goossens</name></author><author><name>Zwi Berneman</name></author><author><name>Marc Peeters</name></author><author><name>Peter van Dam</name></author><author><name>Samir Kumar-Singh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cytokines, chemokines and (angiogenic) growth factors (CCGs) have been shown to play an intricate role in the progression of both solid and haematological malignancies. Recent studies have shown that SARS-CoV-2 infection leads to worse outcome in cancer patients, especially in haematological malignancy patients. Here, we investigated how SARS-CoV-2 infection impacts the already altered CCG levels in solid or haematological malignancies, specifically whether there is a protective effect or rather a potentially higher risk for major COVID-19 complications in cancer patients due to elevated CCGs linked to cancer progression. Serially analysing immune responses with 55 CCGs in cancer patients under active treatment with or without SARS-CoV-2 infection, we first showed that cancer patients without SARS-CoV-2 infection (n=54) demonstrate elevated levels of 35 CCGs compared to the non-cancer, non-infected control group of health care workers (n=42). Of the 35 CCGs, 19 were common to both solid and haematological malignancy groups and comprised previously described cytokines such as IL-6, TNF-α, IL-1Ra, IL-17A, and VEGF, but also several less well described cytokines/chemokines such as Fractalkine, Tie-2, and T cell chemokine CTACK. Importantly, we show here that 7 CCGs are significantly altered in SARS-CoV-2 exposed cancer patients (n=52). Of these TNF-α, IFN-β, TSLP and sVCAM-1, identified to be elevated in haematological cancers, are also known tumour-promoting factors. Longitudinal analysis conducted over 3 months showed persistence of several tumour-promoting CCGs in SARS-CoV-2 exposed cancer patients. These data urge for increased vigilance for haematological malignancy patients as a part of long COVID follow-up.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.21265511" rel="alternate" title="Blood cytokine analysis suggests that SARS-CoV-2 infection results in a sustained tumour promoting environment in cancer patients (53 tweets)"/><category term="Oncology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465865</id><title>Excessive inflammatory and metabolic responses to acute SARS-CoV-2 infection are associated with a distinct gut microbiota composition (41 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.226268+00:00</updated><author><name>Werner C. Albrich</name></author><author><name>Tarini Shankar Ghosh</name></author><author><name>Sinead Ahearn-Ford</name></author><author><name>Flora Mikaeloff</name></author><author><name>Nonhlanhla Lunjani</name></author><author><name>Brian Forde</name></author><author><name>Noémie Suh</name></author><author><name>Gian-Reto Kleger</name></author><author><name>Urs Pietsch</name></author><author><name>Manuel Frischknecht</name></author><author><name>Christian Garzoni</name></author><author><name>Rossella Forlenza</name></author><author><name>Mary Horgan</name></author><author><name>Corinna Sadlier</name></author><author><name>Tommaso Rochat Negro</name></author><author><name>Jérôme Pugin</name></author><author><name>Hannah Wozniak</name></author><author><name>Andreas Cerny</name></author><author><name>Ujjwal Neogi</name></author><author><name>Paul W. O’Toole</name></author><author><name>Liam O’Mahony</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protection against severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection and associated clinical sequelae requires well-coordinated metabolic and immune responses that limit viral spread and promote recovery of damaged systems. In order to understand potential mechanisms and interactions that influence coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) outcomes, we performed a multi-omics analysis on hospitalised COVID-19 patients and compared those with the most severe outcome (i.e. death) to those with severe non-fatal disease, or mild/moderate disease, that recovered. A distinct subset of 8 cytokines and 140 metabolites in sera identified those with a fatal outcome to infection. In addition, elevated levels of multiple pathobionts and lower levels of protective or anti-inflammatory microbes were observed in the faecal microbiome of those with the poorest clinical outcomes. Weighted gene correlation network analysis (WGCNA) identified modules that associated severity-associated cytokines with tryptophan metabolism, coagulation-linked fibrinopeptides, and bile acids with multiple pathobionts. In contrast, less severe clinical outcomes associated with clusters of anti-inflammatory microbes such as &lt;italic&gt;Bifidobacterium&lt;/italic&gt; or &lt;italic&gt;Ruminococcus&lt;/italic&gt;, short chain fatty acids (SCFAs) and IL-17A. Our study uncovered distinct mechanistic modules that link host and microbiome processes with fatal outcomes to SARS-CoV-2 infection. These features may be useful to identify at risk individuals, but also highlight a role for the microbiome in modifying hyperinflammatory responses to SARS-CoV-2 and other infectious agents.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465865" rel="alternate" title="Excessive inflammatory and metabolic responses to acute SARS-CoV-2 infection are associated with a distinct gut microbiota composition (41 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466163</id><title>Prime-boost vaccination regimens with INO-4800 and INO-4802 augment and broaden immune responses against SARS-CoV-2 in nonhuman primates (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.226901+00:00</updated><author><name>Jewell N Walters</name></author><author><name>Blake Schouest</name></author><author><name>Ami Patel</name></author><author><name>Emma L Reuschel</name></author><author><name>Katherine Schultheis</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Parzych</name></author><author><name>Igor Maricic</name></author><author><name>Ebony N Gary</name></author><author><name>Mansi Purwar</name></author><author><name>Viviane M Andrade</name></author><author><name>Arthur Doan</name></author><author><name>Dustin Elwood</name></author><author><name>Zeena Eblimit</name></author><author><name>Brian Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Drew Frase</name></author><author><name>Faraz I Zaidi</name></author><author><name>Abhijeet Kulkarni</name></author><author><name>Alison Generotti</name></author><author><name>J Joseph Kim</name></author><author><name>Laurent M Humeau</name></author><author><name>Stephanie J Ramos</name></author><author><name>Trevor R.F. Smith</name></author><author><name>David B Weiner</name></author><author><name>Kate E Broderick</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The enhanced transmissibility and immune evasion associated with emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants demands the development of next-generation vaccines capable of inducing superior protection amid a shifting pandemic landscape. Since a portion of the global population harbors some level of immunity from vaccines based on the original Wuhan-Hu-1 SARS-CoV-2 sequence or natural infection, an important question going forward is whether this immunity can be boosted by next-generation vaccines that target emerging variants while simultaneously maintaining long-term protection against existing strains. Here, we evaluated the immunogenicity of INO-4800, our synthetic DNA vaccine candidate for COVID-19 currently in clinical evaluation, and INO-4802, a next-generation DNA vaccine designed to broadly target emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants, as booster vaccines in nonhuman primates. Rhesus macaques primed over one year prior with the first-generation INO-4800 vaccine were boosted with either INO-4800 or INO-4802 in homologous or heterologous prime-boost regimens. Both boosting schedules led to an expansion of antibody responses which were characterized by improved neutralizing and ACE2 blocking activity across wild-type SARS-CoV-2 as well as multiple variants of concern. These data illustrate the durability of immunity following vaccination with INO-4800 and additionally support the use of either INO-4800 or INO-4802 in prime-boost regimens.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466163" rel="alternate" title="Prime-boost vaccination regimens with INO-4800 and INO-4802 augment and broaden immune responses against SARS-CoV-2 in nonhuman primates (37 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.21265476</id><title>A “Made-in-Canada” serology solution for profiling humoral immune responses to SARS-CoV-2 infection and vaccination (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.228970+00:00</updated><author><name>Karen Colwill</name></author><author><name>Yannick Galipeau</name></author><author><name>Matthew Stuible</name></author><author><name>Christian Gervais</name></author><author><name>Corey Arnold</name></author><author><name>Bhavisha Rathod</name></author><author><name>Kento T. Abe</name></author><author><name>Jenny H. Wang</name></author><author><name>Adrian Pasculescu</name></author><author><name>Mariam Maltseva</name></author><author><name>Lynda Rocheleau</name></author><author><name>Martin Pelchat</name></author><author><name>Mahya Fazel-Zarandi</name></author><author><name>Mariam Iskilova</name></author><author><name>Miriam Barrios-Rodiles</name></author><author><name>Linda Bennett</name></author><author><name>Kevin Yau</name></author><author><name>François Cholette</name></author><author><name>Christine Mesa</name></author><author><name>Angel X. Li</name></author><author><name>Aimee Paterson</name></author><author><name>Michelle A. Hladunewich</name></author><author><name>Pamela J. Goodwin</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey L. Wrana</name></author><author><name>Steven J. Drews</name></author><author><name>Samira Mubareka</name></author><author><name>Allison J. McGeer</name></author><author><name>John Kim</name></author><author><name>Marc-André Langlois</name></author><author><name>Anne-Claude Gingras</name></author><author><name>Yves Durocher</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Testing for antibodies against severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) has been instrumental in detecting previous exposures and analyzing vaccine-elicited immune responses. Here, we describe a scalable “Made-in-Canada” solution that can detect and quantify SARS-CoV-2 antibodies, discriminate between natural infection- and vaccination-induced responses, and assess antibody-mediated inhibition of the spike-angiotensin converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) interaction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;METHODS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We developed a set of methods and reagents to detect SARS-CoV-2 antibodies by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA). The main assays focus on the parallel detection of immunoglobulin (Ig)Gs against the spike trimer, its receptor binding domain (RBD), and the nucleocapsid (N) protein. These antigens are complemented by a detection antibody (human anti-IgG fused to horseradish peroxidase (HRP)) and a positive control reference antibody (recombinant IgG against the RBD), permitting intra- and inter-laboratory comparisons. Using this toolkit and commercial reagents, we optimized automated ELISAs on two different high throughput platforms to measure antibody responses to SARS-CoV-2 antigens. The assays were calibrated to a reference standard from the World Health Organization. We also automated a surrogate neutralization (sn)ELISA that measures inhibition of ACE2-Spike or -RBD interactions by antibodies using biotinylated ACE2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;RESULTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our individual IgG-based ELISAs measure antibody levels in single-point measurements in reference to a standard antibody curve to accurately distinguish non-infected and infected individuals (area under the curve &amp;gt; 0.96 for each assay). Positivity thresholds can be established in individual assays using precision-recall analysis (e.g., by fixing the false positive rate), or more stringently, by scoring against the distribution of the means of negative samples across multiple assays performed over several months. For seroprevalence assessment (in a non-vaccinated cohort), classifying a sample as positive if antibodies were detected for at least 2 of the 3 antigens provided the highest specificity. In vaccinated cohorts, increases in anti-spike and -RBD (but not -N) antibodies are observed. Here, we present detailed protocols to perform these assays using either serum/plasma or dried blood spots both manually and on two automated platforms, and to express the results in international units to facilitate data harmonization and inter-study comparisons. We also demonstrate that the snELISA can be performed automatically at single points, increasing the scalability of this functional assay for large seroprevalence studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;INTERPRETATION&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ability to measure antibodies to three viral antigens and identify neutralizing antibodies capable of disrupting spike-ACE2 interactions in high-throughput assays enables large-scale analyses of humoral immune responses to SARS-CoV-2 infection and vaccination. The “Made-in-Canada” set of protein reagents, produced at the National Research Council of Canada are publicly available to enable the up-scaling of standardized serological assays, permitting nationwide data comparison and aggregation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.21265476" rel="alternate" title="A “Made-in-Canada” serology solution for profiling humoral immune responses to SARS-CoV-2 infection and vaccination (37 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466408</id><title>The glycosylated extracellular domain of MUC1 protects against SARS-CoV-2 infection at the respiratory surface (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.229652+00:00</updated><author><name>Maitrayee Chatterjee</name></author><author><name>Liane Z.X Huang</name></author><author><name>Chunyan Wang</name></author><author><name>Anna Z Mykytyn</name></author><author><name>Bart Westendorp</name></author><author><name>Richard W Wubbolts</name></author><author><name>Berend Jan Bosch</name></author><author><name>Bart Haagmans</name></author><author><name>Jos P.M van Putten</name></author><author><name>Karin Strijbis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mucins play an essential role in protecting the respiratory tract against microbial infections. The heavily O-glycosylated gel-forming mucins MUC5AC and MUC5B eliminate pathogens by mucociliary clearance while transmembrane mucins MUC1, MUC4, and MUC16 restrict microbial invasion at the apical surface of the epithelium. In this study, we determined the impact of host mucins and mucin glycans on SARS-CoV-2 spike-mediated epithelial entry. Human lung epithelial Calu-3 cells have endogenous expression of the SARS-CoV-2 entry receptor ACE2 and express high levels of glycosylated MUC1 on the surface but not MUC4 and MUC16. Removal of the MUC1 extracellular domain (ED) using the O-glycan-specific mucinase StcE greatly enhanced spike binding and viral infection. By contrast, removal of mucin glycans sialic acid and fucose did not impact viral invasion. This study implicates the glycosylated ED of MUC1 as an important component of the host defense that restricts the severity of SARS-CoV-2 infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466408" rel="alternate" title="The glycosylated extracellular domain of MUC1 protects against SARS-CoV-2 infection at the respiratory surface (20 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466206</id><title>A multi-tissue study of immune gene expression profiling highlights the key role of the nasal epithelium in COVID-19 severity (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.230011+00:00</updated><author><name>Alberto Gomez-Carballa</name></author><author><name>Irene Rivero-Calle</name></author><author><name>Jacobo Pardo-Seco</name></author><author><name>Jose Gomez-Rial</name></author><author><name>Carmen Rivero-Velasco</name></author><author><name>Nuria Rodriguez-Nunez</name></author><author><name>Gema Barbeito-Castineiras</name></author><author><name>Hugo Perez-Freixo</name></author><author><name>Miriam Cebey-Lopez</name></author><author><name>Ruth Barral-Arca</name></author><author><name>Carmen Rodriguez-Tenreiro</name></author><author><name>Ana Dacosta-Urbieta</name></author><author><name>Xabier Bello</name></author><author><name>Sara Pischedda</name></author><author><name>Maria Jose Curras-Tuala</name></author><author><name>Sandra Viz-Lasheras</name></author><author><name>Federico Martinon-Torres</name></author><author><name>Antonio Salas</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: COVID-19 symptoms range from mild to severe illness; the cause for this differential response to infection remains unknown. Unravelling the immune mechanisms acting at different levels of the colonization process might be key to understand these differences. Methods and findings: We carried out a multi-tissue (nasal, buccal and blood; n = 156) gene expression analysis of immune-related genes from patients affected by different COVID-19 severities, and healthy controls through the nCounter technology. We then used a differential expression approach and pathways analysis to detect tissue specific immune severity signals in COVID-19 patients. Mild and asymptomatic cases showed a powerful innate antiviral response in nasal epithelium, characterized by activation of interferon (IFN) pathway and downstream cascades, successfully controlling the infection at local level. In contrast, weak macrophage/monocyte driven innate antiviral response and lack of IFN signalling activity were shown in severe cases. Consequently, oral mucosa from severe patients showed signals of viral activity, cell arresting and viral dissemination to the lower respiratory tract, which ultimately could explain the exacerbated innate immune response and impaired adaptative immune responses observed at systemic level. Results from saliva transcriptome suggest that the buccal cavity might play a key role in SARS-CoV-2 infection and dissemination in patients with worse prognosis. Conclusions: We found severity-related signatures in patient tissues mainly represented by genes involved in the innate immune system and cytokine/chemokine signalling. Local immune response could be key to determine the course of the systemic response and thus COVID-19 severity. Our findings provide a framework to investigate severity host gene biomarkers and pathways that might be relevant to diagnosis, prognosis, and therapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466206" rel="alternate" title="A multi-tissue study of immune gene expression profiling highlights the key role of the nasal epithelium in COVID-19 severity (19 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265616</id><title>Risk factors for severe PCR-positive SARS-CoV-2 infection in hospitalized children: a multicenter cohort study (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.230475+00:00</updated><author><name>Tilmann Schober</name></author><author><name>Chelsea Caya</name></author><author><name>Michelle Barton</name></author><author><name>Ann Bayliss</name></author><author><name>Ari Bitnun</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Bowes</name></author><author><name>Helena Brenes-Chacon</name></author><author><name>Jared Bullard</name></author><author><name>Suzette Cooke</name></author><author><name>Tammie Dewan</name></author><author><name>Rachel Dwilow</name></author><author><name>Tala El Tal</name></author><author><name>Cheryl Foo</name></author><author><name>Peter Gill</name></author><author><name>Behzad Haghighi Aski</name></author><author><name>Fatima Kakkar</name></author><author><name>Janell Lautermilch</name></author><author><name>Ronald M. Laxer</name></author><author><name>Marie-Astrid Lefebvre</name></author><author><name>Kirk Leifso</name></author><author><name>Nicole Le Saux</name></author><author><name>Alison Lopez</name></author><author><name>Ali Manafi</name></author><author><name>Shaun K. Morris</name></author><author><name>Alireza Nateghian</name></author><author><name>Luc Panetta</name></author><author><name>Dara Petel</name></author><author><name>Dominique Piche</name></author><author><name>Rupeena Purewal</name></author><author><name>Lea Restivo</name></author><author><name>Ashley Roberts</name></author><author><name>Manish Sadarangani</name></author><author><name>Rosie Scuccimarri</name></author><author><name>Alejandra Soriano-Fallas</name></author><author><name>Sarah Tehseen</name></author><author><name>Karina A. Top</name></author><author><name>Rolando Ulloa-Gutierrez</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Viel-Theriaul</name></author><author><name>Jacqueline K. Wong</name></author><author><name>Carmen Yea</name></author><author><name>Ann Yeh</name></author><author><name>Adriana Yock-Corrales</name></author><author><name>Joan Robinson</name></author><author><name>Jesse Papenburg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Importance: Children are less likely than adults to have severe outcomes from SARS-CoV-2 infection and the corresponding risk factors are not well established. 
Objective: To identify risk factors for severe disease in symptomatic children hospitalized for PCR-positive SARS-CoV-2 infection.
Design: Cohort study, enrollment from February 1, 2020 until May 31, 2021
Setting 15 children's hospitals in Canada, Iran, and Costa Rica
Participants: Patients &amp;lt;18 years of age hospitalized with symptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection, including PCR-positive multisystem inflammatory syndrome in children (MIS-C)
Exposures: Variables assessed for their association with disease severity included patient demographics, presence of comorbidities, clinical manifestations, laboratory parameters and chest imaging findings.
Main Outcomes and Measures: The primary outcome was severe disease defined as a WHO COVID-19 clinical progression scale of ≥6, i.e., requirement of non-invasive ventilation, high flow nasal cannula, mechanical ventilation, vasopressors, or death. Multivariable logistic regression was used to evaluate factors associated with severe disease.
Results: We identified 403 hospitalizations. Median age was 3.78 years (IQR 0.53-10.77). At least one comorbidity was present in 46.4% (187/403) and multiple comorbidities in 18.6% (75/403). Severe disease occurred in 33.8% (102/403). In multivariable analyses, presence of multiple comorbidities (adjusted odds ratio 2.24, 95% confidence interval 1.04-4.81), obesity (2.87, 1.19-6.93), neurological disorder (3.22, 1.37-7.56), anemia, and/or hemoglobinopathy (5.88, 1.30-26.46), shortness of breath (4.37, 2.08-9.16), bacterial and/or viral coinfections (2.26, 1.08-4.73), chest imaging compatible with COVID-19 (2.99, 1.51-5.92), neutrophilia (2.60, 1.35-5.02), and MIS-C diagnosis (3.86, 1.56-9.51) were independent risk factors for severity. Comorbidities, especially obesity (40.9% vs 3.9%, p&amp;lt;0.001), were more frequently present in adolescents ≥12 years of age. Neurological disorder (3.16, 1.19-8.43) in children &amp;lt;12 years of age and obesity (3.21, 1.15-8.93) in adolescents were the specific comorbidities associated with disease severity in age-stratified adjusted analyses. Sensitivity analyses excluding the 81 cases with MIS-C did not substantially change the identified risk factors. 
Conclusions and Relevance: Pediatric risk factors for severe SARS-CoV-2 infection vary according to age and can potentially guide vaccination programs and treatment approaches in children.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265616" rel="alternate" title="Risk factors for severe PCR-positive SARS-CoV-2 infection in hospitalized children: a multicenter cohort study (19 tweets)"/><category term="Pediatrics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265499</id><title>Time of day of vaccination affects SARS-CoV-2 antibody responses in an observational study of healthcare workers (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.231570+00:00</updated><author><name>Wei Wang</name></author><author><name>Peter Balfe</name></author><author><name>David W Eyre</name></author><author><name>Sheila F Lumley</name></author><author><name>Denise O'Donnell</name></author><author><name>Fiona Warren</name></author><author><name>Derrick W Crook</name></author><author><name>Katie Jeffery</name></author><author><name>Philippa C Matthews</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth B Klerman</name></author><author><name>Jane McKeating</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) is a global crisis with unprecedented challenges for public health. Vaccinations against SARS-CoV-2 have slowed the incidence of new infections and reduced disease severity. As the time-of-day of vaccination has been reported to influence host immune responses to multiple pathogens, we quantified the influence of SARS-CoV-2 vaccination time, vaccine type, age, sex, and days post-vaccination on anti-Spike antibody responses in healthcare workers. The magnitude of the anti-Spike antibody response associated with the time-of-day of vaccination, vaccine type, participant age, sex, and days post vaccination. These results may be relevant for optimizing SARS-CoV-2 vaccine efficacy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265499" rel="alternate" title="Time of day of vaccination affects SARS-CoV-2 antibody responses in an observational study of healthcare workers (16 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466298</id><title>Identification of COVID-19 and COPD common key genes and pathways using a protein-protein interaction approach (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.232101+00:00</updated><author><name>Thiviya S. Thambiraja</name></author><author><name>Kalimuthu Karuppanan</name></author><author><name>Gunasekaran Subramaniam</name></author><author><name>Suresh Kumar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) is an extremely contagious and cognitive disease that could cause immense hypoxemia. The rise in critically ill patients in epidemic regions has put enormous pressure on hospitals. There is a need to define extreme COVID- 19 clinical determinants to optimize clinical diagnosis and the management system is strong. Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is linked to a rapidly increasing risk of death rates in population pneumonia. In this research, a network of protein-protein interaction (PPI) was developed using constructed datasets of COVID-19 and COPD genes to define the interrelationship between COVID-19 and COPD, how it affects each other, and the genes that are responsible for the process. The PPI network shows the top 10 common overlapping genes, which include IL10, TLR4, TNF, IL6, CXCL8, IL4, ICAM1, IFNG, TLR2, and IL18. These are the genes that COVID-19 and high-risk COPD patients are known to be expressed. These important genes shared by COVID-19 and COPD are involved in pathways such as malaria, African trypanosomiasis, inflammatory bowel disease, Chagas disease, influenza, and tuberculosis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466298" rel="alternate" title="Identification of COVID-19 and COPD common key genes and pathways using a protein-protein interaction approach (12 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.21265261</id><title>Safety Monitoring of mRNA Vaccines Administered During the Initial 6 Months of the U.S. COVID-19 Vaccination Program: Reports to Vaccine Adverse Events Reporting System (VAERS) and v-safe (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.232498+00:00</updated><author><name>Hannah G. Rosenblum</name></author><author><name>Julianne M. Gee</name></author><author><name>Ruiling Liu</name></author><author><name>Paige L. Marquez</name></author><author><name>Bicheng Zhang</name></author><author><name>Penelope Strid</name></author><author><name>Winston E. Abara</name></author><author><name>Michael M. McNeil</name></author><author><name>Tanya R. Myers</name></author><author><name>Anne M. Hause</name></author><author><name>John R. Su</name></author><author><name>Bethany Baer</name></author><author><name>David Menschik</name></author><author><name>Lauri E. Markowitz</name></author><author><name>Tom T. Shimabukuro</name></author><author><name>David K. Shay</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In December 2020, two mRNA-based COVID-19 vaccines were authorized for use in the United States. Vaccine safety was monitored using the Vaccine Adverse Event Reporting System (VAERS), a passive surveillance system, and v-safe, an active surveillance system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;VAERS and v-safe data during December 14, 2020—June 14, 2021 were analyzed. VAERS reports were categorized as non-serious, serious, or death; reporting rates were calculated. Rates of reported deaths were compared to expected mortality rates by age. Proportions of v-safe participants reporting local and systemic reactions or health impacts the week following doses 1 and 2 were determined.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the analytic period, 298,792,852 doses of mRNA vaccines were administered in the United States. VAERS processed 340,522 reports; 92·1% were non-serious; 6·6%, serious, non-death; and 1·3%, death. Over half of 7,914,583 v-safe participants self-reported local and systemic reactogenicity, more frequently after dose 2. Injection-site pain, fatigue, and headache were commonly reported during days 0–7 following vaccination. Reactogenicity was reported most frequently one day after vaccination; most reactions were mild. More reports of being unable to work or do normal activities occurred after dose 2 (32·1%) than dose 1 (11·9%); &amp;lt;1% of participants reported seeking medical care after vaccination. Rates of deaths reported to VAERS were lower than expected background rates by age group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Safety data from &amp;gt;298 million doses of mRNA COVID-19 vaccine administered in the first 6 months of the U.S. vaccination program show the majority of reported adverse events were mild and short in duration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.21265261" rel="alternate" title="Safety Monitoring of mRNA Vaccines Administered During the Initial 6 Months of the U.S. COVID-19 Vaccination Program: Reports to Vaccine Adverse Events Reporting System (VAERS) and v-safe (11 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.465226</id><title>A Potential Novel COVID-19 Vaccine With RBD-HR1/HR2 Hexamer Structure (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.234132+00:00</updated><author><name>Hongbo Liu</name></author><author><name>Xiang Gao</name></author><author><name>Guoyong Wang</name></author><author><name>Jianjun Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jiajie Zhou</name></author><author><name>Tingting Wei</name></author><author><name>Yu Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yujiao Liu</name></author><author><name>Jinhua Piao</name></author><author><name>Qiulei Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yayuan Wang</name></author><author><name>Xin Ma</name></author><author><name>Xiaoting Zhu</name></author><author><name>Yikun Rao</name></author><author><name>Wenjuan Xia</name></author><author><name>Heng Xie</name></author><author><name>Wei Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic and the continued spreading of the SARS-CoV-2 variants have brought a grave public health consequence and severely devastated the global economy with recessions. Vaccination is considered as one of the most promising and efficient methods to end the COVID-19 pandemic and mitigate the disease conditions if infected. Although a few vaccines have been developed with an unprecedented speed, scientists around the world are continuing pursuing the best possible vaccines with innovations. Comparing to the expensive mRNA vaccines and attenuated/inactivated SARS-CoV-2 vaccines, recombinant protein vaccines have certain advantages, including their safety (non-virus components), potential stronger immunogenicity, broader protection, ease of scaling-up production, reduced cost, etc. In this study, we reported a novel COVID-19 vaccine generated with RBD-HR1/HR2 hexamer that was creatively fused with the RBD domain and heptad repeat 1 (HR1) or heptad repeat 2 (HR2) to form a dumbbell-shaped hexamer to target the spike S1 subunit. The novel hexamer COVID-19 vaccine induced high titers of neutralizing antibody in mouse studies (&amp;gt;100,000), and further experiments also showed that the vaccine also induced an alternative antibody to the HR1 region, which probably alleviated the drop of immunogenicity from the frequent mutations of SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.465226" rel="alternate" title="A Potential Novel COVID-19 Vaccine With RBD-HR1/HR2 Hexamer Structure (10 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.21265456</id><title>Trends in social exposure to SARS-Cov-2 in France. Evidence from the national socio-epidemiological cohort – EPICOV (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.234802+00:00</updated><author><name>Josiane Warszawski</name></author><author><name>Laurence Meyer</name></author><author><name>Jeanna-Eve Franck</name></author><author><name>Delphine Rahib</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Lydié</name></author><author><name>Anne Gosselin</name></author><author><name>Emilie Counil</name></author><author><name>Robin Kreling</name></author><author><name>Sophie Novelli</name></author><author><name>Remy Slama</name></author><author><name>Philippe Raynaud</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Bagein</name></author><author><name>Vianney Costemalle</name></author><author><name>Patrick Sillard</name></author><author><name>Toscane Fourie</name></author><author><name>Xavier de Lamballerie</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Bajos</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We aimed to study whether social patterns of exposure to SARS-CoV-2 infection changed in France throughout the year 2020, in light to the easing of social contact restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A population-based cohort of individuals aged 15 years or over was randomly selected from the national tax register to collect socio-economic data, migration history, and living conditions in May and November 2020. Home self-sampling on dried blood was proposed to a 10% random subsample in May and to all in November. A positive anti-SARS-CoV-2 ELISA IgG result against the virus spike protein (ELISA-S) was the primary outcome. The design, including sampling and post-stratification weights, was taken into account in univariate and multivariate analyses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of the 134,391 participants in May, 107,759 completed the second questionnaire in November, and respectively 12,114 and 63,524 were tested. The national ELISA-S seroprevalence was 4.5% [95%CI: 4.0%-5.1%] in May and 6.2% [5.9%-6.6%] in November. It increased markedly in 18-24-year-old population from 4.8% to 10.0%, and among second-generation immigrants from outside Europe from 5.9% to 14.4%. This group remained strongly associated with seropositivity in November, after controlling for any contextual or individual variables, with an adjusted OR of 2.1 [1.7-2.7], compared to the majority population. In both periods, seroprevalence remained higher in healthcare professions than in other occupations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The risk of Covid-19 infection increased among young people and second-generation migrants between the first and second epidemic waves, in a context of less strict social restrictions, which seems to have reinforced territorialized socialization among peers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.21265456" rel="alternate" title="Trends in social exposure to SARS-Cov-2 in France. Evidence from the national socio-epidemiological cohort – EPICOV (8 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.21265422</id><title>Limited impact of Delta variant’s mutations in the effectiveness of neutralization conferred by natural infection or COVID-19 vaccines in a Latino population (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.237018+00:00</updated><author><name>Carlos A. Sariol</name></author><author><name>Crisanta Serrano-Collazo</name></author><author><name>Edwin J. Ortiz</name></author><author><name>Petraleigh Pantoja</name></author><author><name>Lorna Cruz</name></author><author><name>Teresa Arana</name></author><author><name>Dianne Atehortua</name></author><author><name>Christina Pabon-Carrero</name></author><author><name>Ana M. Espino</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The SARS-CoV-2 pandemic has impacted public health systems all over the world. The Delta variant seems to possess enhanced transmissibility, but no clear evidence suggests it has increased virulence. Our data shows that pre-exposed individuals had similar neutralizing activity against the authentic COVID-19 strain and the Delta and Epsilon variants. After one vaccine dose, the neutralization capacity expands to all tested variants. Healthy vaccinated individuals showed a limited breadth of neutralization. One vaccine dose induced similar neutralizing antibodies against the Delta compared to the authentic strain. However, even after two doses, this capacity only expanded to the Epsilon variant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.21265422" rel="alternate" title="Limited impact of Delta variant’s mutations in the effectiveness of neutralization conferred by natural infection or COVID-19 vaccines in a Latino population (7 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.21265248</id><title>Safety and immunogenicity of a high-dose quadrivalent influenza vaccine administered concomitantly with a third dose of the mRNA-1273 SARS-CoV-2 vaccine in adults ≥ 65 years of age: a Phase II, open-label study (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.237636+00:00</updated><author><name>Ruvim Izikson</name></author><author><name>Daniel Brune</name></author><author><name>Jean-Sébastien Bolduc</name></author><author><name>Pierre Bourron</name></author><author><name>Marion Fournier</name></author><author><name>Tamala Mallett Moore</name></author><author><name>Aseem Pandey</name></author><author><name>Lucia Perez</name></author><author><name>Nessryne Sater</name></author><author><name>Anju Shrestha</name></author><author><name>Sophie Wague</name></author><author><name>Sandrine I Samson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;Background&lt;/bold&gt;

Concomitant seasonal influenza vaccination with a COVID-19 vaccine booster could help to minimise potential disruption to the seasonal influenza vaccination campaign and maximise protection against both diseases among individuals at risk of severe disease and hospitalisation. This study assesses the safety and immunogenicity of concomitant administration of high-dose quadrivalent influenza vaccine (QIV-HD) and a mRNA-1273 vaccine booster dose in older adults.

&lt;bold&gt;Methods&lt;/bold&gt;

This is an ongoing Phase II, multi-centre, open-label study (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT04969276"&gt;NCT04969276&lt;/ext-link&gt;). We describe interim results up to 21 days after vaccination (July 2021–August 2021). Adults aged ≥ 65 years living in the community, who were to have received a second mRNA-1273 dose at least five months previously, were randomised (1:1:1) to concomitant QIV-HD and mRNA-1273 vaccination (Coad), QIV-HD alone, or mRNA-1273 vaccine alone. Unsolicited adverse events (AEs) occurring immediately, solicited local and systemic reactions up to day (D)8, and unsolicited AEs, serious AEs (SAEs), AEs of special interest (AESIs) and medically attended AEs (MAAEs) up to D22 were reported. Haemagglutination inhibition (HAI) antibody responses to influenza A/H1N1, A/H3N2, B/Yamagata and B/Victoria strains and SARS CoV-2 binding antibody responses (SARS-CoV-2 Pre-Spike IgG ELISA) were assessed at D1 and D22.

&lt;bold&gt;Findings&lt;/bold&gt;

Of 306 participants randomised, 296 were included for analysis (Coad, n=100; QIV-HD, n=92; mRNA-1273, n=104). Reactogenicity profiles were similar between the Coad and mRNA-1273 groups, with lower reactogenicity rates in the QIV-HD group (frequency [95% CIs] of solicited injection site reactions: 86·0% [77·6–92·1], 91·3% [84·2–96·0] and 61·8% [50·9–71·9] ; solicited systemic reactions: 80·0% [70·8–87·3], 83·7% [75·1–90·2] and 49·4% [38·7–60·2], respectively). Up to D22, unsolicited AEs were reported for 17·0% and 14·4% participants in the Coad and mRNA-1273 groups, respectively, with a lower rate (10·9%) in the QIV-HD group. Seven MAAEs were reported (Coad, n=3; QIV-HD, n=1; mRNA-1273, n=3). There were no SAEs, AESIs or deaths. HAI antibody geometric mean titres (GMTs) increased from D1 to D22 to similar levels for each influenza strain in the Coad and QIV-HD groups (GMTs [95% confidence interval], range across strains: Coad, 286 [233–352] to 429 [350–525] ; QIV-HD, 315 [257–386] to 471 [378–588]). SARS-CoV-2 binding antibody geometric mean concentrations (GMCs) also increased to similar levels in the Coad and mRNA-1273 groups (D22 GMCs [95% confidence interval]: 7634 [6445–9042] and 7904 [6883–9077], respectively).

&lt;bold&gt;Interpretation&lt;/bold&gt;

No safety concerns or immune interference were observed for concomitant administration of QIV-HD with mRNA-1273 booster in adults aged ≥ 65 years, supporting co-administration recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.21265248" rel="alternate" title="Safety and immunogenicity of a high-dose quadrivalent influenza vaccine administered concomitantly with a third dose of the mRNA-1273 SARS-CoV-2 vaccine in adults ≥ 65 years of age: a Phase II, open-label study (7 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.21265508</id><title>Six-month sequelae of post-vaccination SARS-CoV-2 infection: a retrospective cohort study of 10,024 breakthrough infections (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.238277+00:00</updated><author><name>Maxime Taquet</name></author><author><name>Quentin Dercon</name></author><author><name>Paul J Harrison</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vaccination has proven effective against infection with SARS-CoV-2, as well as death and hospitalisation following COVID-19 illness. However, little is known about the effect of vaccination on other acute and post-acute outcomes of COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Data were obtained from the TriNetX electronic health records network (over 81 million patients mostly in the USA). Using a retrospective cohort study and time-to-event analysis, we compared the incidences of COVID-19 outcomes between individuals who received a COVID-19 vaccine (approved for use in the USA) at least 2 weeks before SARS-CoV-2 infection and propensity score-matched individuals unvaccinated for COVID-19 but who had received an influenza vaccine. Outcomes were ICD-10 codes representing documented COVID-19 sequelae in the 6 months after a confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection (recorded between January 1 and August 31, 2021). Associations with the number of vaccine doses (1 vs. 2) and age (&amp;lt; 60 vs. ≥ 60 years-old) were assessed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among 10,024 vaccinated individuals with SARS-CoV-2 infection, 9479 were matched to unvaccinated controls. Receiving at least one COVID-19 vaccine dose was associated with a significantly lower risk of respiratory failure, ICU admission, intubation/ventilation, hypoxaemia, oxygen requirement, hypercoagulopathy/venous thromboembolism, seizures, psychotic disorder, and hair loss (each as composite endpoints with death to account for competing risks; HR 0.70-0.83, Bonferroni-corrected p&amp;lt;.05), but not other outcomes, including long-COVID features, renal disease, mood, anxiety, and sleep disorders. Receiving 2 vaccine doses was associated with lower risks for most outcomes. Associations between prior vaccination and outcomes of SARS-CoV-2 infection were marked in those &amp;lt; 60 years-old, whereas no robust associations were observed in those ≥ 60 years-old.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 vaccination is associated with lower risk of several, but not all, COVID-19 sequelae in those with breakthrough SARS-CoV-2 infection. These benefits of vaccination were clear in younger people but not in the over-60s. The findings may inform service planning, contribute to forecasting public health impacts of vaccination programmes, and highlight the need to identify additional interventions for COVID-19 sequelae.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;National Institute for Health Research (NIHR) Oxford Health Biomedical Research Centre.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.21265508" rel="alternate" title="Six-month sequelae of post-vaccination SARS-CoV-2 infection: a retrospective cohort study of 10,024 breakthrough infections (7 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.465224</id><title>An iTSC-derived placental model of SARS-CoV-2 infection unveils ACE2-dependent susceptibility in syncytiotrophoblasts (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.238600+00:00</updated><author><name>Joseph Chen</name></author><author><name>Jessica A Neil</name></author><author><name>Jia Ping Tan</name></author><author><name>Raj Rudraraju</name></author><author><name>Monika Mohenska</name></author><author><name>Yu BY Sun</name></author><author><name>Guizhi Sun</name></author><author><name>Yichen Zhou</name></author><author><name>Ying Li</name></author><author><name>Damien Drew</name></author><author><name>Phill Pymm</name></author><author><name>Wai-Hong Tham</name></author><author><name>Fernando J Rossello</name></author><author><name>Guiying Nie</name></author><author><name>Xiaodong Liu</name></author><author><name>Kanta Subbarao</name></author><author><name>Jose Maria Polo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection causing coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) has caused a global health crisis. The primary  site of infection is in the respiratory tract but the virus has been associated with a variety of complications involving the gastrointestinal and cardiovascular systems. Since the virus affects a variety of tissue types, there has been interest in understanding SARS-CoV-2 infection in early development and the placenta. The expression of ACE2 or TMPRSS2, both genes  critical for viral entry, is present in placental-specific cell types such as extravillous trophoblasts (EVTs) and, especially, syncytiotrophoblasts (STs). The potential of SARS-CoV-2 to infect these placental cells and its effect on placental development and function is still unclear. Furthermore, it is crucial to understand the possible mechanism of vertical transmission of SARS-CoV-2 through the placenta. Here, we developed an in vitro model of SARS-CoV-2 infection of placental cell types using induced trophoblast stem cells (iTSCs). This model allowed us to show that STs but not EVTs are infected. Importantly, infected STs lack the expression of key differentiation genes, lack typically observed differentiated morphology and produce significantly lower human chorionic gonadotropin (HCG) compared to non-infected controls. We also show that an anti-ACE2 antibody prevents SARS-CoV-2 infection and restores normal ST differentiation and function. We highlight the establishment of a platform to study SARS-CoV-2 infection in early placental cell types, which will  facilitate investigation of antiviral therapy to protect the placenta during early pregnancy and development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.465224" rel="alternate" title="An iTSC-derived placental model of SARS-CoV-2 infection unveils ACE2-dependent susceptibility in syncytiotrophoblasts (7 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265588</id><title>Designing an evidence-based Bayesian network for estimating the risk versus benefits of AstraZeneca COVID-19 vaccine (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.239135+00:00</updated><author><name>Helen J Mayfield</name></author><author><name>Colleen L Lau</name></author><author><name>Jane E Sinclair</name></author><author><name>Samuel J Brown</name></author><author><name>Andrew Baird</name></author><author><name>John Litt</name></author><author><name>Aapeli Vuorinen</name></author><author><name>Kirsty R Short</name></author><author><name>Michael Waller</name></author><author><name>Kerrie Mengersen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Uncertainty surrounding the risk of developing and dying from Thrombosis and Thromobocytopenia Syndrome (TTS) associated with the AstraZeneca (AZ) COVID-19 vaccine may contribute to vaccine hesitancy. A model is urgently needed to combine and effectively communicate the existing evidence on the risks versus benefits of the AZ vaccine. We developed a Bayesian network to consolidate the existing evidence on risks and benefits of the AZ vaccine, and parameterised the model using data from a range of empirical studies, government reports, and expert advisory groups. Expert judgement was used to interpret the available evidence and determine the structure of the model, relevant variables, data to be included, and how these data were used to inform the model. 
The model can be used as a decision support tool to generate scenarios based on age, sex, virus variant and community transmission rates, making it a useful for individuals, clinicians, and researchers to assess the chances of different health outcomes. Model outputs include the risk of dying from TTS following the AZ COVID-19 vaccine, the risk of dying from COVID-19 or COVID-19-associated atypical severe blood clots under different scenarios. Although the model is focused on Australia, it can be easily adaptable to international settings by re-parameterising it with local data. This paper provides detailed description of the model-building methodology, which can used to expand the scope of the model to include other COVID-19 vaccines, booster doses, comorbidities and other health outcomes (e.g., long COVID) to ensure the model remains relevant in the face of constantly changing discussion on risks versus benefits of COVID-19 vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265588" rel="alternate" title="Designing an evidence-based Bayesian network for estimating the risk versus benefits of AstraZeneca COVID-19 vaccine (7 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465946</id><title>Multi-label topic classification for COVID-19 literature annotation using an ensemble model based on PubMedBERT (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.239697+00:00</updated><author><name>Shubo Tian</name></author><author><name>Jinfeng Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The BioCreative VII Track 5 calls for participants to tackle the multi-label classification task for automated topic annotation of COVID-19 literature. In our participation, we evaluated several deep learning models built on PubMedBERT, a pre-trained language model, with different strategies addressing the challenges of the task. Specifically, multi-instance learning was used to deal with the large variation in the lengths of the articles, and focal loss function was used to address the imbalance in the distribution of different topics. We found that the ensemble model performed the best among all the models we have tested. Test results of our submissions showed that our approach was able to achieve satisfactory performance with an F1 score of 0.9247, which is significantly better than the baseline model (F1 score: 0.8678) and the mean of all the submissions (F1 score: 0.8931).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465946" rel="alternate" title="Multi-label topic classification for COVID-19 literature annotation using an ensemble model based on PubMedBERT (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265544</id><title>In vitro characterisation and clinical evaluation of the diagnostic accuracy of a new antigen test for SARS-CoV-2 detection. (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.240076+00:00</updated><author><name>J.J. Montoya</name></author><author><name>J.M. Rubio</name></author><author><name>Y. Ouahid</name></author><author><name>A. Lopez-Lopez</name></author><author><name>A. Madejon</name></author><author><name>A.I. Gil-Garcia</name></author><author><name>R.J. Hannam</name></author><author><name>H.R.E. Butler</name></author><author><name>P. Castan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background and aims: Quick, user-friendly and sensitive diagnostic tools are the key to controlling the spread of the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic in the new epidemiologic landscape. The aim of this work is to characterise a new Covid-19 antigen test that uses an innovative chromatographic Affimer-based technology designed for the qualitative detection of SARS-CoV-2 antigen. As rapid technology to detect Covid-19, the test was extensively characterised in vitro. Once the analytical parameters of performance were set, the test system was challenged in a test field study. The aim of this study was to evaluate its diagnostic accuracy, as compared by the gold standard RT-PCR and other existing lateral flow tests. The study was approved by MiRNAX corporate review board to ensure i) that the test complied with all the ethical requirements, ii) that the rights of participants were protected, and iii) that donors were fully informed about the likelihood that they would not personally benefit from the research. The tests were completed under the frame of Project SENSORNAS RTC-20176501 in collaboration with MiRNAX Biosens Ltd. and Hospital Carlos III and are currently under submission and review from the Ethics Committee of Universidad Autonoma de Madrid.
Keywords: respiratory disease COVID-19; SARS-CoV-2; ELISA; RT-PCR; antigen lateral flow test.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265544" rel="alternate" title="In vitro characterisation and clinical evaluation of the diagnostic accuracy of a new antigen test for SARS-CoV-2 detection. (6 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265596</id><title>A Novel Indicator for COVID-19 Pandemic Assessment and Comparison (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.279701+00:00</updated><author><name>Kanchan Mukherjee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Introduction
In an increasingly globalized world, no country can remain immune to the effect of the COVID-19 pandemic. The pandemic has exposed the need for effective public health surveillance in the interest of global health security. However, current indicators are limited in doing a comparative intercountry assessment and comparison because of variation in testing rates and reporting standards. Hence, this study attempts at addressing this gap.

Methods 
The study proposes incremental change in cases per testing rate (ICTR) as an indicator for doing cross country comparison of the pandemic progress. The equation for calculating this indicator is explained in this study. This is followed by measuring its strength of association and predictive power for determining change in SARS-CoV-2 cases in five countries (USA, UK, India, Pakistan and Bangladesh).

Results and discussion
ICTR was found to have a significantly higher strength of association and predictive power (than the existing indicator- test positivity rate) for determining change in cases over different time periods. Using ICTR, cross country comparison was done for the five countries for15 months to draw deeper insights into the progress of the pandemic. 

Conclusions
The study finds ICTR to be a suitable indicator for inter country comparison and intra country monitoring of the pandemic, which would be useful for global COVID-19 surveillance. 

Key words: Incremental analysis, SARS-CoV-2, low-middle income country, high income country, testing rate, test positivity rate, surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265596" rel="alternate" title="A Novel Indicator for COVID-19 Pandemic Assessment and Comparison (6 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.466002</id><title>Whole-genome sequencing of Vero E6 (C1008) and comparative analysis of four Vero cell sublines (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.280363+00:00</updated><author><name>Kazuhiro Konishi</name></author><author><name>Toshiyuki Yamaji</name></author><author><name>Chisato Sakuma</name></author><author><name>Fumio Kasai</name></author><author><name>Toshinori Endo</name></author><author><name>Arihiro Kohara</name></author><author><name>Kentaro Hanada</name></author><author><name>Naoki Osada</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Vero cell line is an immortalized cell line established from kidney epithelial cells of the African green monkey. A variety of sublines have been established from the original cell line, which display different characteristics. In this study, we determined the whole-genome sequence of Vero E6 (C1008) and performed comparative analysis among Vero JCRB 0111, Vero CCL-81, Vero 76 and Vero E6. Analysis of the copy number changes and loss of heterozygosity revealed that all sublines share a large deletion and loss of heterozygosity on chromosome 12, which harbors type I interferon and CDKN2 gene clusters. We identified a substantial number of genetic differences among the sublines including single nucleotide variants, indels, and copy number variations. The spectrum of single nucleotide variants indicated a close genetic relationship between Vero JCRB0111 and Vero CCL-81, and between Vero 76 and Vero E6, and a considerable genetic gap between the former two and the latter two lines. In contrast, we confirmed the pattern of genomic integration sites of simian endogenous retroviral sequences, which was consistent among the sublines. We identified subline-specific/enriched loss of function and missense variants, which potentially contribute to the differences in response to viral infection among the Vero sublines. In particular, we focused on Vero E6-specific/enriched variants and identified four genes (IL1RAP, TRIM25, RB1CC1, and ATG2A) that contained missense variants specific or enriched in Vero E6. In addition, we found that V739I variants of ACE2, which functions as the receptor for SARS-CoV-2, were heterozygous in Vero JCRB0111, Vero CCL-81, and Vero 76; however, Vero E6 contained the allele with isoleucine, resulting from the loss of one of the X chromosomes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.466002" rel="alternate" title="Whole-genome sequencing of Vero E6 (C1008) and comparative analysis of four Vero cell sublines (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.465996</id><title>Camel nanobodies broadly neutralize SARS-CoV-2 variants (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.338129+00:00</updated><author><name>Jessica Hong</name></author><author><name>Hyung Joon Kwon</name></author><author><name>Raul Cachau</name></author><author><name>Catherine Z Chen</name></author><author><name>Kevin John Butay</name></author><author><name>Zhijian Duan</name></author><author><name>Dan Li</name></author><author><name>Hua Ren</name></author><author><name>Tianyuzhou Liang</name></author><author><name>Jianghai Zhu</name></author><author><name>Venkata P Dandey</name></author><author><name>Negin P. Martin</name></author><author><name>Dominic Esposito</name></author><author><name>Uriel Ortega-Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Miao Xu</name></author><author><name>Mario J. Borgnia</name></author><author><name>Hang Xie</name></author><author><name>Mitchell Ho</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;With the emergence of SARS-CoV-2 variants, there is urgent need to develop broadly neutralizing antibodies. Here, we isolate two VHH nanobodies (7A3 and 8A2) from dromedary camels by phage display, which have high affinity for the receptor-binding domain (RBD) and broad neutralization activities against SARS-CoV-2 and its emerging variants. Cryo-EM complex structures reveal that 8A2 binds the RBD in its up mode and 7A3 inhibits receptor binding by uniquely targeting a highly conserved and deeply buried site in the spike regardless of the RBD conformational state. 7A3 at a dose of ≥5 mg/kg efficiently protects K18-hACE2 transgenic mice from the lethal challenge of B.1.351 or B.1.617.2, suggesting that the nanobody has promising therapeutic potentials to curb the COVID-19 surge with emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.465996" rel="alternate" title="Camel nanobodies broadly neutralize SARS-CoV-2 variants (6 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466067</id><title>Novel pectin from crude polysaccharide of Syzygium aromaticum against SARS-CoV-2 activities by targeting 3CLpro (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.338513+00:00</updated><author><name>Can Jin</name></author><author><name>Bo Feng</name></author><author><name>Rong juan Pei</name></author><author><name>Ya qi Ding</name></author><author><name>Mei xia Li</name></author><author><name>Xia Chen</name></author><author><name>Zhen yun Du</name></author><author><name>Yang xiao Ding</name></author><author><name>Chun fan Huang</name></author><author><name>Bo Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xin wen Chen</name></author><author><name>Yi Zang</name></author><author><name>Jia Li</name></author><author><name>Kan Ding</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To date, COVID-19 is still a severe threat to public health, hence specific effective therapeutic drugs development against SARS-CoV-2 is urgent needed. 3CLpro and PLpro and RdRp are the enzymes required for the SARS-CoV-2 RNA synthesis. Therefore, binding to the enzyme may interfere the enzyme function. Before, we found that sulfated polysaccharide binding to 3CLpro might block the virus replication. Hence, we hypothesize that negative charged pectin glycan may also impede the virus replication. Here we show that 922 crude polysaccharide from Syzygium aromaticum may near completely block SARS-CoV-2 replication. The inhibition rate was 99.9% (EC50 : 0.90 muM). Interestingly, 922 can associates with 3CLpro, PLpro and RdRp. We further show that the homogeneous glycan 922211 from 922 may specifically attenuate 3CL protease activity. The IC50s of 922 and 922211 against 3CLpro are 4.73 plusmn 1.05 muM and 0.18 plusmn 0.01 muM, respectively. Monosaccharide composition analysis reveals that 922211 with molecular weight of 78.7 kDa is composed of rhamnose, galacturonic acid, galactose and arabinose in the molar ratio of 8.21 : 37.81 : 3.58 : 4.49. The structure characterization demonstrated that 922211 is a homogalacturonan linked to RG-I pectin polysaccharide. The linear homogalacturonan part in the backbone may be partly methyl esterified while RG-I type part bearing 1, 4-linked alpha-GalpA, 1, 4-linked alpha-GalpAOMe and 1, 2, 4-linked alpha-Rhap. There are four branches attached to C-1 or C4 position of Rhamnose glycosyl residues on the backbone. The branches are composed of 1, 3-linked beta-Galp, terminal (T)-linked beta-Galp, 1, 5-linked alpha-Araf, T-linked alpha-Araf, 4-linked alpha-GalpA and/or 4-linked beta-GalpA. The above results suggest that 922 and 922211 might be a potential novel leading compound for anti-SARS-CoV-2 new drug development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466067" rel="alternate" title="Novel pectin from crude polysaccharide of Syzygium aromaticum against SARS-CoV-2 activities by targeting 3CLpro (6 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.466019</id><title>Analyzing SARS CoV-2 Patient Data Using Quantum Supervised Machine Learning (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.338757+00:00</updated><author><name>Zara Yu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The novel coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) has created a serious threat to global health. We developed a new quantum machine learning (QML) assisted diagnostic method that can provide an accurate diagnosis to aid decision processes of medical providers. One of the key elements in our method was to implement the quantum variational method to efficiently classify data, taking crucial multiple correlations among the features into account. We established and fine-tuned this quantum classifier by using a group of data drawn from publicly available COVID-19 cases. We have shown that QML is capable of processing patient information efficiently and accurately for the diagnosis of COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.466019" rel="alternate" title="Analyzing SARS CoV-2 Patient Data Using Quantum Supervised Machine Learning (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265598</id><title>Personalized survival probabilities for SARS-CoV-2 positive patients by explainable machine learning (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.339210+00:00</updated><author><name>Adrian G. Zucco</name></author><author><name>Rudi Agius</name></author><author><name>Rebecka Svanberg</name></author><author><name>Kasper S. Moestrup</name></author><author><name>Ramtin Z. Marandi</name></author><author><name>Cameron Ross MacPherson</name></author><author><name>Jens Lundgren</name></author><author><name>Sisse R. Ostrowski</name></author><author><name>Carsten U. Niemann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Interpretable risk assessment of SARS-CoV-2 positive patients can aid clinicians to implement precision medicine. Here we trained a machine learning model to predict mortality within 12 weeks of a first positive SARS-CoV-2 test. By leveraging data on 33,928 confirmed SARS-CoV-2 cases in eastern Denmark, we considered 2,723 variables extracted from electronic health records (EHR) including demographics, diagnoses, medications, laboratory test results and vital parameters. A discrete-time framework for survival modelling enabled us to predict personalized survival curves and explain individual risk factors. Performances of weighted concordance index 0.95 and precision-recall area under the curve 0.71 were measured on the test set. Age, sex, number of medications, previous hospitalizations and lymphocyte counts were identified as top mortality risk factors. Our explainable survival model developed on EHR data also revealed temporal dynamics of the 22 selected risk factors. Upon further validation, this model may allow direct reporting of personalized survival probabilities in routine care.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265598" rel="alternate" title="Personalized survival probabilities for SARS-CoV-2 positive patients by explainable machine learning (6 tweets)"/><category term="Health Informatics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.21265504</id><title>Global diversity of policy, coverage, and demand of COVID-19 vaccines: a descriptive study (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.339465+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhiyuan Chen</name></author><author><name>Wen Zheng</name></author><author><name>Qianhui Wu</name></author><author><name>Xinghui Chen</name></author><author><name>Cheng Peng</name></author><author><name>Yuyang Tian</name></author><author><name>Ruijia Sun</name></author><author><name>Minghan Wang</name></author><author><name>Xiaoyu Zhou</name></author><author><name>Zeyao Zhao</name></author><author><name>Guangjie Zhong</name></author><author><name>Xuemei Yan</name></author><author><name>Nuolan Liu</name></author><author><name>Feiran Hao</name></author><author><name>Sihong Zhao</name></author><author><name>Tingyu Zhuang</name></author><author><name>Juan Yang</name></author><author><name>Andrew S. Azman</name></author><author><name>Hongjie Yu</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of millions of doses of COVID-19 vaccines have been administered globally, but progress in vaccination varies considerably between countries. We aim to provide an overall picture of COVID-19 vaccination campaigns, including policy, coverage, and demand of COVID-19 vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted a descriptive study of vaccination policy and doses administered data obtained from multiple public sources as of 23 October 2021. We used these data to develop coverage indicators and explore associations of vaccine coverage with socioeconomic and healthcare-related factors. We estimated vaccine demand as numbers of doses required to complete vaccination of countries’ target populations according to their national immunization program policies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use of both mRNA and adenovirus vectored vaccines was the most commonly used COVID-19 vaccines formulary in high-income countries, while adenovirus vectored vaccines were the most widely used vaccines worldwide (176 countries). Almost all countries (98.3%, 173/176) have authorized vaccines for the general public, with 53.4% (94/176) targeting individuals over 12 years and 33.0% (58/176) targeting those ≥18 years. Forty-one and sixty-seven countries have started additional-dose and booster-dose vaccination programs, respectively. Globally, there have been 116.5 doses administered per 100 target population, although with marked inter-region and inter-country heterogeneity. Completed vaccination series coverage ranged from 0% to more than 95.0% of country target populations, and numbers of doses administered ranged from 0 to 239.6 per 100 target population. Doses administered per 100 total population correlated with healthcare access and quality index (R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 0.58), socio-demographic index (R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 0.56), and GDP per capita (R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 0.65). At least 5.54 billion doses will be required to complete interim vaccination programs – 4.65 billion for primary immunization and 0.89 billion for additional/booster programs. Globally, 0.84 and 0.96 dose per individual in the target population are needed for primary immunization and additional/booster programs, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is wide country-level disparity and inequity in COVID-19 vaccines rollout, suggesting large gaps in immunity, especially in low-income countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Key Program of the National Natural Science Foundation of China, the US National Institutes of Health.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Research in context&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Evidence before this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We searched PubMed for articles in any language published up to October 21, 2021, using the following search terms: (“COVID-19” OR “SARS-CoV-2”) AND (“vaccination” OR “vaccine”) AND (“inequalit*” OR “inequity” OR “disparit*” OR “heterogeneity”). We also searched for dashboards associated with vaccine rollout from public websites. We identified several studies on tracking global inequalities of vaccine access, one of which constructed a COVID-19 vaccine dashboard (Our World in Data), and another that explored disparities in COVID-19 vaccination among different-income countries. However, we found no studies that depict global COVID-19 vaccination policies country-by-country and estimate demand for vaccine necessary to completely vaccinate countries’ designated target populations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Added value of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To our knowledge, our study provides the most recent picture of COVID-19 vaccination campaigns, focusing on global vaccination policy and target-population demand. We found a diverse portfolio of vaccines in five technical platforms being administered globally, with 173 countries having authorized administration of vaccines to the general public in various age groups. We observed inter-region and inter-country heterogeneity in one-or-more-dose and full-dose coverage; countries with higher socio-demographic or health resource-related levels had higher coverage. We estimated dose-level demand for completing primary immunization programs and additional/booster dose programs separately.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Implications of all the available evidence&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Worldwide disparity and inequity of vaccine rollout implies that susceptibility among unvaccinated populations in some countries may impede or reverse pandemic control, especially in face of the emergence of variants and the dilemma of waning antibodies. Our findings suggest that global-level responses to the pandemic - financially, politically, and technically - are needed to overcome complex challenges that lie ahead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.21265504" rel="alternate" title="Global diversity of policy, coverage, and demand of COVID-19 vaccines: a descriptive study (6 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265615</id><title>Transmission dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 in a strictly-Orthodox Jewish community in the UK (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.339760+00:00</updated><author><name>William Waites</name></author><author><name>Carl AB Pearson</name></author><author><name>Katherine M Gaskell</name></author><author><name>Thomas House</name></author><author><name>Lorenzo Pellis</name></author><author><name>Marina Johnson</name></author><author><name>Victoria Gould</name></author><author><name>Adam Hunt</name></author><author><name>Neil RH Stone</name></author><author><name>Ben Kasstan</name></author><author><name>Tracey Chantler</name></author><author><name>Sham Lal</name></author><author><name>Chrissy h Roberts</name></author><author><name>David Goldblatt</name></author><author><name>Michael Marks</name></author><author><name>Rosalind M Eggo</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Some social settings such as households and workplaces, have been identified as high risk for SARS-CoV-2 transmission. Identifying and quantifying the importance of these settings is critical for designing interventions. A tightly-knit religious community in the UK experienced a very large COVID-19 epidemic in 2020, reaching 64.3% seroprevalence within 10 months, and we surveyed this community both for serological status and individual-level attendance at particular settings. Using these data, and a network model of people and places represented as a stochastic graph rewriting system, we estimated the relative contribution of transmission in households, schools and religious institutions to the epidemic, and the relative risk of infection in each of these settings. All congregate settings were important for transmission, with some such as primary schools and places of worship having a higher share of transmission than others. We found that the model needed a higher general-community transmission rate for women (3.3-fold), and lower susceptibility to infection in children to recreate the observed serological data. The precise share of transmission in each place was related to assumptions about the internal structure of those places. Identification of key settings of transmission  can allow public health interventions to be targeted at these locations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265615" rel="alternate" title="Transmission dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 in a strictly-Orthodox Jewish community in the UK (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265578</id><title>Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on routine immunization coverage in children under 2 years old in Ontario, Canada: A retrospective cohort study (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.340006+00:00</updated><author><name>Catherine Ji</name></author><author><name>Pierre-Philippe Piche-Renaud</name></author><author><name>Jemisha Apajee</name></author><author><name>Ellen Stephenson</name></author><author><name>Milena Forte</name></author><author><name>Jeremy N Friedman</name></author><author><name>Michelle Science</name></author><author><name>Stanley Zlotkin</name></author><author><name>Shaun K Morris</name></author><author><name>Karen Tu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: The COVID-19 pandemic has caused a disruption in childhood immunization coverage around the world. This study aimed to determine the change in immunization coverage for children under 2 years old in Ontario, Canada, comparing time periods pre-pandemic to during the pandemic.
Methods: We conducted an observational retrospective open cohort study, using primary care electronic medical record data from the University of Toronto Practice-Based Research Network (UTOPIAN) database, from January 2019 to December 2020. Children under 2 years old who had at least 2 visits recorded in UTOPIAN were included. We measured up-to-date (UTD) immunization coverage rates, overall and by type of vaccine (DTaP-IPV-Hib, Pneu-C-13, Rot, Men-C-C, MMR, Var), and on-time immunization coverage rates by age milestone (2, 4, 6, 12, 15 and 18 months). We compared average coverage rates over 3 periods of time: January 2019-March 2020 (T1); March-July 2020 (T2); and August-December 2020 (T3).
Results: 12,313 children were included. Overall UTD coverage for all children was 71.0% in T1, dropped by 5.7% (95% CI: -6.2, -5.1) in T2, slightly increased in T3 but remained lower than in T1. MMR vaccine UTD coverage slightly decreased in T2 and T3 by approximately 2%. The largest decreases were seen at ages 15-month and 18-month old, with drops in on-time coverage of 14.7% (95% CI: -18.7, -10.6) and 16.4% (95% CI: -20.0, -12.8) respectively during T2. When stratified by sociodemographic characteristics, no specific subgroup of children was found to have been differentially impacted by the pandemic.
Conclusion: Childhood immunization coverage rates for children under 2 years in Ontario decreased significantly during the early period of the COVID-19 pandemic and only partially recovered during the rest of 2020. Public health and educational interventions for providers and parents are needed to ensure adequate catch-up of delayed/missed immunizations to prevent potential outbreaks of vaccine-preventable diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265578" rel="alternate" title="Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on routine immunization coverage in children under 2 years old in Ontario, Canada: A retrospective cohort study (4 tweets)"/><category term="Primary Care Research"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265604</id><title>Transferability of Psychological Interventions from Disaster-Exposed Employees to Healthcare Workers Working during the COVID-19 Pandemic (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.340216+00:00</updated><author><name>Sean Treacy</name></author><author><name>Shane O Donnell</name></author><author><name>Blanaid Gavin</name></author><author><name>Tamara Schloemer</name></author><author><name>Etain Quigley</name></author><author><name>Dimitrios Adamis</name></author><author><name>Fiona Mc Nicholas</name></author><author><name>John Hayden</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: The COVID-19 Pandemic had a significant negative impact on the mental health of healthcare workers. Evidence-based interventions that could be used to mitigate this impact are lacking in the literature. This review aims to evaluate psychological interventions used for employees following previous disasters and assess the transferability of these interventions to a healthcare setting during the COVID-19 pandemic. 
Methods: Intervention information from a previously published systematic review of the literature published up to 2015 was extracted, and an additional search of studies published from 2015-2020 was conducted.  Studies were assessed for transferability using a checklist derived from the PIET-T process model. 
Results: Interventions from eighteen studies were assessed for transferability (including three studies identified in an updated literature search). Interventions established as most transferable included resilience training, meditation/mindfulness interventions, and cognitive behavioural therapy. Psychological debriefing was transferable but as it is contrary to current recommendations is not deemed appropriate for adoption. 
Implications: Several existing interventions have the potential to be utilised within the COVID-19 context/pandemic. More research needs to be undertaken in this area to assess these interventions upon transfer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265604" rel="alternate" title="Transferability of Psychological Interventions from Disaster-Exposed Employees to Healthcare Workers Working during the COVID-19 Pandemic (4 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265608</id><title>Social discrimination and stigma on the community of health professionals during the Covid-19 pandemic. An ethnographic approach (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.340475+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexandros Argyriadis</name></author><author><name>Athina Patelarou</name></author><author><name>Vasiliki Kitsona</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Trivli</name></author><author><name>Evridiki Patelarou</name></author><author><name>Agathi Argyriadi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus Type 2 (SARS-CoV-2) that caused the pandemic since March 2020, has affected among others, health professionals who work in covid-19 units by facing social discrimination. The aim of this study was to record the experiences of health professionals working in the first line of treatment of the pandemic, to analyse the effects of the pandemic on the interpersonal relationships of health professionals, and to ask about the stigma they faced during their work with people with covid-19.
This is a qualitative study with an ethnographic approach based on 160 semi-structured interviews with health professionals living and working in the Epirus Region, Greece. For the data collection we used semi-structured interviews, discussions and participatory observation.  Specifically, the interviews were conducted on health professionals and more specifically doctors, nurses, rescuers, physiotherapists and administrative staff, working in covid-19 units at the University General Hospital of Ioannina (Reference hospital for Ioannina, in Epirus), which assists in the treatment of patients with covid-19, and in the branch of the rescue department of Ioannina. 
The data were analysed in four thematic units based on their common characteristics: a) emotions and experiences of health professionals, b) interpersonal relations of health professionals, c) social exclusion and discrimination, and d) health professionals as patients. The results showed that the main emotions that health professionals experienced when they were moved to covid-19 clinics were fear, anxiety, distress, anger and insecurity. These feelings worsened when their family environment treated them with fear and hesitancy. Their social environment tended to avoid them, leading to a state of self-isolation. To conclude, health professionals faced discriminating behaviors and stigma both from their families and social environment, and from other health professionals. The government struggled to handle the situation in keeping a balance between both the security and well-being of health professionals as it was not prepared for a pandemic like this.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265608" rel="alternate" title="Social discrimination and stigma on the community of health professionals during the Covid-19 pandemic. An ethnographic approach (4 tweets)"/><category term="Nursing"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265610</id><title>COVID-19 Patients Symptoms: Gastrointestinal Presentations, Comorbidities and Outcome in a Canadian Hospital setting (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.340694+00:00</updated><author><name>Hassan Brim</name></author><author><name>Michal Moshkovich</name></author><author><name>Nikhil Pai</name></author><author><name>Melanie Figueiredo</name></author><author><name>Emily Hartung</name></author><author><name>Antonio Pizuorno</name></author><author><name>Lee Hill</name></author><author><name>Jelena Popov</name></author><author><name>Eyitope Olaide Awoyemi</name></author><author><name>Waliul I Khan</name></author><author><name>Reza Oskrochi</name></author><author><name>Hassan Ashktorab</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: The Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic has had a significant global impact and Canada has seen significant morbidity and mortality nationwide. While public health interventions and provincially regulated health insurance coverage have been credited with minimizing transmission rates in Canada relative to neighboring countries, disease presentation has been presumed to be the same. 
Aim: We sought to determine factors associated with differences in gastrointestinal outcomes in COVID-19 patients at a Canadian hospital.
Methods: We collected data from 192 hospital records of COVID-19 patients across seven Hamilton Health Sciences hospitals, a network of academic health centers located in Hamilton, Ontario serving one of the largest metropolitan areas in Canada. Statistical and correlative analysis of symptoms, comorbidities, and mortality were performed.
Results: There were 192 patients. The mean age was 57.6 years (SD=21.0). For patients who died (n=27, 14%), mean age was 79.2 years old (SD=10.6) versus 54 years for survivors (SD=20.1). There was a higher mortality among patients with older age (p=0.000), long hospital stay (p=0.004), male patients (p=0.032), and patients in nursing homes (p=0.000). Patients with dyspnea (p=0.028) and hypertension (p=0.004) were more likely to have a poor outcome.  Laboratory test values that were significant in determining outcomes were an elevated INR (p=0.007) and elevated creatinine (p=0.000). Cough and hypertension were the most common symptom and comorbidity, respectively. Diarrhea was the most prevalent (14.5%) gastrointestinal symptom. Impaired liver function was related to negative outcome (LR 5.6; p=0.018). 
Conclusion: In a Canadian cohort, elevated liver enzymes, prolonged INR and elevated creatinine were associated with poor prognosis. Hypertension was also linked to a higher likelihood of negative outcome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.21265610" rel="alternate" title="COVID-19 Patients Symptoms: Gastrointestinal Presentations, Comorbidities and Outcome in a Canadian Hospital setting (4 tweets)"/><category term="Pediatrics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466182</id><title>Efficacy of anti-microbial gel vapours against aerosolised coronavirus, bacteria, and fungi (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.340923+00:00</updated><author><name>Parthasarathi Kalaiselvan</name></author><author><name>Muhammad Yasir</name></author><author><name>Mark D. P. Willcox</name></author><author><name>Ajay Kumar Vijay</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: The urban population spends up to 90% of their time indoors. The indoor environment harbours a diverse microbial population including viruses, bacteria, and fungi. Pathogens present in the indoor environment can be transmitted to humans through aerosols. Aim: This study evaluated the efficacy of an antimicrobial gel containing a mix of essential oils against aerosols of bacteria, fungi, and coronavirus. Methods: The antimicrobial gel was allowed to vapourize inside a glass chamber for 10 or 20 minutes. Microbial aerosols of Escerichia coli, Aspergillus flavus spores or murine hepatitis virus MHV 1, a surrogate of SARS CoV-2 was passed through the gel vapours and then collected on a 6-stage Andersen sampler. The number of viable microbes present in the aerosols collected in the different stages were enumerated and compared to number of viable microbes in control microbial aerosols that were not exposed to the gel vapours. Results: Vaporizing the antimicrobial gel for 10 and 20 minutes resulted in a 48% (p = 0.002 Vs. control) and 53% (p = 0.001 Vs. control) reduction in the number of MHV-1 in the aerosols, respectively. The antimicrobial gel vaporised for 10 minutes, reduced the number of viable E. coli by 51% (p = 0.032 Vs. control) and Aspergillus flavus spores by 72% (p=0.008 Vs. control) in the aerosols. Conclusions: The antimicrobial gel may be able to reduce aerosol transmission of microbes. Keywords: Aerosol, Coronavirus, SARS-CoV-2, Indoor Air, Antimicrobial, Essential oils&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466182" rel="alternate" title="Efficacy of anti-microbial gel vapours against aerosolised coronavirus, bacteria, and fungi (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.21265475</id><title>Optimising the balance of acute and intermediate care capacity for the complex discharge pathway: computer modelling study during COVID-19 recovery in England (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.341163+00:00</updated><author><name>Z Onen-Dumlu</name></author><author><name>AL Harper</name></author><author><name>PG Forte</name></author><author><name>AL Powell</name></author><author><name>M Pitt</name></author><author><name>C Vasilakis</name></author><author><name>RM Wood</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;While there has been significant research on the pressures facing acute hospitals during the COVID-19 pandemic, there has been less interest in downstream community services which have also been challenged in meeting demand. This study aimed to estimate the theoretical cost-optimal capacity requirement for ‘step down’ intermediate care services within a major healthcare system in England, at a time when considerable uncertainty remained regarding vaccination uptake and the easing of societal restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Demand for intermediate care was projected using an epidemiological model (for COVID-19 demand) and regressing upon public mobility (for non-COVID-19 demand). These were inputted to a computer simulation model of patient flow from acute discharge readiness to bedded and home-based Discharge to Assess (D2A) intermediate care services. Cost-optimal capacity was defined as that which yielded the lowest total cost of intermediate care provision and corresponding acute discharge delays.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Increased intermediate care capacity is likely to bring about lower system-level costs, with the additional D2A investment more than offset by substantial reductions in costly acute discharge delays (leading also to improved patient outcome and experience). Results suggest that completely eliminating acute ‘bed blocking’ is unlikely economical (requiring large amounts of downstream capacity), and that health systems should instead target an appropriate tolerance based upon the specific characteristics of the pathway.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Computer modelling can be a valuable asset for determining optimal capacity allocation along the complex care pathway. With results supporting a Business Case for increased downstream capacity, this study demonstrates how modelling can be applied in practice and provides a blueprint for use alongside the freely-available model code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.21265475" rel="alternate" title="Optimising the balance of acute and intermediate care capacity for the complex discharge pathway: computer modelling study during COVID-19 recovery in England (3 tweets)"/><category term="Health Systems and Quality Improvement"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.21265480</id><title>Development of health and safety training for Vietnamese American nail salon owners and workers (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.341428+00:00</updated><author><name>Tran B Huynh</name></author><author><name>Duong T Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Nga Vu</name></author><author><name>Catherine Freeland</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nail salon workers are an underserved worker population that faces multiple barriers to accessing occupational health training and services. We developed a series of occupational health training modules, which were culturally tailored to Vietnamese-speaking workers, covering topics on infection control, musculoskeletal disorder prevention, chemical safety, and labor practices. We delivered the training online (due to COVID-19) to a small group of Vietnamese owners and workers in the Philadelphia metro area to obtain feedback on the training content and potential implementation challenges.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seven participants (three owners and four workers) were recruited to attend the training. Qualitative feedback was obtained after each training session, followed by a more in-depth interviewer-assisted open-ended questionnaire to gain better understanding of the potential challenges of implementing the recommended changes. The Health Belief Model was used to guide the analysis of the participants’ responses to identify the perceived benefits and barriers of the training.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Themes of perceived benefits of the training were bridging the gap of cosmetology school training, offering practical tips to protect their health at work, and inspiring conversations about work dignity and labor practices. Themes of perceived barriers were availability of affordable safer products and lack of resources, desire to please customers, lack of commitment from owners, and ubiquitous low wage that impacts employee’s job satisfaction and motivation to change, and difficulty in obtaining a work license.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our study revealed the multitude of social and economic barriers facing immigrant nail salon owners and workers. Potential policies and strategies to overcome some of these structural barriers are discussed for the long-term health protection of nail salon workers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.21265480" rel="alternate" title="Development of health and safety training for Vietnamese American nail salon owners and workers (3 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.21265494</id><title>Health workers Motivators to uptake of the Covid-19 vaccine at Iganga Hospital Eastern Uganda, and Mengo Hospital Kampala Uganda; A qualitative study (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.341602+00:00</updated><author><name>Lubega Muhamadi</name></author><author><name>Namulema Edith</name></author><author><name>Waako James</name></author><author><name>Nazarius Mbona Tumwesigye</name></author><author><name>Safinah Kisu Museene</name></author><author><name>Stefan Swartling Peterson</name></author><author><name>Anna Mia Ekström</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Uganda continues extensive mobilization and administration of the Covid 19 vaccine to its people albeit some vaccine hesitancy with in the population. Amongst the health workers however, approximately 70% had received their first dose while 40% had received their second dose of the Covid-19 vaccine by September 2021 respectively. These figures represent a recognizable acceptance rate among health workers. Exploring motivators to vaccine uptake among health workers is vital for the government’s general population vaccine rollout plan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted 12 focus group discussions and 20 in-depth interviews with health workers (vaccinated and unvaccinated) to understand motivators to vaccine acceptance in their own perspective in central and eastern Uganda. Reported motivators to vaccine acceptance included; risk susceptibility/protection, fear of death and/or cost of treatment and experiences of Covid related grief. Other were trust in the vaccine, call to government policy and vaccine success stories elsewhere, real or perceived benefits of vaccination and peer influence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We recommend intensified dissemination of health worker tailor made tools/guides for information, education and communication about the Covid 19 vaccine. The tools need to emphasize the elicited themes/motivators. We also recommend use of peers who have taken up the vaccine and survived Covid-19 or got a mild form of the disease to elicit positive peer influence about the vaccine amongst health workers. The information dissemination and peer narratives could be done through the health worker’s social media platforms, union or association websites, personal statements, editorials or other media.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.21265494" rel="alternate" title="Health workers Motivators to uptake of the Covid-19 vaccine at Iganga Hospital Eastern Uganda, and Mengo Hospital Kampala Uganda; A qualitative study (3 tweets)"/><category term="Health Systems and Quality Improvement"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>