<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.173320+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.21266735</id><title>Increased risk of infection with SARS-CoV-2 Beta, Gamma, and Delta variant compared to Alpha variant in vaccinated individuals (1266 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.174473+00:00</updated><author><name>Stijn P. Andeweg</name></author><author><name>Harry Vennema</name></author><author><name>Irene Veldhuijzen</name></author><author><name>Naomi Smorenburg</name></author><author><name>Dennis Schmitz</name></author><author><name>Florian Zwagemaker</name></author><author><name>Arianne B. van Gageldonk-Lafeber</name></author><author><name>Susan J.M. Hahné</name></author><author><name>Chantal Reusken</name></author><author><name>Mirjam J. Knol</name></author><author><name>Dirk Eggink</name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The extent to which severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) variants of concern (VOC) break through infection- or vaccine-induced immunity is not well understood. Here, we analyze 28,578 sequenced SARS-CoV-2 samples from individuals with known immune status obtained through national community testing in the Netherlands from March to August 2021. We find evidence for an increased risk of infection by the Beta (B.1.351), Gamma (P.1), or Delta (B.1.617.2) variants compared to the Alpha (B.1.1.7) variant after vaccination. No clear differences were found between vaccines. However, the effect was larger in the first 14-59 days after complete vaccination compared to 60 days and longer. In contrast to vaccine-induced immunity, no increased risk for reinfection with Beta, Gamma or Delta variants relative to Alpha variant was found in individuals with infection-induced immunity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.21266735" rel="alternate" title="Increased risk of infection with SARS-CoV-2 Beta, Gamma, and Delta variant compared to Alpha variant in vaccinated individuals (1266 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.21266484</id><title>Durability of SARS-CoV-2 Antibodies from Natural Infection in Children and Adolescents (233 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.175288+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah E. Messiah</name></author><author><name>Frances Brito</name></author><author><name>Harold W. Kohl</name></author><author><name>Stacia DeSantis</name></author><author><name>Melissa Valerio-Shewmaker</name></author><author><name>Jessica Ross</name></author><author><name>Michael D. Swartz</name></author><author><name>Ashraf Yaseen</name></author><author><name>Steven H. Kelder</name></author><author><name>Shiming Zhang</name></author><author><name>Onyinye S Omega-Njemnobi</name></author><author><name>Michael O. Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Leqing Wu</name></author><author><name>Eric Boerwinkle</name></author><author><name>David Lakey</name></author><author><name>Jennifer A. Shuford</name></author><author><name>Stephen J. Pont</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recent data suggest the SARS-CoV-2 Delta (B.1.617.2) variant is more transmissible among children compared to the Alpha (B.1.1.7) variant. The true incidence and longitudinal presence of antibody response to SARS-CoV-2 infection is not known, however. We provided estimates of antibody response using Texas Coronavirus Antibody REsponse Survey (Texas CARES) data, a prospective population-based seroprevalence project designed to assess antibody status over time among the general population throughout the state.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In October 2020 Texas CARES began enrolling adults (aged 20-80 years) and children (aged 5-19 years). Participants were offered a series of three SARS-CoV-2 antibody tests over 6-8 months, or every 2-3 months that includes the immunoassay for detection of antibodies to the SARS-CoV-2 nucleocapsid protein (Roche N-test). Descriptive characteristics and COVID-19 infection-related symptom status was determined by questionnaire at the time of enrollment and prior to each successive blood draw. This analysis included participants ages 5-to-19 years old who have completed all three antibody assessments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;From our sample (n=159; mean age 12.5 years, SD 3.6), 96% of those with evidence of nucleocapsid antibodies at baseline assessment continued to have antibodies &amp;gt; six months later (mean 7.0 months, SD 0.97). There was no difference in the presence of antibodies by symptom status (asymptotic versus symptomatic) or severity (mild-moderate versus severe), sex, age group, or body mass index group (underweight, healthy weight, overweight, obesity) over the three antibody measurement timepoints.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;These results suggest that infection-induced antibodies persist and thus may provide some protection against future infection for at least half a year. 57.9% of the sample were negative for infection-induced antibodies at their third measurement point, suggesting a significant proportion of children have still not acquired natural infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.21266484" rel="alternate" title="Durability of SARS-CoV-2 Antibodies from Natural Infection in Children and Adolescents (233 tweets)"/><category term="Pediatrics"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469770</id><title>Characterization of the immune resistance of SARS-CoV-2 Mu variant and the immunity induced by Mu infection (101 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.175777+00:00</updated><author><name>Keiya Uriu</name></author><author><name>Paúl Cárdenas</name></author><author><name>Erika Muñoz</name></author><author><name>Veronica Barragan</name></author><author><name>Yusuke Kosugi</name></author><author><name>Kotaro Shirakawa</name></author><author><name>Akifumi Takaori-Kondo</name></author><author><name>Kei Sato</name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We have revealed that the SARS-CoV-2 Mu variant is highly resistant to COVID-19 convalescent sera and vaccine sera.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; However, it remains unclear how the immune resistance of the Mu variant is determined. Also, although the Mu variant is highly resistant to the sera obtained from COVID-19 convalescent during early pandemic (i.e., infected with prototypic virus) and vaccinated individuals (i.e., immunized based on prototypic virus), it was unaddressed how the convalescent sera from Mu-infected individuals function. In this study, we revealed that the two mutations in the spike protein of Mu variant, YY144-145TSN and E484K, are responsible for the potent immune resistance of Mu variant. Additionally, we showed that the convalescent sera obtained from the Mu-infected individuals can be broadly antiviral against the Mu variant as well as other SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern/interest. Our findings suggest that developing novel vaccines based on the Mu variant can be more effective against a broad range of SARS-CoV-2 variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469770" rel="alternate" title="Characterization of the immune resistance of SARS-CoV-2 Mu variant and the immunity induced by Mu infection (101 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266775</id><title>Recurring Spatiotemporal Patterns of COVID-19 in the United States (94 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.176197+00:00</updated><author><name>Hawre Jalal</name></author><author><name>Kyueun Lee</name></author><author><name>Donald S. Burke</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We analyzed the waxing and waning patterns (“surges”) of reported SARS-CoV-2 cases from January 1, 2020 through Oct 31, 2021 in all states and provinces (n = 93) in the USA, Mexico, and Canada, and across all counties (N = 3142) in the USA. A correlation matrix of the 576 × 576 daily case incidence rates in the 50 US states generates a distinctive “checkerboard” pattern showing that the epidemic has consisted of seven distinct internally coherent spatiotemporal wave patterns, four in the first year of the epidemic, and three thus far in the second year. Geoclustering of state case rate trajectories reveals three dominant co-varying spatial clusters of similar case rate trajectories, in the northeastern, southeastern and central/western regions of the USA. The spatiotemporal patterns of epidemic year 1 have thus far been repeated (p&amp;lt;.001) in epidemic year 2. The “checkerboard” pattern of the correlation matrix of case trajectories can be closely simulated as three sets of interacting sine waves with annual frequencies of 1:1:2 major cycles per year, corresponding to the northeastern, central/western, and southeastern state clusters. Case incidence patterns in Mexico and Canada have been similar to nearby regions in the southern US and the northern US, respectively. Time lapse videos allow visualization of the wave patterns. These highly structured geographical and temporal patterns, coupled with emerging evidence of annual repetition of these same patterns, show that SARS-CoV-2 case rates are driven at least in part by predictable seasonal factors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local COVID-19 rates wax and wane. Often these epidemic changes are attributed to localized human behavioral factors. Our finding of highly structured continental scale spatiotemporal patterns that cross state and national boundaries, coupled with emerging evidence of annual repetition of these same patterns, shows that COVID-19 transmission is driven at least in part by seasonal factors. Other epidemic factors such as vaccine coverage rates, or emergence of new strains like the Delta variant of SARS-CoV-2 appear to modify, but not totally eclipse, these underlying seasonal patterns. COVID-19 seasonal transmission patterns are associated with, and may be driven by, seasonal weather patterns. Predictability of these patterns can provide opportunities for forecasting the epidemic and for guiding public health preparedness and control efforts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266775" rel="alternate" title="Recurring Spatiotemporal Patterns of COVID-19 in the United States (94 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.21266401</id><title>Effectiveness of BNT162b2 and ChAdOx1 against SARS-CoV-2 household transmission: a prospective cohort study in England (71 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.176973+00:00</updated><author><name>Samuel Clifford</name></author><author><name>Pauline Waight</name></author><author><name>Jada Hackman</name></author><author><name>Stephane Hué</name></author><author><name>Charlotte M Gower</name></author><author><name>Freja CM Kirsebom</name></author><author><name>Catriona Skarnes</name></author><author><name>Louise Letley</name></author><author><name>Jamie Lopez Bernal</name></author><author><name>Nick Andrews</name></author><author><name>Stefan Flasche</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Miller</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ability of SARS-CoV-2 vaccines to protect against infection and onward transmission determines whether immunisation can control global circulation. We estimated effectiveness of BNT162b2 and ChAdOx1 vaccines against acquisition and transmission of the Alpha and Delta variants in a prospective household study in England.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adult index cases in the community and their household contacts took oral-nasal swabs on days 1, 3 and 7 after enrolment. Swabs were tested by RT-qPCR with genomic sequencing conducted on a subset. We used Bayesian logistic regression to infer vaccine effectiveness against acquisition and transmission, adjusted for age, vaccination history and variant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Between 2 February 2021 and 10 September 2021 213 index cases and 312 contacts were followed up. After excluding households lacking genomic proximity (N=2) or with unlikely serial intervals (N=16), 195 households with 278 contacts remained of whom 113 (41%) became PCR positive. Delta lineages had 1.64 times the risk (95% Credible Interval: 1.15 – 2.44) of transmission than Alpha; contacts older than 18 years were 1.19 times (1.04 - 1.52) more likely to acquire infection than children. Effectiveness of two doses of BNT162b2 against transmission of Delta was 31% (−3%, 61%) and 42% (14%, 69%) for ChAdOx1, similar to their effectiveness for Alpha. Protection against infection with Alpha was higher than for Delta, 71% (12%,95%) vs 24% (−2%, 64%) respectively for BNT162b2 and 26% (−39%, 73%) vs 14% (−5%, 46%) respectively for ChAdOx1.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;BNT162b2 and ChAdOx1 reduce transmission of the Delta variant from breakthrough infections in the household setting though their protection against infection is low.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study was funded by the UK Health Security Agency (formerly Public Health England) as part of the COVID-19 response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.21266401" rel="alternate" title="Effectiveness of BNT162b2 and ChAdOx1 against SARS-CoV-2 household transmission: a prospective cohort study in England (71 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.21266779</id><title>Severe COVID-19 induces molecular signatures of aging in the human brain (59 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.177775+00:00</updated><author><name>Maria Mavrikaki</name></author><author><name>Jonathan D. Lee</name></author><author><name>Isaac H. Solomon</name></author><author><name>Frank J. Slack</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) is predominantly an acute respiratory disease caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) and remains a significant threat to public health. COVID-19 is accompanied by neurological symptoms and cognitive decline, but the molecular mechanisms underlying this effect remain unclear. As aging induces distinct molecular signatures in the brain associated with cognitive decline in healthy populations, we hypothesized that COVID-19 may induce molecular signatures of aging. Here, we performed whole transcriptomic analysis of human frontal cortex, a critical area for cognitive function, in 12 COVID-19 cases and age- and sex-matched uninfected controls. COVID-19 induces profound changes in gene expression, despite the absence of detectable virus in brain tissue. Pathway analysis shows downregulation of genes involved in synaptic function and cognition and upregulation of genes involved in immune processes. Comparison with five independent transcriptomic datasets of aging human frontal cortex reveals striking similarities between aged individuals and severe COVID-19 patients. Critically, individuals below 65 years of age exhibit profound transcriptomic changes not observed among older individuals in our patient cohort. Our data indicate that severe COVID-19 induces molecular signatures of aging in the human brain and emphasize the value of neurological follow-up in recovered individuals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.21266779" rel="alternate" title="Severe COVID-19 induces molecular signatures of aging in the human brain (59 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266690</id><title>Favipiravir for treatment of outpatients with asymptomatic or uncomplicated COVID-19: a double-blind randomized, placebo-controlled, phase 2 trial (49 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.178045+00:00</updated><author><name>Marisa Holubar</name></author><author><name>Aruna Subramanian</name></author><author><name>Natasha Purington</name></author><author><name>Haley Hedlin</name></author><author><name>Bryan Bunning</name></author><author><name>Katharine S. Walter</name></author><author><name>Hector Bonilla</name></author><author><name>Athanasia Boumis</name></author><author><name>Michael Chen</name></author><author><name>Kimberly Clinton</name></author><author><name>Liisa Dewhurst</name></author><author><name>Carol Epstein</name></author><author><name>Prasanna Jagannathan</name></author><author><name>Richard H. Kaszynski</name></author><author><name>Lori Panu</name></author><author><name>Julie Parsonnet</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth L. Ponder</name></author><author><name>Orlando Quintero</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Sefton</name></author><author><name>Upinder Singh</name></author><author><name>Luke Soberanis</name></author><author><name>Henry Truong</name></author><author><name>Jason R. Andrews</name></author><author><name>Manisha Desai</name></author><author><name>Chaitan Khosla</name></author><author><name>Yvonne Maldonado</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Favipiravir is an oral, RNA-dependent RNA polymerase inhibitor with &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; activity against SARS-CoV2. Despite limited data, favipiravir is administered to patients with COVID-19 in several countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted a phase 2 double-blind randomized controlled outpatient trial of favipiravir in asymptomatic or mildly symptomatic adults with a positive SARS-CoV2 RT-PCR within 72 hours of enrollment. Participants were randomized 1:1 to receive placebo or favipiravir (1800 mg BID Day 1, 800mg BID Days 2-10). The primary outcome was SARS-CoV-2 shedding cessation in a modified intention-to-treat (mITT) cohort of participants with positive enrollment RT-PCRs. Using SARS-CoV-2 deep sequencing, we assessed favipiravir’s impact on mutagenesis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;From July 8, 2020 - March 23, 2021, we randomized 149 participants with 116 included in the mITT cohort. The participants’ mean age was 43 years (SD 12.5) and 57 (49%) were women. We found no difference in time to shedding cessation by treatment arm overall (HR 0.76 favoring placebo, 95% confidence interval [CI] 0.48 – 1.20) or in sub-group analyses (age, sex, high-risk comorbidities, seropositivity or symptom duration at enrollment). We observed no difference in time to symptom resolution (initial: HR 0.84, 95% CI 0.54 – 1.29; sustained: HR 0.87, 95% CI 0.52 – 1.45). We detected no difference in accumulation of transition mutations in the viral genome during treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our data do not support favipiravir use at commonly used doses in outpatients with uncomplicated COVID-19. Further research is needed to ascertain if higher doses of favipiravir are effective and safe for patients with COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Trial registration number&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;NCT04346628&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this phase 2 double-blind randomized controlled outpatient trial of favipiravir in asymptomatic or uncomplicated patients with COVID-19, we found no difference in time to shedding cessation or time to symptom resolution by treatment arm.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266690" rel="alternate" title="Favipiravir for treatment of outpatients with asymptomatic or uncomplicated COVID-19: a double-blind randomized, placebo-controlled, phase 2 trial (49 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266692</id><title>Serological responses to COVID-19 booster vaccine in England (44 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.179096+00:00</updated><author><name>Georgina Ireland</name></author><author><name>Heather Whitaker</name></author><author><name>Shamez N Ladhani</name></author><author><name>Frances Baawuah</name></author><author><name>Vani Subbarao</name></author><author><name>Ezra Linley</name></author><author><name>Lenesha Warrener</name></author><author><name>Michelle O’Brien</name></author><author><name>Corinne Whillock</name></author><author><name>Paul Moss</name></author><author><name>Mary E Ramsay</name></author><author><name>Gayatri Amirthalingam</name></author><author><name>Kevin E Brown</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are limited data on immune responses after COVID-19 vaccine boosters in individuals receiving primary immunisation with BNT162b2 (Pfizer-BioNTech) or AZD1222 (AstraZeneca).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A prospective, cohort study to assess SARS-CoV-2 antibody responses before and after booster vaccination with BNT162b2 in adults receiving either (i) two BNT162b2 doses &amp;lt;30 days apart (BNT162b2-control), (ii) two BNT162b2 doses ≥30 days apart (BNT162b2-extended) or (iii) two AZD1222 doses ≥30 days apart (AZD1222-extended) in London, England. SARS-CoV-2 spike protein antibody geometric mean titres (GMTs) before and 2-4 weeks after booster were compared.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of 750 participants, 626 provided serum samples for up to 38 weeks after their second vaccine dose. Antibody GMTs peaked at 2-4 weeks after the second dose, before declining by 68% at 36-38 weeks after dose 2 for BNT162b2-control participants, 85% at 24-29 weeks for BNT162b2-extended participants and 78% at 24-29 weeks for AZD1222-extended participants. Antibody GMTs was highest in BNT162b2-extended participants (942 [95%CI, 797-1113]) than AZD1222-extended (183 [124-268]) participants at 24-29 weeks or BNT162b2-control participants at 36-38 weeks (208; 95%CI, 150-289). At 2-4 weeks after booster, GMTs were significantly higher than after primary vaccination in all three groups: 18,104 (95%CI, 13,911-23,560; n=47) in BNT162b2-control (76.3-fold), 13,980 (11,902-16,421; n=118) in BNT162b2-extended (15.9-fold) and 10,799 (8,510-13,704; n=43) in AZD1222-extended (57.2-fold) participants. BNT162b2-control participants (median:262 days) had a longer interval between primary and booster doses than BNT162b2-extended or AZD1222-extended (both median:186 days) participants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We observed rapid serological responses to boosting with BNT162b2, irrespective of vaccine type or schedule used for primary immunisation, with higher post-booster responses with longer interval between primary immunisation and boosting. Boosters will not only provide additional protection for those at highest risk of severe COVID-19 but also prevent infection and, therefore, interrupt transmission, thereby reducing infections rates in the population. Ongoing surveillance will be important for monitoring the duration of protection after the booster.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266692" rel="alternate" title="Serological responses to COVID-19 booster vaccine in England (44 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469599</id><title>A metagenomic DNA sequencing assay that is robust against environmental DNA contamination (42 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.183246+00:00</updated><author><name>Omary Mzava</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Pellan Cheng</name></author><author><name>Adrienne Chang</name></author><author><name>Sami Smalling</name></author><author><name>Liz-Audrey Djomnang Kounatse</name></author><author><name>Joan Lenz</name></author><author><name>Randy Longman</name></author><author><name>Amy Steadman</name></author><author><name>Mirella Salvatore</name></author><author><name>Manikkam Suthanthiran</name></author><author><name>John R. Lee</name></author><author><name>Christopher E. Mason</name></author><author><name>Darshana Dadhania</name></author><author><name>Iwijn De Vlaminck</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Metagenomic DNA sequencing is a powerful tool to characterize microbial communities but is sensitive to environmental DNA contamination, in particular when applied to samples with low microbial biomass. Here, we present contamination-free metagenomic DNA sequencing (Coffee-seq), a metagenomic sequencing assay that is robust against environmental contamination. The core idea of Coffee-seq is to tag the DNA in the sample prior to DNA isolation and library preparation with a label that can be recorded by DNA sequencing. Any contaminating DNA that is introduced in the sample after tagging can then be bioinformatically identified and removed. We applied Coffee-seq to screen for infections from microorganisms with low burden in blood and urine, to identify COVID-19 co-infection, to characterize the urinary microbiome, and to identify microbial DNA signatures of inflammatory bowel disease in blood.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469599" rel="alternate" title="A metagenomic DNA sequencing assay that is robust against environmental DNA contamination (42 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266767</id><title>An immune correlate of SARS-CoV-2 infection and severity of reinfections (42 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.183682+00:00</updated><author><name>Hannah E. Maier</name></author><author><name>Angel Balmaseda</name></author><author><name>Sergio Ojeda</name></author><author><name>Cristiam Cerpas</name></author><author><name>Nery Sanchez</name></author><author><name>Miguel Plazaola</name></author><author><name>Harm van Bakel</name></author><author><name>John Kubale</name></author><author><name>Roger Lopez</name></author><author><name>Saira Saborio</name></author><author><name>Carlos Barilla</name></author><author><name>Eva Harris</name></author><author><name>Guillermina Kuan</name></author><author><name>Aubree Gordon</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;An immune correlate of protection from SARS-CoV-2 infection is urgently needed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used an ongoing household cohort with an embedded transmission study that closely monitors participants regardless of symptom status. Real-time reverse-transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) and Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assays (ELISAs) were used to measure infections and seropositivity. Sequencing was performed to determine circulating strains of SARS-CoV-2. We investigated the protection associated with seropositivity resulting from prior infection, the anti-spike antibody titers needed for protection, and we compared the severity of first and second infections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In March 2021, 62.3% of the cohort was seropositive. After March 2021, gamma and delta variants predominated. Seropositivity was associated with 69.2% protection from any infection (95% CI: 60.7%-75.9%), with higher protection against moderate or severe infection (79.4%, 95% CI: 64.9%-87.9%). Anti-spike titers of 327 and 2,551 were associated with 50% and 80% protection from any infection; titers of 284 and 656 were sufficient for protection against moderate or severe disease. Second infections were less severe than first infections (Relative Risk (RR) of moderated or severe disease: 0.6, 95% CI: 0.38-0.98; RR of subclinical disease:1.9, 95% CI: 1.33-2.73).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prior infection-induced immunity is protective against infection when predominantly gamma and delta SARS-CoV-2 circulated. The protective antibody titers presented may be useful for vaccine policy and control measures. While second infections were somewhat less severe, they were not as mild as ideal. A strategy involving vaccination will be needed to ease the burden of the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266767" rel="alternate" title="An immune correlate of SARS-CoV-2 infection and severity of reinfections (42 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.21266229</id><title>Efficacy and safety of a novel antiviral preparation in ICU-admitted patients with COVID-19: a phase III randomized controlled trial (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.184349+00:00</updated><author><name>Hossein Faramarzi</name></author><author><name>Amirhossein Sahebkar</name></author><author><name>Ahmad Hosseinpour</name></author><author><name>Vahid Khaloo</name></author><author><name>Parisa Chamanpara</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Reza Heydari</name></author><author><name>Sajad Najafi</name></author><author><name>Fatemeh Fotoohi Khankahdany</name></author><author><name>Ahmad Movahedpour</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite an increasing number of studies, there is as yet no efficient antiviral treatment developed for the disease. In this clinical trial, we examined the efficacy of a novel herbal antiviral preparation comprising &lt;italic&gt;Zataria multiflora Boiss, Glycyrrhiza glabra, Cinnamomum Vermont, Allium sativuml&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;Syzygium aromaticum&lt;/italic&gt; in critically ill patients with COVID-19 patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A total number of 120 ICU-admitted patients requiring pulmonary support with a diagnosis of COVID-19 pneumonia were recruited to the trial. Participants were equally randomized to receive either the novel antiviral preparation sublingually, for up to two consecutive weeks or till discharge, or normal saline as the matching placebo. Clinical and laboratory parameters as well as survival rates were compared between the two groups at the study end.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cumulative incidence of death throughout the study period was 8.33% in the medication group and 60% in the placebo group (risk ratio: 0.14; 95% confidence interval [CI], 0.05 to 0.32; P&amp;lt;0.001). Survival rates were significantly higher in the treatment group. Additionally, on day 7, several laboratory factors including white blood cells (WBCs) count, C-reactive protein (CRP), and SpO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; were improved in patients treated with the novel antiviral preparation compared with the placebo group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The novel antiviral preparation tested in this trial significantly improved the survival rate and reduced mortality in critically ill patients with COVID-19. Thus, this preparation might be suggested as a potentially promising COVID-19 treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Funded by Shimi Teb Salamat Co., Shiraz, Iran, and registered on the Iranian registry of clinical trials (registration No. IRCT20200509047373N2).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.21266229" rel="alternate" title="Efficacy and safety of a novel antiviral preparation in ICU-admitted patients with COVID-19: a phase III randomized controlled trial (30 tweets)"/><category term="Intensive Care and Critical Care Medicine"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266565</id><title>Impacts of vaccination and asymptomatic testing on SARS-CoV-2 transmission dynamics in a university setting (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.185311+00:00</updated><author><name>Emily Nixon</name></author><author><name>Amy Thomas</name></author><author><name>Daniel Stocks</name></author><author><name>Antoine M.G. Barreaux</name></author><author><name>Gibran Hemani</name></author><author><name>Adam Trickey</name></author><author><name>Rachel Kwiatkowska</name></author><author><name>Josephine Walker</name></author><author><name>David Ellis</name></author><author><name>Leon Danon</name></author><author><name>Caroline Relton</name></author><author><name>Hannah Christensen</name></author><author><name>Ellen Brooks-Pollock</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We investigate the impact of vaccination and asymptomatic testing uptake on SARS-CoV-2 transmission in a university student population using a stochastic compartmental model. We find that the magnitude and timing of outbreaks is highly variable under different vaccine uptake levels. With low level interventions (no asymptomatic testing, 30% vaccinated), 53-71% of students become infected during the first term; with high interventions (90% using asymptomatic testing, 90% vaccinated) cumulative incidence is 7-9%, with around 80% of these cases estimated to be asymptomatic. Asymptomatic testing is most useful when vaccine uptake is low: when 30% of students are vaccinated, 90% uptake of asymptomatic testing leads to almost half the case numbers. Under high levels of vaccine uptake (70-90%), case numbers in the student population are largely driven by community importation. Our findings suggest that vaccination is critical for controlling SARS-CoV-2 transmission in university settings with asymptomatic testing being a useful supporting measure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266565" rel="alternate" title="Impacts of vaccination and asymptomatic testing on SARS-CoV-2 transmission dynamics in a university setting (30 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.21266807</id><title>A population framework for predicting the proportion of people infected by the far-field airborne transmission of SARS-CoV-2 indoors (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.185685+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher Iddon</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Jones</name></author><author><name>Patrick Sharpe</name></author><author><name>Muge Cevik</name></author><author><name>Shaun Fitzgerald</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The number of occupants in a space influences the risk of far-field airborne transmission of the SARS-CoV-2 virus because the likelihood of having infectious and susceptible people both scale with the number of occupants. Mass-balance and dose-response models determine far-field transmission risks for an individual person and a population of people after sub-dividing a large &lt;italic&gt;reference&lt;/italic&gt; space into 10 identical &lt;italic&gt;comparator&lt;/italic&gt; spaces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a single infected person when the &lt;italic&gt;per capita&lt;/italic&gt; ventilation rate is preserved, the dose received by an individual person in the &lt;italic&gt;comparator&lt;/italic&gt; space is 10-times higher because the equivalent ventilation rate per infected person is lower.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, accounting for population dispersion, such as the community infection rate, the probability of an infected person being present and uncertainty in their viral load, shows the probability of transmission increases with occupancy. Also, far-field transmission is likely to be a rare event that requires a set of Goldilocks conditions that are &lt;italic&gt;just right&lt;/italic&gt;, when mitigation measures have limited effect.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Therefore, resilient buildings should deliver the equivalent ventilation rate required by standards and increase the space volume per person, but also require reductions in the viral loads and the infection rate of the wider population.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.21266807" rel="alternate" title="A population framework for predicting the proportion of people infected by the far-field airborne transmission of SARS-CoV-2 indoors (26 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469335</id><title>Acute SARS-CoV-2 infection in pregnancy is associated with placental ACE-2 shedding (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.186484+00:00</updated><author><name>Elizabeth S. Taglauer</name></author><author><name>Elisha M. Wachman</name></author><author><name>Lillian Juttukonda</name></author><author><name>Timothy Klouda</name></author><author><name>Jiwon Kim</name></author><author><name>Qiong Wang</name></author><author><name>Asuka Ishiyama</name></author><author><name>David J. Hackam</name></author><author><name>Ke Yuan</name></author><author><name>Hongpeng Jia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human placental tissues have variable rates of SARS-CoV-2 invasion resulting in consistently low rates of fetal transmission suggesting a unique physiologic blockade against SARS-CoV-2. Angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE)-2, the main receptor for SARS-CoV-2, is expressed as cell surface and soluble forms regulated by a metalloprotease cleavage enzyme, ADAM17. ACE-2 is expressed in the human placenta, but the regulation of placental ACE-2 expression in relation to timing of maternal SARS-CoV-2 infection in pregnancy is not well understood. In this study, we evaluated ACE-2 expression, ADAM17 activity and serum ACE-2 abundance in a cohort of matched villous placental and maternal serum samples from Control pregnancies (SARS-CoV-2 negative, n=8) and pregnancies affected by symptomatic maternal SARS-CoV-2 infections in the 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; trimester (“2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt;Tri COVID”, n=8) and 3rd trimester (“3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt;Tri COVID”, n=8). In 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt;Tri COVID as compared to control and 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt;Tri-COVID villous placental tissues ACE-2 mRNA expression was remarkably elevated, however, ACE-2 protein expression was significantly decreased with a parallel increase in ADAM17 activity. Soluble ACE-2 was also significantly increased in the maternal serum from 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt;Tri COVID infections as compared to control and 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt;Tri-COVID pregnancies. These data suggest that in acute maternal SARS-CoV-2 infections, decreased placental ACE-2 protein may be the result of ACE-2 shedding. Overall, this work highlights the importance of ACE-2 for ongoing studies on SARS-CoV-2 responses at the maternal-fetal interface.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469335" rel="alternate" title="Acute SARS-CoV-2 infection in pregnancy is associated with placental ACE-2 shedding (24 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.21266741</id><title>A genome-wide association study of COVID-19 related hospitalization in Spain reveals genetic disparities among sexes (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.186764+00:00</updated><author><name>Ángel Carracedo</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We describe the results of the Spanish Coalition to Unlock Research on Host Genetics on COVID-19 (SCOURGE). In sex-disaggregated genome-wide studies of COVID-19 hospitalization, we found two known loci associated among males (&lt;italic&gt;SLC6A20&lt;/italic&gt;-&lt;italic&gt;LZTFL1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;IFNAR2&lt;/italic&gt;), and a novel one among females (&lt;italic&gt;TLE1&lt;/italic&gt;). Meta-analyses with independent studies revealed two novel associations (&lt;italic&gt;AQP3&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;ARHGAP33&lt;/italic&gt;) and replicated &lt;italic&gt;ELF5&lt;/italic&gt;. A genetic risk score predicted COVID-19 severity, especially among younger males. We found less SNP-heritability and larger heritability differences by age (&amp;lt;60/≥60 years) among males than females. Inbreeding depression was associated with COVID-19 hospitalization and severity, and the effect was stronger among older males.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.21266741" rel="alternate" title="A genome-wide association study of COVID-19 related hospitalization in Spain reveals genetic disparities among sexes (24 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469860</id><title>Nanopore ReCappable Sequencing maps SARS-CoV-2 5' capping sites and provides new insights into the structure of sgRNAs (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.197730+00:00</updated><author><name>Camilla Ugolini</name></author><author><name>Logan Mulroney</name></author><author><name>Adrien Leger</name></author><author><name>Matteo Castelli</name></author><author><name>Elena Criscuolo</name></author><author><name>Maia Kavanagh Williamson</name></author><author><name>Andrew D Davidson</name></author><author><name>Abdulaziz Almuqrin</name></author><author><name>Roberto Giambruno</name></author><author><name>Miten Jain</name></author><author><name>Gianmaria Frigè</name></author><author><name>Hugh Olsen</name></author><author><name>George Tzertzinis</name></author><author><name>Ira Schildkraut</name></author><author><name>Madalee F Wulf</name></author><author><name>Ivan R. Corrêa</name></author><author><name>Laurence Ettwiller</name></author><author><name>Nicola Clementi</name></author><author><name>Massimo Clementi</name></author><author><name>Nicasio Mancini</name></author><author><name>Ewan Birney</name></author><author><name>Mark Akeson</name></author><author><name>Francesco Nicassio</name></author><author><name>David A Matthews</name></author><author><name>Tommaso Leonardi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The SARS-CoV-2 virus has a complex transcriptome characterised by multiple, nested sub genomic RNAs used to express structural and accessory proteins. Long-read sequencing technologies such as nanopore direct RNA sequencing can recover full-length transcripts, greatly simplifying the assembly of structurally complex RNAs. However, these techniques do not detect the 5′ cap, thus preventing reliable identification and quantification of full-length, coding transcript models. Here we used Nanopore ReCappable Sequencing (NRCeq), a new technique that can identify capped full-length RNAs, to assemble a complete annotation of SARS-CoV-2 sgRNAs and annotate the location of capping sites across the viral genome. We obtained robust estimates of sgRNA expression across cell lines and viral isolates and identified novel canonical and non-canonical sgRNAs, including one that uses a previously un-annotated leader-to-body junction site. The data generated in this work constitute a useful resource for the scientific community and provide important insights into the mechanisms that regulate the transcription of SARS-CoV-2 sgRNAs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469860" rel="alternate" title="Nanopore ReCappable Sequencing maps SARS-CoV-2 5' capping sites and provides new insights into the structure of sgRNAs (24 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266709</id><title>COVID-19 vaccination and menstrual cycle changes: A United Kingdom (UK) retrospective case-control study (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.199072+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexandra Alvergne</name></author><author><name>Gabriella Kountourides</name></author><author><name>M. Austin Argentieri</name></author><author><name>Lisa Agyen</name></author><author><name>Natalie Rogers</name></author><author><name>Dawn Knight</name></author><author><name>Gemma C Sharp</name></author><author><name>Jacqueline A Maybin</name></author><author><name>Zuzanna Olszewska</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There has been increasing public concern that COVID-19 vaccines cause menstrual cycle disturbances, yet there is currently limited data to evaluate the impact of vaccination on menstrual health. Our objectives were (1) to evaluate the prevalence of menstrual changes following vaccination against COVID-19, (2) to test potential risk factors for any such changes, and (3) to identify patterns of symptoms in participants’ written accounts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We performed a secondary analysis of a retrospective online survey titled “The Covid-19 Pandemic and Women’s Reproductive Health”, conducted in March 2021 in the UK before widespread media attention regarding potential impacts of SARS-CoV-2 vaccination on menstruation. Participants were recruited via a Facebook ad campaign in the UK and eligibility criteria for survey completion were age greater than 18 years, having ever menstruated and currently living in the UK. In total, 26,710 people gave consent and completed the survey. For this analysis we selected 4,989 participants who were pre-menopausal and vaccinated. These participants were aged 28 to 43, predominantly from England (81%), of white background (95%) and not using hormonal contraception (58%).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among pre-menopausal vaccinated individuals (n=4,989), 80% did not report any menstrual cycle changes up to 4 months after their first COVID-19 vaccine injection. Current use of combined oral contraceptives was associated with lower odds of reporting any changes by 48% (OR = 0.52, 95CI = [0.34 to 0.78], &lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;&amp;lt;0.001). Odds of reporting any menstrual changes were increased by 44% for current smokers (OR = 1.16, 95CI = [1.06 to 1.26], &lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;&amp;lt;0.01) and by more than 50% for individuals with a positive COVID status [Long Covid (OR = 1.61, 95CI = [1.28 to 2.02], &lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;&amp;lt;0.001), acute COVID (OR = 1.54, 95CI = [1.27 to 1.86], &lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;&amp;lt;0.001)]. The effects remain after adjusting for self-reported magnitude of menstrual cycle changes over the year preceding the survey. Written accounts report diverse symptoms; the most common words include “cramps”, “late”, “early”, “spotting”, “heavy” and “irregular”, with a low level of clustering among them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following vaccination for COVID-19, menstrual disturbance occurred in 20% of individuals in a UK sample. Out of 33 variables investigated, smoking and a previous history of SARS-CoV-2 infection were found to be risk factors while using oestradiol-containing contraceptives was found to be a protective factor. Diverse experiences were reported, from menstrual bleeding cessation to heavy menstrual bleeding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266709" rel="alternate" title="COVID-19 vaccination and menstrual cycle changes: A United Kingdom (UK) retrospective case-control study (19 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469695</id><title>Antiviral activity of molnupiravir precursor NHC against Variants of Concern (VOCs) and its therapeutic window in a human lung cell model (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.199448+00:00</updated><author><name>Tessa Prince</name></author><author><name>I’ah Donovan-Banfield</name></author><author><name>Hannah Goldswain</name></author><author><name>Rebekah Penrice-Randal</name></author><author><name>Lance Turtle</name></author><author><name>Tom Fletcher</name></author><author><name>Saye Khoo</name></author><author><name>Julian A. Hiscox</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK Medicines and Regulatory Healthcare Agency (MHRA) have recently licensed the anti-viral drug, molnupiravir, for use in patients with mild-moderate COVID-19 disease with one or more risk factors for serious illness. Treatment with anti-viral drugs is best initiated early to prevent progression to severe disease, although the therapeutic window for intervention has not yet been fully defined.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study aimed to determine the activity of the molnupiravir parent drug (NHC) to different SARS-CoV-2 Variants of Concern (VoCs), and to establish the therapeutic window in human lung cell model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dose response assays were performed in parallel to determine the IC50 (the concentration of drug required to inhibit virus titre by 50%) of NHC against different variants. Human ACE-2 A549 cells were treated with NHC at different time points either before, during or after infection with SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we demonstrate that ß-D-N4-hydroxycytidine (NHC), the active metabolite of molnupiravir, has equivalent activity against four variants of SARS-CoV-2 in a human lung cell line ranging 0.04-0.16µM IC50. Furthermore, we demonstrate that activity of the drug begins to drop after 48 hours post-infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the main advantages of molnupiravir is that it can be administered orally, and thus given to patients in an out-patient setting. These results support giving the drug early on after diagnosis or even in prophylaxis for individuals with high risk of developing severe disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469695" rel="alternate" title="Antiviral activity of molnupiravir precursor NHC against Variants of Concern (VOCs) and its therapeutic window in a human lung cell model (18 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266574</id><title>Reinfection with SARS-CoV-2: outcome, risk factors and vaccine efficacy in a Scottish cohort (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.199931+00:00</updated><author><name>Paul M McKeigue</name></author><author><name>David A McAllister</name></author><author><name>Chris Robertson</name></author><author><name>Diane Stockton</name></author><author><name>Helen M Colhoun</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The objective of this study was to investigate how protection against COVID-19 conferred by previous infection is modified by vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a cohort of all 152655 individuals in Scotland alive at 90 days after a positive test for SARS-CoV-2 (confirmed by cycle threshold &amp;lt; 30, or two tests) followed till 22 September 2021, rate ratios for reinfection were estimated with calendar time or tests as timescale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rates of detected and hospitalised reinfection with COVID-19 while unvaccinated were respectively 6.8 (95% CI 6.4 to 7.2) and 0.18 (95% CI 0.12 to 0.25) per 1000 person-months. These rates were respectively 68% and 74% lower than in a matched cohort of individuals who had not previously tested positive. Efficacy of two doses of vaccine in those with previous infection was estimated as as 84% (95 percent CI 81% to 86%) against detected reinfection and 71% (95 percent CI 29% to 88%) against hospitalised or fatal reinfection. The rate of detected reinfection after two doses of vaccine was 1.35 (95% CI 1.02 to 1.78) times higher in those vaccinated before first infection than in those unvaccinated at first infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The combination of natural infection and vaccination provides maximal protection against new infection with SARS-CoV-2: prior vaccination does not impair this protection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;No specific funding was received for this work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Research in context&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Evidence before this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a recent systematic review of cohort studies reported up to July 2021, the average reduction in COVID-19 infection rates in those with previous infection compared with those without evidence of previous infection was 90%. There is little information about the protective effect of previous infection against severe COVID-19, or about how the protective effects of previous infection against reinfection and severe disease are modified by vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What this paper adds&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In unvaccinated individuals the protection against hospitalised COVID-19 conferred by previous infection is similar to that induced by vaccination. In those with previous infection, vaccination reduces the rates of reinfection and hospitalised COVID-19 by about 70%.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Implications of all the available evidence&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The combination of natural infection and vaccination provides maximal protection against COVID-19: prior vaccination does not seriously impair this protection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266574" rel="alternate" title="Reinfection with SARS-CoV-2: outcome, risk factors and vaccine efficacy in a Scottish cohort (18 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.469409</id><title>Airway epithelial interferon response to SARS-CoV-2 is inferior to rhinovirus and heterologous rhinovirus infection suppresses SARS-CoV-2 replication (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.200294+00:00</updated><author><name>Elizabeth R. Vanderwall</name></author><author><name>Kaitlyn A. Barrow</name></author><author><name>Lucille M. Rich</name></author><author><name>David F. Read</name></author><author><name>Cole Trapnell</name></author><author><name>Oghenemega Okoloko</name></author><author><name>Steven F. Ziegler</name></author><author><name>Teal S. Hallstrand</name></author><author><name>Maria P. White</name></author><author><name>Jason S. Debley</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Common alphacoronaviruses and human rhinoviruses (HRV) induce type I and III interferon (IFN) responses important to limiting viral replication in the airway epithelium. In contrast, highly pathogenic betacoronaviruses including SARS-CoV-2 may evade or antagonize RNA-induced IFN I/III responses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In airway epithelial cells (AECs) from children and older adults we compared IFN I/III responses to SARS-CoV-2 and HRV-16, and assessed whether pre-infection with HRV-16, or pretreatment with recombinant IFN-β or IFN-λ, modified SARS-CoV-2 replication. Bronchial AECs from children (ages 6-18 yrs.) and older adults (ages 60-75 yrs.) were differentiated &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; to generate organotypic cultures. In a biosafety level 3 (BSL-3) facility, cultures were infected with SARS-CoV-2 or HRV-16, and RNA and protein was harvested from cell lysates 96 hrs. following infection and supernatant was collected 48 and 96 hrs. following infection. In additional experiments cultures were pre-infected with HRV-16, or pre-treated with recombinant IFN-β1 or IFN-λ2 before SARS-CoV-2 infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite significant between-donor heterogeneity SARS-CoV-2 replicated 100 times more efficiently than HRV-16. IFNB1, INFL2, and CXCL10 gene expression and protein production following HRV-16 infection was significantly greater than following SARS-CoV-2. IFN gene expression and protein production were inversely correlated with SARS-CoV-2 replication. Treatment of cultures with recombinant IFNβ1 or IFNλ2, or pre-infection of cultures with HRV-16, markedly reduced SARS-CoV-2 replication.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Discussion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition to marked between-donor heterogeneity in IFN responses and viral replication, SARS-CoV-2 elicits a less robust IFN response in primary AEC cultures than does rhinovirus, and heterologous rhinovirus infection, or treatment with recombinant IFN-β1 or IFN-λ2, markedly reduces SARS-CoV-2 replication.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.469409" rel="alternate" title="Airway epithelial interferon response to SARS-CoV-2 is inferior to rhinovirus and heterologous rhinovirus infection suppresses SARS-CoV-2 replication (18 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469663</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern Alpha, Beta, Gamma and Delta have extended ACE2 receptor host-ranges (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.200734+00:00</updated><author><name>Nazia Thakur</name></author><author><name>Giulia Gallo</name></author><author><name>Joseph Newman</name></author><author><name>Thomas P. Peacock</name></author><author><name>Luca Biasetti</name></author><author><name>Catherine N. Hall</name></author><author><name>Edward Wright</name></author><author><name>Wendy Barclay</name></author><author><name>Dalan Bailey</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Following the emergence of SARS-CoV-2 in China in late 2019 a number of variants have emerged, with two of these – Alpha and Delta – subsequently growing to global prevalence. One characteristic of these variants are changes within the Spike protein, in particular the receptor binding domain (RBD). From a public health perspective these changes have important implications for increased transmissibility and immune escape; however, their presence could also modify the intrinsic host-range of the virus. Using viral pseudotyping we examined whether the variants of concern (VOCs) Alpha, Beta, Gamma and Delta have differing host ACE2 receptor usage patterns, focusing on a range of relevant mammalian ACE2 proteins. All four VOCs were able to overcome a previous restriction for mouse ACE2, with demonstrable differences also seen for individual VOCs with rat, ferret or civet ACE2 receptors, changes which we subsequently attribute to N501Y and E484K substitutions within the Spike RBD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469663" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern Alpha, Beta, Gamma and Delta have extended ACE2 receptor host-ranges (16 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469537</id><title>Neurotoxic Amyloidogenic Peptides Identified in the Proteome of SARS-COV2: Potential Implications for Neurological Symptoms in COVID-19 (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.201192+00:00</updated><author><name>Saba Islam</name></author><author><name>Mirren Charnley</name></author><author><name>Guneet Bindra</name></author><author><name>Julian Ratcliffe</name></author><author><name>Jiangtao Zhou</name></author><author><name>Raffaele Mezzenga</name></author><author><name>Mark Hulett</name></author><author><name>Kyunghoon Han</name></author><author><name>Joshua T. Berryman</name></author><author><name>Nicholas P. Reynolds</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 is primarily known as a respiratory disease caused by the virus SARS-CoV-2. However, neurological symptoms such as memory loss, sensory confusion, cognitive and psychiatric issues, severe headaches, and even stroke are reported in as many as 30% of cases and can persist even after the infection is over (so-called ‘long COVID’). These neurological symptoms are thought to be caused by brain inflammation, triggered by the virus infecting the central nervous system of COVID-19 patients, however we still don’t fully understand the mechanisms for these symptoms. The neurological effects of COVID-19 share many similarities to neurodegenerative diseases such as Alzheimer’s and Parkinson’s in which the presence of cytotoxic protein-based amyloid aggregates is a common etiological feature. Following the hypothesis that some neurological symptoms of COVID-19 may also follow an amyloid etiology we performed a bioinformatic scan of the SARS-CoV-2 proteome, detecting peptide fragments that were predicted to be highly amyloidogenic. We selected two of these peptides and discovered that they do rapidly self-assemble into amyloid. Furthermore, these amyloid assemblies were shown to be highly toxic to a neuronal cell line. We introduce and support the idea that cytotoxic amyloid aggregates of SARS-CoV-2 proteins are causing some of the neurological symptoms commonly found in COVID-19 and contributing to long COVID, especially those symptoms which are novel to long COVID in contrast to other post-viral syndromes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469537" rel="alternate" title="Neurotoxic Amyloidogenic Peptides Identified in the Proteome of SARS-COV2: Potential Implications for Neurological Symptoms in COVID-19 (15 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.469369</id><title>Decidual immune response following COVID-19 during pregnancy varies by timing of maternal SARS-CoV-2 infection (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.201559+00:00</updated><author><name>Lillian J. Juttukonda</name></author><author><name>Elisha M. Wachman</name></author><author><name>Jeffery Boateng</name></author><author><name>Mayuri Jain</name></author><author><name>Yoel Benarroch</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth S. Taglauer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;While COVID-19 infection during pregnancy is common, fetal transmission is rare, suggesting that intrauterine mechanisms form an effective blockade against SARS-CoV-2. Key among these is the decidual immune environment of the placenta. We hypothesized that decidual leukocytes are altered by maternal SARS-CoV-2 infection in pregnancy and that this decidual immune resonse is shaped by the timing of infection during gestation. To address this hypothesis, we collected decidua basalis tissues at delivery from women with symptomatic COVID-19 during second (2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; Tri COVID, n=8) or third trimester (3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; Tri COVID, n=8) and SARS-CoV-2-negative controls (Control, n=8). Decidual natural killer (NK) cells, macrophages and T cells were evaluated using quantitative microscopy, and pro- and anti-inflammatory cytokine mRNA expression was evaluated using quantitative reverse transcriptase PCR (qRT-PCR). When compared with the Control group, decidual tissues from 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; Tri COVID exhibited significantly increased macrophages, NK cells and T cells, whereas 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; Tri COVID only had significantly increased T cells. In evaluating decidual cytokine expression, we noted that IL-6, IL-8, IL-10 and TNF-α were significantly correlated with macrophage cell abundance. However, in 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; Tri COVID tissues, there was significant downregulation of IL-6, IL-8, IL-10, and TNF-α. Taken together, these results suggest innate and adaptive immune responses are present at the maternal-fetal interface in maternal SARS-CoV-2 infections late in pregnancy, and that infections earlier in pregnancy show evidence of a resolving immune response. Further studies are warranted to characterize the full scope of intrauterine immune responses in pregnancies affected by maternal COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.469369" rel="alternate" title="Decidual immune response following COVID-19 during pregnancy varies by timing of maternal SARS-CoV-2 infection (15 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469642</id><title>Unambiguous detection of SARS-CoV-2 subgenomic mRNAs with single cell RNA sequencing (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.201843+00:00</updated><author><name>Phillip Cohen</name></author><author><name>Emma J DeGrace</name></author><author><name>Oded Danziger</name></author><author><name>Roosheel S Patel</name></author><author><name>Brad R Rosenberg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single cell RNA sequencing (scRNAseq) studies have provided critical insight into the pathogenesis of Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome CoronaVirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), the causative agent of COronaVIrus Disease 2019 (COVID-19). scRNAseq workflows are generally designed for the detection and quantification of eukaryotic host mRNAs and not viral RNAs. The performance of different scRNAseq methods to study SARS-CoV-2 RNAs has not been thoroughly evaluated. Here, we compare different scRNAseq methods for their ability to quantify and detect SARS-CoV-2 RNAs with a focus on subgenomic mRNAs (sgmRNAs), which are produced only during active viral replication and not present in viral particles. We present a data processing strategy, single cell CoronaVirus sequencing (scCoVseq), which quantifies reads unambiguously assigned to sgmRNAs or genomic RNA (gRNA). Compared to standard 10X Genomics Chromium Next GEM Single Cell 3′ (10X 3′) and Chromium Next GEM Single Cell V(D)J (10X 5′) sequencing, we find that 10X 5′ with an extended R1 sequencing strategy maximizes the unambiguous detection of sgmRNAs by increasing the number of reads spanning leader-sgmRNA junction sites. Differential gene expression testing and KEGG enrichment analysis of infected cells compared with bystander or mock cells showed an enrichment for COVID19-associated genes, supporting the ability of our method to accurately identify infected cells. Our method allows for quantification of coronavirus sgmRNA expression at single-cell resolution, and thereby supports high resolution studies of the dynamics of coronavirus RNA synthesis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Single cell RNA sequencing (scRNAseq) has emerged as a valuable tool to study host-viral interactions particularly in the context of COronaVIrus Disease-2019 (COVID-19). scRNAseq has been developed and optimized for analyzing eukaryotic mRNAs, and the ability of scRNAseq to measure RNAs produced by Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) has not been fully characterized. Here we compare the performance of different scRNAseq methods to detect and quantify SARS-CoV-2 RNAs and develop an analysis workflow to specifically quantify unambiguous reads derived from SARS-CoV-2 genomic RNA and subgenomic mRNAs. Our work demonstrates the strengths and limitations of scRNAseq to measure SARS-CoV-2 RNA and identifies experimental and analytical approaches that allow for SARS-CoV-2 RNA detection and quantification. These developments will allow for studies of coronavirus RNA biogenesis at single-cell resolution to improve our understanding of viral pathogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469642" rel="alternate" title="Unambiguous detection of SARS-CoV-2 subgenomic mRNAs with single cell RNA sequencing (14 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266766</id><title>Vaccination strategies in structured populations under partial immunity and reinfection (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.202131+00:00</updated><author><name>Gabriel Rodriguez-Maroto</name></author><author><name>Iker Atienza-Diez</name></author><author><name>Saúl Ares</name></author><author><name>Susanna Manrubia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Optimal protocols of vaccine administration to minimize the effects of infectious diseases depend on a number of variables that admit different degrees of control. Examples include the characteristics of the disease and how it impacts on different groups of individuals as a function of sex, age or socioeconomic status, its transmission mode, or the demographic structure of the affected population. Here we introduce a compartmental model of infection propagation with vaccination and reinfection and analyse the effect that variations on the rates of these two processes have on the progression of the disease and on the number of fatalities. The population is split into two groups to highlight the overall effects on disease caused by different relationships between vaccine administration and various demographic structures. We show that optimal administration protocols depend on the vaccination rate, a variable severely conditioned by vaccine supply and acceptance. As a practical example, we study COVID-19 dynamics in various countries using real demographic data. The model can be easily applied to any other disease and demographic structure through a suitable estimation of parameter values. Simulations of the general model can be carried out at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://mybinder.org/v2/gh/IkerAtienza/SIYRD/main?urlpath=%2Fvoila%2Frender%2FSimulator.ipynb"&gt;this interactive webpage&lt;/ext-link&gt; [1].&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vaccination campaigns can have varying degrees of success in minimizing the effects of an infectious disease. It is often very difficult to assess &lt;italic&gt;a priori&lt;/italic&gt; the importance and effect of different relevant factors. To gain insight into this problem, we present a model of infection propagation with vaccination and use it to study the effects of vaccination rate and population structure. We find that when the disease affects in different ways distinct population groups, the best vaccination strategy depends non-trivially on the rate at which vaccines can be administered. The application of our analysis to COVID-19 reveals that, in countries with aged populations, the best strategy is always to vaccinate first the elderly, while for youthful populations maximizing vaccination rate regardless of other considerations may save more lives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266766" rel="alternate" title="Vaccination strategies in structured populations under partial immunity and reinfection (13 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266734</id><title>Establishing and characterising large COVID-19 cohorts after mapping the Information System for Research in Primary Care in Catalonia to the OMOP Common Data Model (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.202575+00:00</updated><author><name>Edward Burn</name></author><author><name>Sergio Fernández-Bertolín</name></author><author><name>Erica A Voss</name></author><author><name>Clair Blacketer</name></author><author><name>Maria Aragón</name></author><author><name>Martina Recalde</name></author><author><name>Elena Roel</name></author><author><name>Andrea Pistillo</name></author><author><name>Berta Raventós</name></author><author><name>Carlen Reyes</name></author><author><name>Sebastiaan van Sandijk</name></author><author><name>Lars Halvorsen</name></author><author><name>Peter R Rijnbeek</name></author><author><name>Talita Duarte-Salles</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Few datasets have been established that capture the full breadth of COVID-19 patient interactions with a health system. Our first objective was to create a COVID-19 dataset that linked primary care data to COVID-19 testing, hospitalisation, and mortality data at a patient level. Our second objective was to provide a descriptive analysis of COVID-19 outcomes among the general population and describe the characteristics of the affected individuals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We mapped patient-level data from Catalonia, Spain, to the Observational Medical Outcomes Partnership (OMOP) Common Data Model (CDM). More than 3,000 data quality checks were performed to assess the readiness of the database for research. Subsequently, to summarise the COVID-19 population captured, we established a general population cohort as of the 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; March 2020 and identified outpatient COVID-19 diagnoses or positive test results for SARS-CoV-2, hospitalisations with COVID-19, and COVID-19 deaths during follow-up, which went up until 30&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; June 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mapping data to the OMOP CDM was performed and high data quality was observed. The mapped database was used to identify a total of 5,870,274 individuals, who were included in the general population cohort as of 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; March 2020. Over follow up, 604,472 had either an outpatient COVID-19 diagnosis or positive test result, 58,991 had a hospitalisation with COVID-19, 5,642 had an ICU admission with COVID-19, and 11,233 had a COVID-19 death. People who were hospitalised or died were more commonly older, male, and with more comorbidities. Those admitted to ICU with COVID-19 were generally younger and more often male than those hospitalised in general and those who died.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have established a comprehensive dataset that captures COVID-19 diagnoses, test results, hospitalisations, and deaths in Catalonia, Spain. Extensive data checks have shown the data to be fit for use. From this dataset, a general population cohort of 5.9 million individuals was identified and their COVID-19 outcomes over time were described.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generalitat de Catalunya and European Health Data and Evidence Network (EHDEN).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266734" rel="alternate" title="Establishing and characterising large COVID-19 cohorts after mapping the Information System for Research in Primary Care in Catalonia to the OMOP Common Data Model (13 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266681</id><title>In vitro, classical complement activation differs by disease severity and between SARS-CoV-2 antigens (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.204769+00:00</updated><author><name>Rachel E Lamerton</name></author><author><name>Edith Marcial Juarez</name></author><author><name>Sian E Faustini</name></author><author><name>Marisol E Perez-Toledo</name></author><author><name>Margaret Goodall</name></author><author><name>Sian E Jossi</name></author><author><name>Maddy L Newby</name></author><author><name>Iain Chapple</name></author><author><name>Thomas Dietrich</name></author><author><name>Tonny Veenith</name></author><author><name>Adrian M Shields</name></author><author><name>Lorraine Harper</name></author><author><name>Ian R Henderson</name></author><author><name>Julie Rayes</name></author><author><name>David C Wraith</name></author><author><name>Steve P Watson</name></author><author><name>Max Crispin</name></author><author><name>Mark T Drayson</name></author><author><name>Alex G Richter</name></author><author><name>Adam F Cunningham</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antibodies specific for the spike glycoprotein (S) and nucleocapsid (N) SARS-CoV-2 proteins are typically present during severe COVID-19, and induced to S after vaccination. The binding of viral antigens by antibody can initiate the classical complement pathway. Since complement could play pathological or protective roles at distinct times during SARS-CoV-2 infection we determined levels of antibody-dependent complement activation along the complement cascade. Here, we used an ELISA assay to assess complement protein binding (C1q) and the deposition of C4b, C3b, and C5b to S and N antigens in the presence of anti-SARS-CoV-2 antibodies from different test groups: non-infected, single and double vaccinees, non-hospitalised convalescent (NHC) COVID-19 patients and convalescent hospitalised (ITU-CONV) COVID-19 patients. C1q binding correlates strongly with antibody responses, especially IgG1 levels. However, detection of downstream complement components, C4b, C3b and C5b shows some variability associated with the antigen and subjects studied. In the ITU-CONV, detection of C3b-C5b to S was observed consistently, but this was not the case in the NHC group. This is in contrast to responses to N, where median levels of complement deposition did not differ between the NHC and ITU-CONV groups. Moreover, for S but not N, downstream complement components were only detected in sera with higher IgG1 levels. Therefore, the classical pathway is activated by antibodies to multiple SARS-CoV-2 antigens, but the downstream effects of this activation may differ depending on the specific antigen targeted and the disease status of the subject.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266681" rel="alternate" title="In vitro, classical complement activation differs by disease severity and between SARS-CoV-2 antigens (13 tweets)"/><category term="Allergy and Immunology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469714</id><title>LRRC15 is an inhibitory receptor blocking SARS-CoV-2 spike-mediated entry in trans (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.205704+00:00</updated><author><name>Jaewon Song</name></author><author><name>Ryan D. Chow</name></author><author><name>Mario Pena-Hernandez</name></author><author><name>Li Zhang</name></author><author><name>Skylar A. Loeb</name></author><author><name>Eui-Young So</name></author><author><name>Olin D. Liang</name></author><author><name>Craig B. Wilen</name></author><author><name>Sanghyun Lee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 infection is mediated by the entry receptor ACE2. Although attachment factors and co-receptors facilitating entry are extensively studied, cellular entry factors inhibiting viral entry are largely unknown. Using a &lt;italic&gt;surface&lt;/italic&gt;ome CRISPR activation screen, we identified human LRRC15 as an inhibitory receptor for SARS-CoV-2 entry. LRRC15 directly binds to the receptor-binding domain (RBD) of spike protein with a moderate affinity and inhibits spike-mediated entry. Analysis of human lung single cell RNA sequencing dataset reveals that expression of LRRC15 is primarily detected in fibroblasts and particularly enriched in pathological fibroblasts in COVID-19 patients. &lt;italic&gt;ACE2&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;LRRC15&lt;/italic&gt; are not co-expressed in the same cell types in the lung. Strikingly, expression of LRRC15 in ACE2-negative cells blocks spike-mediated viral entry in ACE2+ cell &lt;italic&gt;in trans&lt;/italic&gt;, suggesting a protective role of LRRC15 in a physiological context. Therefore, LRRC15 represents an inhibitory receptor for SARS-CoV-2 regulating viral entry &lt;italic&gt;in trans&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469714" rel="alternate" title="LRRC15 is an inhibitory receptor blocking SARS-CoV-2 spike-mediated entry in trans (12 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266512</id><title>Association of COVID-19 with arterial and venous vascular diseases: a population-wide cohort study of 48 million adults in England and Wales (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.205926+00:00</updated><author><name>Rochelle Knight</name></author><author><name>Venexia Walker</name></author><author><name>Samantha Ip</name></author><author><name>Jennifer A Cooper</name></author><author><name>Thomas Bolton</name></author><author><name>Spencer Keene</name></author><author><name>Rachel Denholm</name></author><author><name>Ashley Akbari</name></author><author><name>Hoda Abbasizanjani</name></author><author><name>Fatemeh Torabi</name></author><author><name>Efosa Omigie</name></author><author><name>Sam Hollings</name></author><author><name>Teri-Louise North</name></author><author><name>Renin Toms</name></author><author><name>Emanuele Di Angelantonio</name></author><author><name>Spiros Denaxas</name></author><author><name>Johan H Thygesen</name></author><author><name>Christopher Tomlinson</name></author><author><name>Ben Bray</name></author><author><name>Craig J Smith</name></author><author><name>Mark Barber</name></author><author><name>George Davey Smith</name></author><author><name>Nishi Chaturvedi</name></author><author><name>Cathie Sudlow</name></author><author><name>William N Whiteley</name></author><author><name>Angela Wood</name></author><author><name>Jonathan A C Sterne</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The long-term effects of COVID-19 on the incidence of vascular diseases are unclear.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To quantify the association between time since diagnosis of COVID-19 and vascular disease, overall and by age, sex, ethnicity, and pre-existing disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cohort study based on population-wide linked electronic health records, with follow up from January 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; to December 7&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting and participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adults registered with an NHS general practice in England or Wales and alive on January 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Exposures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Time since diagnosis of COVID-19 (categorised as 0-6 days, 1-2 weeks, 3-4, 5-8, 9-12, 13-26 and 27-49 weeks since diagnosis), with and without hospitalisation within 28 days of diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main outcomes and measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Primary outcomes were arterial thromboses (mainly acute myocardial infarction and ischaemic stroke) and venous thromboembolic events (VTE, mainly pulmonary embolism and lower limb deep vein thrombosis). We also studied other vascular events (transient ischaemic attack, haemorrhagic stroke, heart failure and angina). Hazard ratios were adjusted for demographic characteristics, previous disease diagnoses, comorbidities and medications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among 48 million adults, 130,930 were and 1,315,471 were not hospitalised within 28 days of COVID-19. In England, there were 259,742 first arterial thromboses and 60,066 first VTE during 41.6 million person-years follow-up. Adjusted hazard ratios (aHRs) for first arterial thrombosis compared with no COVID-19 declined rapidly from 21.7 (95% CI 21.0-22.4) to 3.87 (3.58-4.19) in weeks 1 and 2 after COVID-19, 2.80 (2.61-3.01) during weeks 3-4 then to 1.34 (1.21-1.48) during weeks 27-49. aHRs for first VTE declined from 33.2 (31.3-35.2) and 8.52 (7.59-9.58) in weeks 1 and 2 to 7.95 (7.28-8.68) and 4.26 (3.86-4.69) during weeks 3-4 and 5-8, then 2.20 (1.99-2.44) and 1.80 (1.50-2.17) during weeks 13-26 and 27-49 respectively. aHRs were higher, for longer after diagnosis, after hospitalised than non-hospitalised COVID-19. aHRs were also higher among people of Black and Asian than White ethnicity and among people without than with a previous event. Across the whole population estimated increases in risk of arterial thromboses and VTEs were 2.5% and 0.6% respectively 49 weeks after COVID-19, corresponding to 7,197 and 3,517 additional events respectively after 1.4 million COVID-19 diagnoses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions and Relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;High rates of vascular disease early after COVID-19 diagnosis decline more rapidly for arterial thromboses than VTEs but rates remain elevated up to 49 weeks after COVID_19. These results support continued policies to avoid COVID-19 infection with effective COVID-19 vaccines and use of secondary preventive agents in high-risk patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Question&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is COVID-19 associated with higher long-term incidence of vascular diseases?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this cohort study of 48 million adults in England and Wales, COVID-19 was associated with higher incidence, that declined with time since diagnosis, of both arterial thromboses [week 1: adjusted HR [aHR] 21.7 (95% CI 21.0-22.4) weeks 27-49: aHR 1.34 (1.21-1.48)] and venous thromboembolism [week 1: aHR 33.2 (31.3-35.2), weeks 27–49 1.80 (1.50-2.17)]. aHRs were higher, for longer, after hospitalised than non-hospitalised COVID-19. The estimated excess number of arterial thromboses and venous thromboembolisms was 10,500.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Meaning&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Avoidance of COVID-19 infection through vaccination, and use of secondary preventive agents after infection in high-risk patients, may reduce post-COVID-19 acute vascular diseases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266512" rel="alternate" title="Association of COVID-19 with arterial and venous vascular diseases: a population-wide cohort study of 48 million adults in England and Wales (12 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266522</id><title>A comparison of health care use after severe COVID-19, respiratory syncytial virus, and influenza in children (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.206247+00:00</updated><author><name>Vilde Bergstad Larsen</name></author><author><name>Ketil Størdal</name></author><author><name>Kjetil Telle</name></author><author><name>Fredrik Methi</name></author><author><name>Karin Magnusson</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We aimed to explore whether children in hospital care with COVID-19 have increased post-discharge health care use when compared to children in hospital care with 1) RSV infection, and 2) other RTIs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 34,214 children aged 1 month to 5 years who were registered with one or more hospital contacts with COVID-19 (N=128), RSV infection (N=4,009) or other RTIs (upper- and lower unspecified RTI as well as influenza) (N=34,457) (January 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt;, 2017 to September 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;, 2021), we used a pre-post study design to investigate the individual all-cause primary and specialist health care use from 12 weeks prior to hospital admission, to 12 weeks after hospital discharge, stratified on infants (1-12 months) and toddlers (1-5 years).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found a slight increase in primary health care use in the first four weeks after discharge for children aged 1-12 months with COVID-19 when compared to children with RSV infection (0.064 percentage points, 95% CI 0.02-0.126, 0.52% relative increase). For children aged 1-5 years, COVID-19 discharge was associated with a 1-4 weeks increase in primary health care use when compared to children with RSV infection (0.068 percentage points, 95% CI 0.022-0.144, 0.53% relative increase) and other RTI (0.046 percentage points, 95% CI 0.002-0.091, 0.45% relative increase). For children aged 1-12 months in hospital care with COVID-19, we found a similar-magnitude-increase in post-discharge inpatient specialist care use, which lasted for 12 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our findings imply no severe impact on health care use after hospitalization with COVID-19 compared to hospitalization with RSV infection or other RTIs. The etiological mechanisms for potentially worse post-hospitalization complaints or health-seeking behavior for COVID-19 than for other RTIs in children should be further explored.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266522" rel="alternate" title="A comparison of health care use after severe COVID-19, respiratory syncytial virus, and influenza in children (11 tweets)"/><category term="Health Economics"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469276</id><title>Hypertonic saline and aprotinin based blockage of SARS-CoV-2 specific furin site cleavage by inhibition of nasal protease activity (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.206417+00:00</updated><author><name>Clarissa Li</name></author><author><name>Adam W. Li</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 enters into the human body mainly through the nasal epithelial cells. Cell entry of SARS-CoV-2 needs to be pre-activated by S1/S2 boundary furin motif cleavage by furin and/or relevant proteases. It is important to locally block SARS-CoV-2 S1/S2 site cleavage caused by furin and other relevant protease activity in the nasal cavity. We tested hypertonic saline and aprotinin-based blockage of SARS-CoV-2 specific furin site cleavage by furin, trypsin and nasal swab samples containing nasal proteases. Our results show that saline and aprotinin block SARS-Cov-2 specific furin site cleavage and that a saline and aprotinin combination could significantly reduce SARS-Cov-2 wild-type and P681R mutant furin site cleavage by inhibition of nasal protease activity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469276" rel="alternate" title="Hypertonic saline and aprotinin based blockage of SARS-CoV-2 specific furin site cleavage by inhibition of nasal protease activity (10 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469842</id><title>Single-domain antibodies efficiently neutralize SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.206578+00:00</updated><author><name>Irina A. Favorskaya</name></author><author><name>Dmitry V. Shcheblyakov</name></author><author><name>Ilias B. Esmagambetov</name></author><author><name>Inna V. Dolzhikova</name></author><author><name>Irina A. Alekseeva</name></author><author><name>Anastasia I. Korobkova</name></author><author><name>Daria V. Voronina</name></author><author><name>Ekaterina I. Ryabova</name></author><author><name>Artem A. Derkaev</name></author><author><name>Anna V. Kovyrshina</name></author><author><name>Anna A. Iliukhina</name></author><author><name>Andrey G. Botikov</name></author><author><name>Olga L. Voronina</name></author><author><name>Daria A. Egorova</name></author><author><name>Olga V. Zubkova</name></author><author><name>Natalia N. Ryzhova</name></author><author><name>Ekaterina I. Aksenova</name></author><author><name>Marina S. Kunda</name></author><author><name>Denis Y. Logunov</name></author><author><name>Boris S. Naroditsky</name></author><author><name>Alexandr L. Gintsburg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Virus-neutralizing antibodies are one of the few treatment options for COVID-19. The evolution of SARS-CoV-2 virus has led to the emergence of virus variants with reduced sensitivity to some antibody-based therapies. The development of potent antibodies with a broad spectrum of neutralizing activity is urgently needed. Here we isolated a panel of single-domain antibodies that specifically bind to the receptor-binding domain of SARS-CoV-2 S glycoprotein. Three of the selected antibodies exhibiting most robust neutralization potency were used to generate dimeric molecules. We observed that these modifications resulted in up to a 200-fold increase in neutralizing activity. The most potent heterodimeric molecule efficiently neutralized each of SARS-CoV-2 variant of concern, including Alpha, Beta, Gamma and Delta variants. This heterodimeric molecule could be a promising drug candidate for a treatment for COVID-19 caused by virus variants of concern.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469842" rel="alternate" title="Single-domain antibodies efficiently neutralize SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (10 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266676</id><title>Investigating SARS-CoV-2 breakthrough infections per variant and vaccine type (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.206916+00:00</updated><author><name>Jozef Dingemans</name></author><author><name>Brian M.J.W. van der Veer</name></author><author><name>Koen M.F. Gorgels</name></author><author><name>Volker Hackert</name></author><author><name>Audrey Y.J. Hensels</name></author><author><name>Casper D.J. den Heijer</name></author><author><name>Christian J.P.A Hoebe</name></author><author><name>Paul H.M. Savelkoul</name></author><author><name>Lieke B. van Alphen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Breakthrough SARS-CoV-2 infections have been reported in fully vaccinated individuals, in spite of the high efficacy of the currently available vaccines, proven in trials and real-world studies. Several variants of concern (VOC) have been proffered to be associated with breakthrough infections following immunization. In this study, we investigated 378 breakthrough infections recorded between January and July 2021 and compared the distribution of SARS-CoV-2 genotypes identified in 225 fully vaccinated individuals to the frequency of circulating community lineages in the region of South Limburg (The Netherlands) in a week-by-week comparison. Although the proportion of breakthrough infections was relatively low and stable when the Alpha variant was predominant, the rapid emergence of the Delta variant lead to a strong increase in breakthrough infections, with a higher relative proportion of individuals vaccinated with Oxford-AstraZeneca or J&amp;amp;J/Janssen being infected compared to those immunized with mRNA-based vaccines. A significant difference in median age was observed when comparing fully vaccinated individuals with severe symptoms (83 years) to asymptomatic cases (46.5 years) or individuals with mild-to-moderate symptoms (42 years). There was no association between SARS-CoV-2 genotype or vaccine type and disease symptoms. Interestingly, symptomatic individuals harbored significantly higher SARS-CoV-2 loads than asymptomatic vaccinated individuals and breakthrough infections caused by the Delta variant are associated with increased viral loads compared to those caused by the Alpha variant. Altogether, these results indicate that the emergence of the Delta variant might have lowered the efficiency of particular vaccine types to prevent SARS-CoV-2 infections and that, although rare, the elderly are particularly at risk of becoming severely infected as the consequence of a breakthrough infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266676" rel="alternate" title="Investigating SARS-CoV-2 breakthrough infections per variant and vaccine type (9 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266584</id><title>Behaviour, booster vaccines and waning vaccine protection: modelling the medium-term dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 transmission in England (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.207129+00:00</updated><author><name>Rosanna C. Barnard</name></author><author><name>Nicholas G. Davies</name></author><author><name>Mark Jit</name></author><author><name>W. John Edmunds</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;England has experienced a heavy burden of COVID-19, with high infection levels observed throughout the summer months of 2021. Alongside the emergence of evidence suggesting that COVID-19 vaccine protection wanes over time, booster vaccinations began for individuals aged 50 and above in September 2021. Using a model fitted to 18 months of epidemiological data, we project potential dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 transmission in England to September 2022. We consider key uncertainties including behavioural change, waning vaccine protection, strategies for vaccination, and the reintroduction of public health and social measures. We project the current wave of transmission will peak in Autumn 2021, with low levels of transmission in early 2022. The extent to which SARS-CoV-2 transmission resurges in 2022 depends largely on assumptions around waning vaccine protection and booster vaccinations. Widespread booster vaccinations or the reimposition of mild public health and social measures such as work-from-home policies could largely mitigate the wave of COVID-19 transmission projected to occur in England in Spring/Summer 2022.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266584" rel="alternate" title="Behaviour, booster vaccines and waning vaccine protection: modelling the medium-term dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 transmission in England (8 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266711</id><title>Germany’s low SARS-CoV-2 seroprevalence confirms effective containment in 2020: Results of the nationwide RKI-SOEP study (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.207298+00:00</updated><author><name>Hannelore Neuhauser</name></author><author><name>Angelika Schaffrath Rosario</name></author><author><name>Hans Butschalowsky</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Haller</name></author><author><name>Jens Hoebel</name></author><author><name>Janine Michel</name></author><author><name>Andreas Nitsche</name></author><author><name>Christina Poethko-Müller</name></author><author><name>Franziska Prütz</name></author><author><name>Martin Schlaud</name></author><author><name>Hans W. Steinhauer</name></author><author><name>Hendrik Wilking</name></author><author><name>Lothar H. Wieler</name></author><author><name>Lars Schaade</name></author><author><name>Stefan Liebig</name></author><author><name>Antje Gößwald</name></author><author><name>Markus M. Grabka</name></author><author><name>Sabine Zinn</name></author><author><name>Thomas Ziese</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pre-vaccine SARS-CoV-2 seroprevalence data from Germany are scarce outside hotspots, and socioeconomic disparities remained largely unexplored. The nationwide RKI-SOEP study with 15,122 adult participants investigated seroprevalence and testing in a supplementary wave of the Socio-Economic-Panel conducted predominantly in October-November 2020. Self-collected oral-nasal swabs were PCR-positive in 0.4% and Euroimmun anti-SARS-CoV-2-S1-IgG ELISA from dry capillary blood in 1.3% (95% CI 0.9-1.7%, population-weighted, corrected for sensitivity=0.811, specificity=0.997). Seroprevalence was 1.7% (95% CI 1.2-2.3%) when additionally adjusting for antibody decay. Overall infection prevalence including self-reports was 2.1%. We estimate 45% (95% CI 21-60%) undetected cases and analyses suggest lower detection in socioeconomically deprived districts. Prior SARS-CoV-2 testing was reported by 18% from the lower educational group compared to 25% and 26% from the medium and high educational group (p&amp;lt;0.0001). Symptom-triggered test frequency was similar across educational groups. However, routine testing was more common in low-educated adults, whereas travel-related testing and testing after contact with an infected person was more common in highly educated groups. In conclusion, pre-vaccine SARS-CoV-2-seroprevalence in Germany was very low. Notified cases appear to capture more than half of infections but may underestimate infections in lower socioeconomic groups. These data confirm the successful containment strategy of Germany until winter 2020.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266711" rel="alternate" title="Germany’s low SARS-CoV-2 seroprevalence confirms effective containment in 2020: Results of the nationwide RKI-SOEP study (8 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469755</id><title>Distinct SARS-CoV-2 sensing pathways in pDCs driving TLR7-antiviral vs. TLR2-immunopathological responses in COVID-19 (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.207552+00:00</updated><author><name>Renée M. van der Sluis</name></author><author><name>Lamin B. Cham</name></author><author><name>Albert Gris Oliver</name></author><author><name>Kristine R. Gammelgaard</name></author><author><name>Jesper G. Pedersen</name></author><author><name>Manja Idorn</name></author><author><name>Ulvi Ahmadov</name></author><author><name>Sabine Sanches Hernandez</name></author><author><name>Ena Cémalovic</name></author><author><name>Stine H. Godsk</name></author><author><name>Jacob Thyrsted</name></author><author><name>Jesper D. Gunst</name></author><author><name>Silke D. Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Janni J. Jørgensen</name></author><author><name>Tobias Wang Bjerg</name></author><author><name>Anders Laustsen</name></author><author><name>Line S. Reinert</name></author><author><name>David Olagnier</name></author><author><name>Rasmus O. Bak</name></author><author><name>Mads Kjolby</name></author><author><name>Christian K. Holm</name></author><author><name>Martin Tolstrup</name></author><author><name>Søren R. Paludan</name></author><author><name>Lasse S. Kristensen</name></author><author><name>Ole S. Søgaard</name></author><author><name>Martin R. Jakobsen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the molecular pathways driving the acute antiviral and inflammatory response to SARS-CoV-2 infection is critical for developing treatments for severe COVID-19. Here we show that in COVID-19 patients, circulating plasmacytoid dendritic cells (pDCs) decline early after symptom onset and this correlated with COVID-19 disease severity. This transient depletion coincides with decreased expression of antiviral type I IFNα and the systemic inflammatory cytokines CXCL10 and IL-6. Importantly, COVID-19 disease severity correlated with decreased pDC frequency in peripheral blood. Using an &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; stem cell-based human pDC model, we demonstrate that pDCs directly sense SARS-CoV-2 and in response produce multiple antiviral (IFNα and IFNλ1) and inflammatory (IL-6, IL-8, CXCL10) cytokines. This immune response is sufficient to protect epithelial cells from de novo SARS-CoV-2 infection. Targeted deletion of specific sensing pathways identified TLR7-MyD88 signaling as being crucial for production of the antiviral IFNs, whereas TLR2 is responsible for the inflammatory IL-6 response. Surprisingly, we found that SARS-CoV-2 engages the neuropilin-1 receptor on pDCs to mitigate the antiviral IFNs but not the IL-6 response. These results demonstrate distinct sensing pathways used by pDCs to elicit antiviral vs. immunopathological responses to SARS-CoV-2 and suggest that targeting neuropilin-1 on pDCs may be clinically relevant for mounting TLR7-mediated antiviral protection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;pDCs sense SARS-CoV-2 and elicit antiviral protection of lung epithelial cells through TLR7, while recognition of TLR2 elicits an IL-6 inflammatory response associated with immunopathology.&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;label&gt;Graphical abstract:&lt;/label&gt;&lt;caption&gt;&lt;title&gt;SARS-CoV-2 sensing by plasmacytoid dendritic cells.&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 is internalized by pDCs via a yet unknown endocytic mechanism. The intracellular TLR7 sensor detects viral RNA and induces a signaling cascade involving MyD88-IRAK4-TRAF6 (1) to induce CXCL10 and, via IRF7 phosphorylation and translocation, inducing type I and III Interferons (2). Once secreted, type I and III IFNs initiate autocrine and paracrine signals that induce the expression of IFN stimulated genes (ISGs), thereby facilitating an antiviral response that can protect the cell against infection. However, SARS-CoV-2, has the intrinsic property to facilitate CD304 signaling, potentially by interfering with IRF7 nuclear translocation, thereby inhibiting type I IFNα production and thus reducing the antiviral response generated by the pDC (4). Furthermore, the SARS-CoV-2 envelope (E) glycoprotein is sensed by the extracellular TLR2/6 heterodimer and this facilitates production of the inflammatory IL-6 cytokine (5). Illustration was created with BioRender.com&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/caption&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="469755v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469755" rel="alternate" title="Distinct SARS-CoV-2 sensing pathways in pDCs driving TLR7-antiviral vs. TLR2-immunopathological responses in COVID-19 (8 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266688</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 genome-based severity predictions correspond to lower qPCR values and higher viral load (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.207876+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Skarzynski</name></author><author><name>Erin M. McAuley</name></author><author><name>Ezekiel J. Maier</name></author><author><name>Anthony C. Fries</name></author><author><name>Jameson D. Voss</name></author><author><name>Richard R. Chapleau</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The 2019 coronavirus disease (COVID-19) pandemic has demonstrated the importance of predicting, identifying, and tracking mutations throughout a pandemic event. As the COVID-19 global pandemic surpassed one year, several variants had emerged resulting in increased severity and transmissibility. In order to reduce the impact on human life, it is critical to rapidly identify which genetic variants result in increased virulence or transmission. To address the former, we evaluated if a genome-based predictive algorithm designed to predict clinical severity could predict polymerase chain reaction (PCR) results, as a surrogate for viral load and severity. Using a previously published algorithm, we compared the viral genome-based severity predictions to clinically-derived PCR-based viral load of 716 viral genomes. For those samples predicted to be “severe” (predicted severity score &amp;gt; 0.5), we observed an average cycle threshold (Ct) of 18.3, whereas those in in the “mild” category (severity prediction &amp;lt; 0.5) had an average Ct of 20.4 (&lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt; = 0.0017). We found a non-trivial correlation between predicted severity probability and cycle threshold (&lt;italic&gt;r&lt;/italic&gt; = −0.199). Additionally, when divided into quartiles by prediction severity probability, the most probable quartile (≥75% probability) had a Ct of 16.6 (n=10) as compared to those least probable to be severe (&amp;lt;25%) of 21.4 (n=350) (&lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt; = 0.0045). Taken together, our results suggest that the severity predicted by a genome-based algorithm can be related to the metrics from the clinical diagnostic test, and that relative severity may be inferred from diagnostic values.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266688" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 genome-based severity predictions correspond to lower qPCR values and higher viral load (7 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469492</id><title>A multi-class gene classifier for SARS-CoV-2 variants based on convolutional neural network (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.208292+00:00</updated><author><name>Junyu Fan</name></author><author><name>Chutao Chen</name></author><author><name>Chen Song</name></author><author><name>Jiajie Pan</name></author><author><name>Guifu Wu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Surveillance of circulating variants of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) is of great importance in controlling the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic. We propose an alignment-free in silico approach for classifying SARS-CoV-2 variants based on their genomic sequences. A deep learning model was constructed utilizing a stacked 1-D convolutional neural network and multilayer perceptron (MLP). The pre-processed genomic sequencing data of the four SARS-CoV-2 variants were first fed to three stacked convolution-pooling nets to extract local linkage patterns in the sequences. Then a 2-layer MLP was used to compute the correlations between the input and output. Finally, a logistic regression model transformed the output and returned the probability values. Learning curves and stratified 10-fold cross-validation showed that the proposed classifier enables robust variant classification. External validation of the classifier showed an accuracy of 0.9962, precision of 0.9963, recall of 0.9963 and F1 score of 0.9962, outperforming other machine learning methods, including logistic regression, K-nearest neighbor, support vector machine, and random forest. By comparing our model with an MLP model without the convolution-pooling network, we demonstrate the essential role of convolution in extracting viral variant features. Thus, our results indicate that the proposed convolution-based multi-class gene classifier is efficient for the variant classification of SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469492" rel="alternate" title="A multi-class gene classifier for SARS-CoV-2 variants based on convolutional neural network (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469765</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 Delta Spike Protein Enhances the Viral Fusogenicity and Inflammatory Cytokine Production (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.208506+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhujun Ao</name></author><author><name>Maggie Jing Ouyang</name></author><author><name>Titus Abiola Olukitibi</name></author><author><name>Xiaojian Yao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Delta variant is now the most dominant and virulent SARS-CoV-2 variant of concern (VOC). In this study, we investigated several virological features of Delta spike protein (SP&lt;sub&gt;Delta&lt;/sub&gt;), including protein maturation and its impact on viral entry of cell-free pseudotyped virus, cell-cell fusion ability and its induction of inflammatory cytokine production in human macrophages and dendritic cells. The results showed that SPΔC&lt;sub&gt;Delta&lt;/sub&gt; exhibited enhanced S1/S2 cleavage in cells and pseudotyped virus-like particles (PVLPs). We further showed that SPΔC&lt;sub&gt;Delta&lt;/sub&gt; elevated pseudovirus infection in human lung cell lines and mediated significantly enhanced syncytia formation. Furthermore, we revealed that SPΔC&lt;sub&gt;Delta&lt;/sub&gt;-PVLPs had stronger effects on stimulating NF-κB and AP-1 signaling in human monocytic THP1 cells and induced significantly higher levels of pro-inflammatory cytokine, such as TNF-α, IL-1β and IL-6, released from human macrophages and dendritic cells. Overall, these studies provide evidence to support the important role of SPΔC&lt;sub&gt;Delta&lt;/sub&gt; during virus infection, transmission and pathogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469765" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 Delta Spike Protein Enhances the Viral Fusogenicity and Inflammatory Cytokine Production (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469117</id><title>Preclinical efficacy, safety, and immunogenicity of PHH-1V, a second-generation COVID-19 vaccine candidate based on a novel recombinant RBD fusion heterodimer of SARS-CoV-2 (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.208672+00:00</updated><author><name>Antonio Barreiro</name></author><author><name>Antoni Prenafeta</name></author><author><name>Gregori Bech-Sabat</name></author><author><name>Mercè Roca</name></author><author><name>Ricard March</name></author><author><name>Luis González</name></author><author><name>Laia Madrenas</name></author><author><name>Júlia Corominas</name></author><author><name>Àlex Fernández</name></author><author><name>Mercè Molas</name></author><author><name>Júlia Vergara-Alert</name></author><author><name>Cristina Lorca-Oró</name></author><author><name>Núria Roca</name></author><author><name>Leira Fernández-Bastit</name></author><author><name>Jordi Rodon</name></author><author><name>Mònica Pérez</name></author><author><name>Joaquim Segalés</name></author><author><name>Edwards Pradenas</name></author><author><name>Silvia Marfil</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Trinité</name></author><author><name>Raquel Ortiz</name></author><author><name>Bonaventura Clotet</name></author><author><name>Julià Blanco</name></author><author><name>Jorge Díaz Pedroza</name></author><author><name>Rosa Ampudia Carrasco</name></author><author><name>Yaiza Rosales Salgado</name></author><author><name>Jordina Loubat Casanovas</name></author><author><name>Sara Capdevila Larripa</name></author><author><name>Julia Garcia Prado</name></author><author><name>Jordi Barretina</name></author><author><name>Marta Sisteré-Oró</name></author><author><name>Paula Cebollada Rica</name></author><author><name>Andreas Meyerhans</name></author><author><name>Laura Ferrer</name></author><author><name>Elia Torroella</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Since the genetic sequence of SARS-CoV-2 became available in January 2020, new vaccines have been developed at an unprecedented speed. The current vaccines have been directly associated with a decline in new infection rates, prevention of severe disease and an outstanding decrease in mortality rates. However, the pandemic is still far from being over. New Variants of Concern (VoCs) are continuously evolving. Thus, it is essential to develop accessible second-generation COVID-19 vaccines against known and future VoCs to mitigate the current pandemic. Here, we provide preclinical data showing the immunogenicity, efficacy, and safety results in mice of a receptor-binding domain (RBD)-based recombinant protein vaccine candidate (PHH-1V) which consists of a novel RBD fusion heterodimer containing the B.1.1.7 (alpha) and B.1.351 (beta) variants of SARS-CoV-2, formulated with an oil-based adjuvant equivalent to MF59C.1. BALB/c and K18-hACE2 mice were immunized with different doses of recombinant RBD fusion heterodimer, following a two-dose prime-and-boost schedule. Upon 20 μg RBD fusion heterodimer/dose immunization, BALB/c mice produced RBD-binding antibodies with neutralising activity against the alpha, beta, gamma, and delta variants. Furthermore, vaccination elicited robust activation of CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells with early expression of Th1 cytokines upon &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; restimulation, along with a good tolerability profile. Importantly, vaccination with 10 μg or 20 μg RBD fusion heterodimer/dose conferred 100% efficacy preventing mortality and bodyweight loss upon SARS-CoV-2 challenge in K18-hACE2 mice. These findings demonstrate the feasibility of this novel recombinant vaccine strategy, allowing the inclusion of up to 2 different RBD proteins in the same vaccine. Most importantly, this new platform is easy to adapt to future VoCs and has a good stability profile, thus ensuring its global distribution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469117" rel="alternate" title="Preclinical efficacy, safety, and immunogenicity of PHH-1V, a second-generation COVID-19 vaccine candidate based on a novel recombinant RBD fusion heterodimer of SARS-CoV-2 (6 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469775</id><title>Atazanavir is a competitive inhibitor of SARS-CoV-2 Mpro, impairing variants replication in vitro and in vivo (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.209139+00:00</updated><author><name>Otávio Augusto Chaves</name></author><author><name>Carolina Q. Sacramento</name></author><author><name>André C. Ferreira</name></author><author><name>Mayara Mattos</name></author><author><name>Natalia Fintelman-Rodrigues</name></author><author><name>Jairo R. Temerozo</name></author><author><name>Douglas Pereira Pinto</name></author><author><name>Gabriel P. E. da Silveira</name></author><author><name>Laís Bastos da Fonseca</name></author><author><name>Heliana Martins Pereira</name></author><author><name>Aluana Santana Carlos</name></author><author><name>Joana da Costa Pinto d’Ávila</name></author><author><name>João P.B. Viola</name></author><author><name>Robson Q. Monteiro</name></author><author><name>Leonardo Vazquez</name></author><author><name>Patrícia T. Bozza</name></author><author><name>Hugo Caire Castro-Faria-Neto</name></author><author><name>Thiago Moreno L. Souza</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Atazanavir (ATV) has already been considered as a potential repurposing drug to 2019 coronavirus disease (COVID-19), however, there are controversial reports on its mechanism of action and effectiveness as anti-severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). Through the pre-clinical chain of experiments: enzymatic, molecular docking, cell-based, and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; assays, it is demonstrated here that both SARS-CoV-2 B.1 lineage and variant of concern gamma are susceptible to this antiretroviral. Enzymatic assays and molecular docking calculations showed that SARS-CoV-2 main protease (M&lt;sup&gt;pro&lt;/sup&gt;) was inhibited by ATV, with Morrison’s inhibitory constant (Ki) 1.5-fold higher than boceprevir (GC376, a positive control). ATV was a competitive inhibition, increasing the M&lt;sup&gt;pro&lt;/sup&gt;’s Michaelis-Menten (K&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt;) more than 6-fold. Cell-based assays indicated that SARS-CoV-2 gamma is more susceptible to ATV than its predecessor strain B.1. Using oral administration of ATV in mice to reach plasmatic exposure similar to humans, transgenic mice expression in human angiotensin converting enzyme 2 (K18-hACE2) were partially protected against lethal challenge with SARS-CoV-2 gamma. Moreover, less cell death and inflammation were observed in the lung from infected and treated mice. Our studies may contribute to a better comprehension of the M&lt;sup&gt;pro&lt;/sup&gt;/ATV interaction, which could pave the way to the development of specific inhibitors of this viral protease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469775" rel="alternate" title="Atazanavir is a competitive inhibitor of SARS-CoV-2 Mpro, impairing variants replication in vitro and in vivo (6 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469172</id><title>Identification of a promiscuous conserved CTL epitope within the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.209588+00:00</updated><author><name>Sheng Jiang</name></author><author><name>Shuting Wu</name></author><author><name>Gan Zhao</name></author><author><name>Yue He</name></author><author><name>Xinrong Guo</name></author><author><name>Zhiyu Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jiawang Hou</name></author><author><name>Yuan Ding</name></author><author><name>Alex Cheng</name></author><author><name>Bin Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 disease caused by infection with SARS-CoV-2 and its variants is devastating to the global public health and economy. To date, over a hundred COVID-19 vaccines are known to be under development and the few that have been approved to fight the disease are using the spike protein as the primary target antigen. Although virus neutralizing epitopes are mainly located within the RBD of the spike protein, the presence of T cell epitopes, particularly the CTL epitopes that are likely to be needed for killing infected cells, has received comparatively little attention. In this study, we predicted several potential T cell epitopes with web-based analytic tools, and narrowed them down from several potential MHC-I and MHC-II epitopes by ELIspot and cytolytic assays to a conserved MHC-I epitope. The epitope is highly conserved in current viral variants and compatible with presentation by most HLA alleles worldwide. In conclusion, we identified a CTL epitope suitable for evaluating the CD8+ T cell-mediated cellular response and potentially for addition into future COVID-19 vaccine candidates to maximize CTL responses against SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469172" rel="alternate" title="Identification of a promiscuous conserved CTL epitope within the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein (6 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266759</id><title>Social Class, Race/Ethnicity, and COVID-19 Mortality Among Working Age Adults in the United States (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.209842+00:00</updated><author><name>Elizabeth B. Pathak</name></author><author><name>Janelle Menard</name></author><author><name>Rebecca B. Garcia</name></author><author><name>Jason L. Salemi</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Substantial racial/ethnic disparities in COVID-19 mortality have been documented. Social class is a likely explanation of mortality disparities across and within racial/ethnic groups. This is the first U.S. study of social class and COVID-19 mortality in working age adults.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To determine the joint effects of social class, race/ethnicity, and gender on the burden of COVID-19 mortality. A secondary objective was to determine whether differences in opportunities for remote work were correlated with COVID-19 death rates for sociodemographic groups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Annual mortality study which used a special government tabulation of 2020 COVID-19 related deaths stratified by decedents’ social class (educational attainment) and race/ethnicity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;United States in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 decedents aged 25 to 64 years old (n=69,001).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Exposures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Social class (working class, some college, college graduate), race/ethnicity (Hispanic, Black, Asian, Indigenous, multiracial, and non-Hispanic white), and gender (women, men). Detailed census data on occupations held by adults in 2020 in each of the 36 sociodemographic groups studied were used to quantify the possibility of remote work for each group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Outcomes and Measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Age-adjusted COVID-19 death rates for 36 sociodemographic groups defined by social class, race/ethnicity, and gender. Disparities were quantified by relative risks and 95% confidence intervals. College graduates were the (low risk) referent group for all relative risk calculations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A higher proportion of Hispanics, Blacks, and Indigenous people were working class in 2020. COVID-19 mortality was five times higher in the working class vs. college graduates (72.2 vs. 14.6 deaths per 100,000, RR=4.94, 95% CI 4.82-5.05). The joint detriments of lower socioeconomic position, Hispanic ethnicity, and male gender resulted in a COVID-19 death rate which was over 27 times higher (178.0 vs. 6.5 deaths/100,000, RR=27.4, 95%CI 25.9-28.9) for working class Hispanic men vs. college graduate white women. In regression modeling, percent employed in never remote jobs explained 72% of the variance in COVID-19 death rates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions and Relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 infection control efforts should prioritize the working class (i.e. those with no college education), particularly those employed in “never remote” jobs with inflexible and unsafe working conditions (i.e. blue collar, service, and retail sales workers).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;KEY POINTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Question&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Did COVID-19 mortality rates among non-elderly adults vary significantly by social class, race/ethnicity, and gender in 2020?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among 69,001 COVID-19 decedents, age-adjusted COVID-19 deaths rates were 5 times higher in working class vs. college graduate adults 25-64 years old. Working class Hispanic, Black, and Indigenous men suffered the highest burden of COVID-19 mortality, while college graduate white women experienced the lowest death rate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Meaning&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 mitigation efforts should prioritize the working class (i.e. those with no college education), particularly blue collar, service, and retail sales workers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266759" rel="alternate" title="Social Class, Race/Ethnicity, and COVID-19 Mortality Among Working Age Adults in the United States (6 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266712</id><title>Human phospho-signaling networks of SARS-CoV-2 infection are rewired by population genetic variants (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.209978+00:00</updated><author><name>Diogo Pellegrina</name></author><author><name>Alexander T. Bahcheli</name></author><author><name>Michal Krassowski</name></author><author><name>Jüri Reimand</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 infection hijacks signaling pathways and induces protein-protein interactions between human and viral proteins. Human genetic variation may impact SARS-CoV-2 infection and COVID-19 pathology; however, the role of genetic variation in these signaling networks remains uncharacterized. We studied human single nucleotide variants (SNVs) affecting phosphorylation sites modulated by SARS-CoV-2 infection, using machine learning to identify amino acid changes altering kinase-bound sequence motifs. We found 2033 infrequent phosphorylation-associated SNVs (pSNVs) that are enriched in sequence motif alterations, potentially reflecting the evolution of signaling networks regulating host defenses. Proteins with pSNVs are involved in viral life cycle processes and host responses, including regulators of RNA splicing and interferon response, as well as glucose homeostasis pathways with potential associations with COVID-19 co-morbidities. Certain pSNVs disrupt CDK and MAPK substrate motifs and replace these with motifs recognized by Tank Binding Kinase 1 (TBK1) involved in innate immune responses, indicating consistent rewiring of infection signaling networks. Our analysis highlights potential genetic factors contributing to the variation of SARS-CoV-2 infection and COVID-19 and suggests leads for mechanistic and translational studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266712" rel="alternate" title="Human phospho-signaling networks of SARS-CoV-2 infection are rewired by population genetic variants (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469576</id><title>A modified porous silicon microparticle promotes mucosal delivery of SARS-CoV-2 antigen and induction of potent and durable systemic and mucosal T helper 1 skewed protective immunity (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.210108+00:00</updated><author><name>Awadalkareem Adam</name></author><author><name>Qing Shi</name></author><author><name>Binbin Wang</name></author><author><name>Jing Zou</name></author><author><name>Junhua Mai</name></author><author><name>Samantha R Osman</name></author><author><name>Wenzhe Wu</name></author><author><name>Xuping Xie</name></author><author><name>Patricia V Aguilar</name></author><author><name>Xiaoyong Bao</name></author><author><name>Pei-Yong Shi</name></author><author><name>Haifa Shen</name></author><author><name>Tian Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Development of optimal SARS-CoV-2 vaccines to induce potent, long-lasting immunity and provide cross-reactive protection against emerging variants remains a high priority. Here, we report that a modified porous silicon microparticle (mPSM)-adjuvanted SARS-CoV-2 receptor-binding domain (RBD) vaccine activated dendritic cells and generated more potent and durable SARS-CoV-2-specific systemic humoral and type 1 helper T (Th) cell-mediated immune responses than alum-formulated RBD following parenteral vaccination, and protected mice from SARS-CoV-2 and Beta variant infection. mPSM facilitated the uptake of SARS-CoV-2 RBD antigens by nasal and airway epithelial cells. Parenteral and intranasal prime and boost vaccinations with mPSM-RBD elicited potent systemic and lung resident memory T and B cells and SARS-CoV-2 specific IgA responses, and markedly diminished viral loads and inflammation in the lung following SARS-CoV-2 Delta variant infection. Our results suggest that mPSM can serve as potent adjuvant for SARS-CoV-2 subunit vaccine which is effective for systemic and mucosal vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469576" rel="alternate" title="A modified porous silicon microparticle promotes mucosal delivery of SARS-CoV-2 antigen and induction of potent and durable systemic and mucosal T helper 1 skewed protective immunity (6 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469747</id><title>Genome-wide characterization of SARS-CoV-2 cytopathogenic proteins in the search of antiviral targets (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.210295+00:00</updated><author><name>Jiantao Zhang</name></author><author><name>Qi Li</name></author><author><name>Ruth S. Cruz Cosme</name></author><author><name>Vladimir Gerzanich</name></author><author><name>Qiyi Tang</name></author><author><name>J. Marc Simard</name></author><author><name>Richard Y. Zhao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Therapeutic inhibition of critical viral functions is important for curtailing coronavirus disease-2019 (COVID-19). We sought to identify antiviral targets through genome-wide characterization of SARS-CoV-2 proteins that are crucial for viral pathogenesis and that cause harmful cytopathic effects. All twenty-nine viral proteins were tested in a fission yeast cell-based system using inducible gene expression. Twelve proteins including eight non-structural proteins (NSP1, NSP3, NSP4, NSP5, NSP6, NSP13, NSP14 and NSP15) and four accessory proteins (ORF3a, ORF6, ORF7a and ORF7b) were identified that altered cellular proliferation and integrity, and induced cell death. Cell death correlated with the activation of cellular oxidative stress. Of the twelve proteins, ORF3a was chosen for further study in mammalian cells. In human pulmonary and kidney epithelial cells, ORF3a induced cellular oxidative stress associated with apoptosis and necrosis, and caused activation of pro-inflammatory response with production of the cytokines TNF-α, IL-6, and IFN-β1, possibly through the activation of NF-κB. To further characterize the mechanism, we tested a natural ORF3a Beta variant, Q57H, and a mutant with deletion of the highly conserved residue, ΔG188. Compared to wild type ORF3a, the ΔG188 variant yielded more robust activation of cellular oxidative stress, cell death, and innate immune response. Since cellular oxidative stress and inflammation contribute to cell death and tissue damage linked to the severity of COVID-19, our findings suggest that ORF3a is a promising, novel therapeutic target against COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ongoing SARS-CoV-2 pandemic has claimed over 5 million lives with more than 250 million people infected world-wide. While vaccines are effective, the emergence of new viral variants could jeopardize vaccine protection. Antiviral drugs provide an alternative to battle against COVID-19. Our goal was to identify viral therapeutic targets that can be used in antiviral drug discovery. Utilizing a genome-wide functional analysis in a fission yeast cell-based system, we identified twelve viral candidates, including ORF3a, which cause cellular oxidative stress, inflammation and apoptosis and necrosis that contribute to COVID-19. Our findings indicate that antiviral agents targeting ORF3a could greatly impact COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469747" rel="alternate" title="Genome-wide characterization of SARS-CoV-2 cytopathogenic proteins in the search of antiviral targets (6 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469552</id><title>Stabilization of the SARS-CoV-2 Receptor Binding Domain by Protein Core Redesign and Deep Mutational Scanning (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.210446+00:00</updated><author><name>Alison C. Leonard</name></author><author><name>Jonathan J. Weinstein</name></author><author><name>Paul J. Steiner</name></author><author><name>Annette H. Erbse</name></author><author><name>Sarel J. Fleishman</name></author><author><name>Timothy A. Whitehead</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Stabilizing antigenic proteins as vaccine immunogens or diagnostic reagents is a stringent case of protein engineering and design as the exterior surface must maintain recognition by receptor(s) and antigen—specific antibodies at multiple distinct epitopes. This is a challenge, as stability-enhancing mutations must be focused on the protein core, whereas successful computational stabilization algorithms typically select mutations at solvent-facing positions. In this study we report the stabilization of SARS-CoV-2 Wuhan Hu-1 Spike receptor binding domain (S RBD) using a combination of deep mutational scanning and computational design, including the FuncLib algorithm. Our most successful design encodes I358F, Y365W, T430I, and I513L RBD mutations, maintains recognition by the receptor ACE2 and a panel of different anti-RBD monoclonal antibodies, is between 1-2°C more thermally stable than the original RBD using a thermal shift assay, and is less proteolytically sensitive to chymotrypsin and thermolysin than the original RBD. Our approach could be applied to the computational stabilization of a wide range of proteins without requiring detailed knowledge of active sites or binding epitopes, particularly powerful for cases when there are multiple or unknown binding sites.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469552" rel="alternate" title="Stabilization of the SARS-CoV-2 Receptor Binding Domain by Protein Core Redesign and Deep Mutational Scanning (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.21266441</id><title>Pausing methotrexate improves immunogenicity of COVID-19 vaccination in patients with rheumatic diseases (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.210587+00:00</updated><author><name>AN Arumahandi de Silva</name></author><author><name>LM Frommert</name></author><author><name>FN Albach</name></author><author><name>J Klotsche</name></author><author><name>V Scholz</name></author><author><name>LM Jeworowski</name></author><author><name>T Schwarz</name></author><author><name>A ten Hagen</name></author><author><name>J Zernicke</name></author><author><name>VM Corman</name></author><author><name>C Drosten</name></author><author><name>GR Burmester</name></author><author><name>R Biesen</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To study the effect of methotrexate (MTX) and its discontinuation on the humoral immune response after COVID-19 vaccination in patients with autoimmune rheumatic diseases (AIRD).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neutralising SARS-CoV-2 antibodies were measured after second vaccination in 64 rheumatic patients on methotrexate therapy, 31 of whom temporarily paused medication without a fixed regimen. The control group consisted of 21 AIRD patients without immunosuppressive medication.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;MTX patients showed a significantly lower median antibody response compared to AIRD patients without immunosuppressive therapy (p&amp;lt; 0.001). Young age (&amp;lt;60 years) and MTX-hold after vaccination were found to be the main factors influencing antibody response after vaccination, while BMI or MTX dose demonstrated no effect. For patients taking MTX, age correlated negatively with immune response (r=-0.49; p&amp;lt;0.001) and all patients with antibody levels (14 %) below the cut-off were older than 60 years. Patients who held MTX during at least one vaccination showed significantly higher median neutralising antibody levels after second vaccination, compared to patients who continued MTX therapy during both vaccinations (68.82 %, 92.73 %, p=&amp;lt;0.001). This effect was particularly pronounced in patients older than 60 years (p=0.0016). The impact of the time period after vaccination was greater than of the time before vaccination with the critical cut-off being 10 days.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;MTX reduces the immunogenicity of SARS-CoV-2 vaccination in an age-dependent manner. Our data further suggest that holding MTX for at least 10 days after vaccination significantly improves the antibody response in patients over 60 years of age.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.21266441" rel="alternate" title="Pausing methotrexate improves immunogenicity of COVID-19 vaccination in patients with rheumatic diseases (5 tweets)"/><category term="Rheumatology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.21266461</id><title>Space-time Classification Index for Assessing COVID-19 Hotspots (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.210868+00:00</updated><author><name>David Haynes</name></author><author><name>Chetan Tiwari</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To develop new methods to address problems associated with use of traditional measures of disease surveillance, including prevalence and positivity rates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We use data from the public New York Times Github repository to develop a space-time classification index of COVID-19 hotspots. The Local Indicator of Spatial Association (LISA) statistic is applied to identify daily clusters of COVID-19 cases, from July 4th to July 19th.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The classification index is a spatial and temporal assessment tool that seeks to incorporate temporal trends of the clusters that are “high-high” and “high-low”. Two classifications support the index: severity and temporal duration. We define severity as the number of times a county is statistically significant and temporal duration captures the number of consecutive days a county is a hotspot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The space-time classification index provides a statistically robust measure of the spatial patterns of COVID-19 hotspots. Spatial information is not captured through measures like the positivity rate, which merely divides the number of cases by tests conducted. The index proposed in this paper can guide intervention efforts by classifying counties with six-levels of importance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.21266461" rel="alternate" title="Space-time Classification Index for Assessing COVID-19 Hotspots (5 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.21266682</id><title>Uptake of Covid-19 preventive measures among 10 immigrant ethnic groups in Norway (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.211002+00:00</updated><author><name>Abdi Gele</name></author><author><name>Naima Said Sheikh</name></author><author><name>Prabhjot Kour</name></author><author><name>Samera A Qureshi</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A pessimistic view of the impact of Covid-19 on immigrants has generated an interest in exploring the role of socio-economic and cultural factors on excess infection, hospitalization and death among immigrants. Nowhere in the world is such interest more palpable than in Western countries, including Norway. An expanding amount of literature has demonstrated that preexisting socio-economic inequalities have affected Covid-19 control programs through a disruption of immigrants’ uptake to preventive measures. Nonetheless, until very recently, no qualitative research has been conducted to address the impact of socio-economic and socio-cultural factors on immigrants’ uptake on preventive measures of Covid-19 in Norway.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;An interview-based qualitative study consisting of 88 participants (49 women and 39 men) from 10 immigrant ethnic groups were carried out. Participants were recruited through purposive sampling and snowballing. In-depth interviews were held through telephone or online for those who have experience in the use of zoom or teams. Data were analyzed using thematic analysis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found that participants’ attitudes toward the pandemic in general, and more specifically their adherence to preventive measures, have increased over time. However, the number of barriers that hinder immigrants from adhering to preventive measures were identified and classified more broadly into three main subthemes: 1) socio-economic barriers; 2) socio-cultural barriers, and 3) other barriers. Socio-economic barriers include overcrowded households, working in first-line jobs, education and language. Socio-cultural barriers include collectivist culture, religious fatalism and risk perception toward the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To reduce the health inequality that arises from overcrowded housing, there is a need for a long-term strategy to help improve the housing situation of low-income immigrant families that live in overcrowded households. In addition, increasing health literacy and more generally, the integration of immigrants, may also reduce the effect of socio-cultural factors on an immigrant’s uptake of preventive measures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.21266682" rel="alternate" title="Uptake of Covid-19 preventive measures among 10 immigrant ethnic groups in Norway (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266761</id><title>Higher Limbic and Basal Ganglia volumes in surviving COVID-negative patients and the relations to fatigue (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.211138+00:00</updated><author><name>Rakibul Hafiz</name></author><author><name>Tapan Kumar Gandhi</name></author><author><name>Sapna Mishra</name></author><author><name>Alok Prasad</name></author><author><name>Vidur Mahajan</name></author><author><name>Xin Di</name></author><author><name>Benjamin H. Natelson</name></author><author><name>Bharat B. Biswal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) has caused a global pandemic. Among several systemic abnormalities, little is known about the critical attack on the central nervous system (CNS). Several patient reports with multiple pathologies – ischemic strokes, mild infarcts, encephalitis, cerebro-vascular abnormalities, cerebral inflammation, and loss of consciousness, indicate CNS involvement. However, due to limited neuroimaging studies, conclusive group level effects are scarce in the literature and replication studies are necessary to verify if these effects persist in surviving acute-COVID patients. Furthermore, recent reports indicate fatigue is highly prevalent among slowly recovering patients. How early structural changes relate to fatigue need to be investigated. Our goal was to address this by scanning COVID subjects two weeks after hospital discharge. We hypothesized these surviving patients will demonstrate altered gray matter volume (GMV) when compared to healthy controls and further demonstrate correlation of GMV with fatigue. Voxel-based morphometry was applied to T1-weighted MRI images between 46 patients with COVID and 32 healthy controls. Significantly higher GMV in the &lt;italic&gt;Limbic System&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Basal Ganglia&lt;/italic&gt; regions were observed in surviving COVID-19 patients when compared to healthy controls. Moreover, within the patient group, there was a significant positive correlation between GMV and self-reported fatigue scores during work, within the &lt;italic&gt;ventral Basal Ganglia&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Ventromedial Prefrontal Cortex&lt;/italic&gt; regions. Therefore, our results align with both single case acute patient reports and current group level neuroimaging findings. Finally, we newly report a positive correlation of GMV with fatigue in COVID survivors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266761" rel="alternate" title="Higher Limbic and Basal Ganglia volumes in surviving COVID-negative patients and the relations to fatigue (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469776</id><title>Engineered ACE2-Fc counters murine lethal SARS-CoV-2 infection through direct neutralization and Fc-effector activities (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.211293+00:00</updated><author><name>Yaozong Chen</name></author><author><name>Lulu Sun</name></author><author><name>Irfan Ullah</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Beaudoin-Bussières</name></author><author><name>Sai Priya Anand</name></author><author><name>Andrew P. Hederman</name></author><author><name>William D. Tolbert</name></author><author><name>Rebekah Sherburn</name></author><author><name>Dung N. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Lorie Marchitto</name></author><author><name>Shilei Ding</name></author><author><name>Di Wu</name></author><author><name>Yuhong Luo</name></author><author><name>Suneetha Gottumukkala</name></author><author><name>Sean Moran</name></author><author><name>Priti Kumar</name></author><author><name>Grzegorz Piszczek</name></author><author><name>Walther Mothes</name></author><author><name>Margaret E. Ackerman</name></author><author><name>Andrés Finzi</name></author><author><name>Pradeep D. Uchil</name></author><author><name>Frank J. Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Marzena Pazgier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Soluble Angiotensin-Converting Enzyme 2 (ACE2) constitutes an attractive antiviral capable of targeting a wide range of coronaviruses utilizing ACE2 as their receptor. Here, using structure-guided approaches, we developed divalent ACE2 molecules by grafting the extracellular ACE2-domain onto a human IgG1 or IgG3 (ACE2-Fc). These ACE2-Fcs harbor structurally validated mutations that enhance spike (S) binding and remove angiotensin enzymatic activity. The lead variant bound tightly to S, mediated &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; neutralization of SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (VOCs) with sub-nanomolar IC&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; and was capable of robust Fc-effector functions, including antibody-dependent-cellular cytotoxicity, phagocytosis and complement deposition. When tested in a stringent K18-hACE2 mouse model, it delayed death or effectively resolved lethal SARS-CoV-2 infection in a prophylactic or therapeutic setting utilizing the combined effect of neutralization and Fc-effector functions. These data confirm the utility of ACE2-Fcs as valuable agents in preventing and eliminating SARS-CoV-2 infection and demonstrate that ACE2-Fc therapeutic activity require Fc-effector functions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469776" rel="alternate" title="Engineered ACE2-Fc counters murine lethal SARS-CoV-2 infection through direct neutralization and Fc-effector activities (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.21266090</id><title>Synthesis of High-Resolution Research-Quality MRI Data from Clinical MRI Data in Patients with COVID-19 (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.211542+00:00</updated><author><name>Ryan J. Cali</name></author><author><name>Holly J. Freeman</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Billot</name></author><author><name>Megan E. Barra</name></author><author><name>David Fischer</name></author><author><name>William R. Sanders</name></author><author><name>Susie Y. Huang</name></author><author><name>John Conklin</name></author><author><name>Bruce Fischl</name></author><author><name>Juan Eugenio Iglesias</name></author><author><name>Brian L. Edlow</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pathophysiological mechanisms of neurological disorders in patients with coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) are poorly understood, partly because of a lack of high-resolution neuroimaging data. We applied SynthSR, a convolutional neural network that synthesizes high-resolution isotropic research-quality data from thick-slice clinical MRI data, to a cohort of 11 patients with severe COVID-19. SynthSR successfully synthesized T1-weighted MPRAGE data at 1 mm spatial resolution for all 11 patients, each of whom had at least one brain lesion. Correlations between volumetric measures derived from synthesized and acquired MPRAGE data were strong for the cortical grey matter, subcortical grey matter, brainstem, hippocampus, and hemispheric white matter (&lt;italic&gt;r&lt;/italic&gt;=0.84 to 0.96, p≤0.001), but absent for the cerebellar white matter and corpus callosum (&lt;italic&gt;r&lt;/italic&gt;=0.04 to 0.17, p&amp;gt;0.61). SynthSR creates an opportunity to quantitatively study clinical MRI scans and elucidate the pathophysiology of neurological disorders in patients with COVID-19, including those with focal lesions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.21266090" rel="alternate" title="Synthesis of High-Resolution Research-Quality MRI Data from Clinical MRI Data in Patients with COVID-19 (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266747</id><title>The experiences of 33 national COVID-19 dashboard teams during the first year of the pandemic in the WHO European Region: a qualitative study (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.211713+00:00</updated><author><name>Erica Barbazza</name></author><author><name>Damir Ivanković</name></author><author><name>Karapet Davtyan</name></author><author><name>Mircha Poldrugovac</name></author><author><name>Zhamin Yelgezekova</name></author><author><name>Claire Willmington</name></author><author><name>Bernardo Meza-Torres</name></author><author><name>Véronique L.L.C. Bos</name></author><author><name>Óscar Brito Fernandes</name></author><author><name>Alexandru Rotar</name></author><author><name>Sabina Nuti</name></author><author><name>Milena Vainieri</name></author><author><name>Fabrizio Carinci</name></author><author><name>Natasha Azzopardi-Muscat</name></author><author><name>Oliver Groene</name></author><author><name>David Novillo-Ortiz</name></author><author><name>Niek Klazinga</name></author><author><name>Dionne Kringos</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Governments across the WHO European Region prioritized dashboards for reporting COVID-19 data. The ubiquitous use of dashboards for public reporting is novel. This study explores the development of COVID-19 dashboards during the pandemic’s first year and common barriers, enablers and lessons from the experiences of teams responsible for their development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Multiple methods were applied to identify and recruit COVID-19 dashboard teams using a purposive, quota sampling approach. Semi-structured group interviews were conducted between April– June 2021. Using elaborative coding and thematic analysis, descriptive and explanatory themes were derived from interview data. A validation workshop with study participants was held in June 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eighty informants, representing 33 national COVID-19 dashboard teams across the WHO European Region participated. Most dashboards were launched swiftly in the first months of the pandemic, between February–May 2020. The urgency, intense workload, limited human resources, data and privacy constraints, and public scrutiny were common to the initial development stage. Themes related to barriers or enablers were identified pertaining to the pre-pandemic context, pandemic itself, people and processes, software, data, and users. Lessons emerged around the themes of simplicity, trust, partnership, software and data, and change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 dashboards were developed in a learning-by-doing approach. The experiences of teams signal initial under-preparedness was compensated by high-level political endorsement, the professionalism of teams, accelerated data improvements, and immediate support of commercial software solutions. To leverage the full potential of dashboards, investments are needed at team-, national- and pan-European-level.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266747" rel="alternate" title="The experiences of 33 national COVID-19 dashboard teams during the first year of the pandemic in the WHO European Region: a qualitative study (4 tweets)"/><category term="Health Informatics"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.21264927</id><title>Development and Evaluation of AccuPower® COVID-19 Multiplex Real-Time RT-PCR Kit and AccuPower® SARS-CoV-2 Multiplex Real-Time RT-PCR Kit for SARS-CoV-2 Detection in Sputum, NPS/OPS, Saliva and Pooled Samples (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.211926+00:00</updated><author><name>In Bum Suh</name></author><author><name>Jaegyun Lim</name></author><author><name>Hyo Seon Kim</name></author><author><name>Guil Rhim</name></author><author><name>Kim Heebum</name></author><author><name>Kim Hana</name></author><author><name>Lee Sae-Mi</name></author><author><name>Park Hyun-sang</name></author><author><name>Song Hyun Ju</name></author><author><name>Hong MyungKook</name></author><author><name>Shin Gyung Sook</name></author><author><name>Moon Jung Kim</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Rapid and accurate detection of the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) is essential for the successful control of the current global COVID-19 pandemic. The real-time reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (Real-time RT-PCR) is the most widely used detection technique. This research describes the development of two novel multiplex real-time RT-PCR kits, &lt;italic&gt;AccuPower&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; COVID-19 Multiplex Real-Time RT-PCR Kit (NCVM) specifically designed for use with the &lt;italic&gt;ExiStation&lt;/italic&gt;™48 system (comprised of &lt;italic&gt;ExiPrep&lt;/italic&gt;™48 Dx and &lt;italic&gt;Exicycler&lt;/italic&gt;™96 by BIONEER, Korea) for sample RNA extraction and PCR detection, and &lt;italic&gt;AccuPower&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; SARS-CoV-2 Multiplex Real-Time RT-PCR Kit (SCVM) designed to be compatible with manufacturers’ on-market PCR instruments. The limit of detection (LoD) of NCVM was 120 copies/μL and the LoD of the SCVM was 2 copies/mL for both the gene and the SARS-CoV-2 gene (N gene and RdRp gene). The &lt;italic&gt;AccuPower&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; kits demonstrated high precision with no cross reactivity to other respiratory-related microorganisms. The clinical performance of &lt;italic&gt;AccuPower&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; kits was evaluated using the following clinical samples: sputum and nasopharyngeal/oropharyngeal swab (NPS/OPS) samples. Overall agreement of the &lt;italic&gt;AccuPower&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; kits with a Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approved emergency use authorized commercial kit (STANDARD™ M nCoV Real-Time Detection kit, SD BIOSENSOR, Korea) was above 95% (Cohen’s kappa coefficient ≥ 0.95), with a sensitivity of over 95%. The NPS/OPS specimen pooling experiment was conducted to verify the usability of &lt;italic&gt;AccuPower&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; kits on pooled samples and the results showed greater than 90% agreement with individual NPS/OPS samples. The clinical performance of &lt;italic&gt;AccuPower&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; kits with saliva samples was also compared with NPS/OPS samples and demonstrated over 95% agreement (Cohen’s kappa coefficient &amp;gt; 0.95). This study shows the BIONEER NCVM and SCVM assays are comparable with the current standard confirmation assay and are suitable for effective clinical management and control of SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.21264927" rel="alternate" title="Development and Evaluation of AccuPower® COVID-19 Multiplex Real-Time RT-PCR Kit and AccuPower® SARS-CoV-2 Multiplex Real-Time RT-PCR Kit for SARS-CoV-2 Detection in Sputum, NPS/OPS, Saliva and Pooled Samples (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.21266655</id><title>Determining international spread of novel B.1.1.523 SARS-CoV-2 lineage (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.212120+00:00</updated><author><name>Lukas Zemaitis</name></author><author><name>Gediminas Alzbutas</name></author><author><name>Dovydas Gecys</name></author><author><name>Andrey Komissarov</name></author><author><name>Arnoldas Pautienius</name></author><author><name>Rasa Ugenskiene</name></author><author><name>Marius Sukys</name></author><author><name>Vaiva Lesauskaite</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Here we report the emergence of variant lineage B.1.1.523 that contains a set of mutations including 156_158del, E484K and S494P in Spike protein. E484K and S494P are known to significantly reduce SARS-CoV-2 neutralization by convalescent and vaccinee sera and are considered as mutations of concern. Lineage B.1.1.523 has presumably originated in Russian Federation and spread across European countries with the peak of transmission in April – May 2021. The B.1.1.523 lineage has now been reported from 27 countries.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.21266655" rel="alternate" title="Determining international spread of novel B.1.1.523 SARS-CoV-2 lineage (4 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266713</id><title>In Vitro Nasal Tissue Model for the Validation of Nasopharyngeal and Mid-turbinate Swabs for SARS-CoV-2 Testing (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.212267+00:00</updated><author><name>Devon R. Hartigan</name></author><author><name>Miryam Adelfio</name></author><author><name>Molly E. Shutt</name></author><author><name>Stephanie M. Jones</name></author><author><name>Shreya Patel</name></author><author><name>Joshua T. Marchand</name></author><author><name>Pamela D. McGuinness</name></author><author><name>Bryan O. Buchholz</name></author><author><name>Chiara E. Ghezzi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Large-scale population testing is a key tool to mitigate the spread of respiratory pathogens, as in the current COVID-19 pandemic, where swabs are used to collect samples in the upper airways (e.g. nasopharyngeal and mid-turbinate nasal cavities) for diagnostics. However, the high volume of supplies required to achieve large-scale population testing has posed unprecedented challenges for swab manufacturing and distribution, resulting in a global shortage that has heavily impacted testing capacity world-wide and prompted the development of new swabs suitable for large-scale production. Newly designed swabs require rigorous pre-clinical and clinical validation studies that are costly and time consuming (&lt;italic&gt;i&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;e&lt;/italic&gt;. months to years long); reducing the risks associated with swab validation is therefore paramount for their rapid deployment. To address these shortages, we developed a 3D-printed tissue model that mimics the nasopharyngeal and mid-turbinate nasal cavities, and we validated its use as a new tool to rapidly test swab performance. In addition to the nasal architecture, the tissue model mimics the soft nasal tissue with a silk-based sponge lining, and the physiological nasal fluid with asymptomatic and symptomatic viscosities of synthetic mucus. We performed several assays comparing standard flocked and injection-molded swabs. We quantified the swab pick-up and release, and determined the effect of viral load and mucus viscosity on swab efficacy by spiking the synthetic mucus with heat-inactivated SARS-CoV-2 virus. By molecular assays, we found that injected molded swabs performed similarly or superiorly in comparison to standard flocked swabs and we underscored a viscosity-dependent difference in cycle threshold values between the asymptomatic and symptomatic mucus for both swabs. To conclude, we developed an &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; nasal tissue model, that corroborated previous swab performance data from clinical studies, with the potential of providing researchers with a clinically relevant, reproducible, safe, and cost-effective validation tool for the rapid development of newly designed swabs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266713" rel="alternate" title="In Vitro Nasal Tissue Model for the Validation of Nasopharyngeal and Mid-turbinate Swabs for SARS-CoV-2 Testing (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.21264092</id><title>Distribution of confirmed with COVID-19 by age and gender in Mexico (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.212610+00:00</updated><author><name>Adalberto Maldonado</name></author><author><name>Marco Reyes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Social, economic, and cultural factors can influence the likelihood of exposure to the virus of each person in sanitary emergencies like those of COVID-19. In this sense, parallel to the biological vulnerability to infection with SARS-CoV-2, said factors determine a complementary vulnerability to infection. Hence, they can influence in gender and age distributions of those confirmed, which is not entirely comprehended yet. The effect that age and gender can have on total vulnerability in Mexico thus far is not understood. A better understanding of such dependence can help policy optimization and decision-making to future similar emergencies. We aim to study the age and gender distributions of those confirmed with COVID-19 in Mexico. We also investigate the vulnerability to the infection with SARS-CoV-2 depending on such features. Two different samples of the Mexican population are analyzed in this non-experimental study to compare each other and evaluate the association of the result of the COVID-19 test with gender and age. Data up until the beginning of the vaccination are considered. The percentage of confirmed males is higher than females in both samples, and most tested and confirmed are working-age. Age distributions are positively skewed, with the peak in [30,39] years, which disagrees with the distribution of the Mexican population. The data suggest that the vulnerability to infection weakly depends on gender and age. Males were identified as the most vulnerable gender, and the age group [70,79] showed a higher vulnerability to infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.21264092" rel="alternate" title="Distribution of confirmed with COVID-19 by age and gender in Mexico (3 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.21266561</id><title>Reactogenicity of COVID-19 vaccine in hemodialysis patients: a single-center retrospective study (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.212742+00:00</updated><author><name>Gaetano Alfano</name></author><author><name>Niccolò Morisi</name></author><author><name>Francesco Fontana</name></author><author><name>Roberta Scarmignan</name></author><author><name>Laura Tonelli</name></author><author><name>Camilla Ferri</name></author><author><name>Martina Montani</name></author><author><name>Silvia Giovanella</name></author><author><name>Giulia Ligabue</name></author><author><name>Giacomo Mori</name></author><author><name>Erica Franceschini</name></author><author><name>Giovanni Guaraldi</name></author><author><name>Gianni Cappelli</name></author><author><name>Riccardo Magistroni</name></author><author><name>Gabriele Donati</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some hemodialysis patients are reluctant to COVID-19 for the development of adverse events (AEs). The aim of this study was to verify the safety of mRNA-1273 vaccine in hemodialysis patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted a retrospective analysis of in-center hemodialysis patients who underwent mRNA-1273 vaccine from March 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; to April 30&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;, 2021. All AEs occurring after the first and the second doses were collected and classified as local or systemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overall, 126 patients on chronic maintenance dialysis without a prior COVID-19 diagnosis were vaccinated with two doses of mRNA-1273 vaccine. Mean age was 68 (IQR, 54,7-76) years and 53.6% of patients were aged ≥ 65 years. During the observational period of 68 (IQR, 66-70) days, AEs occurred in 57.9% and 61.9% of patients after the first dose and second dose, respectively. The most common AEs were: injection-site pain (61.9%), erythema (4.8%), itching (4.8%), swelling (16.7%), axillary swelling/tenderness (2.4%), fever (17.5%) headache (7.9%), fatigue (23.8%), myalgia (17.5%), arthralgia (12.7%), dyspnoea (2.4%), nausea/vomiting (7.1%), diarrhoea (5.6%), shivers (4%) and vertigo (1.6%).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The rates of local AEs were similar after the first and second doses (P=0.8), whereas systemic AEs occurred more frequently after the second dose (P=0.001). Fever (P=0.03), fatigue (P=0.02) and nausea/vomiting (P=0.03) were significantly more frequent after the second dose of the vaccine. There were no age-related differences in the rate of AEs. Overall, vaccine-related AEs in hemodialysis patients seem to be lower than in the general population.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;RNA-1273 vaccine was associated with the development of transient AEs after the first (57.9%) and second doses (61.9%) in patients on chronic maintenance hemodialysis. Systemic AEs were more common after the second dose. Overall, all AEs lasted for a few days, without any apparent sequelae.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.21266561" rel="alternate" title="Reactogenicity of COVID-19 vaccine in hemodialysis patients: a single-center retrospective study (3 tweets)"/><category term="Nephrology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.21266594</id><title>Sustained negative mental health outcomes among healthcare workers over the first year of the COVID-19 pandemic: a prospective cohort study (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.213157+00:00</updated><author><name>Roberto Mediavilla</name></author><author><name>Eduardo Fernández-Jiménez</name></author><author><name>Irene Martinez-Morata</name></author><author><name>Fabiola Jaramillo</name></author><author><name>Jorge Andreo-Jover</name></author><author><name>Inés Morán-Sánchez</name></author><author><name>Franco Mascayano</name></author><author><name>Berta Moreno-Küstner</name></author><author><name>Sergio Minué</name></author><author><name>José Luis Ayuso-Mateos</name></author><author><name>Richard A. Bryant</name></author><author><name>María-Fe Bravo-Ortiz</name></author><author><name>Gonzalo Martínez-Alés</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To characterize the evolution of healthcare workers’ mental health status over the 1-year period following the initial COVID-19 pandemic outbreak and to examine baseline characteristics associated with resolution or persistence of mental health problems over time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted an 8-month follow-up cohort study. Eligible participants were healthcare workers working in Spain. Baseline data were collected during the initial pandemic outbreak. Survey-based self-reported measures included COVID-19-related exposures, sociodemographic characteristics, and three mental health outcomes (psychological distress, depression symptoms, and posttraumatic stress disorder symptoms). We examined three longitudinal trajectories in mental health outcomes between baseline and follow-up assessments (namely &lt;italic&gt;asymptomatic/stable, recovering&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;persistently symptomatic/worsening&lt;/italic&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We recruited 1,807 participants. Between baseline and follow-up assessments, the proportion of respondents screening positive for psychological distress and probable depression decreased, respectively, from 74% to 56% and from 28% to 21%. Two-thirds remained asymptomatic/stable in terms of depression symptoms and 56% remained symptomatic or worsened over time in terms of psychological distress.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Poor mental health outcomes among healthcare workers persisted over time. Occupational programs and mental health strategies should be put in place.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.21266594" rel="alternate" title="Sustained negative mental health outcomes among healthcare workers over the first year of the COVID-19 pandemic: a prospective cohort study (3 tweets)"/><category term="Psychiatry and Clinical Psychology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266785</id><title>A RANDOMIZED CLINICAL TRIAL OF 2-WEEK METHOTREXATE DISCONTINUATION IN RHEUMATOID ARTHRITIS PATIENTS VACCINATED WITH INACTIVATED SARS-COV-2 VACCINE (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.213540+00:00</updated><author><name>Carlo S R Araujo</name></author><author><name>Ana C Medeiros-Ribeiro</name></author><author><name>Carla G S Saad</name></author><author><name>Karina R Bonfiglioli</name></author><author><name>Diogo S Domiciano</name></author><author><name>Andrea Y Shimabuco</name></author><author><name>Matheus R Silva</name></author><author><name>Emily F N Yuki</name></author><author><name>Sandra G Pasoto</name></author><author><name>Tatiana N Pedrosa</name></author><author><name>Leonard Kupa</name></author><author><name>Gioanna Zou</name></author><author><name>Rosa M R Pereira</name></author><author><name>Clovis A Silva</name></author><author><name>Nadia E Aikawa</name></author><author><name>Eloisa Bonfa</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To evaluate the effect on immunogenicity and safety of 2-week methotrexate(MTX) discontinuation after each dose of the Sinovac-CoronaVac vaccine versus MTX maintenance in rheumatoid arthritis(RA) patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was a single-center, prospective, randomized, investigator-blinded, intervention study (#&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT04754698"&gt;NCT04754698&lt;/ext-link&gt;, CoronavRheum), including adult RA patients(stable CDAI&amp;lt;10, prednisone&amp;lt;7.5mg/day), randomized(1:1) to withdraw MTX(MTX-hold) for 2 weeks after each vaccine dose or maintain MTX(MTX-maintain), evaluated at D0, D28 and D69. Co-primary outcomes were anti-SARS-CoV-2 S1/S2 IgG seroconversion(SC) and neutralizing antibody(NAb) positivity at D69. Secondary outcomes were GMT and changes in disease activity scores. For immunogenicity analyses, we excluded patients with baseline positive IgG/NAb, and, for safety reasons, those unable to hold MTX twice(CDAI&amp;gt;10 at D28).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Randomization included 138 patients with 9 exclusions(5 COVID-19, 4 protocol violations). Safety evaluation included 60(MTX-hold) and 69(MTX-maintain) patients. Further exclusions consisted of 27 patients[13(21.7%) vs. 14(20.3%),p=0.848] with positive baseline IgG/NAb and 10 patients(21.3%) in MTX-hold with CDAI&amp;gt;10 at D28. At D69, a higher increase in SC[29(78.4%) vs 30(54.5%),p=0.019] was observed in MTX-hold(n=37) in comparison to MTX-maintain(n=55), with parallel augmentation in GMT[34.2(25.2-46.4) &lt;italic&gt;vs&lt;/italic&gt; 16.8(11.9-23.6),p=0.006]. No differences were observed for NAb positivity[23(62.2%) &lt;italic&gt;vs&lt;/italic&gt; 27(49.1%),p=0.217]. Longitudinal variations in disease activity scores were alike in both groups(CDAI,p=0.144; DAS28-CRP,p=0.718).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We provided novel data that 2-week MTX withdrawal after each vaccine dose improves anti-SARS-CoV-2 immunogenicity. The comparable longitudinal variations of disease activity in both groups suggest that discontinuation is a feasible and efficient strategy in well-controlled RA patients, and may be even safer for vaccines with longer interval between doses or single dose schedules.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;FAPESP/CNPq/B3-Bolsa de Valores-Brasil.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266785" rel="alternate" title="A RANDOMIZED CLINICAL TRIAL OF 2-WEEK METHOTREXATE DISCONTINUATION IN RHEUMATOID ARTHRITIS PATIENTS VACCINATED WITH INACTIVATED SARS-COV-2 VACCINE (3 tweets)"/><category term="Rheumatology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266559</id><title>Factors associated with COVID-19 vaccine acceptance and hesitancy among residents of Northern California jails (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.213929+00:00</updated><author><name>Yiran E Liu</name></author><author><name>Jillian Oto</name></author><author><name>John Will</name></author><author><name>Christopher LeBoa</name></author><author><name>Alexis Doyle</name></author><author><name>Neil Rens</name></author><author><name>Shelley Aggarwal</name></author><author><name>Iryna Kalish</name></author><author><name>Marcela Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Beruk Sherif</name></author><author><name>Chrisele Trinidad</name></author><author><name>Michael Del Rosario</name></author><author><name>Sophie Allen</name></author><author><name>Robert Spencer</name></author><author><name>Carlos Morales</name></author><author><name>Alexander Chyorny</name></author><author><name>Jason R Andrews</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carceral facilities are high-risk settings for COVID-19 transmission. Understanding of factors associated with COVID-19 vaccine acceptance and hesitancy among incarcerated individuals is incomplete, especially for people living in jails.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted a retrospective review of COVID-19 vaccination data from the electronic health record (EHR) of residents in two Northern California county jails to examine factors associated with vaccine uptake in this population. We additionally administered a survey in four jails to assess reasons for vaccine hesitancy, sources of COVID-19 information, and medical mistrust. We performed multivariate logistic regression to determine associations with vaccine uptake or hesitancy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of 2,584 jail residents offered a COVID-19 vaccine between March 19, 2021 and June 30, 2021, 1,464 (56.7%) accepted at least one dose. Among vaccinated residents, 538 (36.7%) initially refused the vaccine. Vaccine uptake was higher among older individuals, women, those with recent flu vaccination, and those living in shared cells or open dorms. Leading reasons for vaccine hesitancy included concerns around side effects and suboptimal efficacy. Television and friends/family were the most commonly cited and the most trusted sources of COVID-19 information, respectively. Vaccine acceptance was associated with increased trust in COVID-19 information sources and in medical personnel both in and out of jail.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ongoing evidence-based COVID-19 vaccination efforts are needed in high-risk carceral settings. Effective interventions to improve vaccination rates in this population should utilize accessible and trusted sources of information to address concerns about vaccine side effects and efficacy and foster medical trust.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266559" rel="alternate" title="Factors associated with COVID-19 vaccine acceptance and hesitancy among residents of Northern California jails (3 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266673</id><title>Neutralization of SARS-CoV-2 variants by rVSV-ΔG-spike-elicited human sera (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.214896+00:00</updated><author><name>Yfat Yahalom-Ronen</name></author><author><name>Noam Erez</name></author><author><name>Morly Fisher</name></author><author><name>Hadas Tamir</name></author><author><name>Boaz Politi</name></author><author><name>Hagit Achdout</name></author><author><name>Sharon Melamed</name></author><author><name>Itai Glinert</name></author><author><name>Shay Weiss</name></author><author><name>Inbar Cohen-Gihon</name></author><author><name>Ofir Israeli</name></author><author><name>Marina Izak</name></author><author><name>Michal Mandelboim</name></author><author><name>Yoseph Caraco</name></author><author><name>Noa Madar-Balakirski</name></author><author><name>Adva Mechaly</name></author><author><name>Eilat Shinar</name></author><author><name>Daniel Cohen</name></author><author><name>Adi Beth-Din</name></author><author><name>Anat Zvi</name></author><author><name>Hadar Marcus</name></author><author><name>Tomer Israely</name></author><author><name>Nir Paran</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;BriLife® (rVSV-ΔG-spike) is a SARS-CoV-2 vaccine candidate based on vesicular stomatitis virus (VSV) platform. We show that sera from BriLife® vaccinees maintain neutralization capacity against alpha, beta, gamma and delta SARS-CoV-2 variants. BriLife® spontaneously-acquired spike mutations, corresponding with key SARS-CoV-2 variants’ mutations, may contribute to its efficacy against SARS-CoV-2 variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266673" rel="alternate" title="Neutralization of SARS-CoV-2 variants by rVSV-ΔG-spike-elicited human sera (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266683</id><title>Final sizes and durations of new COVID-19 pandemic waves in Ukraine and around the world predicted by generalized SIR model (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.217321+00:00</updated><author><name>Igor Nesteruk</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;New waves of the COVID-19 pandemic in Ukraine, which began in the summer of 2021, and after holidays in the middle of October 2021, were characterized by almost exponential growth of smoothed daily numbers of new cases. This is a matter of great concern and the need to immediately predict the epidemic dynamics in order to assess the possible maximum values of new cases, the risk of infection and the number of deaths. The generalized SIR-model and corresponding parameter identification procedure was used to simulate and predict the dynamics of two new epidemic waves in Ukraine and one in the whole world. Results of calculations show that new cases in Ukraine will not stop to appear before November 2022. If the global situation with vaccination, testing and treatment will not change, the pandemic could continue for another ten years.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266683" rel="alternate" title="Final sizes and durations of new COVID-19 pandemic waves in Ukraine and around the world predicted by generalized SIR model (3 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266721</id><title>Simulating the impact of vaccination rates on the initial stages of a COVID-19 outbreak in New Zealand (Aotearoa) with a stochastic model (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.217704+00:00</updated><author><name>Leighton M. Watson</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aim&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The August 2021 COVID-19 outbreak in Auckland has caused the New Zealand government to transition from an elimination strategy to suppression, which relies heavily on high vaccination rates in the population. As restrictions are eased and as COVID-19 leaks through the Auckland boundary, there is a need to understand how different levels of vaccination will impact the initial stages of COVID-19 outbreaks that are seeded around the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Method&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A stochastic branching process model is used to simulate the initial spread of a COVID-19 outbreak for different vaccination rates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;High vaccination rates are effective at minimizing the number of infections and hospitalizations. Increasing vaccination rates from 20% (approximate value at the start of the August 2021 outbreak) to 80% (approximate proposed target) of the total population can reduce the median number of infections that occur within the first four weeks of an outbreak from 1011 to 14 (25&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; and 75&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; quantiles of 545-1602 and 2-32 for V=20% and V=80%, respectively). As the vaccination rate increases, the number of breakthrough infections (infections in fully vaccinated individuals) and hospitalizations of vaccinated individuals increases. Unvaccinated individuals, however, are 3.3x more likely to be infected with COVID-19 and 25x more likely to be hospitalized.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This work demonstrates the importance of vaccination in protecting individuals from COVID-19, preventing high caseloads, and minimizing the number of hospitalizations and hence limiting the pressure on the healthcare system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.21266721" rel="alternate" title="Simulating the impact of vaccination rates on the initial stages of a COVID-19 outbreak in New Zealand (Aotearoa) with a stochastic model (3 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>