<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.524007+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.31.454592</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 fears green: the chlorophyll catabolite Pheophorbide a is a potent antiviral (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.524458+00:00</updated><author><name>Guillermo H. Jimenez-Aleman</name></author><author><name>Victoria Castro</name></author><author><name>Addis Longdaitsbehere</name></author><author><name>Marta Gutierrez-Rodríguez</name></author><author><name>Urtzi Garaigorta</name></author><author><name>Roberto Solano</name></author><author><name>Pablo Gastaminza</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 pandemic is having devastating consequences worldwide. Although vaccination advances at good pace, effectiveness against emerging variants is unpredictable. The virus has displayed a remarkable resistance to treatments and no drugs have been proved fully effective against Covid-19. Thus, despite the international efforts, there is still an urgent need for new potent and safe antivirals against SARS-CoV-2. Here we exploited the enormous potential of plant metabolism using the bryophyte &lt;italic&gt;Marchantia polymorpha&lt;/italic&gt; and identified a potent SARS-CoV-2 antiviral, following a bioactivity-guided fractionation and mass-spectrometry approach. We found that the chlorophyll derivative Pheophorbide a (PheoA), a porphyrin compound similar to animal Protoporphyrin IX, has an extraordinary antiviral activity against SARS-CoV-2 preventing infection of cultured monkey and human cells, without noticeable cytotoxicity. We also show that PheoA prevents coronavirus entry into the cells by directly targeting the viral particle. Besides SARS-CoV-2, PheoA also displayed a broad-spectrum antiviral activity against (+) strand RNA viral pathogens such as HCV, West Nile, and other coronaviruses, but not against (−) strand RNA viruses, such as VSV. Our results indicate that PheoA displays a remarkable potency and a satisfactory therapeutic index, which together with its previous use in photoactivable cancer therapy in humans, suggest that it may be considered as a potential candidate for antiviral therapy against SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.31.454592" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 fears green: the chlorophyll catabolite Pheophorbide a is a potent antiviral (24 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.01.454662</id><title>Langerhans cells and cDC1s play redundant roles in mRNA-LNP induced protective anti-influenza and anti-SARS-CoV-2 responses (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.524698+00:00</updated><author><name>Sonia Ndeupen</name></author><author><name>Aurélie Bouteau</name></author><author><name>Christopher Herbst</name></author><author><name>Zhen Qin</name></author><author><name>Zachary Hutchins</name></author><author><name>Drishya Kurup</name></author><author><name>Leila Zabihi Diba</name></author><author><name>Botond Z. Igyártó</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nucleoside modified mRNA combined with Acuitas Therapeutics’ lipid nanoparticles (LNP) have been shown to support robust humoral immune responses in many preclinical animal vaccine studies and later in humans with the SARS-CoV-2 vaccination. We recently showed that this platform is highly inflammatory due to the LNPs’ ionizable lipid component. The inflammatory property is key to support the development of potent humoral immune responses. However, the mechanism by which this platform drives T follicular helper cells (Tfh) and humoral immune responses remains unknown. Here we show that lack of Langerhans cells or cDC1s neither significantly affected the induction of PR8 HA and SARS-CoV-2 RBD-specific Tfh cells and humoral immune responses, nor susceptibility towards the lethal challenge of influenza and SARS-CoV-2. However, the combined deletion of these two DC subsets led to a significant decrease in the induction of PR8 HA and SARS-CoV-2 RBD-specific Tfh cell and humoral immune responses. Despite these observed defects, the still high antibody titers were sufficient to confer protection towards lethal viral challenges. We further found that IL-6, but not neutrophils, was required to generate Tfh cells and antibody responses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In summary, here we bring evidence that the mRNA-LNP platform can support protective adaptive immune responses in the absence of specific DC subsets through an IL-6 dependent and neutrophil independent mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.01.454662" rel="alternate" title="Langerhans cells and cDC1s play redundant roles in mRNA-LNP induced protective anti-influenza and anti-SARS-CoV-2 responses (11 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.03.21261545</id><title>Domestic and international mobility trends in the United Kingdom during the COVID-19 pandemic: An analysis of Facebook data (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.524888+00:00</updated><author><name>Harry ER Shepherd</name></author><author><name>Florence S Atherden</name></author><author><name>Ho Man Theophilus Chan</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Loveridge</name></author><author><name>Andrew J Tatem</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Since early March 2020, the COVID-19 epidemic across the United Kingdom has led to a range of social distancing policies, which resulted in changes to mobility across different regions. An understanding of how these policies impacted travel patterns over time and at different spatial scales is important for designing effective strategies, future pandemic planning and in providing broader insights on the population geography of the country. Crowd level data on mobile phone usage can be used as a proxy for population mobility patterns and provide a way of quantifying in near-real time the impact of social distancing measures on changes in mobility. Here we explore patterns of change in densities, domestic and international flows and co-location of Facebook users in the UK from March 2020 to March 2021. We find substantial heterogeneities across time and region, with large changes observed compared to pre-pandemic patterns. The impacts of periods of lockdown on distances travelled and flow volumes are evident, with each showing variations, but some significant reductions in co-location rates. Clear differences in multiple metrics of mobility are seen in central London compared to the rest of the UK, with each of Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland showing significant deviations from England at times. Moreover, the impacts of rapid changes in rules on international travel to and from the UK are seen in substantial fluctuations in traveller volumes by destination. While questions remain about the representativeness of the Facebook data, previous studies have shown strong correspondence with census-based data and alternative mobility measures, suggesting that findings here are valuable for guiding strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.03.21261545" rel="alternate" title="Domestic and international mobility trends in the United Kingdom during the COVID-19 pandemic: An analysis of Facebook data (9 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.02.21261459</id><title>Dynamics of COVID-19 pandemic in India and Pakistan: A metapopulation modelling approach (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.525055+00:00</updated><author><name>Samantha J. Brozak</name></author><author><name>Binod Pant</name></author><author><name>Salman Safdar</name></author><author><name>Abba B. Gumel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;India has been the latest global epicenter for COVID-19, a novel coronavirus disease that emerged in China in late 2019. We present a base mathematical model for the transmission dynamics of COVID-19 in India and its neighbor, Pakistan. The base model, which takes the form of a deterministic system of nonlinear differential equations, is parameterized using cumulative COVID-19 mortality data from each of the two countries. The model was used to assess the population-level impact of the control and mitigation strategies implemented in the two countries (notably community lockdowns, use of face masks, and social-distancing). Numerical simulations of the basic model indicate that, based on the current baseline levels of the control and mitigation strategies implemented, the pandemic trajectory in India is on a downward trend (as characterized by the reproduction number of the disease dynamics in India below, but close to, unity). This downward trend will be reversed, and India will be recording mild outbreaks (i.e., pandemic waves), if the control and mitigation strategies are relaxed from their current levels (e.g., relaxed to the extent that the associated community transmission parameters are increased by 20% or 40% from their current baseline values). Our simulations suggest that India could record up to 460,000 cumulative deaths by early September 2021 under the baseline levels of the control strategies implemented (up to 25,000 of the projected deaths could be averted if the control and mitigation measures are strengthened to the extent that the associated community transmission parameters are reduced by 20% from their baseline values). Our simulations show that the pandemic in Pakistan is much milder, with an estimated projected cumulative mortality of about 24,000 by early September 2021 under the baseline scenario. The basic model was extended to assess the impact of back-and-forth mobility between the two countries. Simulations of the resulting metapopulation model, which uses a Lagrangian mobility framework (based on residence-time spent in each country), shows that the burden of the pandemic in Pakistan increases with increasing values of the average time residents of India spend in Pakistan. In particular, it is shown that the India-to-Pakistan mobility pattern may trigger a significant fourth wave of the pandemic in Pakistan (under certain mobility scenarios and mitigation levels), with daily mortality peaking in mid-August to mid-September of 2021. It is also shown that extending the current travel restrictions by at least three months would significantly enhance the prospect of eliminating the pandemic in both countries. On the other hand, it is shown that, in addition to causing future multiple waves of the pandemic, easing the current levels of control and mitigation measures in the two countries (including travel restrictions) would result in delaying pandemic elimination in India and Pakistan to November and July 2022, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.02.21261459" rel="alternate" title="Dynamics of COVID-19 pandemic in India and Pakistan: A metapopulation modelling approach (5 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.06.455441</id><title>VPS29 exerts opposing effects on endocytic viral entry (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.525211+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Poston</name></author><author><name>Yiska Weisblum</name></author><author><name>Alvaro Hobbs</name></author><author><name>Paul D Bieniasz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Emerging zoonotic viral pathogens threaten global health and there is an urgent need to discover host and viral determinants influencing infection. We performed a loss-of-function genome-wide CRISPR screen in a human lung cell line using HCoV-OC43, a human betacoronavirus. One candidate gene, VPS29, was required for infection by HCoV-OC43, SARS-CoV-2, other endemic and pandemic threat coronaviruses as well as ebolavirus. However, VPS29 deficiency had no effect on certain other viruses that enter cells via endosomes and had an opposing, enhancing effect on influenza A virus infection. VPS29 deficiency caused changes endosome morphology, and acidity and attenuated the activity of endosomal proteases. These changes in endosome properties caused incoming coronavirus, but not influenza virus particles, to become entrapped therein. Overall, these data show how host regulation of endosome characteristics can influence viral susceptibility and identify a host pathway that could serve as a pharmaceutical target for intervention in zoonotic viral diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.06.455441" rel="alternate" title="VPS29 exerts opposing effects on endocytic viral entry (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>