<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.386616+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.21.21257595</id><title>Ivermectin for the treatment of COVID-19: A systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials (1122 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.387095+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuani M. Roman</name></author><author><name>Paula Alejandra Burela</name></author><author><name>Vinay Pasupuleti</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Piscoya</name></author><author><name>Jose E. Vidal</name></author><author><name>Adrian V. Hernandez</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We systematically assessed benefits and harms of the use of ivermectin (IVM) in COVID-19 patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Published and preprint randomized controlled trials (RCTs) assessing IVM effects on COVID-19 adult patients were searched until March 15, 2021 in five engines. Primary outcomes were all-cause mortality, length of stay (LOS), and adverse events (AE). Secondary outcomes included viral clearance and severe AEs. We evaluated risk of bias (RoB) using the Cochrane RoB 2·0 tool. Inverse variance random effect meta-analyses were performed with quality of evidence (QoE) evaluated using GRADE methodology. Subgroup analyses by severity of disease and RoB, and sensitivity analyses by time of follow-up were conducted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ten RCTs (n=1173) were included. Controls were standard of care [SOC] in five RCTs and placebo in five RCTs. RCTs sample size ranged from 24 to 398 patients, mean age from 26 to 56 years-old, and severity of COVID-19 disease was mild in 8 RCTs, moderate in one RCT, and mild and moderate in one RCT. IVM did not reduce all-cause mortality vs. controls (RR 0.37, 95%CI 0.12 to 1.13, very low QoE). IVM did not reduce LOS vs. controls (MD 0.72 days, 95%CI -0.86 to 2.29, very low QoE). AEs, severe AE and viral clearance were similar between IVM and controls (low QoE for these three outcomes). Subgroups by severity of COVID-19 or RoB were mostly consistent with main analyses; all-cause mortality in three RCTs at high RoB was reduced with IVM. Sensitivity analyses excluding RCTs with follow up &amp;lt;21 days showed no difference in all-cause mortality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In comparison to SOC or placebo, IVM did not reduce all-cause mortality, length of stay or viral clearance in RCTs in COVID-19 patients with mostly mild disease. IVM did not have effect on AEs or SAEs. IVM is not a viable option to treat COVID-19 patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.21.21257595" rel="alternate" title="Ivermectin for the treatment of COVID-19: A systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials (1122 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.22.21257633</id><title>Genomic reconstruction of the SARS-CoV-2 epidemic across England from September 2020 to May 2021 (392 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.387533+00:00</updated><author><name>Harald S. Vöhringer</name></author><author><name>Theo Sanderson</name></author><author><name>Matthew Sinnott</name></author><author><name>Nicola De Maio</name></author><author><name>Thuy Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Richard Goater</name></author><author><name>Frank Schwach</name></author><author><name>Ian Harrison</name></author><author><name>Joel Hellewell</name></author><author><name>Cristina Ariani</name></author><author><name>Sonia Gonçalves</name></author><author><name>David Jackson</name></author><author><name>Ian Johnston</name></author><author><name>Alexander W. Jung</name></author><author><name>Callum Saint</name></author><author><name>John Sillitoe</name></author><author><name>Maria Suciu</name></author><author><name>Nick Goldman</name></author><author><name>Ewan Birney</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Funk</name></author><author><name>Erik Volz</name></author><author><name>Dominic Kwiatkowski</name></author><author><name>Meera Chand</name></author><author><name>Inigo Martincorena</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey C. Barrett</name></author><author><name>Moritz Gerstung</name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite regional successes in controlling the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic, global cases have reached an all time high in April 2021 in part due to the evolution of more transmissible variants. Here we use the dense genomic surveillance generated by the COVID-19 Genomics UK Consortium to reconstruct the dynamics of 62 different lineages in each of 315 English local authorities between September 2020 and April 2021. This analysis reveals a series of sub-epidemics that peaked in the early autumn of 2020, followed by a singular jump in transmissibility of the B.1.1.7 lineage. B.1.1.7 grew when other lineages declined during the second national lockdown and regionally tiered restrictions between November and December 2020. A third more stringent national lockdown eventually suppressed B.1.1.7 and eliminated nearly all other lineages in early 2021. However, a series of variants (mostly containing the spike E484K mutation) defied these trends and persisted at moderately increasing proportions. Accounting for sustained introductions, however, indicates that their transmissibility is unlikely to exceed that of B.1.1.7. Finally, B.1.617.2 was repeatedly introduced to England and grew rapidly in April 2021, constituting approximately 40% of sampled COVID-19 genomes on May 15.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.22.21257633" rel="alternate" title="Genomic reconstruction of the SARS-CoV-2 epidemic across England from September 2020 to May 2021 (392 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.446163</id><title>The SARS-CoV-2 variants associated with infections in India, B.1.617, show enhanced spike cleavage by furin (371 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.388581+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas P. Peacock</name></author><author><name>Carol M. Sheppard</name></author><author><name>Jonathan C. Brown</name></author><author><name>Niluka Goonawardane</name></author><author><name>Jie Zhou</name></author><author><name>Max Whiteley</name></author><author><name>Thushan I. de Silva</name></author><author><name>Wendy S. Barclay</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The SARS-CoV-2 spike (S) glycoprotein contains a suboptimal furin cleavage site at the S1/S2 junction with the sequence &lt;sub&gt;681&lt;/sub&gt;PRRAR/S&lt;sub&gt;686&lt;/sub&gt;. This cleavage site is required for efficient airway replication, transmission, and pathogenicity of the virus. The B.1.617 lineage has recently emerged in India, coinciding with substantial disease burden across the country. Early evidence suggests that B.1.617.2 (a sublineage of B.1.617) is more highly transmissible than contemporary lineages. B.1.617 and its sublineages contain a constellation of S mutations including the substitution P681R predicted to further optimise this furin cleavage site. In this short report we provide experimental evidence that virus of the B.1.617 lineage has enhanced S cleavage, that enhanced processing of an expressed B.1.617 S protein in cells is due to P681R, and that this mutation enables more efficient cleavage of a peptide mimetic of the B.1.617 S1/S2 cleavage site by recombinant furin. Together, these data demonstrate viruses in this emerging lineage have enhanced S cleavage by furin which we hypothesise could be enhancing transmissibility and pathogenicity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.446163" rel="alternate" title="The SARS-CoV-2 variants associated with infections in India, B.1.617, show enhanced spike cleavage by furin (371 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.22.21257658</id><title>Effectiveness of COVID-19 vaccines against the B.1.617.2 variant (308 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.389153+00:00</updated><author><name>Jamie Lopez Bernal</name></author><author><name>Nick Andrews</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Gower</name></author><author><name>Eileen Gallagher</name></author><author><name>Ruth Simmons</name></author><author><name>Simon Thelwall</name></author><author><name>Julia Stowe</name></author><author><name>Elise Tessier</name></author><author><name>Natalie Groves</name></author><author><name>Gavin Dabrera</name></author><author><name>Richard Myers</name></author><author><name>Colin Campbell</name></author><author><name>Gayatri Amirthalingam</name></author><author><name>Matt Edmunds</name></author><author><name>Maria Zambon</name></author><author><name>Kevin Brown</name></author><author><name>Susan Hopkins</name></author><author><name>Meera Chand</name></author><author><name>Mary Ramsay</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The B.1.617.2 COVID-19 variant has contributed to the surge in cases in India and has now been detected across the globe, including a notable increase in cases in the UK. We estimate the effectiveness of the BNT162b2 and ChAdOx1 COVID-19 vaccines against this variant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A test negative case control design was used to estimate the effectiveness of vaccination against symptomatic disease with both variants over the period that B.1.617.2 began circulating with cases identified based on sequencing and S-gene target status. Data on all symptomatic sequenced cases of COVID-19 in England was used to estimate the proportion of cases with B.1.617.2 compared to the predominant strain (B.1.1.7) by vaccination status.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Effectiveness was notably lower after 1 dose of vaccine with B.1.617.2 cases 33.5% (95%CI: 20.6 to 44.3) compared to B.1.1.7 cases 51.1% (95%CI: 47.3 to 54.7) with similar results for both vaccines. With BNT162b2 2 dose effectiveness reduced from 93.4% (95%CI: 90.4 to 95.5) with B.1.1.7 to 87.9% (95%CI: 78.2 to 93.2) with B.1.617.2. With ChAdOx1 2 dose effectiveness reduced from 66.1% (95% CI: 54.0 to 75.0) with B.1.1.7 to 59.8% (95%CI: 28.9 to 77.3) with B.1.617.2. Sequenced cases detected after 1 or 2 doses of vaccination had a higher odds of infection with B.1.617.2 compared to unvaccinated cases (OR 1.40; 95%CI: 1.13-1.75).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;After 2 doses of either vaccine there were only modest differences in vaccine effectiveness with the B.1.617.2 variant. Absolute differences in vaccine effectiveness were more marked with dose 1. This would support maximising vaccine uptake with two doses among vulnerable groups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.22.21257658" rel="alternate" title="Effectiveness of COVID-19 vaccines against the B.1.617.2 variant (308 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.21257823</id><title>Estimating the wave 1 and wave 2 infection fatality rates from SARS-CoV-2 in India (131 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.389464+00:00</updated><author><name>Soumik Purkayastha</name></author><author><name>Ritoban Kundu</name></author><author><name>Ritwik Bhaduri</name></author><author><name>Daniel Barker</name></author><author><name>Michael Kleinsasser</name></author><author><name>Debashree Ray</name></author><author><name>Bhramar Mukherjee</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There has been much discussion and debate around the underreporting of COVID-19 infections and deaths in India. In this short report we first estimate the underreporting factor for infections from publicly available data released by the Indian Council of Medical Research on reported number of cases and national seroprevalence surveys. We then use a compartmental epidemiologic model to estimate the undetected number of infections and deaths, yielding estimates of the corresponding underreporting factors. We compare the serosurvey based ad hoc estimate of the infection fatality rate (IFR) with the model-based estimate. Since the first and second waves in India are intrinsically different in nature, we carry out this exercise in two periods: the first wave (April 1, 2020 - January 31, 2021) and part of the second wave (February 1, 2021 – May 15, 2021). The latest national seroprevalence estimate is from January 2021, and thus only relevant to our wave 1 calculations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both wave 1 and wave 2 estimates qualitatively show that there is a large degree of “covert infections” in India, with model-based estimated underreporting factor for infections as &lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;11&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;11 (95% credible interval (CrI) 10&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;71-11&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;47)&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt; and for deaths as &lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;3&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;56 (95% CrI 3&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;48 - 3&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;64)&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt; for wave 1. For wave 2, underreporting factor for infections escalate to &lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;26&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;77 (95% CrI 24&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;26 – 28&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;81)&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt; and to &lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;5&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;77 (95% CrI 5&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;34 – 6&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;15)&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt; for deaths. If we rely on only reported deaths, the IFR estimate is &lt;italic&gt;0&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;13%&lt;/italic&gt; for wave 1 and &lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;0&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;03%&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt; for part of wave 2. Taking underreporting of deaths into account, the IFR estimate is &lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;0&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;46%&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt; for wave 1 and &lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;0&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;18%&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt; for wave 2 (till May 15). Combining waves 1 and 2, as of May 15, while India reported a total of nearly 25 million cases and 270 thousand deaths, the estimated number of infections and deaths stand at 491 million (36% of the population) and 1.21 million respectively, yielding an estimated (combined) infection fatality rate of &lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;0&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;25%&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt;. There is considerable variation in these estimates across Indian states. Up to date seroprevalence studies and mortality data are needed to validate these model-based estimates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.21257823" rel="alternate" title="Estimating the wave 1 and wave 2 infection fatality rates from SARS-CoV-2 in India (131 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.21.445189</id><title>Evaluation of mRNA-1273 against SARS-CoV-2 B.1.351 Infection in Nonhuman Primates (90 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.389661+00:00</updated><author><name>Kizzmekia S. Corbett</name></author><author><name>Anne P. Werner</name></author><author><name>Sarah O’ Connell</name></author><author><name>Matthew Gagne</name></author><author><name>Lilin Lai</name></author><author><name>Juan I. Moliva</name></author><author><name>Barbara Flynn</name></author><author><name>Angela Choi</name></author><author><name>Matthew Koch</name></author><author><name>Kathryn E. Foulds</name></author><author><name>Shayne F. Andrew</name></author><author><name>Dillon R. Flebbe</name></author><author><name>Evan Lamb</name></author><author><name>Saule T. Nurmukhambetova</name></author><author><name>Samantha J. Provost</name></author><author><name>Kevin W. Bock</name></author><author><name>Mahnaz Minai</name></author><author><name>Bianca M. Nagata</name></author><author><name>Alex Van Ry</name></author><author><name>Zackery Flinchbaugh</name></author><author><name>Timothy S. Johnston</name></author><author><name>Elham Bayat Mokhtari</name></author><author><name>Prakriti Mudvari</name></author><author><name>Amy R. Henry</name></author><author><name>Farida Laboune</name></author><author><name>Becky Chang</name></author><author><name>Maciel Porto</name></author><author><name>Jaclyn Wear</name></author><author><name>Gabriela S. Alvarado</name></author><author><name>Seyhan Boyoglu-Barnum</name></author><author><name>John-Paul M. Todd</name></author><author><name>Bridget Bart</name></author><author><name>Anthony Cook</name></author><author><name>Alan Dodson</name></author><author><name>Laurent Pessaint</name></author><author><name>Katelyn Steingrebe</name></author><author><name>Sayda Elbashir</name></author><author><name>Hanne Andersen</name></author><author><name>Kai Wu</name></author><author><name>Darin K. Edwards</name></author><author><name>Swagata Kar</name></author><author><name>Mark G. Lewis</name></author><author><name>Eli Bortiz</name></author><author><name>Ian N. Moore</name></author><author><name>Andrea Carfi</name></author><author><name>Mehul S. Suthar</name></author><author><name>Adrian McDermott</name></author><author><name>Mario Roederer</name></author><author><name>Martha C. Nason</name></author><author><name>Nancy J. Sullivan</name></author><author><name>Daniel C. Douek</name></author><author><name>Barney S. Graham</name></author><author><name>Robert A. Seder</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vaccine efficacy against the B.1.351 variant following mRNA-1273 vaccination in humans has not been determined. Nonhuman primates (NHP) are a useful model for demonstrating whether mRNA-1273 mediates protection against B.1.351.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nonhuman primates received 30 or 100 µg of mRNA-1273 as a prime-boost vaccine at 0 and 4 weeks, a single immunization of 30 µg at week 0, or no vaccine. Antibody and T cell responses were assessed in blood, bronchioalveolar lavages (BAL), and nasal washes. Viral replication in BAL and nasal swabs were determined by qRT-PCR for sgRNA, and histopathology and viral antigen quantification were performed on lung tissue post-challenge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eight weeks post-boost, 100 µg x2 of mRNA-1273 induced reciprocal ID&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; neutralizing geometric mean titers against live SARS-CoV-2 D614G and B.1.351 of 3300 and 240, respectively, and 430 and 84 for the 30 µg x2 group. There were no detectable neutralizing antibodies against B.1351 after the single immunization of 30 µg. On day 2 following B.1.351 challenge, sgRNA in BAL was undetectable in 6 of 8 NHP that received 100 µg x2 of mRNA-1273, and there was a ∼2-log reduction in sgRNA in NHP that received two doses of 30 µg compared to controls. In nasal swabs, there was a 1-log&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;/sub&gt; reduction observed in the 100 µg x2 group. There was limited inflammation or viral antigen in lungs of vaccinated NHP post-challenge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Immunization with two doses of mRNA-1273 achieves effective immunity that rapidly controls lower and upper airway viral replication against the B.1.351 variant in NHP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.21.445189" rel="alternate" title="Evaluation of mRNA-1273 against SARS-CoV-2 B.1.351 Infection in Nonhuman Primates (90 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445356</id><title>Reprogrammed tracrRNAs enable repurposing RNAs as crRNAs and detecting RNAs (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.390349+00:00</updated><author><name>Yang Liu</name></author><author><name>Filipe Pinto</name></author><author><name>Xinyi Wan</name></author><author><name>Shuguang Peng</name></author><author><name>Mengxi Li</name></author><author><name>Zhen Xie</name></author><author><name>Christopher E French</name></author><author><name>Baojun Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In type II CRISPR systems, the guide RNA (gRNA) consists of a CRISPR RNA (crRNA) and a hybridized trans-acting CRISPR RNA (tracrRNA) which interacts directly with Cas9 and is essential to its guided DNA targeting function. Though tracrRNAs are diverse in sequences and structures across type II CRISPR systems, the programmability of crRNA-tracrRNA hybridization for particular Cas9 has not been studied adequately. Here, we revealed the high programmability of crRNA-tracrRNA hybridization for Streptococcus pyogenes Cas9. By reprogramming the crRNA-tracrRNA hybridized sequence, reprogrammed tracrRNAs can repurpose various RNAs as crRNAs to trigger CRISPR function. We showed that the engineered crRNA-tracrRNA pairs enable design of orthogonal cellular computing devices and hijacking of endogenous RNAs as crRNAs. We next designed novel RNA sensors that can monitor the transcriptional activity of specific genes on the host genome and detect SARS-CoV-2 RNA in vitro. The engineering potential of crRNA-tracrRNA interaction has therefore redefined the capabilities of CRISPR/Cas9 system.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445356" rel="alternate" title="Reprogrammed tracrRNAs enable repurposing RNAs as crRNAs and detecting RNAs (16 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.21257644</id><title>Engagement with daily testing instead of self-isolating in contacts of confirmed cases of SARS-CoV-2: A qualitative analysis (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.390580+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah Denford</name></author><author><name>Alex F. Martin</name></author><author><name>Nicola Love</name></author><author><name>Derren Ready</name></author><author><name>Isabel Oliver</name></author><author><name>Richard Amlôt</name></author><author><name>Lucy Yardley</name></author><author><name>G. James Rubin</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In December 2020 and January 2021 Public Health England (PHE) with NHS Test and Trace conducted a study to explore the feasibility and acceptability of daily testing as an alternative to self-isolation following close contact with a confirmed COVID-19 case. This qualitative paper aims to identify factors influencing uptake among those offered daily testing, and the subsequent impact on behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted in-depth interviews with 52 participants who had taken part in the feasibility study. Participants were asked about their experiences of daily testing or self-isolating, their reasons for choosing to test or isolate, and their behaviour during the study period. Data were analysed using inductive thematic analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Results are presented under two main headings: 1) factors influencing acceptance of testing and 2) impact of test results. Participants appeared highly motivated to engage in behaviours that would protect others from the virus. Factors influencing the decision to accept testing included 1) needing to avoid self-isolation 2) concerns about test sensitivity and 3) perceived benefits of detecting infection. Participants who were taking tests reported:1) positive consequences following confirmation of COVID status 2) engaging in essential activities 3) uncertainty and 4) self-isolating whilst testing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study has identified a range of factors that appear to influence the decision to engage in daily testing or to self-isolate following close contact with a positive case, many of which could be addressed by clear communications. Covid-19 infection rates and government restrictions influenced experiences, and so further research is needed to explore perceptions of daily testing and behaviour following close contact with a positive case among a wider range of individuals, in the context of lower rates of COVID-19, few government restrictions on general population behaviour and more widespread testing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.21257644" rel="alternate" title="Engagement with daily testing instead of self-isolating in contacts of confirmed cases of SARS-CoV-2: A qualitative analysis (11 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.23.445305</id><title>Dimerization of SARS-CoV-2 nucleocapsid protein affects sensitivity of ELISA based diagnostics of COVID-19 (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.390888+00:00</updated><author><name>Wajihul Hasan Khan</name></author><author><name>Nida Khan</name></author><author><name>Avinash Mishra</name></author><author><name>Surbhi Gupta</name></author><author><name>Vikrant Bansode</name></author><author><name>Deepa Mehta</name></author><author><name>Rahul Bhambure</name></author><author><name>Anurag S. Rathore</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Diagnostics has played a significant role in effective management of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). Nucleocapsid protein (N protein) is the primary antigen of the virus for development of sensitive diagnostic assays. Thus far, limited knowledge exists about the antigenic properties of the N protein. In this paper, we demonstrate the significant impact of dimerization of SARS-CoV-2 nucleocapsid protein on sensitivity of enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) based diagnostics of COVID-19. The expressed purified protein from &lt;italic&gt;E&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;coli&lt;/italic&gt; consists of two forms, dimeric and monomeric forms, which have been further characterized by biophysical and immunological means. Indirect ELISA indicated elevated susceptibility of the dimeric form of the nucleocapsid protein for identification of protein-specific monoclonal antibody as compared to the monomeric form of the protein. These findings have also been confirmed with the modelled structure of monomeric and dimeric nucleocapsid protein &lt;italic&gt;via&lt;/italic&gt; HHPred software and its solvent accessible surface area, which indicates higher stability and antigenicity of the dimeric type as compared to the monomeric form. It is evident that use of the dimeric form will increase the sensitivity of the current nucleocapsid dependent ELISA for rapid COVID-19 diagnostic. Further, the results indicate that monitoring and maintaining of the monomerdimer composition is critical for accurate and robust diagnostics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="445305v2_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.23.445305" rel="alternate" title="Dimerization of SARS-CoV-2 nucleocapsid protein affects sensitivity of ELISA based diagnostics of COVID-19 (9 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.21257402</id><title>Retrospective screening for SARS-CoV-2 among 5,800 hospitalizations related to influenza-like illness during the 2018-19 pre-pandemic and 2019-2020 pandemic influenza seasons in the VAHNSI network, Spain (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.391086+00:00</updated><author><name>Ainara Mira-Iglesias</name></author><author><name>Beatriz Mengual-Chuliá</name></author><author><name>Laura Cano</name></author><author><name>Javier García-Rubio</name></author><author><name>Miguel Tortajada-Girbés</name></author><author><name>Mario Carballido-Fernández</name></author><author><name>Juan Mollar-Maseres</name></author><author><name>Germán Schwarz-Chavarri</name></author><author><name>Sandra García-Esteban</name></author><author><name>Joan Puig-Barberà</name></author><author><name>Javier Díez-Domingo</name></author><author><name>F. Xavier López-Labrador</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;On March 9 2020 the WHO Global Influenza Program (GIP) asked participant sites on the Global Influenza Hospital Surveillance Network (GIHSN) to contribute to data collection concerning severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). We re-analysed 5,833 viral RNA archived samples collected prospectively from hospital admissions for influenza-like illness (ILI) in the Valencia Region of Spain by the VAHNSI network (4 hospitals, catchment area population 1,118,732) during the prepandemic 2018/2019 (n=4,010) and pandemic 2019/2020 (n=1,823) influenza seasons, for the presence of SARS-CoV-2. We did not find evidence for community-acquired SARS-CoV-2 infection in hospital admissions for ILI in our region before early March 2020.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.21257402" rel="alternate" title="Retrospective screening for SARS-CoV-2 among 5,800 hospitalizations related to influenza-like illness during the 2018-19 pre-pandemic and 2019-2020 pandemic influenza seasons in the VAHNSI network, Spain (9 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445443</id><title>Cooperative multivalent receptor binding promotes exposure of the SARS-CoV-2 fusion machinery core (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.391325+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander J. Pak</name></author><author><name>Alvin Yu</name></author><author><name>Zunlong Ke</name></author><author><name>John A. G. Briggs</name></author><author><name>Gregory A. Voth</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The molecular events that permit the spike glycoprotein of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) to bind, fuse, and enter cells are important to understand for both fundamental and therapeutic reasons. Spike proteins consist of S1 and S2 domains, which recognize angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) receptors and contain the viral fusion machinery, respectively. Ostensibly, the binding of spike trimers to ACE2 receptors promotes the preparation of the fusion machinery by dissociation of the S1 domains. We report the development and use of coarse-grained models and simulations to investigate the dynamical mechanisms involved in viral binding and exposure of the S2 trimeric core. We show that spike trimers cooperatively bind to multiple ACE2 dimers. The multivalent interaction cyclically and processively induces S1 dissociation, thereby exposing the S2 core containing the fusion machinery. Our simulations thus reveal an important concerted interaction between spike trimers and ACE2 dimers that primes the virus for membrane fusion and entry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Viral particles of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), the causative agent of the COVID-19 pandemic, are decorated by spike trimer proteins that mediate entry into cells. Spike trimers first bind to angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) receptors, and subsequently shed their receptor-binding components to expose and prepare the viral fusion machinery. Here, we present systematically developed coarse-grained models and molecular dynamics simulations of viral binding and shedding prior to membrane fusion. Our analysis shows that spike trimers are capable of binding to multiple ACE2 dimers and that this multivalent interaction facilitates exposure of the viral fusion core machinery. Our findings demonstrate the necessity of concerted, cooperative interactions between viral proteins and host cell receptors, and advance fundamental understanding and therapeutic efforts on coronaviruses, aspects of which are at present difficult if not impossible to obtain by experimental means alone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445443" rel="alternate" title="Cooperative multivalent receptor binding promotes exposure of the SARS-CoV-2 fusion machinery core (8 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445386</id><title>Nucleocapsid mutation R203K/G204R increases the infectivity, fitness and virulence of SARS-CoV-2 (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.391493+00:00</updated><author><name>Haibo Wu</name></author><author><name>Na Xing</name></author><author><name>Kaiwen Meng</name></author><author><name>Beibei Fu</name></author><author><name>Weiwei Xue</name></author><author><name>Pan Dong</name></author><author><name>Yang Xiao</name></author><author><name>Gexin Liu</name></author><author><name>Haitao Luo</name></author><author><name>Wenzhuang Zhu</name></author><author><name>Xiaoyuan Lin</name></author><author><name>Geng Meng</name></author><author><name>Zhenglin Zhu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In addition to the mutations on the spike protein (S), co-occurring mutations on nucleocapsid (N) protein are also emerging in SARS-CoV-2 world widely. Mutations R203K/G204R on N, carried by high transmissibility SARS-CoV-2 lineages including B.1.1.7 and P.1, has a rapid spread in the pandemic during the past year. In this study, we performed comprehensive population genomic analyses and virology experiment concerning on the evolution, causation and virology consequence of R203K/G204R mutations. The global incidence frequency (IF) of 203K/204R has rose up from nearly zero to 76% to date with a shrinking from August to November in 2020 but bounced later. Our results show that the emergence of B.1.1.7 is associated with the second growth of R203K/G204R mutants. We identified positive selection evidences that support the adaptiveness of 203K/204R variants. The R203K/G204R mutant virus was created and compared with the native virus. The virus competition experiments show that 203K/204R variants possess a replication advantage over the preceding R203/G204 variants, possibly in relation to the ribonucleocapsid (RNP) assemble during the virus replication. Moreover, the 203K/204R virus increased the infectivity in a human lung cell line and induced an enhanced damage to blood vessel of infected hamsters’ lungs. In consistence, we observed a positive association between the increased severity of COVID-19 and the IF of 203K/204R from in silicon analysis of global clinical and epidemic data. In combination with the informatics and virology experiment, our work suggested the contribution of 203K/204R to the increased transmission and virulence of the SARS-CoV-2. In addition to mutations on the S protein, the mutations on the N protein are also important to virus spread during the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445386" rel="alternate" title="Nucleocapsid mutation R203K/G204R increases the infectivity, fitness and virulence of SARS-CoV-2 (6 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.27.21257940</id><title>The rapid reemergence of seasonal respiratory viruses in Houston, Texas, after relaxing COVID-19 restrictions (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.391712+00:00</updated><author><name>Parsa Hodjat</name></author><author><name>Paul Christensen</name></author><author><name>Sishir Subedi</name></author><author><name>Randall James Olsen</name></author><author><name>David W Bernard</name></author><author><name>Scott Wesley Long</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Implementation of measures to limit the spread of the SARS-CoV-2 virus at the start of the COVID-19 pandemic resulted in a rapid decrease in all other respiratory pathogens. As COVID-19 containment measures were relaxed, the first non-COVID respiratory viruses to return to prepandemic levels were members of the rhinovirus/enterovirus, followed by the rapid return of seasonal coronaviruses, parainfluenza, and respiratory syncytial virus after the complete removal of COVID-19 precautions at the state level, including an end to mask mandates. Inasmuch as COVID-19 has dominated the landscape of respiratory infections since early 2020, it is important for clinicians to recognize the return of non-COVID respiratory pathogens may be rapid and significant when COVID-19 containment measures are removed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.27.21257940" rel="alternate" title="The rapid reemergence of seasonal respiratory viruses in Houston, Texas, after relaxing COVID-19 restrictions (6 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2021-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.21257594</id><title>A comparative study of SIR Model, Linear Regression, Logistic Function and ARIMA Model for forecasting COVID-19 cases (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.392001+00:00</updated><author><name>Saina Abolmaali</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Starting February 2020, COVID-19 was confirmed in 11,946 people worldwide, with a mortality rate of almost 2%. A significant number of epidemic diseases including human Coronavirus display patterns. In this study with the benefit of data analytic, we develop regression models and a Susceptible-Infected-Recovered (SIR) model for the contagion to compare the performance of models to predict number of cases. first, we implement a good understanding of data and perform Exploratory Data Analysis (EDA). Then, we derive the parameters of the model from the available data corresponding to the top 4 regions based on the history of infections and the most infected people as of the end of August 2020. Then models are compared and further research are introduced.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.21257594" rel="alternate" title="A comparative study of SIR Model, Linear Regression, Logistic Function and ARIMA Model for forecasting COVID-19 cases (5 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.444482</id><title>Investigating the possible origin and transmission routes of SARS-CoV-2 genomes and variants of concern in Bangladesh (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.392177+00:00</updated><author><name>Abdullah Al Nahid</name></author><author><name>Ajit Ghosh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic induced by the SARS-CoV-2 virus and its variants has ravaged most countries around the world including Bangladesh. We have analyzed publicly available genomic data to understand the current COVID-19 outbreak scenario as well as the evolutionary origin and transmission routes of SARS-CoV-2 isolates in Bangladesh. All the early isolates as well as recent B.1.1.7 and B.1.351 variants had already spread across the major divisional cities of Bangladesh. A sex biasness towards male COVID-19 patient samples sequencing has observed over female in all age-group, that could be the trend in infection rate. Phylogenetic analysis indicated a total of 13 estimated countries, including Italy, India, United Kingdom, Saudi Arabia, United Arab Emirates, Germany, Australia, New Zealand, South Africa, Democratic Republic of the Congo, United States, Russia, and Denmark, could be the possible origin introduced SARS-CoV-2 isolates in Bangladesh because of regional and intercontinental travel. Recent, B.1.1.7 variant could be imported from a total of 7 estimated countries including UK, India, Nigeria, Spain, Ireland, Australia, and Indonesia, while South Africa and the United States are the most likely sources of B.1351 variant in Bangladesh. Based on these findings, public health strategies could be designed and implemented to reduce the local transmission of the virus.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.444482" rel="alternate" title="Investigating the possible origin and transmission routes of SARS-CoV-2 genomes and variants of concern in Bangladesh (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445374</id><title>Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus-2 genome sequence variations relate to morbidity and mortality in Coronavirus Disease-19 (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.392767+00:00</updated><author><name>Poonam Mehta</name></author><author><name>Saumya Sarkar</name></author><author><name>Ujjala Ghoshal</name></author><author><name>Ankita Pandey</name></author><author><name>Ratender Singh</name></author><author><name>Dharamveer Singh</name></author><author><name>Rahul Vishvkarma</name></author><author><name>Uday Chand Ghoshal</name></author><author><name>Ranjeet Maurya</name></author><author><name>Rajesh Pandey</name></author><author><name>Ravishankar Ramachandran</name></author><author><name>Punyasloke Bhadury</name></author><author><name>Tapas K Kundu</name></author><author><name>Singh Rajender</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Outcome of infection with Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) may depend on the host, virus or the host-virus interaction-related factors. Complete SARS-CoV-2 genome was sequenced using Illumina and Nanopore platforms from naso-/oro-pharyngeal ribonucleic acid (RNA) specimens from COVID-19 patients of varying severity and outcomes, including patients with mild upper respiratory symptoms (n=35), severe disease ad-mitted to intensive care with respiratory and gastrointestinal symptoms (n=21), fatal COVID-19 outcome (n=17) and asymptomatic (n=42). Of a number of genome variants observed, p.16L&amp;gt;L (Nsp1), p.39C&amp;gt;C (Nsp3), p.57Q&amp;gt;H (ORF3a), p.71Y&amp;gt;Y (Membrane glycoprotein), p.194S&amp;gt;L (Nucleocapsid protein) were observed in similar frequencies in different patient subgroups. However, seventeen other variants were observed only in symptomatic patients with severe and fatal COVID-19. Out of the latter, one was in the 5’UTR (g.241C&amp;gt;T), eight were synonymous (p.14V&amp;gt;V and p.92L&amp;gt;L in Nsp1 protein, p.226D&amp;gt;D, p.253V&amp;gt;V, and p.305N&amp;gt;N in Nsp3, p.34G&amp;gt;G and p.79C&amp;gt;C in Nsp10 protein, p.789Y&amp;gt;Y in Spike protein), and eight were non-synonymous (p.106P&amp;gt;S, p.157V&amp;gt;F and p.159A&amp;gt;V in Nsp2, p.1197S&amp;gt;R and p.1198T&amp;gt;K in Nsp3, p.97A&amp;gt;V in RdRp, p.614D&amp;gt;G in Spike protein, p.13P&amp;gt;L in nucleocapsid). These were completely absent in the asymptomatic group. SARS-CoV-2 genome variations have a significant impact on COVID-19 presentation, severity and outcome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445374" rel="alternate" title="Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus-2 genome sequence variations relate to morbidity and mortality in Coronavirus Disease-19 (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445335</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 spike protein unlikely to bind to integrins via the Arg-Gly-Asp (RGD) motif of the Receptor Binding Domain: evidence from structural analysis and microscale accelerated molecular dynamics (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.393037+00:00</updated><author><name>Houcemeddine Othman</name></author><author><name>Haifa Ben Messaoud</name></author><author><name>Oussema Khamessi</name></author><author><name>Hazem Ben Mabrouk</name></author><author><name>Kais Ghedira</name></author><author><name>Avani Bharuthram</name></author><author><name>Florette Treurnicht</name></author><author><name>Ikechukwu Achilonu</name></author><author><name>Yasien Sayed</name></author><author><name>Najet Srairi-Abid</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Receptor Binding Domain (RBD) of SARS-CoV-2 virus harbors a sequence of Arg-Gly-Asp tripeptide named RGD motif, which has also been identified in extracellular matrix proteins that bind integrins as well as other disintegrins and viruses. Accordingly, integrins have been proposed as host receptors for SARS-CoV-2. The hypothesis was supported by sequence and structural analysis. However, given that the microenvironment of the RGD motif imposes structural hindrance to the protein-protein association, the validity of this hypothesis is still uncertain. Here, we used normal mode analysis, accelerated molecular dynamics microscale simulation, and protein-protein docking to investigate the putative role of RGD motif of SARS-CoV-2 RBD for interacting with integrins. We found, by molecular dynamics, that neither RGD motif nore its microenvironment show any significant conformational shift in the RBD structure. Highly populated clusters were used to run a protein-protein docking against three RGD-binding integrin types, showing no capability of the RBD domain to interact with the RGD binding site. Moreover, the free energy landscape revealed that the RGD conformation within RBD could not acquire an optimal geometry to allow the interaction with integrins. Our results highlighted different structural features of the RGD motif that may prevent its involvement in the interaction with integrins. We, therefore, suggest, in the case where integrins are confirmed to be the direct host receptors for SARS-CoV-2, a possible involvement of other residues to stabilize the interaction.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445335" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 spike protein unlikely to bind to integrins via the Arg-Gly-Asp (RGD) motif of the Receptor Binding Domain: evidence from structural analysis and microscale accelerated molecular dynamics (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.21257770</id><title>Early transfusion of convalescent plasma improves the clinical outcome in severe SARS-CoV2 infection (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.393350+00:00</updated><author><name>Eszter Fodor</name></author><author><name>Veronika Müller</name></author><author><name>Zsolt Iványi</name></author><author><name>Tímea Berki</name></author><author><name>Kuten Pella Olga</name></author><author><name>Mira Ambrus</name></author><author><name>Ágnes Sárkány</name></author><author><name>Árpád Skázel</name></author><author><name>Ágnes Madár</name></author><author><name>Dorottya Kardos</name></author><author><name>Gábor Kemenesi</name></author><author><name>Fanni Földes</name></author><author><name>Sándor Nagy</name></author><author><name>Andrea Matusovits</name></author><author><name>Nacsa János</name></author><author><name>Attila Tordai</name></author><author><name>Ferenc Jakab</name></author><author><name>Zsombor Lacza</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Plasma harvested from convalescent COVID-19 patients (CCP) has been applied as first-line therapy in the early phase of the SARS-CoV2 pandemic through clinical studies using various protocols. We present data from a cohort of 267 hospitalized, severe COVID-19 patients who received CCP. No transfusion-related complications were reported, indicating the overall safety of CCP therapy. Patients who eventually died from COVID-19 received CCP significantly later (3.95 versus 5.22 days after hospital admission) and had higher interleukin 6 (IL-6) levels (28.9 pg/ml versus 102.5 pg/ml) than those who survived. In addition, CCP-transfusion caused a significant reduction in the overall inflammatory status of the patients regardless of the severity of disease or outcome, as evidenced by decreasing C-reactive protein, IL6 and ferritin levels. We conclude that, CCP-transfusion is a safe and effective supplementary treatment modality for hospitalized COVID-19 patients characterized by better expected outcome if applied as early as possible. We also observed that, IL-6 may be a suitable laboratory parameter for patient selection and monitoring of CCP therapy effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.21257770" rel="alternate" title="Early transfusion of convalescent plasma improves the clinical outcome in severe SARS-CoV2 infection (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.26.445809</id><title>Impaired function and delayed regeneration of dendritic cells in COVID-19 (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.393639+00:00</updated><author><name>Elena Winheim</name></author><author><name>Linus Rinke</name></author><author><name>Konstantin Lutz</name></author><author><name>Anna Reischer</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Leutbecher</name></author><author><name>Lina Wolfram</name></author><author><name>Lisa Rausch</name></author><author><name>Jan Kranich</name></author><author><name>Paul R. Wratil</name></author><author><name>Johanna E. Huber</name></author><author><name>Dirk Baumjohann</name></author><author><name>Simon Rothenfußer</name></author><author><name>Johannes C. Hellmuth</name></author><author><name>Clemens Scherer</name></author><author><name>Maximilian Muenchhoff</name></author><author><name>Michael von Bergwelt-Baildon</name></author><author><name>Konstantin Stark</name></author><author><name>Tobias Straub</name></author><author><name>Thomas Brocker</name></author><author><name>Oliver T. Keppler</name></author><author><name>Marion Subklewe</name></author><author><name>Anne B. Krug</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Disease manifestations in COVID-19 range from mild to severe illness associated with a dysregulated innate immune response. Alterations in function and regeneration of dendritic cells (DC) and monocytes may contribute to immunopathology and influence adaptive immune responses in COVID-19 patients. We analyzed circulating DC and monocyte subsets in 65 hospitalized COVID-19 patients with mild/moderate or severe disease from acute disease to recovery and in healthy controls. Persisting reduction of all DC subpopulations was accompanied by an expansion of proliferating Lineage&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; HLADR&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; cells lacking DC markers. Increased frequency of the recently discovered CD163&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; CD14&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; DC3 subpopulation in patients with more severe disease was associated with systemic inflammation, activated T follicular helper cells, and antibody-secreting cells. Persistent downregulation of CD86 and upregulation of PD-L1 in conventional DC (cDC2 and DC3) and classical monocytes associated with a reduced capacity to stimulate naïve CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells correlated with disease severity. Long-lasting depletion and functional impairment of DCs and monocytes may have consequences for susceptibility to secondary infections and therapy of COVID-19 patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.26.445809" rel="alternate" title="Impaired function and delayed regeneration of dendritic cells in COVID-19 (5 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.21.21257624</id><title>Monoclonal Antibody Treatment, Prophylaxis and Vaccines Combined to Reduce SARS CoV-2 Spread (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.393957+00:00</updated><author><name>Mohamed A. Kamal</name></author><author><name>Andreas Kuznik</name></author><author><name>Luyuan Qi</name></author><author><name>Witold Więcek</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Hussein</name></author><author><name>Hazem E. Hassan</name></author><author><name>Kashyap Patel</name></author><author><name>Thomas Obadia</name></author><author><name>Masood Khaksar Toroghi</name></author><author><name>Daniela J. Conrado</name></author><author><name>Nidal Al-Huniti</name></author><author><name>Roman Casciano</name></author><author><name>Meagan P. O’Brien</name></author><author><name>Ruanne V. Barnabas</name></author><author><name>Myron S. Cohen</name></author><author><name>Patrick F. Smith</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Antiviral monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) developed for treatment of COVID-19 reduce the magnitude and duration of viral shedding and can thus potentially contribute to reducing transmission of the causative virus, severe acute respiratory coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). However, use of these mAbs in combination with a vaccine program has not been considered in public health strategic planning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We developed an agent-based model to characterize SARS-CoV-2 transmission in the US population during an aggressive phase of the pandemic (October 2020 to April 2021), and simulated the effects on infections and mortality of combining mAbs as treatment and post-exposure prophylaxis (PEP) with a vaccine program plus non-pharmaceutical interventions. We also interrogated the impact of rapid diagnostic testing, increased mAb supply, and vaccine rollout.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Allocation of mAbs as PEP or targeting those ≥65 years provided the greatest incremental benefits relative to vaccine in averting infections and deaths, by up to 17% and 41%, respectively. Rapid testing, facilitating earlier diagnosis and mAb use, amplified these benefits. The model was sensitive to mAb supply; doubling supply further reduced infections and mortality, by up to two-fold, relative to vaccine. mAbs continued to provide incremental benefits even as proportion of the vaccinated population increased.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use of anti-viral mAbs as treatment and PEP in combination with a vaccination program would substantially reduce SARS-CoV-2 transmission and pandemic burden. These results may help guide resource allocation and patient management decisions for COVID-19 and can also be used to inform public health policy for current and future pandemic preparedness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regeneron Pharmaceuticals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.21.21257624" rel="alternate" title="Monoclonal Antibody Treatment, Prophylaxis and Vaccines Combined to Reduce SARS CoV-2 Spread (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.21.21257631</id><title>Detecting COVID-19 Related Pneumonia on CT Scans using Hyperdimensional Computing (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.394200+00:00</updated><author><name>Neftali Watkinson</name></author><author><name>Tony Givargis</name></author><author><name>Victor Joe</name></author><author><name>Alexandru Nicolau</name></author><author><name>Alexander Veidenbaum</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pneumonia is a common complication associated with COVID-19 infections. Unlike common versions of pneumonia spread quickly through large lung regions, COVID-19 related pneumonia starts in small localized pockets before spreading over the course of several days. This makes the infection more resilient and with a high probability of developing acute respiratory distress syndrome. Because of the peculiar spread pattern, the use of pulmonary computerized tomography (CT) scans was key in identifying COVID-19 infections. Identifying uncommon pulmonary diseases could be a strong line of defense in early detection of new respiratory infection-causing viruses. In this paper we describe a classification algorithm based on hyperdimensional computing for the detection of COVID-19 pneumonia in CT scans. We test our algorithm using three different datasets. The highest reported accuracy is 95.2% with an F1 score of 0.90, and all three models had a precision of 1 (0 false positives).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.21.21257631" rel="alternate" title="Detecting COVID-19 Related Pneumonia on CT Scans using Hyperdimensional Computing (5 tweets)"/><category term="Health Informatics"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>