<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.636343+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.21268436</id><title>Vaccine effectiveness against hospital admission in South African health care workers who received a homologous booster of Ad26.COV2 during an Omicron COVID19 wave: Preliminary Results of the Sisonke 2 Study. (382 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.636898+00:00</updated><author><name>Glenda E Gray</name></author><author><name>Shirley COLLIE</name></author><author><name>Nigel Garrett</name></author><author><name>Ameena Goga</name></author><author><name>Jared Champion</name></author><author><name>Matt Zylstra</name></author><author><name>Tarylee Reddy</name></author><author><name>Nonhlanhla Yende</name></author><author><name>Ishen Seocharan</name></author><author><name>Azwi Takalani</name></author><author><name>Ian Sanne</name></author><author><name>Fatima Mayat</name></author><author><name>Jackline Odhiambo</name></author><author><name>Lesley Bamford</name></author><author><name>Harry Moultrie</name></author><author><name>Lara Fairall</name></author><author><name>Linda-Gail Bekker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Following the results of the ENSEMBLE 2 study, which demonstrated improved vaccine efficacy of a two-dose regimen of Ad26.COV.2 vaccine given 2 months apart, we expanded the Sisonke study which had provided single dose Ad26.COV.2 vaccine to almost 500 000 health care workers (HCW) in South Africa to include a booster dose of the Ad26.COV.2. Sisonke 2 enrolled 227 310 HCW from the 8 November to the 17 December 2021. Enrolment commenced before the onset of the Omicron driven fourth wave in South Africa affording us an opportunity to evaluate early VE in preventing hospital admissions of a homologous boost of the Ad26.COV.2 vaccine given 6-9 months after the initial vaccination in HCW.
We estimated vaccine effectiveness (VE) of the Ad26.COV2.S vaccine booster in 69 092 HCW as compared to unvaccinated individuals enrolled in the same managed care organization using a test negative design. We compared VE against COVID19 admission for omicron during the period 15 November to 20 December 2021. After adjusting for confounders, we observed that VE for hospitalisation increased over time since booster dose, from 63% (95%CI 31-81%); to 84% (95% CI 67-92%) and then 85% (95% CI: 54-95%), 0-13 days, 14-27 days, and 1-2 months post-boost.
We provide the first evidence of the effectiveness of a homologous Ad26.COV.2 vaccine boost given 6-9 months after the initial single vaccination series during a period of omicron variant circulation. This data is important given the increased reliance on the Ad26.COV.2 vaccine in Africa.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.21268436" rel="alternate" title="Vaccine effectiveness against hospital admission in South African health care workers who received a homologous booster of Ad26.COV2 during an Omicron COVID19 wave: Preliminary Results of the Sisonke 2 Study. (382 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.25.474149</id><title>Expanded ACE2 dependencies of diverse SARS-like coronavirus receptor binding domains (71 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.637405+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah M Roelle</name></author><author><name>Nidhi Shukla</name></author><author><name>Anh T Pham</name></author><author><name>Anna M Bruchez</name></author><author><name>Kenneth A Matreyek</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Viral spillover from animal reservoirs can trigger public health crises and cripple the world economy. Knowing which viruses are primed for zoonotic transmission can focus surveillance efforts and mitigation strategies for future pandemics. Successful engagement of receptor protein orthologs is necessary during cross-species transmission. The clade 1 sarbecoviruses including SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 enter cells via engagement of ACE2, while the receptor for clade 2 and clade 3 remains largely uncharacterized. We developed a mixed cell pseudotyped virus infection assay to determine whether various clade 2 and 3 sarbecovirus spike proteins can enter HEK 293T cells expressing human or Rhinolophus horseshoe bat ACE2 proteins. The receptor binding domains from BtKY72 and Khosta-2 used human ACE2 for entry, while BtKY72 and Khosta-1 exhibited widespread use of diverse rhinolophid ACE2s. A lysine at ACE2 position 31 appeared to be a major determinant of the inability of these RBDs to use a certain ACE2 sequence. The ACE2 protein from R. alcyone engaged all known clade 3 and clade 1 receptor binding domains. We observed little use of Rhinolophus ACE2 orthologs by the clade 2 viruses, supporting the likely use of a separate, unknown receptor. Our results suggest that clade 3 sarbecoviruses from Africa and Europe use Rhinolophus ACE2 for entry, and their spike proteins appear primed to contribute to zoonosis under the right conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.25.474149" rel="alternate" title="Expanded ACE2 dependencies of diverse SARS-like coronavirus receptor binding domains (71 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.21268540</id><title>Magnitude and breadth of neutralizing antibody responses elicited by SARS-CoV-2 infection or vaccination (29 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.637813+00:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin L. Sievers</name></author><author><name>Saborni Chakraborty</name></author><author><name>Yong Xue</name></author><author><name>Terri Gelbart</name></author><author><name>Joseph C. Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Arianna G. Cassidy</name></author><author><name>Yarden Golan</name></author><author><name>Mary Prahl</name></author><author><name>Stephanie L. Gaw</name></author><author><name>Prabhu S Arunachalam</name></author><author><name>Catherine A Blish</name></author><author><name>Scott D. Boyd</name></author><author><name>Mark M Davis</name></author><author><name>Prasanna Jagannathan</name></author><author><name>Kari C. Nadeau</name></author><author><name>Bali Pulendran</name></author><author><name>Upinder Singh</name></author><author><name>Richard H. Scheuermann</name></author><author><name>Matthew H. Frieman</name></author><author><name>Sanjay Vashee</name></author><author><name>Taia T. Wang</name></author><author><name>Gene S Tan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Multiple SARS-CoV-2 variants that possess mutations associated with increased transmission and antibody escape have arisen over the course of the current pandemic. While the current vaccines have largely been effective against past variants, the number of mutations found on the Omicron (B.1.529) spike appear to diminish the efficacy of pre-existing immunity. Using pseudoparticles expressing the spike of several SARS-CoV-2 variants, we evaluated the magnitude and breadth of the neutralizing antibody response over time in naturally infected and in mRNA-vaccinated individuals. We observed that while boosting increases the magnitude of the antibody response to wildtype (D614), Beta, Delta and Omicron variants, the Omicron variant was the most resistant to neutralization. We further observed that vaccinated healthy adults had robust and broad antibody responses while responses were relatively reduced in vaccinated pregnant women, underscoring the importance of learning how to maximize mRNA vaccine responses in pregnant populations. Findings from this study show substantial heterogeneity in the magnitude and breadth of responses after infection and mRNA vaccination and may support the addition of more conserved viral antigens to existing SARS-CoV-2 vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.21268540" rel="alternate" title="Magnitude and breadth of neutralizing antibody responses elicited by SARS-CoV-2 infection or vaccination (29 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.24.21268378</id><title>Preserved Omicron Spike specific antibody binding and Fc-recognition across COVID-19 vaccine platforms (23 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.638403+00:00</updated><author><name>Yannic Bartsch</name></author><author><name>Xin Tong</name></author><author><name>Jaweon Kang</name></author><author><name>María José Avendaño</name></author><author><name>Eileen F. Serrano</name></author><author><name>Tamara García-Salum</name></author><author><name>Catalina Pardo-Roa</name></author><author><name>Arnoldo Riquelme</name></author><author><name>Rafael A. Medina</name></author><author><name>Galit Alter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite the dramatic spread of Omicron globally, even among highly vaccinated populations, death rates have not increased concomitantly. These data argue that alternative immune mechanisms, beyond neutralization, may continue to confer protection against severe disease. Beyond their ability to bind and block infection, antibodies contribute to control and clearance of multiple infections via their ability to direct antiviral immunity via Fc-effector mechanisms. Thus, here we probed the ability of vaccine induced antibodies, across three COVID-19 vaccines, to drive Fc-effector activity against Omicron. Despite the significant loss of IgM, IgA and IgG binding to the Omicron Receptor Binding Domain (RBD) across BNT162b2, mRNA-1273, and CoronaVac vaccines, stable isotype binding was observed across all of these vaccines to the Omicron Spike. Compromised RBD binding IgG was accompanied by a significant loss of cross RBD-specific antibody Fcγ-receptor binding by the CoronaVac vaccine, but preservation of RBD-specific FcγR2a and Fcγ3a binding across the mRNA vaccines. Conversely, Spike-specific antibodies exhibited persistent binding to Fcγ-receptors, across all three vaccines, albeit higher binding was observed with the mRNA vaccines, marked by a selective preservation of FcγR2a and Fcγ3a binding antibodies. Thus, despite the significant to near complete loss of Omicron neutralization across several vaccine platforms against Omicron, vaccine induced Spike-specific antibodies continue to recognize the virus and recruit Fc-receptors pointing to a persistent capacity for extra-neutralizing antibodies to contribute Omicron disease attenuation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.24.21268378" rel="alternate" title="Preserved Omicron Spike specific antibody binding and Fc-recognition across COVID-19 vaccine platforms (23 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.21268538</id><title>Protective effect of BNT162b2 vaccination on aerobic capacity following mild to moderate SARS-CoV-2 infection: a cross sectional study, Israel, March-December 2021 (15 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.638725+00:00</updated><author><name>Yair Blumberg</name></author><author><name>Michael Edelstein</name></author><author><name>Kamal Abu Jabal</name></author><author><name>Ron Golan</name></author><author><name>Yuval Perets</name></author><author><name>Musa Saad</name></author><author><name>Tatyana Levinas</name></author><author><name>Saleem Dabbah</name></author><author><name>Zeev Israeli</name></author><author><name>Salah Yacoubi</name></author><author><name>Alaa Abu Raya</name></author><author><name>Anat Amital</name></author><author><name>Majdi Halabi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;There is increasing evidence that patients who were infected with SARS-CoV-2 may experience adverse health outcomes months after the acute infection has resolved including reduction in aerobic capacity and fatigue. In this study, we compared aerobic capacity and exercise performance of 28 unvaccinated participants to 15 vaccinated ones who performed a symptom limited cardio-pulmonary exercise test (CPET) after acute COVID-19. We identified a significant difference in aerobic capacity between vaccinated and unvaccinated individuals, with a lower V'O2 peak percentage of predicted in the unvaccinated group. In addition, the unvaccinated group had a reduction in the peak-exercise heart rate and lower ventilation values. Our results suggest objective limitations to exercise capacity in the months following acute COVID19 illness, mitigated by vaccination&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.21268538" rel="alternate" title="Protective effect of BNT162b2 vaccination on aerobic capacity following mild to moderate SARS-CoV-2 infection: a cross sectional study, Israel, March-December 2021 (15 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.31.21268575</id><title>COVID-19 severity prediction based on patient risk factors and number of vaccines received (12 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.638994+00:00</updated><author><name>Ariel Israel</name></author><author><name>Alejandro A. Schäffer</name></author><author><name>Eugene Merzon</name></author><author><name>Ilan Green</name></author><author><name>Eli Magen</name></author><author><name>Avivit Golan-Cohen</name></author><author><name>Shlomo Vinker</name></author><author><name>Eytan Ruppin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background
Vaccines are highly effective in preventing severe disease and death from COVID-19, and new medications that can reduce severity of disease have been approved. However, many countries are facing limited supply of vaccine doses and medications. A model estimating the probabilities for hospitalization and mortality according to individual risk factors and vaccine doses received could help prioritize vaccination and yet scarce medications to maximize lives saved and reduce the burden on hospitalization facilities.
Methods
Electronic health records from 101,034 individuals infected with SARS-CoV-2, since the beginning of the pandemic and until November 30, 2021 were extracted from a national healthcare organization in Israel. Logistic regression models were built to estimate the risk for subsequent hospitalization and death based on the number of BNT162b2 mRNA vaccine doses received and few major risk factors (age, sex, body mass index, hemoglobin A1C, kidney function, and presence of hypertension, pulmonary disease or malignancy).
Results
The models built predict the outcome of newly infected individuals with remarkable accuracy: area under the curve was 0.889 for predicting hospitalization, and 0.967 for predicting mortality. Even when a breakthrough infection occurs, having received three vaccination doses significantly reduces the risk of hospitalization by 66% (OR=0.336) and of death by 78% (OR=0.220).
Conclusions
The models enable rapid identification of individuals at high risk for hospitalization and death when infected. These patients can be prioritized to receive booster vaccination and the yet scarce medications. A calculator based on these models is made publicly available on http://covidest.web.app&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.31.21268575" rel="alternate" title="COVID-19 severity prediction based on patient risk factors and number of vaccines received (12 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.26.474085</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 Omicron-B.1.1.529 Variant leads to less severe disease than Pango B and Delta variants strains in a mouse model of severe COVID-19 (12 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.639214+00:00</updated><author><name>Eleanor G Bentley</name></author><author><name>Adam Kirby</name></author><author><name>Parul Sharma</name></author><author><name>Anja Kipar</name></author><author><name>Daniele F Mega</name></author><author><name>Chloe Bramwell</name></author><author><name>Rebekah Penrice-Randal</name></author><author><name>Tessa Prince</name></author><author><name>Jonathan C Brown</name></author><author><name>Jie Zhou</name></author><author><name>Gavin R Screaton</name></author><author><name>Wendy S Barclay</name></author><author><name>Andrew Owen</name></author><author><name>Julian Alexander Hiscox</name></author><author><name>James P Stewart</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 is a spectrum of clinical symptoms in humans caused by infection with SARS-CoV-2. The B.1.1.529 Omicron variant is rapidly emerging and has been designated a Variant of Concern (VOC). The variant is highly transmissible and partially or fully evades a spectrum of neutralising antibodies due to a high number of substitutions in the spike glycoprotein. A major question is the relative severity of disease caused by the Omicron variant compared with previous and currently circulating variants of SARS-CoV-2. To address this, a mouse model of infection that recapitulates severe disease in humans, K18-hACE2 mice, were infected with either a Pango B, Delta or Omicron variant of SARS-CoV-2 and their relative pathogenesis compared. In contrast to mice infected with Pango B and Delta variant viruses, those infected with the Omicron variant had less severe clinical signs (weight loss), showed recovery and had a lower virus load in both the lower and upper respiratory tract. This is also reflected by less extensive inflammatory processes in the lungs. Although T cell epitopes may be conserved, the antigenic diversity of Omicron from previous variants would suggest that a change in vaccine may be required to mitigate against the higher transmissibility and global disease burden. However, the lead time to develop such a response may be too late to mitigate the spread and effects of Omicron. These animal model data suggest the clinical consequences of infection with the Omicron variant may be less severe but the higher transmissibility could still place huge burden upon healthcare systems even if a lower proportion of infected patients are hospitalised.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.26.474085" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 Omicron-B.1.1.529 Variant leads to less severe disease than Pango B and Delta variants strains in a mouse model of severe COVID-19 (12 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.24.474110</id><title>Reduced infectivity but increased immune escape of the new SARS-CoV-2 variant of concern Omicron (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.639498+00:00</updated><author><name>Jie Hu</name></author><author><name>Pai Peng</name></author><author><name>Kang Wu</name></author><author><name>Quan-xin Long</name></author><author><name>Juan Chen</name></author><author><name>Kai Wang</name></author><author><name>Ni Tang</name></author><author><name>Ai-long Huang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A new detected SARS-CoV-2 variant Omicron (B.1.1.529) had reported from more than 80 countries. In the past few weeks, a new wave of infection driven by Omicron is in progress. Omicron Spike (S) protein pseudotyped virus was used to determine the effect of S mutations on its capacity of infectivity and immune evasion. Our results showed the lower entry efficiency and less cleavage ability of Omicron than D614G variant. Pseudotype-based neutralizing assay was performed to analyze neutralizing antibodies elicited by previously infection or the RBD-based protein subunit vaccine ZF2001 against the Omicron variant. Sera sampled at around one month after symptom onset from 12 convalescents who were previously infected by SARS-CoV-2 original strain shows a more than 20-fold decrease of neutralizing activity against Omicron variant, when compared to D614G variant. Among 12 individuals vaccinated by RBD subunit vaccine, 58.3% (7/12) sera sampled at 15-60 days after 3rd-dose vaccination did not neutralize Omicron. Geometric mean titers (GMTs, 50% inhibitory dose [ID50]) of these sera against Omicron were 9.4-fold lower than against D614G. These results suggested a higher risk of Omicron breakthrough infections and reduced efficiency of the protective immunity elicited by existing vaccines. There are important implications about the modification and optimization of the current epidemic prevention and control including vaccine strategies and therapeutic antibodies against Omicron variant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.24.474110" rel="alternate" title="Reduced infectivity but increased immune escape of the new SARS-CoV-2 variant of concern Omicron (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.24.474138</id><title>Homologous or Heterologous Booster of Inactivated Vaccine Reduces SARS-CoV-2 Omicron Variant Escape from Neutralizing Antibodies (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.639775+00:00</updated><author><name>Xun Wang</name></author><author><name>Xiaoyu Zhao</name></author><author><name>Jieyu Song</name></author><author><name>Jing Wu</name></author><author><name>Yuqi Zhu</name></author><author><name>Minghui Li</name></author><author><name>Yuchen Cui</name></author><author><name>Yanjia Chen</name></author><author><name>Lulu Yang</name></author><author><name>Jun Liu</name></author><author><name>Huanzhang Zhu</name></author><author><name>Shibo Jiang</name></author><author><name>Pengfei Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The massive and rapid transmission of SARS-CoV-2 has led to the emergence of several viral variants of concern (VOCs), with the most recent one, B.1.1.529 (Omicron), which accumulated a large number of spike mutations, raising the specter that this newly identified variant may escape from the currently available vaccines and therapeutic antibodies. Using VSV-based pseudovirus, we found that Omicron variant is markedly resistant to neutralization of sera form convalescents or individuals vaccinated by two doses of inactivated whole-virion vaccines (BBIBP-CorV). However, a homologous inactivated vaccine booster or a heterologous booster with protein subunit vaccine (ZF2001) significantly increased neutralization titers to both WT and Omicron variant. Moreover, at day 14 post the third dose, neutralizing antibody titer reduction for Omicron was less than that for convalescents or individuals who had only two doses of the vaccine, indicating that a homologous or heterologous booster can reduce the Omicron escape from neutralizing. In addition, we tested a panel of 17 SARS-CoV-2 monoclonal antibodies (mAbs). Omicron resists 7 of 8 authorized/approved mAbs, as well as most of the other mAbs targeting distinct epitopes on RBD and NTD. Taken together, our results suggest the urgency to push forward the booster vaccination to combat the emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.24.474138" rel="alternate" title="Homologous or Heterologous Booster of Inactivated Vaccine Reduces SARS-CoV-2 Omicron Variant Escape from Neutralizing Antibodies (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.21268244</id><title>Effectiveness of casirivimab and imdevimab, and sotrovimab during Delta variant surge: a prospective cohort study and comparative effectiveness randomized trial (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.640030+00:00</updated><author><name>David T. Huang</name></author><author><name>Erin K. McCreary</name></author><author><name>J. Ryan Bariola</name></author><author><name>Tami E. Minnier</name></author><author><name>Richard J. Wadas</name></author><author><name>Judith A. Shovel</name></author><author><name>Debbie Albin</name></author><author><name>Oscar C. Marroquin</name></author><author><name>Kevin E. Kip</name></author><author><name>Kevin Collins</name></author><author><name>Mark Schmidhofer</name></author><author><name>Mary Kay Wisniewski</name></author><author><name>David A. Nace</name></author><author><name>Colleen Sullivan</name></author><author><name>Meredith Axe</name></author><author><name>Russell Meyers</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Weissman</name></author><author><name>William Garrard</name></author><author><name>Octavia M. Peck-Palmer</name></author><author><name>Alan Wells</name></author><author><name>Robert D. Bart</name></author><author><name>Anne Yang</name></author><author><name>Lindsay R. Berry</name></author><author><name>Scott Berry</name></author><author><name>Amy M. Crawford</name></author><author><name>Anna McGlothlin</name></author><author><name>Tina Khadem</name></author><author><name>Kelsey Linstrum</name></author><author><name>Stephanie K. Montgomery</name></author><author><name>Daniel Ricketts</name></author><author><name>Jason N. Kennedy</name></author><author><name>Caroline J. Pidro</name></author><author><name>Rachel L. Zapf</name></author><author><name>Paula L. Kip</name></author><author><name>Ghady Haidar</name></author><author><name>Graham M. Snyder</name></author><author><name>Bryan J. McVerry</name></author><author><name>Donald M. Yealy</name></author><author><name>Derek C. Angus</name></author><author><name>Christopher W. Seymour</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The effectiveness of monoclonal antibodies (mAbs), casirivimab and imdevimab, and sotrovimab, for patients with mild to moderate COVID-19 from the Delta variant is unknown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;OBJECTIVE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To evaluate the effectiveness of mAbs for the Delta variant compared to no treatment, and the comparative effectiveness between mAbs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;DESIGN, SETTING, AND PARTICIPANTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two parallel studies among patients who met Emergency Use Authorization criteria for mAbs from July 14, 2021 to September 29, 2021: i.) prospective observational cohort study comparing mAb treatment to no mAb treatment and, ii.) Bayesian adaptive randomized trial comparing the effectiveness of casirivimab-imdevimab versus sotrovimab. In the observational study, we compared eligible patients who received mAb at an outpatient infusion center at UPMC, to nontreated patients with a positive SARS-CoV-2 test. In the comparative effectiveness trial, we randomly allocated casirivimab-imdevimab or sotrovimab to patients presenting to infusion centers and emergency departments, per system therapeutic interchange policy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;EXPOSURE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Intravenous mAb per their EUA criteria.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;MAIN OUTCOMES AND MEASURES&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the observational study, risk ratio estimates for hospitalization or death by 28 days were compared between mAb treatment to no mAb treatment using propensity matched models. For the comparative effectiveness trial, the primary outcome was hospital-free days (days alive and free of hospital) within 28 days, where patients who died were assigned -1 day) in a Bayesian cumulative logistic model, adjusted for treatment location, age, sex, and time. Inferiority was defined as a 99% posterior probability of an odds ratio &amp;lt;1. Equivalence was defined as a 95% posterior probability that the odds ratio is within a given bound.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;RESULTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among 3,558 patients receiving mAb, the mean age was 54 (SD 18 years), 1,511 (43%) were treated in an infusion center, and 450 (13%) were hospitalized or died by day 28. In propensity matched models, mAb treatment was associated with reduced risk of hospitalization or death compared to no treatment (risk ratio (RR)=0.40, 95% CI: 0.28–0.57). Both casirivimab and imdevimab (RR=0.31, 95% CI: 0.20–0.50), and sotrovimab (RR=0.60, 95% CI: 0.37–1.00) reduced hospitalization or death compared to no mAb treatment. Among patients allocated randomly to casirivimab and imdevimab (n=2,454) or sotrovimab (n=1,104), the median hospital-free days were 28 (IQR 28–28) for both groups, 28-day mortality was 0.5% (n=12) and 0.6% (n=7), and hospitalization by day 28 was 12% (n=291) and 12% (n=140), respectively. Compared to casirivimab and imdevimab, the median adjusted odds ratio for hospital-free days was 0.88 (95% credible interval, 0.70–1.11) for sotrovimab. This odds ratio yielded 86% probability of inferiority of sotrovimab versus casirivimab and imdevimab, and 79% probability of equivalence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;CONCLUSIONS AND RELEVANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In non-hospitalized patients with mild to moderate COVID-19 due to the Delta variant, casirivimab and imdevimab and sotrovimab were both associated with a reduced risk of hospitalization or death. The comparative effectiveness of mAbs appeared similar, though prespecified criteria for statistical inferiority or equivalence were not met.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;TRIAL REGISTRATION&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov"&gt;ClinicalTrials.gov&lt;/ext-link&gt;: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT04790786"&gt;NCT04790786&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key Points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Question&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In non-hospitalized patients with mild to moderate COVID-19 due to the Delta variant, what is the effectiveness of monoclonal antibodies (mAb) compared to no treatment, and what is the comparative effectiveness between mAb?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among 3,069 patients, mAb treatment (casirivimab and imdevimab or sotrovimab) was associated with reduced risk of hospitalization or death by 28 days compared to no treatment (risk ratio=0.40, 95% CI: 0.28–0.57). In a Bayesian randomized comparative effectiveness trial of casirivimab and imdevimab vs. sotrovimab in 3,558 patients, the median hospital–free days were 28 days for both groups. Compared to casirivimab-imdevimab, the median adjusted odds ratio for hospital-free days was 0.88 (95% credible interval, 0.70–1.11) for sotrovimab, an 86% probability of inferiority of sotrovimab versus casirivimab and imdevimab, and 79% probability of equivalence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Meaning&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In non-hospitalized patients with mild to moderate COVID-19 due to the Delta variant, casirivimab and imdevimab and sotrovimab were associated with reduced risk of hospitalization or death compared to no treatment. The comparative effectiveness of mAbs appeared similar, though prespecified criteria for statistical inferiority or equivalence were not met.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.21268244" rel="alternate" title="Effectiveness of casirivimab and imdevimab, and sotrovimab during Delta variant surge: a prospective cohort study and comparative effectiveness randomized trial (7 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.21268505</id><title>Head-to-head comparison of nasal and nasopharyngeal sampling using SARS-CoV-2 rapid antigen testing in Lesotho (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.640529+00:00</updated><author><name>Niklaus Daniel Labhardt</name></author><author><name>Lucia Gonzalez Fernandez</name></author><author><name>Bulemba Katende</name></author><author><name>Josephine Muhairwe</name></author><author><name>Moniek Bresser</name></author><author><name>Alain Amstutz</name></author><author><name>Tracy R Glass</name></author><author><name>Morten Ruhwald</name></author><author><name>Jilian A Sacks</name></author><author><name>Camille Escadafal</name></author><author><name>Mathabo Mareka</name></author><author><name>Mooko Sekhele Mookho</name></author><author><name>Margaretha Daniel de Vos</name></author><author><name>Klaus Reither</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Objectives
To assess the real-world diagnostic performance of nasal and nasopharyngeal swabs for SD Biosensor STANDARD Q COVID-19 Antigen Rapid Diagnostic Test (Ag-RDT).
Methods
Individuals ≥5 years with COVID-19 compatible symptoms or history of exposure to SARS-CoV-2 presenting at hospitals in Lesotho received two nasopharyngeal and one nasal swab. Ag-RDT from nasal and nasopharyngeal swabs were performed as point-of-care on site, the second nasopharyngeal swab used for polymerase chain reaction (PCR) as the reference standard. 
Results 
Out of 2198 participants enrolled, 2131 had a valid PCR result (61% female, median age 41 years, 8% children), 84.5% were symptomatic. Overall PCR positivity rate was 5.8%. The sensitivity for nasopharyngeal, nasal, and combined nasal and nasopharyngeal Ag-RDT result was 70.2% (95%CI: 61.3-78.0), 67.3% (57.3-76.3) and 74.4% (65.5-82.0), respectively. The respective specificity was 97.9% (97.1-98.4), 97.9% (97.2-98.5) and 97.5% (96.7-98.2). For both sampling modalities, sensitivity was higher in participants with symptom duration ≤ 3days versus ≤ 7days. Agreement between nasal and nasopharyngeal Ag-RDT was 99.4%.
Conclusions
The STANDARD Q Ag-RDT showed high specificity. Sensitivity was, however, below the WHO recommended minimum requirement of ≥ 80%. The high agreement between nasal and nasopharyngeal sampling suggests that for Ag-RDT nasal sampling is a good alternative to nasopharyngeal sampling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.21268505" rel="alternate" title="Head-to-head comparison of nasal and nasopharyngeal sampling using SARS-CoV-2 rapid antigen testing in Lesotho (6 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.25.21268206</id><title>Topological data analysis identifies distinct biomarker phenotypes during the inflammatory phase of COVID-19 (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.641168+00:00</updated><author><name>Paul W Blair</name></author><author><name>Joost Brandsma</name></author><author><name>Josh G. Chenoweth</name></author><author><name>Stephanie A. Richard</name></author><author><name>Nusrat J. Epsi</name></author><author><name>Rittal Mehta</name></author><author><name>Deborah A. Striegel</name></author><author><name>Emily G. Clemens</name></author><author><name>David A. Lindholm</name></author><author><name>Ryan C. Maves</name></author><author><name>Derek T. Larson</name></author><author><name>Katrin Mende</name></author><author><name>Rhonda E. Colombo</name></author><author><name>Anuradha Ganesan</name></author><author><name>Tahaniyat Lalani</name></author><author><name>Christopher J. Colombo</name></author><author><name>Allison A. Malloy</name></author><author><name>Andrew L. Snow</name></author><author><name>Kevin L. Schully</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Lanteri</name></author><author><name>Mark P. Simons</name></author><author><name>John S. Dumler</name></author><author><name>David Tribble</name></author><author><name>Timothy Burgess</name></author><author><name>Simon Pollett</name></author><author><name>Brian K. Agan</name></author><author><name>Danielle V. Clark</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;OBJECTIVES: The relationships between baseline clinical phenotypes and the cytokine milieu of the peak inflammatory phase of coronavirus 2019 (COVID-19) are not yet well understood. We used Topological Data Analysis (TDA), a dimensionality reduction technique to identify patterns of inflammation associated with COVID-19 severity and clinical characteristics.
DESIGN: Exploratory analysis from a multi-center prospective cohort study.
SETTING: Eight military hospitals across the United States between April 2020 and January 2021.
PATIENTS: Adult (≥18 years of age) SARS-CoV-2 positive inpatient and outpatient participants were enrolled with plasma samples selected from the putative inflammatory phase of COVID-19, defined as 15-28 days post symptom onset. 
INTERVENTIONS: None.
MEASUREMENTS AND MAIN RESULTS: Concentrations of 12 inflammatory protein biomarkers were measured using a broad dynamic range immunoassay. TDA identified 3 distinct inflammatory protein expression clusters. Peak severity (outpatient, hospitalized, ICU admission or death), Charlson Comorbidity Index (CCI), and body mass index (BMI) were evaluated with logistic regression for associations with each cluster. The study population (n=129, 33.3% female, median 41.3 years of age) included 77 outpatient, 31 inpatient, 16 ICU-level, and 5 fatal cases. Three distinct clusters were found that differed by peak disease severity (p &amp;lt;0.001), age (p &amp;lt;0.001), BMI (p&amp;lt;0.001), and CCI (p=0.001). 
CONCLUSIONS: Exploratory clustering methods can stratify heterogeneous patient populations and identify distinct inflammation patterns associated with comorbid disease, obesity, and severe illness due to COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.25.21268206" rel="alternate" title="Topological data analysis identifies distinct biomarker phenotypes during the inflammatory phase of COVID-19 (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.21268553</id><title>Performance of COVIDSeq and Swift normalase amplicon SARS-CoV-2 panels for SARS-CoV-2 Genomes Sequencing: Practical Guide and Combining FASTQ Strategy (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.641653+00:00</updated><author><name>Hosoon Choi</name></author><author><name>Munok Hwang</name></author><author><name>Dhammika Navarathna</name></author><author><name>Jing Xu</name></author><author><name>Janell Lukey</name></author><author><name>Chetan Jinadatha</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The whole genomic sequencing (WGS) of SARS-CoV-2 has been performed extensively and is playing a crucial role in fighting against COVID-19 pandemic. Obtaining sufficient WGS data from clinical samples is often challenging especially from the samples with low viral load. We evaluated two SARS-CoV-2 sequencing protocols for their efficiency/accuracy and limitations. Sequence coverage of &amp;gt;95% was obtained by Swift normalase amplicon SARS-CoV-2 panels (SNAP) protocol for all the samples with Ct ≤ 35 and by COVIDSeq protocol for 97% of samples with Ct ≤ 30. Sample RNA quantitation obtained using digital PCR provided more precise cutoff values. The quantitative digital PCR cutoff values for obtaining 95% coverage are 10.5 copies/μL for SNAP protocol and 147 copies/μL for COVIDSeq protocol. Combining FASTQ files obtained from 2 protocols improved the outcome of sequence analysis by compensating for missing amplicon regions. This process resulted in an increase of sequencing coverage and lineage call precision.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.21268553" rel="alternate" title="Performance of COVIDSeq and Swift normalase amplicon SARS-CoV-2 panels for SARS-CoV-2 Genomes Sequencing: Practical Guide and Combining FASTQ Strategy (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>