<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.644670+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460111</id><title>Therapeutic efficacy of an oral nucleoside analog of remdesivir against SARS-CoV-2 pathogenesis in mice. (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.645911+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexandra Schafer</name></author><author><name>David R Martinez</name></author><author><name>John J Won</name></author><author><name>Fernanado R Moreira</name></author><author><name>Ariane J Brown</name></author><author><name>Kendra L Gully</name></author><author><name>Rao Kalla</name></author><author><name>Kwon Chun</name></author><author><name>Venice Du Pont</name></author><author><name>Darius Babusis</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Tang</name></author><author><name>Eisuke Murakami</name></author><author><name>Raju Subramanian</name></author><author><name>Kimberly T Barrett</name></author><author><name>Blake J. Bleier</name></author><author><name>Roy Bannister</name></author><author><name>Joy Y. Feng</name></author><author><name>John P. Bilello</name></author><author><name>Tomas Cihlar</name></author><author><name>Richard L. Mackman</name></author><author><name>Stephanie A. Montgomery</name></author><author><name>Ralph S. Baric</name></author><author><name>Timothy P. Sheahan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic remains uncontrolled despite the rapid rollout of safe and effective SARS-CoV-2 vaccines, underscoring the need to develop highly effective antivirals. In the setting of waning immunity from infection and vaccination, breakthrough infections are becoming increasingly common and treatment options remain limited. Additionally, the emergence of SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern with their potential to escape therapeutic monoclonal antibodies emphasizes the need to develop second-generation oral antivirals targeting highly conserved viral proteins that can be rapidly deployed to outpatients. Here, we demonstrate the in vitro antiviral activity and in vivo therapeutic efficacy of GS-621763, an orally bioavailable prodrug of GS-441524, the parental nucleoside of remdesivir, which targets the highly conserved RNA-dependent RNA polymerase. GS-621763 exhibited significant antiviral activity in lung cell lines and two different human primary lung cell culture systems. The dose-proportional pharmacokinetic profile observed after oral administration of GS-621763 translated to dose-dependent antiviral activity in mice infected with SARS-CoV-2. Therapeutic GS-621763 significantly reduced viral load, lung pathology, and improved pulmonary function in COVID-19 mouse model. A direct comparison of GS-621763 with molnupiravir, an oral nucleoside analog antiviral currently in human clinical trial, proved both drugs to be similarly efficacious. These data demonstrate that therapy with oral prodrugs of remdesivir can significantly improve outcomes in SARS-CoV-2 infected mice. Thus, GS-621763 supports the exploration of GS-441524 oral prodrugs for the treatment of COVID-19 in humans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460111" rel="alternate" title="Therapeutic efficacy of an oral nucleoside analog of remdesivir against SARS-CoV-2 pathogenesis in mice. (37 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.21263331</id><title>Second wave of the Covid-19 pandemic in Delhi, India: high seroprevalence not a deterrent? (34 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.651068+00:00</updated><author><name>Nandini Sharma</name></author><author><name>Pragya Sharma</name></author><author><name>Saurav Basu</name></author><author><name>Ritika Bakshi</name></author><author><name>Ekta Gupta</name></author><author><name>Reshu Agarwal</name></author><author><name>Kumar Dushyant</name></author><author><name>Nutan Mundeja</name></author><author><name>Zeasley Marak</name></author><author><name>Sanjay Singh</name></author><author><name>Gautam Kumar Singh</name></author><author><name>Ruchir Rustagi</name></author><author><name>S K Sarin</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We report the findings of a large follow-up community-based serosurvey and correlating it with the COVID-19 test-positivity rate and the case load observed during the peak of the second wave of the Covid-19 pandemic in Delhi, India.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individuals of age ≥5 years were recruited from 274 wards of the state (population ∼ 19.6 million) during January 11 to January 22’ 2021. A total of 100 participants each were included from all the wards for a net sample size of ∼28,000. A multi-stage sampling technique was applied for selection of participants for the household serosurvey. Anti SARS CoV-2 IgG antibodies were detected by using the VITROS assay (90% Sn, 100% Sp).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Antibody positivity was observed in 14,298 (50.76%) of the 28,169 samples. The age, sex and district population weighted seroprevalence of the IgG SARS-CoV-2 was 50.52% (95% C.I. 49.94-51.10) and after adjustment for assay characteristics was 56.13% (95% C.I. 55.49-56.77). On adjusted analysis, participants aged ≥50 years, of female gender, housewives, having ever lived in containment zones, urban slum dwellers, and diabetes or hypertensive patients had significantly higher odds of SARS-CoV-2 antibody positivity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The peak infection rate and the test positivity rate since October 2020 were initially observed in mid-November 2020 with a subsequent steep declining trend, followed by a period of persistently low case burden lasting until the first week of March 2021. This was followed by a steady increase followed by an exponential surge in infections from April 2021 onwards culminating in the second wave of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The presence of infection induced immunity from SARS-CoV-2 even in more than one in two people can be ineffective in protecting the population.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.21263331" rel="alternate" title="Second wave of the Covid-19 pandemic in Delhi, India: high seroprevalence not a deterrent? (34 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460408</id><title>Synthetic lethality-based prediction of anti-SARS-CoV-2 targets (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.653452+00:00</updated><author><name>Lipika R. Pal</name></author><author><name>Kuoyuan Cheng</name></author><author><name>Nishanth Ulhas Nair</name></author><author><name>Laura Martin-Sancho</name></author><author><name>Sanju Sinha</name></author><author><name>Yuan Pu</name></author><author><name>Laura Riva</name></author><author><name>Xin Yin</name></author><author><name>Fiorella Schischlik</name></author><author><name>Joo Sang Lee</name></author><author><name>Sumit K. Chanda</name></author><author><name>Eytan Ruppin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Novel strategies are needed to identify drug targets and treatments for the COVID-19 pandemic. The altered gene expression of virus-infected host cells provides an opportunity to specifically inhibit viral propagation via targeting the synthetic lethal (SL) partners of such altered host genes. Pursuing this antiviral strategy, here we comprehensively analyzed multiple &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; bulk and single-cell RNA-sequencing datasets of SARS-CoV-2 infection to predict clinically relevant candidate antiviral targets that are SL with altered host genes. The predicted SL-based targets are highly enriched for infected cell inhibiting genes reported in four SARS-CoV-2 CRISPR-Cas9 genome-wide genetic screens. Integrating our predictions with the results of these screens, we further selected a focused subset of 26 genes that we experimentally tested in a targeted siRNA screen using human Caco-2 cells. Notably, as predicted, knocking down these targets reduced viral replication and cell viability only under the infected condition without harming non-infected cells. Our results are made publicly available, to facilitate their in vivo testing and further validation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460408" rel="alternate" title="Synthetic lethality-based prediction of anti-SARS-CoV-2 targets (15 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460076</id><title>Elicitation of potent SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibody responses through immunization using a versatile adenovirus-inspired multimerization platform (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.658157+00:00</updated><author><name>C Chevillard</name></author><author><name>A Amen</name></author><author><name>S Besson</name></author><author><name>D Hannani</name></author><author><name>I Bally</name></author><author><name>V Dettling</name></author><author><name>E Gout</name></author><author><name>CJ Moreau</name></author><author><name>M Buisson</name></author><author><name>S Gallet</name></author><author><name>D Fenel</name></author><author><name>E Vassal-Stermann</name></author><author><name>G Schoehn</name></author><author><name>P Poignard</name></author><author><name>MC Dagher</name></author><author><name>P Fender</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) pandemic has shown that vaccine preparedness is critical to anticipate a fast response to emergent pathogens with high infectivity. To rapidly reach herd immunity, an affordable, easy to store and versatile vaccine platform is thus desirable. We previously designed a non-infectious adenovirus-inspired nanoparticle (ADDomer), and in the present work, we efficiently decorated this original vaccine platform with glycosylated receptor binding domain (RBD) of SARS-CoV-2. Cryo-Electron Microscopy structure revealed that up to 60 copies of this antigenic domain were bound on a single ADDomer particle with the symmetrical arrangements of a dodecahedron. Mouse immunization with the RBD decorated particles showed as early as the first immunization a significant anti-coronavirus humoral response, which was boosted after a second immunization. Neutralization assays with spike pseudo-typed-virus demonstrated the elicitation of strong neutralization titers. Remarkably, the existence of pre-existing immunity against adenoviral-derived particles enhanced the humoral response against SARS-CoV-2. This plug and play vaccine platform revisits the way of using adenovirus to combat emergent pathogens while potentially taking advantage of the adenovirus pre-immunity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460076" rel="alternate" title="Elicitation of potent SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibody responses through immunization using a versatile adenovirus-inspired multimerization platform (12 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460211</id><title>Mitoxantrone dihydrochloride, an FDA approved drug, binds with SARS-CoV-2 NSP1 C-terminal (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.658734+00:00</updated><author><name>Prateek Kumar</name></author><author><name>Taniya Bhardwaj</name></author><author><name>Rajanish Giri</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;One of the major virulence factors of SARS-CoV-2, NSP1, is a vital drug target due to its role in host immune evasion through multiple pathways. NSP1 protein is associated with inhibiting host mRNA translation by binding to the small subunit of ribosome through its C-terminal region. Previously, we have shown the structural dynamics of NSP1 C-terminal region (NSP1-CTR) in different physiological environments. So, it would be very interesting to investigate the druggable compounds that could bind with NSP1-CTR. Here, in this article, we have performed the different spectroscopic technique-based binding assays of an anticancer drug Mitoxantrone dihydrochloride (MTX) against the NSP1-CTR. We have also performed molecular docking followed by computational simulations with two different forcefields up to one microsecond. Overall, our results have suggested good binding between NSP1-CTR and MTX and may have implications in developing therapeutic strategies targeting NSP1 protein of SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460211" rel="alternate" title="Mitoxantrone dihydrochloride, an FDA approved drug, binds with SARS-CoV-2 NSP1 C-terminal (11 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.15.459215</id><title>Signatures of adaptive evolution during human to mink SARS CoV2 cross-species transmission inform estimates of the COVID19 pandemic timing (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.666266+00:00</updated><author><name>Jui-Hung Tai</name></author><author><name>Shu-Miaw Chaw</name></author><author><name>Hsiao-Yu Sun</name></author><author><name>Yi-Cheng Tseng</name></author><author><name>Guanghao Li</name></author><author><name>Sui-Yuan Chang</name></author><author><name>Shiou-Hwei Yeh</name></author><author><name>Pei-Jer Chen</name></author><author><name>Hurng-Yi Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;One of the unique features of SARS-CoV-2 is that it mainly evolved neutrally or under purifying selection during the early pandemic. This contrasts with the preceding epidemics of the closely related SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV, both of which evolved adaptively. It is possible that the SARS-CoV-2 exhibits a unique or adaptive feature which deviates from other coronaviruses. Alternatively, the virus may have been cryptically circulating in humans for a sufficient time to have acquired adaptive changes for efficient transmission before the onset of the current pandemic. In order to test the above scenarios, we analyzed the SARS-CoV-2 sequences from minks (&lt;italic&gt;Neovision vision&lt;/italic&gt;) and parenteral human strains. In the early phase of the mink epidemic (April to May 2020), nonsynonymous to synonymous mutation ratios per site within the spike protein was 2.93, indicating a selection process favoring adaptive amino acid changes. In addition, mutations within this protein concentrated within its receptor binding domain and receptor binding motif. Positive selection also left a trace on linked neutral variation. An excess of high frequency derived variants produced by genetic hitchhiking was found during middle (June to July 2020) and early late (August to September 2020) phases of the mink epidemic, but quickly diminished in October and November 2020. Strong positive selection found in SARS-CoV-2 from minks implies that the virus may be not unique in super-adapting to a wide range of new hosts. The mink study suggests that SARS-CoV-2 already went through adaptive evolution in humans, and likely been circulating in humans at least six months before the first case found in Wuhan, China. We also discuss circumstances under which the virus can be well-adapted to its host but fail to induce an outbreak.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.15.459215" rel="alternate" title="Signatures of adaptive evolution during human to mink SARS CoV2 cross-species transmission inform estimates of the COVID19 pandemic timing (9 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.21263026</id><title>The clinically extremely vulnerable to COVID: Identification and changes in healthcare while self-isolating (shielding) during the coronavirus pandemic (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.666929+00:00</updated><author><name>Jessica E. Butler</name></author><author><name>Mintu Nath</name></author><author><name>Dimitra Blana</name></author><author><name>William P. Ball</name></author><author><name>Nicola Beech</name></author><author><name>Corri Black</name></author><author><name>Graham Osler</name></author><author><name>Sebastien Peytrignet</name></author><author><name>Katie Wilde</name></author><author><name>Artur Wozniak</name></author><author><name>Simon Sawhney</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In March 2020, the government of Scotland identified people deemed clinically extremely vulnerable to COVID due to their pre-existing health conditions. These people were advised to strictly self-isolate (shield) at the start of the pandemic, except for necessary healthcare. We examined who was identified as clinically extremely vulnerable, how their healthcare changed during isolation, and whether this process exacerbated healthcare inequalities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We linked those on the shielding register in NHS Grampian, a health authority in Scotland, to healthcare records from 2015-2020. We described the source of identification, demographics, and clinical history of the cohort. We measured changes in out-patient, in-patient, and emergency healthcare during isolation in the shielding population and compared to the general non-shielding population.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The register included 16,092 people (3% of the population), clinically vulnerable primarily due to a respiratory disease, immunosuppression, or cancer. Among them, 42% were not identified by national healthcare record screening but added &lt;italic&gt;ad hoc&lt;/italic&gt;, with these additions including more children and fewer economically-deprived.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During isolation, all forms of healthcare use decreased (25%-46%), with larger decreases in scheduled care than in emergency care. However, people shielding had better maintained scheduled care compared to the non-shielding general population: out-patient visits decreased 35% vs 49%; in-patient visits decreased 46% vs 81%. Notably, there was substantial variation in whose scheduled care was maintained during isolation: younger people and those with cancer had significantly higher visit rates, but there was no difference between sexes or socioeconomic levels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Healthcare changed dramatically for the clinically extremely vulnerable population during the pandemic. The increased reliance on emergency care while isolating indicates that continuity of care for existing conditions was not optimal. However, compared to the general population, there was success in maintaining scheduled care, particularly in young people and those with cancer. We suggest that integrating demographic and primary care data would improve identification of the clinically vulnerable and could aid prioritising their care.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.21263026" rel="alternate" title="The clinically extremely vulnerable to COVID: Identification and changes in healthcare while self-isolating (shielding) during the coronavirus pandemic (6 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.21263383</id><title>Social-economic drivers overwhelm climate in underlying the COVID-19 early growth rate (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.667397+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhenghua Liu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Identifying the drivers underlying the spatial occurrence and spreading rate of COVID-19 can provide valuable information for their preventions and controls. Here, we examine how socio-economic and climate drivers affect the early growth rates of COVID-19 in China and the other countries, the former of which have consistently stricter quarantine during early epidemic and thus are used to enquire the influences of human interventions on trainsimissions. We find that the early growth rates of COVID-19 are higher in China than the other countries, which is consistent with previous reports. The global spread is mainly driven by the socio-economic factors such as GDP per capita, human movement and population density rather than climate. Among socio-economic factors, GDP per capita is most important showing negative relationships in China, while positive in the other countries. However, the predicability of early growth rates by socio-economic and climate variables is at least 1.6 times higher in China’s provinces than the other countries, which is further supported by metapopulation network model. These findings collectively indicate that the stochasticity of transimission processes decrease upon strict quarantine measures such as travel restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;GDP per capita is most important in driving the spread of COVID-19, which shows negative relationships within China, while positive in the other countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Socio-economic and climate factors are key in driving the early growth rate of COVID-19, while the former is more important.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Socio-economic and climate features explain more variations of early growth rates in China due to the decreased stochasticity of transimission processes upon strict quarantine measures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.21263383" rel="alternate" title="Social-economic drivers overwhelm climate in underlying the COVID-19 early growth rate (5 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.21263371</id><title>Spread of SARS-CoV-2 Delta variant infections bearing the S:E484Q and S:T95I mutations in July and August 2021 in France (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.667689+00:00</updated><author><name>Laura Verdurme</name></author><author><name>Gonché Danesh</name></author><author><name>Sabine Trombert-Paolantoni</name></author><author><name>Mircea T. Sofonea</name></author><author><name>Valérie Noel</name></author><author><name>Vincent Foulongne</name></author><author><name>Brigitte Montès</name></author><author><name>Edouard Tuaillon</name></author><author><name>Stéphanie Haim-Boukobza</name></author><author><name>Bénédicte Roquebert</name></author><author><name>Samuel Alizon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Analysing 92,598 variant screening tests performed on SARS-CoV-2 positive samples collected in France between 1 July and 31 August 2021 shows an increase of Kappa-like infections. Full genome sequencing reveals that these correspond to Delta variants bearing the S:E484Q mutation. Most of these sequences belong to a phylogenetic cluster and also bear the S:T95I mutation. Further monitoring is needed to determine if this trend is driven by undocumented superspreading events or an early signal of future viral evolutionary dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.21263371" rel="alternate" title="Spread of SARS-CoV-2 Delta variant infections bearing the S:E484Q and S:T95I mutations in July and August 2021 in France (4 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.21263194</id><title>COVID-19 convalescent plasma and randomized clinical trials: rebuilding confidence by explaining failures and finding signals of efficacy (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.669471+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniele Focosi</name></author><author><name>Massimo Franchini</name></author><author><name>Liise-anne Pirofski</name></author><author><name>Thierry Burnouf</name></author><author><name>Nigel Paneth</name></author><author><name>Michael J. Joyner</name></author><author><name>Arturo Casadevall</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Convalescent plasma (CP) recurs as a frontline treatment in epidemics because it is available as soon as there are survivors. The COVID-19 pandemic represented the first large-scale opportunity to shed light into mechanisms of action, safety and efficacy of convalescent plasma using modern evidence-based medicine approaches. Studies ranging from observational case series to randomized controlled trials (RCT) have reported highly variable efficacy results for COVID-19 CP (CCP), resulting in more doubt than certainty. Reasons for CCP success and failure may be hidden in study details, which are usually difficult to explain to physicians and the public but provide fertile ground for designing next-generation studies. In this paper we analyzed variables associated with efficacy such as clinical settings, disease severity, CCP SARS-CoV-2 antibody levels and function, dose, timing of administration (variously defined as time from onset of symptoms, molecular diagnosis, diagnosis of pneumonia, or hospitalization, or by serostatus), outcomes (defined as hospitalization, requirement for ventilation, clinical improvement or mortality), CCP provenance and time for collection, and criteria for efficacy. Focusing only on the results from the 23 available RCT we noted that these were more likely to show signals of efficacy, including reductions in mortality, if the plasma neutralizing titer was ≥ 160 and the time to randomization was ≤ 9 days, consistent with passive antibody therapy efficacy requiring dosing with sufficient antibody. The fact that most studies revealed signals of efficacy despite variability in CCP and its use suggest robust therapeutic effects that become apparent despite the data noise.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.21263194" rel="alternate" title="COVID-19 convalescent plasma and randomized clinical trials: rebuilding confidence by explaining failures and finding signals of efficacy (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.17.460664</id><title>Genetically diverse mouse models of SARS-CoV-2 infection model clinical variation and cytokine responses in COVID-19 (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.669919+00:00</updated><author><name>Shelly Robertson</name></author><author><name>Olivia Bedard</name></author><author><name>Kristin McNally</name></author><author><name>Matthew Lewis</name></author><author><name>Chad Clancy</name></author><author><name>Carl Shaia</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Broeckel</name></author><author><name>Abhilash Chiramel</name></author><author><name>Gail Sturdevant</name></author><author><name>Elvira Forte</name></author><author><name>Christoph Preuss</name></author><author><name>Candice Baker</name></author><author><name>Daniel Sturdevant</name></author><author><name>Craig Martens</name></author><author><name>Steven Holland</name></author><author><name>Nadia Rosenthal</name></author><author><name>Sonja Best</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Host genetics are a significant determinant of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). Animal models that reflect genetic diversity and a range of clinical outcomes observed in human populations are needed to understand mechanisms of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection dynamics and disease. Here, we report a mouse panel comprising the diverse genetic backgrounds of the Collaborative Cross (CC) founder strains crossed to C57BL/6J mice expressing the K18-hACE2 transgene3 that enables infection by SARS-CoV-2. Infection of CCxK18-hACE2 F1 progeny resulted in a spectrum of weight loss, survival, viral replication kinetics, histopathology, and cytokine profiles, some of which were sex-specific. Importantly, survival was closely associated with early type I interferon expression and a phased proinflammatory response distinct from mice with severe disease. Thus, dynamics of inflammatory responses observed in COVID-19 can be modeled in diverse mice that provide a genetically tractable platform for understanding antiviral immunity and evaluating countermeasures.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.17.460664" rel="alternate" title="Genetically diverse mouse models of SARS-CoV-2 infection model clinical variation and cytokine responses in COVID-19 (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>