<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.696552+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.28.21259673</id><title>Infectivity and immune escape of the new SARS-CoV-2 variant of interest Lambda (910 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.697455+00:00</updated><author><name>Mónica L. Acevedo</name></author><author><name>Luis Alonso-Palomares</name></author><author><name>Andrés Bustamante</name></author><author><name>Aldo Gaggero</name></author><author><name>Fabio Paredes</name></author><author><name>Claudia P. Cortés</name></author><author><name>Fernando Valiente-Echeverría</name></author><author><name>Ricardo Soto-Rifo</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The newly described SARS-CoV-2 lineage C.37 was recently classified as a variant of interest by the WHO (Lambda variant) based on its high circulation rates in South American countries and the presence of critical mutations in the spike protein. The impact of such mutations in infectivity and immune escape from neutralizing antibodies are entirely unknown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We performed a pseudotyped virus neutralization assay and determined the impact of the Lambda variant on infectivity and immune escape using plasma samples from healthcare workers (HCW) from two centers in Santiago, Chile who received the two-doses scheme of the inactivated virus vaccine CoronaVac.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We observed an increased infectivity mediated by the Lambda spike protein that was even higher than that of the D614G (lineage B) or the Alpha and Gamma variants. Compared to the Wild type (lineage A), neutralization was decreased by 3.05-fold for the Lambda variant while it was 2.33-fold for the Gamma variant and 2.03-fold for the Alpha variant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our results indicate that mutations present in the spike protein of the Lambda variant of interest confer increased infectivity and immune escape from neutralizing antibodies elicited by CoronaVac. These data reinforce the idea that massive vaccination campaigns in countries with high SARS-CoV-2 circulation must be accompanied by strict genomic surveillance allowing the identification of new isolates carrying spike mutations and immunology studies aimed to determine the impact of these mutations in immune escape and vaccines breakthrough.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.28.21259673" rel="alternate" title="Infectivity and immune escape of the new SARS-CoV-2 variant of interest Lambda (910 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450356</id><title>Thrombocytopenia and splenic platelet directed immune responses after intravenous ChAdOx1 nCov-19 administration (564 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.698297+00:00</updated><author><name>Leo Nicolai</name></author><author><name>Alexander Leunig</name></author><author><name>Kami Pekayvaz</name></author><author><name>Afra Anjum</name></author><author><name>Eva Riedlinger</name></author><author><name>Luke Eivers</name></author><author><name>Marie-Louise Hoffknecht</name></author><author><name>Dario Rossaro</name></author><author><name>Raphael Escaig</name></author><author><name>Rainer Kaiser</name></author><author><name>Vivien Polewka</name></author><author><name>Anna Titova</name></author><author><name>Karsten Spiekermann</name></author><author><name>Matteo Iannacone</name></author><author><name>Konstantin Stark</name></author><author><name>Steffen Massberg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Vaccines against SARS-CoV-2 are based on a range of novel vaccine platforms, with adenovirus-based approaches (like ChAdOx1 nCov-19) being one of them. Recently a rare and novel complication of SARS-CoV-2 targeted adenovirus vaccines has emerged: thrombosis with thrombocytopenia syndrome (TTS). TTS is characterized by low platelet counts, clot formation at unusual anatomic sites and platelet-activating PF4-polyanion antibodies reminiscent of heparin-induced thrombocytopenia. Here, we employ &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; models to characterize the possible mechanisms of this platelet-targeted autoimmunity. We show that intravenous but not intramuscular injection of ChAdOx1 nCov-19 triggers platelet-adenovirus aggregate formation and platelet activation. After intravenous injection, these aggregates are phagocytosed by macrophages in the spleen and platelet remnants are found in the marginal zone and follicles. This is followed by a pronounced B-cell response with the emergence of circulating antibodies binding to platelets. Our work contributes to the understanding of TTS and highlights accidental intravenous injection as potential mechanism for post-vaccination TTS. Hence, safe intramuscular injection, with aspiration prior to injection, could be a potential preventive measure when administering adenovirus-based vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450356" rel="alternate" title="Thrombocytopenia and splenic platelet directed immune responses after intravenous ChAdOx1 nCov-19 administration (564 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.01.450676</id><title>Neutralization of Delta variant with sera of Covishield vaccinees and COVID-19 recovered vaccinated individuals (513 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.698876+00:00</updated><author><name>Gajanan Sapkal</name></author><author><name>Pragya D Yadav</name></author><author><name>Rima R Sahay</name></author><author><name>Gururaj Deshpande</name></author><author><name>Nivedita Gupta</name></author><author><name>Dimpal A Nyayanit</name></author><author><name>Deepak Y Patil</name></author><author><name>Sanjay Kumar</name></author><author><name>Priya Abraham</name></author><author><name>Samiran Panda</name></author><author><name>Balram Bhargava</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The recent emergence of B.1.617 lineage has created grave public health problem in India. The lineage further mutated to generate sub-lineages B.1.617.1 (Kappa), B.1.617.2 (Delta), B.1.617.3. Apparently, the Delta variant has slowly dominated the other variants including B.1.617.1 (Kappa), B.1.617.2 (Delta), B.1.617.3. With this, World Health Organization has described this sub-lineage as variant of concern. The high transmissibility associated with Delta variant has led to second wave of pandemic in India which affected millions of people. Besides this, variant of concerns has been reported to show lower neutralization to several approved vaccines. This has led to breakthrough infections after completion of vaccination regimen. There is limited information available on the duration of protective immune response post-infection, vaccination or breakthrough infection with SARS-CoV-2. In this study, we have evaluated immune response in sera of the Covishield vaccinated individuals belonging to category: I. one dose vaccinated, II. two doses vaccinated, III. COVID-19 recovered plus one dose vaccinated, IV. COVID-19 recovered plus two doses vaccinated and V. breakthrough COVID-19 cases. The findings of the study demonstrated that the breakthrough cases and the COVID-19 recovered individuals with one or two dose of vaccine had relatively higher protection against Delta variant in comparison to the participants who were administered either one or two doses of Covishield. Prior vaccination results in less severe disease against subsequent infection provide evidence that both humoral and cellular immune response play an important role in protection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.01.450676" rel="alternate" title="Neutralization of Delta variant with sera of Covishield vaccinees and COVID-19 recovered vaccinated individuals (513 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.28.21259658</id><title>Post COVID-19 sequelae: A prospective observational study from Northern India (41 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.699179+00:00</updated><author><name>Shivdas Naik</name></author><author><name>Manish Soneja</name></author><author><name>Soumendra Haldar</name></author><author><name>Netto George Mundadan</name></author><author><name>Prerna Garg</name></author><author><name>Ankit Mittal</name></author><author><name>Devashish Desai</name></author><author><name>Praveen Kumar Trilangi</name></author><author><name>Sayan Chakraborty</name></author><author><name>Nazneen Nahar Begam</name></author><author><name>Bisakh Bhattacharya</name></author><author><name>Ganesh Maher</name></author><author><name>Swathi S Kumar</name></author><author><name>J Kirthana</name></author><author><name>Bharathi Arunan</name></author><author><name>Ankesh Gupta</name></author><author><name>Niranjan Mahishi</name></author><author><name>Chaitra Rajanna</name></author><author><name>Prateek Parsoon</name></author><author><name>Nikhil A Kumar</name></author><author><name>Sayan Maharatna</name></author><author><name>Akashneel Bhattacharya</name></author><author><name>Vishakh C Keri</name></author><author><name>Sameer A Samed</name></author><author><name>AK Adarsh</name></author><author><name>Imtiyaz Shareef</name></author><author><name>Neeren Ravela</name></author><author><name>Satish Swain</name></author><author><name>Radhika Sarda</name></author><author><name>Harshith B Kadnur</name></author><author><name>Ashok Dudhwal</name></author><author><name>Ayush Agarwal</name></author><author><name>Kartik Vedula</name></author><author><name>Ashish Gupta</name></author><author><name>Shubham Agarwal</name></author><author><name>R Anand</name></author><author><name>Pratima Lalikar</name></author><author><name>Pallavi Jagtap</name></author><author><name>B Premjeet</name></author><author><name>Parul Kodan</name></author><author><name>Prayas Sethi</name></author><author><name>Animesh Ray</name></author><author><name>Pankaj Jorwal</name></author><author><name>Arvind Kumar</name></author><author><name>Neeraj Nischal</name></author><author><name>Sanjeev Sinha</name></author><author><name>Ashutosh Biswas</name></author><author><name>Naveet Wig</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Long COVID, or post-COVID-19 sequelae, is being seen in a growing number of patients reporting a constellation of symptoms, both pulmonary and extrapulmonary. Studies on COVID-19 recovered patients are scarce. Thus, there is a need to add granularity to our existing knowledge about the course and long-term effects of the infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aim&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To describe the clinical details and risk factors of post-COVID sequelae in the North Indian population.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Method&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This prospective observational study was conducted at a tertiary healthcare centre in Northern India between October 2020 to February 2021. Patients aged &amp;gt;18 years with a confirmed COVID-19 disease were recruited after at least two weeks of diagnosis and interviewed for any post-COVID-19 symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of 1234 patients recruited, who were followed up for a median duration of 91 days (IQR: 45-181 days), 495 (40.11%) patients had symptoms. In 223 (18.1%) patients, the symptoms resolved within four weeks, 150 (12.1%) patients had symptoms till twelve weeks, and 122 (9.9%) patients had symptoms beyond twelve weeks of diagnosis of COVID-19. Most common long COVID-19 symptoms included myalgia (10.9%), fatigue (5.5%), shortness of breath (6.1%), cough (2.1%), disturbed sleep (1.4%), mood disturbances (0.48%) and anxiety (0.6%). The major determinants of developing post-COVID-19 symptoms in the patients were hypothyroidism and the severity of the disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most often, patients complain of myalgias, fatigue, dyspnoea, cough and disturbed sleep. Patients who are hypothyroid or have recovered from moderate to severe COVID-19 are at higher risk of developing post-COVID sequelae. Therefore, a multidisciplinary approach is required to diagnose and manage COVID-19 recovered patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.28.21259658" rel="alternate" title="Post COVID-19 sequelae: A prospective observational study from Northern India (41 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450483</id><title>Large scale screening discovers clofoctol as an inhibitor of SARS-CoV-2 replication that reduces COVID-19-like pathology (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.700016+00:00</updated><author><name>Sandrine Belouzard</name></author><author><name>Arnaud Machelart</name></author><author><name>Valentin Sencio</name></author><author><name>Thibaut Vausselin</name></author><author><name>Eik Hoffmann</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Deboosere</name></author><author><name>Yves Rouillé</name></author><author><name>Lowiese Desmarets</name></author><author><name>Karin Séron</name></author><author><name>Adeline Danneels</name></author><author><name>Cyril Robil</name></author><author><name>Loïc Belloy</name></author><author><name>Camille Moreau</name></author><author><name>Catherine Piveteau</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Biela</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Vandeputte</name></author><author><name>Séverine Heumel</name></author><author><name>Lucie Deruyter</name></author><author><name>Julie Dumont</name></author><author><name>Florence Leroux</name></author><author><name>Ilka Engelmann</name></author><author><name>Enagnon Kazali Alidjinou</name></author><author><name>Didier Hober</name></author><author><name>Priscille Brodin</name></author><author><name>Terence Beghyn</name></author><author><name>François Trottein</name></author><author><name>Benoît Déprez</name></author><author><name>Jean Dubuisson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The fastest way to implement a treatment against a new rapidly emerging viral disease consists in screening the potential antiviral activity of drugs approved for human use. This has the advantage of shortening regulatory preclinical development steps. Here, we screened a library of drug compounds, already registered in one or several geographical areas, to identify those exhibiting antiviral activity against SARS-CoV-2 with relevant potency. Of the 1,942 compounds tested, 21 exhibited a substantial antiviral activity in Vero-81 cells. Among them, clofoctol, an antibacterial drug used for the treatment of bacterial respiratory tract infections, was further investigated due to its favorable safety profile and its pharmacokinetic properties. Notably, the peak concentration of clofoctol that can be achieved in human lungs is more than 20 times higher than its IC&lt;sub&gt;95&lt;/sub&gt; measured against SARS-CoV-2 in human pulmonary cells. Mechanistically, this compound inhibits SARS-CoV-2 at a post-entry step by specifically blocking translation initiation of viral RNA. Lastly, therapeutic treatment of human ACE2 receptor transgenic mice decreased viral load, reduced inflammatory gene expression and improved pulmonary pathology. Altogether, these data strongly support clofoctol as a therapeutic candidate for the treatment of COVID-19 patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450483" rel="alternate" title="Large scale screening discovers clofoctol as an inhibitor of SARS-CoV-2 replication that reduces COVID-19-like pathology (31 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.02.450663</id><title>Natural infection of SARS-CoV-2 delta variant in Asiatic lions (Panthera leo persica) in India (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.700753+00:00</updated><author><name>Anamika Mishra</name></author><author><name>Naveen Kumar</name></author><author><name>Sandeep Bhatia</name></author><author><name>Ashutosh Aasdev</name></author><author><name>Sridhar Kanniappan</name></author><author><name>A. Thayasekhar</name></author><author><name>Aparna Gopinadhan</name></author><author><name>R. Silambarasan</name></author><author><name>C. Sreekumar</name></author><author><name>Chandan Kumar Dubey</name></author><author><name>Meghna Tripathi</name></author><author><name>Ashwin Ashok Raut</name></author><author><name>Vijendra Pal Singh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In May 2021, severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) was detected in nine Asiatic lions (Panthera leo persica) in Arignar Anna Zoological Park, Chennai, Tamil Nadu, India. Sequence and phylogenetic analysis showed that the SARS-CoV-2 viruses belong to a variant of concern (VOC, delta variant, B.1.617.2 lineage) and that these viruses clustered with B.1.617.2 lineage viruses of the same geographical region detected in the same month.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.02.450663" rel="alternate" title="Natural infection of SARS-CoV-2 delta variant in Asiatic lions (Panthera leo persica) in India (21 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450426</id><title>Varenicline Prevents SARS-CoV-2 Infection In Vitro and in Rhesus Macaques (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.701284+00:00</updated><author><name>Jeffrey Nau</name></author><author><name>Priya Luthra</name></author><author><name>Kathleen Lanzer</name></author><author><name>Frank Szaba</name></author><author><name>Tres Cookenham</name></author><author><name>Eric Carlson</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 infections have resulted in a global pandemic, but an antiviral therapy for this novel strain of coronavirus does not currently exist. The objective of our study was to investigate the antiviral potential of the nicotinic acetylcholine receptor (nACHR) agonist varenicline tartrate against SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We assessed antiviral activity using &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; human cell assays and we assessed &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; efficacy in a rhesus macaque model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;In vitro&lt;/italic&gt; studies found that varenicline tartrate, over a range of concentrations, reduced the infectivity of SARS-CoV-2 wildtype, alpha, and beta variants in Calu-3 cells and Caco-2 cells, with maintenance of cell viability. &lt;italic&gt;In vivo&lt;/italic&gt; studies found that varenicline tartrate, administered as a nasal spray to rhesus macaques, reduced SARS-CoV-2 wildtype viral load and inhibited viral replication in the nasal mucosa and upper airway.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the study reported here was exploratory, we have confirmed that the nAChR agonist varenicline has the potential to interact with and inhibit SARS-CoV-2 infection and replication.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450426" rel="alternate" title="Varenicline Prevents SARS-CoV-2 Infection In Vitro and in Rhesus Macaques (16 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.25.21259372</id><title>A systematic review of persistent symptoms and residual abnormal functioning following acute COVID-19: Ongoing symptomatic phase vs. post-COVID-19 syndrome (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.701718+00:00</updated><author><name>Glenn Jennings</name></author><author><name>Ann Monaghan</name></author><author><name>Feng Xue</name></author><author><name>David Mockler</name></author><author><name>Román Romero-Ortuño</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To compare the two phases of long COVID, namely ongoing symptomatic COVID-19 (OSC; signs and symptoms from 4 to 12 weeks from initial infection) and post-COVID-19 syndrome (PCS; signs and symptoms beyond 12 weeks) with respect to symptomatology, abnormal functioning, psychological burden, and quality of life.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Systematic review.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data Sources&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic search of EMBASE, MEDLINE, ProQuest Coronavirus Research Database, LitCOVID, and Google Scholar between January and April 2021, and manual search for relevant citations from review articles.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Eligibility Criteria&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cross-sectional studies, cohort studies, randomised control trials, and case-control studies with participant data concerning long COVID symptomatology or abnormal functioning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data Extraction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Studies were screened and assessed for risk of bias by two independent reviewers, with conflicts resolved with a third reviewer. The AXIS tool was utilised to appraise the quality of the evidence. Data were extracted and collated using a data extraction tool in Microsoft Excel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of the 1,145 studies screened, 39 were included, all describing adult cohorts with long COVID and sample sizes ranging from 32 to 1,733. Studies included data pertaining to symptomatology, pulmonary functioning, chest imaging, cognitive functioning, psychological disorder, and/or quality of life. Fatigue presented as the most prevalent symptom during both OSC and PCS at 43% and 44%, respectively. Sleep disorder (36%; 33%), dyspnoea (31%; 40%), and cough (26%; 22%) followed in prevalence. Abnormal spirometry (FEV&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;lt;80% predicted) was observed in 15% and 11%, and abnormal chest imaging observed in 34% and 28%, respectively. Cognitive impairments were also evident (20%; 15%), as well as anxiety (28%; 34%) and depression (25%; 32%). Decreased quality of life was reported by 40% of patients with OSC and 57% by those with PCS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The prevalences of OSC and PCS were highly variable. Reported symptoms covered a wide range of body systems, with general overlap in frequencies between the two phases. However, abnormalities in lung function and imaging seemed to be more common in OSC, whilst anxiety, depression, and poor quality of life seemed more frequent in PCS. In general, the quality of the evidence was moderate and further research is needed to better understand the complex interplay of somatic versus psychosocial drivers in long COVID.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Systematic Review Registration&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Registered with PROSPERO with ID #CRD42021247846.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.25.21259372" rel="alternate" title="A systematic review of persistent symptoms and residual abnormal functioning following acute COVID-19: Ongoing symptomatic phase vs. post-COVID-19 syndrome (12 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.28.21259671</id><title>Dimeric IgA is a specific biomarker of recent SARS-CoV-2 infection (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.702238+00:00</updated><author><name>Heidi E Drummer</name></author><author><name>Huy Van</name></author><author><name>Ethan Klock</name></author><author><name>Shuning Zheng</name></author><author><name>Zihui Wei</name></author><author><name>Irene Boo</name></author><author><name>Rob J Center</name></author><author><name>Fan Li</name></author><author><name>Purnima Bhat</name></author><author><name>Rosemary Ffrench</name></author><author><name>Jillian SY Lau</name></author><author><name>James McMahon</name></author><author><name>Oliver Laeyendecker</name></author><author><name>Reinaldo E. Fernandez</name></author><author><name>Yukari C. Manabe</name></author><author><name>Sabra L. Klein</name></author><author><name>Thomas C. Quinn</name></author><author><name>David A. Anderson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Current tests for SARS-CoV-2 antibodies (IgG, IgM, IgA) cannot differentiate recent and past infections. We describe a point of care, lateral flow assay for SARS-CoV-2 dIgA based on the highly selective binding of dIgA to a chimeric form of secretory component (CSC), that distinguishes dIgA from monomeric IgA. Detection of specific dIgA uses a complex of biotinylated SARS-CoV-2 receptor binding domain and streptavidin-colloidal gold. SARS-CoV-2-specific dIgA was measured both in 112 cross-sectional samples and a longitudinal panel of 362 plasma samples from 45 patients with PCR-confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection, and 193 discrete pre-COVID-19 or PCR-negative patient samples. The assay demonstrated 100% sensitivity from 11 days post-symptom onset, and a specificity of 98.2%. With an estimated half-life of 6.3 days, dIgA provides a unique biomarker for the detection of recent SARS-CoV-2 infections with potential to enhance diagnosis and management of COVID-19 at point-of-care.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.28.21259671" rel="alternate" title="Dimeric IgA is a specific biomarker of recent SARS-CoV-2 infection (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450298</id><title>Pathology and immunity after SARS-CoV-2 infection in male ferrets is affected by age and inoculation route (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.703082+00:00</updated><author><name>Koen van de Ven</name></author><author><name>Harry van Dijken</name></author><author><name>Lisa Wijsman</name></author><author><name>Angéla Gomersbach</name></author><author><name>Tanja Schouten</name></author><author><name>Jolanda Kool</name></author><author><name>Stefanie Lenz</name></author><author><name>Paul Roholl</name></author><author><name>Adam Meijer</name></author><author><name>Puck van Kasteren</name></author><author><name>Jørgen de Jonge</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Improving COVID-19 intervention strategies partly relies on animal models to study SARS-CoV-2 disease and immunity. In our pursuit to establish a model for severe COVID-19, we inoculated young and adult male ferrets intranasally or intratracheally with SARS-CoV-2. Intranasal inoculation established an infection in all ferrets, with viral dissemination into the brain and gut. Upon intratracheal inoculation only adult ferrets became infected. However, neither inoculation route induced observable COVID-19 symptoms. Despite this, a persistent inflammation in the nose was prominent in especially young ferrets and follicular hyperplasia in the bronchi developed 21 days post infection. These effects -if sustained- might resemble long-COVID. Respiratory and systemic cellular responses and antibody responses were induced only in animals with an established infection. We conclude that intranasally-infected ferrets resemble asymptomatic COVID-19 and possibly aspects of long-COVID. Combined with the increasing portfolio to measure adaptive immunity, ferrets are a relevant model for SARS-CoV-2 vaccine research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450298" rel="alternate" title="Pathology and immunity after SARS-CoV-2 infection in male ferrets is affected by age and inoculation route (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>