<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.345756+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.22269010</id><title>Infectious viral load in unvaccinated and vaccinated patients infected with SARS-CoV-2 WT, Delta and Omicron (2384 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.346034+00:00</updated><author><name>Olha Puhach</name></author><author><name>Kenneth Adea</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Hulo</name></author><author><name>Pascale Sattonnet</name></author><author><name>Camille Genecand</name></author><author><name>Anne Iten</name></author><author><name>Frédérique Jacquérioz Bausch</name></author><author><name>Laurent Kaiser</name></author><author><name>Pauline Vetter</name></author><author><name>Isabella Eckerle</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Meyer</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Viral load (VL) is one determinant of secondary transmission of SARS-CoV-2. Emergence of variants of concerns (VOC) Alpha and Delta was ascribed, at least partly, to higher VL. Furthermore, with parts of the population vaccinated, knowledge on VL in vaccine breakthrough infections is crucial. As RNA VL is only a weak proxy for infectiousness, studies on infectious virus presence by cell culture isolation are of importance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We assessed nasopharyngeal swabs of COVID-19 patients for quantitative infectious viral titres (IVT) by focus-forming assay and compared to overall virus isolation success and RNA genome copies. We assessed infectious viral titres during the first 5 symptomatic days in a total of 384 patients: unvaccinated individuals infected with pre-VOC SARS-CoV-2 (n= 118) or Delta (n= 127) and vaccine breakthrough infections with Delta (n= 121) or Omicron (n=18).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Correlation between RNA copy number and IVT was low for all groups. No correlation between IVTs and age or sex was seen. We observed higher RNA genome copies in pre-VOC SARS-CoV-2 compared to Delta, but significantly higher IVTs in Delta infected individuals. In vaccinated vs. unvaccinated Delta infected individuals, RNA genome copies were comparable but vaccinated individuals have significantly lower IVTs, and cleared virus faster. Vaccinated individuals with Omicron infection had comparable IVTs to Delta breakthrough infections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Quantitative IVTs can give detailed insights into virus shedding kinetics. Vaccination was associated with lower infectious titres and faster clearance for Delta, showing that vaccination would also lower transmission risk. Omicron vaccine breakthrough infections did not show elevated IVTs compared to Delta, suggesting that other mechanisms than increase VL contribute to the high infectiousness of Omicron.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This work was supported by the Swiss National Science Foundation 196644, 196383, NRP (National Research Program) 78 Covid-19 Grant 198412, the Fondation Ancrage Bienfaisance du Groupe Pictet and the Fondation Privée des Hôpitaux Universitaires de Genève.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.22269010" rel="alternate" title="Infectious viral load in unvaccinated and vaccinated patients infected with SARS-CoV-2 WT, Delta and Omicron (2384 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476031</id><title>The SARS-CoV-2 Omicron (B.1.1.529) variant exhibits altered pathogenicity, transmissibility, and fitness in the golden Syrian hamster model (368 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.346200+00:00</updated><author><name>Shuofeng Yuan</name></author><author><name>Zi-Wei Ye</name></author><author><name>Ronghui Liang</name></author><author><name>Kaiming Tang</name></author><author><name>Anna Jinxia Zhang</name></author><author><name>Gang Lu</name></author><author><name>Chon Phin Ong</name></author><author><name>Vincent Kwok-Man Poon</name></author><author><name>Chris Chung-Sing Chan</name></author><author><name>Bobo Wing-Yee Mok</name></author><author><name>Zhenzhi Qin</name></author><author><name>Yubin Xie</name></author><author><name>Haoran Sun</name></author><author><name>Jessica Oi-Ling Tsang</name></author><author><name>Terrence Tsz-Tai Yuen</name></author><author><name>Kenn Ka-Heng Chik</name></author><author><name>Chris Chun-Yiu Chan</name></author><author><name>Jian-Piao Cai</name></author><author><name>Cuiting Luo</name></author><author><name>Lu Lu</name></author><author><name>Cyril Chik-Yan Yip</name></author><author><name>Hin Chu</name></author><author><name>Kelvin Kai-Wang To</name></author><author><name>Honglin Chen</name></author><author><name>Dong-Yan Jin</name></author><author><name>Kwok-Yung Yuen</name></author><author><name>Jasper Fuk-Woo Chan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The newly emerging SARS-CoV-2 Omicron (B.1.1.529) variant first identified in South Africa in November 2021 is characterized by an unusual number of amino acid mutations in its spike that renders existing vaccines and therapeutic monoclonal antibodies dramatically less effective. The &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; pathogenicity, transmissibility, and fitness of this new Variant of Concerns are unknown. We investigated these virological attributes of the Omicron variant in comparison with those of the currently dominant Delta (B.1.617.2) variant in the golden Syrian hamster COVID-19 model. Omicron-infected hamsters developed significantly less body weight losses, clinical scores, respiratory tract viral burdens, cytokine/chemokine dysregulation, and tissue damages than Delta-infected hamsters. The Omicron and Delta variant were both highly transmissible (100% vs 100%) via contact transmission. Importantly, the Omicron variant consistently demonstrated about 10-20% higher transmissibility than the already-highly transmissible Delta variant in repeated non-contact transmission studies (overall: 30/36 vs 24/36, 83.3% vs 66.7%). The Delta variant displayed higher fitness advantage than the Omicron variant without selection pressure in both &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; competition models. However, this scenario drastically changed once immune selection pressure with neutralizing antibodies active against the Delta variant but poorly active against the Omicron variant were introduced, with the Omicron variant significantly outcompeting the Delta variant. Taken together, our findings demonstrated that while the Omicron variant is less pathogenic than the Delta variant, it is highly transmissible and can outcompete the Delta variant under immune selection pressure. Next-generation vaccines and antivirals effective against this new VOC are urgently needed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The novel SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant, though less pathogenic, is highly transmissible and outcompetes the Delta variant under immune selection pressure in the golden Syrian hamster COVID-19 model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476031" rel="alternate" title="The SARS-CoV-2 Omicron (B.1.1.529) variant exhibits altered pathogenicity, transmissibility, and fitness in the golden Syrian hamster model (368 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.22269288</id><title>Characterizing features of outbreak duration for novel SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (46 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.346467+00:00</updated><author><name>Alex D. Washburne</name></author><author><name>Nathaniel Hupert</name></author><author><name>Nicole Kogan</name></author><author><name>William Hanage</name></author><author><name>Mauricio Santillana</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Characterizing the dynamics of epidemic trajectories is critical to understanding the potential impacts of emerging outbreaks and to designing appropriate mitigation strategies. As the COVID-19 pandemic evolves, however, the emergence of SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern has complicated our ability to assess in real-time the potential effects of imminent outbreaks, such as those presently caused by the Omicron variant. Here, we report that SARS-CoV-2 outbreaks across regions exhibit strain-specific times from onset to peak, specifically for Delta and Omicron variants. Our findings may facilitate real-time identification of peak medical demand and may help fine-tune ongoing and future outbreak mitigation deployment efforts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.22269288" rel="alternate" title="Characterizing features of outbreak duration for novel SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (46 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.21267633</id><title>National-scale surveillance of emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants in wastewater (44 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.346549+00:00</updated><author><name>Fabian Amman</name></author><author><name>Rudolf Markt</name></author><author><name>Lukas Endler</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Hupfauf</name></author><author><name>Benedikt Agerer</name></author><author><name>Anna Schedl</name></author><author><name>Lukas Richter</name></author><author><name>Melanie Zechmeister</name></author><author><name>Martin Bicher</name></author><author><name>Georg Heiler</name></author><author><name>Petr Triska</name></author><author><name>Matthew Thornton</name></author><author><name>Thomas Penz</name></author><author><name>Martin Senekowitsch</name></author><author><name>Jan Laine</name></author><author><name>Zsofia Keszei</name></author><author><name>Beatrice Daleiden</name></author><author><name>Martin Steinlechner</name></author><author><name>Harald Niederstaetter</name></author><author><name>Christoph Scheffknecht</name></author><author><name>Gunther Vogl</name></author><author><name>Guenther Weichlinger</name></author><author><name>Andreas Wagner</name></author><author><name>Katarzyna Slipko</name></author><author><name>Amandine Masseron</name></author><author><name>Elena Radu</name></author><author><name>Franz Allerberger</name></author><author><name>Niki Popper</name></author><author><name>Christoph Bock</name></author><author><name>Daniela Schmid</name></author><author><name>Herbert Oberacher</name></author><author><name>Norbert Kreuzinger</name></author><author><name>Heribert Insam</name></author><author><name>Andreas Bergthaler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 surveillance is crucial to identify variants with altered epidemiological properties. Wastewater-based epidemiology (WBE) provides an unbiased and complementary approach to sequencing individual cases. Yet, national WBE surveillance programs have not been widely implemented and data analyses remain challenging. We deep-sequenced 2,093 wastewater samples representing 95 municipal catchments, covering &amp;gt;57% of Austria's population, from December 2020 to September 2021. Our Variant Quantification in Sewage pipeline designed for Robustness (VaQuERo) enabled us to deduce variant abundance from complex wastewater samples and delineate the spatiotemporal dynamics of the dominant Alpha and Delta variants as well as regional clusters of other variants of concern. These results were cross validated by epidemiological records of &amp;gt;130,000 individual cases. Finally, we provide a framework to predict emerging variants de novo and infer variant-specific reproduction numbers from wastewater. This study demonstrates the power of national-scale WBE to support public health and promises particular value for countries without dense individual monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.21267633" rel="alternate" title="National-scale surveillance of emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants in wastewater (44 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475922</id><title>Structural and functional impact by SARS-CoV-2 Omicron spike mutations (41 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.346745+00:00</updated><author><name>Jun Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yongfei Cai</name></author><author><name>Christy L. Lavine</name></author><author><name>Hanqin Peng</name></author><author><name>Haisun Zhu</name></author><author><name>Krishna Anand</name></author><author><name>Pei Tong</name></author><author><name>Avneesh Gautam</name></author><author><name>Megan L. Mayer</name></author><author><name>Sophia Rits-Volloch</name></author><author><name>Shaowei Wang</name></author><author><name>Piotr Sliz</name></author><author><name>Duane R. Wesemann</name></author><author><name>Wei Yang</name></author><author><name>Michael S. Seaman</name></author><author><name>Jianming Lu</name></author><author><name>Tianshu Xiao</name></author><author><name>Bing Chen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Omicron variant of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), bearing an unusually high number of mutations, has become a dominant strain in many countries within several weeks. We report here structural, functional and antigenic properties of its full-length spike (S) protein with a native sequence in comparison with those of previously prevalent variants. Omicron S requires a substantially higher level of host receptor ACE2 for efficient membrane fusion than other variants, possibly explaining its unexpected cellular tropism. Mutations not only remodel the antigenic structure of the N-terminal domain of the S protein, but also alter the surface of the receptor-binding domain in a way not seen in other variants, consistent with its remarkable resistance to neutralizing antibodies. These results suggest that Omicron S has acquired an extraordinary ability to evade host immunity by excessive mutations, which also compromise its fusogenic capability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475922" rel="alternate" title="Structural and functional impact by SARS-CoV-2 Omicron spike mutations (41 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475327</id><title>Systemic infection of SARS-CoV-2 in free ranging Leopard (Panthera pardus fusca) in India (38 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.346872+00:00</updated><author><name>Sonalika Mahajan</name></author><author><name>Mathesh Karikalan</name></author><author><name>Vishal Chander</name></author><author><name>Abhijit M. Pawde</name></author><author><name>G Saikumar</name></author><author><name>M Semmaran</name></author><author><name>P Sree Lakshmi</name></author><author><name>Megha Sharma</name></author><author><name>Sukdeb Nandi</name></author><author><name>Karam Pal Singh</name></author><author><name>Vivek Kumar Gupta</name></author><author><name>Raj Kumar Singh</name></author><author><name>Gaurav Kumar Sharma</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We report patho-morphological and virological characterization of SARS-CoV-2 in naturally infected, free ranging Indian Leopard (&lt;italic&gt;Panthera pardus fusca&lt;/italic&gt;). Whole genome sequence analysis confirmed infection of Delta variant of SARS-CoV-2, possibly spill over from humans, but the case was detected when infection level had dropped significantly in human population. This report underlines the need for intensive screening of wild animals for keeping track of the virus evolution and development of carrier status of SARS-CoV-2 among wildlife species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475327" rel="alternate" title="Systemic infection of SARS-CoV-2 in free ranging Leopard (Panthera pardus fusca) in India (38 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22269017</id><title>Healthcare workers’ views on mandatory SARS-CoV-2 vaccination in the United Kingdom: findings from the UK-REACH prospective longitudinal cohort study (36 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.346982+00:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Woolf</name></author><author><name>Mayuri Gogoi</name></author><author><name>Christopher A Martin</name></author><author><name>Padmasayee Papineni</name></author><author><name>Susie Lagrata</name></author><author><name>Laura B Nellums</name></author><author><name>I Chris McManus</name></author><author><name>Anna L Guyatt</name></author><author><name>Carl Melbourne</name></author><author><name>Luke Bryant</name></author><author><name>Amit Gupta</name></author><author><name>Catherine John</name></author><author><name>Sue Carr</name></author><author><name>Martin D Tobin</name></author><author><name>Sandra Simpson</name></author><author><name>Bindu Gregary</name></author><author><name>Avinash Aujayeb</name></author><author><name>Stephen Zingwe</name></author><author><name>Rubina Reza</name></author><author><name>Laura J Gray</name></author><author><name>Kamlesh Khunti</name></author><author><name>Manish Pareek</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Several countries now have mandatory SARS-CoV-2/COVID-19 vaccination for healthcare workers (HCWs) or the general population. HCWs’ views on this are largely unknown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We administered an online questionnaire to 17891 United Kingdom (UK) HCWs in Spring 2021 as part of the United Kingdom Research study into Ethnicity And COVID-19 outcomes in Healthcare workers (UK-REACH) nationwide prospective cohort study. We categorised responses to a free-text question “What should society do if people don’t get vaccinated against COVID-19?” using content analysis. We collapsed categories into a binary variable: favours mandatory vaccination or not and used logistic regression to calculate its demographic predictors, and occupational, health and attitudinal predictors adjusted for demographics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of 5633 questionnaire respondents, 3235 answered the freetext question; 18% (n=578) of those favoured mandatory vaccination but the most frequent suggestion was education (32%, n=1047). Older HCWs, HCWs vaccinated against influenza (OR 1.48; 95%CI 1.10 – 1.99, vs none) and with more positive vaccination attitudes generally (OR 1.10; 95%CI 1.06 – 1.14) were more likely to favour mandatory vaccination (OR 1.26; 95%CI 1.17 – 1.37, per decade increase), whereas female HCWs (OR= 0.80, 95%CI 0.65 – 0.99, vs male), Black HCWs (OR= 0.48, 95%CI 0.26 – 0.87, vs White), those hesitant about COVID-19 vaccination (OR= 0.56; 95%CI 0.43 – 0.71, vs not hesitant), in an Allied Health Profession (OR 0.67; 95%CI 0.51 – 0.88, vs Medical), or who trusted their organisation (OR 0.78; 95%CI 0.63 – 0.96) were less likely to.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Only one in six of the HCWs in this large, diverse, UK-wide sample favoured mandatory vaccination. Building trust, educating and supporting HCWs who are hesitant about vaccination may be more acceptable, effective and equitable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;MRC-UK Research and Innovation grant (MR/V027549/1) and the Department of Health and Social Care via the National Institute for Health Research.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22269017" rel="alternate" title="Healthcare workers’ views on mandatory SARS-CoV-2 vaccination in the United Kingdom: findings from the UK-REACH prospective longitudinal cohort study (36 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475947</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 drives NLRP3 inflammasome activation in human microglia through spike-ACE2 receptor interaction (28 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.347123+00:00</updated><author><name>Eduardo Albornoz</name></author><author><name>Alberto A Amarilla</name></author><author><name>Naphak Modhiran</name></author><author><name>Sandra Parker</name></author><author><name>Xaria X. Li</name></author><author><name>Danushka K. Wijesundara</name></author><author><name>Adriana Pliego Zamora</name></author><author><name>Christopher LD McMillan</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Liang</name></author><author><name>Nias Y.G. Peng</name></author><author><name>Julian D.J. Sng</name></author><author><name>Fatema Tuj Saima</name></author><author><name>Devina Paramitha</name></author><author><name>Rhys Parry</name></author><author><name>Michael S. Avumegah</name></author><author><name>Ariel Isaacs</name></author><author><name>Martin Lo</name></author><author><name>Zaray Miranda-Chacon</name></author><author><name>Daniella Bradshaw</name></author><author><name>Constanza Salinas-Rebolledo</name></author><author><name>Niwanthi W. Rajapakse</name></author><author><name>Trent Munro</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Rojas-Fernandez</name></author><author><name>Paul R. Young</name></author><author><name>Katryn J Stacey</name></author><author><name>Alexander A. Khromykh</name></author><author><name>Keith J. Chappell</name></author><author><name>Daniel Watterson</name></author><author><name>Trent M. Woodruff</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Coronavirus disease-2019 (COVID-19) is primarily a respiratory disease, however, an increasing number of reports indicate that SARS-CoV-2 infection can also cause severe neurological manifestations, including precipitating cases of probable Parkinson’s disease. As microglial NLRP3 inflammasome activation is a major driver of neurodegeneration, here we interrogated whether SARS-CoV-2 can promote microglial NLRP3 inflammasome activation utilising a model of human monocyte-derived microglia. We identified that SARS-CoV-2 isolates can bind and enter microglia, triggering inflammasome activation in the absence of viral replication. Mechanistically, microglial NLRP3 could be both primed and activated with SARS-CoV-2 spike glycoprotein in a NF-κB and ACE2-dependent manner. Notably, virus- and spike protein-mediated inflammasome activation in microglia was significantly enhanced in the presence of α-synuclein fibrils, which was entirely ablated by NLRP3-inhibition. These results support a possible mechanism of microglia activation by SARS-CoV-2, which could explain the increased vulnerability to developing neurological symptoms akin to Parkinson’s disease in certain COVID-19 infected individuals, and a potential therapeutic avenue for intervention.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SIGNIFICANCE STATEMENT&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) principally affects the lungs, however there is evidence that the virus can also reach the brain and lead to chronic neurological symptoms. In this study, we examined the interaction SARS-CoV-2 with brain immune cells, by using an ex-vivo model of human monocyte-derived microglia. We identified robust activation of the innate immune sensor complex, NLRP3 inflammasome, in cells exposed to SARS-CoV-2. This was dependent on spike protein-ACE2 receptor interaction and was potentiated in the presence of α-synuclein. We therefore identify a possible mechanism for SARS-CoV-2 and increased vulnerability to developing neurological dysfunction. These findings support a potential therapeutic avenue for treatment of SARS-CoV-2 driven neurological manifestations, through use of NLRP3 inflammasome or ACE2 inhibitors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475947" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 drives NLRP3 inflammasome activation in human microglia through spike-ACE2 receptor interaction (28 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.22269008</id><title>Hydroxychloroquine/Chloroquine for the Treatment of Hospitalized Patients with COVID-19: An Individual Participant Data Meta-Analysis (26 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.347286+00:00</updated><author><name>Leon Di Stefano</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth L. Ogburn</name></author><author><name>Malathi Ram</name></author><author><name>Daniel O. Scharfstein</name></author><author><name>Tianjing Li</name></author><author><name>Preeti Khanal</name></author><author><name>Sheriza N. Baksh</name></author><author><name>Nichol McBee</name></author><author><name>Joshua Gruber</name></author><author><name>Marianne R. Gildea</name></author><author><name>Neil A. Goldenberg</name></author><author><name>Yussef Bennani</name></author><author><name>Samuel M. Brown</name></author><author><name>Whitney R. Buckel</name></author><author><name>Meredith E. Clement</name></author><author><name>Mark J. Mulligan</name></author><author><name>Jane A. O’Halloran</name></author><author><name>Adriana M. Rauseo</name></author><author><name>Wesley H. Self</name></author><author><name>Matthew W. Semler</name></author><author><name>Todd Seto</name></author><author><name>Jason E. Stout</name></author><author><name>Robert J. Ulrich</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Victory</name></author><author><name>Barbara E. Bierer</name></author><author><name>Daniel F. Hanley</name></author><author><name>Daniel Freilich</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Results from observational studies and randomized clinical trials (RCTs) have led to the consensus that hydroxychloroquine (HCQ) and chloroquine (CQ) are not effective for COVID-19 prevention or treatment. Pooling individual participant data (IPD), including unanalyzed data from trials terminated early, enables further investigation of the efficacy and safety of HCQ/CQ.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To assess efficacy of HCQ/CQ in patients hospitalized with COVID-19, both overall and in prespecified subgroups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data Sources&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov"&gt;ClinicalTrials.gov&lt;/ext-link&gt; was searched multiple times in May-June 2020. Principal investigators of US-based RCTs evaluating HCQ/CQ in hospitalized COVID-19 patients were invited to collaborate in this IPD meta-analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Study Selection&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;RCTs in which: (1) HCQ/CQ was a treatment arm; (2) patient informed consent and/or individual study IRB approval allowed for data sharing; (3) principal investigators/their institutions signed a data use agreement for the present study; and (4) the outcomes defined in this study were recorded or could be extrapolated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data Extraction and Synthesis&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wherever possible, harmonized de-identified data were collected via a common template spreadsheet sent to each principal investigator, then shared via a secure online data sharing platform to create a pooled data set. When this was not possible, individual study data were harmonized and merged manually. Data were analyzed by fitting a prespecified Bayesian ordinal regression model and standardizing the resulting predictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Outcome(s) and Measure(s)&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;7-point ordinal scale, measured between day 28 and 35 post-enrollment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eight of 19 trials met eligibility criteria and agreed to participate. Patient-level data were available from 770 participants (412 HCQ/CQ vs 358 control). Baseline characteristics were similar between groups. We found no evidence of a difference in ordinal scores between days 28 and 35 post-enrollment in the pooled patient population (odds ratio, 0.97; 95% credible interval, 0.76-1.24; higher favors HCQ/CQ), and no convincing evidence of meaningful treatment effect heterogeneity among prespecified subgroups. Adverse event and serious adverse event rates were numerically higher with HCQ/CQ vs control (0.39 vs 0.29 and 0.13 vs 0.09 per patient, respectively).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions and Relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The findings of this IPD meta-analysis reinforce those of individual RCTs that HCQ/CQ is not efficacious for treatment of COVID-19 in hospitalized patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key Points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Question&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Does hydroxychloroquine/chloroquine benefit hospitalized patients with COVID-19, overall or within prespecified subgroups?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this individual participant data meta-analysis of 770 hospitalized COVID-19 patients across 8 clinical trials, we did not find evidence of a benefit of hydroxychloroquine/chloroquine, measured by a 7-point ordinal COVID-19 severity score at 28-35 days post-enrollment, in the pooled study population. We also found no substantial treatment effect heterogeneity among prespecified patient subgroups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Meaning&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study supports the consensus that hydroxychloroquine/chloroquine should not be used to treat hospitalized patients with COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.22269008" rel="alternate" title="Hydroxychloroquine/Chloroquine for the Treatment of Hospitalized Patients with COVID-19: An Individual Participant Data Meta-Analysis (26 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22269097</id><title>High-cited favorable studies for COVID-19 treatments ineffective in large trials (21 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.347453+00:00</updated><author><name>John P.A. Ioannidis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Importance. COVID-19 has resulted in massive production, publication and wide dissemination of clinical studies trying to identify effective treatments. However, several widely touted treatments failed to show effectiveness in large well-done randomized controlled trials (RCTs). 
Objective. To evaluate for COVID-19 treatments that showed no benefits in subsequent large RCTs how many of their most-cited clinical studies had declared favorable results for these interventions. 
Methods. Scopus (last update December 23, 2021) identified articles on lopinavir-ritonavir, hydroxycholoroquine/azithromycin, remdesivir, convalescent plasma, colchicine or interferon (index interventions) that represented clinical trials and that had received &amp;gt;150 citations. Their conclusions were assessed and correlated with study design features. The ten most recent citations for the most-cited article on each index intervention were examined on whether they were critical to the highly-cited study. Altmetric scores were also obtained. 
Findings. 40 articles of clinical studies on these index interventions had received &amp;gt;150 citations (7 exceeded 1,000 citations). 20/40 (50%) had favorable conclusions and 4 were equivocal. Highly-cited articles with favorable conclusions were rarely RCTs while those without favorable conclusions were mostly RCTs (3/20 vs 15/20, p=0.0003). Only 1 RCT with favorable conclusions had sample size &amp;gt;160. Citation counts correlated strongly with Altmetric scores, in particular news items. Only 9 (15%) of 60 recent citations to the most highly-cited studies with favorable or equivocal conclusions were critical to the highly-cited study. 
Conclusion. Many clinical studies with favorable conclusions for largely ineffective COVID-19 treatments are uncritically heavily cited and disseminated. Early observational studies and small randomized trials may cause spurious claims of effectiveness that get perpetuated.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22269097" rel="alternate" title="High-cited favorable studies for COVID-19 treatments ineffective in large trials (21 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475889</id><title>Favipiravir, umifenovir and camostat mesylate: a comparative study against SARS-CoV-2 (20 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.347510+00:00</updated><author><name>Mehnmet Altay Unal</name></author><author><name>Omur Besbinar</name></author><author><name>Hasan Nazir</name></author><author><name>Gokce Yagmur Summak</name></author><author><name>Fatma Bayrakdar</name></author><author><name>Lucia Gemma Delogu</name></author><author><name>Tambay Taskin</name></author><author><name>Sibel Aysil Ozkan</name></author><author><name>Kamil Can Akcali</name></author><author><name>Acelya Yilmazer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Since the first cases the coronavirus disease caused by SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19) reported in December 2019, worldwide continuous efforts have been placed both for the prevention and treatment of this infectious disease. As new variants of the virus emerge, the need for an effective antiviral treatment continues. The concept of preventing SARS-CoV-2 on both pre-entry and post-entry stages has not been much studied. Therefore, we compared the antiviral activities of three antiviral drugs which have been currently used in the clinic. In silico docking analyses and in vitro viral infection in Vero E6 cells were performed to delineate their antiviral effectivity when used alone or in combination. Both in silico and in vitro results suggest that the combinatorial treatment by favipiravir and umifenovir or camostat mesylate has more antiviral activity against SARS-CoV-2 rather than single drug treatment. These results suggest that inhibiting both viral entry and viral replication at the same time is much more effective for the antiviral treatment of SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475889" rel="alternate" title="Favipiravir, umifenovir and camostat mesylate: a comparative study against SARS-CoV-2 (20 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475722</id><title>UV-C light completely blocks highly contagious Delta SARS-CoV-2 aerosol transmission in hamsters (18 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.347602+00:00</updated><author><name>Robert J. Fischer</name></author><author><name>Julia R. Port</name></author><author><name>Myndi G. Holbrook</name></author><author><name>Kwe Claude Yinda</name></author><author><name>Martin Creusen</name></author><author><name>Jeroen ter Stege</name></author><author><name>Marc de Samber</name></author><author><name>Vincent J. Munster</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Behavioral and medical control measures are not effective in containing the spread of SARS-CoV-2. Here we report on the effectiveness of a preemptive environmental strategy using UV-C light to prevent airborne transmission of the virus in a hamster model and show that UV-C exposure completely prevents airborne transmission between individuals&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475722" rel="alternate" title="UV-C light completely blocks highly contagious Delta SARS-CoV-2 aerosol transmission in hamsters (18 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476120</id><title>An antibody targeting the N-terminal domain of SARS-CoV-2 disrupts the spike trimer (18 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.347684+00:00</updated><author><name>Naveenchandra Suryadevara</name></author><author><name>Andrea R. Shiakolas</name></author><author><name>Laura A. VanBlargan</name></author><author><name>Elad Binshtein</name></author><author><name>Rita E. Chen</name></author><author><name>James Brett Case</name></author><author><name>Kevin J. Kramer</name></author><author><name>Erica Armstrong</name></author><author><name>Luke Myers</name></author><author><name>Andrew Trivette</name></author><author><name>Christopher Gainza</name></author><author><name>Rachel S. Nargi</name></author><author><name>Christopher N. Selverian</name></author><author><name>Edgar Davidson</name></author><author><name>Benjamin J. Doranz</name></author><author><name>Summer M. Diaz</name></author><author><name>Laura S. Handal</name></author><author><name>Robert H. Carnahan</name></author><author><name>Michael S. Diamond</name></author><author><name>Ivelin S. Georgiev</name></author><author><name>James E. Crowe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The protective human antibody response to the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) virus focuses on the spike (S) protein which decorates the virion surface and mediates cell binding and entry. Most SARS-CoV-2 protective antibodies target the receptor- binding domain or a single dominant epitope (‘supersite’) on the N terminal domain (NTD). Here, using the single B cell technology LIBRA-seq, we isolated a large panel of NTD-reactive and SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibodies from an individual who had recovered from COVID-19. We found that neutralizing antibodies to the NTD supersite commonly are encoded by the &lt;italic&gt;IGHV1-24&lt;/italic&gt; gene, forming a genetic cluster that represents a public B cell clonotype. However, we also discovered a rare human antibody, COV2-3434, that recognizes a site of vulnerability on the SARS-CoV-2 S protein in the trimer interface and possesses a distinct class of functional activity. COV2-3434 disrupted the integrity of S protein trimers, inhibited cell-to-cell spread of virus in culture, and conferred protection in human ACE2 transgenic mice against SARS-CoV-2 challenge. This study provides insight about antibody targeting of the S protein trimer interface region, suggesting this region may be a site of virus vulnerability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476120" rel="alternate" title="An antibody targeting the N-terminal domain of SARS-CoV-2 disrupts the spike trimer (18 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22268736</id><title>COVID-19 vaccination breakthrough infections in a real-world setting: Using community reporters to evaluate vaccine effectiveness (17 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.347817+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew W Reynolds</name></author><author><name>Yiqiong Xie</name></author><author><name>Kendall B Knuth</name></author><author><name>Christina D Mack</name></author><author><name>Emma Brinkley</name></author><author><name>Stephen Toovey</name></author><author><name>Nancy A Dreyer</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 has highlighted the need for new methods of pharmacovigilance. Here we use community volunteers to obtain systematic information on vaccine effectiveness and the nature and severity of breakthrough infections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Between December 15, 2020 to September 16, 2021, 10,412 unpaid community-based participants reported the following information to an on-line registry: COVID-19 test results, vaccination (Pfizer, Moderna, or Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson), COVID-19 symptoms and perceived severity using a 4-point scale. COVID-19 infections were described for those who were 1) fully vaccinated, 2) partially vaccinated (received first of two dose vaccines or were &amp;lt;14 days post-final dose), or 3) unvaccinated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of 8,554 who were vaccinated, COVID-19 infections were reported by 74 (1.0%) of those who were fully vaccinated and 198 (2.3%) of those who were partially vaccinated. Among the 74 participants who reported a breakthrough infection after full vaccination, the median time to reported positive test result was 104.5 days (Interquartile range: 77-135 days), with no difference among vaccine manufactures. One quarter (25.7%) of breakthrough infections in the fully vaccinated cases were asymptomatic. More than 97% of fully vaccinated participants reported no moderate/severe symptoms compared to 89.3% of the unvaccinated cases; and only 1.4% of fully vaccinated participants reported experiencing at least 3 moderate to severe symptoms compared to 7.8% in the unvaccinated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Person-generated health data, also referred to as patient-reported outcomes, is a useful resource for quantifying breakthrough infections and their severity, showing here that fully vaccinated participants report no or very mild COVID-19 symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Trial registration&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Clinicaltrials.gov"&gt;Clinicaltrials.gov&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT04368065"&gt;NCT04368065&lt;/ext-link&gt;, EU PAS Register EUPAS36240&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22268736" rel="alternate" title="COVID-19 vaccination breakthrough infections in a real-world setting: Using community reporters to evaluate vaccine effectiveness (17 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.22269234</id><title>Increased airborne transmission of COVID-19 with new variants. Implications for health policies. (17 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.347896+00:00</updated><author><name>Bertrand R Rowe</name></author><author><name>Andre Canosa</name></author><author><name>Amina Meslem</name></author><author><name>Frantz Rowe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The aim of the present paper is to highlight that new variants, either of higher viral load such as delta or higher contagiousness like omicron, lead to an even higher airborne transmission than historical strains. We first review the question of the route of contamination and of the dose following exposure, and the importance of the counting unit for pathogens, itself linked to the dose-response law. Using the counting unit of Wells, i.e. the quantum of contagium, we develop the conservation equation of quanta which allows deriving the value of the quantum concentration at steady state for a well-mixed room. With the choice of an exponential response function, this leads to the famous Wells-Riley equation. The analysis points out the importance of a number of parameters such as the time of exposure, the quantum production rate, mask wearing and the incidence rate in the population in order to evaluate the risk. The link with the monitoring concentration of carbon dioxide is made and used for a risk analysis of a variety of situations for which we have made concrete CO2 time monitoring. The main conclusion of these observations is that the present norms of ventilation, already insufficient, are not respected, especially in a variety of public premises, leading to high risk of contamination. Finally, we insist that public health policy in the field of airborne transmission should be based on a multi parameter analysis, considering the whole complexity of dose evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.22269234" rel="alternate" title="Increased airborne transmission of COVID-19 with new variants. Implications for health policies. (17 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476352</id><title>A semi-supervised Bayesian mixture modelling approach for joint batch correction and classification (15 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.347963+00:00</updated><author><name>Stephen Coleman</name></author><author><name>Xaquin Castro Dopico</name></author><author><name>Gunilla B. Karlsson Hedestam</name></author><author><name>Paul D.W. Kirk</name></author><author><name>Chris Wallace</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Systematic differences between batches of samples present significant challenges when analysing biological data. Such &lt;italic&gt;batch effects&lt;/italic&gt; are well-studied and are liable to occur in any setting where multiple batches are assayed. Many existing methods for accounting for these have focused on high-dimensional data such as RNA-seq and have assumptions that reflect this. Here we focus on batch-correction in low-dimensional classification problems. We propose a semi-supervised Bayesian generative classifier based on mixture models that jointly predicts class labels and models batch effects. Our model allows observations to be probabilistically assigned to classes in a way that incorporates uncertainty arising from batch effects. We explore two choices for the within-class densities: the multivariate normal and the multivariate &lt;italic&gt;t&lt;/italic&gt;. A simulation study demonstrates that our method performs well compared to popular off-the-shelf machine learning methods and is also quick; performing 15,000 iterations on a dataset of 500 samples with 2 measurements each in 7.3 seconds for the MVN mixture model and 11.9 seconds for the MVT mixture model. We apply our model to two datasets generated using the enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA), a spectrophotometric assay often used to screen for antibodies. The examples we consider were collected in 2020 and measure seropositivity for SARS-CoV-2. We use our model to estimate seroprevalence in the populations studied. We implement the models in C++ using a Metropolis-within-Gibbs algorithm; this is available in the R package at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/stcolema/BatchMixtureModel"&gt;https://github.com/stcolema/BatchMixtureModel&lt;/ext-link&gt;. Scripts to recreate our analysis are at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/stcolema/BatchClassifierPaper"&gt;https://github.com/stcolema/BatchClassifierPaper&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476352" rel="alternate" title="A semi-supervised Bayesian mixture modelling approach for joint batch correction and classification (15 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.22269318</id><title>Implementation of a Rapid RT-LAMP Saliva-based SARS-CoV-2 Testing Program in the Workplace (13 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.348033+00:00</updated><author><name>Bradley W.M. Cook</name></author><author><name>Kaitlyn Kobasa</name></author><author><name>Marielou Tamayo</name></author><author><name>Natasha Theriault</name></author><author><name>Diane J.R. Gordon Pappas</name></author><author><name>Steven S. Theriault</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Rising SARS-CoV-2 cases, testing delays and the risk of pre-symptomatic and asymptomatic transmission provided the impetus for an in-house rapid testing pro-gram. Employees and their household contacts were encouraged to self-collect saliva samples which were pooled for routine testing using an established colorimetric reverse transcription loop-mediated isothermal amplification (RT-LAMP) assay. In brief, individual or a maximum of four saliva samples were pooled, heat-inactivated to render microorganisms, especially SARS-CoV-2, non-infectious prior to being added to RT-LAMP assay tubes containing either human sample control gene, RNase P or a region of the SARS-CoV-2 gene, ORF1ab. During the second wave of SARS-CoV-2 infections in November 2020, two samples from an employee and a member of their household tested positive via RT-LAMP within two days of each other. A delayed clinical qRT-PCR test confirmation of both individuals 5 days later underscores the power of routine rapid testing with within-the-hour turnaround times. Workplace rapid testing programs using RT-LAMP are flexible in their design, have a reduced cost compared to qRT-PCR, may involve non-invasive self-saliva collection for increased safety for the testing personnel, and can be performed with minimal training.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.22269318" rel="alternate" title="Implementation of a Rapid RT-LAMP Saliva-based SARS-CoV-2 Testing Program in the Workplace (13 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476159</id><title>In vitro Kinase-to-Phosphosite database (iKiP-DB) predicts kinase activity in phosphoproteomic datasets (13 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.348108+00:00</updated><author><name>Tommaso Mari</name></author><author><name>Kristin Moesbauer</name></author><author><name>Emanuel Wyler</name></author><author><name>Markus Landthaler</name></author><author><name>Christian Drosten</name></author><author><name>Matthias Selbach</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Phosphoproteomics routinely quantifies changes in the levels of thousands of phosphorylation sites, but functional analysis of such data remains a major challenge. While databases like PhosphoSitePlus contain information about many phosphorylation sites, the vast majority of known sites are not assigned to any protein kinase. Assigning changes in the phosphoproteome to the activity of individual kinases therefore remains a key challenge.. A recent large-scale study systematically identified in vitro substrates for most human protein kinases. Here, we reprocessed and filtered these data to generate an in vitro Kinase-to-Phosphosite database (iKiP-DB). We show that iKiP-DB can accurately predict changes in kinase activity in published phosphoproteomic datasets for both well-studied and poorly characterized kinases. We apply iKiP-DB to a newly generated phosphoproteomic analysis of SARS-CoV-2 infected human lung epithelial cells and provide evidence for coronavirus-induced changes in host cell kinase activity. In summary, we show that iKiP-DB is widely applicable to facilitate the functional analysis of phosphoproteomic datasets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476159" rel="alternate" title="In vitro Kinase-to-Phosphosite database (iKiP-DB) predicts kinase activity in phosphoproteomic datasets (13 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22269069</id><title>Hydroxychloroquine/Chloroquine in COVID-19 With Focus on Hospitalized Patients - A Systematic Review (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.348182+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Freilich</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Victory</name></author><author><name>Anne Gadomski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background
In the beginning of the COVID-19 pandemic, many hospitalized patients received empiric hydroxychloroquine/chloroquine (HC/CQ). Although some retrospective-observational trials suggested potential benefit, all subsequent randomized clinical trials (RCTs) failed to show benefit and use generally ceased. Herein, we summarize key studies that clinicians advising patients on HC/CQ efficacy:safety calculus in hospitalized COVID-19 patients would want to know about in a practical one-stop-shopping source.

Methods
Pubmed and Google were searched on November 4, 2021. Search words included: COVID-19, hydroxychloroquine, chloroquine, in vitro, animal studies, clinical trials, and meta-analyses. Studies were assessed for import and included if considered impactful for benefit:risk assessment.

Results
These searches led to inclusion of 12 in vitro and animal reports; 12 retrospective-observational trials, 19 interventional clinical trials (17 RCTs, 1 single-arm, 1 controlled but unblinded), and 51 meta-analyses in hospitalized patients.
Inconsistent efficacy was seen in vitro and in animal studies for coronaviruses and nil in SARS-CoV-2 animal models specifically. Most retrospective-observational studies in hospitalized COVID-19 patients found no efficacy; QT prolongation and increased adverse events and mortality were reported in some. All RCTs and almost all meta-analyses provided robust data showing no benefit in overall populations and subgroups, yet concerning safety issues in many.

Conclusions
HC/CQ have inconsistent anti-coronavirus efficacy in vitro and in animal models, and no convincing efficacy yet substantial safety issues in the overwhelming majority of retrospective-observational trials, RCTs, and meta-analyses in hospitalized COVID-19 patients. HC/CQ should not be prescribed for hospitalized COVID-19 patients outside of clinical trials.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22269069" rel="alternate" title="Hydroxychloroquine/Chloroquine in COVID-19 With Focus on Hospitalized Patients - A Systematic Review (11 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.22269295</id><title>Simple risk scores to predict hospitalization or death in outpatients with COVID-19 (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.348245+00:00</updated><author><name>Mark H. Ebell</name></author><author><name>Roya Hamadani</name></author><author><name>Autumn Kieber-Emmons</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Outpatient physicians need guidance to support their clinical decisions regarding management of patients with COVID-19, in particular whether to hospitalize a patient and if managed as an outpatient, how closely to follow them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To develop and prospectively validate a clinical prediction rule to predict the likelihood of hospitalization for outpatients with COVID-19 that does not require laboratory testing or imaging.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Derivation and temporal validation of a clinical prediction rule, and prospective validation of two externally derived clinical prediction rules.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Primary and Express care clinics in a Pennsylvania health system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients 12 years and older presenting to outpatient clinics who had a positive polymerase chain reaction test for COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main outcomes and measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Classification accuracy (percentage in each risk group hospitalized) and area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUC).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overall, 7.4% of outpatients in the early derivation cohort (5843 patients presenting before 3/1/21) and 5.5% in the late validation cohort (3806 patients presenting 3/1/21 or later) were ultimately hospitalized. We developed and temporally validated three risk scores that all included age, dyspnea, and the presence of comorbidities, adding respiratory rate for the second score and oxygen saturation for the third. All had very good overall accuracy (AUC 0.77 to 0.78) and classified over half of patients in the validation cohort as very low risk with a 1.7% or lower likelihood of hospitalization. Two externally derived risk scores identified more low risk patients, but with a higher overall risk of hospitalization (2.8%).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions and relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Simple risk scores applicable to outpatient and telehealth settings can identify patients with very low (1.6% to 1.7%), low (5.2% to 5.9%), moderate (14.7% to 15.6%), and high risk (32.0% to 34.2%) of hospitalization. The Lehigh Outpatient COVID Hospitalization (LOCH) risk score is available online as a free app: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ebell-projects.shinyapps.io/LehighRiskScore/"&gt;https://ebell-projects.shinyapps.io/LehighRiskScore/&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.22269295" rel="alternate" title="Simple risk scores to predict hospitalization or death in outpatients with COVID-19 (10 tweets)"/><category term="Primary Care Research"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.22268948</id><title>Algorithmic Fairness and Bias Mitigation for Clinical Machine Learning: Insights from Rapid COVID-19 Diagnosis by Adversarial Learning (9 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.348308+00:00</updated><author><name>Jenny Yang</name></author><author><name>Andrew AS Soltan</name></author><author><name>Yang Yang</name></author><author><name>David A Clifton</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Machine learning is becoming increasingly promi-
nent in healthcare. Although its benefits are clear, growing attention is being given to how machine learning may exacerbate existing biases and disparities. In this study, we introduce an
adversarial training framework that is capable of mitigating biases that may have been acquired through data collection or magnified during model development. For example, if one class is
over-presented or errors/inconsistencies in practice are reflected in the training data, then a model can be biased by these. To evaluate our adversarial training framework, we used the statistical definition of equalized odds. We evaluated our model for the task of rapidly predicting COVID-19 for patients presenting to
hospital emergency departments, and aimed to mitigate regional (hospital) and ethnic biases present. We trained our framework on a large, real-world COVID-19 dataset and demonstrated that
adversarial training demonstrably improves outcome fairness (with respect to equalized odds), while still achieving clinically-effective
screening performances (NPV&amp;gt;0.98). We compared our method to the benchmark set by related previous work, and performed prospective and external validation on four independent hospital
cohorts. Our method can be generalized to any outcomes, models, and definitions of fairness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.22268948" rel="alternate" title="Algorithmic Fairness and Bias Mitigation for Clinical Machine Learning: Insights from Rapid COVID-19 Diagnosis by Adversarial Learning (9 tweets)"/><category term="Health Informatics"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22269065</id><title>The incidence and mortality of COVID-19 related TB infection in Sub-Saharan Africa: A systematic review and meta-analysis (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.348375+00:00</updated><author><name>Jacques L Tamuzi</name></author><author><name>Gomer Lulendo</name></author><author><name>Patrick Mbuesse</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) is also associated with other co-morbidities among with previous and current pulmonary tuberculosis (PTB). PTB is a risk factor for COVID-19, both in terms of severity and mortality, regardless of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) status. However, there is less information available on COVID-19 associated with PTB in point of view incidence and mortality rates in sub-Saharan Africa (SSA) as a high burden TB region. This systematic review served to provide data synthesis of available evidence on COVID-19/PTB incidence and case fatality rates, and mortality rate found in clinical and post-mortem COVID-19/PTB diagnostics in SSA.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted a systematic electronic search in the PubMed, Medline, Google Scholar, Medrxix and COVID-19 Global literature on coronavirus disease databases for studies including COVID-19 associated with PTB in sub-Saharan Africa. The main outcomes were the proportion of people with COVID-19 associated to current /or previous PTB and the case fatality associated to COVID-19/PTB. The combination method was based on methodological similarities in the included random effect model studies using Prometa 3 software. We further undertook sensitivity analysis and meta-regression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;From the 548 references extracted by the literature search, 25 studies were selected and included in the meta-analysis with a total of 191, 250 COVID-19 infected patients and 11, 452 COVID-19 deaths. The pooled COVID-19/PTB incidence was 2% [1%-3%] and mortality of 10% [4%-20%]. The pooled estimates for case fatality rate among COVID-19/PTB were 6% [3%-11%] for clinical PTB diagnostic and 26% [14%-48%] for post-mortem PTB diagnostic. Meta-regression model including the effect sizes and cumulative COVID-19 cases (P= 0.032), HIV prevalence (P= 0.041) and TB incidence (P= 0.002) to explained high heterogeneity between studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a summary, the incidence of TB associated with COVID-19 and case fatality rates are higher in SSA. However, COVID-19 associated to TB may be underreported in the studies conducted in SSA as the post-mortem TB diagnostic was higher. Large-scale cohort studies that adequately clear tool on previous and/or current TB diagnostic tools are required to confirmed COVID-19/TB incidence and case fatality in SSA.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Review registration&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;PROSPERO (CRD42021233387)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22269065" rel="alternate" title="The incidence and mortality of COVID-19 related TB infection in Sub-Saharan Africa: A systematic review and meta-analysis (8 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.22269022</id><title>A national survey of early treatment seeking behavior among those with incident SARS-CoV-2 infection (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.348437+00:00</updated><author><name>Noah Kojima</name></author><author><name>Matthew Brobeck</name></author><author><name>Vladimir Slepnev</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey D Klausner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Despite effective means to treat SARS-CoV-2 infection, the early treatment seeking behavior of those newly diagnosed with infection is not clear.
Methods: We surveyed users of a national SARS-CoV-2 testing company to assess the frequency and correlates of early treatment seeking behavior for a positive test result.
We recruited adults (18 years or older) who had tested positive for SARS-CoV-2 by PCR at a large clinical laboratory. To be eligible, individuals had to have a positive test result within 7 days of enrollment. Surveys were anonymous and voluntary. We collected data on demographic characteristics, general health care access and utilization, awareness of treatment for COVID-19, treatment seeking behavior, and treatments received. Descriptive statistics and odds ratios (OR) with 95% confidence intervals (95% CI) were calculated on StataSE.
Results: Participants were surveyed from 3-7 January 2022: among the 15,991 who viewed a survey request, 7,647 individuals were eligible and provided responses. The median age of a respondent was 42 years (interquartile range: 32 to 54), 68.9% of respondents were women, and respondents represented 33 different states, districts, and territories. Among respondents, 23.1% reported they had sought treatment or medical advice for their current COVID-19 diagnosis. Of those who were very aware of treatment for COVID-19, 31.0% sought treatment versus 16.7% who were unaware (p-value&amp;lt; 0.001). The odds of treatment seeking behavior were higher for those that were contacted by a medical professional after their diagnosis (OR: 4.57 [95% CI: 3.89 to 5.37]), those with a primary doctor (OR: 2.94 [95% CI: 2.52 to 3.43]), those who self-measured their oxygen saturation (OR: 2.53 [95% CI: 2.25 to 2.84]), and those over 65 years of age (OR: 2.36 [95% CI: 2.02 to 2.76]). There was no difference in those seeking treatment based on heritage, ethnicity, prior COVID-19 diagnosis, state political affiliation, or vaccination status. The odds of seeking treatment were lower among men (OR: 0.88 [95% CI: 0.78 to 0.99]) and those without insurance (OR: 0.62 [95% CI: 0.52 to 0.72]). The most common treatment locations were clinics and most common treatments were Vitamin C, Vitamin D, Zinc, Tylenol, and NSAIDs.
Conclusion: More public outreach is needed to raise awareness of the benefits of treatment for COVID-19. We found that people who were more aware about treatment for COVID-19 were more likely to seek medical advice or therapy. Efforts to increase awareness might increase early treatment for SARS-CoV-2 infection. Increased outreach with treatment facilitation from medical professionals and/or public health staff to those with newly detected SARS-CoV-2 infections, particularly among those at higher-risk of complications, might also be helpful.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.22269022" rel="alternate" title="A national survey of early treatment seeking behavior among those with incident SARS-CoV-2 infection (7 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475901</id><title>Effect of cannabidiol on apoptosis and cellular interferon and interferon-stimulated gene responses to the SARS-CoV-2 genes ORF8, ORF10 and M protein (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.348504+00:00</updated><author><name>Maria Fernanda Fernandes</name></author><author><name>John Zewen Chan</name></author><author><name>Chia Chun Joey Hung</name></author><author><name>Michelle Victoria Tomczewski</name></author><author><name>Robin Elaine Duncan</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aims&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To study effects on cellular innate immune responses to novel genes &lt;italic&gt;ORF8&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;ORF10,&lt;/italic&gt; and the more conserved &lt;italic&gt;Membrane protein&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;M protein&lt;/italic&gt;) from the Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) that causes COVID-19, either alone, or in combination with cannabidiol (CBD).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;HEK293 cells were transfected with a control plasmid, or plasmids expressing &lt;italic&gt;ORF8&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;ORF10&lt;/italic&gt;, or &lt;italic&gt;M protein&lt;/italic&gt;, and assayed for cell number and markers of apoptosis at 24 h, and expression of interferon and interferon-stimulated genes at 14 h.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A significant reduction in cell number, and increase in early and late apoptosis, was found after 24 h in cells where expression of viral genes was combined with 1-2 μM CBD treatment, but not in control-transfected cells treated with CBD, or in cells expressing viral genes but treated only with vehicle. CBD (2 μM) augmented expression of &lt;italic&gt;IFNγ&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;IFNλ1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;IFNλ2/3&lt;/italic&gt;, as well as the 2’-5’-oligoadenylate synthetase (OAS) family members &lt;italic&gt;OAS1&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;OAS2&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;OAS3&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;OASL,&lt;/italic&gt; in cells expressing &lt;italic&gt;ORF8&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;ORF10&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;M protein&lt;/italic&gt;. CBD also augmented expression of these genes in control cells not expressing viral genes, without enhancing apoptosis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our results demonstrate a poor ability of HEK293 cells to respond to SARS-CoV-2 genes alone, but suggest an augmented innate anti-viral response to these genes in the presence of CBD. Furthermore, our results indicate that CBD may prime components of the innate immune system, increasing readiness to respond to viral infection without activating apoptosis, and therefore could be studied for potential in prophylaxis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475901" rel="alternate" title="Effect of cannabidiol on apoptosis and cellular interferon and interferon-stimulated gene responses to the SARS-CoV-2 genes ORF8, ORF10 and M protein (7 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476223</id><title>ATP6V1B2 and IFI27 and their intrinsic functional genomic characteristics associated with SARS-CoV-2 (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.348608+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhengjun Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genes functionally associated with SARS-CoV-2 and genes functionally related to COVID-19 disease can be different, whose distinction will become the first essential step for successfully fighting against the COVID-19 pandemic. Unfortunately, this first step has not been completed in all biological and medical research. Using a newly developed max-competing logistic classifier, two genes, ATP6V1B2 and IFI27, stand out to be critical in transcriptional response to SARS-CoV-2 with differential expressions derived from NP/OP swab PCR. This finding is evidenced by combining these two genes with one another gene in predicting disease status to achieve better-indicating power than existing classifiers with the same number of genes. In addition, combining these two genes with three other genes to form a five-gene classifier outperforms existing classifiers with ten or more genes. With their exceptional predicting power, these two genes can be critical in fighting against the COVID-19 pandemic as a new focus and direction. Comparing the functional effects of these genes with a  five-gene classifier with 100% accuracy identified and tested from blood samples in the literature, genes and their transcriptional response and functional effects to SARS-CoV-2 and genes and their functional signature patterns to COVID-19 antibody are significantly different, which can be interpreted as the former is the point of a phenomenon, and the latter is the essence of the disease. Such significant findings can help explore the causal and pathological clue between SARS-CoV-2 and COVID-19 disease and fight against the disease with more targeted vaccines, antiviral drugs, and therapies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476223" rel="alternate" title="ATP6V1B2 and IFI27 and their intrinsic functional genomic characteristics associated with SARS-CoV-2 (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22269106</id><title>COVID-19 policies in practice and their direct and indirect impacts in Northern California jails (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.348665+00:00</updated><author><name>Yiran E. Liu</name></author><author><name>Christopher LeBoa</name></author><author><name>Marcela Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Beruk Sherif</name></author><author><name>Chrisele Trinidad</name></author><author><name>Michael del Rosario</name></author><author><name>Sophie Allen</name></author><author><name>Christine Clifford</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Redding</name></author><author><name>Wei-ting Chen</name></author><author><name>Lisa G. Rosas</name></author><author><name>Carlos Morales</name></author><author><name>Alexander Chyorny</name></author><author><name>Jason R. Andrews</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the increased risk of COVID-19 in carceral facilities is well documented, little is known about the practical barriers to infection control and indirect impacts of pandemic policies in these settings. Evidence in jails is especially scarce.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Between July 8, 2020 and April 30, 2021 we performed SARS-CoV-2 serology testing and administered a questionnaire among residents and staff in four Northern California jails. We analyzed seroprevalence in conjunction with demographic factors and survey responses of self-perceived COVID-19 risk, recent illness, COVID-19 test results, and symptom reporting behaviors. We additionally assessed COVID-19 policies in practice and evaluated their impacts on court dates, mental health, and routine health care. We engaged stakeholder representatives, including incarcerated individuals and their advocates, to guide study design, conduct, and interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We enrolled 788 incarcerated individuals and 380 staff across four county jails. Most seropositive individuals had not previously tested positive for COVID-19, despite many suspecting prior infection. Among incarcerated participants, we identified deficient access to face masks and prevalent symptom underreporting associated with fears of isolation and perceptions of medical neglect in jail. Incarcerated participants also reported substantial hindrances to court cases and reductions in routine health care due to COVID-19. Incarcerated individuals and staff both cited worsened mental health due to COVID-19, which for incarcerated individuals was largely attributable to further isolation from loved ones and other pandemic restrictions on recreation and programming.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Perceptions of inadequate protection from COVID-19 were pervasive among incarcerated individuals. Simultaneously, restrictive measures compounded poor mental health and fostered fears of isolation that undermined effective infection control. Custody officials should work to systematically improve provision of masks, understand and mitigate fears and mistrust, and take proactive steps to minimize the detrimental impacts of restrictive policies on residents’ mental health and well-being.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22269106" rel="alternate" title="COVID-19 policies in practice and their direct and indirect impacts in Northern California jails (6 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22269101</id><title>Racial/ethnic disparities in exposure to COVID-19, susceptibility to COVID-19 and access to health care - findings from a U.S. national cohort (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.348775+00:00</updated><author><name>McKaylee Robertson</name></author><author><name>Meghana Shamsunder</name></author><author><name>Ellen Brazier</name></author><author><name>Mekhala Mantravadi</name></author><author><name>Madhura S Rane</name></author><author><name>Drew A Westmoreland</name></author><author><name>Angela Parcesepe</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Zimba</name></author><author><name>Andrew R Maroko</name></author><author><name>Sarah Kulkarni</name></author><author><name>Christian Grov</name></author><author><name>Denis Nash</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We examined the influence of racial/ethnic differences in socioeconomic position on COVID-19 seroconversion and hospitalization within a community-based prospective cohort enrolled in March 2020 and followed through October 2021 (N=6740). The ability to social distance as a measure of exposure to COVID-19, susceptibility to COVID-19 complications, and access to healthcare varied by race/ethnicity with non-white participants having more exposure risk and more difficulty with healthcare access than white participants. Participants with more (versus less) exposure had greater odds of seroconversion (aOR:1.64, 95% Confidence Interval [CI] 1.18-2.29). Participants with more susceptibility and more barriers to healthcare had greater odds of hospitalization (respective aOR:2.36; 1.90-2.96 and 2.31; 1.69-2.68). Race/ethnicity positively modified the association between susceptibility and hospitalization (aORnon-White:2.79, 2.06-3.78). Findings may explain the disproportionate burden of COVID-19 infections and complications among Hispanic and non-Hispanic Black persons. Primary and secondary prevention efforts should address disparities in exposure, COVID-19 vaccination, and treatment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22269101" rel="alternate" title="Racial/ethnic disparities in exposure to COVID-19, susceptibility to COVID-19 and access to health care - findings from a U.S. national cohort (5 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476204</id><title>Covariance predicts conserved protein residue interactions important to the emergence and continued evolution of SARS-CoV-2 as a human pathogen (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.348873+00:00</updated><author><name>William P. Robins</name></author><author><name>John J. Mekalanos</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 is one of three recognized coronaviruses (CoVs) that have caused epidemics or pandemics in the 21st century and that likely emerged from animal reservoirs. Differences in nucleotide and protein sequence composition within related β-coronaviruses are often used to better understand CoV evolution, host adaptation, and their emergence as human pathogens. Here we report the comprehensive analysis of amino acid residue changes that have occurred in lineage B β-coronaviruses (sarbecoviruses) that show covariance with each other. This analysis revealed patterns of covariance within conserved viral proteins that potentially define conserved interactions within and between core proteins encoded by SARS-CoV-2 related β-coranaviruses. We identified not only individual pairs but also networks of amino acid residues that exhibited statistically high frequencies of covariance with each other using an independent pair model followed by a tandem model approach. Using 149 different CoV genomes that vary in their relatedness, we identified networks of unique combinations of alleles that can be incrementally traced genome by genome within different phylogenic lineages. Remarkably, covariant residues and their respective regions most abundantly represented are implicated in the emergence of SARS-CoV-2 and are also enriched in dominant SARS-CoV-2 variants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There currently are enormous international efforts to better understand the emergence of SARS-CoV-2 as a human pathogen and its persistence in the ongoing pandemic in various mutated forms. Most studies have focused on identifying presumptive gain-of-fitness mutations in core viral proteins. The contributions of residues unique to SARS-CoV-2 or those conserved in other β-coronaviruses are not yet understood. Also, the absence of an identified ancestral virus to SARS-CoV-2 prevents a continuous comparison-driven analysis within a lineage of other potential bat-, civet-, and human-adapted viruses such as SARS-CoV that may have similarly contributed to the emergence of SAR-CoV-2 through viral evolution and recombination. Here we identified unique amino acid residues that are found to be variable between distinct β-coronaviruses but are conserved in covariant pairs or networks of covariant residues within or between viral proteins. The relationships revealed are likely preserved in the evolutionary record because these covariant residues impose selective pressure on each other through direct or indirect interactions. The covariant residues we identified could play key roles in the emergence of SARS-CoV-2 as a human pathogen and its continued evolution in more recently emerged variants of clinical interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476204" rel="alternate" title="Covariance predicts conserved protein residue interactions important to the emergence and continued evolution of SARS-CoV-2 as a human pathogen (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.22269064</id><title>Evaluation and modelling of the performance of an automated SARS-CoV-2 antigen assay according to sample type, target population and epidemic trends (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.348932+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicolas Yin</name></author><author><name>Cyril Debuysschere</name></author><author><name>Valery Daubie</name></author><author><name>Marc Hildebrand</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Martin</name></author><author><name>Sonja Curac</name></author><author><name>Fanny Ponthieux</name></author><author><name>Marie-Christine Payen</name></author><author><name>Olivier Vandenberg</name></author><author><name>Marie Hallin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Lumipulse® G SARS-CoV-2 Ag assay performance was evaluated on prospectively collected saliva and nasopharyngeal swabs (NPS) of recently ill in- and outpatients and according to the estimated viral load. Performances were calculated using RT-PCR positive NPS from patients with symptoms ≤ 7 days and RT-PCR negative NPS as gold standard. In addition, non-selected positive NPS were analyzed to assess the performances on various viral loads. This assay yielded a sensitivity of 93.1% on NPS and 71.4% on saliva for recently ill patients. For NPS with a viral load &amp;gt; 103 RNA copies/mL, sensitivity was 96.4%. A model established on our daily routine showed fluctuations of the performances depending on the epidemic trends but an overall good negative predictive value. Lumipulse® G SARS-CoV-2 assay yielded good performance for an automated antigen detection assay on NPS. Using it for the detection of recently ill patient or to screen high-risk patients could be an interesting alternative to the more expensive RT-PCR.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.22269064" rel="alternate" title="Evaluation and modelling of the performance of an automated SARS-CoV-2 antigen assay according to sample type, target population and epidemic trends (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.21268270</id><title>Health and Economic Consequences of Universal Paid Sick Leave Policies During the COVID-19 Pandemic (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.349024+00:00</updated><author><name>David Naimark</name></author><author><name>Juan David Rios</name></author><author><name>Sharmistha Mishra</name></author><author><name>Beate Sander</name></author><author><name>Petros Pechlivanoglou</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Universal paid sick-leave (PSL) policies have been implemented in jurisdictions to mitigate the spread of SARS-CoV-2. However empirical data regarding health and economic consequences of PSL policies is scarce.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To estimate effects of a universal PSL policy in Ontario, Canada’s most populous province.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;An agent-based model (ABM) to simulate SARS-CoV-2 transmission informed by data from Statistics Canada, health administrative sources, and from the literature.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ontario from January 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; to May 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt;, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A synthetic population (1 million) with occupation and household characteristics representative of Ontario residents (14.5 million).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Exposure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A base case of existing employer-based PSL alone versus the addition of a 3-or 10-day universal PSL policy to facilitate testing and self-isolation among workers infected with SARS-CoV-2 themselves or because of infected household members.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Outcome(s) and Measure(s)&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Number of SARS-CoV-2 infections and COVID-19 hospitalizations, worker productivity, lost wages, and presenteeism (going to a workplace while infected).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;If a 3- and 10-day universal PSL were implemented over the 4-month study period, then compared with the base-case, the PSL policies were estimated to reduce cumulative SARS-CoV-2 cases by 85,531 (95% credible interval, CrI -2,484; 195,318) and 215,302 (81,500; 413,742), COVID-19 hospital admissions by 1,307 (-201; 3,205) and 3,352 (1,223; 6,528), numbers of workers forgoing wages by 558 (-327;1,608) and 7,406 (6,764; 8,072), and numbers of workers engaged in presenteeism by 24,499 (216; 54,170) and 279,863 (262,696; 295,449). Hours of productivity loss were estimated to be 10,854,379 (10,212,304; 11,465,635) in the base case, 17,446,525 (15,934,321; 18,854,683) in the 3-day scenario, and 26,127,165 (20,047,239; 29,875,161) in the 10-day scenario. Lost wages were $5,256,316 ($4,077,280; $6,804,983) and $12,610,962 ($11,463,128; $13,724,664) lower in the 3 day and 10 day scenarios respectively, relative to the base case.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions and Relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Expanded access to PSL is estimated to reduce total numbers of COVID-19 cases, reduce presenteeism of workers with SARS-CoV-2 at workplaces, and mitigate wage loss experienced by workers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Competing interests&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The authors have no competing interests relevant to this article to disclose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supported by COVID-19 Rapid Research Funding (C-291-2431272-SANDER). This research was further supported, in part, by a Canada Research Chair in Economics of Infectious Diseases held by Beate Sander (CRC-950-232429). The study sponsor had no role in the design, collection, analysis, interpretation of the data, manuscript preparation or the decision to submit for publication.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Contributions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Conceptualization: PP, JDR, BS, DN&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Data Curation: PP, JDR, BS, DN&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Formal Analysis: PP, JDR, DN&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Methodology: PP, JDR, BS, DN&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supervision: PP, DN, BS&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Validation: PP, JDR, BS, DN&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;First Draft: PP, JDR, BS, DN&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Review and Edit&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;PP, JDR, BS, DN&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Question&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;What could be the health and economic consequence of more generous paid sick leave policies in the context of the COVID-19 pandemic?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;More generous policies are estimated to reduce SARS-CoV-2 infections (and thus COVID-19 hospitalizations), lost wages and presence of individuals with infection at workplaces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Meaning&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;More generous paid sick leave can be a valuable addition to other COVID-19 public health interventions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.21268270" rel="alternate" title="Health and Economic Consequences of Universal Paid Sick Leave Policies During the COVID-19 Pandemic (4 tweets)"/><category term="Health Economics"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.22269182</id><title>Immunosuppression impaired the immunogenicity of inactivated SARS-CoV-2 vaccine in non-dialysis kidney disease patients (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.349095+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuemiao Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xingzi Liu</name></author><author><name>Miaomiao Lin</name></author><author><name>Jincan Zan</name></author><author><name>Yitong Hu</name></author><author><name>Xiangqiu Wang</name></author><author><name>Wenqi Wu</name></author><author><name>Taicheng Zhou</name></author><author><name>Hong Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jicheng Lv</name></author><author><name>Li Yang</name></author><author><name>Zijie Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Patients with chronic kidney disease (CKD) are at higher risk for coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19)-related morbidity and mortality. However, a significant portion of CKD patients showed hesitation toward vaccination in telephone survey of our center. Yet no serial data available on humoral response in patients with CKD, especially those on immunosuppression. We conducted a pilot, prospective study to survey the safety and humoral response to inactivated SARS-CoV-2 vaccine in CKD patients receiving a 2-dose immunization of inactivated SARS-CoV-2 vaccine. We found the neutralizing antibody titers in CKD patients was significantly lower than that in healthy controls, hypertension patients, and diabetes patients. Notably, immunosuppressive medication rather than eGFR levels or disease types  showed effect on the reduction of immunogenicity. Interestingly, a third dose significantly boosted neutralizing antibody in CKD patients while immunosuppressants impeded the boosting effects. In conclusion, our data demonstrates that CKD patients, even for those on immunosuppression treatment, can benefit from a third vaccination boost by improving their humoral immunity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.22269182" rel="alternate" title="Immunosuppression impaired the immunogenicity of inactivated SARS-CoV-2 vaccine in non-dialysis kidney disease patients (4 tweets)"/><category term="Nephrology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.22269373</id><title>The statistical analysis of daily data associated with different parameters of the New Coronavirus COVID-19 pandemic in Georgia and their monthly interval prediction from September 1, 2021 to December 31, 2021 (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.349209+00:00</updated><author><name>Avtandil G. Amiranashvili</name></author><author><name>Ketevan R. Khazaradze</name></author><author><name>Nino D. Japaridze</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The lockdown introduced in Georgia on November 28, 2020 contributed to positive trends in the spread of COVID-19 until February - the first half of March 2021. Then, in April-May 2021, the epidemiological situation worsened significantly, and from June to the end of December COVID - situation in Georgia was very difficult. 
	In this work results of the next statistical analysis of the daily data associated with New Coronavirus COVID-19 infection of confirmed (C), recovered (R), deaths (D) and infection rate (I) cases of the population of Georgia in the period from September 01, 2021 to December 31, 2021 are presented. It also presents the results of the analysis of monthly forecasting of the values of C, D and I. As earlier, the information was regularly sent to the National Center for Disease Control &amp;amp; Public Health of Georgia and posted on the Facebook page https://www.facebook.com/Avtandil1948/.
The analysis of data is carried out with the use of the standard statistical analysis methods of random events and methods of mathematical statistics for the non-accidental time-series of observations. In particular, the following results were obtained.
Georgia's ranking in the world for Covid-19 monthly mean values of infection and deaths cases in investigation period (per 1 million population) was determined. Among 157 countries with population ≥ 1 million inhabitants in October 2021 Georgia was in the 4 place on new infection cases, and in September - in the 1 place on death. Georgia took the best place in terms of confirmed cases of diseases (thirteenth) in December, and in mortality (fifth) - in October.
A comparison between the daily mortality from Covid-19 in Georgia from September 01, 2021 to December 31, 2021with the average daily mortality rate in 2015-2019 shows, that the largest share value of D from mean death in 2015-2019 was 76.8 % (September 03, 2021), the smallest 18.7 % (November 10, 2021). 
As in previous work [9,10] the statistical analysis of the daily and decade data associated with coronavirus COVID-19 pandemic of confirmed, recovered, deaths cases and infection rate of the population of Georgia are carried out. Maximum daily values of investigation parameters are following: C = 6024 (November 3, 2021), R = 6017 (November 15, 2021), D = 86 (September 3, 2021), I = 12.04 % (November 24, 2021). Maximum mean decade values of investigation parameters are following: C = 4757 (1 Decade of November 2021), R = 4427 (3 Decade of November 2021), D = 76 (2 Decade of November 2021), I = 10.55 % (1 Decade of November 2021).
It was found that as in spring and summer 2021 [9,10], from September to December 2021 the regression equations for the time variability of the daily values of C, R, D and I have the form of a tenth order polynomial.
Mean values of speed of change of confirmed -V(C), recovered - V(R), deaths - V(D) and infection rate V(I) coronavirus-related cases in different decades of months for the indicated period of time were determined.  Maximum mean decade values of investigation parameters are following: V(C) = +139 cases/day (1 Decade of October 2021), V(R) = +124 cases/day (3 Decade of October 2021), V(D) = +1.7 cases/day (3 Decade of October 2021), V(I) = + 0.20 %/ day (1 decades of October 2021).
Cross-correlations analysis between confirmed COVID-19 cases with recovered and deaths cases shows, that from September 1, 2021 to November 30, 2021 the maximum effect of recovery is observed on 12 and 14 days after infection (CR=0.77 and 0.78 respectively), and deaths - after 7, 9, 11, 13 and 14 days (0.70≤CR≤0.72); from October 1, 2021 to December 31, 2021 -  the maximum effect of recovery is observed on 14 days after infection (RC=0.71), and deaths - after 9 days (CR=0.43). In Georgia from September 1, 2021 to November 30, 2021 the duration of the impact of the delta variant of the coronavirus on people (recovery, mortality) could be up to 28 and 35 days respectively; from October 1, 2021 to December 31, 2021 - up to 21 and 29 days respectively.
	Comparison of daily real and calculated monthly predictions data of C, D and I in Georgia are carried out. It was found that in investigation period of time daily and mean monthly real values of C, D and I practically fall into the 67% - 99.99% confidence interval of these predicted values.	
	Traditionally, the comparison of data about C and D in Georgia (GEO) with similar data in Armenia (ARM), Azerbaijan (AZE), Russia (RUS), Turkey (TUR) and in the World (WRL) is also carried out.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.22269373" rel="alternate" title="The statistical analysis of daily data associated with different parameters of the New Coronavirus COVID-19 pandemic in Georgia and their monthly interval prediction from September 1, 2021 to December 31, 2021 (4 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.22268980</id><title>HAT-field: a very cheap, robust and quantitative point-of-care serological test for Covid-19. (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.349273+00:00</updated><author><name>Etienne Joly</name></author><author><name>Agnes Maurel Ribes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We have recently described a very simple and cheap serological test called HAT to detect antibodies directed against the RBD of the SARS-Cov-2 virus. HAT is based on hemagglutination, triggered by a single reagent (IH4-RBD) comprised of the viral RBD domain fused to a nanobody specific for glycophorin, which is expressed at very high levels at the surface of human red blood cells (RBCs). 
One of the main initial goals of this study was to devise a test protocol that would be sensitive and reliable, yet require no specialized laboratory equipment such as adjustable pipets, so that it could be performed in the most remote corners of the world by people with minimal levels of training. Because antibody levels against the viral RBD have been found to correlate closely with sero-neutralisation titers, and thus with protection against reinfection, it has become obvious during the course of this study that making this test reliably quantitative would be a further significant advantage. 
We have found that, in PBN, a buffer which contains BSA and sodium azide, IH4-RBD is stable for over 6 months at room temperature, and that PBN also improves HAT performance compared to using straight PBS. We also show that performing HAT at either 4°C, room temperature or 37°C has minimal influence on the results, and that quantitative evaluation of the levels of antibodies directed against the SARS-CoV-2 RBD can be achieved in a single step using titration of the IH4-RBD reagent.
The HAT-field protocol described here requires only very simple disposable equipment and a few microliters of whole blood, such as can be obtained by finger prick. Because it is based on a single soluble reagent, the test can be adapted very simply and rapidly to detect antibodies against variants of the SARS-CoV-2, or conceivably against different pathogens.
HAT-field appears well suited to provide quantitative assessments of the serological protection of populations as well as individuals, and given its very low cost, the stability of the IH4-RBD reagent in the adapted buffer, and the simplicity of the procedure, could be deployed pretty much anywhere, including in the poorest countries and the most remote corners of the globe.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.22268980" rel="alternate" title="HAT-field: a very cheap, robust and quantitative point-of-care serological test for Covid-19. (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22269068</id><title>The impact of post-hospital remote monitoring of COVID-19 patients using pulse oximetry: a national observational study using hospital activity data (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.349333+00:00</updated><author><name>Theo Georghiou</name></author><author><name>Chris Sherlaw-Johnson</name></author><author><name>Efthalia Massou</name></author><author><name>Stephen Morris</name></author><author><name>Nadia E Crellin</name></author><author><name>Lauren Herlitz</name></author><author><name>Manbinder S Sidhu</name></author><author><name>Sonila M Tomini</name></author><author><name>Cecilia Vindrola-Padros</name></author><author><name>Holly Walton</name></author><author><name>Naomi J Fulop</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was a national roll out of ‘COVID Virtual Wards’ (CVW) during England’s second COVID-19 wave (Autumn 2020 – Spring 2021). These services used remote pulse oximetry monitoring for COVID-19 patients following discharge from hospital. A key aim was to enable rapid detection of patient deterioration. It was anticipated that the services would support early discharge and avoid readmissions, reducing pressure on beds. This study is an evaluation of the impact of the CVW services on hospital activity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using retrospective patient-level hospital admissions data, we built multivariate models to analyse the relationship between the implementation of CVW services and hospital activity outcomes: length of COVID-19 related stays and subsequent COVID-19 readmissions within 28 days. We used data from more than 98% of recorded COVID-19 hospital stays in England, where the patient was discharged alive between mid-August 2020 and late February 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found a longer length of stay for COVID-19 patients discharged from hospitals where a CVW was available, when compared to patients discharged from hospitals where there was no CVW (adjusted IRR 1·05, 95% CI 1·01 to 1·09). We found no evidence of a relationship between the availability of CVW and subsequent rates of readmission for COVID-19 (adjusted OR 0·95, 95% CI 0·89 to 1·02).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found no evidence of early discharges or reduced readmissions associated with the roll out of COVID Virtual Wards across England. Our analysis made pragmatic use of national-scale hospital data, but it is possible that a lack of specific data (for example, on which patients were enrolled) may have meant that true impacts, especially at a local level, were not ultimately discernible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is independent research funded by the National Institute for Health Research, Health Services &amp;amp; Delivery Research programme and NHSEI.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Research in context&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Evidence before this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Post-hospital virtual wards have been found to have a positive impact on patient outcomes when focussed on patients with specific diseases, for example those with heart disease. There has been less evidence of impact for more heterogenous groups of patients. While these services have been rolled out at scale in England, there has been little evidence thus far that post-hospital virtual wards (using pulse oximetry monitoring) have helped to reduce the length of stay of hospitalised COVID-19 patients, or rates of subsequent readmissions for COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Added value of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This national-scale study provides evidence that the rollout of post-hospital discharge virtual ward services for COVID-19 patients in England did not reduce lengths of stay in hospital, or rates of readmission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Implications of all the available evidence&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;While there is currently an absence of evidence of positive impacts for COVID-19 patients discharged to a virtual ward, our study emphasises the need for quality data to be collected as part of future service implementation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.22269068" rel="alternate" title="The impact of post-hospital remote monitoring of COVID-19 patients using pulse oximetry: a national observational study using hospital activity data (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.475264</id><title>Hypercapnia limits β-catenin-mediated alveolar type 2 cell progenitor function by altering Wnt production from adjacent fibroblasts (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.349428+00:00</updated><author><name>Laura A. Dada</name></author><author><name>Lynn C. Welch</name></author><author><name>Natalia D. Magnani</name></author><author><name>Ziyou Ren</name></author><author><name>Patricia L. Brazee</name></author><author><name>Diego Celli</name></author><author><name>Annette S. Flozak</name></author><author><name>Anthea Weng</name></author><author><name>Mariana Maciel-Herrerias</name></author><author><name>Vitalii Kryvenko</name></author><author><name>István Vadász</name></author><author><name>Constance E Runyan</name></author><author><name>Hiam Abdala-Valencia</name></author><author><name>Masahiko Shigemura</name></author><author><name>S. Marina Casalino-Matsuda</name></author><author><name>Alexander V. Misharin</name></author><author><name>G.R. Scott Budinger</name></author><author><name>Cara J. Gottardi</name></author><author><name>Jacob I. Sznajder</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Persistent symptoms and radiographic abnormalities suggestive of failed lung repair are among the most common symptoms in patients with COVID-19 after hospital discharge. In mechanically ventilated patients with ARDS secondary to SARS-CoV-2 pneumonia, low tidal volumes to reduce ventilator-induced lung injury necessarily elevate blood CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; levels, often leading to hypercapnia. The role of hypercapnia on lung repair after injury is not completely understood. Here, we show that hypercapnia limits β-catenin signaling in alveolar type 2 (AT2) cells, leading to reduced proliferative capacity. Hypercapnia alters expression of major Wnts in PDGFRa+-fibroblasts from those maintaining AT2 progenitor activity and towards those that antagonize β-catenin signaling and limit progenitor function. Activation of β-catenin signaling in AT2 cells, rescues the inhibition AT2 proliferation induced by hypercapnia. Inhibition of AT2 proliferation in hypercapnic patients may contribute to impaired lung repair after injury, preventing sealing of the epithelial barrier, increasing lung flooding, ventilator dependency and mortality.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.475264" rel="alternate" title="Hypercapnia limits β-catenin-mediated alveolar type 2 cell progenitor function by altering Wnt production from adjacent fibroblasts (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>