<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>BioRxiv or medRxiv preprints about COVID posted in the last week with at least 5 tweets</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.023852+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.04.21255938</id><title>Longitudinal Changes in COVID-19 Associated In-Hospital Mortality (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.027211+00:00</updated><author><name>Frederick Warner</name></author><author><name>Matt D.T. Hitchings</name></author><author><name>Derek A.T. Cummings</name></author><author><name>Jacob McPadden</name></author><author><name>Harlan M. Krumholz</name></author><author><name>Albert I. Ko</name></author><author><name>Wade L. Schulz</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the COVID-19 pandemic has evolved, a key question for health care systems is whether in-hospital mortality has changed over time and if so, what factors contributed to these changes. Our goal was to leverage real-world data spanning two COVID-19 surges over the first year of the pandemic to determine the temporal trend of in-hospital mortality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was an observational, retrospective study based on real-world data for patients admitted with COVID-19. Generalized additive models (GAM) were used to evaluate the association of covariates with the composite outcome over time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting and Population&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We identified a retrospective cohort of all patients who were hospitalized within the Yale New Haven Health (YNHH) system with an admission diagnosis of COVID-19 between March 1, 2020 and February 28, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main outcome&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The primary outcome for the study was a composite endpoint of in-hospital mortality, defined as death during the index hospitalization or discharge to hospice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among 6,477 discharges over the study period, the mean age was 66.2 years (SD=17.6), 52.5% (n=3,401) were male and the overall composite mortality was 14.2% (n=920). Composite in-hospital mortality was significantly associated with increased age, comorbidity index, respiratory rate, and heart rate; decreased systolic blood pressure; male sex; and admission from a long-term care facility (LTCF). The significant temporal decrease in mortality that was observed for patients admitted from a location other than a LTCF was not seen in those admitted from a LTCF.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found that the adjusted in-hospital mortality rate declined over the first year of the pandemic, despite a second surge in COVID-19-related hospitalizations. Importantly, the decrease in mortality appeared to be driven by declines in risk in those not admitted from a LTCF. The observed decrease in mortality over time suggests that improved outcomes may be due to progressive, incremental learning and continuous evolution in hospital practice and policy over the course of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.04.21256298</id><title>Fatal cytokine release syndrome by an aberrant FLIP/STAT3 axis (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.026238+00:00</updated><author><name>Chiara Musiu</name></author><author><name>Simone Caligola</name></author><author><name>Alessandra Fiore</name></author><author><name>Alessia Lamolinara</name></author><author><name>Cristina Frusteri</name></author><author><name>Francesco Domenico Del Pizzo</name></author><author><name>Francesco De Sanctis</name></author><author><name>Stefania Canè</name></author><author><name>Annalisa Adamo</name></author><author><name>Francesca Hofer</name></author><author><name>Roza Maria Barouni</name></author><author><name>Andrea Grilli</name></author><author><name>Serena Zilio</name></author><author><name>Paolo Serafini</name></author><author><name>Evelina Tacconelli</name></author><author><name>Katia Donadello</name></author><author><name>Leonardo Gottin</name></author><author><name>Enrico Polati</name></author><author><name>Domenico Girelli</name></author><author><name>Ildo Polidoro</name></author><author><name>Piera Amelia Iezzi</name></author><author><name>Domenico Angelucci</name></author><author><name>Andrea Capece</name></author><author><name>Ying Chen</name></author><author><name>Zheng-Li Shi</name></author><author><name>Peter J. Murray</name></author><author><name>Marco Chilosi</name></author><author><name>Ido Amit</name></author><author><name>Silvio Bicciato</name></author><author><name>Manuela Iezzi</name></author><author><name>Vincenzo Bronte</name></author><author><name>Stefano Ugel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Inflammatory responses rapidly detect pathogen invasion and mount a regulated reaction. However, dysregulated anti-pathogen immune responses can provoke life-threatening inflammatory pathologies collectively known as cytokine release syndrome (CRS), exemplified by key clinical phenotypes unearthed during the SARS-Cov-2 pandemic. The underlying pathophysiology of CRS remains elusive. We found that FLIP, a protein that controls caspase-8 death pathways, was highly expressed in myeloid cells of COVID-19 lungs. FLIP controlled CRS by fueling a STAT3-dependent inflammatory program. Indeed, constitutive expression of a viral FLIP homologue in myeloid cells triggered a STAT3-linked, progressive and fatal inflammatory syndrome in mice, characterized by elevated cytokine output, lymphopenia, lung injury and multiple organ dysfunctions that mimicked human CRS. As STAT3-targeting approaches relieved inflammation, immune disorders, and organ failures in these mice, targeted intervention towards this pathway could suppress the lethal CRS inflammatory state.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;FLIP-expressing myeloid cells are key drivers of CRS through aberrant overexpression of STAT3 pathway. STAT3-targeting is effective in mitigating CRS like severe COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.06.21256651</id><title>Higher case fatality rate among obstetric patients with COVID-19 in the second year of pandemic in Brazil: do new genetic variants play a role? (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.025974+00:00</updated><author><name>Maira Libertad Soligo Takemoto</name></author><author><name>Marcos Nakamura-Pereira</name></author><author><name>Mariane de Oliveira Menezes</name></author><author><name>Leila Katz</name></author><author><name>Roxana Knobel</name></author><author><name>Melania Maria Ramos Amorim</name></author><author><name>Carla Betina Andreucci</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: In Brazil, a 20% increase in maternal mortality rate due to COVID-19 is projected for 2020. On January 4, 2021, the P.1 SARS-CoV-2 genetic variant was firstly identified in the country and recent data has indicated an association with higher hospitalization rates and mortality. The impact of P.1 variant in the obstetric population remains unclear.
Methods: We carried out a preliminary analysis of sociodemographic and clinical characteristics of COVID-19 confirmed maternal deaths (between 10-50 years old) comparing cases reported to the Brazilian official severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) surveillance system (SS) in 2020 with those from 2021 (until April 12, 2021). This preliminary analysis employed methods described in previous reports from our group.
Results: 803 maternal deaths out of 8,248 COVID-19 maternal SARS cases with a recorded outcome were reported to the SARS-SS since March 2020. Case fatality rate was significantly higher in 2021 (15.6% vs 7.4%). The first three months of 2021 already account for 46.2% of all deaths occurred in the 13-months analysed period. COVID-19 fatal cases from 2021 had a lower proportion of at least one risk factor or comorbidity as compared to 2020 but had a higher frequency of obesity. There were no significant differences in terms of age, type of residence area (urban, rural, or peri-urban), type of funding of the notification unit (public vs. private), COVID-19 diagnostic criteria, pregnancy status (pregnancy or postpartum), cardiovascular disease or diabetes. The proportion of hospitalization, ICU admission, and respiratory support before death was also not significantly different. 
Conclusion: Case fatality rate was increased in the three first months of 2021 when compared to 2020. Once variables related to health care access and demographics are not significantly different and women seem to be healthier in the 2021 sample, such difference may be related to the circulation of more aggressive genetic variants in the country.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.04.21256107</id><title>Environmental Screening for Surface SARS-CoV-2 Contamination in Urban High-Touch Areas (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.025714+00:00</updated><author><name>Lauren Roppolo Brazell</name></author><author><name>Shawna Stetz</name></author><author><name>Adam Hipp</name></author><author><name>Samantha Taylor</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Stark</name></author><author><name>Katherine Jensen</name></author><author><name>Md Ariful Islam Juel</name></author><author><name>Patrick Deegan</name></author><author><name>Mariya Munir</name></author><author><name>Jessica Schlueter</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Weller</name></author><author><name>Cynthia Gibas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The novel human coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) is responsible for the COVID-19 outbreak, which reached pandemic-level infection rates in just a few short months after being identified in late 2019. Early transmission models focused on surface contamination, but current research provides evidence for person-to-person transmission via aerosolized viral particles. As such, the CDC’s guidance has recently been updated to increasingly redirect the focus of prevention methods to aerosol routes. Inhalation of SARS-CoV-2 particles presents the most significant threat of infection to individuals. A secondary route, from hand to mouth, eyes or nose, is likely after contact with a surface contaminated with particles that have settled out of aerosols or been deposited by contaminated hands. Using common molecular detection methods including endpoint and quantitative PCR, we investigated whether there is detectable contamination by SARS-CoV-2 on high-touch surfaces on public transit vehicles and on other high-touch surfaces on a college campus during normal use. Our results indicate that SARS-CoV-2 can be successfully recovered and detected on common high-touch surfaces, albeit in comparatively lower frequencies as public health guidance progressed and more rigorous sanitization procedures were implemented.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract Figure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="21256107v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;Graphical abstract created with permission from &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://BioRender.com"&gt;BioRender.com&lt;/ext-link&gt; (2021)&lt;/bold&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.05.442742</id><title>Sequencing SARS-CoV-2 in a malaria research laboratory in Mali, West Africa: the road to sequencing the first SARS-CoV-2 genome in Mali (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.025540+00:00</updated><author><name>Antoine Dara</name></author><author><name>Bouréma Kouriba</name></author><author><name>Amadou Daou</name></author><author><name>Abdoul Karim Sangare</name></author><author><name>Djibril Kassogue</name></author><author><name>Charles Dara</name></author><author><name>Abdoulaye Djimde</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Next generation sequencing (NGS) has become a necessary tool for genomic epidemiology. Even though the utility of genomics in human health has been proved, the genomic surveillance has never been so important until the COVID 19 pandemic. This has been evidenced with the detection of new variants of SARS-CoV-2 in the United Kingdom, South Africa and Brazil recently using genomic surveillance. Until recently, Malian scientists did not have access to any local NGS platform and samples had to be shipped abroad for sequencing. Here, we report on how we adapted a laboratory setup for &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium&lt;/italic&gt; research to generate the first complete SARS-CoV-2 genome locally. Total RNA underwent a library preparation using an Illumina TruSeq stranded RNA kit. A metagenomics sequencing was performed on an Illumina MiSeq platform following by bioinformatic analyses on a local server in Mali. We recovered a full genome of SARS-CoV-2 of 29 kb with an average depth coverage of 200x. We have demonstrated our capability of generating a high quality genome with limited resources and highlight the need to develop genomics capacity locally to solve health problems. We discuss challenges related to access to reagents during a pandemic period and propose some home-made solutions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.05.442780</id><title>Prior aerosol infection with lineage A SARS-CoV-2 variant protects hamsters from disease, but not reinfection with B.1.351 SARS-CoV-2 variant (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.025341+00:00</updated><author><name>Claude Kwe Yinda</name></author><author><name>Julia R. Port</name></author><author><name>Trenton Bushmaker</name></author><author><name>Robert J. Fischer</name></author><author><name>Jonathan E. Schulz</name></author><author><name>Myndi G. Holbrook</name></author><author><name>Carl Shaia</name></author><author><name>Emmie de Wit</name></author><author><name>Neeltje van Doremalen</name></author><author><name>Vincent J. Munster</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The circulation of SARS-CoV-2 has resulted in the emergence of variants of concern (VOCs). It is currently unclear whether previous infection with SARS-CoV-2 provides protection against reinfection with VOCs. Here, we show that low dose aerosol exposure to hCoV-19/human/USA/WA-CDC-WA1/2020 (WA1, lineage A), resulted in a productive mild infection. In contrast, low dose of SARS-CoV-2 via fomites did not result in productive infection in the majority of exposed hamsters and these animals remained non-seroconverted. After recovery, hamsters were re-exposed to hCoV-19/South African/KRISP-K005325/2020 (VOC B.1.351) via an intranasal challenge. Seroconverted rechallenged animals did not lose weight and shed virus for 3 days. They had little infectious virus and no pathology in the lungs. In contrast, shedding, weight loss and extensive pulmonary pathology caused by B.1.351 replication was observed in the non-seroconverted animals. The rechallenged seroconverted animals did not transmit virus to naïve sentinels via direct contact transmission, in contrast to the non-seroconverted animals. Reinfection with B.1.351 triggered an anamnestic response that boosted not only neutralizing titers against lineage A, but also titers against B.1.351. Our results confirm that aerosol exposure is a more efficient infection route than fomite exposure. Furthermore, initial infection with SARS-CoV-2 lineage A does not prevent heterologous reinfection with B.1.351 but prevents disease and onward transmission. These data suggest that previous SARS-CoV-2 exposure induces partial protective immunity. The reinfection generated a broadly neutralizing humoral response capable of effectively neutralizing B.1.351 while maintaining its ability to neutralize the virus to which the initial response was directed against.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.05.21256257</id><title>A Rapid and Reliable Liquid Chromatography/Mass Spectrometry Method for SARS-CoV-2 Diagnostics from Gargle Solutions and Saliva (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.025190+00:00</updated><author><name>Marc Kipping</name></author><author><name>Dirk Taenzler</name></author><author><name>Andrea Sinz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We describe a rapid liquid chromatography/mass spectrometry (LC/MS) method for the direct detection and quantitation of SARS-CoV-2 nucleoprotein in gargle solutions and saliva. The method is based on a multiple-reaction monitoring (MRM) mass spectrometry approach with a total cycle time of 5 minutes per analysis and allows the detection and accurate quantitation of SARS-CoV-2 nucleoprotein as low as 500 amol/ul. We improved the sample preparation protocol of our recent piloting SARS-CoV-2 LC/MS study regarding sensitivity, reproducibility, and compatibility with a complementary reverse transcriptase quantitative polymerase chain reaction (RT-qPCR) analysis of the same sample. The aim of this work is to promote diagnostic tools that allow identifying and monitoring SARS-CoV-2 infections by LC/MS methods in a routine clinical environment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.05.21256598</id><title>How can risk of COVID-19 transmission be minimised in domiciliary care for older people: development, parameterisation and initial results of a simple mathematical model (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.024860+00:00</updated><author><name>Istvan Kiss</name></author><author><name>Konstantin Blyuss</name></author><author><name>Yuliya Kyrychko</name></author><author><name>Jo Middleton</name></author><author><name>Daniel Roland</name></author><author><name>Lavinia Bertini</name></author><author><name>Leanne Bogen-Johnston</name></author><author><name>Wendy Wood</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Sharp</name></author><author><name>Julien Forder</name></author><author><name>Jackie A Cassell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This paper proposes and analyses a stochastic model for the spread of an infec- tious disease that is transmitted between clients and care workers in the UK domicil- iary care setting. Interactions between clients and care workers are modelled using specially generated networks, with network parameters reflecting realistic patterns of care needs and visit allocation. These networks are then used to simulate and SEIR-type epidemic dynamics with different numbers of infectious and recovery stages. The results indicate that with the same overall capacity provided by care workers, the minimum peak proportion of infection, and the smallest overall size of infection are achieved for the highest proportion of overlap between visit allocation, i.e. when care workers have the highest chances of being allocated a visit to the same client they have visited before. An intuitive explanation of this is that while providing the required care coverage, maximising overlap in visit allocation reduces the possibility of an infectious care worker inadvertently spreading the infection to other clients. The model is quite generic and can be adapted to any particular directly transmitted infectious disease, such as, more recently, COVID-19, provided accurate estimates of disease parameters can be obtained from real data.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.06.442916</id><title>Identification of DAXX As A Restriction Factor Of SARS-CoV-2 Through A CRISPR/Cas9 Screen (46 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.024571+00:00</updated><author><name>Alice Mac Kain</name></author><author><name>Ghizlane Maarifi</name></author><author><name>Sophie-Marie Aicher</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Arhel</name></author><author><name>Artem Baidaliuk</name></author><author><name>Thomas Vallet</name></author><author><name>Quang Dinh Tran</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Hardy</name></author><author><name>Maxime Chazal</name></author><author><name>Françoise Porrot</name></author><author><name>Molly OhAinle</name></author><author><name>Jared Carlson-Stevermer</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Oki</name></author><author><name>Kevin Holden</name></author><author><name>Etienne Simon-Lorière</name></author><author><name>Timothée Bruel</name></author><author><name>Olivier Schwartz</name></author><author><name>Nolwenn Jouvenet</name></author><author><name>Sébastien Nisole</name></author><author><name>Marco Vignuzzi</name></author><author><name>Ferdinand Roesch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;While interferon restricts SARS-CoV-2 replication in cell culture, only a handful of Interferon Stimulated Genes with antiviral activity against SARS-CoV-2 have been identified. Here, we describe a functional CRISPR/Cas9 screen aiming at identifying SARS-CoV-2 restriction factors. We identified DAXX, a scaffold protein residing in PML nuclear bodies known to limit the replication of DNA viruses and retroviruses, as a potent inhibitor of SARS-CoV-2 replication in human cells. Basal expression of DAXX was sufficient to limit the replication of the virus, and DAXX over-expression further restricted infection. In contrast with most of its previously described antiviral activities, DAXX-mediated restriction of SARS-CoV-2 was independent of the SUMOylation pathway. SARS-CoV-2 infection triggered the re-localization of DAXX to cytoplasmic sites of viral replication and led to its degradation. Together, these results demonstrate that DAXX is a potent restriction factor for SARS-CoV-2 and that the virus has evolved a mechanism to counteract its action.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.06.21256403</id><title>Detection of persistent SARS-CoV-2 IgG antibodies in oral mucosal fluid and upper respiratory tract specimens following COVID-19 mRNA vaccination (2792 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.024268+00:00</updated><author><name>Aubree Mades</name></author><author><name>Prithivi Chellamuthu</name></author><author><name>Lauren Lopez</name></author><author><name>Noah Kojima</name></author><author><name>Melanie A MacMullan</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Denny</name></author><author><name>Aaron N Angel</name></author><author><name>Joseph Casian</name></author><author><name>Matthew Brobeck</name></author><author><name>Nina Nirema</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey D Klausner</name></author><author><name>Frederick E Turner</name></author><author><name>Vladimir I Slepnev</name></author><author><name>Albina Ibrayeva</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Previous studies have shown that mRNA COVID-19 vaccines are highly effective at preventing SAR-CoV-2 infection by generating an immune response, which in part produces SARS-CoV-2 IgG antibodies in serum. In this study, we hypothesized that COVID-19 vaccines may elicit production of SARS-CoV-2 IgG antibodies in the upper respiratory tract, such as in oral and nasal mucosal fluid. To test that hypothesis, we enrolled 114 participants within 3-7 days of receiving the first dose of the Moderna mRNA COVID-19 vaccine and collected oral mucosal fluid samples on days 5, 10, 15, and 20 after each vaccine dose. Of participants naive to SARS-CoV-2 (n = 89), 79 (85.4%) tested positive for SARS-CoV-2 IgG antibodies by time point 2 (10 days +/-2 days after first vaccine dose), and 100% tested positive for SARS-CoV-2 IgG by time point 3 (15 days +/- 2 days after first vaccine dose). Additionally, we collected paired oral mucosal fluid and anterior nares samples from 10 participants who had received both vaccine doses. We found that participants had an average SARS-CoV-2 IgG antibody concentration of 2496.0 +/- 2698.0ng/mL in nasal mucosal fluid versus 153.4 +/- 141.0ng/mL in oral mucosal fluid. Here, we demonstrate detection and longitudinal persistence of SARS-CoV-2 IgG antibodies in upper respiratory tract specimens following COVID-19 mRNA vaccination. A high concentration of IgG targeting viral spike protein in the upper respiratory system may play an unexplored role in the prevention of SARS-CoV-2 infection and deserves further investigation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>