<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.272327+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.21265703</id><title>Efficacy and safety of SOBERANA 02, a COVID-19 conjugate vaccine in heterologous three-dose combination (176 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.274078+00:00</updated><author><name>Maria Eugenia Toledo-Romani</name></author><author><name>Mayra Garcia-Carmenate</name></author><author><name>Carmen Valenzuela Silva</name></author><author><name>Waldemar Baldoquin-Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Marisel Martinez Perez</name></author><author><name>Meiby C Rodriguez Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Beatriz Paredes Moreno</name></author><author><name>Ivis Mendoza Hernandez</name></author><author><name>Raul Gonzalez-Mujica Romero</name></author><author><name>Oscar Samon Tabio</name></author><author><name>Pablo Velazco Villares</name></author><author><name>Juan Pablo Bacallao Castillo</name></author><author><name>Ernesto Licea Martin</name></author><author><name>Misladys Rodriguez Ortega,</name></author><author><name>Nuris Liem Herrera Marrero</name></author><author><name>Esperanza Caballero Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Liudmila Ibelin Egues Torres</name></author><author><name>Reinaldo Duarte Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Serguey Garcia Blanco</name></author><author><name>Suzette Perez Cabrera</name></author><author><name>Santos Huete Ferreira</name></author><author><name>Kirenia Idalmis Idalmis Cisnero</name></author><author><name>Omaida Fonte Galindo</name></author><author><name>Dania Melia Perez</name></author><author><name>Ivonne Rojas Remedios</name></author><author><name>Sonsire Fernandez Castillo</name></author><author><name>Yanet Climent Ruiz</name></author><author><name>Yury Valdes Balbin</name></author><author><name>Dagmar Garcia Rivera</name></author><author><name>vicente Verez-Bencomo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: SOBERANA 02 is a COVID19 conjugate vaccine (recombinant RBD
conjugated to tetanus toxoid). Phase 1 and 2 clinical trials demonstrated its high
immunogenicity, promoting neutralizing IgG and specific Tcell response. A third dose, of
SOBERANA Plus (RBDdimer), further increased the specific anti RBD neutralizing
antibodies.
Methods: In a randomized, double-blind, placebo controlled, phase 3 trial
(https://rpcec.sld.cu/trials/RPCEC00000354-En) we randomly assigned 44 031 participants,
aged 19 to 80 years to three groups to receive a) two doses, SOBERANA 02, or b) two doses,
SOBERANA 02 and a third dose, SOBERANA Plus, or c) placebo. Study endpoints are
vaccine efficacy (VE) evaluated through confirmed symptomatic COVID-19 and safety.
During the trial, the SARS CoV-2 isolates in Havana were 74.0 BETA;, shifting gradually to
100% DELTA; .
Results: Two doses of SOBERANA 02 protected against symptomatic COVID-19: 43
cases in the two-dose group (14 371) vs. 155 in the placebo group (14 403), VE 71.0%,
adjusted (CI 95%, 58.9 to 79.1). The heterologous three-dose combination increased the
protection: 15 cases in the vaccine groups (13 833) vs. 155 in the placebo group (14 303),
VE 92.4%, adjusted (CI 95%, 86.9 to 95.6%). For the two-dose schedule, VE against severe
COVID-19 was 63.0% and for death, 59.0%; for the heterologous three-dose schedule, VE
was 100% in both cases.
Conclusions: This is the first phase-3 study of a three-dose, heterologous COVID-19
vaccine. Two doses of SOBERANA 02 were safe and attained efficacy of 71.0% in the
adult population 19-80 y/o; incorporating SOBERANA Plus increased efficacy from 71.0
% to 92.4%.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.21265703" rel="alternate" title="Efficacy and safety of SOBERANA 02, a COVID-19 conjugate vaccine in heterologous three-dose combination (176 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467077</id><title>The oral protease inhibitor (PF-07321332) protects Syrian hamsters against infection with SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (68 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.278449+00:00</updated><author><name>Rana Abdelnabi</name></author><author><name>Caroline Shi-Yan Foo</name></author><author><name>Dirk Jochmans</name></author><author><name>Laura Vangeel</name></author><author><name>Steven De Jonghe</name></author><author><name>Patrick Augustijns</name></author><author><name>Raf Mols</name></author><author><name>Birgit Weynand</name></author><author><name>Thanaporn Wattanakul</name></author><author><name>Richard Hoglund</name></author><author><name>Joel Tarning</name></author><author><name>Charles Mowbray</name></author><author><name>Peter Sjo</name></author><author><name>Fanny Escudie</name></author><author><name>Ivan Scandale</name></author><author><name>Eric Chatelain</name></author><author><name>Johan Neyts</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;There is an urgent need for potent and selective antivirals against SARS-CoV-2. Pfizer developed PF-07321332 (PF-332), a potent inhibitor of the main viral protease (Mpro, 3CLpro) that can be dosed orally; the compound is in clinical development. We demonstrate that PF-332 exerts equipotent in vitro activity against the four SARS-CoV-2 variants of concerns (VoC) and can completely arrest replication of the alpha variant in primary human airway epithelial cells grown at the air-liquid interface. Treatment of Syrian hamsters with PF-332 (250 mg/kg, twice daily) completely protected the animals against intranasal infection with the beta (B.1.351) and delta (B.1.617.2) SARS-CoV-2 variants. Moreover, treatment of SARS-CoV-2 (B.1.617.2) infected animals with PF-332 completely prevented transmission to untreated co-housed sentinels. The trough drug concentration at this efficacious dose were above the in vitro efficacious concentrations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467077" rel="alternate" title="The oral protease inhibitor (PF-07321332) protects Syrian hamsters against infection with SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (68 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467378</id><title>A high-throughput, automated, cell-free expression and screening platform for antibody discovery (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.280258+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew C Hunt</name></author><author><name>Bastian Vogeli</name></author><author><name>Weston K. Kightlinger</name></author><author><name>Danielle J. Yoesep</name></author><author><name>Antje Kruger</name></author><author><name>Michael C. Jewett</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antibody discovery is bottlenecked by the individual expression and evaluation of antigen- specific hits. Here, we address this gap by developing an automated workflow combining cell-free DNA template generation, protein synthesis, and high-throughput binding measurements of antibody fragments in a process that takes hours rather than weeks. We apply this workflow to 119 published SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibodies and demonstrate rapid identification of the most potent antibody candidates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467378" rel="alternate" title="A high-throughput, automated, cell-free expression and screening platform for antibody discovery (23 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467308</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 infection in free-ranging white-tailed deer (Odocoileus virginianus) (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.280766+00:00</updated><author><name>Vanessa L Hale</name></author><author><name>Patricia M Dennis</name></author><author><name>Dillon S McBride</name></author><author><name>Jacqueline M Nolting</name></author><author><name>Christopher Madden</name></author><author><name>Devra Huey</name></author><author><name>Margot Ehrlich</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Grieser</name></author><author><name>Jenessa A Winston</name></author><author><name>Dusty Lombardi</name></author><author><name>Stormy Gibson</name></author><author><name>Linda Saif</name></author><author><name>Mary Lea Killian</name></author><author><name>Kristina Lantz</name></author><author><name>Rachel M Tell</name></author><author><name>Mia Kim Torchetti</name></author><author><name>Suelee Robbe-Austerman</name></author><author><name>Martha I Nelson</name></author><author><name>Seth A Faith</name></author><author><name>Andrew Bowman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human-to-animal spillover of SARS-CoV-2 virus has occurred in a wide range of animals, but thus far, the establishment of a new natural animal reservoir has not been detected. Here, we detected SARS-CoV-2 virus using rRT-PCR in 129 out of 360 (35.8%) free-ranging white-tailed deer (Odocoileus virginianus) from northeast Ohio (USA) sampled between January-March 2021. Deer in 6 locations were infected with at least 3 lineages of SARS-CoV-2 (B.1.2, B.1.596, B.1.582). The B.1.2 viruses, dominant in Ohio at the time, spilled over multiple times into deer populations in different locations. Deer-to-deer transmission may have occurred in three locations. The establishment of a natural reservoir of SARS-CoV-2 in white-tailed deer could facilitate divergent evolutionary trajectories and future spillback to humans, further complicating long-term COVID-19 control strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467308" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 infection in free-ranging white-tailed deer (Odocoileus virginianus) (22 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.21265843</id><title>A RCT of a third dose CoronaVac or BNT162b2 vaccine in adults with two doses of CoronaVac (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.281225+00:00</updated><author><name>Chris Ka Pun Mok</name></author><author><name>Samuel M.S. Cheng</name></author><author><name>Chunke Chen</name></author><author><name>Karen Yiu</name></author><author><name>Tat-On Chan</name></author><author><name>Kiu Cheung Lai</name></author><author><name>Kwun Cheung Ling</name></author><author><name>Yuanxin Sun</name></author><author><name>Lun Lai Ho</name></author><author><name>Malik Peiris</name></author><author><name>David S Hui</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Poor immunogenicity and antibody waning were found in vaccinees of CoronaVac. There is lack of randomized controlled trial (RCT) data to compare the immunogenicity and safety of schedules using homologous and heterologous vaccine as a booster dose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We randomly assigned adults who had received 2 doses of CoronaVac with low antibody response to receive an additional booster dose of either BNT162b2 or CoronaVac. The local and systemic adverse reactions were recorded. Levels of SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing and spike binding antibody in plasma were measured.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;At one month after the third dose of vaccine, BNT162b2 vaccines elicited significantly higher surrogate virus neutralizing test (sVNT), spike receptor binding, spike N terminal domain binding, spike S2 domain binding levels than CoronaVac. More participants from the BNT162b2 group reported injection site pain and swelling as well as fatigue and muscle pain than those who received CoronaVac as the third dose. The mean results of the sVNT against the wild type, beta, gamma and delta variants in the BNT162b2 boosted group was 96.83%, 92.29%, 92.51% and 95.33% respectively which were significantly higher than the CoronaVac boosted group (Wild type: 57.75%; Beta: 38.79 %; Gamma: 32.22%; Delta: 48.87%)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our RCT study shows that BNT162b2 booster dose for those people who poorly responded to the previous vaccination of CoronaVac is significantly more immunogenic than a CoronaVac booster. BNT162b2 also elicits higher levels of SARS-CoV-2 specific neutralizing antibodies to different variants of concern. The adverse reactions were only mild and short-lived.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;At a Glance Commentary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Scientific Knowledge on the Subject&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Poor immunogenicity and antibody waning were found in vaccinees of CoronaVac. There is lack of randomized controlled trial (RCT) data to compare the immunogenicity and safety of schedules using homologous and heterologous vaccine as a booster dose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What This Study Adds to the Field&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our RCT study shows that BNT162b2 booster dose for those people who poorly responded to the previous vaccination of CoronaVac is significantly more immunogenic than a CoronaVac booster. The adverse reactions were only mild and short-lived.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.21265843" rel="alternate" title="A RCT of a third dose CoronaVac or BNT162b2 vaccine in adults with two doses of CoronaVac (21 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.21265555</id><title>IFI27 transcription is an early predictor for COVID-19 outcomes; a multi-cohort observational study (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.281897+00:00</updated><author><name>Maryam Shojaei</name></author><author><name>Amir Shamshirian</name></author><author><name>James Monkman</name></author><author><name>Laura Grice</name></author><author><name>Minh Tran</name></author><author><name>Chin Wee Tan</name></author><author><name>Gustavo Rodrigues Rossi</name></author><author><name>Timothy R. McCulloch</name></author><author><name>Marek Nalos</name></author><author><name>Keng Yih Chew</name></author><author><name>Yanshan Zhu</name></author><author><name>Yao Xia</name></author><author><name>Timothy J. Wells</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Cristina Senegaglia</name></author><author><name>Carmen Lúcia Kuniyoshi Rebelatto</name></author><author><name>Claudio Luciano Franck</name></author><author><name>Anna Flavia Ribeiro dos Santos</name></author><author><name>Lucia de Noronha</name></author><author><name>Sepideh Motamen</name></author><author><name>Reza Valadan</name></author><author><name>Omolbanin Amjadi</name></author><author><name>Rajan Gogna</name></author><author><name>Esha Madan</name></author><author><name>Reza Alizadeh-Navaei</name></author><author><name>Liliana Lamperti</name></author><author><name>Felipe Zuñiga</name></author><author><name>Estefania Nova-Lamperti</name></author><author><name>Gonzalo Labarca</name></author><author><name>Ben Knippenberg</name></author><author><name>Velma Herwanto</name></author><author><name>Ya Wang</name></author><author><name>Amy Phu</name></author><author><name>Tracy Chew</name></author><author><name>Timothy Kwan</name></author><author><name>Karan Kim</name></author><author><name>Sally Teoh</name></author><author><name>Tiana M Pelaia</name></author><author><name>Win Sen Kuan</name></author><author><name>Yvette Jee</name></author><author><name>Jon Iredell</name></author><author><name>Ken O’Byrne</name></author><author><name>John F. Fraser</name></author><author><name>Melissa J. Davis</name></author><author><name>Gabrielle Belz</name></author><author><name>Majid Warkiani</name></author><author><name>Carlos Salomon Gallo</name></author><author><name>Fernando Souza-Fonseca-Guimaraes</name></author><author><name>Quan Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Anthony Mclean</name></author><author><name>Arutha Kulasinghe</name></author><author><name>Kirsty R. Short</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Tang</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Robust biomarkers that predict disease outcomes amongst COVID-19 patients are necessary for both patient triage and resource prioritisation. Numerous candidate biomarkers have been proposed for COVID-19. However, at present, there is no consensus on the best diagnostic approach to predict outcomes in infected patients. Moreover, it is not clear whether such tools would apply to other potentially pandemic pathogens and therefore of use as stockpile for future pandemic preparedness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted a multi-cohort observational study to investigate the biology and the prognostic role of interferon alpha-inducible protein 27 (&lt;italic&gt;IFI27&lt;/italic&gt;) in COVID-19 patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We show that &lt;italic&gt;IFI27&lt;/italic&gt; is expressed in the respiratory tract of COVID-19 patients and elevated &lt;italic&gt;IFI27&lt;/italic&gt; expression is associated with the presence of a high viral load. We further demonstrate that systemic host response, as measured by blood &lt;italic&gt;IFI27&lt;/italic&gt; expression, is associated with COVID-19 severity. For clinical outcome prediction (e.g. respiratory failure), &lt;italic&gt;IFI27&lt;/italic&gt; expression displays a high positive (0.83) and negative (0.95) predictive value, outperforming all other known predictors of COVID-19 severity. Furthermore, &lt;italic&gt;IFI27&lt;/italic&gt; is upregulated in the blood of infected patients in response to other respiratory viruses. For example, in the pandemic H1N1/09 swine influenza virus infection, &lt;italic&gt;IFI27-&lt;/italic&gt;like genes were highly upregulated in the blood samples of severely infected patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;These data suggest that prognostic biomarkers targeting the family of &lt;italic&gt;IFI27&lt;/italic&gt; genes could potentially supplement conventional diagnostic tools in future virus pandemics, independent of whether such pandemics are caused by a coronavirus, an influenza virus or another as yet-to-be discovered respiratory virus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Research in context&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Evidence before this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We searched the scientific literature using PubMed to identify studies that used the &lt;italic&gt;IFI27&lt;/italic&gt; biomarker to predict outcomes in COVID-19 patients. We used the search terms “&lt;italic&gt;IFI27&lt;/italic&gt;”, “COVID-19, “gene expression” and “outcome prediction”. We did not identify any study that investigated the role of &lt;italic&gt;IFI27&lt;/italic&gt; biomarker in outcome prediction. Although ten studies were identified using the general terms of “gene expression” and “COVID-19”, &lt;italic&gt;IFI27&lt;/italic&gt; was only mentioned in passing as one of the identified genes. All these studies addressed the broader question of the host response to COVID-19; none focused solely on using &lt;italic&gt;IFI27&lt;/italic&gt; to improve the risk stratification of infected patients in a pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Added value of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we present the findings of a multi-cohort study of the &lt;italic&gt;IFI27&lt;/italic&gt; biomarker in COVID-19 patients. Our findings show that the host response, as reflected by blood &lt;italic&gt;IFI27&lt;/italic&gt; gene expression, accurately predicts COVID-19 disease progression (positive and negative predictive values; 0.83 and 0.95, respectively), outperforming age, comorbidity, C-reactive protein and all other known risk factors. The strong association of &lt;italic&gt;IFI27&lt;/italic&gt; with disease severity occurs not only in SARS-CoV-2 infection, but also in other respiratory viruses with pandemic potential, such as the influenza virus. These findings suggest that host response biomarkers, such as &lt;italic&gt;IFI27&lt;/italic&gt;, could help identify high-risk COVID-19 patients - those who are more likely to develop infection complications - and therefore may help improve patient triage in a pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Implications of all the available evidence&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the first systemic study of the clinical role of &lt;italic&gt;IFI27&lt;/italic&gt; in the current COVID-19 pandemic and its possible future application in other respiratory virus pandemics. The findings not only could help improve the current management of COVID-19 patients but may also improve future pandemic preparedness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.21265555" rel="alternate" title="IFI27 transcription is an early predictor for COVID-19 outcomes; a multi-cohort observational study (18 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466834</id><title>Glycan-masking spike antigen in NTD and RBD elicits broadly neutralizing antibodies against SARS-CoV-2 variants (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.282552+00:00</updated><author><name>Wei-Shuo Lin</name></author><author><name>I-Chen Chen</name></author><author><name>Hui-Chen Chen</name></author><author><name>Yi-Chien Lee</name></author><author><name>Suh-Chin Wu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glycan-masking the vaccine antigen by mutating the undesired antigenic sites with an additional N-linked glycosylation motif can refocus B-cell responses to desired/undesired epitopes, without affecting the antigen’s overall-folded structure. This study examine the impact of glycan-masking mutants of the N-terminal domain (NTD) and receptor-binding domain (RBD) of SARS-CoV-2, and found that the antigenic design of the S protein increases the neutralizing antibody titers against the Wuhan-Hu-1 ancestral strain and the recently emerged SARS-CoV-2 variants Alpha (B.1.1.7), Beta (B.1.351), and Delta (B.1.617.2). Our results demonstrated that the use of glycan-masking Ad-S-R158N/Y160T in the NTD elicited a 2.8-fold, 6.5-fold, and 4.6-fold increase in the IC-50 NT titer against the Alpha (B.1.1.7), Beta (B.1.351) and Delta (B.1.617.2) variants, respectively. Glycan-masking of Ad-S-D428N in the RBD resulted in a 3.0-fold and 2.0-fold increase in the IC50 neutralization titer against the Alpha (B.1.1.7) and Beta (B.1.351) variants, respectively. The use of glycan-masking in Ad-S-R158N/Y160T and Ad-S-D428N antigen design may help develop universal COVID-19 vaccines against current and future emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466834" rel="alternate" title="Glycan-masking spike antigen in NTD and RBD elicits broadly neutralizing antibodies against SARS-CoV-2 variants (14 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.21265711</id><title>Cross-border transmissions of delta substrain AY.29 during Olympic and Paralympic Games (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.283214+00:00</updated><author><name>Takahiko Koyama</name></author><author><name>Reitaro Tokumasu</name></author><author><name>Kotoe Katayama</name></author><author><name>Ayumu Saito</name></author><author><name>Michiharu Kudo</name></author><author><name>Seiya Imoto</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tokyo Olympic and Paralympic Games, postponed for COVID-19 pandemic, were finally held in summer of 2021. Just before the games, alpha variant was being replaced with more contagious delta variant (B.1.617.2). AY.4 substrain AY.29, which harbors two additional characteristic mutations of 5239C&amp;gt;T (NSP3 Y840Y) and 5514T&amp;gt;C (NSP3 V932A), emerged in Japan and became the dominant strain in Tokyo by the time of the Olympic Games. As of October 18, 98 AY.29 samples are identified in 16 countries outside of Japan. Phylogenetic analysis and ancestral searches identified 46 distinct introductions of AY.29 strains into those 16 countries. United States has 44 samples with 10 distinct introductions, and United Kingdom has 13 distinct AY.29 strains introduced in 16 samples. Other countries or regions with multiple introductions of AY.29 are Canada, Germany, South Korea, and Hong Kong while Italy, France, Spain, Sweden, Belgium, Peru, Australia, New Zealand, and Indonesia have only one distinct strain introduced. There exists no unambiguous evidence that Olympic and Paralympic Games induced cross-border transmission of the delta substrain AY.29. Since most of unvaccinated countries are also under sampled for genome analysis with longer lead time for data sharing, it will take longer to capture the whole picture of cross-border transmissions of AY.29.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.21265711" rel="alternate" title="Cross-border transmissions of delta substrain AY.29 during Olympic and Paralympic Games (12 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466863</id><title>mRNA Vaccines Induce Rapid Antibody Responses in Mice (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.283629+00:00</updated><author><name>Makda S. Gebre</name></author><author><name>Susanne Rauch</name></author><author><name>Nicole Roth</name></author><author><name>Janina Gergen</name></author><author><name>Jingyou Yu</name></author><author><name>Xiaowen Liu</name></author><author><name>Andrew C. Cole</name></author><author><name>Stefan O. Mueller</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Petsch</name></author><author><name>Dan H. Barouch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;mRNA vaccines can be developed and produced quickly, making them attractive for immediate outbreak responses. Furthermore, clinical trials have demonstrated rapid protection following mRNA vaccination. We sought to investigate how quickly mRNA vaccines elicit antibody responses compared to other vaccine modalities. We first examined immune kinetics of mRNA and DNA vaccines expressing SARS-CoV-2 spike in mice. We observed rapid induction of antigen-specific binding and neutralizing antibodies by day 5 following mRNA, but not DNA, immunization. The mRNA vaccine also induced increased levels of IL-5, IL-6 and MCP-1. We then evaluated immune kinetics of an HIV-1 mRNA vaccine in comparison to DNA, protein, and rhesus adenovirus 52 (RhAd52) vaccines with the same HIV-1 envelope antigen in mice. Induction of envelope-specific antibodies was observed by day 5 following mRNA vaccination, whereas antibodies were detected by day 7-14 following DNA, protein, and RhAd52 vaccination. Eliciting rapid humoral immunity may be an advantageous property of mRNA vaccines for controlling infectious disease outbreaks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;mRNA vaccines can be developed and produced in record time. Here we demonstrate induction of rapid antibody responses by mRNA vaccines encoding two different viral antigens by day 5 following immunization in mice. The rapid immune kinetics of mRNA vaccines can be an advantageous property that makes them well suited for rapid control of infectious disease outbreaks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466863" rel="alternate" title="mRNA Vaccines Induce Rapid Antibody Responses in Mice (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265876</id><title>Investigating the relationship between interventions, contact patterns, and SARS-CoV-2 transmissibility (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.284856+00:00</updated><author><name>Filippo Trentini</name></author><author><name>Adriana Manna</name></author><author><name>Nicoletta Balbo</name></author><author><name>Valentina Marziano</name></author><author><name>Giorgio Guzzetta</name></author><author><name>Stefano Merler</name></author><author><name>Marco Ajelli</name></author><author><name>Piero Poletti</name></author><author><name>Alessia Melegaro</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a rapid upsurge of COVID-19 cases in Italy during the fall of 2020, the government introduced a three-tiered restriction system aimed at increasing physical distancing. The Ministry of Health, after periodic epidemiological risk assessments, assigned a tier to each of the 21 Italian regions and autonomous provinces (AP). It is still unclear to what extent these different measures altered mixing patterns and how quickly the population adapted their social interactions to continuous changes in restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods and findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted a survey between July 2020 and March 2021 to monitor changes in social contact patterns among individuals in the metropolitan city of Milan, Italy, which was hardly hit by the second wave of COVID-19 pandemic. The number of contacts during periods characterized by different levels of restrictions was analyzed through negative binomial regression models and age-specific contact matrices were estimated under the different tiers. Relying on the empirically estimated mixing patterns, we quantified relative changes in SARS-CoV-2 transmission potential associated with the different tiers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As tighter restrictions were implemented during the fall of 2020, a progressive reduction in the mean number of contacts recorded by study participants was observed: from 16.4% under mild restrictions (yellow tier), to 45.6% under strong restrictions (red tier). Higher restrictions levels were also found to increase the relative contribution of contacts occurring within the household. The SARS-CoV-2 reproduction number was estimated to decrease by 18.7% (95%CI: 4.6-30.8), 33.4% (95%CI: 22.7-43.2), and 50.2% (95%CI: 40.9-57.7) under the yellow, orange, and red tiers, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our results give an important quantification of the expected contribution of different restriction levels in shaping social contacts and decreasing the transmission potential of SARS-CoV-2. These estimates can find an operational use in anticipating the effect that the implementation of these tiered restriction can have on SARS-CoV-2 reproduction number under an evolving epidemiological situation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265876" rel="alternate" title="Investigating the relationship between interventions, contact patterns, and SARS-CoV-2 transmissibility (11 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265863</id><title>Downsizing of contact tracing during COVID-19 vaccine roll-out (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.285140+00:00</updated><author><name>Maria M. Martignoni</name></author><author><name>Josh Renault</name></author><author><name>Joseph Baafi</name></author><author><name>Amy Hurford</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Contact tracing is a key component of successful management of COVID-19. Contacts of infected individuals are asked to quarantine, which can significantly slow down (or prevent) community spread. Contact tracing is particularly effective when infections are detected quickly (e.g., through rapid testing), when contacts are traced with high probability, when the initial number of cases is low, and when social distancing and border restrictions are in place. However, the magnitude of the individual contribution of these factors in reducing epidemic spread and the impact of vaccination in determining contact tracing outputs is not fully understood. We present a delayed differential equation model to investigate how vaccine roll-out and the relaxation of social distancing requirements affect contact tracing practises. We provide an analytical criteria to determine the minimal contact tracing efficiency (defined as the the probability of identifying and quarantining contacts of symptomatic individuals) required to keep an outbreak under control, with respect to the contact rate and vaccination status of the population. Additionally, we consider how delays in outbreak detection and increased case importation rates affect the number of contacts to be traced daily. We show that in vaccinated communities a lower contact tracing efficiency is required to avoid uncontrolled epidemic spread, and delayed outbreak detection and relaxation of border restrictions do not lead to a significantly higher risk of overwhelming contact tracing. We find that investing in testing programs, rather than increasing the contact tracing capacity, has a larger impact in determining whether an outbreak will be controllable. This is because early detection activates contact tracing, which will slow, and eventually reverse exponential growth, while the contact tracing capacity is a threshold that will easily become overwhelmed if exponential growth is not curbed. Finally, we evaluate quarantine effectiveness during vaccine roll-out, by considering the proportion of people that will develop an infection while in isolation in relation to the vaccination status of the population and for different viral variants. We show that quarantine effectiveness decreases with increasing proportion of fully vaccinated individuals, and increases in the presence of more transmissible variants. These results suggest that a cost-effective approach during vaccine roll-out is to establish different quarantine rules for vaccinated and unvaccinated individuals, where rules should depend on viral trans-missibility. Altogether, our study provides quantitative information for contact tracing downsizing during vaccine roll-out, to guide COVID-19 exit strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265863" rel="alternate" title="Downsizing of contact tracing during COVID-19 vaccine roll-out (10 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466951</id><title>Drug targeting Nsp1-ribosomal complex shows antiviral activity against SARS-CoV-2 (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.285314+00:00</updated><author><name>Mohammad Afsar</name></author><author><name>Rohan Narayan</name></author><author><name>Md Noor Akhtar</name></author><author><name>Huma Rahil</name></author><author><name>Sandeep M Eswarappa</name></author><author><name>Shashank Tripathi</name></author><author><name>Tanweer Hussain</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The SARS-Cov-2 non-structural protein 1 (Nsp1) contains an N-terminal domain and C-terminal helices connected by a short linker region. The C-terminal helices of Nsp1 (Nsp1-C-ter) from SARS-Cov-2 bind in the mRNA entry channel of the 40S ribosomal subunit and block the entry of mRNAs thereby shutting down host protein synthesis. Nsp1 suppresses the host immune function and is vital for viral replication. Hence, Nsp1 appears to be an attractive target for therapeutics. In this study, we have &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; screened Food and Drug Administration (FDA)-approved drugs against Nsp1-C-ter and find that montelukast sodium hydrate binds to Nsp1-C-ter with a binding affinity (K&lt;sub&gt;D&lt;/sub&gt;) of 10.8±0.2 μM &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and forms a stable complex with it in simulation runs with a binding energy of −76.71±8.95 kJ/mol. The drug also rescues the inhibitory effect of Nsp1 in host protein synthesis as demonstrated by the expression of firefly luciferase reporter gene in cells. Importantly, montelukast sodium hydrate demonstrates antiviral activity against SARS-CoV-2 with reduced viral replication in HEK cells expressing ACE2 and Vero-E6 cells. We therefore propose montelukast sodium hydrate may help in combatting SARS-CoV-2 infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466951" rel="alternate" title="Drug targeting Nsp1-ribosomal complex shows antiviral activity against SARS-CoV-2 (10 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.21265668</id><title>Black and Native Overdose Mortality Overtook that of White Individuals During the COVID-19 Pandemic (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.285526+00:00</updated><author><name>Joseph Friedman</name></author><author><name>Helena Hansen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Drug overdose mortality rates have increased sharply during the COVID-19 pandemic. In recent years, overdose death rates were rising most rapidly among racial/ethnic minority communities. The pandemic has disproportionately affected communities of color in a wide swath of health, social, and economic outcomes. Careful attention is therefore warranted to trends in overdose mortality by race/ethnicity during COVID-19. We calculated total drug overdose death rates per 100,000 population by race/ethnicity for the 1999-2020 time period. We find that Black overdose mortality overtook that of White individuals in 2020 for the first time since 1999. Between 2019 and 2020 Black individuals had the largest percent increase in overdose mortality, of 48.8%, compared to 26.3% among White individuals. In 2020, Black overdose death rates rose to 36.8 per 100,000, representing 16.3% higher than the rate for White individuals for the same period. American Indian and Alaska Native (AI/AN) individuals experienced the highest rate of overdose mortality in 2020, of 41.4 per 100,000, representing 30.8% higher than the rate among White individuals. Our findings suggest that drug overdose mortality is increasingly becoming a racial justice issue in the United States and appears to have been exacerbated by the COVID-19 pandemic. Providing individuals with a safer supply of drugs, closing gaps in access to MOUD and harm reductions services, and ending routine incarceration of individuals with substance use disorders represent urgently needed, evidence-based strategies that can be employed to reduce rising inequalities in overdose.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.21265668" rel="alternate" title="Black and Native Overdose Mortality Overtook that of White Individuals During the COVID-19 Pandemic (10 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467344</id><title>Brilacidin, a COVID-19 Drug Candidate, demonstrates broad-spectrum antiviral activity against human coronaviruses OC43, 229E and NL63 through targeting both the virus and the host cell (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.285695+00:00</updated><author><name>Yanmei Hu</name></author><author><name>Hyunil Jo</name></author><author><name>William DeGrado</name></author><author><name>Jun Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Brilacidin, a mimetic of host defense peptides (HDPs), is currently in phase 2 clinical trial as an antibiotic drug candidate. A recent study reported that brilacidin has antiviral activity against SARS-CoV-2 by inactivating the virus. In this work, we discovered an additional mechanism of action of brilacidin by targeting heparan sulfate proteoglycans (HSPGs) on host cell surface. Brilacidin, but not acetyl brilacidin, inhibits the entry of SARS-CoV-2 pseudovirus into multiple cell lines, and heparin, a HSPG mimetic, abolishes the inhibitory activity of brilacidin on SARS-CoV-2 pseudovirus cell entry. In addition, we found that brilacidin has broad-spectrum antiviral activity against multiple human coronaviruses (HCoVs) including HCoV-229E, HCoV-OC43, and HCoV-NL63. Mechanistic studies revealed that brilacidin has a dual antiviral mechanism of action including virucidal activity and binding to coronavirus attachment factor HSPGs on host cell surface. Brilacidin partially loses its antiviral activity when heparin was included in the cell cultures, supporting the host-targeting mechanism. Drug combination therapy showed that brilacidin has a strong synergistic effect with remdesivir against HCoV-OC43 in cell culture. Taken together, this study provides appealing findings for the translational potential of brilacidin as a broad-spectrum antiviral for coronaviruses including SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467344" rel="alternate" title="Brilacidin, a COVID-19 Drug Candidate, demonstrates broad-spectrum antiviral activity against human coronaviruses OC43, 229E and NL63 through targeting both the virus and the host cell (10 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.21265945</id><title>Inhaled Corticosteroids for Outpatients with Covid-19: A Meta-Analysis (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.289166+00:00</updated><author><name>Todd C Lee</name></author><author><name>Emilie Bortolussi-Courval</name></author><author><name>Sara Belga</name></author><author><name>Nick Daneman</name></author><author><name>Adrienne K Chan</name></author><author><name>Ryan Hanula</name></author><author><name>Nicole Ezer</name></author><author><name>Emily G McDonald</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The role of inhaled corticosteroids for outpatient COVID-19 is evolving. We meta-analyzed reported clinical trials and estimated probability of any effect and number needed to treat of 50 or 20 for symptom resolution by day 14 [100%, 99.8%, 93.1%] and hospitalization [88.6%, 72.7%, 26.3%] respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.21265945" rel="alternate" title="Inhaled Corticosteroids for Outpatients with Covid-19: A Meta-Analysis (9 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265819</id><title>Effectiveness of COVID-19 Vaccines and Post-vaccination SARS-COV 2 Infection, Hospitalization, and Mortality: a Systematic Review and Meta-analysis of Observational Studies (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.291099+00:00</updated><author><name>Kazem Rahmani</name></author><author><name>Rasoul Shavaleh</name></author><author><name>Mahtab Forouhi</name></author><author><name>Hamideh Feiz Disfani</name></author><author><name>Mostafa Kamandi</name></author><author><name>Aram Asareh Zadegan Dezfuli</name></author><author><name>Rozita Khatamian Oskooi</name></author><author><name>Molood Foogerdi</name></author><author><name>Moslem Soltani</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction &amp;amp; Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vaccination is one of the most important and effective ways of preventing infectious diseases, and has recently been used in the COVID-19 epidemic and pandemic. The present meta-analysis study aimed to evaluate the effectiveness of COVID-19 vaccines in reducing the incidence of infection, hospitalization, and mortality in observational studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Materials and Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A systematic search was performed independently in Scopus, PubMed, ProQuest, and Google Scholar electronic databases as well as Preprint servers using the keywords under study. The heterogeneity of the studies was assessed using &lt;italic&gt;I&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;and&lt;/italic&gt; χ&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; statistics, according to which the I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; of &amp;gt; 50% and P -value &amp;lt;0.1 was reported as heterogeneity of the studies. In addition, the Pooled Vaccine Effectiveness (PVE) obtained from the studies was calculated by converting (1-Pooled estimate × 100%) based on the type of outcome.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A total of 54 records were included in this meta-analysis. The rate of PVE against SARS-COV 2 infection was about 71% (OR = 0.29, 95% CI: 0.23-0.36) in the first dose and 87% (OR = 0.13, 95% CI: 0.08-0.21) in the second, and the highest effectiveness in the first and second doses was that of BNT162b2 mRNA and combined studies. The PVE versus COVID-19-associated hospitalization was 73% (OR = 0.27, 95% CI: 0.18-0.41) in the first dose and 89% (OR = 0.11, 95% CI: 0.07-0.17) in the second. mRNA-1273 and combined studies in the first dose and ChAdOx1 and mRNA-1273 in the second dose had the highest effectiveness. Regarding the COVID-19-related mortality, PVE was about 28% (HR = 0.39, 95% CI: 0.23-0.45) in the first dose and 89% (HR = 0.11, 95% CI: 0.03-0.43) in the second.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The evidence obtained from this study showed that the effectiveness of BNT162b2 mRNA, mRNA-1273, and ChAdOx1 in the first and second doses, and even combined studies were associated with increased effectiveness against SARS-COV2 infection, hospitalization, and death from COVID-19. In addition, considering that the second dose was significantly more efficient than the first one, a booster dose injection could be effective in high-risk individuals. On the other hand, it was important to observe other prevention considerations in the first days after taking the first dose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265819" rel="alternate" title="Effectiveness of COVID-19 Vaccines and Post-vaccination SARS-COV 2 Infection, Hospitalization, and Mortality: a Systematic Review and Meta-analysis of Observational Studies (8 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.21265627</id><title>Predictors of COVID testing among Australian youth: Insights from the Longitudinal Study of Australian Children (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.291606+00:00</updated><author><name>Md Irteja Islam</name></author><author><name>Verity Chadwick</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Martiniuk</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Testing has played a crucial role in reducing the spread of COVID. Although COVID symptoms tend to be less severe in children and adolescents, a key concern is young people’s role in the transmission of the virus given their highly social lifestyles. In this study, we aimed to identify the predictors associated with COVID testing in Australian youth using data from the Longitudinal Study of Australian Children (LSAC).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used the latest wave 9C1 of the LSAC, where data were collected from 16–21-year-old Australians via an online survey between October and December 2021. In total, 2291 Australian youths responded to the questions about COVID testing and COVID symptom severity. Data was stratified by living with/without parents, and bivariate and logistic regression analyses examined predictor variables (age, sex, country of birth, remoteness, education level, employment, relationship status, number of household members, living with parents, receiving the COVID financial supplement from government and index of relative socio-economic advantage and disadvantage) and their distributions over the outcome variable COVID testing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Youths aged 16-17 were more likely to live at home than youths aged 20-21 years. The strongest predictor of COVID testing was living in major cities (regardless of living with or without parents). Changed household composition was significantly associated with COVID testing among the youths living in the parental home. While among the respondents living without their parents, living with multiple household members and low or no cohesion among household members was associated with higher rates of COVID testing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our study revealed young people have been very good at getting tested for COVID. To further incentivise testing in this age group, we should consider providing this age group with continued financial and social support while awaiting the outcome of the test and during any isolation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Strengths and limitations of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Large national cohort of young people strengthened the findings of the study and allowing us to examine the factors associated with COVID testing for the first time in Australia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;A broad-based assessment of potential predictors of COVID testing, including sociodemographic and coronavirus specific factor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cross-sectional observational design limits causal inference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Self-reported information about COVID testing can be subject to recall as well as social desirability bias.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.21265627" rel="alternate" title="Predictors of COVID testing among Australian youth: Insights from the Longitudinal Study of Australian Children (8 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466971</id><title>Protein arginylation is regulated during SARS-CoV-2 infection (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.301198+00:00</updated><author><name>Janaina Macedo-da-Silva</name></author><author><name>Livia Rosa-Fernandes</name></author><author><name>Vinicius de Moraes Gomes</name></author><author><name>Veronica Feijoli Santiago</name></author><author><name>Catarina Maria Stanischesk Molnar</name></author><author><name>Bruno R Barboza</name></author><author><name>Edmarcia Elisa de Sousa</name></author><author><name>Edison Luiz Durigon</name></author><author><name>Claudio Romero Farias Marinho</name></author><author><name>Carsten Wrenger</name></author><author><name>Suely Kazue Nagahashi Marie</name></author><author><name>Giuseppe Palmisano</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In 2019, the world witnessed the onset of an unprecedented pandemic. In September 2021, the infection by SARS-CoV-2 had already been responsible for the death of more than 4 million people worldwide. Recently, we and other groups discovered that SARS-CoV-2 infection induces ER-stress and activation of unfolded protein response (UPR) pathway. The degradation of misfolded/unfolded proteins is an essential element of proteostasis and occurs mainly in lysosomes or proteasomes. The N-terminal arginylation of proteins is characterized as an inducer of ubiquitination and proteasomal degradation by the N-end rule pathway. Here we present, for the first time, data on the role of arginylation during SARS-CoV-2 infection. We studied the modulation of protein arginylation in Vero CCL-81 and Calu-3 cells infected after 2h, 6h, 12h, 24h, and 48h. A reanalysis of in vivo and in vitro public omics data combined with immunoblotting was performed to measure the levels of ATE1 and arginylated proteins. This regulation is seen specifically during infections by coronaviruses. We demonstrate that during SARS-CoV-2 infection there is an increase in the expression of the ATE1 enzyme associated with regulated levels of specific arginylated proteins. On the other hand, infected macrophages showed no ATE1 regulation. An important finding revealed that modulation of the N-end rule pathway differs between different types of infected cells. We also confirmed the potential of tannic acid to reduce viral load, and furthermore, to modulate ATE1 levels during infection. In addition, the arginylation inhibitor merbromin (MER) is also capable of both reducing viral load and reducing ATE1 levels. Taken together, these data show the importance of arginylation during the progression of SARS-CoV-2 infection and open the door for future studies that may unravel the role of ATE1 and its inhibitors in pathogen infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466971" rel="alternate" title="Protein arginylation is regulated during SARS-CoV-2 infection (7 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.21265672</id><title>Chest X-ray Severity and its Association with Outcomes in Patients with COVID-19 Presenting to the Emergency Department (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.302641+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Kotok</name></author><author><name>Jose Rivera Robles</name></author><author><name>Christine Girard</name></author><author><name>Shruti Shettigar</name></author><author><name>Allen Lavina</name></author><author><name>Samantha Gillenwater</name></author><author><name>Andrew Kim</name></author><author><name>Anas Hadeh</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Severity of radiographic abnormalities on chest X-ray (CXR) in patients with COVID-19 has been shown to be associated with worse outcomes, but studies are limited by different scoring systems, sample size, patient age and study duration. Data regarding the longitudinal evolution of radiographic abnormalities and its association with outcomes is scarce. We sought to evaluate these questions using a well-validated scoring system (the Radiographic Assessment of Lung Edema [RALE] score) using data over 6 months from a large, multi-hospital healthcare system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We collected clinical and demographic data and quantified radiographic edema on CXRs obtained in the emergency department (ED) as well as on days 1-2 and 3-5 (in those admitted) in patients with a nasopharyngeal swab positive for SARS-CoV-2 PCR visiting the ED for COVID-19-related complaints between March and September 2020. We examined the association of baseline and longitudinal evolution of radiographic edema with severity of hypoxemia and clinical outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;870 patients were included (median age 53.6, 50.8% female). Inter-rate agreement for RALE scores was excellent (ICC = 0.84, 95% CI 0.82 - 0.87, p &amp;lt; 0.0001). RALE scores correlated with hypoxemia as quantified by SpO2-FiO2 ratio (r = -0.42, p &amp;lt; 0.001). Admitted patients had higher RALE scores than those discharged (6 [2, 11] vs 0 [0, 3], p &amp;lt; 0.001). An increase of RALE score of 4 or more was associated with worse 30-day survival (p &amp;lt; 0.01). Larger increases in the RALE score were associated with worse survival.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The RALE score is reproducible and easily implementable in adult patients presenting to the ED with COVID-19. Its association with physiologic parameters and outcomes at baseline and longitudinally makes it a readily available tool for prognostication and early ICU triage, particularly in patients with worsening radiographic edema.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.21265672" rel="alternate" title="Chest X-ray Severity and its Association with Outcomes in Patients with COVID-19 Presenting to the Emergency Department (7 tweets)"/><category term="Respiratory Medicine"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265478</id><title>Waning of the Humoral Response to SARS-CoV-2 in Pregnancy is Variant-Dependent (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.304236+00:00</updated><author><name>Romina Plitman Mayo</name></author><author><name>Tal Raz</name></author><author><name>Bar Ben David</name></author><author><name>Gila Meir</name></author><author><name>Haim Barr</name></author><author><name>Leonardo J. Solmesky</name></author><author><name>Rony Chen</name></author><author><name>Ana Idelson</name></author><author><name>Lucilla Zorzetti</name></author><author><name>Rinat Gabbay-Benziv</name></author><author><name>Yuval Jaffe Moshkovich</name></author><author><name>Tal Biron-Shental</name></author><author><name>Gil Shechter-Maor</name></author><author><name>Hen Yitzhak Sela</name></author><author><name>Itamar Glick</name></author><author><name>Hedi Benyamini Raischer</name></author><author><name>Raed Salim</name></author><author><name>Yariv Yogev</name></author><author><name>Ofer Beharier</name></author><author><name>Debra Goldman-Wohl</name></author><author><name>Ariel Many</name></author><author><name>Michal Kovo</name></author><author><name>Simcha Yagel</name></author><author><name>Michal Neeman</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;The&lt;/bold&gt; SARS-CoV-2 alpha variant posed increased risk for COVID-19 complications in pregnant women. However, its impact on the maternal humoral response and placental IgG transport remains unclear.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To characterize the maternal humoral waning and neonate immunity acquired during the 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; COVID-19 wave in Israel, dominated by the Alpha variant, as compared to earlier Wildtype infections and humoral response to vaccination across gestation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Maternal and fetal blood serum were collected at delivery since April 2020 from parturients. Sera IgG and IgM titers were measured using the Milliplex MAP SARS-CoV-2 Antigen Panel supplemented with additional HA-coupled microspheres.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A nationwide multicenter cohort study on SARS-CoV-2 infections and vaccination during pregnancy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Expectant women presenting for delivery were recruited at 8 medical centers across Israel and assigned to 3 primary groups: SARS-CoV-2 positive (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; = 157) and fully vaccinated during pregnancy (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; = 125), and unvaccinated noninfected controls matched to the infected group by BMI, maternal age, comorbidities and gestational age (&lt;italic&gt;n =&lt;/italic&gt; 212). Eligibility criteria included pregnant women without active COVID-19 disease, age ≥18 years and willingness to provide informed consent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Outcome(s) and Measure(s)&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pregnant women’s humoral response is dependent on the SARS-CoV-2 strain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The humoral response to infection as detected at birth, showed a gradual and significant decline as the interval between infection/vaccination and delivery increased. Significantly faster decay of antibody titers was found for infections occurring during the 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; wave compared to earlier infections/vaccination. Cord blood IgG antigens levels correlated with maternal IgG. However, cord IgG-HA variance significantly differed in SARS-CoV2 infections as compared to the other groups. No sexual dimorphism in IgG transfer was observed. Lastly, high fetal IgM response to SARS-CoV-2 was detected in 17 neonates, all showing elevated IgM to N suggesting exposure to SARS-Cov-2 antigens.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions and Relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Infections occurring during the 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; wave induced a faster decline in humoral response when compared to Wildtype infections or mRNA BNT162b2 vaccination during pregnancy, consistent with a shift in disease etiology and severity induced by the Alpha variant. Vaccination policies in previously infected pregnant women should consider the timing of exposure along pregnancy as well as the risk of infection to specific variants of concern.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key Points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Question&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;What is the difference in the maternal-fetal humoral response between Alpha variant and SARS-CoV-2 Wildtype infections?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this nationwide multicenter study including 494 pregnant women, the maternal humoral response to Alpha variant infection was weaker and shorter when compared to Wildtype infections. Placental transport compensated for the maternal waning of immunity. Fetal sex did not affect humoral response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Meaning&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vaccination policies should be adjusted to account for the timing of infection and the SARS-CoV-2 variant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265478" rel="alternate" title="Waning of the Humoral Response to SARS-CoV-2 in Pregnancy is Variant-Dependent (6 tweets)"/><category term="Obstetrics and Gynecology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466695</id><title>Antiviral activity of Pacific oyster (Crassostrea gigas) hemolymph against a human coronavirus (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.607049+00:00</updated><author><name>Rebecca L. Pedler</name></author><author><name>James O. Harris</name></author><author><name>Peter G. Speck</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Coronaviruses can cause severe respiratory infections in humans. This study aimed to assess the antiviral activity of Pacific oyster (&lt;italic&gt;Crassostrea gigas&lt;/italic&gt;) hemolymph against a human coronavirus, HCoV-229E. An eight-fold reduction in infectivity of HCoV-229E on Huh-7 cells was observed in the presence of 10% &lt;italic&gt;C. gigas&lt;/italic&gt; hemolymph. Antiviral activity of &lt;italic&gt;C. gigas&lt;/italic&gt; hemolymph positively correlated with its concentration and appears to be active during an intracellular stage of HCoV-229E infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466695" rel="alternate" title="Antiviral activity of Pacific oyster (Crassostrea gigas) hemolymph against a human coronavirus (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265807</id><title>Use cases for COVID-19 screening and surveillance with rapid antigen-detecting tests: a systematic review (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.608356+00:00</updated><author><name>Apoorva Anand</name></author><author><name>Jacob Bigio</name></author><author><name>Emily MacLean</name></author><author><name>Talya Underwood</name></author><author><name>Nitika Pant Pai</name></author><author><name>Sergio Carmona</name></author><author><name>Samuel G. Schumacher</name></author><author><name>Amy Toporowski</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Testing is critical to controlling the COVID-19 pandemic. Antigen-detecting rapid diagnostic tests (Ag-RDTs) that can be used at the point of care have the potential to increase access to COVID-19 testing, particularly in settings with limited laboratory capacity. This systematic review synthesized literature on specific use cases and performance of Ag-RDTs for detecting SARS-CoV-2, for the first comprehensive assessment of Ag-RDT use in real-world settings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We searched three databases (PubMed, EMBASE and medRxiv) up to 12 April 2021 for publications on Ag-RDT use for large-scale screening, irrespective of symptoms, and surveillance of COVID-19, excluding studies of only presumptive COVID-19 patients. We tabulated data on the study setting, populations, type of test, diagnostic performance and operational findings. We assessed risk of bias using QUADAS-2 and an adapted tool for prevalence studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;From 4313 citations, 39 studies conducted in asymptomatic and symptomatic adults were included. Study sample sizes varied from 40 to &amp;gt;5 million. Of 39 studies, 37 (94.9%) investigated lateral flow Ag-RDTs and two (5.1%) investigated multiplex sandwich chemiluminescent enzyme immunoassay Ag-RDTs. Six categories of testing (screening/surveillance) initiatives were identified: mass screening (n=13), targeted screening (n=11), healthcare entry testing (n=6), at-home testing (n=4), surveillance (n=4) and prevalence survey (n=1). Across studies, Ag-RDT sensitivity varied from 40% to 100%. Ag-RDTs were noted as convenient, easy-to-use and low cost, with a rapid turnaround time and high user acceptability. Risk of bias was generally low or unclear across the studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This systematic review demonstrates the use of Ag-RDTs across a wide range of real-world settings for screening and surveillance of COVID-19 in both symptomatic and asymptomatic individuals. Ag-RDTs were overall found to be easy-to-use, low cost and rapid tools, when consideration is given to their implementation and interpretation. The review was funded by FIND, the global alliance for diagnostics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What is already known?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Antigen-detecting rapid diagnostic tests (Ag-RDTs) have the potential to substantially improve access to timely testing for COVID-19 and are being deployed in a variety of settings around the world&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;While studies have investigated the diagnostic accuracy of Ag-RDTs, less is known about how and in what settings Ag-RDTs are being used around the world and their performance in these different settings&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What are the new findings?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ag-RDTs are being used in a diverse range of real-world settings for mass screening and surveillance of COVID-19 among symptomatic and asymptomatic individuals&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The sensitivity of Ag-RDTs is variable - ranging from 40% to 100% - and in some cases low compared with RT-PCR, meaning that the value of testing with Ag-RDTs needs to be carefully evaluated for each use case taking into account factors such as the prevalence of COVID-19 in the population, the consequences of false positive or false negative results, and whether confirmatory testing of positive or negative Ag-RDT results with RT-PCR is required&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, Ag-RDTs are generally reported as being easy to use and low cost, with a rapid turnaround time that enables timely identification of cases and subsequent interventions to prevent onward transmission of COVID-19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What do the new findings imply?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The evidence indicates that Ag-RDTs can be effectively deployed across a broad range of settings when consideration is given to how they are implemented and interpreted&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The development of more detailed, evidence-based testing policies for Ag-RDTs will be important to help countries implement effective testing programmes and make the best use of Ag-RDTs as part of the COVID-19 testing toolkit&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265807" rel="alternate" title="Use cases for COVID-19 screening and surveillance with rapid antigen-detecting tests: a systematic review (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.21265918</id><title>Longitudinal Changes of Cardiac and Aortic Imaging Phenotypes Following COVID-19 in the UK Biobank Cohort (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.609859+00:00</updated><author><name>Wenjia Bai</name></author><author><name>Betty Raman</name></author><author><name>Steffen E Peterson</name></author><author><name>Stefan Neubauer</name></author><author><name>Zahra Raisi-Estabragh</name></author><author><name>Nay Aung</name></author><author><name>Nicholas C Harvey</name></author><author><name>Naomi Allen</name></author><author><name>Rory Collins</name></author><author><name>Paul M Matthews</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Case studies conducted after recovery from acute infection with SARS-CoV-2 have frequently identified abnormalities on CMR imaging, suggesting the possibility that SARS-CoV-2 infection commonly leads to cardiac pathology.  However, these observations have not been able to distinguish between associations that reflect pre-existing cardiac abnormalities (that might confer a greater likelihood of more severe infection) from those that arise as consequences of infection.  To address this question, UK Biobank volunteers (n=1285; 54.5% women; mean age at baseline, 59.8 years old; 96.3% white) who attended an imaging assessment including cardiac magnetic resonance (CMR) before the start of the COVID-19 pandemic were invited to attend a second imaging assessment in 2021.  Cases with evidence of previous SARS-CoV-2 infection were identified through linkage to PCR-testing or other medical records, or a positive antibody lateral flow test; n=640 in data available on 22 Sep 2021) and were matched to controls with no evidence of previous infection (n=645). The majority of these infections were milder and did not involve hospitalisation.  Measures of cardiac and aortic structure and function were derived from the CMR images obtained on the cases before and after SARS-CoV-2 infection from images for the controls obtained over the same time interval using a previously validated, automated algorithm.  Cases and controls had similar cardiac and aortic imaging phenotypes at their first imaging assessment.  Changes between CMR imaging measures in cases before and after infection were not significantly different from those in the matched control group. Additional adjustment for comorbidities made no material difference to the results.  While these results are preliminary and limited to imaging metrics derived from automated analyses, they do not suggest clinically significant persistent cardiac pathology in the UK Biobank population after generally milder (non-hospitalised) SARS-CoV-2 infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.21265918" rel="alternate" title="Longitudinal Changes of Cardiac and Aortic Imaging Phenotypes Following COVID-19 in the UK Biobank Cohort (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.30.21265662</id><title>Heterogenous pattern of the inflammasome-related markers in the critically ill COVID-19 patients at the ICU admission (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.610615+00:00</updated><author><name>Barbara Adamik</name></author><author><name>Magdalena Ambrożek-Latecka</name></author><author><name>Barbara Dragan</name></author><author><name>Aldona Jeznach</name></author><author><name>Jakub Śmiechowicz</name></author><author><name>Waldemar Goździk</name></author><author><name>Tomasz Skirecki</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Purpose&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Development of targeted biological therapies for COVID-19 requires reliable biomarkers that could help indicate the responding patients. Hyperactivation of the inflammasome by SARS-CoV2 virus is hypothesized to contribute to severe course of the COVID-19 disease. Therefore, we aimed to evaluate the prognostic value of several inflammasome-related cytokines and proteins at the admission to the intensive care unit (ICU).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Patients and methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plasma samples were obtained from 45 critically ill COVID-19 patients and from10 patients with severe traumatic brain injury (TBI) at the admission to the ICU. The concentration of IL-1&lt;italic&gt;α&lt;/italic&gt;, IL-1&lt;italic&gt;β&lt;/italic&gt;, IL-18, IL-1RA, galectin-1, ASC, LDH, ferritin, and gasdermin D were analyzed. A novel cell-free caspase-1 plasma assay was developed by inhibitor-based immunoprecipitation followed by Western Blot. Demographic and clinical characteristics were recorded.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The inflammasome-related biomarkers were in similar concentration in COVID-19 and TBI patients except for galectin-1 being lower in the former. None of the tested markers were related to the outcome, length of stay or development of secondary infections. Patients with SOFA score of &amp;gt;9 at admission who were at high risk of death had significantly higher galectin-1 but lower IL-1RA in comparison to low-risk patients. Weak but significant correlations were observed between: IL-1&lt;italic&gt;α&lt;/italic&gt; and platelets, IL-1&lt;italic&gt;β&lt;/italic&gt; and platelets, ferritin and INR. Activated caspase-1 p35 was detectable in 12/22 COVID-19 patients but in none of the TBI patients. Its presence was related with higher fibrinogen and lower D-dimers. It was also significantly higher in patients with SOFA&amp;gt;9.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our results indicate that the activation of the inflammasome in critically ill COVID-19 patients is a heterogenous process and is not directly related with outcome. Therefore, potential interventions aimed at the inflammasome pathway in this group of patients may be of limited effectiveness and should be biomarker-guided.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.30.21265662" rel="alternate" title="Heterogenous pattern of the inflammasome-related markers in the critically ill COVID-19 patients at the ICU admission (5 tweets)"/><category term="Intensive Care and Critical Care Medicine"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265861</id><title>The impact of the initial and 2nd national COVID-19 lockdown on mental health in young people with and without pre-existing depressive symptoms (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.610921+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrea Joensen</name></author><author><name>Stine Danielsen</name></author><author><name>Per Kragh Andersen</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Groot</name></author><author><name>Katrine Strandberg-Larsen</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The evidence on mental well-being and loneliness among young people during the initial lockdown is mixed, and little is known about the long-lasting impact of the sequential lockdowns. We examine changes in young people’s mental health from before to during the initial and second more prolonged lockdown, and whether women and those with pre-existing depressive symptoms were disproportionally impacted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Participants reported on mental health indicators in an ongoing 18-year data collection in the Danish National Birth Cohort and in a COVID-19 survey, including 8 data points: 7 in the initial lockdown, and 1 year post. Changes in quality of life (QoL), mental well-being, and loneliness were estimated with random effect linear regressions on longitudinal data (N=32,985), and linear regressions on repeated cross-sections (N=28,579).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interim deterioration in mental well-being and loneliness was observed during the initial lockdown, and only in those without pre-existing depressive symptoms. During the second lockdown, a modest deterioration was again observed for mental well-being and loneliness. QoL likewise only declined among those without pre-existing symptoms, where women showed a greater decline than men. QoL did not normalise during the initial lockdown and remained at lower levels during the second lockdown. These findings were not replicated in the repeated cross-sections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Except for an interim decrease in mental health during lockdown, and only in those without pre-existing depressive symptoms, this study’s findings do not suggest a substantial detrimental impact of the lockdowns. Potential methodological differences in-between studies are a possible explanation for the mixed evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Velux Foundation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Research in context&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Evidence before this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We searched PubMed, PsycINFO, MedrXiv, and PsyArXiv with the terms (“Mental*” OR “Psychological*” OR “Emotional*”) AND (“Youth” OR “Young Adult*”) AND (“COVID*” OR “Coronavirus” OR “Lockdown*”) for articles published in English between January 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; 2020 and October 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; 2021. Included studies varied in terms of quality of data used but overall studies reported a detrimental impact of the lockdowns on young people’s mental health. However, the evidence on mental well-being and loneliness has shown to be inconsistent and with signs of resilience. Young people, women, and those with a pre-existing mental disorder have been identified as vulnerable subgroups, but only a few studies investigating mental health in individuals with a pre-existing mental disorder included a pre-lockdown measurement. The included studies also demonstrated that there is a gap in the evidence in understanding how mental health changed week by week, as well as the long-term impact over the course of the lockdowns.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Added value of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;With longitudinal data, this study shows an interim impact of the initial and second lockdown on mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic in young individuals without pre-existing symptoms in Denmark. Since commencement of the initial lockdown, the levels of mental health returned to before levels, but one year after the initial lockdown, the levels were still lower than before lockdown in young people without pre-existing depressive symptoms. Young individuals with pre-existing depressive symptoms did not experience more detrimental impact of the lockdown, but rather indication of resilience or even improvements in mental health were observed. A disproportional impact of the lockdown on women compared to men was only observed for QoL, as women without pre-exiting depressive symptoms experienced a greater decline in QoL than men without pre-existing depressive symptoms. However, findings based on the repeated cross-sectional data did not show similar interim impact – but instead no – or clinically irrelevant impact. Thus, taken together our findings do not suggest a substantial lasting impact of the lockdowns on mental health among young individuals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Implications of all available evidence&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A great majority of earlier studies suggest that the lockdowns due to the COVID-19 pandemic have had substantial detrimental impact on mental health, and that women and those with a pre-existing mental disorder constitute vulnerable subgroups. However, these studies vary considerably in terms of method applied. Our findings emphasise the importance of the use of different data setups, as well as methodology applied for the investigation of mental health. More studies based on high-quality data used in different settings are needed to fully understand the impact of the lockdowns on young people’s mental health, including potential disproportional impact on vulnerable subgroups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265861" rel="alternate" title="The impact of the initial and 2nd national COVID-19 lockdown on mental health in young people with and without pre-existing depressive symptoms (4 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265877</id><title>REACT-1 round 15 interim report: High and rising prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 infection in England from end of September 2021 followed by a fall in late October 2021 (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.611348+00:00</updated><author><name>Marc Chadeau-Hyam</name></author><author><name>Oliver Eales</name></author><author><name>Barbara Bodinier</name></author><author><name>Haowei Wang</name></author><author><name>David Haw</name></author><author><name>Matthew Whitaker</name></author><author><name>Caroline E. Walters</name></author><author><name>Christina Atchison</name></author><author><name>Peter J. Diggle</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Page</name></author><author><name>Deborah Ashby</name></author><author><name>Wendy Barclay</name></author><author><name>Graham Taylor</name></author><author><name>Graham Cooke</name></author><author><name>Helen Ward</name></author><author><name>Ara Darzi</name></author><author><name>Christl A. Donnelly</name></author><author><name>Paul Elliott</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The third wave of COVID-19 in England coincided with the rapid spread of the Delta variant of SARS-CoV-2 from the end of May 2021. Case incidence data from the national testing programme (Pillar 2) in England may be affected by changes in testing behaviour and other biases. Community surveys may provide important contextual information to inform policy and the public health response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We estimated patterns of community prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 infection in England using RT-PCR swab-positivity, demographic and other risk factor data from round 15 (interim) of the REal-time Assessment of Community Transmission-1 (REACT-1) study (round 15a, carried out from 19 to 29 October 2021). We compared these findings with those from round 14 (9 to 27 September 2021).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;During mid- to late-October 2021 (round 15a) weighted prevalence was 1.72% (1.61%, 1.84%) compared to 0.83% (0.76%, 0.89%) in September 2021 (round 14). The overall reproduction number (R) from round 14 to round 15a was 1.12 (1.11, 1.14) with increases in prevalence over this period (September to October) across age groups and regions except Yorkshire and The Humber. However, within round 15a (mid- to late-October) there was evidence of a fall in prevalence with R of 0.76 (0.65, 0.88). The highest weighted prevalence was observed among children aged 5 to 12 years at 5.85% (5.10%, 6.70%) and 13 to 17 years at 5.75% (5.02%, 6.57%). At regional level, there was an almost four-fold increase in weighted prevalence in South West from round 14 at 0.59% (0.43%,0.80%) to round 15a at 2.18% (1.84%, 2.58%), with highest smoothed prevalence at subregional level also found in South West in round 15a. Age, sex, key worker status, and presence of children in the home jointly contributed to the risk of swab-positivity. Among the 126 sequenced positive swabs obtained up until 23 October, all were Delta variant; 13 (10.3%) were identified as the AY.4.2 sub-lineage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Discussion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We observed the highest overall prevalence of swab-positivity seen in the REACT-1 study in England to date in round 15a (October 2021), with a two-fold rise in swab-positivity from round 14 (September 2021). Despite evidence of a fall in prevalence from mid- to late-October 2021, prevalence remains high, particularly in school-aged children, with evidence also of higher prevalence in households with one or more children. Thus, vaccination of children aged 12 and over remains a high priority (with possible extension to children aged 5-12) to help reduce within-household transmission and disruptions to education, as well as among adults, to lessen the risk of serious disease among those infected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265877" rel="alternate" title="REACT-1 round 15 interim report: High and rising prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 infection in England from end of September 2021 followed by a fall in late October 2021 (4 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.21265569</id><title>Evaluation of patients treated by telemedicine in the COVID-19 pandemic by a private clinic in Sao Paulo, Brazil: A non-randomized clinical trial preliminary study (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.611797+00:00</updated><author><name>Michelle Chechter</name></author><author><name>Gustavo Maximiliano Dutra da Silva</name></author><author><name>Thomas Gabriel Miklos</name></author><author><name>Marta Maria Kemp</name></author><author><name>Nilzio Antonio da Silva</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Lober Lober</name></author><author><name>Marcela Ferreira Tavares Zanut</name></author><author><name>Rute Alves Pereira e Costa</name></author><author><name>Aline Pinheiro dos Santos Cortada</name></author><author><name>Luciana de Nazare Lima da Cruz</name></author><author><name>Paulo Macio Porto de Melo</name></author><author><name>Bruno Campello de Souza</name></author><author><name>Morton Aaron Scheinberg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Introduction: As a result of the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic the year 2020 brought major changes on the delivery of health care and face to face physician patient communication was significantly reduced and the practice of remote telehealth care using computer technology is assuming a standard of care particularly with COVID-19 patients with attempts to reduce viral spread.
Objective: To describe the clinical practice experience using telemedicine towards COVID-19 and the respective clinical outcomes.
Methods: We performed a pilot open-label non-randomized controlled clinical trial. The patients were divided into four groups according severity of symptoms: (1) asymptomatic (2) mild symptoms (3) moderate symptoms and (4) severe symptoms and were followed up for five days counted from the beginning of the symptoms. A drug intervention was performed in group 3 for which the protocol followed as suggested by the International Pulmonology Societys consensus for adults with moderate symptoms: first day (attack phase) hydroxychloroquine sulfate 400 mg 12/12h second to fifth day (maintenance phase) 200 mg (half pill) 12/12h. The medication was associated with azithromycin 500mg once a day for five days. For children with moderate symptoms were used: hydroxychloroquine sulfate 6.5 mg/kg/dose every 12 hours in the first day and 3.25 mg/kg/dose every 12 hours from day 2 to 5. The therapeutic response was telemonitored. Group 4 patients were directly oriented to seek hospital care. During the use of the drugs, the patients were telemonitored daily.
Results: One hundred eighty-seven patients were seen with mean age of 37,6 years (about 15,6). The most frequent symptom was cough (57,6%) followed by malaise (60,3%) fever (41,1%) headache (56,0%) muscle pain (51,1%). Of all the patients that sought telemedicine service in our center 23% were asymptomatic despite contact with people with probable diagnostic of COVID-19 29,4% reported mild symptoms 43,9% moderate symptoms and 3,7% severe symptoms. It was possible to observe in patients treated their symptoms of COVID-19 (group 3) with hydroxychloroquine and azithromycin for five days presented statistically better improvement of the symptoms when compared to those that did not follow the protocol (p = 0.039). Three patients were hospitalized and discharged after recovery.
Conclusions: Our study showed that patients with COVID-19 who had delivery of health care through telemedicine initiated in early stages of the disease presented satisfactory clinical response, reducing the need of face-to-face consultations and hospitalizations. Our results indicate that the use of telemedicine with diagnosis and drug treatment protocols is a safe and effective strategy to reduce overload of health services and the exposure of healthcare providers and the general population to infected patients in a pandemic situation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.21265569" rel="alternate" title="Evaluation of patients treated by telemedicine in the COVID-19 pandemic by a private clinic in Sao Paulo, Brazil: A non-randomized clinical trial preliminary study (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.21265714</id><title>Azithromycin consumption during the COVID-19 pandemic in Croatia, 2020 (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.612140+00:00</updated><author><name>Nikolina Bogdanić</name></author><author><name>Loris Močibob</name></author><author><name>Toni Vidović</name></author><author><name>Ana Soldo</name></author><author><name>Josip Begovac</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the initial phase of the COVID-19 pandemic, there was great enthusiasm for the use of azithromycin with or without hydroxychloroquine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We analyzed azithromycin consumption in Croatia in 2020 and compared this to the period 2017–2019.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Azithromycin consumption was evaluated using the IQVIA Adriatic d.o.o. database which collects data on azithromycin distribution from wholesale pharmacies to hospital and non-hospital pharmacies in Croatia. We analyzed data for the period from January 2017 to December 2020. Azithromycin distribution was measured as days of therapy (DOT) and reported as per 1000 inhabitants or per 1000 inhabitant-days.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the period 2017–2020, total azithromycin DOT in Croatia increased in 2017, 2018, 2019, and 2020 (1.76, 1.91, 1.91 and 2.01/1000 inhabitant-days, respectively). Non-hospital pharmacies received 2.18 times and hospital pharmacies 4.39 times more DOT units/1000 inhabitants of azithromycin in March 2020 compared to the average distribution rate in March 2017–2019. During the peak of the COVID-19 epidemic (November and December 2020) azithromycin distribution increased considerably in hospital (3.62 and 3.19 times, respectively) and non-hospital pharmacies (1.93 and 1.84 times, respectively) compared to the average consumption in the same months in 2017–2019.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our data showed increased azithromycin distribution in the period 2017 – 2020 which indicates azithromycin overuse. Preliminary information on COVID-19 treatments with a desire to offer and try what is available even in the absence of strong scientific evidence may have influenced practices of antimicrobial prescriptions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.21265714" rel="alternate" title="Azithromycin consumption during the COVID-19 pandemic in Croatia, 2020 (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265791</id><title>Cohort study of Covid-19 vaccine effectiveness among healthcare workers in Finland, December 2020 - October 2021 (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.612415+00:00</updated><author><name>Eero Poukka</name></author><author><name>Ulrike Baum</name></author><author><name>Arto A Palmu</name></author><author><name>Toni O Lehtonen</name></author><author><name>Heini Salo</name></author><author><name>Hanna Nohynek</name></author><author><name>Tuija Leino</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recently, Covid-19 vaccine effectiveness has decreased especially against mild disease due to emergence of the Delta variant and waning protection. In this register-based study among healthcare workers in Finland, the vaccine effectiveness of two-dose mRNA vaccine series against SARS-CoV-2 infection decreased from 82% (95% CI 79-85%) 14-90 days after vaccination to 53% (43-62%) after 6 months. Similar trend was observed for other series. Waning was not observed against Covid-19 hospitalization. These results facilitate decision-making of booster doses for healthcare workers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265791" rel="alternate" title="Cohort study of Covid-19 vaccine effectiveness among healthcare workers in Finland, December 2020 - October 2021 (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467186</id><title>Stenoparib, an inhibitor of cellular poly (ADP-ribose) polymerases (PARPs), blocks in vitro replication of SARS-CoV-2 variants (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.612749+00:00</updated><author><name>Katherine E Zarn</name></author><author><name>Sierra A Jaramillo</name></author><author><name>Anthony R Zapata</name></author><author><name>Nathan E Stone</name></author><author><name>Ashley N Jones</name></author><author><name>Haley E Nunnally</name></author><author><name>Erik W Settles</name></author><author><name>Ken Ng</name></author><author><name>Paul S Keim</name></author><author><name>Steen Knudsen</name></author><author><name>Patricia M Nuijten</name></author><author><name>Aloys SI Tijsma</name></author><author><name>Christopher T French</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We recently published a preliminary assessment of the activity of a poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase (PARP) inhibitor, stenoparib, also known as 2X-121, which inhibits viral replication by affecting pathways of the host. Stenoparib is an inhibitor of mammalian poly (ADP-ribose) polymerases (PARPs). Here we show that stenoparib effectively inhibits additional SARS-CoV-2 variants, including an additional wild-type strain (Germany/BavPat1/2020), and the variants &lt;italic&gt;alpha&lt;/italic&gt; (B.1.1.7), &lt;italic&gt;beta&lt;/italic&gt; (B.1.351) and &lt;italic&gt;gamma&lt;/italic&gt; (P.1) &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, with 50% effective concentration (EC&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;) estimates of 4.1 μM, 8.5 μM, 24.2 μM and 13.6 μM, respectively. A second study focusing on a combination of 10 μM stenoparib and 0.5 µM remdesivir resulted in over 90% inhibition of the &lt;italic&gt;alpha&lt;/italic&gt; (B.1.1.7) variant, which is substantially greater than what was achieved with stenoparib or remdesivir alone at these concentrations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467186" rel="alternate" title="Stenoparib, an inhibitor of cellular poly (ADP-ribose) polymerases (PARPs), blocks in vitro replication of SARS-CoV-2 variants (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.30.21265430</id><title>Automated Interpretable Discovery of Heterogeneous Treatment Effectiveness: A Covid-19 Case Study (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.613667+00:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin J. Lengerich</name></author><author><name>Mark E. Nunally</name></author><author><name>Yin Aphinyanaphongs</name></author><author><name>Rich Caruana</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Testing multiple treatments for heterogeneous (varying) effectiveness with respect to many underlying risk factors requires many pairwise tests; we would like to instead automatically discover and visualize patient archetypes and predictors of treatment effectiveness using multitask machine learning. In this paper, we present a method to estimate these heterogeneous treatment effects with an interpretable hierarchical framework that uses additive models to visualize expected treatment benefits as a function of patient factors (identifying personalized treatment benefits) and concurrent treatments (identifying combinatorial treatment benefits). This method achieves state-of-the-art predictive power for Covid-19 in-hospital mortality and interpretable identification of heterogeneous treatment benefits. We first validate this method on the large public MIMIC-IV dataset of ICU patients to test recovery of heterogeneous treatment effects. Next we apply this method to a proprietary dataset of over 3000 patients hospitalized for Covid-19, and find evidence of heterogeneous treatment effectiveness predicted largely by indicators of inflammation and throm-bosis risk: patients with few indicators of thrombosis risk benefit most from treatments against inflammation, while patients with few indicators of inflammation risk benefit most from treatments against thrombosis. This approach provides an automated methodology to discover heterogeneous and individualized effectiveness of treatments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.30.21265430" rel="alternate" title="Automated Interpretable Discovery of Heterogeneous Treatment Effectiveness: A Covid-19 Case Study (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.21265767</id><title>Determinants of pre-vaccination antibody responses to SARS-CoV-2: a population-based longitudinal study (COVIDENCE UK) (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.614101+00:00</updated><author><name>Mohammad Talaei</name></author><author><name>Sian Faustini</name></author><author><name>Hayley Holt</name></author><author><name>David A. Jolliffe</name></author><author><name>Giulia Vivaldi</name></author><author><name>Matthew Greenig</name></author><author><name>Natalia Perdek</name></author><author><name>Sheena Maltby</name></author><author><name>Jane Symons</name></author><author><name>Gwyneth A Davies</name></author><author><name>Ronan A Lyons</name></author><author><name>Christopher J Griffiths</name></author><author><name>Frank Kee</name></author><author><name>Aziz Sheikh</name></author><author><name>Alex G Richter</name></author><author><name>Seif O Shaheen</name></author><author><name>Adrian R Martineau</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prospective population-based studies investigating multiple determinants of pre-vaccination antibody responses to SARS-CoV-2 are lacking.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We did a prospective population-based study in SARS-CoV-2 vaccine-naive UK adults between May 1 and Nov 2, 2020. Information on 88 potential risk factors was obtained through online questionnaires, and combined IgG/IgA/IgM responses to SARS-CoV-2 spike glycoprotein were determined in dried blood spots. We used logistic and linear regression to estimate adjusted odds ratios (aORs) and adjusted geometric mean ratios (aGMRs) for potential determinants of SARS-CoV-2 seropositivity (all participants) and antibody titres (seropositive participants only), respectively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;1696 (15.2%) of 11,130 participants were seropositive. Factors independently associated with increased risk included frontline health/care occupation (aOR 1.86, 95% CI 1.49–2.33), international travel (1.22, 1.08–1.37), BMI &amp;gt;30 &lt;italic&gt;vs&lt;/italic&gt; &amp;lt;25 kg/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; (1.22, 1.05–1.42), Asian/Asian British &lt;italic&gt;vs&lt;/italic&gt; White ethnicity (1.65, 1.10–2.47), and alcohol consumption ≥15 &lt;italic&gt;vs&lt;/italic&gt; 0 units/week (1.26, 1.06–1.49). Light physical exercise associated with decreased risk (0.80, 0.69–0.93, for ≥10 &lt;italic&gt;vs&lt;/italic&gt; 0–4 h/week). Higher titres associated with frontline health/care occupation (aGMR 1.26, 95% CI 1.13–1.41), international travel (1.10, 1.04–1.16), BMI &amp;gt;30 &lt;italic&gt;vs&lt;/italic&gt; &amp;lt;25 kg/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; (1.09, 1.01–1.17), and Asian/Asian British &lt;italic&gt;vs&lt;/italic&gt; White ethnicity (1.23, 1.03–1.46); these associations were not substantially attenuated by adjustment for disease severity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Higher alcohol consumption and reduced physical exercise represent new modifiable risk factors for SARS-CoV-2 infection. Recognised associations between Asian/Asian British ethnic origin and obesity and increased risk of SARS-CoV-2 seropositivity were independent of other sociodemographic, clinical, or behavioural factors investigated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Barts Charity, Health Data Research UK.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.21265767" rel="alternate" title="Determinants of pre-vaccination antibody responses to SARS-CoV-2: a population-based longitudinal study (COVIDENCE UK) (4 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.21265831</id><title>Multiplex Solid-Phase RPA Coupled CRISPR-Based Visual Detection of SARS-CoV-2 (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.614587+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaochen Qin</name></author><author><name>Yuyuan Zhou</name></author><author><name>Ratul Paul</name></author><author><name>Yue Wu</name></author><author><name>Yaling Liu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 has challenged the world’s public health and led to over 4.5 million deaths. A rapid, sensitive, and cost-effective point-of-care virus detection device is crucial to the control and surveillance of the contagious severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) pandemic. Here we demonstrate a solid phase isothermal recombinase polymerase amplification coupled CRISPR-based (spRPA-CRISPR) assay for on-chip multiplexed, sensitive and visual COVID-19 DNA detection. By targeting the SARS-CoV-2 structure protein encoded genomes, two specific genes were simultaneously detected with the control sample without cross-interaction with other sequences. The endpoint signal can be directly visualized for rapid detection of COVID-19. The amplified target sequences were immobilized on the one-pot device surface and detected using the mixed Cas12a-crRNA collateral cleavage of reporter released fluorescent signal when specific genes were recognized. The system was tested with samples of a broad range of concentrations (20 to 2×10&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; copies) and showed analytical sensitivity down to 20 copies per reaction. Furthermore, a low-cost LED UV flashlight (∼$12) was used to provide a visible SARS-CoV-2 detection signal of the spRPA-CRISPR assay which could be purchased online easily. Thus, our platform provides a sensitive and easy-to-read multiplexed gene detection method with the capacity to specifically identify low concentration genes. Similar CRISPR biosensor chips can support a broad range of applications such as HPV DNA detection, influenza SARS-CoV-2 multiplex detection, and other infectious disease testing assays.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;A commercially available UV flashlight excited CRISPR-Cas12a based visual sensor combined with solid-phase RPA&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The developed assay could detect SARS-CoV-2 down to 20 copies with no signal crosswalk&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;This multiplexed on-chip virus detection system would provide great insight for detecting and differentiating SARS-CoV-2 from other viral infections with a single sample simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.21265831" rel="alternate" title="Multiplex Solid-Phase RPA Coupled CRISPR-Based Visual Detection of SARS-CoV-2 (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.21265729</id><title>Quantifying the effects of non-pharmaceutical and pharmaceutical interventions against COVID-19 epidemic in the Republic of Korea: Mathematical model-based approach considering age groups and the Delta variant (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.627090+00:00</updated><author><name>Youngsuk Ko</name></author><author><name>Victoria May P. Mendoza</name></author><author><name>Yubin Seo</name></author><author><name>Jacob Lee</name></author><author><name>Yeonju Kim</name></author><author><name>Donghyok Kwon</name></author><author><name>Eunok Jung</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Early vaccination efforts and non-pharmaceutical interventions were insufficient to prevent a surge of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) cases triggered by the Delta variant. This study aims to understand how vaccination and variants contribute to the spread of COVID-19 so that appropriate measures are implemented.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A compartment model that includes age, vaccination, and infection with the Delta or non-Delta variants was developed. We estimated the transmission rates using maximum likelihood estimation and phase-dependent reduction effect of non-pharmaceutical interventions (NPIs) according to government policies from 26 February to 8 October 2021. We extended our model simulation until 31 December considering the initiation of eased NPIs. Furthermore, we also performed simulations to examine the effect of NPIs, arrival timing of Delta variant, and speed of vaccine administration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The estimated transmission rate matrices show distinct pattern, with the transmission rates of younger age groups (0 39 years) much larger than non-Delta. Social distancing (SD) level 2 and SD4 in Korea were associated with transmission reduction factors of 0.64 to 0.69 and 0.70 to 0.78, respectively. The easing of NPIs to a level comparable to SD2 should be initiated not earlier than 16 October to keep the number of severe cases below the capacity of Korea’s healthcare system. Simulation results also showed that a surge prompted by the spread of the Delta variant can be prevented if the number of people vaccinated daily was larger.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Simulations showed that the timing of easing and intensity of NPIs, vaccination speed, and screening measures are key factors in preventing another epidemic wave.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;label&gt;2&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key Messages&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Maximum likelihood estimation can be utilized to determine the transmission rates of the Delta and non-Delta variants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The phase-dependent NPIs implemented by the Korean government were effectively quantified in the modelling study.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even with fast vaccination, resurgence of cases is still possible if NPIs are eased too early or screening measures are relaxed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The model can be used as a guide for policy makers on deciding appropriate SD level that considers not only disease control, but also the socio-economic impact of maintaining strict measures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.21265729" rel="alternate" title="Quantifying the effects of non-pharmaceutical and pharmaceutical interventions against COVID-19 epidemic in the Republic of Korea: Mathematical model-based approach considering age groups and the Delta variant (4 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.21265937</id><title>Estimation of the basic reproduction number of COVID-19 from the incubation period distribution (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.638157+00:00</updated><author><name>Lasko Basnarkov</name></author><author><name>Igor Tomovski</name></author><author><name>Florin Avram</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background


The estimates of future course of spreading of the SARS-CoV-2 virus are frequently based on Markovian models in which the transitions between the compartments are exponentially distributed. Specifically, the basic reproduction number R0 is also determined from formulae where it is related to the parameters of such models. The observations show that the start of infectivity of an individual appears nearly at the same time as the onset of symptoms, while the distribution of the incubation period is not an exponential.

Methods

We propose a method for estimation of R0 for COVID-19 based on the empirical incubation period distribution and assumed very short infectivity period that lasts only few days around the onset of symptoms. It is tested on daily new cases in six major countries in Europe, in the first wave of epidemic in spring, 2020. 

Results

The calculations show that even if the infectivity starts two days before the onset of symptoms and stops immediately when they appear, the value of R0 is larger than that from the classical, Markovian approach. For more realistic cases, when only individuals with mild symptoms spread the virus for few days after onset of symptoms, the respective values are even larger.

Conclusions

The calculations of R0 and other characteristics of spreading of COVID-19 based on the classical, Markovian approaches should be taken very cautiously. Instead, non-Markovian models with general distribution functions of transition between compartments should be considered as more appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.21265937" rel="alternate" title="Estimation of the basic reproduction number of COVID-19 from the incubation period distribution (3 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.466677</id><title>Multiple spillovers and onward transmission of SARS-Cov-2 in free-living and captive White-tailed deer (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.639822+00:00</updated><author><name>Suresh V Kuchipudi</name></author><author><name>Meera Surendran-Nair</name></author><author><name>Rachel M Ruden</name></author><author><name>Michele Yon</name></author><author><name>Ruth H Nissly</name></author><author><name>Rahul K Nelli</name></author><author><name>Lingling Li</name></author><author><name>Bhushan M Jayarao</name></author><author><name>Kurt Vandegrift</name></author><author><name>Costas D Maranas</name></author><author><name>Nicole Levine</name></author><author><name>Katriina Willgert</name></author><author><name>Andrew J.K Conlan</name></author><author><name>Randall J Olsen</name></author><author><name>James Davis</name></author><author><name>James M. Musser</name></author><author><name>Peter J Hudson</name></author><author><name>Vivek Kapur</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many animal species are susceptible to SARS-CoV-2 and could potentially act as reservoirs, yet transmission of the virus in non-human free-living animals has not been documented. White-tailed deer (Odocoileus virginianus), the predominant cervid in North America, are susceptible to SARS-CoV-2 infection, and experimentally infected fawns can transmit the virus. To test the hypothesis that SARS-CoV-2 may be circulating in deer, we tested 283 retropharyngeal lymph node (RPLN) samples collected from 151 free-living and 132 captive deer in Iowa from April 2020 through December of 2020 for the presence of SARS-CoV-2 RNA.  Ninety-four of the 283 deer (33.2%; 95% CI: 28, 38.9) samples were positive for SARS-CoV-2 RNA as assessed by RT-PCR. Notably, between November 23, 2020 and January 10, 2021, 80 of 97 (82.5%; 95% CI 73.7, 88.8) RPLN samples had detectable SARS-CoV-2 RNA by RT-PCR. Whole genome sequencing of the 94 positive RPLN samples identified 12 SARS-CoV-2 lineages, with B.1.2 (n = 51; 54.5%), and B.1.311 (n = 19; 20%) accounting for ~75% of all samples. The geographic distribution and nesting of clusters of deer and human lineages strongly suggest multiple zooanthroponotic spillover events and deer-to-deer transmission. The discovery of sylvatic and enzootic SARS-CoV-2 transmission in deer has important implications for the ecology and long-term persistence, as well as the potential for spillover to other animals and spillback into humans.  These findings highlight an urgent need for a robust and proactive One Health approach to obtaining a better understanding of the ecology and evolution of SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.466677" rel="alternate" title="Multiple spillovers and onward transmission of SARS-Cov-2 in free-living and captive White-tailed deer (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.21265826</id><title>The basic reproduction number of COVID-19 across Africa (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.652125+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarafa A. Iyaniwura</name></author><author><name>Musa Rabiu</name></author><author><name>Jummy F. David</name></author><author><name>Jude D. Kong</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The pandemic of the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) took the world by surprise. Following the first outbreak of COVID-19 in December 2019, several models have been developed to study and understand its transmission dynamics. Although the spread of COVID-19 is being slowed down by vaccination and other interventions, there is still a need to have a clear understanding of the evolution of the pandemic across countries, states and communities. To this end, there is a need to have a clearer picture of the initial spread of the disease in different regions. In this project, we used a simple SEIR model and a Bayesian inference framework to estimate the basic reproduction number of COVID-19 across Africa. Our estimates vary between 1.98 (Sudan) and 9.66 (Mauritius), with a median of 3.67 (90% CrI: 3.31 - 4.12). The estimates provided in this paper will help to inform COVID-19 modeling in the respective countries/regions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.21265826" rel="alternate" title="The basic reproduction number of COVID-19 across Africa (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466865</id><title>Low selectivity index of ivermectin and macrocyclic lactones on SARS-CoV2 replication in vitro argues against their therapeutic use for COVID-19 (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.655339+00:00</updated><author><name>Christine Chable-Bessia</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Boullé</name></author><author><name>Aymeric Neyret</name></author><author><name>Jitandrya Swain</name></author><author><name>Mathilde Hénaut</name></author><author><name>Peggy Merida</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Gros</name></author><author><name>Alain Makinson</name></author><author><name>Sébastien Lyonnais</name></author><author><name>Cédric B. Chesnais</name></author><author><name>Delphine Muriaux</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;There are very limited antiviral therapeutic options for coronavirus infections, therefore global drug re-purposing efforts are paramount to identify available compounds that could provide clinical benefits to patients with COVID-19. Ivermectin was first approved for human use as an endectocide in the 1980s. It remains one of the most important global health medicines in history and has recently been shown to exert &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; activity against SARS-CoV-2. However, the macrocyclic lactone family of compounds has not previously been evaluated for activity against SARS-CoV-2. The present study aims at comparing their anti-viral activity in relevant pulmonary cell lines in vitro. Here, &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; antiviral activity of the avermectins (ivermectin and selamectin) and milbemycins (moxidectin and milbemycin oxime) were assessed against a clinical isolate from a CHU Montpellier patient infected with SARS-CoV-2 in 2020. Ivermectin demonstrated anti-SARS-CoV-2 activity in vitro in human pulmonary cells in comparison to VeroE6 (with EC&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; of 1-3 μM). Similarly, the other macrocyclic lactones moxidectin, milbemycin oxime and selamectin reduced SARS-CoV-2 replication in vitro (with EC&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; of 2-5 μM). Immunofluorescence assays with ivermectin and moxidectin showed a reduction in the number of infected and polynuclear cells suggesting a drug action on viral cell fusion. However, cellular toxicity of the avermectins and milbemycins during infection showed a very low selectivity index &amp;lt;10 for all compounds. In conclusion, none of these agents appears suitable for human use for its anti-SARS-CoV-2 activity &lt;italic&gt;per se&lt;/italic&gt;, due to low selectivity index. This is discussed in regards to recent clinical COVID studies on ivermectin.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466865" rel="alternate" title="Low selectivity index of ivermectin and macrocyclic lactones on SARS-CoV2 replication in vitro argues against their therapeutic use for COVID-19 (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265685</id><title>Hypothyroidism does not lead to worse prognosis in COVID-19: findings from the Brazilian COVID-19 registry (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.655720+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniella Nunes Pereira</name></author><author><name>Leticia Ferreira Gontijo Silveira</name></author><author><name>Milena Maria Moreira Guimarães</name></author><author><name>Carísi Anne Polanczyk</name></author><author><name>Aline Gabrielle Sousa Nunes</name></author><author><name>André Soares de Moura Costa</name></author><author><name>Barbara Lopes Farace</name></author><author><name>Christiane Corrêa Rodrigues Cimini</name></author><author><name>Cíntia Alcantara de Carvalho</name></author><author><name>Daniela Ponce</name></author><author><name>Eliane Würdig Roesch</name></author><author><name>Euler Roberto Fernandes Manenti</name></author><author><name>Fernanda Barbosa Lucas</name></author><author><name>Fernanda d’Athayde Rodrigues</name></author><author><name>Fernando Anschau</name></author><author><name>Fernando Graça Aranha</name></author><author><name>Frederico Bartolazzi</name></author><author><name>Giovanna Grunewald Vietta</name></author><author><name>Guilherme Fagundes Nascimento</name></author><author><name>Helena Duani</name></author><author><name>Heloisa Reniers Vianna</name></author><author><name>Henrique Cerqueira Guimarães</name></author><author><name>Jamille Hemétrio Salles Martins Costa</name></author><author><name>Joanna d’Arc Lyra Batista</name></author><author><name>Joice Coutinho de Alvarenga</name></author><author><name>José Miguel Chatkin</name></author><author><name>Júlia Drumond Parreiras de Morais</name></author><author><name>Juliana Machado-Rugolo</name></author><author><name>Karen Brasil Ruschel</name></author><author><name>Lílian Santos Pinheiro</name></author><author><name>Luanna Silva Monteiro Menezes</name></author><author><name>Luciana Siuves Ferreira Couto</name></author><author><name>Luciane Kopittke</name></author><author><name>Luís César de Castro</name></author><author><name>Luiz Antônio Nasi</name></author><author><name>Máderson Alvares de Souza Cabral</name></author><author><name>Maiara Anschau Floriani</name></author><author><name>Maíra Dias Souza</name></author><author><name>Marcelo Carneiro</name></author><author><name>Maria Aparecida Camargos Bicalho</name></author><author><name>Mariana Frizzo de Godoy</name></author><author><name>Matheus Carvalho Alves Nogueira</name></author><author><name>Milton Henriques Guimarães Júnior</name></author><author><name>Natália da Cunha Severino Sampaio</name></author><author><name>Neimy Ramos de Oliveira</name></author><author><name>Pedro Ledic Assaf</name></author><author><name>Renan Goulart Finger</name></author><author><name>Roberta Xavier Campos</name></author><author><name>Rochele Mosmann Menezes</name></author><author><name>Saionara Cristina Francisco</name></author><author><name>Samuel Penchel Alvarenga</name></author><author><name>Silvana Mangeon Mereilles Guimarães</name></author><author><name>Silvia Ferreira Araújo</name></author><author><name>Talita Fischer Oliveira</name></author><author><name>Thulio Henrique Oliveira Diniz</name></author><author><name>Yuri Carlotto Ramires</name></author><author><name>Evelin Paola de Almeida Cenci</name></author><author><name>Thainara Conceição de Oliveira</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Vargas Schwarzbold</name></author><author><name>Patricia Klarmann Ziegelmann</name></author><author><name>Roberta Pozza</name></author><author><name>Magda Carvalho Pires</name></author><author><name>Milena Soriano Marcolino</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is not clear whether previous thyroid diseases influence the course and outcomes of COVID-19. The study aims to compare clinical characteristics and outcomes of COVID-19 patients with and without hypothyroidism.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study is a part of a multicentric cohort of patients with confirmed COVID-19 diagnosis, including data collected from 37 hospitals. Matching for age, sex, number of comorbidities and hospital was performed to select the patients without hypothyroidism for the paired analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;From 7,762 COVID-19 patients, 526 had previously diagnosed hypothyroidism (50%) and 526 were selected as matched controls. The median age was 70 (interquartile range 59.0-80.0) years-old and 68.3% were females. The prevalence of underlying comorbidities were similar between groups, except for coronary and chronic kidney diseases, that had a higher prevalence in the hypothyroidism group (9.7% vs. 5.7%, p=0.015 and 9.9% vs. 4.8%, p=0.001, respectively). At hospital presentation, patients with hypothyroidism had a lower frequency of respiratory rate &amp;gt; 24 breaths per minute (36.1% vs 42.0%; p=0.050) and need of mechanical ventilation (4.0% vs 7.4%; p=0.016). D-dimer levels were slightly lower in hypothyroid patients (2.3 times higher than the reference value vs 2.9 times higher; p=0.037). In-hospital management was similar between groups, but hospital length-of-stay (8 vs 9 days; p=0.029) and mechanical ventilation requirement (25.4% vs. 33.1%; p=0.006) were lower for patients with hypothyroidism. There was a trend of lower in-hospital mortality in patients with hypothyroidism (22.1% vs. 27.0%; p=0.062).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this large Brazilian COVID-19 Registry, patients with hypothyroidism had a lower requirement of mechanical ventilation, and showed a trend of lower in-hospital mortality. Therefore, hypothyroidism does not seem to be associated with a worse prognosis, and should not be considered among the comorbidities that indicate a risk factor for COVID-19 severity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265685" rel="alternate" title="Hypothyroidism does not lead to worse prognosis in COVID-19: findings from the Brazilian COVID-19 registry (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21260184</id><title>Whole-Blood DNA Methylation Analysis Reveals Respiratory Environmental Traits Involved in COVID-19 Severity Following SARS-CoV-2 Infection (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.656801+00:00</updated><author><name>Guillermo Barturen</name></author><author><name>Elena Carnero-Montoro</name></author><author><name>Manuel Martínez-Bueno</name></author><author><name>Silvia Rojo-Rello</name></author><author><name>Beatriz Sobrino</name></author><author><name>Clara Alcántara-Domínguez</name></author><author><name>David Bernardo</name></author><author><name>Marta E. Alarcón-Riquelme</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 causes a severe inflammatory syndrome (COVID-19) leading, in many cases, to bilateral pneumonia, severe dyspnea and in ∼5% of these, death. DNA methylation is known to play an important role in the regulation of the immune processes behind COVID-19 progression, however it has not been studied in depth, yet. In this study, we aim to evaluate the implication of DNA methylation in COVID-19 progression by means of a genome-wide DNA methylation analysis combined with DNA genotyping.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The results reveal the existence of epigenomic regulation of functional pathways associated with COVID-19 progression and mediated by genetic loci. We found an environmental trait-related signature that discriminates mild from severe cases, and regulates IL-6 expression via the transcription factor CEBP. The analyses suggest that an interaction between environmental contribution, genetics and epigenetics might be playing a role in triggering the cytokine storm described in the most severe cases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21260184" rel="alternate" title="Whole-Blood DNA Methylation Analysis Reveals Respiratory Environmental Traits Involved in COVID-19 Severity Following SARS-CoV-2 Infection (3 tweets)"/><category term="Allergy and Immunology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>