<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.396359+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.18.21257267</id><title>Colchicine in patients admitted to hospital with COVID-19 (RECOVERY): a randomised, controlled, open-label, platform trial (1221 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.396807+00:00</updated><author><name> </name></author><author><name>Peter W Horby</name></author><author><name>Mark Campbell</name></author><author><name>Enti Spata</name></author><author><name>Jonathan R Emberson</name></author><author><name>Natalie Staplin</name></author><author><name>Guilherme Pessoa-Amorim</name></author><author><name>Leon Peto</name></author><author><name>Martin Wiselka</name></author><author><name>Laura Wiffen</name></author><author><name>Simon Tiberi</name></author><author><name>Ben Caplin</name></author><author><name>Caroline Wroe</name></author><author><name>Christopher Green</name></author><author><name>Paul Hine</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Prudon</name></author><author><name>Tina George</name></author><author><name>Andrew Wight</name></author><author><name>J Kenneth Baillie</name></author><author><name>Buddha Basnyat</name></author><author><name>Maya H Buch</name></author><author><name>Lucy C Chappell</name></author><author><name>Jeremy N Day</name></author><author><name>Saul N Faust</name></author><author><name>Raph L Hamers</name></author><author><name>Thomas Jaki</name></author><author><name>Edmund Juszczak</name></author><author><name>Katie Jeffery</name></author><author><name>Wei Shen Lim</name></author><author><name>Alan Montgomery</name></author><author><name>Andrew Mumford</name></author><author><name>Kathryn Rowan</name></author><author><name>Guy Thwaites</name></author><author><name>Marion Mafham</name></author><author><name>Richard Haynes</name></author><author><name>Martin J Landray</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Colchicine has been proposed as a treatment for COVID-19 on the basis of its anti-inflammatory actions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this randomised, controlled, open-label trial, several possible treatments were compared with usual care in patients hospitalised with COVID-19. Eligible and consenting adults were randomly allocated in a 1:1 ratio to either usual standard of care alone or usual standard of care plus colchicine twice daily for 10 days or until discharge (or one of the other treatment arms) using web-based simple (unstratified) randomisation with allocation concealment. The primary outcome was 28-day mortality. The trial is registered with ISRCTN (50189673) and &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov"&gt;clinicaltrials.gov&lt;/ext-link&gt; (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT04381936"&gt;NCT04381936&lt;/ext-link&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Between 27 November 2020 and 4 March 2021, 5610 patients were randomly allocated to receive colchicine and 5730 patients to receive usual care alone. Overall, 1173 (21%) patients allocated to colchicine and 1190 (21%) patients allocated to usual care died within 28 days (rate ratio 1.01; 95% confidence interval [CI] 0.93-1.10; p=0.77). Consistent results were seen in all pre-specified subgroups of patients. There was no significant difference in duration of hospitalisation (median 10 days vs. 10 days) or the proportion of patients discharged from hospital alive within 28 days (70% vs. 70%; rate ratio 0.98; 95% CI 0.94-1.03; p=0.44). Among those not on invasive mechanical ventilation at baseline, there was no significant difference in the proportion meeting the composite endpoint of invasive mechanical ventilation or death (25% vs. 25%; risk ratio 1.02; 95% CI 0.96-1.09; p=0.47).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In adults hospitalised with COVID-19, colchicine was not associated with reductions in 28-day mortality, duration of hospital stay, or risk of progressing to invasive mechanical ventilation or death.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;UK Research and Innovation (Medical Research Council) and National Institute of Health Research (Grant ref: MC_PC_19056). Wellcome Trust (Grant Ref: 222406/Z/20/Z) through the COVID-19 Therapeutics Accelerator.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.18.21257267" rel="alternate" title="Colchicine in patients admitted to hospital with COVID-19 (RECOVERY): a randomised, controlled, open-label, platform trial (1221 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.21257461</id><title>Efficacy Estimates for Various COVID-19 Vaccines: What we Know from the Literature and Reports (220 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.397664+00:00</updated><author><name>Julia Shapiro</name></author><author><name>Natalie E Dean</name></author><author><name>Zachary J. Madewell</name></author><author><name>Yang Yang</name></author><author><name>M Elizabeth Halloran</name></author><author><name>Ira M Longini</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In this report, we provide summary estimates, from publications and reports, of vaccine
efficacy (VE) for the COVID-19 vaccines that are being rolled out on a global scale. We  find
that, on average, the efficacy against any disease with infection is 85% (95% CI: 71 - 93%)
after a full course of vaccination. The VE against severe disease, hospitalization or death
averages close to 100%. The average VE against infection, regardless of symptoms, is 84%
(95% CI: 70 - 91%). We also find that the average VE against transmission to others for
Infected vaccinated people is 54% (95% CI: 38 - 66%). Finally, we prove summary estimates
of the VE against any disease with infection for some of the variants of concern (VOC). The
average VE for the VOC B.1.1.7, B.1.1.28 (P1) and B.1.351 are 86% (95% CI: 65 - 84%),
61% (95% CI: 43 - 73%) and 56% (95% CI: 29 - 73%), respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.21257461" rel="alternate" title="Efficacy Estimates for Various COVID-19 Vaccines: What we Know from the Literature and Reports (220 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.445008</id><title>Acute SARS-CoV-2 infection is associated with an expansion of bacteria pathogens in the nose including Pseudomonas Aeruginosa (105 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.397972+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas S. Rhoades</name></author><author><name>Amanda Pinski</name></author><author><name>Alisha N. Monsibais</name></author><author><name>Allen Jankeel</name></author><author><name>Brianna M. Doratt</name></author><author><name>Isaac R. Cinco</name></author><author><name>Izabela Ibraim</name></author><author><name>Ilhem Messaoudi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Much of the research conducted on SARS-CoV-2 and COVID-19 has focused on the systemic host response, especially that generated by severely ill patients. Very few studies have investigated the impact of acute SARS-CoV-2 within the nasopharynx, the site of initial infection and viral replication. In this study we profiled changes in the nasal microbial communities as well as in host transcriptional profile during acute SARS-CoV-2 infection using 16S amplicon sequencing and RNA sequencing. These analyses were coupled to viral genome sequencing. Our microbiome analysis revealed that the nasal microbiome of COVID patients was unique and was marked by an expansion of bacterial pathogens. Some of these microbes (i.e. &lt;italic&gt;Acinetobacter&lt;/italic&gt;) were shared with COVID negative health care providers from the same medical center but absent in COVID negative outpatients seeking care at the same institutions suggesting acquisition of nosocomial respiratory pathogens. Specifically, we report a distinct increase in the prevalence and abundance of the pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; in COVID patients that correlated with viral RNA load. These data suggest that the inflammatory environment caused by SARS-CoV-2 infection and potentially exposure to the hospital environment leads to an expansion of bacterial pathogens in the nasal cavity that could contribute to increased incidence of secondary bacterial infections. Additionally, we observed a robust host transcriptional response in the nasal epithelia of COVID patients, indicative of an antiviral innate immune repones and neuronal damage. Finally, analysis of viral genomes did not reveal an association between viral loads and viral sequences.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.445008" rel="alternate" title="Acute SARS-CoV-2 infection is associated with an expansion of bacteria pathogens in the nose including Pseudomonas Aeruginosa (105 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.444882</id><title>The Structure of ChAdOx1/AZD-1222 Reveals Interactions with CAR and PF4 with Implications for Vaccine-induced Immune Thrombotic Thrombocytopenia (100 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.398288+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander T. Baker</name></author><author><name>Ryan J. Boyd</name></author><author><name>Daipayan Sarkar</name></author><author><name>John Vant</name></author><author><name>Alicia Teijeira Crespo</name></author><author><name>Chloe D. Truong</name></author><author><name>Emily Bates</name></author><author><name>Eric Wilson</name></author><author><name>Chun Kit Chan</name></author><author><name>Magdalena Lipka-Lloyd</name></author><author><name>Petra Fromme</name></author><author><name>Marius Bolni Nagalo</name></author><author><name>Meike Heurich</name></author><author><name>Dewight Williams</name></author><author><name>Po-Lin Chiu</name></author><author><name>Pierre J. Rizkallah</name></author><author><name>Alan L. Parker</name></author><author><name>Abhishek Singharoy</name></author><author><name>Mitesh J. Borad</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Adenovirus derived vectors, based on chimpanzee adenovirus Y25 (ChAdOx1) and human adenovirus type 26 are proving critical in combatting the 2019 SARS-CoV-2 pandemic. Following emergency use authorisation, scale up in vaccine administration has inevitably revealed vaccine related adverse effects; too rare to observe even in large Phase-III clinical trials. These include vaccine-induced thrombotic thrombocytopenia (VITT), an ultra-rare adverse event in which patients develop life-threatening blood clots 5-24 days following vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To investigate vector-host interactions of ChAdOx1 underpinning VITT we solved the structure of the ChAdOx1 capsid by CryoEM, and the structure of the primary receptor tropism determining fiber-knob protein by crystallography. These structural insights have enabled us to unravel key protein interactions involved in ChAdOx1 cell entry and a possible means by which it may generate misplaced immunity to platelet factor 4 (PF4), a protein involved in coagulation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We use in vitro cell binding assays to show that the fiber-knob protein uses coxsackie and adenovirus receptor (CAR) as a high affinity binding partner, while it does not form a stable interface with CD46. Computational simulations identified a putative mechanism by which the ChAdOx1 capsid interacts with PF4 by binding in the spaces between hexon proteins, with downstream implications for the causes of VITT.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present the structure of the ChAdOx1 viral vector, derived from chimpanzee adenovirus Y25 at 4.2Å resolution&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. ChAdOx1 is in global use in the AstraZeneca vaccine, ChAdOx1 nCoV-19/AZD-1222, to combat the SARS-CoV-2 coronavirus pandemic. Recently observed, rare, adverse events make detailed mechanistic understanding of this vector key to informing proper treatment of affected patients and the development of safer viral vectors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we determine a primary mechanism ChAdOx1 uses to attach to cells is coxsackie and adenovirus receptor (CAR), a protein which is identical in humans and chimpanzees. We demonstrate the vector does not form a stable CD46 interaction, a common species B adenovirus receptor, via its primary attachment protein.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further, we reveal the surface of the ChAdOx1 viral capsid has a strong electronegative potential. Molecular simulations suggest this charge, together with shape complementarity, are a mechanism by which an oppositely charged protein, platelet factor 4 (PF4) may bind the vector surface. PF4 is a key protein involved in the formation of blood clots&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, and the target of auto-antibodies in heparin-induced immune thrombotic thrombocytopenia (HITT)&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;, an adverse reaction to heparin therapy which presents similarly to vaccine-induced immune thrombotic thrombocytopenia (VITT), a rare complication of ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 vaccination&lt;sup&gt;4–6&lt;/sup&gt;. We propose a mechanism in which the ChAdOx1-PF4 complex may stimulate the production of antibodies against PF4, leading to delayed blood clot formation, as observed in VITT.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.444882" rel="alternate" title="The Structure of ChAdOx1/AZD-1222 Reveals Interactions with CAR and PF4 with Implications for Vaccine-induced Immune Thrombotic Thrombocytopenia (100 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.21256972</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccines induce a greater array of spike-specific antibody isotypes with more potent complement binding capacity than natural infection (55 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.415463+00:00</updated><author><name>Jéromine Klingler</name></author><author><name>Gregory S. Lambert</name></author><author><name>Vincenza Itri</name></author><author><name>Sean Liu</name></author><author><name>Juan C. Bandres</name></author><author><name>Gospel Enyindah-Asonye</name></author><author><name>Xiaomei Liu</name></author><author><name>Kasopefoluwa Y. Oguntuyo</name></author><author><name>Fatima Amanat</name></author><author><name>Benhur Lee</name></author><author><name>Susan Zolla-Pazner</name></author><author><name>Chitra Upadhyay</name></author><author><name>Catarina E. Hioe</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mass vaccination against severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) is on-going in the United States with vaccines approved for emergency use by the FDA. Each vaccine can induce spike-specific antibodies (Abs) with virus-neutralizing activities; however, the Fc-mediated Ab activities have received little attention. Moreover, while plasma/serum Abs are commonly studied, scant information is available about Abs in the respiratory mucosa, the site of SARS-CoV-2 transmission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plasma and saliva were collected from mRNA vaccine recipients and convalescent coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) patients. Antigen-specific total Ig and Ig isotypes were measured. In addition to virus neutralization, Fc-mediated activities were investigated, including antibody-dependent cellular phagocytosis (ADCP) and complement deposition.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Similar to infection, vaccination stimulated spike-specific Ab responses detected in plasma and saliva, with IgG1 as the dominant isotype. Interestingly, vaccination produced greater IgG2, IgG3, and IgG4 responses and higher ratios of (IgG1+IgG3)/(IgG2+IgG4) than infection. Moreover, while plasma neutralization and ADCP potencies were comparable in vaccinated and convalescent individuals, vaccine-induced plasma Abs elicited stronger complement binding and activation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compared with natural infection, mRNA vaccines induced a greater array of IgG subtypes against spike in saliva and plasma. The vaccine-induced Abs were also more potent in mediating complement activation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.21256972" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccines induce a greater array of spike-specific antibody isotypes with more potent complement binding capacity than natural infection (55 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.444823</id><title>Bidirectional genome-wide CRISPR screens reveal host factors regulating SARS-CoV-2, MERS-CoV and seasonal coronaviruses (54 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.415992+00:00</updated><author><name>Antoine Rebendenne</name></author><author><name>Priyanka Roy</name></author><author><name>Boris Bonaventure</name></author><author><name>Ana Luiza Chaves Valadão</name></author><author><name>Lowiese Desmarets</name></author><author><name>Yves Rouillé</name></author><author><name>Marine Tauziet</name></author><author><name>Mary Arnaud-Arnould</name></author><author><name>Donatella Giovannini</name></author><author><name>Yenarae Lee</name></author><author><name>Peter DeWeirdt</name></author><author><name>Mudra Hegde</name></author><author><name>Francisco Garcia de Gracia</name></author><author><name>Joe McKellar</name></author><author><name>Mélanie Wencker</name></author><author><name>Jean Dubuisson</name></author><author><name>Sandrine Belouzard</name></author><author><name>Olivier Moncorgé</name></author><author><name>John G Doench</name></author><author><name>Caroline Goujon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Several genome-wide CRISPR knockout screens have been conducted to identify host factors regulating SARS-CoV-2 replication, but the models used have often relied on overexpression of ACE2 receptor. Additionally, such screens have yet to identify the protease TMPRSS2, known to be important for viral entry at the plasma membrane. Here, we conducted a meta-analysis of these screens and showed a high level of cell-type specificity of the identified hits, arguing for the necessity of additional models to uncover the full landscape of SARS-CoV-2 host factors. We performed genome-wide knockout and activation CRISPR screens in Calu-3 lung epithelial cells, as well as knockout screens in Caco-2 intestinal cells. In addition to identifying ACE2 and TMPRSS2 as top hits, our study reveals a series of so far unidentified and critical host-dependency factors, including the Adaptins AP1G1 and AP1B1 and the flippase ATP8B1. Moreover, new anti-SARS-CoV-2 proteins with potent activity, including several membrane-associated Mucins, IL6R, and CD44 were identified. We further observed that these genes mostly acted at the critical step of viral entry, with the notable exception of ATP8B1, the knockout of which prevented late stages of viral replication. Exploring the pro- and anti-viral breadth of these genes using highly pathogenic MERS-CoV, seasonal HCoV-NL63 and -229E and influenza A orthomyxovirus, we reveal that some genes such as AP1G1 and ATP8B1 are general coronavirus cofactors. In contrast, Mucins recapitulated their known role as a general antiviral defense mechanism. These results demonstrate the value of considering multiple cell models and perturbational modalities for understanding SARS-CoV-2 replication and provide a list of potential new targets for therapeutic interventions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.444823" rel="alternate" title="Bidirectional genome-wide CRISPR screens reveal host factors regulating SARS-CoV-2, MERS-CoV and seasonal coronaviruses (54 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.21257337</id><title>Pregnancy and birth outcomes after SARS-CoV-2 vaccination in pregnancy (49 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.429444+00:00</updated><author><name>Regan N. Theiler</name></author><author><name>Myra Wick</name></author><author><name>Ramila Mehta</name></author><author><name>Amy Weaver</name></author><author><name>Abinash Virk</name></author><author><name>Melanie Swift</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 infection during pregnancy is associated with significant maternal morbidity and increased rates of preterm birth. For this reason, COVID-19 vaccine administration in pregnancy has been endorsed by multiple professional societies including ACOG and SMFM despite exclusion of pregnant women from initial clinical trials of vaccine safety and efficacy. However, to date little data exists regarding outcomes after COVID-19 vaccination of pregnant patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Study Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A comprehensive vaccine registry was combined with a delivery database for an integrated healthcare system to create a delivery cohort including vaccinated patients. Maternal sociodemographic data were examined univariately for factors associated with COVID-19 vaccination. Pregnancy and birth outcomes were analyzed, including a composite measure of maternal and neonatal pregnancy complications, the Adverse Outcome Index.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of 2002 patients in the delivery cohort, 140 (7.0%) received a COVID-19 vaccination during pregnancy and 212 (10.6%) experienced a COVID-19 infection during pregnancy. The median gestational age at first vaccination was 32 weeks (range 13 6/7-40 4/7), and patients vaccinated during pregnancy were less likely than unvaccinated patients to experience COVID-19 infection prior to delivery (1.4% (2/140) vs. 11.3% (210/1862)) P&amp;lt;0.001No maternal COVID-19 infections occurred after vaccination during pregnancy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Factors significantly associated with increased likelihood of vaccination included older age, higher level of maternal education, lower pre-pregnancy BMI, and use of infertility treatment for the current pregnancy. Tobacco or other substance use, Hispanic ethnicity, and higher gravidity were associated with a lower likelihood of vaccination. No significant difference in the composite adverse outcome (5.0% (7/140) vs. 4.9% (91/1862) P=0.95) or other maternal or neonatal complications, including thromboembolic events and preterm birth, was observed in vaccinated mothers compared to unvaccinated patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vaccinated pregnant women in this birth cohort were less likely to experience COVID-19 infection compared to unvaccinated pregnant patients, and COVID-19 vaccination during pregnancy was not associated with increased pregnancy or delivery complications. Significant sociodemographic disparities in vaccine uptake and/or access were observed among pregnant patients, and future efforts should focus on outreach to low-uptake populations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.21257337" rel="alternate" title="Pregnancy and birth outcomes after SARS-CoV-2 vaccination in pregnancy (49 tweets)"/><category term="Obstetrics and Gynecology"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.21257123</id><title>Occupation and COVID-19 mortality in England: a national linked data study of 14.3 million adults (48 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.429987+00:00</updated><author><name>Vahé Nafilyan</name></author><author><name>Piotr Pawelek</name></author><author><name>Dan Ayoubkhani</name></author><author><name>Sarah Rhodes</name></author><author><name>Lucy Pembrey</name></author><author><name>Melissa Matz</name></author><author><name>Michel P Coleman</name></author><author><name>Claudia Allemani</name></author><author><name>Ben Windsor-Shellard</name></author><author><name>Martie van Tongeren</name></author><author><name>Neil Pearce</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To estimate occupational differences in COVID-19 mortality, and test whether these are confounded by factors, such as regional differences, ethnicity and education or due to non-workplace factors, such as deprivation or pre-pandemic health.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Retrospective cohort study&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;People living in private households England&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;14,295,900 people aged 40-64 years (mean age 52 years, 51% female) who were alive on 24 January 2020, living in private households in England in 2019, were employed in 2011, and completed the 2011 census.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main outcome measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 related death, assessed between 24 January 2020 and 28 December 2020. We estimated age-standardised mortality rates per 100,000 person-years at risk (ASMR) stratified by sex and occupations. To estimate the effect of occupation due to work-related exposures, we used Cox proportional hazard models to adjust for confounding (region, ethnicity, education), as well as non-workplace factors that are related to occupation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is wide variation between occupations in COVID-19 mortality. Several occupations, particularly those involving contact with patients or the public, show three-fold or four-fold risks. These elevated risks were greatly attenuated after adjustment for confounding and mediating non-workplace factors. For example, the hazard ratio (HR) for men working as taxi and cab drivers or chauffeurs changed from 4.60 [95%CI 3.62-5.84] to 1.47 [1.14-1.89] after adjustment. More generally, the overall HR for men working in essential occupations compared with men in non-essential occupations changed from 1.45 [1.34 - 1.56] to 1.22 [1.13 - 1.32] after adjustment. For most occupations, confounding and other mediating factors explained about 70% to 80% of the age-adjusted hazard ratios.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Working conditions are likely to play a role in COVID-19 mortality, particularly in occupations involving contact with COVID-19 patients or the public. However, there is also a substantial contribution from non-workplace factors, including regional factors, socio-demographic factors, and pre-pandemic health.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.21257123" rel="alternate" title="Occupation and COVID-19 mortality in England: a national linked data study of 14.3 million adults (48 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.21257335</id><title>Reduction in COPD exacerbations during COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis (38 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.430782+00:00</updated><author><name>Jaber S. Alqahtani</name></author><author><name>Tope Oyelade</name></author><author><name>Abdulelah M. Aldhahir</name></author><author><name>Renata Gonçalves Mendes</name></author><author><name>Saeed M. Alghamdi</name></author><author><name>Marc Miravitlles</name></author><author><name>Swapna Mandal</name></author><author><name>John R. Hurst</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reports have suggested a reduction in exacerbations of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) during the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic, particularly hospital admissions for severe exacerbations. However, the magnitude of this reduction varies between studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Method&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic databases were searched from January 2020 to May 2021. Two independent reviewers screened titles and abstracts and, when necessary, full text to determine if studies met inclusion criteria. A modified version of the Newcastle-Ottawa Scale was used to assess study quality. A narrative summary of eligible studies was synthesised, and meta-analysis was conducted using a random effect model to pool the rate ratio and 95% confidence intervals (95% CI) for hospital admissions. Exacerbation reduction was compared against the COVID-19 Containment and Health Index.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A total of 13 of 745 studies met the inclusion criteria and were included in this review, with data from nine countries. Seven studies could be included in the meta-analysis. The pooled rate ratio of hospital admissions for COPD exacerbations during the pandemic period was 0.50 (95% CI 0.42-0.58). Findings on the rate of community-treated exacerbations were inconclusive. Three studies reported a significant decrease in the incidence of respiratory viral infections compared with the pre-pandemic period. There was not a significant relationship between exacerbation reduction and the COVID-19 Containment and Health Index.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was a 50% reduction in admissions for COPD exacerbations during the COVID-19 pandemic period, associated with a reduction in respiratory viral infections that trigger exacerbations. We provide pooled evidence supporting the potential effectiveness of COVID-19 preventive interventions in reducing the risk of admissions for COPD exacerbations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.21257335" rel="alternate" title="Reduction in COPD exacerbations during COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis (38 tweets)"/><category term="Respiratory Medicine"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.16.21257283</id><title>Early Anakinra Treatment for COVID-19 Guided by Urokinase Plasminogen Receptor (33 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.431282+00:00</updated><author><name>Evdoxia Kyriazopoulou</name></author><author><name>Garyfallia Poulakou</name></author><author><name>Haralampos Milionis</name></author><author><name>Simeon Metallidis</name></author><author><name>Georgios Adamis</name></author><author><name>Konstantinos Tsiakos</name></author><author><name>Archontoula Fragkou</name></author><author><name>Aggeliki Rapti</name></author><author><name>Christina Damoulari</name></author><author><name>Massimo Fantoni</name></author><author><name>Ioannis Kalomenidis</name></author><author><name>Georgios Chrysos</name></author><author><name>Andrea Angheben</name></author><author><name>Ilias Kainis</name></author><author><name>Zoi Alexiou</name></author><author><name>Francesco Castelli</name></author><author><name>Francesco Saverio Serino</name></author><author><name>Petros Bakakos</name></author><author><name>Emanuele Nicastri</name></author><author><name>Vassiliki Tzavara</name></author><author><name>Evangelos Kostis</name></author><author><name>Lorenzo Dagna</name></author><author><name>Panagiotis Koufargyris</name></author><author><name>Katerina Dimakou</name></author><author><name>Glykeria Tzatzagou</name></author><author><name>Maria Chini</name></author><author><name>Matteo Bassetti</name></author><author><name>Konstantina Katrini</name></author><author><name>Vasileios Kotsis</name></author><author><name>George Tsoukalas</name></author><author><name>Carlo Selmi</name></author><author><name>Ioannis Bliziotis</name></author><author><name>Michael Samarkos</name></author><author><name>Michael Doumas</name></author><author><name>Sofia Ktena</name></author><author><name>Aikaterini Masgala</name></author><author><name>Ilias Papanikolaou</name></author><author><name>Aikaterini Argyraki</name></author><author><name>Chiara Simona Cardellino</name></author><author><name>Eleni-Ioanna Katsigianni</name></author><author><name>Efthymia Giannitsioti</name></author><author><name>Antonella Cingolani</name></author><author><name>Karolina Akinosoglou</name></author><author><name>Orestis Liatsis-Douvitsas</name></author><author><name>Styliani Symbardi</name></author><author><name>Maria Mouktaroudi</name></author><author><name>Giuseppe Ippolito</name></author><author><name>Eleni Florou</name></author><author><name>Antigone Kotsaki</name></author><author><name>Mihai G. Netea</name></author><author><name>Jesper Eugen-Olsen</name></author><author><name>Miltiades Kyprianou</name></author><author><name>Periklis Panagopoulos</name></author><author><name>George N. Dalekos</name></author><author><name>Evangelos J. Giamarellos-Bourboulis</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a previous open-label trial, early anakinra treatment guided by elevated soluble urokinase plasminogen activator receptor (suPAR) prevented progression of COVID-19 pneumonia into respiratory failure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the SAVE-MORE multicenter trial, 594 hospitalized patients with moderate and severe COVID-19 pneumonia and plasma suPAR 6 ng/ml or more and receiving standard-of-care were 1:2 randomized to subcutaneous treatment with placebo or 100 mg anakinra once daily for 10 days. The primary endpoint was the overall clinical status of the 11-point World Health Organization ordinal Clinical Progression Scale (WHO-CPS) at day 28. The changes of the WHO-CPS and of the sequential organ failure assessment (SOFA) score were the main secondary endpoints.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anakinra-treated patients were distributed to lower strata of WHO-CPS by day 28 (adjusted odds ratio-OR 0.36; 95%CI 0.26-0.50; P&amp;lt;0.001); anakinra protected from severe disease or death (6 or more points of WHO-CPS) (OR: 0.46; P: 0.010). The median absolute decrease of WHO-CPS in the placebo and anakinra groups from baseline was 3 and 4 points respectively at day 28 (OR 0.40; P&amp;lt;0.0001); and 2 and 3 points at day 14 (OR 0.63; P: 0.003); the absolute decrease of SOFA score was 0 and 1 points (OR 0.63; P: 0.004). 28-day mortality decreased (hazard ratio: 0.45; P: 0.045). Hospital stay was shorter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Early start of anakinra treatment guided by suPAR provides 2.78 times better improvement of overall clinical status in moderate and severe COVID-19 pneumonia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Sponsored by the Hellenic Institute for the Study of Sepsis &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov"&gt;ClinicalTrials.gov&lt;/ext-link&gt; identifier, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT04680949"&gt;NCT04680949&lt;/ext-link&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.16.21257283" rel="alternate" title="Early Anakinra Treatment for COVID-19 Guided by Urokinase Plasminogen Receptor (33 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444397</id><title>An intranasal ASO therapeutic targeting SARS-CoV-2 (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.434901+00:00</updated><author><name>Chi Zhu</name></author><author><name>Justin Y. Lee</name></author><author><name>Jia Z. Woo</name></author><author><name>Lei Xu</name></author><author><name>Xammy Nguyenla</name></author><author><name>Livia H. Yamashiro</name></author><author><name>Fei Ji</name></author><author><name>Scott B. Biering</name></author><author><name>Erik Van Dis</name></author><author><name>Federico Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Douglas Fox</name></author><author><name>Arjun Rustagi</name></author><author><name>Benjamin A. Pinsky</name></author><author><name>Catherine A. Blish</name></author><author><name>Charles Chiu</name></author><author><name>Eva Harris</name></author><author><name>Ruslan I. Sadreyev</name></author><author><name>Sarah Stanley</name></author><author><name>Sakari Kauppinen</name></author><author><name>Silvi Rouskin</name></author><author><name>Anders M. Näär</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic is exacting an increasing toll worldwide, with new SARS-CoV-2 variants emerging that exhibit higher infectivity rates and that may partially evade vaccine and antibody immunity&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. Rapid deployment of non-invasive therapeutic avenues capable of preventing infection by all SARS-CoV-2 variants could complement current vaccination efforts and help turn the tide on the COVID-19 pandemic&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. Here, we describe a novel therapeutic strategy targeting the SARS-CoV-2 RNA using locked nucleic acid antisense oligonucleotides (LNA ASOs). We identified an LNA ASO binding to the 5’ leader sequence of SARS-CoV-2 ORF1a/b that disrupts a highly conserved stem-loop structure with nanomolar efficacy in preventing viral replication in human cells. Daily intranasal administration of this LNA ASO in the K18-hACE2 humanized COVID-19 mouse model potently (98-99%) suppressed viral replication in the lungs of infected mice, revealing strong prophylactic and treatment effects. We found that the LNA ASO also represses viral infection in golden Syrian hamsters, and is highly efficacious in countering all SARS-CoV-2 “variants of concern” tested &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, including B.1.427, B.1.1.7, and B.1.351 variants&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;. Hence, inhaled LNA ASOs targeting SARS-CoV-2 represents a promising therapeutic approach to reduce transmission of variants partially resistant to vaccines and monoclonal antibodies, and could be deployed intranasally for prophylaxis or via lung delivery by nebulizer to decrease severity of COVID-19 in infected individuals. LNA ASOs are chemically stable and can be flexibly modified to target different viral RNA sequences&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;, and they may have particular impact in areas where vaccine distribution is a challenge, and could be stockpiled for future coronavirus pandemics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444397" rel="alternate" title="An intranasal ASO therapeutic targeting SARS-CoV-2 (30 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.444021</id><title>Global mapping of RNA homodimers in living cells (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.435339+00:00</updated><author><name>Marta M Gabryelska</name></author><author><name>Grzegorz Kudla</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;RNA homodimerization is important for various physiological processes, including the assembly of membraneless organelles, RNA subcellular localization, and packaging of viral genomes. However, understanding of RNA homodimerization has been hampered by the lack of systematic &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; detection methods. Here we show that PARIS, COMRADES, and other RNA proximity ligation methods can detect RNA homodimers transcriptome-wide as “overlapping” chimeric reads that contain more than one copy of the same sequence. Analysing published proximity ligation datasets, we show that RNA:RNA homodimers mediated by direct base-pairing interactions are rare across the transcriptome, but highly enriched in specific transcripts, including U8 snoRNA, U2 snRNA and a subset of tRNAs. Analysis of data from virus-infected cells reveals homodimerization of SARS-CoV-2 and Zika genomes, mediated by specific palindromic sequences located within protein-coding regions of N protein in SARS-CoV-2 and NS2A gene in Zika. We speculate that regions of viral genomes involved in homodimerization may constitute effective targets for antiviral therapies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.444021" rel="alternate" title="Global mapping of RNA homodimers in living cells (24 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.18.444646</id><title>Effects of common mutations in the SARS-CoV-2 Spike RBD domain and its ligand the human ACE2 receptor on binding affinity and kinetics (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.437669+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael I. Barton</name></author><author><name>Stuart MacGowan</name></author><author><name>Mikhail Kutuzov</name></author><author><name>Omer Dushek</name></author><author><name>Geoffrey J. Barton</name></author><author><name>P. Anton van der Merwe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The interaction between the SARS-CoV-2 virus Spike protein’s receptor binding domain (RBD) and the ACE2 cell surface protein is required for viral infection of cells. Mutations in the RBD domain are present in SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern that have emerged independently worldwide. For example, the more transmissible B.1.1.7 lineage has a mutation (N501Y) in its Spike RBD domain that enhances binding to ACE2. There are also ACE2 alleles in humans with mutations in the RBD binding site. Here we perform a detailed affinity and kinetics analysis of the effect of five common RBD mutations (K417N, K417T, N501Y, E484K and S477N) and two common ACE2 mutations (S19P and K26R) on the RBD/ACE2 interaction. We analysed the effects of individual RBD mutations, and combinations found in new SARS-CoV-2 variants first identified in the UK (B.1.1.7), South Africa (B.1.351) and Brazil (P1). Most of these mutations increased the affinity of the RBD/ACE2 interaction. The exceptions were mutations K417N/T, which decreased the affinity. Taken together with other studies, our results suggest that the N501Y and S477N mutations primarily enhance transmission, the K417N/T mutations facilitate immune escape, and the E484K mutation facilitates both transmission and immune escape.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.18.444646" rel="alternate" title="Effects of common mutations in the SARS-CoV-2 Spike RBD domain and its ligand the human ACE2 receptor on binding affinity and kinetics (21 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.18.21255620</id><title>Emergence and spread of the potential variant of interest (VOI) B.1.1.519 predominantly present in Mexico (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.439901+00:00</updated><author><name>Abril Paulina Rodríguez-Maldonado</name></author><author><name>Joel Armando Vázquez-Pérez</name></author><author><name>Alberto Cedro-Tanda</name></author><author><name>Blanca Taboada</name></author><author><name>Celia Boukadida</name></author><author><name>Claudia Wong-Arámbula</name></author><author><name>Tatiana Ernestina Nuñez-García</name></author><author><name>Natividad Cruz-Ortiz</name></author><author><name>Gisela Barrera-Badillo</name></author><author><name>Lucía Hernández-Rivas</name></author><author><name>Irma López-Martínez</name></author><author><name>Alfredo Mendoza-Vargas</name></author><author><name>Juan Pablo Reyes-Grajeda</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Alcaraz</name></author><author><name>Fernando Peñaloza-Figueroa</name></author><author><name>Dulibeth Gonzalez-Barrera</name></author><author><name>Daniel Rangel-DeLeon</name></author><author><name>Luis Alonso Herrera-Montalvo</name></author><author><name>Fidencio Mejía-Nepomuceno</name></author><author><name>Alejandra Hernández-Terán</name></author><author><name>Mario Mújica-Sánchez</name></author><author><name>Eduardo Becerril-Vargas</name></author><author><name>José Arturo Martínez-Orozco</name></author><author><name>Rogelio Pérez-Padilla</name></author><author><name>Jorge Salas-Hernández</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Sanchez-Flores</name></author><author><name>Pavel Isa</name></author><author><name>Margarita Matías-Florentino</name></author><author><name>Santiago Ávila-Ríos</name></author><author><name>José Esteban Muñoz-Medina</name></author><author><name>Concepción Grajales-Muñiz</name></author><author><name>Angel Gustavo Salas-Lais</name></author><author><name>Andrea Santos Coy-Arechavaleta</name></author><author><name>Alfredo Hidalgo-Miranda</name></author><author><name>Carlos F. Arias</name></author><author><name>José Ernesto Ramírez-González</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 variants have emerged in late 2020 and there are at least three variants of concern (B.1.1.7, B.1.351, P1) reported by WHO. These variants have several substitutions in the Spike protein that affect receptor binding; they present increased transmissibility and may be associated with reduced vaccine effectiveness. In the present work, we are reporting the identification of a potential variant of interest harboring the mutations T478K, P681H, and T732A in the Spike protein, within the newly named lineage B.1.1.519, which rapidly outcompeted the preexisting variants in Mexico and has been the dominant virus in the country during the first trimester of 2021.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.18.21255620" rel="alternate" title="Emergence and spread of the potential variant of interest (VOI) B.1.1.519 predominantly present in Mexico (18 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.15.21257271</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 transmission in K-12 schools in the Vancouver Coastal Health Region: a descriptive epidemiologic study (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.441252+00:00</updated><author><name>Diana Bark</name></author><author><name>Nalin Dhillon</name></author><author><name>Martin St-Jean</name></author><author><name>Brooke Kinniburgh</name></author><author><name>Geoff McKee</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Choi</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is an urgent need to assess the role of schools in the spread of SARS-CoV-2 in Canada to inform public health measures. We describe the epidemiology of SARS-CoV-2 infection in students and staff in the Vancouver Coastal Health (VCH) region in the first three months of the 2020/2021 academic year, and examine the extent of transmission in schools.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This descriptive epidemiologic study using contact tracing data included all SARS-CoV-2 cases reported to VCH between September 10 and December 18, 2020 who worked in or attended K-12 schools in-person. Case and cluster characteristics were described.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There were 699 school staff and student cases during the study period, for an incidence of 55 cases per 10,000 population, compared to 73 per 10,000 population in all VCH residents. Among VCH resident staff and student cases, 53% were linked to a household case/cluster, &amp;lt;1.5% were hospitalized and there were no deaths. Out of 699 cases present at school, 26 clusters with school-based transmission resulted in 55 secondary cases. Staff members accounted for 54% of index cases (14/26) while comprising 14% of the school population. Among clusters, 88% had fewer than 4 secondary cases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 incidence in the school population was lower than that of the general population. There were no deaths and severe disease was rare. School-based transmissions of SARS-CoV-2 were uncommon and clusters were small. Our results support the growing body of evidence that schools do not play a major role in the spread of SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.15.21257271" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 transmission in K-12 schools in the Vancouver Coastal Health Region: a descriptive epidemiologic study (16 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444848</id><title>Alum:CpG adjuvant enables SARS-CoV-2 RBD-induced protection in aged mice and synergistic activation of human elder type 1 immunity (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.441599+00:00</updated><author><name>Etsuro Nanishi</name></author><author><name>Francesco Borriello</name></author><author><name>Timothy R. O’Meara</name></author><author><name>Marisa E. McGrath</name></author><author><name>Yoshine Saito</name></author><author><name>Robert E. Haupt</name></author><author><name>Hyuk-Soo Seo</name></author><author><name>Simon D. van Haren</name></author><author><name>Byron Brook</name></author><author><name>Jing Chen</name></author><author><name>Joann Diray-Arce</name></author><author><name>Simon Doss-Gollin</name></author><author><name>Maria De Leon</name></author><author><name>Katherine Chew</name></author><author><name>Manisha Menon</name></author><author><name>Kijun Song</name></author><author><name>Andrew Z. Xu</name></author><author><name>Timothy M. Caradonna</name></author><author><name>Jared Feldman</name></author><author><name>Blake M. Hauser</name></author><author><name>Aaron G. Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Amy C. Sherman</name></author><author><name>Lindsey R. Baden</name></author><author><name>Robert K. Ernst</name></author><author><name>Carly Dillen</name></author><author><name>Stuart M. Weston</name></author><author><name>Robert M. Johnson</name></author><author><name>Holly L. Hammond</name></author><author><name>Romana Mayer</name></author><author><name>Allen Burke</name></author><author><name>Maria E. Bottazzi</name></author><author><name>Peter J. Hotez</name></author><author><name>Ulrich Strych</name></author><author><name>Aiquan Chang</name></author><author><name>Jingyou Yu</name></author><author><name>Dan H. Barouch</name></author><author><name>Sirano Dhe-Paganon</name></author><author><name>Ivan Zanoni</name></author><author><name>Al Ozonoff</name></author><author><name>Matthew B. Frieman</name></author><author><name>Ofer Levy</name></author><author><name>David J. Dowling</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Global deployment of vaccines that can provide protection across several age groups is still urgently needed to end the COVID-19 pandemic especially for low- and middle-income countries. While vaccines against SARS-CoV-2 based on mRNA and adenoviral-vector technologies have been rapidly developed, additional practical and scalable SARS-CoV-2 vaccines are needed to meet global demand. In this context, protein subunit vaccines formulated with appropriate adjuvants represent a promising approach to address this urgent need. Receptor-binding domain (RBD) is a key target of neutralizing antibodies (Abs) but is poorly immunogenic. We therefore compared pattern recognition receptor (PRR) agonists, including those activating STING, TLR3, TLR4 and TLR9, alone or formulated with aluminum hydroxide (AH), and benchmarked them to AS01B and AS03-like emulsion-based adjuvants for their potential to enhance RBD immunogenicity in young and aged mice. We found that the AH and CpG adjuvant formulation (AH:CpG) demonstrated the highest enhancement of anti-RBD neutralizing Ab titers in both age groups (∼80-fold over AH), and protected aged mice from the SARS-CoV-2 challenge. Notably, AH:CpG-adjuvanted RBD vaccine elicited neutralizing Abs against both wild-type SARS-CoV-2 and B.1.351 variant at serum concentrations comparable to those induced by the authorized mRNA BNT162b2 vaccine. AH:CpG induced similar cytokine and chemokine gene enrichment patterns in the draining lymph nodes of both young adult and aged mice and synergistically enhanced cytokine and chemokine production in human young adult and elderly mononuclear cells. These data support further development of AH:CpG-adjuvanted RBD as an affordable vaccine that may be effective across multiple age groups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alum and CpG enhance SARS-CoV-2 RBD protective immunity, variant neutralization in aged mice and Th1-polarizing cytokine production by human elder leukocytes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444848" rel="alternate" title="Alum:CpG adjuvant enables SARS-CoV-2 RBD-induced protection in aged mice and synergistic activation of human elder type 1 immunity (14 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.21257231</id><title>Patient Characteristics in Cases of Reinfection or Prolonged viral shedding in SARS-CoV-2 (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.442465+00:00</updated><author><name>Richard M. Yoo</name></author><author><name>Roland A. Romero</name></author><author><name>Joseph Mabajen</name></author><author><name>Suchit Mehrotra</name></author><author><name>Isaac S. Kohane</name></author><author><name>Natalie E Sheils</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;As testing options increase for COVID-19, their interpretability is challenged by the increasing variety of clinical contexts in which results are obtained. In particular, positive COVID-19 diagnostic (RT-PCR) tests that occur after a patient has seroconverted may be indicative of reinfection. However, in the absence of SARS-CoV-2 sequence data, the possibility of prolonged viral shedding may not be excluded. We highlight a testing pattern that identifies such cases and study its statistical power in identifying potential reinfection. We also study the medical records of patients that matched the pattern.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To describe the frequency and demographic information of people with a testing pattern indicative of SARS-CoV-2 reinfection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We examined 4.2 million test results from a large national health insurer in the United States. Specifically, we identified the pattern of a positive RT-PCR test followed by a positive IgG test, again followed by a positive RT-PCR.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Data from outpatient laboratories across the United States was joined with claims data from a single large commercial insurer’s administrative claims database.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Study participants are those whose insurance, either commercial or Medicare, is provided by a single US based insurer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Exposures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;People who received at least two positive diagnostic tests via RT-PCR for SARS-Cov-2 separated by 42 or more days with at least one serological test (IgG) indicating the presence of antibodies between diagnostic tests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Outcomes and Measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Count and characteristics of people with the timeline of three tests as described in Exposures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We identified 79 patients who had two positive RT-PCR tests separated by more than six weeks, with a positive IgG test in between. These patients tended to be older than those COVID-19 patients without this pattern (median age 56 vs. 42), and they exhibited comorbidities typically attributed to a compromised immune system and heart disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions and Relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;While the testing pattern alone was not sufficient to distinguish potential reinfection from prolonged viral shedding, we were able to identify common traits of the patients identified through the pattern.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.21257231" rel="alternate" title="Patient Characteristics in Cases of Reinfection or Prolonged viral shedding in SARS-CoV-2 (14 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.18.21256584</id><title>Critically ill COVID-19 associated trait genetics reveals CDK6 inhibitors as potential treatment (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.442905+00:00</updated><author><name>Joern E. Klinger</name></author><author><name>Charles N. J. Ravarani</name></author><author><name>Colin Bannard</name></author><author><name>Margaretha R. J. Lamparter</name></author><author><name>Alexander R. E. C. Schwinges</name></author><author><name>Justin L. Cope</name></author><author><name>Hannes A. Baukmann</name></author><author><name>Marco F. Schmidt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite the recent development of vaccines and monoclonal antibodies preventing SARS-CoV-2 infection, treating critically ill COVID-19 patients still remains a top goal. In principle, drug repurposing – the use of an already existing drug for a new indication – could provide a shortcut to a treatment. However, drug repurposing is often very speculative due to the lack of clinical evidence. We here report on a methodology to find and test gene drug target candidates for drug repurposing. We matched critically ill COVID-19 cases from the UK Biobank with healthy controls and screened for significant differences in 33 blood cell types, 30 blood biochemistries, and body mass index in cases and controls. Significant differences in traits that have previously been associated with critically ill COVID-19 status, such as alanine aminotransferase, body mass index, C-reactive protein, and neutrophil cell count were further investigated. In-depth statistical analysis of COVID-19 associated traits and their genetics using regression modeling and propensity score stratification identified cyclin-dependent kinase 6 (CDK6) as a more promising drug target to selectively treat critically ill COVID-19 patients than the previously reported interleukin 6. Four existing CDK6 inhibitors abemaciclib, ribociclib, trilaciclib, and palbociclib have been approved for breast cancer. Clinical evidence for CDK6 inhibitors in treating critically ill COVID-19 has been reported. Further clinical investigations are ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.18.21256584" rel="alternate" title="Critically ill COVID-19 associated trait genetics reveals CDK6 inhibitors as potential treatment (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.21257429</id><title>Efficacy of Sofosbuvir plus Ledipasvir in Egyptian patients with COVID-19 compared to standard treatment: Randomized controlled trial (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.443285+00:00</updated><author><name>Mohamed Abdel-Salam Elgohary</name></author><author><name>Eman Medhat Hasan</name></author><author><name>Amany Ahmad Ibrahim</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Farouk Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Raafat Zaher Abdel-Rahman</name></author><author><name>Ashraf Ibrahim Zaki</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Bakr Elaatar</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Thabet Elnagar</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Emam Emam</name></author><author><name>Mahmoud Moustafa Hamada</name></author><author><name>Taimour Mohamed Abdel-Hamid</name></author><author><name>Ahmad Samir Abdel-Hafez</name></author><author><name>Mohamed G. Seadawy</name></author><author><name>Ahmad Rashad Fatoh</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Ali Elsaied</name></author><author><name>Marwa Abdel-Rahman Sakr</name></author><author><name>Ahmed Omar Elkady</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Muawad Shehata</name></author><author><name>Osama Mohamed Nawar</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Abu-elnaga Selem</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Saeed Abd-aal</name></author><author><name>Hany Hafez Lotfy</name></author><author><name>Tarek Refaat Elnagdy</name></author><author><name>Sherine Helmy</name></author><author><name>Magdy Amin Mubark</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: COVID-19 is a pandemic disease caused by SARS-CoV-2, which is an RNA virus similar to HCV in the replication process. Sofosbuvir/ledipasvir is an approved drug by the FDA to treat HCV infection. This study investigates the efficacy of Sofosbuvir/ledipasvir as a treatment for patients with moderate COVID-19 infection..
Methods: This is a single-blinded parallel-randomized controlled trial. The participants were randomized equally into the intervention group received Sofosbuvir/ledipasvir (S.L. group), and the control group received Oseltamivir, Hydroxychloroquine, and Azithromycin (OCH group). The primary outcomes were the cure rate over time and the incidence of serious adverse events. The secondary outcomes included the laboratory findings.
Results: Two hundred and fifty patients were divided equally into each group. Both groups were similar regarding gender, but age was higher in the S.L. group (p=0.001). In the S.L. group, 89 (71.2%) patients were cured, while only 51 (40.8%) patients were cured in the OCH group. The cure rate was significantly higher in the S.L. group (RR=1.75, p&amp;lt;0.001). Kaplan-Meir plot showed a considerably higher cure over time in the S.L. group (Log-rank test, p=0.032). There were no deaths in the S.L. group, but there were six deaths (4.8%) in the OCH group (RR=0.08, p=0.013). Seven patients (5.6%) in the S.L. group and six patients (4.8%) in the OCH group were admitted to ICU (RR=1.17, P=0.776). There was no significant difference between treatment groups regarding Total Leukocyte Count, Neutrophils count, Lymph, Alanine transaminase, and Urea.
Conclusion: Sofosbuvir/ledipasvir is suggestive of being effective in treating  patients with moderate  COVID-19 infection. Further studies are needed to compare Sofosbuvir/ledipasvir with the new treatment protocols.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.21257429" rel="alternate" title="Efficacy of Sofosbuvir plus Ledipasvir in Egyptian patients with COVID-19 compared to standard treatment: Randomized controlled trial (8 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.21257244</id><title>Controlling risk of SARS-CoV-2 infection in essential workers of enclosed food manufacturing facilities (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.443978+00:00</updated><author><name>Julia S. Sobolik</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth T. Sajewski</name></author><author><name>Lee-Ann Jaykus</name></author><author><name>D. Kane Cooper</name></author><author><name>Ben A. Lopman</name></author><author><name>Alicia NM. Kraay</name></author><author><name>P. Barry Ryan</name></author><author><name>Juan S. Leon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The SARS-CoV-2 global pandemic poses significant health risks to workers who are essential to maintaining the food supply chain. Using a quantitative risk assessment model, this study characterized the impact of risk reduction strategies for controlling SARS-CoV-2 transmission (droplet, aerosol, fomite-mediated) among front-line workers in a representative enclosed food manufacturing facility. We simulated: 1) individual and cumulative SARS-CoV-2 infection risks from close contact (droplet and aerosols at 1-3m), aerosol, and fomite-mediated exposures to a susceptible worker following exposure to an infected worker during an 8h-shift; and 2) the relative reduction in SARS-CoV-2 infection risk attributed to infection control interventions (physical distancing, mask use, ventilation, surface disinfection, hand hygiene). Without mitigation measures, the SARS-CoV-2 infection risk was largest for close contact (droplet and aerosol) at 1m (0.96, 95%CI: 0.67–1.0). In comparison, risk associated with fomite (0.26, 95%CI: 0.10–0.56) or aerosol exposure alone (0.05, 95%CI: 0.01–0.13) at 1m distance was substantially lower (73-95%). At 1m, droplet transmission predominated over aerosol and fomite-mediated transmission, however, this changed by 3m, with aerosols comprising the majority of the exposure dose. Increasing physical distancing reduced risk by 84% (1 to 2m) and 91% (1 to 3m). Universal mask use reduced infection risk by 52-88%, depending on mask type. Increasing ventilation (from 0.1 to 2-8 air changes/hour) resulted in risk reductions of 14-54% (1m) and 55-85% (2m). Combining these strategies, together with handwashing and surface disinfection, resulted in &amp;lt;1% infection risk. Current industry SARS-CoV-2 risk reduction strategies, particularly when bundled, provide significant protection to essential food workers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using mathematical modeling, we find that workers in enclosed food manufacturing facilities are at higher risk of SARS-CoV-2 infection from close contact transmission (exposure to large droplets and small aerosol particles) than fomite transmission. Thus, strategies protecting workers should prioritize close contact transmission pathways, such as physical distancing, universal mask use, and room air changes, with surface disinfection (reducing fomite transmission) and handwashing of secondary importance. Our work supports current international (EU-OSHA), domestic (FDA, OSHA), and food industry-standard guidance for managing COVID-19 transmission in essential workers in the food manufacturing sector. Although our model was designed for an indoor food manufacturing setting, it can be readily adapted to other indoor environments and infectious respiratory pathogens.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.21257244" rel="alternate" title="Controlling risk of SARS-CoV-2 infection in essential workers of enclosed food manufacturing facilities (7 tweets)"/><category term="Occupational and Environmental Health"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.21257557</id><title>Early Detection of COVID-19 Outbreaks Using Human Mobility Data (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.444293+00:00</updated><author><name>Grace Guan</name></author><author><name>Yotam Dery</name></author><author><name>Matan Yechezkel</name></author><author><name>Irad Ben-Gal</name></author><author><name>Dan Yamin</name></author><author><name>Margaret Brandeau</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background
Contact mixing plays a key role in the spread of COVID-19. Thus, mobility restrictions of varying degrees up to and including nationwide lockdowns have been implemented in over 200 countries. To appropriately target the timing, location, and severity of measures intended to encourage social distancing at a country level, it is essential to predict when and where outbreaks will occur, and how widespread they will be. 

Methods
We analyze aggregated, anonymized health data and cell phone mobility data from Israel. We develop predictive models for daily new cases and the test positivity rate over the next 7 days for different geographic regions in Israel. We evaluate model goodness of fit using root mean squared error (RMSE). We use these predictions in a five-tier categorization scheme to predict the severity of COVID-19 in each region over the next week. We measure magnitude accuracy (MA), the extent to which the correct severity tier is predicted.

Results
Models using mobility data outperformed models that did not use mobility data, reducing RMSE by 17.3% when predicting new cases and by 10.2% when predicting the test positivity rate. The best set of predictors for new cases consisted of 1-day lag of past 7-day average new cases, along with a measure of internal movement within a region. The best set of predictors for the test positivity rate consisted of 3-days lag of past 7-day average test positivity rate, along with the same measure of internal movement. Using these predictors, RMSE was 4.812 cases per 100,000 people when predicting new cases and 0.79% when predicting the test positivity rate. MA in predicting new cases was 0.775, and accuracy of prediction to within one tier was 1.0. MA in predicting the test positivity rate was 0.820, and accuracy to within one tier was 0.998.

Conclusions
Using anonymized, macro-level data human mobility data along with health data aids predictions of when and where COVID-19 outbreaks are likely to occur. Our method provides a useful tool for government decision makers, particularly in the post-vaccination era, when focused interventions are needed to contain COVID-19 outbreaks while mitigating the collateral damage of more global restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.21257557" rel="alternate" title="Early Detection of COVID-19 Outbreaks Using Human Mobility Data (7 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.16.21257299</id><title>Indian Interventional trials for COVID-19 drugs: Insights and Learnings (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.444636+00:00</updated><author><name>Arati Ranade</name></author><author><name>Kirtee Wani</name></author><author><name>V. Premnath</name></author><author><name>Chitra Lele</name></author><author><name>Smita Kale</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Since the COVID-19 pandemic began, India has substantially contributed to drug development and clinical research. Task Force on Repurposing of Drugs (TFORD) for COVID19 has tried to look at the overall position of India in terms of interventional clinical trials and highlight learnings which can prepare us to fight future pandemics in a better way. Trials registered on CTRI from March 2020 to December 2020 were considered for this purpose. From a total 409 trials registered, 108 focused on modern drugs. From 108 trials studied, 92 were randomized trials, 34 trials were sponsored by Indian Pharmaceutical industry, 23 were self-sponsored and 20 were sponsored by Research institutes and hospitals. Only 83 trials studied the repurposed drugs. An unfortunate revelation was that out of 108 trials, 79 showed as not yet recruiting. This highlights the urgent need for Government, Research institutions and Indian Pharmaceutical industries to break down silos and work together towards this common cause.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.16.21257299" rel="alternate" title="Indian Interventional trials for COVID-19 drugs: Insights and Learnings (7 tweets)"/><category term="Health Policy"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.15.21257261</id><title>Systematic Review and Meta-analysis on COVID-19 Vaccine Hesitancy (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.445627+00:00</updated><author><name>Iman Ahmed Fathalla Aboelsaad</name></author><author><name>Dina Mohamed Hafez</name></author><author><name>Abdallah Almaghraby</name></author><author><name>Shaimaa Abdulaziz Abdulmoneim</name></author><author><name>Samar Ossama El-ganainy</name></author><author><name>Noha Alaa Hamdy</name></author><author><name>Ehsan Akram Deghidy</name></author><author><name>Ahmed El-Sayed Nour El-Deen</name></author><author><name>Ehab Mohamed Adel Elrewany</name></author><author><name>Alaa Hamdy Taha Khalil</name></author><author><name>Karem Mohamed Salem</name></author><author><name>Samar Galal kabeel</name></author><author><name>Yasir Ahmed Mohammed Elhadi</name></author><author><name>Ramy Shaaban</name></author><author><name>Amr Alnagar</name></author><author><name>Eman Ahmad Fadel Elsherbeny</name></author><author><name>Nagwa Ibrahim Elfeshawy</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Moustafa Tahoun</name></author><author><name>Ramy Mohamed Ghazy</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background:&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The presented meta-analysis was developed in response to the publication of several studies addressing COVID-19 vaccines hesitancy. We aimed to identify the proportion of vaccine acceptance and rejection, and factors affecting vaccine hesitancy worldwide especially with the fast emergency approval of vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods:&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Online database search was performed, and relevant studies were included with no language restriction. A meta-analysis was conducted using R software to obtain the random effect model of the pooled prevalence of vaccine acceptance and rejection. Egger’s regression test was performed to assess publication bias. Quality assessment was assessed using Newcastle-Ottawa Scale quality assessment tool.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results:&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thirty-nine out of 12246 articles met the predefined inclusion criteria. All studies were cross-sectional designs. The pooled proportion of COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy was 17% (95% CI: 14-20) while the pooled proportion of COVID-19 vaccine acceptance was 75% (95% CI: 71-79). The vaccine hesitancy and the vaccine acceptance showed high heterogeneity (I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;=100%). Case fatality ratio and the number of reported cases had significant effect on the vaccine acceptance as the pooled proportion of vaccine acceptance increased by 39.95% (95% CI: 20.1-59.8) for each 1% increase in case fatality (P&amp;lt;0.0001) and decreased by 0.1% (95% CI: -0.2-0.01) for each 1000 reported case of COVID-19, P= 0.0183).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transparency in reporting the number of newly diagnosed COVID-19 cases and deaths is mandatory as these factors are the main determinants of COVID-19 vaccine acceptance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.15.21257261" rel="alternate" title="Systematic Review and Meta-analysis on COVID-19 Vaccine Hesitancy (7 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.21.445118</id><title>Missense variants in human ACE2 modify binding to SARS-CoV-2 Spike (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.446447+00:00</updated><author><name>Stuart A MacGowan</name></author><author><name>Michael I Barton</name></author><author><name>Mikhail Kutuzov</name></author><author><name>Omer Dushek</name></author><author><name>Philip Anton van der Merwe</name></author><author><name>Geoffrey J Barton</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 infection begins with the interaction of the SARS-CoV-2 Spike (Spike) and human angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2). To explore whether population variants in ACE2 might influence Spike binding and hence infection, we selected 10 ACE2 variants based on affinity predictions and prevalence in gnomAD and measured their affinities for Spike receptor binding domain through surface plasmon resonance (SPR). We discovered variants that enhance and reduce binding, including two variants with distinct population distributions that enhanced affinity for Spike. ACE2 p.Ser19Pro (ΔΔG = 0.59 ± 0.08 kcal mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) is often seen in the gnomAD African cohort (AF = 0.003) whilst p.Lys26Arg (ΔΔG = 0.26 ± 0.09 kcal mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) is predominant in the Ashkenazi Jewish (AF = 0.01) and European non-Finnish (AF = 0.006) cohorts. Carriers of these alleles may be more susceptible to infection or severe disease and these variants may influence the global epidemiology of Covid-19. We also identified three rare ACE2 variants that strongly inhibited (p.Glu37Lys, ΔΔG = -1.33 ± 0.15 kcal mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; and p.Gly352Val, predicted ΔΔG = -1.17 kcal mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) or abolished (p.Asp355Asn) Spike binding. These variants may confer resistance to infection. Finally, we calibrated the mCSM-PPI2 ΔΔG prediction algorithm against our SPR data, give new predictions for all possible ACE2 missense variants at the Spike interface and estimate the overall burden of ACE2 variants on Covid-19 phenotypes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.21.445118" rel="alternate" title="Missense variants in human ACE2 modify binding to SARS-CoV-2 Spike (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.21257181</id><title>Clinical and experimental factors that affect the reported performance characteristics of rapid testing for SARS-CoV-2 (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.446715+00:00</updated><author><name>Valentin Parvu</name></author><author><name>Devin Gary</name></author><author><name>Joseph Mann</name></author><author><name>Yu-Chih Lin</name></author><author><name>Dorsey Mills</name></author><author><name>Lauren Cooper</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey C. Andrews</name></author><author><name>Yukari Manabe</name></author><author><name>Andrew Pekosz</name></author><author><name>Charles K. Cooper</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;ABSTRACT 
Tests that detect the presence of SARS-CoV-2 antigen in clinical specimens from the upper respiratory tract can provide a rapid means of COVID-19 disease diagnosis and help identify individuals that may be infectious and should isolate to prevent SARS-CoV-2 transmission. This systematic review assesses the diagnostic accuracy of SARS-CoV-2 antigen detection in COVID-19 symptomatic and asymptomatic individuals compared to RT-qPCR, and summarizes antigen test sensitivity using meta-regression. In total, 83 studies were included that compared SARS-CoV-2 rapid antigen lateral flow testing (RALFT) to RT-qPCR for SARS-CoV-2. Generally, the quality of the evaluated studies was inconsistent, nevertheless, the overall sensitivity for RALFT was determined to be 75.0% (95% confidence interval [CI]: 71.0-78.0). Additionally, RALFT sensitivity was found to be higher for symptomatic versus asymptomatic individuals and was higher for a symptomatic population within 7 days from symptom onset (DSO) compared to a population with extended days of symptoms. Viral load was found to be the most important factor for determining SARS-CoV-2 antigen test sensitivity. Other design factors, such as specimen storage and anatomical collection type, also affect the performance of RAFLT. RALFT and RT-qPCR testing both achieve high sensitivity when compared to SARS-CoV-2 viral culture.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.21257181" rel="alternate" title="Clinical and experimental factors that affect the reported performance characteristics of rapid testing for SARS-CoV-2 (6 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444952</id><title>A CRISPR/Cas9 genetically engineered organoid biobank reveals essential host factors for coronaviruses (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.447079+00:00</updated><author><name>Joep Beumer</name></author><author><name>Maarten H. Geurts</name></author><author><name>Mart M. Lamers</name></author><author><name>Jens Puschhof</name></author><author><name>Jingshu Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jelte van der Vaart</name></author><author><name>Anna Z. Mykytyn</name></author><author><name>Tim I. Breugem</name></author><author><name>Samra Riesebosch</name></author><author><name>Debby Schipper</name></author><author><name>Petra B. van den Doel</name></author><author><name>Wim de Lau</name></author><author><name>Cayetano Pleguezuelos-Manzano</name></author><author><name>Georg Busslinger</name></author><author><name>Bart L. Haagmans</name></author><author><name>Hans Clevers</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Rapid identification of host genes essential for virus replication may expedite the generation of therapeutic interventions. Genetic screens are often performed in transformed cell lines that poorly represent viral target cells in vivo, leading to discoveries that may not be translated to the clinic. Intestinal organoids (IOs) are increasingly used to model human disease and are amenable to genetic engineering. To discern which host factors are reliable anti-coronavirus therapeutic targets, we generate mutant clonal IOs for 19 host genes previously implicated in coronavirus biology. We verify ACE2 and DPP4 as entry receptors for SARS-CoV/SARS-CoV-2 and MERS-CoV respectively. SARS-CoV-2 replication in IOs does not require the endosomal Cathepsin B/L proteases, but specifically depends on the cell surface protease TMPRSS2. Other TMPRSS family members were not essential. The newly emerging coronavirus variant B.1.1.7, as well as SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV similarly depended on TMPRSS2. These findings underscore the relevance of non-transformed human models for coronavirus research, identify TMPRSS2 as an attractive pan-coronavirus therapeutic target, and demonstrate that an organoid knockout biobank is a valuable tool to investigate the biology of current and future emerging coronaviruses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444952" rel="alternate" title="A CRISPR/Cas9 genetically engineered organoid biobank reveals essential host factors for coronaviruses (6 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.18.21256717</id><title>Effect of Covid-19 on inequalities in premature mortality in England: an analysis of excess mortality by deprivation and ethnicity (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.447541+00:00</updated><author><name>Sharmani Barnard</name></author><author><name>Paul Fryers</name></author><author><name>Justine Fitzpatrick</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Fox</name></author><author><name>Allan Baker</name></author><author><name>Paul Burton</name></author><author><name>John Newton</name></author><author><name>Yvonne Doyle</name></author><author><name>Peter Goldblatt</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To examine the impact of the Covid-19 pandemic on inequalities in premature mortality in England by deprivation and ethnicity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A statistical model to estimate increased mortality in population sub-groups during the Covid-19 pandemic by comparing observed with expected mortality in each group based on trends over the previous five years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Information on deaths registered in England since 2015 was used, including age, sex, area of residence, and cause of death. Ethnicity was obtained from Hospital Episode Statistics (HES) records linked to death registration data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Population study of England, including all 569,824 deaths from all causes registered between 21 March 2020 and 26 February 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main outcome measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Excess mortality in each sub-group over and above the number expected based on trends in mortality in that group over the previous five years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The gradient in excess mortality by deprivation was greater in the under 75s (most deprived had 1.25 times as many deaths as expected, least deprived 1.14) than in all ages (most deprived had 1.24 times as many deaths as expected, least deprived 1.20). Among the Black and Asian groups, all deprivation quintiles had significantly larger excesses than the most deprived White group and there were no clear gradients across quintiles. Among the White group, only the most deprived had more excess deaths than deaths directly involving Covid-19. Among the Black group all deprivation quintiles experienced more excess deaths than deaths directly involving Covid-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Covid-19 pandemic has widened inequalities in premature mortality by deprivation. Among those under 75, the direct and indirect effects of the pandemic on deaths have disproportionately impacted ethnic minority groups irrespective of deprivation, and the most deprived White group. Statistics limited to deaths directly involving Covid-19 understate the pandemic’s impact on inequalities by deprivation and ethnic group at younger ages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key Messages&lt;/title&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What is already known on this topic&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Estimates of excess mortality for all ages combined for the period March 2020 to February 2021 show a small difference in the relative impact of Covid-19 on excess mortality between the most deprived and the least deprived&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Throughout the pandemic estimates of excess mortality have been greater for ethnic minority groups compared with the white group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What this study adds&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among the under 75s the gradient of excess mortality across the deprivation spectrum indicates a stark increase in already established inequalities in premature mortality&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Independent of deprivation, excess mortality in Black and Asian ethnic groups is much higher than that of the white group, indicating that ethnicity is a determinant of excess mortality, regardless of level of area-based deprivation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.18.21256717" rel="alternate" title="Effect of Covid-19 on inequalities in premature mortality in England: an analysis of excess mortality by deprivation and ethnicity (6 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.21257455</id><title>A COVID-19 Community Vulnerability Index to drive precision policy in the US (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.448031+00:00</updated><author><name>Peter Smittenaar</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Stewart</name></author><author><name>Staci Sutermaster</name></author><author><name>Lindsay Coome</name></author><author><name>Aaron Dibner-Dunlap</name></author><author><name>Mokshada Jain</name></author><author><name>Yael Caplan</name></author><author><name>Christine Campigotto</name></author><author><name>Sema K. Sgaier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: In April 2020 we released the US COVID-19 Community Vulnerability Index (CCVI) to bring to life vulnerability to health, economic, and social impact of COVID-19 at the state, county, and census tract level. Here we describe the methodology, how vulnerability is distributed across the U.S., and assess the impact on vulnerable communities over the first year of the pandemic.
Methods: The index combines 40 indicators into seven themes, drawing on both public and proprietary data. We associate timeseries of COVID-19 cases, deaths, test site access, and rental arrears with vulnerability.
Results: Although overall COVID-19 vulnerability is concentrated in the South, the seven underlying themes show substantial spatial variability. As of May 13, 2021, the top-third of vulnerable counties have seen 21% more cases and 47% more deaths than the bottom-third of vulnerable counties, despite receiving 27% fewer tests (adjusted for population). Individual vulnerability themes vary over time in their relationship with mortality as the virus swept across the country. Over 20% of households in the top vulnerability tercile have fallen behind on rent. Poorer test site access for rural vulnerable populations early in the pandemic has since been alleviated.
Conclusion: The CCVI captures greater risk of health and economic impact. It has enjoyed widespread use in response planning, and we share lessons learned about developing a data-driven tool in the midst of a fast-moving pandemic. The CCVI and an interactive data explorer are available at precisionforcovid.org/ccvi.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.21257455" rel="alternate" title="A COVID-19 Community Vulnerability Index to drive precision policy in the US (6 tweets)"/><category term="Health Policy"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.15.21257200</id><title>Measurement of Respiratory Rate using Wearable Devices and Applications to COVID-19 Detection (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.448386+00:00</updated><author><name>Aravind Natarajan</name></author><author><name>Hao-Wei Su</name></author><author><name>Conor Heneghan</name></author><author><name>Leanna Blunt</name></author><author><name>Corey O’Connor</name></author><author><name>Logan Niehaus</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We show that heart rate enabled wearable devices can be used to measure respiratory rate. Respiration modulates the heart rate creating excess power in the heart rate variability at a frequency equal to the respiratory rate, a phenomenon known as respiratory sinus arrhythmia. We isolate this component from the power spectral density of the heart beat interval time series, and show that the respiratory rate thus estimated is in good agreement with a validation dataset acquired from sleep studies (root mean squared error = 0.648 min&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt;, mean absolute percentage error = 3%). Using the same respiratory rate algorithm, we investigate population level characteristics by computing the respiratory rate from 10,000 individuals over a 14 day period, with equal number of males and females ranging in age from 20 - 69 years. 90% of respiratory rate values for healthy adults fall within the range 11.8 min&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt; 19.2 min&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt; with a mean value of 15.4 min&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt;. Respiratory rate is shown to increase with nocturnal heart rate. It also varies with BMI, reaching a minimum at 25 kg/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, and increasing for lower and higher BMI. The respiratory rate decreases slightly with age and is higher in females compared to males for age &amp;lt; 50 years, with no difference between females and males thereafter. The 90% range for the coefficient of variation in a 14 day period for females (males) varies from 2.3%−9.2% (2.3%−9.5%) for ages 20−24 yr, to 2.5%−16.8% (2.7%−21.7%) for ages 65−69 yr. We show that respiratory rate is often elevated in subjects diagnosed with COVID-19. In a 7 day window centered on the date when symptoms present (or the test date for asymptomatic cases), we find that 33% (18%) of symptomatic (asymptomatic) individuals had at least one measurement of respiratory rate 3 min&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt; higher than the regular rate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.15.21257200" rel="alternate" title="Measurement of Respiratory Rate using Wearable Devices and Applications to COVID-19 Detection (6 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.21257247</id><title>Rapidly emerging SARS-CoV-2 B.1.1.7 sub-lineage in the United States of America with spike protein D178H and membrane protein V70L mutations (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.448900+00:00</updated><author><name>Lishuang Shen</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Dien Bard</name></author><author><name>Timothy J. Triche</name></author><author><name>Alexander R. Judkins</name></author><author><name>Jaclyn A. Biegel</name></author><author><name>Xiaowu Gai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The SARS-CoV-2 B.1.1.7 lineage is highly infectious and as of April 2021 accounted for 92% of COVID-19 cases in Europe and 59% of COVID-19 cases in the U.S. It is defined by the N501Y mutation in the receptor binding domain (RBD) of the Spike (S) protein, and a few other mutations. These include two mutations in the N terminal domain (NTD) of the S protein, HV69-70del and Y144del (also known as Y145del due to the presence of tyrosine at both positions). We recently identified several emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants of concerns, characterized by Membrane (M) protein mutations, including I82T and V70L. We now identify a sub-lineage of B.1.1.7 that emerged through sequential acquisitions of M:V70L in November 2020 followed by a novel S:D178H mutation first observed in early February 2021. The percentage of B.1.1.7 isolates in the U.S. that belong to this sub-lineage increased from 0.15% in February 2021 to 1.8% in April 2021. To date this sub-lineage appears to be U.S.-specific with reported cases in 31 states, including Hawaii. As of April 2021 it constituted 36.8% of all B.1.1.7 isolates in Washington. Phylogenetic analysis and transmission inference with Nextstrain suggests this sub-lineage likely originated in either California or Washington. Structural analysis revealed that the S:D178H mutation is in the NTD of the S protein and close to two other signature mutations of B.1.1.7, HV69-70del and Y144del. It is surface exposed and may alter NTD tertiary configuration or accessibility, and thus has the potential to affect neutralization by NTD directed antibodies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.21257247" rel="alternate" title="Rapidly emerging SARS-CoV-2 B.1.1.7 sub-lineage in the United States of America with spike protein D178H and membrane protein V70L mutations (6 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.21257485</id><title>Dysbiosis and structural disruption of the respiratory microbiota in COVID-19 patients with severe and fatal outcomes (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.449542+00:00</updated><author><name>Alejandra Hernandez-Teran</name></author><author><name>Fidencio Mejia-Nepomuceno</name></author><author><name>Maria Teresa Herrera</name></author><author><name>Omar Barreto</name></author><author><name>Emma Garcia</name></author><author><name>Manuel Castillejos</name></author><author><name>Celia Boukadida</name></author><author><name>Santiago Avila-Rios</name></author><author><name>Margarita Matias-Florentino</name></author><author><name>Alma Rincon-Rubio</name></author><author><name>Mario Mujica-Sanchez</name></author><author><name>Ricardo Serna-Munoz</name></author><author><name>Eduardo Becerril-Vargas</name></author><author><name>Cristobal Guadarrama-Perez</name></author><author><name>Victor Ahumada-Topete</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Jose A. Martinez-Orozco</name></author><author><name>Jorge Salas-Hernandez</name></author><author><name>Rogelio Perez-Padilla</name></author><author><name>Joel A. Vazquez-Perez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 outbreak has caused over 3 million deaths worldwide. Understanding disease pathology and the factors that drive severe and fatal clinical outcomes is of special relevance. Studying the role of the respiratory microbiota in COVID-19 is particularly important since it is known that the respiratory microbiota interacts with the host immune system, contributing to clinical outcomes in chronic and acute respiratory diseases. Here, we characterized the microbiota in the respiratory tract of patients with mild, severe, or fatal COVID-19, and compared with healthy controls and patients with non-COVID-19-pneumonia. We comparatively studied the microbial composition, diversity, and microbiota structure across study groups and correlated the results with clinical data. We found differences in diversity and abundance of bacteria between groups, higher levels of dysbiosis in the respiratory microbiota of COVID-19 patients (regardless of severity level), differences in diversity structure among mild, severe, and fatal COVID-19, and the presence of specific bacteria that correlated with clinical variables associated with increased mortality risk.  Our data suggest that host-related and environmental factors could be affecting the respiratory microbiota before SARS-CoV-2 infection, potentially compromising the immunological response of the host against disease and promoting secondary bacterial infections. For instance, the high levels of dysbiosis coupled with low microbial structural complexity in the respiratory microbiota of COVID-19 patients, possibly resulted from antibiotic uptake and comorbidities, could have consequences for the host and microbial community level. Altogether, our findings identify the respiratory microbiota as a potential factor associated with COVID-19 severity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.21257485" rel="alternate" title="Dysbiosis and structural disruption of the respiratory microbiota in COVID-19 patients with severe and fatal outcomes (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.21257309</id><title>Mitigating the psychological impacts of COVID-19 restrictions: The Behavioural Activation in Social Isolation (BASIL) pilot randomised controlled trial to prevent depression and loneliness among older people with long term conditions (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.449935+00:00</updated><author><name>Simon Gilbody</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Littlewood</name></author><author><name>Dean McMillan</name></author><author><name>Carolyn A. Chew-Graham</name></author><author><name>Della Bailey</name></author><author><name>Samantha Gascoyne</name></author><author><name>Claire Sloan</name></author><author><name>Lauren Burke</name></author><author><name>Peter Coventry</name></author><author><name>Suzanne Crosland</name></author><author><name>Caroline Fairhurst</name></author><author><name>Andrew Henry</name></author><author><name>Catherine Hewitt</name></author><author><name>Kalpita Joshi</name></author><author><name>Eloise Ryde</name></author><author><name>Leanne Shearsmith</name></author><author><name>Gemma Traviss-Turner</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Woodhouse</name></author><author><name>Andrew Clegg</name></author><author><name>Tom Gentry</name></author><author><name>Andrew Hill</name></author><author><name>Karina Lovell</name></author><author><name>Sarah Dexter Smith</name></author><author><name>Judith Webster</name></author><author><name>David Ekers</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Older adults with long-term conditions have become more socially isolated (often due to advice to ‘shield’ to protect them from COVID-19) and are thus at particular risk of depression and loneliness. There is a need for brief scalable psychosocial interventions to mitigate the psychological impacts of social isolation. Behavioural Activation is a plausible intervention, but a trial is needed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We undertook an external randomised pilot trial (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="isrctn" xlink:href="94091479"&gt;ISRCTN94091479&lt;/ext-link&gt;) designed to test recruitment, retention and engagement with, and the acceptability and preliminary effects of the intervention. Participants aged ≥ 65 years with two or more long-term conditions were recruited between June and October 2020. Behavioural Activation was offered to intervention participants (n=47), and control participants received usual care (n=49).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Remote recruitment was possible and 45/47 (95.7%) randomised to the intervention completed one or more sessions (median 6 sessions). 90 (93.8%) completed the one month follow-up, and 86 (89.6%) completed the three month follow-up. The between-group comparison for the primary clinical outcome at one month was an adjusted between group mean difference of −0.50 PHQ-9 points (95% CI −2.01 to 1.01), but only a small number of participants had completed the intervention at this point. At three months, the PHQ-9 adjusted mean difference was 0.19 (95% CI −1.36 to 1.75). When we examined loneliness, the between-group difference in the De Jong Gierveld Loneliness scale at one month was 0.28 (95% CI −0.51 to 1.06), and there was statistically significant between group difference at three months (−0.87; 95% CI −1.56 to −0.18). Participants who withdrew had minimal depressive symptoms at entry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Behavioural Activation is a plausible intervention to mitigate the psychological impacts of COVID-19 isolation for older adults. The intervention can be delivered remotely and at scale, but should be reserved for older adults with evidence of depressive symptoms. The significant reduction in loneliness is unlikely to be a chance finding, and this will now be confirmed in a fully powered RCT.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study was funded by National Institute for Health Research (NIHR) Programme Grants for Applied Research (PGfAR) RP-PG-0217-20006&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.21257309" rel="alternate" title="Mitigating the psychological impacts of COVID-19 restrictions: The Behavioural Activation in Social Isolation (BASIL) pilot randomised controlled trial to prevent depression and loneliness among older people with long term conditions (5 tweets)"/><category term="Psychiatry and Clinical Psychology"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444935</id><title>Fluorescence signatures of SARS CoV-2 spike S1 proteins and an human ACE-2: excitation-emission maps and fluorescence lifetimes (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.450293+00:00</updated><author><name>Jonas Grzesiak</name></author><author><name>Lea Fellner</name></author><author><name>Karin Grünewald</name></author><author><name>Christoph Kölbl</name></author><author><name>Arne Walter</name></author><author><name>Reinhold Horlacher</name></author><author><name>Frank Duschek</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fast and reliable detection of infectious virus loads of the SARS CoV-2 virus is still an important issue even after more than one year of the pandemic’s outbreak. The spike protein’s S1 subunit (including its receptor-binding domain) and human angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (hACE2) are known as key players in the reproduction mechanism of the SARS CoV-2 virus. Because of its high sensitivity and simple application, fluorescence spectroscopy is promising to meet the sensitivity requirements for a virus detection in a clean environment. In such highly complex protein systems, a comprehensive knowledge of fluorescence data is presumed in order to evaluate the specificity of the spectra with respect to a possible detection. This includes full featured information on the fluorescence process, i. e. wavelength and time-dependent data. In this work, fluorescence spectral excitation-emission maps of the involved proteins are presented, namely the S1 part of the spike protein and its receptor-binding domain as well as the hACE2 enzyme. In addition, measurements of fluorescence lifetimes of the proteins are presented and analyzed by a bi-exponential kinetic approach.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444935" rel="alternate" title="Fluorescence signatures of SARS CoV-2 spike S1 proteins and an human ACE-2: excitation-emission maps and fluorescence lifetimes (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444592</id><title>Higher concentrations of bacterial enveloped virus Phi6 can protect the virus from environmental decay (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.450658+00:00</updated><author><name>Ronald Bangiyev</name></author><author><name>Maxim Chudaev</name></author><author><name>Donald W. Schaffner</name></author><author><name>Emanuel Goldman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Phage Phi6 is an enveloped virus considered as a possible non-pathogenic surrogate for SARS-CoV-2 and other viral pathogens in transmission studies. Higher input amounts of bacteriophage Phi6 are shown to delay and protect the phage from environmental decay, both when the phage are dried in plastic tubes, and when they are stored in saline solution at 4°C. When bacteriophage Phi6 are placed in LB (Luria-Bertani) growth medium prior to placement on the plastic surface, viral recovery is not influenced by the starting concentration. The protection is reflected in longer half-lives of the phage at higher concentrations compared to lower. Because experiments supporting the possibility of fomite transmission of SARS-CoV-2 and other viruses rely upon survival of infectious virus following inoculation of various surfaces, high initial amounts of input virus on a surface may generate artificially inflated survival times compared to realistic lower levels of virus that a subject would normally encounter. This is not only because there are extra half-lives to go through at the higher concentrations, but also because the half-lives themselves are extended at the higher virus concentrations. It is important to design surface drying experiments for pathogens with realistic levels of input virus, and to consider the role of the carrier and matrix if the results are to be clinically relevant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the COVID-19 pandemic, a lot of attention has been paid to the environmental decay of SARS-CoV-2 due to proposed transmission of the virus via fomites. However, published experiments have commenced with very high virus titer inoculums, an experimental design not representative of real-life conditions. The study described here evaluated the impact of initial virus titer on environmental decay of an enveloped virus, using a non-pathogenic surrogate for SARS-CoV-2, enveloped bacteriophage Phi6. We establish that higher concentrations of virus can protect the virus from environmental decay, depending on conditions. This has important implications for stability studies of SARS-CoV-2 and other viruses. Our results point to a limitation in the fundamental methodology that has been used to attribute fomite transmission for almost all respiratory viruses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444592" rel="alternate" title="Higher concentrations of bacterial enveloped virus Phi6 can protect the virus from environmental decay (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.21257470</id><title>RT-qPCR half reaction optimization for the detection of SARS-CoV-2 (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.451321+00:00</updated><author><name>Priscila Lamb Wink</name></author><author><name>Fabiana Volpato</name></author><author><name>Daiana Lima-Morales</name></author><author><name>Rodrigo Minuto Paiva</name></author><author><name>Julia Biz Willig</name></author><author><name>Hugo Bock</name></author><author><name>Fernanda de-Paris</name></author><author><name>Afonso Luis Barth</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND: The main laboratory test for the diagnosis of COVID-19 is the reverse transcription real-time polymerase chain reaction (RT-qPCR). However, the RT-qPCR is an expensive method due to the number of tests required.
OBJECTIVES: To evaluate an alternative RT-qPCR approach for the detection of SARS-CoV-2 sing half of the total volume currently recommended by the US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.
METHODS: The analytical limit of detection (LoD) and the reaction efficiency using half volumes of RT-qPCR assay were evaluated for both the N1 and N2 regions by using a synthetic control RNA. A panel of 76 SARS-CoV-2-positive and 26 SARS-CoV-2-negative clinical samples were evaluated to establish the clinical sensitivity and specificity.
FINDINGS: The RT-qPCR assay efficiency was 105% for both the half and standard reactions considering the N2 target and 84% (standard) and 101% (half) for N1. The RT-qPCR half reaction LoD for N1 and N2 were 20 and 80 copies/uL, respectively. Clinical sensitivity and specificity were 100%. The half reaction presented a decrease of up to 5.5 cycle thresholds when compared with the standard RT-qPCR.
CONCLUSIONS: The use of RT-qPCR half reaction proved to be a feasible and economic strategy for detection of SARS-CoV-2 RNA.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.21257470" rel="alternate" title="RT-qPCR half reaction optimization for the detection of SARS-CoV-2 (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.21257473</id><title>Characterization of the Second Wave of the COVID-19 Pandemic in India: A Google Trends Analysis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.452383+00:00</updated><author><name>Aayush Visaria</name></author><author><name>Pooja Polamarasetti</name></author><author><name>Shivani Reddy</name></author><author><name>Alizah Ali</name></author><author><name>Fariha R Hameed</name></author><author><name>Joel James</name></author><author><name>Moizz Akhtar</name></author><author><name>Sumaiya Islam</name></author><author><name>Priyanka Raju</name></author><author><name>Rajat Thawani</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: The second wave of the COVID-19 pandemic has led to considerable morbidity and mortality in India, in part due to lack of healthcare access, low health literacy, and poor disease surveillance. In this retrospective, descriptive ecological study, we utilized Google Trends (GT) to characterize the second COVID-19 wave and its association with official case counts based on search terms related to symptoms, testing, disease complications, medications, preventive behaviors, and healthcare utilization.

Methods: GT is a publicly available, online tracking system of Google searches. Searches are presented as relative search volumes (RSV) from 0 (least) to 100 (most number of searches). We performed pre-defined Web searches in India from 2/12/2021 to 5/09/2021. We characterized the peak RSV, RSV doubling rates, and Spearman rank correlation of selected search terms with official case counts. We also used date-adjusted linear regression to estimate the association between highly correlated search terms and official case counts. We then qualitatively classified public search queries into thematic groups to better understand public awareness and needs related to COVID-19.

Results: We observed that searches for symptoms (most searched terms in order: fever, cough, headache, fatigue, chest pain), disease states (infection, pneumonia), COVID-19-related medications (remdesivir, ivermectin, azithromycin, Fabiflu, dexamethasone), testing modalities (PCR, CT Scan, D-dimer, C-reactive protein, oxygen saturation), healthcare utilization (oxygen cylinders, hospital, physician), and preventive behaviors (lockdown, mask, pulse oximetry, hand sanitizer, quarantine) all demonstrated increases, in line with increases in official case counts. Symptoms, PCR testing, outpatient medications, and preventive behaviors peaked around April 24th, approximately two weeks prior to the peak RSV in official case counts. Contrarily, healthcare utilization factors, including searches for hospital, physicians, beds, disease states, and inpatient medications did not peak until the first week of May. There were highly significant correlations between "Coronavirus Disease 2019" (r=0.959), "fever" (r=0.935), "pulse oximetry" (r=0.952), "oxygen saturation" (r=0.944), "C-reactive protein" (r=0.955), "D-Dimer" (r=0.945), &amp;amp; "Fabiflu" (r=0.943) and official case counts.

Conclusion: GT search terms related to symptoms, testing, and medications are highly correlated with official case counts in India, suggesting need for further studies examining GT's potential use as a disease surveillance and public informant tool for public health officials.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.21257473" rel="alternate" title="Characterization of the Second Wave of the COVID-19 Pandemic in India: A Google Trends Analysis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>