<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.403130+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.19.21260767</id><title>Children with SARS-CoV-2 in the National COVID Cohort Collaborative (N3C) (625 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.403667+00:00</updated><author><name>Blake Martin</name></author><author><name>Peter E. DeWitt</name></author><author><name>Seth Russell</name></author><author><name>Adit Anand</name></author><author><name>Katie R. Bradwell</name></author><author><name>Carolyn Bremer</name></author><author><name>Davera Gabriel</name></author><author><name>Andrew T. Girvin</name></author><author><name>Janos G. Hajagos</name></author><author><name>Julie A. McMurry</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Neumann</name></author><author><name>Emily R. Pfaff</name></author><author><name>Anita Walden</name></author><author><name>Jacob T. Wooldridge</name></author><author><name>Yun Jae Yoo</name></author><author><name>Joel Saltz</name></author><author><name>Ken R. Gersing</name></author><author><name>Christopher G. Chute</name></author><author><name>Melissa A. Haendel</name></author><author><name>Richard Moffitt</name></author><author><name>Tellen D. Bennett</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To determine the characteristics, changes over time, outcomes, and severity risk factors of SARS-CoV-2 affected children within the National COVID Cohort Collaborative (N3C)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prospective cohort study of patient encounters with end dates before May 27th, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;45 N3C institutions&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Children &amp;lt;19-years-old at initial SARS-CoV-2 testing&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Outcomes and Measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Case incidence and severity over time, demographic and comorbidity severity risk factors, vital sign and laboratory trajectories, clinical outcomes, and acute COVID-19 vs MIS-C contrasts for children infected with SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;728,047 children in the N3C were tested for SARS-CoV-2; of these, 91,865 (12.6%) were positive. Among the 5,213 (6%) hospitalized children, 685 (13%) met criteria for severe disease: mechanical ventilation (7%), vasopressor/inotropic support (7%), ECMO (0.6%), or death/discharge to hospice (1.1%). Male gender, African American race, older age, and several pediatric complex chronic condition (PCCC) subcategories were associated with higher clinical severity (p&lt;italic&gt;≤&lt;/italic&gt;0.05). Vital signs (all p≤0.002) and many laboratory tests from the first day of hospitalization were predictive of peak disease severity. Children with severe (vs moderate) disease were more likely to receive antimicrobials (71% vs 32%, p&amp;lt;0.001) and immunomodulatory medications (53% vs 16%, p&amp;lt;0.001).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compared to those with acute COVID-19, children with MIS-C were more likely to be male, Black/African American, 1-to-12-years-old, and less likely to have asthma, diabetes, or a PCCC (p&lt;italic&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/italic&gt;0.04). MIS-C cases demonstrated a more inflammatory laboratory profile and more severe clinical phenotype with higher rates of invasive ventilation (12% vs 6%) and need for vasoactive-inotropic support (31% vs 6%) compared to acute COVID-19 cases, respectively (p&amp;lt;0.03).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the largest U.S. SARS-CoV-2-positive pediatric cohort to date, we observed differences in demographics, pre-existing comorbidities, and initial vital sign and laboratory test values between severity subgroups. Taken together, these results suggest that early identification of children likely to progress to severe disease could be achieved using readily available data elements from the day of admission. Further work is needed to translate this knowledge into improved outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.19.21260767" rel="alternate" title="Children with SARS-CoV-2 in the National COVID Cohort Collaborative (N3C) (625 tweets)"/><category term="Pediatrics"/><published>2021-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261030</id><title>Breakthrough Symptomatic COVID-19 Infections Leading to Long Covid: Report from Long Covid Facebook Group Poll (232 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.404041+00:00</updated><author><name>Daisy Massey</name></author><author><name>Diana Berrent</name></author><author><name>Harlan Krumholz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Vaccines have been shown to be extremely effective in preventing COVID-19 hospitalizations and deaths. However, a question remains whether vaccine breakthrough cases can still lead to Post-Acute Sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 (PASC), also known as Long Covid. To address this question, the Survivor Corps group, a grassroots COVID-19 organization focused on patient support and research, posted a poll to its 169,900 members that asked about breakthrough cases, Long Covid, and hospitalizations. 1,949 people who self-report being fully vaccinated have responded to date. While robust data are needed in a larger, unbiased sample to extrapolate rates to the population, we analyzed the results of this public poll to determine what people were reporting regarding Long Covid after breakthrough infection and to prompt discussion of how breakthrough cases are measured. The poll was posted in the Survivor Corps Facebook group (∼169,900 members). Of the 1,949 participants who responded to the poll, 44 reported a symptomatic breakthrough case and 24 of those reported that the case led to symptoms of Long Covid. 1 of these 24 cases was reported to have led to hospitalization in addition to Long Covid.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261030" rel="alternate" title="Breakthrough Symptomatic COVID-19 Infections Leading to Long Covid: Report from Long Covid Facebook Group Poll (232 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.21261040</id><title>Novel risk factors for Coronavirus disease-associated mucormycosis (CAM): a case control study during the outbreak in India (47 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.404228+00:00</updated><author><name>Umang Arora</name></author><author><name>Megha Priyadarshi</name></author><author><name>Varidh Katiyar</name></author><author><name>Manish Soneja</name></author><author><name>Prerna Garg</name></author><author><name>Ishan Gupta</name></author><author><name>Vishwesh Bharadiya</name></author><author><name>Parul Berry</name></author><author><name>Tamoghna Ghosh</name></author><author><name>Lajjaben Patel</name></author><author><name>Radhika Sarda</name></author><author><name>Shreya Garg</name></author><author><name>Shubham Agarwal</name></author><author><name>Veronica Arora</name></author><author><name>Aishwarya Ramprasad</name></author><author><name>Amit Kumar</name></author><author><name>Rohit Kumar Garg</name></author><author><name>Parul Kodan</name></author><author><name>Neeraj Nischal</name></author><author><name>Gagandeep Singh</name></author><author><name>Pankaj Jorwal</name></author><author><name>Arvind Kumar</name></author><author><name>Upendra Baitha</name></author><author><name>Ved Prakash Meena</name></author><author><name>Animesh Ray</name></author><author><name>Prayas Sethi</name></author><author><name>Immaculata Xess</name></author><author><name>Naval Vikram</name></author><author><name>Sanjeev Sinha</name></author><author><name>Ashutosh Biswas</name></author><author><name>Alok Thakar</name></author><author><name>Sushma Bhatnagar</name></author><author><name>Anjan Trikha</name></author><author><name>Naveet Wig</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The epidemiology of the Coronavirus-disease associated mucormycosis (CAM) syndemic is poorly elucidated. We aimed to identify risk factors that may explain the burden of cases and help develop preventive strategies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We performed a case-control study comparing cases diagnosed with CAM and those who had recovered from COVID-19 without developing mucormycosis (controls). Information on comorbidities, glycemic control, and practices related to COVID-19 prevention and treatment was recorded.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;352 patients (152 cases and 200 controls) diagnosed with COVID-19 during April-May 2021 were included. In the CAM group, symptoms of mucormycosis began a mean 18.9 (SD 9.1) days after onset of COVID-19, and predominantly rhino-sinus and orbital involvement was present. All, but one, CAM cases carried conventional risk factors of diabetes and steroid use. On multivariable regression, increased odds of CAM were associated with the presence of diabetes (adjusted OR 3.5, 95%CI 1.1-11), use of systemic steroids (aOR 7.7,95% CI 2.4-24.7), prolonged use of cloth and surgical masks (vs no mask, aOR 6.9, 95%CI 1.5-33.1), and repeated nasopharyngeal swab testing during the COVID-19 illness (aOR 1.6,95% CI 1.2-2.2). Zinc therapy, probably due to its utility in immune function, was found to be protective (aOR 0.05, 95%CI 0.01-0.19). Notably, the requirement of oxygen supplementation or hospitalization did not affect the risk of CAM.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Judicious use of steroids and stringent glycemic control are vital to preventing mucormycosis. Use of clean masks, preference for N95 masks if available, and minimizing swab testing after the diagnosis of COVID-19 may further reduce the incidence of CAM.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.21261040" rel="alternate" title="Novel risk factors for Coronavirus disease-associated mucormycosis (CAM): a case control study during the outbreak in India (47 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261041</id><title>The impact of large mobile air purifiers on aerosol concentration in classrooms and the reduction of airborne transmission of SARS-CoV-2 (44 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.404613+00:00</updated><author><name>F. F. Duill</name></author><author><name>F. Schulz</name></author><author><name>A. Jain</name></author><author><name>L. Krieger</name></author><author><name>B. van Wachem</name></author><author><name>F. Beyrau</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the wake of the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic, an increased risk of infection by virus-containing aerosols indoors is assumed. Especially in schools, the duration of stay is long and the number of people in the rooms is large, increasing the risk of infection. This problem particularly affects schools without pre-installed ventilation systems that are equipped with filters and/or operate with fresh air. Here, the aerosol concentration is reduced by natural ventilation. In this context, we are investigating the effect of large mobile air purifiers (AP) with HEPA filters on particle concentration and their suitability for classroom use in a primary school in Germany. The three tested APs differ significantly in their air outlet characteristics. Measurements of the number of particles, the particle size distribution, and the CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; concentration were carried out in the classroom with students (April/May 2021) and with an aerosol generator without students. In this regard, the use of APs leads to a substantial reduction in aerosol particles. At the same time, the three APs are found to have differences in their particle decay rate, noise level, and flow velocity. In addition to the measurements, the effect of various influencing parameters on the potential inhaled particle dose was investigated using a calculation model. The parameters considered include the duration of stay, particle concentration in exhaled air, respiratory flow rate, virus lifetime, ventilation interval, ventilation efficiency, AP volumetric flow, as well as room size. Based on the resulting effect diagrams, significant recommendations can be derived for reducing the risk of infection from virus-laden aerosols. Finally, the measurements were compared to computational fluid dynamics (CFD) modeling, as such tools can aid the optimal placement and configuration of APs and can be used to study the effect of the spread of aerosols from a source in the classroom.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261041" rel="alternate" title="The impact of large mobile air purifiers on aerosol concentration in classrooms and the reduction of airborne transmission of SARS-CoV-2 (44 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453521</id><title>Probiotic consortia improve anti-viral immunity to SARS-CoV-2 in Ferrets (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.404823+00:00</updated><author><name>J Lehtinen Markus</name></author><author><name>Kumar Ritesh</name></author><author><name>Zabel Bryan</name></author><author><name>M Mäkelä Sanna</name></author><author><name>Nedveck Derek</name></author><author><name>Tang Peipei</name></author><author><name>Latvala Sinikka</name></author><author><name>Guery Sebastien</name></author><author><name>R Budinoff Charles</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Probiotics have been suggested as one solution to counter detrimental health effects by SARS-CoV-2, however, data so far is scarce. We tested the effect of two probiotic consortia, OL-1 and OL-2, against SARS-CoV-2 in ferrets and assessed their effect on cytokine production and transcriptome in a human monocyte-derived macrophage (Mf) and dendritic cell (DC) model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The results showed that the consortia significantly reduced the viral load, modulated immune response, and regulated viral receptor expression in ferrets compared to placebo. In human Mf and DC model, OL-1 and OL-2 induced cytokine production and genes related to SARS-CoV-2 anti-viral immunity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study results indicate that probiotic stimulation of the ferret immune system leads to improved anti-viral immunity against SARS-COV-2 and that critical genes and cytokines for anti-SARS-CoV-2 immunity are stimulated in human immune cells &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. The effect of the consortia against SARS-CoV-2 warrants further investigations in human clinical trials.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453521" rel="alternate" title="Probiotic consortia improve anti-viral immunity to SARS-CoV-2 in Ferrets (37 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.21261093</id><title>Protection afforded by the BNT162b2 and mRNA-1273 COVID-19 vaccines in fully vaccinated cohorts with and without prior infection (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.405034+00:00</updated><author><name>Laith J. Abu-Raddad</name></author><author><name>Hiam Chemaitelly</name></author><author><name>Houssein H. Ayoub</name></author><author><name>Hadi M. Yassine</name></author><author><name>Fatiha M. Benslimane</name></author><author><name>Hebah A. Al Khatib</name></author><author><name>Patrick Tang</name></author><author><name>Mohammad R. Hasan</name></author><author><name>Peter Coyle</name></author><author><name>Zaina Al Kanaani</name></author><author><name>Einas Al Kuwari</name></author><author><name>Andrew Jeremijenko</name></author><author><name>Anvar Hassan Kaleeckal</name></author><author><name>Ali Nizar Latif</name></author><author><name>Riyazuddin Mohammad Shaik</name></author><author><name>Hanan F. Abdul Rahim</name></author><author><name>Gheyath K. Nasrallah</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Ghaith Al Kuwari</name></author><author><name>Adeel A. Butt</name></author><author><name>Hamad Eid Al Romaihi</name></author><author><name>Mohamed H. Al-Thani</name></author><author><name>Abdullatif Al Khal</name></author><author><name>Roberto Bertollini</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Effect of prior SARS-CoV-2 infection on vaccine protection remains poorly understood. Here, we investigated whether persons vaccinated after a prior infection have better protection against future infection than those vaccinated without prior infection. Effect of prior infection was assessed in Qatar’s population, where the Alpha (B.1.1.7) and Beta (B.1.351) variants dominate incidence, using two national retrospective, matched-cohort studies, one for the BNT162b2 (Pfizer-BioNTech) vaccine, and one for the mRNA-1273 (Moderna) vaccine. Incidence rates of infection among BNT162b2-vaccinated persons, with and without prior infection, were estimated, respectively, at 1.66 (95% CI: 1.26-2.18) and 11.02 (95% CI: 9.90-12.26) per 10,000 person-weeks. The incidence rate ratio was 0.15 (95% CI: 0.11-0.20). Analogous incidence rates among mRNA-1273-vaccinated persons were estimated at 1.55 (95% CI: 0.86-2.80) and 1.83 (95% CI: 1.07-3.16) per 10,000 person-weeks. The incidence rate ratio was 0.85 (95% CI: 0.34-2.05). Prior infection enhanced protection of those BNT162b2-vaccinated, but not those mRNA-1273-vaccinated. These findings may have implications for dosing, interval between doses, and potential need for booster vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.21261093" rel="alternate" title="Protection afforded by the BNT162b2 and mRNA-1273 COVID-19 vaccines in fully vaccinated cohorts with and without prior infection (31 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.21261130</id><title>Vaccine effectiveness when combining the ChAdOx1 vaccine as the first dose with an mRNA COVID-19 vaccine as the second dose (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.405342+00:00</updated><author><name>Mie Agermose Gram</name></author><author><name>Hanne-Dorthe Emborg</name></author><author><name>Ida Rask Moustsen-Helms</name></author><author><name>Jens Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Anne Katrine Bj&amp;oslashrkholt S&amp;oslashrensen</name></author><author><name>Palle Valentiner-Branth</name></author><author><name>Astrid Blicher Schelde</name></author><author><name>Katrine Finderup Nielsen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: The recommendations in several countries to stop using the ChAdOx1 vaccine has led to vaccine programs combining different vaccine types, which necessitates new knowledge on vaccine effectiveness (VE). In this study, we aimed to estimate the VE when combining the ChAdOx1 vaccine as the first dose and an mRNA vaccine as the second dose. 
Methods: This nationwide population-based cohort study estimated VE against SARS-CoV-2 infection, all-cause and COVID-19 related hospitalization and death after receiving the ChAdOx1 vaccine as the first dose followed by an mRNA vaccine as the second dose. VE estimates were obtained using a Cox regression with calendar time as underlying time and adjusted for sex, age, comorbidity, heritage and hospital admission. Information on all individuals was extracted and linked from high-quality national registries. 
Results: A total of 5,542,079 individuals were included in the analyses (97.6% of the total Danish population). A total of 144,360 were vaccinated with the ChAdOx1 vaccine as the first dose and of these 136,551 individuals received an mRNA vaccine as the second dose. A total of 1,691,464 person-years and 83,034 cases of SARS-CoV-2 infection were included. The VE against SARS-CoV-2 infection when combining the ChAdOx1 and an mRNA vaccine was 88% (95% confidence interval (CI): 83; 92) 14 days after the second dose and onwards. There were no COVID-19 related hospitalizations and deaths among the individuals vaccinated with the combination of the ChAdOx1 and an mRNA vaccine during the study period. 
Conclusion: In conclusion, this study found a reduction in the risk of SARS-CoV-2 infection when combining the ChAdOx1 and an mRNA vaccine, compared with unvaccinated individuals. This is similar to the VE of two doses of an mRNA vaccine. Longer follow-up time is needed to confirm vaccine induced protection against severe events, such as COVID-19 related hospitalization and death.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.21261130" rel="alternate" title="Vaccine effectiveness when combining the ChAdOx1 vaccine as the first dose with an mRNA COVID-19 vaccine as the second dose (22 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-07-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.21260852</id><title>Comparison of infected and vaccinated transplant recipients highlights the role of Tfh and neutralizing IgG in COVID-19 protection (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.405552+00:00</updated><author><name>Xavier Charmetant</name></author><author><name>Maxime ESPI</name></author><author><name>Ilies Benotmane</name></author><author><name>Francoise Heibel</name></author><author><name>Fanny Buron</name></author><author><name>Gabriela Gautier-Vargas</name></author><author><name>Marion Delafosse</name></author><author><name>Peggy Perrin</name></author><author><name>Alice Koenig</name></author><author><name>Noelle Cognard</name></author><author><name>Charlene Levi</name></author><author><name>Floriane Gallais</name></author><author><name>Louis Maniere</name></author><author><name>Paola Rossolillo</name></author><author><name>Eric Soulier</name></author><author><name>Florian Pierre</name></author><author><name>Anne Ovize</name></author><author><name>Emmanuel Morelon</name></author><author><name>Thierry Defrance</name></author><author><name>Samira Fafi-Kremer</name></author><author><name>Sophie Caillard</name></author><author><name>Olivier Thaunat</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Transplant recipients, which receive therapeutic immunosuppression to prevent graft rejection, are characterized by high COVID-19-related mortality and defective response to vaccines. Having observed that previous infection by SARS-CoV-2 but not the standard 2 doses scheme of vaccination, provided complete protection against COVID-19 to transplant recipients, we undertook this translational study to compare the cellular and humoral immune responses of these 2 groups of patients. Neutralizing anti-Receptor Binding Domain (RBD) IgG were identified as the critical immune effectors associated with protection. Generation of anti-RBD IgG was dependent upon spike-specific T follicular helper (Tfh) CD4+ T cells, which acted as limiting checkpoint. Tfh generation was impeded by high dose mycophenolate mofetil in non-responders to vaccine but not in infected patients, suggesting that increasing immunogenicity of vaccine could improve response rate to mRNA vaccine. This theory was validated in two independent prospective cohorts, in which administration of a 3rd dose of vaccine resulted in the generation of anti-RBD IgG in half of non-responders to 2 doses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.21260852" rel="alternate" title="Comparison of infected and vaccinated transplant recipients highlights the role of Tfh and neutralizing IgG in COVID-19 protection (20 tweets)"/><category term="Transplantation"/><published>2021-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453673</id><title>Multivariate mining of an alpaca immune repertoire identifies potent cross-neutralising SARS-CoV-2 nanobodies (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.405856+00:00</updated><author><name>Leo Hanke</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Sheward</name></author><author><name>Alec Pankow</name></author><author><name>Laura Perez Vidakovics</name></author><author><name>Vivien Karl</name></author><author><name>Changil Kim</name></author><author><name>Egon Urgard</name></author><author><name>Natalie L. Smith</name></author><author><name>Juan Astorga-Wells</name></author><author><name>Simon Ekström</name></author><author><name>Jonathan M. Coquet</name></author><author><name>Gerald M. McInerney</name></author><author><name>Ben Murrell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Conventional approaches to isolate and characterize nanobodies are laborious and cumbersome. Here we combine phage display, multivariate enrichment, and novel sequence analysis techniques to annotate an entire nanobody repertoire from an immunized alpaca. We combine this approach with a streamlined screening strategy to identify numerous anti-SARS-CoV-2 nanobodies, and use neutralization assays and Hydrogen/Deuterium exchange coupled to mass spectrometry (HDX-MS) epitope mapping to characterize their potency and specificity. Epitope mapping revealed that the binding site is a key determinant of neutralization potency, rather than affinity alone. The most potent nanobodies bind to the receptor binding motif of the RBD, directly preventing interaction with the host cell receptor ACE2, and we identify two exceptionally potent members of this category (with monomeric IC50s around 13 and 16 ng/ml). Other nanobodies bind to a more conserved epitope on the side of the RBD, and are able to potently neutralize the SARS-CoV-2 founder virus (42 ng/ml), the beta variant (B.1.351/501Y.V2) (35 ng/ml), and also cross-neutralize the more distantly related SARS-CoV-1 (0.46 μg/ml). The approach presented here is well suited for the screening of phage libraries to identify functional nanobodies for various biomedical and biochemical applications.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453673" rel="alternate" title="Multivariate mining of an alpaca immune repertoire identifies potent cross-neutralising SARS-CoV-2 nanobodies (15 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.21260551</id><title>Willingness to receive vaccination against COVID-19: results from a large nationally representative Australian population survey (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.406091+00:00</updated><author><name>Sharon R Davis</name></author><author><name>Rosario D Ampon</name></author><author><name>Leanne M Poulos</name></author><author><name>Guy B Marks</name></author><author><name>Brett G Toelle</name></author><author><name>Helen K Reddel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We surveyed 10,024 Australians regarding COVID-19 vaccine willingness. Overall, 59.9% indicated yes, 13.9% no and 26.3% unsure/don’t know. Vaccine willingness was higher in males, and increased with increasing education and socioeconomic advantage. Results contrast with earlier, smaller Australian surveys regarding vaccination willingness and confirm the need for targeted vaccination information.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.21260551" rel="alternate" title="Willingness to receive vaccination against COVID-19: results from a large nationally representative Australian population survey (14 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261042</id><title>Robust antibody levels in both diabetic and non-diabetic individuals after BNT162b2 mRNA COVID-19 vaccination (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.406512+00:00</updated><author><name>Hamad Ali</name></author><author><name>Abdelmohsen Al-Terki</name></author><author><name>Sardar Sindhu</name></author><author><name>Barrak Alahmad</name></author><author><name>Maha Hammad</name></author><author><name>Salman Al-Sabah</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Alghounaim</name></author><author><name>Mohammad H. Jamal</name></author><author><name>Ali Aldei</name></author><author><name>Mohammad J. Mairza</name></author><author><name>Maitham Husain</name></author><author><name>Sriraman Deverajan</name></author><author><name>Rasheed Ahmad</name></author><author><name>Preethi Cherian</name></author><author><name>Irina Alkhairi</name></author><author><name>Abdullah Alkandari</name></author><author><name>Jehad Abubaker</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Abu-Farha</name></author><author><name>Fahd Al-Mulla</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The emergence of effective vaccines for COVID-19 has been welcomed by the world with great optimism. Given their increased susceptibility to COVID-19, the question arises whether individuals with type-2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) and other metabolic conditions can respond effectively to the mRNA-based vaccine. We aimed to evaluate the levels of anti-SARS-CoV-2 IgG and neutralizing antibodies in people with T2DM and/or other metabolic risk factors (hypertension and obesity) compared to those without. This study included 262 people that took two doses of BNT162b2 (Pfizer–BioNTech) mRNA vaccine. Both T2DM and non-diabetic individuals had a robust response to vaccination as demonstrated by their high antibody titers. However, both SARS-CoV-2 IgG and neutralizing antibodies titers were lower in people with T2DM. Their levels were 154±49.1 vs. 138±59.4BAU/mL for IgG and 87.1±11.6 vs. 79.7±19.5% for neutralizing antibodies in individuals without diabetes compared to those with T2DM, respectively. In a multiple linear regression adjusted for individual characteristics, comorbidities, previous COVID-19 infection and duration since second vaccine dose, diabetics had 13.86 BAU/ml (95%CI: −27.08 to −0.64BAU/ml, p=0.041) less IgG antibodies and 4.42% (95%CI: −8.53 to −0.32%, p=0.036) less neutralizing antibodies than non-diabetics. Hypertension and obesity did not show significant changes in antibody titers. Taken together, both type-2 diabetic and non-diabetic individuals elicited strong immune responses to SARS-CoV-2 BNT162b2 mRNA vaccine; nonetheless, lower levels were seen in people with diabetes. Continuous monitoring of the antibody levels might be a good indicator to guide personalized needs for further booster shots to maintain adaptive immunity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261042" rel="alternate" title="Robust antibody levels in both diabetic and non-diabetic individuals after BNT162b2 mRNA COVID-19 vaccination (10 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.21258785</id><title>Proton pump inhibitor use is not associated with severe COVID-19 related outcomes: A propensity score weighted analysis of a national veteran cohort (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.406805+00:00</updated><author><name>Shailja C. Shah</name></author><author><name>Alese Halvorson</name></author><author><name>Brandon McBay</name></author><author><name>Chad Dorn</name></author><author><name>Otis Wilson</name></author><author><name>Sony Tuteja</name></author><author><name>Kyong-Mi Chang</name></author><author><name>Ayako Suzuki</name></author><author><name>Christine Hunt</name></author><author><name>Richard Hauger</name></author><author><name>Kelly Cho</name></author><author><name>Edward Siew</name></author><author><name>Michael Matheny</name></author><author><name>Adriana Hung</name></author><author><name>Robert Greevy</name></author><author><name>Christianne Roumie</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background and Aims: Low pH deactivates most pathogens, including coronaviruses. Proton pump inhibitors (PPIs) are potent gastric acid suppressing medications. Whether PPI use vs non-use is associated with severe Coronavirus disease-2019 (COVID-19) outcomes remains uncertain. We aimed to compare severe COVID-19 outcomes between current outpatient PPI users and non-users.

Methods: We conducted a retrospective propensity score-weighted analysis of a national cohort of US veterans with established care who tested positive for severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) through January 9, 2021, and who had 60 days of follow-up. The positive test date was the index date. Current outpatient PPI use up to and including the index date (primary exposure) was compared to non-use, defined as no PPI prescription fill in the 365 days prior to the index date. The primary outcome was a composite of use of mechanical ventilation or death within 60 days. Weighted logistic regression models evaluated severe COVID-19 outcomes between current PPI users vs non-users.

Results: Of 97,674 Veterans with SARS-CoV-2 testing, 14,958 tested positive (6262 [41.9%] current PPI users, 8696 [58.1%] non-users) and comprised the analytic cohort. After weighting, all covariates were well-balanced. In the weighted cohort, there was no difference in the primary composite outcome (8.2% vs 8.0%; OR 1.03, 95% CI 0.91-1.16), secondary composite outcome, nor individual component outcomes between current PPI users and non-users. There was no significant interaction between age and PPI use on outcomes.

Conclusion: Among patients with SARS-CoV-2 infection, current PPI use vs non-use is not associated with severe COVID-19 outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.21258785" rel="alternate" title="Proton pump inhibitor use is not associated with severe COVID-19 related outcomes: A propensity score weighted analysis of a national veteran cohort (8 tweets)"/><category term="Gastroenterology"/><published>2021-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.453029</id><title>CD8+ T cell signature in acute SARS-CoV-2 infection identifies memory precursors (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.407051+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah Adamo</name></author><author><name>Jan Michler</name></author><author><name>Yves Zurbuchen</name></author><author><name>Carlo Cervia</name></author><author><name>Patrick Taeschler</name></author><author><name>Miro E. Raeber</name></author><author><name>Simona Baghai Sain</name></author><author><name>Jakob Nilsson</name></author><author><name>Andreas E. Moor</name></author><author><name>Onur Boyman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Immunological memory is a hallmark of adaptive immunity and facilitates an accelerated and enhanced immune response upon re-infection with the same pathogen&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt;. Since the outbreak of the ongoing coronavirus disease 19 (COVID-19) pandemic, a key question has focused on whether severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2)-specific T cells stimulated during acute infection give rise to long-lived memory T cells&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;. Using spectral flow cytometry combined with cellular indexing of transcriptomes and T cell receptor (TCR) sequencing we longitudinally characterize individual SARS-CoV-2-specific CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells of COVID-19 patients from acute infection to one year into recovery and find a distinct signature identifying long-lived memory CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells. SARS-CoV-2-specific memory CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells persisting one year after acute infection re-express CD45RA and interleukin-7 receptor α (CD127), upregulate T cell factor-1 (TCF1), and maintain low CCR7, thus resembling CD45RA&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; effector-memory T (T&lt;sub&gt;EMRA&lt;/sub&gt;) cells. Tracking individual clones of SARS-CoV-2-specific CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells, we reveal that an interferon signature marks clones giving rise to long-lived cells, whereas prolonged proliferation and mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) signaling are associated with clone contraction and disappearance. Collectively, we identify a transcriptional signature differentiating short-from long-lived memory CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells following an acute virus infection in humans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.453029" rel="alternate" title="CD8+ T cell signature in acute SARS-CoV-2 infection identifies memory precursors (8 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.21261065</id><title>COVID-Q: validation of the first COVID-19 questionnaire based on patient-rated symptom gravity (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.407258+00:00</updated><author><name>G Spinato</name></author><author><name>C Fabbris</name></author><author><name>F Conte</name></author><author><name>A Menegaldo</name></author><author><name>L Franz</name></author><author><name>P Gaudioso</name></author><author><name>F Cinetto</name></author><author><name>C Agostini</name></author><author><name>G Costantini</name></author><author><name>P Boscolo-Rizzo</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The aim of the present study was to develop and validate the CoronaVirus Disease – 2019 (COVID-19) Questionnaire (COVID-Q), a novel symptom questionnaire specific for COVID-19 patients, to provide a comprehensive evaluation which may be helpful for physicians.. A secondary goal of the present study was to evaluate the performance of the COVID-Q in identifying subjects at higher risk of being tested positive for COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Material and methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consecutive non-hospitalized adults who underwent nasopharyngeal and throat swab for severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) detection at Treviso Hospital in March 2020, were enrolled. Subjects were divided into positive (cases) and negative (controls) in equal number. All of them gave consent and answered the COVID-Q. Patients not able to answer the COVID-Q due to clinical conditions were excluded.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Parallel Analysis and Principal Component Analysis were used to identify clusters of items measuring the same dimension. The Item Response Theory (IRT)-based analyses evaluated the functioning of item categories, the presence of clusters of local dependence among items, item fit within the model and model fit to the data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Answers obtained from 230 COVID-19 cases (113 males, and 117 females; mean age 55 years, range 20-99 years) and 230 controls (61 males, and 169 females; mean age 46 years, range 21-89) were analyzed. Parallel analysis led to the extraction of six components, which corresponded to as many clinical presentation patterns: asthenia, influenza-like symptoms, ear and nose symptoms, breathing issues, throat symptoms, and anosmia/ageusia. The final IRT models retained 27 items as significant for symptom assessment. The total score on the questionnaire was significantly associated with positivity to the molecular SARS-CoV-2 test: subjects with multiple symptoms were significantly more likely to be affected by COVID-19 (p &amp;lt; .001). Older age and male gender also represented risk factors. Presence of breathing issues and anosmia/ageusia were significantly related to positivity to SARS-CoV-2 (p &amp;lt; 0.001). None of the examined comorbidities had a significant association with COVID-19 diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the analyses, COVID-Q could be validated since the aspects it evaluated were overall significantly related to SARS-CoV-2 infection. The application of the novel COVID-Q to everyday clinical practice may help identifying subjects who are likely to be affected by COVID-19 and address them to a nasopharyngeal swab in order to achieve an early diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What is already known about this topic?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 symptoms are widely known. Lots of studies have been published regarding self-administered questionnaires in order to characterize and know as much as possible regarding this disease. By the way, no specific questionnaires have been validated, yet, and there is no consensus regarding this topic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What does this article add?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper shows the COVID-Q, a novel symptom questionnaire specific for COVID-19 patients. The aim is to provide a comprehensive evaluation that may be helpful to clinicians in order to suspect SARS-CoV-2 infection or not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.21261065" rel="alternate" title="COVID-Q: validation of the first COVID-19 questionnaire based on patient-rated symptom gravity (7 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261025</id><title>Clinical echocardiography does not indicate cardiac dysfunction in critically ill Covid-19 patients (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.407473+00:00</updated><author><name>Henrik Isackson</name></author><author><name>Anders Larsson</name></author><author><name>Miklos Lipcsey</name></author><author><name>Robert Frithiof</name></author><author><name>Frank A. Flachskampf</name></author><author><name>Michael Hultström</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aims&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We aimed to investigate the acute effects of severe SARS-CoV-2 on myocardial function.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods and Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is an observational study generated from the first 79 patients admitted to intensive care in Uppsala due to respiratory failure with SARS-CoV-2 infection, during the first wave in 2020, included in the PRONMED study. From this group 34 underwent echocardiographic examination of which 25 were included in the study, and compared to 44 non-echo patients. Demographic analysis compared standard parameters and previous morbidities between the echo and non-echo group. Standard echocardiographic parameters were analysed indicating a reduced left ventricular function as assessed by global longitudinal strain and very discrete increases in wall thickness in the group as a whole. A group comparison between the outcomes survival and death was carried out. Right sided dimensions and functional parameters did not indicate major strain. An increased maximum tricuspid valve regurgitation velocity indicating increased pulmonary arterial pressure was significantly associated with death, but failed to maintain significance when corrected for multiple comparison. Biochemical cardiac markers and D-dimer correlated to initiation of echocardiography and mortality. Tricuspid regurgitation maximum velocity was positively correlated with maximum troponin I.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;These results suggests that there is no clear negative effect on cardiac function in critical SARS-CoV-2 infection. There are indications that pulmonary pressure elevation carries a negative predictive outcome suggesting pulmonary disease as the major driver of mortality. Cardiac biomarkers as well as D-dimer carry a predictive outcome value.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261025" rel="alternate" title="Clinical echocardiography does not indicate cardiac dysfunction in critically ill Covid-19 patients (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cardiovascular Medicine"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.21261046</id><title>Respiratory Viral Sequencing Panel identifies SARS-CoV-2 variants, transmission and other co-circulating viruses in Georgia, USA: A Diagnostic and Epidemiologic Tool for Mass Surveillance in COVID-19 Pandemic (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.407655+00:00</updated><author><name>Nikhil S Sahajpal</name></author><author><name>Ashis K Mondal</name></author><author><name>Allan Njau</name></author><author><name>Zachary Petty</name></author><author><name>Jiani Chen</name></author><author><name>Sudha Ananth</name></author><author><name>Pankaj Ahluwalia</name></author><author><name>Colin Williams</name></author><author><name>Ted M Ross</name></author><author><name>Alka Chaubey</name></author><author><name>Grace DeSantis</name></author><author><name>Gary P. Schroth</name></author><author><name>Justin Bahl</name></author><author><name>Ravindra Kolhe</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the current phase of COVID-19 pandemic, we are facing two serious public health challenges that include deficits in SARS-CoV-2 variant monitoring, and neglect of other co-circulating respiratory viruses. Additionally, accurate assessment of the evolution, extent and dynamics of the outbreak are required to understand the transmission of the virus amongst seemingly unrelated cases and provide critical epidemiological information. To address these challenges, we evaluated a new high-throughput next-generation sequencing (NGS), respiratory viral panel (RVP) that includes 40 viral pathogens with the aim of analyzing viral subtypes, mutational variants of SARS-CoV-2, model to understand the spread of the virus in the state of Georgia, USA, and to assess other circulating viruses in the same population.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study evaluated a total of 522 samples that included 483 patient samples and 42 synthetic positive control material. The performance metrics were calculated for both clinical and reference control samples by comparing detection results with the RT-PCR assay. The limit of detection (LoD) studies were conducted as per the FDA guidelines. Inference and visualization of the phylogeny of the SARS-CoV-2 sequences were performed through the Nextstrain Command-Line Interface (CLI) tool, utilizing the associated augur and auspice toolkits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The performance metrics calculated using both the clinical samples and the reference controls revealed a PPA, NPA and accuracy of 95.98%, 85.96% and 94.4%, respectively. The LoD was determined to be 10 copies/ml with all 25 replicates detected across two different runs. The clade for pangolin lineage B that contains certain distant variants, including P4715L in ORF1ab, Q57H in ORF 3a and, S84L in ORF8 covarying with the D614G spike protein mutation were the most prevalent, early in the pandemic, in Georgia, USA. In our analysis, isolates from the same county formed paraphyletic groups, which indicated virus transmission between counties.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study demonstrates the clinical and public health utility of the NGS-RVP to identify novel variants that can provide actionable information to prevent or mitigate emerging viral threats, models that provide insights into viral transmission patterns and predict transmission/ resurgence of regional outbreaks and provide critical information on co-circulating respiratory viruses that might be independent factors contributing to the global disease burden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.21261046" rel="alternate" title="Respiratory Viral Sequencing Panel identifies SARS-CoV-2 variants, transmission and other co-circulating viruses in Georgia, USA: A Diagnostic and Epidemiologic Tool for Mass Surveillance in COVID-19 Pandemic (6 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261038</id><title>Epidemics of chikungunya, Zika, and COVID-19 reveal bias in case-based mapping (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.407886+00:00</updated><author><name>Fausto Andres Bustos Carrillo</name></author><author><name>Brenda Lopez Mercado</name></author><author><name>Jairo Carey Monterrey</name></author><author><name>Damaris Collado</name></author><author><name>Saira Saborio</name></author><author><name>Tatiana Miranda</name></author><author><name>Carlos Barilla</name></author><author><name>Sergio Ojeda</name></author><author><name>Nery Sanchez</name></author><author><name>Miguel Plazaola</name></author><author><name>Harold Suazo Laguna</name></author><author><name>Douglas Elizondo</name></author><author><name>Sonia Arguello</name></author><author><name>Anna M. Gajewski</name></author><author><name>Hannah E. Maier</name></author><author><name>Krista Latta</name></author><author><name>Bradley Carlson</name></author><author><name>Josefina Coloma</name></author><author><name>Leah Katzelnick</name></author><author><name>Hugh Sturrock</name></author><author><name>Angel Balmaseda</name></author><author><name>Guillermina Kuan</name></author><author><name>Aubree Gordon</name></author><author><name>Eva Harris</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Explosive epidemics of chikungunya, Zika, and COVID-19 have recently occurred worldwide, all of which featured large proportions of subclinical infections. Spatial studies of infectious disease epidemics typically use symptomatic infections (cases) to estimate incidence rates (cases/total population), often misinterpreting them as infection risks (infections/total population) or disease risks (cases/infected population). We examined these three measures in a pediatric cohort (N≈3,000) over two chikungunya epidemics and one Zika epidemic and in a household cohort (N=1,793) over one COVID-19 epidemic in Nicaragua. Across different analyses and all epidemics, case incidence rates considerably underestimated both risk-based measures. Spatial infection risk differed from spatial disease risk, and typical case-only approaches precluded a full understanding of the spatial seroprevalence patterns. For epidemics of pathogens that cause many subclinical infections, relying on case-only datasets and misinterpreting incidence rates, as is common, results in substantial bias, a general finding applicable to many pathogens of high human concern.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261038" rel="alternate" title="Epidemics of chikungunya, Zika, and COVID-19 reveal bias in case-based mapping (5 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.21260972</id><title>The mystery of COVID-19 reinfections: A global systematic review and meta-analysis of 577 cases (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.408177+00:00</updated><author><name>Rubaid Azhar Dhillon</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Aadil Qamar</name></author><author><name>Omar Irfan</name></author><author><name>Jaleed Ahmed Gilani</name></author><author><name>Usama Waqar</name></author><author><name>Mir Ibrahim Sajid</name></author><author><name>Syed Faisal Mahmood</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the COVID-19 pandemic rages on, reports on disparities in vaccine roll out alongside reinfection and reactivation from previously recovered cases have been emerging. With newer waves and variants of COVID-19, we conducted a systematic review to assess the determinants and disease spectrum of COVID-19 reinfection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A comprehensive search covering relevant databases was conducted for observational studies reporting Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) confirmed infection and reinfection cases. Quality assessment tool developed by the National Institute of Health (NIH) for assessment of case series was used. Meta-analyses were performed using RevMan 5.3 for pooled proportions of findings in first infection and reinfection with 95% confidence interval (CI).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eighty-one studies reporting 577 cases were included from 22 countries. The mean age of patients was 46.2±18.9 years with males accounting for 45.8% of the study population while 179 (31.0%) cases of comorbidities were reported. The average time duration between first infection and reinfection was 63.6±48.9 days. During first infection and reinfection, fever was the most common symptom (41.4% and 36.4%, respectively) whilst anti-viral therapy was the most common treatment regimen administered (44.5% and 43.0%, respectively). Overall, comparable odds of symptomatic presentation and management were reported in the two infections. However, a higher Intensive Care Unit (ICU) admission rate was observed in reinfection compared to first infection (10 vs 3). Ten deaths were reported with 565 patients fully recovering. Respiratory failure was the most common cause of death (7/10 deaths). Seventy-two studies were determined to be of good quality whilst nine studies were of fair quality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the first global-scale systematic review of its kind, our findings support immunization practices given increased ICU admissions and mortality in reinfections. Our cohort serves as a guide for clinicians and authorities for devising an optimal strategy for controlling the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.21260972" rel="alternate" title="The mystery of COVID-19 reinfections: A global systematic review and meta-analysis of 577 cases (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.21261076</id><title>The U.S. COVID-19 Trends and Impact Survey, 2020-2021: Continuous real-time measurement of COVID-19 symptoms, risks, protective behaviors, testing and vaccination (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.411291+00:00</updated><author><name>Joshua A. Salomon</name></author><author><name>Alex Reinhart</name></author><author><name>Alyssa Bilinski</name></author><author><name>Eu Jing Chua</name></author><author><name>Wichada La Motte-Kerr</name></author><author><name>Minttu M. Rönn</name></author><author><name>Marissa Reitsma</name></author><author><name>Katherine Ann Morris</name></author><author><name>Sarah LaRocca</name></author><author><name>Tamar Farag</name></author><author><name>Frauke Kreuter</name></author><author><name>Roni Rosenfeld</name></author><author><name>Ryan J. Tibshirani</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The U.S. COVID-19 Trends and Impact Survey (CTIS) is a large, cross-sectional, Internet-based survey that has operated continuously since April 6, 2020. By inviting a random sample of Facebook active users each day, CTIS collects information about COVID-19 symptoms, risks, mitigating behaviors, mental health, testing, vaccination, and other key priorities. The large scale of the survey – over 20 million responses in its first year of operation – allows tracking of trends over short timescales and allows comparisons at fine demographic and geographic detail. The survey has been repeatedly revised to respond to emerging public health priorities. In this paper, we describe the survey methods and content and give examples of CTIS results that illuminate key patterns and trends and help answer high-priority policy questions relevant to the COVID-19 epidemic and response. These results demonstrate how large online surveys can provide continuous, real-time indicators of important outcomes that are not subject to public health reporting delays and backlogs. The CTIS offers high value as a supplement to official reporting data by supplying essential information about behaviors, attitudes toward policy and preventive measures, economic impacts, and other topics not reported in public health surveillance systems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. COVID-19 Trends and Impact Survey (CTIS) has operated continuously since April 6, 2020, collecting over 20 million responses. The largest public health survey ever conducted in the United States, CTIS was designed to facilitate detailed demographic and geographic analyses, track trends over time, and accommodate rapid response to emerging priorities. Using examples of CTIS results illuminating trends in symptoms, risks, mitigating behaviors, testing and vaccination in relation to evolving high-priority policy questions over 12 months of the pandemic, we illustrate the value of online surveys for tracking patterns and trends in COVID outcomes as an adjunct to official reporting, and showcase unique insights that would not be visible through traditional public health reporting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.21261076" rel="alternate" title="The U.S. COVID-19 Trends and Impact Survey, 2020-2021: Continuous real-time measurement of COVID-19 symptoms, risks, protective behaviors, testing and vaccination (3 tweets)"/><category term="Health Informatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261039</id><title>Geographical concentration of COVID-19 cases by social determinants of health in 16 large metropolitan areas in Canada – a cross-sectional study (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.414841+00:00</updated><author><name>Yiqing Xia</name></author><author><name>Huiting Ma</name></author><author><name>Gary Moloney</name></author><author><name>Héctor A. Velásquez García</name></author><author><name>Monica Sirski</name></author><author><name>Naveed Z. Janjua</name></author><author><name>David Vickers</name></author><author><name>Tyler Williamson</name></author><author><name>Alan Katz</name></author><author><name>Kristy Yu</name></author><author><name>Rafal Kustra</name></author><author><name>David L Buckeridge</name></author><author><name>Marc Brisson</name></author><author><name>Stefan D Baral</name></author><author><name>Sharmistha Mishra</name></author><author><name>Mathieu Maheu-Giroux</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a growing recognition that strategies to reduce SARS-CoV-2 transmission should be responsive to local transmission dynamics. Studies have revealed inequalities along social determinants of health, but little investigation was conducted surrounding geographic concentration within cities. We quantified social determinants of geographic concentration of COVID-19 cases across sixteen census metropolitan areas (CMA) in four Canadian provinces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used surveillance data on confirmed COVID-19 cases at the level of dissemination area. Gini (co-Gini) coefficients were calculated by CMA based on the proportion of the population in ranks of diagnosed cases and each social determinant using census data (income, education, visible minority, recent immigration, suitable housing, and essential workers) and the corresponding share of cases. Heterogeneity was visualized using Lorenz (concentration) curves.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Geographic concentration was observed in all CMAs (half of the cumulative cases were concentrated among 21-35% of each city’s population): with the greatest geographic heterogeneity in Ontario CMAs (Gini coefficients, 0.32-0.47), followed by British Columbia (0.23-0.36), Manitoba (0.32), and Québec (0.28-0.37). Cases were disproportionately concentrated in areas with lower income, education attainment, and suitable housing; and higher proportion of visible minorities, recent immigrants, and essential workers. Although a consistent feature across CMAs was concentration by proportion visible minorities, the magnitude of concentration by social determinants varied across CMAs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The feature of geographical concentration of COVID-19 cases was consistent across CMAs, but the pattern by social determinants varied. Geographically-prioritized allocation of resources and services should be tailored to the local drivers of inequalities in transmission in response to SARS-CoV-2’s resurgence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261039" rel="alternate" title="Geographical concentration of COVID-19 cases by social determinants of health in 16 large metropolitan areas in Canada – a cross-sectional study (3 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>