<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.082245+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470946</id><title>Omicron and Delta Variant of SARS-CoV-2: A Comparative Computational Study of Spike protein (182 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.082973+00:00</updated><author><name>Suresh Kumar</name></author><author><name>Thiviya S Thambiraja</name></author><author><name>Kalimuthu Karuppanan</name></author><author><name>Gunasekaran Subramaniam</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants, especially those of concern, may have an impact on the virus's transmissibility and pathogenicity, as well as diagnostic equipment performance and vaccine effectiveness. Even though the SARS-CoV-2 Delta variant (B.1.617.2) emerged during India's second wave of infections, Delta variants have grown dominant internationally and are still evolving. On November 26, 2021, WHO identified the variant B.1.1.529 as a variant of concern, naming it Omicron, based on evidence that Omicron contains numerous mutations that may influence its behaviour. However, the mode of transmission and severity of the Omicron variant remains unknown. We used computational studies to examine the Delta and Omicron variants in this work and found that the Omicron variant had a higher affinity for human ACE2 than the Delta variant due to a significant number of mutations in the SARS-CoV-2 receptor binding domain, indicating a higher potential for transmission. Based on docking studies, the Q493R, N501Y, S371L, S373P, S375F, Q498R, and T478K mutations contribute significantly to high binding affinity with human ACE2. In comparison to the Delta variant, both the entire spike protein and the RBD in Omicron include a high proportion of hydrophobic amino acids such as leucine and phenylalanine. These amino acids are located within the protein's core and are required for structural stability. Omicron has a higher percentage of alpha-helix structure than the Delta variant in both whole spike protein and RBD, indicating that it has a more stable structure. We observed a disorder-order transition in the Omicron variant between spike protein RBD regions 468-473, and it may be significant in the influence of disordered residues/regions on spike protein stability and binding to ACE2. A future study might investigate the epidemiological and biological consequences of the Omicron variant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470946" rel="alternate" title="Omicron and Delta Variant of SARS-CoV-2: A Comparative Computational Study of Spike protein (182 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470568</id><title>Broad human and animal coronavirus neutralisation by SARS-CoV-2 S2-targeted vaccination (95 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.084215+00:00</updated><author><name>Kevin W. Ng</name></author><author><name>Nikhil Faulkner</name></author><author><name>Katja Finsterbusch</name></author><author><name>Mary Wu</name></author><author><name>Ruth Harvey</name></author><author><name>Saira Hussain</name></author><author><name>Maria Greco</name></author><author><name>Yafei Liu</name></author><author><name>Svend Kjaer</name></author><author><name>Charles Swanton</name></author><author><name>Sonia Gandhi</name></author><author><name>Rupert Beale</name></author><author><name>Steve J. Gamblin</name></author><author><name>Peter Cherepanov</name></author><author><name>John McCauley</name></author><author><name>Rodney Daniels</name></author><author><name>Michael Howell</name></author><author><name>Hisashi Arase</name></author><author><name>Andeas Wack</name></author><author><name>David L.V. Bauer</name></author><author><name>George Kassiotis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Several common-cold coronaviruses (HCoVs) are endemic in humans and several variants of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) have emerged during the current Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic. Whilst antibody cross-reactivity with the Spike glycoproteins (S) of diverse coronaviruses has been documented, it remains unclear whether such antibody responses, typically targeting the conserved S2 subunit, contribute to or mediate protection, when induced naturally or through vaccination. Using a mouse model, we show that prior HCoV-OC43 S immunity primes neutralising antibody responses to otherwise subimmunogenic SARS-CoV-2 S exposure and promotes S2-targeting antibody responses. Moreover, mouse vaccination with SARS-CoV-2 S2 elicits antibodies that neutralise diverse animal and human alphacoronaviruses and betacoronaviruses &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, and protects against SARS-CoV-2 challenge &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Lastly, in mice with a history of SARS-CoV-2 Wuhan-based S vaccination, further S2 vaccination induces stronger and broader neutralising antibody response than booster Wuhan S vaccination, suggesting it may prevent repertoire focusing caused by repeated homologous vaccination. The data presented here establish the protective value of an S2-targeting vaccine and support the notion that S2 vaccination may better prepare the immune system to respond to the changing nature of the S1 subunit in SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (VOCs), as well as to unpredictable, yet inevitable future coronavirus zoonoses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470568" rel="alternate" title="Broad human and animal coronavirus neutralisation by SARS-CoV-2 S2-targeted vaccination (95 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.21266756</id><title>Association of subcutaneous or intravenous route of administration of casirivimab and imdevimab monoclonal antibodies with clinical outcomes in COVID-19 (90 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.084805+00:00</updated><author><name>Erin K. McCreary</name></author><author><name>J. Ryan Bariola</name></author><author><name>Richard J. Wadas</name></author><author><name>Judith A. Shovel</name></author><author><name>Mary Kay Wisniewski</name></author><author><name>Michelle Adam</name></author><author><name>Debbie Albin</name></author><author><name>Tami Minnier</name></author><author><name>Mark Schmidhofer</name></author><author><name>Russell Meyers</name></author><author><name>Oscar C. Marroquin</name></author><author><name>Kevin Collins</name></author><author><name>William Garrard</name></author><author><name>Lindsay R. Berry</name></author><author><name>Scott Berry</name></author><author><name>Amy M. Crawford</name></author><author><name>Anna McGlothlin</name></author><author><name>Kelsey Linstrum</name></author><author><name>Anna Nakayama</name></author><author><name>Stephanie K. Montgomery</name></author><author><name>Graham M. Snyder</name></author><author><name>Donald M. Yealy</name></author><author><name>Derek C. Angus</name></author><author><name>Paula L. Kip</name></author><author><name>Christopher W. Seymour</name></author><author><name>David T. Huang</name></author><author><name>Kevin E. Kip</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Monoclonal antibody (mAb) treatment decreases hospitalization and death in outpatients with mild to moderate COVID-19; however, only intravenous administration has been evaluated in randomized clinical trials of treatment. Subcutaneous administration may expand outpatient treatment capacity and qualified staff available to administer treatment, but association with patient outcomes is understudied.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To evaluate whether or not, i.) subcutaneous casirivimab and imdevimab treatment is associated with reduced 28-day hospitalization/death than non-treatment among mAb-eligible patients, and ii.) subcutaneous casirivimab and imdevimab treatment is clinically and statistically similar to intravenous casirivimab and imdevimab treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design, Setting, and Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prospective cohort study of outpatients in a learning health system in the United States with mild to moderate COVID-19 symptoms from July 14 to October 26, 2021 who were eligible for mAb treatment under emergency use authorization. A nontreated control group of eligible patients was also selected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Intervention&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Subcutaneous injection or intravenous administration of the combined single dose of casirivimab 600mg and imdevimab 600mg.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Outcomes and Measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The primary outcome was the 28-day adjusted risk ratio or adjusted risk difference for hospitalization or death. Secondary outcomes included 28-day adjusted risk ratios/differences of hospitalization, death, composite endpoint of ED admission and hospitalization, and rates of adverse events.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among 1,956 matched adults with mild to moderate COVID-19, patients who received casirivimab and imdevimab subcutaneously had a 28-day rate of hospitalization/death of 3.4% (n=652) compared to 7.8% (n=1,304) in nontreated controls [risk ratio 0.44 (95% confidence interval: 0.28 to 0.68, p &amp;lt; .001)]. Among 2,185 patients treated with subcutaneous (n=969) or intravenous (n=1,216) casirivimab and imdevimab, the 28-day rate of hospitalization/death was 2.8% vs. 1.7%, respectively which resulted in an adjusted risk difference of 1.5% (95% confidence interval: -0.5% to 3.5%, p=.14). The 28-day adjusted risk differences (subcutaneous – intravenous) for death, ICU admission, and mechanical ventilation were 0.3% or less, although the 95% confidence intervals were wide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions and Relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Subcutaneously administered casirivimab-imdevimab is associated with reduced risk-adjusted hospitalization or death amongst outpatients with mild to moderate COVID-19 compared to no treatment and indicates low adjusted risk difference compared to patients treated intravenously.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key Points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Question&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among outpatients with mild to moderate COVID-19, is subcutaneously administered casirivimab and imdevimab associated with improved risk-adjusted 28-day clinical outcomes compared to non-treatment with monoclonal antibodies, and clinically similar association compared to intravenously administered casirivimab and imdevimab?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among 1,956 propensity-matched adults, outpatients who received casirivimab and imdevimab subcutaneously had a 28-day rate of hospitalization or death of 3.4% (n=652) compared to 7.8% (n=1,304) in non-treated controls [risk ratio 0.44 (95% confidence interval: 0.28 to 0.68, p &amp;lt; .001)]. Among 2,185 outpatients who received subcutaneous (n=969) or intravenous (n=1,216) casirivimab and imdevimab, the 28-day rate of hospitalization/death was 2.8% vs. 1.7%, respectively, which resulted in an adjusted risk difference of 1.5% (95% confidence interval: -0.5% to 3.5%, p=.14). The 28-day adjusted risk differences comparing subcutaneous to intravenous route for death, ICU admission, and mechanical ventilation were 0.3% or less, although the 95% confidence intervals were wide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Meaning&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Subcutaneously administered casirivimab and imdevimab is associated with reduced hospitalization or death amongst outpatients with mild to moderate COVID-19 compared to no treatment, and has a small, adjusted risk difference compared to patients treated intravenously.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.21266756" rel="alternate" title="Association of subcutaneous or intravenous route of administration of casirivimab and imdevimab monoclonal antibodies with clinical outcomes in COVID-19 (90 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.21267146</id><title>Internal Tremors and Vibration Symptoms Among People with Post-Acute Sequelae of SARS-CoV-2: A narrative review of patient reports (73 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.085648+00:00</updated><author><name>Daisy Massey</name></author><author><name>Anna D Baker</name></author><author><name>Diana Zicklin Berrent</name></author><author><name>Nick Güthe</name></author><author><name>Suzanne Pincus Shidlovsky</name></author><author><name>Liza Fisher</name></author><author><name>Connor B Grady</name></author><author><name>César Caraballo</name></author><author><name>Richa Sharma</name></author><author><name>Harlan M Krumholz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To introduce the perspective of patients who have PASC with vibrations and tremors as a prominent component, we leveraged the efforts by &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.survivorcorps.com/"&gt;Survivor Corps&lt;/ext-link&gt;, a grassroots COVID-19 patient advocacy group, to gather information from people in their Facebook group suffering from vibrations and tremors. Survivor Corps collected 140 emails and 450 Facebook comments from members. From the emails, we identified 22 themes and 7 broader domains based on common coding techniques for qualitative data and the constant comparative method of qualitative data analysis. Facebook comments were analyzed using Word Clouds to visualize frequency of terms. The respondents’ emails reflected 7 domains that formed the basis of characterizing their experience with vibrations and tremors. These domains were: (1) symptom experience, description, and anatomic location; (2) initial symptom onset; (3) symptom timing; (4) symptom triggers or alleviators; (5) change from baseline health status; (6) experience with medical establishment; and (7) impact on people’s lives and livelihood. There were 22 themes total, each corresponding to one of the broader domains. The Facebook comments Word Cloud revealed that the 10 most common words used in comments were: tremors (64), covid (55), pain (51), vibrations (43), months (36), burning (29), feet (24), hands (22), legs (21), back (20). Overall, these patient narratives described intense suffering, and there is still no diagnosis or treatment available.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.21267146" rel="alternate" title="Internal Tremors and Vibration Symptoms Among People with Post-Acute Sequelae of SARS-CoV-2: A narrative review of patient reports (73 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.21266716</id><title>Third COVID-19 Vaccine Dose Boosts Neutralising Antibodies in Poor Responders (69 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.086020+00:00</updated><author><name>Douglas F. Lake</name></author><author><name>Alexa J. Roeder</name></author><author><name>Maria J. Gonzalez-Moa</name></author><author><name>Megan Koehler</name></author><author><name>Erin Kaleta</name></author><author><name>Paniz Jasbi</name></author><author><name>John Vanderhoof</name></author><author><name>Davis McKechnie</name></author><author><name>Jack Forman</name></author><author><name>Baylee Edwards</name></author><author><name>Alim Seit-Nebi</name></author><author><name>Sergei Svarovsky</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To determine if poor responders to COVID-19 RNA vaccines (&amp;lt;50% neutralisation) after two doses would remain poor responders, or if a third dose could elicit high levels of NAbs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clinical follow-up study&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Academic and medical institutions in USA&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;269 healthy individuals ranging in age from 19 to 80 (Average age = 51; 165 females and 104 males) who received either BNT162b2 (Pfizer) or mRNA1273 (Moderna) vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Outcome Measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;NAb levels were measured: i) 2-4 weeks after a second vaccine dose, ii) 2-4 months after the second dose, iii) within 1-2 weeks prior to a third dose and iv) 2-4 weeks after a third RNA vaccine dose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 269 study participants, percent neutralisation ranged from 0% to 99% 2-4 weeks after a second vaccine dose. The majority of vaccine recipients (154/269, 57%) demonstrated NAb levels at ≥75% 2-4 weeks after their second dose. Our study also revealed that 25% of vaccine recipients did not neutralise above 50% (Median neutralisation = 21%, titers &amp;lt;1:80) within a month after their second dose. We called these individuals “vaccine poor responders” (VPRs). Twenty-three VPRs ranging in age from 31 to 79 (10 males, 13 females, average age = 62.5) independently obtained a third dose of either BNT162b2 or mRNA-1273 vaccine 1-8 months (average = 5 months) after their second dose. Within a month after their third dose, poor responders showed an average 20-fold increase in NAb levels (range 46%-99%).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The results suggest that poor responders are not permanently poor responders; they can generate high NAb levels with an additional vaccine dose–independent of mRNA vaccine manufacturer. Previous reports indicate that NAb levels decline much more rapidly than clinical protection from hospitalisation and disease, but that does not account for vaccine recipients who never generated high levels of NAbs after two doses. It is possible that poor responders are a source of breakthrough infections. Although it is not known what levels of NAbs protect from infection or disease, many vaccine recipients in high-risk professions may wish to keep peripheral NAb levels high, limiting infection, asymptomatic viral replication, and potential transmission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.21266716" rel="alternate" title="Third COVID-19 Vaccine Dose Boosts Neutralising Antibodies in Poor Responders (69 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470356</id><title>A human monoclonal antibody potently pan-neutralizes SARS-CoV-2 VOCs by targeting RBD invariant sites (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.088156+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaofei Wang</name></author><author><name>Ao Hu</name></author><author><name>Xiangyu Chen</name></author><author><name>Yixin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Fei Yu</name></author><author><name>Shuai Yue</name></author><author><name>Arong Li</name></author><author><name>Junsong Zhang</name></author><author><name>Zhiwei Pan</name></author><author><name>Yang Yang</name></author><author><name>Yao Lin</name></author><author><name>Leiqiong Gao</name></author><author><name>Jing Zhou</name></author><author><name>Jing Zhao</name></author><author><name>Fang Li</name></author><author><name>Yaling Shi</name></author><author><name>Feng Huang</name></author><author><name>Xiaofan Yang</name></author><author><name>Yi Peng</name></author><author><name>Luoyang Tu</name></author><author><name>Huan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Huanying Zheng</name></author><author><name>Jun He</name></author><author><name>Hui Zhang</name></author><author><name>Lifan Xu</name></author><author><name>Qizhao Huang</name></author><author><name>Yongqun Zhu</name></author><author><name>Kai Deng</name></author><author><name>Lilin Ye</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) has caused a global pandemic of novel corona virus disease (COVID-19). The neutralizing monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) targeting the receptor binding domain (RBD) of SARS-CoV-2 are among the most promising strategies to prevent and treat COVID-19. However, SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (VOCs) profoundly reduced the efficacies of most of mAbs and vaccines approved for clinical use. Herein, we demonstrated mAb 35B5 efficiently neutralizes both wild-type (WT) SARS-CoV-2 and VOCs, including B.1.617.2 (delta) variant, &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Cryo-electron microscopy (cryo-EM) revealed that 35B5 neutralizes SARS-CoV-2 by targeting a unique epitope that avoids the prevailing mutation sites on RBD identified in circulating VOCs, providing the molecular basis for its pan-neutralizing efficacy. The 35B5-binding epitope could also be exploited for the rational design of a universal SARS-CoV-2 vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470356" rel="alternate" title="A human monoclonal antibody potently pan-neutralizes SARS-CoV-2 VOCs by targeting RBD invariant sites (37 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470978</id><title>Secreted ORF8 is a pathogenic cause of severe Covid-19 and potentially targetable with select NLRP3 inhibitors (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.088745+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaosheng Wu</name></author><author><name>Michelle K Manske</name></author><author><name>Gordon Ruan</name></author><author><name>Kevin E Nowakowski</name></author><author><name>Jithma P Abeykoon</name></author><author><name>Xinyi Tang</name></author><author><name>Yue Yu</name></author><author><name>Taylor L Witter</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Taupin</name></author><author><name>Jonas Paludo</name></author><author><name>Stephen M Ansell</name></author><author><name>Andrew D Badley</name></author><author><name>Matthew Schellenberg</name></author><author><name>Thomas E Witzig</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite extensive research, the specific factor associated with SARS-CoV-2 infection that mediates the life-threatening inflammatory cytokine response in patients with severe Covid-19 remains unidentified. Herein we demonstrate that the virus-encoded Open Reading Frame 8 (ORF8) protein is abundantly secreted as a glycoprotein in vitro and in patients with newly diagnosed Covid-19. ORF8 specifically binds to the NOD-like receptor family pyrin domain-containing 3 (NLRP3) in CD14+/CD16+ monocytes to induce an inflammasomal cytokine response. The levels of ORF8 protein in the blood correlate with disease mortality in patients with acute infection, and the disease trajectory in patients with severe Covid-19. Furthermore, in vitro the ORF8-induced inflammasome response can be readily inhibited by the select NLRP3 inhibitor MCC950. Our results identify the pathogenic cause and mechanism of severe disease, and a potential new treatment of severe Covid-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470978" rel="alternate" title="Secreted ORF8 is a pathogenic cause of severe Covid-19 and potentially targetable with select NLRP3 inhibitors (15 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.21267155</id><title>High viral loads: what drives fatal cases of COVID-19 in vaccinees? an autopsy study (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.091317+00:00</updated><author><name>Klaus Hirschbuehl</name></author><author><name>Tina Schaller</name></author><author><name>Bruno Maerkl</name></author><author><name>Rainer Claus</name></author><author><name>Eva Sipos</name></author><author><name>Lukas Rentschler</name></author><author><name>Andrea Maccagno</name></author><author><name>Bianca Grosser</name></author><author><name>Elisabeth Kling</name></author><author><name>Michael Neidig</name></author><author><name>Thomas Kroencke</name></author><author><name>Oliver Spring</name></author><author><name>Georg Braun</name></author><author><name>Hans Boesmueller</name></author><author><name>Maximilian Seidl</name></author><author><name>Irene Esposito</name></author><author><name>Jessica Pablik</name></author><author><name>Julia Hilsenbeck</name></author><author><name>Peter Boor</name></author><author><name>Martin Beer</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Dintner</name></author><author><name>Claudia Wylezich</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: The rate of SARS-CoV-2 breakthrough infections in vaccinees is becoming an increasingly serious issue. 
Objective: To determine the causes of death, histological organ alteration, and viral spread in relation to demographic, clinical-pathological, viral variants, and vaccine types. 
Design: Comprehensive retrospective observational cohort study.
Setting: Consecutive cases from four German academic medical centers.
Patients: Deceased with proven SARS-CoV-2 infection after vaccination who died between January and November 2021. Collections of 29 vaccinees which were analyzed and compared to 141 nonvaccinated control cases.
Results: Autopsies were performed on 16 partially and 13 fully vaccinated individuals. Most patients were elderly and suffered from several relevant comorbidities. Real-time RT-PCR (RT-qPCR) identified a significantly increased rate of generalized viral dissemination within the organism in vaccinated cases versus nonvaccinated cases (45% vs. 16%, respectively; P = 0.008). Vaccinated cases also showed high viral loads, reaching Ct values below 10, especially in the upper airways and lungs. This was accompanied by high rates of pulmonal bacterial or mycotic superinfections and the occurrence of immunocompromising factors such as malignancies, immunosuppressive drug intake, or decreased immunoglobulin levels. All these findings were particularly accentuated in partially vaccinated patients compared to fully vaccinated individuals. A fatal course after vaccination occurred in only 14% of all COVID-19 deceased in Augsburg.
Limitations: Restricted number of cases
Conclusions: Fatal cases of COVID-19 in vaccinees were rare and often associated with severe comorbidities or other immunosuppressive conditions. Interestingly, we observed striking virus dissemination in our case study, which may indicate a decreased ability to eliminate the virus in patients with an impaired immune system. However, the potential role of antibody-dependent enhancement must also be ruled out in future studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.21267155" rel="alternate" title="High viral loads: what drives fatal cases of COVID-19 in vaccinees? an autopsy study (13 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.21267198</id><title>Ad26.COV2.S or BNT162b2 Boosting of BNT162b2 Vaccinated Individuals (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.091812+00:00</updated><author><name>C. Sabrina Tan</name></author><author><name>Ai-ris Collier</name></author><author><name>Jinyan Liu</name></author><author><name>Jingyou Yu</name></author><author><name>Huahua Wan</name></author><author><name>Katherine McMahan</name></author><author><name>Xuan He</name></author><author><name>Catherine Jacob-Dolan</name></author><author><name>Abishek Chandrashekar</name></author><author><name>Daniel Sellers</name></author><author><name>Kathryn Stephenson</name></author><author><name>Samuel Vidal</name></author><author><name>Kate Jaegle</name></author><author><name>Jessica Curran</name></author><author><name>Marjorie Rowe</name></author><author><name>Rachel Hemod</name></author><author><name>Lorriane Bermudez Rivera</name></author><author><name>Tochi Anioke</name></author><author><name>Julia Barrett</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Chung</name></author><author><name>Sarah Gardner</name></author><author><name>Makda Gebre</name></author><author><name>Michelle Lifton</name></author><author><name>Olivia Powers</name></author><author><name>Haley VanWyk</name></author><author><name>Cindy Wu</name></author><author><name>Dan Barouch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Previous studies have reported that a third dose of the BNT162b2 (Pfizer) COVID-19 vaccine increased antibody titers and protective efficacy.  Here we compare humoral and cellular immune responses in 65 individuals who were vaccinated with the BNT162b2 vaccine and were boosted after at least 6 months with either Ad26.COV2.S (Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson; N=41) or BNT162b2 (Pfizer; N=24).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.21267198" rel="alternate" title="Ad26.COV2.S or BNT162b2 Boosting of BNT162b2 Vaccinated Individuals (12 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470470</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 variants impact RBD conformational dynamics and ACE2 accessibility (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.092552+00:00</updated><author><name>Mariana Valério</name></author><author><name>Luís Borges-Araújo</name></author><author><name>Manuel N. Melo</name></author><author><name>Diana Lousa</name></author><author><name>Cláudio M. Soares</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic, caused by the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), has killed over 5 million people and is causing a devastating social and economic impact all over the world. The rise of new variants of concern (VOCs) represents a difficult challenge due to the loss vaccine and natural immunity, and increased transmissibility. All circulating VOCs contain mutations in the spike glycoprotein, which mediates fusion between the viral and host cell membranes, via its receptor binding domain (RBD) that binds to angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2). In an attempt to understand the effect of RBD mutations in circulating VOCs, a lot of attention has been given to the RBD-ACE2 interaction. However, this type of analysis is limited, since it ignores more indirect effects, such as the conformational dynamics of the RBD itself. Observing that some VOCs mutations occur in residues that are not in direct contact with ACE2, we hypothesized that they could affect RBD conformational dynamics. To test this, we performed long atomistic (AA) molecular dynamics (MD) simulations to investigate the structural dynamics of &lt;italic&gt;wt&lt;/italic&gt; RBD, and that of three circulating VOCs (alpha, beta, and delta). Our results show that in solution, wt RBD presents two distinct conformations: an “open” conformation where it is free to bind ACE2; and a “closed” conformation, where the RBM ridge blocks the binding surface. The alpha and beta variants significantly impact the open/closed equilibrium, shifting it towards the open conformation by roughly 20%. This shift likely increases ACE2 binding affinity. Simulations of the currently predominant delta variant RBD were extreme in this regard, in that a closed conformation was never observed. Instead, the system alternated between the before mentioned open conformation and an alternative “reversed” one, with a significantly changed orientation of the RBM ridge flanking the RBD. This alternate conformation could potentially provide a fitness advantage not only due to increased availability for ACE2 binding, but also by aiding antibody escape through epitope occlusion. These results support the hypothesis that VOCs, and particularly the delta variant, impact RBD conformational dynamics in a direction that simultaneously promotes efficient binding to ACE2 and antibody escape.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470470" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 variants impact RBD conformational dynamics and ACE2 accessibility (11 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.21266853</id><title>Digital exclusion predicts worse mental health among adolescents during COVID-19 (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.092875+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas E. Metherell</name></author><author><name>Sakshi Ghai</name></author><author><name>Ethan M. McCormick</name></author><author><name>Tamsin J. Ford</name></author><author><name>Amy Orben</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Social isolation is strongly associated with poor mental health. The COVID-19 pandemic and ensuing social restrictions disrupted young people’s social interactions and resulted in several periods during which school closures necessitated online learning. We hypothesise that digitally excluded young people would demonstrate greater deterioration in their mental health than their digitally connected peers during this time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We analysed representative mental health data from a sample of UK 10–15-year-olds (&lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt; = 1387); Understanding Society collected the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire in 2017-19 and thrice during the pandemic (July 2020, November 2020 and March 2021). We employed cross-sectional methods and longitudinal latent growth curve modelling to describe trajectories of adolescent mental health for participants with and without access to a computer or a good internet connection for schoolwork.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Outcomes&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adolescent mental health had a quadratic trajectory during the COVID-19 pandemic, with the highest mean Total Difficulties score around December 2020. The worsening and recovery of mental health during the pandemic was greatly pronounced among those without access to a computer, although we did not find evidence for a similar effect among those without a good internet connection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Digital exclusion, as indicated by lack of access to a computer, is a tractable risk factor that likely compounds other adversities facing children and young people during periods of social isolation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;British Psychological Society; School of the Biological Sciences, University of Cambridge; NIHR Applied Research Centre; Medical Research Council; Economic and Social Research Council; and Emmanuel College, University of Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.21266853" rel="alternate" title="Digital exclusion predicts worse mental health among adolescents during COVID-19 (9 tweets)"/><category term="Psychiatry and Clinical Psychology"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470748</id><title>Investigating the mutational landscape of the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant via ab initio quantum mechanical modeling (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.093653+00:00</updated><author><name>Luigi Genovese</name></author><author><name>Marco Zaccaria</name></author><author><name>Michael Farzan</name></author><author><name>Welkin E Johnson</name></author><author><name>Babak Momeni</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 variant "Omicron" B1.1.529 was first identified in South Africa in November 2021. Given the large number of mutations in Omicron's spike protein compared to the original Wuhan strain, its binding efficacy to the ACE2 receptor and its potential to escape antibodies are in the spotlight. Recently, we presented an ab initio quantum mechanical model to characterize the interactions of spike protein's Receptor Binding Domain (RBD) with select antibodies and ACE2 variants. The model identified weak links among the residues constituting interactions with the human ACE2 receptor (hACE2), and also enabled us to characterize in silico mutated RBDs to identify potential Variants of Concern (VOC). In particular, we focused on the role of RBD residue 484 in the interaction of the Delta variant with ACE2 and neutralizing antibodies (nAbs). In this report, we apply our model to the Omicron VOC, and characterize its interaction pattern with hACE2. Our results show that (i) binding affinity with hACE2, compared to Delta, is considerably increased, possibly contributing to increased infectivity. (ii) The interaction pattern between B1.1.529 and hACE2 differs from previous variants by shifting the hot-spot interaction residues on hACE2, and potentially affecting nAbs efficacy. (iii) A K mutation in the RBD residue 484 can further improve Omicron's binding of hACE2 and evasion of nAbs. Finally, we argue that a library of hot-spots for point-mutations can predict binding interaction energies of complex variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470748" rel="alternate" title="Investigating the mutational landscape of the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant via ab initio quantum mechanical modeling (8 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470767</id><title>A public antibody class recognizes a novel S2 epitope exposed on open conformations of SARS-CoV-2 spike (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.094365+00:00</updated><author><name>Mathieu Claireaux</name></author><author><name>Tom G Caniels</name></author><author><name>Marlon de Gast</name></author><author><name>Julianna Han</name></author><author><name>Denise Guerra</name></author><author><name>Gius Kerster</name></author><author><name>Barbera DC van Schaik</name></author><author><name>Aldo Jongejan</name></author><author><name>Angela I Schriek</name></author><author><name>Marloes Grobben</name></author><author><name>Philip JM Brouwer</name></author><author><name>Karlijn van der Straten</name></author><author><name>Yoann Aldon</name></author><author><name>Joan Capella-Pujol</name></author><author><name>Jonne L Snitselaar</name></author><author><name>Wouter Olijhoek</name></author><author><name>Aafke Aartse</name></author><author><name>Mitch Brinkkemper</name></author><author><name>Ilja Bontjer</name></author><author><name>Judith A Burger</name></author><author><name>Meliawati Poniman</name></author><author><name>Tom PL Bijl</name></author><author><name>Jonathan L Torres</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey Copps</name></author><author><name>Isabel Cuella Martin</name></author><author><name>Steven W de Taeye</name></author><author><name>Godelieve J de Bree</name></author><author><name>Andrew B Ward</name></author><author><name>Kwinten Sliepen</name></author><author><name>Antoine HC van Kampen</name></author><author><name>Perry D Moerland</name></author><author><name>Rogier W Sanders</name></author><author><name>Marit J van Gils</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Delineating the origins and properties of antibodies elicited by SARS-CoV-2 infection and vaccination is critical for understanding their benefits and potential shortcomings. Therefore, we investigated the SARS-CoV-2 spike (S)-reactive B cell repertoire in unexposed individuals by flow cytometry and single-cell sequencing. We found that ~82% of SARS-CoV-2 S-reactive B cells show a naive phenotype, which represents an unusually high fraction of total human naive B cells (~0.1%). Approximately 10% of these naive S-reactive B cells shared an IGHV1-69/IGKV3-11 B cell receptor pairing, an enrichment of 18-fold compared to the complete naive repertoire. A proportion of memory B cells, comprising switched (~0.05%) and unswitched B cells (~0.04%), was also reactive with S and some of these cells were reactive with ADAMTS13, which is associated with thrombotic thrombocytopenia. Following SARS-CoV-2 infection, we report an average 37-fold enrichment of IGHV1-69/IGKV3-11 B cell receptor pairing in the S-reactive memory B cells compared to the unselected memory repertoire. This class of B cells targets a previously undefined non-neutralizing epitope on the S2 subunit that becomes exposed on S proteins used in approved vaccines when they transition away from the native pre-fusion state because of instability. These findings can help guide the improvement of SARS-CoV-2 vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470767" rel="alternate" title="A public antibody class recognizes a novel S2 epitope exposed on open conformations of SARS-CoV-2 spike (8 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470414</id><title>Th1, Th2 and Th17 inflammatory pathways synergistically correlate with cardiometabolic processes. A case study in COVID-19. (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.095050+00:00</updated><author><name>James R Michels</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Shaheed Nazrul</name></author><author><name>Sudeep Adhikari</name></author><author><name>Dawn Wilkins</name></author><author><name>Ana B Pavel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A predominant source of complication in SARS-CoV-2 patients arises from the cytokine storm, an elevated expression of inflammatory helper T-cell associated cytokines that can lead to tissue damage and organ failure. The high inflammatory burden of this viral infection often results in cardiovascular comorbidities. A better understanding of the interaction between the cytokine storm and cardiovascular proteins might inform medical decisions and therapeutic approaches. We hypothesized that all major helper T-cell inflammatory pathways (Th1, Th2 and Th17) synergistically contribute to cardiometabolic modifications in serum of COVID-19 patients. We proved our hypothesis by integrating Th1, Th2 and Th17 cytokines to predict expression of cardiometabolic proteins profiled by OLINK proteomics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470414" rel="alternate" title="Th1, Th2 and Th17 inflammatory pathways synergistically correlate with cardiometabolic processes. A case study in COVID-19. (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470293</id><title>Protective immunity of the primary SARS-CoV-2 infection reduces disease severity post re-infection with Delta variants in Syrian hamsters (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.095389+00:00</updated><author><name>Sreelekshmy Mohandas</name></author><author><name>Pragya D. Yadav</name></author><author><name>Anita Shete</name></author><author><name>Dimpal Nyayanit</name></author><author><name>Rajlaxmi Jain</name></author><author><name>Gajanan Sapkal</name></author><author><name>Chandrasekhar Mote</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Delta variant has evolved to become dominant SARS-CoV-2 lineage worldwide and there are reports of secondary infections with varying severity in vaccinated and unvaccinated naturally recovered COVID-19 patients. As the protective immunity following the infection wanes within few months, studies of re-infection after prolonged duration is needed. Hence we assessed the potential of re-infection by Delta, Delta AY.1 and B.1 in COVID-19 recovered hamsters after 3 months of infection. Re-infection with Delta and B.1 variants in hamsters showed reduced viral shedding, lung pathology and lung viral load, whereas the upper respiratory tract viral load remained similar to that of first infection. The reduction in viral load and lung pathology after re-infection with Delta AY.1 variant was not marked. Further we assessed the disease characteristics of Delta AY.1 to understand whether it has any replication advantage over Delta variant and B.1 variant, an early isolate in Syrian hamsters. Body weight changes, viral load in respiratory organs, lung pathology, cytokine response and neutralizing antibody response were assessed. Delta AY.1 variant produced milder disease in comparison to Delta variant and the neutralizing response was similar against Delta, B.1 and B.1.351 variant in contrast to Delta or B.1 infected hamsters which showed a significant reduction in neutralization titres against B.1.351. Elevation of IL-6 levels was observed post infection in hamsters after primary infection. The prior infection could not produce sterilizing immunity but the protective effect was evident following reinfection. This indicates the importance of the transmission prevention efforts even after achieving herd immunity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Research in context&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Evidence before this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secondary infections with Delta variant are being widely reported and there are reports of increased disease severity. Delta sub lineages with K417N substitution has caused concern worldwide due to the presence of the same substitution in Beta variant, a Variant of Concern known for its immune evasion. The information on the biological characteristics of this sub lineage is also scanty.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Added value of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The present study showed that the secondary infection with Delta variant does not show any evidence of increased disease severity in hamster model. Delta AY. 1 variant produces mild disease in Syrian hamsters in contrast to severe disease caused by Delta variant. Delta, B.1 and AY.1 variant infected hamster sera showed comparable cross neutralizing response against each other. In contrast to the lower neutralizing response shown by B.1 and Delta variant infected animals against B.1.351 variant, Delta AY.1 showed comparable response as that with other variants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Implications of the available evidence&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 infections do not produce sterilizing immunity but protect from developing severe disease in case of Delta variant re-infection indicating the importance of the transmission prevention efforts even after achieving herd immunity. Delta AY. 1 infection in hamsters did not show any evidence of speculated immune evasion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470293" rel="alternate" title="Protective immunity of the primary SARS-CoV-2 infection reduces disease severity post re-infection with Delta variants in Syrian hamsters (7 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470349</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 Virus like Particles produced by a single recombinant baculovirus generate potent neutralizing antibody that protects against variant challenge (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.095699+00:00</updated><author><name>Edward Sullivan</name></author><author><name>Po-Yu Sung</name></author><author><name>Weining Wu</name></author><author><name>Neil Berry</name></author><author><name>Sarah Kempster</name></author><author><name>Deborah Ferguson</name></author><author><name>Neil Almond</name></author><author><name>Ian M. Jones</name></author><author><name>Polly Roy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Covid-19 pandemic caused by SARS-CoV-2 infection has highlighted the need for the rapid generation of efficient vaccines for emerging disease. Virus-like particles, VLPs, are an established vaccine technology that produces virus-like mimics, based on expression of the structural proteins of a target virus that can stimulate strong neutralizing antibody responses. SARS-CoV-2 is a coronavirus where the basis of VLP formation has been shown to be the co-expression of the spike, membrane and envelope structural proteins. Here we describe the generation of SARS-CoV-2 VLPs by the co-expression of the salient structural proteins in insect cells using the established baculovirus expression system. VLPs were heterologous ∼100nm diameter enveloped particles with a distinct fringe that reacted strongly with SARS-CoV-2 convalescent sera. In a Syrian hamster challenge model, a non-adjuvanted VLPs induced neutralizing antibodies to the VLP-associated Wuhan S protein, reduced virus shedding following a virulent challenge with SARS-CoV-2 (B.1.1.7 variant) and protected against disease associated weight loss. Immunized animals showed reduced lung pathology and lower challenge virus replication than the non-immunized controls. Our data, using an established and scalable technology, suggest SARS-CoV-2 VLPs offer an efficient vaccine that mitigates against virus load and prevents severe disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470349" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 Virus like Particles produced by a single recombinant baculovirus generate potent neutralizing antibody that protects against variant challenge (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470642</id><title>Variance in Variants: Propagating Genome Sequence Uncertainty into Phylogenetic Lineage Assignment (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.096115+00:00</updated><author><name>David Champredon</name></author><author><name>Devan Becker</name></author><author><name>Connor Chato</name></author><author><name>Gopi Gugan</name></author><author><name>Art Poon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genetic sequencing is subject to many different types of errors, but most analyses treat the resultant sequences as if they are known without error. Next generation sequencing methods rely on significantly larger numbers of reads than previous sequencing methods in exchange for a loss of accuracy in each individual read. Still, the coverage of such machines is imperfect and leaves uncertainty in many of the base calls. On top of this machine-level uncertainty, there is uncertainty induced by human error, such as errors in data entry or incorrect parameter settings. In this work, we demonstrate that the uncertainty in sequencing techniques will affect downstream analysis and propose a straightforward method to propagate the uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our method uses a probabilistic matrix representation of individual sequences which incorporates base quality scores as a measure of uncertainty that naturally lead to resampling and replication as a framework for uncertainty propagation. With the matrix representation, resampling possible base calls according to quality scores provides a bootstrap- or prior distribution-like first step towards genetic analysis. Analyses based on these re-sampled sequences will include a more complete evaluation of the error involved in such analyses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We demonstrate our resampling method on SARS-CoV-2 data. The resampling procedures adds a linear computational cost to the analyses, but the large impact on the variance in downstream estimates makes it clear that ignoring this uncertainty may lead to overly confident conclusions. We show that SARS-CoV-2 lineage designations via Pangolin are much less certain than the bootstrap support reported by Pangolin would imply and the clock rate estimates for SARS-CoV-2 are much more variable than reported.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470642" rel="alternate" title="Variance in Variants: Propagating Genome Sequence Uncertainty into Phylogenetic Lineage Assignment (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470353</id><title>Possible Interference in Protein – Protein interaction as a new approach in microinhibition of respiratory pathogens on nasal– oral epithelium: An early on-screen study with reference toSARS-Cov-2–ACE2 binding interference (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.096369+00:00</updated><author><name>Debatosh Datta</name></author><author><name>Suyash Pant</name></author><author><name>Devendra Kumar Dhaked</name></author><author><name>Somasundaram Arumugam</name></author><author><name>Ravichandiran Velayutham</name></author><author><name>Pallab Datta</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Upper and lower respiratory pathogens, both microbes and viruses, are responsible for very high morbidity, man, hour loss, residual long term clinical conditions and even mortality. In india only, high incidence of annual respiratory infections, both UT and LT, demands prophylactic intervention in addition to all therapeutic interventions available. The issue of respiratory infections is more pronounced now in the backdrop of nearly uncontrolled high incidences of SARS,Cov,2 affection resulting in death and damage of human lives to the extent of hundreds of millions spreading over entire world , with incidence variations from country to country. After the initial unanswered phase of spread of SARS,Cov,2 virus with attendant unseen mortalities, quickest invention of a series of unusual vaccines have stemmed the lethal progress to a very significant extent, although vaccinating each and every human subject, nearly 8 to 9 bn in supremely divided world, economically,, is an unthinkable proposition where economic disparity dictates vaccine availability and implementation. Moreover being of highly unstable nucleic acid composition, the original virus, by now has a thick set of variants around the globe with variable clinical outcome. Given this complex background of scanty availability and inefficient implementation, there always is a need of a preventive approach which can possibly micro, fix the pathogens, including SARS,2 on nasal epithelium so as to interfere with viral [or any pathogen] entry through specified receptor gate[s] or any other ways. The present formulation is under study,, as a candidate of interference on nasal / oral mucosa for all respiratory pathogens. This brief report describes dry on,screen studies of protein , protein interaction as well as its possible interference by an amino acid Lysine. Phospholipid bilayer responses in presence of added loads of the same essential amino acid, Lysine, showed unusual and unexplained behavior both in structural integrity as well in spatial orientation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470353" rel="alternate" title="Possible Interference in Protein – Protein interaction as a new approach in microinhibition of respiratory pathogens on nasal– oral epithelium: An early on-screen study with reference toSARS-Cov-2–ACE2 binding interference (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470917</id><title>PEPPI: Whole-proteome protein-protein interaction prediction through structure and sequence similarity, functional association, and machine learning (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.096623+00:00</updated><author><name>Eric W Bell</name></author><author><name>Jacob H Schwartz</name></author><author><name>Peter L. Freddolino</name></author><author><name>Yang Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Proteome-wide identification of protein-protein interactions is a formidable task which has yet to be sufficiently addressed by experimental methodologies. Many computational methods have been developed to predict proteome-wide interaction networks, but few leverage both the sensitivity of structural information and the wide availability of sequence data. We present PEPPI, a pipeline which integrates structural similarity, sequence similarity, functional association data, and machine learning-based classification through a naive Bayesian classifier model to accurately predict protein-protein interactions at a proteomic scale. Through benchmarking against a set of 798 ground truth interactions and an equal number of non-interactions, we have found that PEPPI attains 4.5% higher AUROC than the best of other state-of-the-art methods. As a proteomic-scale application, PEPPI was applied to model the interactions which occur between SARS-CoV-2 and human host cells during coronavirus infection, where 403 high-confidence interactions were identified with predictions covering 73% of a gold standard dataset from PSICQUIC and demonstrating significant complementarity with the most recent high-throughput experiments. PEPPI is available both as a webserver and in a standalone version and should be a powerful and generally applicable tool for computational screening of protein-protein interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470917" rel="alternate" title="PEPPI: Whole-proteome protein-protein interaction prediction through structure and sequence similarity, functional association, and machine learning (3 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>