<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.824051+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455984</id><title>Durability of SARS-CoV-2-specific T cell responses at 12-months post-infection (1091 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.824458+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhongyan Lu</name></author><author><name>Eric D. Laing</name></author><author><name>Jarina Pena-Damata</name></author><author><name>Katherine Pohida</name></author><author><name>Marana S. Tso</name></author><author><name>Emily C. Samuels</name></author><author><name>Nusrat J. Epsi</name></author><author><name>Batsukh Dorjbal</name></author><author><name>Camille Lake</name></author><author><name>Stephanie A. Richard</name></author><author><name>Ryan C. Maves</name></author><author><name>David A. Lindholm</name></author><author><name>Julia Rozman</name></author><author><name>Caroline English</name></author><author><name>Nikhil Huprikar</name></author><author><name>Katrin Mende</name></author><author><name>Rhonda E. Colombo</name></author><author><name>Christopher J. Colombo</name></author><author><name>Christopher C. Broder</name></author><author><name>Anuradha Ganesan</name></author><author><name>Charlotte A. Lanteri</name></author><author><name>Brian K. Agan</name></author><author><name>David Tribble</name></author><author><name>Mark P. Simons</name></author><author><name>Clifton L. Dalgard</name></author><author><name>Paul W. Blair</name></author><author><name>Josh Chenoweth</name></author><author><name>Simon D. Pollett</name></author><author><name>Andrew L. Snow</name></author><author><name>Timothy H. Burgess</name></author><author><name>Allison M.W. Malloy</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Characterizing the longevity and quality of cellular immune responses to SARS-CoV-2 is critical to understanding immunologic approaches to protection against COVID-19. Prior studies suggest SARS-CoV-2-specific T cells are present in peripheral blood 10 months after infection. Further analysis of the function, durability, and diversity of the cellular response long after natural infection, over a wider range of ages and disease phenotypes, is needed to further identify preventative and therapeutic interventions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We identified participants in our multi-site longitudinal, prospective cohort study 12-months post SARS-CoV-2 infection representing a range of disease severity. We investigated the function, phenotypes, and frequency of T cells specific for SARS-CoV-2 using intracellular cytokine staining and spectral flow cytometry. In parallel, the magnitude of SARS-CoV-2-specific antibodies was compared.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2-specific antibodies and T cells were detected at 12-months post-infection. Severity of acute illness was associated with higher frequencies of SARS-CoV-2-specific CD4 T cells and antibodies at 12-months. In contrast, polyfunctional and cytotoxic T cells responsive to SARS-CoV-2 were identified in participants over a wide spectrum of disease severity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our data show that SARS-CoV-2 infection induces polyfunctional memory T cells detectable at 12-months post-infection, with higher frequency noted in those who originally experienced severe disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455984" rel="alternate" title="Durability of SARS-CoV-2-specific T cell responses at 12-months post-infection (1091 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.21261989</id><title>Infectious SARS-CoV-2 in Exhaled Aerosols and Efficacy of Masks During Early Mild Infection (863 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.824809+00:00</updated><author><name>Oluwasanmi Oladapo Adenaiye</name></author><author><name>Jianyu Lai</name></author><author><name>P. Jacob Bueno de Mesquita</name></author><author><name>Filbert H. Hong</name></author><author><name>Somayeh Youssefi</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Rebecca German</name></author><author><name>S.-H. Sheldon Tai</name></author><author><name>Barbara Jean Albert</name></author><author><name>Maria Schanz</name></author><author><name>Stuart Weston</name></author><author><name>Jun Hang</name></author><author><name>Christian K. Fung</name></author><author><name>Hye Kyung Chung</name></author><author><name>Kristen K. Coleman</name></author><author><name>Nicolae Sapoval</name></author><author><name>Todd Treangen</name></author><author><name>Irina Maljkovic Berry</name></author><author><name>Kristin E. Mullins</name></author><author><name>Matthew Frieman</name></author><author><name>Tianzhou Ma</name></author><author><name>Donald K. Milton</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: SARS-CoV-2 epidemiology implicates airborne transmission; mask source-control efficacy for, variant impact on, and infectiousness of aerosols are not well understood.
Methods: We recruited COVID-19 cases to give blood, saliva, mid-turbinate and fomite (phone) swabs, and 30-minute breath samples while vocalizing into a Gesundheit-II, with and without masks at up to two visits two days apart. We quantified and sequenced viral RNA, cultured virus, and assayed sera for anti-spike and anti-receptor binding domain antibodies. 
Results: We enrolled 61 participants with active infection, May 2020 through April 2021. Among 49 seronegative cases (mean days post onset 3.8 ±2.1), we detected SARS-CoV-2 RNA in 45% of fine (≥5 μm), 31% of coarse (&amp;gt;5 μm) aerosols, and 65% of fomite samples overall and in all samples from four alpha variant cases. Masks reduced viral RNA by 48% (95% confidence interval [CI], 3 to 72%) in fine and by 77% (95% CI, 51 to 89%) in coarse aerosols. The alpha variant was associated with a 43-fold (95% CI, 6.6 to 280-fold) increase in fine aerosol viral RNA that remained a significant 18-fold (95% CI, 3.4 to 92-fold) increase adjusting for viral RNA in saliva, in mid-turbinate swabs, and other potential confounders. Two fine aerosol samples, collected days 2-3 post illness onset, while participants wore masks, were culture-positive.
Conclusion: SARS-CoV-2 is evolving toward more efficient airborne transmission and loose-fitting masks provide significant but only modest source control. Therefore, until vaccination rates are very high, continued layered controls and tight-fitting masks and respirators will be necessary.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.21261989" rel="alternate" title="Infectious SARS-CoV-2 in Exhaled Aerosols and Efficacy of Masks During Early Mild Infection (863 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456173</id><title>Delta spike P681R mutation enhances SARS-CoV-2 fitness over Alpha variant (738 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.825062+00:00</updated><author><name>Yang Liu</name></author><author><name>Jianying Liu</name></author><author><name>Bryan A. Johnson</name></author><author><name>Hongjie Xia</name></author><author><name>Zhiqiang Ku</name></author><author><name>Craig Schindewolf</name></author><author><name>Steven G. Widen</name></author><author><name>Zhiqiang An</name></author><author><name>Scott Weaver</name></author><author><name>Vineet D Menachery</name></author><author><name>Xuping Xie</name></author><author><name>Pei-Yong Shi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 Delta variant has rapidly replaced the Alpha variant around the world. The mechanism that drives this global replacement has not been defined. Here we report that Delta spike mutation P681R plays a key role in the Alpha-to-Delta variant replacement. In a replication competition assay, Delta SARS-CoV-2 efficiently outcompeted the Alpha variant in human lung epithelial cells and primary human airway tissues. Delta SARS-CoV-2 bearing the Alpha-spike glycoprotein replicated less efficiently than the wild-type Delta variant, suggesting the importance of Delta spike in enhancing viral replication. The Delta spike has accumulated mutation P681R located at a furin cleavage site that separates the spike 1 (S1) and S2 subunits. Reverting the P681R mutation to wild-type P681 significantly reduced the replication of Delta variant, to a level lower than the Alpha variant. Mechanistically, the Delta P681R mutation enhanced the cleavage of the full-length spike to S1 and S2, leading to increased infection via cell surface entry. In contrast, the Alpha spike also has a mutation at the same amino acid (P681H), but the spike cleavage from purified Alpha virions was reduced compared to the Delta spike. Collectively, our results indicate P681R as a key mutation in enhancing Delta variant replication via increased S1/S2 cleavage. Spike mutations that potentially affect furin cleavage efficiency must be closely monitored for future variant surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456173" rel="alternate" title="Delta spike P681R mutation enhances SARS-CoV-2 fitness over Alpha variant (738 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455956</id><title>Molecular basis of immune evasion by the delta and kappa SARS-CoV-2 variants (237 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.825257+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew McCallum</name></author><author><name>Alexandra C. Walls</name></author><author><name>Kaitlin R. Sprouse</name></author><author><name>John E. Bowen</name></author><author><name>Laura Rosen</name></author><author><name>Ha V. Dang</name></author><author><name>Anna deMarco</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Franko</name></author><author><name>Sasha W Tilles</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Logue</name></author><author><name>Marcos C. Miranda</name></author><author><name>Margaret Ahlrichs</name></author><author><name>Lauren Carter</name></author><author><name>Gyorgy Snell</name></author><author><name>Matteo Samuele Pizzuto</name></author><author><name>Helen Y. Chu</name></author><author><name>Wesley C. Van Voorhis</name></author><author><name>Davide Corti</name></author><author><name>David Veesler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Worldwide SARS-CoV-2 transmission leads to the recurrent emergence of variants, such as the recently described B.1.617.1 (kappa), B.1.617.2 (delta) and B.1.617.2+ (delta+). The B.1.617.2 (delta) variant of concern is causing a new wave of infections in many countries, mostly affecting unvaccinated individuals, and has become globally dominant. We show that these variants dampen the in vitro potency of vaccine-elicited serum neutralizing antibodies and provide a structural framework for describing the impact of individual mutations on immune evasion. Mutations in the B.1.617.1 (kappa) and B.1.617.2 (delta) spike glycoproteins abrogate recognition by several monoclonal antibodies via alteration of key antigenic sites, including an unexpected remodeling of the B.1.617.2 (delta) N-terminal domain. The binding affinity of the B.1.617.1 (kappa) and B.1.617.2 (delta) receptor-binding domain for ACE2 is comparable to the ancestral virus whereas B.1.617.2+ (delta+) exhibits markedly reduced affinity. We describe a previously uncharacterized class of N-terminal domain-directed human neutralizing monoclonal antibodies cross-reacting with several variants of concern, revealing a possible target for vaccine development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455956" rel="alternate" title="Molecular basis of immune evasion by the delta and kappa SARS-CoV-2 variants (237 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455901</id><title>Robust and Functional Immunity up to 9 months after SARS-CoV-2 infection: a Southeast Asian longitudinal cohort (211 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.825571+00:00</updated><author><name>Vo Hoa Thi My</name></author><author><name>Maestri Alvino</name></author><author><name>Auerswald Heidi</name></author><author><name>Sorn Sopheak</name></author><author><name>Lay Sokchea</name></author><author><name>Heng Seng</name></author><author><name>Sann Sotheary</name></author><author><name>Ya Nisa</name></author><author><name>Pean Polidy</name></author><author><name>Dussart Philippe</name></author><author><name>Schwartz Olivier</name></author><author><name>Ly Sovann</name></author><author><name>Bruel Timothee</name></author><author><name>Ly Sowath</name></author><author><name>Duong Veasna</name></author><author><name>Karlsson Erik A</name></author><author><name>Cantaert Tineke</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Assessing the duration of humoral and cellular immunity remains key to overcome the current SARS-CoV-2 pandemic, especially in understudied populations in least developed countries. Sixty-four Cambodian individuals with laboratory-confirmed infection with asymptomatic or mild/moderate clinical presentation were evaluated for humoral immune response to the viral spike protein and antibody effector functions during acute phase of infection and at 6-9 months follow-up. Antigen-specific B cells, CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells were characterized, and T cells were interrogated for functionality at late convalescence. Anti-spike (S) antibody titers decreased over time, but effector functions mediated by S-specific antibodies remained stable. S- and nucleocapsid (N)-specific B cells could be detected in late convalescence in the activated memory B cell compartment and are mostly IgG&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;. CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cell immunity was maintained to S and membrane (M) protein. Asymptomatic infection resulted in decreased ADCC and frequency of SARS-CoV-2-specific CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells at late convalescence. Whereas anti-S antibodies correlated with S-specific B cells, there was no correlation between T cell response and humoral immunity. Hence, all aspects of a protective immune response are maintained up to nine months after SARS-CoV-2 infection in the absence of re-infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Functional immune memory to SARS-CoV-2, consisting of polyfunctional antibodies, memory B cells and memory T cells are maintained up to nine months in a South-East Asian cohort in the absence of re-infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455901" rel="alternate" title="Robust and Functional Immunity up to 9 months after SARS-CoV-2 infection: a Southeast Asian longitudinal cohort (211 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261991</id><title>Transmission dynamics and epidemiological characteristics of Delta variant infections in China (209 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.825791+00:00</updated><author><name>Min Kang</name></author><author><name>Hualei Xin</name></author><author><name>Jun Yuan</name></author><author><name>Sheikh Taslim Ali</name></author><author><name>Zimian Liang</name></author><author><name>Jiayi Zhang</name></author><author><name>Ting Hu</name></author><author><name>Eric Lau</name></author><author><name>Yingtao Zhang</name></author><author><name>Meng Zhang</name></author><author><name>Benjamin J Cowling</name></author><author><name>Yan Li</name></author><author><name>Peng Wu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: The Delta variant of SARS-CoV-2 has become predominant globally. We evaluated the transmission dynamics and epidemiological characteristics of the Delta variant in an outbreak in southern China. 

Methods: Data on confirmed cases and their close contacts were retrospectively collected from the outbreak that occurred in Guangdong, China in May-June 2021. Key epidemiological parameters, temporal trend of viral loads and secondary attack rates were estimated and compared between the Delta variant and the wild-type SARS-CoV-2 virus. We also evaluated the association of vaccination with viral load and transmission. 

Results: We identified 167 patients infected with the Delta variant in the Guangdong outbreak. The mean estimates of the latent period and the incubation period were 4.0 days and 5.8 days, respectively. A relatively higher viral load was observed in Delta cases than in wild-type infections. The secondary attack rate among close contacts of Delta cases was 1.4%, and 73.9% (95% confidence interval: 67.2%, 81.3%) of the transmissions occurred before onset. Index cases without vaccination (OR: 2.84, 95% confidence interval: 1.19, 8.45) or with one dose of vaccination (OR: 6.02, 95% confidence interval: 2.45, 18.16) were more likely to transmit infection to their contacts than those who had received 2 doses of vaccination.

Discussion: Patients infected with the Delta variant had more rapid symptom onset. The shorter and time-varying serial interval should be accounted in estimation of reproductive numbers. The higher viral load and higher risk of pre-symptomatic transmission indicated the challenges in control of infections with the Delta variant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261991" rel="alternate" title="Transmission dynamics and epidemiological characteristics of Delta variant infections in China (209 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.21261855</id><title>Clinical features, demography and predictors of outcomes of SARS-CoV-2 infection in a tertiary care hospital in India-A cohort study (190 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.825990+00:00</updated><author><name>Arunmozhimaran Elavarasi</name></author><author><name>Hari Krishna Raju Sagiraju</name></author><author><name>Rohit Kumar Garg</name></author><author><name>Brajesh Ratre</name></author><author><name>Prashant Sirohiya</name></author><author><name>Nishkarsh Gupta</name></author><author><name>Rakesh Garg</name></author><author><name>Anuja Pandit</name></author><author><name>Saurabh Vig</name></author><author><name>Ram Nalwa</name></author><author><name>Balbir Kumar</name></author><author><name>Ved Prakash Meena</name></author><author><name>Naveet Wig</name></author><author><name>Saurabh Mittal</name></author><author><name>Saurabh Pahuja</name></author><author><name>Karan Madan</name></author><author><name>Randeep Guleria</name></author><author><name>Anant Mohan</name></author><author><name>Tanima Dwivedi</name></author><author><name>Ritu Gupta</name></author><author><name>Ashima Jain Vidyarthi</name></author><author><name>Laxmitej Wundawalli</name></author><author><name>Angel Rajan Singh</name></author><author><name>Sheetal Singh</name></author><author><name>Sunil Kumar</name></author><author><name>Sushma Bhatnagar</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ‘second wave’ of the COVID-19 pandemic hit India from early April 2021 to June 2021 and more than 400,000 cases per day were reported in the country. We describe the clinical features, demography, treatment trends, baseline laboratory parameters of a cohort of patients admitted at the All India Institute of Medical Sciences, New Delhi with SARS-CoV-2 infection and their association with the outcome.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was a retrospective cohort study describing the clinical, laboratory and treatment patterns of consecutive patients admitted with SARS-CoV-2 infection. Multivariate logistic regression models were fitted to identify the clinical and biochemical predictors of developing hypoxia, deterioration during the hospital stay and death.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A total of 2080 patients were included in the study. The case fatality rate was 19.5%. Amongst the survivors, the median duration of hospital stay was 8 (5-11) days. Out of 853 (42.3%%) of patients who had COVID-19 Acute respiratory distress syndrome at presentation, 340 (39.9%) died. Patients aged 45-60 years [OR (95% CI): 1.8 (1.2-2.6)p =0.003] and those aged &amp;gt;60 years [OR (95%CI): 3.4 (2.3-5.2), p&amp;lt;0.001] had a higher odds of death as compared to the 18-44 age group. Vaccination reduced the odds of death by 30% [OR (95% CI): 0.7 (0.5-0.9), p=0.036]. Patients with hyper inflammation at baseline as suggested by leucocytosis [OR (95% CI): 2.1 (1.4-3.10), p &amp;lt;0.001], raised d-dimer &amp;gt;500 mg/dL [OR (95% CI): 3.2 (2.2-4.6), p &amp;lt;0.001] and raised C-reactive peptide &amp;gt;0.5 mg/L [OR (95% CI): 3.8 (1.1-13), p=0.037] had higher odds of death. Patients who were admitted in the second week had lower odds of death and those admitted in the third week had higher odds of death.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the largest cohort of patients admitted with COVID-19 from India reported to date and has shown that vaccination status and early admission during the inflammatory phase can change the course of illness of these patients. Strategies should be made to improve vaccination rates and early admission of patients with moderate and severe COVID-19 to improve outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;No funding was received&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Research in context&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Evidence before this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic has been ravaging the world since December 2019 and the cases in various regions are being reported in waves. We found that the case fatality rates ranging from 1.4% to 28.3% have been reported in the first wave in India. Older age and the presence of comorbidities are known predictors of mortality. There are no reports regarding the effectiveness of vaccination, correlation of mortality with the timing of admission to the health care facility and inflammatory markers in the ‘second wave’ of the COVID-19 pandemic in India.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Added-value of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study reports the real-world situation where patients get admitted at varying time points of their illness due to the mismatch between the availability of hospital beds and the rising number of COVID-19 patients during the pandemic. It reports the odds of developing severe hypoxia necessitating oxygen therapy and death thus helping identify priority groups for admission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Implications of all the available evidence&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study found increased odds of requiring oxygen support or death in patients older than 45 years of age, with comorbidities, and those who had hyper-inflammation with raised C-reactive peptide, d-dimer or leukocytosis. Patients who were admitted in the second week of illness had lower odds of death as compared to those admitted in the third week implying that treatment with corticosteroids in the second week of the illness during the ‘inflammatory phase’ could lead to reduced mortality. These findings would help triage patients and provide guidance for developing admission policy during times where hospital beds are scarce. Vaccination was found to reduce the odds of deterioration or death and should be fast-tracked to prevent further ‘waves’ of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.21261855" rel="alternate" title="Clinical features, demography and predictors of outcomes of SARS-CoV-2 infection in a tertiary care hospital in India-A cohort study (190 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.08.21261768</id><title>Full vaccination suppresses SARS-CoV-2 delta variant mutation frequency (157 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.826305+00:00</updated><author><name>Ting-Yu Yeh</name></author><author><name>Gregory P. Contreras</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This study presents the first evidence that full vaccination against COVID-19 suppresses emergent mutations of SARS-CoV-2 delta variants. An evolution algorithm, Tajima’s &lt;italic&gt;D&lt;/italic&gt; test with a threshold value as -2.50, can provide a promising tool to forecast new COVID-19 outbreaks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Question&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;It remains unclear how human interventions (vaccinations, lockdowns, etc.) affect viral mutation or generate selection pressure of SARS-CoV-2. It has also been obscure if there are differences in various geographic populations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The vaccination coverage rate is inversely correlated to the mutation frequency of the SARS-CoV-2 delta variants in 16 countries of 20 countries studied. We also discovered delta variants evolved differently under the positive selection pressure in the United Kingdom and India.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Meaning&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Full vaccination against COVID-19 is critical to suppress emergent mutations. Tajima’s &lt;italic&gt;D&lt;/italic&gt; test score, with a threshold value as -2.50, can provide a promising tool to forecast new COVID-19 outbreaks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.08.21261768" rel="alternate" title="Full vaccination suppresses SARS-CoV-2 delta variant mutation frequency (157 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.08.21261763</id><title>Neuro-COVID long-haulers exhibit broad dysfunction in T cell memory generation and responses to vaccination (63 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.826633+00:00</updated><author><name>Lavanya Visvabharathy</name></author><author><name>Barbara Hanson</name></author><author><name>Zachary Orban</name></author><author><name>Patrick H. Lim</name></author><author><name>Nicole Palacio</name></author><author><name>Rishi Jain</name></author><author><name>Eric Michael Liotta</name></author><author><name>Pablo Penaloza-MacMaster</name></author><author><name>Igor J. Koralnik</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The high prevalence of post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection (PASC) is a significant health concern. In particular, virus-specific immunity in patients who suffer from chronic neurologic symptoms after mild acute COVID remain poorly understood. Here, we report that neuro-PASC patients have a specific signature composed of humoral and cellular immune responses that are biased towards different structural proteins compared to healthy COVID convalescents. Interestingly, the severity of cognitive deficits or quality of life markers in neuro-PASC patients are associated with reduced effector molecule expressionn in memory T cells. Furthermore, we demonstrate that T cell responses to SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccines are aberrantly elevated in longitudinally sampled neuro-PASC patients compared with healthy COVID convalescents. These data provide a framework for the rational design of diagnostics and predictive biomarkers for long-COVID disease, as well as a blueprint for improved therapeutics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.08.21261763" rel="alternate" title="Neuro-COVID long-haulers exhibit broad dysfunction in T cell memory generation and responses to vaccination (63 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.21261992</id><title>Another step toward final call on Remdesivir efficacy as a treatment for hospitalized COVID-19 patients: a multicenter open-label trial (59 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.826852+00:00</updated><author><name>Hamed Hosseini</name></author><author><name>Anahita Sadeghi</name></author><author><name>Payam Tabarsi</name></author><author><name>Azin Etemadimanesh</name></author><author><name>Ilad Alavi Darazam</name></author><author><name>Nasser Aghdami</name></author><author><name>Saeed Kalantari</name></author><author><name>Mehrdad Hasibi</name></author><author><name>Azar Hadadi</name></author><author><name>Farhang Babamahmoodi</name></author><author><name>Mansooreh Momen-Heravi</name></author><author><name>Ahmad Hormati</name></author><author><name>Yunes Panahi</name></author><author><name>Rozita Khodashahi</name></author><author><name>Mohammadreza Salehi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Introduction: After emerging the global pandemic of SARS-CoV2 some preliminary studies demonstrated the efficacy of antiviral treatments. But shortly thereafter, inconsistencies in the results of further clinical trials raised doubts on the efficacy of these agents. In this study, we aimed to evaluate the effect of Remdesivir on hospitalized COVID-19 patients' outcomes.
Material and methods: This study was an open-label, single-armed, clinical trial on hospitalized patients diagnosed with COVID-19 who had progressive respiratory symptoms despite receiving standard care. All patients received Remdesivir and their characteristics, outcomes, time of treatment initiation, and respiratory support stages during hospitalization were registered and followed up for 14 days.
Results: 145 patients with a mean age of 52.89 +- 1.12 years enrolled in this study, 38 (26.2%) died at the end of 14 days period. The mean time interval from the onset of the symptoms to antiviral treatment was 10.63+-0.56 days.  Thirty deceased patients (78.9%) were men, showing 2.8 times higher mortality chance compared to women (ORadj=2.77; 95%CI=1.08-7.09). The type of respiratory support on the first day of treatment initiation showed a significantly lower mortality chance in patients receiving O2 only than those who needed non-invasive and/or mechanical ventilation (ORadj=3.91; 95%CI=1.64-9.32). The start time (early vs late administration) and duration (less or more than 7 days) of antiviral treatment had no statistically significant association with mortality or ventilation escalation among the patients (p-value &amp;gt; 0.05). 
Conclusion: In this study, we showed that Remdesivir probably is not effective on the outcome of hospitalized COVID-19 patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.21261992" rel="alternate" title="Another step toward final call on Remdesivir efficacy as a treatment for hospitalized COVID-19 patients: a multicenter open-label trial (59 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455959</id><title>Multiplexed detection of SARS-CoV-2 genomic and subgenomic RNA using in situ hybridization (43 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.827072+00:00</updated><author><name>Kofi K. Acheampong</name></author><author><name>Dylan L. Schaff</name></author><author><name>Benjamin L. Emert</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Lake</name></author><author><name>Sam Reffsin</name></author><author><name>Emily K. Shea</name></author><author><name>Courtney E. Comar</name></author><author><name>Leslie A. Litzky</name></author><author><name>Nigar A. Khurram</name></author><author><name>Rebecca L. Linn</name></author><author><name>Michael Feldman</name></author><author><name>Susan R. Weiss</name></author><author><name>Kathleen T. Montone</name></author><author><name>Sara Cherry</name></author><author><name>Sydney M. Shaffer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The widespread Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) is caused by infection with the novel coronavirus SARS-CoV-2. Currently, we have a limited toolset available for visualizing SARS-CoV-2 in cells and tissues, particularly in tissues from patients who died from COVID-19. Generally, single-molecule RNA FISH techniques have shown mixed results in formalin fixed paraffin embedded tissues such as those preserved from human autopsies. Here, we present a platform for preparing autopsy tissue for visualizing SARS-CoV-2 RNA using RNA FISH with amplification by hybridization chain reaction (HCR). We developed probe sets that target different regions of SARS-CoV-2 (including ORF1a and N) as well as probe sets that specifically target SARS-CoV-2 subgenomic mRNAs. We validated these probe sets in cell culture and tissues (lung, lymph node, and placenta) from infected patients. Using this technology, we observe distinct subcellular localization patterns of the ORF1a and N regions, with the ORF1a concentrated around the nucleus and the N showing a diffuse distribution across the cytoplasm. In human lung tissue, we performed multiplexed RNA FISH HCR for SARS-CoV-2 and cell-type specific marker genes. We found viral RNA in cells containing the alveolar type 2 (AT2) cell marker gene (&lt;italic&gt;SFTPC&lt;/italic&gt;) and the alveolar macrophage marker gene (&lt;italic&gt;MARCO&lt;/italic&gt;), but did not identify viral RNA in cells containing the alveolar type 1 (AT1) cell marker gene (&lt;italic&gt;AGER&lt;/italic&gt;). Moreover, we observed distinct subcellular localization patterns of viral RNA in AT2 cells and alveolar macrophages, consistent with phagocytosis of infected cells. In sum, we demonstrate the use of RNA FISH HCR for visualizing different RNA species from SARS-CoV-2 in cell lines and FFPE autopsy specimens. Furthermore, we multiplex this assay with probes for cellular genes to determine what cell-types are infected within the lung. We anticipate that this platform could be broadly useful for studying SARS-CoV-2 pathology in tissues as well as extended for other applications including investigating the viral life cycle, viral diagnostics, and drug screening.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455959" rel="alternate" title="Multiplexed detection of SARS-CoV-2 genomic and subgenomic RNA using in situ hybridization (43 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261876</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 variants: levels of neutralisation required for protective immunity (43 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.827315+00:00</updated><author><name>Deborah Cromer</name></author><author><name>Megan Steain</name></author><author><name>Arnold Reynaldi</name></author><author><name>Timothy E Schlub</name></author><author><name>Adam K Wheatley</name></author><author><name>Jennifer A Juno</name></author><author><name>Stephen J Kent</name></author><author><name>James A Triccas</name></author><author><name>David S Khoury</name></author><author><name>Miles Philip Davenport</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A number of SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (VOC) have been identified that partially escape serum neutralisation activity elicited by current vaccines. Recent studies have also shown that vaccines demonstrate reduced protection against symptomatic infection with SARS-CoV-2 variants.  Here we integrate published data on in vitro neutralisation and clinical protection to understand and predict vaccine efficacy against existing SARS-CoV-2 variants. We find that neutralising activity against the ancestral SARS-CoV-2 is highly predictive of neutralisation of the VOC, with all vaccines showing a similar drop in neutralisation to the variants. Neutralisation levels remain strongly correlated with protection from infection with SARS-CoV-2 VOC (r=0.81, p=0.0005). We apply an existing model relating in vitro neutralisation to protection (parameterised on data from ancestral virus infection) and find this remains predictive of vaccine efficacy against VOC once drops in neutralisation to the VOC are taken into account. Modelling of predicted vaccine efficacy against variants over time suggests that protection against symptomatic infection may drop below 50% within the first year after vaccination for some current vaccines. Boosting of previously infected individuals with existing vaccines (which target ancestral virus) has been shown to significantly increase neutralising antibodies. Our modelling suggests that booster vaccination should enable high levels of immunity that prevent severe infection outcomes with the current SARS-CoV-2 VOC, at least in the medium term.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261876" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 variants: levels of neutralisation required for protective immunity (43 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456077</id><title>Hybrid immunity improves B cell frequency, antibody potency and breadth against SARS-CoV-2 and variants of concern (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.827505+00:00</updated><author><name>Emanuele Andreano</name></author><author><name>Ida Paciello</name></author><author><name>Giulia Piccini</name></author><author><name>Noemi Manganaro</name></author><author><name>Piero Pileri</name></author><author><name>Inesa Hyseni</name></author><author><name>Margherita Leonardi</name></author><author><name>Elisa Pantano</name></author><author><name>Valentina Abbiento</name></author><author><name>Linda Benincasa</name></author><author><name>Ginevra Giglioli</name></author><author><name>Concetta De Santi</name></author><author><name>Massimiliano Fabbiani</name></author><author><name>Ilaria Rancan</name></author><author><name>Mario Tumbarello</name></author><author><name>Francesca Montagnani</name></author><author><name>Claudia Sala</name></author><author><name>Emanuele Montomoli</name></author><author><name>Rino Rappuoli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To understand the nature of the antibody response to SARS-CoV-2 vaccination, we analyzed at single cell level the B cell responses of five naïve and five convalescent people immunized with the BNT162b2 mRNA vaccine. Convalescents had higher frequency of spike protein specific memory B cells and by cell sorting delivered 3,532 B cells, compared with 2,352 from naïve people. Of these, 944 from naïve and 2,299 from convalescents produced monoclonal antibodies against the spike protein and 411 of them neutralized the original Wuhan SARS-CoV-2 virus. More than 75% of the monoclonal antibodies from naïve people lost their neutralization activity against the B.1.351 (beta) and B.1.1.248 (gamma) variants while this happened only for 61% of those from convalescents. The overall loss of neutralization was lower for the B.1.1.7 (alpha) and B.1.617.2 (delta) variants, however it was always significantly higher in those of naïve people. In part this was due to the IGHV2-5;IGHJ4-1 germline, which was found only in convalescents and generated potent and broadly neutralizing antibodies. Overall, vaccination of seropositive people increases the frequency of B cells encoding antibodies with high potency and that are not susceptible to escape by any of the four variants of concern. Our data suggest that people that are seropositive following infection or primary vaccination will produce antibodies with increased potency and breadth and will be able to better control SARS-CoV-2 emerging variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456077" rel="alternate" title="Hybrid immunity improves B cell frequency, antibody potency and breadth against SARS-CoV-2 and variants of concern (37 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261806</id><title>Efficacy of SARS-CoV-2 vaccine in thoracic cancer patients: a prospective study supporting a third dose in patients with minimal serologic response after two vaccine doses (33 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.827742+00:00</updated><author><name>Valerie GOUNANT</name></author><author><name>Valentine Marie FERRE</name></author><author><name>Ghassen SOUSSI</name></author><author><name>Charlotte charpentier</name></author><author><name>Heloise FLAMENT</name></author><author><name>Nadhira FIDOUH</name></author><author><name>Gilles COLLIN</name></author><author><name>Celine NAMOUR</name></author><author><name>Sandra ASSOUN</name></author><author><name>Alexandra BIZOT</name></author><author><name>Zohra BROUK</name></author><author><name>Eric VICAUT</name></author><author><name>Luis TEXEIRA</name></author><author><name>Diane DESCAMPS</name></author><author><name>Gerard ZALCMAN</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hypothesis
Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) resulted in a 30% mortality rate in thoracic cancer patients. Given that cancer patients were excluded from serum anti-severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV2) vaccine registration trials, it is still unknown whether they would develop a protective anti-spike antibody response following vaccination. This prospective vaccine monitoring study primarily aimed to assess humoral responses to SARS-CoV2 vaccine in thoracic cancer patients. 

Methods
SARS-CoV2-spike antibodies were measured using Abbot ARCHITECT SARS-CoV-2 IgG immunoassay, prior to first injection of BNT162b2 mRNA vaccine, as well as at Week 4, and two-to-sixteen weeks after second vaccine dose. The factors associated with antibody response were analyzed.

Results
Overall, 306 patients, with a median age of 67.0 years (IQR=58-74), were vaccinated. Of these, 283 patients received two vaccine doses at 28-day intervals. After 4.7-month median follow-up, seven patients (2.3%) contracted proven symptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection, with rapid favorable evolution. Of 269 serological results available beyond Day 14 post-second vaccine dose, 17 (6.3%) were still negative (&amp;lt;50 AU/mL) (arbitrary units/mL), while 34 (11%) were &amp;lt;300 AU/mL (12.5th percentile). In multivariate analysis, only age and chronic corticosteroid treatment were significantly associated with a lack of immunization. Thirty patients received a third vaccine dose, with only three patients showing persistent negative serology thereafter, whereas the others demonstrated clear seroconversion.

Conclusion
SARS-CoV2 vaccines were shown to be efficient in thoracic cancer patients, most of them being immunized after two doses. A third shot given to 11% of patients with persistent low antibody titers resulted in a 88% immunization rate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261806" rel="alternate" title="Efficacy of SARS-CoV-2 vaccine in thoracic cancer patients: a prospective study supporting a third dose in patients with minimal serologic response after two vaccine doses (33 tweets)"/><category term="Oncology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261921</id><title>Clinical course impacts early kinetics and long-term magnitude and amplitude of SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibodies beyond one year after infection (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.827956+00:00</updated><author><name>Edwards Pradenas</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Trinité</name></author><author><name>Víctor Urrea</name></author><author><name>Silvia Marfil</name></author><author><name>Ferran Tarrés-Freixas</name></author><author><name>Raquel Ortiz</name></author><author><name>Carla Rovirosa</name></author><author><name>Jordi Rodon</name></author><author><name>Júlia Vergara-Alert</name></author><author><name>Joaquim Segalés</name></author><author><name>Victor Guallar</name></author><author><name>Alfonso Valencia</name></author><author><name>Nuria Izquierdo-Useros</name></author><author><name>Marc Noguera-Julian</name></author><author><name>Jorge Carrillo</name></author><author><name>Roger Paredes</name></author><author><name>Lourdes Mateu</name></author><author><name>Anna Chamorro</name></author><author><name>Ruth Toledo</name></author><author><name>Marta Massanella</name></author><author><name>Bonaventura Clotet</name></author><author><name>Julià Blanco</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Understanding the determinants of long-term immune responses to SARS-CoV-2 and the concurrent impact of vaccination and emerging variants of concern will guide optimal strategies to achieve global protection against the COVID-19 pandemic.

Methods: A prospective cohort of 332 COVID-19 patients was followed beyond one year. Plasma neutralizing activity was evaluated using HIV-based reporter pseudoviruses expressing different SARS-CoV-2 spikes and was longitudinally analyzed using mixed-effects models.

Findings: Long-term neutralizing activity was stable beyond one year after infection in mild/asymptomatic and hospitalized participants. However, longitudinal models suggest that hospitalized individuals generate both short- and long-lived memory B cells, while outpatient responses were dominated by long-lived B cells. In both groups, vaccination boosted responses to natural infection, although viral variants, mainly B.1.351, reduced the efficacy of neutralization. Importantly, despite showing higher neutralization titers, hospitalized patients showed lower cross-neutralization of B.1.351 variant compared to outpatients. Multivariate analysis identified severity of primary infection as the factor that independently determines both the magnitude and the inferior cross-neutralization activity of long-term neutralizing responses.

Conclusions: Neutralizing response induced by SARS-CoV-2 is heterogeneous in magnitude but stable beyond one year after infection. Vaccination boosts these long-lasting natural neutralizing responses, counteracting the significant resistance to neutralization of new viral variants. Severity of primary infection determines higher magnitude but poorer quality of long-term neutralizing responses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261921" rel="alternate" title="Clinical course impacts early kinetics and long-term magnitude and amplitude of SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibodies beyond one year after infection (27 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455737</id><title>Molecular mimicry between Spike and human thrombopoietin may induce thrombocytopenia in COVID-19 (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.828212+00:00</updated><author><name>Janelle Nunez-Castilla</name></author><author><name>Vitalii Stebliankin</name></author><author><name>Prabin Baral</name></author><author><name>Christian A Balbin</name></author><author><name>Masrur Sobhan</name></author><author><name>Trevor Cickovski</name></author><author><name>Ananda Mohan Mondal</name></author><author><name>Giri Narasimhan</name></author><author><name>Prem Chapagain</name></author><author><name>Kalai Mathee</name></author><author><name>Jessica Siltberg-Liberles</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Thrombocytopenia, characterized by reduced platelet count, increases mortality in COVID-19 patients. We performed a computational investigation of antibody-induced cross-reactivity due to molecular mimicry between SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein and human thrombopoietin, the regulator of platelet production, as a mechanism for thrombocytopenia in COVID-19 infections. The presence of a common sequence motif with similar structure and antibody-binding properties for these proteins strongly indicate shared molecular mimicry. Recent reports of antibodies in COVID-19 patients and pre-pandemic samples against epitopes containing the motif offer additional support for the cross-reactivity. Altogether, this suggests cross-reactivity between an antibody with affinity for Spike protein and a human protein. Consideration of cross-reactivity for SARS-CoV-2 is important for therapeutic intervention and when designing the next generation of COVID-19 vaccines to avoid potential autoimmune interference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein may trigger the production of antibodies that can cross-react with human thrombopoietin.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455737" rel="alternate" title="Molecular mimicry between Spike and human thrombopoietin may induce thrombocytopenia in COVID-19 (26 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456266</id><title>Secreted SARS-CoV-2 ORF8 modulates the cytokine expression profile of human macrophages (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.828407+00:00</updated><author><name>Nisha Kriplani</name></author><author><name>Sara Mary Rose Clohisey</name></author><author><name>Sonia Fonseca</name></author><author><name>Sarah Fletcher</name></author><author><name>Hui-Min Lee</name></author><author><name>Jordan Ashworth</name></author><author><name>Dominic Kurian</name></author><author><name>Samantha J Lycett</name></author><author><name>Christine Tait-Burkard</name></author><author><name>J Kenneth Baillie</name></author><author><name>Mark E J Woolhouse</name></author><author><name>Simon R Carding</name></author><author><name>James P Stewart</name></author><author><name>Paul Digard</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) is still adapting to its new human host. Attention has focussed on the viral spike protein, but substantial variation has been seen in the ORF8 gene. Here, we show that SARS-CoV-2 ORF8 protein undergoes signal peptide-mediated processing through the endoplasmic reticulum and is secreted as a glycosylated, disulphide-linked dimer. The secreted protein from the prototype SARS-CoV-2 virus had no major effect on viability of a variety of cell types, or on IFN or NF-κB; signalling. However, it modulated cytokine expression from primary CSF1-derived human macrophages, most notably by decreasing IL-6 and IL-8 secretion. Furthermore, a sequence polymorphism L84S that appeared early in the pandemic associated with the Clade S lineage of virus, showed a markedly different effect, of increasing IL-6 production. We conclude that ORF8 sequence polymorphisms can potentially affect SARS-CoV-2 virulence and should therefore be monitored in sequencing-based surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456266" rel="alternate" title="Secreted SARS-CoV-2 ORF8 modulates the cytokine expression profile of human macrophages (26 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261732</id><title>COVID-19 in Connecticut institutions of higher education during the 2020-2021 academic year (25 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.828616+00:00</updated><author><name>Olivia Schultes</name></author><author><name>Victoria Clarke</name></author><author><name>A David Paltiel</name></author><author><name>Matthew Cartter</name></author><author><name>Lynn Sosa</name></author><author><name>Forrest W. Crawford</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: During the 2020-2021 academic year, many institutions of higher education reopened to residential students while pursuing strategies to mitigate the risk of SARS-CoV-2 transmission on campus.  Reopening guidance emphasized PCR or antigen testing for residential students and social distancing measures to reduce the frequency of close interpersonal contact.  Connecticut colleges and universities employed a variety of approaches to reopening campuses to residential students. Methods: We used data on testing, cases, and social contact in 18 residential college and university campuses in Connecticut to characterize institutional reopening strategies and COVID-19 outcomes. We compared institutions' fall 2020 COVID-19 plans, submitted to the Connecticut Department of Public Health, and analyzed contact rates and COVID-19 outcomes throughout the academic year.  Results: In census block groups containing residence halls, fall student move-in resulted in a 475% (95% CI 373%-606%) increase in average contact, and spring move-in resulted in a 561% (441%-713%) increase in average contact. The relationship between test frequency and case rate per residential student was complex: institutions that tested students infrequently detected few cases but failed to blunt transmission, while institutions that tested students more frequently detected more cases and prevented further spread. In fall 2020, each additional test per student per week was associated with a reduction of 0.0014 cases per student per week (95% CI: -0.0028, -0.000012). Residential student case rates were associated with higher case rates in the town where the school was located, but it is not possible to determine whether on-campus infections were transmitted to the broader community or vice versa. Conclusions: Campus outbreaks among residential students might be avoided or mitigated by frequent testing, social distancing, and mandatory vaccination.  Vaccination rates among residential students and surrounding communities may determine the necessary scale of residential testing programs and social distancing measures during the 2021-2022 academic year.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261732" rel="alternate" title="COVID-19 in Connecticut institutions of higher education during the 2020-2021 academic year (25 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261825</id><title>Pandemic excess mortality in Spain, Sweden, and Switzerland during the COVID-19 pandemic in 2020 was at its highest since 1918 (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.828781+00:00</updated><author><name>Kaspar Staub</name></author><author><name>Radoslaw Panczak</name></author><author><name>Katarina L Matthes</name></author><author><name>Joel Floris</name></author><author><name>Claudia Berlin</name></author><author><name>Christoph Junker</name></author><author><name>Rolf Weitkunat</name></author><author><name>Svenn-Erik Mamelund</name></author><author><name>Matthias Egger</name></author><author><name>Marcel Zwahlen</name></author><author><name>Julien Riou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Estimating excess mortality allows quantification of overall pandemic impact. For recent decades, mortality data are easily accessible for most industrialized countries, but only a few countries have continuous data available for longer periods. Since Spain, Sweden, and Switzerland were militarily neutral and not involved in combat during both world wars, these countries have monthly all-cause mortality statistics available for over 100 years with no interruptions. We show that during the COVID-19 pandemic in 2020, Spain, Sweden and Switzerland recorded the highest aggregated monthly excess mortality (17%, 9% and 14%) since the 1918 influenza pandemic (53%, 33% and 49%), when compared to respective expected values. For Sweden and Switzerland, the highest monthly spikes in 2020 almost reached those of January 1890. These findings emphasize the historical dimensions of the ongoing pandemic and support the notion of a pandemic disaster memory gap.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261825" rel="alternate" title="Pandemic excess mortality in Spain, Sweden, and Switzerland during the COVID-19 pandemic in 2020 was at its highest since 1918 (19 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456228</id><title>A diabetic milieu increases cellular susceptibility to SARS-CoV-2 infections in engineered human kidney organoids and diabetic patients (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.828971+00:00</updated><author><name>Elena Garreta</name></author><author><name>Praticia Prado</name></author><author><name>Megan L. Stanifer</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Monteil</name></author><author><name>Carmen Hurtado del Pozo</name></author><author><name>Asier Ullate-Agote</name></author><author><name>Amaia Vilas-Zornoza</name></author><author><name>Juan Pablo Romero</name></author><author><name>Gustav Jonsson</name></author><author><name>Roger Oria</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Leopoldi</name></author><author><name>Astrid Hagelkrueys</name></author><author><name>Daniel Moya-Rull</name></author><author><name>Federico Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Andres Marco</name></author><author><name>Carolina Tarantino</name></author><author><name>Pere Domingo-Pedrol</name></author><author><name>Omar HasanAli</name></author><author><name>Pedro Ventura-Aguiar</name></author><author><name>Josep Maria Campistol</name></author><author><name>Felipe Prosper</name></author><author><name>Ali Mirazimi</name></author><author><name>Steeve Boulant</name></author><author><name>Josef Penninger</name></author><author><name>Nuria Montserrat</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 infections lead to a high risk of hospitalization and mortality in diabetic patients. Why diabetic individuals are more prone to develop severe COVID-19 remains unclear. Here, we established a novel human kidney organoid model that mimics early hallmarks of diabetic nephropathy. High oscillatory glucose exposure resulted in metabolic changes, expansion of extracellular membrane components, gene expression changes determined by scRNAseq, and marked upregulation of angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2). Upon SARS-CoV-2 infection, hyperglycemic conditions lead to markedly higher viral loads in kidney organoids compared to normoglycemia. Genetic deletion of ACE2, but not of the candidate receptor BSG/CD147, in kidney organoids demonstrated the essential role of ACE2 in SARS-CoV-2 infections and completely prevented SARS-CoV-2 infection in the diabetogenic microenvironment. These data introduce a novel organoid model for diabetic kidney disease and show that diabetic-induced ACE2 licenses the diabetic kidney to enhanced SARS-CoV-2 replication.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456228" rel="alternate" title="A diabetic milieu increases cellular susceptibility to SARS-CoV-2 infections in engineered human kidney organoids and diabetic patients (18 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261934</id><title>The D614G virus mutation enhances anosmia in COVID-19 patients: Evidence from a systematic review and meta-analysis of studies from South Asia (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.829977+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher S. von Bartheld</name></author><author><name>Molly M. Hagen</name></author><author><name>Rafal Butowt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The prevalence of chemosensory dysfunction in patients with COVID-19 varies greatly between populations. It is unclear whether such differences are due to factors at the level of the human host, or at the level of the coronavirus, or both. At the host level, the entry proteins which allow virus binding and entry have variants with distinct properties, and the frequency of such variants differs between ethnicities. At the level of the virus, the D614G mutation enhances virus entry to the host cell. Since the two virus strains (D614 and G614) co-existed in the first six months of the pandemic in most populations, it has been difficult to distinguish between contributions of the virus and contributions of the host for anosmia. To answer this question, we conducted a systematic review and meta-analysis of studies in South Asian populations when either the D614 or the G614 virus was dominant. We show that populations infected predominantly with the G614 virus had a much higher prevalence of anosmia (pooled prevalence of 31.8%) compared with the same ethnic populations infected mostly with the D614 virus strain (pooled anosmia prevalence of 5.3%). We conclude that the D614G mutation is a major contributing factor that increases the prevalence of anosmia in COVID-19, and that this enhanced effect on olfaction constitutes a previously unrecognized phenotype of the D614G mutation. The new virus strains that have additional mutations on the background of the D614G mutation can be expected to cause a similarly increased prevalence of chemosensory dysfunctions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="21261934v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261934" rel="alternate" title="The D614G virus mutation enhances anosmia in COVID-19 patients: Evidence from a systematic review and meta-analysis of studies from South Asia (18 tweets)"/><category term="Otolaryngology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.21262006</id><title>Altered increase in STAT1 expression and phosphorylation in severe COVID-19 (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.830356+00:00</updated><author><name>Hectot Rincon-Arevalo</name></author><author><name>Arman Aue</name></author><author><name>Jacob Ritter</name></author><author><name>Franziska Szelinski</name></author><author><name>Dmytro Khadzhynov</name></author><author><name>Daniel Zickler</name></author><author><name>Ana-Luisa Stefanski</name></author><author><name>Andreia C Lino</name></author><author><name>Sixten Koerper</name></author><author><name>Kai-Uwe Eckardt</name></author><author><name>Hubert Schrezenmeier</name></author><author><name>Thomas Doerner</name></author><author><name>Eva Schrezenmeier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The interferon pathway represents a key antiviral defense mechanism and is being considered as a therapeutic target in COVID-19. Both, substitution of interferon and blocking interferon signaling through JAK STAT inhibition to limit cytokine storms have been proposed. However, little is known so far about possible abnormalities in STAT signaling in immune cells during SARS-CoV-2 infection. In the current study, we investigated downstream targets of interferon signaling, including STAT1, pSTAT1 and 2 and IRF1, 7 and 9 by flow cytometry in 30 patients with COVID-19, 17 with mild and 13 with severe infection. We report an upregulation of STAT1 and IRF9 in mild and severe COVID-19 cases, which correlated with the IFN-signature assessed by Siglec-1 (CD169) expression on peripheral monocytes. Most interestingly, Siglec-1 and STAT1 in CD14+ monocytes and plasmablasts showed lower expression among severe COVID-19 cases compared to mild cases. Contrary to the baseline whole protein STAT1 expression, the phosphorylation of STAT1 was enhanced in severe COVID-19 cases, indicating a dysbalanced JAK STAT signaling that fails to induce transcription of interferon stimulated response elements (ISRE). This abnormality persisted after IFN-α and IFN-γ stimulation of PBMCs from patients with severe COVID-19. The data suggest impaired STAT1 transcriptional upregulation among severely infected patients which may represent a potential predictive biomarker and may allow stratification of patients for certain interferon-pathway targeted treatments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.21262006" rel="alternate" title="Altered increase in STAT1 expression and phosphorylation in severe COVID-19 (16 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.21261704</id><title>Antibody-mediated neutralization of authentic SARS-CoV-2 B.1.617 variants harboring L452R and T478K/E484Q (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.830743+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Wilhelm</name></author><author><name>Tuna Toptan</name></author><author><name>Christiane Pallas</name></author><author><name>Timo Wolf</name></author><author><name>Udo Goetsch</name></author><author><name>Rene Gottschalk</name></author><author><name>Maria JGT Vehreschild</name></author><author><name>Sandra Ciesek</name></author><author><name>Marek Widera</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The capacity of convalescent and vaccine-elicited sera and monoclonal antibodies (mAb) to neutralize SARS-CoV-2 variants is currently of high relevance to assess the protection against infections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We performed a cell culture-based neutralization assay focusing on authentic SARS-CoV-2 variants B.1.617.1 (Kappa), B.1.617.2 (Delta), B.1.427/B.1.429 (Epsilon), all harboring the spike substitution L452R.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found that authentic SARS-CoV-2 variants harboring L452R had reduced susceptibility to convalescent and vaccine-elicited sera and mAbs. Compared to B.1, Kappa and Delta showed a reduced neutralization by convalescent sera by a factor of 8.00 and 5.33, respectively, which constitutes a 2-fold greater reduction when compared to Epsilon. BNT2b2 and mRNA1273 vaccine-elicited sera were less effective against Kappa, Delta, and Epsilon compared to B.1. No difference was observed between Kappa and Delta towards vaccine-elicited sera, whereas convalescent sera were 1.5-fold less effective against Delta, respectively. Both B.1.617 variants Kappa (+E484Q) and Delta (+T478K) were less susceptible to either casirivimab or imdevimab.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, in contrast to the parallel circulating Kappa variant, the neutralization efficiency of convalescent and vaccine-elicited sera against Delta was moderately reduced. Delta was resistant to imdevimab, which however, might be circumvented by a combination therapy with casirivimab together.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.21261704" rel="alternate" title="Antibody-mediated neutralization of authentic SARS-CoV-2 B.1.617 variants harboring L452R and T478K/E484Q (15 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455899</id><title>Cross-sectional genomic perspective of epidemic waves of SARS-CoV-2: a pan India study (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.831219+00:00</updated><author><name>Sanjeet Kumar</name></author><author><name>Kanika Bansal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 has posed unforeseen circumstances and throttled major economies worldwide. India has witnessed two waves affecting around 31 million people representing 16% of the cases globally. To date, the epidemic waves have not been comprehensively investigated to understand pandemic progress in India. In the present study, we aim for a cross-sectional analysis since its first incidence up to 26th July 2021. We have performed the pan Indian evolutionary study using 20,086 high-quality complete genomes of SARS-CoV-2. Based on the number of cases reported and mutation rates, we could divide the Indian epidemic into seven different phases. First, three phases constituting the pre-first wave had a very less average mutation rate (&amp;lt;11), which increased in the first wave to 17 and then doubled in the second wave (~34). In accordance with the mutation rate, variants of concern (alpha, beta, gamma and delta) and interest (eta and kappa) also started appearing in the first wave (1.5% of the genomes), which dominated the second (~96% of genomes) and post-second wave (100% of genomes) phases. Whole genome-based phylogeny could demarcate the post-first wave isolates from previous ones by the point of diversification leading to incidences of VOCs and VOIs in India. Nation-wide mutational analysis depicted more than 0.5 million events with four major mutations in ~97% of the total 20,086 genomes in the study. These included two mutations in coding (spike (D614G) and NSP 12b (P314L) of RNA dependent RNA polymerase), one silent mutation (NSP3 F106F) and one extragenic mutation (5’ UTR 241). Large scale genome-wide mutational analysis is crucial in expanding knowledge on evolution of deadly variants of SARS-CoV-2 and timely management of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455899" rel="alternate" title="Cross-sectional genomic perspective of epidemic waves of SARS-CoV-2: a pan India study (15 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261845</id><title>Changing Dynamics of COVID-19 in the U.S. with the Emergence of the Delta Variant: Projections of the COVID-19 Simulator (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.831447+00:00</updated><author><name>Jagpreet Chhatwal</name></author><author><name>Yingying (Jade) Xiao</name></author><author><name>Peter Carl Powell Mueller</name></author><author><name>Turgay Ayer</name></author><author><name>Madeline Grace Adee</name></author><author><name>Ozden Dalgic</name></author><author><name>Mary Ann Ladd</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Linas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;With the recent emergence of the B.1.617.2 (Delta) variant of SARS-CoV-2 in the U.S., many states are seeing rising cases and hospitalizations after a period of steady decline. As We used the COVID-19 Simulator, an interactive online tool that utilizes a validated mathematical model, to simulate the trajectory of COVID-19 at the state level in the U.S. COVID-19 Simulator's forecasts are updated weekly and included in the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) ensemble model. We employed our model to analyze scenarios where the Delta variant becomes dominant in every state.
 
The combination of high transmissibility of the Delta variant, low vaccination coverage in several regions, and a more relaxed attitude towards social distancing is expected to result in a surge in COVID-19 deaths in at least 40 states. In several states -- including Idaho, Maine, Montana, Nebraska, North Carolina, Oregon, Puerto Rico, Washington, and West Virginia -- the projected daily deaths in 2021 could exceed the prior peak daily deaths under current social distancing behavior and vaccination rate. The number of COVID-19 deaths across the U.S. could exceed 1600 per day. 

Between August 1, 2021, and December 31, 2021, there could be additional 157,000 COVID-19 deaths across the U.S. Of note, our model projected approximately 20,700 COVID-19 deaths in Texas, 16,000 in California, 12,400 in Florida, 12,000 in North Carolina, and 9,300 in Georgia during this period. In contrast, the projected number of COVID-19 deaths would remain below 200 in New Jersey, Massachusetts, Connecticut, Vermont, and Rhode Island.  

We project COVID-19 deaths based on the current vaccination rates and social distancing behavior. Our hope is that the findings of this report serve a warning sign and people revert to wearing masks and maintain social distancing to reduce COVID-19 associated deaths in the U.S. Our projections are updated weekly by incorporating vaccination rates and social distancing measures in each state; the latest results can be found at the COVID-19 Simulator website.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261845" rel="alternate" title="Changing Dynamics of COVID-19 in the U.S. with the Emergence of the Delta Variant: Projections of the COVID-19 Simulator (14 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456131</id><title>Phylogenetic reconciliation reveals extensive ancestral recombination in Sarbecoviruses and the SARS-CoV-2 lineage (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.831897+00:00</updated><author><name>Sumaira Zaman</name></author><author><name>Samuel Sledzieski</name></author><author><name>Bonnie Berger</name></author><author><name>Yi-Chieh Wu</name></author><author><name>Mukul S. Bansal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;An accurate understanding of the evolutionary history of rapidly-evolving viruses like SARS-CoV-2, responsible for the COVID-19 pandemic, is crucial to tracking and preventing the spread of emerging pathogens. However, viruses undergo frequent recombination, which makes it difficult to trace their evolutionary history using traditional phylogenetic methods. Here, we present a phylogenetic workflow, virDTL, for analyzing viral evolution in the presence of recombination. Our approach leverages reconciliation methods developed for inferring horizontal gene transfer in prokaryotes, and, compared to existing tools, is uniquely able to identify ancestral recombinations while accounting for several sources of inference uncertainty, including in the construction of a strain tree, estimation and rooting of gene family trees, and reconciliation itself. We apply this workflow to the &lt;italic&gt;Sarbecovirus&lt;/italic&gt; subgenus and demonstrate how a principled analysis of predicted recombination gives insight into the evolution of SARS-CoV-2. In addition to providing confirming evidence for the horseshoe bat as its zoonotic origin, we identify several ancestral recombination events that merit further study.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456131" rel="alternate" title="Phylogenetic reconciliation reveals extensive ancestral recombination in Sarbecoviruses and the SARS-CoV-2 lineage (13 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456015</id><title>Protection against SARS-CoV-2 Beta Variant in mRNA-1273 Boosted Nonhuman Primates (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.832088+00:00</updated><author><name>Kizzmekia S. Corbett</name></author><author><name>Matthew Gagne</name></author><author><name>Danielle A. Wagner</name></author><author><name>Sarah O’ Connell</name></author><author><name>Sandeep R. Narpala</name></author><author><name>Dillon R. Flebbe</name></author><author><name>Shayne F. Andrew</name></author><author><name>Rachel L. Davis</name></author><author><name>Barbara Flynn</name></author><author><name>Timothy S. Johnston</name></author><author><name>Christopher Stringham</name></author><author><name>Lilin Lai</name></author><author><name>Daniel Valentin</name></author><author><name>Alex Van Ry</name></author><author><name>Zackery Flinchbaugh</name></author><author><name>Anne P. Werner</name></author><author><name>Juan I. Moliva</name></author><author><name>Manjari Sriparna</name></author><author><name>Sijy O’Dell</name></author><author><name>Stephen D. Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Courtney Tucker</name></author><author><name>Angela Choi</name></author><author><name>Matthew Koch</name></author><author><name>Kevin W. Bock</name></author><author><name>Mahnaz Minai</name></author><author><name>Bianca M. Nagata</name></author><author><name>Gabriela S. Alvarado</name></author><author><name>Amy R. Henry</name></author><author><name>Farida Laboune</name></author><author><name>Chaim A. Schramm</name></author><author><name>Yi Zhang</name></author><author><name>Lingshu Wang</name></author><author><name>Misook Choe</name></author><author><name>Seyhan Boyoglu-Barnum</name></author><author><name>Wei Shi</name></author><author><name>Evan Lamb</name></author><author><name>Saule T. Nurmukhambetova</name></author><author><name>Samantha J. Provost</name></author><author><name>Mitzi M. Donaldson</name></author><author><name>Josue Marquez</name></author><author><name>John-Paul M. Todd</name></author><author><name>Anthony Cook</name></author><author><name>Alan Dodson</name></author><author><name>Andrew Pekosz</name></author><author><name>Eli Boritz</name></author><author><name>Aurélie Ploquin</name></author><author><name>Nicole Doria-Rose</name></author><author><name>Laurent Pessaint</name></author><author><name>Hanne Andersen</name></author><author><name>Kathryn E. Foulds</name></author><author><name>John Misasi</name></author><author><name>Kai Wu</name></author><author><name>Andrea Carfi</name></author><author><name>Martha C. Nason</name></author><author><name>John Mascola</name></author><author><name>Ian N. Moore</name></author><author><name>Darin K. Edwards</name></author><author><name>Mark G. Lewis</name></author><author><name>Mehul S. Suthar</name></author><author><name>Mario Roederer</name></author><author><name>Adrian McDermott</name></author><author><name>Daniel C. Douek</name></author><author><name>Nancy J. Sullivan</name></author><author><name>Barney S. Graham</name></author><author><name>Robert A. Seder</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neutralizing antibody responses gradually wane after vaccination with mRNA-1273 against several variants of concern (VOC), and additional boost vaccinations may be required to sustain immunity and protection. Here, we evaluated the immune responses in nonhuman primates that received 100 µg of mRNA-1273 vaccine at 0 and 4 weeks and were boosted at week 29 with mRNA-1273 (homologous) or mRNA-1273.β (heterologous), which encompasses the spike sequence of the B.1.351 (beta or β) variant. Reciprocal ID&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; pseudovirus neutralizing antibody geometric mean titers (GMT) against live SARS-CoV-2 D614G and the β variant, were 4700 and 765, respectively, at week 6, the peak of primary response, and 644 and 553, respectively, at a 5-month post-vaccination memory time point. Two weeks following homologous or heterologous boost β-specific reciprocal ID&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; GMT were 5000 and 3000, respectively. At week 38, animals were challenged in the upper and lower airway with the β variant. Two days post-challenge, viral replication was low to undetectable in both BAL and nasal swabs in most of the boosted animals. These data show that boosting with the homologous mRNA-1273 vaccine six months after primary immunization provides up to a 20-fold increase in neutralizing antibody responses across all VOC, which may be required to sustain high-level protection against severe disease, especially for at-risk populations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;mRNA-1273 boosted nonhuman primates have increased immune responses and are protected against SARS-CoV-2 beta infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456015" rel="alternate" title="Protection against SARS-CoV-2 Beta Variant in mRNA-1273 Boosted Nonhuman Primates (13 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455942</id><title>A single shot of a hybrid hAdV5-based anti-COVID-19 vaccine induces a long-lasting immune response and broad coverage against VOC (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.832724+00:00</updated><author><name>M. Verónica López</name></author><author><name>Sabrina E. Vinzón</name></author><author><name>Eduardo G. A. Cafferata</name></author><author><name>Felipe J. Nuñez</name></author><author><name>Ariadna Soto</name></author><author><name>Maximiliano Sanchez-Lamas</name></author><author><name>Jimena Afonso</name></author><author><name>Diana Aguilar-Cortes</name></author><author><name>Gregorio D. Ríos</name></author><author><name>Juliana T. Maricato</name></author><author><name>Carla Torres-Braconi</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Barbosa-da Silveira</name></author><author><name>Tatiane Montes-de Andrade</name></author><author><name>Tatiana Carvalho-de Souza Bonetti</name></author><author><name>Luiz M. Ramos Janini</name></author><author><name>Manoel J. B. Castello Girão</name></author><author><name>Andrea S. Llera</name></author><author><name>Karina Gomez</name></author><author><name>Hugo H. Ortega</name></author><author><name>Paula M. Berguer</name></author><author><name>Osvaldo L. Podhajcer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Most approved vaccines against COVID-19 have to be administered in a prime/boost regimen. We engineered a novel vaccine based on a chimeric hAdV5 vector. The vaccine (named CoroVaxG.3) is based on three pillars: i) high expression of Spike to enhance its immunodominance by using a potent promoter and a mRNA stabilizer; ii) enhanced infection of muscle and dendritic cells by replacing the fiber knob domain of hAdV5 by hAdV3; iii) use of Spike stabilized in a prefusion conformation. Transduction with CoroVaxG.3 expressing Spike (D614G) dramatically enhanced Spike expression in human muscle cells, monocytes and dendritic cells compared to CoroVaxG.5 that expressed the native fiber knob domain. A single dose of CoroVaxG.3 induced potent humoral immunity with a balanced Th1/Th2 ratio and potent T-cell immunity, both lasting for at least 5 months. Sera from CoroVaxG.3 vaccinated mice was able to neutralize pseudoviruses expressing B.1 (wild type D614G), B.1.117 (alpha) and P.1 (gamma) Spikes, as well as an authentic WT and P.1 SARS-CoV-2 isolates. Neutralizing antibodies did not wane even after 5 months making this kind of vaccine a likely candidate to enter clinical trials&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455942" rel="alternate" title="A single shot of a hybrid hAdV5-based anti-COVID-19 vaccine induces a long-lasting immune response and broad coverage against VOC (13 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261462</id><title>Field performance of NowCheck Rapid antigen test for SARS-CoV-2 in Kisumu County, western Kenya (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.833224+00:00</updated><author><name>Simon N Onsongo</name></author><author><name>Kephas Otieno</name></author><author><name>Shannen van Duijn</name></author><author><name>Hellen Barsosio</name></author><author><name>Emily R Adams</name></author><author><name>Isdora Akoth</name></author><author><name>Corrie M Omollo</name></author><author><name>Alloys K'Oloo</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Houben</name></author><author><name>Emmanuel Milimo</name></author><author><name>Robert Aroka</name></author><author><name>Fredrick Oluoch</name></author><author><name>Albert Odhiambo</name></author><author><name>Simon Kariuki</name></author><author><name>Tobias F Rinke de Wit</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Abstract 
Background
Low- and middle-income countries (LMICs) are increasingly adopting low-cost Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) rapid antigen tests to meet the high demand for SARS-CoV-2 testing. Whilst testing using real-time polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) is the current gold standard, its widespread use in LMICs is limited by high costs, turnaround times and is not readily available in most places. COVID-19 antigen tests (Ag-RDT) provide a suitable alternative due to their low cost, rapid turnaround time and easy to set up and use. This study aimed to assess the field performance of the NowCheck COVID-19 antigen kit (Ag-RDT) as a point of care test (POCT) in select healthcare facilities in western Kenya.  
Methods
We conducted a prospective multi-facility field evaluation study of the NowCheck COVID-19 rapid antigen test (Ag-RDT) compared to SARS-CoV-2 RT-PCR (RT-PCR). After obtaining informed consent, trained laboratory technicians collected two pairs of oropharyngeal and nasopharyngeal swabs, both antigen and RT-PCR testing, first for Ag-RDT and next for RT-PCR. We performed Ag-RDTs on-site and shared the results with both the study participants and their healthcare providers within 15-30 minutes. We carried out all RT-PCR tests in a central referral laboratory. The turnaround time for RT-PCR results was typically 24-48 hours. We captured the results of both methods using an electronic digital application.
Findings
Between December 2020 and March 2021, we enrolled 997 participants who met the Kenyan Ministry of Health COVID-19 case definition. The median age of study participants was 39 years (range one to 80 years), with 54% male. Ag-RDT had a sensitivity of 84.5% (76.0-90.8) and a specificity of 94.4% (95% CI: 92.7-95.8) with an accuracy of 94.2% (92.5- 95.6) when a cycle threshold value (Ct value) of ≤35 was used. The highest sensitivity of 87.7% (77.2-94.5) was observed in samples with Ct values ≤ 30 and the highest specificity of 97.5% (96.2-98.5) at Ct value of &amp;lt;40. 
Interpretation
The NowCheck COVID-19 Ag-RDT showed good performance in field evaluation in multiple healthcare facilities in a developing country. The sensitivity of the kit exceeded the minimum recommended cut-off of 80% as recommended by WHO1.  The high specificity of this kit at 94.4% at Ct values ≤33 and 97.5% at Ct values &amp;lt;40 matched that of real-time PCR, making it a good rule-out test for symptomatic patients with COVID-19- like symptoms. The faster turnaround time to results, lower cost, simple analytical steps requiring no equipment or infrastructure makes antigen testing an attractive field-screening method to meet the high demand for COVID-19 testing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261462" rel="alternate" title="Field performance of NowCheck Rapid antigen test for SARS-CoV-2 in Kisumu County, western Kenya (12 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456154</id><title>Mechanisms of Coupling between Angiotensin Converting Enzyme 2 and Nicotinic Acetylcholine Receptors (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.833620+00:00</updated><author><name>Nadine Kabbani</name></author><author><name>Kyle D. Brumfield</name></author><author><name>Patricia Sinclair</name></author><author><name>Arvind Ramanathan</name></author><author><name>Menu Leddy</name></author><author><name>Rita R. Colwell</name></author><author><name>James L Olds</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), an RNA virus encapsulated by a spike (S) glycoprotein envelope, binds with high affinity to angiotensin converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) during cell entry of a susceptible host. Recent studies suggest nicotinic acetylcholine receptors (nAChRs) play a role in functional ACE2 regulation and nicotine may contribute to the progression of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). Here, we present evidence for coupling between ACE2 and nAChR through bioinformatic analysis and cell culture experiments. Following molecular and structural protein comparison of over 250 ACE2 vertebrate orthologues, a region of human ACE2 at positions C542-L554 was identified to have sequence similarity to nAChR-binding neurotoxin and rabies virus glycoproteins (RBVG). Furthermore, experiments conducted in PC12 cells indicate a potential for physical interaction between ACE2 and α7 nAChR proteins. Our findings support a model of nAChR involvement in in COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456154" rel="alternate" title="Mechanisms of Coupling between Angiotensin Converting Enzyme 2 and Nicotinic Acetylcholine Receptors (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.21261738</id><title>Beneficial Effects of novel Aureobasidium Pullulans strains produced Beta-1,3-1,6 Glucans on Interleukin-6 and D-Dimer levels in COVID-19 patients; results of a randomized multiple-arm pilot clinical study (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.833807+00:00</updated><author><name>Kadalraja Raghavan</name></author><author><name>Vidyasagar Devaprasad Dedeepiya</name></author><author><name>Vaddi Suryaprakash</name></author><author><name>Kosagi-Sharaf Rao</name></author><author><name>Nobunao Ikewaki</name></author><author><name>Tohru Sonoda</name></author><author><name>Gary A. Levy</name></author><author><name>Masaru Iwasaki</name></author><author><name>Rajappa Senthilkumar</name></author><author><name>Senthilkumar Preethy</name></author><author><name>Samuel JK Abraham</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Objective: Cytokine storm and Coagulopathy have been implicated as major causes of morbidity and mortality in COVID-19 patients. A black yeast Aureobasidium pullulans AFO 202 strain produced beta 1,3 1,6 glucan has been reported to offer potential immune enhancement and metabolism balancing, as well as mitigation of coagulopathy risks. The N 163 strain produced beta glucan is an efficient anti-inflammatory immune modulator. In this pilot clinical study, we report the beneficial effects of these two beta glucans on the biomarkers for cytokine storm and coagulopathy in COVID-19 patients.
Methods: A total of 24 RT PCR positive COVID 19 patients were recruited (Age range: 18~62; 17 males and 7 females). Patients were randomly divided into three groups (Gr): Gr. 1 control (n=8); Gr. 2: AFO-202 beta glucan (n=8); and Gr. 3, a combination of AFO-202 and N-163 beta glucans (n=8). All three groups received the standard care while groups 2 and 3 received additional supplementation of beta glucans for 30 days. In addition to basic clinical parameters, we periodically evaluated D Dimer, IL6, erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR), C reactive protein (CRP), the neutrophil to lymphocyte ratio (NLR), the lymphocyte to CRP ratio (LCR) and the leukocyte CRP ratio (LeCR). 
Results: The duration of hospital stay for all three groups was nearly equivalent. There was no mortality of the subjects in any of the groups. Intermittent oxygen was administered from day of admission for up to four to five days with mask (two to four Lpm) to two subjects in Gr. 2 and one subject in Gr. 3. None of the subjects required ventilation. The D Dimer values in Gr. 1, which was on average 751 ng/ml at baseline, decreased to 143.89 ng/ml on day 15, but increased to 202.5 ng/ml on day 30, which in groups 2 and 3 decreased on day 15 and continued to remain at normal levels until day 30. IL6 levels decreased on day 15 from an average of 7.395 pg/ml to 3.16 pg/ml in the control, 26.18 pg/ml to 6.94 pg/ml in Gr. 2 and 6.25 pg/ml to 5.22 pg/ml in Gr. 3. However, when measured on day 30, in Gr. 1, the IL-6 increased to 55.37 pg/ml while there was only slight marginal increase in Gr. 2 but within normal range, and the levels further decreased to less than 0.5 pg/ml in Gr. 3. The same trend was observed with ESR. LCR and LeCR increased significantly in Gr. 3. NLR decreased significantly in groups 2 and 3. There was no difference in CRP within the groups.
Conclusion:  In this exploratory study, consumption of Aureobasidium pullulans produced beta glucans for thirty days, results in a significant control of IL6, D Dimer and NLR, a significant increase in LCR, LeCR and marginal control of ESR in COVID 19 patients. As these beta glucans are well known food supplements with decades of a track record for safety, based on these results, we recommend larger multi-centric clinical studies to validate their use as an adjunct in the management of COVID-19 and the ensuing long COVID-19 syndrome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.21261738" rel="alternate" title="Beneficial Effects of novel Aureobasidium Pullulans strains produced Beta-1,3-1,6 Glucans on Interleukin-6 and D-Dimer levels in COVID-19 patients; results of a randomized multiple-arm pilot clinical study (10 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261929</id><title>Seroprevalence of anti-SARS-CoV-2 antibodies six months into the vaccination campaign in Geneva, Switzerland (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.834010+00:00</updated><author><name>Silvia Stringhini</name></author><author><name>María-Eugenia Zaballa</name></author><author><name>Nick Pullen</name></author><author><name>Javier Perez-Saez</name></author><author><name>Carlos de Mestral</name></author><author><name>Andrea Loizeau</name></author><author><name>Julien Lamour</name></author><author><name>Francesco Pennacchio</name></author><author><name>Ania Wisniak</name></author><author><name>Roxane Dumont</name></author><author><name>Hélène Baysson</name></author><author><name>Viviane Richard</name></author><author><name>Elsa Lorthe</name></author><author><name>Claire Semaani</name></author><author><name>Jean-François Balavoine</name></author><author><name>Didier Pittet</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Vuilleumier</name></author><author><name>François Chappuis</name></author><author><name>Omar Kherad</name></author><author><name>Andrew S Azman</name></author><author><name>Klara Posfay-Barbe</name></author><author><name>Laurent Kaiser</name></author><author><name>Idris Guessous</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Up-to-date seroprevalence estimates are critical to describe the SARS-CoV-2 immune landscape in the population and guide public health measures. We aimed to estimate the seroprevalence of anti-SARS-CoV-2 antibodies 15 months into the COVID-19 pandemic and six months into the vaccination campaign.
Methods: We conducted a population-based cross-sectional serosurvey between June 1 and July 7, 2021, recruiting participants from age- and sex-stratified random samples of the general population. We tested participants for anti-SARS-CoV-2 antibodies targeting the spike (S) or nucleocapsid (N) proteins (Roche Elecsys immunoassays). We estimated the anti-SARS-CoV-2 antibodies seroprevalence following vaccination and/or infection (anti-S antibodies), or infection only (anti-N antibodies).
Results: We included 3355 individuals, of which 1814 (54.1%) were women, 697 (20.8%) were aged &amp;lt;18 years and 449 (13.4%) were aged ≥65 years, 2161 (64.4%) tested positive for anti-S antibodies, and 906 (27.0%) tested positive for anti-N antibodies. The total seroprevalence of anti-SARS-CoV-2 antibodies was 66.1% (95% credible interval, 64.1-68.0). Considering the presence of anti-N antibodies, we estimated that 29.9% (28.0-31.9) of the population developed antibodies after infection; the rest having developed antibodies only via vaccination. Seroprevalence estimates were similar across sexes, but differed markedly across age groups, being lowest among children aged 0-5 years (20.8% [15.5-26.7]) and highest among older adults aged ≥75 years (93.1% [89.6-96.0]). Seroprevalence of antibodies developed via infection and/or vaccination was higher among participants with a higher educational level.
Conclusions: Most adults have developed anti-SARS-CoV-2 antibodies, while most teenagers and children remain vulnerable to infection. As the SARS-CoV-2 Delta variant spreads and vaccination rates stagnate, efforts are needed to address vaccine hesitancy, particularly among younger individuals and socioeconomically disadvantaged groups, and to minimize spread among children.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261929" rel="alternate" title="Seroprevalence of anti-SARS-CoV-2 antibodies six months into the vaccination campaign in Geneva, Switzerland (10 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261966</id><title>B and T cell responses after a third dose of SARS-CoV-2 vaccine in Kidney Transplant Recipients (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.834294+00:00</updated><author><name>Eva Schrezenmeier</name></author><author><name>Hector Rincon-Arevalo</name></author><author><name>Ana-Luisa Stefanski</name></author><author><name>Alexander Potekhin</name></author><author><name>Henriette Staub-Hohenbleicher</name></author><author><name>Mira Choi</name></author><author><name>Friederike Bachmann</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Pross</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Hammett</name></author><author><name>Hubert Schrezenmeier</name></author><author><name>Carolin Ludwig</name></author><author><name>Bernd Jahrsdörfer</name></author><author><name>Andreia C. Lino</name></author><author><name>Kai-Uwe Eckardt</name></author><author><name>Katja Kotsch</name></author><author><name>Thomas Dörner</name></author><author><name>Klemens Budde</name></author><author><name>Arne Sattler</name></author><author><name>Fabian Halleck</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accumulating evidence suggests that solid organ transplant recipients, as opposed to the general population, show strongly impaired responsiveness towards standard SARS-CoV-2 mRNA-based vaccination, demanding alternative strategies for protection of this vulnerable group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In line with recent recommendations, a third dose of either heterologous ChAdOx1 (AstraZeneca) or homologous BNT162b2 (BioNTech) was administered to 25 kidney transplant recipients (KTR) without humoral response after 2 doses of BNT162b2, followed by analysis of serological responses and vaccine-specific B- and T-cell immunity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;9/25 (36%) KTR under standard immunosuppressive treatment seroconverted until day 27 after the third vaccination, while one patient developed severe COVID-19 infection immediately after vaccination. Cellular analysis seven days after the third dose showed significantly elevated frequencies of viral spike protein receptor binding domain specific B cells in humoral responders as compared to non-responders. Likewise, portions of spike-reactive CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T helper cells were significantly elevated in seroconverting patients. Furthermore, overall frequencies of IL-2&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;, IL-4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and polyfunctional CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells significantly increased after the third dose, whereas memory/effector differentiation remained unaffected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our data suggest that a fraction of transplant recipients benefits from triple vaccination, where seroconversion is associated with quantitative and qualitative changes of cellular immunity. At the same time, the study highlights that modified vaccination approaches for immunosuppressed patients still remain an urgent medical need.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Protection of solid organ transplant recipients against SARS-Cov-2 by vaccination remains an unmet need given the low immunogenicity of available vaccines in the presence of immunosuppression. Administration of a third dose to 25 kidney transplant recipients (KTR) resulted in seroconversion in 36% of patients, associated with significant quantitative and functional changes within the spike-antigen-specific B-cell− and CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T-helper cell compartment. Our data support the need for individual humoral monitoring of immunosuppressed individuals after vaccination as well as continued efforts to adapt vaccination protocols for this at-risk group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261966" rel="alternate" title="B and T cell responses after a third dose of SARS-CoV-2 vaccine in Kidney Transplant Recipients (10 tweets)"/><category term="Nephrology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455627</id><title>An ultrapotent neutralizing bispecific antibody with broad spectrum against SARS-CoV-2 variants (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.834543+00:00</updated><author><name>Hui Zhang</name></author><author><name>Haohui Huang</name></author><author><name>Rong Li</name></author><author><name>Lu Zhang</name></author><author><name>Zhiwei Wang</name></author><author><name>Jiaping Li</name></author><author><name>Junyou Chen</name></author><author><name>Huafei Su</name></author><author><name>Dandan Zheng</name></author><author><name>Ziqi Su</name></author><author><name>Li Wang</name></author><author><name>Chunping Deng</name></author><author><name>shujun Pei</name></author><author><name>Shenghua Zhu</name></author><author><name>Chan Li</name></author><author><name>Yaochang Yuan</name></author><author><name>Haitao Yue</name></author><author><name>Yanqun Wang</name></author><author><name>Xiaobo Li</name></author><author><name>Cuihua Liu</name></author><author><name>Jinchen Yu</name></author><author><name>Hui Zhang</name></author><author><name>Shengfeng Li</name></author><author><name>Xianming Huang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In spite of the successful development of effective countermeasures against Covid-19, variants have and will continue to emerge that could compromise the efficacy of currently approved neutralizing antibodies and vaccines. Consequently, novel and more efficacious agents are urgently needed. We have developed a bispecific antibody, 2022, consisting of two antibodies, 2F8 and VHH18. 2F8 was isolated from our proprietary fully synthetic human IDEAL (Intelligently Designed and Engineered Antibody Library)-VH/VL library and VHH18 is a single domain antibody isolated from IDEAL-nanobody library. 2022 was constructed by attaching VHH18 to the C-terminal of Fc of 2F8. 2022 binds two non-overlapping epitopes simultaneously on the RBD of the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein and blocks the binding of RBD to human angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2). 2022 potently neutralizes SARS-CoV-2 and all of the variants tested in both pseudovirus and live virus assays, including variants carrying mutations known to resist neutralizing antibodies approved under EUA and that reduce the protection efficiency of current effective vaccines. The half-maximum inhibitory concentration (IC50) of 2022 is 270 pM, 30 pM, 20 pM, and 1 pM, for wild-type, alpha, beta, and delta pseudovirus, respectively. In the live virus assay, 2022 has an IC50 of 26.4 pM, 13.3 pM, and 88.6 pM, for wild-type, beta, and delta live virus, respectively. In a mouse model of SARS-CoV-2, 2022 showed strong prophylactic and therapeutic effects. A single administration of 2022 intranasal (i.n.) or intraperitoneal (i.p.) 24 hours before virus challenge completely protected all mice from bodyweight loss, as compared with up to 20% loss of bodyweight in placebo treated mice. In addition, the lung viral titers were undetectable (FRNT assay) in all mice treated with 2022 either prophylactically or therapeutically, as compared with around 1×10&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; pfu/g lung tissue in placebo treated mice. In summary, bispecific antibody 2022 showed potent binding and neutralizing activity across a variety of SARS-CoV-2 variants and could be an attractive weapon to combat the ongoing waves of the COVID-19 pandemic propagated mainly by variants, especially, the much more contagious delta variant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455627" rel="alternate" title="An ultrapotent neutralizing bispecific antibody with broad spectrum against SARS-CoV-2 variants (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261830</id><title>Diagnostic accuracy of rapid point-of-care tests for diagnosis of current SARS-CoV-2 infections in children: A systematic review and meta-analysis (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.834806+00:00</updated><author><name>Naomi Fujita-Rohwerder</name></author><author><name>Lars Beckmann</name></author><author><name>Yvonne Zens</name></author><author><name>Arpana Verma</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Objective: To systematically assess the diagnostic accuracy of rapid point-of-care tests for diagnosis of current SARS-CoV-2 infections in children under real-life conditions.

Study design: Multiple bibliographic databases including MEDLINE and Embase, clinical trial registries and further information sources were systematically searched for literature (last bibliographic search: May 7, 2021). Diagnostic cross-sectional or cohort studies that included paediatric study participants and evaluated rapid point-of care tests for diagnosing current SARS-CoV-2 infections against RT-PCR as the reference standard were eligible for inclusion. QUADAS-2 was used to assess the risk of bias and the applicability of the included studies. Bivariate meta-analyses with random effects were performed. Variability was assessed by subgroup analyses. 

Results: We included 17 studies with a total of 6355 paediatric study participants. All included studies compared antigen tests against RT-PCR. Only one study was at low risk of bias. The pooled overall diagnostic sensitivity and specificity in paediatric populations was 64.2% (95% CI: 57.4%-70.5%) and 99.1% (95% CI: 98.2%-99.5%), respectively. In symptomatic children, the pooled diagnostic sensitivity was 71.8% (95% CI: 63.6%-78.8%) and the pooled diagnostic specificity was 98.7% (95% CI: 96.6%-99.5%). The pooled diagnostic sensitivity in asymptomatic children was 56.2% (95% CI: 47.6%-64.4%) and the pooled diagnostic specificity was 98.6% (95% CI: 97.3%-99.3%). 

Conclusions: Performance of current antigen tests under real-life conditions varies broadly. Policymakers should especially be aware of the low diagnostic sensitivity of current antigen tests. Results should be interpreted with caution since risk of bias was predominantly judged as unclear due to poor reporting.

Study Registration: CRD42021236313 (PROSPERO).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261830" rel="alternate" title="Diagnostic accuracy of rapid point-of-care tests for diagnosis of current SARS-CoV-2 infections in children: A systematic review and meta-analysis (9 tweets)"/><category term="Pediatrics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.21261878</id><title>The influence of repeated mild lockdown on mental and physical health during the COVID-19 pandemic: a large-scale longitudinal study in Japan (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.834959+00:00</updated><author><name>Tetsuya Yamamoto</name></author><author><name>Chigusa Uchiumi</name></author><author><name>Naho Suzuki</name></author><author><name>Nagisa Sugaya</name></author><author><name>Eric Murillo-Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>S_rgio Machado</name></author><author><name>Claudio Imperatori</name></author><author><name>Henning Budde</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mental and physical effects of repeated lockdowns are unknown. We conducted a longitudinal study of the influence of repeated mild lockdowns during two emergency declarations in Japan, in May 2020 and February 2021. The analyses included 7,893 people who participated in all online surveys. During repeated mild lockdowns, mental and physical symptoms decreased overall, while loneliness increased and social networks decreased. Subgroup analyses revealed that depression and suicidal ideation did not decrease only in the younger age group (aged 18-29) and that younger and middle-aged people (aged 18-49), women, people with a history of treatment for mental illness, and people who were socially disadvantaged in terms of income had higher levels of mental and physical symptoms at all survey times. Additionally, comprehensive extraction of the interaction structure between depression, demographic attributes, and psychosocial variables indicated that loneliness and social networks were most closely associated with depression. These results indicate that repeated lockdowns have cumulative negative effects on interpersonal interaction and loneliness and that susceptible populations, such as young people and those with high levels of loneliness, require special consideration during repetitive lockdown situations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.21261878" rel="alternate" title="The influence of repeated mild lockdown on mental and physical health during the COVID-19 pandemic: a large-scale longitudinal study in Japan (9 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456190</id><title>Screening of cell-virus, cell-cell, gene-gene interactions among kingdoms of life at single cell resolution (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.835132+00:00</updated><author><name>Dongsheng Chen</name></author><author><name>Zhihua Ou</name></author><author><name>Jiacheng Zhu</name></author><author><name>Peiwen Ding</name></author><author><name>Haoyu Wang</name></author><author><name>Lihua Luo</name></author><author><name>Xiangning Ding</name></author><author><name>Tianming Lan</name></author><author><name>Weiying Wu</name></author><author><name>Yuting Yuan</name></author><author><name>Wendi Wu</name></author><author><name>Jiaying Qiu</name></author><author><name>Yixin Zhu</name></author><author><name>Yi Jia</name></author><author><name>Yanan Wei</name></author><author><name>Qiuyu Qin</name></author><author><name>Runchu Li</name></author><author><name>Chengcheng Sun</name></author><author><name>Wandong Zhao</name></author><author><name>Zhiyuan Lv</name></author><author><name>Mingyi Pu</name></author><author><name>Shangchen Yang</name></author><author><name>Ashley Chang</name></author><author><name>Xiaofeng Wei</name></author><author><name>Fengzhen Chen</name></author><author><name>Tao Yang</name></author><author><name>Zhenyong Wei</name></author><author><name>Fan Yang</name></author><author><name>Yuejiao Li</name></author><author><name>Yan Hua</name></author><author><name>Huan Liu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The outbreak of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) issued a significant and urgent threat to global health. The exact animal origin of SARS-CoV-2 remains obscure and understanding its host range is vital for preventing interspecies transmission of this virus. Previously, we have assessed the target cell profiles of SARS-CoV-2 in pets, livestock, poultry and wild animals. With the reverse zoonotic transmission of SARS-CoV-2 to farm animals. Herein, we expand this investigation to a wider range of animal species and viruses to provide it is urgent to expand the a comprehensive source for large-scale susceptible host screening of potential virus hosts to a larger scale. Therefore, we constructed the single cell atlas for several representative mammalian species (alpaca, hamster, hedgehog, chinchilla etc.), as well as comparative atlas for lung, brain and peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) for various lineages of animals were constructed, from which we systemically analyzed the virus entry factors for SARS-CoV-2 to identify potential host species. Moreover, to fully apply these resources to the prevention of other infectious diseases, we further evaluated the target cells for 113 viruses over 10 million single cells covering 102 species from mammalians, birds, reptiles, amphibians and invertebrates. Conserved cellular connectomes and regulomes were also identified, with great implication for revealing the fundamental cell-cell and gene-gene cross-talks between these species. Overall, our study could help understand the transmission identify the potential host range and tissue tropism of SARS-CoV-2 and, as well as many other diverse set of viruses and, revealing the host-virus co-evolution footprints and throw light upon the control and prevention of current and future pandemics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456190" rel="alternate" title="Screening of cell-virus, cell-cell, gene-gene interactions among kingdoms of life at single cell resolution (9 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261981</id><title>COVID-19 vaccine uptake among older people in relation to sociodemographic factors: cohort results from southern Sweden (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.835471+00:00</updated><author><name>Malin Inghammar</name></author><author><name>Mahnaz Moghaddassi</name></author><author><name>Magnus Rasmussen</name></author><author><name>Ulf Malmqvist</name></author><author><name>Fredrik Kahn</name></author><author><name>Jonas Bjork</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The aim of this cohort study was to investigate sociodemographic determinants of COVID-19 vaccine uptake in the 70+ age group in Skane county, Sweden (n = 216 243 at baseline). Uptake of the first dose was high (91.9%) overall, but markedly lower (75.3%) among persons born outside the Nordic countries. Vaccine uptake was generally satisfactory among native Swedes also in areas with lower socioeconomic status, but dropped substantially among non-Nordic born in those areas. The identified clusters of unvaccinated older people, mainly representing ethnic minorities in disadvantaged areas, warrants intensified efforts regarding tailored communication, easier vaccine access and local engagement.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261981" rel="alternate" title="COVID-19 vaccine uptake among older people in relation to sociodemographic factors: cohort results from southern Sweden (8 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261987</id><title>Characterising the persistence of RT-PCR positivity and incidence in a community survey of SARS-CoV-2 (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.835640+00:00</updated><author><name>Oliver Eales</name></author><author><name>Caroline E. Walters</name></author><author><name>Haowei Wang</name></author><author><name>David Haw</name></author><author><name>Kylie E. C. Ainslie</name></author><author><name>Christina Atchinson</name></author><author><name>Andrew Page</name></author><author><name>Sophie Prosolek</name></author><author><name>Alexander J. Trotter</name></author><author><name>Thanh Le Viet</name></author><author><name>Nabil-Fareed Alikhan</name></author><author><name>Leigh M Jackson</name></author><author><name>Catherine Ludden</name></author><author><name>Deborah Ashby</name></author><author><name>Christl A Donnelly</name></author><author><name>Graham Cooke</name></author><author><name>Wendy Barclay</name></author><author><name>Helen Ward</name></author><author><name>Ara Darzi</name></author><author><name>Paul Elliott</name></author><author><name>Steven Riley</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background
Community surveys of SARS-CoV-2 RT-PCR swab-positivity provide prevalence estimates largely unaffected by biases from who presents for routine case testing. The REal-time Assessment of Community Transmission-1(REACT-1) has estimated swab-positivity approximately monthly since May 2020 in England from RT-PCR testing of self-administered throat and nose swabs in random non-overlapping cross-sectional community samples. Estimating infection incidence from swab-positivity requires an understanding of the persistence of RT-PCR swab positivity in the community.

Methods
During round 8 of REACT-1 from 6 January to 22 January 2021, of the 2,282 participants who tested RT-PCR positive, we recruited 896 (39%)  from whom we collected up to two additional swabs for RT-PCR approximately 6 and 9 days after the initial swab. We estimated sensitivity and duration of positivity using an exponential model of positivity decay, for all participants and for subsets by initial N-gene cycle threshold (Ct) value, symptom status, lineage and age. Estimates of infection incidence were obtained for the entire duration of the REACT-1 study using P-splines. 

Results 
We estimated the overall sensitivity of REACT-1 to detect virus on a single swab as 0.79 (0.77, 0.81) and median duration of positivity following a positive test as 9.7 (8.9, 10.6) days. We found greater median duration of positivity where there was a low N-gene Ct value, in those exhibiting symptoms, or for infection with the Alpha variant. The estimated proportion of positive individuals detected on first swab, P0, was found to be higher for those with an initially low N-gene Ct value and those who were pre-symptomatic. When compared to swab-positivity, estimates of infection incidence over the duration of REACT-1 included sharper features with evident transient increases around the time of key changes in social distancing measures.

Discussion
Home self-swabbing for RT-PCR based on a single swab, as implemented in REACT-1, has high overall sensitivity. However, participants' time-since-infection,  symptom status and viral lineage affect the probability of detection and the duration of positivity. These results validate previous efforts to estimate incidence of SARS-CoV-2 from swab-positivity data, and provide a reliable means to obtain community infection estimates to inform policy response.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261987" rel="alternate" title="Characterising the persistence of RT-PCR positivity and incidence in a community survey of SARS-CoV-2 (8 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456012</id><title>In vitro determination of inhibitory effects by humic substances complexing Zn and Se on SARS-CoV-2 virus replication (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.835895+00:00</updated><author><name>Bernadett Pályi</name></author><author><name>Zoltán Kis</name></author><author><name>Polett Hajdrik</name></author><author><name>Noémi Kovács</name></author><author><name>Daniel S. Veres</name></author><author><name>Krisztián Szigeti</name></author><author><name>Imre Hegedűs</name></author><author><name>Tibor Kovács</name></author><author><name>Ralf Bergmann</name></author><author><name>Domokos Máthé</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Humic substances are well known human nutritional supplement materials and play important performance-enhancing roles as animal feed additives, too. For decades, ingredients of humic substances have also been proven to carry potent antiviral effects against different viruses. Here, the antiviral activity of a humic substance containing ascorbic acid, Se&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt; and Zn&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; ions intended as a nutritional supplement material was investigated against SARS-CoV-2 virus B1.1.7 Variant of Concern (“Alpha Variant”) in a VeroE6 cell line. Results show that this combination has a significant &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; antiviral effect at a very low concentration range of its intended active ingredients. Even picomolar concentration ranges of humic substances, vitamin C and Zn/Se ions in the given composition were enough to achieve fifty percent viral replication inhibition in the applied SARS-CoV-2 virus inhibition test.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456012" rel="alternate" title="In vitro determination of inhibitory effects by humic substances complexing Zn and Se on SARS-CoV-2 virus replication (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456258</id><title>Covid-19 vaccine immunogenicity in people living with HIV-1 (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.836085+00:00</updated><author><name>Lauriane Nault</name></author><author><name>Lorie Marchitto</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Goyette</name></author><author><name>Daniel Tremblay-Sher</name></author><author><name>Claude Fortin</name></author><author><name>Valerie Martel-Laferriere</name></author><author><name>Benoit Trottier</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Richard</name></author><author><name>Madeleine Durand</name></author><author><name>Daniel E Kaufmann</name></author><author><name>Andres Finzi</name></author><author><name>Cecile Tremblay</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Introduction:  COVID-19 vaccine efficacy has been evaluated in large clinical trials and in real-world situation. Although they have proven to be very effective in the general population, little is known about their efficacy in immunocompromised patients. HIV-infected individuals response to vaccine may vary according to the type of vaccine and their level of immunosuppression. We evaluated immunogenicity of an mRNA anti-SARS CoV-2 vaccine in HIV-positive individuals.
Methods: HIV-positive individuals (n=121) were recruited from HIV clinics in Montreal and stratified according to their CD4 counts. A control group of 20 health care workers naive to SARS CoV-2 was used. The participants Anti-RBD IgG responses were measured by ELISA at baseline and 3 to 4 weeks after receiving the first dose of an mRNA vaccine.
Results: Eleven of 121 participants had anti-COVID-19 antibodies at baseline, and a further 4 had incomplete data for the analysis. Mean anti-RBD IgG responses were similar between between the HIV negative control group (n=20) and the combined HIV+ group (n=106) (p = 0.72). However, these responses were significantly lower in the group with &amp;lt;250 CD4 cells/mm3. (p&amp;lt;0.0001). Increasing age was independently associated with decreased immunogenicity.
Conclusion: HIV-positive individuals with CD4 counts over 250 cells/mm3 have an anti-RBD IgG response similar to the general population. However, HIV-positive individuals with the lowest CD4 counts (&amp;lt;250 cells/mm3) have a weaker response. These data would support the hypothesis that a booster dose might be needed in this subgroup of HIV-positive individuals, depending on their response to the second dose.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456258" rel="alternate" title="Covid-19 vaccine immunogenicity in people living with HIV-1 (7 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261946</id><title>A Novel Convolutional Neural Network for COVID-19 detection and classification using Chest X-Ray images (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.836503+00:00</updated><author><name>Muhammad Talha Nafees</name></author><author><name>Irshad ullah</name></author><author><name>Muhammad Rizwan</name></author><author><name>Maaz ullah</name></author><author><name>Muhammad Irfanullah Khan</name></author><author><name>Muhammad Farhan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The early and rapid diagnosis of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS CoV-2), the main cause of fatal pandemic coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), with the analysis of patients chest X-ray (CXR) images has lifesaving importance for both patients and medical professionals. In this research a very simple novel and robust deep-learning convolutional neural network (CNN) model with less number of trainable-parameters is proposed to assist the radiologists and physicians in the early detection of COVID-19 patients. It also helps to classify patients into COVID-19, pneumonia and normal on the bases of analysis of augmented X-ray images. This augmented dataset contains 4803 COVID-19 from 686 publicly available chest X-ray images along with 5000 normal and 5000 pneumonia samples. These images are divided into 80% training and 20 % validation. The proposed CNN model is trained on training dataset and then tested on validation dataset. This model has a promising performance with a mean accuracy of 92.29%, precision of 99.96%, Specificity of 99.85% along with Sensitivity value of 85.92%. The result can further be improved if more data of expert radiologist is publically available.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261946" rel="alternate" title="A Novel Convolutional Neural Network for COVID-19 detection and classification using Chest X-Ray images (6 tweets)"/><category term="Radiology and Imaging"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261898</id><title>Association of Naive B Cells with Humoral Response to SARS-CoV-2 Vaccination (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.836713+00:00</updated><author><name>Eduard Schulz</name></author><author><name>Isabel Hodl</name></author><author><name>Patrick Forstner</name></author><author><name>Stefan Hatzl</name></author><author><name>Nazanin Sareban</name></author><author><name>Martina Moritz</name></author><author><name>Johannes Fessler</name></author><author><name>Barbara Dreo</name></author><author><name>Barbara Uhl</name></author><author><name>Claudia Url</name></author><author><name>Andrea Grisold</name></author><author><name>Michael Khalil</name></author><author><name>Barbara Kleinhappl</name></author><author><name>Christian Enzinger</name></author><author><name>Martin Helmut Stradner</name></author><author><name>Hildegard Greinix</name></author><author><name>Peter Schlenke</name></author><author><name>Ivo Steinmetz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Objectives 
Immunocompromised patients are at risk of severe coronavirus disease 2019 and are considered a high priority for severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) vaccination. Humoral vaccination response is impaired in these patients when circulating B cells are lacking. We aimed to analyze B-cell subsets at the time of vaccination to identify potential predictors of humoral vaccination response. 
Methods 
Patients (n=120) receiving B-cell-depleting therapy (n=41), those suffering from inborn errors of immunity (n=25) and hematologic malignancies (n=56), and healthy controls (n=79) were vaccinated twice with BNT162b2 or mRNA 1273. B-cell subsets were analyzed prior to vaccination. Two independent anti-SARS-CoV-2 S immunoassays targeting the receptor-binding domain (RBD) or trimeric S protein (TSP) were performed three to four weeks after the second vaccination.
Results 
Seroconversion occurred in 100% of the healthy controls, in contrast to 67% (RBD) and 82% (TSP) of the patients, while only 32% (RBD) and 22% (TSP) achieved antibody levels comparable to those of healthy controls. The number of circulating naive B cell was strongly associated with antibody levels (r=0.761, P&amp;lt;0.001) across all immunosuppressive treatments or conditions. In multivariable analysis, the number of naive B cells was an independent predictor for achieving antibody levels comparable to healthy controls, and receiver operating characteristic analysis predicted that at least six naive B cells per microL were required.
Conclusions 
Assessing the abundance of naive B cells in immunocompromised patients could be useful in predicting the optimal vaccination response.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261898" rel="alternate" title="Association of Naive B Cells with Humoral Response to SARS-CoV-2 Vaccination (6 tweets)"/><category term="Rheumatology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261976</id><title>The production of anti-PF4 antibodies in anti-phospholipid antibody-positive patients is not affected by COVID-19 vaccination (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.836959+00:00</updated><author><name>Paola Lonati</name></author><author><name>Caterina Bodio</name></author><author><name>Mariangela Scavone</name></author><author><name>Giuliana Martini</name></author><author><name>Elisa Pesce</name></author><author><name>Alessandra Bandera</name></author><author><name>Andrea Lombardi</name></author><author><name>Maria Gerosa</name></author><author><name>Franco Franceschini</name></author><author><name>Angela Tincani</name></author><author><name>Gianmarco Podda</name></author><author><name>Sergio Abrignani</name></author><author><name>Renata Grifantini</name></author><author><name>Marco Cattaneo</name></author><author><name>Maria Orietta Borghi</name></author><author><name>Pier Luigi Meroni</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antibodies against cationic platelet chemokine, platelet factor 4 (PF4/CXCL4) have been described in heparin-induced thrombocytopenia (HIT) but also in patients positive for anti-phospholipid antibodies (aPL) even in the absence of heparin treatment and HIT-related clinical manifestations. Anti-PF4 antibodies have been recently described also in subjects who developed thrombosis with thrombocytopenia syndrome (TTS) in association with adenoviral vector-based, but not with mRNA-based COVID-19 vaccines. 
We investigated whether COVID-19 vaccination affects the production of anti-PF4 immunoglobulins detectable by solid-phase assay in aPL-positive patients and their ability to induce in vitro platelet activation. Anti-PF4 were found in 9/126 aPL-positive patients, 4/50 COVID-19, 9/49 other infections, and 1/50 aPL-negative systemic lupus erythematosus patients. Clinical manifestations of TTS were not observed in any aPL patient positive for anti-PF4, whose sera failed to cause platelet aggregations. The administration of COVID-19 vaccines did not affect the production of anti-PF4 immunoglobulins or their ability to cause platelet aggregation in 44 aPL-positive patients tested before and after vaccination. In conclusion, heparin treatment-independent anti-PF4 antibodies can be found in aPL-positive patients and asymptomatic carriers, but their presence, titer as well as in vitro effect on platelet activation are not affected by COVID-19 vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261976" rel="alternate" title="The production of anti-PF4 antibodies in anti-phospholipid antibody-positive patients is not affected by COVID-19 vaccination (6 tweets)"/><category term="Rheumatology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261932</id><title>Mathematical modeling of vaccination rollout and NPIs lifting on COVID-19 transmission with VOC: a case study in Toronto, Canada (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.837281+00:00</updated><author><name>Elena Aruffo</name></author><author><name>Pei Yuan</name></author><author><name>Yi Tan</name></author><author><name>Evgenia Gatov</name></author><author><name>Iain Moyles</name></author><author><name>Jacques Belair</name></author><author><name>James Watmough</name></author><author><name>Sarah Collier</name></author><author><name>Julien Arino</name></author><author><name>Huaiping Zhu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;ABSTRACT 
Background: Since December 2020, public health agencies have implemented a variety of vaccination strategies to curb the spread of SARS-CoV-2, along with pre-existing Nonpharmaceutical Interventions (NPIs). Initial strategy focused on vaccinating the elderly to prevent hospitalizations and deaths. With vaccines becoming available to the broader population, we aimed to determine the optimal strategy to enable the safe lifting of NPIs while avoiding virus resurgence. 
Methods: We developed a compartmental deterministic SEIR model to simulate the lifting of NPIs under different vaccination rollout scenarios. Using case and vaccination data from Toronto, Canada between December 28, 2020 and May 19, 2021, we estimated transmission throughout past stages of NPI escalation/relaxation to compare the impact of lifting NPIs on different dates on cases, hospitalizations, and deaths, given varying degrees of vaccine coverages by 20-year age groups, accounting for waning immunity.  
Results: We found that, once coverage among the elderly is high enough (80% with at least one dose), the main age groups to target are 20-39 and 40-59 years, whereby first-dose coverage of at least 70% by mid-June 2021 is needed to minimize the possibility of resurgence if NPIs are to be lifted in the summer. While a resurgence was observed for every scenario of NPI lifting, we also found that under an optimistic vaccination coverage (70% by mid-June, postponing reopening from August 2021 to September 2021can reduce case counts and severe outcomes by roughly 80% by December 31, 2021. 
Conclusions: Our results suggest that focusing the vaccination strategy on the working-age population can curb the spread of SARS-CoV-2. However, even with high vaccination coverage in adults, lifting NPIs to pre-pandemic levels is not advisable since a resurgence is expected to occur, especially with earlier reopening.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261932" rel="alternate" title="Mathematical modeling of vaccination rollout and NPIs lifting on COVID-19 transmission with VOC: a case study in Toronto, Canada (6 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.21261290</id><title>Immune Correlates Analysis of the mRNA-1273 COVID-19 Vaccine Efficacy Trial (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.837637+00:00</updated><author><name>Peter B. Gilbert</name></author><author><name>David C. Montefiori</name></author><author><name>Adrian McDermott</name></author><author><name>Youyi Fong</name></author><author><name>David C. Benkeser</name></author><author><name>Weiping Deng</name></author><author><name>Honghong Zhou</name></author><author><name>Christopher R. Houchens</name></author><author><name>Karen Martins</name></author><author><name>Lakshmi Jayashankar</name></author><author><name>Flora Castellino</name></author><author><name>Britta Flach</name></author><author><name>Bob C. Lin</name></author><author><name>Sarah O'Connell</name></author><author><name>Charlene McDanal</name></author><author><name>Amanda Eaton</name></author><author><name>Marcella Sarzotti-Kelsoe</name></author><author><name>Yiwen Lu</name></author><author><name>Chenchen Yu</name></author><author><name>Bhavesh Borate</name></author><author><name>Lars W. P. van der Laan</name></author><author><name>Nima Hejazi</name></author><author><name>Chuong Huynh</name></author><author><name>Jacqueline Miller</name></author><author><name>Hana M. El Sahly</name></author><author><name>Lindsey R. Baden</name></author><author><name>Mira Baron</name></author><author><name>Luis De La Cruz</name></author><author><name>Cynthia Gay</name></author><author><name>Spyros Kalams</name></author><author><name>Colleen F. Kelley</name></author><author><name>Mark Kutner</name></author><author><name>Michele P. Andrasik</name></author><author><name>James G. Kublin</name></author><author><name>Lawrence Corey</name></author><author><name>Kathleen M. Neuzil</name></author><author><name>Lindsay N. Carpp</name></author><author><name>Rolando Pajon</name></author><author><name>Dean Follmann</name></author><author><name>Ruben O. Donis</name></author><author><name>Richard A. Koup</name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: In the Coronavirus Efficacy (COVE) trial, estimated mRNA-1273 vaccine efficacy against coronavirus disease-19 (COVID-19) was 94%. SARS-CoV-2 antibody measurements were assessed as correlates of COVID-19 risk and as correlates of protection. 
Methods: Through case-cohort sampling, participants were selected for measurement of four serum antibody markers at Day 1 (first dose), Day 29 (second dose), and Day 57: IgG binding antibodies (bAbs) to Spike, bAbs to Spike receptor-binding domain (RBD), and 50% and 80% inhibitory dilution pseudovirus neutralizing antibody titers calibrated to the WHO International Standard (cID50 and cID80).  Participants with no evidence of previous SARS-CoV-2 infection were included.   Cox regression assessed in vaccine recipients the association of each Day 29 or 57 serologic marker with COVID-19 through 126 or 100 days of follow-up, respectively, adjusting for risk factors.
Results: Day 57 Spike IgG, RBD IgG, cID50, and cID80 neutralization levels were each inversely correlated with risk of COVID-19: hazard ratios 0.66 (95% CI 0.50, 0.88; p=0.005); 0.57 (0.40, 0.82; p=0.002); 0.42 (0.27, 0.65; p&amp;lt;0.001); 0.35 (0.20, 0.61; p&amp;lt;0.001) per 10-fold increase in marker level, respectively, multiplicity adjusted P-values 0.003-0.010. Results were similar for Day 29 markers (multiplicity adjusted P-values &amp;lt;0.001-0.003).  For vaccine recipients with Day 57 reciprocal cID50 neutralization titers that were undetectable (&amp;lt;2.42), 100, or 1000, respectively, cumulative incidence of COVID-19 through 100 days post Day 57 was 0.030 (0.010, 0.093), 0.0056 (0.0039, 0.0080), and 0.0023 (0.0013, 0.0036).  For vaccine recipients at these titer levels, respectively, vaccine efficacy was 50.8% (-51.2, 83.0%), 90.7% (86.7, 93.6%), and 96.1% (94.0, 97.8%).  Causal mediation analysis estimated that the proportion of vaccine efficacy mediated through Day 29 cID50 titer was 68.5% (58.5, 78.4%). 
Conclusions:  Binding and neutralizing antibodies correlated with COVID-19 risk and vaccine efficacy and likely have utility in predicting mRNA-1273 vaccine efficacy against COVID-19. 
Trial registration number: COVE ClinicalTrials.gov number, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT04470427"&gt;NCT04470427&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.21261290" rel="alternate" title="Immune Correlates Analysis of the mRNA-1273 COVID-19 Vaccine Efficacy Trial (6 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.21261777</id><title>Testing Denmark: A Danish nationwide surveillance study of COVID-19 (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.838482+00:00</updated><author><name>Kamille Fogh</name></author><author><name>Jarl E Strange</name></author><author><name>Bibi FSS Scharff</name></author><author><name>Alexandra RR Eriksen</name></author><author><name>Rasmus B Hasselbalch</name></author><author><name>Henning Bundgaard</name></author><author><name>Susanne D Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Charlotte S Joergensen</name></author><author><name>Christian Erikstrup</name></author><author><name>Jakob Norsk</name></author><author><name>Pernille B Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Jonas H Kristensen</name></author><author><name>Lars Oestergaard</name></author><author><name>Svend Ellermann-Eriksen</name></author><author><name>Berit Andersen</name></author><author><name>Henrik Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Isik S Johansen</name></author><author><name>Lothar Wiese</name></author><author><name>Lone Simonsen</name></author><author><name>Thea K Fischer</name></author><author><name>Fredrik Folke</name></author><author><name>Freddy Lippert</name></author><author><name>Sisse R Ostrowski</name></author><author><name>Thomas Benfield</name></author><author><name>Kaare Moelbak</name></author><author><name>Steen Ethelberg</name></author><author><name>Anders Koch</name></author><author><name>Ute W Sonksen</name></author><author><name>Anne-Marie Vangsted</name></author><author><name>Tyra Grove Krause</name></author><author><name>Anders Formsgaard</name></author><author><name>Henrik Ullum</name></author><author><name>Robert Skov</name></author><author><name>Kasper Iversen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background
National data on the spread of SARS-CoV-2 infection and knowledge on associated risk factors are important for understanding the course of the pandemic. Testing Denmark is a national large-scale epidemiological surveillance study of SARS-CoV-2 in the Danish population. 

Methods
Between September and October 2020, approximately 1.3 million of 5.8 million Danish citizens (age &amp;gt; 15 years) were randomly invited to fill in an electronic questionnaire covering COVID-19 exposures and symptoms. The prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 antibodies was determined by Point-of Care rapid Test (POCT) distributed to participants home addresses. 

Findings
In total 318,552 participants (24.5% invitees) completed the questionnaire and provided the result of the POCT. Of these, 2,519 (0.79%) were seropositive (median age 55 years) and women were more often seropositive than men, interquartile range (IQR) 42-64, 40.2% males. Of participants with a prior positive Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) test (n=1,828), 29.1% were seropositive in the POCT. Seropositivity increased with age irrespective of sex. Elderly participants (&amp;gt;61 years) reported less symptoms and had less frequently been tested for SARS-CoV-2 compared to younger participants. Seropositivity was associated with physical contact with SARS-CoV-2 infected individuals (Risk ratio (RR) 7.43, 95% CI: 6.57-8.41) and in particular household members (RR 17.70, 95% CI: 15.60-20.10). Home care workers had a higher risk of seropositivity (RR 2.09 (95% CI: 1.58-2.78) as compared to office workers. Geographic population density was not associated to seropositivity. A high degree of compliance with national preventive recommendations was reported (e.g., &amp;gt; 80% use of face masks), but no difference was found between seropositive and seronegative participants.

Interpretation
This study provides insight into the immunity of the Danish population seven to eight months after the first COVID-19 case in Denmark. The seroprevalence was lower than expected probably due to a low sensitivity of the POCT used or due to challenges relating to the reading of test results. Occupation or exposure in local communities were major routes of infection. As elderly participants were more often seropositive despite fewer symptoms and less PCR tests performed, more emphasis should be placed on testing this age group.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.21261777" rel="alternate" title="Testing Denmark: A Danish nationwide surveillance study of COVID-19 (6 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.21262002</id><title>How did people cope during the COVID-19 pandemic? A Structural Topic Modelling Analysis of Free-Text Data from 11,000 UK Adults (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.839036+00:00</updated><author><name>Liam Wright</name></author><author><name>Meg E Fluharty</name></author><author><name>Andrew Steptoe</name></author><author><name>Daisy Fancourt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: The COVID-19 pandemic has had substantial impacts on lives across the globe. Job losses have been widespread, and individuals have experienced significant restrictions on their usual activities, including extended isolation from family and friends. While studies suggest population mental health worsened from before the pandemic, not all individuals appear to have experienced poorer mental health. This raises the question of how people managed to cope during the pandemic. Methods: To understand the coping strategies individuals employed during the COVID-19 pandemic, we used structural topic modelling, a text mining technique, to extract themes from free-text data on coping from over 11,000 UK adults, collected between 14 October and 26 November 2020. Results: We identified 16 topics. The most discussed coping strategy was 'thinking positively' and involved themes of gratefulness and positivity. Other strategies included engaging in activities and hobbies (such as doing DIY, exercising, walking and spending time in nature), keeping routines, and focusing on one day at a time. Some participants reported more avoidant coping strategies, such as drinking alcohol and binge eating. Coping strategies varied by respondent characteristics including age, personality traits and sociodemographic characteristics and some coping strategies, such as engaging in creative activities, were associated with more positive lockdown experiences. Conclusion: A variety of coping strategies were employed by individuals during the COVID-19 pandemic. The coping strategy an individual adopted was related to their overall lockdown experiences. This may be useful for helping individuals prepare for future lockdowns or other events resulting in self-isolation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.21262002" rel="alternate" title="How did people cope during the COVID-19 pandemic? A Structural Topic Modelling Analysis of Free-Text Data from 11,000 UK Adults (5 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455903</id><title>Structural Differences In 3C-like protease (Mpro) From SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2: Molecular Insights For Drug Repurposing Against COVID-19 Revealed by Molecular Dynamics Simulations (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.839318+00:00</updated><author><name>Meet Parmar</name></author><author><name>Ritik Thumar</name></author><author><name>Bhumi Patel</name></author><author><name>Mohd Athar</name></author><author><name>Prakash C. Jha</name></author><author><name>Dhaval Patel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A recent fatal outbreak of novel coronavirus SARS-CoV-2, identified preliminary as a causative agent for series of unusual pneumonia cases in Wuhan city, China has infected more than 20 million individuals with more than 4 million mortalities. Since, the infection crossed geographical barriers, the WHO permanently named the causing disease as COVID-2019 by declaring it a pandemic situation. SARS-CoV-2 is an enveloped single-stranded RNA virus causing a wide range of pathological conditions from common cold symptoms to pneumonia and fatal severe respiratory syndrome. Genome sequencing of SARS-CoV-2 has revealed 96% identity to the bat coronavirus and 79.6% sequence identity to the previous SARS-CoV. The main protease (known as 3C-like proteinase/ Mpro) plays a vital role during the infection with the processing of replicase polyprotein thus offering an attractive target for therapeutic interventions. SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 Mpro shares 97% sequence identity, with 12 variable residues but none of them present in the catalytic and substrate binding site. With the high level of sequence and structural similarity and absence of any drug/vaccine against SARS-CoV-2, drug repurposing against Mpro is an effective strategy to combat COVID-19. Here, we report a detailed comparison of SARS-CoV-2 Mpro with SARS-CoV Mpro using molecular dynamics simulations to assess the impact of 12 divergent residues on the molecular microenvironment of Mpro. A structural comparison and analysis is made on how these variable residues affects the intra-molecular interactions between key residues in the monomer and biologically active dimer form of Mpro. The present MD simulations study concluded the change in microenvironment of active-site residues at the entrance (T25, T26, M49 and Q189), near the catalytic region (F140, H163, H164, M165 and H172) and other residues in substrate binding site (V35T, N65S, K88R and N180K) due to 12 mutation incorporated in the SARS-CoV-2 Mpro. It is also evident that SARS-CoV-2 dimer is more stable and less flexible state compared to monomer which may be due to these variable residues, mainly F140, E166 and H172 which are involved in dimerization. This also warrants a need for inhibitor design considering the more stable dimer form. The mutation accumulated in SARS-CoV-2 Mpro indirectly reconfigures the key molecular networks around the active site conferring a potential change in SARS-CoV-2, thus posing a challenge in drug repurposing SARS drugs for COVID-19. The new networks and changes in microenvironment identified by our work might guide attempts needed for repurposing and identification of new Mpro inhibitors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455903" rel="alternate" title="Structural Differences In 3C-like protease (Mpro) From SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2: Molecular Insights For Drug Repurposing Against COVID-19 Revealed by Molecular Dynamics Simulations (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261829</id><title>The role of incentives in deciding to receive the available COVID-19 vaccine (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.839659+00:00</updated><author><name>Liora Shmueli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Objective: To assess the public intention to get vaccinated immediately after COVID-19 vaccine became available, and to determine the role of incentives beyond socio-demographic, health-related and behavioral factors, in predicting this intention.
Methods: An online survey was conducted among adults in Israel (n=461), immediately after the first COVID-19 vaccine became available (22/12/2020 to 10/1/2021). Two regressions were performed to investigate determinants of intention to receive the available COVID-19 vaccine and sense of urgency to receive the vaccine. 
Results: Although many adults were willing to receive available COVID-19 vaccine, only 65% were willing to immediately receive the vaccine, 16% preferred to wait 3 months and 18% preferred to wait a year. The sense of urgency to get vaccinated differed by age, periphery level, perceived barriers, cues to action and availability. Incentives such as monetary rewards or the green pass did not increase the probability of getting vaccination immediately.
Conclusions: Providing data on the role of incentives in increasing the intention to immediately receive the available COVID-19 vaccine is important for health policy makers and healthcare providers. Our findings underscore the importance of COVID-19 vaccine accessibility. 
Practice Implications: Health policy makers should consider allocating funds for making the vaccine accessible and encourage methods of persuasion, instead of investing funds in monetary incentives.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261829" rel="alternate" title="The role of incentives in deciding to receive the available COVID-19 vaccine (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.21261959</id><title>Factors influencing wellbeing in young people during COVID-19. (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.839903+00:00</updated><author><name>Michaela James</name></author><author><name>Hope Jones</name></author><author><name>Amana Baig</name></author><author><name>Emily Marchant</name></author><author><name>Tegan Waites</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Todd</name></author><author><name>Karen Hughes</name></author><author><name>Sinead Brophy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 infection and the resultant restrictions has impacted all aspects of life across the world. This study explores factors that promote or support wellbeing for young people during the pandemic, how they differ by age, using a self-reported online survey with those aged 8 - 25 in Wales between September 2020 and February 2021. Open-ended responses were analysed via thematic analysis to provide further context. A total of 6,291 responses were obtained from 81 education settings across Wales (including primary and secondary schools as well as sixth form, colleges and universities). Wellbeing was highest in primary school children and boys and lowest in those who were at secondary school children, who were girls and, those who preferred not to give a gender. Among primary school children, higher wellbeing was seen for those who played with others (rather than alone), were of Asian ethnicity (OR 2.3, 95% CI: 1.26 to 4.3), lived in a safe area (OR: 2.0, 95% CI:  1.67 to 2.5) and had more sleep. To support their wellbeing young people reported they would like to be able to play with their friends more. Among secondary school children those who were of mixed ethnicity reported lower wellbeing (OR: 5.10, 95% CI: 1.70 to 15.80). To support their wellbeing they reported they would like more support with mental health (due to anxiety and pressure to achieve when learning online). This study found self-reported wellbeing differed by gender, ethnicity and deprivation and found younger children report the need for play and to see friends to support wellbeing but older children/young people wanted more support with anxiety and educational pressures.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.21261959" rel="alternate" title="Factors influencing wellbeing in young people during COVID-19. (5 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261915</id><title>Molecular and serological investigation of the 2021 COVID-19 case surge in Mongolian vaccinees (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.840156+00:00</updated><author><name>Naranjargal J. Dashdorj</name></author><author><name>Naranbaatar D. Dashdorj</name></author><author><name>Mitali Mishra</name></author><author><name>Lisa Danzig</name></author><author><name>Thomas Briese</name></author><author><name>Walter Ian Lipkin</name></author><author><name>Nischay Mishra</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A surge in Covid-19 cases in Mongolia in March 2021 resulted in a government-mandated shutdown. This shutdown was relaxed in May 2021 as case numbers decreased and nationwide vaccination rates using Sinopharm, Covishield/AstraZeneca, Sputnik V, and Pfizer/BioNTech vaccines exceeded 50% of the population. Case rates increased again in early June 2021 in both vaccinated and non-vaccinated individuals. To determine whether the surge was due to the emergence of Delta or another variant, or vaccine failure, a rapid, opportunistic investigation was conducted that comprised virus sequence analysis of nasal swab samples from breakthrough cases and antibody assays of plasma from healthy vaccinees. More than 90% of breakthrough infections during the second case surge were due to the Alpha variant. Spike protein ELISA and SARS-CoV-2 neutralization assays data revealed large differences in plasma titers of antibodies to SARS-CoV-2, with mRNA vaccines eliciting higher titers than adenovirus-vectored or killed virus vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261915" rel="alternate" title="Molecular and serological investigation of the 2021 COVID-19 case surge in Mongolian vaccinees (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261903</id><title>The fomite contribution to the transmission of COVID-19 in the UK: an evolutionary population estimate (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.840364+00:00</updated><author><name>Avery Meiksin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A SEIR model with an added fomite term is used to constrain the contribution of fomites to the spread of COVID-19 under the Spring 2020 lockdown in the UK. Assuming uniform priors on the reproduction number in lockdown and the fomite transmission rate, an upper limit is found on the fomite transmission rate of less than 1 contaminated object in 7 per day per infectious person (95% CL). Basing the prior on the reproduction rate during lockdown instead on the CoMix study results for the reduction in social contacts under lockdown, and assuming the reproduction number scales with the number of social contacts, provides a much more restrictive upper limit on the transmission rate by contaminated objects of fewer than 1 in 30 per day per infectious person (95% CL). Applied to postal deliveries and groceries, the upper limit on the fomite transmission rate corresponds to a probability below 1 in 70 (95% CL) that a contaminated object transmits the infection. Fewer than about half (95% CL) of the total number of deaths during the lockdown are found to arise from fomites, and most likely fewer than a quarter. These findings apply only to fomites with a transmission rate that is unaffected by a lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261903" rel="alternate" title="The fomite contribution to the transmission of COVID-19 in the UK: an evolutionary population estimate (4 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261917</id><title>Epidemiological Study of COVID-19 Infections: Case of Ga East Municipal Hospital Treatment Centre - Kwabenya-Ghana. (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.840524+00:00</updated><author><name>Shirley Crankson</name></author><author><name>Ebenezer Oduro-Mensah</name></author><author><name>Delali Asubonteng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Abstract
Background 
The COVID-19 pandemic still poses a considerable threat to global health, resulting in an unprecedented demand for regular research to continuously identify and update its risk profiles to ensure relevant interventions. 

Objectives 
This study aimed to examine the epidemiological characteristics of the COVID-19 outbreak in Ghana and identify risk factors for severe COVID-19 disease.

Method 
This was a cross-sectional study involving the data of patients with COVID-19 clinically managed at the Ga-East Municipal Hospital, the main COVID-19 treatment centre in Ghana, from 21st March to 21st June 2020. The data were retrieved from the electronic medical records and folders of the patients. It included sociodemographic characteristics, COVID-19 disease severity, and treatment outcomes. Binomial logistic regression was used to identify risk factors of severe COVID-19 illness.

Result 
Among the 360 COVID-19 cases in this study, 55.3% were males, and 44.7% were females. Their mean age was 39.9 years. Most of them were Ghanaians (92.8%) and employed (72.5%). The majority (93%) presented with mild disease, and hypertension (19.2%) was the most common comorbidity. The average length of hospital admission was 10.6 days. Many of the cases recovered (98.6%), resulting in a case fatality of 1.4%. Finally, the logistic regression showed that increasing age (OR=1.12, p= 0.002) and diabetes mellitus (OR=19.85, p=0.007) are risk factors for severe COVID-19 disease.

Conclusion 
Findings from the study confirmed that increasing age and diabetes mellitus are risk factors for severe COVID-19 disease. Thus, Ghana could prioritise these identified populations when implementing interventions to reduce the COVID-19 disease burden.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261917" rel="alternate" title="Epidemiological Study of COVID-19 Infections: Case of Ga East Municipal Hospital Treatment Centre - Kwabenya-Ghana. (4 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261712</id><title>Mental Health Utilization in Children in the time of COVID-19 (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.840710+00:00</updated><author><name>Leah Coates</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Marshall</name></author><author><name>Kyle Johnson</name></author><author><name>Byron Alexander Foster</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: In early 2020, coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) was declared a public health emergency and a combination of lockdown and social distancing measures were put in place across the globe. Many children, adolescents and adults have experienced adverse mental health effects related to the pandemic and its impact on daily life, although the long-term impact on individuals and health systems is not well understood.  

Methods: This cross-sectional study was based on data from 2018-2021 collected via medical records from our hospital. Admissions were transformed into time-series data, and models were generated to analyze changes in admission rates for mental health emergencies in 2020 and 2021 compared to previous years. 
Results: Of 1906 inpatient encounters among 1543 unique patients seen by the Child and Adolescent Psychiatry Consultation-Liaison service, there was a decrease in overall admissions beginning in March 2020, coinciding with statewide lock down due to the COVID-19 pandemic. In April 2020, admissions were reduced 36% compared to average admissions from 2018-2019. By 2021, overall admissions were significantly higher than for the previous three years. Similarly, the count of suicide attempts was significantly higher in 2021 compared to previous years. The rate of patients admitted to inpatient facilities upon discharge was significantly higher during the COVID-19 pandemic period. 
Conclusion: Admissions for mental health emergencies fluctuated during the period associated with the COVID-19 pandemic across an array of diagnoses. Increases in admissions and severity of mental health emergencies during COVID-19 may reflect a detrimental impact of the pandemic on the mental health of children, as well as unmet needs during this time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261712" rel="alternate" title="Mental Health Utilization in Children in the time of COVID-19 (4 tweets)"/><category term="Pediatrics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261793</id><title>Development and use analysis of 'gestioemocional.cat', a web app for promoting emotional self-care and access to professional mental health resources during the covid-19 pandemic (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.840867+00:00</updated><author><name>Sara Guila Fidel-Kinori</name></author><author><name>Gerard Carot-Sans</name></author><author><name>Andrés Cuartero-Barbanoj</name></author><author><name>Damià Valero</name></author><author><name>Jordi Piera-Jiménez</name></author><author><name>Rosa Romà-Monfà</name></author><author><name>Elisabet Garcia-Ribatallada</name></author><author><name>Pol Pérez-Sust</name></author><author><name>Jordi Blanch-Andreu</name></author><author><name>Josep Antoni Ramos-Quiroga</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Quarantines and nationwide lockdowns dictated for containing the spread of the COVID-19 pandemic may lead to distress and increase the frequency of anxiety and depression symptoms among the general population. During the national lockdown of the first wave of the COVID-19 outbreak in Spain, we developed and launched a Web App (Gestioemocional.cat) to promote emotional self-care in the general population and facilitate contact with healthcare professionals. 
Methods: Gestioemocional.cat targeted all individuals aged 18 years or more and was designed by adapting the contents of a mobile App for adjuvant treatment of post-traumatic stress disorder (i.e., the PTSD Coach App) to the general population and the pandemic/lockdown scenario. We retrospectively assessed the utilization pattern of the Web App using data systematically retrieved from Google Analytics. Data were grouped into three time periods, defined using a join point analysis of COVID-19 incidence in our area: first wave, between-wave period, and second wave.
Results: The resulting Web App, maintains the navigation structure of the PTSD Coach App, with three main modules: tools for emotional self-care, a self-assessment test, and professional resources for on-demand contact. The self-assessment test combines the Patient Health Questionnaire-2 (PHQ-2) and the 7-item Generalized Anxiety Disorder Scale (GAD-7) and offers professional contact in the advent of a high level of depression and anxiety; contact is prioritized according to a screening questionnaire administered at the time of obtaining individual consent to be contacted. The tools for emotional self-care can be accessed either on-demand or symptom-driven. The utilization analysis showed a high number of weekly accesses during the first wave. In this period, press releases regarding critical events of the pandemic progression and government decisions on containment measures were followed by a utilization peak, irrespective of the sense (i.e., positive or negative) of the information. Positive information pieces (e.g., relaxation of containment measures due to a reduction of COVID-19 cases) resulted in a sharp increase in utilization immediately after information release, followed by a successive decline in utilization. The second wave was characterized by a lower and less responsive utilization of the Web App. 
Conclusions: mHealth tools may help the general population coping with stressful conditions associated with the pandemic scenario. Future studies shall investigate the effectiveness of these tools among the general population―including individuals without diagnosed mental illnesses―and strategies to reach as many people as possible.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261793" rel="alternate" title="Development and use analysis of 'gestioemocional.cat', a web app for promoting emotional self-care and access to professional mental health resources during the covid-19 pandemic (4 tweets)"/><category term="Health Informatics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455941</id><title>Modeling the SARS-CoV-2 mutation based on geographical regions and time (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.841069+00:00</updated><author><name>Bomin Wei</name></author><author><name>Xiang Gong</name></author><author><name>Yuzhe Sun</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) epidemic was first detected in late-December 2019 in Wuhan, China. So far, it has caused more than 200 million confirmed cases and over 4.2 million deaths in the world. We collected sequences from 150,659 COVID-19 patients. Based on the previous phylogenomic analysis, we found three major branches of the virus RNA genomic mutation located in Asia, America, and Europe which is consistent with other studies. We selected sites with high mutation frequencies from Asia, America, and Europe. There are only 13 common mutation sites in these three regions. It infers that the viral mutations are highly dependent on their location and different locations have specific mutations. Most mutations can lead to amino acid substitutions, which occurred in 3/5’UTR, S/N/M protein, and ORF1ab/3a/8/10. Thus, the mutations may affect the pathogenesis of the virus. In addition, we applied a ARIMA model to predict the short-term frequency change of these top mutation sites during the spread of the disease. We tested a variety of settings of ARIMA model to optimize the prediction effect of three patterns. This model can provide a good help for predicting short-term mutation frequency changes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455941" rel="alternate" title="Modeling the SARS-CoV-2 mutation based on geographical regions and time (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.21261861</id><title>Healthcare presentations with self-harm and the association with COVID-19: an e-cohort whole-population-based study using individual-level linked routine electronic health records in Wales, UK, 2016 - March 2021 (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.841382+00:00</updated><author><name>Marcos del Pozo Banos</name></author><author><name>Sze Chim Lee</name></author><author><name>Yasmin Friedmann</name></author><author><name>Ashley Akbari</name></author><author><name>Fatemeh Tobari</name></author><author><name>Keith R Lloyd</name></author><author><name>Ronan A Lyons</name></author><author><name>Ann John</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background
Multi-setting population-based studies on healthcare service presentations with self-harm covering the first 12 months of the COVID-19 pandemic are yet to be published.
Aims
Ascertain changes across settings in healthcare service presentations with self-harm during Waves 1 and 2 of the COVID-19 pandemic.
Method
E-cohort study using individual-level linked routine healthcare data from Wales, UK, 2016-March 2021. We measured weekly proportion of self-harm contacts and people who self-harmed in contact with general practice (GP), emergency department (ED) and hospital admissions. We modelled weekly trends using linear regression and generalised estimated equations, quantifying time differences using difference-in-difference (DiD).
Results
We included 3,552,210 Welsh residents aged ≥10 years. Counts of self-harm presentations across settings was at a minimum at the start of stay-at-home restrictions during both waves and recovered compared to previous years in 3-5 months. Those who self-harmed in April 2020 were more likely to be seen in GP compared to other settings and previous years - mean rate of OR=1.2, although actual numbers fell. The proportion of self-harm ED contacts admitted to hospital dropped from June 2020 (1.9 [1.5-2.3] pp/month). Self-harm and COVID-19 infection had a bidirectional effect - self-harm history had OR=1.4 [1.2-1.6] and incidence had DiD=1.1 [0.8-1.4].
Conclusions
Those that self-harmed and sought help during the COVID-19 pandemic potentially encountered stringent criteria for hospitalisation, particularly in Wave 2, while in Wave 1 they preferentially presented to GP. Reductions in contacts likely resulted in unmet healthcare needs which may later emerge placing further burden on individuals and healthcare services.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.21261861" rel="alternate" title="Healthcare presentations with self-harm and the association with COVID-19: an e-cohort whole-population-based study using individual-level linked routine electronic health records in Wales, UK, 2016 - March 2021 (4 tweets)"/><category term="Health Informatics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456182</id><title>Conserved T-cell epitopes predicted by bioinformatics in SARS-COV-2 variants (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.841900+00:00</updated><author><name>Feiyu Lu</name></author><author><name>Shengnan Wang</name></author><author><name>Ying Wang</name></author><author><name>Yunpeng Yao</name></author><author><name>Yangeng Wang</name></author><author><name>Shujun Liu</name></author><author><name>Yangyang Wang</name></author><author><name>Yongli Yu</name></author><author><name>Liying Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Finding conservative T cell epitopes in the proteome of numerous variants of SARS-COV-2 is required to develop T cell activating SARS-COV-2 capable of inducing T cell responses against SARS-COV-2 variants. 
Methods: A computational workflow was performed to find HLA restricted CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cell epitopes among conserved amino acid sequences across the proteome of 474727 SARS-CoV-2 strains.
Results: A batch of covserved regions in the amino acid sequences were found in the proteome of the SARS-COV-2 strains. 2852 and 847 peptides were predicted to have high binding affinity to distint HLA class I and class II molecules. Among them, 1456 and 484 peptides are antigenic. 392 and 111 of the antigenic peptides were found in the conseved amino acid sequences. Among the antigenic-conserved peptides, 6 CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cell epitopes and 7 CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cell epitopes were identifed. The T cell epitopes could be presented to T cells by high-affinity HLA molecules which are encoded by the HLA alleles with high population coverage. 
Conclusions: The T cell epitopes are conservative, antigenic and HLA presentable, and could be constructed into SARS-COV-2 vaccines for inducing protective T cell immunity against SARS-COV-2 and their variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456182" rel="alternate" title="Conserved T-cell epitopes predicted by bioinformatics in SARS-COV-2 variants (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.21261968</id><title>Rapid antigen testing as a reactive public health response to surges in SARS-CoV-2 outbreak risk in healthcare settings (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.842164+00:00</updated><author><name>David RM Smith</name></author><author><name>Audrey Duval</name></author><author><name>Jean Ralph Zahar</name></author><author><name>lulla opatowski</name></author><author><name>Laura TEMIME</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Surges in community SARS-CoV-2 incidence increase risk of importation and subsequent transmission in healthcare facilities. Antigen rapid diagnostic testing (Ag-RDT) is widely used for population screening, but its health and economic benefits as a reactive intervention in healthcare settings are unclear. 
 
Methods: We used stochastic, individual-based modelling to simulate SARS-CoV-2 transmission in a long-term care facility with varying COVID-19 containment measures in place (social distancing, face masks, vaccination). In contrast to routine symptomatic testing using reverse-transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR), we evaluated the efficacy and health-economic efficiency of single or repeated population-wide Ag-RDT screening interventions implemented in response to surges in nosocomial outbreak risk. 
 
Results: Depending on the baseline containment measures in place, nosocomial SARS-CoV-2 incidence was reduced by up to 40-47% (range of means) with routine RT-PCR testing, 59-63% with the addition of a timely round of Ag-RDT screening, and 69-75% with well-timed two-round screening. For the latter, a delay of 4 to 5 days between the first and second rounds was optimal for transmission prevention. Efficacy varied depending on test sensitivity, subpopulations targeted, and SARS-CoV-2 incidence in the community. Efficiency, however, varied primarily depending on the other containment measures in place: surveillance costs for a combined strategy of routine RT-PCR testing and reactive Ag-RDT screening ranged from a mean €420-€10,260/infection averted across scenarios (default unit costs: €5/Ag-RDT test, €50/RT-PCR test).

Interpretation: Reactive Ag-RDT screening complements routine RT-PCR testing, and systematic two-round screening helps overcome limited, time-varying diagnostic sensitivity. Health-economic gains scale significantly with underlying nosocomial outbreak risk.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.21261968" rel="alternate" title="Rapid antigen testing as a reactive public health response to surges in SARS-CoV-2 outbreak risk in healthcare settings (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261875</id><title>Harmony COVID-19: a ready-to-use kit, low-cost detector, and smartphone app for point-of-care SARS-CoV-2 RNA detection (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.842395+00:00</updated><author><name>Nuttada Panpradist</name></author><author><name>Enos Kline</name></author><author><name>Robert G Atkinson</name></author><author><name>Michael Roller</name></author><author><name>Qin Wang</name></author><author><name>Ian T Hull</name></author><author><name>Jack H Kotnik</name></author><author><name>Amy Oreskovic</name></author><author><name>Crissa Bennett</name></author><author><name>Daniel Leon</name></author><author><name>Victoria Lyon</name></author><author><name>Shane Gilligan-Steinberg</name></author><author><name>Peter D Han</name></author><author><name>Paul K Drain</name></author><author><name>Lea M Starita</name></author><author><name>Matthew J Thompson</name></author><author><name>Barry R Lutz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;RNA amplification tests sensitively detect SARS-CoV-2 infection, but their complexity and cost are prohibitive for expanding COVID-19 testing. We developed Harmony COVID-19, a point-of-care test using inexpensive consumables, ready-to-use reagents, and a simple device accommodating up to 4 samples simultaneously. Our ready-to-use, 4-plex reverse-transcription, loop-mediated isothermal amplification (RT-LAMP) can detect down to 0.38 SARS-CoV-2 RNA copies/μL and can report in 17 min for high viral load samples (5,000 copies/μL). Harmony detected 97% or 83% of contrived samples with ≥0.5 viral particles/μL in nasal matrix or saliva, respectively. Evaluation in clinical nasal specimens in viral transport media (VTM, n=101) showed 100% detection of RNA extracted from specimens with ≥0.5 SARS-CoV-2 RNA copies/μL, with 100% specificity in specimens positive for other respiratory pathogens. VTM is non-ideal for Harmony system, yet extraction-free analysis of VTM specimens (n=29) had 95% success in specimens with ≥1 RNA copies/μL. Usability testing performed first-time by healthcare workers showed 95% accuracy&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261875" rel="alternate" title="Harmony COVID-19: a ready-to-use kit, low-cost detector, and smartphone app for point-of-care SARS-CoV-2 RNA detection (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261913</id><title>What has changed in the experiences of people with mental health problems during the COVID-19 pandemic? Findings from follow-up interviews using a coproduced, participatory qualitative approach (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.842819+00:00</updated><author><name>Prisha Shah</name></author><author><name>Jackie Hardy</name></author><author><name>Mary Birken</name></author><author><name>Una Foye</name></author><author><name>Rachel Rowan Olive</name></author><author><name>Patrick Nyikavaranda</name></author><author><name>Ceri Dare</name></author><author><name>Theodora Stefanidou</name></author><author><name>Merle Schlief</name></author><author><name>Eiluned Pearce</name></author><author><name>Natasha Lyons</name></author><author><name>Karen Machin</name></author><author><name>Tamar Jeynes</name></author><author><name>Beverley Chipp</name></author><author><name>Anjie Chhapia</name></author><author><name>Nick Barber</name></author><author><name>Steven Gillard</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Pitman</name></author><author><name>Alan Simpson</name></author><author><name>Sonia Johnson</name></author><author><name>Brynmor Lloyd-Evans</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Purpose: We sought to understand how the experiences of people in the UK with pre-existing mental health conditions had developed during the course of the COVID-19 pandemic. 
Methods: In September-October 2020 we interviewed adults with mental health conditions pre-dating the pandemic whom we had previously interviewed three months earlier. Participants had been recruited through online advertising and voluntary sector community organisations. Interviews were conducted by telephone or video-conference by researchers with lived experience of mental health difficulties and explored changes over time in experiences of participants of the pandemic. 
Results: We interviewed 44 people, achieving diversity of demographic characteristics and a range of mental health conditions and service use among our sample. Three overarching themes were derived from interviews. The first theme Spectrum of adaptation: to difficulties in access to, or the quality of, statutory mental health services, through developing new personal coping strategies or identifying alternative sources of support. The second theme is Accumulating pressures: from pandemic-related anxieties and sustained disruption to social contact and support, and to mental health treatment. The third theme Feeling overlooked: A sense of people with pre-existing mental health conditions being overlooked during the pandemic by policy-makers at all levels. The latter was compounded for people from ethnic minority communities or with physical health problems.  
Conclusion: Our study highlights the need to support marginalised groups who are at risk of increased inequalities, and to maintain crucial mental and physical healthcare and social care for people with existing mental health conditions, notwithstanding challenges of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.21261913" rel="alternate" title="What has changed in the experiences of people with mental health problems during the COVID-19 pandemic? Findings from follow-up interviews using a coproduced, participatory qualitative approach (4 tweets)"/><category term="Psychiatry and Clinical Psychology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261877</id><title>Serological detection of SARS-CoV-2 IgG using a commercially available enzyme immunoassays on dried blood spots collected from patients (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.843072+00:00</updated><author><name>Gregory J Walker</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Davis</name></author><author><name>Zin Naing</name></author><author><name>Brad McEntee</name></author><author><name>Yonghui Lu</name></author><author><name>Tatijana Denadija</name></author><author><name>William D Rawlinson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Serological testing for SARS-CoV-2 antibodies provides important research and diagnostic information relating to COVID-19 immune response and surveillance. A major challenge when addressing protection post- infection or vaccination is the difficulty of specimen collection from infants and children. Dried blood spots (DBS) collected by finger prick or heel prick are a minimally invasive sample collection alternative previously used to detect antibodies to other viruses. In this study we evaluated DBS for the detection of SARS-CoV-2 antibodies on three commercially available enzyme (EIA) and chemiluminescent (CLIA) immunoassays by analysing paired DBS and serum samples collected from 54 subjects. We demonstrate that testing of DBS samples was highly sensitive and specific, and quantitative results strongly correlated with those of paired serum. These results suggest that DBS derived blood is a viable alternative to plasma or serum for use in EIAs and CLIAs, and has particular utility as a minimally invasive collection tool for COVID-19 serological testing of infants and children.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261877" rel="alternate" title="Serological detection of SARS-CoV-2 IgG using a commercially available enzyme immunoassays on dried blood spots collected from patients (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261760</id><title>THE EFFECT OF BARICITINIB USAGE ON THE CLINICAL AND BIOCHEMICAL PROFILES OF COVID-19 PATIENTS- A RETROSPECTIVE OBSERVATIONAL STUDY (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.843397+00:00</updated><author><name>Anoop Amarnath</name></author><author><name>Ananya Das</name></author><author><name>Venkata Sai Shashank Mutya</name></author><author><name>Irfan Ibrahim</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Coronaviruses typically cause influenza like illness which progresses to ARDS along with other systemic manifestations.  India is experiencing its second wave with a huge surge in the number of cases exponentially causing huge impact on health care infrastructure and the demand supply chain. As a result several new modalities have been used, one of which is the use of remdesivir and baricitinib. Hence this study is aimed at finding out the clinical and biochemical profile of the patients who have received the combination
Materials and Methods: All the patients who have received the combination meeting the inclusion and exclusion criteria have been included in the study. A total of 31 participants were included and their records were retrospectively analyzed.
Results: There was a significant reduction in the oxygen requirement, CRP and IL-6 levels with p values&amp;lt;0.05. However, in the non-survivors group, there was no statistically significant reduction. Serial monitoring of NLR ratio showed increase towards the fifth day, especially in the non-survivor group it was as high as 41.24. The mortality rate was found to be 10% and the cause being secondary sepsis in all of them.
Conclusion: The ACTT-2 trail has proved the efficacy of the use of the remdesivir and baricitinib combination with mortality benefit. In our study we found similar results which was well co-related with clinical and biochemical parameters like CRP and IL-6 especially in people with co-morbidites.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.21261760" rel="alternate" title="THE EFFECT OF BARICITINIB USAGE ON THE CLINICAL AND BIOCHEMICAL PROFILES OF COVID-19 PATIENTS- A RETROSPECTIVE OBSERVATIONAL STUDY (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>