<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.234198+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.25.457692</id><title>The Lambda variant of SARS-CoV-2 has a better chance than the Delta variant to escape vaccines (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.234614+00:00</updated><author><name>Haolin Liu</name></author><author><name>Pengcheng Wei</name></author><author><name>Qianqian Zhang</name></author><author><name>Katja Aviszus</name></author><author><name>Jared Linderberger</name></author><author><name>John Yang</name></author><author><name>Junfeng Liu</name></author><author><name>Zhongzhou Chen</name></author><author><name>Hassan Waheed</name></author><author><name>Lyndon Reynoso</name></author><author><name>Gregory P. Downey</name></author><author><name>Stephen K. Frankel</name></author><author><name>John Kappler</name></author><author><name>Philippa Marrack</name></author><author><name>Gongyi Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The newly emerging variants of SARS-CoV-2 from India (Delta variant) and South America (Lambda variant) have led to a higher infection rate of either vaccinated or unvaccinated people. We found that sera from Pfizer-BioNTech vaccine remain high reactivity toward the receptor binding domain (RBD) of Delta variant while it drops dramatically toward that of Lambda variant. Interestingly, the overall titer of antibodies of Pfizer-BioNTech vaccinated individuals drops 3-fold after 6 months, which could be one of major reasons for breakthrough infections, emphasizing the importance of potential third boost shot. While a therapeutic antibody, Bamlanivimab, decreases binding affinity to Delta variant by ~20 fold, it fully lost binding to Lambda variant. Structural modeling of complexes of RBD with human receptor, Angiotensin Converting Enzyme 2 (ACE2), and Bamlanivimab suggest the potential basis of the change of binding. The data suggest possible danger and a potential surge of Lambda variant in near future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.25.457692" rel="alternate" title="The Lambda variant of SARS-CoV-2 has a better chance than the Delta variant to escape vaccines (24 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.23.457408</id><title>Deep immune profiling of the maternal-fetal interface with mild SARS-CoV-2 infection (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.234940+00:00</updated><author><name>Suhas Sureshchandra</name></author><author><name>Michael Z Zulu</name></author><author><name>Brianna Doratt</name></author><author><name>Allen Jankeel</name></author><author><name>Delia Tifrea</name></author><author><name>Robert Edwards</name></author><author><name>Monica Rincon</name></author><author><name>Nicole E. Marshall</name></author><author><name>Ilhem Messaoudi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pregnant women are an at-risk group for severe COVID-19, though the majority experience mild/asymptomatic disease. Although severe COVID-19 has been shown to be associated with immune activation at the maternal-fetal interface even in the absence of active viral replication, the immune response to asymptomatic/mild COVID-19 remains unknown. Here, we assessed immunological adaptations in both blood and term decidua from 9 SARS-exposed pregnant women with asymptomatic/mild disease and 15 pregnant SARS-naive women. In addition to selective loss of tissue-resident decidual macrophages, we report attenuation of antigen presentation and type I IFN signaling but upregulation of inflammatory cytokines and chemokines in blood monocyte derived decidual macrophages. On the other hand, infection was associated with remodeling of the T cell compartment with increased frequencies of activated CD69+ tissue-resident T cells and decreased abundance of Tregs. Interestingly, frequencies of cytotoxic CD4 and CD8 T cells increased only in the blood, while CD8 effector memory T cells were expanded in the decidua. In contrast to decidual macrophages, signatures of type I IFN signaling were increased in decidual T cells. Finally, T cell receptor diversity was significantly reduced with infection in both compartments, albeit to a much greater extent in the blood. The resulting aberrant immune activation in the placenta, even with asymptomatic disease may alter the exquisitely sensitive developing fetal immune system, leading to long-term adverse outcomes for offspring.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.23.457408" rel="alternate" title="Deep immune profiling of the maternal-fetal interface with mild SARS-CoV-2 infection (9 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>