<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.489653+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.31.21262943</id><title>Ensemble forecast of COVID-19 in Karnataka for vulnerability assessment and policy interventions (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.490001+00:00</updated><author><name>Sashikumaar Ganesan</name></author><author><name>Deepak Subramani</name></author><author><name>Thivin Anandh</name></author><author><name>Divij Ghose</name></author><author><name>Giridhara R Babu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We present an ensemble forecast for Wave-3 of COVID-19 in the state of Karnataka, India, using the IISc Population Balance Model for infectious disease spread. The reported data of confirmed, recovered, and deceased cases in Karnataka from 1 July 2020 to 4 July 2021 is utilized to tune the model’s parameters, and an ensemble forecast is done from 5 July 2021 to 30 June 2022. The ensemble is built with 972 members by varying seven critical parameters that quantify the uncertainty in the spread dynamics (antibody waning, viral mutation) and interventions (pharmaceutical, non-pharmaceutical). The probability of Wave-3, the peak date distribution, and the peak caseload distribution are estimated from the ensemble forecast. Our analysis shows that the most significant causal factors are compliance to Covid-appropriate behavior, daily vaccination rate, and the immune escape new variant emergence-time. These causal factors determine when and how severe the Wave-3 of COVID-19 would be in Karnataka. We observe that when compliance to Covid-Appropriate Behavior is good (i.e., lockdown-like compliance), the emergence of new immune-escape variants beyond Sep ‘21 is unlikely to induce a new wave. A new wave is inevitable when compliance to Covid-Appropriate Behavior is only partial. Increasing the daily vaccination rates reduces the peak active caseload at Wave-3. Consequently, the hospitalization, ICU, and Oxygen requirements also decrease. Compared to Wave-2, the ensemble forecast indicates that the number of daily confirmed cases of children (0-17 years) at Wave-3’s peak could be seven times more on average. Our results provide insights to plan science-informed policy interventions and public health response.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.31.21262943" rel="alternate" title="Ensemble forecast of COVID-19 in Karnataka for vulnerability assessment and policy interventions (29 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.03.458877</id><title>Discovery of highly potent pancoronavirus fusion inhibitors that also effectively inhibit COVID-19 variants from the UK and South Africa (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.490231+00:00</updated><author><name>Francesca Curreli</name></author><author><name>Shahad Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Sofia M. B. Victor</name></author><author><name>Aleksandra Drelich</name></author><author><name>Siva S. Panda</name></author><author><name>Andrea Altieri</name></author><author><name>Alexander Kurkin</name></author><author><name>Chien-Te Tseng</name></author><author><name>Christopher Hillyer</name></author><author><name>Asim Debnath</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We report the discovery of a series of benzoic acid-based inhibitors that show highly potent pancoronavirus activity. Some compounds also show complete inhibition of CPE (IC&lt;sub&gt;100&lt;/sub&gt;) at 1.25 μM against an authentic SARS-CoV-2 (US_WA-1/2020). Furthermore, the most active inhibitors also potently inhibited variants initially identified in the UK and South Africa. We confirmed that one of the potent inhibitors binds to the prefusion spike protein trimer of SARS-CoV-2 by SPR. Besides, we showed that they inhibit virus-mediated cell-cell fusion. The ADME data show druglike characteristics, and in vivo PK in rats demonstrated excellent half-life (t½) of 11.3 h, mean resident time (MRT) of 14.2 h, and orally bioavailable. Despite the presence of ene-rhodamine moiety, we conclusively demonstrated that these inhibitors target the viral spike protein and are not promiscuous or colloidal aggregators. We expect the lead inhibitors to pave the way for further development to preclinical and clinical candidates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.03.458877" rel="alternate" title="Discovery of highly potent pancoronavirus fusion inhibitors that also effectively inhibit COVID-19 variants from the UK and South Africa (27 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-09-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.29.21262789</id><title>Vaccines alone are no silver bullets: a modeling study on the impact of efficient contact tracing on COVID-19 infection and transmission (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.490438+00:00</updated><author><name>Dhesi Baha Raja</name></author><author><name>Nur Asheila Abdul Taib</name></author><author><name>Alvin Kuo Jing Teo</name></author><author><name>Vivek Jason Jayaraj</name></author><author><name>Choo-Yee Ting</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The computer simulation presented in this study aimed to investigate the effect of contact tracing on COVID-19 transmission and infection in the context of rising vaccination rates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study proposed a deterministic SEIRV model with contact tracing and vaccination components. We initialized some parameters using the Malaysian COVID-19 data to inform the model. We defined contact tracing effectiveness as the proportion of contacts of a positive case that was successfully traced and vaccination rate as the proportion of daily doses administered per population in Malaysia. Sensitivity analyses on the untraced and infectious populations were conducted. The study presented in silico findings on multiple scenarios by varying the contact tracing effectiveness and daily vaccination rates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a vaccination rate of 1.4%, a contact tracing with the effectiveness of 70% could delay the peak of untraced asymptomatic cases by 17 days and reduce the highest number of daily cases by 70% compared with a 30% contact tracing effectiveness. A similar trend was observed for symptomatic cases when a similar experiment setting was used. We also performed sensitivity analyses by using different combinations of contact tracing effectiveness and vaccination rates. In all scenarios, the effect of contact tracing on COVID-19 incidence persisted for both asymptomatic and symptomatic cases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite testing only on two public health and social measures (PHSMs), we observed the scenario with low contact tracing and increasing vaccination rates successfully mimicked the current transmission trend in Malaysia. Hence, while vaccines are progressively rolled out, efficient contact tracing must be rapidly implemented concurrently to reach, find, test, isolate, and support the affected populations to bring the pandemic under control.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.29.21262789" rel="alternate" title="Vaccines alone are no silver bullets: a modeling study on the impact of efficient contact tracing on COVID-19 infection and transmission (7 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-08-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.01.458520</id><title>Early post-infection treatment of SARS-CoV-2 infected macaques with human convalescent plasma with high neutralizing activity reduces lung inflammation (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.490607+00:00</updated><author><name>Koen K.A. Van Rompay</name></author><author><name>Katherine J. Olstad</name></author><author><name>Rebecca L. Sammak</name></author><author><name>Joseph Dutra</name></author><author><name>Jennifer K. Watanabe</name></author><author><name>Jodie L. Usachenko</name></author><author><name>Ramya Immareddy</name></author><author><name>Jamin W. Roh</name></author><author><name>Anil Verma</name></author><author><name>Yashavanth Shaan Lakshmanappa</name></author><author><name>Brian A. Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Clara Di Germanio</name></author><author><name>Nabeela Rizvi</name></author><author><name>Mars Stone</name></author><author><name>Graham Simmons</name></author><author><name>Larry J. Dumont</name></author><author><name>A. Mark Allen</name></author><author><name>Sarah Lockwood</name></author><author><name>Rachel E. Pollard</name></author><author><name>Rafael Ramiro de Assis</name></author><author><name>JoAnn L. Yee</name></author><author><name>Peter B. Nham</name></author><author><name>Amir Ardeshir</name></author><author><name>Jesse D. Deere</name></author><author><name>Jean Patterson</name></author><author><name>Aarti Jain</name></author><author><name>Philip L. Felgner</name></author><author><name>Smita S. Iyer</name></author><author><name>Dennis J. Hartigan-O’Connor</name></author><author><name>Michael P. Busch</name></author><author><name>J. Rachel Reader</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Early in the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic, there was a high level of optimism based on observational studies and small controlled trials that treating hospitalized patients with convalescent plasma from COVID-19 survivors (CCP) would be an important immunotherapy. However, as more data from controlled trials became available, the results became disappointing, with at best moderate evidence of efficacy when CCP with high titers of neutralizing antibodies was used early in infection. To better understand the potential therapeutic efficacy of CCP, and to further validate SARS-CoV-2 infection of macaques as a reliable animal model for testing such strategies, we inoculated 12 adult rhesus macaques with SARS-CoV-2 by intratracheal and intranasal routes. One day later, 8 animals were infused with pooled human CCP with a high titer of neutralizing antibodies (RVPN NT&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; value of 3,003), while 4 control animals received normal human plasma. Animals were monitored for 7 days. Animals treated with CCP had detectable levels of antiviral antibodies after infusion. In comparison to the control animals, they had similar levels of virus replication in the upper and lower respiratory tract, but had significantly reduced interstitial pneumonia, as measured by comprehensive lung histology. By highlighting strengths and weaknesses, data of this study can help to further optimize nonhuman primate models to provide proof-of-concept of intervention strategies, and guide the future use of convalescent plasma against SARS-CoV-2 and potentially other newly emerging respiratory viruses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The results of treating SARS-CoV-2 infected hospitalized patients with COVID-19 convalescent plasma (CCP), collected from survivors of natural infection, have been disappointing. The available data from various studies indicate at best moderate clinical benefits only when CCP with high titer of neutralizing antibodies was infused early in infection. The macaque model of SARS-CoV-2 infection can be useful to gain further insights in the value of CCP therapy. In this study, animals were infected with SARS-CoV-2 and the next day, were infused with pooled human convalescent plasma, selected to have a very high titer of neutralizing antibodies. While administration of CCP did not result in a detectable reduction in virus replication in the respiratory tract, it significantly reduced lung inflammation. These data, combined with the results of monoclonal antibody studies, emphasize the need to use products with high titers of neutralizing antibodies, and guide the future development of CCP-based therapies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.01.458520" rel="alternate" title="Early post-infection treatment of SARS-CoV-2 infected macaques with human convalescent plasma with high neutralizing activity reduces lung inflammation (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.01.458516</id><title>Absence of severe COVID-19 in patients with clonal mast cells activation disorders: effective anti-SARS-CoV-2 immune response (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.491474+00:00</updated><author><name>Julien Rossignol</name></author><author><name>Amani Ouedrani</name></author><author><name>Cristina Bulai Livideanu</name></author><author><name>Stéphane Barete</name></author><author><name>Louis Terriou</name></author><author><name>David Launay</name></author><author><name>Richard Lemal</name></author><author><name>Celine Greco</name></author><author><name>Laurent Frenzel</name></author><author><name>Cecile Meni</name></author><author><name>Christine Bodemere-Skandalis</name></author><author><name>Laura Polivka</name></author><author><name>Anne-Florence Collange</name></author><author><name>Hassiba Hachichi</name></author><author><name>Sonia Bouzourine</name></author><author><name>Djazira Nait Messaoud</name></author><author><name>Mathilde Negretto</name></author><author><name>Laurence Vendrame</name></author><author><name>Marguerite Jambou</name></author><author><name>Marie Gousseff</name></author><author><name>Stéphane Durupt</name></author><author><name>Jean-Christophe Lega</name></author><author><name>Jean-Marc Durand</name></author><author><name>Caroline Gaudy</name></author><author><name>Gandhi Damaj</name></author><author><name>Marie-Pierre Gourin</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Hamidou</name></author><author><name>Laurence Bouillet</name></author><author><name>Edwige Le Mouel</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Maria</name></author><author><name>Patricia Zunic</name></author><author><name>Quentin Cabrera</name></author><author><name>Denis Vincent</name></author><author><name>Christian Lavigne</name></author><author><name>Etienne Riviere</name></author><author><name>Clement Gourguechon</name></author><author><name>Anne Brignier</name></author><author><name>Ludovic Lhermitte</name></author><author><name>Thierry Jo Molina</name></author><author><name>Julie Bruneau</name></author><author><name>Julie Agopian</name></author><author><name>Patrice Dubreuil</name></author><author><name>Dana Ranta</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Mania</name></author><author><name>Michel Arock</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Staropoli</name></author><author><name>Olivier Tournilhac</name></author><author><name>Olivier Lortholary</name></author><author><name>Olivier Schwartz</name></author><author><name>Lucienne Chatenoud</name></author><author><name>Olivier Hermine</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mast cells are key actors of innate immunity and Th2 adaptive immune response which counterbalance Th1 response, critical for anti-viral immunity. Clonal Mast Cells Activation Disorders (cMCADs) such as mastocytosis and clonal mast cells activation syndrome are characterized by an abnormal mast cells accumulation and/or activation. No data have been published on the anti-viral immune response of patients with cMCADs. The aims of the study were to collected, in a comprehensive way, outcomes of cMCADs patients who experienced a biologically-proven COVID-19 and to characterize both anti-endemic coronaviruses and specific anti-SARS-CoV-2 immune responses in these patients. Clinical follow-up and outcome data were collected prospectively for one year within the French rare disease network CEREMAST encompassing patients from all over the country. Anti-SARS-CoV-2 and anti-endemic coronaviruses specific T-cells were assessed with an enzyme-linked immunospot assay (EliSpot) and anti-SARS-CoV-2 humoral response with dosage of circulating levels of specific IgG, IgA and neutralizing antibodies. Overall, 32 cMCADs patients were identified. None of them required non-invasive or mechanical ventilation; two patients were hospitalized to receive oxygen and steroid therapy. In 21 patients, a characterization of the SARS-CoV-2-specific immune response has been performed. A majority of patients showed a high proportion of circulating SARS-CoV-2-specific interferon (IFN)-γ producing T-cells and high levels of anti-Spike IgG antibodies with neutralizing activity. In addition, no defects in anti-endemic coronaviruses responses were found in patients with cMCADs compared to non-cMCADs controls. Patients with cMCADs frequently showed a spontaneous IFN-γ T-cell production in absence of any stimulation that correlated with circulating basal tryptase levels, a marker of mast cells burden. These findings underscore that patients with cMCADs might be not at risk of severe COVID-19 and the spontaneous IFN-γ production might explain this observation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mast cells are immune cells involved in many biological processes including the anti-microbial response. However, previous studies suggest that mast cells may have a detrimental role in the response against viruses such as SARS-CoV-2, responsible for COVID-19. When a mutation occurs in mast cells, it can lead to a group of diseases called clonal mast cells activation disorders (cMCADs), characterized by deregulated activation of these cells. Hence, patients with cMCADs might be more susceptible to severe COVID-19 than general population.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We therefore conducted a 1-year study in France to collect data from all cMCADs patients included in the CEREMAST rare disease French network and who experienced COVID-19. Interestingly, we did not find any severe COVID-19 (i.e. requiring non-invasive or mechanical ventilation) in spite of well-known risk factors for severe COVID-19 in a part of cMCADs patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We then have studied the immune response against SARS-CoV-2 and other endemic coronaviruses in these patients. We did not observe any abnormalities in the immune response either at the level of T and B lymphocytes. These findings underscore that these patients might not be at risk of severe COVID-19 as one might have feared.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.01.458516" rel="alternate" title="Absence of severe COVID-19 in patients with clonal mast cells activation disorders: effective anti-SARS-CoV-2 immune response (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.02.21262965</id><title>Whole genome sequencing identifies multiple loci for critical illness caused by COVID-19 (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.492237+00:00</updated><author><name>Athanasios Kousathanas</name></author><author><name>Erola Pairo-Castineira</name></author><author><name>Konrad Rawlik</name></author><author><name>Alex Stuckey</name></author><author><name>Christopher A Odhams</name></author><author><name>Susan Walker</name></author><author><name>Clark D Russell</name></author><author><name>Tomas Malinauskas</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Millar</name></author><author><name>Katherine S Elliott</name></author><author><name>Fiona Griffiths</name></author><author><name>Wilna Oosthuyzen</name></author><author><name>Kirstie Morrice</name></author><author><name>Sean Keating</name></author><author><name>Bo Wang</name></author><author><name>Daniel Rhodes</name></author><author><name>Lucija Klaric</name></author><author><name>Marie Zechner</name></author><author><name>Nick Parkinson</name></author><author><name>Andrew D. Bretherick</name></author><author><name>Afshan Siddiq</name></author><author><name>Peter Goddard</name></author><author><name>Sally Donovan</name></author><author><name>David Maslove</name></author><author><name>Alistair Nichol</name></author><author><name>Malcolm G Semple</name></author><author><name>Tala Zainy</name></author><author><name>Fiona Maleady-Crowe</name></author><author><name>Linda Todd</name></author><author><name>Shahla Salehi</name></author><author><name>Julian Knight</name></author><author><name>Greg Elgar</name></author><author><name>Georgia Chan</name></author><author><name>Prabhu Arumugam</name></author><author><name>Tom A Fowler</name></author><author><name>Augusto Rendon</name></author><author><name>Manu Shankar-Hari</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Summers</name></author><author><name>Paul Elliott</name></author><author><name>Jian Yang</name></author><author><name>Yang Wu</name></author><author><name>Angie Fawkes</name></author><author><name>Lee Murphy</name></author><author><name>Kathy Rowan</name></author><author><name>Chris P Ponting</name></author><author><name>Veronique Vitart</name></author><author><name>James F Wilson</name></author><author><name>Richard H Scott</name></author><author><name>Sara Clohisey</name></author><author><name>Loukas Moutsianas</name></author><author><name>Andy Law</name></author><author><name>Mark J Caulfield</name></author><author><name>J. Kenneth Baillie</name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Critical illness in COVID-19 is caused by inflammatory lung injury, mediated by the host immune system. We and others have shown that host genetic variation influences the development of illness requiring critical care&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; or hospitalisation&lt;sup&gt;2;3;4&lt;/sup&gt; following SARS-Co-V2 infection. The GenOMICC (Genetics of Mortality in Critical Care) study is designed to compare genetic variants in critically-ill cases with population controls in order to find underlying disease mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we use whole genome sequencing and statistical fine mapping in 7,491 critically-ill cases compared with 48,400 population controls to discover and replicate 22 independent variants that significantly predispose to life-threatening COVID-19. We identify 15 new independent associations with critical COVID-19, including variants within genes involved in interferon signalling (&lt;italic&gt;IL10RB, PLSCR1&lt;/italic&gt;), leucocyte differentiation (&lt;italic&gt;BCL11A&lt;/italic&gt;), and blood type antigen secretor status (&lt;italic&gt;FUT2&lt;/italic&gt;). Using transcriptome-wide association and colocalisation to infer the effect of gene expression on disease severity, we find evidence implicating expression of multiple genes, including reduced expression of a membrane flippase (&lt;italic&gt;ATP11A&lt;/italic&gt;), and increased mucin expression (&lt;italic&gt;MUC1&lt;/italic&gt;), in critical disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We show that comparison between critically-ill cases and population controls is highly efficient for genetic association analysis and enables detection of therapeutically-relevant mechanisms of disease. Therapeutic predictions arising from these findings require testing in clinical trials.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.02.21262965" rel="alternate" title="Whole genome sequencing identifies multiple loci for critical illness caused by COVID-19 (3 tweets)"/><category term="Intensive Care and Critical Care Medicine"/><published>2021-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>