<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.138861+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472630</id><title>Considerable escape of SARS-CoV-2 variant Omicron to antibody neutralization (646 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.139249+00:00</updated><author><name>Delphine Planas</name></author><author><name>Nell Saunders</name></author><author><name>Piet Maes</name></author><author><name>Florence Guivel-Benhassine</name></author><author><name>Cyril Planchais</name></author><author><name>Julian Buchrieser</name></author><author><name>William-Henry Bolland</name></author><author><name>Françoise Porrot</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Staropoli</name></author><author><name>Frederic Lemoine</name></author><author><name>Hélène Péré</name></author><author><name>David Veyer</name></author><author><name>Julien Puech</name></author><author><name>Julien Rodary</name></author><author><name>Guy Baela</name></author><author><name>Simon Dellicour</name></author><author><name>Joren Raymenants</name></author><author><name>Sarah Gorissen</name></author><author><name>Caspar Geenen</name></author><author><name>Bert Vanmechelen</name></author><author><name>Tony Wawina-Bokalanga</name></author><author><name>Joan Martí-Carrerasi</name></author><author><name>Lize Cuypers</name></author><author><name>Aymeric Sève</name></author><author><name>Laurent Hocqueloux</name></author><author><name>Thierry Prazuck</name></author><author><name>Félix Rey</name></author><author><name>Etienne Simon-Lorrière</name></author><author><name>Timothée Bruel</name></author><author><name>Hugo Mouquet</name></author><author><name>Emmanuel André</name></author><author><name>Olivier Schwartz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant was first identified in November 2021 in Botswana and South Africa&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt;. It has in the meantime spread to many countries and is expected to rapidly become dominant worldwide. The lineage is characterized by the presence of about 32 mutations in the Spike, located mostly in the N-terminal domain (NTD) and the receptor binding domain (RBD), which may enhance viral fitness and allow antibody evasion. Here, we isolated an infectious Omicron virus in Belgium, from a traveller returning from Egypt. We examined its sensitivity to 9 monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) clinically approved or in development&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;, and to antibodies present in 90 sera from COVID-19 vaccine recipients or convalescent individuals. Omicron was totally or partially resistant to neutralization by all mAbs tested. Sera from Pfizer or AstraZeneca vaccine recipients, sampled 5 months after complete vaccination, barely inhibited Omicron. Sera from COVID-19 convalescent patients collected 6 or 12 months post symptoms displayed low or no neutralizing activity against Omicron. Administration of a booster Pfizer dose as well as vaccination of previously infected individuals generated an anti-Omicron neutralizing response, with titers 5 to 31 fold lower against Omicron than against Delta. Thus, Omicron escapes most therapeutic monoclonal antibodies and to a large extent vaccine-elicited antibodies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472630" rel="alternate" title="Considerable escape of SARS-CoV-2 variant Omicron to antibody neutralization (646 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267755</id><title>mRNA-based COVID-19 vaccine boosters induce neutralizing immunity against SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant (520 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.139831+00:00</updated><author><name>Wilfredo F. Garcia-Beltran</name></author><author><name>Kerri J. St. Denis</name></author><author><name>Angelique Hoelzemer</name></author><author><name>Evan C. Lam</name></author><author><name>Adam D. Nitido</name></author><author><name>Maegan L. Sheehan</name></author><author><name>Cristhian Berrios</name></author><author><name>Onosereme Ofoman</name></author><author><name>Christina C. Chang</name></author><author><name>Blake M. Hauser</name></author><author><name>Jared Feldman</name></author><author><name>David J. Gregory</name></author><author><name>Mark C. Poznansky</name></author><author><name>Aaron G. Schmidt</name></author><author><name>A. John Iafrate</name></author><author><name>Vivek Naranbhai</name></author><author><name>Alejandro B. Balazs</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent surveillance has revealed the emergence of the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant (BA.1/B.1.1.529) harboring up to 36 mutations in spike protein, the target of vaccine-induced neutralizing antibodies. Given its potential to escape vaccine-induced humoral immunity, we measured neutralization potency of sera from 88 mRNA-1273, 111 BNT162b, and 40 Ad26.COV2.S vaccine recipients against wild type, Delta, and Omicron SARS-CoV-2 pseudoviruses. We included individuals that were vaccinated recently (&amp;lt;3 months), distantly (6-12 months), or recently boosted, and accounted for prior SARS-CoV-2 infection. Remarkably, neutralization of Omicron was undetectable in most vaccinated individuals. However, individuals boosted with mRNA vaccines exhibited potent neutralization of Omicron only 4-6-fold lower than wild type, suggesting that boosters enhance the cross-reactivity of neutralizing antibody responses. In addition, we find Omicron pseudovirus is more infectious than any other variant tested. Overall, this study highlights the importance of boosters to broaden neutralizing antibody responses against highly divergent SARS-CoV-2 variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267755" rel="alternate" title="mRNA-based COVID-19 vaccine boosters induce neutralizing immunity against SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant (520 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.21267523</id><title>Human serum from SARS-CoV-2 vaccinated and COVID-19 patients shows reduced binding to the RBD of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant (142 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.140060+00:00</updated><author><name>Maren Schubert</name></author><author><name>Federico Bertoglio</name></author><author><name>Stephan Steinke</name></author><author><name>Philip Alexander Heine</name></author><author><name>Mario Alberto Ynga-Durand</name></author><author><name>Fanglei Zuo</name></author><author><name>Likun Du</name></author><author><name>Janin Korn</name></author><author><name>Marko Milošević</name></author><author><name>Esther Veronika Wenzel</name></author><author><name>Henrike Maass</name></author><author><name>Fran Krstanović</name></author><author><name>Saskia Polten</name></author><author><name>Marina Pribanić-Matešić</name></author><author><name>Ilija Brizić</name></author><author><name>Antonio Piralla</name></author><author><name>Fausto Baldanti</name></author><author><name>Lennart Hammarström</name></author><author><name>Stefan Dübel</name></author><author><name>Alan Šustić</name></author><author><name>Harold Marcotte</name></author><author><name>Monika Strengert</name></author><author><name>Alen Protić</name></author><author><name>Qiang Pan-Hammarström</name></author><author><name>Luka Čičin-Šain</name></author><author><name>Michael Hust</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic is caused by the betacoronavirus SARS-CoV-2. In November 2021, the Omicron variant was discovered and classified as a variant of concern (VOC). Omicron shows substantially more mutations in the spike protein than any previous variant, mostly in the receptor binding domain (RBD). We analyzed the binding of the Omicron RBD to the human ACE2 receptor and the ability of human sera from COVID-19 patients or vaccinees in comparison to Wuhan, Beta or Delta RBDs variants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All RBDs were produced in insect cells. RBD binding to hACE was analyzed by ELISA and microscale thermophoresis (MST). Similarly, sera from 27 COVID-19 patients, 21 fully vaccinated individuals and 16 booster recipients were titrated by ELISA on the fixed RBDs from the original Wuhan strain, Beta, Delta and Omicron VOC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, the Omicron RBD showed the weakest binding to ACE2, arguing that improved ACE2 binding is not a likely driver of Omicron evolution. Serum antibody titers were significantly lower against Omicron RBD than against the original Wuhan strain. Serum titers against Beta and Delta RBDs were also reduced, but to a lesser degree. The reduced binding of sera to Omicron RBD adds evidence that current vaccination protocols may be less efficient against the Omicron variant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.21267523" rel="alternate" title="Human serum from SARS-CoV-2 vaccinated and COVID-19 patients shows reduced binding to the RBD of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant (142 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472668</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein activates TMEM16F-mediated platelet pro-coagulant activity (142 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.140708+00:00</updated><author><name>Ambra Cappelletto</name></author><author><name>Harriet E. Allan</name></author><author><name>Marilena Crescente</name></author><author><name>Edoardo Schneider</name></author><author><name>Rossana Bussani</name></author><author><name>Hashim Ali</name></author><author><name>Ilaria Secco</name></author><author><name>Simone Vodret</name></author><author><name>Roberto Simeone</name></author><author><name>Luca Mascaretti</name></author><author><name>Serena Zacchigna</name></author><author><name>Timothy D. Warner</name></author><author><name>Mauro Giacca</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thrombosis of the lung micro-vasculature is a characteristic of COVID-19 disease, which is observed in large excess compared to other forms of acute respiratory distress syndrome and thus suggests a trigger for thrombosis endogenous to the lung. Our recent work has shown that the SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein activates the cellular TMEM16F chloride channel and scramblase. Through a screening on &amp;gt;3,000 FDA/EMA approved drugs, we identified Niclosamide and Clofazimine as the most effective molecules at inhibiting this activity. As TMEM16F plays an important role in the stimulation of the pro-coagulant activity of platelets, and considering that platelet abnormalities are common in COVID-19 patients, we investigated whether Spike directly affects platelet activation and pro-thrombotic function and tested the effect of Niclosamide and Clofazimine on these processes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We produced SARS-CoV-2 Spike or VSV-G protein-pseudotyped virions, or generated cells expressing Spike on their plasma membrane, and tested their effects on platelet adhesion (fluorescence), aggregation (absorbance), exposure of phosphatidylserine (flow cytometry for annexin V binding), calcium flux (flow cytometry for fluo-4 AM), and clot formation and retraction. These experiments were also conducted in the presence of the TMEM16F activity inhibitors Niclosamide and Clofazimine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we show that exposure to SARS-CoV-2 Spike promotes platelet activation, adhesion and spreading, both when present on the envelope of virions or upon expression on the plasma membrane of cells. Spike was effective both as a sole agonist or by enhancing the effect of known platelet activators, such as collagen and collagen-related peptide. In particular, Spike exerted a noticeable effect on the procoagulant phenotype of platelets, by enhancing calcium flux, phosphatidylserine externalisation, and thrombin generation. Eventually, this resulted in a striking increase in thrombin-induced clot formation and retraction. Both Niclosamide and Clofazimine almost abolished this Spike-induced pro-coagulant response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Together, these findings provide a pathogenic mechanism to explain thrombosis associated to COVID-19 lung disease, by which Spike present in SARS-CoV-2 virions or exposed on the surface of infected cells, leads to local platelet stimulation and subsequent activation of the coagulation cascade. As platelet TMEM16F is central in this process, these findings reinforce the rationale of repurposing drugs targeting this protein, such as Niclosamide, for COVID-19 therapy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472668" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein activates TMEM16F-mediated platelet pro-coagulant activity (142 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267791</id><title>Global epidemiology of SARS-CoV-2 infection: a systematic review and meta-analysis of standardized population-based seroprevalence studies, Jan 2020-Oct 2021 (100 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.141182+00:00</updated><author><name>Isabel Bergeri</name></author><author><name>Mairead Whelan</name></author><author><name>Harriet Ware</name></author><author><name>Lorenzo Subissi</name></author><author><name>Anthony Nardone</name></author><author><name>Hannah C Lewis</name></author><author><name>Zihan Li</name></author><author><name>Xiaomeng Ma</name></author><author><name>Marta Valenciano</name></author><author><name>Brianna Cheng</name></author><author><name>Lubna Al Ariqi</name></author><author><name>Arash Rashidian</name></author><author><name>Joseph Okeibunor</name></author><author><name>Tasnim Azim</name></author><author><name>Pushpa Wijesinghe</name></author><author><name>Linh-Vi Le</name></author><author><name>Aisling Vaughan</name></author><author><name>Richard Pebody</name></author><author><name>Andrea Vicari</name></author><author><name>Tingting Yan</name></author><author><name>Mercedes Yanes-Lane</name></author><author><name>Christian Cao</name></author><author><name>Matthew P Cheng</name></author><author><name>Jesse Papenburg</name></author><author><name>David Buckeridge</name></author><author><name>Niklas Bobrovitz</name></author><author><name>Rahul K Arora</name></author><author><name>Maria D van Kerkhove</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 case data underestimates infection and immunity, especially in low- and middle-income countries (LMICs). We meta-analyzed standardized SARS-CoV-2 seroprevalence studies to estimate global seroprevalence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives/Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted a systematic review and meta-analysis, searching MEDLINE, Embase, Web of Science, preprints, and grey literature for SARS-CoV-2 seroprevalence studies aligned with the WHO UNITY protocol published between 2020-01-01 and 2021-10-29. Eligible studies were extracted and critically appraised in duplicate. We meta-analyzed seroprevalence by country and month, pooling to estimate regional and global seroprevalence over time; compared seroprevalence from infection to confirmed cases to estimate under-ascertainment; meta-analyzed differences in seroprevalence between demographic subgroups; and identified national factors associated with seroprevalence using meta-regression. PROSPERO: CRD42020183634.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We identified 396 full texts reporting 736 distinct seroprevalence studies (41% LMIC), including 355 low/moderate risk of bias studies with national/sub-national scope in further analysis. By April 2021, global SARS-CoV-2 seroprevalence was 26.1%, 95% CI [24.6-27.6%]. Seroprevalence rose steeply in the first half of 2021 due to infection in some regions (e.g., 18.2% to 45.9% in Africa) and vaccination and infection in others (e.g., 11.3% to 57.4% in the Americas high-income countries), but remained low in others (e.g., 0.3% to 1.6% in the Western Pacific). In 2021 Q1, median seroprevalence to case ratios were 1.9:1 in HICs and 61.9:1 in LMICs. Children 0-9 years and adults 60+ were at lower risk of seropositivity than adults 20-29. In a multivariate model using data pre-vaccination, more stringent public health and social measures were associated with lower seroprevalence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Global seroprevalence has risen considerably over time and with regional variation, however much of the global population remains susceptible to SARS-CoV-2 infection. True infections far exceed reported COVID-19 cases. Standardized seroprevalence studies are essential to inform COVID-19 control measures, particularly in resource-limited regions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267791" rel="alternate" title="Global epidemiology of SARS-CoV-2 infection: a systematic review and meta-analysis of standardized population-based seroprevalence studies, Jan 2020-Oct 2021 (100 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472704</id><title>Simulation of the omicron variant of SARS-CoV-2 shows broad antibody escape, weakened ACE2 binding, and modest increase in furin binding (91 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.141971+00:00</updated><author><name>M. Zaki Jawaid</name></author><author><name>A. Baidya</name></author><author><name>R. Mahboubi-Ardakani</name></author><author><name>Richard L. Davis</name></author><author><name>Daniel L. Cox</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The recent emergence of the omicron variant of the SARS-CoV-2 virus with large numbers of mutations has raised concern about a potential new surge in infections. Here we use molecular dynamics to study the biophysics of the interface of the omicron spike protein binding to (i) the ACE2 receptor protein, (ii) antibodies from all known binding regions, and (iii) the furin binding domain. Our simulations suggest that while there is significant reduction of antibody binding strength corresponding to escape, the omicron spike pays a cost in terms of weaker receptor binding. The furin cleavage domain is the same or weaker binding than the alpha variant, suggesting less viral load and disease intensity than the extant delta variant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472704" rel="alternate" title="Simulation of the omicron variant of SARS-CoV-2 shows broad antibody escape, weakened ACE2 binding, and modest increase in furin binding (91 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472920</id><title>Amyloidogenesis of SARS-CoV-2 Spike Protein (80 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.142611+00:00</updated><author><name>Sofie Nystrom</name></author><author><name>Per Hammarstrom</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 infection is associated with a surprising number of morbidities. Uncanny similarities with amyloid-disease associated blood coagulation and fibrinolytic disturbances together with neurologic and cardiac problems led us to investigate the amyloidogenicity of the SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein (S-protein). Amyloid fibril assays of peptide library mixtures and theoretical predictions identified seven amyloidogenic sequences within the S-protein. All seven peptides in isolation formed aggregates during incubation at 37°C. Three 20-amino acid long synthetic Spike peptides (sequence 191-210, 599-618, 1165-1184) fulfilled three amyloid fibril criteria: nucleation dependent polymerization kinetics by ThT, Congo red positivity and ultrastructural fibrillar morphology. Full-length folded S-protein did not form amyloid fibrils, but amyloid-like fibrils with evident branching were formed during 24 hours of S-protein co-incubation with the protease neutrophil elastase (NE) in vitro. NE efficiently cleaved S-protein rendering exposure of amyloidogenic segments and accumulation of the peptide 193-202, part of the most amyloidogenic synthetic Spike peptide. NE is overexpressed at inflamed sites of viral infection and at vaccine injection sites. Our data propose a molecular mechanism for amyloidogenesis of SARS-CoV-2 S-protein in humans facilitated by endoproteolysis. The potential implications of S-protein amyloidogenesis in COVID-19 disease associated pathogenesis and consequences following S-protein based vaccines should be addressed in understanding the disease, long COVID-19, and vaccine side effects.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472920" rel="alternate" title="Amyloidogenesis of SARS-CoV-2 Spike Protein (80 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.472112</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 Spike triggers barrier dysfunction and vascular leak via integrins and TGF-β signaling (72 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.143297+00:00</updated><author><name>Scott B. Biering</name></author><author><name>Francielle Tramontini Gomes de Sousa</name></author><author><name>Laurentia V. Tjang</name></author><author><name>Felix Pahmeier</name></author><author><name>Richard Ruan</name></author><author><name>Sophie F. Blanc</name></author><author><name>Trishna S. Patel</name></author><author><name>Caroline M. Worthington</name></author><author><name>Dustin R. Glasner</name></author><author><name>Bryan Castillo-Rojas</name></author><author><name>Venice Servellita</name></author><author><name>Nicholas T.N. Lo</name></author><author><name>Marcus P. Wong</name></author><author><name>Colin M. Warnes</name></author><author><name>Daniel R. Sandoval</name></author><author><name>Thomas Mandel Clausen</name></author><author><name>Yale A. Santos</name></author><author><name>Victoria Ortega</name></author><author><name>Hector C. Aguilar</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey D. Esko</name></author><author><name>Charles Y. Chui</name></author><author><name>John E. Pak</name></author><author><name>P. Robert Beatty</name></author><author><name>Eva Harris</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Severe COVID-19 is associated with epithelial and endothelial barrier dysfunction within the lung as well as in distal organs. While it is appreciated that an exaggerated inflammatory response is associated with barrier dysfunction, the triggers of this pathology are unclear. Here, we report that cell-intrinsic interactions between the Spike (S) glycoprotein of SARS-CoV-2 and epithelial/endothelial cells are sufficient to trigger barrier dysfunction &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and vascular leak &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, independently of viral replication and the ACE2 receptor. We identify an S-triggered transcriptional response associated with extracellular matrix reorganization and TGF-β signaling. Using genetic knockouts and specific inhibitors, we demonstrate that glycosaminoglycans, integrins, and the TGF-β signaling axis are required for S-mediated barrier dysfunction. Our findings suggest that S interactions with barrier cells are a contributing factor to COVID-19 disease severity and offer mechanistic insight into SARS-CoV-2 triggered vascular leak, providing a starting point for development of therapies targeting COVID-19 pathogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.472112" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 Spike triggers barrier dysfunction and vascular leak via integrins and TGF-β signaling (72 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472252</id><title>Improved neutralization of the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant after Pfizer-BioNTech BNT162b2 COVID-19 vaccine boosting (66 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.143722+00:00</updated><author><name>Kerri Basile</name></author><author><name>Rebecca J Rockett</name></author><author><name>Kenneth McPhie</name></author><author><name>Michael Fennell</name></author><author><name>Jessica Johnson-Mackinnon</name></author><author><name>Jessica E Agius</name></author><author><name>Winkie Fong</name></author><author><name>Hossinur Rahman</name></author><author><name>Danny Ko</name></author><author><name>Linda Donavan</name></author><author><name>Linda Hueston</name></author><author><name>Connie Lam</name></author><author><name>Alicia Arnott</name></author><author><name>Sharon C-A Chen</name></author><author><name>Susan Maddocks</name></author><author><name>Matthew V O’Sullivan</name></author><author><name>Dominic E Dwyer</name></author><author><name>Vitali Sintchenko</name></author><author><name>Jen Kok</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In late November 2021, the World Health Organization declared the SARS-CoV-2 lineage B.1.1.529 the fifth variant of concern, Omicron. This variant has acquired 15 mutations in the receptor binding domain of the spike protein, raising concerns that Omicron could evade naturally acquired and vaccine-derived immunity. We utilized an authentic virus, multicycle neutralisation assay to demonstrate that sera collected 1, 3, and 6 months post-two doses of Pfizer-BioNTech BNT162b2 has a limited ability to neutralise SARS-CoV-2. However, four weeks after a third dose, neutralizing antibody titres are boosted. Despite this increase, neutralising antibody titres are reduced 4-fold for Omicron compared to lineage A.2.2 SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472252" rel="alternate" title="Improved neutralization of the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant after Pfizer-BioNTech BNT162b2 COVID-19 vaccine boosting (66 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472719</id><title>Striking Antibody Evasion Manifested by the Omicron Variant of SARS-CoV-2 (48 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.144027+00:00</updated><author><name>Lihong Liu</name></author><author><name>Sho Iketani</name></author><author><name>Yicheng Guo</name></author><author><name>Jasper Fuk-Woo Chan</name></author><author><name>Maple Wang</name></author><author><name>Liyuan Liu</name></author><author><name>Yang Luo</name></author><author><name>Hin Chu</name></author><author><name>Yiming Huang</name></author><author><name>Manoj S. Nair</name></author><author><name>Jian Yu</name></author><author><name>Kenn Ka-Heng Chik</name></author><author><name>Terrence Tsz-Tai Yuen</name></author><author><name>Chaemin Yoon</name></author><author><name>Kelvin Kai-Wang To</name></author><author><name>Honglin Chen</name></author><author><name>Michael T. Yin</name></author><author><name>Magdalena E. Sobieszczyk</name></author><author><name>Yaoxing Huang</name></author><author><name>Harris H. Wang</name></author><author><name>Zizhang Sheng</name></author><author><name>Kwok-Yung Yuen</name></author><author><name>David D. Ho</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Omicron (B.1.1.529) variant of SARS-CoV-2 was only recently detected in southern Africa, but its subsequent spread has been extensive, both regionally and globally.  It is expected to become dominant in the coming weeks, probably due to enhanced transmissibility.  A striking feature of this variant is the large number of spike mutations that pose a threat to the efficacy of current COVID-19 vaccines and antibody therapies. This concern is amplified by the findings from our study.  We found B.1.1.529 to be markedly resistant to neutralization by serum not only from convalescent patients, but also from individuals vaccinated with one of the four widely used COVID-19 vaccines. Even serum from persons vaccinated and boosted with mRNA-based vaccines exhibited substantially diminished neutralizing activity against B.1.1.529. By evaluating a panel of monoclonal antibodies to all known epitope clusters on the spike protein, we noted that the activity of 18 of the 19 antibodies tested were either abolished or impaired, including ones currently authorized or approved for use in patients. In addition, we also identified four new spike mutations (S371L, N440K, G446S, and Q493R) that confer greater antibody resistance to B.1.1.529. The Omicron variant presents a serious threat to many existing COVID-19 vaccines and therapies, compelling the development of new interventions that anticipate the evolutionary trajectory of SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472719" rel="alternate" title="Striking Antibody Evasion Manifested by the Omicron Variant of SARS-CoV-2 (48 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.21267684</id><title>The impact of the COVID-19 school closure on adolescents’ use of mental healthcare services in Sweden (38 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.144302+00:00</updated><author><name>Helena Svaleryd</name></author><author><name>Evelina Björkegren</name></author><author><name>Jonas Vlachos</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;School closures used to contain the COVID-19 pandemic may have negative impacts on students’ mental health but credible evidence is scarce. Sweden moved upper-secondary students to remote learning but, as the only country in the OECD, kept schools at lower levers open throughout the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using nationwide register data, we estimate the difference in the use of mental healthcare services between upper- and lower-secondary students during the pandemic, and relate this to the same group difference prior to the pandemic. For the main analysis, this difference-in-difference approach is applied to the period April-June 2020 when upper-secondary schools were fully closed. We also study the periods July-December 2020 when upper-secondary schools were largely open, and January-March 2021 when they were partially closed. We study the impact on all contacts with hospitals and specialist psychiatric care due to mental and behavioral disorder, as well as prescriptions for antidepressants, insomnia, and ADHD drugs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compared with expected rates, the use of mental healthcare services among upper-secondary students fell by -3.71 [CI95 -5.52 to -1.91] cases per 1000 during April-June 2020, largely due to a reduction in depression and anxiety-related diagnoses (-1.49; CI95 [-2.36 to -0.63]) and prescriptions (-1.80; CI95 [-2.93 to -0.68]). This reduction in the use of mental healthcare services corresponds to a 4.36% CI95 [-6.47 to -2.25]) decrease compared to the level prior to the pandemic. The decrease compared to expected rates persists through July-December 2020 (-3.55%; CI95 [-5.38 to -1.71]) and January-March 2021 (-5.23%; CI95 [-7.24 to -3.21]). The reduction is stronger among students in the 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; (-5.06%; CI95 [-8.02 to -2.09]) and 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; (-4.86%; CI95 [-8.19 to -1.53]) year of upper-secondary school. The decrease is concentrated to students who was not in contact with mental healthcare services earlier in the academic year (-16.70%; CI95 [-22.20 to -11.20]). The relative reduction is largest for unplanned care (-13.88%; CI95 [-19.35 to -8.42]) and care at emergency units (-18.19%; CI95 [-26.44 to -9.92]).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Closing upper-secondary schools in Sweden reduced use of mental healthcare services. There is no indication of this being due to reduced accessibility. In a setting with no strict lockdown, moving to online teaching for a limited period did not worsen mental health among students in upper-secondary schools.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.21267684" rel="alternate" title="The impact of the COVID-19 school closure on adolescents’ use of mental healthcare services in Sweden (38 tweets)"/><category term="Psychiatry and Clinical Psychology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472585</id><title>Compared with SARS-CoV2 wild type’s spike protein, the SARS-CoV2 omicron’s receptor binding motif has adopted a more SARS-CoV1 and/or bat/civet-like structure (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.145948+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael O. Glocker</name></author><author><name>Kwabena F.M. Opuni</name></author><author><name>Hans-Juergen Thiesen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Our study focuses on free energy calculations of SARS-CoV2 spike protein receptor binding motives (RBMs) from wild type and variants-of-concern with particular emphasis on currently emerging SARS- CoV2 omicron variants of concern (VOC). Our computational free energy analysis underlines the occurrence of positive selection processes that specify omicron host adaption and bring changes on the molecular level into context with clinically relevant observations. Our free energy calculations studies regarding the interaction of omicron’s RBM with human ACE2 shows weaker binding to ACE2 than alpha’s, delta’s, or wild type’s RBM. Thus, less virus is predicted to be generated in time per infected cell. Our mutant analyses predict with focus on omicron variants a reduced spike-protein binding to ACE2-receptor protein possibly enhancing viral fitness / transmissibility and resulting in a delayed induction of danger signals as trade-off. Finally, more virus is produced but less per cell accompanied with delayed Covid-19 immunogenicity and pathogenicity. Regarding the latter, more virus is assumed to be required to initiate inflammatory immune responses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472585" rel="alternate" title="Compared with SARS-CoV2 wild type’s spike protein, the SARS-CoV2 omicron’s receptor binding motif has adopted a more SARS-CoV1 and/or bat/civet-like structure (37 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267729</id><title>Interdependencies between cellular and humoral immune responses in heterologous and homologous SARS-CoV-2 vaccination (36 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.146224+00:00</updated><author><name>Moritz M. Hollstein</name></author><author><name>Lennart Münsterkötter</name></author><author><name>Michael P. Schön</name></author><author><name>Armin Bergmann</name></author><author><name>Thea M. Husar</name></author><author><name>Anna Abratis</name></author><author><name>Abass Eidizadeh</name></author><author><name>Meike Schaffrinski</name></author><author><name>Karolin Zachmann</name></author><author><name>Anne Schmitz</name></author><author><name>Jason Scott Holsapple</name></author><author><name>Hedwig Stanisz-Bogeski</name></author><author><name>Julie Schanz</name></author><author><name>Uwe Groß</name></author><author><name>Andreas Leha</name></author><author><name>Andreas E. Zautner</name></author><author><name>Moritz Schnelle</name></author><author><name>Luise Erpenbeck</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Homologous and heterologous SARS-CoV-2-vaccinations yield different spike protein-directed humoral and cellular immune responses. However, their interdependencies remain elusive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COV-ADAPT is a prospective, observational cohort study of 417 healthcare workers who received homologous vaccination with Astra (ChAdOx1-S; AstraZeneca) or BNT (BNT162b2; Biontech/Pfizer) or heterologous vaccination with Astra/BNT. We assessed the humoral (anti-spike-RBD-IgG, neutralizing antibodies, antibody avidity) and cellular (spike-induced T cell interferon-γ release) immune response in blood samples up to 2 weeks before (T1) and 2 to 12 weeks following secondary immunization (T2).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Initial vaccination with Astra resulted in lower anti-spike-RBD-IgG responses compared to BNT (70±114 vs. 226±279 BAU/ml, p&amp;lt;0.01) at T1, whereas T cell activation did not differ significantly. Booster vaccination with BNT proved superior to Astra at T2 (anti-spike-RBD-IgG: Astra/BNT 2387±1627 and BNT/BNT 3202±2184 vs. Astra/Astra 413±461 BAU/ml, both p&amp;lt;0.001; spike-induced T cell interferon-&lt;italic&gt;γ&lt;/italic&gt; release: Astra/BNT 5069±6733 and BNT/BNT 4880±7570 vs. Astra/Astra 1152±2243 mIU/ml, both p&amp;lt;0.001). No significant differences were detected between BNT-boostered groups at T2. For Astra, we observed no booster effect on T cell activation. We found associations between anti-spike-RBD-IgG levels (Astra/BNT and BNT/BNT) and T cell responses (Astra/Astra and Astra/BNT) from T1 to T2. There were also links between levels of anti-spike-RBD-IgG and T cell at both time points (all groups combined). All regimes yielded neutralizing antibodies and increased antibody avidity at T2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interdependencies between humoral and cellular immune responses differ between common SARS-CoV-2 vaccination regimes. T cell activation is unlikely to compensate for poor humoral responses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG), ER723/3-1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Research in context&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Evidence before this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We searched Pubmed for papers published between 01/01/2019 and 14/05/2021 with the search terms “covid-19” combined with “vaccination” and “heterologous”, excluding “BCG”. Of the 41 papers found, none addressed the combination of ChAdOx1-S by AstraZeneca (Astra) and BNT162b2 by Biontech/Pfizer (BNT). After our study was initiated, the CombiVacS trial reported a significant booster effect when BNT was given after initial vaccination with Astra.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; The investigators of the CoCo trial subsequently published data on heterologous immunization in comparison to homologous Astra in a small population (n=87), with the heterologous immunization scheme showing a superior humoral and cellular immune response.&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; Further studies investigated heterologous vaccinations with Astra and BNT as well as homologous Astra and BNT regimes and also found superior humoral and cellular immune responses in the heterologous regimes compared to homologous Astra, and comparable or slightly superior immune responses when compared to homologous BNT vaccination.&lt;sup&gt;3–6&lt;/sup&gt; The body of research covering the effects of heterologous immunization regimes has recently been aggregated in a systematic review.&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Added value of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To our knowledge, this is the first study that evaluates the interdependencies of cellular and humoral immune responses following heterologous vaccination with Astra/BNT in a large group of individuals. Our data show strong correlations between humoral and cellular immune responses with the prime-boost combination Astra/BNT. The findings suggest that individuals with a robust initial response developed strong humoral and cellular immune responses after booster immunization.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Implications of all the available evidence&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our study and the available data suggest that due to its superior capacity to elicit a humoral and cellular immune response, mRNA-based vaccines such as BNT should be chosen for booster vaccination rather than Astra. This seems to be particularly important in individuals whose immune response was poor after initial vaccination with Astra.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We demonstrate here an association between humoral and cellular immune responses following vaccination. Our findings suggest that distinct differences between common COVID-19 vaccination regimes should be taken into account in population-based vaccine programs. The present data indicate that a poor humoral immune response is unlikely to be mitigated by a strong cellular immune response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267729" rel="alternate" title="Interdependencies between cellular and humoral immune responses in heterologous and homologous SARS-CoV-2 vaccination (36 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.21267834</id><title>Comparison of the Immunogenicity of five COVID-19 vaccines in Sri Lanka (28 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.146554+00:00</updated><author><name>Chandima Jeewandara</name></author><author><name>Inoka Sepali Aberathna</name></author><author><name>Saubhagya Danasekara</name></author><author><name>Laksiri Gomes</name></author><author><name>Suranga Fernando</name></author><author><name>Dinuka Guruge</name></author><author><name>Thushali Ranasinghe</name></author><author><name>Banuri Gunasekera</name></author><author><name>Achala Kamaladasa</name></author><author><name>Heshan Kuruppu</name></author><author><name>Gayasha Somathilake</name></author><author><name>Jeewantha Jayamali</name></author><author><name>Deshni Jayathilaka</name></author><author><name>Helanka Dinesh Kumara Wijayatilake</name></author><author><name>Pradeep Darshana Pushpakumara</name></author><author><name>Michael Harvie</name></author><author><name>Thashmi Nimasha</name></author><author><name>Shiromi Devika Grace de Silva</name></author><author><name>Ruwan Wijayamuni</name></author><author><name>Lisa Schimanski</name></author><author><name>Pramila Rijal</name></author><author><name>Jack Tan</name></author><author><name>Alain Townsend</name></author><author><name>Graham S. Ogg</name></author><author><name>Gathsaurie Neelika Malavige</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We assessed antibody responses 3 months post-vaccination in those who received mRNA-1273 (n=225), Sputnik V (n=128) or the first dose of Gam-COVID-Vac (n=184) and compared the results with previously reported data of Sinopharm and AZD1222 vaccinees. 99.5% of Moderna &amp;gt;94% of AZD1222 or Sputnik V, 72% to 76% of Gam-COVID-Vac (first dose) and 38.1% to 68.3% of Sinopharm vaccinees had ACE2 blocking antibodies above the positive threshold. The ACE2 blocking antibody levels were highest to lowest was Moderna &amp;gt; Sputnik V/ AZD1222 (had equal levels)&amp;gt; first dose of Gam-COVID-Vac &amp;gt; Sinopharm. All Moderna recipients had antibodies above the positive threshold to the ancestral (WT), B.1.1.7, B.1.351.1 and 80% positivity rate for B.1.617.2. Positivity rates of Sputnik V vaccinees for WT and variants, were higher than AZD1222 vaccinees, while Sinopharm vaccinees had the lowest positivity rates (&amp;lt;16.7%). These findings highlight the need for further studies to understand the effects on clinical outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.21267834" rel="alternate" title="Comparison of the Immunogenicity of five COVID-19 vaccines in Sri Lanka (28 tweets)"/><category term="Allergy and Immunology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472838</id><title>A third vaccination with a single T cell epitope protects against SARS-CoV-2 infection in the absence of neutralizing antibodies (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.146997+00:00</updated><author><name>Iris N. Pardieck</name></author><author><name>Esme T.I. van der Gracht</name></author><author><name>Dominique M.B. Veerkamp</name></author><author><name>Felix M. Behr</name></author><author><name>Suzanne van Duikeren</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Beyrend</name></author><author><name>Jasper Rip</name></author><author><name>Reza Nadafi</name></author><author><name>Tetje C. van der Sluis</name></author><author><name>Elham Beyranvand Nejad</name></author><author><name>Nils Mulling</name></author><author><name>Dena J. Brasem</name></author><author><name>Marcel G.M. Camps</name></author><author><name>Sebenzile K. Myeni</name></author><author><name>Peter J. Bredenbeek</name></author><author><name>Marjolein Kikkert</name></author><author><name>Yeonsu Kim</name></author><author><name>Luka Cicin-Sain</name></author><author><name>Tamim Abdelaal</name></author><author><name>Klaas P.J.M. van Gisbergen</name></author><author><name>Kees L.M.C. Franken</name></author><author><name>Jan Wouter Drijfhout</name></author><author><name>Cornelius J.M. Melief</name></author><author><name>Gerben C.M. Zondag</name></author><author><name>Ferry Ossendorp</name></author><author><name>Ramon Arens</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the mechanisms and impact of booster vaccinations can facilitate decisions on vaccination programmes. This study shows that three doses of the same synthetic peptide vaccine eliciting an exclusive CD8+ T cell response against one SARS-CoV-2 Spike epitope protected all mice against lethal SARS-CoV-2 infection in the K18-hACE2 transgenic mouse model in the absence of neutralizing antibodies, while only a second vaccination with this T cell vaccine was insufficient to provide protection. The third vaccine dose of the single T cell epitope peptide resulted in superior generation of effector-memory T cells in the circulation and tissue-resident memory T (TRM) cells, and these tertiary vaccine-specific CD8+ T cells were characterized by enhanced polyfunctional cytokine production. Moreover, fate mapping showed that a substantial fraction of the tertiary effector-memory CD8+ T cells developed from remigrated TRM cells. Thus, repeated booster vaccinations quantitatively and qualitatively improve the CD8+ T cell response leading to protection against otherwise lethal SARS-CoV-2 infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472838" rel="alternate" title="A third vaccination with a single T cell epitope protects against SARS-CoV-2 infection in the absence of neutralizing antibodies (24 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472619</id><title>Transcriptomic responses of the human kidney to acute injury at single cell resolution (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.147288+00:00</updated><author><name>Christian Hinze</name></author><author><name>Christine Kocks</name></author><author><name>Janna Leiz</name></author><author><name>Nikos Karaiskos</name></author><author><name>Anastasiya Boltengagen</name></author><author><name>Christopher Mark Skopnik</name></author><author><name>Jan Klocke</name></author><author><name>Jan-Hendrik Hardenberg</name></author><author><name>Helena Stockmann</name></author><author><name>Inka Gotthardt</name></author><author><name>Benedikt Obermayer</name></author><author><name>Laleh Haghverdi</name></author><author><name>Emanuel Wyler</name></author><author><name>Markus Landthaler</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Bachmann</name></author><author><name>Andreas C. Hocke</name></author><author><name>Victor Corman</name></author><author><name>Jonas Busch</name></author><author><name>Wolfgang Schneider</name></author><author><name>Nina Himmerkus</name></author><author><name>Markus Bleich</name></author><author><name>Kai-Uwe Eckardt</name></author><author><name>Philipp Enghard</name></author><author><name>Nikolaus Rajewsky</name></author><author><name>Kai M Schmidt-Ott</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Acute kidney injury (AKI) occurs frequently in critically ill patients and is associated with adverse outcomes. Cellular mechanisms underlying AKI and kidney cell responses to injury remain incompletely understood. Methods: We performed single-nuclei transcriptomics, bulk transcriptomics, molecular imaging studies, and conventional histology on kidney tissues from 8 individuals with severe AKI (stage 2 or 3 according to Kidney Disease: Improving Global Outcomes (KDIGO) criteria). Specimens were obtained within 1-2 hours after individuals had succumbed to critical illness associated with respiratory infections, with 4 of 8 individuals diagnosed with COVID-19. Control kidney tissues were obtained post-mortem or after nephrectomy from individuals without AKI. Results: High-depth single cell-resolved gene expression data of human kidneys affected by AKI revealed enrichment of novel injury-associated cell states within the major cell types of the tubular epithelium, in particular in proximal tubules, thick ascending limbs and distal convoluted tubules. Four distinct, hierarchically interconnected injured cell states were distinguishable and characterized by transcriptome patterns associated with oxidative stress, hypoxia, interferon response, and epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition, respectively. Transcriptome differences between individuals with AKI were driven primarily by the cell type-specific abundance of these four injury subtypes rather than by private molecular responses. AKI-associated changes in gene expression between individuals with and without COVID-19 were similar. Conclusion: The study provides an extensive resource of the cell type-specific transcriptomic responses associated with critical illness-associated AKI in humans, highlighting recurrent disease-associated signatures and inter-individual heterogeneity. Personalized molecular disease assessment in human AKI may foster the development of tailored therapies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472619" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptomic responses of the human kidney to acute injury at single cell resolution (24 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.21267582</id><title>Echinacea purpurea for the Long-term Prevention of Viral Respiratory Tract Infections during COVID-19 Pandemic: A Randomized, Open, Controlled, Exploratory Clinical Study (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.147692+00:00</updated><author><name>Emil Kolev</name></author><author><name>Lilyana Mircheva</name></author><author><name>Michael R. Edwards</name></author><author><name>Sebastian L. Johnston</name></author><author><name>Krassimir Kalinov</name></author><author><name>Rainer Stange</name></author><author><name>Giuseppe Gancitano</name></author><author><name>Wim Vanden Berghe</name></author><author><name>Samo Kreft</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 vaccination is effective in preventing severe COVID-19, but efficacy in reducing viral load and transmission wanes over time. In addition, the emergence of novel SARS-CoV-2 variants increases the threat of uncontrolled dissemination and additional antiviral therapies are urgently needed for effective containment. In previous &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; studies &lt;italic&gt;Echinacea purpurea&lt;/italic&gt; demonstrated strong antiviral activity against enveloped viruses, including SARS-CoV-2. In this study, we examined the potential of &lt;italic&gt;Echinacea purpurea&lt;/italic&gt; in preventing and treating respiratory tract infections (RTIs) and in particular, SARS-CoV-2 infections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;120 healthy volunteers (m,f, 18 – 75 years) were randomly assigned to &lt;italic&gt;Echinacea&lt;/italic&gt; prevention or control group without any intervention. After a run-in week, participants went through 3 prevention cycles of 2, 2 and 1 months with daily 2’400mg &lt;italic&gt;Echinacea purpurea&lt;/italic&gt; extract (Echinaforce®, EF). The prevention cycles were interrupted by breaks of 1 week. Acute respiratory symptoms were treated with 4’000 mg EF for up to 10 days, and their severity assessed via a diary. Naso/oropharyngeal swabs and venous blood samples were routinely collected every month and during acute illnesses for detection and identification of respiratory viruses, including SARS-CoV-2 via RT-qPCR and serology.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Summarized over all phases of prevention, 21 and 29 samples tested positive for any virus in the EF and control group, of which 5 and 14 samples tested SARS-CoV-2 positive (RR=0.37, Chi-square test, p=0.03). Overall, 10 and 14 symptomatic episodes occurred, of which 5 and 8 were COVID-19 (RR=0.70, Chi-square test, p&amp;gt;0.05). EF treatment when applied during acute episodes significantly reduced the overall virus load by at least 2.12 log&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;/sub&gt; or approx. 99% (t-test, p&amp;lt;0.05), the time to virus clearance by 8.0 days for all viruses (Wilcoxon test, p=0.02) and by 4.8 days for SARS-CoV-2 (p&amp;gt;0.05) in comparison to control. Finally, EF treatment significantly reduced fever days (1 day vs 11 days, Chi-square test, p=0.003) but not the overall symptom severity. There were fewer COVID-19 related hospitalizations in the EF treatment group (N=0 vs N=2).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Discussion/Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;EF exhibited antiviral effects and reduced the risk of viral RTIs, including SARS-CoV-2. By substantially reducing virus loads in infected subjects, EF offers a supportive addition to existing mandated treatments like vaccinations. Future confirmatory studies are warranted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Clinical Trials registration Nr&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;NCT05002179&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.21267582" rel="alternate" title="Echinacea purpurea for the Long-term Prevention of Viral Respiratory Tract Infections during COVID-19 Pandemic: A Randomized, Open, Controlled, Exploratory Clinical Study (23 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472255</id><title>Broad antiviral effects of Echinacea purpurea against SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern and potential mechanism of action (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.147860+00:00</updated><author><name>Selvarani Vimalanathan</name></author><author><name>Mahmoud Shehata</name></author><author><name>Kannan Sadasivam</name></author><author><name>Serena Delbue</name></author><author><name>Maria Dolci</name></author><author><name>Elena Pariani</name></author><author><name>Sarah D’Alessandro</name></author><author><name>Stephan Pleschka</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (VOC) represent an alarming threat as they show altered biological behavior and may escape vaccination effectiveness. Some exhibit increased pathogenicity and transmissibility compared to the original wild type WUHAN (Hu-1). Broad-spectrum antivirals could complement and further enhance preventive benefits achieved through SARS-CoV-2 vaccination campaigns&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The anti-coronavirus activity of &lt;italic&gt;Echinacea purpurea&lt;/italic&gt; (Echinaforce® extract, EF) against (i) VOCs B1.1.7 (alpha), B.1.351.1 (beta), P.1 (gamma), B1.617.2 (delta), AV.1 (Scottish) and B1.525 (eta), (ii) SARS-CoV-2 spike (S) protein-pseudotyped viral particles and reference strain OC43 as well as (iii) wild-type SARS-CoV-2 (Hu-1) were analyzed. Molecular dynamics (MD) were applied to study interaction of Echinacea’s phytochemical markers with known pharmacological viral and host cell targets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;EF extract broadly inhibited propagation of all investigated SARS-CoV-2 VOCs as well as entry of SARS-CoV-2 pseudoparticles at EC50’s ranging from 3.62 to 12.03 µg/ml. Preventive addition of 20 µg/ml EF to epithelial cells significantly reduced sequential infection with SARS-CoV-2 (Hu-1) as well as with the common human strain OC43. MD analyses showed constant binding affinities to Hu-1, B1.1.7, B.1.351, P.1 and B1.617.2-typic S protein variants for alkylamides, caftaric acidand feruoyl-tartaric acid in EF extract. They further indicated that the EF extract could possibly interact with TMPRSS-2, a serine protease required for virus endocytosis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;EF extract demonstrated stable antiviral activity across 6 tested VOCs, which is likely due to the constant affinity of the contained phytochemical marker substances to all spike variants. A possible interaction of EF with TMPRSS-2 partially would explain cell protective benefits of the extract by inhibition of endocytosis. EF may therefore offer a supportive addition to vaccination endeavors in the control of existing and future SARS-CoV-2 virus mutations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472255" rel="alternate" title="Broad antiviral effects of Echinacea purpurea against SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern and potential mechanism of action (19 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267810</id><title>Early detection and improved genomic surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 variants from deep sequencing data (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.148091+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniele Ramazzotti</name></author><author><name>Davide Maspero</name></author><author><name>Fabrizio Angaroni</name></author><author><name>Marco Antoniotti</name></author><author><name>Rocco Piazza</name></author><author><name>Alex Graudenzi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the definition of fruitful strategies to contrast the worldwide diffusion of SARS-CoV-2, maximum efforts must be devoted to the early detection of dangerous variants. An effective help to this end is granted by the analysis of deep sequencing data of viral samples, which are typically discarded after the creation of consensus sequences. Indeed, only with deep sequencing data it is possible to identify intra-host low-frequency mutations, which are a direct footprint of mutational processes that may eventually lead to the origination of functionally advantageous variants. Accordingly, a timely and statistically robust identification of such mutations might inform political decision-making with significant anticipation with respect to standard analyses based on con-sensus sequences.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To support our claim, we here present the largest study to date of SARS-CoV-2 deep sequencing data, which involves 220,788 high quality samples, collected over 20 months from 137 distinct studies. Importantly, we show that a rele-vant number of spike and nucleocapsid mutations of interest associated to the most circulating variants, including Beta, Delta and Omicron, might have been intercepted several months in advance, possibly leading to different public-health decisions. In addition, we show that a refined genomic surveillance system involving high- and low-frequency mutations might allow one to pin-point possibly dangerous emerging mutation patterns, providing a data-driven automated support to epidemiologists and virologists.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267810" rel="alternate" title="Early detection and improved genomic surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 variants from deep sequencing data (17 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472622</id><title>Computational analysis of the effect of SARS-CoV-2 variant Omicron Spike protein mutations on dynamics, ACE2 binding and propensity for immune escape (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.148257+00:00</updated><author><name>Natalia Teruel</name></author><author><name>Matthew Crown</name></author><author><name>Matthew Bashton</name></author><author><name>Rafael Najmanovich</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The recently reported Omicron (B.1.1.529) SARS-CoV-2 variant has a large number of mutations in the Spike (S) protein compared to previous variants. Here we evaluate the potential effect of Omicron S mutations on S protein dynamics and ACE2 binding as contributing factors to infectivity as well as propensity for immune escape. We define a consensus set of mutations from 77 sequences assigned as Omicron in GISAID as of November 25. We create structural models of the Omicron S protein in the open and closed states, as part of a complex with ACE2 and for each of 77 complexes of S bound to different antibodies with known structures. We have previously utilized Dynamical Signatures (DS) and the Vibrational Entropy Score (VDS) to evaluate the propensity of S variants to favour the open state. Here, we introduce the Binding Influence Score (BIS) to evaluate the influence of mutations on binding affinity based on the net gain or loss of interactions within the protein-protein interface. BIS shows excellent correlation with experimental data (Pearson correlation coefficient of 0.87) on individual mutations in the ACE2 interface for the Alpha, Beta, Gamma, Delta and Omicron variants combined. On the one hand, the DS of Omicron highly favours a more rigid open state and a more flexible closed state with the largest VDS of all variants to date, suggesting a large increase in the chances to interact with ACE2. On the other hand, the BIS shows that apart from N501Y, all other mutations in the interface reduce ACE2 binding affinity. VDS and BIS show opposing effects on the overall effectiveness of Omicron mutations to promote binding to ACE2 and therefore initiate infection. To evaluate the propensity for immune escape we calculated the net change of favourable and unfavourable interactions within each S-antibody interface. The net change of interactions shows a positive score (a net increase of favourable interactions and decrease of unfavourable ones) for 41 out of 77 antibodies, a nil score for 15 and a negative score for 21 antibodies. Therefore, in only 28% of S-antibody complexes (21/77) we predict some level of immune escape due to a weakening of the interactions with Omicron S. Considering that most antibody epitopes and the mutations are within the S-ACE2 interface our results suggest that mutations within the RBD of Omicron may give rise to only partial immune escape, which comes at the expense of reduced ACE2 binding affinity. However, this reduced ACE2 affinity appears to have been offset by increasing the occupancy of the open state of the Spike protein.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472622" rel="alternate" title="Computational analysis of the effect of SARS-CoV-2 variant Omicron Spike protein mutations on dynamics, ACE2 binding and propensity for immune escape (16 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.21267793</id><title>Antibody-mediated Immunogenicity against SARS-CoV-2 following priming, boosting and hybrid immunity: insights from 11 months of follow-up of a healthcare worker cohort in Israel, December 2020-October 2021 (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.148386+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael Edelstein</name></author><author><name>Karine Wiegler Beiruti</name></author><author><name>Hila Ben-Amram</name></author><author><name>Naor Bar-Zeev</name></author><author><name>Christian Sussan</name></author><author><name>Hani Asulin</name></author><author><name>David Strauss</name></author><author><name>Younes Bathish</name></author><author><name>Salman Zarka</name></author><author><name>Kamal Abu Jabal</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We determined circulating anti-S SARS-CoV-2 IgG antibody titres in a vaccinated healthcare workers (HCWs) cohort from Northern Israel in the 11 months following primary vaccination according to age, ethnicity, boosting timing and previous infection status.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;All consenting HCWs were invited to have their circulating IgG levels measured before vaccination and at 6 subsequent timepoints. All HCWs with suspected COVID-19 were PCR tested. We described trends in circulating IgG geometric mean concentration by age, ethnicity, timing of boosting and previous infection status and compared strata using Kruskall-Wallis tests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among 985 vaccinated HCWs. IgG titres gradually decreased in all groups over the study duration. Younger or previously infected individuals had higher initial IgG levels (p&amp;lt;0.001 in both cases); differences substantially decreased or disappeared at 7-9 months, before boosting. Pre-infection IgG levels in infected participants were similar to levels measured at the same timepoint in HCWs who remained uninfected (p&amp;gt;0.3). IgG GMC in those boosted 6-7 months after dose 2 was lower compared with those boosted 8-9 months after (1999-vs 2736, p=0.02).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Immunity waned 6 months post-priming in all age groups and in previously infected individuals, reversed by boosting. IgG titres decrease among previously infected individuals and the proportion of reinfected individuals in this group, comparable to the proportion of breakthrough infection in previously uninfected individuals suggests individuals with hybrid immunity (infection+vaccination) may also require further doses. Our study also highlights the difficulty in determining protective IgG levels and the need to clarify the optimal timing in 3 dose regimens&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.21267793" rel="alternate" title="Antibody-mediated Immunogenicity against SARS-CoV-2 following priming, boosting and hybrid immunity: insights from 11 months of follow-up of a healthcare worker cohort in Israel, December 2020-October 2021 (13 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472433</id><title>Production and secretion of functional full-length SARS-CoV-2 spike protein in Chlamydomonas reinhardtii (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.148633+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna Kiefer</name></author><author><name>Justus Niemeyer</name></author><author><name>Anna Probst</name></author><author><name>Gerhard Erkel</name></author><author><name>Michael Schroda</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The spike protein is the major protein on the surface of coronaviruses. It is therefore the prominent target of neutralizing antibodies and consequently the antigen of all currently admitted vaccines against SARS-CoV-2. Since it is a 1273-amino acids glycoprotein with 22 N-linked glycans, the production of functional, full-length spike protein was limited to mammalian and insect cells, requiring complex culture media. Here we report the production of full-length SARS-CoV-2 spike protein – lacking the C-terminal membrane anchor – as a secreted protein in the prefusion-stabilized conformation in the unicellular green alga &lt;italic&gt;Chlamydomonas reinhardtii&lt;/italic&gt;. We show that the spike protein is efficiently cleaved at the furin cleavage site during synthesis in the alga and that cleavage is abolished upon mutation of the multi-basic cleavage site. We could enrich the spike protein from culture medium by ammonium sulfate precipitation and demonstrate its functionality based on its interaction with recombinant ACE2 and ACE2 expressed on human 293T cells. &lt;italic&gt;Chlamydomonas reinhardtii&lt;/italic&gt; is a GRAS organism that can be cultivated at low cost in simple media at a large scale, making it an attractive production platform for recombinant spike protein and other biopharmaceuticals in low-income countries.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472433" rel="alternate" title="Production and secretion of functional full-length SARS-CoV-2 spike protein in Chlamydomonas reinhardtii (12 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.21267350</id><title>Risk of SARS-CoV-2 testing, PCR-confirmed infections and COVID-19-related hospital admissions in children and young people: birth cohort study (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.148781+00:00</updated><author><name>Pia Hardelid</name></author><author><name>Graziella Favarato</name></author><author><name>Linda Wijlaars</name></author><author><name>Lynda Fenton</name></author><author><name>Jim McMenamin</name></author><author><name>Tom Clemens</name></author><author><name>Chris DIBBEN</name></author><author><name>Ai Milojevic</name></author><author><name>Alison Macfarlane</name></author><author><name>Jonathon Taylor</name></author><author><name>Steve Cunningham</name></author><author><name>Rachael Wood</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background
There have been no population-based studies of SARS-CoV-2 testing, PCR-confirmed infections and COVID-19-related hospital admissions across the full paediatric age range. We examine the epidemiology of SARS-CoV-2 in children and young people (CYP) aged &amp;lt;23 years. 

Methods
We used a birth cohort of all children born in Scotland since 1997, constructed via linkage between vital statistics, hospital records and SARS-CoV-2 surveillance data. We calculated risks of tests and PCR-confirmed infections per 1000 CYP-years between August and December 2020, and COVID-19-related hospital admissions per 100,000 CYP-years between February and December 2020. We used Poisson and Cox proportional hazards regression models to determine risk factors.

Results
Among the 1226855 CYP in the cohort, there were 378402 tests, 19005 PCR confirmed infections and 346 admissions, corresponding to rates of 770.8/1000 (95% confidence interval 768.4-773.3), 179.4 (176.9-182.0) and 29.4/100,000 (26.3-32.8) CYP-years respectively. Infants had the highest COVID-19-related admission rates. Chronic conditions, particularly multiple types of conditions, was strongly associated with COVID-19-related admissions across all ages. The hazard ratio for &amp;gt;1 chronic condition type was 12.2 (7.9-18.82) compared to children with no chronic conditions. 89% of admitted children had no chronic conditions recorded.

Conclusions
Infants, and CYP with chronic conditions are at highest risk of admission with COVID-19, however the majority of admitted CYP have no chronic conditions. These results provide evidence to support risk/benefit analyses for paediatric COVID-19 vaccination programmes. Studies examining whether maternal vaccine during pregnancy prevents COVID-19 admissions in infants are urgently needed. 

Funding
UK Research and Innovation-Medical Research Council&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.21267350" rel="alternate" title="Risk of SARS-CoV-2 testing, PCR-confirmed infections and COVID-19-related hospital admissions in children and young people: birth cohort study (12 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.21267847</id><title>COVID-19 vaccination, from first dose to booster: New insights into the frequency of most common systemic adverse events and possible booster nocebo effects based on a systematic review (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.148963+00:00</updated><author><name>Claudia Behrens</name></author><author><name>Maria Samii-Moghadam</name></author><author><name>Tatiana Gasperazzo</name></author><author><name>Anna M. Gross</name></author><author><name>Jack Mitchell</name></author><author><name>Johannes B. Lampe</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on placebo data, it has been recently demonstrated that the frequencies of most common adverse events (AEs) of COVID-19 vaccination are overestimated due to negative expectation bias of vaccine recipients (nocebo effect). Since booster studies lack comparators, estimating the extent of the nocebo effect is difficult. We aimed to overcome this obstacle through a systematic comparison of most common AE frequencies across vaccine doses (first, second, booster), age groups, and vaccine vs. placebo arms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We systematically assessed systemic AEs in approved COVID-19 vaccines according to the PRISMA guidelines. All documents regarding COVID-19 vaccines with a booster dose authorized by the FDA (cutoff date 19 November 2021) were systematically searched on PubMed and the FDA website. Solicited systemic AEs from all documents supporting approval/authorization were collected. After standardization of doses and age groups, AE frequencies were compared between vaccine and placebo.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two trials were identified for BNT162b2 (n=21,785 participants), two for mRNA-1273 (n=22,324), and one for Ad26.COV2.S (n=4,085). Fever cases dropped to about half with the booster dose in all vaccines, whereas all other systemic AE frequencies were similar to the preceding dose. Almost no fever cases occurred with placebo (first/second dose); all other systemic AEs occurred at high frequencies. After subtracting placebo arm values from vaccine values, the frequencies for the various AEs were roughly comparable within each dose for each vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fever is the only solicited systemic AE that can be assessed objectively. It occurs about 50% less often with the booster than with the preceding dose. This may indirectly indicate a considerable overestimation of systemic AEs in the case of booster vaccinations and a pronounced nocebo effect. The nocebo effect appears to substantially contribute to the differences in the frequencies of the various systemic AEs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;No funding received.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Research in context&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Evidence before this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A high nocebo effect has recently been shown for the most common solicited adverse events (AEs) based on the randomized controlled trials of several vaccines approved for COVID-19. To date, there has been no systematic review of systemic AEs in COVID-19 vaccines with a booster dose approved by the FDA. Normally, assessing the extent of the nocebo effect requires the implementation of randomized, placebo-controlled studies. However, for ethical reasons, studies underlying the authorization of COVID-19 booster vaccines are not controlled. Therefore, reported AEs lack any reference parameter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We searched PubMed and medRxiv for nocebo effects regarding the objectively measurable AE fever using the terms “(COVID) AND (nocebo) AND (fever)” with no language restrictions; no hits were found on PubMed and six were found on medRxiv. The search without any indication, using only the search terms “(nocebo) AND (fever)”, resulted in two hits on PubMed and six hits on medRxiv. An additional search was performed for “(vaccine or COVID) AND nocebo”; 21 hits were found on PubMed and 12 on medRxiv. None of the hits obtained with the three searches showed evidence of relevance for the present topic of a direct association of fever with the nocebo effect.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Added value of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instead of placebo AE data as reference parameter, we suggest fever as an objectively measurable value to estimate the extent of the nocebo effect in uncontrolled vaccination studies. To our knowledge, this is a new concept with which evidence for the extent of a possible nocebo effect in COVID-19 booster vaccination can be provided. With this approach we directly supplement information on the most recently reported nocebo effects in first, second and booster vaccine doses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to indirectly compare the solicited systemic AE frequencies of approved COVID-19 vaccines across all doses, with easy-to-understand graphs and based on all approval-relevant trials. This is astonishing, as in the context of a pandemic it is essential to communicate scientific data in a generally understandable manner and according to the highest scientific standards. The graphs provided in this work could serve as an example for such clear communication.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Implications of all the available evidence&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using the example of systemic AEs, we were able to show that the frequency of AEs in COVID-19 booster vaccination may be overestimated. Fever as an objective measure to estimate the nocebo effect could help to optimize public awareness campaigns in the future. The graphic presentation of results facilitates a deeper understanding of complex scientific data and provides new insights. It is therefore ideal for a highly dynamic scientific field and may also be applied to other challenges in the COVID-19 pandemic and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.21267847" rel="alternate" title="COVID-19 vaccination, from first dose to booster: New insights into the frequency of most common systemic adverse events and possible booster nocebo effects based on a systematic review (12 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472466</id><title>Enrichment analysis on regulatory subspaces: a novel direction for the superior description of cellular responses to SARS-CoV-2 (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.149201+00:00</updated><author><name>Pedro P. Rodrigues</name></author><author><name>Rafael S. Costa</name></author><author><name>Rui Henriques</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Statement: The enrichment analysis of discriminative cell transcriptional responses to SARS-CoV-2 infection using biclustering produces a broader set of superiorly enriched GO terms and KEGG pathways against alternative state-of-the-art machine learning approaches, unraveling novel knowledge. Motivation and methods: The comprehensive understanding of the impacts of the SARS-CoV-2 virus on infected cells is still incomplete. This work identifies and analyses the main cell regulatory processes affected and induced by SARS-CoV-2, using transcriptomic data from several infectable cell lines available in public databases and in vivo samples. We propose a new class of statistical models to handle three major challenges, namely the scarcity of observations, the high dimensionality of the data, and the complexity of the interactions between genes. Additionally, we analyse the function of these genes and their interactions within cells to compare them to ones affected by IAV (H1N1), RSV and HPIV3 in the target cell lines. Results: Gathered results show that, although clustering and predictive algorithms aid classic functional enrichment analysis, recent pattern-based biclustering algorithms significantly improve the number and quality of the detected biological processes. Additionally, a comparative analysis of these processes is performed to identify potential pathophysiological characteristics of COVID-19. These are further compared to those identified by other authors for the same virus as well as related ones such as SARS-CoV-1. This approach is particularly relevant due to a lack of other works utilizing more complex machine learning tools within this context.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472466" rel="alternate" title="Enrichment analysis on regulatory subspaces: a novel direction for the superior description of cellular responses to SARS-CoV-2 (12 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267809</id><title>mRNA COVID-19 vaccine effectiveness against SARS-CoV-2 infection in a prospective community cohort, rural Wisconsin, November 2020-December 2021 (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.149329+00:00</updated><author><name>Huong Q McLean</name></author><author><name>David L McClure</name></author><author><name>Jennifer P King</name></author><author><name>Jennifer K Meece</name></author><author><name>David Pattinson</name></author><author><name>Gabriele Neumann</name></author><author><name>Yoshihiro Kawaoka</name></author><author><name>Melissa A Rolfes</name></author><author><name>Edward A Belongia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Reduced COVID-19 vaccine effectiveness (VE) has been observed with increasing predominance of the Delta variant. In a prospective rural community cohort of 1265 participants, VE against symptomatic and asymptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection was 56% for mRNA COVID-19 vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267809" rel="alternate" title="mRNA COVID-19 vaccine effectiveness against SARS-CoV-2 infection in a prospective community cohort, rural Wisconsin, November 2020-December 2021 (12 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472657</id><title>Development and Characterization of Recombinant Vesicular Stomatitis Virus (rVSV)-based Bivalent Vaccine Against COVID-19 Delta Variant and Influenza Virus (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.149491+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhujun Ao</name></author><author><name>Maggie Jing Ouyang</name></author><author><name>Titus Abiola Olukitibi</name></author><author><name>Bryce Warner</name></author><author><name>Robert Vendramelli</name></author><author><name>Thang Truong</name></author><author><name>Manli Zhang</name></author><author><name>Sam Kung</name></author><author><name>Keith R Fowke</name></author><author><name>Darwyn Kobasa</name></author><author><name>Xiaojian Yao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 and influenza are both highly contagious respiratory diseases with a wide range of severe symptoms and cause great disease burdens globally. It has become very urgent and important to develop a bivalent vaccine that is able to target these two infectious diseases simultaneously. In this study, we generated three attenuated replicating recombinant VSV (rVSV) vaccine candidates. These rVSV-based vaccines co-express SARS-CoV-2 Delta variant spike protein (SP) or the receptor binding domain (RBD) and four copies of the highly conserved M2 ectodomain (M2e) of influenza A fused with the Ebola glycoprotein DC-targeting/activation domain. Animal studies have shown that immunization with these bivalent rVSV vaccines induced efficient but variable levels of humoral and cell-mediated immune responses against both SARS-CoV-2 and influenza M2e protein. Significantly, our vaccine candidates induced production of high levels of neutralizing antibodies that protected cells against SARS-CoV-2 Delta and other SP-pseudovirus infections in culture. Furthermore, vaccination with the bivalent VSV vaccine via either intramuscular or intranasal route efficiently protected mice from the lethal challenge of H1N1 and H3N2 influenza viruses and significantly reduced viral load in the lungs. These studies provide convincing evidence for the high efficacy of this bivalent vaccine to prevent influenza replication and initiate robust immune responses against SARS-CoV-2 Delta variants. Further investigation of its efficacy to protect against SARS-CoV-2 Delta variants will provide substantial evidence for new avenues to control two contagious respiratory infections, COVID-19 and influenza.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472657" rel="alternate" title="Development and Characterization of Recombinant Vesicular Stomatitis Virus (rVSV)-based Bivalent Vaccine Against COVID-19 Delta Variant and Influenza Virus (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.21267573</id><title>The age-dependent immunogenicity after two doses of MVC-COV1901 vaccine (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.149759+00:00</updated><author><name>Chia En Lien</name></author><author><name>Yi-Jiun Lin</name></author><author><name>Yi-Ling Lin</name></author><author><name>I-Chen Tai</name></author><author><name>Charles Chen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A post-hoc analysis of the phase 2 data was performed for the SARS-COV-2 subunit protein vaccine MVC-COV1901. Anti-spike IgG, neutralization assays with live virus and pseudovirus were used to demonstrate age-dependent vaccine-induced antibody response to the vaccine. Results showed that an association exists between age and immune responses to the vaccine, providing further support for the need of booster shots, especially for the older age groups.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.21267573" rel="alternate" title="The age-dependent immunogenicity after two doses of MVC-COV1901 vaccine (11 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.472134</id><title>SARS-CoV2 variant-specific replicating RNA vaccines protect from disease and pathology and reduce viral shedding following challenge with heterologous SARS-CoV2 variants of concern (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.149897+00:00</updated><author><name>David W. Hawman</name></author><author><name>Kimberly Meade-White</name></author><author><name>Jacob Archer</name></author><author><name>Shanna Leventhal</name></author><author><name>Drew Wilson</name></author><author><name>Carl Shaia</name></author><author><name>Samantha Randall</name></author><author><name>Amit P. Khandhar</name></author><author><name>Tien-Ying Hsiang</name></author><author><name>Michael Gale</name></author><author><name>Peter Berglund</name></author><author><name>Deborah Heydenburg Fuller</name></author><author><name>Heinz Feldmann</name></author><author><name>Jesse H. Erasmus</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite mass public health efforts, the SARS-CoV2 pandemic continues as of late-2021 with resurgent case numbers in many parts of the world. The emergence of SARS-CoV2 variants of concern (VoC) and evidence that existing vaccines that were designed to protect from the original strains of SARS-CoV-2 may have reduced potency for protection from infection against these VoC is driving continued development of second generation vaccines that can protect against multiple VoC. In this report, we evaluated an alphavirus-based replicating RNA vaccine expressing Spike proteins from the original SARS-CoV-2 Alpha strain and recent VoCs delivered &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; via a lipid inorganic nanoparticle. Vaccination of both mice and Syrian Golden hamsters showed that vaccination induced potent neutralizing titers against each homologous VoC but reduced neutralization against heterologous challenges. Vaccinated hamsters challenged with homologous SARS-CoV2 variants exhibited complete protection from infection. In addition, vaccinated hamsters challenged with heterologous SARS-CoV-2 variants exhibited significantly reduced shedding of infectious virus. Our data demonstrate that this vaccine platform elicits significant protective immunity against SARS-CoV2 variants and supports continued development of this platform.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.472134" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV2 variant-specific replicating RNA vaccines protect from disease and pathology and reduce viral shedding following challenge with heterologous SARS-CoV2 variants of concern (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472476</id><title>Potential cross-protection against SARS-CoV-2 from previous exposure to bovine coronavirus (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.150192+00:00</updated><author><name>Lana Bazan Peters Querne</name></author><author><name>Fernanda Zettel Bastos</name></author><author><name>Breno Castello Branco Beirão</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Humans have long shared infectious agents with cattle, and the common cold OC-43 CoV is a not-so-distant example of cross-species viral spillover. Human exposure to BCoV is certainly common, as the virus is endemic in cattle-raising regions. This article shows an &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; investigation of shared viral epitopes between BCoV and SARS-CoV-2. HLA recognition and lymphocyte reactivity were assessed using freely-available resources. Several epitopes were shared between BCoV and SARS-CoV-2, both for B and T lymphocytes. These data demonstrate that possible cross-protection is being induced by human exposure to cattle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472476" rel="alternate" title="Potential cross-protection against SARS-CoV-2 from previous exposure to bovine coronavirus (9 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.21267574</id><title>Safety and immunogenicity of a heterologous booster of protein subunit vaccine MVC-COV1901 after two doses of adenoviral vector vaccine AZD1222 (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.150321+00:00</updated><author><name>Shu-Hsing Cheng</name></author><author><name>Yi-Chun Lin</name></author><author><name>Cheng-Pin Chen</name></author><author><name>Chien-Yu Cheng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We report the interim safety and immunogenicity results in participants administrated with a booster dose of protein subunit vaccine MVC-COV1901 at 12 or 24 weeks after two doses of AZD1222 (ChAdOx1 nCoV-19). In subjects fully vaccinated with two doses of AZD1222, waning antibody immunity was apparent within six months of the second dose of AZD1222. At one month after the MVC-COV1901 booster dose, anti-SARS-CoV-2 spike IgG antibody titers and neutralizing antibody titers were 14- and 8.6-fold increased, respectively, when compared to the titer levels on the day of the booster dose. These interim results support the use of MVC-COV1901 as a heterologous booster for individuals vaccinated with AZD1222.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.21267574" rel="alternate" title="Safety and immunogenicity of a heterologous booster of protein subunit vaccine MVC-COV1901 after two doses of adenoviral vector vaccine AZD1222 (8 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267732</id><title>Modelling the recovery of elective waiting lists following COVID-19: scenario projections for England (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.150478+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas C Howlett</name></author><author><name>Richard M Wood</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A significant indirect impact of COVID-19 has been the increasing elective waiting times observed in many countries. In England’s National Health Service, the waiting list has grown from 4.4 million in February 2020 to 5.7m by August 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aims&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The objective of this study was to estimate the trajectory of future waiting list size and waiting times to December 2025.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A scenario analysis was performed using computer simulation and publicly available data as of November 2021. Future demand assumed a phased return of various proportions (0, 25, 50 and 75%) of the estimated 7.1 million referrals ‘missed’ during the pandemic. Future capacity assumed 90, 100 and 110% of that provided in the 12 months immediately before the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a worst case, the waiting list would reach 13.6m (95% CI: 12.4m to 15.6m) by Autumn 2022, if 75% of missed referrals returned and only 90% of pre pandemic capacity could be achieved. Under this scenario, the proportion of patients waiting under 18 weeks would reduce from 67.6% in August 2021 to 42.2% (37.4% to 46.2%) with the number waiting over 52 weeks reaching 1.6m (0.8m to 3.1m) by Summer 2023. At this time, 29.0% (21.3% to 36.8%) of patients would be leaving the waiting list before treatment. Waiting lists would remain pressured under even the most optimistic of scenarios considered, with 18-week performance struggling to maintain 60% (against the 92% constitutional target).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study reveals the long-term challenge for the NHS in recovering elective waiting lists as well as potential implications for patient outcomes and experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267732" rel="alternate" title="Modelling the recovery of elective waiting lists following COVID-19: scenario projections for England (8 tweets)"/><category term="Health Policy"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267549</id><title>The impact of environmental mycobiomes on geographic variation in COVID-19 mortality (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.150754+00:00</updated><author><name>Joshua Ladau</name></author><author><name>Katrina Abuabara</name></author><author><name>Angelica M. Walker</name></author><author><name>Marcin P. Joachimiak</name></author><author><name>Ishan Bansal</name></author><author><name>Yulun Wu</name></author><author><name>Elijah B. Hoffman</name></author><author><name>Chaincy Kuo</name></author><author><name>Nicola Falco</name></author><author><name>Jared Streich</name></author><author><name>Mark J. van der Laan</name></author><author><name>Haruko M. Wainwright</name></author><author><name>Eoin L. Brodie</name></author><author><name>Matthias Hess</name></author><author><name>Daniel Jacobson</name></author><author><name>James B. Brown</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mortality rates during the COVID-19 pandemic have varied by orders of magnitude across communities in the United States&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. Individual, socioeconomic, and environmental factors have been linked to health outcomes of COVID-19&lt;sup&gt;2,3,4,5&lt;/sup&gt;. It is now widely appreciated that the environmental microbiome, composed of microbial communities associated with soil, water, atmosphere, and the built environment, impacts immune system development and susceptibility to immune-mediated disease&lt;sup&gt;6,7,8&lt;/sup&gt;. The human microbiome has been linked to individual COVID-19 disease outcomes&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;, but there are limited data on the influence of the environmental microbiome on geographic variation in COVID-19 across populations&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;. To fill this knowledge gap, we used taxonomic profiles of fungal communities associated with 1,135 homes in 494 counties from across the United States in a machine learning analysis to predict COVID-19 Infection Fatality Ratios (the number of deaths caused by COVID-19 per 1000 SARS-CoV-2 infections&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;; ‘IFR’). Here we show that increased fungal diversity, and in particular indoor exposure to outdoor fungi, is associated with reduced SARS-CoV-2 IFR. Further, we identify seven fungal genera that are the predominant drivers of this protective signal and may play a role in suppressing COVID-19 mortality. This relationship is strongest in counties where human populations have remained stable over at least the previous decade, consistent with the importance of early-life microbial exposures&lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;. We also assessed the explanatory power of 754 other environmental and socioeconomic factors, and found that indoor-outdoor fungal beta-diversity is amongst the strongest predictors of county-level IFR, on par with the most important known COVID-19 risk factors, including age&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;. We anticipate that our study will be a starting point for further integration of environmental mycobiome data with population health information, providing an important missing link in our capacity to identify vulnerable populations. Ultimately, our identification of specific genera predicted to be protective against COVID-19 mortality may point toward novel, proactive therapeutic approaches to infectious disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267549" rel="alternate" title="The impact of environmental mycobiomes on geographic variation in COVID-19 mortality (8 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.21267993</id><title>Predictive value of isolated symptoms for diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2 infection in children tested during peak circulation of the delta variant (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.151523+00:00</updated><author><name>Adrianna L. Westbrook</name></author><author><name>Laura C. Benedit</name></author><author><name>Jennifer K. Frediani</name></author><author><name>Mark A. Griffiths</name></author><author><name>Nabeel Y. Khan</name></author><author><name>Joshua M. Levy</name></author><author><name>Claudia R. Morris</name></author><author><name>Christina A. Rostad</name></author><author><name>Cheryl L. Stone</name></author><author><name>Julie Sullivan</name></author><author><name>Miriam B. Vos</name></author><author><name>Jean Welsh</name></author><author><name>Anna Wood</name></author><author><name>Greg S. Martin</name></author><author><name>Wilbur Lam</name></author><author><name>Nira R. Pollock</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: COVID-19 testing policies for symptomatic children attending U.S. schools or daycare vary, and whether isolated symptoms should prompt testing is unclear. We evaluated children presenting for SARS-CoV-2 testing to determine if the likelihood of having a positive SARS-CoV-2 test differed between participants with one versus ≥ 2 symptoms, and to examine the predictive capability of isolated symptoms. 
Methods: Participants ≤ 18 years presenting for clinical SARS-CoV-2 molecular testing in six sites in urban/suburban/rural Georgia (July-October, 2021; delta variant predominant) were queried about individual symptoms. Participants were classified into three groups: asymptomatic, one symptom only, or ≥ 2 symptoms. SARS-CoV-2 test results and clinical characteristics of the three groups were compared. Sensitivity, specificity, and positive/negative predictive values (PPV/NPV) for isolated symptoms were calculated by fitting a saturated Poisson model. 
Results: Of 602 participants, 21.8% tested positive and 48.7% had a known or suspected close contact. Children reporting one symptom (n=82; OR=6.00, 95% CI: 2.70-13.33) and children reporting ≥ 2 symptoms (n=365; OR=5.25: 2.66-10.38) were significantly more likely to have a positive COVID-19 test than asymptomatic children (n=155), but they were not significantly different from each other (OR=0.88: 0.52-1.49). Sensitivity/PPV were highest for isolated fever (33%/57%), cough (25%/32%), and sore throat (21%/45%); headache had low sensitivity (8%) but higher PPV (33%). Sensitivity/PPV of isolated congestion/rhinorrhea were 8%/9%. 
Conclusions:  With high delta variant prevalence, children with isolated symptoms were as likely as those with multiple symptoms to test positive for COVID-19. Isolated fever, cough, sore throat, or headache, but not congestion/rhinorrhea, offered highest predictive value.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.21267993" rel="alternate" title="Predictive value of isolated symptoms for diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2 infection in children tested during peak circulation of the delta variant (8 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472554</id><title>Relationship between monomer packing and receptor binding domain pocket status in the spike trimer of SARS-CoV-2 variants (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.152061+00:00</updated><author><name>Jim Warwicker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Existence of a SARS-CoV-2 spike protein trimer form with closer packing between monomers when receptor binding domains (RBDs) are all down, locked as opposed to closed, has been associated with linoleic acid (LA) binding at neutral pH, or can occur at acidic pH in the absence of LA binding.  The relationship between degree of closure of the LA binding pocket of the RBD, and monomer burial in the trimer, is examined for a range of spike protein structures, including those with D614G mutation, and that of the Delta variant (which also carries D614G).  Some spike protein structures with this aspartic acid mutation show monomer packing approaching that of the locked form (at neutral pH, without LA binding) for two segments, a third (around the RBD) remains less closely packed.  Analysis of other coronavirus RBD structures suggests that mutation of the RBD in spike protein of the Omicron variant could lead to LA binding pocket changes.  It is proposed that these changes could lead to one of two consequences for the Omicron variant spike protein (which also has the D614G mutation), at neutral pH and without LA binding, either easier access to a locked form throughout that leads to cooperative transitions between all RBD down and all RBD up, or maintenance of a spike trimer with locked characteristics C-terminal to the RBD at the same time as the RBD is free to transit between down and up states.  The situation may also be impacted by spike protein charge mutations in the Omicron lineage that alter pH-dependence around the RBD, in a similar way to the changes induced elsewhere by D614G.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472554" rel="alternate" title="Relationship between monomer packing and receptor binding domain pocket status in the spike trimer of SARS-CoV-2 variants (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267368</id><title>Acute COVID-19 severity and 16-month mental morbidity trajectories in patient populations of six nations (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.152246+00:00</updated><author><name>Ingibjorg Magnusdottir</name></author><author><name>Aniko Lovik</name></author><author><name>Anna Bara Unnarsdottir</name></author><author><name>Daniel L. McCartney</name></author><author><name>Helga Ask</name></author><author><name>Kadri Koiv</name></author><author><name>Lea Arregui Nordahl Christoffersen</name></author><author><name>Sverre Urnes Johnson</name></author><author><name>Andrew M McIntosh</name></author><author><name>Anna K. Kahler</name></author><author><name>Archie Campbell</name></author><author><name>Arna Hauksdottir</name></author><author><name>Chloe Fawns-Ritchie</name></author><author><name>Christian Erikstrup</name></author><author><name>Dorte Helenius</name></author><author><name>Drew Altschul</name></author><author><name>Edda Bjork Thordardottir</name></author><author><name>Elias Eythorsson</name></author><author><name>Emma M. Frans</name></author><author><name>Gunnar Tomasson</name></author><author><name>Harpa Lind Jonsdottir</name></author><author><name>Harpa Runarsdottir</name></author><author><name>Henrik Hjalgrim</name></author><author><name>Hronn Hardardottir</name></author><author><name>Juan Gonzalez-Hijon</name></author><author><name>Karina Banasik</name></author><author><name>Khoa Manh Dinh</name></author><author><name>Li Lu</name></author><author><name>Lili Milani</name></author><author><name>Lill Trogstad</name></author><author><name>Maria Didriksen</name></author><author><name>Omid V. Ebrahimi</name></author><author><name>Patrick F. Sullivan</name></author><author><name>Per Minor Magnus</name></author><author><name>Qing Shen</name></author><author><name>Ragnar Nesvag</name></author><author><name>Reedik Magi</name></author><author><name>Runolfur Palsson</name></author><author><name>Sisse Rye Ostrowski</name></author><author><name>Thomas Werge</name></author><author><name>Asle Hoffart</name></author><author><name>David J. Porteous</name></author><author><name>Fang Fang</name></author><author><name>Johanna Jakobsdottir</name></author><author><name>Kelli Lehto</name></author><author><name>Ole A. Andreassen</name></author><author><name>Ole B.V. Pedersen</name></author><author><name>Thor Aspelund</name></author><author><name>Unnur Anna Valdimarsdottir</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND
The aim of this multinational study was to assess the development of adverse mental health symptoms among individuals diagnosed with COVID-19 in the general population by acute infection severity up to 16 months after diagnosis.
METHODS
Participants consisted of 247 249 individuals from seven cohorts across six countries (Denmark, Estonia, Iceland, Norway, Scotland, and Sweden) recruited from April 2020 through August 2021. We used multivariable Poisson regression to contrast symptom-prevalence of depression, anxiety, COVID-19 related distress, and poor sleep quality among individuals with and without a diagnosis of COVID-19 at entry to respective cohorts by time (0-16 months) from diagnosis. We also applied generalised estimating equations (GEE) analysis to test differences in repeated measures of mental health symptoms before and after COVID-19 diagnosis among individuals ever diagnosed with COVID-19 over time.
FINDINGS
A total of 9979 individuals (4%) were diagnosed with COVID-19 during the study period and presented overall with a higher symptom burden of depression (prevalence ratio [PR] 1.18, 95% confidence interval [95% CI] 1.03-1.36) and poorer sleep quality (1.13, 1.03-1.24) but not with higher levels of symptoms of anxiety or COVID-19 related distress compared with individuals without a COVID-19 diagnosis. While the prevalence of depression and COVID-19 related distress attenuated with time, the trajectories varied significantly by COVID-19 acute infection severity. Individuals diagnosed with COVID-19 but never bedridden due to their illness were consistently at lower risks of depression and anxiety (PR 0.83, 95% CI 0.75-0.91 and 0.77, 0.63-0.94, respectively), while patients bedridden for more than 7 days were persistently at higher risks of symptoms of depression and anxiety (PR 1.61, 95% CI 1.27-2.05 and 1.43, 1.26-1.63, respectively) throughout the 16-month study period.
CONCLUSION
Acute infection severity is a key determinant of long-term mental morbidity among COVID-19 patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267368" rel="alternate" title="Acute COVID-19 severity and 16-month mental morbidity trajectories in patient populations of six nations (6 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267698</id><title>Development and external validation of the DOAT and DOATS scores: simple decision support tools to identify disease progression among nonelderly patients with mild/moderate COVID-19 (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.152934+00:00</updated><author><name>Yoko Shibata</name></author><author><name>Hiroyuki Minemura</name></author><author><name>Yasuhito Suzuki</name></author><author><name>Takefumi Nikaido</name></author><author><name>Yoshinori Tanino</name></author><author><name>Atsuro Fukuhara</name></author><author><name>Ryuzo Kanno</name></author><author><name>Hiroyuki Saito</name></author><author><name>Shuzo Suzuki</name></author><author><name>Taeko Ishii</name></author><author><name>Yayoi Inokoshi</name></author><author><name>Eiichiro Sando</name></author><author><name>Hirofumi Sakuma</name></author><author><name>Tatsuho Kobayashi</name></author><author><name>Hiroaki Kume</name></author><author><name>Masahiro Kamimoto</name></author><author><name>Hideko Aoki</name></author><author><name>Akira Takama</name></author><author><name>Takamichi Kamiyama</name></author><author><name>Masaru Nakayama</name></author><author><name>Kiyoshi Saito</name></author><author><name>Koichi Tanigawa</name></author><author><name>Masahiko Sato</name></author><author><name>Toshiyuki Kanbe</name></author><author><name>Norio Kanzaki</name></author><author><name>Teruhisa Azuma</name></author><author><name>Keiji Sakamoto</name></author><author><name>Yuichi Nakamura</name></author><author><name>Hiroshi Otani</name></author><author><name>Mitsuru Waragai</name></author><author><name>Shinsaku Maeda</name></author><author><name>Tokiya Ishida</name></author><author><name>Keishi Sugino</name></author><author><name>Minoru Inage</name></author><author><name>Noriyuki Hirama</name></author><author><name>Kodai Furuyama</name></author><author><name>Shigeyuki Fukushima</name></author><author><name>Hiroshi Saito</name></author><author><name>Jun-ichi Machiya</name></author><author><name>Hiroyoshi Machida</name></author><author><name>Koya Abe</name></author><author><name>Katsuyoshi Iwabuchi</name></author><author><name>Yuji Katagiri</name></author><author><name>Yasuko Aida</name></author><author><name>Yuki Abe</name></author><author><name>Takahito Ota</name></author><author><name>Yuki Ishizawa</name></author><author><name>Yasuhiko Tsukada</name></author><author><name>Ryuki Yamada</name></author><author><name>Riko Sato</name></author><author><name>Takumi Omuna</name></author><author><name>Hikaru Tomita</name></author><author><name>Mikako Saito</name></author><author><name>Natsumi Watanabe</name></author><author><name>Mami Rikimaru</name></author><author><name>Takaya Kawamata</name></author><author><name>Takashi Umeda</name></author><author><name>Julia Morimoto</name></author><author><name>Ryuichi Togawa</name></author><author><name>Yuki Sato</name></author><author><name>Junpei Saito</name></author><author><name>Kenya Kanazawa</name></author><author><name>Kenji Omae</name></author><author><name>Kurita Noriaki</name></author><author><name>Ken Iseki</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Due to the dissemination of vaccination against severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 in the elderly, the virus-susceptible subjects have shifted to unvaccinated non-elderlies. The risk factors of COVID-19 deterioration in non-elderly patients without respiratory failure have not yet been determined. This study was aimed to create simple predicting method to identify such patients who have high risk for exacerbation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;METHODS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We analyzed the data of 1,675 patients aged under 65 years who were admitted to hospitals with mild-to-moderate COVID-19. For validation, 324 similar patients were enrolled. Disease progression was defined as administration of medication, oxygen inhalation and mechanical ventilator starting one day or longer after admission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;RESULTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The patients who exacerbated tended to be older, male, had histories of smoking, and had high body temperatures, lower oxygen saturation, and comorbidities such as diabetes/obesity and hypertension. Stepwise logistic regression analyses revealed that comorbidities of &lt;underline&gt;d&lt;/underline&gt;iabetes/&lt;underline&gt;o&lt;/underline&gt;besity, &lt;underline&gt;a&lt;/underline&gt;ge ≥ 40 years, body temperature ≥ 38°C, and oxygen saturation &amp;lt; 96% (DOATS) were independent risk factors of worsening COVID-19. As a result two predictive scores were created: DOATS score, which includes all the above risk factors; and DOAT score, which includes all factors except for oxygen saturation. In the original cohort, the areas under the receiver operating characteristic curve of the DOATS and DOAT scores were 0.789 and 0.771, respectively. In the validation, the areas were 0.702 and 0.722, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We established two simple prediction scores that can quickly evaluate the risk of progression of COVID-19 in non-elderly, mild/moderate patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The risk stratification models using independent risks, namely comorbidity of &lt;underline&gt;d&lt;/underline&gt;iabetes or &lt;underline&gt;o&lt;/underline&gt;besity, &lt;underline&gt;a&lt;/underline&gt;ge ≥ 40 years, high body temperature ≥ 38□, and oxygen saturation &amp;lt; 96%, DOATS and DOAT scores, predicted worsening COVID-19 in patients with mild-to-moderate cases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267698" rel="alternate" title="Development and external validation of the DOAT and DOATS scores: simple decision support tools to identify disease progression among nonelderly patients with mild/moderate COVID-19 (6 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267711</id><title>Relationship Between Alcohol Consumption and Telecommuting Preference-Practice Mismatch During the COVID-19 Pandemic (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.153611+00:00</updated><author><name>Chihiro Watanabe</name></author><author><name>Yusuke Konno</name></author><author><name>Reiji Yoshimura</name></author><author><name>Seiichiro Tateishi</name></author><author><name>Ayako Hino</name></author><author><name>Mayumi Tsuji</name></author><author><name>Akira Ogami</name></author><author><name>Masako Nagata</name></author><author><name>Keiji Muramatsu</name></author><author><name>Yoshihisa Fujino</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study examined the association between increased alcohol consumption and telecommuting, comparing employees who expressed a preference for telecommuting and those who did not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted an internet monitor survey. Responses from 20,395 of the 33,302 participants were included in the final sample. Participants were asked about their desire for and frequency of telecommuting, and about changes in alcohol consumption under the COVID-19 pandemic. Data were analyzed by logistic regression analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Participants who telecommuted despite preferring not to do so reported significantly increased alcohol consumption, as revealed by a multivariate analysis (OR=1.62, 95% CI 1.25-2.12). Participants who expressed a preference for telecommuting showed no such increase.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the COVID-19 pandemic, telecommuting that involves a mismatch with employee preference for way of working may be a new risk factor for problematic drinking.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267711" rel="alternate" title="Relationship Between Alcohol Consumption and Telecommuting Preference-Practice Mismatch During the COVID-19 Pandemic (6 tweets)"/><category term="Occupational and Environmental Health"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267800</id><title>A Cloth Facemask Causes No Major Respiratory or Cardiovascular Perturbations during Moderate to Heavy Exercise (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.153885+00:00</updated><author><name>Natália Mendes Guardieiro</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Barreto</name></author><author><name>Felipe Miguel Marticorena</name></author><author><name>Tamires Nunes Oliveira</name></author><author><name>Luana Farias de Oliveira</name></author><author><name>Ana Lucia de Sá Pinto</name></author><author><name>Danilo Marcelo Leite do Prado</name></author><author><name>Bryan Saunders</name></author><author><name>Bruno Gualano</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To investigate whether wearing a cloth facemask could affect physiological and perceptual responses to exercise at distinct exercise intensities in non-trained men and women.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a crossover design, participants (17 men and 18 women) underwent a progressive square-wave test at four intensities (i. at 80% of the ventilatory anerobic threshold [80%VAT]; ii. at VAT; iii. at the respiratory compensation point [RCP]; iv. at exercise peak [Peak] to exhaustion), with or without a triple-layered cloth mask (Mask or No-Mask). Several physiological, metabolic and perceptual measures were analyzed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mask reduced inspiratory capacity at all exercise intensities vs. No-Mask (p&amp;lt;0.0001), irrespective of sex. Mask reduced respiratory frequency vs. No-Mask (p=0.001) at Peak (−8.3 breaths·min&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;; CI: -5.8, -10.8), RCP (−6.9 breaths·min&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;; CI: -4.6, -9.2) and VAT (−6.5 breaths·min&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;; CI: -4.1, -8.8), but not at Baseline or at 80%VAT. Mask also reduced tidal volume (p&amp;lt;0.0001) at both RCP (−0.5L; CI: -0.3, -0.6) and Peak (−0.8L; CI: -0.6, -0.9), but not at Baseline, 80%VAT or VAT. Shallow breathing index was increased with Mask at Peak compared to No-Mask (11.3; CI: 7.5, 15.1), but not at any other intensities. Mask did not change heart rate, lactate, ratings of perceived exertion, blood pressure or oxygen saturation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wearing a cloth facemask during exercise at moderate to heavy intensities is unlikely to incur significant respiratory or cardiovascular changes, irrespective of sex. These data can inform new exercise recommendations for health during the COVID-19 pandemic and debunk unfounded allegations of harmful effects of masks during exercise. ClinicalTrials.gov: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT04887714"&gt;NCT04887714&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What are the new findings?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="simple"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;✓&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using a progressive square-wave test, we showed that wearing a cloth facemask during exercise increased breathing difficulty, but this was dependent upon the exercise intensity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;✓&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Respiratory variables (e.g., inspiratory capacity, respiratory frequency, shallow breathing index) were affected at higher rather than lower intensities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;✓&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mask wearing did not change heart rate, lactate, ratings of perceived exertion, blood pressure or oxygen saturation at any exercise intensity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;✓&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;There were no substantial sex differences on the effects of mask wearing during exercise.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;How might it impact on clinical practice in the future?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="simple"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;✓&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;These data can debunk unfounded allegations on harmful effects of masks during exercise, and help inform new exercise recommendations for health during the COVID-19 pandemic, particularly where facemasks remain necessary.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267800" rel="alternate" title="A Cloth Facemask Causes No Major Respiratory or Cardiovascular Perturbations during Moderate to Heavy Exercise (6 tweets)"/><category term="Sports Medicine"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.21267655</id><title>Presentation, characteristics, treatments and outcomes of mechanically ventilated patients with COVID-19 in Bulgaria (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.154141+00:00</updated><author><name>Neda Bakalova</name></author><author><name>Ivats Natsev</name></author><author><name>Hristo Damov</name></author><author><name>Irina Yatsenko</name></author><author><name>Stefanija Jovinska</name></author><author><name>Rostislav Enev</name></author><author><name>Mikhail Cholakov</name></author><author><name>Filip Abedinov</name></author><author><name>Denitza Kalendjieva</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: The first surge of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) cases in Bulgaria occurred in the fall of 2020. To accommodate the rising number of critically ill patients, new intensive care units were formed in several hospitals. Here we describe the clinical presentation, patient characteristics, treatments and outcomes of mechanically ventilated COVID-19 patients in a newly formed COVID-19 ICU at a tertiary cardiac center in Sofia, Bulgaria.  

Methods: This is a retrospective observational study of mechanically ventilated COVID-19 patients admitted to Sveta Ekaterina University Hospital in Sofia, Bulgaria, between November 4th, 2020 and January 6th, 2021. Data were collected from electronic and written patient records and charts. 

Results: We identified 38 critical care patients admitted with respiratory failure and treated with mechanical ventilation at our COVID-19 ICU during this period. The median age was 66 (IQR 57-76, range 27-89) and 74% were male. Most patients, 36 (95%), had at least one comorbidity. The most common comorbidities were hypertension, valvular heart disease, ischemic heart disease and diabetes mellitus. Overall, 27 (71%) patients had a concomitant cardiac disease other than hypertension and 24% were recent cardiac surgical patients. Inotropic support was required in 29 (76%) patients, renal replacement therapy in 12 (32%) patients and prone positioning and ECMO were used in 5 (13%) and 2 (5%) patients respectively. The median duration of mechanical ventilation was 7.5 (IQR 5-14) days overall and 9 (IQR 6-13) days for survivors. At 30-days 28 (74%) of patients had died. Overall, 32 (84%) patients died in hospital and only 6 (16%) patients were discharged home. 

Conclusions: During the first major surge of COVID-19 cases in Bulgaria, despite the wave arriving later than in other countries, the healthcare system was largely unprepared. In our setting, mortality in critically ill patients requiring mechanical ventilation was very high at 85%. There may be several factors contributing to these results, namely the predominance of cardiovascular comorbidities in our patient population, the strained ICU capacity and the lack of medical personnel to provide adequate intensive care to such complex patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.21267655" rel="alternate" title="Presentation, characteristics, treatments and outcomes of mechanically ventilated patients with COVID-19 in Bulgaria (6 tweets)"/><category term="Intensive Care and Critical Care Medicine"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267039</id><title>Anti-SARS-CoV-2 cellular immunity in 571 vaccinees assessed using an interferon-γ release assay (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.154346+00:00</updated><author><name>Yoshifumi Uwamino</name></author><author><name>Masatoshi Wakui</name></author><author><name>Yoko Yatabe</name></author><author><name>Terumichi Nakagawa</name></author><author><name>Akiko Sakai</name></author><author><name>Toshinobu Kurafuji</name></author><author><name>Ayako Shibata</name></author><author><name>Yukari Tomita</name></author><author><name>Masayo Noguchi</name></author><author><name>Akiko Tanabe</name></author><author><name>Tomoko Arai</name></author><author><name>Akemi Ohno</name></author><author><name>Hiromitsu Yokota</name></author><author><name>Shunsuke Uno</name></author><author><name>Wakako Yamasawa</name></author><author><name>Yasunori Sato</name></author><author><name>Mari Ikeda</name></author><author><name>Akihiko Yoshimura</name></author><author><name>Naoki Hasegawa</name></author><author><name>Hideyuki Saya</name></author><author><name>Mitsuru Murata</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Generation of antigen-specific memory T cells has been analyzed only for few coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) vaccinees, whereas antibody titers have been serologically measured for a large number of individuals. Here, we assessed the anti-severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) cellular immune response in a large cohort using interferon (IFN)-γ release assays (IGRAs) based on short-term whole blood culture. The study included 571 individuals who received the viral spike (S) protein-expressing BNT162b2 mRNA SARS-CoV-2 vaccine. Serum IgG titers against the receptor-binding domain (RBD) of S protein were measured. Samples of 28 vaccinees were subjected to flow cytometry analysis of T cells derived from short-term whole blood culture. IFN-γ production triggered by S antigens was observed in most individuals 8 weeks after receiving the second dose of the vaccine, indicating acquisition of T cell memory responses. The frequencies of activated T cell subsets were strongly correlated with IFN-γ levels, supporting the usability of our approach. S antigen-stimulated IFN-γ levels were weakly correlated with anti-RBD IgG titers and associated with pre-vaccination infection and adverse reactions after the second dose. Our approach revealed cellular immunity acquired after COVID-19 vaccination, providing insights regarding the effects and adverse reactions of vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267039" rel="alternate" title="Anti-SARS-CoV-2 cellular immunity in 571 vaccinees assessed using an interferon-γ release assay (6 tweets)"/><category term="Allergy and Immunology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267562</id><title>Real-world data on immune responses following heterologous prime-boost COVID-19 vaccination schedule with Pfizer and AstraZeneca vaccines in England (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.154680+00:00</updated><author><name>Samantha J Westrop</name></author><author><name>Heather J Whitaker</name></author><author><name>Annabel A Powell</name></author><author><name>Linda Power</name></author><author><name>Corinne Whillock</name></author><author><name>Helen Campbell</name></author><author><name>Ruth Simmons</name></author><author><name>Lenesha Warrener</name></author><author><name>Mary E Ramsay</name></author><author><name>Shamez N Ladhani</name></author><author><name>Kevin E Brown</name></author><author><name>Gayatri Amirthalingham</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;Background&lt;/bold&gt;
There are limited data on immune responses to heterologous COVID–19 immunisation schedules, especially following an extended ≥12–week interval between doses.
&lt;bold&gt;Methods&lt;/bold&gt;
SARS–CoV–2 infection–naïve and previously–infected adults receiving ChAd–BNT (ChAdOx1 nCoV–19, AstraZeneca followed by BNT162b2, Pfizer–BioNTech) or BNT–ChAd as part of the UK national immunisation programme provided blood samples at 30 days and 12 weeks after their second dose. Geometric mean concentrations (GMC) of anti–SARS–CoV–2 spike (S-antibody) and nucleoprotein (N-antibody) IgG antibodies and geometric mean ratios (GMR) were compared with a contemporaneous cohort receiving homologous ChAd–ChAd or BNT–BNT.
&lt;bold&gt;Results&lt;/bold&gt;
During March–October 2021, 75,827 individuals were identified as having received heterologous vaccination, 9,489 invited to participate, 1,836 responded (19.3%) and 656 were eligible. In previously–uninfected adults, S–antibody GMC at 30 days post–second dose were lowest for ChAd–ChAd (862 (95%CI, 694– 1069)) and significantly higher for ChAd–BNT (6233 (5522– 7035); GMR 6.29; (5.04– 7.85); p&amp;lt;0.001), BNT-ChAd (4776 (4066– 5610); GMR 4.55 (3.56– 5.81); p&amp;lt;0.001) and BNT–BNT (5377 (4596– 6289); GMR 5.66 (4.49– 7.15); p&amp;lt;0.001). By 12 weeks after dose two, S–antibody GMC had declined in all groups and remained significantly lower for ChAd–ChAd compared to ChAd–BNT (GMR 5.12 (3.79– 6.92); p&amp;lt;0.001), BNT–ChAd (GMR 4.1 (2.96– 5.69); p&amp;lt;0.001) and BNT–BNT (GMR 6.06 (4.32– 8.50); p&amp;lt;0.001). Previously infected adults had higher S–antibody GMC compared to infection–naïve adults at all time–points and with all vaccine schedules. 
&lt;bold&gt;Conclusions&lt;/bold&gt;
These real–world findings demonstrate heterologous schedules with adenoviral–vector and mRNA vaccines are highly immunogenic and may be recommended after a serious adverse reaction to one vaccine product, or to increase programmatic flexibility where vaccine supplies are constrained.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267562" rel="alternate" title="Real-world data on immune responses following heterologous prime-boost COVID-19 vaccination schedule with Pfizer and AstraZeneca vaccines in England (6 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.11.472202</id><title>Epistatic models predict mutable sites in SARS-CoV-2 proteins and epitopes (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.154958+00:00</updated><author><name>Juan Rodriguez-Rivas</name></author><author><name>Giancarlo Croce</name></author><author><name>Maureen Muscat</name></author><author><name>Martin Weigt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The emergence of new variants of SARS-CoV-2 is a major concern given their potential impact on the transmissibility and pathogenicity of the virus as well as the efficacy of therapeutic interventions. Here, we predict the mutability of all positions in SARS-CoV-2 protein domains to forecast the appearance of unseen variants. Using sequence data from other coronaviruses, pre-existing to SARS-CoV-2, we build statistical models that do not only capture amino-acid conservation but more complex patterns resulting from epistasis. We show that these models are notably superior to conservation profiles in estimating the already observable SARS-CoV-2 variability. In the receptor binding domain of the spike protein, we observe that the predicted mutability correlates well with experimental measures of protein stability and that both are reliable mutability predictors (ROC AUC ~0.8). Most interestingly, we observe an increasing agreement between our model and the observed variability as more data become available over time, proving the anticipatory capacity of our model. When combined with data concerning the immune response, our approach identifies positions where current variants of concern are highly overrepresented. These results could assist studies on viral evolution, future viral outbreaks and, in particular, guide the exploration and anticipation of potentially harmful future SARS-CoV-2 variants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the COVID pandemic, new SARS-CoV-2 variants emerge and spread, some being of major concern due to their increased infectivity or their capacity to reduce vaccine efficiency. Anticipating new mutations, which might give rise to new variants, would be of great interest. Here we construct sequence models predicting how mutable SARS-CoV-2 positions are, using a single SARS-CoV-2 sequence and databases of other coronaviruses. Predictions are tested against available mutagenesis data and the observed variability of SARS-CoV-2 proteins. Interestingly, our predictions agree increasingly with observations, as more SARS-CoV-2 sequences become available. Combining predictions with immunological data, we find a clear overrepresentation of mutations in current variants of concern. The approach may become relevant for potential outbreaks of future viral diseases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.11.472202" rel="alternate" title="Epistatic models predict mutable sites in SARS-CoV-2 proteins and epitopes (6 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.21267794</id><title>Changing of therapeutic trends between the 1st and 2nd wave did not reduce COVID-19 related mortality of renal transplant recipients: a national registry study (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.155213+00:00</updated><author><name>Bastien Berger</name></author><author><name>Marc Hazzan</name></author><author><name>Nassim Kamar</name></author><author><name>Hélène Francois</name></author><author><name>Marie Matignon</name></author><author><name>Clarisse Greze</name></author><author><name>Philippe Gatault</name></author><author><name>Luc Frimat</name></author><author><name>Pierre F Westeel</name></author><author><name>Valentin Goutaudier</name></author><author><name>Renaud Snanoudj</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Colosio</name></author><author><name>Antoine Sicard</name></author><author><name>Dominique Bertrand</name></author><author><name>Christiane Mousson</name></author><author><name>Jamal Bamoulid</name></author><author><name>Antoine Thierry</name></author><author><name>Dany Anglicheau</name></author><author><name>Lionel Couzi</name></author><author><name>Jonathan M Chemouny</name></author><author><name>Agnes Duveau</name></author><author><name>Valerie Moal</name></author><author><name>Yannick Le Meur</name></author><author><name>Gilles Blancho</name></author><author><name>Jérôme Tourret</name></author><author><name>Paolo Malvezzi</name></author><author><name>Christophe Mariat</name></author><author><name>Jean-Philippe Rerolle</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Bouvier</name></author><author><name>Sophie Caillard</name></author><author><name>Olivier Thaunat</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 pandemic evolved in two consecutive waves over 2020 (for France: 1st wave from March 1 to July 31; and 2nd wave from August 1 to December 31). Improvements in the management of COVID-19 led to a reduction of mortality rates in hospitalized patients during the second wave. Whether this progress also benefited to kidney transplant recipients (KTR), a population particularly vulnerable to severe COVID-19, remained unclear.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In France, 957 KTR were hospitalized for COVID-19 in 2020 and their data were prospectively collected in the French SOT COVID registry. The presentation, management, and outcomes of the 359 KTR diagnosed during the 1st wave were compared to those of the 598 of the 2nd wave. Baseline comorbidities were largely similar between KTR of the 2 waves. Maintenance immunosuppression was reduced in most patients but withdrawal of antimetabolite (73.7% vs 58.4%, p&amp;lt;0.001) or CNI (32.1% vs 16.6%, p&amp;lt;0.001) was less frequent during the 2nd wave. Hydroxychloroquine and azithromycin that were commonly used during the 1st wave (21.7% and 30.9%, respectively) were almost abandoned during the 2nd. In contrast, the use of high dose corticosteroids doubled (19.5% vs. 41.6%, p&amp;lt;0.001). Despite these changing trends in COVID-19 management, 60-day mortality was not statistically different between the 2 waves (25.3% vs. 23.9%; Log Rank, p=0.48).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conclude that changing of therapeutic trends during 2020 did not reduce COVID-19 related mortality in KTR. Our data indirectly support the importance of vaccination and monoclonal neutralizing anti-SARS-CoV-2 antibodies to protect KTR from severe COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.21267794" rel="alternate" title="Changing of therapeutic trends between the 1st and 2nd wave did not reduce COVID-19 related mortality of renal transplant recipients: a national registry study (6 tweets)"/><category term="Transplantation"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267740</id><title>Determinants of RSV epidemiology following suppression through pandemic contact restrictions (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.155875+00:00</updated><author><name>Mihaly Koltai</name></author><author><name>Fabienne Krauer</name></author><author><name>David Hodgson</name></author><author><name>Edwin van Leeuwen</name></author><author><name>Marina Treskova-Schwarzbach</name></author><author><name>Mark Jit</name></author><author><name>Stefan Flasche</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 related non-pharmaceutical interventions (NPIs) led to a suppression of RSV circulation in winter 2020/21 throughout Europe and an off-season resurgence in Summer 2021 in several European countries. We explore how such temporary interruption may shape future RSV epidemiology and what factors drive the associated uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We developed an age-structured dynamic transmission model to simulate pre-pandemic RSV infections and hospitalisations. We sampled parameters governing RSV seasonality, immunity acquisition and duration of post-infection immunity and retained those simulations that qualitatively fit the UK’s pre-pandemic epidemiology. From Spring 2020 to Summer 2021 we assumed a 50% reduced contact frequency, returning to pre-pandemic levels from mid-May 2021. We simulated transmission forwards until 2023 and evaluated the impact of the sampled parameters on the projected trajectories of RSV hospitalisations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a lifting of contact restrictions in summer 2021 the model replicated an out-of-season resurgence of RSV. If unmitigated, paediatric RSV hospitalisation incidence in the 2021/22 season was projected to increase by 32% to 67% compared to pre-pandemic levels. The size of the increase depended most on whether infection risk was primarily determined by immunity acquired from previous exposure or general immune maturation. While infants were less affected, the increase in seasonal hospitalisation incidence exceeded 100% in 1-2 year old children and 275% in 2-5 year old children, respectively, in some simulations where immunity from previous exposure dominated. Consequently, the average age of a case increased by 1 to 5 months, most markedly if there was strong immunity acquisition from previous exposure. If immunity to infection was largely determined by age rather than previous exposure, the 2021/22 season started earlier and lasted longer but with a peak incidence lower or similar to pre-pandemic levels. For subsequent seasons, simulations suggested a quick return to pre-pandemic epidemiology, with some slight oscillating behaviour possible depending on the strength of post-exposure immunity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 mitigation measures stopped RSV circulation in the 2020/21 season and generated immunity debt that will likely lead to a temporary increase in RSV burden in the season following the lifting of restrictions, particularly in 1 to 5 year old children. A more accurate understanding of immunity drivers for RSV is needed to better predict the size of such an increase and plan a potential expansion of pharmaceutical and non-pharmaceutical mitigation measures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267740" rel="alternate" title="Determinants of RSV epidemiology following suppression through pandemic contact restrictions (5 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.21267816</id><title>COVID-19 and Indian population: a comparative genetic analysis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.156127+00:00</updated><author><name>Saurabh Patil</name></author><author><name>Sandhya Kiran Pemmasani</name></author><author><name>Neelima Chitturi</name></author><author><name>Ishita Bhatnagar</name></author><author><name>Anuradha Acharya</name></author><author><name>Lingareddy Venkata Subash</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major risk factors of COVID-19 include older age, male gender, and comorbidities. In addition, host genetic makeup is also known to play a major role in COVID-19 susceptibility and severity. To assess the genetic predisposition of the Indian population to COVID-19, a comparative analysis of the frequencies of polymorphisms directly or potentially associated with COVID-19 susceptibility, severity, immune response, and fatal outcomes was done between the Indian population and other major populations (European, African, East Asian, South Asian, and American).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Materials and methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Polymorphisms directly or potentially associated with COVID-19 susceptibility, severity, immune response, and mortality were mined from genetic association studies, comparative genetic studies, expression quantitative trait loci studies among others. Genotype data of these polymorphisms were either sourced from the GenomegaDB™ database of Mapmygenome India Ltd. (sample size = 3054; Indian origin) or were imputed. Polymorphisms with minor allele frequency &amp;gt;= 0.05 and that are in Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium in the Indian population were considered for allele frequency comparison between the Indian population and 1000 Genome population groups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Allele frequencies of 421 polymorphisms were found to be significantly different in the Indian population compared to European, African, East Asian, South Asian, and American populations. 128 polymorphisms were shortlisted based on linkage disequilibrium and were analyzed in detail. Apart from well-studied genes, like ACE2, TMPRSS2, ADAM17, and FURIN, variants from AHSG, IFITM3, PTPN2, CD209, CCL5, HEATR9, SELENBP9, AGO1, HLA-G, MX1, ICAM3, MUC5B, CRP, C1GALT1, and other genes were also found to be significantly different in Indian population. These variants might be implicated in COVID-19 susceptibility and progression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our comparative study unraveled multiple genetic variants whose allele frequencies were significantly different in the Indian population and might have a potential role in COVID-19 susceptibility, its severity, and fatal outcomes. This study can be very useful for selecting candidate genes/variants for future COVID-19 related genetic association studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.21267816" rel="alternate" title="COVID-19 and Indian population: a comparative genetic analysis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267783</id><title>Dynamics of anti-Spike IgG antibody level after full BNT162b2 COVID-19 vaccination in health care workers (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.156357+00:00</updated><author><name>Hiroaki Ikezaki</name></author><author><name>Ryoko Nakashima</name></author><author><name>Kahori Miyoshi</name></author><author><name>Yuichi Hara</name></author><author><name>Jun Hayashi</name></author><author><name>Hiroshi Hara</name></author><author><name>Hideyuki Nomura</name></author><author><name>Nobuyuki Shimono</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The administration of a third vaccine is ongoing in many countries, but the evaluation of vaccine-induced immunity is still insufficient. This study evaluated anti-spike IgG levels in 373 health care workers six months after the BNT162b2 vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dynamics of anti-spike IgG levels six months after the 2nd vaccination were assessed in 49 participants (Analysis-1). A cross-sectional assessment of anti-spike IgG level was performed in 373 participants (Analysis-2). Participants positive for anti-nucleocapsid IgG or IgM and receiving immunosuppressants were excluded from Analysis-2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Analysis 1, the median anti-spike IgG level was lower in the older age group and decreased consistently after the second vaccination regardless of age. In Analysis-2, the anti-spike IgG level was significantly negatively associated with age (r = −0.35, p &amp;lt; 0.01). This correlation remained statistically significant (r = −0.28, p &amp;lt; 0.01) even after adjusting for sex, BMI, smoking habits, alcohol drinking habits, allergies, and the presence of fever or other adverse reactions at the time of the vaccination. Alcohol drinking habit was also associated with the anti-spike IgG level; daily alcohol drinkers had significantly lower anti-spike IgG levels than never alcohol drinkers. Sex, smoking habit, allergy, and fever and other side effects after the vaccination were not associated with anti-spike IgG levels six months after the 2nd vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Six months after the vaccination, the anti-spike IgG level was substantially low among older persons and daily alcohol drinkers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267783" rel="alternate" title="Dynamics of anti-Spike IgG antibody level after full BNT162b2 COVID-19 vaccination in health care workers (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267696</id><title>Impact Of an Immune Modulator Mycobacterium-w On Adaptive Natural Killer Cells and Protection Against COVID-19 (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.156697+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarita Rani Jaiswal</name></author><author><name>Jaganath Arunachalam</name></author><author><name>Ashraf Saifullah</name></author><author><name>Anupama Mehta</name></author><author><name>Gitali Bhagawati</name></author><author><name>Rohit Lakhchaura</name></author><author><name>Hemamalini Aiyer</name></author><author><name>Bakulesh Khamar</name></author><author><name>Suparno Chakrabarti</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The kinetics of NKG2C&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; adaptive natural killer (ANK) cells and NKG2A&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;inhibitory NK (iNK) cells with respect to the incidence of SARS-CoV-2 infection were studied in a cohort of health-care workers following administration of heat killed &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium w&lt;/italic&gt; (Mw group) in comparison to a control group. COVID-19 infection correlated with a lower NKG2C&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;ANK cells at baseline. NKG2C&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;ANK cells at baseline did not differ, but there was a significant upregulation of NKG2C expression and cytokine release in the Mw group (p=0.0009), particularly in those with lower baseline NKG2C expression (&amp;lt;15%), along with marked downregulation of NKG2A&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;iNK cells (p&amp;lt;0.0001), and an increase in the NKG2C&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;ANK/NKG2A&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;iNK ratio. This translated to a significant reduction in COVID-19 and its severity in the Mw group. No impact was observed on T cell subsets. Mw was observed to have a salutary impact on the ANK cell profile which might have provided protection against COVID-19 over a prolonged period in a non-immune high-risk population.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267696" rel="alternate" title="Impact Of an Immune Modulator Mycobacterium-w On Adaptive Natural Killer Cells and Protection Against COVID-19 (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267757</id><title>A systematic literature review of individual-level psychological and behavioral responses to the health information of COVID-19 from social media and legacy media (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.157055+00:00</updated><author><name>Wei Zhai</name></author><author><name>Jian Bian</name></author><author><name>Jing Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xueyin Bai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Covid-19 has been recognized as a terrifying global health threat since its detection, with far-reaching consequences that are unprecedented in the modern era. Since the outbreak of the pandemic, social media and legacy media have collectively delivered health information related to COVID-19 to the public as a catalyst to community perception of risk. However, the existing literature exhibits different viewpoints toward the role of social media and legacy media in disseminating health information of COVID-19. In this regard, this article conducted a systematic literature review to provide an overview of the current state of research concerning individuals-level psychological and behavioral response to COVID-19 related information from different sources, as well as presents the challenges and future research directions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267757" rel="alternate" title="A systematic literature review of individual-level psychological and behavioral responses to the health information of COVID-19 from social media and legacy media (5 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267773</id><title>COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy in diverse groups in the UK - is the driver economic or cultural in student populations? (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.157630+00:00</updated><author><name>Francis Drobniewski</name></author><author><name>Dian Kusuma</name></author><author><name>Agnieszka Broda</name></author><author><name>Enrique Castro-Sánchez</name></author><author><name>Raheelah Ahmad</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Studies have identified a greater reluctance for members of the Black, Asian, and minority ethnic communities to be vaccinated against COVID-19 despite a higher probability of greater harm from COVID-19. We conducted an anonymised questionnaire-based study of students (recruiting primarily before first reports of embolic events) at two London universities to identify whether economic or educational levels were primarily responsible for this reluctance: a postgraduate core group (PGCC) n=860 and a pilot study of undergraduate medical and nursing students (n=103). Asian and Black students were 2.0 and 3.2 times (PGCC) less likely to accept the COVID vaccine than White British students. Similar findings were noted in the pilot study students. As students were studying for Masters or PhD degrees and voluntarily paying high fees, educational and economic reasons were unlikely to be the underlying cause, and wider cultural reservations were more likely. Politicians exerted a strong negative influence, suggesting that campaigns should omit politicians.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267773" rel="alternate" title="COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy in diverse groups in the UK - is the driver economic or cultural in student populations? (4 tweets)"/><category term="Health Policy"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267812</id><title>Analytical Solution of a New SEIR Model Based on Latent Period-Infectious Period Chronological Order (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.157903+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaoping Liu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Susceptible-Infectious-Recovered (&lt;italic&gt;SIR&lt;/italic&gt;) and &lt;italic&gt;SIR&lt;/italic&gt; derived epidemic models have been commonly used to analyze the spread of infectious diseases. The underlying assumption in these models, such as Susceptible-Exposed-Infectious-Recovered (&lt;italic&gt;SEIR&lt;/italic&gt;) model, is that the change in variables &lt;italic&gt;E, I&lt;/italic&gt; or &lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt; at time &lt;italic&gt;t&lt;/italic&gt; is dependent on a fraction of &lt;italic&gt;E&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;I&lt;/italic&gt; at time &lt;italic&gt;t&lt;/italic&gt;. This means that after exposed on a day, this individual may become contagious or even recover on the same day. However, the real situation is different: an exposed individual will become infectious after a latent period (&lt;italic&gt;l&lt;/italic&gt;) and then recover after an infectious period (&lt;italic&gt;i&lt;/italic&gt;). In this study, we proposed a new &lt;italic&gt;SEIR&lt;/italic&gt; model based on the latent period-infectious period chronological order (Liu X., Results Phys. 2021; 20:103712). An analytical solution to equations of this new &lt;italic&gt;SEIR&lt;/italic&gt; model was derived. From this new &lt;italic&gt;SEIR&lt;/italic&gt; model, we obtained a propagated curve of infectious cases under conditions &lt;italic&gt;l&lt;/italic&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;italic&gt;i&lt;/italic&gt;. Similar propagated epidemic curves were reported in literature. However, the conventional &lt;italic&gt;SEIR&lt;/italic&gt; model failed to simulate the propagated epidemic curves under the same conditions. For &lt;italic&gt;l&lt;/italic&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;italic&gt;i&lt;/italic&gt;, the new &lt;italic&gt;SEIR&lt;/italic&gt; models generated bell-shaped curves for infectious cases, and the curve is near symmetrical to the vertical line passing the curve peak. This characteristic can be found in many epidemic curves of daily COVID-19 cases reported from different countries. However, the curve generated from the conventional &lt;italic&gt;SEIR&lt;/italic&gt; model is a right-skewed bell-shaped curve. An example for applying the analytical solution of the new &lt;italic&gt;SEIR&lt;/italic&gt; model equations to simulate the reported daily COVID-19 cases was also given in this paper.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267812" rel="alternate" title="Analytical Solution of a New SEIR Model Based on Latent Period-Infectious Period Chronological Order (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267818</id><title>Performances of community pharmacists and community pharmacies during COVID-19 outbreak: a cross-sectional study (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.158113+00:00</updated><author><name>Afsaneh Sadeghinejad</name></author><author><name>Naemeh Nikvarz</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Community pharmacists can play an important role in the management of coronavirus disease-19 (COVID-19) outbreak by providing pharmaceutical care and education services. In addition to providing drug-related services, community pharmacies must take measures to reduce the risk of COVID-19 transmission to customers and technicians in pharmacy. Therefore, a study was designed to assess community pharmacists’ performance and community pharmacies’ preparedness during COVID-19 outbreak.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Materials &amp;amp; Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A cross-sectional study was conducted in Kerman, Iran. A 20-item checklist consisting of nine items assessing the practice of pharmacists regarding use of personal protective equipment (PPE) and education of people about routes of transmission, prophylaxis and treatment of COVID-19 and eleven items evaluating the adherence of pharmacies to principles of reducing the risk of COVID-19 transmission in public places was used.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of 95 enrolled pharmacists, 55 (57.9%) were female and 78.9% had work experience ≤ 10 years. More than 90% of pharmacists used appropriate PPE and provided information about medications for prevention and treatment of COVID-19 and routs of its transmission to the pharmacy customers. Phone consultation was done by 71.6% of pharmacists. Concerning the preparedness of pharmacies, 92% of personnel used PPE, and hand sanitizers were available in 89.5% of pharmacies. However, a clear sheet was not placed at counters in the majority of pharmacies, and home delivery services were not provided by most pharmacies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The practice of most community pharmacists was acceptable. However, stricter measures should be taken to diminish the probability of COVID-19 transmission in community pharmacies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267818" rel="alternate" title="Performances of community pharmacists and community pharmacies during COVID-19 outbreak: a cross-sectional study (4 tweets)"/><category term="Health Systems and Quality Improvement"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.21267986</id><title>Magnitude, global variation, and temporal development of the COVID-19 infection fatality burden (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.158320+00:00</updated><author><name>Christina Bohk-Ewald</name></author><author><name>Enrique Acosta</name></author><author><name>Tim Riffe</name></author><author><name>Christian Dudel</name></author><author><name>Mikko Myrskyla</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;How deadly is an infection with SARS-CoV-2 worldwide over time? This information is critical for developing and assessing public health responses on the country and global levels. However, imperfect data have been the most limiting factor for estimating the COVID-19 infection fatality burden during the first year of the pandemic. Here we leverage recently emerged compelling data sources and broadly applicable modeling strategies to estimate the crude infection fatality rate (cIFR) in 77 countries from 28 March 2020 to 31 March 2021, using 2.4 million reported deaths and estimated 435 million infections by age, sex, country, and date. The global average of all cIFR estimates is 1.2% (10th to 90th percentile: 0.2% to 2.4%). The cIFR varies strongly across countries, but little within countries over time, and it is often lower for women than men. Cross-country differences in cIFR are largely driven by the age structures of both the general and the truly infected population. While the broad trends and patterns of the cIFR estimates are more robust, we show that their levels are uncertain and sensitive to input data and modeling choices. In consequence, increased efforts at collecting high-quality data are essential for accurately estimating the cIFR, which is a key indicator for better understanding the health and mortality consequences of this pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.21267986" rel="alternate" title="Magnitude, global variation, and temporal development of the COVID-19 infection fatality burden (4 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267804</id><title>Emerging from the COVID-19 pandemic: impacts of variants, vaccines, and duration of immunity (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.159435+00:00</updated><author><name>Ken Newcomb</name></author><author><name>Edwin Michael</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The advent of vaccines against SARS-CoV-2 and the roll out of mass vaccination programs are thought to present the most effective means to control and even end the ongoing pandemic. However, uncertainties connected with the partial effectiveness of present vaccines, duration of immunity against SARS-CoV-2, and potential impact of variant dynamics, mean that it is still possible that the contagion could follow different future paths in different communities. Here, we use an extended SEIR for SARS-COV-2 transmission sequentially calibrated to data on cases and interventions implemented in the state of Florida to explore how these factors may interact to govern potential pandemic futures. Our data-driven forecasts indicate while the introduction of vaccinations could lead to the permanent, albeit drawn-out, ending of the pandemic if the immunity generated through vaccinations and natural infections acts over the long-term, additional futures could become possible if this immunity wanes over time. These futures will be marked by repeated waves of infection, the amplitude and periodicity of which will depend on the duration over which the immunity generated in a population will operate. We conclude that the possibility of these complex futures will require continual vigilance and perhaps fundamental changes in societal responses if we are to effectively control SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.21267804" rel="alternate" title="Emerging from the COVID-19 pandemic: impacts of variants, vaccines, and duration of immunity (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.21267851</id><title>Home monitoring of HbA1c in diabetes mellitus: A protocol for systematic review and narrative synthesis on reliability, accuracy, and patient acceptability (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.159751+00:00</updated><author><name>Jack Colley</name></author><author><name>Hajira Dambha-Miller</name></author><author><name>Beth Stuart</name></author><author><name>Jazz Bartholomew</name></author><author><name>Hermione Price</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Worldwide there are an estimated 463 million people with diabetes. [1] In the UK people with diabetes are offered an annual review including monitoring of Haemoglobin A1c (HbA1c). [2] [3] This can identify people with diabetes who are not meeting their glycaemic targets, enabling early intervention. Those who do not attend these reviews often have higher HbA1c levels and poorer health outcomes. [4] During the Coronavirus disease of 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic, there was a 77% reduction in monitoring of HbA1c in the UK. [5] We hypothesise that people with diabetes could take finger-prick samples at home for the measurement of HbA1c.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Method and Analysis&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We will perform a systematic review of current evidence for capillary blood collected at home for the measurement of HbA1c. We will examine the validity, reliability, safety, and patient acceptability of the use of capillary blood compared with the usual standard of care of venous blood. We will explore variables which affect validity of results. Using core terms of ‘Diabetes’, ‘HbA1c’ and ‘Capillary sampling’ we will search MEDLINE, Embase, CINAHL, Web of Science Core Collection, Google Scholar, Open Grey and other grey literature from database inception until 2021. Risk of bias will be assessed using the ‘COSMIN risk of bias tool to assess the quality of studies on reliability and measurement error’. Database searches and data extraction for primary outcomes will be conducted in duplicate. We will produce a narrative synthesis exploring how variables of capillary blood collection impact on validity, as well as exploring the safety and acceptability of patient self-collection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Ethics and Dissemination&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This review will be submitted for publication in a peer-reviewed open-access journal. We will present our results at both national and international conferences. As a systematic review with no primary participant data or involvement, ethical approval is not applicable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;PROSPERO registration number&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;CRD42021225606&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Strengths and limitations of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;To our knowledge this is the first systematic review to explore all postal methods of capillary blood collection for the measurement of HbA1c.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;This review follows the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses guidelines, which offers transparency and enhances reproducibility.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Due to anticipated heterogeneity in statistical approaches, summary analyses, sample storage, transportation, extraction, and assay, meta-analysis is unlikely to be appropriate and therefore narrative synthesis will be used.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Due to the exclusion criteria, our findings may not be generalisable to a wider population including children, and those with haemoglobinopathies, high erythrocyte turnover or other conditions likely to affect HbA1c result.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.21267851" rel="alternate" title="Home monitoring of HbA1c in diabetes mellitus: A protocol for systematic review and narrative synthesis on reliability, accuracy, and patient acceptability (3 tweets)"/><category term="Endocrinology (including Diabetes Mellitus and Metabolic Disease)"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267077</id><title>Change in Finances, Peer Access, and Mental Health Among Trans and Non-binary People in Canada During COVID-19 (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.160067+00:00</updated><author><name>Monica A. Ghabrial</name></author><author><name>Ayden I. Scheim</name></author><author><name>Caiden Chih</name></author><author><name>Heather Santos</name></author><author><name>Noah James Adams</name></author><author><name>Greta R. Bauer</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Purpose&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-related stressors associated with loss of income and community are compounded with gender minority stress among trans and non-binary people (TNB) – which may result in mental health burden. The present study examined the effect of COVID-related change in finances and TNB gathering access on anxiety and depression among TNB people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Participants were 18 years and older (&lt;italic&gt;M&lt;/italic&gt; age = 30) who completed both pre-pandemic baseline (Fall 2019) and pandemic follow-up (Fall 2020) surveys in the Trans PULSE Canada study. Multivariable regression analyses examined associations between change in (1) finances and (2) access to TNB peers and mental health during the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of 780 participants, 50% reported that COVID had a negative effect on personal income and 58.3% reported loss in access to TNB peer or friend gatherings (in person or online). Depression and anxiety symptoms increased from pre-pandemic to follow-up, and most participants were above measurement cut-offs for clinical levels during the pandemic. Changes in finances and access to peer gatherings were associated with depression symptoms during the pandemic, but effects depended on level of pre-pandemic depression. For participants with high pre-pandemic depression, financial stability was not protective against increased depression at follow-up. Participants experiencing unprecedentedly high levels of depression during COVID may have pursued more TNB gatherings. Neither financial change nor access to TNB gatherings were associated with pandemic anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Findings suggest need for a multifaceted approach to mental health programmes and services to address structural barriers, including financial support and meaningful TNB community engagement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267077" rel="alternate" title="Change in Finances, Peer Access, and Mental Health Among Trans and Non-binary People in Canada During COVID-19 (3 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267727</id><title>Adult life-course trajectories of psychological distress and economic outcomes in midlife during the COVID-19 pandemic (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.160406+00:00</updated><author><name>V Moulton</name></author><author><name>A Sullivan</name></author><author><name>A Goodman</name></author><author><name>S Parsons</name></author><author><name>G Ploubidis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This study used two British birth cohorts to examine whether pre-pandemic trajectories of psychological distress were associated with a greater risk of changes in financial and employment situation during the pandemic, as well as increased need for government support and use of other methods to mitigate their economic situation. We identified 5 differential life-course trajectories of psychological distress from adolescence to midlife and explored their relation to changes in financial and employment circumstances at different stages during the pandemic from May 2020 to March 2021, applying multinomial logistic regression and controlling for numerous early life covariates. In addition, we ran modified Poisson models with robust standard errors to identify whether different trajectories were more likely to have been supported by the benefit system, payment holidays, borrowing and other methods of mitigating the economic shock. We found that despite the UK governments economic response package economic inequalities for pre-pandemic psychological distress trajectories with differential onset, severity and chronicity across the life-course were exacerbated by the COVID-19 economic shock. Furthermore, the subsequent cut in government support, alongside increases in the cost of living may widen economic inequalities for differential pre-pandemic psychological distress trajectories, which in turn may also worsen mental health. This work highlights, different pre-pandemic trajectories of psychological distress were more vulnerable to economic shock.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.21267727" rel="alternate" title="Adult life-course trajectories of psychological distress and economic outcomes in midlife during the COVID-19 pandemic (3 tweets)"/><category term="Psychiatry and Clinical Psychology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>