<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.785860+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.06.21264535</id><title>Analytical performance of eleven SARS-CoV-2 antigen-detecting rapid tests for Delta variant (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.786220+00:00</updated><author><name>Meriem Bekliz</name></author><author><name>Kenneth Adea</name></author><author><name>Manel Essaidi-Laziosi</name></author><author><name>Camille Escadafal</name></author><author><name>Jilian A Sacks</name></author><author><name>Laurent Kaiser</name></author><author><name>Isabella Eckerle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Global concerns arose as the emerged and rapidly spreading SARS-CoV-2 Delta variant. To date, few data on routine diagnostic performance for Delta are available. Here, we investigate the analytical performance of eleven commercially available antigen-detecting rapid diagnostic tests (Ag-RDTs) for Delta VOC in comparison with current and earlier VOCs (Alpha, Beta and Gamma) and early pandemic variant using cultured SARS-CoV-2. Comparable sensitivity was observed for Delta for the majority of Ag-RDTs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.06.21264535" rel="alternate" title="Analytical performance of eleven SARS-CoV-2 antigen-detecting rapid tests for Delta variant (37 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463402</id><title>Inhibition of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein palmitoylation reduces virus infectivity (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.786479+00:00</updated><author><name>Ahmed A. Ramadan</name></author><author><name>Karthick Mayilsamy</name></author><author><name>Andrew R. McGill</name></author><author><name>Anandita Ghosh</name></author><author><name>Marc A. Giulianotti</name></author><author><name>Haley M. Donow</name></author><author><name>Shyam S. Mohapatra</name></author><author><name>Subhra Mohapatra</name></author><author><name>Bala Chandran</name></author><author><name>Robert J. Deschenes</name></author><author><name>Arunava Roy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spike glycoproteins of almost all enveloped viruses are known to undergo post-translational attachment of palmitic acid moieties. The precise role of such palmitoylation of the spike protein in membrane fusion and infection is not completely understood. Here, we report that palmitoylation of the first five cysteine residues of the c-terminal cysteine-rich domain of the SARS-CoV-2 spike are indispensable for infection, and palmitoylation deficient spike mutants are defective in trimerization and subsequent membrane fusion. The DHHC9 palmitoyltransferase interacts with and palmitoylates the spike protein in the ER and Golgi, and knockdown of DHHC9 results in reduced fusion and infection of SARS-CoV-2. Two bis-piperazine backbone-based DHHC9 inhibitors inhibit SARS-CoV-2 spike protein palmitoylation and the resulting progeny virion particles released are defective in fusion and infection. This establishes these palmitoyltransferase inhibitors as potential new intervention strategies against SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463402" rel="alternate" title="Inhibition of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein palmitoylation reduces virus infectivity (7 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463234</id><title>High-throughput Activity Assay for Screening Inhibitors of the SARS-CoV-2 Mac1 Macrodomain (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.786740+00:00</updated><author><name>Morgan Dasovich</name></author><author><name>Junlin Zhuo</name></author><author><name>Jack A. Goodman</name></author><author><name>Ajit Thomas</name></author><author><name>Robert Lyle McPherson</name></author><author><name>Aravinth Kumar Jayabalan</name></author><author><name>Veronica F. Busa</name></author><author><name>Shang-Jung Cheng</name></author><author><name>Brennan A. Murphy</name></author><author><name>Karli R. Redinger</name></author><author><name>Takashi Tsukamoto</name></author><author><name>Barbara Slusher</name></author><author><name>Jürgen Bosch</name></author><author><name>Huijun Wei</name></author><author><name>Anthony K. L. Leung</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Macrodomains are a class of conserved ADP-ribosylhydrolases expressed by viruses of pandemic concern, including coronaviruses and alphaviruses. Viral macrodomains are critical for replication and virus-induced pathogenesis; therefore, these enzymes are a promising target for antiviral therapy. However, no potent or selective viral macrodomain inhibitors currently exist, in part due to the lack of a high-throughput assay for this class of enzymes. Here, we developed a high-throughput ADP-ribosylhydrolase assay using the SARS-CoV-2 macrodomain Mac1. We performed a pilot screen which identified dasatinib and dihydralazine as ADP-ribosylhydrolase inhibitors. Importantly, dasatinib does not inhibit MacroD2, the closest Mac1 homolog in humans. Our study demonstrates the feasibility of identifying selective inhibitors based on ADP-ribosylhydrolase activity, paving the way for screening large compound libraries to identify improved macrodomain inhibitors and explore their potential as antiviral therapies for SARS-CoV-2 and future viral threats.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463234" rel="alternate" title="High-throughput Activity Assay for Screening Inhibitors of the SARS-CoV-2 Mac1 Macrodomain (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.09.21264771</id><title>Taste loss as a distinct symptom of COVID-19: A systematic review and meta-analysis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.787181+00:00</updated><author><name>Mackenzie R Hannum</name></author><author><name>Riley Koch</name></author><author><name>Vicente Ramirez</name></author><author><name>Sarah Marks</name></author><author><name>Aurora Toskala</name></author><author><name>Riley Herriman</name></author><author><name>Cailu Lin</name></author><author><name>Paule Valery Joseph</name></author><author><name>Danielle R Reed</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chemosensory scientists have been skeptical that reports of COVID–19 taste loss are genuine, in part because, before COVID–19, taste loss was rare and often confused with smell loss. Therefore, to establish the predicted prevalence rate of taste loss in COVID–19 patients, we conducted a systematic review and meta–analysis of 376 papers published in 2020 and 2021, with 241 of the papers meeting all inclusion criteria. Additionally, we explored how methodological differences (direct vs. self-report measures) may affect these estimates. We hypothesized that direct prevalence measures of taste loss would be the most valid because they avoid the taste/smell confusion of self-report. The meta–analysis showed that, among 138,897 COVID–19–positive patients, 39.2% reported taste dysfunction (95% CI: 35.34–43.12%), and the prevalence estimates were slightly but not significantly higher from studies using direct (n = 18) versus self-report (n = 223) methodologies (Q = 0.57, df = 1, p = 0.45). Generally, males reported lower rates of taste loss than did females and taste loss was highest in middle-aged groups. Thus, taste loss is a bona fide symptom COVID–19, meriting further research into the most appropriate direct methods to measure it and its underlying mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.09.21264771" rel="alternate" title="Taste loss as a distinct symptom of COVID-19: A systematic review and meta-analysis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Allergy and Immunology"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>