<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.189108+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.19.21265208</id><title>Airborne transmission of SARS-CoV-2 over distances greater than two metres: a rapid systematic review (1705 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.189680+00:00</updated><author><name>Jennifer C Palmer</name></author><author><name>Daphne Duval</name></author><author><name>Isobel Tudge</name></author><author><name>Jason Kwasi Sarfo-Annin</name></author><author><name>Nicola Pearce-Smith</name></author><author><name>Emer O’Connell</name></author><author><name>Allan Bennett</name></author><author><name>Rachel Clark</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To evaluate the potential for long-distance (over two metres) airborne transmission of SARS-CoV-2 in indoor community settings and investigate factors which may impact this transmission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Systematic review and narrative synthesis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data source&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;MEDLINE, Embase, medRxiv, Arxiv and WHO COVID-19 Research Database for studies published from 27 July 2020 to 21 April 2021; existing relevant rapid systematic reviews for studies published between 1 January to 27 July 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Eligibility criteria for study selection&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Observational studies that included a thorough epidemiological assessment of routes of transmission and which reported on the likelihood of airborne transmission of SARS-CoV-2 at a distance greater than two metres in indoor community settings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data extraction and synthesis&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Data extraction was completed by one reviewer and independently checked by a second reviewer. Primary outcomes were COVID-19 infections via airborne transmission over distances greater than two metres and any factors that may have modified transmission risk. Included studies were rated using a quality criteria checklist (QCC) for primary research and certainty of key outcomes was determined using GRADE. Narrative synthesis was themed by setting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of the 3,780 articles screened for inclusion, 15 publications reporting on 13 epidemiological investigations were included (three high, six medium and four low quality). Airborne transmission at distances greater than two metres was likely to have occurred for some or all transmission events in 12 studies and was unclear in one study (GRADE: very low certainty). In all studies, one or more factors plausibly increased the likelihood of long-distance airborne transmission occurring, particularly insufficient air replacement (GRADE: very low certainty), recirculating air flow (GRADE: very low certainty) and singing (GRADE: very low certainty). In nine studies, the primary cases were reported as being asymptomatic, presymptomatic or around symptom onset at the time of transmission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This rapid systematic review found evidence of long-distance airborne transmission of SARS-CoV-2 in indoor community settings and identified factors that likely contributed to this transmission in all included studies. These results strengthen the need for adequate mitigation measures in indoor community settings, particularly adequate ventilation with fresh air, and caution required with the use of recirculating air flow systems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Systematic review registration&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;PROSPERO CRD42021236762&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.19.21265208" rel="alternate" title="Airborne transmission of SARS-CoV-2 over distances greater than two metres: a rapid systematic review (1705 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.18.21264623</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 variants associated with vaccine breakthrough in the Delaware Valley through summer 2021 (419 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.189947+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew D. Marques</name></author><author><name>Scott Sherrill-Mix</name></author><author><name>John Everett</name></author><author><name>Shantan Reddy</name></author><author><name>Pascha Hokama</name></author><author><name>Aoife M. Roche</name></author><author><name>Young Hwang</name></author><author><name>Abigail Glascock</name></author><author><name>Samantha A. Whiteside</name></author><author><name>Jevon Graham-Wooten</name></author><author><name>Layla A. Khatib</name></author><author><name>Ayannah S. Fitzgerald</name></author><author><name>Ahmed M. Moustafa</name></author><author><name>Colleen Bianco</name></author><author><name>Swetha Rajagopal</name></author><author><name>Jenna Helton</name></author><author><name>Regan Deming</name></author><author><name>Lidiya Denu</name></author><author><name>Azad Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Eimear Kitt</name></author><author><name>Susan E. Coffin</name></author><author><name>Claire Newbern</name></author><author><name>Josh Chang Mell</name></author><author><name>Paul J. Planet</name></author><author><name>Nitika Badjatia</name></author><author><name>Bonnie Richards</name></author><author><name>Zi-Xuan Wang</name></author><author><name>Carolyn C. Cannuscio</name></author><author><name>Katherine M. Strelau</name></author><author><name>Anne Jaskowiak-Barr</name></author><author><name>Leigh Cressman</name></author><author><name>Sean Loughrey</name></author><author><name>Arupa Ganguly</name></author><author><name>Michael D. Feldman</name></author><author><name>Ronald G. Collman</name></author><author><name>Kyle G. Rodino</name></author><author><name>Brendan J. Kelly</name></author><author><name>Frederic D. Bushman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The severe acute respiratory coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) is the cause of the global outbreak of COVID-19. Evidence suggests that the virus is evolving to allow efficient spread through the human population, including vaccinated individuals. Here we report a study of viral variants from surveillance of the Delaware Valley, including the city of Philadelphia, and variants infecting vaccinated subjects. We sequenced and analyzed complete viral genomes from 2621 surveillance samples from March 2020 to September 2021 and compared them to genome sequences from 159 vaccine breakthroughs. In the early spring of 2020, all detected variants were of the B.1 and closely related lineages. A mixture of lineages followed, notably including B.1.243 followed by B.1.1.7 (alpha), with other lineages present at lower levels. Later isolations were dominated by B.1.617.2 (delta) and other delta lineages; delta was the exclusive variant present by the last time sampled. To investigate whether any variants appeared preferentially in vaccine breakthroughs, we devised a model based on Bayesian autoregressive moving average logistic multinomial regression to allow rigorous comparison. This revealed that B.1.617.2 (delta) showed three-fold enrichment in vaccine breakthrough cases (odds ratio of 3; 95% credible interval 0.89-11). Viral point substitutions could also be associated with vaccine breakthroughs, notably the N501Y substitution found in the alpha, beta and gamma variants (odds ratio 2.04; 95% credible interval of 1.25-3.18). This study thus provides a detailed picture of viral evolution in the Delaware Valley and a geographically matched analysis of vaccine breakthroughs; it also introduces a rigorous statistical approach to interrogating enrichment of viral variants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 vaccination is highly effective at reducing viral infection, hospitalization and death. However, vaccine breakthrough infections have been widely observed, raising the question of whether particular viral variants or viral mutations are associated with breakthrough. Here we report analysis of 2621 surveillance isolates from xsxpeople diagnosed with COVID-19 in the Delaware Valley in South Eastern Pennsylvania, allowing rigorous comparison to 159 vaccine breakthrough case specimens. Our best estimate is a three-fold enrichment for some lineages of delta among breakthroughs, and enrichment of a notable spike substitution, N501Y. We introduce statistical methods that should be widely useful for evaluating vaccine breakthroughs and other viral phenotypes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.18.21264623" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 variants associated with vaccine breakthrough in the Delaware Valley through summer 2021 (419 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.18.21265113</id><title>Immune Responses in Fully Vaccinated Individuals Following Breakthrough Infection with the SARS-CoV-2 Delta Variant in Provincetown, Massachusetts (90 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.190634+00:00</updated><author><name>Ai-ris Y. Collier</name></author><author><name>Catherine M. Brown</name></author><author><name>Katherine Mcmahan</name></author><author><name>Jingyou Yu</name></author><author><name>Jinyan Liu</name></author><author><name>Catherine Jacob-Dolan</name></author><author><name>Abishek Chandrashekar</name></author><author><name>Dylan Tierney</name></author><author><name>Jessica L. Ansel</name></author><author><name>Marjorie Rowe</name></author><author><name>Daniel Sellers</name></author><author><name>Kunza Ahmad</name></author><author><name>Ricardo Aguayo</name></author><author><name>Tochi Anioke</name></author><author><name>Sarah Gardner</name></author><author><name>Mazuba Siamatu</name></author><author><name>Lorraine Bermudez Rivera</name></author><author><name>Michele R. Hacker</name></author><author><name>Lawrence C. Madoff</name></author><author><name>Dan H. Barouch</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A cluster of over a thousand infections with the SARS-CoV-2 delta variant was identified in a predominantly fully vaccinated population in Provincetown, Massachusetts in July 2021. Immune responses in breakthrough infections with the SARS-CoV-2 delta variant remain to be defined.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Humoral and cellular immune responses were assessed in 35 vaccinated individuals who were tested for SARS-CoV-2 in the Massachusetts Department of Public Health outbreak investigation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vaccinated individuals who tested positive for SARS-CoV-2 demonstrated substantially higher antibody responses than vaccinated individuals who tested negative for SARS-CoV-2, including 28-fold higher binding antibody titers and 34-fold higher neutralizing antibody titers against the SARS-CoV-2 delta variant. Vaccinated individuals who tested positive also showed 4.4-fold higher Spike-specific CD8+ T cell responses against the SARS-CoV-2 delta variant than vaccinated individuals who tested negative.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fully vaccinated individuals developed robust anamnestic antibody and T cell responses following infection with the SARS-CoV-2 delta variant. These data suggest important immunologic benefits of vaccination in the context of breakthrough infections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.18.21265113" rel="alternate" title="Immune Responses in Fully Vaccinated Individuals Following Breakthrough Infection with the SARS-CoV-2 Delta Variant in Provincetown, Massachusetts (90 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.17.21265101</id><title>Time-Varying Effectiveness of Three Covid-19 Vaccines in Puerto Rico (33 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.190912+00:00</updated><author><name>Mónica M. Robles Fontán</name></author><author><name>Elvis G. Nieves</name></author><author><name>Iris Cardona Gerena</name></author><author><name>Rafael A. Irizarry</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of October 1, 2021 2,217,547 individuals were fully vaccinated against COVID-19 in Puerto Rico. Since the vaccination process commenced on December 15, 2020 111,052 laboratory-confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infections have been reported. These data permitted us to quantify the benefits of the immunization campaign and to compare effectiveness of the mRNA-1273 (Moderna), BNT162b2 (Pfizer), and Ad26.COV2.S (J&amp;amp;J) vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Department of Health databases holding vaccination status, SARS-CoV-2 test results, and COVID-19 hospitalizations and deaths were integrated. We fit a statistical model that adjusted for time-varying incidence rates and age to estimate vaccine effectiveness and hospitalization and death relative risks. Code and data are provided here: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/rafalab/vax-eff-pr"&gt;https://github.com/rafalab/vax-eff-pr&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the peak of their protection, mRNA-1273, BNT162b2, and Ad26.COV2.S had an effectiveness of 90% (88%-91%), 87% (85%-89%), and 58% (51%-65%), respectively. After four months, effectiveness waned to about 70%, 60%, and 30%. We found no evidence that effectiveness was different after the Delta variant became dominant. For those infected, the vaccines provided further protection against hospitalization and deaths across all age groups. All vaccines had a lower effectiveness for those over 85 years, with a larger decrease for the Ad26.COV2.S vaccine. Overall, thousands of hospitalizations and deaths were avoided thanks to the vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The mRNA-1273 and BNT162b2 vaccines were highly effective across all age groups. They were still effective after four months although the protection waned. The Ad26.COV2.S vaccine was effective but to a lesser degree, especially for older age groups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.17.21265101" rel="alternate" title="Time-Varying Effectiveness of Three Covid-19 Vaccines in Puerto Rico (33 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-10-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.465386</id><title>Variations in cell-surface ACE2 levels alter direct binding of SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein and viral infectivity: Implications for measuring Spike protein interactions with animal ACE2 orthologs (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.191083+00:00</updated><author><name>Soheila Kazemi</name></author><author><name>Alberto Domingo López-Muńoz</name></author><author><name>Jaroslav Hollý</name></author><author><name>Ling Jin</name></author><author><name>Jonathan W. Yewdell</name></author><author><name>Brian P. Dolan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) is the causative agent of COVID-19, the most severe pandemic in a century. The virus gains access to host cells when the viral Spike protein (S-protein) binds to the host cell-surface receptor angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2). Studies have attempted to understand SARS-CoV-2 S-protein interaction with vertebrate orthologs of ACE2 by expressing ACE2 orthologs in mammalian cells and measuring viral infection or S- protein binding. Often these cells only transiently express ACE2 proteins and levels of ACE2 at the cell surface are not quantified. Here, we describe a cell-based assay that uses stably transfected cells expressing ACE2 proteins in a bi-cistronic vector with an easy to quantify reporter protein to normalize ACE2 expression. We found that both binding of the S-protein receptor-binding domain (RBD) and infection with a SARS-CoV-2 pseudovirus is proportional to the amount of human ACE2 expressed at the cell surface, which can be inferred by quantifying the level of reporter protein, Thy1.1. We also compared different ACE2 orthologs which were expressed in stably transfected cells expressing equivalent levels of Thy1.1. When ranked for either viral infectivity or RBD binding, mouse ACE2 had a weak to undetectable affinity for S-protein while human ACE2 was the highest level detected and feline ACE2 had an intermediate phenotype. The generation of stably transfected cells whose ACE2 level can be normalized for cross-ortholog comparisons allows us to create a reusable cellular library useful for measuring emerging SARS-CoV-2 variant’s ability to potentially infect different animals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.465386" rel="alternate" title="Variations in cell-surface ACE2 levels alter direct binding of SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein and viral infectivity: Implications for measuring Spike protein interactions with animal ACE2 orthologs (21 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.19.21265226</id><title>Wastewater and surface monitoring to detect COVID-19 in elementary school settings: The Safer at School Early Alert project (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.191261+00:00</updated><author><name>Rebecca K Fielding-Miller</name></author><author><name>Smruthi Karthikeyan</name></author><author><name>Tommi Gaines</name></author><author><name>Richard S Garfein</name></author><author><name>Rodolfo A Salido</name></author><author><name>Victor Cantu</name></author><author><name>Laura Kohn</name></author><author><name>Fitri C Wijaya</name></author><author><name>Marlene Flores</name></author><author><name>Vinton Omaleki</name></author><author><name>Araz Majnoonian</name></author><author><name>Natasha K Martin</name></author><author><name>Dahl Austin</name></author><author><name>Louise C Laurent</name></author><author><name>Patricia Gonzalez-Zuniga</name></author><author><name>Megan Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Anh V Vo</name></author><author><name>Tina T Le</name></author><author><name>Dawn Duong</name></author><author><name>Ashkan Hassani</name></author><author><name>Samantha Tweeten</name></author><author><name>Kristen Jepsen</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Henson</name></author><author><name>Abbas Hakim</name></author><author><name>Amanda Birmingham</name></author><author><name>Adam M Mark</name></author><author><name>Chanond A Nasamran</name></author><author><name>Sara B Rosenthal</name></author><author><name>Niema Moshiri</name></author><author><name>Kathleen M Fisch</name></author><author><name>Greg Humphrey</name></author><author><name>Sawyer Farmer</name></author><author><name>Helena Tubb</name></author><author><name>Tommy Valles</name></author><author><name>Justin Morris</name></author><author><name>Jaeyoung Kang</name></author><author><name>Behnam Khaleghi</name></author><author><name>Colin Young</name></author><author><name>Ameen D Akel</name></author><author><name>Sean Eilert</name></author><author><name>Justin Eno</name></author><author><name>Ken Curewitz</name></author><author><name>Tajana Rosing</name></author><author><name>Rob Knight</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Schools are high-risk settings for SARS-CoV-2 transmission, but necessary for children's educational and social-emotional wellbeing. While wastewater monitoring has been implemented to mitigate outbreak risk in universities and residential settings, its effectiveness in community K-12 sites is unknown. We implemented a wastewater and surface monitoring system to detect SARS-CoV-2 in nine elementary schools in San Diego County. Ninety-three percent of identified cases were associated with either a positive wastewater or surface sample; 67% were associated with a positive wastewater sample, and 40% were associated with a positive surface sample. The techniques we utilized allowed for near-complete genomic sequencing of wastewater and surface samples. Passive environmental surveillance can complement approaches that require individual consent, particularly in communities with limited access and/or high rates of testing hesitancy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.19.21265226" rel="alternate" title="Wastewater and surface monitoring to detect COVID-19 in elementary school settings: The Safer at School Early Alert project (13 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.20.21265245</id><title>Comparative effectiveness of allocation strategies of COVID-19 vaccines and antivirals against emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern in East Asia and Pacific region (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.191683+00:00</updated><author><name>Kathy Leung</name></author><author><name>Mark Jit</name></author><author><name>Gabriel M Leung</name></author><author><name>Joseph T Wu</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We aimed to evaluate the impact of various allocation strategies of COVID-19 vaccines and antiviral such that the pandemic exit strategy could be tailored to risks and preferences of jurisdictions in the East Asia and Pacific region (EAP) to improve its efficiency and effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vaccine efficacies were estimated from the titre distributions of 50% plaque reduction neutralization test (PRNT50), assuming that PRNT50 titres of primary vaccination decreased by 2-10 folds due to antibody waning and emergence of VOCs, and an additional dose of vaccine would increase PRNT50 titres by 3- or 9-fold. We then used an existing SARS-CoV-2 transmission model to assess the outcomes of vaccine allocation strategies with and without the use of antivirals for symptomatic patients in Japan, Hong Kong and Vietnam.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Increasing primary vaccination coverage was the most important contributing factor in reducing the total and peak number of COVID-19 hospitalizations, especially when population vaccine coverage or vaccine uptake among older adults was low. Providing antivirals to 50% of symptomatic infections only further reduced total and peak hospitalizations by 10-13%. The effectiveness of an additional dose of vaccine was highly dependent on the immune escape potential of VOCs and antibody waning, but less dependent on the boosting efficacy of the additional dose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Increasing primary vaccination coverage should be prioritised in the design of allocation strategies of COVID-19 vaccines and antivirals in the EAP region. Heterologous vaccination with any available vaccine as the additional dose could be considered when planning pandemic exit strategies tailored to the circumstances of EAP jurisdictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Health and Medical Research Fund, General Research Fund, AIR@InnoHK&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.20.21265245" rel="alternate" title="Comparative effectiveness of allocation strategies of COVID-19 vaccines and antivirals against emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern in East Asia and Pacific region (11 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.22.465468</id><title>PermaPhosSer: autonomous synthesis of functional, permanently phosphorylated proteins (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.191859+00:00</updated><author><name>Phillip Zhu</name></author><author><name>Rachel Franklin</name></author><author><name>Amber Vogel</name></author><author><name>Stanislau Stanisheuski</name></author><author><name>Patrick Reardon</name></author><author><name>Joseph S Beckman</name></author><author><name>P. Andrew Karplus</name></author><author><name>Ryan A Mehl</name></author><author><name>Richard B Cooley</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Installing stable, functional mimics of phosphorylated amino acids into proteins offers a powerful strategy to study protein regulation. Previously, a genetic code expansion (GCE) system was developed to translationally install non-hydrolyzable phosphoserine (nhpSer), with the γ-oxygen replaced with carbon, but it has seen limited usage. Here, we achieve a 40-fold improvement in this system by engineering into &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; a biosynthetic pathway that produces nhpSer from the central metabolite phosphoenolpyruvate. Using this "PermaPhos&lt;sup&gt;Ser&lt;/sup&gt;" system — an autonomous 21-amino acid &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; expression system for incorporating nhpSer into target proteins — we show that nhpSer faithfully mimics the effects of phosphoserine in three stringent test cases: promoting 14-3-3/client complexation, disrupting 14-3-3 dimers, and activating GSK3-β phosphorylation of the SARS-CoV-2 nucleocapsid protein. This facile access to nhpSer containing proteins should allow nhpSer to replace Asp and Glu as the go-to pSer phosphomimetic for proteins produced in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.22.465468" rel="alternate" title="PermaPhosSer: autonomous synthesis of functional, permanently phosphorylated proteins (10 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-10-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.19.21265062</id><title>Mutations on non-structural proteins of SARS-CoV-2 are possibly responsible for adverse clinical outcomes in a real-life practice (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.192076+00:00</updated><author><name>Takaya Ichikawa</name></author><author><name>Shiho Torii</name></author><author><name>Hikoyu Suzuki</name></author><author><name>Akio Takada</name></author><author><name>Satoshi Suzuki</name></author><author><name>Masahide Nakajima</name></author><author><name>Akihito Tampo</name></author><author><name>Yasutaka Kakinoki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Among a single COVID-19 cluster population from the end of March through April 2021 in Asahikawa, we experienced the cases in which patients manifested severe clinical symptoms compared to patients who were infected before that. A hundred three patients (age range: 65 to 89 years old) enrolled in this study were divided into two groups, group A: the patients infected from November 2020 to March 2021, and group B: the patients in this cluster population. The mortality rates were 6.1% in group A and 16.2% in group B (OR: 2.97, 95%CI: 0.65-15.38). For the severity of disease, the patients in group B reached to the clinical state which requires higher oxygen flow rate more quickly (mild; p=0.892, moderate; p=0.117, severe; p=0.029). Whole viral genome sequences revealed five non-synonymous mutations by comparison of the isolates with each group. Of these, four were on NSPs including nsp3, 6 and 15, and one was on S protein located near the C-terminus, suggesting that mutations on NSPs could be responsible for adverse clinical outcomes in COVID-19 patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.19.21265062" rel="alternate" title="Mutations on non-structural proteins of SARS-CoV-2 are possibly responsible for adverse clinical outcomes in a real-life practice (9 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.20.21265239</id><title>Immunogenicity of BNT162b2 Vaccine in Patients with Inflammatory Bowel Disease on Infliximab Combination Therapy: A Multicenter Prospective Study (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.192263+00:00</updated><author><name>Mohammad Shehab</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Abu-Farha</name></author><author><name>Fatema Alrashed</name></author><author><name>Ahmad Alfadhli</name></author><author><name>Khazna AlOtaibi</name></author><author><name>Abdulla AlSahli</name></author><author><name>Thangavel Alphonse Thanaraj</name></author><author><name>Arshad Channanath</name></author><author><name>Hamad Ali</name></author><author><name>Jehad Abubaker</name></author><author><name>Fahd Al-Mulla</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vaccination is a promising strategy to protect vulnerable groups like inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) patients against COVID-19 and associated severe outcomes. COVID-19 Vaccines clinical trials excluded IBD patients taking infliximab with azathioprine or 6-mercaptopurine (infliximab combination). Therefore, we sought to evaluate serologic responses to COVID-19 vaccination with the mRNA vaccine, BNT162b2 in IBD patients receiving infliximab combination therapy compared to healthy participants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a multicenter prospective study. IBD patients were recruited at the time of attendance at infusion center between August 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt;, 2021, and September 15&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;, 2021. Our primary outcome was the concentrations of SARS-CoV-2 antibodies 4-10 weeks after vaccination with two doses of BNT162b2 vaccine in IBD patients taking infliximab combination therapy (study group) compared to healthy participants group (control group). Both study and healthy participants groups were matched for age, sex and time-since-last-vaccine-dose using optimal pair matching method.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In total 116 participants were recruited in the study, 58 patients in the study group and 58 in the control group. Median (IQR) IgG concentrations were lower in the study group [99 BAU/mL (40, 177)] than the control group [139 BAU/mL (120, 188)], following vaccination (p = 0.0032). Neutralizing antibodies was also lower in the study group compared to the control group [64% (23, 94) vs 91% (85, 94), p &amp;lt;0.001]. The median IgA levels in the study group was also significantly lower when compared to the control group [6 U/ml (3, 34) vs 13 U/ml (7, 30), p =0.0097]. In the study group, the percentage of patients who achieved positive IgG, neutralizing antibody and IgA levels were 81%, 75% and 40% respectively. In the control group, all participants (100%) had positive IgG and neutralizing antibody levels while 62% had positive IgA levels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In patients with IBD receiving infliximab combination therapy, IgG, IgA and neutralizing antibody levels after BNT162b2 vaccine were lower compared to healthy participants. However, most patients treated with infliximab combination therapy seroconverted after two doses of the vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.20.21265239" rel="alternate" title="Immunogenicity of BNT162b2 Vaccine in Patients with Inflammatory Bowel Disease on Infliximab Combination Therapy: A Multicenter Prospective Study (9 tweets)"/><category term="Gastroenterology"/><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.18.21265130</id><title>Survey of Direct and Indirect Effects of COVID-19 on Eyes and the Common Ocular Manifestations (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.192465+00:00</updated><author><name>Dianeh Rabi</name></author><author><name>Razan Rabi</name></author><author><name>Arkan Jarrar</name></author><author><name>Sarah Mharma</name></author><author><name>Aya Jaradat</name></author><author><name>Shatha Bzoor</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Purpose&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ocular manifestations were reported in many recent observations that studied either the effect of COVID-19 directly on eyes or of face mask use. Hence, this study aimed to investigate the effect of COVID-19 on the eyes and make a clear comparison of its direct and indirect effect from face mask-wearing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was a cross-sectional study of both written and web-based questionnaires, distributed among a group of COVID-19 patients and a matched control group, the questionnaire consisted of common demographic data, COVID-19 infection history and its symptoms, focusing on ocular symptoms and the presence of conditions related to or cause eye symptoms. As well as the use of face masks that were assessed in terms of the complained ocular manifestation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of 618 participants, 252 had COVID-19 and 366 never had COVID-19. Ocular manifestation among COVID-19 incidence was 44%, significantly higher than non-infected participants’ incidence (35.8%), adjusted odds ratio, 95% confidence interval (AOR, 95%CI); 1.45 (1.02-2.06)). Eye discharges (p-value = 0.033) and photosensitivity (p-value = 0.003) were noted more commonly among COVID-19 participants compared to healthy control. When comparing long periods of face mask use with each ocular symptom; dry eye based on OSDI, forging body sensation, eye pain and eye discharges, were found significantly common among extended periods of face mask use.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 pandemic affected eyes, both directly from the virus or from its preventive measure of face mask use.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.18.21265130" rel="alternate" title="Survey of Direct and Indirect Effects of COVID-19 on Eyes and the Common Ocular Manifestations (8 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.19.21265222</id><title>Monoclonal Antibody Treatment of Breakthrough COVID-19 in Fully Vaccinated Individuals with High-Risk Comorbidities (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.192637+00:00</updated><author><name>Dennis M. Bierle</name></author><author><name>Ravindra Ganesh</name></author><author><name>Sidna Tulledge-Scheitel</name></author><author><name>Sara N. Hanson</name></author><author><name>Lori L. Arndt</name></author><author><name>Caroline G. Wilker</name></author><author><name>Raymund R. Razonable</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Breakthrough COVID-19 may occur in fully vaccinated persons. In this cohort of 1395 persons (mean age, 54.3 years; 60% female; median body mass index, 30.7) who developed breakthrough COVID-19, there were 107 (7.7%) who required hospitalization by day 28. Hospitalization was significantly associated with the number of medical comorbidities. Anti-spike monoclonal antibody treatment was significantly associated with a lower risk of hospitalization (Odds Ratio: 0.227; 95% confidence interval, 0.128 - 0.403; p&amp;lt;0.001). The number needed to treat to prevent one hospitalization was 225 among the lowest-risk patient group compared to 4 among the groups with highest numbers of medical comorbidity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Breakthrough COVID-19 may occur among vaccinated individuals with a high number of medical comorbidities, especially during the surge of SARS-CoV-2 Delta variant. Treatment with anti-spike monoclonal antibody was associated with significantly lower rates of hospitalization and oxygen supplementation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.19.21265222" rel="alternate" title="Monoclonal Antibody Treatment of Breakthrough COVID-19 in Fully Vaccinated Individuals with High-Risk Comorbidities (6 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.14.21264762</id><title>Longitudinal and comparative analysis of humoral response upon COVID-19 vaccination (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.192814+00:00</updated><author><name>Salvador Romero-Pinedo</name></author><author><name>Marina Quesada</name></author><author><name>Stela Álvarez-Fernández</name></author><author><name>Asunción Olmo</name></author><author><name>David Abia</name></author><author><name>Balbino Alarcón</name></author><author><name>Pilar Delgado</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The emergence of COVID-19 has led to a worldwide challenge for the rapid development of vaccines. Several types of safe and effective vaccines have been available in a time frame never seen before. Comparative studies to know the extent of protection and the immune response elicited by the different vaccines are of outstanding utility. Here, as a correlate for protection, we perform a comparative study of the humoral response to three vaccines, ChAdOx1 (Oxford-AstraZeneca), mRNA-1273 (Moderna), and BNT162b2 (Pfizer-BioNTech) by applying a flow cytometry-based highly sensitive method that we had previously developed. We have found that mRNA vaccines (mRNA-1273 and BNT162b2) induce a stronger humoral response that lasts for at least 6 months after vaccination. We also show that only one dose of BNT162b2 is enough to achieve the maximum response in seropositive pre-vaccination donors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.14.21264762" rel="alternate" title="Longitudinal and comparative analysis of humoral response upon COVID-19 vaccination (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.19.21265230</id><title>Psychological, social and financial impact of COVID-19 on culturally and linguistically diverse communities: a cross-sectional Australian study (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.193068+00:00</updated><author><name>Danielle M Muscat</name></author><author><name>Julie Ayre</name></author><author><name>Olivia Mac</name></author><author><name>Carys Batcup</name></author><author><name>Erin Cvejic</name></author><author><name>Kristen Pickles</name></author><author><name>Hankiz Dolan</name></author><author><name>Carissa Bonner</name></author><author><name>Dana Mouwad</name></author><author><name>Dipti Zachariah</name></author><author><name>Una Turalic</name></author><author><name>Yvonne Santalucia</name></author><author><name>Tingting Chen</name></author><author><name>Gordana Vasic</name></author><author><name>Kirsten J McCaffery</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Objective: This study aimed to explore the psychological, social, and financial impacts of COVID-19 on culturally and linguistically diverse communities in Australia.

Design: Cross-sectional survey informed by the Framework for Culturally Competent Health Research conducted between March and July, 2021.

Setting: Participants were recruited from Greater Western Sydney, New South Wales, Australia.

Participants: 708 community members who speak a language other than English at home participated (mean age: 45.4years [range 18 to 91]; 88% [n=622] born outside of Australia).

Outcome measures: Fifteen items regarding impacts of COVID-19, adapted from validated scales, previous surveys or co-designed in partnership with Multicultural Health and interpreter service staff. Logistic regression models (using post-stratification weighted frequencies) identified factors associated with psychological, social, and financial impacts. Surveys were available in English or translated (11 languages). 

Results: Even prior to the COVID-19 outbreak in Sydney, 25% of the sample reported feeling nervous or stressed most/all of the time and 22% felt lonely or alone most/all of the time. One quarter of participants reported negative impacts on their spousal relationships as a result of COVID-19 and most parents reported that their children were less active (64%), had more screen time (63%), and were finding school harder (45%). Mean financial burden was 2.9/5 (95%CI=2.8 to 2.9). Regression analyses consistently showed distinct impact patterns for different language groups and more negative outcomes for those with comorbidities. 

Conclusion: Culturally and linguistically diverse communities experience significant psychological, social and financial impacts of COVID-19, with distinct impact patterns across language groups. A whole-of-government approach with policy and sustainable infrastructure is needed to co-design innovative, tailored and culturally-safe COVID-19 support packages.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.19.21265230" rel="alternate" title="Psychological, social and financial impact of COVID-19 on culturally and linguistically diverse communities: a cross-sectional Australian study (5 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.21264693</id><title>Modeling brings additional insights into the kinetics of SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibody (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.193309+00:00</updated><author><name>Prague Mélanie</name></author><author><name>Quentin Clairon</name></author><author><name>Jérémie Guedj</name></author><author><name>Rodolphe Thiébaut</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Following the paper by Seow et al. published in Nature Microbiology, we reanalyzed the publicly available data using dynamical models of humoral response. The main conclusion is that, from available data, we can demonstrate that the decline of neutralizing antibodies (as measured with ID50) is biphasic, which is compatible with two types of antibody secreting cells (short lived and long lived). We found that lower bound of half life of the long-lived antibody secreting cells is 450 days. Moreover, our model predicts that the neutralizing antibody response could be more durable than suggested (up to 129 days for individuals with no requirement of supplemental oxygen and up to 175 days for others). A result which adds insight on the longevity of immune response.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.21264693" rel="alternate" title="Modeling brings additional insights into the kinetics of SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibody (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.18.21264783</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 variant transmission in a community-health population (Mexico City, Mexico) (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.193474+00:00</updated><author><name>Wenjuan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Marcela Martinez</name></author><author><name>Brian D Davis</name></author><author><name>Stephanie S Chen</name></author><author><name>Jorge Sincuir Martinez</name></author><author><name>Clara Corona</name></author><author><name>Guadalupe Diaz</name></author><author><name>Elias Makhoul</name></author><author><name>Saleh Heneidi</name></author><author><name>Jorge Goldberg</name></author><author><name>Jasmine T Plummer</name></author><author><name>Eric Vail</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The SARS-CoV-2 variant, B.1.1.519, arose in North and Central America, circulating primarily in Mexico. We demonstrate that this variant peaked during the second wave of COVID-19 in Mexico City in the spring of 2021. This variant is likely more infectious, attributed to mutation in the RBD of the spike protein T478K also seen in the alpha variant (B.1.1.7). However the time dynamics of the spread of this variant drastically changed upon the introduction of delta (B.1.617.2) to the country in which we observe a shift from 0% in May 2021 to 55% delta in the span of one month. Since the delta variant has dominantly spread across the globe, we investigated the increasing frequency of the Mexico variant, B.1.1.519, in the public community within Mexico City. Once present, the delta variant was 78% of the Mexico City catchment in July 2021, a time which marked the commencement of Mexico’s third wave. Our data supports the growing concern that the delta variant is closely associated with the massive infection spread of the VOC in Central and South America. While the T478K mutation, also seen in the alpha variant, has evidence for increased transmissibility, these data suggest that the delta variant shows overall increased fitness seeing as it outcompeted the B.1.1519 this Mexico community.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.18.21264783" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 variant transmission in a community-health population (Mexico City, Mexico) (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.20.21265279</id><title>Factors affecting the mental health of pregnant women using UK maternity services during the COVID-19 pandemic: A qualitative interview study (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.193683+00:00</updated><author><name>A R McKinlay</name></author><author><name>D Fancourt</name></author><author><name>A Burton</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;People using maternity services in the United Kingdom (UK) have faced significant changes brought on by the COVID-19 pandemic and social distancing regulations. We focused on the experiences of pregnant women using UK maternity services during the pandemic and the impact of social distancing rules on their mental health and wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted 23 qualitative semi-structured interviews from June 2020 to August 2021, with women from across the UK who experienced a pregnancy during the pandemic. Nineteen women in the study carried their pregnancy to term and four women experienced a miscarriage during the pandemic. Interviews took place remotely over video or telephone call, discussing topics such as mental health during pregnancy and use of UK maternity services. We used reflexive thematic analysis to analyse interview transcripts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We generated six higher order themes: (1) Some pregnancy discomforts alleviated by social distancing measures, (2) The importance of relationships that support coping and adjustment, (3) Missed pregnancy and parenthood experiences, (4) The mental health consequences of birth partner and visitor restrictions, (5) Maternity services under pressure, and (6) Lack of connection with staff. Many participants felt a sense of loss over a pregnancy experience that differed so remarkably to what they had expected because of the pandemic. Supportive relationships were important to help cope with pregnancy and pandemic-related changes; but feelings of isolation were compounded for some participants because opportunities to build social connections through face-to-face parent groups were unavailable. Participants also described feeling alone due to restrictions on partners being present when accessing UK maternity services.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our findings highlight some of the changes that may have affected pregnant women’s mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic. Reduced social support and being unable to have a partner or support person present during maternity service use were the greatest concerns reported by women in this study, as this absence removed a protective buffer in times of uncertainty and distress. This suggests that the availability of a birth partner or support person must be prioritised wherever possible to protect the mental health of women experiencing pregnancy and miscarriage in times of pandemics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.20.21265279" rel="alternate" title="Factors affecting the mental health of pregnant women using UK maternity services during the COVID-19 pandemic: A qualitative interview study (4 tweets)"/><category term="Psychiatry and Clinical Psychology"/><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.21264946</id><title>Clinical observation of high-flow nasal cannula (HFNC) with non-rebreather mask (NRM) use on severe or critically ill COVID-19 diabetic patients (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.193902+00:00</updated><author><name>AFM Tareq Bhuiyan</name></author><author><name>Sudipta Deb Nath</name></author><author><name>Shuva Das</name></author><author><name>Moumita Das</name></author><author><name>Rajdeep Biswas</name></author><author><name>Moinul Ahsan</name></author><author><name>Md. Iftekher-E-Alam Ziad</name></author><author><name>Fahmida Khatun Padma</name></author><author><name>Rana Dey</name></author><author><name>AKM Shamsul Alam</name></author><author><name>Farial Hoque Zehan</name></author><author><name>Ayan Saha</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Objective: Diabetes prevalence is a vital factor in COVID-19's clinical prognosis. This study aimed to investigate and compare the efficacy of High-flow Nasal Cannula (HFNC) with/without non-rebreather mask (NRM) on critical COVID-19 patients with/without diabetes. 
Materials and methods: For analysis and comparison, epidemiological, biochemical, and clinical data were collected from 240 HFNC±NRM treated severe and critical COVID-19 ICU patients (diabetic = 136; non-diabetic = 104) of five hospitals in Chattogram, Bangladesh. 
Results and Discussion: 59.1% patients with fever had diabetes (p=0.012). ICU stay was longer for diabetic patients (9.06±5.70) than non-diabetic ones (7.41±5.11) (p=0.020). Majority of hypertensive patients were diabetic (68.3%; p&amp;lt;0.001). Most of the diabetic patients (70.4%; p&amp;lt;0.005) had elevated creatinine levels. The partial pressure of oxygen after HFNC (only) was significantly (p=0.031) higher in non-diabetic patients (69.30±23.56) than diabetic ones (61.50±14.49). Diabetic (62.64±13.05) and non-diabetic patients (59.40±13.22) had similar partial pressure of oxygen from HFNC+NRM. Majority of the diabetic patients who required HFNC+NRM had elevated RBS (73.8%; p=0.001) and creatinine (75.7%; p=0.009). Factors affecting the HFNC only treated patients were fever and impaired glucose tolerance. Besides, increased plasma glucose level, age, and hypertension affected the HFNC + NRM treated diabetic patients.
Conclusion: The results of this study imply that oxygen supply with HFNC+NRM may be beneficial for the elderly/hypertensive diabetic patients with COVID-19 associated AHRF; and that IGT and increased blood glucose levels could be determinants for COVID-19 severity. However, further experiments to substantiate these claims are required on a larger sample and among different clinical cohorts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.21264946" rel="alternate" title="Clinical observation of high-flow nasal cannula (HFNC) with non-rebreather mask (NRM) use on severe or critically ill COVID-19 diabetic patients (3 tweets)"/><category term="Intensive Care and Critical Care Medicine"/><published>2021-10-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.18.21265057</id><title>Impact of routine asymptomatic screening on COVID-19 incidence in a highly vaccinated university population (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.194425+00:00</updated><author><name>Rebeca C. Falcão</name></author><author><name>Michael Otterstatter</name></author><author><name>May A. Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Michelle Spencer</name></author><author><name>Sarafa Iyaniwura</name></author><author><name>Naveed Z. Janjua</name></author><author><name>Geoff McKee</name></author><author><name>Michael A. Irvine</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the return of in-person classes, an understanding of COVID-19 transmission in vaccinated university campuses is essential. Given the context of high anticipated vaccination rates and other measures, there are outstanding questions of the potential impact of campus-based asymptomatic screening.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We estimated the expected number of cases and hospitalizations in one semester using rates derived for British Columbia (BC), Canada up to September 15&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;, 2021 and age-standardizing to a University population. To estimate the expected number of secondary cases averted due to routine tests of unvaccinated individuals in a BC post-secondary institution, we used a probabilistic model based on the incidence, vaccination effectiveness, vaccination coverage and &lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;. We examined multiple scenarios of vaccine coverage, screening frequency, and pre-vaccination &lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;For one 12 week semester, the expected number of cases is 67 per 50,000 for 80% vaccination coverage and 37 per 50,000 for 95% vaccination coverage. Screening of the unvaccinated population averts an expected 6-16 cases per 50,000 at 80% decreasing to 1-2 averted cases per 50,000 at 95% vaccination coverage for weekly to daily screening. Further scenarios can be explored using a web-based application.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Routine screening of unvaccinated individuals may be of limited benefit if vaccination coverage is 80% or greater within a university setting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.18.21265057" rel="alternate" title="Impact of routine asymptomatic screening on COVID-19 incidence in a highly vaccinated university population (3 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>