<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.765807+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467705</id><title>Molecular signature of postmortem lung tissue from COVID-19 patients suggests distinct trajectories driving mortality (70 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.766474+00:00</updated><author><name>Anshul Budhraja</name></author><author><name>Anubhav Basu</name></author><author><name>Atish Gheware</name></author><author><name>Dasari Abhilash</name></author><author><name>Seesandra Rajagopala</name></author><author><name>Suman Pakala</name></author><author><name>Madhuresh Sumit</name></author><author><name>Animesh Ray</name></author><author><name>S Arulselvi</name></author><author><name>Purva Mathur</name></author><author><name>Aruna Nambirajan</name></author><author><name>Sachin Kumar</name></author><author><name>Ritu Gupta</name></author><author><name>Naveet Wig</name></author><author><name>Anjan Trikha</name></author><author><name>Randeep Guleria</name></author><author><name>Chitra Sarkar</name></author><author><name>Ishaan Gupta</name></author><author><name>Deepali Jain</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The precise molecular mechanisms behind severe life-threatening lung abnormalities during severe SARS-CoV-2 infections are still unclear. To address this challenge, we performed whole transcriptome sequencing of lung autopsies from 31 patients suffering from severe COVID-19 related complications and 10 uninfected controls. Using a metatranscriptome analysis of lung tissue samples we identified the existence of two distinct molecular signatures of lethal COVID-19. The dominant “classical” signature (n=23) showed upregulation of unfolded protein response, steroid biosynthesis and complement activation supported by massive metabolic reprogramming leading to characteristic lung damage. The rarer signature (n=8) potentially representing “Cytokine Release Syndrome” (CRS) showed upregulation of IL1 cytokines such CCL19 but absence of complement activation and muted inflammation. Further, dissecting expression of individual genes within enriched pathways for patient signature suggests heterogeneity in host response to the primary infection. We found that the majority of patients cleared the SARS-CoV-2 infection, but all suffered from acute dysbiosis with characteristic enrichment of opportunistic pathogens such as &lt;italic&gt;Gordonia bronchialis&lt;/italic&gt; in “classical” patients and &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus warneri&lt;/italic&gt; in CRS patients. Our results suggest two distinct models of lung pathology in severe COVID-19 patients that can be identified through the status of the complement activation, presence of specific cytokines and characteristic microbiome. This information can be used to design personalized therapy to treat COVID-19 related complications corresponding to patient signature such as using the identified drug molecules or mitigating specific secondary infections.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467705" rel="alternate" title="Molecular signature of postmortem lung tissue from COVID-19 patients suggests distinct trajectories driving mortality (70 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467773</id><title>A self-amplifying mRNA COVID-19 vaccine drives potent and broad immune responses at low doses that protects non-human primates against SARS-CoV-2 (38 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.767041+00:00</updated><author><name>Amy R. Rappaport</name></author><author><name>Sue-Jean Hong</name></author><author><name>Ciaran D. Scallan</name></author><author><name>Leonid Gitlin</name></author><author><name>Arvin Akoopie</name></author><author><name>Gregory R. Boucher</name></author><author><name>Milana Egorova</name></author><author><name>J. Aaron Espinosa</name></author><author><name>Mario Fidanza</name></author><author><name>Melissa A. Kachura</name></author><author><name>Annie Shen</name></author><author><name>Gloria Sivko</name></author><author><name>Anne Van Abbema</name></author><author><name>Robert L. Veres</name></author><author><name>Karin Jooss</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic continues to spread globally, highlighting the urgent need for safe and effective vaccines that could be rapidly mobilized to immunize large populations. We report the preclinical development of a self-amplifying mRNA (SAM) vaccine encoding a prefusion stabilized severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) spike glycoprotein and demonstrate potent cellular and humoral immune responses at low doses in mice and rhesus macaques. The homologous prime-boost vaccination regimen of SAM at 3, 10 and 30 μg induced potent neutralizing antibody titers in rhesus macaques following two SAM vaccinations at all dose levels, with the 10 μg dose generating geometric mean titers (GMT) 48-fold greater than the GMT of a panel of SARS-CoV-2 convalescent human sera. Spike-specific T cell responses were observed at all dose levels. SAM vaccination provided protective efficacy against SARS-CoV-2 challenge as both a homologous prime-boost and as a single boost following ChAd prime, demonstrating reduction of viral replication in both the upper and lower airways. Protection was most effective with a SAM prime-boost vaccination regimen at 10 and 30 μg and with a ChAd/SAM heterologous prime-boost regimen. The SAM vaccine is currently being evaluated in clinical trials as both a homologous prime-boost regimen at low doses and as a boost following heterologous prime.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467773" rel="alternate" title="A self-amplifying mRNA COVID-19 vaccine drives potent and broad immune responses at low doses that protects non-human primates against SARS-CoV-2 (38 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265533</id><title>Effect of the Neutralizing SARS-CoV-2 Antibody Sotrovimab in Preventing Progression of COVID-19: A Randomized Clinical Trial (34 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.767573+00:00</updated><author><name>Anil Gupta</name></author><author><name>Yaneicy Gonzalez-Rojas</name></author><author><name>Erick Juarez</name></author><author><name>Manuel Crespo Casal</name></author><author><name>Jaynier Moya</name></author><author><name>Diego Rodrigues Falci</name></author><author><name>Elias Sarkis</name></author><author><name>Joel Solis</name></author><author><name>Hanzhe Zheng</name></author><author><name>Nicola Scott</name></author><author><name>Andrea L. Cathcart</name></author><author><name>Sergio Parra</name></author><author><name>Jennifer E. Sager</name></author><author><name>Daren Austin</name></author><author><name>Amanda Peppercorn</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Alexander</name></author><author><name>Wendy W. Yeh</name></author><author><name>Cynthia Brinson</name></author><author><name>Melissa Aldinger</name></author><author><name>Adrienne E. Shapiro</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Older patients and those with underlying comorbidities infected with SARS-CoV-2 may be at increased risk of hospitalization and death from COVID-19. Sotrovimab is a neutralizing antibody designed for treatment of high-risk patients to prevent COVID-19 progression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To evaluate the efficacy and safety of sotrovimab in preventing progression of mild to moderate COVID-19 to severe disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Randomized, double-blind, multicenter, placebo-controlled, phase 3 study.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;57 centers in 5 countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nonhospitalized patients with symptomatic, mild to moderate COVID-19 and at least 1 risk factor for disease progression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Intervention&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients were randomized (1:1) to an intravenous infusion of sotrovimab 500 mg or placebo.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Outcomes and Measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The primary efficacy outcome was the proportion of patients with COVID-19 progression, defined as all-cause hospitalization longer than 24 hours for acute illness management or death through day 29. Key secondary outcomes included the proportion of patients with COVID-19 progression, defined as emergency room visit, hospitalization of any duration, or death, and proportion of patients developing severe/critical respiratory COVID-19 requiring supplemental oxygen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among 1057 patients randomized (sotrovimab, 528; placebo, 529), all-cause hospitalization longer than 24 hours or death was significantly reduced with sotrovimab (6/528 [1%]) vs placebo (30/529 [6%]) by 79% (95% CI, 50% to 91%; &lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;&amp;lt;.001). Secondary outcome results further demonstrated the effect of sotrovimab in reducing emergency room visits, hospitalization of any duration, or death, which was reduced by 66% (95% CI, 37% to 81%; &lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;&amp;lt;.001), and severe/critical respiratory COVID-19, which was reduced by 74% (95% CI, 41% to 88%; &lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;=.002). No patients receiving sotrovimab required high-flow oxygen, oxygen via nonrebreather mask, or mechanical ventilation compared with 14 patients receiving placebo. The proportion of patients reporting adverse events was similar between treatment groups; sotrovimab was well tolerated, and no safety concerns were identified.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions and Relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among nonhospitalized patients with mild to moderate COVID-19, a single 500-mg intravenous dose of sotrovimab prevented progression of COVID-19, with a reduction in hospitalization and need for supplemental oxygen. Sotrovimab is a well-tolerated, effective treatment option for patients at high risk for severe morbidity and mortality from COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Trial Registration&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov"&gt;ClinicalTrials.gov&lt;/ext-link&gt; Identifier: &lt;underline&gt;NCT04545060&lt;/underline&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265533" rel="alternate" title="Effect of the Neutralizing SARS-CoV-2 Antibody Sotrovimab in Preventing Progression of COVID-19: A Randomized Clinical Trial (34 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.21265656</id><title>REGEN-COV® for Treatment of Hospitalized Patients with Covid-19 (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.768395+00:00</updated><author><name>Selin Somersan-Karakaya</name></author><author><name>Eleftherios Mylonakis</name></author><author><name>Vidya P. Menon</name></author><author><name>Jason C. Wells</name></author><author><name>Shazia Ali</name></author><author><name>Sumathi Sivapalasingam</name></author><author><name>Yiping Sun</name></author><author><name>Rafia Bhore</name></author><author><name>Jingning Mei</name></author><author><name>Jutta Miller</name></author><author><name>Lisa Cupelli</name></author><author><name>Andrea T. Hooper</name></author><author><name>Jennifer D. Hamilton</name></author><author><name>Cynthia Pan</name></author><author><name>Viet Pham</name></author><author><name>Yuming Zhao</name></author><author><name>Romana Hosain</name></author><author><name>Adnan Mahmood</name></author><author><name>John D. Davis</name></author><author><name>Kenneth C. Turner</name></author><author><name>Yunji Kim</name></author><author><name>Amanda Cook</name></author><author><name>Bari Kowal</name></author><author><name>Yuhwen Soo</name></author><author><name>A. Thomas DiCioccio</name></author><author><name>Gregory P. Geba</name></author><author><name>Neil Stahl</name></author><author><name>Leah Lipsich</name></author><author><name>Ned Braunstein</name></author><author><name>Gary A. Herman</name></author><author><name>George D. Yancopoulos</name></author><author><name>David M. Weinreich</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hospitalized patients with Covid-19 experience high mortality rates, ranging from 10-30%. Casirivimab and imdevimab (REGEN-COV&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt;) is authorized in various jurisdictions for use in outpatients with Covid-19 and in post-exposure prophylaxis. The UK-based platform RECOVERY study reported improved survival in hospitalized seronegative patients treated with REGEN-COV, but in most of the world, anti-spike monoclonal antibody therapy is currently not approved for use in hospitalized patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this phase 1/2/3 double-blind placebo-controlled trial, patients on low-flow or no supplemental oxygen hospitalized with Covid-19 were randomized (1:1:1) to 2.4 g or 8.0 g REGEN-COV or placebo and characterized at baseline for viral load and SARS-CoV-2 endogenous immune response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;1336 patients on low-flow or no supplemental oxygen were treated. The primary endpoint was met: in seronegative patients, the LS mean difference (REGEN-COV vs. placebo) for TWA change from baseline viral load was −0.28 log&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;/sub&gt; copies/mL (95% CI: −0.51, −0.05; P=0.0172). The primary clinical analysis of death or mechanical ventilation from day 6-29 in patients with high-viral load had a strong positive trend but did not reach significance. REGEN-COV reduced all-cause mortality in seronegative patients through day 29 (RRR, 55.6%; 95% CI: 24.2%, 74%). No safety concerns were noted overall nor in seropositive patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In hospitalized patients with Covid-19 on low-flow or no oxygen, REGEN-COV treatment reduced viral load and the risk of death or mechanical ventilation as well as all-cause mortality in the overall population, with the benefit driven by seronegative patients and no harm observed in seropositive patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov"&gt;ClinicalTrials.gov&lt;/ext-link&gt; number, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT04426695"&gt;NCT04426695&lt;/ext-link&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.21265656" rel="alternate" title="REGEN-COV® for Treatment of Hospitalized Patients with Covid-19 (30 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468057</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 ORF8 encoded protein contains a histone mimic, disrupts chromatin regulation, and enhances replication (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.769127+00:00</updated><author><name>John Kee</name></author><author><name>Samuel Thudium</name></author><author><name>David Renner</name></author><author><name>Karl Glastad</name></author><author><name>Katherine Palozola</name></author><author><name>Zhen Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yize Li</name></author><author><name>Joseph Cesare</name></author><author><name>Yemin Lan</name></author><author><name>Rachel Truitt</name></author><author><name>Fabian L. Cardenas-Diaz</name></author><author><name>Darrell N. Kotton</name></author><author><name>Konstantinos D. Alysandratos</name></author><author><name>Xianwen Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xuping Xie</name></author><author><name>Pei-Yong Shi</name></author><author><name>Wenli Yang</name></author><author><name>Edward Morrisey</name></author><author><name>Benjamin A. Garcia</name></author><author><name>Shelley L. Berger</name></author><author><name>Susan R. Weiss</name></author><author><name>Erica Korb</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 emerged in China at the end of 2019 and caused the global pandemic of COVID-19, a disease with high morbidity and mortality. While our understanding of this new virus is rapidly increasing, gaps remain in our understanding of how SARS-CoV-2 can effectively suppress host cell antiviral responses. Recent work on other viruses has demonstrated a novel mechanism through which viral proteins can mimic critical regions of human histone proteins. Histone proteins are responsible for governing genome accessibility and their precise regulation is critical for a cell’s ability to control transcription and respond to viral threats. Here, we show that the protein encoded by ORF8 (Orf8) in SARS-CoV-2 functions as a histone mimic of the ARKS motif in histone 3. Orf8 is associated with chromatin, binds to numerous histone-associated proteins, and is itself acetylated within the histone mimic site. Orf8 expression in cells disrupts multiple critical histone post-translational modifications (PTMs) including H3K9ac, H3K9me3, and H3K27me3 and promotes chromatin compaction while Orf8 lacking the histone mimic motif does not. Further, SARS-CoV-2 infection in human cell lines and postmortem patient lung tissue cause these same disruptions to chromatin. However, deletion of the Orf8 gene from SARS-CoV-2 largely blocks its ability to disrupt host-cell chromatin indicating that Orf8 is responsible for these effects. Finally, deletion of the ORF8 gene affects the host-cell transcriptional response to SARS-CoV-2 infection in multiple cell types and decreases the replication of SARS-CoV-2 in human induced pluripotent stem cell-derived lung alveolar type 2 (iAT2) pulmonary cells. These findings demonstrate a novel function for the poorly understood ORF8-encoded protein and a mechanism through which SARS-CoV-2 disrupts host cell epigenetic regulation. Finally, this work provides a molecular basis for the finding that SARS-CoV-2 lacking ORF8 is associated with decreased severity of COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468057" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 ORF8 encoded protein contains a histone mimic, disrupts chromatin regulation, and enhances replication (23 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.06.467547</id><title>Accelerated decline of genome heterogeneity in the SARS-CoV-2 coronavirus (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.769737+00:00</updated><author><name>José L. Oliver</name></author><author><name>Pedro Bernaola-Galván</name></author><author><name>Francisco Perfectti</name></author><author><name>Cristina Gómez-Martín</name></author><author><name>Miguel Verdú</name></author><author><name>Andrés Moya</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the brief time since the outbreak of the COVID-19 pandemic, and despite its proofreading mechanism, the SARS-CoV-2 coronavirus has accumulated a significant amount of genetic variability through recombination and mutation events. To test evolutionary trends that could inform us on the adaptive process of the virus to its human host, we summarize all this variability in the Sequence Compositional Complexity (&lt;italic&gt;SCC&lt;/italic&gt;), a measure of genome heterogeneity that captures the mutational and recombinational changes accumulated by a nucleotide sequence along time. Despite the brief time elapsed, we detected many differences in the number and length of compositional domains, as well as in their nucleotide frequencies, in more than 12,000 high-quality coronavirus genomes from across the globe. These differences in &lt;italic&gt;SCC&lt;/italic&gt; are phylogenetically structured, as revealed by significant phylogenetic signal. Phylogenetic ridge regression shows that &lt;italic&gt;SCC&lt;/italic&gt; followed a generalized decreasing trend along the ongoing process of pathogen evolution. In contrast, &lt;italic&gt;SCC&lt;/italic&gt; evolutionary rate increased with time, showing that it accelerates toward the present. In addition, a low rate set of genomes was detected in all the genome groups, suggesting the existence of a stepwise distribution of rates, a strong indication of selection in favor of different dominant strains. Coronavirus variants reveal an exacerbation of this trend: non-significant &lt;italic&gt;SCC&lt;/italic&gt; regression, low phylogenetic signal and, concomitantly, a threefold increase in the evolutionary rate. Altogether, these results show an accelerated decline of genome heterogeneity along with the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic expansion, a process that might be related to viral adaptation to the human host, perhaps paralleling the transformation of the current pandemic to epidemic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.06.467547" rel="alternate" title="Accelerated decline of genome heterogeneity in the SARS-CoV-2 coronavirus (22 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467523</id><title>SARS-COV-2 Delta variant displays moderate resistance to neutralizing antibodies and spike protein properties of higher soluble ACE2 sensitivity, enhanced cleavage and fusogenic activity (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.770058+00:00</updated><author><name>Sabari Nath Neerukonda</name></author><author><name>Russell Vassell</name></author><author><name>Sabrina Lusvarghi</name></author><author><name>Richard Wang</name></author><author><name>Fernando Echegaray</name></author><author><name>Lisa Bentley</name></author><author><name>Ann E. Eakin</name></author><author><name>Karl J. Erlandson</name></author><author><name>Leah C. Katzelnick</name></author><author><name>Carol D. Weiss</name></author><author><name>Wei Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The SARS-CoV-2 B.1.617 lineage variants, Kappa (B.1.617.1) and Delta (B.1.617.2, AY) emerged during the second wave of infections in India, but the Delta variants have become dominant worldwide and continue to evolve. The spike proteins of B.1.617.1, B.1.617.2, and AY.1 variants have several substitutions in the receptor binding domain (RBD), including L452R+E484Q, L452R+T478K, and K417N+L452R+T478K, respectively, that could potentially reduce effectiveness of therapeutic antibodies and current vaccines. Here we compared B.1.617 variants, and their single and double RBD substitutions for resistance to neutralization by convalescent sera, mRNA vaccine-elicited sera, and therapeutic neutralizing antibodies using a pseudovirus neutralization assay. Pseudoviruses with the B.1.617.1, B.1.617.2, and AY.1 spike showed a modest 1.5 to 4.4-fold reduction in neutralization titer by convalescent sera and vaccine-elicited sera. In comparison, similar modest reductions were also observed for pseudoviruses with C.37, P.1, R.1, and B.1.526 spikes, but seven- and sixteen-fold reduction for vaccine-elicited and convalescent sera, respectively, was seen for pseudoviruses with the B.1.351 spike. Four of twenty-three therapeutic neutralizing antibodies showed either complete or partial loss of neutralization against B.1.617.2 pseudoviruses due to the L452R substitution, whereas six of twenty-three therapeutic neutralizing antibodies showed either complete or partial loss of neutralization against B.1.617.1 pseudoviruses due to either the E484Q or L452R substitution. Against AY.1 pseudoviruses, the L452R and K417N substitutions accounted for the loss of neutralization by four antibodies and one antibody, respectively, whereas one antibody lost potency that could not be fully accounted for by a single RBD substitution. The modest resistance of B.1.617 variants to vaccine-elicited sera suggest that current mRNA-based vaccines will likely remain effective in protecting against B.1.617 variants, but the therapeutic antibodies need to be carefully selected based on their resistance profiles. Finally, the spike proteins of B.1.617 variants are more efficiently cleaved due to the P681R substitution, and the spike of Delta variants exhibited greater sensitivity to soluble ACE2 neutralization, as well as fusogenic activity, which may contribute to enhanced spread of Delta variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467523" rel="alternate" title="SARS-COV-2 Delta variant displays moderate resistance to neutralizing antibodies and spike protein properties of higher soluble ACE2 sensitivity, enhanced cleavage and fusogenic activity (19 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468037</id><title>Potent antibody immunity to SARS-CoV-2 variants elicited by a third dose of inactivated vaccine (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.770396+00:00</updated><author><name>Bin Ju</name></author><author><name>Bing Zhou</name></author><author><name>Shuo Song</name></author><author><name>Qing Fan</name></author><author><name>Xiangyang Ge</name></author><author><name>Haiyan Wang</name></author><author><name>Lin Cheng</name></author><author><name>Huimin Guo</name></author><author><name>Dan Shu</name></author><author><name>Lei Liu</name></author><author><name>Zheng Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 variants are still prevalent worldwide and continue to pose a challenge to the effectiveness of current vaccines. It remains unknown whether a third dose of inactivated vaccine elicits immune potential against SARS-CoV-2 variants. Here, we showed a significant decline in plasma neutralization against SARS-CoV-2 at seven months after a second dose of the inactivated vaccine in a large-scale cohort. However, we also found that a third vaccination with an inactivated vaccine largely increased plasma neutralization against variants including Beta, Delta, and Lambda. More importantly, the high-affinity anti-RBD memory B cells were also generated by the third vaccination, suggesting a more potent and longer protection. These findings highlighted the importance and effectiveness of a third dose of inactivated vaccine in conferring higher protection against the emerging variants in populations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468037" rel="alternate" title="Potent antibody immunity to SARS-CoV-2 variants elicited by a third dose of inactivated vaccine (14 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467648</id><title>Phage-like particle vaccines are highly immunogenic and protect against pathogenic coronavirus infection and disease (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.770700+00:00</updated><author><name>Bennett J. Davenport</name></author><author><name>Alexis Catala</name></author><author><name>Stuart M. Weston</name></author><author><name>Robert M. Johnson</name></author><author><name>Jeremy Ardunay</name></author><author><name>Holly L. Hammond</name></author><author><name>Carly Dillen</name></author><author><name>Matthew B. Frieman</name></author><author><name>Carlos E. Catalano</name></author><author><name>Thomas E. Morrison</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The response by vaccine developers to the COVID-19 pandemic has been extraordinary with effective vaccines authorized for emergency use in the U.S. within one year of the appearance of the first COVID-19 cases. However, the emergence of SARS-CoV-2 variants and obstacles with the global rollout of new vaccines highlight the need for platforms that are amenable to rapid tuning and stable formulation to facilitate the logistics of vaccine delivery worldwide. We developed a “designer nanoparticle” platform using phage-like particles (PLPs) derived from bacteriophage lambda for multivalent display of antigens in rigorously defined ratios. Here, we engineered PLPs that display the receptor binding domain (RBD) protein from SARS-CoV-2 and MERS-CoV, alone (RBD&lt;sub&gt;SARS&lt;/sub&gt;-PLPs, RBD&lt;sub&gt;MERS&lt;/sub&gt;-PLPs) and in combination (hCoV-RBD PLPs). Functionalized particles possess physiochemical properties compatible with pharmaceutical standards and retain antigenicity. Following primary immunization, BALB/c mice immunized with RBD&lt;sub&gt;SARS&lt;/sub&gt;- or RBD&lt;sub&gt;MERS&lt;/sub&gt;-PLPs display serum RBD-specific IgG endpoint and live virus neutralization titers that, in the case of SARS-CoV-2, were comparable to those detected in convalescent plasma from infected patients. Further, these antibody levels remain elevated up to 6 months post-prime. In dose response studies, immunization with as little as one microgram of RBD&lt;sub&gt;SARS&lt;/sub&gt;-PLPs elicited robust neutralizing antibody responses. Finally, animals immunized with RBD&lt;sub&gt;SARS&lt;/sub&gt;-PLPs, RBD&lt;sub&gt;MERS&lt;/sub&gt;-PLPs, and hCoV-RBD PLPs were protected against SARS-CoV-2 and/or MERS-CoV lung infection and disease. Collectively, these data suggest that the designer PLP system provides a platform for facile and rapid generation of single and multi-target vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467648" rel="alternate" title="Phage-like particle vaccines are highly immunogenic and protect against pathogenic coronavirus infection and disease (12 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.07.21266027</id><title>Ethnicity and outcomes in COVID-19 in the United Kingdom: a systematic review and meta-analysis (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.771009+00:00</updated><author><name>Sania Siddiq</name></author><author><name>Saima Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Irfan Akram</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This systematic review and meta-analysis evaluated the clinical outcomes of COVID-19 disease in the ethnic minorities of the UK in comparison to the White ethnic group. Medline, Embase, Cochrane, MedRxiv, and Prospero were searched for articles published between May 2020 to April 2021. PROSPERO ID: CRD42021248117. Fourteen studies (767177 participants) were included in the review. In the adjusted analysis, the pooled Odds Ratio (OR) for the mortality outcome was higher for the Black (1.83, 95% CI: 1.21-2.76), Asian (1.16, 95% CI: 0.85-1.57), and Mixed and Other (MO) groups (1.12, 95% CI: 1.04-1.20) compared to the White group. The adjusted and unadjusted ORs of intensive care admission were more than double for all ethnicities (OR Black 2.32, 95% CI: 1.73-3.11, Asian 2.34, 95% CI: 1.89-2.90, MO group 2.26, 95% CI: 1.64-3.11). In the adjusted analysis of mechanical ventilation need the ORs were similarly significantly raised (Black group 2.03, 95% CI: 1.80-2.29, Asian group 1.84, 95% CI: 1.20-2.80, MO 2.09, 95% CI: 1.35-3.22). This review confirmed that all ethnic groups in the UK suffered from increased disease severity and mortality with regards to COVID-19. This has urgent public health and policy implications to reduce the health disparities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.07.21266027" rel="alternate" title="Ethnicity and outcomes in COVID-19 in the United Kingdom: a systematic review and meta-analysis (10 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.21266174</id><title>Understanding national trends in COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy in Canada – April 2020 to March 2021 (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.771243+00:00</updated><author><name>Kim L. Lavoie</name></author><author><name>Vincent Gosselin-Boucher</name></author><author><name>Jovana Stojanovic</name></author><author><name>Samir Gupta</name></author><author><name>Myriam Gagne</name></author><author><name>Keven Joyal-Desmarais</name></author><author><name>Katherine Seguin</name></author><author><name>Sherri Sheinfield-Gorin</name></author><author><name>Paula Ribeiro</name></author><author><name>Brigitte Voisard</name></author><author><name>Michael Vallis</name></author><author><name>Kim Corace</name></author><author><name>Justin Presseau</name></author><author><name>Simon L. Bacon</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Key to reducing COVID-19 morbidity and mortality and reducing the need for further lockdown measures in Canada and worldwide is widespread acceptance of COVID-19 vaccines. Vaccine hesitancy has emerged as a key barrier to achieving optimal vaccination rates, for which there is little data among Canadians. This study examined rates of vaccine hesitancy and their correlates among Canadian adults.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study analyzed data from five age, sex and province-weighted population-based samples to describe rates of hesitancy between April 2020 and March 2021 among Canadians who completed online surveys as part of the iCARE Study, and various sociodemographic, clinical and psychological correlates. Vaccine hesitancy was assessed by asking: “&lt;italic&gt;If a vaccine for COVID-19 were available today, what is the likelihood that you would get vaccinated?&lt;/italic&gt;” Responses were dichotomized into ‘very likely’, ‘unlikely’, ‘somewhat unlikely’ (reflecting some degree of vaccine hesitancy) vs ‘extremely likely’ to get the vaccine, which was the comparator.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overall, 15,019 respondents participated in the study. A total of 42.2% of respondents reported vaccine hesitancy over the course of the study, which was lowest during surveys 1 (April 2020) and 5 (March 2021) and highest during survey 3 (November 2020). Fully adjusted multivariate logistic regression analyses revealed that women, those aged 50 and younger, non-Whites, those with high school education or less, and those with annual household incomes below the poverty line in Canada (i.e., $60,000) were significantly more likely to report being vaccine hesitant over the study period, as were essential and healthcare workers, parents of children under the age of 18, and those who do not get regular flu vaccines. Believing engaging in infection prevention behaviours (like vaccination) is important for reducing virus transmission and high COVID-19 health concerns (being infected and infecting others) were associated with 77% and 54% reduction in vaccine hesitancy, respectively, and having high personal financial concerns (worried about job or income loss) was associated with 1.33 times increased odds of vaccine hesitancy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Results point to the importance of targeting vaccine efforts to women, younger people and socioeconomically disadvantaged groups, and that vaccine messaging should emphasize the benefits of getting vaccinated, and how the benefits (particularly to health) far outweigh the risks. Future research is needed to monitor ongoing changes in vaccine intentions and behaviour, as well as to better understand motivators and facilitators of vaccine acceptance, particularly among vulnerable groups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.21266174" rel="alternate" title="Understanding national trends in COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy in Canada – April 2020 to March 2021 (8 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.21265763</id><title>Surveillance of COVID-19 in a Vaccinated Population: A Rapid Literature Review (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.771871+00:00</updated><author><name>Oluwaseun Egunsola</name></author><author><name>Brenlea Farkas</name></author><author><name>Jordyn Flanagan</name></author><author><name>Charleen Salmon</name></author><author><name>Liza Mastikhina</name></author><author><name>Fiona Clement</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the availability of COVID-19 vaccines, public health focus is shifting to post-vaccination surveillance to identify breakthrough infections in vaccinated populations. Therefore, the objectives of these reviews are to identify scientific evidence and international guidance on surveillance and testing approaches to monitor the presence of the virus in a vaccinated population.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Method&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We searched Ovid MEDLINE®, including Epub Ahead of Print, In-Process &amp;amp; Other Non-Indexed Citations, Embase, EBM Reviews - Cochrane Central Register of Controlled Trials, and EBM Reviews - Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews. We also searched the Web of Science Core Collection. A grey literature search was also conducted. This search was limited to studies conducted since December 2020 and current to June 13th, 2021. There were no language limitations. COVID-19 surveillance studies that were published after December 2020 but did not specify whether they tested a vaccinated population were also considered for inclusion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the international guidance review, a grey literature search was conducted, including a thorough search of Google, websites of international government organizations (e.g., Center for Disease Control and Prevention [CDC], World Health Organization [WHO]), and McMaster Health Forum (CoVID-END). This search was primarily examining surveillance guidance published since December 2020 (to capture guidance specific to vaccinations) and any relevant pre-December 2020 guidance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thirty-three studies were included for data synthesis of scientific evidence on surveillance of COVID-19. All the studies were published between April and June 2021. Twenty-one studies were from peer-reviewed journals. Five approaches to monitoring post-vaccination COVID-19 cases and emerging variants of concern were identified, including screening with reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) and/or a rapid antigen test, genomic surveillance, wastewater surveillance, metagenomics, and testing of air filters on public buses. For population surveillance, the following considerations and limitations were observed: variability in person-to-person testing frequency; lower sensitivity of antigen tests; timing of infections relative to PCR testing can result in missed infections; large studies may fail to identify local variations; and loss of interest in testing by participants in long follow-up studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Through comprehensive grey literature searching, 68 international guidance documents were captured for full-text review. A total of 26 documents met the inclusion criteria and were included in our synthesis. Seven overarching surveillance methods emerged in the literature. PCR-testing was the most recommended surveillance method, followed by genomic screening, serosurveillance, wastewater surveillance, antigen testing, health record screening, and syndromic surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Evidence for post-vaccination COVID-19 surveillance was derived from studies in partially or fully vaccinated populations. Population PCR screening, supplemented by rapid antigen tests, was the most frequently used surveillance method and also the most commonly recommended across jurisdictions. Most recent guidance on COVID-19 surveillance is not specific to vaccinated individuals, or it is in effect but has not yet been updated to reflect that. Therefore, more evidence-informed guidance on testing and surveillance approaches in a vaccinated population that incorporates all testing modalities is required.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;EXECUTIVE SUMMARY&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the availability of COVID-19 vaccines, public health focus is shifting to post-vaccination surveillance to identify breakthrough infections in vaccinated populations. Therefore, the objectives of these reviews are to: 1) identify scientific evidence on surveillance and testing approaches to monitor the presence of the virus in a vaccinated population and determine how these influence testing strategies; 2) identify international guidance on testing and surveillance for COVID-19 and its variants of concern in a vaccinated population; and 3) identify emerging technologies for surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A rapid review was conducted to identify scientific evidence on COVID-19 surveillance and testing approaches, and a targeted literature review was conducted on international guidance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Method&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We searched Ovid MEDLINE®, including Epub Ahead of Print, In-Process &amp;amp; Other Non-Indexed Citations, Embase, EBM Reviews - Cochrane Central Register of Controlled Trials, and EBM Reviews - Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews. We also searched the Web of Science Core Collection. We performed all searches on June 13, 2021. A grey literature search was also conducted, including: MedRxiv, Google, McMaster Health Forum (COVID-END), and websites of international government organizations (e.g., Center for Disease Control and Prevention [CDC], World Health Organization [WHO]). This search was limited to studies conducted since December 2020 and current to June 13th, 2021. There were no language limitations. COVID-19 surveillance studies that were published after December 2020 but did not specify whether they tested a vaccinated population were also considered for inclusion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the international guidance review, a grey literature search was conducted, including a thorough search of Google, websites of international government organizations (e.g., Center for Disease Control and Prevention [CDC], World Health Organization [WHO]), and McMaster Health Forum (CoVID-END). This search was primarily examining surveillance guidance published since December 2020 (to capture guidance specific to vaccinations) and any relevant pre-December 2020 guidance. Although the primary focus was on surveillance guidance in a vaccinated population, guidance that was published after December 2020 but was not vaccine-specific was also considered for inclusion; it was assumed that this guidance was still in effect and was not yet updated. There were no language limitations. A patient partner was engaged during the co-production of a plain language summary for both the rapid review of primary literature and the review of international guidance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thirty-three studies were included for data synthesis of scientific evidence on surveillance of COVID-19. All the studies were published between April and June 2021. Twenty-one studies were from peer-reviewed journals. Five approaches to monitoring post-vaccination COVID-19 cases and emerging variants of concern were identified including, screening with reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) and/or a rapid antigen test, genomic surveillance, wastewater surveillance, metagenomics, and testing of air filters on public buses. Population surveillance with RT-PCR testing and/or rapid antigen testing was utilized in 22 studies, mostly in healthcare settings, but also in long-term care facilities (LTCFs) and in the community. The frequency of testing varied depending on whether there was an outbreak.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For population surveillance, the following considerations and limitations were observed: studies with discretionary access to testing have highly variable person-to-person testing frequency; antigen tests have lower sensitivity, therefore some positive cases may be missed; timing of infections relative to PCR testing as well as the sensitivity of the tests can result in missed infections; large sample sizes from multicentre studies increase generalizability, but fail to identify local variations from individual centres; with electronic database surveillance, it is difficult to confirm whether patients with a breakthrough infection and a previous positive SARS-CoV-2 test result had a true reinfection or had prolonged shedding from the previous infection; and participants lose interest in studies with long follow-up, with decrease in testing rates over time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Six wastewater surveillance and three genomic surveillance studies were identified in this review. A number of benefits such as, good correlation with clinical data, ability to predict major outbreaks, and rapid turnaround time were observed with wastewater surveillance. However, challenges such as, inconsistencies in variant representation depending on where the samples were taken within the community, differences in the capacity of wastewater to predict case numbers based on the size of the wastewater treatment plants, and cost, were noted. Emerging technologies like viral detection in public transport filters, novel sampling, and assay platforms were also identified.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Through comprehensive grey literature searching, 68 international guidance documents were captured for full-text review. A total of 26 documents met the inclusion criteria and were included in our synthesis. Most were not specific to vaccinated populations but reported on a surveillance method of COVID-19 and were therefore included in the review; it was assumed that they were still in effect but have not yet been updated. Eleven countries/regions were represented, including Australia, Brazil, France, Germany, India, New Zealand, Spain, United Kingdom, United States, Europe, and International. All of the guidance documents included surveillance methods appropriate for community settings. Other settings of interest were healthcare settings, including hospitals and primary care centres, long-term care facilities, points of entry for travel, schools, and other sentinel sites (e.g., prisons and closed settings). Seven overarching surveillance methods emerged in the literature. PCR-testing was the most recommended surveillance method, followed by genomic screening, serosurveillance, wastewater surveillance, antigen testing, health record screening, and syndromic surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Only one document (published by Public Health England) was identified that provided guidance on surveillance specific to vaccinated populations. The document outlined a plan to surveil and monitor COVID-19 in vaccinated populations through a series of targeted longitudinal studies, routine surveillance, enhanced surveillance, use of electronic health records, surveillance of vaccine failure (including follow-up with viral whole genome sequencing), and sero-surveillance (including blood donor samples, routine blood tests, and residual sera).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Evidence for post-vaccination COVID-19 surveillance was derived from studies in partially or fully vaccinated populations. Population PCR screening, supplemented by rapid antigen tests, was the most frequently used surveillance method and also the most commonly recommended across jurisdictions. The selection of testing method and the frequency of testing was determined by the intensity of the disease and the scale of testing. Other common testing methods included wastewater surveillance and genomic surveillance. A few novel technologies are emerging, however, many of these are yet to be utilized in the real-world setting. There is limited evidence-based guidance on surveillance in a vaccinated population. Most recent guidance on COVID-19 surveillance is not specific to vaccinated individuals, or it is in effect but has not yet been updated to reflect that. Therefore, more evidence-informed guidance on testing and surveillance approaches in a vaccinated population that incorporates all testing modalities is required.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Protocol/Topic Registration&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;PROSPERO-CRD42021261215.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key Definitions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;Antigen:&lt;/bold&gt; a foreign protein which induces an immune response in the body, especially the production of antibodies&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;Fully vaccinated&lt;/bold&gt;: refers to individuals who have received complete dosage of a given vaccine&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;Partially vaccinated:&lt;/bold&gt; refers to individuals who have received an incomplete dosage of a given vaccine&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;Sero-surveillance:&lt;/bold&gt; estimation of antibody levels against infectious diseases&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;Surveillance:&lt;/bold&gt; ongoing systematic collection, analysis, and interpretation of health data that are essential to the planning, implementation, and evaluation of public health practice&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;Variants of Concern:&lt;/bold&gt; a variant for which there is evidence of an increase in transmissibility and/or more severe disease&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;Variants:&lt;/bold&gt; virus with a permanent change in its genetic sequence&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.21265763" rel="alternate" title="Surveillance of COVID-19 in a Vaccinated Population: A Rapid Literature Review (7 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.21265977</id><title>Waning, Boosting and a Path to Endemicity for SARS-CoV-2 (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.772192+00:00</updated><author><name>Matt J. Keeling</name></author><author><name>Amy Thomas</name></author><author><name>Edward M. Hill</name></author><author><name>Robin N. Thompson</name></author><author><name>Louise Dyson</name></author><author><name>Michael J. Tildesley</name></author><author><name>Sam Moore</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In many countries, an extensive vaccination programme has substantially reduced the public-health impact of SARS-CoV-2, limiting the number of hospital admissions and deaths compared to an unmitigated epidemic. Ensuring a low-risk transition from the current situation to one in which SARS-CoV-2 is endemic requires maintenance of high levels of population immunity. The observed waning of vaccine efficacy over time suggests that booster doses may be required to maintain population immunity especially in the most vulnerable groups. Here, using data and models for England, we consider the dynamics of COVID-19 over a two-year time-frame, and the role that booster vaccinations can play in mitigating the worst effects. We find that boosters are necessary to suppress the imminent wave of infections that would be generated by waning vaccine efficacy. Projecting further into the future, the optimal deployment of boosters is highly sensitive to their long-term action. If protection from boosters wanes slowly (akin to protection following infection) then a single booster dose to the over 50s may be all that is needed over the next two-years. However, if protection wanes more rapidly (akin to protection following second dose vaccination) then annual or even biannual boosters are required to limit subsequent epidemic peaks an reduce the pressure on public health services.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.21265977" rel="alternate" title="Waning, Boosting and a Path to Endemicity for SARS-CoV-2 (7 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.07.467640</id><title>An interactome landscape of SARS-CoV-2 virus-human protein-protein interactions by protein sequence-based multi-label classifiers (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.772709+00:00</updated><author><name>Ho-Joon Lee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The new coronavirus species, SARS-CoV-2, caused an unprecedented global pandemic of COVID-19 disease since late December 2019. A comprehensive characterization of protein-protein interactions (PPIs) between SARS-CoV-2 and human cells is a key to understanding the infection and preventing the disease. Here we present a novel approach to predict virus-host PPIs by multi-label machine learning classifiers of random forests and XGBoost using amino acid composition profiles of virus and human proteins. Our models harness a large-scale database of Viruses.STRING with &amp;gt;80,000 virus-host PPIs along with evidence scores for multi-level evidence prediction, which is distinct from predicting binary interactions in previous studies. Our multi-label classifiers are based on 5 evidence levels binned from evidence scores. Our best model of XGBoost achieves 74% AUC and 68% accuracy on average in 10-fold cross validation. The most important amino acids are cysteine and histidine. In addition, our model predicts experimental PPIs with higher evidence level than text mining-based PPIs. We then predict evidence levels of ~2,000 SARS-CoV-2 virus-human PPIs from public experimental proteomics data. Interactions with SARS-CoV-2 Nsp7b show high evidence. We also predict evidence levels of all pairwise PPIs of ~550,000 between the SARS-CoV-2 and human proteomes to provide a draft virus-host interactome landscape for SARS-CoV-2 infection in humans in a comprehensive and unbiased way in silico. Most human proteins from 140 highest evidence predictions interact with SARS-CoV-2 Nsp7, Nsp1, and ORF14, with significant enrichment in the top 2 pathways of vascular smooth muscle contraction (CALD1, NPR2, CALML3) and Myc targets (CBX3, PES1). Our prediction also suggests that histone H2A components are targeted by multiple SARS-CoV-2 proteins.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.07.467640" rel="alternate" title="An interactome landscape of SARS-CoV-2 virus-human protein-protein interactions by protein sequence-based multi-label classifiers (7 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.21266075</id><title>Neutralisation of SARS-CoV-2 Delta sub-lineage AY.4.2 and B.1.617.2+E484K by BNT162b2 mRNA vaccine-elicited sera (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.773590+00:00</updated><author><name>Ria Lassaunière</name></author><author><name>Charlotta Polacek</name></author><author><name>Jannik Fonager</name></author><author><name>Marc Bennedbæk</name></author><author><name>Lasse Boding</name></author><author><name>Morten Rasmussen</name></author><author><name>Anders Fomsgaard</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A sublineage of the Delta variant, AY.4.2, recently accounted for an increased proportion of Delta cases in United Kingdom (UK), Romania, Poland, and Denmark. Several factors may account for the increased spread of AY.4.2. Here, we evaluated the sensitivity of AY.4.2 to neutralisation by sera from Pfizer/BioNTech (BNT162b2) vaccinees. AY.4.2 was not more resistant to neutralisation relative to other circulating Delta lineages or sublineages and showed only a modest 2.3-fold reduction in neutralisation relative to the vaccine strain. In contrast, the more rare B.1.617.2+E484K variant showed a 4.2-fold reduction in neutralisation that warrants surveillance of strains with the acquired E484K mutation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.21266075" rel="alternate" title="Neutralisation of SARS-CoV-2 Delta sub-lineage AY.4.2 and B.1.617.2+E484K by BNT162b2 mRNA vaccine-elicited sera (7 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.21265969</id><title>COVID-19: a study about the impact of coronavirus on physicians of La Plata, Argentina (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.774103+00:00</updated><author><name>María Virginia Croce</name></author><author><name>Elsa Chiappa</name></author><author><name>Adriana Moiso</name></author><author><name>Martin E Rabassa</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Argentina, the burden of COVID-19 on health systems and physicians was substantial with difficulties on daily triage decisions which have to be made in the context of grave shortages of basic equipment and consumables.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Purpose&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;this study was performed to understand what physicians were experiencing during the COVID-19 pandemic in La Plata (capital city of Buenos Aires province, Argentina).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A cross-sectional study was performed; a questionnaire was sent by e-mail to physicians who work in this city during November 2020. The questionnaire was made based on Medscape US and International Physicians’ COVID-19 Experience Report: Risk, Burnout, Loneliness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Statistical analysis&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;test for normality was performed employing the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test while Chi-square test of independence to examine the relationship between sex and workplace with nominal variables. For categorical variables, Kendall’s tau correlation was performed to test for independence. ANOVA was developed to examine differences between physician’s age. Statistical significance was set to p &amp;lt; 0.05 in all cases. All statistical analysis was done employing SPSS Statistics, Version 24 (IBM, USA).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;203 physicians answered the questionnaire; the majority of physicians (96%) considered stressful their experience during pandemic and reported distress episodes being for more than 60% the most stressful of their practices, 30% presented depression and were medically treated, while 32.7% felt loneliness with 4 physicians with suicidal thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The results highlight the need to protect the psychological well-being of the healthcare community, and to invest resources to significantly promote the mental health of professionals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.21265969" rel="alternate" title="COVID-19: a study about the impact of coronavirus on physicians of La Plata, Argentina (6 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.21266141</id><title>PBPK modelling of dexamethasone in patients with COVID-19 and liver disease (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.774374+00:00</updated><author><name>Maiara Camotti Montanha</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Cottura</name></author><author><name>Michael Booth</name></author><author><name>Daryl Hodge</name></author><author><name>Fazila Bunglawala</name></author><author><name>Hannah Kinvig</name></author><author><name>Sandra Grañana-Castillo</name></author><author><name>Andrew Lloyd</name></author><author><name>Saye Khoo</name></author><author><name>Marco Siccardi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The aim of the study was to apply Physiologically-Based Pharmacokinetic (PBPK) modelling to predict the effect of liver disease (LD) on the pharmacokinetics (PK) of dexamethasone (DEX) in the treatment of COVID-19. A whole-body PBPK model was created to simulate 100 adult individuals aged 18-60 years. Physiological changes (e.g., plasma protein concentration, liver size, CP450 expression, hepatic blood flow) and portal vein shunt were incorporated into the LD model. The changes were implemented by using the Child-Pugh (CP) classification system. DEX was qualified using clinical data in healthy adults for both oral (PO) and intravenous (IV) administrations and similarly propranolol (PRO) and midazolam (MDZ) were qualified with PO and IV clinical data in healthy and LD adults. The qualified model was subsequently used to simulate a 6 mg PO and 20 mg IV dose of DEX in patients with varying degrees of LD, with and without shunting. The PBPK model was successfully qualified across DEX, MDZ and PRO. In contrast to healthy adults, the simulated systemic clearance of DEX decreased (35% - 60%) and the plasma concentrations increased (170% - 400%) in patients with LD. Moreover, at higher doses of DEX, the AUC ratio between healthy/LD individuals remained comparable to lower doses. The exposure of DEX in different stages of LD was predicted through PBPK modelling, providing a rational framework to predict PK in complex clinical scenarios related to COVID-19. Model simulations suggest dose adjustments of DEX in LD patients are not necessary considering the low dose administered in the COVID-19 protocol.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.21266141" rel="alternate" title="PBPK modelling of dexamethasone in patients with COVID-19 and liver disease (4 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Therapeutics"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.21265992</id><title>Modeling COVID-19 epidemic trends and health system needs leading to projections for developing countries: a case study of Thailand (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.774681+00:00</updated><author><name>Nawaphan Metchanun</name></author><author><name>Christian Borgemeister</name></author><author><name>Caitlin Bever</name></author><author><name>David Galick</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Thailand was the first country outside China to report a COVID-19 case but had a mild impact from the outbreak especially at the beginning of the pandemic. This study systematically investigates the evolution of the COVID-19 epidemic in Thailand from January 2020 to March 2021 to uncover the COVID-19 situation in the country. By modeling all health districts throughout the country, the study found that COVID-19 contributed to an increase in excess deaths and that COVID-19 deaths might be underreported. There was a lag time in ramping up testing although testing is key to control the disease. The estimated total number of beds required by COVID-19 seems low, but it may not ensure the capacity to take care of critical cases that required ICU beds, specific medical equipment, and trained medical staff.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.21265992" rel="alternate" title="Modeling COVID-19 epidemic trends and health system needs leading to projections for developing countries: a case study of Thailand (4 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>