<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.804291+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.11.21264863</id><title>Characterizing menstrual bleeding changes occurring after SARS-CoV-2 vaccination (226 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.804673+00:00</updated><author><name>Katharine MN Lee</name></author><author><name>Eleanor J Junkins</name></author><author><name>Urooba A Fatima</name></author><author><name>Maria L Cox</name></author><author><name>Kathryn BH Clancy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many people began sharing that they experienced unexpected menstrual bleeding after SARS-CoV-2 inoculation. This emerging phenomenon was undeniable yet understudied. We investigated menstrual bleeding patterns among currently and formerly menstruating people, with a research design based off our expectations that these bleeding changes related to changes in clotting or inflammation, affecting normal menstrual repair. In this sample, 42% of people with regular menstrual cycles bled more heavily than usual, while 44% reported no change, after being vaccinated. Among people who typically do not menstruate, 71% of people on long-acting reversible contraceptives, 39% of people on gender-affirming hormones, and 66% of post-menopausal people reported breakthrough bleeding. We found increased/breakthrough bleeding was significantly associated with age, other vaccine side effects (fever, fatigue), history of pregnancy or birth, and ethnicity. Changes to menstrual bleeding are not uncommon nor dangerous, yet attention to these experiences is necessary to build trust in medicine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Teaser&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Increased bleeding can occur post SARS-CoV-2 vaccines; this study characterizes patterns to enable future hypothesis testing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.11.21264863" rel="alternate" title="Characterizing menstrual bleeding changes occurring after SARS-CoV-2 vaccination (226 tweets)"/><category term="Obstetrics and Gynecology"/><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463334</id><title>Covid-19 genomic analysis reveals clusters of emerging sublineages within the delta variant (44 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.804933+00:00</updated><author><name>Evans K. Rono</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants may potentially have enhanced transmissibility and virulence of the virus, and impacts on performance of diagnostic tools and efficacy of vaccines. Genomic surveillance provides an opportunity to detect and characterize new mutations early enough for effective deployment of control strategies. Here, genomic data from Germany and United Kingdom were examined for genetic diversity by assessing gene mutations and inferring phylogeny. Delta variant sublineages were grouped into seven distinct clusters of spike mutations located in N-terminal domain of S1 region (T95I, D138H, *D142G, Y145H and A222V) and S2 region (T719I and *N950D). The most predominant cluster was T95I mutation, with the highest frequencies (71.1% - 83.9%) in Wales, England and Scotland, and the least frequencies (8.9% - 12.1%) in Germany. Two mutations, *D142G and *N950D here described as *reverse mutations and T719I mutation, were largely unique to Germany. In a month, frequencies of D142G had increased from 55.6% to 67.8 % in Germany. Additionally, a cluster of D142G+T719I/T mutation went up from 27.7% to 34.1%, while a T95I+ D142G+N950D/N cluster rose from 19.2% to 26.2%. Although, two distinct clusters of T95I+D138H (2.6% - 3.8%) and T95I+Y145H+A222V (2.5% - 8.5%) mutations were present in all the countries, they were most predominant in Wales and Scotland respectively. Results suggest divergent evolutionary trajectories between the clusters of D142G mutation and those of T95I mutation. These findings provide insights into underlying dynamics of evolution of the delta variant. Future studies may evaluate the epidemiological and biological implications of these sublineages.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463334" rel="alternate" title="Covid-19 genomic analysis reveals clusters of emerging sublineages within the delta variant (44 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.21264960</id><title>Evaluation of real-life use of Point-Of-Care Rapid Antigen TEsting for SARS-CoV-2 in schools for outbreak control (EPOCRATES) (36 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.805092+00:00</updated><author><name>Ana C. Blanchard</name></author><author><name>Marc Desforges</name></author><author><name>Annie-Claude Labbé</name></author><author><name>Cat Tuong Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Yves Petit</name></author><author><name>Dominic Besner</name></author><author><name>Kate Zinszer</name></author><author><name>Olivier Séguin</name></author><author><name>Zineb Laghdir</name></author><author><name>Kelsey Adams</name></author><author><name>Marie-Ève Benoit</name></author><author><name>Geneviève Leduc</name></author><author><name>Jean Longtin</name></author><author><name>Ioannis Ragoussis</name></author><author><name>David L. Buckeridge</name></author><author><name>Caroline Quach</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We evaluated the use of rapid antigen detection tests (RADT) for the diagnosis of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection in school settings to determine RADT’s performance characteristics compared to PCR.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We did a real-world, prospective observational cohort study where recruited high-school students and staff from two high-schools in Montreal (Canada) were followed from January 25&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; to June 10&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;, 2021. Twenty-five percent of asymptomatic participants were tested weekly by RADT (nasal) and PCR (gargle). Class contacts of a case were tested. Symptomatic participants were tested by RADT (nasal) and PCR (nasal and gargle). The number of cases/outbreak and number of outbreaks were compared to other high schools in the same area.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overall, 2,099 students and 286 school staff members consented to participate. The overall RADT’s specificity varied from 99.8 to 100%, with a lower sensitivity, varying from 28.6% in asymptomatic to 83.3% in symptomatic participants. The number of outbreaks was not different in the 2 participating schools compared to other high schools in the same area, but included a greater proportion of asymptomatic cases. Returning students to school after a 7-day quarantine, with a negative PCR on D6-7 after exposure, did not lead to subsequent outbreaks, as shown by serial testing. Of cases for whom the source was known, 37 of 57 (72.5%) were secondary to household transmission, 13 (25%) to intra-school transmission and one to community contacts between students in the same school.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;RADT did not perform well as a screening tool in asymptomatic individuals. Reinforcing policies for symptom screening when entering schools and testing symptomatic individuals with RADT on the spot may avoid subsequent significant exposures in class.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Research in context&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Evidence before this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rapid antigen detection tests (RADT) have been used for years to diagnose respiratory pathogens, such as influenza and respiratory syncytial virus. These tests detect the presence of a specific viral antigen and are usually performed on nasopharyngeal or nasal specimens. RADT are relatively inexpensive and can be used at the point-of-care. Their performance characteristics vary, but they usually have high specificity and moderate sensitivity compared with PCR. For SARS-CoV-2, RADT’s specificity has been quite high (99.5%), but with sensitivity ranging from 28.9% to 98.3%.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Added value of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study determined the sensitivity and specificity of RADT against PCR for the diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2 in a real-life setting in high school students. The test performed well, in terms of specificity, but had a sensitivity that was as low as 28.6% in asymptomatic individuals to 83.3% in symptomatic individuals. The longitudinal aspect of the study also allowed to determine the impact of RADT on school outbreaks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Implication of all available evidence&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;RADT does not perform well as a screening tool for asymptomatic individuals. Reinforcing policies for symptom screening when entering schools and testing symptomatic individuals with RADT on the spot may avoid subsequent significant exposures in class.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.21264960" rel="alternate" title="Evaluation of real-life use of Point-Of-Care Rapid Antigen TEsting for SARS-CoV-2 in schools for outbreak control (EPOCRATES) (36 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.10.21264827</id><title>Heterologous SARS-CoV-2 Booster Vaccinations – Preliminary Report (36 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.805375+00:00</updated><author><name>Robert L. Atmar</name></author><author><name>Kirsten E. Lyke</name></author><author><name>Meagan E. Deming</name></author><author><name>Lisa A. Jackson</name></author><author><name>Angela R. Branche</name></author><author><name>Hana M. El Sahly</name></author><author><name>Christina A. Rostad</name></author><author><name>Judith M. Martin</name></author><author><name>Christine Johnston</name></author><author><name>Richard E. Rupp</name></author><author><name>Mark J. Mulligan</name></author><author><name>Rebecca C. Brady</name></author><author><name>Robert W. Frenck</name></author><author><name>Martín Bäcker</name></author><author><name>Angelica C. Kottkamp</name></author><author><name>Tara M. Babu</name></author><author><name>Kumaravel Rajakumar</name></author><author><name>Srilatha Edupuganti</name></author><author><name>Ann R. Falsey</name></author><author><name>Christine M. Posavad</name></author><author><name>Janet I. Archer</name></author><author><name>Sonja Crandon</name></author><author><name>Seema U. Nayak</name></author><author><name>Daniel Szydlo</name></author><author><name>Jillian Zemanek</name></author><author><name>Clara P. Dominguez Islas</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth R. Brown</name></author><author><name>Mehul S. Suthar</name></author><author><name>M. Juliana McElrath</name></author><author><name>Adrian B. McDermott</name></author><author><name>Sarah E. O’Connell</name></author><author><name>David C. Montefiori</name></author><author><name>Amanda Eaton</name></author><author><name>Kathleen M. Neuzil</name></author><author><name>David S. Stephens</name></author><author><name>Paul C. Roberts</name></author><author><name>John H. Beigel</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;While Coronavirus disease 2019 (Covid-19) vaccines are highly effective, breakthrough infections are occurring. Booster vaccinations have recently received emergency use authorization (EUA) for certain populations but are restricted to homologous mRNA vaccines. We evaluated homologous and heterologous booster vaccination in persons who had received an EUA Covid-19 vaccine regimen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this phase 1/2 open-label clinical trial conducted at ten U.S. sites, adults who received one of three EUA Covid-19 vaccines at least 12 weeks prior to enrollment and had no reported history of SARS-CoV-2 infection received a booster injection with one of three vaccines (Moderna mRNA-1273 100-μg, Janssen Ad26.COV2.S 5×10&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt; virus particles, or Pfizer-BioNTech BNT162b2 30-μg; nine combinations). The primary outcomes were safety, reactogenicity, and humoral immunogenicity on study days 15 and 29.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;458 individuals were enrolled: 154 received mRNA-1273, 150 received Ad26.CoV2.S, and 154 received BNT162b2 booster vaccines. Reactogenicity was similar to that reported for the primary series. Injection site pain, malaise, headache, and myalgia occurred in more than half the participants. Booster vaccines increased the neutralizing activity against a D614G pseudovirus (4.2-76-fold) and binding antibody titers (4.6-56-fold) for all combinations; homologous boost increased neutralizing antibody titers 4.2-20-fold whereas heterologous boost increased titers 6.2-76-fold. Day 15 neutralizing and binding antibody titers varied by 28.7-fold and 20.9-fold, respectively, across the nine prime-boost combinations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Homologous and heterologous booster vaccinations were well-tolerated and immunogenic in adults who completed a primary Covid-19 vaccine regimen at least 12 weeks earlier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Funded by National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases; &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov"&gt;ClinicalTrials.gov&lt;/ext-link&gt; number, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT04889209"&gt;NCT04889209&lt;/ext-link&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.10.21264827" rel="alternate" title="Heterologous SARS-CoV-2 Booster Vaccinations – Preliminary Report (36 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.11.463956</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 variants exhibit increased kinetic stability of open spike conformations as an evolutionary strategy (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.806630+00:00</updated><author><name>Ziwei Yang</name></author><author><name>Yang Han</name></author><author><name>Shilei Ding</name></author><author><name>Andrés Finzi</name></author><author><name>Walther Mothes</name></author><author><name>Maolin Lu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern harbor mutations in the Spike (S) glycoprotein that confer more efficient transmission and dampen the efficacy of COVID-19 vaccines and antibody therapies. S mediates virus entry and is the primary target for antibody responses. Structural studies of soluble S variants have revealed an increased propensity towards conformations accessible to receptor human Angiotensin-Converting Enzyme 2 (hACE2). However, real-time observations of conformational dynamics that govern the structural equilibriums of the S variants have been lacking. Here, we report single-molecule Förster Resonance Energy Transfer (smFRET) studies of S variants containing critical mutations, including D614G and E484K, in the context of virus particles. Investigated variants predominantly occupied more open hACE2-accessible conformations, agreeing with previous structures of soluble trimers. Additionally, these S variants exhibited decelerated transitions in hACE2-accessible/bound states. Our finding of increased S kinetic stability in the open conformation provides a new perspective on SARS-CoV-2 adaptation to the human population.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.11.463956" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 variants exhibit increased kinetic stability of open spike conformations as an evolutionary strategy (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.21264719</id><title>Trans Sodium Crocetinate (TSC) to Improve Oxygenation in COVID-19 (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.807183+00:00</updated><author><name>Anca Streinu-Cercel</name></author><author><name>Oana Săndulescu</name></author><author><name>Victor Daniel Miron</name></author><author><name>Alina-Alexandra Oană</name></author><author><name>Maria Magdalena Motoi</name></author><author><name>Christopher D. Galloway</name></author><author><name>Adrian Streinu-Cercel</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trans Sodium Crocetinate (TSC) is a bipolar synthetic carotenoid under development as a drug to enhance oxygenation to hypoxic tissue in addition to standard of care. TSC acts via a novel mechanism of action, improving the diffusivity of oxygen in blood plasma. Thus, it is based on physical-chemical principles, unlike most drugs which are based on biochemistry-based mechanisms. We explored the use of escalating doses and multiple daily dosing of TSC as a potential therapeutic for patients suffering from hypoxemia due to SARS-CoV-2 infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individuals ≥18 years who were hospitalized with confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection and hypoxemia, defined as SpO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;lt; 94% on room air or requiring supplemental oxygen, WHO ordinal scale 3 through 7 (exclusive of Extra Corporeal Membrane Oxygenation [ECMO]) were enrolled in cohorts of six subjects, each of whom received the same dose (0.25, 0.5, 1.0, or 1.5 mg/kg) of TSC via intravenous bolus every 6 hours in addition to standard of care (SOC).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This report describes the safety and efficacy results from the lead-in phase of the study and the population pharmacokinetics (PK) analyses. Safety was assessed as the number of serious adverse events and dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs) observed with each dose. Several efficacy parameters were examined in the lead-in phase and descriptive statistics of efficacy parameters are provided. No formal statistical analyses were performed. The population PK analyses were based on previous analyses and examination of the concentration profiles, and two-compartment linear pharmacokinetic models were evaluated and validated. Covariates, including body size, age, sex, organ function, and dose level, were evaluated for inclusion into the model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;TSC was well tolerated. There were no treatment emergent adverse events (TEAEs) reported. There were 2 serious adverse events (SAEs) reported during the study, neither were considered treatment-related. A total of 24 (96%) subjects survived. One subject (4.0%) died during the study as a result of an SAE (respiratory failure), and that event was determined to be due to COVID-19 complications and not related to study drug.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was an observed reduction in the time to improvement in WHO Ordinal Scale with increasing dose. The median time to 1-point reduction in subjects receiving 0.25 mg/kg was 11.5 days versus 7.5 days in the 1.5 mg/kg treatment cohort. The overall range across all doses was 1 day to 28 days. A total of 36.0% of subjects had a 1-point improvement in WHO Ordinal Scale to Day 7. The 1.5 mg/kg dose resulted in observed superior outcomes for multiple secondary clinical outcomes: time to 1-point WHO Ordinal Score improvement through Day 29/discharge, 1-point improvement by Day 7, days to return to room air, and hospital length of stay.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The PK results showed that the two-compartment model fit the data well. Clearance decreased with increasing dose level and there was no evidence that clearance was affected by covariates other than dose level.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;These findings suggest that TSC administration every 6 hours at doses up to 1.5 mg/kg for up to 15 days is safe and well tolerated with predictable pharmacokinetics and demonstrated an observed clinical benefit in the treatment of COVID-19-related hypoxemia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov"&gt;ClinicalTrials.gov&lt;/ext-link&gt; number, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT04573322"&gt;NCT04573322&lt;/ext-link&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.21264719" rel="alternate" title="Trans Sodium Crocetinate (TSC) to Improve Oxygenation in COVID-19 (6 tweets)"/><category term="Intensive Care and Critical Care Medicine"/><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.11.463689</id><title>Mutating novel interaction sites in NRP1 reduces SARS-CoV-2 spike protein internalization (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.807861+00:00</updated><author><name>Debjani Pal</name></author><author><name>Kuntal De</name></author><author><name>Timothy B. Yates</name></author><author><name>Wellington Muchero</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The global pandemic of Coronavirus disease 2019 caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 has become a severe global health problem because of its rapid spread(&lt;italic&gt;1&lt;/italic&gt;). Both angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 and neuropilin 1 provide initial viral binding sites for SARS-CoV-2 (&lt;italic&gt;2, 3&lt;/italic&gt;). Here, we show that three cysteine residues located in a1/a2 and b1 domains of neuropilin 1 are necessary for SARS-CoV-2 spike protein internalization in human cells. Mutating cysteines C82, C104 and C147 altered neuropilin 1 stability and binding ability as well as cellular internalization and lysosomal translocation of the spike protein. This resulted in up to 4 times reduction in spike protein load in cells for the original, alpha and delta SARS-CoV-2 variants even in the presence of the endogenous angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 receptor. Transcriptome analysis of cells transfected with mutated NRP1 revealed significantly reduced expression of genes involved in viral infection and replication, including eight members of the ribosomal protein L, ten members of ribosomal protein S and five members of the proteasome β subunit family proteins. We also observed higher expression of genes involved in suppression of inflammation and endoplasmic reticulum associated degradation. These observations suggest that these cysteines offer viable targets for therapies against COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.11.463689" rel="alternate" title="Mutating novel interaction sites in NRP1 reduces SARS-CoV-2 spike protein internalization (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.09.21264758</id><title>The military as a neglected pathogen transmitter and its implications for COVID-19: A systematic review (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.808158+00:00</updated><author><name>Claudia Chaufan</name></author><author><name>Ilinca A. Dutescu</name></author><author><name>Hanah Fekre</name></author><author><name>Saba Marzabadi</name></author><author><name>K.J. Noh</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The risk of outbreaks escalating into pandemics has soared with globalization. Therefore, understanding transmission mechanisms of infectious diseases has become critical to formulating global public health policy. This systematic review assessed the evidence for the military as a disease vector, an historically relevant one, yet overlooked in times of COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We searched 3 electronic databases without temporal restrictions. We identified 2010 of 6477 studies spanning over two centuries (1810 – 2020) that met our inclusion criteria and provided evidence for the military as a pathogen transmitter, within itself or between it and civilians. Two researchers independently extracted study data using a standardized form. Through team discussions, studies were grouped according to their type of transmission mechanism and direct quotes were extracted to generate themes and sub-themes. A content analysis was later performed and frequency distributions for each theme were generated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Biological mechanisms driving transmission included person-to-person transmission, contaminated food and water, vector-borne, and airborne routes. Social mechanisms facilitating transmission included crowded living spaces, unhygienic conditions, strenuous working, training conditions, absent or inadequate vaccination programs, pressure from military leadership, poor compliance with public health advice, contractor mismanagement, high-risk behaviours, and occupation-specific freedom of movement. Contaminated food and/or water was the most common biological transmission route. Living conditions were the most common social transmission mechanism, with young, low ranking military personnel repeatedly reported as the most affected group. Certain social mechanisms, such as employment-related freedom of movement, were unique to the military as a social institution. While few studies explicitly studied civilian populations, considerably more contained information that implied that civilians were likely impacted by outbreaks described in the military.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Features of the military identified in this study pose a significant public health threat, especially to countries with substantial military presence or underdeveloped health systems. Many social transmission mechanisms, unlike biological ones, were unique to the military, facilitating large-spreader events and affecting civilian health. As an increasingly interconnected world faces the challenges of COVID-19 and future infectious diseases, the identified features of the military may exacerbate current and similar challenges and impair attempts to implement successful and equitable pandemic policies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.09.21264758" rel="alternate" title="The military as a neglected pathogen transmitter and its implications for COVID-19: A systematic review (4 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.11.463917</id><title>Secondary structure of subgenomic RNA M of SARS-CoV-2 (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.808483+00:00</updated><author><name>Marta Soszynska-Jozwiak</name></author><author><name>Ryszard Kierzek</name></author><author><name>Elzbieta Kierzek</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 belongs the &lt;italic&gt;Coronavirinae&lt;/italic&gt; family. As other coronaviruses, SARS-CoV-2 is enveloped and possesses positive-sense, single-stranded RNA genome of ∼ 30 kb. Genome RNA is used as the template for replication and transcription. During these processes, positive-sense genomic RNA (gRNA) and subgenomic RNAs (sgRNAs) are created. Several studies showed importance of genomic RNA secondary structure in SARS-CoV-2 replication. However, the structure of sgRNAs have remained largely unsolved so far. In this study, we performed probing of sgRNA M of SARS-CoV-2 &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. This is the first experimentally informed secondary structure model of sgRNA M, which presents features likely to be important in sgRNA M function. The knowledge about sgRNA M provides insights to better understand virus biology and could be used for designing new therapeutics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.11.463917" rel="alternate" title="Secondary structure of subgenomic RNA M of SARS-CoV-2 (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>