<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.587507+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.07.447437</id><title>FXa cleaves the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein and blocks cell entry to protect against infection with inferior effects in B.1.1.7 variant (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.588269+00:00</updated><author><name>Wenjuan Dong</name></author><author><name>Jing Wang</name></author><author><name>Lei Tian</name></author><author><name>Jianying Zhang</name></author><author><name>Heather Mead</name></author><author><name>Sierra A. Jaramillo</name></author><author><name>Aimin Li</name></author><author><name>Ross E. Zumwalt</name></author><author><name>Sean P.J. Whelan</name></author><author><name>Erik W. Settles</name></author><author><name>Paul S. Keim</name></author><author><name>Bridget Marie Barker</name></author><author><name>Michael A. Caligiuri</name></author><author><name>Jianhua Yu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ongoing coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic is caused by infection with severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). Human natural defense mechanisms against SARS-CoV-2 are largely unknown. Serine proteases (SPs) including furin and TMPRSS2 cleave SARS-CoV-2 spike protein, facilitating viral entry. Here, we show that FXa, a SP for blood coagulation, is upregulated in COVID-19 patients compared to non-COVID-19 donors and exerts anti-viral activity. Mechanistically, FXa cleaves the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein, which prevents its binding to ACE2, and thus blocks viral entry. Furthermore, the variant B.1.1.7 with several mutations is dramatically resistant to the anti-viral effect of FXa compared to wild-type SARA-CoV-2 &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. The anti-coagulant rivaroxaban directly inhibits FXa and facilitates viral entry, whereas the indirect inhibitor fondaparinux does not. In a lethal humanized hACE2 mouse model of SARS-CoV-2, FXa prolonged survival while combination with rivaroxaban but not fondaparinux abrogated this protection. These preclinical results identify a previously unknown SP function and associated anti-viral host defense mechanism and suggest caution in considering direct inhibitors for prevention or treatment of thrombotic complications in COVID-19 patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.07.447437" rel="alternate" title="FXa cleaves the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein and blocks cell entry to protect against infection with inferior effects in B.1.1.7 variant (26 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.07.447334</id><title>Dynamics and self-assembly of the SARS-CoV-2 spike transmembrane domain (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.588940+00:00</updated><author><name>Sahil Lall</name></author><author><name>Padmanabhan Balaram</name></author><author><name>Shachi Gosavi</name></author><author><name>M.K. Mathew</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The spike (S) protein is a trimeric, membrane-anchored fusion protein that enables coronaviruses, such as the SARS-CoV-2, to recognize and fuse with their hosts’ cells. While the prefusion and postfusion structures of the ectomembrane domain of the spike protein are available, the corresponding organization of its transmembrane domain is obscure. Since the transmembrane and ectomembrane domains of fusion proteins are conformationally linked, an understanding of trimerization and transmembrane conformations in the viral envelope is a prerequisite to completely understand viral fusion by the spike protein. To address this, we computationally explored the self-assembly of the SARS-CoV-2 spike transmembrane domain, starting first by determining the membrane boundaries of the spike transmembrane helix. Using atomistic molecular dynamics simulations, we found the spike protein transmembrane domain to be plastic, and the transmembrane helix to be very dynamic. The observed movements of the helix changed the membrane embedded sequence, and thereby affected the conformational ensemble of the transmembrane assembly in Martini coarse grained simulations, even flipping the super-helical handedness. Analysis of the transmembrane organization of the spike transmembrane helix provided rich insights into the interfaces utilized to self-associate. Moreover, we identified two distinct cholesterol binding regions on the transmembrane helix with different affinities for the sterol. The cholesterol binding pockets overlapped with regions involved in the initiation of transmembrane protein-protein interaction. Together, the results from our multiscale simulations not only provide insight into understudied trimeric helical interfaces in biomembranes, but also enhance our understanding of the elusive transmembrane conformational dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 spike and more generally of viral fusion proteins. These insights should enable the inclusion of the conformations of the spike protein transmembrane domain into the prevalent models of virus fusion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Enveloped viruses rely on fusion proteins, called spike proteins in coronaviruses, to infect cells by fusing the virus envelope with the host cell membrane. The transmembrane domain (TMD) of the coronavirus spike protein is critically involved in successful viral fusion and other aspects of the virus lifecycle, but is poorly studied. Using multiscale molecular dynamics simulations of the SARS-CoV-2 spike TMD, we explore its conformational dynamics and self-assembly in different lipid environments. The results provided here improve our understanding of transmembrane stabilization of spike trimers, which are indispensable for viral infection. Exploiting this knowledge to destabilize spike trimers should facilitate design of transmembrane domain targeted viral fusion inhibitors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.07.447334" rel="alternate" title="Dynamics and self-assembly of the SARS-CoV-2 spike transmembrane domain (17 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.05.21258394</id><title>The Effect of Pandemic Prevalence on the Reported Efficacy of SARS-CoV-2 Vaccine Candidates: A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.589380+00:00</updated><author><name>Rajeev Sharma</name></author><author><name>Abhijith Anand</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The efficacy of SARS-CoV-2 vaccine candidates reported in Phase 3 trials varies from ∼45% to ∼95%. It is important to explain the reasons for this heterogeneity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To test the hypothesis that the efficacy of SARS-CoV-2 vaccine candidates falls with increasing prevalence of the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data Sources&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;ClinicalTrials.gov&lt;/italic&gt;, WHO, McGill and LSHTM trackers of COVID-19 candidate vaccines, peer reviewed publications, and press releases were searched until March 31&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt;, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Study Selection&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;All RCTs reporting efficacy outcomes from Phase 3 trials till March 31&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt;, 2021 were included. Of the 11 vaccine candidates that had started their Phase 3 trials by November 1, 2020. Phase 3 efficacy outcomes were available for 8 vaccine candidates. (PROSPERO CRD42021243121).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data Extraction and Synthesis&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both authors independently extracted the data required from identified sources, using PRISMA guidelines. The analysis included all RCTs reported in peer reviewed publications and publicly available sources. A random effects model with restricted maximum likelihood estimator was used to summarize the treatment effects. Cochrane Risk of Bias Assessment Tool was used to assess risk of bias. Certainty of evidence was assessed using the GRADE tool.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Outcomes and Measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 infections per protocol in vaccine and placebo groups, risk ratio, prevalence of the COVID-19 infection rate in the populations where the Phase 3 trials were conducted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;8 vaccine candidates had reported efficacy data from a total of 20 independent Phase 3 trials, representing a total of 221,968 subjects, 453 infections across the vaccinated groups and 1,554 infections across the placebo groups. The overall estimate of the risk-ratio is 0.24 (95% CI, 0.17-0.34, p &amp;lt; 0.01), with an I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; statistic of 88.73%. The meta-regression analysis with pandemic prevalence as the moderator explains almost half the variance in risk ratios across trials (R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;=49.06%, p&amp;lt;0.01).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion and Relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pandemic prevalence explains almost half of the between-trial variance in reported efficacies. Efficacy of SARS-CoV-2 vaccine candidates declines as the pandemic prevalence increases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key Points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Question&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Does the prevalence of the COVID-19 pandemic explain the heterogeneity in efficacies reported across Phase 3 trials of SARS-CoV-2 vaccine candidates?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Almost 50% of the variance in efficacies reported across Phase 3 trials can be explained by differences in COVID-19 infection rate prevailing across trials. Efficacy of evaluated SARS-CoV-2 vaccine candidates falls significantly with increasing prevalence of the COVID-19 pandemic across trial sites.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Meaning&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Efficacy of SARS-CoV-2 vaccine candidates needs to be interpreted in conjunction with the prevalence of the COVID-19 pandemic. Adjustment for location-level prevalence analysis would provide better insights into the efficacy results of Phase 3 trials.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.05.21258394" rel="alternate" title="The Effect of Pandemic Prevalence on the Reported Efficacy of SARS-CoV-2 Vaccine Candidates: A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis (15 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.447999</id><title>A combination of RBD and NTD neutralizing antibodies limits the generation of SARS-CoV-2 spike neutralization-escape mutants (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.589752+00:00</updated><author><name>Denise Haslwanter</name></author><author><name>M. Eugenia Dieterle</name></author><author><name>Anna Z. Wec</name></author><author><name>Cecilia M. O'Brien</name></author><author><name>Mrunal Sakharkar</name></author><author><name>Catalina Florez</name></author><author><name>Karen Tong</name></author><author><name>C. Garrett Rappazzo</name></author><author><name>Gorka Lasso</name></author><author><name>Olivia Vergnolle</name></author><author><name>Ariel S. Wirchnianski</name></author><author><name>Robert H. Bortz</name></author><author><name>Ethan Laudermilch</name></author><author><name>J. Maximilian Fels</name></author><author><name>Amanda Mengotto</name></author><author><name>Ryan J Malonis</name></author><author><name>George I Georgiev</name></author><author><name>Jose Quiroz</name></author><author><name>Daniel Wrapp</name></author><author><name>Nianshuang Wang</name></author><author><name>Kathryn E Dye</name></author><author><name>Jason Barnhill</name></author><author><name>John M Dye</name></author><author><name>Jason S. McLellan</name></author><author><name>Johanna P. Daily</name></author><author><name>Jonathan R. Lai</name></author><author><name>Andrew S Herbert</name></author><author><name>Laura Walker</name></author><author><name>Kartik Chandran</name></author><author><name>Rohit K. Jangra</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Most known SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibodies (nAbs), including those approved by the FDA for emergency use, inhibit viral infection by targeting the receptor-binding domain (RBD) of the spike (S) protein. Variants of concern (VOC) carrying mutations in the RBD or other regions of S reduce the effectiveness of many nAbs and vaccines by evading neutralization. Therefore, therapies that are less susceptible to resistance are urgently needed. Here, we characterized the memory B-cell repertoire of COVID-19 convalescent donors and analyzed their RBD and non-RBD nAbs. We found that many of the non-RBD-targeting nAbs were specific to the N-terminal domain (NTD). Using neutralization assays with authentic SARS-CoV-2 and a recombinant vesicular stomatitis virus carrying SARS-CoV-2 S protein (rVSV-SARS2), we defined a panel of potent RBD and NTD nAbs. Next, we used a combination of neutralization-escape rVSV-SARS2 mutants and a yeast display library of RBD mutants to map their epitopes. The most potent RBD nAb competed with hACE2 binding and targeted an epitope that includes residue F490. The most potent NTD nAb epitope included Y145, K150 and W152. As seen with some of the natural VOC, the neutralization potencies of COVID-19 convalescent sera were reduced by 4-16-fold against rVSV-SARS2 bearing Y145D, K150E or W152R spike mutations. Moreover, we found that combining RBD and NTD nAbs modestly enhanced their neutralization potential. Notably, the same combination of RBD and NTD nAbs limited the development of neutralization-escape mutants &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, suggesting such a strategy may have higher efficacy and utility for mitigating the emergence of VOC.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.447999" rel="alternate" title="A combination of RBD and NTD neutralizing antibodies limits the generation of SARS-CoV-2 spike neutralization-escape mutants (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.11.448134</id><title>UK B.1.1.7 variant exhibits increased respiratory replication and shedding in nonhuman primates (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.590705+00:00</updated><author><name>Kyle Rosenke</name></author><author><name>Friederike Feldmann</name></author><author><name>Atsushi Okumura</name></author><author><name>Frederick Hansen</name></author><author><name>Tsing-Lee Tang-Huau</name></author><author><name>Kimberly Meade-White</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Kaza</name></author><author><name>Brian J Smith</name></author><author><name>Patrick W Hanley</name></author><author><name>Jamie Lovaglio</name></author><author><name>Michael Jarvis</name></author><author><name>Carl Shaia</name></author><author><name>Heinz Feldmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The continuing emergence of SARS-CoV-2 variants calls for regular assessment to identify differences in viral replication, shedding and associated disease. In this study, African green monkeys were infected intranasally with either a contemporary D614G or the UK B.1.1.7 variant. Both variants caused mild respiratory disease with no significant differences in clinical presentation. Significantly higher levels of viral RNA and infectious virus were found in upper and lower respiratory tract samples and tissues from B.1.1.7 infected animals. Interestingly, D614G infected animals showed significantly higher levels of viral RNA and infectious virus in rectal swabs and gastrointestinal tract tissues. Our results indicate that B.1.1.7 infection in African green monkeys is associated with increased respiratory replication and shedding but no disease enhancement similar to human B.1.1.7 cases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.11.448134" rel="alternate" title="UK B.1.1.7 variant exhibits increased respiratory replication and shedding in nonhuman primates (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.09.21258612</id><title>Second wave of COVID-19 in India could be predicted with genomic surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 variants coupled with epidemiological data: A tool for future (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.591289+00:00</updated><author><name>Ashutosh Kumar</name></author><author><name>Prakhar Dwivedi</name></author><author><name>Gopichand Kumar</name></author><author><name>Ravi K. Narayan</name></author><author><name>Rakesh K. Jha</name></author><author><name>Rakesh Parashar</name></author><author><name>Chetan Sahni</name></author><author><name>Sada N. Pandey</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;India has witnessed a devastating second wave of COVID-19, which peaked during the last week of April and the second week of May, 2021. We aimed to understand whether the arrival of second wave was predictable and whether it was driven by the existing SARS-CoV-2 strains or any of the emerging variants. We analyzed the monthly distribution of the genomic sequence data for SARS-CoV-2 from India and correlated that with the epidemiological data for new cases and deaths, for the corresponding period of the second wave. Our analysis shows that the first indications of arrival of the second wave were observable by January, 2021, and by March, 2021 it was clearly predictable. B.1.617 lineage variants drove the wave, particularly B.1.617.2 (a.k.a. delta variant). We propose that genomic surveillance of the SARS-CoV-2 variants augmented with epidemiological data can be a promising tool for predicting future COVID-19 waves.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.09.21258612" rel="alternate" title="Second wave of COVID-19 in India could be predicted with genomic surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 variants coupled with epidemiological data: A tool for future (6 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.09.447722</id><title>Neutralizing antibodies elicited by the Ad26.COV2.S COVID-19 vaccine show reduced activity against 501Y.V2 (B.1.351), despite protection against severe disease by this variant. (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.591894+00:00</updated><author><name>Penny Moore</name></author><author><name>Thandeka Moyo</name></author><author><name>Tandile Hermanus</name></author><author><name>Prudence Kgagudi</name></author><author><name>Frances Ayres</name></author><author><name>Zanele Makhado</name></author><author><name>Jerald Sadoff</name></author><author><name>Mathieu Le Gars</name></author><author><name>Griet van Roey</name></author><author><name>Carol Crowther</name></author><author><name>Nigel Garrett</name></author><author><name>Linda-Gail Bekker</name></author><author><name>Lynn Morris</name></author><author><name>Hanneke Schuitemaker</name></author><author><name>Glenda Gray</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The emergence of SARS-CoV-2 variants, such as 501Y.V2, with immune evasion mutations in the spike has resulted in reduced efficacy of several COVID-19 vaccines. However, the efficacy of the Ad26.COV2.S vaccine, when tested in South Africa after the emergence of  501Y.V2, was not adversely impacted. We therefore assessed the binding and neutralization capacity of n=120 South African sera (from Day 29, post-vaccination) from the Janssen phase 3 study, Ensemble. Spike binding assays using both the Wuhan-1 D614G and 501Y.V2 Spikes showed high levels of cross-reactivity. In contrast, in a subset of 27 sera, we observed significantly reduced neutralization of 501Y.V2 compared to Wuhan-1 D614G, with 22/27 (82%) of sera showing no detectable neutralization of 501Y.V2 at Day 29. These data suggest that even low levels of neutralizing antibodies may contribute to protection from moderate/severe disease. In addition, Fc effector function and T cells may play an important role in protection by this vaccine against 501Y.V2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.09.447722" rel="alternate" title="Neutralizing antibodies elicited by the Ad26.COV2.S COVID-19 vaccine show reduced activity against 501Y.V2 (B.1.351), despite protection against severe disease by this variant. (6 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.08.21258545</id><title>The Impact of Face-Masks on Total Mortality Heterogenous Effects by Gender and Age (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.592823+00:00</updated><author><name>giacomo de giorgi</name></author><author><name>maria maddalena speziali</name></author><author><name>Felix Michalik</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Governments around the world have been implementing several non-pharmaceutical interventions (NPIs) to fight Covid-19 spread and its associated mortality. We estimate the causal impact of mandatory face-mask wearing policy in public places on (total) mortality in Switzerland. We exploit the staggered introduction of the policy across Swiss cantons using a Difference-in-Difference and an event study approach. We find that the extension of compulsory mask wearing to public places has an heterogeneous impact on mortality, with small positive effects on male mortality entirely driven by older age-cohorts (90+). Finally, we show that adding contact tracing and stricter distancing to compulsory face-mask policy does not lead to better results in terms of mortality.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.08.21258545" rel="alternate" title="The Impact of Face-Masks on Total Mortality Heterogenous Effects by Gender and Age (5 tweets)"/><category term="Health Policy"/><published>2021-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.21254528</id><title>NEWS-2 score assessment of inpatient referral during the COVID 19 epidemic (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.594027+00:00</updated><author><name>Valerie FAURE</name></author><author><name>Marc SOURIS</name></author><author><name>Arnaud WILMET</name></author><author><name>Franck BAUDINO</name></author><author><name>Albert BRIZIO</name></author><author><name>Christopher MALHAIRE</name></author><author><name>Francois-Xavier PECCAUD</name></author><author><name>Jean-Paul GONZALEZ</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aim. To manage patients with suspected coronavirus disease (COVID-19) when they arrive at the hospital emergency department (ED), a clinical severity score is required to quickly identify patients requiring immediate hospital admission and close monitoring. The aim of this study was to evaluate, within the context of the pandemic, the performance of National Early Warning Score 2 (NEWS-2) to anticipate the admission of patients with suspected COVID-19 to a specialised emergency care unit.
Methods. This retrospective study was conducted on patients presenting at the COVID-19 entrance of the ED of the Vert-Galant private hospital (Paris, France) during the first national pandemic peak from March 20 to April 20, 2020. All patients completed a questionnaire and clinical data and vital signs were recorded. Statistical analysis and modelling were used to estimate the ability of different scores (NEWS-2, qSOFA, CRB-65) to predict hospital emergency admission and/or early COVID-19 diagnosis. 
Results. NEWS-2, with a cut off value of 5, predicted hospital admission with 82% sensitivity, 98% specificity and an area under the curve (AUC) of 96%. NEWS-2 was superior to qSOFA and CRB-65 scores for predicting hospital admission of COVID-19 patients. Multilinear or logistic regression analysis of clinical data did not improve this result. 
Conclusion. NEWS-2 is an excellent score to predict hospital admission of COVID-19 patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.21254528" rel="alternate" title="NEWS-2 score assessment of inpatient referral during the COVID 19 epidemic (5 tweets)"/><category term="Emergency Medicine"/><published>2021-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>