<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.625052+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.19.21260767</id><title>Children with SARS-CoV-2 in the National COVID Cohort Collaborative (N3C) (542 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.625577+00:00</updated><author><name>Blake Martin</name></author><author><name>Peter E. DeWitt</name></author><author><name>Seth Russell</name></author><author><name>Adit Anand</name></author><author><name>Katie R. Bradwell</name></author><author><name>Carolyn Bremer</name></author><author><name>Davera Gabriel</name></author><author><name>Andrew T. Girvin</name></author><author><name>Janos G. Hajagos</name></author><author><name>Julie A. McMurry</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Neumann</name></author><author><name>Emily R. Pfaff</name></author><author><name>Anita Walden</name></author><author><name>Jacob T. Wooldridge</name></author><author><name>Yun Jae Yoo</name></author><author><name>Joel Saltz</name></author><author><name>Ken R. Gersing</name></author><author><name>Christopher G. Chute</name></author><author><name>Melissa A. Haendel</name></author><author><name>Richard Moffitt</name></author><author><name>Tellen D. Bennett</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To determine the characteristics, changes over time, outcomes, and severity risk factors of SARS-CoV-2 affected children within the National COVID Cohort Collaborative (N3C)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prospective cohort study of patient encounters with end dates before May 27th, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;45 N3C institutions&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Children &amp;lt;19-years-old at initial SARS-CoV-2 testing&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Outcomes and Measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Case incidence and severity over time, demographic and comorbidity severity risk factors, vital sign and laboratory trajectories, clinical outcomes, and acute COVID-19 vs MIS-C contrasts for children infected with SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;728,047 children in the N3C were tested for SARS-CoV-2; of these, 91,865 (12.6%) were positive. Among the 5,213 (6%) hospitalized children, 685 (13%) met criteria for severe disease: mechanical ventilation (7%), vasopressor/inotropic support (7%), ECMO (0.6%), or death/discharge to hospice (1.1%). Male gender, African American race, older age, and several pediatric complex chronic condition (PCCC) subcategories were associated with higher clinical severity (p&lt;italic&gt;≤&lt;/italic&gt;0.05). Vital signs (all p≤0.002) and many laboratory tests from the first day of hospitalization were predictive of peak disease severity. Children with severe (vs moderate) disease were more likely to receive antimicrobials (71% vs 32%, p&amp;lt;0.001) and immunomodulatory medications (53% vs 16%, p&amp;lt;0.001).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compared to those with acute COVID-19, children with MIS-C were more likely to be male, Black/African American, 1-to-12-years-old, and less likely to have asthma, diabetes, or a PCCC (p&lt;italic&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/italic&gt;0.04). MIS-C cases demonstrated a more inflammatory laboratory profile and more severe clinical phenotype with higher rates of invasive ventilation (12% vs 6%) and need for vasoactive-inotropic support (31% vs 6%) compared to acute COVID-19 cases, respectively (p&amp;lt;0.03).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the largest U.S. SARS-CoV-2-positive pediatric cohort to date, we observed differences in demographics, pre-existing comorbidities, and initial vital sign and laboratory test values between severity subgroups. Taken together, these results suggest that early identification of children likely to progress to severe disease could be achieved using readily available data elements from the day of admission. Further work is needed to translate this knowledge into improved outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.19.21260767" rel="alternate" title="Children with SARS-CoV-2 in the National COVID Cohort Collaborative (N3C) (542 tweets)"/><category term="Pediatrics"/><published>2021-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.15.21260561</id><title>Viral Load of SARS-CoV-2 in Respiratory Aerosols Emitted by COVID-19 Patients while Breathing, Talking, and Singing (405 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.626043+00:00</updated><author><name>Kristen K. Coleman</name></author><author><name>Douglas Jie Wen Tay</name></author><author><name>Kai Sen Tan</name></author><author><name>Sean Wei Xiang Ong</name></author><author><name>Than The Son</name></author><author><name>Ming Hui Koh</name></author><author><name>Yi Qing Chin</name></author><author><name>Haziq Nasir</name></author><author><name>Tze Minn Mak</name></author><author><name>Justin Jang Hann Chu</name></author><author><name>Donald K. Milton</name></author><author><name>Vincent T. K. Chow</name></author><author><name>Paul Anantharajah Tambyah</name></author><author><name>Mark Chen</name></author><author><name>Tham Kwok Wai</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Multiple SARS-CoV-2 superspreading events suggest that aerosols play an important role in driving the COVID-19 pandemic. However, the detailed roles of coarse (&amp;gt;5μm) and fine (≤5μm) respiratory aerosols produced when breathing, talking, and singing are not well-understood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using a G-II exhaled breath collector, we measured viral RNA in coarse and fine respiratory aerosols emitted by COVID-19 patients during 30 minutes of breathing, 15 minutes of talking, and 15 minutes of singing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among the 22 study participants, 13 (59%) emitted detectable levels of SARS-CoV-2 RNA in respiratory aerosols, including 3 asymptomatic patients and 1 presymptomatic patient. Viral loads ranged from 63–5,821 N gene copies per expiratory activity per patient. Patients earlier in illness were more likely to emit detectable RNA, and loads differed significantly between breathing, talking, and singing. The largest proportion of SARS-CoV-2 RNA copies was emitted by singing (53%), followed by talking (41%) and breathing (6%). Overall, fine aerosols constituted 85% of the viral load detected in our study. Virus cultures were negative.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fine aerosols produced by talking and singing contain more SARS-CoV-2 copies than coarse aerosols and may play a significant role in the transmission of SARS-CoV-2. Exposure to fine aerosols should be mitigated, especially in indoor environments where airborne transmission of SARS-CoV-2 is likely to occur. Isolating viable SARS-CoV-2 from respiratory aerosol samples remains challenging, and whether this can be more easily accomplished for emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants is an important enquiry for future studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key Points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We sampled respiratory aerosols emitted by COVID-19 patients and discovered that fine aerosols (≤5μm) generated during talking and singing contain more SARS-CoV-2 copies than coarse aerosols (&amp;gt;5μm) and may play a significant role in the transmission of SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.15.21260561" rel="alternate" title="Viral Load of SARS-CoV-2 in Respiratory Aerosols Emitted by COVID-19 Patients while Breathing, Talking, and Singing (405 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.21.451321</id><title>Unlike Chloroquine, mefloquine inhibits SARS-CoV-2 infection in physiologically relevant cells and does not induce viral variants (219 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.626346+00:00</updated><author><name>Carolina Q. Sacramento</name></author><author><name>Natalia Fintelman-Rodrigues</name></author><author><name>Suelen S. G. Dias</name></author><author><name>Jairo R. Temerozo</name></author><author><name>Aline de Paula D. Da Silva</name></author><author><name>Carine S. da Silva</name></author><author><name>André C. Ferreira</name></author><author><name>Mayara Mattos</name></author><author><name>Vinicius C. Soares</name></author><author><name>Filipe Pereira-Dutra</name></author><author><name>Milene D. Miranda</name></author><author><name>Debora F. Barreto-Vieira</name></author><author><name>Marcos Alexandre N. da Silva</name></author><author><name>Suzana S. Santos</name></author><author><name>Mateo Torres</name></author><author><name>Rajith K R Rajoli</name></author><author><name>Alberto Paccanaro</name></author><author><name>Andrew Owen</name></author><author><name>Dumith Chequer Bou-Habib</name></author><author><name>Patrícia T. Bozza</name></author><author><name>Thiago Moreno L. Souza</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Repositioning of clinical approved drugs could represent the fastest way to identify therapeutic options during public health emergencies, the majority of drugs explored for repurposing as antivirals for 2019 coronavirus disease (COVID-19) have failed to demonstrate clinical benefit. Without specific antivirals, the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) pandemic continues to cause major global mortality. Antimalarial drugs, such as chloroquine (CQ)/hydroxychloroquine (HCQ) and mefloquine have emerged as potential anti-SARS-CoV-2 antivirals. CQ/HCQ entered the Solidarity and RECOVERY clinical trials against COVID-19 and showed lack of efficacy. Importantly, mefloquine is not a 4-aminoquinoline like CQ and HCQ and has been previously repurposed for other respiratory diseases. Unlike the 4-aminoquinolines that accumulate in the high pH of intracellular lysosomes of the lung, the high respiratory tract penetration of mefloquine is driven by its high lipophilicity. While CQ and HCQ exhibit activity in Vero E6 cells, their activity is obviated in TMPRSS2-expressing cells, such as Calu-3 cells, which more accurately recapitulate in vivo entry mechanisms for SARS-CoV-2. Accordingly, here we report the anti-SARS-CoV-2 activity of mefloquine in Calu-3 type II pneumocytes and primary human monocytes. Mefloquine inhibited SARS-CoV-2 replication in Calu-3 cells with low cytotoxicity and EC&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; and EC&lt;sub&gt;90&lt;/sub&gt; values of 1.2 and 5.3 µM, respectively. In addition, mefloquine reduced up to 68% the SARS-CoV-2 RNA levels in infected monocytes, reducing viral-induced inflammation. Mefloquine blocked early steps of the SARS-CoV-2 replicative cycle and was less prone than CQ to induce drug-associated viral mutations and synergized with RNA polymerase inhibitor. The pharmacological parameters of mefloquine are consistent with its plasma exposure in humans and its tissue-to-plasma predicted coefficient points that this drug may accumulate in the lungs. These data indicate that mefloquine could represent an orally available clinically approved drug option against COVID-19 and should not be neglected on the basis of the failure of CQ and HCQ.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.21.451321" rel="alternate" title="Unlike Chloroquine, mefloquine inhibits SARS-CoV-2 infection in physiologically relevant cells and does not induce viral variants (219 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.19.452771</id><title>Comparison of Neutralizing Antibody Titers Elicited by mRNA and Adenoviral Vector Vaccine against SARS-CoV-2 Variants (50 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.627015+00:00</updated><author><name>Takuya Tada</name></author><author><name>Hao Zhou</name></author><author><name>Marie I. Samanovic</name></author><author><name>Belinda M. Dcosta</name></author><author><name>Amber Cornelius</name></author><author><name>Mark J. Mulligan</name></author><author><name>Nathaniel R. Landau</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The increasing prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 variants has raised concerns regarding possible decreases in vaccine efficacy. Here, neutralizing antibody titers elicited by mRNA-based and an adenoviral vector-based vaccine against variant pseudotyped viruses were compared. BNT162b2 and mRNA-1273-elicited antibodies showed modest neutralization resistance against Beta, Delta, Delta plus and Lambda variants whereas Ad26.COV2.S-elicited antibodies from a significant fraction of vaccinated individuals were of low neutralizing titer (IC&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;lt;50). The data underscore the importance of surveillance for breakthrough infections that result in severe COVID-19 and suggest the benefit of a second immunization following Ad26.COV2.S to increase protection against the variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.19.452771" rel="alternate" title="Comparison of Neutralizing Antibody Titers Elicited by mRNA and Adenoviral Vector Vaccine against SARS-CoV-2 Variants (50 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453521</id><title>Probiotic consortia improve anti-viral immunity to SARS-CoV-2 in Ferrets (35 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.627261+00:00</updated><author><name>J Lehtinen Markus</name></author><author><name>Kumar Ritesh</name></author><author><name>Zabel Bryan</name></author><author><name>M Mäkelä Sanna</name></author><author><name>Nedveck Derek</name></author><author><name>Tang Peipei</name></author><author><name>Latvala Sinikka</name></author><author><name>Guery Sebastien</name></author><author><name>R Budinoff Charles</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Probiotics have been suggested as one solution to counter detrimental health effects by SARS-CoV-2, however, data so far is scarce. We tested the effect of two probiotic consortia, OL-1 and OL-2, against SARS-CoV-2 in ferrets and assessed their effect on cytokine production and transcriptome in a human monocyte-derived macrophage (Mf) and dendritic cell (DC) model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The results showed that the consortia significantly reduced the viral load, modulated immune response, and regulated viral receptor expression in ferrets compared to placebo. In human Mf and DC model, OL-1 and OL-2 induced cytokine production and genes related to SARS-CoV-2 anti-viral immunity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study results indicate that probiotic stimulation of the ferret immune system leads to improved anti-viral immunity against SARS-COV-2 and that critical genes and cytokines for anti-SARS-CoV-2 immunity are stimulated in human immune cells &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. The effect of the consortia against SARS-CoV-2 warrants further investigations in human clinical trials.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453521" rel="alternate" title="Probiotic consortia improve anti-viral immunity to SARS-CoV-2 in Ferrets (35 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.21260852</id><title>Comparison of infected and vaccinated transplant recipients highlights the role of Tfh and neutralizing IgG in COVID-19 protection (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.627503+00:00</updated><author><name>Xavier Charmetant</name></author><author><name>Maxime ESPI</name></author><author><name>Ilies Benotmane</name></author><author><name>Francoise Heibel</name></author><author><name>Fanny Buron</name></author><author><name>Gabriela Gautier-Vargas</name></author><author><name>Marion Delafosse</name></author><author><name>Peggy Perrin</name></author><author><name>Alice Koenig</name></author><author><name>Noelle Cognard</name></author><author><name>Charlene Levi</name></author><author><name>Floriane Gallais</name></author><author><name>Louis Maniere</name></author><author><name>Paola Rossolillo</name></author><author><name>Eric Soulier</name></author><author><name>Florian Pierre</name></author><author><name>Anne Ovize</name></author><author><name>Emmanuel Morelon</name></author><author><name>Thierry Defrance</name></author><author><name>Samira Fafi-Kremer</name></author><author><name>Sophie Caillard</name></author><author><name>Olivier Thaunat</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Transplant recipients, which receive therapeutic immunosuppression to prevent graft rejection, are characterized by high COVID-19-related mortality and defective response to vaccines. Having observed that previous infection by SARS-CoV-2 but not the standard 2 doses scheme of vaccination, provided complete protection against COVID-19 to transplant recipients, we undertook this translational study to compare the cellular and humoral immune responses of these 2 groups of patients. Neutralizing anti-Receptor Binding Domain (RBD) IgG were identified as the critical immune effectors associated with protection. Generation of anti-RBD IgG was dependent upon spike-specific T follicular helper (Tfh) CD4+ T cells, which acted as limiting checkpoint. Tfh generation was impeded by high dose mycophenolate mofetil in non-responders to vaccine but not in infected patients, suggesting that increasing immunogenicity of vaccine could improve response rate to mRNA vaccine. This theory was validated in two independent prospective cohorts, in which administration of a 3rd dose of vaccine resulted in the generation of anti-RBD IgG in half of non-responders to 2 doses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.21260852" rel="alternate" title="Comparison of infected and vaccinated transplant recipients highlights the role of Tfh and neutralizing IgG in COVID-19 protection (19 tweets)"/><category term="Transplantation"/><published>2021-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.21260551</id><title>Willingness to receive vaccination against COVID-19: results from a large nationally representative Australian population survey (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.627859+00:00</updated><author><name>Sharon R Davis</name></author><author><name>Rosario D Ampon</name></author><author><name>Leanne D Poulos</name></author><author><name>Guy B Marks</name></author><author><name>Brett Gregory Toelle</name></author><author><name>Helen K Reddel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We surveyed 10,024 Australians regarding COVID-19 vaccine willingness. Overall, 59.9% indicated yes, 13.9% no and 26.3% unsure/dont know. Vaccine willingness was higher in males, and increased with increasing education and socioeconomic advantage. Results contrast with earlier, smaller Australian surveys regarding vaccination willingness and confirm the need for targeted vaccination information.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.21260551" rel="alternate" title="Willingness to receive vaccination against COVID-19: results from a large nationally representative Australian population survey (12 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.21258785</id><title>Proton pump inhibitor use is not associated with severe COVID-19 related outcomes: A propensity score weighted analysis of a national veteran cohort (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.628068+00:00</updated><author><name>Shailja C. Shah</name></author><author><name>Alese Halvorson</name></author><author><name>Brandon McBay</name></author><author><name>Chad Dorn</name></author><author><name>Otis Wilson</name></author><author><name>Sony Tuteja</name></author><author><name>Kyong-Mi Chang</name></author><author><name>Ayako Suzuki</name></author><author><name>Christine Hunt</name></author><author><name>Richard Hauger</name></author><author><name>Kelly Cho</name></author><author><name>Edward Siew</name></author><author><name>Michael Matheny</name></author><author><name>Adriana Hung</name></author><author><name>Robert Greevy</name></author><author><name>Christianne Roumie</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background and Aims: Low pH deactivates most pathogens, including coronaviruses. Proton pump inhibitors (PPIs) are potent gastric acid suppressing medications. Whether PPI use vs non-use is associated with severe Coronavirus disease-2019 (COVID-19) outcomes remains uncertain. We aimed to compare severe COVID-19 outcomes between current outpatient PPI users and non-users.

Methods: We conducted a retrospective propensity score-weighted analysis of a national cohort of US veterans with established care who tested positive for severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) through January 9, 2021, and who had 60 days of follow-up. The positive test date was the index date. Current outpatient PPI use up to and including the index date (primary exposure) was compared to non-use, defined as no PPI prescription fill in the 365 days prior to the index date. The primary outcome was a composite of use of mechanical ventilation or death within 60 days. Weighted logistic regression models evaluated severe COVID-19 outcomes between current PPI users vs non-users.

Results: Of 97,674 Veterans with SARS-CoV-2 testing, 14,958 tested positive (6262 [41.9%] current PPI users, 8696 [58.1%] non-users) and comprised the analytic cohort. After weighting, all covariates were well-balanced. In the weighted cohort, there was no difference in the primary composite outcome (8.2% vs 8.0%; OR 1.03, 95% CI 0.91-1.16), secondary composite outcome, nor individual component outcomes between current PPI users and non-users. There was no significant interaction between age and PPI use on outcomes.

Conclusion: Among patients with SARS-CoV-2 infection, current PPI use vs non-use is not associated with severe COVID-19 outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.21258785" rel="alternate" title="Proton pump inhibitor use is not associated with severe COVID-19 related outcomes: A propensity score weighted analysis of a national veteran cohort (9 tweets)"/><category term="Gastroenterology"/><published>2021-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261042</id><title>Robust antibody levels in both diabetic and non-diabetic individuals after BNT162b2 mRNA COVID-19 vaccination (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.628374+00:00</updated><author><name>Hamad Ali</name></author><author><name>Abdulmohsen Al-Terki</name></author><author><name>Sardar Sindhu</name></author><author><name>Barrak Alahmad</name></author><author><name>Maha Hammad</name></author><author><name>Salman Al-Sabah</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Alghounaim</name></author><author><name>Mohammad H. Jamal</name></author><author><name>Ali Aldei</name></author><author><name>Mohammad J. Mairza</name></author><author><name>Maitham Husain</name></author><author><name>Sriraman Devarajan</name></author><author><name>Rasheed Ahmad</name></author><author><name>Preethi Cherian</name></author><author><name>Irina Alkhairi</name></author><author><name>Abdullah Alkandari</name></author><author><name>Jehad Abubaker</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Abu-farha</name></author><author><name>Fahd Al-Mulla</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The emergence of effective vaccines for COVID-19 has been welcomed by the world with great optimism. Given their increased susceptibility to COVID-19, the question arises whether individuals with type-2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) and other metabolic conditions can respond effectively to the mRNA-based vaccine. We aimed to evaluate the levels of anti-SARS-CoV-2 IgG and neutralizing antibodies in people with T2DM and/or other metabolic risk factors (hypertension and obesity) compared to those without. This study included 262 people that took two doses of BNT162b2 (Pfizer-BioNTech) mRNA vaccine. Both T2DM and non-diabetic individuals had a robust response to vaccination as demonstrated by their high antibody titers. However, both SARS-CoV-2 IgG and neutralizing antibodies titers were lower in people with T2DM. Their levels were 154±49.1 vs. 138±59.4BAU/mL for IgG and 87.1±11.6 vs. 79.7±19.5% for neutralizing antibodies in individuals without diabetes compared to those with T2DM, respectively. In a multiple linear regression adjusted for individual characteristics, comorbidities, previous COVID-19 infection and duration since second vaccine dose, diabetics had 13.86 BAU/ml (95%CI: -27.08 to -0.64BAU/ml, p=0.041) less IgG antibodies and 4.42% (95%CI: -8.53 to -0.32%, p=0.036) less neutralizing antibodies than non-diabetics. Hypertension and obesity did not show significant changes in antibody titers. Taken together, both type-2 diabetic and non-diabetic individuals elicited strong immune responses to SARS-CoV-2 BNT162b2 mRNA vaccine; nonetheless, lower levels were seen in people with diabetes. Continuous monitoring of the antibody levels might be a good indicator to guide personalized needs for further booster shots to maintain adaptive immunity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261042" rel="alternate" title="Robust antibody levels in both diabetic and non-diabetic individuals after BNT162b2 mRNA COVID-19 vaccination (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261041</id><title>The impact of large mobile air purifiers on aerosol concentration in classrooms and the reduction of airborne transmission of SARS-CoV-2 (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.628738+00:00</updated><author><name>Finn F. Duill</name></author><author><name>Florian Schulz</name></author><author><name>Aman Jain</name></author><author><name>Leve Krieger</name></author><author><name>Berend van Wachem</name></author><author><name>Frank Beyrau</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the wake of the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic, an increased risk of infection by virus-containing aerosols indoors is assumed. Especially in schools, the duration of stay is long and the number of people in the rooms is large, increasing the risk of infection. This problem particularly affects schools without pre-installed ventilation systems that are equipped with filters and/or operate with fresh air. Here, the aerosol concentration is reduced by natural ventilation. In this context, we are investigating the effect of large mobile air purifiers (AP) with HEPA filters on particle concentration and their suitability for classroom use in a primary school in Germany. The three tested APs differ significantly in their air outlet characteristics. Measurements of the number of particles, the particle size distribution, and the CO2 concentration were carried out in the classroom with students (April/May 2021) and with an aerosol generator without students. In this regard, the use of APs leads to a substantial reduction in aerosol particles. At the same time, the three APs are found to have differences in their particle decay rate, noise level, and flow velocity. In addition to the measurements, the effect of various influencing parameters on the potential inhaled particle dose was investigated using a calculation model. The parameters considered include the duration of stay, particle concentration in exhaled air, respiratory flow rate, virus lifetime, ventilation interval, ventilation efficiency, AP volumetric flow, as well as room size. Based on the resulting effect diagrams, significant recommendations can be derived for reducing the risk of infection from virus-laden aerosols. Finally, the measurements were compared to computational fluid dynamics (CFD) modeling, as such tools can aid the optimal placement and configuration of APs and can be used to study the effect of the spread of aerosols from a source in the classroom.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261041" rel="alternate" title="The impact of large mobile air purifiers on aerosol concentration in classrooms and the reduction of airborne transmission of SARS-CoV-2 (4 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>