<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.887945+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468472</id><title>A live attenuated influenza virus-vectored intranasal COVID-19 vaccine provides rapid, prolonged, and broad protection against SARS-CoV-2 infection (502 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.888364+00:00</updated><author><name>Junyu Chen</name></author><author><name>Pui Wang</name></author><author><name>Lunzhi Yuan</name></author><author><name>Liang Zhang</name></author><author><name>Limin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Hui Zhao</name></author><author><name>Congjie Chen</name></author><author><name>Yaode Chen</name></author><author><name>Jinle Han</name></author><author><name>Jizong Jia</name></author><author><name>Zhen Lu</name></author><author><name>Junping Hong</name></author><author><name>Liqiang Chen</name></author><author><name>Changfa Fan</name></author><author><name>Zicen Lu</name></author><author><name>Qian Wang</name></author><author><name>Rirong Chen</name></author><author><name>Minping Cai</name></author><author><name>Ruoyao Qi</name></author><author><name>Xijing Wang</name></author><author><name>Jian Ma</name></author><author><name>Min Zhou</name></author><author><name>Huan Yu</name></author><author><name>Chunlan Zhuang</name></author><author><name>Xiaohui Liu</name></author><author><name>Qiangyuan Han</name></author><author><name>Guosong Wang</name></author><author><name>Yingying Su</name></author><author><name>Quan Yuan</name></author><author><name>Tong Cheng</name></author><author><name>Ting Wu</name></author><author><name>Xiangzhong Ye</name></author><author><name>Changgui Li</name></author><author><name>Tianying Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jun Zhang</name></author><author><name>Huachen Zhu</name></author><author><name>Yixin Chen</name></author><author><name>Honglin Chen</name></author><author><name>Ningshao Xia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Remarkable progress has been made in developing intramuscular vaccines against severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2); however, they are limited with respect to eliciting local immunity in the respiratory tract, which is the primary infection site for SARS-CoV-2. To overcome the limitations of intramuscular vaccines, we constructed a nasal vaccine candidate based on an influenza vector by inserting a gene encoding the receptor-binding domain (RBD) of the spike protein of SARS-CoV-2, named CA4-dNS1-nCoV-RBD (dNS1-RBD). A preclinical study showed that in hamsters challenged 1 day and 7 days after single-dose vaccination or 6 months after booster vaccination, dNS1-RBD largely mitigated lung pathology, with no loss of body weight, caused by either the prototype-like strain or beta variant of SARS-CoV-2. Lasted data showed that the animals could be well protected against beta variant challenge 9 months after vaccination. Notably, the weight loss and lung pathological changes of hamsters could still be significantly reduced when the hamster was vaccinated 24 h after challenge. Moreover, such cellular immunity is relatively unimpaired for the most concerning SARS-CoV-2 variants. The protective immune mechanism of dNS1-RBD could be attributed to the innate immune response in the nasal epithelium, local RBD-specific T cell response in the lung, and RBD-specific IgA and IgG response. Thus, this study demonstrates that the intranasally delivered dNS1-RBD vaccine candidate may offer an important addition to fight against the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic, compensating limitations of current intramuscular vaccines, particularly at the start of an outbreak.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468472" rel="alternate" title="A live attenuated influenza virus-vectored intranasal COVID-19 vaccine provides rapid, prolonged, and broad protection against SARS-CoV-2 infection (502 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469078</id><title>Metformin Suppresses SARS-CoV-2 in Cell Culture (145 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.889142+00:00</updated><author><name>Dixit Tandel</name></author><author><name>Haripriya Parthasarathy</name></author><author><name>Krishnan Harinivas Harshan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;People with diabetes are reported to have a higher risk of experiencing severe COVID-19 complications. Metformin, a first-line medication for type 2 diabetes, has antiviral properties. Some studies have indicated its prognostic potential in COVID-19. Here, we report that metformin significantly inhibits SARS-CoV-2 growth in cell culture models. SARS-CoV-2 infection of gut epithelial cell line, Caco2, resulted in higher phosphorylation of AMPK. Metformin reduced viral titers in the infected cells by nearly 99%, and by about 90% when cells were treated prior to infection. Metformin pre-treatment resulted in further phosphorylation of AMPK and caused a ten-fold reduction of viral titers indicating its potential in preventing naive infections. Confirming the positive impact of AMPK activation, another AMPK activator AICAR substantially inhibited of viral titers and, AMPK inhibitor Compound C, augmented it considerably. Metformin treatment post-SARS-CoV-2 infection resulted in nearly hundred-fold reduction of viral titers, indicating that the antiviral potency of the drug is far higher in infected cells, while still being able to reduce fresh infection. Metformin displayed SARS-CoV-2 TCID50 and TCID90 at 3.5 and 8.9 mM, respectively. In conclusion, our study demonstrates that metformin is very effective in limiting the replication of SARS-CoV-2 in cell culture and thus possibly could offer double benefits to diabetic COVID-19 patients by lowering both blood glucose levels and viral load.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469078" rel="alternate" title="Metformin Suppresses SARS-CoV-2 in Cell Culture (145 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468777</id><title>The Delta variant of SARS-CoV-2 maintains high sensitivity to interferons in human lung cells (99 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.889347+00:00</updated><author><name>Rayhane Nchioua</name></author><author><name>Annika Schundner</name></author><author><name>Susanne Klute</name></author><author><name>Sabrina Noettger</name></author><author><name>Fabian Zech</name></author><author><name>Lennart Koepke</name></author><author><name>Alexander Graf</name></author><author><name>Stefan Krebs</name></author><author><name>Helmut Blum</name></author><author><name>Dorota Kmiec</name></author><author><name>Manfred Frick</name></author><author><name>Frank Kirchhoff</name></author><author><name>Konstantin M.J. Sparrer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Interferons are a major part of the anti-viral innate defense system. Successful pathogens, including the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), need to overcome these defenses to establish an infection. Early induction of interferons (IFNs) protects against severe coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). In line with this, SARS-CoV-2 is inhibited by IFNs &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, and IFN-based therapies against COVID-19 are investigated in clinical trials. However, SARS-CoV-2 continues to adapt to the human population resulting in the emergence of variants characterized by increased transmission fitness and/or decreased sensitivity to preventive or therapeutic measures. It has been suggested that the efficient spread of these so-called “Variants of Concern” (VOCs) may also involve reduced sensitivity to IFNs. Here, we examined whether the four current VOCs (Alpha, Beta, Gamma and Delta) differ in replication efficiency or IFN sensitivity from an early isolate of SARS-CoV-2. All viruses replicated in a human lung cell line and in iPSC-derived alveolar type II cells (iAT2). The Delta variant showed accelerated replication kinetics and higher infectious virus production compared to the early 2020 isolate. Replication of all SARS-CoV-2 VOCs was reduced in the presence of exogenous type I, II and III IFNs. On average, the Alpha variant was the least susceptible to IFNs and the Alpha, Beta and Gamma variants show increased resistance against type III IFN. Although the Delta variant has outcompeted all other variants in humans it remained as sensitive to IFNs as an early 2020 SARS-CoV-2 isolate. This suggests that increased replication fitness rather than IFN resistance may be a reason for its dominance. Our results may help to understand changes in innate immune susceptibility of VOCs, and inform clinical trials exploring IFN-based COVID-19 therapies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468777" rel="alternate" title="The Delta variant of SARS-CoV-2 maintains high sensitivity to interferons in human lung cells (99 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.21266295</id><title>Estimation of R0 for the spread of SARS-CoV-2 in Germany from Excess Mortality (93 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.889631+00:00</updated><author><name>Juan Pablo Prada</name></author><author><name>Luca Estelle Maag</name></author><author><name>Laura Siegmund</name></author><author><name>Elena Bencurova</name></author><author><name>Liang Chunguang</name></author><author><name>Eleni Koutsilieri</name></author><author><name>Thomas Dandekar</name></author><author><name>Carsten Scheller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;For SARS-CoV-2, R0 calculations report usually 2-3, biased by PCR testing increases. Covid-19-induced excess mortality is less biased.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used data from Robert Koch Institute on Covid incidence, deaths, and PCR tests and excess mortality to determine early, policy-free R0 estimates with a serial interval of 4.7 days.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The PCR-based R0 value was 2.56 (95% CI 2.52-2.60) for Covid-19 cases and 2.03 (95%CI 1.96-2.10) for Covid-19-related deaths. As the number of PCR tests increased, R0 values were corrected accordingly, yielding 1.86 for Covid-19 cases and 1.47 for Covid-19 deaths, excess deaths were 1.34 (95% CI 1.32-1.37).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;R0 is much lower than previously thought. This fits the observed seasonal pattern of infection across Europe in 2020-2021, including emergence of more contagious escape variants such as delta.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Excess mortality reveals infection speed in Covid-19 is surprisingly low with seasonal infection patterns and escape variants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.21266295" rel="alternate" title="Estimation of R0 for the spread of SARS-CoV-2 in Germany from Excess Mortality (93 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.21265758</id><title>Seroprevalence in Tamil Nadu through India’s two COVID waves: Evidence on antibody decline following infection and vaccination (54 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.889863+00:00</updated><author><name>T.S. Selvavinayagam</name></author><author><name>A. Somasundaram</name></author><author><name>Jerard Maria Selvam</name></author><author><name>Sabareesh Ramachandran</name></author><author><name>P. Sampath</name></author><author><name>V. Vijayalakshmi</name></author><author><name>C. Ajith Brabhu Kumar</name></author><author><name>Sudharshini Subramaniam</name></author><author><name>S Raju</name></author><author><name>R Avudaiselvi</name></author><author><name>V. Prakash</name></author><author><name>N. Yogananth</name></author><author><name>Gurunathan Subramanian</name></author><author><name>A Roshini</name></author><author><name>D.N. Dhiliban</name></author><author><name>Sofia Imad</name></author><author><name>Vaidehi Tandel</name></author><author><name>Rajeswari Parasa</name></author><author><name>Stuti Sachdeva</name></author><author><name>Anup Malani</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Three rounds of population-representative serological studies through India’s two COVID waves (round 1, 19 October-30 November 2020; round 2, 7-30 April 2021; and round 3, 28 June-7 July7, 2021) were conducted at the district-level in Tamil Nadu state (population 72 million). State-level seroprevalence in rounds 1, 2 and 3 were 31.5%, 22.9%, and 67.1%. Estimated seroprevalence implies that at least 22.6 and 48.1 million persons were infected by the 30 November 2020 and 7 July 2021. There was substantial variation across districts in the state in each round. Seroprevalence ranged from 11.1 to 49.8% (round 1), 7.9 to 50.3% (round 2), and 37.8 to 84% (round 3). Seroprevalence in urban areas was higher than in rural areas (35.7 v. 25.7% in round 1, 74.8% v. 64.1% in round 3). Females had similar seroprevalence to males (30.8 v. 30.2% in round 1, 67.5 v. 65.5% in round 3). While working age populations (age 40-49: 31.6%) had significantly higher seroprevalence than the youth (age 18-29: 30.4%) or elderly (age 70+: 26.5%) in round 1, only the gap between working age (age 40-49: 66.7%) and elderly (age 70+: 59.6%) remained significant in round 3. Seroprevalence was greater among those who were vaccinated for COVID (25.7% v. 20.9% in round 2, 80.0% v. 62.3% in round 3). While the decline in seroprevalence from round 1 to 2 suggests antibody decline after natural infection, we do not find significant decline in antibodies among those receiving at least 1 dose of vaccine between rounds 2 and 3.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.21265758" rel="alternate" title="Seroprevalence in Tamil Nadu through India’s two COVID waves: Evidence on antibody decline following infection and vaccination (54 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468761</id><title>Microglia do not restrict SARS-CoV-2 replication following infection of the central nervous system of K18-hACE2 transgenic mice (50 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.890198+00:00</updated><author><name>Gema M. Olivarria</name></author><author><name>Yuting Cheng</name></author><author><name>Susana Furman</name></author><author><name>Collin Pachow</name></author><author><name>Lindsay A. Hohsfield</name></author><author><name>Charlene Smith-Geater</name></author><author><name>Ricardo Miramontes</name></author><author><name>Jie Wu</name></author><author><name>Mara S. Burns</name></author><author><name>Kate I. Tsourmas</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Stocksdale</name></author><author><name>Cynthia Manlapaz</name></author><author><name>William H. Yong</name></author><author><name>John Teijaro</name></author><author><name>Robert Edwards</name></author><author><name>Kim N. Green</name></author><author><name>Leslie M. Thompson</name></author><author><name>Thomas E. Lane</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Unlike SARS-CoV-1 and MERS-CoV, infection with SARS-CoV-2, the viral pathogen responsible for COVID-19, is often associated with neurologic symptoms that range from mild to severe, yet increasing evidence argues the virus does not exhibit extensive neuroinvasive properties. We demonstrate SARS-CoV-2 can infect and replicate in human iPSC-derived neurons and that infection shows limited anti-viral and inflammatory responses but increased activation of EIF2 signaling following infection as determined by RNA sequencing. Intranasal infection of K18 human ACE2 transgenic mice (K18-hACE2) with SARS-CoV-2 resulted in lung pathology associated with viral replication and immune cell infiltration. In addition, ∼50% of infected mice exhibited CNS infection characterized by wide-spread viral replication in neurons accompanied by increased expression of chemokine (&lt;italic&gt;Cxcl9, Cxcl10, Ccl2, Ccl5&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Ccl19&lt;/italic&gt;) and cytokine (&lt;italic&gt;Ifn-λ&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Tnf-α&lt;/italic&gt;) transcripts associated with microgliosis and a neuroinflammatory response consisting primarily of monocytes/macrophages. Microglia depletion via administration of colony-stimulating factor 1 receptor inhibitor, PLX5622, in SARS-CoV-2 infected mice did not affect survival or viral replication but did result in dampened expression of proinflammatory cytokine/chemokine transcripts and a reduction in monocyte/macrophage infiltration. These results argue that microglia are dispensable in terms of controlling SARS-CoV-2 replication in in the K18-hACE2 model but do contribute to an inflammatory response through expression of pro-inflammatory genes. Collectively, these findings contribute to previous work demonstrating the ability of SARS-CoV-2 to infect neurons as well as emphasizing the potential use of the K18-hACE2 model to study immunological and neuropathological aspects related to SARS-CoV-2-induced neurologic disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Understanding the immunological mechanisms contributing to both host defense and disease following viral infection of the CNS is of critical importance given the increasing number of viruses that are capable of infecting and replicating within the nervous system. With this in mind, the present study was undertaken to evaluate the role of microglia in aiding in host defense following experimental infection of the central nervous system (CNS) of K18-hACE2 with SARS-CoV-2, the causative agent of COVID-19. Neurologic symptoms that range in severity are common in COVID-19 patients and understanding immune responses that contribute to restricting neurologic disease can provide important insight into better understanding consequences associated with SARS-CoV-2 infection of the CNS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468761" rel="alternate" title="Microglia do not restrict SARS-CoV-2 replication following infection of the central nervous system of K18-hACE2 transgenic mice (50 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.21266187</id><title>Controlling SARS-CoV-2 in schools using repetitive testing strategies (41 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.890515+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrea Torneri</name></author><author><name>Lander Willem</name></author><author><name>Vittoria Colizza</name></author><author><name>Cécile Kremer</name></author><author><name>Christelle Meuris</name></author><author><name>Gilles Darcis</name></author><author><name>Niel Hens</name></author><author><name>Pieter Libin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 remains a worldwide emergency. While vaccines have been approved and are widely administered, these are only available to adults and adolescents in Europe. Therefore, in order to mitigate the spread of more transmissible SARS-CoV-2 variants among children, the use of non-pharmaceutical interventions is still warranted. We investigate the impact of different testing strategies on the SARS-CoV-2 infection dynamics in a primary school environment, using an individual-based modelling approach. Specifically, we consider three testing strategies: 1) &lt;italic&gt;symptomatic isolation&lt;/italic&gt;, where we test symptomatic individuals and isolate them when they test positive, 2) &lt;italic&gt;reactive screening&lt;/italic&gt;, where a class is screened once one symptomatic individual was identified, and 3) &lt;italic&gt;repetitive screening&lt;/italic&gt;, where the school in its entirety is screened on regular time intervals. Through this analysis, we demonstrate that repetitive testing strategies can significantly reduce the attack rate in schools, contrary to a reactive screening approach. Furthermore, we investigate the impact of these testing strategies on the average number of school days lost per child.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.21266187" rel="alternate" title="Controlling SARS-CoV-2 in schools using repetitive testing strategies (41 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.21266552</id><title>Low neutralizing antibody titers against the Mu variant of SARS-CoV-2 in BNT162b2 vaccinated individuals (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.890833+00:00</updated><author><name>Diego A. Álvarez-Díaz</name></author><author><name>Ana Luisa Muñoz</name></author><author><name>Pilar Tavera-Rodríguez</name></author><author><name>María T. Herrera-Sepúlveda</name></author><author><name>Hector Alejandro Ruiz-Moreno</name></author><author><name>Katherine Laiton-Donato</name></author><author><name>Carlos Franco-Muñoz</name></author><author><name>Dioselina Pelaez-Carvajal</name></author><author><name>Diego Cuellar</name></author><author><name>Alejandra M. Muñoz-Ramirez</name></author><author><name>Marisol Galindo</name></author><author><name>Edgar J. Arias-Ramirez</name></author><author><name>Marcela Mercado-Reyes</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Global surveillance programs for the virus that causes COVID-19 are showing the emergence of variants with mutations in the Spike protein, including the Mu variant, recently declared a Variant of Interest (VOI) by the World Health Organization. Genomic and laboratory surveillance is important in these types of variants because they may be more infectious or less susceptible to antiviral treatments and vaccine-induced antibodies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To evaluate the sensitivity of the Mu variant (B.1.621) to neutralizing antibodies induced by the BNT162b2 vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Study design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Three of the most predominant SARS-CoV-2 variants in Colombia during the epidemiological peaks of 2021 were isolated. Microneutralization assays were performed by incubating 120 TCDI&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; of each SARS-CoV-2 isolate with five 2-fold serial dilutions of sera from 14 BNT162b2 vaccinated volunteers. The MN&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; titer was calculated by the Reed-Muench formula&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The three isolated variants were Mu, a Variant of Interest (VOI), Gamma, a variant of concern (VOC), and B.1.111 that lacks genetic markers associated with greater virulence. At the end of August, the Mu and Gamma variants were widely distributed in Colombia. Mu was predominant (49%), followed by Gamma (25%). In contrast, B.1.111 became almost undetectable. The evaluation of neutralizing antibodies suggests that patients vaccinated with BNT162-2 generate neutralizing antibody titers against the Mu variant at significantly lower concentrations relative to B.1.111 and Gamma.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study shows the importance of continuing with surveillance programs of emerging variants as well as the need to evaluate the neutralizing antibody response induced by other vaccines circulating in the country against Mu and other variants with high epidemiological impact.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mu and Gamma variants represented 49% and 25% of cases in Colombia by August 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Increased proportion of SARS-COV-2 cases were mostly associated with Mu variant, despite being detected simultaneously with the VOC Gamma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Mu variant remarkably escapes from neutralizing antibodies elicited by the BNT162b2-vaccine&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Laboratory studies of neutralizing antibodies are useful to determine the efficacy of SARS-CoV-2 vaccines against VOC and VOI.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.21266552" rel="alternate" title="Low neutralizing antibody titers against the Mu variant of SARS-CoV-2 in BNT162b2 vaccinated individuals (27 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.468537</id><title>Viral E Protein Neutralizes BET Protein-Mediated Post-Entry Antagonism of SARS-CoV-2 (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.891830+00:00</updated><author><name>Irene P. Chen</name></author><author><name>James E. Longbotham</name></author><author><name>Sarah McMahon</name></author><author><name>Rahul K. Suryawanshi</name></author><author><name>Jared Carlson-Stevermer</name></author><author><name>Meghna Gupta</name></author><author><name>Meng Yao Zhang</name></author><author><name>Frank W. Soveg</name></author><author><name>Jennifer M. Hayashi</name></author><author><name>Taha Y. Taha</name></author><author><name>Victor L. Lam</name></author><author><name>Yang Li</name></author><author><name>Zanlin Yu</name></author><author><name>Erron W. Titus</name></author><author><name>Amy Diallo</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Oki</name></author><author><name>Kevin Holden</name></author><author><name>Nevan Krogan</name></author><author><name>Danica Galonić Fujimori</name></author><author><name>Melanie Ott</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Inhibitors of Bromodomain and Extra-terminal domain (BET) proteins are possible anti-SARS-CoV-2 prophylactics as they downregulate angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2). Here, we show that BET proteins should not be inactivated therapeutically as they are critical antiviral factors at the post-entry level. Knockouts of BRD3 or BRD4 in cells overexpressing ACE2 exacerbate SARS-CoV-2 infection; the same is observed when cells with endogenous ACE2 expression are treated with BET inhibitors during infection, and not before. Viral replication and mortality are also enhanced in BET inhibitor-treated mice overexpressing ACE2. BET inactivation suppresses interferon production induced by SARS-CoV-2, a process phenocopied by the envelope (E) protein previously identified as a possible “histone mimetic.” E protein, in an acetylated form, directly binds the second bromodomain of BRD4. Our data support a model where SARS-CoV-2 E protein evolved to antagonize interferon responses via BET protein inhibition; this neutralization should not be further enhanced with BET inhibitor treatment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.468537" rel="alternate" title="Viral E Protein Neutralizes BET Protein-Mediated Post-Entry Antagonism of SARS-CoV-2 (26 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468374</id><title>Full protection against all four SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (VOC) in hamsters requires revision of spike antigen used for vaccination (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.892707+00:00</updated><author><name>Sapna Sharma</name></author><author><name>Thomas Vercruysse</name></author><author><name>Lorena Sanchez-Felipe</name></author><author><name>Winnie Kerstens</name></author><author><name>Rana Abdelnabi</name></author><author><name>Caroline Foo</name></author><author><name>Viktor Lemmens</name></author><author><name>Dominique Van Looveren</name></author><author><name>Piet Maes</name></author><author><name>Guy Baele</name></author><author><name>Birgit Weynand</name></author><author><name>Philippe Lemey</name></author><author><name>Johan Neyts</name></author><author><name>Hendrik Jan Thibaut</name></author><author><name>Kai Dallmeier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Current licensed COVID-19 vaccines are based on antigen sequences of initial SARS-CoV-2 isolates that emerged in 2019. By mid 2021 these historical virus strains have been completely replaced by new cosmopolitan SARS-CoV-2 lineages. The ongoing pandemic has been further driven by emerging variants of concern (VOC) Alpha, Beta, Gamma and, lately predominant, Delta. These are characterized by an increased transmissibility and possible escape from naturally acquired or vaccine-induced immunity. We here show, using a YF17D-vectored first-generation COVID-19 vaccine (Sanchez-Felipe et al., 2021) and a stringent hamster challenge model (Abdelnabi et al., 2021) that the immunity elicited by a prototypic spike antigen is insufficient to provide optimal protection against the Beta VoC, urging for an antigenic update. We therefore designed an updated second-generation vaccine candidate that carries the sequence of a spike antigen that includes crucial epitopes from multiple VOCs. This vaccine candidate yielded a marked change in target antigen spectrum covered as demonstrated by (&lt;italic&gt;i&lt;/italic&gt;) antigenic cartography and (&lt;italic&gt;ii&lt;/italic&gt;) full protection against infection and virus-induced disease caused by any of the four VOCs (Alpha, Beta, Gamma and Delta) used for challenge. This more universal COVID-19 vaccine candidate also efficiently blocked direct transmission of VOC Delta from vaccinated infected hamsters to non-vaccinated sentinels under prolonged co-housing conditions. In conclusion, our data suggest that current first-generation COVID-19 vaccines need to be adapted to cover emerging sequence diversity of VOC to preserve vaccine efficacy and to contain virus spread at the community level.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468374" rel="alternate" title="Full protection against all four SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (VOC) in hamsters requires revision of spike antigen used for vaccination (21 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.21263608</id><title>Reduced Incidence of Long-COVID Symptoms Related to Administration of COVID-19 Vaccines Both Before COVID-19 Diagnosis and Up to 12 Weeks After (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.894181+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael A. Simon</name></author><author><name>Ryan D. Luginbuhl</name></author><author><name>Richard Parker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Both clinical trials and studies leveraging real-world data have repeatedly confirmed the three COVID-19 vaccines authorized for use by the Food and Drug Administration are safe and effective at preventing infection, hospitalization, and death due to COVID-19 and a recent observational study of self-reported symptoms provides support that vaccination may also reduce the probability of developing long-COVID. As part of a federated research study with the COVID-19 Patient Recovery Alliance, Arcadia.io performed a retrospective analysis of the medical history of 240,648 COVID-19-infected persons to identity factors influencing the development and progression of long-COVID. This analysis revealed that patients who received at least one dose of any of the three COVID vaccines prior to their diagnosis with COVID-19 were 7-10 times less likely to report two or more long-COVID symptoms compared to unvaccinated patients. Furthermore, unvaccinated patients who received their first COVID-19 vaccination within four weeks of SARS-CoV-2 infection were 4-6 times less likely to report multiple long-COVID symptoms, and those who received their first dose 4-8 weeks after diagnosis were 3 times less likely to report multiple long-COVID symptoms compared to those who remained unvaccinated. This relationship supports the hypothesis that COVID-19 vaccination is protective against long-COVID and that effect persists even if vaccination occurs up to 12 weeks after COVID-19 diagnosis. A critical objective of this study was hypothesis generation, and the authors intend to perform further studies to substantiate the findings and encourage other researchers to as well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.21263608" rel="alternate" title="Reduced Incidence of Long-COVID Symptoms Related to Administration of COVID-19 Vaccines Both Before COVID-19 Diagnosis and Up to 12 Weeks After (18 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.21266294</id><title>Inactivated virus vaccine BBV152/Covaxin elicits robust cellular immune memory to SARS-CoV-2 and variants of concern (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.894742+00:00</updated><author><name>Rajesh Vikkurthi</name></author><author><name>Asgar Ansari</name></author><author><name>Anupama R Pai</name></author><author><name>Someshwar Nath Jha</name></author><author><name>Shilpa Sachan</name></author><author><name>Suvechchha Pandit</name></author><author><name>Bhushan Nikam</name></author><author><name>Anurag Kalia</name></author><author><name>Bimal Prasad Jit</name></author><author><name>Hilal Ahmad Parray</name></author><author><name>Savita Singh</name></author><author><name>Pallavi Kshetrapal</name></author><author><name>Nitya Wadhwa</name></author><author><name>Tripti Shrivastava</name></author><author><name>Poonam Coshic</name></author><author><name>Suresh Kumar</name></author><author><name>Pragya Sharma</name></author><author><name>Nandini Sharma</name></author><author><name>Juhi Taneja</name></author><author><name>Anil K Pandey</name></author><author><name>Ashok Sharma</name></author><author><name>Ramachandran Thiruvengadam</name></author><author><name>Alba Grifoni</name></author><author><name>Shinjini Bhatnagar</name></author><author><name>Daniela Weiskopf</name></author><author><name>Alessandro Sette</name></author><author><name>Pramod Kumar Garg</name></author><author><name>Nimesh Gupta</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The characteristics of immune memory established in response to inactivated SARS-CoV-2 vaccines remains unclear. We determined the magnitude, quality and persistence of cellular and humoral memory responses up to 6 months after vaccination with BBV152/Covaxin. Here, we show that the quantity of vaccine-induced spike- and nucleoprotein-antibodies is comparable to that following natural infection and the antibodies are detectable up to 6 months. The RBD-specific antibodies decline in the range of 3 to 10-fold against the SARS-CoV-2 variants in the order of alpha (B.1.1.7) &amp;gt; delta (B.1.617.2) &amp;gt; beta (B.1.351), with no observed impact of gamma (P.1) and kappa (B.1.617.1) variant. We found that the vaccine induces memory B cells, similar to natural infection, which are impacted by virus variants in the same order as antibodies. The vaccine further induced antigen-specific functionally potent multi-cytokine expressing CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells in ∼85% of the subjects, targeting spike and nucleoprotein of SARS-CoV-2. Marginal ∼1.3 fold-reduction was observed in vaccine-induced CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells against the beta variant, with no significant impact of the alpha and the delta variants. The antigen-specific CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells were populated in the central memory compartment and persisted up to 6 months of vaccination. Importantly the vaccine generated Tfh cells that are endowed with B cell help potential, similar to the Tfh cells induced after natural infection. Altogether, these findings establish that the inactivated virus vaccine BBV152 induces robust immune memory to SARS-CoV-2 and variants of concern, which persist for at least 6 months after vaccination. This study provides insight into the attributes of BBV152-elicited immune memory, and has implication for future vaccine development, guidance for use of inactivated virus vaccine, and booster immunization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.21266294" rel="alternate" title="Inactivated virus vaccine BBV152/Covaxin elicits robust cellular immune memory to SARS-CoV-2 and variants of concern (18 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468963</id><title>Epoxidized graphene grid for high-throughput high-resolution cryoEM structural analysis (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.895362+00:00</updated><author><name>Junso Fujita</name></author><author><name>Fumiaki Makino</name></author><author><name>Haruyasu Asahara</name></author><author><name>Maiko Moriguchi</name></author><author><name>Shota Kumano</name></author><author><name>Itsuki Anzai</name></author><author><name>Jun-ichi Kishikawa</name></author><author><name>Yoshiharu Matsuura</name></author><author><name>Takayuki Kato</name></author><author><name>Keiichi Namba</name></author><author><name>Tsuyoshi Inoue</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many specimens suffer from low particle density and/or preferred orientation in cryoEM specimen grid preparation, making data collection and structure determination time consuming. We developed an epoxidized graphene grid (EG-grid) that effectively immobilizes protein particles by applying an oxidation reaction using photoactivated ClO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;•&lt;/sup&gt; and further chemical modification. The particle density and orientation distribution are both dramatically improved, having enabled us to reconstruct the density map of GroEL and glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH), at 1.99 and 2.16 Å resolution from only 504 and 241 micrographs, respectively. A low concentration sample solution of 0.1 mg ml&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt; was sufficient to reconstruct a 3.10 Å resolution density map of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein from 1,163 micrographs. The density maps of V&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;-ATPase, β-galactosidase, and apoferritin were also reconstructed at 3.03, 1.81, and 1.29 Å resolution, respectively. These results indicate that the EG-grid will be a powerful tool for high-throughput cryoEM data collection to accelerate high-resolution structural analysis of biological macromolecules.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468963" rel="alternate" title="Epoxidized graphene grid for high-throughput high-resolution cryoEM structural analysis (16 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468942</id><title>IFITM dependency of SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.895646+00:00</updated><author><name>Rayhane Nchioua</name></author><author><name>Annika Schundner</name></author><author><name>Dorota Kmiec</name></author><author><name>Caterina Prelli Bozzo</name></author><author><name>Fabian Zech</name></author><author><name>Lennart Koepke</name></author><author><name>Manfred Frick</name></author><author><name>Konstantin M. J. Sparrer</name></author><author><name>Frank Kirchhoff</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We have recently shown that a SARS-CoV-2 strain isolated in the Netherlands in February 2020 (NL-02-2020) hijacks interferon-induced transmembrane proteins, especially IFITM2, as entry cofactors for efficient infection. Here, we examined whether SARS-CoV-2 “variants of concern” (VOCs), including the currently dominating delta variant, maintained the dependency on IFITMs for efficient replication. Depletion of IFITM2 reduced viral RNA production from 31- (B.1.1.7) to 755-fold (P.1). In comparison, silencing of IFITM1 had little effect, while knock-down of IFITM3 resulted in an intermediate phenotype. Strikingly, silencing of IFITM2 generally reduced infectious virus production in Calu-3 cells to near background levels. An antibody directed against the N-terminus of IFITM2 inhibited SARS-CoV-2 VOC replication in iPSC-derived alveolar epithelial type II cells. In conclusion, endogenously expressed IFITM proteins (especially IFITM2) are important cofactors for replication of genuine SARS-CoV-2 VOCs, including the Delta variant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468942" rel="alternate" title="IFITM dependency of SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (15 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468633</id><title>Tunneling nanotubes provide a novel route for SARS-CoV-2 spreading between permissive cells and to non-permissive neuronal cells (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.895894+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna Pepe</name></author><author><name>Stefano Pietropaoli</name></author><author><name>Matthijn Vos</name></author><author><name>Giovanna Barba-Spaeth</name></author><author><name>Chiara Zurzolo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 entry into host cells is mediated by the binding of its spike glycoprotein to the angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) receptor, highly expressed in several organs, but very low in the brain. The mechanism through which SARS-CoV-2 infects neurons is not understood. Tunneling nanotubes (TNTs), actin-based intercellular conduits that connect distant cells, allow the transfer of cargos, including viruses. Here, we explored the neuroinvasive potential of SARS-CoV-2 and whether TNTs are involved in its spreading between cells &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. We report that neuronal cells, not permissive to SARS-CoV-2 through an exocytosis/endocytosis dependent pathway, can be infected when co-cultured with permissive infected epithelial cells. SARS-CoV-2 induces TNTs formation between permissive cells and exploits this route to spread to uninfected permissive cells in co-culture. Correlative Cryo-electron tomography reveals that SARS-CoV-2 is associated with the plasma membrane of TNTs formed between permissive cells and virus-like vesicular structures are inside TNTs established both between permissive cells and between permissive and non-permissive cells. Our data highlight a potential novel mechanism of SARS-CoV-2 spreading which could serve as route to invade non-permissive cells and potentiate infection in permissive cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468633" rel="alternate" title="Tunneling nanotubes provide a novel route for SARS-CoV-2 spreading between permissive cells and to non-permissive neuronal cells (13 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468228</id><title>Structural and functional characterization of NEMO cleavage by SARS-CoV-2 3CLpro (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.896106+00:00</updated><author><name>Mikhail Ali Hameedi</name></author><author><name>Erica T. Prates</name></author><author><name>Michael R. Garvin</name></author><author><name>Irimpan Mathews</name></author><author><name>B Kirtley Amos</name></author><author><name>Omar Demerdash</name></author><author><name>Mark Bechthold</name></author><author><name>Mamta Iyer</name></author><author><name>Simin Rahighi</name></author><author><name>Daniel W. Kneller</name></author><author><name>Andrey Kovalevsky</name></author><author><name>Stephan Irle</name></author><author><name>Van-Quan Vuong</name></author><author><name>Julie C. Mitchell</name></author><author><name>Audrey Labbe</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Galanie</name></author><author><name>Soichi Wakatsuki</name></author><author><name>Daniel Jacobson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In addition to its essential role in viral polyprotein processing, the SARS-CoV-2 3C-like (3CLpro) protease can cleave human immune signaling proteins, like NF-κB Essential Modulator (NEMO) and deregulate the host immune response. Here, &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; assays show that SARS-CoV-2 3CLpro cleaves NEMO with fine-tuned efficiency. Analysis of the 2.14 Å resolution crystal structure of 3CLpro C145S bound to NEMO&lt;sub&gt;226-235&lt;/sub&gt; reveals subsites that tolerate a range of viral and host substrates through main chain hydrogen bonds while also enforcing specificity using side chain hydrogen bonds and hydrophobic contacts. Machine learning- and physics-based computational methods predict that variation in key binding residues of 3CLpro- NEMO helps explain the high fitness of SARS-CoV-2 in humans. We posit that cleavage of NEMO is an important piece of information to be accounted for in the pathology of COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468228" rel="alternate" title="Structural and functional characterization of NEMO cleavage by SARS-CoV-2 3CLpro (13 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468929</id><title>Predicting SARS-CoV-2 epitope-specific TCR recognition using pre-trained protein embeddings (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.896443+00:00</updated><author><name>Youngmahn Han</name></author><author><name>Aeri Lee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic is ongoing because of the high transmission rate and the emergence of SARS-CoV-2 variants. The &lt;bold&gt;P272L&lt;/bold&gt; mutation in SARS-Cov-2 &lt;bold&gt;S&lt;/bold&gt;-protein is known to be highly relevant to the viral escape associated with the second pandemic wave in Europe. Epitope-specific T-cell receptor (TCR) recognition is a key factor in determining the T-cell immunogenicity of a SARS-CoV-2 epitope. Although several data-driven methods for predicting epitope-specific TCR recognition have been proposed, they remain challenging owing to the enormous diversity of TCRs and the lack of available training data. Self-supervised transfer learning has recently been demonstrated to be powerful for extracting useful information from unlabeled protein sequences and increasing the predictive performance of the fine-tuned models in downstream tasks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we present a predictive model based on Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers (BERT), employing self-supervised transfer learning, to predict SARS-CoV-2 T-cell epitope-specific TCR recognition. The fine-tuned model showed notably high predictive performance for independent evaluation using the SARS-CoV-2 epitope-specific TCR CDR3β sequence datasets. In particular, we found the proline at position 4 corresponding to the &lt;bold&gt;P272L&lt;/bold&gt; mutation in the SARS-CoV-2 &lt;bold&gt;S&lt;/bold&gt;-protein&lt;sub&gt;269-277&lt;/sub&gt; epitope (&lt;bold&gt;YLQPRTFLL&lt;/bold&gt;) may contribute substantially to TCR recognition of the epitope through interpreting the output attention weights of our model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We anticipate that our findings will provide new directions for constructing a reliable data-driven model to predict the immunogenic T-cell epitopes using limited training data and help accelerate the development of an effective vaccine in response to SARS-CoV-2 variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468929" rel="alternate" title="Predicting SARS-CoV-2 epitope-specific TCR recognition using pre-trained protein embeddings (11 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468283</id><title>Mutagenic distinction between the receptor-binding and fusion subunits of the SARS-CoV-2 spike glycoprotein (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.896620+00:00</updated><author><name>Robert Penner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We observe that a residue R of the spike glycoprotein of SARS-CoV-2 which has mutated in one or more of the current Variants of Concern or Interest and under Monitoring rarely participates in a backbone hydrogen bond if R lies in the S&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; subunit and usually participates in one if R lies in the S&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; subunit. A possible explanation for this based upon free energy is explored as a potentially general principle in the mutagenesis of viral glycoproteins. This observation could help target future vaccine cargos for the evolving coronavirus as well as more generally.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468283" rel="alternate" title="Mutagenic distinction between the receptor-binding and fusion subunits of the SARS-CoV-2 spike glycoprotein (10 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.21266408</id><title>HLA-A*03:01 is associated with increased risk of fever, chills, and more severe reaction to Pfizer-BioNTech COVID-19 vaccination (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.896785+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexandre Bolze</name></author><author><name>Iva Neveux</name></author><author><name>Kelly M Schiabor Barrett</name></author><author><name>Simon White</name></author><author><name>Magnus Isaksson</name></author><author><name>Shaun Dabe</name></author><author><name>William Lee</name></author><author><name>Joseph J Grzymski</name></author><author><name>Nicole L Washington</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth T Cirulli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 vaccines are safe and highly effective, but some individuals experience unpleasant reactions to vaccination. As the majority of adults in the US have received a COVID-19 vaccine this year, there is an unprecedented opportunity to study the genetics of reactions to vaccination via surveys of individuals who are already part of genetic research studies. Here, we have queried 17,440 participants in the Helix DNA Discovery Project and Healthy Nevada Project about their reactions to COVID-19 vaccination. Our GWAS identifies an association between severe difficulties with daily routine after vaccination and HLA-A*03:01. This association was statistically significant only for those who received the Pfizer-BioNTech vaccine (BNT162b2; p=4.70E-11), but showed a trending association in those who received the Moderna vaccine (mRNA-1273; p=0.005) despite similar sample sizes for study. In Pfizer-BioNTech recipients, HLA-A*03:01 was associated with a two-fold increase in risk of severe vaccine reactions. The effect was consistent across ages, sexes, and whether the person had previously had a COVID-19 infection. The reactions experienced by HLA-A*03:01 carriers were driven by associations with chills, fever, fatigue, and in general feeling unwell.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.21266408" rel="alternate" title="HLA-A*03:01 is associated with increased risk of fever, chills, and more severe reaction to Pfizer-BioNTech COVID-19 vaccination (10 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468834</id><title>Global Mutational Sweep of SARS-CoV-2: from Chaos to Order (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.897034+00:00</updated><author><name>Xin Wang</name></author><author><name>Mingda Hu</name></author><author><name>Yuan Jin</name></author><author><name>Boqian Wang</name></author><author><name>Yunxiang Zhao</name></author><author><name>Long Liang</name></author><author><name>Junjie Yue</name></author><author><name>Hongguang Ren</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Analysis of large-scale genome sequences demonstrates the mutation of SARS-CoV-2 has been undergoing significant sweeps. Driven by emerging variants, global sweeps are accelerated and purified over time. This may prolong the pandemic with repeating epidemics, presenting challenges to the control and prevention of SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468834" rel="alternate" title="Global Mutational Sweep of SARS-CoV-2: from Chaos to Order (9 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.21266322</id><title>Should we Mitigate or Suppress the next Pandemic? Time-Horizons and Costs shape optimal Social Distancing Strategies (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.899868+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah Nowak</name></author><author><name>Pedro Nascimento de Lima</name></author><author><name>Raffaele Vardavas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic has called for swift action from local governments, which have instated Nonpharmaceutical Interventions (NPIs) to curb the spread of SARS-Cov-2. The quick and decisive decision to save lives through blunt instruments has raised questions about the conditions under which decision-makers should employ mitigation or suppression strategies to tackle the COVID-19 pandemic. More broadly, there are still debates over which set of strategies should be adopted to control different pandemics, and the lessons learned for SARS-Cov-2 may not apply to a new pathogen. While curbing SARS-Cov-2 required blunt instruments, it is unclear whether a less-transmissible and less-deadly emerging pathogen would justify the same response. This paper illuminates this question using a parsimonious transmission model by formulating the social distancing lives vs. livelihoods dilemma as a boundary value problem. In this setup, society balances the costs and benefits of social distancing contingent on the costs of reducing transmission relative to the burden imposed by the disease. To the best of our knowledge, our approach is distinct in the sense that strategies emerge from the problem structure rather than being imposed &lt;italic&gt;a priori&lt;/italic&gt;. We find that the relative time-horizon of the pandemic (i.e., the time it takes to develop effective vaccines and treatments) and the relative cost of social distancing influence the choice of the optimal policy. Unsurprisingly, we find that the appropriate policy response depends on these two factors. We discuss the conditions under which each policy archetype (suppression vs. mitigation) appears to be the most appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.21266322" rel="alternate" title="Should we Mitigate or Suppress the next Pandemic? Time-Horizons and Costs shape optimal Social Distancing Strategies (8 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.21266178</id><title>The challenge of SARS-CoV-2 environmental monitoring in schools using floors and portable HEPA filtration units: Fresh or relic RNA? (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.900145+00:00</updated><author><name>Rogelio Zuniga-Montanez</name></author><author><name>David A. Coil</name></author><author><name>Jonathan A. Eisen</name></author><author><name>Randi Pechacek</name></author><author><name>Roque G. Guerrero</name></author><author><name>Minji Kim</name></author><author><name>Karen Shapiro</name></author><author><name>Heather N. Bischel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Testing surfaces in school classrooms for the presence of SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19, can provide public-health information that complements clinical testing. We monitored the presence of SARS-CoV-2 RNA in five schools (96 classrooms) in Davis, California (USA) by collecting weekly surface-swab samples from classroom floors and/or portable high-efficiency particulate air (HEPA) units. Twenty-two surfaces tested positive, with qPCR cycle threshold (Ct) values ranging from 36.07–38.01. Intermittent repeated positives in a single room were observed for both floor and HEPA filter samples for up to 52 days, even following regular cleaning and HEPA filter replacement after a positive result. We compared the two environmental sampling strategies by testing one floor and two HEPA filter samples in 57 classrooms at Schools D and E. HEPA filter sampling yielded 3.02% and 0.41% positivity rates per filter sample collected for Schools D and E, respectively, while floor sampling yielded 0.48% and 0% positivity rates. Our results indicate that HEPA filter swabs are more sensitive than floor swabs at detecting SARS-CoV-2 RNA in interior spaces. During the study, all schools were offered weekly free COVID-19 clinical testing. On-site clinical testing was offered in Schools D and E, and upticks in testing participation were observed following a confirmed positive environmental sample. However, no confirmed COVID-19 cases were identified among students associated with classrooms yielding positive environmental samples. The positive samples detected in this study appeared to reflect relic viral RNA from individuals infected before the monitoring program started and/or RNA transported into classrooms via fomites. The high-Ct positive results from environmental swabs further suggest the absence of active infections. Additional research is needed to differentiate between fresh and relic SARS-CoV-2 RNA in environmental samples and to determine what types of results should trigger interventions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.21266178" rel="alternate" title="The challenge of SARS-CoV-2 environmental monitoring in schools using floors and portable HEPA filtration units: Fresh or relic RNA? (8 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.21266249</id><title>Early and rapid identification of COVID-19 patients with neutralizing type I-interferon auto-antibodies by an easily implementable algorithm (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.900732+00:00</updated><author><name>Bengisu Akbil</name></author><author><name>Tim Meyer</name></author><author><name>Paula Stubbemann</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Thibeault</name></author><author><name>Olga Staudacher</name></author><author><name>Daniela Niemeyer</name></author><author><name>Jenny Jansen</name></author><author><name>Barbara Mühlemann</name></author><author><name>Jan Doehn</name></author><author><name>Christoph Tabeling</name></author><author><name>Christian Nusshag</name></author><author><name>Cédric Hirzel</name></author><author><name>David Sökler Sanchez</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Nieters</name></author><author><name>Achim Lother</name></author><author><name>Daniel Duerschmied</name></author><author><name>Nils Schallner</name></author><author><name>Jan Nikolaus Lieberum</name></author><author><name>Dietrich August</name></author><author><name>Siegbert Rieg</name></author><author><name>Valeria Falcone</name></author><author><name>Hartmut Hengel</name></author><author><name>Uwe Kölsch</name></author><author><name>Nadine Unterwalder</name></author><author><name>Ralf-Harto Hübner</name></author><author><name>Terry C. Jones</name></author><author><name>Norbert Suttorp</name></author><author><name>Christian Drosten</name></author><author><name>Klaus Warnatz</name></author><author><name>Thibaud Spinetti</name></author><author><name>Joerg C. Schefold</name></author><author><name>Thomas Dörner</name></author><author><name>Leif Sander</name></author><author><name>Victor M. Corman</name></author><author><name>Uta Merle</name></author><author><name>Florian Kurth</name></author><author><name>Horst von Bernuth</name></author><author><name>Christian Meisel</name></author><author><name>Christine Goffinet</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Purpose&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Six-19% of critically ill COVID-19 patients display circulating auto-antibodies against type I interferons (IFN-AABs). Here, we establish a clinically applicable strategy for early identification of IFN-AAB-positive patients for potential subsequent clinical interventions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We analysed sera of 430 COVID-19 patients with severe and critical disease from four hospitals for presence of IFN-AABs by ELISA. Binding specificity and neutralizing activity were evaluated via competition assay and virus-infection-based neutralization assay. We defined clinical parameters associated with IFN-AAB positivity. In a subgroup of critically ill patients, we analyzed effects of therapeutic plasma exchange (TPE) on the levels of IFN-AABs, SARS-CoV-2 antibodies and clinical outcome.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The prevalence of neutralizing AABs to IFN-α and IFN-ω in COVID-19 patients was 4.2% (18/430), while being undetectable in an uninfected control cohort. Neutralizing IFN-AABs were detectable exclusively in critically affected, predominantly male (83%) patients (7.6% IFN-α and 4.6% IFN-ω in 207 patients with critical COVID-19). IFN-AABs were present early post-symptom onset and at the peak of disease. Fever and oxygen requirement at hospital admission co-presented with neutralizing IFN-AAB positivity. IFN-AABs were associated with higher mortality (92.3% versus 19.1 % in patients without IFN-AABs). TPE reduced levels of IFN-AABs in three of five patients and may increase survival of IFN-AAB-positive patients compared to those not undergoing TPE.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;IFN-AABs may serve as early biomarker for development of severe COVID-19. We propose to implement routine screening of hospitalized COVID-19 patients according to our algorithm for rapid identification of patients with IFN-AABs who most likely benefit from specific therapies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.21266249" rel="alternate" title="Early and rapid identification of COVID-19 patients with neutralizing type I-interferon auto-antibodies by an easily implementable algorithm (7 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.21266309</id><title>Safety and immunogenicity of anti-SARS CoV-2 vaccine SOBERANA 02 in homologous or heterologous scheme (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.901584+00:00</updated><author><name>Maria Eugenia-Toledo-Romani</name></author><author><name>Leslihana Verdecia-Sánchez</name></author><author><name>Meybis Rodriguez-González</name></author><author><name>Laura Rodríguez-Noda</name></author><author><name>Carmen Valenzuela-Silva</name></author><author><name>Beatriz Paredes-Moreno</name></author><author><name>Belinda Sanchez-Ramirez</name></author><author><name>Rocmira Perez-Nicado</name></author><author><name>Raul González-Mugica</name></author><author><name>Tays Hernández-Garcia</name></author><author><name>Gretchen Bergado-Baez</name></author><author><name>Franciscary Pi-Estopiñán</name></author><author><name>Otto Cruz-Sui</name></author><author><name>Anitza Fraga-Quintero</name></author><author><name>Majela García-Montero</name></author><author><name>Ariel Palenzuela-Diaz</name></author><author><name>Gerardo Baro-Roman</name></author><author><name>Ivis Mendosa-Hernández</name></author><author><name>Sonsire Fernandez-Castillo</name></author><author><name>Yanet Climent-Ruiz</name></author><author><name>Darielys Santana-Mederos</name></author><author><name>Ubel Ramírez Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Yanelda García-Vega</name></author><author><name>Beatriz Perez-Massón</name></author><author><name> Guang-Wu-Chen</name></author><author><name>Tammy Boggiano-Ayo</name></author><author><name>Eduardo Ojito-Magaz</name></author><author><name>Daniel G. Rivera</name></author><author><name>Yury Valdés-Balbín</name></author><author><name>Dagmar García-Rivera</name></author><author><name>Vicente Vérez-Bencomo</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SOBERANA 02 is a COVID-19 conjugate vaccine candidate based on SARS-CoV-2 recombinant RBD conjugated to tetanus toxoid. SOBERANA Plus antigen is dimeric-RBD. Here we report safety, reactogenicity and immunogenicity from phase I and IIa clinical trials using two-doses SOBERANA 02 (homologous protocol) and three-doses (homologous) or heterologous (with SOBERANA Plus) protocols.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Method&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We performed an open-label, monocentric, sequential and adaptive phase I for evaluating safety, reactogenicity and exploring immunogenicity of SOBERANA 02 in two formulations (15 and 25 μg) in 40 subjects, 19–59 years old. Phase IIa was open-label including 100 volunteers 19–80 years, receiving two doses of SOBERANA 02-25 μg. In both trials, half of volunteers received a third dose of SOBERANA 02, half received a heterologous dose of SOBERANA Plus-50 μg. Primary outcomes were safety and reactogenicity. The secondary outcome was vaccine immunogenicity evaluated by anti-RBD IgG ELISA, molecular neutralization test of RBD:hACE2 interaction, live-virus neutralization test and specific T-cells response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most frequent AE was local pain, other AEs had frequencies ≤ 5%. No serious related AEs were reported. Phase IIa confirmed the safety results in 60–80 years subjects. In phase-I SOBERANA 02-25µg elicited higher immune response than SOBERANA 02-15 µg; in consequence, the higher dose progressed to phase IIa. Phase IIa results confirmed the immunogenicity of SOBERANA 02-25 μg even in 60–80 age range. Two doses of SOBERANA02-25 μg elicited an immune response similar to that of the Cuban Convalescent Serum Panel; it was higher after both the homologous and heterologous third doses; the heterologous scheme showing a higher immunological response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SOBERANA 02 was safe and immunogenic in persons aged 19–80 years, eliciting neutralizing antibodies and specific T cell response. Highest immune responses were obtained in the heterologous three doses protocol. Trial registry: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://rpcec.sld.cu/trials/RPCEC00000340"&gt;https://rpcec.sld.cu/trials/RPCEC00000340&lt;/ext-link&gt; and &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://rpcec.sld.cu/trials/RPCEC00000347"&gt;https://rpcec.sld.cu/trials/RPCEC00000347&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.21266309" rel="alternate" title="Safety and immunogenicity of anti-SARS CoV-2 vaccine SOBERANA 02 in homologous or heterologous scheme (7 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.21266115</id><title>Epithelial RIG-I inflammasome activation suppresses antiviral immunity and promotes inflammatory responses in virus-induced asthma exacerbations and COVID-19 (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.902238+00:00</updated><author><name>U Radzikowska</name></author><author><name>A Eljaszewicz</name></author><author><name>G Tan</name></author><author><name>N Stocker</name></author><author><name>A Heider</name></author><author><name>P Westermann</name></author><author><name>S Steiner</name></author><author><name>A Dreher</name></author><author><name>P Wawrzyniak</name></author><author><name>B Rückert</name></author><author><name>J Rodriguez-Coira</name></author><author><name>D Zhakparov</name></author><author><name>M Huang</name></author><author><name>B Jakiela</name></author><author><name>M Sanak</name></author><author><name>M Moniuszko</name></author><author><name>L O’Mahony</name></author><author><name>T Kebadze</name></author><author><name>DJ Jackson</name></author><author><name>MR Edwards</name></author><author><name>V Thiel</name></author><author><name>SL Johnston</name></author><author><name>CA Akdis</name></author><author><name>M Sokolowska</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Rhinoviruses (RV) and inhaled allergens, such as house dust mite (HDM) are the major agents responsible for asthma onset, its life-threatening exacerbations and progression to severe disease. The role of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) in exacerbations of asthma or the influence of preexisting viral or allergic airway inflammation on the development of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) is largely unknown. To address this, we compared molecular mechanisms of HDM, RV and SARS-CoV-2 interactions in experimental RV infection in patients with asthma and healthy individuals. RV infection was sensed via retinoic acid-inducible gene I (RIG-I) helicase, but not via NLR family pyrin domain containing 3 (NLRP3), which led to subsequent apoptosis-associated speck like protein containing a caspase recruitment domain (ASC) recruitment, oligomerization and RIG-I inflammasome activation. This phenomenon was augmented in bronchial epithelium in patients with asthma, especially upon pre-exposure to HDM, which itself induced a priming step, pro-IL-1&lt;italic&gt;β&lt;/italic&gt; release and early inhibition of RIG-I/TANK binding kinase 1/I&lt;italic&gt;κ&lt;/italic&gt;B kinase &lt;italic&gt;ε&lt;/italic&gt; /type I/III interferons (RIG-I/TBK1/IKK&lt;italic&gt;ε&lt;/italic&gt;/IFN-I/III) responses. Excessive activation of RIG-I inflammasomes was partially responsible for the alteration and persistence of type I/III IFN responses, prolonged viral clearance and unresolved inflammation in asthma. RV/HDM-induced sustained IFN I/III responses initially restricted SARS- CoV-2 replication in epithelium of patients with asthma, but even this limited infection with SARS-CoV-2 augmented RIG-I inflammasome activation. Timely inhibition of the epithelial RIG-I inflammasome and reduction of IL-1&lt;italic&gt;β&lt;/italic&gt; signaling may lead to more efficient viral clearance and lower the burden of RV and SARS- CoV-2 infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.21266115" rel="alternate" title="Epithelial RIG-I inflammasome activation suppresses antiviral immunity and promotes inflammatory responses in virus-induced asthma exacerbations and COVID-19 (6 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.21266289</id><title>AI/ML Models to Aid in the Diagnosis of COVID-19 Illness from Forced Cough Vocalizations: Good Machine Learning Practice and Good Clinical Practices from Concept to Consumer for AI/ML Software Devices (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.902914+00:00</updated><author><name>K. Kelley</name></author><author><name>M. Kelley</name></author><author><name>S. C. Kelley</name></author><author><name>A.A. Sakara</name></author><author><name>M.A. Ramirez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;From a comprehensive and systematic search of the relevant literature on signal data signature (SDS)-based artificial intelligence/machine learning (AI/ML) systems designed to aid in the diagnosis of COVID-19 illness, we identified the highest quality articles with statistically significant data sets for a head-to-head comparison to our own model in development. Further comparisons were made to the recently released “Good Machine Learning Practice (GMLP) for Medical Device Development: Guiding Principles” and, in conclusions, we proposed supplemental principles aimed at bringing AI/ML technologies in closer alignment GMLP and Good Clinical Practices (GCP).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.21266289" rel="alternate" title="AI/ML Models to Aid in the Diagnosis of COVID-19 Illness from Forced Cough Vocalizations: Good Machine Learning Practice and Good Clinical Practices from Concept to Consumer for AI/ML Software Devices (6 tweets)"/><category term="Health Policy"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.21266330</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 Mortality Surveillance among Community Deaths brought to University Teaching Hospital Mortuary in Lusaka, Zambia, 2020 (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.903750+00:00</updated><author><name>Amos Hamukale</name></author><author><name>Jonas Z. Hines</name></author><author><name>Nyambe Sinyange</name></author><author><name>Sombo Fwoloshi</name></author><author><name>Warren Malambo</name></author><author><name>Suilanji Sivile</name></author><author><name>Stephen Chanda</name></author><author><name>Luchenga Adam Mucheleng’anga</name></author><author><name>Nkomba Kayeyi</name></author><author><name>Cordelia Maria Himwaze</name></author><author><name>Aaron Shibemba</name></author><author><name>Tally Leigh</name></author><author><name>Mazyanga L. Mazaba</name></author><author><name>Nathan Kapata</name></author><author><name>Paul Zulu</name></author><author><name>Khozya Zyambo</name></author><author><name>Francis Mupeta</name></author><author><name>Simon Agolory</name></author><author><name>Lloyd B. Mulenga</name></author><author><name>Kennedy Malama</name></author><author><name>Muzala Kapina</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;During March-December 2020, Zambia recorded 20,725 confirmed COVID-19 cases, with the first wave peaking between July and August. Of the 388 COVID-19-related deaths occurring nationwide, most occurred in the community. We report findings from COVID-19 mortality surveillance among community deaths brought to the University Teaching Hospital (UTH) mortuary in Lusaka.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Zambia, when a person dies in the community, and is brought into a health facility mortuary, they are recorded as ‘brought in dead’ (BID). The UTH mortuary accepts persons BID for Lusaka District, the most populated district in Zambia. We analyzed data for persons BID at UTH during 2020. We analyzed two data sources: weekly SARS-CoV-2 test results for persons BID and monthly all-cause mortality numbers among persons BID. For all-cause mortality among persons BID, monthly deaths during 2020 that were above the upper bound of the 95% confidence interval for the historic mean (2017-2019) were considered significant. Spearman’s rank test was used to correlate the overall percent positivity in Zambia with all-cause mortality and SARS-CoV-2 testing among persons BID at UTH mortuary.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;During 2020, 7,756 persons were BID at UTH (monthly range 556-810). SARS-CoV-2 testing began in April 2020, and through December 3,131 (51.9%) of 6,022 persons BID were tested. Of these, 212 (6.8%) were SARS-CoV-2 positive with weekly percent test positivity ranging from 0-32%, with the highest positivity occurring during July 2020. There were 1,139 excess persons BID from all causes at UTH mortuary in 2020 compared to the 2017-2019 mean. The monthly number of persons BID from all causes was above the upper bound of the 95% confidence interval during June-September and December.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Increases in all-cause mortality and SARS-CoV-2 test positivity among persons BID at UTH mortuary corresponded with the first peak of the COVID-19 epidemic in June and August 2020, indicating possible increased mortality related to the COVID-19 epidemic in Zambia. Combining all-cause mortality and SARS-CoV-2 testing for persons BID provides useful information about the severity of the epidemic in Lusaka and should be implemented throughout Zambia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.21266330" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 Mortality Surveillance among Community Deaths brought to University Teaching Hospital Mortuary in Lusaka, Zambia, 2020 (6 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.21266325</id><title>Higher Vaccination Rate Predicts Reduction in SARS-CoV-2 Transmission across the United States (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.904275+00:00</updated><author><name>Jacky Au</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) began proliferating widely throughout the world in late 2019/early 2020, creating a global pandemic and health crisis. Although vaccines became available to the public approximately one year after the onset of the pandemic, there still remains much hesitancy surrounding vaccination even two years into the pandemic. One key concern comes from reports of breakthrough infections among the vaccinated that show comparable levels of peak viral load as the unvaccinated, calling into question the ability of vaccines to slow or prevent transmission. Therefore young, healthy individuals who are at low risk of serious complications themselves have little incentive to receive a vaccine that they are not convinced will protect others around them. To address this important concern, this article analyzes COVID-19 incidence in the United States as a function of each state’s vaccination rate. Results show that states with higher percentages of fully vaccinated individuals report fewer new cases among the remaining unvaccinated population. These data add to accumulating evidence that COVID-19 vaccinations can indeed slow the spread of SARS-CoV-2, and are an important tool in society’s arsenal to put this pandemic behind us.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.21266325" rel="alternate" title="Higher Vaccination Rate Predicts Reduction in SARS-CoV-2 Transmission across the United States (6 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468893</id><title>BSG/CD147 and ACE2 receptors facilitate SARS-CoV-2 infection of human iPS cell-derived kidney podocytes (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.904491+00:00</updated><author><name>Titilola D. Kalejaiye</name></author><author><name>Rohan Bhattacharya</name></author><author><name>Morgan A. Burt</name></author><author><name>Tatianna Travieso</name></author><author><name>Arinze E. Okafor</name></author><author><name>Xingrui Mou</name></author><author><name>Maria Blasi</name></author><author><name>Samira Musah</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) causes the Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), which was declared a pandemic by the World Health Organization (WHO) in March 2020. The disease has caused more than 5.1 million deaths worldwide. While cells in the respiratory system are frequently the initial target for SARS-CoV-2, clinical studies suggest that COVID-19 can become a multi-organ disease in the most severe cases. Still, the direct affinity of SARS-CoV-2 for cells in other organs such as the kidneys, which are often affected in severe COVID-19, remains poorly understood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Method&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this study, we employed a human induced pluripotent stem (iPS) cell-derived model to investigate the affinity of SARS-CoV-2 for kidney glomerular podocytes. We studied uptake of the live SARS-CoV-2 virus as well as pseudotyped viral particles by human iPS cell derived podocytes using qPCR, western blot, and immunofluorescence. Global gene expression and qPCR analyses revealed that human iPS cell-derived podocytes express many host factor genes (including ACE2, BSG/CD147, PLS3, ACTR3, DOCK7, TMPRSS2, CTSL CD209, and CD33) associated with SARS-CoV-2 binding and viral processing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Result&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Infection of podocytes with live SARS-CoV-2 or spike-pseudotyped lentiviral particles revealed viral uptake by the cells at low Multiplicity of Infection (MOI of 0.01) as confirmed by RNA quantification and immunofluorescence studies. Our results also indicate that direct infection of human iPS cell-derived podocytes by SARS-CoV-2 virus can cause cell death and podocyte foot process retraction, a hallmark of podocytopathies and progressive glomerular diseases including collapsing glomerulopathy observed in patients with severe COVID-19 disease. Additionally, antibody blocking experiments identified BSG/CD147 and ACE2 receptors as key mediators of spike binding activity in human iPS cell-derived podocytes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;These results show that SARS-CoV-2 can infect kidney glomerular podocytes &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. These results also show that the uptake of SARS-CoV-2 by kidney podocytes occurs via multiple binding interactions and partners, which may underlie the high affinity of SARS-CoV-2 for kidney tissues. This stem cell-derived model is potentially useful for kidney-specific antiviral drug screening and mechanistic studies of COVID-19 organotropism.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significant statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many patients with COVID19 disease exhibit multiorgan complications, suggesting that SARS-CoV-2 infection can extend beyond the respiratory system. Acute kidney injury is a common COVID-19 complication contributing to increased morbidity and mortality. Still, SARS-Cov-2 affinity for specialized kidney cells remain less clear. By leveraging our protocol for stem cell differentiation, we show that SARS-CoV-2 can directly infect kidney glomerular podocytes by using multiple Spike-binding proteins including ACE2 and BSG/CD147. Our results also indicate that infection by SARS-CoV-2 virus can cause podocyte cell death and foot process effacement, a hallmark of podocytopathies including collapsing glomerulopathy observed in patients with severe COVID-19 disease. This stem cell-derived model is potentially useful for kidney-specific antiviral drug screening and mechanistic studies of COVID-19 organotropism.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468893" rel="alternate" title="BSG/CD147 and ACE2 receptors facilitate SARS-CoV-2 infection of human iPS cell-derived kidney podocytes (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468720</id><title>Susceptibility of sheep to experimental co-infection with the ancestral lineage of SARS-CoV-2 and its alpha variant (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.904773+00:00</updated><author><name>Natasha N. Gaudreault</name></author><author><name>Konner Cool</name></author><author><name>Jessie D. Trujillo</name></author><author><name>Igor Morozov</name></author><author><name>David A. Meekins</name></author><author><name>Chester McDowell</name></author><author><name>Dashzeveg Bold</name></author><author><name>Mariano Carossino</name></author><author><name>Velmurugan Balaraman</name></author><author><name>Dana Mitzel</name></author><author><name>Taeyong Kwon</name></author><author><name>Daniel W. Madden</name></author><author><name>Bianca Libanori Artiaga</name></author><author><name>Roman M. Pogranichniy</name></author><author><name>Gleyder Roman-Sosa</name></author><author><name>William C. Wilson</name></author><author><name>Udeni B. R. Balasuriya</name></author><author><name>Adolfo García-Sastre</name></author><author><name>Juergen A. Richt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) is responsible for a global pandemic that has had significant impacts on human health and economies worldwide. SARS-CoV-2 is highly transmissible and the cause of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) in humans. A wide range of animal species have also been shown to be susceptible to SARS-CoV-2 infection by experimental and/or natural infections. Domestic and large cats, mink, ferrets, hamsters, deer mice, white-tailed deer, and non-human primates have been shown to be highly susceptible, whereas other species such as mice, dogs, pigs, and cattle appear to be refractory to infection or have very limited susceptibility. Sheep (&lt;italic&gt;Ovis aries&lt;/italic&gt;) are a commonly farmed domestic ruminant that have not previously been thoroughly investigated for their susceptibility to SARS-CoV-2. Therefore, we performed &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; studies which consisted of infection of ruminant-derived cell cultures and experimental challenge of sheep to investigate their susceptibility to SARS-CoV-2. Our results showed that sheep-derived cell cultures support SARS-CoV-2 replication. Furthermore, experimental challenge of sheep demonstrated limited infection with viral RNA shed in nasal and oral swabs primarily at 1-day post challenge (DPC), and also detected in the respiratory tract and lymphoid tissues at 4 and 8 DPC. Sero-reactivity was also observed in some of the principal infected sheep but not the contact sentinels, indicating that transmission to co-mingled naïve sheep was not highly efficient; however, viral RNA was detected in some of the respiratory tract tissues of sentinel animals at 21 DPC. Furthermore, we used challenge inoculum consisting of a mixture of two SARS-CoV-2 isolates, representatives of the ancestral lineage A and the B.1.1.7-like alpha variant of concern (VOC), to study competition of the two virus strains. Our results indicate that sheep show low susceptibility to SARS-CoV-2 infection, and that the alpha VOC outcompeted the ancestral lineage A strain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468720" rel="alternate" title="Susceptibility of sheep to experimental co-infection with the ancestral lineage of SARS-CoV-2 and its alpha variant (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.21266481</id><title>Effects of trust, risk perception, and health behavior on COVID-19 disease burden: Evidence from a multi-state US survey (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.906561+00:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin J. Ridenhour</name></author><author><name>Dilshani Sarathchandra</name></author><author><name>Erich Seamon</name></author><author><name>Helen Brown</name></author><author><name>Fok-Yan Leung</name></author><author><name>Maureen Johnson-Leon</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Megheib</name></author><author><name>Craig R. Miller</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Johnson-Leung</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Early public health strategies to prevent the spread of COVID-19 in the United States relied on non-pharmaceutical interventions (NPIs) as vaccines and therapeutic treatments were not yet available. Implementation of NPIs, primarily social distancing and mask wearing, varied widely between communities within the US due to variable government mandates, as well as differences in attitudes and opinions. To understand the interplay of trust, risk perception, behavioral intention, and disease burden, we developed a survey instrument to study attitudes concerning COVID-19 and pandemic behavioral change in three states: Idaho, Texas, and Vermont. We designed our survey (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; = 1034) to detect whether these relationships were significantly different in rural populations. The best fitting structural equation models show that trust indirectly affects protective pandemic behaviors via health and economic risk perception. We explore two different variations of this social cognitive model: the first assumes behavioral intention affects future disease burden while the second assumes that observed disease burden affects behavioral intention. In our models we include several exogenous variables to control for demographic and geographic effects. Notably, political ideology is the only exogenous variable which significantly affects all aspects of the social cognitive model (trust, risk perception, and behavioral intention). While there is a direct negative effect associated with rurality on disease burden, likely due to the protective effect of low population density in the early pandemic waves, we found a marginally significant, positive, indirect effect of rurality on disease burden via decreased trust (&lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt; = 0.095). This trust deficit creates additional vulnerabilities to COVID-19 in rural communities which also have reduced healthcare capacity. Increasing trust by methods such as in-group messaging could potentially remove some of the disparities inferred by our models and increase NPI effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.21266481" rel="alternate" title="Effects of trust, risk perception, and health behavior on COVID-19 disease burden: Evidence from a multi-state US survey (4 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.21266286</id><title>CAN A MACHINE LEARNING ALGORITHM IDENTIFY SARS-COV-2 VARIANTS BASED ON CONVENTIONAL rRT-PCR? PROOF OF CONCEPT (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.907206+00:00</updated><author><name>Jorge Cabrera Alvargonzález</name></author><author><name>Ana Larrañaga Janeiro</name></author><author><name>Sonia Pérez Castro</name></author><author><name>Javier Martínez Torres</name></author><author><name>Lucía Martínez Lamas</name></author><author><name>Carlos Daviña Nuñez</name></author><author><name>Víctor Del Campo-Pérez</name></author><author><name>Silvia Suarez Luque</name></author><author><name>Benito Regueiro García</name></author><author><name>Jacobo Porteiro Fresco</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) has been and remains one of the major challenges humanity has faced thus far. Over the past few months, large amounts of information have been collected that are only now beginning to be assimilated. In the present work, the existence of residual information in the massive numbers of rRT-PCRs that tested positive out of the almost half a million tests that were performed during the pandemic is investigated. This residual information is believed to be highly related to a pattern in the number of cycles that are necessary to detect positive samples as such. Thus, a database of more than 20,000 positive samples was collected, and two supervised classification algorithms (a support vector machine and a neural network) were trained to temporally locate each sample based solely and exclusively on the number of cycles determined in the rRT-PCR of each individual. Finally, the results obtained from the classification show how the appearance of each wave is coincident with the surge of each of the variants present in the region of Galicia (Spain) during the development of the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic and clearly identified with the classification algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.21266286" rel="alternate" title="CAN A MACHINE LEARNING ALGORITHM IDENTIFY SARS-COV-2 VARIANTS BASED ON CONVENTIONAL rRT-PCR? PROOF OF CONCEPT (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.21266338</id><title>Comparative analysis of antibody production by mRNA 1273, AZD 1222 and BBIBP-CorV on elderly people suffering from different co-morbidity in Bangladesh (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.907566+00:00</updated><author><name>Ashraful Hoque</name></author><author><name>Md Marufur Rahman</name></author><author><name>Shahnewaz Parvez</name></author><author><name>Hossain Imam</name></author><author><name>Nurun Nahar</name></author><author><name>Forhad Uddin Hasan Chowdhury</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the pandemic spread so quickly all over the world, the scientist did not get the right time to cover all age group populations for a vaccine trial. The elderly population is usually vulnerable for COVID-19 which was proven by different research work and focus was to save this group of people was the prime concern for every country of the world. Though vaccines that got emergency use authorization have proven their efficacy which one is better for elderly people suffering from different co-morbid conditions is still not established. In this study, we want to evaluate the antibody production by mRNA 1273, AZD 1222, and BBIBP-CorV in elderly people with different comorbidity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Method&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We include 40 people in each group who have at least one comorbid condition and the total sample size was 120. The sample was taken from them before vaccination and 14 days after the second dose. Adverse event following immunization was recorded if any. Antibody measurement was done by ELISA method by using DiaSino SARS-CoV-2 S1 RBD IgG Quant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Result&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among 120 participants with an equal number of participants in each of the vaccine groups all of them were aged between 60-72 years, of whom 65% were males and 35 % were females. Anti S1 RBD IgG was detected among all the participants from each vaccine group after 14 days of taking their 2nd dose. A non-parametric multiple comparison test (Kruskal-Wallis test) of Anti S1 RBD IgG levels among three vaccine groups revealed significant differences (P-value &amp;lt;0.05) between groups. The IgG level was almost twice in the mRNA-1273 group (mean 577.1± 44.33 AU/ml) compared to AZD1222(mean 308.5 ±37.91 AU/ml) and BBIBP-CorV group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;From this small sample size, we predicate that mRNA 1273 produce much higher anti-S1 RBD IgG than the other two vaccines. Every vaccine is safe and effective whose is approved by WHO. Calculative use of the vaccine may produce an outcome for the future as we are still way behind in the proper amount of vaccine production.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.21266338" rel="alternate" title="Comparative analysis of antibody production by mRNA 1273, AZD 1222 and BBIBP-CorV on elderly people suffering from different co-morbidity in Bangladesh (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.21265797</id><title>Curating, collecting, and cataloguing global COVID-19 datasets for the aim of predicting personalized risk (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.907916+00:00</updated><author><name>Sepehr Golriz Khatami</name></author><author><name>Maria Francesca Russo</name></author><author><name>Daniel Domingo-Fernández</name></author><author><name>Andrea Zaliani</name></author><author><name>Sarah Mubeen</name></author><author><name>Yojana Gadiya</name></author><author><name>Astghik Sargsyan</name></author><author><name>Reagon Karki</name></author><author><name>Stephan Gebel</name></author><author><name>Ram Kumar Ruppa Surulinathan</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Lage-Rupprecht</name></author><author><name>Saulius Archipovas</name></author><author><name>Geltrude Mingrone</name></author><author><name>Marc Jacobs</name></author><author><name>Carsten Claussen</name></author><author><name>Martin Hofmann-Apitius</name></author><author><name>Alpha Tom Kodamullil</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 data catalogue is a repository that provides a landscape view of COVID-19 studies and datasets as a putative source to enable researchers to develop personalized COVID-19 predictive risk models. The COVID-19 data catalogue currently contains over 400 studies and their relevant information collected from a wide range of global sources such as global initiatives, clinical trial repositories, publications and data repositories. Further, the curated content stored in this data catalogue is complemented by a web application, providing visualizations of these studies, including their references, relevant information such as measured variables, and the geographical locations of where these studies were performed. This resource is one of the first to capture, organize and store studies, datasets and metadata in the area of COVID-19 in a comprehensive repository. We are convinced that our work will facilitate future research and development of personalized predictive risk models of COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.21265797" rel="alternate" title="Curating, collecting, and cataloguing global COVID-19 datasets for the aim of predicting personalized risk (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469098</id><title>Mechanistic insights into global suppressors of protein folding defects (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.908352+00:00</updated><author><name>Gopinath Chattopadhyay</name></author><author><name>Jayantika Bhowmick</name></author><author><name>Kavyashree Manjunath</name></author><author><name>Shahbaz Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Parveen Goyal</name></author><author><name>Raghavan Varadarajan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Most amino acid substitutions in a protein either lead to partial loss of function or are near neutral. Several studies have shown the existence of second-site mutations that can rescue defects caused by diverse loss of function mutations. Such global suppressor mutations are key drivers of protein evolution. However, the mechanisms responsible for such suppression remain poorly understood. To address this, we characterized multiple suppressor mutations both in isolation and in combination with inactive mutants. We examined five global suppressors of the bacterial toxin CcdB, the known M182T global suppressor of TEM-1 β-lactamase, the N239Y global suppressor of p53-DBD and three suppressors of the SARS-CoV-2 spike Receptor Binding Domain. The suppressors both alone, and in conjunction with inactive mutants, stabilise the protein both thermodynamically and kinetically in-vitro, predominantly through acceleration of the refolding rate parameters. When coupled to inactive mutants they promote increased in-vivo solubilities as well as regain-of-function phenotypes. Our study also demonstrates that the global suppressor approach can be used to consistently stabilise wild-type proteins, including for downstream translational applications.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469098" rel="alternate" title="Mechanistic insights into global suppressors of protein folding defects (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.21266532</id><title>Monitoring of SARS-CoV-2 Antibodies Using Dried Blood Spot for At-Home Collection (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.908670+00:00</updated><author><name>Peyton K. Miesse</name></author><author><name>Bradley B. Collier</name></author><author><name>Russell P. Grant</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The utilization of vaccines to fight the spread of SARS-CoV-2 has led to a growing need for expansive serological testing. To address this, an EUA approved immunoassay for detection of antibodies to SARS-CoV-2 in venous serum samples was investigated for use with dried blood spot (DBS) samples. Results from self-collected DBS samples demonstrated a 98.1% categorical agreement to venous serum with a correlation (R) of 0.9600 while professionally collected DBS samples demonstrated a categorical agreement of 100.0% with a correlation of 0.9888 to venous serum. Additional studies were performed to stress aspects of at-home DBS collection, including shipping stability, interference effects, and other sample-specific robustness studies. These studies demonstrated a categorical agreement of at least 95.0% and a mean bias less than ±20.0%. Furthermore, the ability to track antibody levels following vaccination with the BioNTech/Pfizer vaccine was demonstrated with self-collected DBS samples from pre-dose (Day 0) out to 19 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.21266532" rel="alternate" title="Monitoring of SARS-CoV-2 Antibodies Using Dried Blood Spot for At-Home Collection (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.21266051</id><title>The unmitigated profile of COVID-19 infectiousness (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.908898+00:00</updated><author><name>Ron Sender</name></author><author><name>Yinon M. Bar-On</name></author><author><name>Sang Woo Park</name></author><author><name>Elad Noor</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Dushoffd</name></author><author><name>Ron Milo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Quantifying the temporal dynamics of infectiousness of individuals infected with SARS-CoV-2 is crucial for understanding the spread of the COVID-19 pandemic and for analyzing the effectiveness of different mitigation strategies. Many studies have tried to use data from the onset of symptoms of infector-infectee pairs to estimate the infectiousness profile of SARS-CoV-2. However, both statistical and epidemiological biases in the data could lead to an underestimation of the duration of infectiousness. We correct for these biases by curating data from the initial outbreak of the pandemic in China (when mitigation steps were still minimal), and find that the infectiousness profile is wider than previously thought. For example, our estimate for the proportion of transmissions occurring 14 days or more after infection is an order of magnitude higher - namely 19% (95% CI 10%-25%). The inferred generation interval distribution is sensitive to the definition of the period of unmitigated transmission, but estimates that rely on later periods are less reliable due to intervention effects. Nonetheless, the results are robust to other factors such as the model, the assumed growth rate and possible bias of the dataset. Knowing the unmitigated infectiousness profile of infected individuals affects estimates of the effectiveness of self-isolation and quarantine of contacts. The framework presented here can help design better quarantine policies in early stages of future epidemics using data from the initial stages of transmission.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.21266051" rel="alternate" title="The unmitigated profile of COVID-19 infectiousness (3 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>