<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:43.885608+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462488</id><title>Durability of immune responses to the BNT162b2 mRNA vaccine (423 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:43.887153+00:00</updated><author><name>Mehul S. Suthar</name></author><author><name>Prabhu S. Arunachalam</name></author><author><name>Mengyun Hu</name></author><author><name>Noah Reis</name></author><author><name>Meera Trisal</name></author><author><name>Olivia Raeber</name></author><author><name>Sharon Chinthrajah</name></author><author><name>Meredith E. Davis-Gardner</name></author><author><name>Kelly Manning</name></author><author><name>Prakriti Mudvari</name></author><author><name>Eli Boritz</name></author><author><name>Sucheta Godbole</name></author><author><name>Amy R. Henry</name></author><author><name>Daniel C. Douek</name></author><author><name>Peter Halfmann</name></author><author><name>Yoshihiro Kawaoka</name></author><author><name>Veronika I. Zarnitsyna</name></author><author><name>Kari Nadeau</name></author><author><name>Bali Pulendran</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The development of the highly efficacious mRNA vaccines in less than a year since the emergence of SARS-CoV-2 represents a landmark in vaccinology. However, reports of waning vaccine efficacy, coupled with the emergence of variants of concern that are resistant to antibody neutralization, have raised concerns about the potential lack of durability of immunity to vaccination. We recently reported findings from a comprehensive analysis of innate and adaptive immune responses in 56 healthy volunteers who received two doses of the BNT162b2 vaccination. Here, we analyzed antibody responses to the homologous Wu strain as well as several variants of concern, including the emerging Mu (B.1.621) variant, and T cell responses in a subset of these volunteers at six months (day 210 post-primary vaccination) after the second dose. Our data demonstrate a substantial waning of antibody responses and T cell immunity to SARS-CoV-2 and its variants, at 6 months following the second immunization with the BNT162b2 vaccine. Notably, a significant proportion of vaccinees have neutralizing titers below the detection limit, and suggest a 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; booster immunization might be warranted to enhance the antibody titers and T cell responses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462488" rel="alternate" title="Durability of immune responses to the BNT162b2 mRNA vaccine (423 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.21264325</id><title>Assessing the Burden of COVID-19 in Developing Countries: Systematic Review, Meta-Analysis, and Public Policy Implications (220 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:43.887989+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew Levin</name></author><author><name>Nana Owusu-Boaitey</name></author><author><name>Sierra Pugh</name></author><author><name>Bailey K. Fosdick</name></author><author><name>Anthony B. Zwi</name></author><author><name>Anup Malani</name></author><author><name>Satej Soman</name></author><author><name>Lonni Besançon</name></author><author><name>Ilya Kashnitsky</name></author><author><name>Sachin Ganesh</name></author><author><name>Aloysius McLaughlin</name></author><author><name>Gayeong Song</name></author><author><name>Rine Uhm</name></author><author><name>Gideon Meyerowitz-Katz</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The infection-fatality rate (IFR) of COVID-19 has been carefully measured and analyzed in high-income countries, whereas there has been no systematic analysis of age-specific seroprevalence or IFR for developing countries. Indeed, it has been suggested that the death rate in developing countries may be far lower than in high-income countries—an outcome that would be starkly different from the typical pattern for many other infectious diseases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We systematically reviewed the literature to identify all serology studies in developing countries that were conducted using representative samples of specimens collected by early 2021. For each of the antibody assays used in these serology studies, we identified data on assay characteristics, including the extent of seroreversion over time. We analyzed the serology data using a Bayesian model that incorporates conventional sampling uncertainty as well as uncertainties about assay sensitivity and specificity. We then calculated IFRs using individual case reports or aggregated public health updates, including age-specific estimates whenever feasible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seroprevalence in many developing country locations was markedly higher than in high-income countries but still far short of herd immunity. In most locations, seroprevalence among older adults was similar to that of younger age-groups. Age-specific IFRs were 1.3-2.5x higher than in high-income countries. The median value of population IFR was 0.5% among developing countries with satisfactory death reporting as of 2016, compared to a median of 0.05% for other developing countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The burden of COVID-19 is far higher in developing countries than in high-income countries, reflecting a combination of elevated transmission to middle-aged and older adults as well as limited access to adequate healthcare. These results underscore the critical need to accelerate the provision of vaccine doses to vulnerable populations in developing countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key Points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="simple"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;‐&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Age-specific prevalence and infection fatality rate (IFR) of COVID-19 for developing countries has not been well assessed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;‐&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seroprevalence in developing countries (as measured by antibodies against SARS-CoV-2) is markedly higher than in high-income countries but still far short of herd immunity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;‐&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seroprevalence among older adults is broadly similar to that of younger age-groups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;‐&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Age-specific IFRs in developing countries are roughly twice those of high-income countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;‐&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Population IFR in developing countries with satisfactory death reporting (based on UN/WHO data as of 2016) is ten times higher than in other developing countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;‐&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;These results underscore the urgency of disseminating vaccines to vulnerable people in developing countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.21264325" rel="alternate" title="Assessing the Burden of COVID-19 in Developing Countries: Systematic Review, Meta-Analysis, and Public Policy Implications (220 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.21264363</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 infections elicit higher levels of original antigenic sin antibodies compared to SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccinations (197 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:43.888804+00:00</updated><author><name>Elizabeth M. Anderson</name></author><author><name>Theresa Eilola</name></author><author><name>Eileen Goodwin</name></author><author><name>Marcus J. Bolton</name></author><author><name>Sigrid Gouma</name></author><author><name>Rishi R. Goel</name></author><author><name>Mark M. Painter</name></author><author><name>Sokratis A. Apostolidis</name></author><author><name>Divij Mathew</name></author><author><name>Debora Dunbar</name></author><author><name>Danielle Fiore</name></author><author><name>Amanda Brock</name></author><author><name>JoEllen Weaver</name></author><author><name>John S. Millar</name></author><author><name>Stephanie DerOhannessian</name></author><author><name>Allison R. Greenplate</name></author><author><name>Ian Frank</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Rader</name></author><author><name>E. John Wherry</name></author><author><name>Scott E. Hensley</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) mRNA vaccines elicit higher levels of antibodies compared to natural SARS-CoV-2 infections in most individuals; however, the specificities of antibodies elicited by vaccination versus infection remain incompletely understood. Here, we characterized the magnitude and specificity of SARS-CoV-2 spike-reactive antibodies from 10 acutely infected health care workers and 23 participants who received mRNA-based SARS-CoV-2 vaccines. We found that infection and primary mRNA vaccination elicited S1 and S2-reactive antibodies, while secondary vaccination boosted mostly S1 antibodies. Using magnetic bead-based absorption assays, we found that SARS-CoV-2 infections elicited a large proportion of original antigenic sin-like antibodies that bound efficiently to common seasonal human coronaviruses but poorly to SARS-CoV-2. In converse, vaccination only modestly boosted antibodies reactive to common seasonal human coronaviruses and these antibodies bound efficiently to SARS-CoV-2. Our data indicate that SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccinations elicit fundamentally different antibody responses compared to SARS-CoV-2 infections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract Figure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="21264363v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;HIGHLIGHTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccines elicit higher levels of antibodies compared to SARS-CoV-2 infections&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first dose of an mRNA vaccine generates both S1 and S2 responses while the second dose boosts primarily S1-specific antibodies&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 infections, but not mRNA vaccinations, elicit high levels of antibodies that bind strongly to seasonal coronaviruses but weakly to SARS-CoV-2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.21264363" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 infections elicit higher levels of original antigenic sin antibodies compared to SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccinations (197 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.21264272</id><title>Associations between SARS-CoV-2 variants and risk of COVID-19 hospitalization among confirmed cases in Washington State: a retrospective cohort study (145 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:43.889658+00:00</updated><author><name>Miguel I. Paredes</name></author><author><name>Stephanie M. Lunn</name></author><author><name>Michael Famulare</name></author><author><name>Lauren A. Frisbie</name></author><author><name>Ian Painter</name></author><author><name>Roy Burstein</name></author><author><name>Pavitra Roychoudhury</name></author><author><name>Hong Xie</name></author><author><name>Shah A. Mohamed Bakhash</name></author><author><name>Ricardo Perez</name></author><author><name>Maria Lukes</name></author><author><name>Sean Ellis</name></author><author><name>Saraswathi Sathees</name></author><author><name>Patrick Mathias</name></author><author><name>Alexander Greninger</name></author><author><name>Lea M. Starita</name></author><author><name>Chris D. Frazar</name></author><author><name>Erica Ryke</name></author><author><name>Weizhi Zhong</name></author><author><name>Luis Gamboa</name></author><author><name>Machiko Threlkeld</name></author><author><name>Jover Lee</name></author><author><name>Deborah A. Nickerson</name></author><author><name>Daniel L. Bates</name></author><author><name>Matthew E. Hartman</name></author><author><name>Eric Haugen</name></author><author><name>Truong N. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Joshua D. Richards</name></author><author><name>Jacob L. Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>John A. Stamatoyannopoulos</name></author><author><name>Eric Thorland</name></author><author><name>Geoff Melly</name></author><author><name>Philip E. Dykema</name></author><author><name>Drew C. MacKellar</name></author><author><name>Hannah K. Gray</name></author><author><name>Avi Singh</name></author><author><name>JohnAric MoonDance Peterson</name></author><author><name>Denny Russell</name></author><author><name>Laura Marcela Torres</name></author><author><name>Scott Lindquist</name></author><author><name>Trevor Bedford</name></author><author><name>Krisandra J. Allen</name></author><author><name>Hanna N. Oltean</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic is now dominated by variant lineages; the resulting impact on disease severity remains unclear. Using a retrospective cohort study, we assessed the risk of hospitalization following infection with nine variants of concern or interest (VOC/VOI).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our study includes individuals with positive SARS-CoV-2 RT-PCR in the Washington Disease Reporting System and with available viral genome data, from December 1, 2020 to July 30, 2021. The main analysis was restricted to cases with specimens collected through sentinel surveillance. Using a Cox proportional hazards model with mixed effects, we estimated hazard ratios (HR) for the risk of hospitalization following infection with a VOC/VOI, adjusting for age, sex, and vaccination status.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of the 27,814 cases, 23,170 (83.3%) were sequenced through sentinel surveillance, of which 726 (3.1%) were hospitalized due to COVID-19. Higher hospitalization risk was found for infections with Gamma (HR 3.17, 95% CI 2.15-4.67), Beta (HR: 2.97, 95% CI 1.65–5.35), Delta (HR: 2.30, 95% CI 1.69-3.15), and Alpha (HR 1.59, 95% CI 1.26–1.99) compared to infections with an ancestral lineage. Following VOC infection, unvaccinated patients show a similar higher hospitalization risk, while vaccinated patients show no significant difference in risk, both when compared to unvaccinated, ancestral lineage cases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Infection with a VOC results in a higher hospitalization risk, with an active vaccination attenuating that risk. Our findings support promoting hospital preparedness, vaccination, and robust genomic surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.21264272" rel="alternate" title="Associations between SARS-CoV-2 variants and risk of COVID-19 hospitalization among confirmed cases in Washington State: a retrospective cohort study (145 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.21264376</id><title>Estimates of pandemic excess mortality in India based on civil registration data (42 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:43.890236+00:00</updated><author><name>Murad Banaji</name></author><author><name>Aashish Gupta</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic has had large impacts on population health. These impacts are less well understood in low-and middle-income countries, where mortality surveillance before the pandemic was patchy. Although limited all-cause mortality data are available in India, interpreting this data remains a challenge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We use existing data on all-cause mortality from civil registration systems of twelve Indian states comprising around 60% of the national population to understand the scale and timing of excess deaths in India during the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We characterize the available data, discuss the various reasons why these data are incomplete, and estimate the extent of coverage in the data. Comparing the pandemic period to 2019, we estimate excess mortality in twelve Indian states, and extrapolate our estimates to the rest of India. We explore sensitivity of the estimates to various assumptions, and present optimistic and pessimistic scenarios along with our central estimates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the 12 states with available all-cause mortality data, we document an increase of 28% in deaths during April 2020-May 2021 relative to expectations from 2019. This level of increase in mortality, if it applies nationally, would imply 2.8-2.9 million excess deaths. More limited data from June 2021 increases national estimates of excess deaths during April 2020-June 2021 to 3.8 million. With more optimistic or pessimistic assumptions, excess deaths during this period could credibly lie between 2.8 million and 5.2 million. We find that the scale of estimated excess deaths is broadly consistent with expectations based on seroprevalence data and international data on COVID-19 fatality rates. Moreover, there is a strong association between the timing of excess deaths, and of recorded COVID-19 deaths.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contribution&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We show that the surveillance of pandemic mortality in India has been extremely poor, with around 8-10 times as many excess deaths as officially recorded COVID-19 deaths. Our findings highlight the utility of all-cause mortality data, as well as the significant challenges in interpreting such data from LMICs. These data reveal that India is among the countries most severely impacted by the pandemic. It is likely that in absolute terms India has seen the highest number of pandemic excess deaths of any country in the world.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.21264376" rel="alternate" title="Estimates of pandemic excess mortality in India based on civil registration data (42 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.21263801</id><title>Analysis of overdispersion in airborne transmission of Covid-19 (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:43.890512+00:00</updated><author><name>Swetaprovo Chaudhuri</name></author><author><name>Prasad Kasibhatla</name></author><author><name>Arnab Mukherjee</name></author><author><name>William Pan</name></author><author><name>Glenn Morrison</name></author><author><name>Sharmistha Mishra</name></author><author><name>Vijaya Kumar Murty</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Superspreading events and overdispersion are hallmarks of the Covid-19 pandemic. To gain insight into the nature and controlling factors of these superspreading events and heterogeneity in transmission, we conducted mechanistic modeling of SARS-CoV-2 transmission by infectious aerosols using real-world occupancy data from a large number of full-service restaurants in ten US metropolises. Including a large number of factors that influence disease transmission in these settings, we demonstrate the emergence of a stretched tail in the probability density function of secondary infection numbers indicating strong heterogeneity in individual infectivity. Derived analytical results further demonstrate that variability in viral loads and variability in occupancy, together, lead to overdispersion in the number of secondary infections arising from individual index cases. Our analysis, connecting mechanistic understanding of SARS-CoV-2 transmission by aerosols with observed large-scale epidemiological characteristics of Covid-19 outbreaks, adds an important dimension to the mounting body of evidence with regards to the determinants of airborne transmission of SARS-CoV-2 by aerosols in indoor settings.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.21263801" rel="alternate" title="Analysis of overdispersion in airborne transmission of Covid-19 (30 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462449</id><title>Pyronaridine Protects Against SARS-CoV-2 in Mouse (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:43.890957+00:00</updated><author><name>Ana C. Puhl</name></author><author><name>Giovanni F. Gomes</name></author><author><name>Samara Damasceno</name></author><author><name>Andre S. Godoy</name></author><author><name>Gabriela D. Noske</name></author><author><name>Aline M. Nakamura</name></author><author><name>Victor O. Gawriljuk</name></author><author><name>Rafaela S. Fernandes</name></author><author><name>Natalia Monakhova</name></author><author><name>Olga Riabova</name></author><author><name>Thomas R. Lane</name></author><author><name>Vadim Makarov</name></author><author><name>Flavio P. Veras</name></author><author><name>Sabrina S. Batah</name></author><author><name>Alexandre T. Fabro</name></author><author><name>Glaucius Oliva</name></author><author><name>Fernando Q. Cunha</name></author><author><name>José C. Alves-Filho</name></author><author><name>Thiago M. Cunha</name></author><author><name>Sean Ekins</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;There are currently relatively few small-molecule antiviral drugs that are either approved or emergency approved for use against SARS-CoV-2. One of these is remdesivir, which was originally repurposed from its use against Ebola and functions by causing early RNA chain termination. We used this as justification to evaluate three molecules we had previously identified computationally with antiviral activity against Ebola and Marburg. Out of these we previously identified pyronaridine, which inhibited the SARS-CoV-2 replication in A549-ACE2 cells. Herein, the &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; efficacy of pyronaridine has now been assessed in a K18-hACE transgenic mouse model of COVID-19. Pyronaridine treatment demonstrated a statistically significant reduction of viral load in the lungs of SARS CoV-2 infected mice. Furthermore, the pyronaridine treated group reduced lung pathology, which was also associated with significant reduction in the levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines/chemokine and cell infiltration. Notably, pyronaridine inhibited the viral PL&lt;sup&gt;pro&lt;/sup&gt; activity &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; (IC&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; of 1.8 µM) without any effect on M&lt;sup&gt;pro&lt;/sup&gt;, indicating a possible molecular mechanism involved in its ability to inhibit SARS-CoV-2 replication. Interestingly, pyronaridine also selectively inhibits the host kinase CAMK1 (IC&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; of 2.4 µM). We have also generated several pyronaridine analogs to assist in understanding the structure activity relationship for PL&lt;sup&gt;pro&lt;/sup&gt; inhibition. Our results indicate that pyronaridine is a potential therapeutic candidate for COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is currently intense interest in discovering small molecules with direct antiviral activity against the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-Cov-2). Pyronaridine, an antiviral drug with in vitro activity against Ebola, Marburg and SARS-CoV-2 has now statistically significantly reduced the viral load in mice along with IL-6, TNF-α, and IFN-β ultimately demonstrating a protective effect against lung damage by infection to provide a new potential treatment for testing clinically.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462449" rel="alternate" title="Pyronaridine Protects Against SARS-CoV-2 in Mouse (14 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.21264089</id><title>Immune Memory Response After a Booster Injection of mRNA-1273 for Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:43.891434+00:00</updated><author><name>Laurence Chu</name></author><author><name>David Montefiori</name></author><author><name>Wenmei Huang</name></author><author><name>Biliana Nestorova</name></author><author><name>Ying Chang</name></author><author><name>Andrea Carfi</name></author><author><name>Darin K. Edwards</name></author><author><name>Judy Oestreicher</name></author><author><name>Holly Legault</name></author><author><name>Bethany Girard</name></author><author><name>Rolando Pajon</name></author><author><name>Jacqueline M. Miller</name></author><author><name>Rituparna Das</name></author><author><name>Brett Leav</name></author><author><name>Roderick McPhee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Rising breakthrough infections of coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) in previously immunized individuals has raised concerns for a booster to combat suspected waning immunity and new variants. Participants immunized 6-8 months earlier with a primary series of two doses of 50 or 100 µg of mRNA-1273 were administered a booster injection of 50 µg of mRNA-1273. Neutralizing antibody levels against wild-type virus and the Delta variant at one month after the booster were 1.7-fold and 2.1-fold higher, respectively, than those 28 days post primary series second injection indicating an immune memory response. The reactogenicity after the booster dose was similar to that after the second dose in the primary series of two doses of mRNA-1273 (50 or 100 µg) with no serious adverse events reported in the one-month follow-up period. These results demonstrate that a booster injection of mRNA-1273 in previously immunized individuals stimulated an immune response greater than the primary vaccination series.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.21264089" rel="alternate" title="Immune Memory Response After a Booster Injection of mRNA-1273 for Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) (6 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.21264328</id><title>Endemic Seasonal Coronavirus Neutralisation and COVID-19 severity (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:43.997818+00:00</updated><author><name>David A. Wells</name></author><author><name>Diego Cantoni</name></author><author><name>Martin Mayora-Neto</name></author><author><name>Cecilia Di Genova</name></author><author><name>Alexander Sampson</name></author><author><name>Matteo Ferrari</name></author><author><name>George Carnell</name></author><author><name>Angalee Nadesalingam</name></author><author><name>Peter Smith</name></author><author><name>Andrew Chan</name></author><author><name>Gianmarco Raddi</name></author><author><name>Javier Castillo-Olivares</name></author><author><name>Helen Baxendale</name></author><author><name>Nigel Temperton</name></author><author><name>Jonathan L. Heeney</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The virus SARS-CoV-2, responsible for the global COVID-19 pandemic, spread rapidly around the world causing high morbidity and mortality because humans have no pre-existing immunity. However, there are four known, endemic seasonal coronaviruses in humans (HCoVs) and whether antibodies for these HCoVs play a role in severity of COVID-19 disease has generated a lot of interest. Of these seasonal viruses NL63 is of particular interest as it uses the same cell entry receptor as SARS-CoV-2.We use functional, neutralising assays to investigate cross reactive antibodies and their relationship with COVID-19 severity. We analysed neutralisation of SARS-CoV-2, NL63, HKU1, and 229E in 38 COVID-19 patients and 62 healthcare workers, and a further 182 samples to specifically study the relationship between SARS-CoV-2 and NL63.We found that although HCoV neutralisation was very common there was little evidence that these antibodies neutralised SARS-CoV-2. Despite no evidence in cross neutralisation, levels of NL63 neutralisating antibodies become elevated after exposure to SARS-CoV-2 through infection or following vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.21264328" rel="alternate" title="Endemic Seasonal Coronavirus Neutralisation and COVID-19 severity (6 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.21264242</id><title>Clinical Trial of Efficacy and Toxicity of Disoproxil Tenofovir Fumarate and Emtricitabine for Mild to Moderate SARS-CoV-2 Infections (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.017295+00:00</updated><author><name>E.A.G. Arruda</name></author><author><name>R.J. Pires-Neto</name></author><author><name>M.S. Medeiros</name></author><author><name>J. Quirino-Filho</name></author><author><name>M. Clementino</name></author><author><name>R.N.D.G. Gondim</name></author><author><name>L.M.V.C. Magalhães</name></author><author><name>K.F. Cavalcante</name></author><author><name>V.A.F. Viana</name></author><author><name>Liana Perdigão Mello</name></author><author><name>R.B Martins</name></author><author><name>A.A. Santos</name></author><author><name>P.J.C. Magalhães</name></author><author><name>A. Havt</name></author><author><name>N.P. Lopes</name></author><author><name>E. Arruda-Neto</name></author><author><name>A.A.M. Lima</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This study aimed to evaluate the efficacy and toxicity of tenofovir (TDF) and TDF combined with emtricitabine (TDF/FTC) in patients with mild to moderate COVID-19 infections. We conducted a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial in patients with clinical suspicion of mild to moderate respiratory infection caused by SARS-CoV-2 who were treated at an outpatient clinic. Patients were randomly recruited to take 10 days of TDF (300 mg/day), TDF (300 mg/day) combined with FTC (200 mg/day) or placebo Vitamin C (500 mg/day). The primary parameter was the score of symptoms and predictive signs of COVID-19, assessed on the seventh day of patient follow-up. From a total of 309 patients with clinical suspicion of SARS-CoV-2, 227 met the inclusion criteria and were randomly distributed into the following groups: (a) 75 (one did not initiate treatment) in the TDF group; (b) 74 in the TDF combined with FTC group; and (c) 77 in the Vitamin C group (placebo). Of the 226 patients, 139 (62%) were positive for SARS-CoV-2. Fever (≥37.8°C), ageusia or dysgeusia, anosmia or dysosmia, and two or more clinical symptoms or signs were significantly associated with SARS-CoV-2 infection. There was no significant change in clinical score based on clinical symptoms and signs between treatment groups. Patients with mild to moderate infection by SARS-CoV-2 had higher concentrations of G-CSF, IL-1β, IL-6 and TNF-α compared to patients without infection. Patients with mild to moderate respiratory infection, with fever (≥37.8°C), loss of smell, loss of taste and two or more symptoms, have a better prediction for the diagnosis of COVID-19. Patients with SARS-CoV-2 showed higher and more persistent proinflammatory cytokines profile compared to patients not infected with SARS-CoV-2. Pharmacological intervention with TDF or TDF combined with FTC did not change the clinical signs and symptoms score in mild to moderate respiratory infection in patients with SARS-CoV-2 compared to the Vitamin C group (placebo).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.21264242" rel="alternate" title="Clinical Trial of Efficacy and Toxicity of Disoproxil Tenofovir Fumarate and Emtricitabine for Mild to Moderate SARS-CoV-2 Infections (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462420</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 Beta variant infection elicits potent lineage-specific and cross-reactive antibodies (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.018236+00:00</updated><author><name>S Momsen Reincke</name></author><author><name>Meng Yuan</name></author><author><name>Hans-Christian Kornau</name></author><author><name>Victor M Corman</name></author><author><name>Scott van Hoof</name></author><author><name>Elisa Sánchez-Sendin</name></author><author><name>Melanie Ramberger</name></author><author><name>Wenli Yu</name></author><author><name>Yuanzi Hua</name></author><author><name>Henry Tien</name></author><author><name>Marie Luisa Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Tatjana Schwarz</name></author><author><name>Lara Maria Jeworowski</name></author><author><name>Sarah E Brandl</name></author><author><name>Helle Foverskov Rasmussen</name></author><author><name>Marie A Homeyer</name></author><author><name>Laura Stöffler</name></author><author><name>Martin Barner</name></author><author><name>Désirée Kunkel</name></author><author><name>Shufan Huo</name></author><author><name>Johannes Horler</name></author><author><name>Niels von Wardenburg</name></author><author><name>Inge Kroidl</name></author><author><name>Tabea M Eser</name></author><author><name>Andreas Wieser</name></author><author><name>Christof Geldmacher</name></author><author><name>Michael Hoelscher</name></author><author><name>Hannes Gänzer</name></author><author><name>Günter Weiss</name></author><author><name>Dietmar Schmitz</name></author><author><name>Christian Drosten</name></author><author><name>Harald Prüss</name></author><author><name>Ian A. Wilson</name></author><author><name>Jakob Kreye</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 Beta variant of concern (VOC) resists neutralization by major classes of antibodies from non-VOC COVID-19 patients and vaccinated individuals. Here, serum of Beta variant infected patients revealed reduced cross-neutralization of non-VOC virus. From these patients, we isolated Beta-specific and cross-reactive receptor-binding domain (RBD) antibodies. The Beta-specificity results from recruitment of novel VOC-specific clonotypes and accommodation of VOC-defining amino acids into a major non-VOC antibody class that is normally sensitive to these mutations. The Beta-elicited cross-reactive antibodies share genetic and structural features with non-VOC-elicited antibodies, including a public VH1-58 clonotype targeting the RBD ridge independent of VOC mutations. These findings advance our understanding of the antibody response to SARS-CoV-2 shaped by antigenic drift with implications for design of next-generation vaccines and therapeutics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 Beta variant elicits lineage-specific antibodies and antibodies with neutralizing breadth against wild-type virus and VOCs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462420" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 Beta variant infection elicits potent lineage-specific and cross-reactive antibodies (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.21264126</id><title>Efficacy of COVID-19 vaccines in immunocompromised patients: A systematic review and meta-analysis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.019792+00:00</updated><author><name>Ainsley Ryan Yan Bin Lee</name></author><author><name>Shi Yin Wong</name></author><author><name>Louis Yi Ann Chai</name></author><author><name>Soo Chin Lee</name></author><author><name>Matilda Lee</name></author><author><name>Mark Dhinesh Muthiah</name></author><author><name>Sen Hee Tay</name></author><author><name>Chong Boon Teo</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Kye Jyn Tan</name></author><author><name>Yiong Huak Chan</name></author><author><name>Raghav Sundar</name></author><author><name>Yu Yang Soon</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To compare the efficacy of COVID 19 vaccines between those with immunocompromised medical conditions and those who are immunocompetent&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Systematic review and meta-analysis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data sources&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;PubMed, EMBASE, CENTRAL, CORD-19 and WHO COVID-19 research databases were searched for eligible comparative studies published between 1 December 2020 and 3 September 2021. ClinicalTrials.gov and the WHO International Clinical Trials Registry Platform were searched in September 2021 to identify registered yet unpublished or ongoing studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Study selection&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prospective observational studies which compared the efficacy of COVID-19 vaccination between those with immunocompromising medical conditions and those who were immunocompetent were included. Two reviewers independently screened for potentially eligible studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data extraction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The primary outcomes of interest were cumulative incidence of seroconversion after first and second doses of COVID vaccination. Secondary outcomes included SARS-CoV-2 antibody titre level after first and second doses of COVID-19 vaccination. After duplicate data abstraction, a frequentist random effects meta-analysis was conducted. Risk of bias was assessed using the ROBINS-I tool. Certainty of evidence was assessed using the GRADE approach.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;After screening 3283 studies, 42 studies that met our inclusion criteria were identified. 18 immunocompromised cohorts from 17 studies reported seroconversion in immunocompromised patients compared to healthy controls after the first dose and 30 immunocompromised cohorts in 28 studies reporting data after the second dose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among immunocompromised groups, in incremental order, transplant recipients had the lowest pooled risk ratio of 0.06 (95%CI: 0.04 to 0.09, I^2=0%, p=0.81) (GRADE=Moderate) followed by haematological cancer patients at 0.36 (95%CI: 0.21 to 0.62, I^2 = 89%, p&amp;lt;0.01) (GRADE=Moderate), solid cancer patients at 0.40 (95%CI: 0.31 to 0.52, I^2 = 63%, p=0.03) (GRADE=Moderate) and IMID patients at 0.66 (95%CI: 0.48 to 0.91, I^2=81%, p&amp;lt;0.01) (GRADE=Moderate).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the second dose, the lowest pooled risk ratio was again seen in transplant recipients at 0.29 (95%CI: 0.21 to 0.40, I^2=91%, p&amp;lt;0.01) (GRADE=Moderate), haematological cancer patients at 0.68 (95%CI: 0.57 to 0.80, I^2=68%, p=0.02) (GRADE=Low), IMID patients at 0.79 (95%CI: 0.72 to 0.86, I^2=87%, p&amp;lt;0.01) (GRADE=Low) and solid cancer at 0.92 (95%CI: 0.89 to 0.95, I^2=26%, p=0.25) (GRADE=Low).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seroconversion rates and serological titres are significantly lower in immunocompromised patients with transplant recipients having the poorest outcomes. Additional strategies on top of the conventional 2-dose regimen will likely be warranted, such as a booster dose of the vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Systematic review registration&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;PROSPERO CRD42021272088&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.21264126" rel="alternate" title="Efficacy of COVID-19 vaccines in immunocompromised patients: A systematic review and meta-analysis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Allergy and Immunology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.461909</id><title>Face masks impair reconstruction of acoustic speech features and higher-level segmentational features in the presence of a distractor speaker (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.020211+00:00</updated><author><name>Chandra Leon Haider</name></author><author><name>Nina Suess</name></author><author><name>Anne Hauswald</name></author><author><name>Hyojin Park</name></author><author><name>Nathan Weisz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Face masks have become a prevalent measure during the Covid-19 pandemic to counteract the transmission of SARS-CoV 2. An unintended “side-effect” of face masks is their adverse influence on speech perception especially in challenging listening situations. So far, behavioural studies have not pinpointed exactly which feature(s) of speech processing face masks affect in such listening situations. We conducted an audiovisual (AV) multi-speaker experiment using naturalistic speech (i.e. an audiobook). In half of the trials, the target speaker wore a (surgical) face mask, while we measured the brain activity of normal hearing participants via magnetoencephalography (MEG). A decoding model on the clear AV speech (i.e. no additional speaker and target speaker not wearing a face mask) was trained and used to reconstruct crucial speech features in each condition. We found significant main effects of face masks on the reconstruction of acoustic features, such as the speech envelope and spectral speech features (i.e. pitch and formant frequencies), while reconstruction of higher level features of speech segmentation (phoneme and word onsets) were especially impaired through masks in difficult listening situations, i.e. when a distracting speaker was also presented. Our findings demonstrate the detrimental impact face masks have on listening and speech perception, thus extending previous behavioural results. Supporting the idea of visual facilitation of speech is the fact that we used surgical face masks in our study, which only show mild effects on speech acoustics. This idea is in line with recent research, also by our group, showing that visual cortical regions track spectral modulations. Since hearing impairment usually affects higher frequencies, the detrimental effect of face masks might pose a particular challenge for individuals who likely need the visual information about higher frequencies (e.g. formants) to compensate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.461909" rel="alternate" title="Face masks impair reconstruction of acoustic speech features and higher-level segmentational features in the presence of a distractor speaker (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462156</id><title>Modulation of immunosuppressant drug treatment to improve SARS-CoV-2 vaccine efficacy in mice (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.020646+00:00</updated><author><name>Amy V. Paschall</name></author><author><name>Ahmet Ozdilek</name></author><author><name>Sydney L. Briner</name></author><author><name>Melinda A. Brindley</name></author><author><name>Fikri Y. Avci</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic dramatically demonstrated the need for improved vaccination strategies and therapeutic responses to combat infectious diseases. However, the efficacy of vaccines has not yet been demonstrated in combination with commonly used immunosuppressive drug regimens. We sought to determine how common pharmaceutical drugs used in autoimmune disorders can alter immune responses to the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We treated mice with five immunosuppressant drugs (cyclophosphamide, leflunomide, methotrexate, methylprednisolone, and mycophenolate mofetil), each with various mechanisms of action prior to and following immunization with SARS-CoV-2 spike protein. We assessed the functionality of antibody responses to spike protein and compared immune cell populations in mice that received no treatment with those that received continuous or temporarily suspended immune suppressive therapy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All tested immunosuppressants significantly reduced the antibody titers in serum and functional antibody response against SARS-CoV-2 spike protein in immunized mice. Temporarily halting selected immunosuppressants (methylprednisolone and methotrexate, but not cyclophosphamide) improved antibody responses significantly. Through proof-of-principle experiments utilizing a mouse model, we demonstrated that immune suppression in autoimmune disorders through pharmaceutical treatments may impair vaccine response to SARS-CoV-2, and temporary suspension of immunosuppressant treatment may be necessary to mount an effective antibody vaccine response. This work provides feasibility for future clinical assessment of the impact of immunosuppressants on vaccine efficacy in humans.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Immunosuppressant regimens are widely used as therapies for a variety of diseases, including autoimmune, inflammatory, and cancer. However, immunosuppressants can impair critical immune responses to vaccination. The impact of standard immunosuppressant use on the critical, developing SARS-CoV-2 vaccination strategies has not been well-described. In this study, we use a mouse model to determine how different immunosuppressant drugs that act through different mechanisms can impair the antibody response to SARS-CoV-2 spike protein, and how modulating these drug regimens may restore antibody levels and function.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462156" rel="alternate" title="Modulation of immunosuppressant drug treatment to improve SARS-CoV-2 vaccine efficacy in mice (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.21264298</id><title>A HOME-TREATMENT ALGORITHM BASED ON ANTI-INFLAMMATORY DRUGS TO PREVENT HOSPITALIZATION OF PATIENTS WITH EARLY COVID-19: A MATCHED-COHORT STUDY (COVER 2) (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.021083+00:00</updated><author><name>Elena Consolaro</name></author><author><name>Fredy Suter</name></author><author><name>Nadia Rubis</name></author><author><name>Stefania Pedroni</name></author><author><name>Chiara Moroni</name></author><author><name>Elena Pastò</name></author><author><name>Maria Vittoria Paganini</name></author><author><name>Grazia Pravettoni</name></author><author><name>Umberto Cantarelli</name></author><author><name>Norberto Perico</name></author><author><name>Annalisa Perna</name></author><author><name>Tobia Peracchi</name></author><author><name>Piero Ruggenenti</name></author><author><name>Giuseppe Remuzzi</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background and Aim&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;While considerable success has been achieved in the management of patients hospitalized with severe coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), far less progress has been made with early outpatient treatment. We assessed whether the implementation of a home treatment algorithm – designed based upon on a pathophysiologic and pharmacologic rationale - during the initial, mild phase of COVID-19, could effectively reduce hospital admissions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This fully academic, matched-cohort study evaluated outcomes in 108 consecutive consenting patients with mild COVID-19 managed at home by their family doctors from January 2021 to May 2021, according to the proposed treatment algorithm and in 108 age-, sex-, and comorbidities-matched patients who were given other therapeutic schedules (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov"&gt;ClinicalTrials.gov&lt;/ext-link&gt;: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT04854824"&gt;NCT04854824&lt;/ext-link&gt;). The primary outcome was COVID-19-related hospitalization. Analyses were by intention-to-treat.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;One (0.9%) patient in the ‘recommended’ cohort and 12 (11.1%) in the ‘control’ cohort were admitted to hospital (P=0.0136). The proposed algorithm reduced, by 85%, the cumulative length of hospital stays (from 141 to 19 days) and related costs (from € 60.316 to € 9.058). Only 9.8 patients needed to be treated with the recommended algorithm to prevent one hospitalization event. The rate of resolution of major symptoms was numerically, but not significantly, higher in the ‘recommended’ compared to the ‘control’ cohort (97.2% versus 93.5%, respectively; P=0.322). Other symptoms lingered in a lower proportion of patients in the ‘recommended’ than in the‘control’ cohort (20.4% versus 63.9%, respectively; P&amp;lt;0.001), and for a shorter period.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The adoption of the proposed outpatient treatment algorithm during the early, mild phase of COVID-19 reduced the incidence of subsequent hospitalization and related costs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.21264298" rel="alternate" title="A HOME-TREATMENT ALGORITHM BASED ON ANTI-INFLAMMATORY DRUGS TO PREVENT HOSPITALIZATION OF PATIENTS WITH EARLY COVID-19: A MATCHED-COHORT STUDY (COVER 2) (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.21264312</id><title>A cross-sectional study of COVID-19 knowledge, beliefs and prevention behaviors among adults in Senegal (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.021581+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew D. Kearney</name></author><author><name>Marta Bornstein</name></author><author><name>Marieme Fall</name></author><author><name>Roch Nianogo</name></author><author><name>Deborah Glik</name></author><author><name>Philip M. Massey</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 is an ongoing threat to global public health since its emergence at the end of 2019, yet little is known about how populations in francophone West Africa have responded to COVID-19 in their daily lives. Senegal, in particular, has been noted for its relative success in mitigating the spread and impact of COVID-19. We report original research findings on COVID-19 beliefs and prevention behaviors in a sample of Senegalese adults.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A multi-modal cross-sectional study was conducted to describe COVID-19 beliefs and prevention behaviors in a sample of Senegalese adults and to identify potential predictors of prevention behaviors. Univariate, bivariate, and multivariate statistics were generated to describe the sample and explore potential correlations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mask wearing, hand washing, and use of hand sanitizer were most frequently reported. Social distancing and staying at home were also reported albeit to a lower degree. We also identified a range of psychosocial and demographic predictors for COVID-19 prevention behaviors. Men, compared to women, had lower odds (OR=0.59) of reporting prevention behaviors. Rural residents (vs. urban; OR=1.49) and participants with at least a high school education (vs. less than high school education; OR=1.33) were more likely to report COVID-19 prevention behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Discussion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stakeholders and decision makers in Senegal and across Africa can use place-based evidence like ours to address COVID-19 risk factors and intervene effectively with policies and programming. Use of both phone and online surveys enhances representation and study generalizability and should be considered in future research with hard-to-reach populations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Article Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Strengths and limitations of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The main strength of our study is the use of a multi-modal data collection strategy, online and via telephone. Had we relied on a single method, our sample’s demographic characteristics would likely have differed while also introducing selection bias.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our recruitment strategy may have also increased the potential for selection bias because participants were recruited online and on-the-ground in Senegal; thus, all participants, by the nature of the recruitment methods, had access to the internet and/or a cell phone. To address potential confounding between recruitment methods, we controlled for recruitment method in our multivariate regression modelling.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prior to our study, little evidence was available about how populations in francophone West Africa have responded to COVID-19 in their daily lives. We adapted pre-existing research panels and developed novel data collection instruments to capture information about COVID-19, and this may serve as a model for the responsiveness of ongoing scholarship to future global events.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;A study with a larger sample may have been able to identify relationships between knowledge and behaviors, and our study was not design with enough statistical power to detect significant differences.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The findings of our study may not be generalizable beyond Senegal, or more specifically Senegalese adults.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.21264312" rel="alternate" title="A cross-sectional study of COVID-19 knowledge, beliefs and prevention behaviors among adults in Senegal (3 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462459</id><title>Structural mapping of antibody landscapes to human betacoronavirus spike proteins (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.021917+00:00</updated><author><name>Sandhya Bangaru</name></author><author><name>Aleksandar Antanasijevic</name></author><author><name>Nurgun Kose</name></author><author><name>Leigh M. Sewall</name></author><author><name>Abigail M. Jackson</name></author><author><name>Naveenchandra Suryadevara</name></author><author><name>Xiaoyan Zhan</name></author><author><name>Jonathan L. Torres</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey Copps</name></author><author><name>Alba Torrents de la Peña</name></author><author><name>James E. Crowe</name></author><author><name>Andrew B. Ward</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Preexisting immunity against seasonal coronaviruses (CoV) represents an important variable in predicting antibody responses and disease severity to Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome CoV-2 (SARS-2) infections. We used electron microscopy based polyclonal epitope mapping (EMPEM) to characterize the antibody specificities against β-CoV spike proteins in sera from healthy donors (HDs) or SARS-2 convalescent donors (CDs). We observed that most HDs possessed antibodies specific to seasonal human CoVs (HCoVs) OC43 and HKU1 spike proteins while the CDs showed reactivity across all human β-CoVs. Detailed molecular mapping of spike-antibody complexes revealed epitopes that were differentially targeted by antibodies in preexisting and convalescent serum. Our studies provide an antigenic landscape to β-HCoV spikes in the general population serving as a basis for cross-reactive epitope analyses in SARS-2 -infected individuals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present the epitope mapping of polyclonal antibodies against beta-coronavirus spike proteins in human sera.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462459" rel="alternate" title="Structural mapping of antibody landscapes to human betacoronavirus spike proteins (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>