<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.366724+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471446</id><title>Minimal cross-over between mutations associated with Omicron variant of SARS-CoV-2 and CD8+ T cell epitopes identified in COVID-19 convalescent individuals (911 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.367181+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew D Redd</name></author><author><name>Alessandra Nardin</name></author><author><name>Hassen Kared</name></author><author><name>Evan M Bloch</name></author><author><name>Brian Abel</name></author><author><name>Andrew Pekosz</name></author><author><name>Oliver Laeyendecker</name></author><author><name>Michael Fehlings</name></author><author><name>Thomas C Quinn</name></author><author><name>Aaron AR Tobian</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;There is a growing concern that ongoing evolution of SARS-CoV-2 could lead to variants of concern (VOC) that are capable of avoiding some or all of the multi-faceted immune response generated by both prior infection or vaccination, with the recently described B.1.1.529 (Omicron) VOC being of particular interest. Peripheral blood mononuclear cell samples from PCR-confirmed, recovered COVID-19 convalescent patients (n=30) infected with SARS-CoV-2 in the United States collected in April and May 2020 who possessed at least one or more of six different HLA haplotypes were selected for examination of their anti-SARS-CoV-2 CD8+ T-cell responses using a multiplexed peptide-MHC tetramer staining approach. This analysis examined if the previously identified viral epitopes targeted by CD8+ T-cells in these individuals (n=52 distinct epitopes) are mutated in the newly described Omicron VOC (n=50 mutations). Within this population, only one low-prevalence epitope from the Spike protein restricted to two HLA alleles and found in 2/30 (7%) individuals contained a single amino acid change associated with the Omicron VOC. These data suggest that virtually all individuals with existing anti-SARS-CoV-2 CD8+ T-cell responses should recognize the Omicron VOC, and that SARS-CoV-2 has not evolved extensive T-cell escape mutations at this time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The newly identified Omicron variant of concern contains more mutations than any of the previous variants described to date. In addition, many of the mutations associated with the Omicron variant are found in areas that are likely bound by neutralizing antibodies, suggesting that the first line of immunological defense against COVID-19 may be compromised. However, both natural infection and vaccination develop T-cell based responses, in addition to antibodies. This study examined if the parts of the virus, or epitopes, targeted by the CD8+ T-cell response in thirty individuals who recovered from COVID-19 in 2020 were mutated in the Omicron variant. Only one of 52 epitopes identified in this population contained an amino acid that was mutated in Omicron. These data suggest that the T-cell immune response in previously infected, and most likely vaccinated individuals, should still be effective against Omicron.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471446" rel="alternate" title="Minimal cross-over between mutations associated with Omicron variant of SARS-CoV-2 and CD8+ T cell epitopes identified in COVID-19 convalescent individuals (911 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.470392</id><title>B.1.1.529 escapes the majority of SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibodies of diverse epitopes (192 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.367504+00:00</updated><author><name>Yunlong Cao</name></author><author><name>Jing Wang</name></author><author><name>Fanchong Jian</name></author><author><name>Tianhe Xiao</name></author><author><name>Weiliang Song</name></author><author><name>Ayijiang Yisimayi</name></author><author><name>Weijin Huang</name></author><author><name>Qianqian Li</name></author><author><name>Peng Wang</name></author><author><name>Ran An</name></author><author><name>Jing Wang</name></author><author><name>Yao Wang</name></author><author><name>Xiao Niu</name></author><author><name>Sijie Yang</name></author><author><name>Hui Liang</name></author><author><name>Haiyan Sun</name></author><author><name>Tao Li</name></author><author><name>Yuanling Yu</name></author><author><name>Qianqian Cui</name></author><author><name>Shuo Liu</name></author><author><name>Xiaodong Yang</name></author><author><name>Shuo Du</name></author><author><name>Zhiying Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xiaohua Hao</name></author><author><name>Fei Shao</name></author><author><name>Ronghua Jin</name></author><author><name>Xiangxi Wang</name></author><author><name>Junyu Xiao</name></author><author><name>Youchun Wang</name></author><author><name>Xiaoliang Sunney Xie</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The SARS-CoV-2 B.1.1.529 variant (Omicron) contains 15 mutations on the receptor-binding domain (RBD). How Omicron would evade RBD neutralizing antibodies (NAbs) and humoral immunity requires immediate investigation. Here, we used high-throughput yeast display screening&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt; to determine the RBD escaping mutation profiles for 247 human anti-RBD NAbs identified from SARS-CoV/SARS-CoV-2 convalescents and vaccinees. Based on the results, NAbs could be unsupervised clustered into six epitope groups (A-F), which is highly concordant with knowledge-based structural classifications&lt;sup&gt;3–5&lt;/sup&gt;. Strikingly, various single mutations of Omicron could impair NAbs of different epitope groups. Specifically, NAbs in Group A-D, whose epitope overlaps with ACE2-binding motif, are largely escaped by K417N, N440K, G446S, E484A, Q493K, and G496S. Group E (S309 site)&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; and F (CR3022 site)&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt; NAbs, which often exhibit broad sarbecovirus neutralizing activity, are less affected by Omicron, but still, a subset of NAbs are escaped by G339D, S371L, and S375F. Furthermore, B.1.1.529 pseudovirus neutralization and RBD binding assay showed that single mutation tolerating NAbs could also be escaped due to multiple synergetic mutations on their epitopes. In total, over 85% of the tested NAbs are escaped by Omicron. Regarding NAb drugs, LY-CoV016/LY-CoV555 cocktail, REGN-CoV2 cocktail, AZD1061/AZD8895 cocktail, and BRII-196 were escaped by Omicron, while VIR7831 and DXP-604 still function at reduced efficacy. Together, data suggest Omicron could cause significant humoral immune evasion, while NAbs targeting the sarbecovirus conserved region remain most effective. Our results offer instructions for developing NAb drugs and vaccines against Omicron and future variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.470392" rel="alternate" title="B.1.1.529 escapes the majority of SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibodies of diverse epitopes (192 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471045</id><title>Receptor binding and escape from Beta antibody responses drive Omicron-B.1.1.529 evolution (142 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.368143+00:00</updated><author><name>Jiří Zahradník</name></author><author><name>Aekkachai Tuekprakhon</name></author><author><name>Helen M. Ginn</name></author><author><name>Helen M.E. Duyvesteyn</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Bahar</name></author><author><name>Suman Khan</name></author><author><name>Ori Avinoam</name></author><author><name>Daming Zhou</name></author><author><name>Rungtiwa Nutalai</name></author><author><name>Piyada Supasa</name></author><author><name>Beibei Wang</name></author><author><name>Wanwisa Dejnirattisai</name></author><author><name>Chang Liu</name></author><author><name>Aiste Dijokaite</name></author><author><name>Nigel Temperton</name></author><author><name>Juthathip Mongkolsapaya</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth E. Fry</name></author><author><name>Ren Jingshan</name></author><author><name>Gavin R. Screaton</name></author><author><name>Gideon Schreiber</name></author><author><name>David I. Stuart</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;On the 24&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; November 2021 the sequence of a new SARS CoV-2 viral isolate spreading rapidly in Southern Africa was announced. Omicron contains a total of 30 substitutions plus deletions and an insertion in Spike, far more than any previously reported variant. The mutations include those previously identified by &lt;italic&gt;In-vitro&lt;/italic&gt; evolution to contribute to high-affinity binding to ACE2, including mutations Q498R and N501Y critical in forming additional interactions in the interface. Together with increased charge complementarity between the RBD and ACE2, these substantially increase affinity and potentially virus transmissibility through increased syncytia formation. Further mutations promote immune evasion. We have studied the binding of a large panel of potent monoclonal antibodies generated from early pandemic or Beta infected cases. Mutations in Omicron will likely compromise the binding of many of these and additionally, the binding of antibodies under commercial development, however residual binding should provide protection from severe disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471045" rel="alternate" title="Receptor binding and escape from Beta antibody responses drive Omicron-B.1.1.529 evolution (142 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.21267356</id><title>A prospective diagnostic evaluation of accuracy of self-taken and healthcare worker-taken swabs for rapid COVID-19 testing (80 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.368501+00:00</updated><author><name>Helen R. Savage</name></author><author><name>Lorna Finch</name></author><author><name>Richard Body</name></author><author><name>Rachel L. Watkins</name></author><author><name>Gail Hayward</name></author><author><name>Eloïse Cook</name></author><author><name>Ana I Cubas-Atienzar</name></author><author><name>Luis E. Cuevas</name></author><author><name>Peter MacPherson</name></author><author><name>Emily R. Adams</name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To compare self-taken and healthcare worker (HCW)-taken throat/nasal swabs to perform rapid diagnostic tests (RDT) for SARS-CoV-2, and how these compare to RT-PCR. We hypothesised that self-taken samples are non-inferior for use with RDTs and in clinical and research settings could have substantial individual and public health benefit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A prospective diagnostic accuracy evaluation as part of the ‘Facilitating Accelerated Clinical Evaluation of Novel Diagnostic Tests for COVID -19 (FALCON C-19), workstream C (undifferentiated community testing)’.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;NHS Test and Trace drive-through community PCR testing site (Liverpool, UK). Participants&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eligible participants 18 years or older with symptoms of COVID-19. 250 participants recruited; one withdrew before analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Sampling&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Self-administered throat/nasal swab for the Covios® RDT, a trained HCW taken throat/nasal sample for PCR and HCW comparison throat/nasal swab for RDT.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main outcome measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sensitivity, specificity, and positive and negative predictive values (PPV, NPV) were calculated; comparisons between self-taken and HCW-taken samples used McNemar’s test.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seventy-five participants (75/249, 30.1%) were positive by RT-PCR. RDTs with self-taken swabs had a sensitivity of 90.5% (67/74, 95% CI: 83.9-97.2), compared to 78.4% (58/74, 95% CI: 69.0-87.8) for HCW-taken swabs (absolute difference 12.2%, 95% CI: 4.7-19.6, p=0.003). Specificity for self-taken swabs was 99.4% (173/174, 95% CI: 98.3-100.0), versus 98.9% (172/174, 95% CI: 97.3-100.0) for HCW-taken swabs (absolute difference 0.6%, 95% CI: 0.5-1.7, p=0.317). The PPV of self-taken RDTs (98.5%, 67/68, 95% CI: 95.7-100.0) and HCW-taken RDTs (96.7%, 58/60, 95% CI 92.1-100.0) were not significantly different (p=0.262). However, the NPV of self-taken swab RDTs was significantly higher (96.1%, 173/180, 95% CI: 93.2-98.9) than HCW-taken RDTs (91.5%, 172/188, 95% CI 87.5-95.5, p=0.003).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Self-taken swabs for COVID-19 testing offer substantial individual benefits in terms of convenience, accuracy, and reduced risk of transmitting infection. Our results demonstrate that self-taken throat/nasal samples can be used by lay individuals as part of rapid testing programmes for symptomatic adults.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Trial Registration&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;IRAS ID:28422, clinical trial ID: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT04408170"&gt;NCT04408170&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What is already known on this topic?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rapid diagnostic tests (RDTs)for SARS-CoV-2 Ag are a cheaper point-of-care alternative to RT-PCR for diagnosing COVID-19 disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The accuracy of tests can vary dependent on sampling technique, test processing and reading of results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What this study adds?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Self-taken throat-nasal swabs for RDTs can be used by symptomatic adults to give reliable results to diagnose SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Self-sampling can be implemented with little training and no assistance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.21267356" rel="alternate" title="A prospective diagnostic evaluation of accuracy of self-taken and healthcare worker-taken swabs for rapid COVID-19 testing (80 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.21267432</id><title>Reduced Neutralization of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron Variant by Vaccine Sera and monoclonal antibodies (61 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.368769+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Wilhelm</name></author><author><name>Marek Widera</name></author><author><name>Katharina Grikscheit</name></author><author><name>Tuna Toptan</name></author><author><name>Barbara Schenk</name></author><author><name>Christiane Pallas</name></author><author><name>Melinda Metzler</name></author><author><name>Niko Kohmer</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Hoehl</name></author><author><name>Fabian A. Helfritz</name></author><author><name>Timo Wolf</name></author><author><name>Udo Goetsch</name></author><author><name>Sandra Ciesek</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Due to numerous mutations in the spike protein, the SARS-CoV-2 variant of concern Omicron (B.1.1.529) raises serious concerns since it may significantly limit the antibody-mediated neutralization and increase the risk of reinfections. While a rapid increase in the number of cases is being reported worldwide, until now there has been uncertainty about the efficacy of vaccinations and monoclonal antibodies. Our &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; findings using authentic SARS-CoV-2 variants indicate that in contrast to the currently circulating Delta variant, the neutralization efficacy of vaccine-elicited sera against Omicron was severely reduced highlighting T-cell mediated immunity as essential barrier to prevent severe COVID-19. Since SARS-CoV-2 Omicron was resistant to casirivimab and imdevimab, genotyping of SARS-CoV-2 may be needed before initiating mAb treatment. Variant-specific vaccines and mAb agents may be required to treat COVID-19 due to Omicron and other emerging variants of concern.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.21267432" rel="alternate" title="Reduced Neutralization of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron Variant by Vaccine Sera and monoclonal antibodies (61 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471664</id><title>Combinatorial mRNA vaccination enhances protection against SARS-CoV-2 delta variant (55 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.369038+00:00</updated><author><name>Renee L Hajnik</name></author><author><name>Jessica A Plante</name></author><author><name>Yuejin Liang</name></author><author><name>Mohamad-Gabriel Alameh</name></author><author><name>Jinyi Tang</name></author><author><name>Chaojie Zhong</name></author><author><name>Awadalkareem Adam</name></author><author><name>Dionna Scharton</name></author><author><name>Grace H Rafael</name></author><author><name>Yang Liu</name></author><author><name>Nicholas C Hazell</name></author><author><name>Jiaren Sun</name></author><author><name>Lynn Soong</name></author><author><name>Pei-Yong Shi</name></author><author><name>Tian Wang</name></author><author><name>Jie Sun</name></author><author><name>Drew Weissman</name></author><author><name>Scott C Weaver</name></author><author><name>Kenneth S Plante</name></author><author><name>Haitao Hu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Emergence of SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (VOC), including the highly transmissible delta strain, has posed challenges to current COVID-19 vaccines that principally target the viral spike protein (S). Here, we report a nucleoside-modified mRNA vaccine that expresses the more conserved viral nucleoprotein (mRNA-N). We show that mRNA-N alone was able to induce a modest but significant control of SARS-CoV-2 in mice and hamsters. Critically, by combining mRNA-N with the clinically approved S-expressing mRNA vaccine (mRNA-S-2P), we found that combinatorial mRNA vaccination (mRNA-S+N) led to markedly enhanced protection against the SARS-CoV-2 delta variant compared to mRNA-S. In a hamster model, we demonstrated that while mRNA-S alone elicited significant control of the delta strain in the lungs (~45-fold reduction in viral loads compared to un-vaccinated control), its effectiveness in the upper respiratory tract was weak, whereas combinatorial mRNA-S+N vaccination induced markedly more robust control of the delta variant infection in the lungs (~450-fold reduction) as well as in the upper respiratory tract (~20-fold reduction). Immune analyses indicated that induction of N-specific immunity as well as augmented S-specific T-cell response and neutralizing antibody activity were collectively associated the enhanced protection against SARS-CoV-2 delta strain by combinatorial mRNA vaccination. These findings suggest that the combined effects of protection in the lungs and upper respiratory tract could both reduce the risk of severe disease as well as of infection and transmission.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471664" rel="alternate" title="Combinatorial mRNA vaccination enhances protection against SARS-CoV-2 delta variant (55 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.21267417</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 Omicron has extensive but incomplete escape of Pfizer BNT162b2 elicited neutralization and requires ACE2 for infection (54 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.369372+00:00</updated><author><name>Sandile Cele</name></author><author><name>Laurelle Jackson</name></author><author><name>Khadija Khan</name></author><author><name>David Khoury</name></author><author><name>Thandeka Moyo-Gwete</name></author><author><name>Houriiyah Tegally</name></author><author><name>Cathrine Scheepers</name></author><author><name>Daniel Amoako</name></author><author><name>Farina Karim</name></author><author><name>Mallory Bernstein</name></author><author><name>Gila Lustig</name></author><author><name>Derseree Archary</name></author><author><name>Muneerah Smith</name></author><author><name>Yashica Ganga</name></author><author><name>Zesuliwe Jule</name></author><author><name>Kajal Reedoy</name></author><author><name>James Emmanuel San</name></author><author><name>Shi-Hsia Hwa</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Giandhari</name></author><author><name>Jonathan M. Blackburn</name></author><author><name>Bernadett I. Gosnell</name></author><author><name>Salim Abdool Karim</name></author><author><name>Willem Hanekom</name></author><author><name>Anne von Gottberg</name></author><author><name>Jinal Bhiman</name></author><author><name>Richard J. Lessells</name></author><author><name>Mahomed-Yunus S. Moosa</name></author><author><name>Miles Davenport</name></author><author><name>Tulio de Oliveira</name></author><author><name>Penny L. Moore</name></author><author><name>Alex Sigal</name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The emergence of the Omicron variant (1) of SARS-CoV-2 in November 2021 in South Africa has raised concerns that, based on the large number of mutations in the spike protein and elsewhere on the virus (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://covdb.stanford.edu/page/mutation-viewer/#sec_b-1-351"&gt;https://covdb.stanford.edu/page/mutation-viewer/#sec_b-1-351&lt;/ext-link&gt;), this variant will have considerable escape from vaccine elicited immunity. Furthermore, several mutations in the receptor binding domain and S2 are predicted to impact transmissibility and affinity for ACE-2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we investigated whether Omicron escapes antibody neutralization elicited by the Pfizer BNT162b2 mRNA vaccine and whether the virus still requires binding to the ACE2 receptor to infect cells. We used an early passage of isolated and sequence confirmed live Omicron virus isolated in South Africa. We used a human lung cell line clone (H1299-ACE2) engineered to express the ACE2 receptor (2) to both isolate the virus and test neutralization. We also tested growth in the parental H1299 which do not overexpress ACE2 and are not appreciably infectable with SARS-CoV-2 (Fig S1). The H1299-ACE2 cells were similar to Vero-E6 in titer dependent focus formation, but were considerably more sensitive (Fig S2).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We observed that Omicron infected the ACE2-expressing cells in a concentration dependent manner but did not infect the parental H1299 cells, indicating that ACE2 is required for Omicron entry (Fig. 1A). We then tested the ability of plasma from BNT162b2 vaccinated study participants to neutralize Omicron versus ancestral D614G virus in a live virus neutralization assay. We tested 14 plasma samples from 12 participants (Table S1), with 6 having no previous record of SARS-CoV-2 infection nor detectable nucleocapsid antibodies indicative of previous infection. For two of these participants, we used samples from two timepoints. The remaining 6 participants had a record of previous infection in the first SARS-CoV-2 infection wave in South Africa where infection was with ancestral D614G virus (Table S1). Geometric mean titer (GMT) FRNT50 (inverse of the plasma dilution required for 50% reduction in infection foci number) was 1321 for D614G. These samples therefore had very strong neutralization of D614G virus, consistent with sampling soon after vaccination. GMT FRNT50 for the same samples was 32 for Omicron, a 41-fold decline (Fig 1B). However, the escape was incomplete, with 5 of the participants, all previously infected, showing relatively high neutralization titers with Omicron.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beta variant escape from BNT162b2 in a live virus neutralization assay has been reported to be substantial (3) and our own data confirmed these results (4), with about 3-fold reduction in FRNT50. The results we present here with Omicron show much more extensive escape. However, escape was incomplete in participants with higher FRNT50 due to previous infection. Previous infection, followed by vaccination or booster is likely to increase the neutralization level and likely confer protection from severe disease in Omicron infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.21267417" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 Omicron has extensive but incomplete escape of Pfizer BNT162b2 elicited neutralization and requires ACE2 for infection (54 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.21267182</id><title>COVID-19 infections post-vaccination by HIV status in the United States (52 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.369830+00:00</updated><author><name>Sally B. Coburn</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Humes</name></author><author><name>Raynell Lang</name></author><author><name>Cameron Stewart</name></author><author><name>Brenna C Hogan</name></author><author><name>Kelly A. Gebo</name></author><author><name>Sonia Napravnik</name></author><author><name>Jessie K. Edwards</name></author><author><name>Lindsay E. Browne</name></author><author><name>Lesley S. Park</name></author><author><name>Amy C. Justice</name></author><author><name>Kirsha Gordon</name></author><author><name>Michael A. Horberg</name></author><author><name>Julia M. Certa</name></author><author><name>Eric Watson</name></author><author><name>Celeena R Jefferson</name></author><author><name>Michael Silverberg</name></author><author><name>Jacek Skarbinski</name></author><author><name>Wendy A Leyden</name></author><author><name>Carolyn F. Williams</name></author><author><name>Keri N. Althoff</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recommendations for additional doses of COVID vaccine are restricted to people with HIV who have advanced disease or unsuppressed HIV viral load. Understanding SARS-CoV-2 infection risk post-vaccination among PWH is essential for informing vaccination guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Estimate the risk of breakthrough infections among fully vaccinated people with (PWH) and without (PWoH) HIV in the US.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design, setting, and participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Corona-Infectious-Virus Epidemiology Team (CIVET)-II cohort collaboration consists of 4 longitudinal cohorts from integrated health systems and academic health centers. Each cohort identified individuals ≥18 years old, in-care, and fully vaccinated for COVID-19 through 30 June 2021. PWH were matched to PWoH on date fully vaccinated, age group, race/ethnicity, and sex at birth. Incidence rates per 1,000 person-years and cumulative incidence of breakthrough infections with 95% confidence intervals ([,]) were estimated by HIV status. Cox proportional hazards models estimated adjusted hazard ratios (aHR) of breakthrough infections by HIV status adjusting for demographic factors, prior COVID-19 illness, vaccine type (BNT162b2, [Pfizer], mRNA-1273 [Moderna], Jansen Ad26.COV2.S [J&amp;amp;J]), calendar time, and cohort. Risk factors for breakthroughs among PWH, were also investigated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Exposure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;HIV infection&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Outcome&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 breakthrough infections, defined as laboratory evidence of SARS-CoV-2 infection or COVID-19 diagnosis after an individual was fully vaccinated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among 109,599 individuals (31,840 PWH and 77,759 PWoH), the rate of breakthrough infections was higher in PWH versus PWoH: 44 [41, 48] vs. 31 [29, 33] per 1,000 person-years. Cumulative incidence at 210 days after date fully vaccinated was low, albeit higher in PWH versus PWoH overall (2.8% versus 2.1%, log-rank p&amp;lt;0.001, risk difference=0.7% [0.4%, 1.0%]) and within each vaccine type. Breakthrough infection risk was 41% higher in PWH versus PWoH (aHR=1.41 [1.28, 1.56]). Among PWH, younger age (18-24 versus 45-54), history of COVID-19 prior to fully vaccinated date, and J&amp;amp;J vaccination (versus Pfizer) were associated with increased risk of breakthroughs. There was no association of breakthrough with HIV viral load suppression or CD4 count among PWH.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions and Relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 vaccination is effective against infection with SARS-CoV-2 strains circulating through 30 Sept 2021. PWH have an increased risk of breakthrough infections compared to PWoH. Recommendations for additional vaccine doses should be expanded to all PWH.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.21267182" rel="alternate" title="COVID-19 infections post-vaccination by HIV status in the United States (52 tweets)"/><category term="HIV/AIDS"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471389</id><title>Mutational cascade of SARS-CoV-2 leading to evolution and emergence of omicron variant (36 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.370185+00:00</updated><author><name>Kanika Bansal</name></author><author><name>Sanjeet Kumar</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Emergence of new variant of SARS-CoV-2, namely omicron, has posed a global concern because of its high rate of transmissibility and mutations in its genome. Researchers worldwide are trying to understand the evolution and emergence of such variants to understand the mutational cascade events.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have considered all omicron genomes (n = 302 genomes) available till 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; December 2021 in the public repository of GISAID along with representatives of variants of concern (VOC), i.e., alpha, beta, gamma, delta, and omicron; variant of interest (VOI) mu and lambda; and variant under monitoring (VUM). Whole genome-based phylogeny and mutational analysis were performed to understand the evolution of SARS CoV-2 leading to emergence of omicron variant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whole genome-based phylogeny depicted two phylogroups (PG-I and PG-II) forming variant specific clades except for gamma and VUM GH. Mutational analysis detected 18,261 mutations in the omicron variant, majority of which were non-synonymous mutations in spike (A67, T547K, D614G, H655Y, N679K, P681H, D796Y, N856K, Q954H), followed by RNA dependent RNA polymerase (rdrp) (A1892T, I189V, P314L, K38R, T492I, V57V), ORF6 (M19M) and nucleocapsid protein (RG203KR).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Delta and omicron have evolutionary diverged into distinct phylogroups and do not share a common ancestry. While, omicron shares common ancestry with VOI lambda and its evolution is mainly derived by the non-synonymous mutations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471389" rel="alternate" title="Mutational cascade of SARS-CoV-2 leading to evolution and emergence of omicron variant (36 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471455</id><title>Loss of Neutralizing Antibody Response to mRNA Vaccination against SARS-CoV-2 Variants: Differing Kinetics and Strong Boosting by Breakthrough Infection (36 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.370352+00:00</updated><author><name>John P. Evans</name></author><author><name>Cong Zeng</name></author><author><name>Claire Carlin</name></author><author><name>Gerard Lozanski</name></author><author><name>Linda J. Saif</name></author><author><name>Eugene M. Oltz</name></author><author><name>Richard J. Gumina</name></author><author><name>Shan-Lu Liu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The waning efficacy of SARS-CoV-2 vaccines combined with the continued emergence of variants resistant to vaccine-induced immunity has reignited debate over the need for booster vaccines. To address this, we examined the neutralizing antibody (nAb) response against four major SARS-CoV-2 variants—D614G, Alpha (B.1.1.7), Beta (B.1.351), and Delta (B.1.617.2)—in health care workers (HCWs) at pre-vaccination, post-first and post-second mRNA vaccine dose, and six months post-second mRNA vaccine dose. Neutralizing antibody titers against all variants, especially the Delta variant, declined dramatically from four weeks to six months post-second mRNA vaccine dose. Notably, SARS-CoV-2 infection enhanced vaccine durability, and mRNA-1273 vaccinated HCWs also exhibited ~2-fold higher nAb titers than BNT162b2 vaccinated HCWs. Together these results demonstrate possible waning of protection from infection against SARS-CoV-2 Delta variant based on decreased nAb titers, dependent on COVID-19 status and the mRNA vaccine received.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471455" rel="alternate" title="Loss of Neutralizing Antibody Response to mRNA Vaccination against SARS-CoV-2 Variants: Differing Kinetics and Strong Boosting by Breakthrough Infection (36 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.21267516</id><title>Changes in the trajectory of Long Covid symptoms following COVID-19 vaccination: community-based cohort study (35 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.370734+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Ayoubkhani</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Bermingham</name></author><author><name>Koen B. Pouwels</name></author><author><name>Myer Glickman</name></author><author><name>Vahé Nafilyan</name></author><author><name>Francesco Zaccardi</name></author><author><name>Kamlesh Khunti</name></author><author><name>Nisreen A. Alwan</name></author><author><name>A. Sarah Walker</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To estimate associations between COVID-19 vaccination and Long Covid symptoms in adults who were infected with SARS-CoV-2 prior to vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Observational cohort study using individual-level interrupted time series analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Random sample from the community population of the UK.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;28,356 COVID-19 Infection Survey participants (mean age 46 years, 56% female, 89% white) aged 18 to 69 years who received at least their first vaccination after test-confirmed infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main outcome measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Presence of long Covid symptoms at least 12 weeks after infection over the follow-up period 3 February to 5 September 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Median follow-up was 141 days from first vaccination (among all participants) and 67 days from second vaccination (84% of participants). First vaccination was associated with an initial 12.8% decrease (95% confidence interval: −18.6% to −6.6%) in the odds of Long Covid, but increasing by 0.3% (−0.6% to +1.2%) per week after the first dose. Second vaccination was associated with an 8.8% decrease (−14.1% to −3.1%) in the odds of Long Covid, with the odds subsequently decreasing by 0.8% (−1.2% to −0.4%) per week. There was no statistical evidence of heterogeneity in associations between vaccination and Long Covid by socio-demographic characteristics, health status, whether hospitalised with acute COVID-19, vaccine type (adenovirus vector or mRNA), or duration from infection to vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The likelihood of Long Covid symptoms reduced after COVID-19 vaccination, and the improvement was sustained over the follow-up period after the second dose. Vaccination may contribute to a reduction in the population health burden of Long Covid, though longer follow-up time is needed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary box&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;What is already known on this topic&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 vaccines are effective at reducing rates of SARS-CoV-2 infection, transmission, hospitalisation, and death&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The incidence of Long Covid may be reduced if infected after vaccination, but the relationship between vaccination and pre-existing long COVID symptoms is unclear, as published studies are generally small and with self-selected participants&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;What this study adds&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The likelihood of Long Covid symptoms reduced after COVID-19 vaccination, and the improvement was sustained over the follow-up period after the second dose&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was no evidence of differences in this relationship by socio-demographic characteristics, health-related factors, vaccine type, or duration from infection to vaccination&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although causality cannot be inferred from this observational evidence, vaccination may contribute to a reduction in the population health burden of Long Covid; further research is needed to understand the biological mechanisms that may ultimately contribute to the development of therapeutics for Long Covid&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.21267516" rel="alternate" title="Changes in the trajectory of Long Covid symptoms following COVID-19 vaccination: community-based cohort study (35 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.21267339</id><title>Systematic review of cardiac adverse effects in children and young people under 18 years of age after SARS-CoV-2 vaccination (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.371068+00:00</updated><author><name>Joana Cruz</name></author><author><name>Amedine Duret</name></author><author><name>Rachel Harwood</name></author><author><name>Lorna K. Fraser</name></author><author><name>Caroline B. Jones</name></author><author><name>Joseph Ward</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Whittaker</name></author><author><name>Simon E. Kenny</name></author><author><name>Russell M. Viner</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reports of myocarditis and pericarditis following vaccination with mRNA vaccines for SARS-CoV-2 have occurred after countries began vaccinating adolescents. We undertook a systematic review of cardiac adverse effects associated with SARS-CoV-2 vaccine in children and young people (CYP)&amp;lt; 18 years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Systematic review with protocol prospectively registered with PROSPERO (CRD42021275380).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Six electronic databases were searched from 1 December 2019 to 14 September 2021. Eligible studies were those reporting on CYP with reported or proven myocarditis, pericarditis and/or myopericarditis associated with vaccination against SARS-CoV-2. We summarized findings across all clinical cases reported in case report / case series studies. As a number of studies reported data from two publicly available vaccine surveillance systems, we updated estimates of reporting rates for cardiac adverse events up to 31 October for the US Vaccine Adverse Event Reporting System (VAERS) and 13 November for EudraVigilance covering European Union and European Economic Area (EUEA) countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Twenty-one studies were included from 338 identified records. Seventeen were case reports/series describing a total of 127 CYP. Three studies described reporting rates from passive surveillance databases (VAERS, EudraVigilance, and the WHO VigiBase) and one described 22 cases from the US Vaccine Safety Datalink (VSD).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clinical series reported that 99.2% presented with chest pain, 100% had raised troponin and 73.8% had an abnormal ECG. Cardiovascular magnetic resonance (CMR) in 91 cases identified myocardial injury in 61.5%, with 90.1% showing late gadolinium enhancement. NSAIDs were the most common treatment (76.0%).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One US dataset (VSD) estimated a significant excess of 29.6 events per million vaccine doses across both sexes and doses. There were 1129 reports of myocarditis and 358 reports of pericarditis from across the USA and EU/EEA. The VAERS reporting rate per million for myocarditis was 12.4 for boys and 1.4 for girls after the first dose, and 49.6 for boys and 6.1 for girls after the second dose. There was a marked trend for VAERS reporting to be highest soon after initiation of the vaccine schedule, suggesting reporting bias.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cardiac adverse effects are very rare after mRNA vaccination for COVID-19 in CYP &amp;lt;18 years. The great majority of cases are mild and self-limiting without significant treatment. No data are yet available on children under 12 years. Larger detailed longitudinal studies are urgently needed from active surveillance sources.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.21267339" rel="alternate" title="Systematic review of cardiac adverse effects in children and young people under 18 years of age after SARS-CoV-2 vaccination (31 tweets)"/><category term="Pediatrics"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471284</id><title>A remote lecture series roadmap to equity, diversity, and inclusion in STEM (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.371329+00:00</updated><author><name>Evan A. Boyle</name></author><author><name>Gabriela Goldberg</name></author><author><name>Jonathan C. Schmok</name></author><author><name>Jillybeth Burgado</name></author><author><name>Fabiana Izidro Layng</name></author><author><name>Hannah A. Grunwald</name></author><author><name>Kylie M. Balotin</name></author><author><name>Michael S. Cuoco</name></author><author><name>Keng-Chi Chang</name></author><author><name>Gertrude Ecklu-Mensah</name></author><author><name>Aleena K. S. Arakaki</name></author><author><name>Noorsher Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Ximena Garcia Arceo</name></author><author><name>Pratibha Jagannatha</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Pekar</name></author><author><name>Mallika Iyer</name></author><author><name>Gene W. Yeo</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Within a year of the shutdowns caused by the COVID-19 pandemic, virtual meetings transformed from an auxiliary service to an essential work platform for hundreds of millions of people worldwide. Universities rapidly accelerated adoption of virtual platforms for remote conferences, classes, and seminars amidst a second crisis testing institutional commitment to the principles of equity, diversity, and inclusion. Here we present thorough guidelines for drawing out hope from the Pandora’s box of virtual programming now open to the world. We review milestones from our first year organizing the Diversity and Science Lecture series (DASL) and explore insights into equity, diversity, and inclusion in STEM gleaned from hosted speakers’ talk content. Nearly every speaker highlighted the importance of social or interpersonal support to their career progression, and three-fifths of speakers commented on race or ethnicity. Other recurring topics each received attention from a minority of speakers: immigrant identity, gender identity, mental health, sexual minorities, disability, and rural or agricultural background. We conclude with generalizable advice on creating new remote lecture series that benefit executive team members, speakers, and attendees. Our success with DASL demonstrates that community building and knowledge sharing can flourish under a remote lecture framework.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471284" rel="alternate" title="A remote lecture series roadmap to equity, diversity, and inclusion in STEM (30 tweets)"/><category term="Scientific Communication and Education"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471707</id><title>Delta breakthrough infections elicit potent, broad and durable neutralizing antibody responses (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.371761+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexandra C Walls</name></author><author><name>Kaitlin R Sprouse</name></author><author><name>Anshu Joshi</name></author><author><name>John E Bowen</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Franko</name></author><author><name>Mary-Jane Navarro</name></author><author><name>Cameron Stewart</name></author><author><name>Matthew McCallum</name></author><author><name>Erin A Goecker</name></author><author><name>Emily J Degli-Angeli</name></author><author><name>Jenni Logue</name></author><author><name>Alex Greninger</name></author><author><name>David Veesler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The SARS-CoV-2 Delta variant is currently responsible for most infections worldwide, including among vaccinated individuals. Although these latter infections lead to milder COVID-19 disease relative to unvaccinated subjects, the specificity and durability of antibody responses elicited by Delta breakthrough cases remain unknown. Here, we demonstrate that breakthrough infections induce serum binding and neutralizing antibody responses that are markedly more potent, durable and resilient to spike mutations observed in variants than those observed in subjects who were infected only or received only two doses of vaccine. We show that Delta breakthrough cases, subjects who were vaccinated after infection and individuals vaccinated three times (without infection) have serum neutralizing activity of comparable magnitude and breadth, indicating that multiple types of exposure or increased number of exposures to SARS-CoV-2 antigen(s) enhance antibody responses. Neutralization of SARS-CoV, however, was moderate, underscoring the importance of developing vaccines eliciting broad sarbecovirus immunity for pandemic preparedness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471707" rel="alternate" title="Delta breakthrough infections elicit potent, broad and durable neutralizing antibody responses (27 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471263</id><title>The structural role of SARS-CoV-2 genetic background in the emergence and success of spike mutations: the case of the spike A222V mutation (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.372093+00:00</updated><author><name>Tiziana Ginex</name></author><author><name>Clara Marco-Marín</name></author><author><name>Miłosz Wieczór</name></author><author><name>Carlos P. Mata</name></author><author><name>James Krieger</name></author><author><name>Maria Luisa López-Redondo</name></author><author><name>Clara Francés-Gómez</name></author><author><name>Paula Ruiz-Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Roberto Melero</name></author><author><name>Carlos Óscar Sánchez-Sorzano</name></author><author><name>Marta Martínez</name></author><author><name>Nadine Gougeard</name></author><author><name>Alicia Forcada-Nadal</name></author><author><name>Sara Zamora-Caballero</name></author><author><name>Roberto Gozalbo-Rovira</name></author><author><name>Carla Sanz-Frasquet</name></author><author><name>Jeronimo Bravo</name></author><author><name>Vicente Rubio</name></author><author><name>Alberto Marina</name></author><author><name>Ron Geller</name></author><author><name>Iñaki Comas</name></author><author><name>Carmen Gil</name></author><author><name>Mireia Coscolla</name></author><author><name>Modesto Orozco</name></author><author><name>José Luis Llácer</name></author><author><name>José-Maria Carazo</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The S:A222V point mutation, within the G clade, was characteristic of the 20E (EU1) SARS-CoV-2 variant identified in Spain in early summer 2020. This mutation has now reappeared in the Delta subvariant AY.4.2, raising questions about its specific effect on viral infection. We report combined serological, functional, structural and computational studies characterizing the impact of this mutation. Our results reveal that S:A222V promotes an increased RBD opening and slightly increases ACE2 binding as compared to the parent S:D614G clade. Finally, S:A222V does not reduce sera neutralization capacity, suggesting it does not affect vaccine effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471263" rel="alternate" title="The structural role of SARS-CoV-2 genetic background in the emergence and success of spike mutations: the case of the spike A222V mutation (22 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.21267238</id><title>Parental perspectives on the grief and support needs of children and young people bereaved during the Covid-19 pandemic: Qualitative findings from a national survey (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.372570+00:00</updated><author><name>Emily Harrop</name></author><author><name>Silvia Goss</name></author><author><name>Mirella Longo</name></author><author><name>Kathy Seddon</name></author><author><name>Anna Torrens-Burton</name></author><author><name>Eileen Sutton</name></author><author><name>Damian JJ Farnell</name></author><author><name>Alison Penny</name></author><author><name>Annmarie Nelson</name></author><author><name>Anthony Byrne</name></author><author><name>Lucy E. Selman</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the Covid-19 pandemic, many children and young people have experienced the death of close family members, whilst also facing unprecedented disruption to their lives. This study aimed to investigate the experiences and support needs of bereaved children and young people from the perspective of their parents and guardians.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We analysed cross-sectional qualitative free-text data from a survey of adults bereaved in the UK during the pandemic. Participants were recruited via media, social media, national associations and community/charitable organisations. Thematic analysis was conducted on free text data collected from parent/guardian participants in response to a survey question on the bereavement experiences and support needs of their children.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Free-text data from 104 parent and grandparent participants was included. Three main themes were identified: the pandemic-related challenges and struggles experienced by children and young people; family support and coping; and support from schools and services. Pandemic-related challenges include the impacts of being separated from the relative prior to their death, isolation from peers and other family members, and disruption to daily routines and wider support networks. Examples were given of effective family coping and communication, but also of difficulties relating to parental grief and children’s existing mental health problems. Schools and bereavement organisations’ provision of specialist support was valued, but there was evidence of unmet need, with some participants reporting a lack of access to specialist grief or mental health support.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Children and young people have faced additional strains and challenges associated with pandemic bereavement. We recommend resources and initiatives that facilitate supportive communication within family and school settings, adequate resourcing of school and community-based specialist bereavement/mental health services, and increased information and signposting to the support that is available.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.21267238" rel="alternate" title="Parental perspectives on the grief and support needs of children and young people bereaved during the Covid-19 pandemic: Qualitative findings from a national survey (21 tweets)"/><category term="Pediatrics"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471153</id><title>Elucidating design principles for engineering cell-derived vesicles to inhibit SARS-CoV-2 infection (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.372849+00:00</updated><author><name>Taylor Franklin Gunnels</name></author><author><name>Devin M Stranford</name></author><author><name>Roxana E Mitrut</name></author><author><name>Neha Kamat</name></author><author><name>Joshua Nathaniel Leonard</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ability of pathogens to develop drug resistance is a global health challenge. The SARS-CoV-2 virus presents an urgent need wherein several variants of concern resist neutralization by monoclonal antibody therapies and vaccine-induced sera. Decoy nanoparticles (cell-mimicking particles that bind and inhibit virions) are an emerging class of therapeutics that may overcome such drug resistance challenges. To date, we lack quantitative understanding as to how design features impact performance of these therapeutics. To address this gap, here we perform a systematic, comparative evaluation of various biologically-derived nanoscale vesicles, which may be particularly well-suited to sustained or repeated administration in the clinic due to low toxicity, and investigate their potential to inhibit multiple classes of model SARS-CoV-2 virions. A key finding is that such particles exhibit potent antiviral efficacy across multiple manufacturing methods, vesicle subclasses, and virus-decoy binding affinities. In addition, these cell-mimicking vesicles effectively inhibit model SARS-CoV-2 variants that evade monoclonal antibodies and recombinant protein-based decoy inhibitors. This study provides a foundation of knowledge that may guide the design of decoy nanoparticle inhibitors for SARS-CoV-2 and other viral infections.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471153" rel="alternate" title="Elucidating design principles for engineering cell-derived vesicles to inhibit SARS-CoV-2 infection (20 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.21267499</id><title>Modeling COVID-19 Aerosol Transmission in Primary Schools (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.373141+00:00</updated><author><name>Tessa Swanson</name></author><author><name>Seth Guikema</name></author><author><name>James Bagian</name></author><author><name>Claire Payne</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Schools must balance public health, education, and social risks associated with returning to in-person learning. These risks are compounded by the ongoing uncertainty about vaccine availability and uptake for children under 12 years of age. In this paper, we show how the risk of infections that result directly from in-class aerosol transmission within an elementary school population can be estimated in order to compare the effects of different countermeasures. We compare the effectiveness of these countermeasures in reducing transmission including required masking at three levels of mask effectiveness, improving room airflow exchange rates, weekly testing of the students, and lunch partitioning. Our results show that multiple layers of interventions are necessary to keep in-class infections relatively low. These results can inform school administrators about how these interventions can help manage COVID-19 spread within their own elementary school populations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.21267499" rel="alternate" title="Modeling COVID-19 Aerosol Transmission in Primary Schools (20 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471245</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 infection of olfactory epithelial cells and neurons drives acute lung injury and lethal COVID-19 in mice (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.376179+00:00</updated><author><name>Alan T. Tang</name></author><author><name>David W. Buchholz</name></author><author><name>Katherine M. Szigety</name></author><author><name>Brian Imbhiaka</name></author><author><name>Siqi Gao</name></author><author><name>Maxwell Frankfurter</name></author><author><name>Min Wang</name></author><author><name>Jisheng Yang</name></author><author><name>Peter Hewins</name></author><author><name>Patricia Mericko-Ishizuka</name></author><author><name>N Adrian Leu</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Sterling</name></author><author><name>Isaac A. Monreal</name></author><author><name>Julie Sahler</name></author><author><name>Avery August</name></author><author><name>Xuming Zhu</name></author><author><name>Kellie A. Jurado</name></author><author><name>Mingang Xu</name></author><author><name>Edward E. Morrisey</name></author><author><name>Sarah E. Millar</name></author><author><name>Hector C. Aguilar</name></author><author><name>Mark L. Kahn</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Lethal COVID-19 is associated with respiratory failure that is thought to be caused by acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) secondary to pulmonary infection. To date, the cellular pathogenesis has been inferred from studies describing the expression of ACE2, a transmembrane protein required for SARS-CoV-2 infection, and detection of viral RNA or protein in infected humans, model animals, and cultured cells. To functionally test the cellular mechanisms of COVID-19, we generated &lt;italic&gt;hACE2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;fl&lt;/sup&gt; animals in which human ACE2 (hACE2) is expressed from the mouse &lt;italic&gt;Ace2&lt;/italic&gt; locus in a manner that permits cell-specific, Cre-mediated loss of function. &lt;italic&gt;hACE2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;fl&lt;/sup&gt; animals developed lethal weight loss and hypoxemia within 7 days of exposure to SARS-CoV-2 that was associated with pulmonary infiltrates, intravascular thrombosis and patchy viral infection of lung epithelial cells. Deletion of hACE2 in lung epithelial cells prevented viral infection of the lung, but not weight loss, hypoxemia or death. Inhalation of SARS-CoV-2 by &lt;italic&gt;hACE2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;fl&lt;/sup&gt; animals resulted in early infection of sustentacular cells with subsequent infection of neurons in the neighboring olfactory bulb and cerebral cortex— events that did not require lung epithelial cell infection. Pharmacologic ablation of the olfactory epithelium or &lt;italic&gt;Foxg1&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Cre&lt;/sup&gt; mediated deletion of hACE2 in olfactory epithelial cells and neurons prevented lethality and neuronal infection following SARS-CoV-2 infection. Conversely, transgenic expression of hACE2 specifically in olfactory epithelial cells and neurons in &lt;italic&gt;Foxg1&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Cre&lt;/sup&gt;; LSL-&lt;italic&gt;hACE2&lt;/italic&gt; mice was sufficient to confer neuronal infection associated with respiratory failure and death. These studies establish mouse loss and gain of function genetic models with which to genetically dissect viral-host interactions and demonstrate that lethal disease due to respiratory failure may arise from extrapulmonary infection of the olfactory epithelium and brain. Future therapeutic efforts focused on preventing olfactory epithelial infection may be an effective means of protecting against severe COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471245" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 infection of olfactory epithelial cells and neurons drives acute lung injury and lethal COVID-19 in mice (16 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.21267494</id><title>Omicron strain spreads with the doubling time of 3.2—3.6 days in South Africa province of Gauteng that achieved herd immunity to Delta variant (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.376949+00:00</updated><author><name>Frederic Grabowski</name></author><author><name>Marek Kochańczyk</name></author><author><name>Tomasz Lipniacki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Omicron, the novel, highly mutated SARS-CoV-2 Variant of Concern (belonging to the Pango lineage B.1.1.529), was first collected on November 8, 2021, in Gauteng province of South Africa. By the end of November 2021 it has spread towards fixation in Gauteng and was detected on all continents. Based on data collected till December 7, 2021, we showed the exponential growth of the Omicron variant over the four-week period in Gauteng (November 8–December 5, 2021) with the doubling time equal 3.38 day [CI 95%: 3.18–3.61 day]. Log–linear regression suggests that the spread began around October 10, 2021, however due to stochasticity in the initial spread this estimate is likely inaccurate. Phylogenetic analysis indicates that the Omicron strain started to diverge in between October 28 and November 5, 2021. This implies that the hidden spread of Omicron before October 10, 2021 (which would suggest slower strain growth) is unlikely. The very short doubling time of Omicron in Gauteng, a province that has reached herd immunity to the Delta variant (implied by the decrease of the weekly number of cases between July and October, 2021, at no significant mobility restrictions), suggests that Omicron will cause abrupt outbreaks of COVID-19 epidemics across the world, and will become the (temporarily) dominant strain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.21267494" rel="alternate" title="Omicron strain spreads with the doubling time of 3.2—3.6 days in South Africa province of Gauteng that achieved herd immunity to Delta variant (14 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471198</id><title>Modeling the trajectory of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein evolution in continuous latent space using a neural network and Gaussian process (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.377298+00:00</updated><author><name>Samuel King</name></author><author><name>Xinyi E. Chen</name></author><author><name>Sarah W. S. Ng</name></author><author><name>Kimia Rostin</name></author><author><name>Tylo Roberts</name></author><author><name>Samuel V. Hahn</name></author><author><name>Janella C. Schwab</name></author><author><name>Parneet Sekhon</name></author><author><name>Madina Kagieva</name></author><author><name>Taylor Reilly</name></author><author><name>Ruo Chen Qi</name></author><author><name>Paarsa Salman</name></author><author><name>Ryan J. Hong</name></author><author><name>Eric J. Ma</name></author><author><name>Steven J. Hallam</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Viral vaccines can lose their efficacy as the genomes of targeted viruses rapidly evolve, resulting in new variants that may evade vaccine-induced immunity. This process is apparent in the emergence of new SARS-CoV-2 variants which have the potential to undermine vaccination efforts and cause further outbreaks. Predictive vaccinology points to a future of pandemic preparedness in which vaccines can be developed preemptively based in part on predictive models of viral evolution. Thus, modeling the trajectory of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein evolution could have value for mRNA vaccine development. Traditionally, &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; sequence evolution has been modeled discretely, while there has been limited investigation into continuous models. Here we present the Viral Predictor for mRNA Evolution (VPRE), an open-source software tool which learns from mutational patterns in viral proteins and models their most statistically likely evolutionary trajectories. We trained a variational autoencoder with real-time and simulated SARS-CoV-2 genome data from Australia to encode discrete spike protein sequences into continuous numerical variables. To simulate evolution along a phylogenetic path, we trained a Gaussian process model with the numerical variables to project spike protein evolution up to five months in advance. Our predictions mapped primarily to a sequence that differed by a single amino acid from the most reported spike protein in Australia within the prediction timeframe, indicating the utility of deep learning and continuous latent spaces for modeling viral protein evolution. VPRE can be readily adapted to investigate and predict the evolution of viruses other than SARS-CoV-2 in temporal, geographic, and lineage-specific pathways.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471198" rel="alternate" title="Modeling the trajectory of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein evolution in continuous latent space using a neural network and Gaussian process (14 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471131</id><title>Plant-based expression of SARS-CoV-2 antigens for use in an oral vaccine (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.377681+00:00</updated><author><name>Monique Power</name></author><author><name>Taha Azad</name></author><author><name>John C Bell</name></author><author><name>Allyson MacLean</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Oral and intra-nasal vaccines represent a key means of inducing mucosal-based immunity against infection with SARS-CoV-2, yet such vaccines represent only a minority of candidates currently in development. In this brief communication, we assessed the expression of the SARS-CoV-2 Receptor Binding Domain (RBD) subunit of the surface-exposed Spike (S) glycoprotein in the leaves of nine edible plant species (lettuce, spinach, collard greens, tomato, cucumber, radish, arugula, pepper, and Coho greens), with a goal of identifying a suitable candidate for the development of a oral vaccine against COVID-19. We report lettuce (Lactuca sativa L. cv. Hilde II Improved) to be a preferred host to support in planta expression of SARS-CoV-2 RBD, representing an important first step towards development of a plant-based oral vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471131" rel="alternate" title="Plant-based expression of SARS-CoV-2 antigens for use in an oral vaccine (14 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471236</id><title>An antibody-escape calculator for mutations to the SARS-CoV-2 receptor-binding domain (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.377882+00:00</updated><author><name>Allison J. Greaney</name></author><author><name>Tyler N. Starr</name></author><author><name>Jesse D. Bloom</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A key goal of SARS-CoV-2 surveillance is to rapidly identify viral variants with mutations that reduce neutralization by polyclonal antibodies elicited by vaccination or infection. Unfortunately, direct experimental characterization of new viral variants lags their sequence-based identification. Here we help address this challenge by aggregating deep mutational scanning data into an “escape calculator” that estimates the antigenic effects of arbitrary combinations of mutations to the virus’s spike receptor-binding domain (RBD). The calculator can be used to intuitively visualize how mutations impact polyclonal antibody recognition, and score the expected antigenic effect of combinations of mutations. These scores correlate with neutralization assays performed on SARS-CoV-2 variants, and emphasize the ominous antigenic properties of the recently described Omicron variant. An interactive version of the calculator is at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://jbloomlab.github.io/SARS2_RBD_Ab_escape_maps/escape-calc/"&gt;https://jbloomlab.github.io/SARS2_RBD_Ab_escape_maps/escape-calc/&lt;/ext-link&gt;, and we provide a Python module for batch processing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471236" rel="alternate" title="An antibody-escape calculator for mutations to the SARS-CoV-2 receptor-binding domain (13 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.21267483</id><title>Risk of hospitalization and mortality after breakthrough SARS-CoV-2 infection by vaccine type and previous SARS-CoV-2 infection utilizing medical claims data (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.378062+00:00</updated><author><name>Meghana Kshirsagar</name></author><author><name>Sumit Mukherjee</name></author><author><name>Md Nasir</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Becker</name></author><author><name>Juan Lavista Ferres</name></author><author><name>Barbra A. Richardson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We compare the risks of hospitalization (n=1121) and mortality (n=138) in a cohort of 17,881 breakthrough SARS-CoV-2 infections for the Pfizer, Moderna and Janssen vaccines for those with and without SARS-CoV-2 infections prior to vaccination. Cox regression analysis results in a lower hazard ratio for those receiving the Moderna vaccine, but a significantly higher hazard ratio for those receiving the Janssen vaccine, as compared to those who got the Pfizer vaccine. Importantly, the risk of hospitalization (P&amp;lt;0.001) and death (P&amp;lt;0.05) were lower among individuals who had a SARS-CoV-2 infection prior to vaccination, independent of age, sex, comorbidities, and vaccine type.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.21267483" rel="alternate" title="Risk of hospitalization and mortality after breakthrough SARS-CoV-2 infection by vaccine type and previous SARS-CoV-2 infection utilizing medical claims data (12 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.21266089</id><title>Post-Vaccination Symptoms after A Third Dose of mRNA SARS-CoV-2 Vaccination in Patients with Inflammatory Bowel Disease (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.378269+00:00</updated><author><name>Dalin Li</name></author><author><name>Philip Debbas</name></author><author><name>Susan Cheng</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Braun</name></author><author><name>Dermot P.B. McGovern</name></author><author><name>Gil Y. Melmed</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Symptoms after SARS-CoV-2 primary vaccination among patients with inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) are generally of similar frequency, severity, and duration to those reported in the general population. The symptom profile after a 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; mRNA vaccine dose in the predominantly immune-compromised IBD population is unknown. We aimed to assess symptomology after a 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; or booster dose of mRNA vaccination in adults with IBD. We surveyed participants of the Coronavirus Risk Associations and Longitudinal Evaluation in IBD (CORALE-IBD) post-vaccination registry for symptom frequency and severity after a 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; mRNA vaccine dose in an observational cohort study. In total, 524 participants (70% female, mean age 45 years) reported a third dose of mRNA vaccination through October 11, 2021. Overall, 41% reported symptoms after a third dose, with symptoms generally more frequent and more severe among participants younger than 55 years. The most frequent postvaccination symptoms were injection site pain (39%), fatigue or malaise (34%), and headache (23%). These symptoms were all less frequently reported after dose 3 than after dose 2. Gastrointestinal symptoms were reported by 8.8%, which was slightly more frequent than after dose 2 (7.8%). Those with severe symptoms after dose 2 were more likely to have severe symptoms after dose 3. These findings can reassure the IBD patient and provider communities that the likelihood and distribution of symptoms after a third mRNA vaccine dose are generally similar to those after a second dose, and that the frequency of postvaccination symptoms after dose 3 are generally lower than after dose 2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.21266089" rel="alternate" title="Post-Vaccination Symptoms after A Third Dose of mRNA SARS-CoV-2 Vaccination in Patients with Inflammatory Bowel Disease (12 tweets)"/><category term="Gastroenterology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.21267000</id><title>A One-Step open RT-qPCR for SARS-CoV-2 detection (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.378477+00:00</updated><author><name>Ariel Cerda</name></author><author><name>Maira Rivera</name></author><author><name>Grace Armijo</name></author><author><name>Catalina Ibarra-Henriquez</name></author><author><name>Javiera Reyes</name></author><author><name>Paula Blázquez-Sánchez</name></author><author><name>Javiera Avilés</name></author><author><name>Aníbal Arce</name></author><author><name>Aldo Seguel</name></author><author><name>Alexander J. Brown</name></author><author><name>Yesseny Vásquez</name></author><author><name>Marcelo Cortez-San Martín</name></author><author><name>Francisco Cubillos</name></author><author><name>Patricia García</name></author><author><name>Marcela Ferres</name></author><author><name>César A. Ramírez-Sarmiento</name></author><author><name>Fernán Federici</name></author><author><name>Rodrigo A. Gutiérrez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), etiological agent of the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), is currently detected by reverse transcription followed by quantitative polymerase chain reaction (RT-qPCR) of its viral RNA genome. Within the available alternatives, One-Step procedures are preferred since they are fast and significantly decrease preanalytical errors, minimizing the risk of diagnostic errors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Increasing the testing capacity and tracing contacts are essential steps to control the pandemic. However, high-cost commercial reagents subject to shortage and poor scalability have hindered the use of these technologies and their adoption for a wide population-scale testing, being even more critical in developing countries. In the current context, open-source initiatives have promoted global collaboration to promote accessible solutions for rapid local deployment. As a result, open protocols are being developed for the local production of SARS-CoV-2 diagnostics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This work aimed to produce an open-source system for SARS-CoV-2 diagnostic tests in RNA clinical samples. We provide guidelines for standardizing an open One-Step RT-qPCR master mix using recombinant M-MLV reverse transcriptase together with either Pfu-Sso7d or Taq DNA polymerase. Both were tested on synthetic RNA and clinical samples, observing a good correlation when compared to commercial RT-qPCR kits. Nevertheless, the best results were obtained using M-MLV RT combined with Taq DNA polymerase in a probe-based RT-qPCR assay, allowing successful discrimination between positive and negative samples with accuracies comparable to a CDC-recommended commercial kit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we demonstrate that these open RT-qPCR systems can be successfully used to identify SARS-CoV-2 in clinical samples and potentially be implemented in any molecular diagnostic laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.21267000" rel="alternate" title="A One-Step open RT-qPCR for SARS-CoV-2 detection (11 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471277</id><title>A zebrafish model of COVID-19-associated cytokine storm syndrome reveals differential proinflammatory activities of Spike proteins of SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.378803+00:00</updated><author><name>Sylwia D. Tyrkalska</name></author><author><name>Alicia Martínez-López</name></author><author><name>Ana B. Arroyo</name></author><author><name>Francisco J. Martínez-Morcillo</name></author><author><name>Sergio Candel</name></author><author><name>Diana García-Moreno</name></author><author><name>Pablo Mesa-del-Castillo</name></author><author><name>María L. Cayuela</name></author><author><name>Victoriano Mulero</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The sudden and unexpected appearance of the COVID-19 pandemic turned the whole world upside down in a very short time. One of the main challenges faced has been to understand COVID-19 patient heterogeneity, as a minority develop life-threatening hyperinflammation, the so-called cytokine storm syndrome (CSS). Using the unique advantages of the zebrafish model we report here the proinflammatory role of Spike (S) proteins from different SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern after injection into the hindbrain ventricle, a cavity filled with cerebrospinal fluid to which immune cells can be easily recruited and that mimics the alveolar environment of the human lung. We found that wild type/Wuhan variant S1 (S1WT) protein promoted neutrophil and macrophage recruitment, local and systemic hyperinflammation, emergency myelopoiesis, and hemorrhages. In addition, S1γ protein was more proinflammatory and S1δ was less proinflammatory than S1WT and, strikingly, S1β promoted delayed and long-lasting inflammation. Pharmacological inhibition of the canonical inflammasome robustly alleviated S1 protein-induced inflammation and emergency myelopoiesis. In contrast, genetic inhibition of angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 strengthened the proinflammatory activity of S1, and the administration of angiopoietin (1-7) fully rescued S1-induced hyperinflammation and hemorrhages. These results shed light into the mechanisms orchestrating the COVID-19-associated CSS and the host immune response to different SARS-CoV-2 S protein variants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;S proteins of SARS-CoV-2 promote hyperinflammation, neutrophilia, monocytosis and hemorrhages in zebrafish.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;S protein effects in zebrafish are mediated via the canonical inflammasome and the Ace2/Angiopoietin (1-7) axis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Delta S1 is less proinflammatory than wild type S1 and fails to induce emergency myelopoiesis in zebrafish.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Naïve and primed human white blood cells are unable to respond to S proteins.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471277" rel="alternate" title="A zebrafish model of COVID-19-associated cytokine storm syndrome reveals differential proinflammatory activities of Spike proteins of SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (11 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471421</id><title>Metabolic dysregulation induces impaired lymphocyte memory formation during severe SARS-CoV-2 infection (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.379042+00:00</updated><author><name>Sanjeev Gurshaney</name></author><author><name>Anamaria Morales Alvarez</name></author><author><name>Kevin Ezhakunnel</name></author><author><name>Andrew Manalo</name></author><author><name>Thien-Huong Huynh</name></author><author><name>Nhat-Tu Le</name></author><author><name>Daniel S. Lupu</name></author><author><name>Stephen J. Gardell</name></author><author><name>Hung Nguyen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cellular metabolic dysregulation is a consequence of COVID-19 infection that is a key determinant of disease severity. To understand the mechanisms underlying these cellular changes, we performed high-dimensional immune cell profiling of PBMCs from COVID-19-infected patients, in combination with single cell transcriptomic analysis of COVID-19 BALFs. Hypoxia, a hallmark of COVID-19 ARDS, was found to elicit a global metabolic reprogramming in effector lymphocytes. In response to oxygen and nutrient-deprived microenvironments, these cells shift from aerobic respiration to increase their dependence on anaerobic processes including glycolysis, mitophagy, and glutaminolysis to fulfill their bioenergetic demands. We also demonstrate metabolic dysregulation of ciliated lung epithelial cells is linked to significant increase of proinflammatory cytokine secretion and upregulation of HLA class 1 machinery. Augmented HLA class-1 antigen stimulation by epithelial cells leads to cellular exhaustion of metabolically dysregulated CD8 and NK cells, impairing their memory cell differentiation. Unsupervised clustering techniques revealed multiple distinct, differentially abundant CD8 and NK memory cell states that are marked by high glycolytic flux, mitochondrial dysfunction, and cellular exhaustion, further highlighting the connection between disrupted metabolism and impaired memory cell function in COVID-19. Our findings provide novel insight on how SARS-CoV-2 infection affects host immunometabolism and anti-viral response during COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="471421v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hypoxia and anaerobic glycolysis drive CD8, NK, NKT dysfunction&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hypoxia and anaerobic glycolysis impair memory differentiation in CD8 and NK cells&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hypoxia and anaerobic glycolysis cause mitochondrial dysfunction in CD8, NK, NKT cells&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471421" rel="alternate" title="Metabolic dysregulation induces impaired lymphocyte memory formation during severe SARS-CoV-2 infection (10 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.21267301</id><title>Investigation of Vaccine Breakthrough Infections by Vaccine strategy during the Delta Variant Wave in France (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.379271+00:00</updated><author><name>Antonin Bal</name></author><author><name>Grégory Destras</name></author><author><name>Bruno Simon</name></author><author><name>Jean-Marc Giannoli</name></author><author><name>Florence Morfin</name></author><author><name>Bruno Lina</name></author><author><name>Laurence Josset</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Herein, we describe the characteristics of vaccine breakthrough infections (VBI) in fully vaccinated individuals according to five vaccine strategies during the Delta wave in France. Inclusion criterion was a positive test at least 2 weeks after a full vaccine schedule: homologous vaccination with Pfizer-BioNTech (BNT162b2) or Moderna (mRNA-1273); heterologous vaccination with Astrazeneca and Pfizer-BioNTech (ChadOx1/BNT162b2); single-dose vaccines Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson (Ad26.COV2.S) or Astrazeneca (ChadOx1). A total of 1630 VBI from patients fully vaccinated between February and July were included in this study. SARS-CoV-2 sequencing performed for 1366 samples showed that the delta variant represented 94.1% (1286/1366). Delta-VBI were mainly symptomatic (mild symptoms) with no difference according to the vaccine strategy (p=0.362). The median RT-PCR Ct values at diagnosis were significantly different between symptomatic and asymptomatic cases only for BNT162b2 group (17.7 (15.07, 20.51) vs 19.00 (16.00, 23.00), p=0.004). Up to 50% of VBI was classified as early-VBI (infected less than one month after full immunization) for BNT162b2, mRNA-1273, ChadOx1, and J Ad26.COV2.S. People aged 14-49 yo were overrepresented in early VBI compared to non-early VBI for BNT162b2 and mRNA-1273 (73.92% vs 37.87% for BNT162b2 and 77.78% vs 46.67 % for mRNA-1273, p&amp;lt;0.05). Our data emphasize a high prevalence of Delta-VBI occurring only one month after full immunization in young patients that might be related to relaxation of barrier gestures.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.21267301" rel="alternate" title="Investigation of Vaccine Breakthrough Infections by Vaccine strategy during the Delta Variant Wave in France (10 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467161</id><title>Critical Negatively Charged Residues Are Important for the Activity of SARS-CoV-1 and SARS-CoV-2 Fusion Peptides (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.379494+00:00</updated><author><name>Alex L. Lai</name></author><author><name>Jack H. Freed</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Coronaviruses are a major infectious disease threat, and include the human pathogens of zoonotic origin SARS-CoV (“SARS-1”), SARS-CoV-2 (“SARS-2”) and MERS-CoV (“MERS”). Entry of coronaviruses into host cells is mediated by the viral spike (S) protein. Previously, we identified that the domain immediately downstream of the S2’ cleavage site is the &lt;italic&gt;bona fide&lt;/italic&gt; FP (amino acids 798-835) for SARS-1 using ESR spectroscopy technology. We also found that the SARS-1 FP induces membrane ordering in a Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; dependent fashion. In this study, we want to know which residues are involved in this Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; binding, to build a topological model and to understand the role of the Ca2+. We performed a systematic mutation study on the negatively charged residues on the SARS-1 FP. While all six negatively charged residues contributes to the membrane ordering activity of the FP to some extent, D812 is the most important residue. We provided a topological model of how the FP binds Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; ions: both FP1 and FP2 bind one Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; ion, and there are two binding sites in FP1 and three in FP2. We also found that the corresponding residue D830 in the SARS-2 FP plays a similar critical role. ITC experiments show that the binding energies between the FP and Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; as well as between the FP and membranes also decreases for all mutants. The binding of Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;, the folding of FP and the ordering activity correlated very well across the mutants, suggesting that the function of the Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; is to help to folding of FP in membranes to enhance its activity. Using a novel pseudotyped virus particle (PP)-liposome methodology, we monitored the membrane ordering induced by the FPs in the whole S proteins in its trimer form in real time. We found that the SARS-1 and SARS-2 PPs also induce membrane ordering as the separate FPs do, and the mutations of the negatively charged residues also greatly reduce the membrane ordering activity. However, the difference in kinetic between the PP and FP indicates a possible role of FP trimerization. This finding could lead to therapeutic solutions that either target the FP-calcium interaction or block the Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; channel to combat the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467161" rel="alternate" title="Critical Negatively Charged Residues Are Important for the Activity of SARS-CoV-1 and SARS-CoV-2 Fusion Peptides (10 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.21267121</id><title>Impact of COVID-19 on healthcare access for Australian adolescents and young adults (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.379656+00:00</updated><author><name>Md Irteja Islam</name></author><author><name>Joseph Freeman</name></author><author><name>Verity Chadwick</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Martiniuk</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Access to healthcare for young people is essential to build the foundation for a healthy life. We investigated the factors associated with healthcare access by Australian young adults during and before the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We included 1110 youths using two recent data collection waves from the Longitudinal Study of Australian Children (LSAC). Data were collected during COVID-19 in 2020 for Wave 9C1 and before COVID-19 in 2018 for Wave 8. The primary outcome for this study was healthcare access. Both bivariate and multivariate logistic regression models were employed to identify the factors associated with reluctance to access healthcare services during COVID-19 and pre-COVID-19 times.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among respondents, 39.6% avoided seeking health services during the first year of the COVID-19 pandemic when they needed them, which was similar to pre-COVID-19 times (41.4%). The factors most strongly impacting upon reluctance and/or barriers to healthcare access during COVID-19 were any illness or disability, and high psychological distress. In comparison, prior to the pandemic the factors which were significantly impeding healthcare access were country of birth, state of residence, presence of any pre-existing condition and psychological distress. The most common reason reported (55.9%) for avoided seeking care was that they thought the problem would go away.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A significant proportion of youths did not seek care when they felt they needed to seek care, both during and before the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What is known about the subject?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some adolescents and young adults do not access healthcare when they need it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Healthcare access and barriers to access is best understood through a multi-system lens including policy, organisational, and individual-level factors. For instance, policy barriers (such as cost), organisational barriers (such as transportation, or difficulty accessing a timely appointment) and individual barriers (such as experiences, knowledge or beliefs).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Barriers to care may differ for sub-groups e.g. rural&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the COVID-19 pandemic, public health restrictions including the stricter “lockdowns” have reduced healthcare access. The burden of cases upon the healthcare system has further reduced healthcare access.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What this study adds?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;A significant proportion of youth did not seek healthcare when they felt they needed to seek care, both before (41.4%) and during the first year of the COVID-19 pandemic (39.6%)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Youth with a disability or chronic condition, asthma and/or psychological distress were more likely to avoid accessing healthcare during COVID-19 times.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most common reason for not seeking healthcare when it was felt to be needed was because the youth thought the problem would go away (pre-COVID-19 35.7% of the sample versus during the first year of COVID-19 55.9%)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the coronavirus restriction period (“lockdown”) the most common reason for not seeking healthcare when it was felt to be needed was because the youth did not want to visit a doctor during lockdown (21.8%) with the next most common reason being because telehealth was the only appointment option available at the time (8.4%)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.21267121" rel="alternate" title="Impact of COVID-19 on healthcare access for Australian adolescents and young adults (9 tweets)"/><category term="Health Systems and Quality Improvement"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.21267334</id><title>Association of regional Covid-19 mortality with indicators of indoor ventilation, including temperature and wind: insights into the upcoming winter (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.379835+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher T. Leffler</name></author><author><name>Joseph D. Lykins V</name></author><author><name>Brandon I. Fram</name></author><author><name>Edward Yang</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Outdoor environmental variables, such as cold temperatures and low wind speed, have been correlated with incidence and mortality from Covid-19 (caused by the SARS-CoV-2 virus). However, as Covid-19 predominantly spreads indoors, the degree to which outdoor environmental variables might directly cause disease spread is unclear.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;World regions were considered to have reliable data if the excess mortality did not greatly exceed reported Covid-19 mortality. The relative risk of Covid-19 mortality for 142 regions as a function of median weekly temperature and wind speed was determined. For instance, Covid-19 mortality following warm weeks in a country was compared with mortality following cold weeks in the same country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Covid-19 mortality increases with cooling from 20 C to close to freezing (0 to 4 C, p&amp;lt;0.001). The relation of Covid-19 mortality with temperature demonstrates a maximum close to freezing. Below -5 C, the decrease in mortality with further cooling was statistically significant (p&amp;lt;0.01). With warming above room temperature (20 to 24 C), there is a nonsignificant trend for mortality to increase again. A literature review demonstrated that window opening and indoor ventilation tend to increase with warming in the range from freezing to room temperature.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The steep decline in Covid-19 mortality with warming in the range from freezing to room temperature may relate to window opening and less indoor crowding when it is comfortable outside. Below freezing, all windows are closed, and further cooling increases stack ventilation (secondary to indoor-outdoor temperature differences) and thereby tends to decrease Covid-19 mortality. Opening windows and other tools for improving indoor ventilation may decrease the spread of Covid-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.21267334" rel="alternate" title="Association of regional Covid-19 mortality with indicators of indoor ventilation, including temperature and wind: insights into the upcoming winter (9 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471206</id><title>Engineering RNA viruses with unnatural amino acid to evoke adjustable immune response in mice (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.380024+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhetao Zheng</name></author><author><name>Yu Wang</name></author><author><name>Xuesheng Wu</name></author><author><name>Haoran Zhang</name></author><author><name>Hongmin Chen</name></author><author><name>Haishuang Lin</name></author><author><name>Yuxuan Shen</name></author><author><name>Qing Xia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ribonucleic acid (RNA) viruses pose heavy burdens on public-health systems. Synthetic biology holds great potential for artificially controlling their replication, a strategy that could be used to attenuate infectious viruses but is still in the exploratory stage. Herein, we used the genetic-code expansion technique to convert &lt;italic&gt;Enterovirus&lt;/italic&gt; 71 (EV71), a model of RNA virus, into a controllable EV71 strain carrying the unnatural amino acid (UAA) Nε-2-azidoethyloxycarbonyl-L-lysine (NAEK), which we termed an EV71-NAEK virus. EV71-NAEK could recapitulate an authentic NAEK time- and dose-dependent infection &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, which could serve as a novel method to manipulate virulent viruses in conventional laboratories. We further validated the prophylactic effect of EV71-NAEK in two mouse models. In susceptible parent mice, vaccination with EV71-NAEK elicited a strong immune response and potentially protected their neonatal offspring from lethal challenge similar to that of commercial vaccines. Meanwhile, in transgenic mice harboring a PylRS-tRNA&lt;sup&gt;Pyl&lt;/sup&gt; pair, substantial elements of genetic-code expansion technology, EV71-NAEK evoked an adjustable neutralizing-antibody response in a strictly external NAEK dose-dependent manner. These findings suggested that EV71-NAEK could be the basis of a feasible immunization program for populations with different levels of immunity. Moreover, we expanded the strategy to generate controllable coxsackieviruses and severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) for conceptual verification. In combination, these results could underlie a competent strategy for attenuating viruses and priming the immune system via artificial control, which might be a promising direction for the development of amenable vaccine candidates and be broadly applied to other RNA viruses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471206" rel="alternate" title="Engineering RNA viruses with unnatural amino acid to evoke adjustable immune response in mice (9 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.21267386</id><title>Factors influencing COVID-19 Infection in older individuals: History of Alcohol Use Disorder, Major Depressive illness, genetic variation and current use of alcohol (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.380257+00:00</updated><author><name>Shirley Y. Hill</name></author><author><name>Brian J. Holmes</name></author><author><name>Jeannette Locke-Wellman</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic continues to be a major public health problem. Vulnerable populations include older individuals with presumed weakening of the immune response. Identification of factors influencing COVID-19 infection could provide an additional means for protecting such individuals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Members of a family study previously interviewed as middle aged individuals were re-contacted and asked to participate in extended phone interview (2-3 hours) covering past and current mental health issues, physical health diagnoses, use of alcohol and drugs, and exposure to anyone with COVID-19. The average follow-up period was 32 years. Detailed medication use was collected to confirm medical diagnoses and to reveal possible protective effects of particular drug classes currently prescribed for the participant by their physician. Serology was available for red cell antigens (ABO, Kell, Duffy, Kidd, Rhesus) and HLA subtypes. Analyses were conducted to contrast COVID-19 + and COVID-19 - individuals for physical and mental health diagnoses, use of alcohol and drugs, and red cell and HLA serology. Additionally, analyses were conducted to contrast these groups with a group reporting known exposure but absence of COVID-19 symptoms or diagnosis by a health professional.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interviews were completed between September 2020 and November 2021. A total of 42 of the 90 individuals interviewed had been vaccinated at the time of interview. At the time of interview, 11.1% reported having developed COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using quantity per occasion (QPO) and quantity by frequency (QXF) totals in the past month by type of alcohol consumed, we found a significant association between QPO for liquor (p=0.017) and marginal effects for QXF for liquor consumption (p=0.06). Exposed individuals who were COVID-19 negative tended to drink more liquor than those who were positive, an average of about one drink per day. Beer and wine consumption were not statistically significant. A diagnosis of alcohol use disorder at baseline evaluation was not a significant predictor of being COVID positive or negative.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Self-reported current depression or depression in the past only was not a predictor of COVID-19 status based on a single question “Are you depressed currently or only in the past?”. In contrast, completion of a clinical interview designed to elicit depressed mood and concurrent symptoms for determination of the lifetime presence or absence of a depressive episode did reveal a significant effect. Comparison of responses at baseline to follow-up showed those most resilient to developing COVID-19 were those without evidence of a depressive episode by lifetime history at both points in time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Physical health issues were analyzed for those that were frequently occurring in our sample such as hypertension but not found to be significant. BMI was analyzed and found to be statistically non-significant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Analysis of HLA variation across the whole sample did not reveal a significant association but among males two variants, A1 and B8, did show significant variation associated with COVID-19+ and COVID-19-status. Analyses of the red cell antigens revealed one significant red cell effect; Kidd genotypic variation was associated with COVID-19 status.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We tentatively conclude that use of specific types of alcohol, namely liquor, is associated with reduced frequency of COVID-19. However, the amount is low, averaging about 1 drink per day. Enlarged samples are needed to confirm these results. The finding that past history of alcohol use disorder does not increase likelihood of developing COVID-19 is important. It should be noted that the 34 individuals diagnosed with AUD at baseline had survived an average of 32 years in order to participate in the current interview suggesting they may be especially resilient to adverse health conditions. The finding that a single question designed to elicit the presence or absence of depressed mood either currently or in the past was not a risk factor for COVID-19 in contrast to report of a clinically significant past history of a depressive episode based on more extensive examination using DSM criteria is important. Results for the KIDD blood group are novel and warrant further investigation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.21267386" rel="alternate" title="Factors influencing COVID-19 Infection in older individuals: History of Alcohol Use Disorder, Major Depressive illness, genetic variation and current use of alcohol (8 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.470766</id><title>Pandemic-scale phylogenetics (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.380426+00:00</updated><author><name>Cheng Ye</name></author><author><name>Bryan Thornlow</name></author><author><name>Alexander Kramer</name></author><author><name>Jakob McBroome</name></author><author><name>Angie Hinrichs</name></author><author><name>Russell Corbett-Detig</name></author><author><name>Yatish Turakhia</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1.&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Phylogenetics has been central to the genomic surveillance, epidemiology and contact tracing efforts during the COVD-19 pandemic. But the massive scale of genomic sequencing has rendered the pre-pandemic tools inadequate for comprehensive phylogenetic analyses. Here, we discuss the phylogenetic package that we developed to address the needs imposed by this pandemic. The package incorporates several pandemic-specific optimization and parallelization techniques and comprises four programs: UShER, matOptimize, RIPPLES and matUtils. Using high-performance computing, UShER and matOptimize maintain and refine daily a massive mutation-annotated phylogenetic tree consisting of all SARS-CoV-2 sequences available in online repositories. With UShER and RIPPLES, individual labs – even with modest compute resources – incorporate newly-sequenced SARS-CoV-2 genomes on this phylogeny and discover evidence for recombination in real-time. With matUtils, they rapidly query and visualize massive SARS-CoV-2 phylogenies. These tools have empowered scientists worldwide to study the SARS-CoV-2 evolution and transmission at an unprecedented scale, resolution and speed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.470766" rel="alternate" title="Pandemic-scale phylogenetics (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.21267410</id><title>International risk of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant importations originating in South Africa (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.380817+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuan Bai</name></author><author><name>Zhanwei Du</name></author><author><name>Mingda Xu</name></author><author><name>Lin Wang</name></author><author><name>Peng Wu</name></author><author><name>Eric H. Y. Lau</name></author><author><name>Benjamin J. Cowling</name></author><author><name>Lauren Ancel Meyers</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Omicron, a fast-spreading SARS-CoV-2 variant of concern reported to the World Health Organization on November 24, 2021, has raised international alarm. We estimated there is at least 50% chance that Omicron had been introduced by travelers from South Africa into all of the 30 countries studied by November 27, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.21267410" rel="alternate" title="International risk of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant importations originating in South Africa (8 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471580</id><title>Predictive profiling of SARS-CoV-2 variants by deep mutational learning (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.381092+00:00</updated><author><name>Joseph M. Taft</name></author><author><name>Cédric R. Weber</name></author><author><name>Beichen Gao</name></author><author><name>Roy A. Ehling</name></author><author><name>Jiami Han</name></author><author><name>Lester Frei</name></author><author><name>Sean W. Metcalfe</name></author><author><name>Alexander Yermanos</name></author><author><name>William Kelton</name></author><author><name>Sai T. Reddy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The continual evolution of the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) and the emergence of variants that show resistance to vaccines and neutralizing antibodies (&lt;italic&gt;1–4&lt;/italic&gt;) threaten to prolong the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic (&lt;italic&gt;5&lt;/italic&gt;). Selection and emergence of SARS-CoV-2 variants are driven in part by mutations within the viral spike protein and in particular the ACE2 receptor-binding domain (RBD), a primary target site for neutralizing antibodies. Here, we develop deep mutational learning (DML), a machine learning-guided protein engineering technology, which is used to interrogate a massive sequence space of combinatorial mutations, representing billions of RBD variants, by accurately predicting their impact on ACE2 binding and antibody escape. A highly diverse landscape of possible SARS-CoV-2 variants is identified that could emerge from a multitude of evolutionary trajectories. DML may be used for predictive profiling on current and prospective variants, including highly mutated variants such as omicron (B.1.1.529), thus supporting decision making for public heath as well as guiding the development of therapeutic antibody treatments and vaccines for COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471580" rel="alternate" title="Predictive profiling of SARS-CoV-2 variants by deep mutational learning (8 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471499</id><title>Insights on the mutational landscape of the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.381344+00:00</updated><author><name>Nathaniel L. Miller</name></author><author><name>Thomas Clark</name></author><author><name>Rahul Raman</name></author><author><name>Ram Sasisekharan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The SARS-COV2 Omicron variant has sparked global concern due to the possibility of enhanced transmissibility and escape from vaccines and therapeutics. In this study, we describe the mutational landscape of the Omicron variant using amino acid interaction (AAI) networks. AAI network analysis is particularly well suited for interrogating the impact of constellations of mutations as occur on Omicron that may function in an epistatic manner. Our analyses suggest that as compared to previous variants of concern, the Omicron variant has increased antibody escape &lt;italic&gt;breadth&lt;/italic&gt; due to mutations in class 3 and 4 antibody epitopes as well as increased escape &lt;italic&gt;depth&lt;/italic&gt; due to accumulated mutations in class 1 antibody epitopes. We note certain RBD mutations that might further enhance Omicron’s escape, and in particular advise careful surveillance of two subclades bearing R346S/K mutations. Further, AAI network analysis suggests that the function of certain therapeutic monoclonal antibodies may be disrupted by Omicron mutations as a result of the cumulative indirect perturbations to the epitope surface properties, despite point-mutation analyses suggesting these antibodies are tolerant of the set of Omicron mutations in isolation. Finally, for several Omicron mutations that do not appear to contribute meaningfully to antibody escape, we find evidence for a plausible role in enhanced transmissibility via disruption of RBD-down conformational stability at the RBD-RBD interface.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471499" rel="alternate" title="Insights on the mutational landscape of the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471483</id><title>Intranasal immunization with a vaccinia virus vaccine vector expressing pre-fusion stabilized SARS-CoV-2 spike fully protected mice against lethal challenge with the heavily mutated mouse-adapted SARS2-N501YMA30 strain of SARS-CoV-2 (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.381541+00:00</updated><author><name>Karen V. Kibler</name></author><author><name>Mateusz Szczerba</name></author><author><name>Douglas Lake</name></author><author><name>Alexa J. Roeder</name></author><author><name>Masmudur Rahman</name></author><author><name>Brenda G. Hogue</name></author><author><name>Lok-Yin Roy Wong</name></author><author><name>Stanley Perlman</name></author><author><name>Yize Li</name></author><author><name>Bertram L. Jacobs</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Omicron SARS-CoV-2 variant has been designated a variant of concern because its spike protein is heavily mutated. In particular, Omicron spike is mutated at 5 positions (K417, N440, E484, Q493 and N501) that have been associated with escape from neutralizing antibodies induced by either infection with or immunization against the early Washington strain of SARS-CoV-2. The mouse-adapted strain of SARS-CoV-2, SARS2-N501Y&lt;sub&gt;MA30&lt;/sub&gt;, contains a spike that is also heavily mutated, with mutations at 4 of the 5 positions in Omicron spike associated with neutralizing antibody escape (K417, E484, Q493 and N501). In this manuscript we show that intranasal immunization with a pre-fusion stabilized Washington strain spike, expressed from a highly attenuated, replication-competent vaccinia virus construct, NYVAC-KC, fully protected mice against disease and death from SARS2-N501Y&lt;sub&gt;MA30&lt;/sub&gt;. Similarly, immunization by scarification on the skin fully protected against death, but not from mild disease. This data demonstrates that Washington strain spike, when expressed from a highly attenuated, replication-competent poxvirus, administered without parenteral injection can fully protect against the heavily mutated mouse-adapted SARS2-N501Y&lt;sub&gt;MA30&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471483" rel="alternate" title="Intranasal immunization with a vaccinia virus vaccine vector expressing pre-fusion stabilized SARS-CoV-2 spike fully protected mice against lethal challenge with the heavily mutated mouse-adapted SARS2-N501YMA30 strain of SARS-CoV-2 (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471489</id><title>Production of novel Spike truncations in Chinese hamster ovary cells (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.381782+00:00</updated><author><name>Shiaki A. Minami</name></author><author><name>Seongwon Jung</name></author><author><name>Yihan Huang</name></author><author><name>Bradley S. Harris</name></author><author><name>Matthew W. Kenaston</name></author><author><name>Roland Faller</name></author><author><name>Somen Nandi</name></author><author><name>Karen A. McDonald</name></author><author><name>Priya S. Shah</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 Spike is a key protein that mediates viral entry into cells and elicits antibody responses. Its importance in infection, diagnostics, and vaccinations has created a large demand for purified Spike for clinical and research applications. Spike is difficult to express, prompting modifications to the protein and expression platforms to improve yields. Alternatively, Spike receptor binding domain (RBD) is commonly expressed with higher titers, though it has lower sensitivity in serological assays. Here, we improve transient Spike expression in Chinese hamster ovary (CHO) cells. We demonstrate that Spike titers increase significantly over the expression period, maximizing at 14 mg/L at day 7. In comparison, RBD titers peak at 54 mg/L at day 3. Next, we develop 8 Spike truncations (T1-T8) in pursuit of a truncation with high expression and antibody binding. The truncations T1 and T4 express at 130 mg/L and 73 mg/L, respectively, which are higher than our RBD titers. Purified proteins were evaluated for binding to antibodies raised against full-length Spike. T1 has similar sensitivity as Spike against a monoclonal antibody and even outperforms Spike for a polyclonal antibody. These results suggest T1 is a promising Spike alternative for use in various applications.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471489" rel="alternate" title="Production of novel Spike truncations in Chinese hamster ovary cells (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471219</id><title>Interactions of SARS-CoV-2 protein E with cell junctions and polarity PDZ-containing proteins (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.382016+00:00</updated><author><name>Yanlei Zhu</name></author><author><name>Flavio Alvarez</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Wolff</name></author><author><name>Ariel Mechaly</name></author><author><name>Sébastien Brûlé</name></author><author><name>Benoit Neitthoffer</name></author><author><name>Sandrine Etienne-Manneville</name></author><author><name>Ahmed Haouz</name></author><author><name>Batiste Boëda</name></author><author><name>Célia Caillet-Saguy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The C-terminus of the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) protein E contains a PBM (PDZ binding motif) targeting PDZ (PSD-95/Dlg/ZO-1) domains identical to the PBM of SARS-CoV. The latter is involved in the pathogenicity of the virus. Recently, we identified ten human PDZ-containing proteins showing significant interactions with SARS-CoV-2 protein E PBM. We selected several of them involved in cellular junctions and cell polarity (TJP1, PARD3, MLLT4, LNX2) and MPP5/Pals1 previously shown to interact with SARS-CoV E PBM. Targeting cellular junctions and polarity components is a common strategy by viruses to hijack cell machinery to their advantage. In this study, we showed that these host PDZ domains TJP1, PARD3, MLLT4, LNX2 and MPP5/PALS1 interact in a PBM-dependent manner &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and colocalize with the full-length E protein &lt;italic&gt;in cellulo&lt;/italic&gt;, sequestrating the PDZ domains to the Golgi compartment. We solved three crystal structures of complexes between human LNX2, MLLT4 and MPP5 PDZs and SARS-CoV-2 E PBM highlighting its binding preferences for several cellular targets. Finally, we showed different affinities for the PDZ domains with the original SARS-CoV-2 C-terminal sequence containing the PBM and the one of the beta variant that contains a mutation close to the PBM. The acquired mutations in E protein localized near the PBM might have important effects both on the structure and the ion-channel activity of the E protein and on the host machinery targeted by the variants during the infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471219" rel="alternate" title="Interactions of SARS-CoV-2 protein E with cell junctions and polarity PDZ-containing proteins (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.21267096</id><title>Statistical Inferences and Analysis based on the COVID-19 data from the United States (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.382264+00:00</updated><author><name>Nivedita Rethnakar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This paper investigates the mortality statistics of the COVID-19 pandemic from the United States perspective. Using empirical data analysis and statistical inference tools, we bring out several exciting and important aspects of the pandemic, otherwise hidden. Specific patterns seen in demo-graphics such as race/ethnicity and age are discussed both qualitatively and quantitatively. We also study the role played by factors such as population density. Connections between COVID-19 and other respiratory diseases are also covered in detail. The temporal dynamics of the COVID-19 outbreak and the impact of vaccines in controlling the pandemic are also looked at with sufficient rigor. It is hoped that statistical inference such as the ones gathered in this paper would be helpful for better scientific understanding, policy preparation and thus adequately preparing, should a similar situation arise in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.21267096" rel="alternate" title="Statistical Inferences and Analysis based on the COVID-19 data from the United States (6 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.21267073</id><title>A Scaling Law for PCR Positivity in the COVID Second Wave (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.382418+00:00</updated><author><name>Keith Johnson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In this preliminary report, PCR positivity data in the second wave of the COVID pandemic (September-January 2020) are shown to obey a scaling law given by:
&lt;disp-formula id="ueqn1"&gt;&lt;alternatives&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="21267073v1_ueqn1.gif" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/alternatives&gt;&lt;/disp-formula&gt;
where % P&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; and Σ&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; are the y- and x-intercepts of a plot of positivity, %P, against the number of tests, Σ. The law holds across international, regional and local boundaries, as demonstrated for Great Britain, Austria, Germany and Sweden, the nine English regions, London - Yorkshire &amp;amp; Humber, and various Local Health Authorities in England. One possible explanation for scaling might be Dorfman pooling.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scaling law can be used to remove a systematic or false positive (FP) component from the daily number of positive tests, or cases, to yield the real number of cases. The results correlate strongly with the ZOE survey for London (R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;=0.787) and Excess Deaths for England (R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;=0.833). The cumulative total of FPs can be estimated as 1.4M by the beginning of 2021, in line with other estimates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.21267073" rel="alternate" title="A Scaling Law for PCR Positivity in the COVID Second Wave (6 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.21267355</id><title>Estimating Active Cases of COVID-19 (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.382569+00:00</updated><author><name>Javier Alvarez</name></author><author><name>Carlos Baquero</name></author><author><name>Elisa Cabana</name></author><author><name>Jaya Prakash Champati</name></author><author><name>Antonio Fernandez Anta</name></author><author><name>Davide Frey</name></author><author><name>Augusto Garcia-Agundez Garcia</name></author><author><name>Chryssis Georgiou</name></author><author><name>Mathieu Goessens</name></author><author><name>Harold Hernandez</name></author><author><name>Rosa Lillo</name></author><author><name>Raquel Menezes</name></author><author><name>Raul Moreno</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Nicolaou</name></author><author><name>Oluwasegun Ojo</name></author><author><name>Antonio Ortega</name></author><author><name>Estrella Rausell</name></author><author><name>Jesus Rufino</name></author><author><name>Efstathios Stavrakis</name></author><author><name>Govind Jeevan</name></author><author><name>Christin Glorioso</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Having accurate and timely data on active COVID-19 cases is challenging, since it depends on the availability of an appropriate infrastructure to perform tests and aggregate their results. In this paper, we consider a case to be active if it is infectious, and we propose methods to estimate the number of active infectious cases of COVID-19 from the official data (of confirmed cases and fatalities) and from public survey data. We show that the latter is a viable option in countries with reduced testing capacity or infrastructures.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.21267355" rel="alternate" title="Estimating Active Cases of COVID-19 (6 tweets)"/><category term="Health Informatics"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.21267218</id><title>Stranded abroad during the COVID-19 pandemic: examining the psychological and financial impact of border restrictions (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.383091+00:00</updated><author><name>Pippa McDermid</name></author><author><name>Adam Craig</name></author><author><name>Meru Sheel</name></author><author><name>Katrina Blazek</name></author><author><name>Siobhan Talty</name></author><author><name>Holly Seale</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the easing of COVID-19-related international travel restrictions in late 2021 it is time to consider the direct and indirect social, emotional, and financial impacts that these border closures have had. The study aims to evaluate the psychological and financial distress reported by people stranded abroad due to international travel restrictions introduced in response to the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Between July and September 2021, we implemented a cross-sectional online survey targeting individuals stranded abroad due to international travel restrictions. The survey collected data about COVID-19 travel restriction-related travel impacts; personal stress, anxiety, and depression (using the validated DASS-21tool); as well as impacts on housing and financial security; and demographic data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We had 1054 participants complete the survey; most were trying to return to the Oceania region (75.4%), with 45% stranded in Europe. Overall, 64.2% reported financial distress while stranded abroad. 64.4% (x̄ =9.43, SD=5.81) reported either a moderate or severe (based on the DASS-21 classification) level of depression, 41.7% for anxiety (x̄ =5.46, SD=4.74), and 58.1% for stress (x̄ =10.64, SD=5.26). Statistically significant factors associated with moderate to extremely severe depression, anxiety, and stress were financial stress, an employment change, being &amp;lt;30yrs, having a high perceived risk of contracting COVID-19 abroad and being stranded for &amp;gt;2 months.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study is among the first to explore the psychological and financial distress-related impacts associated with being stranded abroad due to COVID-19 travel restrictions. It highlights a range of unintended consequences that arise from pandemic-related travel restriction, identifies the health and social needs for a particularly vulnerable population, and provides clues as to the types of support that may be adopted to best support them. This research will assist policymakers in identifying support packages for people stranded abroad due to global disaster.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.21267218" rel="alternate" title="Stranded abroad during the COVID-19 pandemic: examining the psychological and financial impact of border restrictions (5 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.21267398</id><title>In-hospital mortality due to breakthrough COVID-19 among recipients of COVISHIELD (ChAdOx nCoV-19) and COVAXIN (BBV152) (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.383411+00:00</updated><author><name>Tejas M Suri</name></author><author><name>Tamoghna Ghosh</name></author><author><name>M Arunachalam</name></author><author><name>Rohit Vadala</name></author><author><name>Saurabh Vig</name></author><author><name>Sushma Bhatnagar</name></author><author><name>Anant Mohan</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Multiple vaccines have received emergency-use authorization in different countries in the fight against the COVID-19 pandemic. India had started its vaccination campaign using the COVISHIELD (ChAdOx nCoV-19) and the COVAXIN (BBV152) vaccines. However, there is a lack of head-to-head comparisons of the different vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We performed a retrospective cohort study during the second wave of the pandemic in India with predominant circulation of the delta strain of SARS-CoV-2. We enrolled adult patients who were hospitalized with breakthrough COVID-19 infection after vaccination. We compared in-hospital outcomes between patients who had received the COVISHIELD (n=181) or COVAXIN vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Between April and June 2021, a total of 353 patients were enrolled, among whom 181 (51.3%) received COVAXIN (156 partially vaccinated and 25 fully vaccinated) and 172 (48.7%) received COVISHIELD (155 partially vaccinated and 17 fully vaccinated). The in-hospital mortality did not differ between the recipients of COVISHIELD or COVAXIN in either the fully vaccinated [2 deaths (11.8%) vs 0 deaths (0%), respectively p=0.08] or the partially vaccinated cohorts [31 deaths (20%) vs 28 deaths (17.9%), respectively, p=0.65].&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients who are hospitalized with breakthrough COVID-19 had similar in-hospital outcome irrespective of whether they received COVISHIELD or COVAXIN.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.21267398" rel="alternate" title="In-hospital mortality due to breakthrough COVID-19 among recipients of COVISHIELD (ChAdOx nCoV-19) and COVAXIN (BBV152) (5 tweets)"/><category term="Allergy and Immunology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471688</id><title>Mutations in the spike RBD of SARS-CoV-2 omicron variant may increase infectivity without dramatically altering the efficacy of current multi-dosage vaccinations (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.383659+00:00</updated><author><name>Bingrui Li</name></author><author><name>Xin Luo</name></author><author><name>Kathleen M McAndrews</name></author><author><name>Raghu Kalluri</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;With the continuous evolution of SARS-CoV-2, variants of concern (VOCs) and their mutations are a focus of rapid assessment. Vital mutations in the VOC are found in spike protein, particularly in the receptor binding domain (RBD), which directly interacts with ACE2 on the host cell membrane, a key determinant of the binding affinity and cell entry. With the reporting of the most recent VOC, omicron, we performed amino acid sequence alignment of the omicron spike protein with that of the wild type and other VOCs. Although it shares several conserved mutations with other variants, we found that omicron has a large number of unique mutations. We applied the Hopp-Woods scale to calculate the hydrophilicity scores of the amino acid stretches of the RBD and the entire spike protein, and found 3 new hydrophilic regions in the RBD of omicron, implying exposure to water, with the potential to bind proteins such as ACE2 increasing transmissibility and infectivity.  However, careful analysis reveals that most of the exposed domains of spike protein can serve as antigenic epitopes for generating B cell and T cell-mediated immune responses. This suggests that in the collection of polyclonal antibodies to various epitopes generated after multiple doses of vaccination, some can likely still bind to the omicron spike protein and the RBD to prevent severe clinical disease. In summary, while the omicron variant might result in more infectivity, it can still bind to a reasonable repertoire of antibodies generated by multiple doses of current vaccines likely preventing severe disease. Effective vaccines may not universally prevent opportunistic infections but can prevent the sequelae of severe disease, as observed for the delta variant. This might still be the case with the omicron variant, albeit, with increased frequency of infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471688" rel="alternate" title="Mutations in the spike RBD of SARS-CoV-2 omicron variant may increase infectivity without dramatically altering the efficacy of current multi-dosage vaccinations (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.21267439</id><title>Safety and Immunogenicity of SARS-CoV-2 S-2P Protein Vaccine MVC-COV1901 in People Living with HIV (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.383853+00:00</updated><author><name>Shu-Hsing Cheng</name></author><author><name>Chia En Lien</name></author><author><name>Szu-Min Hsieh</name></author><author><name>Chien-Yu Cheng</name></author><author><name>Wang-Da Liu</name></author><author><name>Ching-Lung Lo</name></author><author><name>Wen-Chien Ko</name></author><author><name>Yen-Hsu Chen</name></author><author><name>Ching-Tai Huang</name></author><author><name>Hsiao-Ting Chang</name></author><author><name>Shinn-Jang Hwang</name></author><author><name>Ning-Chi Wang</name></author><author><name>Ming-Che Liu</name></author><author><name>Yu-Lin Lee</name></author><author><name>I-Chen Tai</name></author><author><name>Josue Antonio Garcia Estrada</name></author><author><name>Tzou-Yien Lin</name></author><author><name>Wen-Sen Lee</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To provide data on the immune response to COVID-19 vaccines in people living with HIV (PWH), MVC-COV1901, a recombinant protein vaccine containing S-2P protein adjuvanted with CpG 1018 and aluminium hydroxide, was assessed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A total of 57 PWH of ≥ 20 years of age who are on stable antiretroviral therapy and with CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cell ≥ 350 cells/mm&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; and HIV viral load &amp;lt; 10&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; copies/ml were compared with 882 HIV-negative participants. Participants received 2 doses of MVC-COV1901 28 days apart. Safety and the immunogenicity were evaluated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;No vaccine-related serious adverse events (SAEs) were recorded. Seroconversion rates (SCRs) of 100% and 99.8% were achieved in people living with HIV (PWH) and comparators, respectively, 28 days after second dose. The geometric mean titers (GMTs) (95% confidence interval [CI]) against wild type SARS-CoV-2 virus were 136.62 IU/mL (WHO Standardized International Unit) (95% CI 114.3-163.3) and 440.41 IU/mL (95% CI 421.3-460.4), for PWH and control groups, respectively, after adjusting for sex, age, BMI category, and comorbidity, and the adjusted GMT ratio of comparator/PWH was 3.22 (95% CI 2.6-4.1). A higher CD4/CD8 ratio was associated with a higher GMT (R=0.27, p=0.039).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;MVC-COV1901 has shown robust safety but weaker immunogenicity responses in PWH. As a result, a third dose or booster doses of MVC-COV1901 may be appropriate for PWH.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.21267439" rel="alternate" title="Safety and Immunogenicity of SARS-CoV-2 S-2P Protein Vaccine MVC-COV1901 in People Living with HIV (5 tweets)"/><category term="HIV/AIDS"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.21266774</id><title>Stressors, Manifestations and Course of COVID-19 Related Distress Among Nurses and Midwives in Tasmania (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.384181+00:00</updated><author><name>Kathryn M. Marsden</name></author><author><name>Julie M. Porter</name></author><author><name>IK. Robertson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The deleterious effects relating to the COVID-19 pandemic on the mental health of healthcare workers has now been widely established. Understanding how COVID-19 affects their work and life is complex and multidimensional. This study describes the critical stressors and how they manifest within both the work and larger social environment for nurses and midwives in Tasmania, Australia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A longitudinal, descriptive survey was designed to explore the trajectory of the psychological health of Tasmanian public sector nurses and midwives during the COIVD-19 pandemic. The survey was distributed at 3 timepoints over a 12-month period and consisted of a battery of psychological tests which included the Patient Health Questionnaire, General Anxiety Disorder, Insomnia Severity Index, and the Impact of Events Scale-Revised, together with free text comments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The associations between outcome and predictor variables were assessed using mixed effects linear regression and linear mixed model analyses. Free text comments were themed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;High levels of stress and mental exhaustion were attributed to threatened workplace team culture; compromised quality of patient care; the impact on family, home, financial and economic domains; lack of clear communication; issues surrounding personal protective equipment; and female gender. Study data show younger nurses and midwives suffered higher levels of stress and mental exhaustion than older.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study highlights the need for stable and functional relationships at home and at work for nurses and midwives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Factors which will help preserve the mental health of nurses and midwives include strong workplace culture with ongoing processes to monitor organisational burnout; building resilience, particularly among younger nurses and midwives; protection of healthcare worker safety; clear communication processes and supporting stable and functional relationships at home. The health service has an imperative to ensure optimum service delivery by safeguarding staff, despite the inevitable health stress imposed by the nature of the work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.21266774" rel="alternate" title="Stressors, Manifestations and Course of COVID-19 Related Distress Among Nurses and Midwives in Tasmania (5 tweets)"/><category term="Nursing"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471525</id><title>A proteomic perspective and involvement of cytokines in SARS-CoV-2 infection (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.384364+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarena Banu</name></author><author><name>Mohammed M Idris</name></author><author><name>Ramakrishnan Nagaraj</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Infection with the SARS-CoV-2 virus results in manifestation of several clinical observations from asymptomatic to multi-organ failure. Biochemically, the serious effects are due to what is described as cytokine storm. The initial infection region for COVID-19 is the nasopharyngeal/oropharyngeal region which is the site where samples are taken to examine the presence of virus. We have earlier shown that several defensin genes are down regulated in cells from this region in patients who tested positive in the RTPCR test. We have now carried out detailed proteomic analysis of the nasopharyngeal/oropharyngeal swab samples collected from normal individuals and those tested positive for SARS-CoV-2 by RTPCR, involving high throughput quantitative proteomics analysis. Several proteins like annexins, cytokines and histones were found differentially regulated in the host human cells following SARS-CoV-2 infection. Genes for these proteins were also observed to be differentially regulated when their expression was analyzed. Majority of the cytokine proteins were found to be up regulated in the infected individuals. Cell to Cell signaling interaction, Immune cell trafficking and inflammatory response pathways were found associated with the differentially regulated proteins based on network pathway analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471525" rel="alternate" title="A proteomic perspective and involvement of cytokines in SARS-CoV-2 infection (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.21267478</id><title>Single cell gene expression profiling of nasal ciliated cells reveals distinctive biological processes related to epigenetic mechanisms in patients with severe COVID-19 (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.384544+00:00</updated><author><name>Luis Diambra</name></author><author><name>Andres M Alonso</name></author><author><name>Silvia Sookoian</name></author><author><name>Carlos J Pirola</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To explore the molecular processes associated with cellular regulatory programs in patients with COVID-19, including gene activation or repression mediated by epigenetic mechanisms. We hypothesized that a comprehensive gene expression profiling of nasopharyngeal epithelial cells might expand understanding of the pathogenic mechanisms of severe COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNAseq) profiling of ciliated cells (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; = 12725) from healthy controls (SARS-CoV-2 negative &lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; =13) and patients with mild/moderate (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; =13) and severe (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; =14) COVID-19. ScRNAseq data at the patient level were used to perform gene set and pathway enrichment analyses. We prioritized candidate miRNA-target interactions and epigenetic mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pathways linked to mitochondrial function, misfolded proteins, and membrane permeability were upregulated in patients with mild/moderate disease compared to healthy controls. Besides, we noted that compared to mild/moderate disease, cells derived from severe COVID-19 patients had downregulation of sub-networks associated with epigenetic mechanisms, including DNA and histone H3K4 methylation and chromatin remodeling regulation. We found 11-ranked miRNAs that may explain miRNA-dependent regulation of histone methylation, some of which share seed sequences with SARS-CoV-2 miRNAs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our results may provide novel insights into the epigenetic mechanisms mediating the clinical course of SARS-CoV-2 infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.21267478" rel="alternate" title="Single cell gene expression profiling of nasal ciliated cells reveals distinctive biological processes related to epigenetic mechanisms in patients with severe COVID-19 (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471528</id><title>The cellular characterisation of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein in virus-infected cells using Receptor Binding Domain-binding specific human monoclonal antibodies (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.384738+00:00</updated><author><name>Conrad En-Zuo Chan</name></author><author><name>Ching-Ging Ng</name></author><author><name>Angeline Pei-Chew Lim</name></author><author><name>Shirley Lay-Kheng Seah</name></author><author><name>De-Hoe Chye</name></author><author><name>Steven Ka- Khuen Wong</name></author><author><name>Jie-Hui Lim</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Zi-Yun Lim</name></author><author><name>Soak-Kuan Lai</name></author><author><name>Pui-San Wong</name></author><author><name>Kok-Mun Leong</name></author><author><name>Yi-Chun Liu</name></author><author><name>Richard J Sugrue</name></author><author><name>Boon-Huan Tan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A human monoclonal antibody panel (PD4, PD5, PD7, SC23 and SC29) was isolated from the B cells of convalescent patients and used to examine the S protein in SARS-CoV-2-infected cells. While all five antibodies bound conformational-specific epitopes within SARS-CoV-2 Spike (S) protein, only PD5, PD7, and SC23 were able to bind to the Receptor Binding Domain (RBD). Immunofluorescence microscopy was used to examine the S protein RBD in cells infected with the Singapore isolates SARS-CoV-2/0334 and SARS-CoV-2/1302. The RBD-binders exhibited a distinct cytoplasmic staining pattern that was primarily localised within the Golgi complex and was distinct from the diffuse cytoplasmic staining pattern exhibited by the non-RBD binders (PD4 and SC29). These data indicated that the S protein adopted a conformation in the Golgi complex that enabled the RBD recognition by the RBD-binders. The RBD-binders also recognised the uncleaved S protein indicating that S protein cleavage was not required for RBD recognition. Electron microscopy indicated high levels of cell-associated virus particles, and multiple cycle virus infection using RBD-binder staining provided evidence for direct cell-to-cell transmission for both isolates. Although similar levels of RBD-binder staining was demonstrated for each isolate, the SARS-CoV-2/1302 exhibited slower rates of cell-to-cell transmission. These data suggest that a conformational change in the S protein occurs during its transit through the Golgi complex that enables RBD recognition by the RBD-binders, and suggests that these antibodies can be used to monitor S protein RBD formation during the early stages of infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The SARS CoV-2 spike (S) protein receptor binding domain (RBD) mediates the attachment of SARS CoV-2 to the host cell. This interaction plays an essential role in initiating virus infection and the S protein RBD is therefore a focus of therapeutic and vaccine interventions. However, new virus variants have emerged with altered biological properties in the RBD that can potentially negate these interventions. Therefore an improved understanding of the biological properties of the RBD in virus-infected cells may offer future therapeutic strategies to mitigate SARS CoV-2 infection. We used physiologically relevant antibodies that were isolated from the B cells of convalescent COVID19 patients to monitor the RBD in cells infected with SARS CoV-2 clinical isolates. These immunological reagents specifically recognise the correctly folded RBD and were used to monitor the appearance of the RBD in SARS CoV-2-infected cells and identified the site where the RBD first appears.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471528" rel="alternate" title="The cellular characterisation of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein in virus-infected cells using Receptor Binding Domain-binding specific human monoclonal antibodies (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471684</id><title>Simultaneous analysis of antigen-specific B and T cells after SARS-CoV-2 infection and vaccination (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.385028+00:00</updated><author><name>Krista L. Newell</name></author><author><name>Mitchell J. Waldran</name></author><author><name>Stephen J. Thomas</name></author><author><name>Timothy P. Endy</name></author><author><name>Adam T. Waickman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Conventional methods for quantifying and phenotyping antigen-specific lymphocytes can rapidly deplete irreplaceable specimens. This is due to the fact that antigen-specific T and B cells have historically been analyzed in independent assays each requiring millions of cells. A technique that facilitates the simultaneous detection of antigen-specific T and B cells would allow for more thorough immune profiling with significantly reduced sample requirements. To this end, we developed the B And T cell Tandem Lymphocyte Evaluation (BATTLE) assay, which allows for the simultaneous identification of SARS-CoV-2 Spike reactive T and B cells using an optimized Activation Induced Marker (AIM) T cell assay and dual-color B cell antigen probes. Using this assay, we demonstrate that antigen-specific B and T cell subsets can be identified simultaneously using conventional flow cytometry platforms and provide insight into the differential effects of mRNA vaccination on B and T cell populations following natural SARS-CoV-2 infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471684" rel="alternate" title="Simultaneous analysis of antigen-specific B and T cells after SARS-CoV-2 infection and vaccination (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.21267405</id><title>SIR Modeling the Dual Disaster Impacts of Omicron B.1.1.529 and Natural Disaster Events on Simulated 6 Months (December 2021 – May 2022) Healthcare System Resiliences in Fragile SE Asia Ring of Fire Ecosystems (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.385234+00:00</updated><author><name>Andri Wibowo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;For some countries that have experienced numerous natural disasters, including massive earthquakes and tsunamis, managing the COVID-19 pandemic can be very challenging. This situation arises considering that the disaster can directly and indirectly affect the healthcare system’ s capacity to serve the COVID-19 cases. With severely damaged healthcare facilities due to the disaster, there will be severely ill COVID-19 cases unmanaged. The coupling and interplay between these two phenomena can indeed be catastrophic. One of the regions where this issue becomes concerned is in Southeast Asia, where most of the Asian countries lie in the fragile ring of fire ecosystem, contributing to the high tsunami and earthquake disasters in the world. At the same time, Asia is one of the regions that have been severely impacted due to the current COVID-19 Delta Variant. Recently, a more contagious Omicron Variant has emerged and put a more massive burden on the healthcare facilities that are impacted by disasters. Then, in this situation, this paper aims to assess healthcare resilience in managing the Omicron pandemic amid disaster impacts. SIR simulation was used to determine whether severely ill Omicron cases were below or above healthcare and ICU capacity under different vaccination coverage. Our result confirms that vaccination coverage was the imminent factor in reducing the severely ill cases in every healthcare facility, whether the facilities were damaged or not. Increasing vaccination coverage from 30% to 60% will significantly reduce the number of severely ill cases that fall below the capacity of healthcare. Based on the current SIR model on the Omicron epidemic variables and Ro, it is estimated that the Omicron will reach its peak after 180 days in February 2022 and will totally disappear in May 2022 in this modeled area. When healthcare system facilities were fully operational and no disaster happened, combined with 60% vaccination rates, all Omicron case numbers were below and under the available hospital beds and even available ICU beds. While the situation is changed when a disaster occurs and causes 30% damage or reduction to healthcare facilities. In this situation, there are portions of Omicron cases that cannot be managed by the healthcare system since the cases have exceeded the available beds. The situations become more apparent where the healthcare facilities are severely damaged and lose 60% of their functionality. In this situation, all modeled Omicron cases and even the severe cases have exceeded the ICU capacity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.21267405" rel="alternate" title="SIR Modeling the Dual Disaster Impacts of Omicron B.1.1.529 and Natural Disaster Events on Simulated 6 Months (December 2021 – May 2022) Healthcare System Resiliences in Fragile SE Asia Ring of Fire Ecosystems (4 tweets)"/><category term="Health Informatics"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.21267486</id><title>Trust in the research community predicts intent to comply with COVID-19 prevention measures: An analysis of a large-scale international survey dataset (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.385425+00:00</updated><author><name>Hyemin Han</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the present study, I explored the relationship between people’s trust in different agents related to prevention of spread of COVID-19 and their compliance with pharmaceutical and non-pharmaceutical preventive measures. The COVIDiSTRESSII Global Survey dataset, which was collected from international samples, was analysed to examine the aforementioned relationship across different countries. For data-driven exploration, network analysis and Bayesian generalized linear model (GLM) analysis were performed. The result from network analysis demonstrated that trust in the scientific research community was most central in the network of trust and compliance. In addition, the outcome from Bayesian GLM analysis indicated that the same factor, trust in the scientific research community, was most fundamental in predicting participants’ intent to comply with both pharmaceutical and non-pharmaceutical preventive measures. I briefly discussed the implications of the findings, the importance of trust in the scientific research community in explaining people’s compliance with measure to prevent spread of COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.21267486" rel="alternate" title="Trust in the research community predicts intent to comply with COVID-19 prevention measures: An analysis of a large-scale international survey dataset (4 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.21267315</id><title>Might first-hand experience of ill-health and economic hardship during the COVID-19 pandemic strengthen public support for vaccination and the reallocation of health sector funding towards health emergency preparedness in South Africa? (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.385602+00:00</updated><author><name>R Mattes</name></author><author><name>K Dalal</name></author><author><name>H Rhoma</name></author><author><name>S Lambert</name></author><author><name>T De Wet</name></author><author><name>GTH Ellison</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aims&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We examined whether first-hand experience of ill-health and economic hardship during the COVID-19 pandemic might strengthen public support for vaccination, and for the reallocation of health sector funding towards health emergency preparedness in South Africa – a country in which high rates of vaccine hesitancy go hand in hand with widespread discontent regarding public service delivery.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using data from 1,600 South African respondents who were surveyed during 2021 for the Eighth Round of Afrobarometer (AB-R8), discrete measures of household- and individual-level sociodemographic and economic factors were generated to permit confounder-adjusted analyses of probabilistic causal relationships between self-reported measures of: personal/household COVID-19 illness and job/income/business loss as a result of COVID-19; and the likelihood that respondents would accept a (government-approved) COVID-19 vaccine, or support the reallocation of health sector funding towards health emergency preparedness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was little evidence that personal/household experience of COVID-19 illness was associated with the likelihood that respondents would (or would not) accept a (government-approved) COVID-19 vaccine (OR: 0.96; 95%CI: 0.72,1.28); or that these respondents would (or would not) support the reallocation of health sector funding towards health emergency preparedness (OR: 0.95; 95%CI: 0.71,1.26), even after adjustment for individual- or household-level sociodemographic and economic covariates considered likely confounders. There was similarly little evidence that personal/household experience of job/income/business loss as a result of the COVID-19 pandemic was associated with support for the reallocation of health sector resources for emergency preparedness (OR: 1.02; 95%CI: 0.80,1.30); again, even after adjustment for potential confounders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, respondents who reported that they or someone in their household had lost their job/income/or business as a result of the COVID-19 pandemic had only around half the odds of reporting that they would accept a (government-approved) COVID-19 vaccine (OR: 0.60; 95%CI: 0.47,0.77) – and this finding, like the others in these analyses, was largely unaffected by the inclusion/exclusion of covariates considered susceptible to change following the onset of the COVID-19 pandemic (i.e. those covariates potentially operating as colliders rather than genuine confounders).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;These findings suggest that – despite the postulated ‘experiential dividend’ of COVID-19 illness (i.e. its expected impact on vaccine hesitancy and support for the reallocation of health sector resources for health emergency preparedness) – no such ‘dividend’ was observed in this broadly representative sample of South African adults. Indeed, job/income/business loss (and associated economic hardship) also had little effect on support for the reallocation of health sector resources for health emergency preparedness; yet this was somewhat paradoxically associated with a much lower odds of vaccine acceptance – paradoxically, since vaccination has been widely viewed as a pragmatic (if somewhat neoliberal) intervention to protect economic activity. However, these findings might simply reflect inadequate confounder adjustment for preceding and entrenched attitudes towards vaccination amongst those South Africans who are also most vulnerable to job/income/business loss as a result of the COVID-19 pandemic. Protecting the livelihood &lt;italic&gt;and&lt;/italic&gt; health of such individuals and households is likely to remain a substantial challenge and key priority for future emergencies in which economic activity is compromised.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aim&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The aim of the present study was to examine whether first-hand experience of ill-health and economic hardship during the COVID-19 pandemic might have strengthened public support for vaccination, and for the reallocation of health sector funding towards health emergency preparedness in South Africa – a country in which high rates of vaccine hesitancy go hand in hand with widespread discontent regarding public service delivery. To this end we drew on data generated by the eighth round of household surveys undertaken by Afrobarometer (AB-R8) which interviewed 1,600 respondents across South Africa during 2021 – more than a year after the country’s first confirmed case of COVID-19 on 5 March 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.21267315" rel="alternate" title="Might first-hand experience of ill-health and economic hardship during the COVID-19 pandemic strengthen public support for vaccination and the reallocation of health sector funding towards health emergency preparedness in South Africa? (4 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.21267391</id><title>The Impact of Mass Exodus on the Resurgence of COVID19 Cases: Study Case of Regions in Indonesia (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.385755+00:00</updated><author><name>Nuning Nuraini</name></author><author><name>Kamal Khairudin Sukandar</name></author><author><name>Wirdatul Aini</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The inclusion of the human mobility aspect is essential for understanding the behavior of COVID-19 spread, especially when millions of people travel across borders near Eid Al-Fitr. This study aims at grasping the effect of mass exodus among regions on the active cases of COVID-19 in a mathematical perspective. We construct a multi-region SIQRD (Susceptible-Infected-Quarantined-Recovered-Death) model that accommodates the direct transfer of people from one region to others. The mobility rate is estimated using the proposed Dawson-like function, which requires the Origin-Destination Matrix data. Assuming only susceptible, unapparent infected, and recovered individuals travel near Eid Al-Fitr, the rendered model is well-depicting the actual data at that time, giving either a significant spike or decline in the number of active cases due to the mass exodus. Most agglomerated regions like Jakarta and Depok City experienced the fall of active cases number, both in actual data and the simulated model. However, most rural areas experienced the opposite, like Bandung District and Cimahi City. This study should confirm that most travelers originated from big cities to the rural regions and scientifically justifies that massive mobility affects the COVID-19 transmission among areas.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.21267391" rel="alternate" title="The Impact of Mass Exodus on the Resurgence of COVID19 Cases: Study Case of Regions in Indonesia (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.21267295</id><title>Population Optimally Immunized after Accounting for Type-Specific COVID-19 Vaccine Waning Intervals: State-Level Prevalence and Trends (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.385883+00:00</updated><author><name>Elizabeth B. Pathak</name></author><author><name>Jason L. Salemi</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 vaccines exhibit real-world waning effectiveness against SARS-CoV-2 infection within the first 3-6 months after a completed series. Consequently, the main metric tracked by the CDC (percent “fully vaccinated,” with no adjustment for booster status) has become insufficiently informative.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;METHODS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We analyzed CDC daily vaccination data to quantify COVID-19 immunization status for 4 mutually-exclusive groups: (1) &lt;italic&gt;not immunized;&lt;/italic&gt; (2) &lt;italic&gt;partially immunized (&lt;/italic&gt;people who received the 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; dose of a 2-dose series); (3) &lt;italic&gt;immunized with waning immunity&lt;/italic&gt; (previously immunized people whose booster dose is overdue); and (4) &lt;italic&gt;optimally immunized&lt;/italic&gt; (people who: (a) received the Janssen vaccine &amp;lt;2 months ago or completed an mRNA vaccine series &amp;lt;6 months ago, or (b) received the Janssen vaccine &amp;gt;2 months ago or completed an mRNA vaccine series &amp;gt;6 months ago and received a booster dose.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;RESULTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The proportion of the total US population who were optimally immunized against COVID-19 fell from a high of 45.3% on July 17 to 29.4% on November 30. During November, the majority of states experienced a worsening trend in the percent of the total population who were overdue for a booster dose, including the 4 largest states, with percentage point increases of 3.5 in New York, 3.4 in California, 2.3 in Texas and 1.7 in Florida.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;CONCLUSIONS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our proposed classification scheme accounts for type-specific vaccine waning intervals, provides an accurate assessment of progress toward national immunization goals, and reveals the urgent need for additional public health mitigation strategies to successfully combat the COVID-19 pandemic in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.21267295" rel="alternate" title="Population Optimally Immunized after Accounting for Type-Specific COVID-19 Vaccine Waning Intervals: State-Level Prevalence and Trends (4 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471415</id><title>Decoupling SARS-CoV-2 ORF6 localization and interferon antagonism (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.386002+00:00</updated><author><name>Hoi Tong Wong</name></author><author><name>Victoria Cheung</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Salamango</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Like many pathogenic viruses, SARS-CoV-2 must overcome interferon (IFN)-mediated host defenses for infection establishment. To achieve this, SARS-CoV-2 deploys overlapping mechanisms to antagonize IFN production and signaling. The strongest IFN antagonist is the accessory protein ORF6, which localizes to multiple membranous compartments, including the nuclear envelope, where it directly binds the nuclear pore components Nup98-Rae1 to inhibit nuclear translocation of activated STAT1/IRF3 transcription factors. However, a direct cause-and-effect relationship between ORF6 localization and IFN antagonism has yet to be explored experimentally. Here, we use extensive mutagenesis studies to define the structural determinants required for steady-state localization and demonstrate that mis-localized ORF6 variants can still potently inhibit nuclear trafficking and IFN signaling. Additionally, expression of a peptide that mimics the ORF6/Nup98 interaction domain robustly inhibited nuclear trafficking. Furthermore, pharmacologic and mutational approaches combined to suggest that ORF6 is likely a peripheral-membrane protein, opposed to being a transmembrane protein as previously speculated. Thus, ORF6 localization and IFN antagonism are independent activities, which raises the possibility that ORF6 may have additional functions within membrane networks to enhance virus replication.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471415" rel="alternate" title="Decoupling SARS-CoV-2 ORF6 localization and interferon antagonism (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.21267520</id><title>First and Second Wave Dynamics of Emergency Department Utilization during the COVID-19 Pandemic: a retrospective study (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.386121+00:00</updated><author><name>Robi Dijk</name></author><author><name>Patricia Plaum</name></author><author><name>Stan Tummers</name></author><author><name>Frits H.M. van Osch</name></author><author><name>Dennis G. Barten</name></author><author><name>Gideon H.P. Latten</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the COVID-19 pandemic, there has been a decrease in emergency department(ED) utilization. Although this has been thoroughly characterized for the first wave(FW), studies during the second wave(SW) are limited. We examined the changes in ED utilization between the FW and SW, compared to 2019 reference periods.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We performed a retrospective analysis of ED utilization in 3 Dutch hospitals in 2020. The FW and SW (March-June and September–December, respectively) were compared to the reference periods in 2019. ED visits were labeled as (non-)COVID-suspected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the FW and SW ED visits decreased by 20.3% and 15.3%, respectively, when compared to reference periods in 2019. During both waves high urgency visits significantly increased with 3.1% and 2.1%, and admission rates (ARs) increased with 5.0% and 10.4%. Trauma related visits decreased by 5.2% and 3.4%. During the SW we observed less COVID-related visits compared to the FW (4,407 vs 3,102 patients). COVID-related visits were significantly more often in higher need of urgent care and ARs where at least 24.0% higher compared to non-COVID visits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;During both COVID-19 waves ED visits were significantly reduced, with the most distinct decline during the FW. ED patients were more often triaged as high urgent and the ARs were increased compared to the reference period in 2019, reflecting a high burden on ED resources. These findings indicate the need to gain more insight into motives of patients to delay or avoid emergency care during pandemics and prepare EDs for future pandemics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;None&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.21267520" rel="alternate" title="First and Second Wave Dynamics of Emergency Department Utilization during the COVID-19 Pandemic: a retrospective study (3 tweets)"/><category term="Emergency Medicine"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.21267102</id><title>Individual vaccine efficacy variation with time since mRNA BNT162b2 vaccination estimated by rapid, quantitative antibody measurements from a finger-prick sample (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.386260+00:00</updated><author><name>Matheus J. T. Vargas</name></author><author><name>Mithileshwari Chandrasekhar</name></author><author><name>Yong Je Kwon</name></author><author><name>Gerrit Sjoerd Deijs</name></author><author><name>Carsten Ma On Wong Corazza</name></author><author><name>Angela (Wai Yin) Chai</name></author><author><name>Rebecca L. Binedell</name></author><author><name>Ellen Jose</name></author><author><name>Bhavesh Govind</name></author><author><name>Laura Huyet</name></author><author><name>Pooja K. Patel</name></author><author><name>Gabrielle Reshef</name></author><author><name>Vijaya Kumar</name></author><author><name>Tiffany Lowe</name></author><author><name>Robert J. Powell</name></author><author><name>Kieran C. Jina</name></author><author><name>Flynn C.W. Walker</name></author><author><name>Apisalome Talemaitoga</name></author><author><name>M. Cather Simpson</name></author><author><name>David E. Williams</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We show that an individual’s immune status to Covid-19 can be monitored through quantitative antibody measurements using a method specifically designed for high throughput and accuracy from a finger-prick blood sample. The quality of the rapid test results is comparable to that from major commercial laboratory testing kits. Anti-Receptor Binding Domain (RBD) IgG concentration showed a log-normal distribution with mean decreasing with time following the second vaccination with mRNA BNT162b2 (Pfizer). Using a model for an individual’s antibody concentration-dependent vaccine efficacy allowed comparison with literature data on changing vaccine efficacy against symptomatic disease across a population. In this small trial (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; = 100) estimated median vaccine efficacy was 90% (range 65-95%) &amp;lt; 90 days post vaccination, 75% (range 35 – 90%) 90 – 170 days and 65% (range 35-90%) 170 – 230 days. The results provide strong support for personalized booster programmes that, by targeting people in the tail of the distribution, should be more effective at diminishing breakthrough infection and optimising booster dose supply than a program that simply mandates a booster at a specific post-vaccination time point.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.21267102" rel="alternate" title="Individual vaccine efficacy variation with time since mRNA BNT162b2 vaccination estimated by rapid, quantitative antibody measurements from a finger-prick sample (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.21267395</id><title>High seroconversion rate and SARS-CoV-2 Delta neutralization in PLWHIV vaccinated with BNT162b2 (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.386485+00:00</updated><author><name>Valérie Pourcher</name></author><author><name>Lisa Belin</name></author><author><name>Cathia Soulie</name></author><author><name>Michelle Rosenzwajg</name></author><author><name>Stéphane Marot</name></author><author><name>Karine Lacombe</name></author><author><name>Nadia Valin</name></author><author><name>Gilles Pialoux</name></author><author><name>Ruxandra Calin</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Malet</name></author><author><name>Karen Zafilaza</name></author><author><name>Roland Tubiana</name></author><author><name>Marc-Antoine Valantin</name></author><author><name>David Klatzmann</name></author><author><name>Vincent Calvez</name></author><author><name>Noémie Simon-Tillaux</name></author><author><name>Anne-Geneviève Marcelin</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To assess the humoral and cellular responses against SARS-CoV-2 Delta variant after BNT162b2 vaccination in PLWHIV.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Multicenter cohort study of PLWHIV, with a CD4 cell count &amp;lt;500/mm&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; and a viral load &amp;lt;50 copies/ml on stable antiretroviral therapy for at least 3 months.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anti-SARS-CoV-2 Receptor Binding Domain IgG antibodies (anti-RBD IgG) were quantified and their neutralization capacity was evaluated using an ELISA (GenScript) and a virus neutralization test (VNT), against historical strain, Beta and Delta variants before vaccination (day 0) and one month after a complete vaccination schedule (M1).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;97 patients were enrolled in the study: 85 received 2 vaccine doses (11 previous COVID-19 and 1 premature exit). The seroconversion rate in anti-RBD IgG was 97% CI95[90%; 100%] at M1. Median (IQR) anti-RBD IgG titer was 0.97 (0.97-5.3) BAU/ml at D0 and 1219 (602-1929) at M1. Neutralizing antibodies (NAbs) capacity improved between D0 (15% CI95[8%; 23%]) and M1 (94% CI95[87%; 98%]) with the GenScript assay (p&amp;lt;0.0001). At M1, NAbs against historical strain, Beta and Delta variants were present in 82%, 77% and 84% patients respectively. The seroconversion rate and median anti-RBD IgG were 91% and 852 BAU/ml in patients with CD4&amp;lt;250/mm3 (n=13) and 98% and 1270 BAU/ml in patients with CD4&amp;gt;250/mm&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; (n=64) (p=0.3994). 73% of patients with CD4&amp;lt;250 had NAbs and 97% of those with CD4&amp;gt;250 (p=0.0130). The NAbs against Beta variant was elicited in 50% in CD4&amp;lt;250 and in 81% in CD4&amp;gt;250 (p=0.0292). No change in CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; or CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells count was observed while a decrease of CD19&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; B cells count was observed (208 ±124 cells/mm3 at D0 vs 188 ±112 cells/mm3 at M1, p&amp;lt;0.01). No notable adverse effects or COVID-19 were reported.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;These results show a high seroconversion rate with a Delta neutralization in PLWHIV patients after a complete BNT162b2 vaccination schedule.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.21267395" rel="alternate" title="High seroconversion rate and SARS-CoV-2 Delta neutralization in PLWHIV vaccinated with BNT162b2 (3 tweets)"/><category term="HIV/AIDS"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.21267311</id><title>SEDRA: Selective Entry Dynamic Risk Assessment A mathematical model to safely keep the borders open during Covid-19 (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.386689+00:00</updated><author><name>Silvano de Gennaro</name></author><author><name>Håkan Lane</name></author><author><name>Radhakhrishna Somanah</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1.&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Covid-19 pandemic has brought the World to a near standstill for most of 2020 and 2021, causing chaos in international travel, driving many economies into the ground, particularly those largely based on tourism. The lack of standard tools to assist decision makers in structuring a coherent policy to allow foreign passengers into their county and the resulting panic-mode opening/closing the borders on every “new case” outburst or new variant “of concern”, have led several countries to costly and often meaningless decisions based on fear rather than science or logic. This study aims at providing a universal method to safely keep the borders open and allow conditional immigration to foreign passengers according to a “Risk Group” table that includes all the countries reporting data on their Covid-19 situation to the WHO and other organisms. The RG table is recalculated on a weekly basis according to a mathematical model described in this paper, dynamically assessing the status of the pandemic worldwide through the calculation of a “Safety Index” for each country. A prototype algorithm has been implemented in VBA/EXCEL and its results are published bi-weekly on a Github repository.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.21267311" rel="alternate" title="SEDRA: Selective Entry Dynamic Risk Assessment A mathematical model to safely keep the borders open during Covid-19 (3 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471464</id><title>Characterization of the interaction between SARS-CoV-2 Membrane Protein and Proliferating Cell Nuclear Antigen (PCNA) as a Potential Therapeutic Target (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.386810+00:00</updated><author><name>Érika Pereira Zambalde</name></author><author><name>Isadora Carolina Betim Pavan</name></author><author><name>Mariana Camargo Silva Mancini</name></author><author><name>Matheus Brandemarte Severino</name></author><author><name>Orlando Bonito Scudero</name></author><author><name>Ana Paula Morelli</name></author><author><name>Mariene Ribeiro Amorim</name></author><author><name>Karina Bispo dos Santos</name></author><author><name>Mariana Marcela Góis</name></author><author><name>Daniel Augusto de Toledo-Teixeira</name></author><author><name>Pierina Lorencini Parise</name></author><author><name>Thais Mauad</name></author><author><name>Marisa Dolhnikoff</name></author><author><name>Paulo Hilário Nascimento Saldiva</name></author><author><name>Henrique Marques-Souza</name></author><author><name>José Luiz Proenca-Modena</name></author><author><name>Armando Morais Ventura</name></author><author><name>Fernando Moreira Simabuco</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 is an emerging virus from the &lt;italic&gt;Coronaviridae&lt;/italic&gt; family and is responsible for the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic. In this work, we explored the previously reported SARS-CoV-2 structural membrane protein (M) interaction with human Proliferating Cell Nuclear Antigen (PCNA). The M protein is responsible for maintaining virion shape, and PCNA is a marker of DNA damage which is essential for DNA replication and repair. We validated the M PCNA interaction through immunoprecipitation, immunofluorescence co-localization, and a PLA assay. In cells infected with SARS-CoV-2 or transfected with M protein, using immunofluorescence and cell fractioning, we documented a reallocation of PCNA from the nucleus to the cytoplasm and the increase of PCNA and γH2AX (another DNA damage marker) expression. We also observed an increase of PCNA and γH2AX expression in the lung of a COVID-19 patient by immunohistochemistry. In addition, the inhibition of PCNA translocation by PCNA I1 and Verdinexor led to a reduction of plaque formation in an in vitro assay. We, therefore, propose that the transport of PCNA to the cytoplasm and its association with M could be a virus strategy to manipulate cell functions and may be considered a target for COVID-19 therapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471464" rel="alternate" title="Characterization of the interaction between SARS-CoV-2 Membrane Protein and Proliferating Cell Nuclear Antigen (PCNA) as a Potential Therapeutic Target (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.21267101</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 Distribution in Residential Housing Suggests Contact Deposition and Correlates with Rothia sp (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.387144+00:00</updated><author><name>Victor J Cantú</name></author><author><name>Rodolfo A. Salido</name></author><author><name>Shi Huang</name></author><author><name>Gibraan Rahman</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Tsai</name></author><author><name>Holly Valentine</name></author><author><name>Celestine G. Magallanes</name></author><author><name>Stefan Aigner</name></author><author><name>Nathan A. Baer</name></author><author><name>Tom Barber</name></author><author><name>Pedro Belda-Ferre</name></author><author><name>Maryann Betty</name></author><author><name>MacKenzie Bryant</name></author><author><name>Martin Casas Maya</name></author><author><name>Anelizze Castro-Martínez</name></author><author><name>Marisol Chacón</name></author><author><name>Willi Cheung</name></author><author><name>Evelyn S. Crescini</name></author><author><name>Peter De Hoff</name></author><author><name>Emily Eisner</name></author><author><name>Sawyer Farmer</name></author><author><name>Abbas Hakim</name></author><author><name>Laura Kohn</name></author><author><name>Alma L. Lastrella</name></author><author><name>Elijah S. Lawrence</name></author><author><name>Sydney C. Morgan</name></author><author><name>Toan T. Ngo</name></author><author><name>Alhakam Nouri</name></author><author><name>R Tyler Ostrander</name></author><author><name>Ashley Plascencia</name></author><author><name>Christopher A. Ruiz</name></author><author><name>Shashank Sathe</name></author><author><name>Phoebe Seaver</name></author><author><name>Tara Shwartz</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth W. Smoot</name></author><author><name>Thomas Valles</name></author><author><name>Gene W. Yeo</name></author><author><name>Louise C. Laurent</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Fielding-Miller</name></author><author><name>Rob Knight</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Monitoring severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) on surfaces is emerging as an important tool for identifying past exposure to individuals shedding viral RNA. Our past work has demonstrated that SARS-CoV-2 reverse transcription-quantitative PCR (RT-qPCR) signals from surfaces can identify when infected individuals have touched surfaces such as Halloween candy, and when they have been present in hospital rooms or schools. However, the sensitivity and specificity of surface sampling as a method for detecting the presence of a SARS-CoV-2 positive individual, as well as guidance about where to sample, has not been established. To address these questions, and to test whether our past observations linking SARS-CoV-2 abundance to &lt;italic&gt;Rothia&lt;/italic&gt; spp. in hospitals also hold in a residential setting, we performed detailed spatial sampling of three isolation housing units, assessing each sample for SARS-CoV-2 abundance by RT-qPCR, linking the results to 16S rRNA gene amplicon sequences to assess the bacterial community at each location and to the Cq value of the contemporaneous clinical test. Our results show that the highest SARS-CoV-2 load in this setting is on touched surfaces such as light switches and faucets, but detectable signal is present in many non-touched surfaces that may be more relevant in settings such as schools where mask wearing is enforced. As in past studies, the bacterial community predicts which samples are positive for SARS-CoV-2, with &lt;italic&gt;Rothia&lt;/italic&gt; sp. showing a positive association.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Surface sampling for detecting SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), is increasingly being used to locate infected individuals. We tested which indoor surfaces had high versus low viral loads by collecting 381 samples from three residential units where infected individuals resided, and interpreted the results in terms of whether SARS-CoV-2 was likely transmitted directly (e.g. touching a light switch) or indirectly (e.g. by droplets or aerosols settling). We found highest loads where the subject touched the surface directly, although enough virus was detected on indirectly contacted surfaces to make such locations useful for sampling (e.g. in schools, where students do not touch the light switches and also wear masks so they have no opportunity to touch their face and then the object). We also documented links between the bacteria present in a sample and the SARS-CoV-2 virus, consistent with earlier studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.21267101" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 Distribution in Residential Housing Suggests Contact Deposition and Correlates with Rothia sp (3 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.21267170</id><title>Facilitating safe discharge through predicting disease progression in moderate COVID-19: a prospective cohort study to develop and validate a clinical prediction model in resource-limited settings (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.388122+00:00</updated><author><name>Arjun Chandna</name></author><author><name>Raman Mahajan</name></author><author><name>Priyanka Gautam</name></author><author><name>Lazaro Mwandigha</name></author><author><name>Karthik Gunasekaran</name></author><author><name>Divendu Bhusan</name></author><author><name>Arthur T L Cheung</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Day</name></author><author><name>Sabine Dittrich</name></author><author><name>Arjen Dondorp</name></author><author><name>Tulasi Geevar</name></author><author><name>Srinivasa R Ghattamaneni</name></author><author><name>Samreen Hussain</name></author><author><name>Carolina Jimenez</name></author><author><name>Rohini Karthikeyan</name></author><author><name>Sanjeev Kumar</name></author><author><name>Shiril Kumar</name></author><author><name>Vikash Kumar</name></author><author><name>Debasree Kundu</name></author><author><name>Ankita Lakshmanan</name></author><author><name>Abi Manesh</name></author><author><name>Chonticha Menggred</name></author><author><name>Mahesh Moorthy</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Osborn</name></author><author><name>Melissa Richard-Greenblatt</name></author><author><name>Sadhana Sharma</name></author><author><name>Veena K Singh</name></author><author><name>Vikash K Singh</name></author><author><name>Javvad Suri</name></author><author><name>Shuichi Suzuki</name></author><author><name>Jaruwan Tubprasert</name></author><author><name>Paul Turner</name></author><author><name>Annavi M G Villanueva</name></author><author><name>Naomi Waithira</name></author><author><name>Pragya Kumar</name></author><author><name>George M Varghese</name></author><author><name>Constantinos Koshiaris</name></author><author><name>Yoel Lubell</name></author><author><name>Sakib Burza</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In locations where few people have received COVID-19 vaccines, health systems remain vulnerable to surges in SARS-CoV-2 infections. Tools to identify patients suitable for community-based management are urgently needed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We prospectively recruited adults presenting to two hospitals in India with moderate symptoms of laboratory-confirmed COVID-19 in order to develop and validate a clinical prediction model to rule-out progression to supplemental oxygen requirement. The primary outcome was defined as any of the following: SpO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;lt; 94%; respiratory rate &amp;gt; 30 bpm; SpO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;/FiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;lt; 400; or death. We specified &lt;italic&gt;a priori&lt;/italic&gt; that each model would contain three clinical parameters (age, sex and SpO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) and one of seven shortlisted biochemical biomarkers measurable using near-patient tests (CRP, D-dimer, IL-6, NLR, PCT, sTREM-1 or suPAR), to ensure the models would be suitable for resource-limited settings. We evaluated discrimination, calibration and clinical utility of the models in a temporal external validation cohort.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;426 participants were recruited, of whom 89 (21·0%) met the primary outcome. 257 participants comprised the development cohort and 166 comprised the validation cohort. The three models containing NLR, suPAR or IL-6 demonstrated promising discrimination (c-statistics: 0·72 to 0·74) and calibration (calibration slopes: 1·01 to 1·05) in the validation cohort, and provided greater utility than a model containing the clinical parameters alone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present three clinical prediction models that could help clinicians identify patients with moderate COVID-19 suitable for community-based management. The models are readily implementable and of particular relevance for locations with limited resources.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Médecins Sans Frontières, India.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;RESEARCH IN CONTEXT&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Evidence before this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A living systematic review by Wynants et al. identified 137 COVID-19 prediction models, 47 of which were derived to predict whether patients with COVID-19 will have an adverse outcome. Most lacked external validation, relied on retrospective data, did not focus on patients with moderate disease, were at high risk of bias, and were not practical for use in resource-limited settings. To identify promising biochemical biomarkers which may have been evaluated independently of a prediction model and therefore not captured by this review, we searched PubMed on 1 June 2020 using synonyms of “SARS-CoV-2” AND [“biomarker” OR “prognosis”]. We identified 1,214 studies evaluating biochemical biomarkers of potential value in the prognostication of COVID-19 illness. In consultation with FIND (Geneva, Switzerland) we shortlisted seven candidates for evaluation in this study, all of which are measurable using near-patient tests which are either currently available or in late-stage development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Added value of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We followed the TRIPOD guidelines to develop and validate three promising clinical prediction models to help clinicians identify which patients presenting with moderate COVID-19 can be safely managed in the community. Each model contains three easily ascertained clinical parameters (age, sex, and SpO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) and one biochemical biomarker (NLR, suPAR or IL-6), and would be practical for implementation in high-patient-throughput low resource settings. The models showed promising discrimination and calibration in the validation cohort. The inclusion of a biomarker test improved prognostication compared to a model containing the clinical parameters alone, and extended the range of contexts in which such a tool might provide utility to include situations when bed pressures are less critical, for example at earlier points in a COVID-19 surge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Implications of all the available evidence&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prognostic models should be developed for clearly-defined clinical use-cases. We report the development and temporal validation of three clinical prediction models to rule-out progression to supplemental oxygen requirement amongst patients presenting with moderate COVID-19. The models are readily implementable and should prove useful in triage and resource allocation. We provide our full models to enable independent validation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.21267170" rel="alternate" title="Facilitating safe discharge through predicting disease progression in moderate COVID-19: a prospective cohort study to develop and validate a clinical prediction model in resource-limited settings (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471597</id><title>Deep Mutational Engineering of broadly-neutralizing and picomolar affinity nanobodies to accommodate SARS-CoV-1 &amp; 2 antigenic polymorphism (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.388742+00:00</updated><author><name>Adrien Laroche</name></author><author><name>Maria Lucia Orsini Delgado</name></author><author><name>Philippe Cuniasse</name></author><author><name>Steven Dubois</name></author><author><name>Raphael Sierocki</name></author><author><name>Fabrice Gallais</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Debroas</name></author><author><name>Laurent Bellanger</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Simon</name></author><author><name>Bernard Maillere</name></author><author><name>Hervé Nozach</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We report in this study the molecular engineering of nanobodies that bind with picomolar affinity to both SARS-CoV-1 and SARS-CoV-2 Receptor Binding Domains (RBD) and are highly neutralizing. We applied Deep Mutational Engineering to VHH72, a nanobody initially specific for SARS-CoV-1 RBD with little cross-reactivity to SARS-CoV-2 antigen. We first identified all the individual VHH substitutions that increase binding to SARS-CoV-2 RBD and then screened highly focused combinatorial libraries to isolate engineered nanobodies with improved properties. The corresponding VHH-Fc molecules show high affinities for SARS-CoV-2 antigens from various emerging variants and SARS-CoV-1, block the interaction between ACE2 and RBD and neutralize the virus with high efficiency. Its rare specificity across sarbecovirus relies on its peculiar epitope outside the immunodominant regions. The engineered nanobodies share a common motif of three amino acids, which contribute to the broad specificity of recognition. These nanobodies appears as promising therapeutic candidates to fight SARS-CoV-2 infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471597" rel="alternate" title="Deep Mutational Engineering of broadly-neutralizing and picomolar affinity nanobodies to accommodate SARS-CoV-1 &amp; 2 antigenic polymorphism (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471590</id><title>A novel bacterial protease inhibitor adjuvant in RBD-based COVID-19 vaccine formulations increases neutralizing antibodies, specific germinal center B cells and confers protection against SARS-CoV-2 infection. (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.389047+00:00</updated><author><name>Lorena M Coria</name></author><author><name>Lucas M Saposnik</name></author><author><name>Celeste Pueblas Castro</name></author><author><name>Eliana F Castro</name></author><author><name>Laura A Bruno</name></author><author><name>William B Stone</name></author><author><name>Paula S Perez</name></author><author><name>M. Laura Darriba</name></author><author><name>Lucia B Chemes</name></author><author><name>Julieta Alcain</name></author><author><name>Ignacio Mazzitelli</name></author><author><name>Augusto Varese</name></author><author><name>Melisa Salvatori</name></author><author><name>Albert J Auguste</name></author><author><name>Diego E Alvarez</name></author><author><name>Karina A Pasquevich</name></author><author><name>Juliana Cassataro</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In this work we evaluated recombinant receptor binding domain (RBD) based vaccine formulation prototypes with potential for further clinical development. We assessed different formulations containing RBD plus Alum, AddaS03, AddaVax or the combination of Alum and U-Omp19: a novel Brucella spp. protease inhibitor vaccine adjuvant. Results show that the vaccine formulation composed of U-Omp19 and Alum as adjuvants have a better performance: it significantly increased mucosal and systemic neutralizing antibodies in comparison to antigen plus Alum, AddaVax or AddaS03. Antibodies induced with the formulation containing U-Omp19 not only increased their neutralization capacity against the wild-type virus but also cross neutralized alpha, lambda and gamma variants with similar potency. Also, addition of U-Omp19 to vaccine formulation increased the frequency of RBD-specific geminal center B cells and plasmablasts. Additionally, U-Omp19+Alum formulation induced RBD-specific Th1 and CD8+ T cell responses in spleens and lungs. Finally, this vaccine formulation conferred protection against an intranasal SARS-CoV-2 challenge of K18-hACE2 mice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471590" rel="alternate" title="A novel bacterial protease inhibitor adjuvant in RBD-based COVID-19 vaccine formulations increases neutralizing antibodies, specific germinal center B cells and confers protection against SARS-CoV-2 infection. (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471588</id><title>Orally administered epeleuton inhibits SARS-CoV-2 viral load, replication and pathology in the Syrian Hamster model (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.389388+00:00</updated><author><name>John Climax</name></author><author><name>Moayed Hamza</name></author><author><name>Adam Lafferty</name></author><author><name>Kate Guilfoyle</name></author><author><name>Geert van Amerongen</name></author><author><name>Konrad Stadler</name></author><author><name>Peter Wohlsein</name></author><author><name>Wolfgang Baumgärtner</name></author><author><name>Markus Weissbach</name></author><author><name>David Coughlan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Early treatment of patients with confirmed COVID-19 presenting mild symptoms can reduce the number that progress to more severe disease and require hospitalization. Considering the potential for the development of drug resistance to existing therapies and the emergence of new SARS-CoV-2 variants, there is a need for an expanded armamentarium of treatment options for COVID-19. Epeleuton is a novel orally administered second-generation n-3 fatty acid with potential direct antiviral and immunomodulatory actions, and a favourable clinical safety profile. In this study we show that epeleuton inhibits SARS-CoV-2 infectious viral load, replication and disease pathology in the lungs and upper airways in the Syrian hamster model of SARS-CoV-2 infection. These data support the potential utility of epeleuton in the early treatment and prevention of SARS-CoV-2 infection. Clinical trials are needed to evaluate the efficacy of epeleuton as an outpatient treatment and prevention of COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471588" rel="alternate" title="Orally administered epeleuton inhibits SARS-CoV-2 viral load, replication and pathology in the Syrian Hamster model (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>