<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.802143+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.12.21258835</id><title>Predicted domination of variant Delta of SARS-CoV-2 before Tokyo Olympic games, Japan (1602 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.802535+00:00</updated><author><name>Kimihito Ito</name></author><author><name>Chayada Piantham</name></author><author><name>Hiroshi Nishiura</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Using nucleotide sequences of SARS-CoV-2 strains collected in Japan, the relative instantaneous reproduction numbers of the R.1, Alpha, and Delta variants with respect to other strains circulation in Japan were estimated at 1.256, 1.449, and 1.776, respectively. The numbers can range 1.198–1.335 for R.1, 1.342–1.596 for Alpha, and 1.557–2.00 for Delta depending on the assumed serial interval distributions. The frequency of the Delta is expected to take over the Alpha in Japan around July 12, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.12.21258835" rel="alternate" title="Predicted domination of variant Delta of SARS-CoV-2 before Tokyo Olympic games, Japan (1602 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.15.448551</id><title>Zinc2+ ion inhibits SARS-CoV-2 main protease and viral replication in vitro (151 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.802774+00:00</updated><author><name>Love Panchariya</name></author><author><name>Wajahat Ali Khan</name></author><author><name>Shobhan Kuila</name></author><author><name>Kirtishila Sonkar</name></author><author><name>Sibasis Sahoo</name></author><author><name>Archita Ghoshal</name></author><author><name>Ankit Kumar</name></author><author><name>Dileep Kumar Verma</name></author><author><name>Abdul Hasan</name></author><author><name>Shubhashis Das</name></author><author><name>Jitendra K Thakur</name></author><author><name>Rajkumar Halder</name></author><author><name>Sujatha Sunil</name></author><author><name>Arulandu Arockiasamy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Zinc deficiency is linked to poor prognosis in COVID-19 patients while clinical trials with Zinc demonstrate better clinical outcome. The molecular target and mechanistic details of anti-coronaviral (SARS-CoV2) activity of Zinc remain obscure. We show that ionic Zinc not only inhibits SARS-CoV-2 main protease (Mpro) with nanomolar affinity, but also viral replication. We present the first crystal structure of Mpro-Zinc&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; complex at 1.9 Å and provide the structural basis of viral replication inhibition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.15.448551" rel="alternate" title="Zinc2+ ion inhibits SARS-CoV-2 main protease and viral replication in vitro (151 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.21258468</id><title>A tale of two variants: Spread of SARS-CoV-2 variants Alpha in Geneva, Switzerland, and Beta in South Africa (118 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.803020+00:00</updated><author><name>Christian L. Althaus</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Baggio</name></author><author><name>Martina L. Reichmuth</name></author><author><name>Emma B. Hodcroft</name></author><author><name>Julien Riou</name></author><author><name>Richard A. Neher</name></author><author><name>Frédérique Jacquerioz</name></author><author><name>Hervé Spechbach</name></author><author><name>Julien Salamun</name></author><author><name>Pauline Vetter</name></author><author><name>Carolyn Williamson</name></author><author><name>Nei-yuan Hsiao</name></author><author><name>Wolfgang Preiser</name></author><author><name>Mary-Ann Davies</name></author><author><name>Richard J. Lessells</name></author><author><name>Tulio de Olivera</name></author><author><name>Laurent Kaiser</name></author><author><name>Isabella Eckerle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Several SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (VOC) are spreading rapidly in different regions of the world. The underlying mechanisms behind their transmission advantage remain unclear. We measured viral load in 950 individuals and found that infections with variant Alpha exhibit a higher viral load and longer viral shedding compared to non-VOC. We then used a transmission model to analyze the spread of variant Alpha in Geneva, Switzerland, and variant Beta in South Africa. We estimated that Alpha is either associated with a 37% (95% compatibility interval, CI: 25–63%) increase in transmissibility or a 51% (95% CI: 32–80%) increase of the infectious duration, or a combination of the two mechanisms. Assuming 50% immune evasion for Beta, we estimated a 23% (95% CI: 10–37%) increase in transmissibility or a 38% (95% CI: 15–78%) increase of the infectious duration for this variant. Beta is expected to outgrow Alpha in regions where the level of naturally acquired immunity from previously circulating variants exceeds 20% to 40%. Close monitoring of Alpha and Beta in regions with different levels of immunity will help to anticipate the global spread of these and future variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.21258468" rel="alternate" title="A tale of two variants: Spread of SARS-CoV-2 variants Alpha in Geneva, Switzerland, and Beta in South Africa (118 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.16.21259052</id><title>Rapid spread of the SARS-CoV-2 δ variant in the area of Paris (France) in June 2021 (76 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.803289+00:00</updated><author><name>Samuel Alizon</name></author><author><name>Stephani Haim-Boukobza</name></author><author><name>Vincent Foulongne</name></author><author><name>Laura Verdurme</name></author><author><name>Sabine Trombert-Paolantoni</name></author><author><name>Emmanue Lecorche</name></author><author><name>Benedicte Roquebert</name></author><author><name>Mircea T. Sofonea</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Analysing 5,061 variant-specific tests performed on SARS-CoV-2 positive samples collected in France between 31 May and 8 June 2021 reveals a rapid growth of the δ variant in the Ile-de-France region. The next weeks will prove decisive but the magnitude of the estimated transmission advantage (with a 95% confidence interval between 67 and 120%) could represent a major challenge for public health authorities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.16.21259052" rel="alternate" title="Rapid spread of the SARS-CoV-2 δ variant in the area of Paris (France) in June 2021 (76 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.12.21258345</id><title>Coadministration of AYUSH 64 as an adjunct to Standard of Care in mild and moderate COVID-19: A randomised, controlled, multicentric clinical trial (41 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.803486+00:00</updated><author><name>Arvind Chopra</name></author><author><name>Girish Tillu</name></author><author><name>Kuldeep Chuadhary</name></author><author><name>Govind Reddy</name></author><author><name>Alok Srivastava</name></author><author><name>Muffazal Lakdawala</name></author><author><name>Dilip Gode</name></author><author><name>Himanshu Reddy</name></author><author><name>Sanjay Tamboli</name></author><author><name>Manjit Saluja</name></author><author><name>Sanjeev Sarmukkaddam</name></author><author><name>Manohar Gundeti</name></author><author><name>Ashwinikumar Raut</name></author><author><name>BCS Rao</name></author><author><name>Babita Yadav</name></author><author><name>Narayanam Srikanth</name></author><author><name>Bhushan Patwardhan</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To compare the co-administration of an Ayurvedic drug AYUSH 64 as an adjunct to standard of care (SOC) and SOC for efficacy and safety in the management of COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Multicentre, parallel efficacy, randomized, controlled, open label, assessor blind, exploratory trial with a convenience sample. Patients followed to complete 12 weeks of study duration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 dedicated non-intensive care wards at 1 government hospital, 1 medical college teaching hospital and 1 medical university teaching hospital&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;140 consenting, eligible, hospitalized adult patients suffering from mild and moderate symptomatic COVID-19 and confirmed by a diagnostic (SARS-CoV-2) RT-PCR assay on nasal and throat swab were randomized to SOC or SOC plus AYUSH 64. To be withdrawn if disease becomes severe.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interventions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two tablets of AYUSH 64, 500 mg each, twice daily after meals, and continued till study completion. SOC (symptomatic and supportive) as per national guidelines of India for mild and moderate disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main outcome measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Time period to clinical recovery (CR) from randomization baseline and proportion with CR within 28 days time frame; CR defined in the protocol&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;140 patients randomized (70 in each arm); 138 patients with CR qualified for analysis. Both groups were matched at baseline. The mean time to CR from randomization was significantly superior in AYUSH 64 group (95% CI -3.03 to 0.59 days); a higher proportion (69.7%) in the first week (p=0.046, Chi-square). No significant differences observed for COVID-19 related blood assays (such as D-Dimer). AYUSH 64 arm showed significant (p&amp;lt;0.05) superior persistent improvement in general health, quality of life, fatigue, anxiety, stress, sleep and other psychosocial metrics. 1 patient on SOC required critical care. 48 adverse events (AE) reported in each group. Barring three SAE (in SOC), AE were mild and none were drug related. 22 participants (8 on AYUSH) were withdrawn. No deaths were reported.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;AYUSH 64 hastened recovery, reduced hospitalization and improved overall health in mild and moderate COVID-19 when co-administered with SOC under medical supervision. It was safe and well tolerated. Further studies are warranted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Trial registration&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Clinical Trials Registry India Number CTRI/2020/06/025557&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;CCRAS, Ministry of AYUSH, Government of India&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.12.21258345" rel="alternate" title="Coadministration of AYUSH 64 as an adjunct to Standard of Care in mild and moderate COVID-19: A randomised, controlled, multicentric clinical trial (41 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Therapeutics"/><published>2021-06-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.12.448149</id><title>Regulatory dissection of the severe COVID-19 risk locus introgressed by Neanderthals (25 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.804079+00:00</updated><author><name>Evelyn Jagoda</name></author><author><name>Davide Marnetto</name></author><author><name>Francesco Montinaro</name></author><author><name>Daniel Richard</name></author><author><name>Luca Pagani</name></author><author><name>Terence D. Capellini</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Individuals infected with the SARS-CoV-2 virus present with a wide variety of phenotypes ranging from asymptomatic to severe and even lethal outcomes. Past research has revealed a genetic haplotype on chromosome 3 that entered the human population via introgression from Neanderthals as the strongest genetic risk factor for the severe COVID-19 phenotype. However, the specific variants along this introgressed haplotype that contribute to this risk and the biological mechanisms that are involved remain unclear. Here, we assess the variants present on the risk haplotype for their likelihood of driving the severe COVID-19 phenotype. We do this by first exploring their impact on the regulation of genes involved in COVID-19 infection using a variety of population genetics and functional genomics tools. We then perform an locus-specific massively parallel reporter assay to individually assess the regulatory potential of each allele on the haplotype in a multipotent immune-related cell line. We ultimately reduce the set of over 600 linked genetic variants to identify 4 introgressed alleles that are strong functional candidates for driving the association between this locus and severe COVID-19. These variants likely drive the locus’ impact on severity by putatively modulating the regulation of two critical chemokine receptor genes: &lt;italic&gt;CCR1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;CCR5&lt;/italic&gt;. These alleles are ideal targets for future functional investigations into the interaction between host genomics and COVID-19 outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.12.448149" rel="alternate" title="Regulatory dissection of the severe COVID-19 risk locus introgressed by Neanderthals (25 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-06-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.15.21256661</id><title>Study on the mucosal and serological immune response to the Novel Coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) vaccines (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.804386+00:00</updated><author><name>Renee WY Chan</name></author><author><name>Shaojun Liu</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Y Cheung</name></author><author><name>Joseph GS Tsun</name></author><author><name>Kate C Chan</name></author><author><name>Kathy YY Chan</name></author><author><name>Genevieve PG Fung</name></author><author><name>Albert M Li</name></author><author><name>Hugh Simon Lam</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Vaccines that elicit mucosal immune responses against SARS-CoV-2 could potentially be of exceptional importance in providing first line defense at the site of viral entry. The serological antibody response induced by SARS-CoV-2 vaccines have already been well characterized. In order to understand the mucosal immune response profiles of SARS-CoV-2 vaccines, we examined both the mucosal and systemic responses of subjects vaccinated by two different vaccination platforms: mRNA (Comirnaty) and inactivated virus (CoronaVac). Serial nasal epithelial lining fluid (NELF) and peripheral blood samples were collected in ten subjects who had received CoronaVac and thirty-two subjects who had received Comirnaty. We quantified IgA and IgG specific to SARS-CoV-2 S1 protein by ELISA in NELF and plasma samples. The neutralization effect of these two sample types were evaluated by surrogate ACE-SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein ELISA. Only Comirnaty induced nasal SARS-CoV-2 S1 protein-specific (S1-specific) IgA and IgG responses, which were evident as early as on 14±2 days after the first dose. The NELF samples of 72% of subjects became IgA+IgG+, while in 62.5% of subjects the samples were neutralizing by 7±2 days after the second dose. In 45% of the subjects their NELF remained neutralizing 50 days after the booster of Comirnaty. In plasma, 91% and 100% Comirnaty subjects possessed S1-specific IgA+IgG+ on 14±2 days after the first dose and 7±2 days after booster, respectively. The plasma collected on 7±2 days after booster was 100% neutralizing. The induction of S1-specific antibody by CoronaVac was IgG dominant, and 70% of the subjects possessed S1-specific IgG by 7±2 days after booster and were all neutralizing. This study reveals that Comirnaty is able to induce S1-specific IgA and IgG response with neutralizing activity in the nasal mucosa in addition to a consistent systemic response. The clinical implications and the biological mechanism of an additional nasal immune response induced by vaccines such as Comirnaty warrant further investigation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;mRNA vaccine (CoronaVac) elicits mucosal IgA and IgG in the nasal epithelial lining fluid together with ELISA-detected anti-wild-type spike neutralizing antibodies as early as day 14 post vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.15.21256661" rel="alternate" title="Study on the mucosal and serological immune response to the Novel Coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) vaccines (10 tweets)"/><category term="Allergy and Immunology"/><published>2021-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.12.448196</id><title>Exposure route, sex, and age influence disease outcome in a golden Syrian hamster model of SARS-CoV-2 infection (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.804743+00:00</updated><author><name>Bryan D. Griffin</name></author><author><name>Bryce M. Warner</name></author><author><name>Mable Chan</name></author><author><name>Emelissa J. Mendoza</name></author><author><name>Nikesh Tailor</name></author><author><name>Logan Banadyga</name></author><author><name>Anders Leung</name></author><author><name>Shihua He</name></author><author><name>Amrit S. Boese</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Audet</name></author><author><name>Wenguang Cao</name></author><author><name>Estella Moffat</name></author><author><name>Lauren Garnett</name></author><author><name>Kevin Tierney</name></author><author><name>Kaylie N. Tran</name></author><author><name>Alixandra Albietz</name></author><author><name>Kathy Manguiat</name></author><author><name>Geoff Soule</name></author><author><name>Alexander Bello</name></author><author><name>Robert Vendramelli</name></author><author><name>Jessica Lin</name></author><author><name>Yvon Deschambault</name></author><author><name>Wenjun Zhu</name></author><author><name>David Safronetz</name></author><author><name>Heidi Wood</name></author><author><name>Samira Mubareka</name></author><author><name>James E. Strong</name></author><author><name>Carissa Embury-Hyatt</name></author><author><name>Darwyn Kobasa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The emergence of Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) and the resultant pandemic of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) has led to over one hundred million confirmed infections, greater than three million deaths, and severe economic and social disruption. Animal models of SARS-CoV-2 are critical tools for the pre-clinical evaluation of antivirals, vaccines, and candidate therapeutics currently under urgent development to curb COVID-19-associated morbidity and mortality. The golden (Syrian) hamster model of SARS-CoV-2 infection recapitulates key characteristics of severe COVID-19, including high-titer viral replication in the upper and lower respiratory tract and the development of pathogenic lesions in the lungs. In this work we examined the influence of the route of exposure, sex, and age on SARS-CoV-2 pathogenesis in golden hamsters. We report that delivery of SARS-CoV-2 primarily to the nasal passages (low-volume intranasal), the upper and lower respiratory tract (high-volume intranasal), or the digestive tract (intragastric) results in comparable viral titers in the lung tissue and similar levels of viral shedding during acute infection. However, low-volume intranasal exposure results in milder weight loss during acute infection while intragastric exposure leads to a diminished capacity to regain body weight following the period of acute illness. Further, we examined both sex and age differences in response to SARS-CoV-2 infection. Male hamsters, and to a greater extent older male hamsters, display an impaired capacity to recover from illness and a delay in viral clearance compared to females. Lastly, route of exposure, sex, and age were found to influence the nature of the host inflammatory cytokine response, but they had a minimal effect on both the quality and durability of the humoral immune response as well as the susceptibility of hamsters to SARS-CoV-2 re-infection. Together, these data indicate that the route of exposure, sex, and age have a meaningful impact SARS-CoV-2 pathogenesis in hamsters and that these variables should be considered when designing pre-clinical challenge studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.12.448196" rel="alternate" title="Exposure route, sex, and age influence disease outcome in a golden Syrian hamster model of SARS-CoV-2 infection (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.14.448436</id><title>Molecular dynamics analysis of fast-spreading severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 variants and their effects in the interaction with human angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.805608+00:00</updated><author><name>Anacleto Silva de Souza</name></author><author><name>Vitor Martins de Freitas Amorim</name></author><author><name>Gabriela D A Guardia</name></author><author><name>Felipe R C dos Santos</name></author><author><name>Filipe F dos Santos</name></author><author><name>Robson Francisco de Souza</name></author><author><name>Guilherme de Araujo Juvenal</name></author><author><name>Yihua Huang</name></author><author><name>Pingju Ge</name></author><author><name>Yinan Jiang</name></author><author><name>Prajwal Paudel</name></author><author><name>Henning Ulrich</name></author><author><name>Pedro A F Galante</name></author><author><name>Cristiane Rodrigues Guzzo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) is evolving with mutations in the Spike protein, especially in the receptor-binding domain (RBD). The failure of public health measures to contain the spread of the disease in many countries has given rise to novel viral variants with increased transmissibility. However, key questions about how quickly the variants can spread and whether they can cause a more severe disease remain unclear. Herein, we performed a structural investigation using molecular dynamics simulations and determined dissociation constant (&lt;italic&gt;K&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;D&lt;/sub&gt;) values using surface plasmon resonance (SPR) assays of three fastspreading SARS-CoV-2 variants, Alpha, Beta and Gamma ones, as well as genetic factors in the host cells that may be related to the viral infection. Our results suggest that the SARS-CoV-2 variants facilitate their entry into the host cell by moderately increased binding affinities to the human ACE2 receptor, different torsions in hACE2 mediated by RBD variants, and an increased Spike exposure time to proteolytic enzymes. We also found that other host cell aspects, such as gene and isoform expression of key genes for the infection (&lt;italic&gt;ACE2, FURIN&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;TMPRSS2&lt;/italic&gt;), may have few contributions to the SARS-CoV-2 variants infectivity. In summary, we concluded that a combination of viral and host cell factors allows SARS-CoV-2 variants to increase their abilities to spread faster than wild-type.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract Figure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="448436v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.14.448436" rel="alternate" title="Molecular dynamics analysis of fast-spreading severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 variants and their effects in the interaction with human angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (10 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.13.448258</id><title>NMPylation and de-NMPylation of SARS-CoV-2 Nsp9 by the NiRAN domain (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.805981+00:00</updated><author><name>Bing Wang</name></author><author><name>Dmitri Svetlov</name></author><author><name>Irina Artsimovitch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nsp12, the catalytic subunit of SARS-CoV-2 RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp), contains two active sites that catalyze nucleotidyl-monophosphate (NMP) transfer (NMPylation). RNA synthesis is mediated by the RdRp active site that is conserved among all RNA viruses and has been a focus of mechanistic studies and drug discovery. The second active site resides in a Nidovirus RdRp-Associated Nucleotidyl transferase (NiRAN) domain. Both catalytic reactions are essential for viral replication, but the mechanism and targets of NiRAN are poorly characterized. One recent study showed that NiRAN transfers NMP to the first residue of RNA-binding protein Nsp9. Another study reported a structure of SARS-CoV-2 replicase with an extended Nsp9 in the NiRAN active site but observed NMP transfer to RNA instead. We show that SARS-CoV-2 Nsp12 efficiently and reversibly NMPylates the native but not the extended Nsp9. Substitutions of the invariant NiRAN residues abolish NMPylation, whereas a substitution of a catalytic RdRp Asp residue does not. NMPylation is inhibited by nucleotide analogs, pyrophosphate, and bisphosphonates, suggesting a path for rational design of NiRAN inhibitors. We hypothesize that Nsp9 remodels both active sites of Nsp12 to support initiation of RNA synthesis by RdRp and subsequent capping of the product RNA by the NiRAN domain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.13.448258" rel="alternate" title="NMPylation and de-NMPylation of SARS-CoV-2 Nsp9 by the NiRAN domain (10 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-06-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.19.449100</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 mRNA Vaccine Induces Robust Specific and Cross-reactive IgG and Unequal Strain-specific Neutralizing Antibodies in Naïve and Previously Infected Recipients (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.806403+00:00</updated><author><name>Tara M Narowski</name></author><author><name>Kristin Raphel</name></author><author><name>Lily E Adams</name></author><author><name>Jenny Huang</name></author><author><name>Nadja A Vielot</name></author><author><name>Ramesh Jadi</name></author><author><name>Aravinda M de Silva</name></author><author><name>Ralph S Baric</name></author><author><name>John E Lafleur</name></author><author><name>Lakshmanane Premkumar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;With the advance of SARS-CoV-2 vaccines, the outlook for overcoming the global COVID-19 pandemic has improved. However, understanding of immunity and protection offered by the SARS-CoV-2 vaccines against circulating variants of concern (VOC) is rapidly evolving. We investigated the mRNA vaccine-induced antibody responses against the referent WIV04 (Wuhan) strain, circulating variants, and human endemic coronaviruses in 168 naive and previously infected people at three-time points. Samples were collected prior to vaccination, after the first and after the second doses of one of the two available mRNA-based vaccines. After full vaccination, both naive and previously infected participants developed comparable robust SARS-CoV-2 specific spike IgG levels, modest IgM and IgA binding antibodies, and varying degrees of HCoV cross-reactive antibodies. However, the strength and frequency of neutralizing antibodies produced in naive people were significantly lower than in the previously infected group. We also found that 1/3rd of previously infected people had undetectable neutralizing antibodies after the first vaccine dose; 40% of this group developed neutralizing antibodies after the second dose. In all subjects neutralizing antibodies produced against the B.1.351 and P.1 variants were weaker than those produced against the reference and B.1.1.7 strains. Our findings provide support for future booster vaccinations modified to be active against the circulating variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.19.449100" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 mRNA Vaccine Induces Robust Specific and Cross-reactive IgG and Unequal Strain-specific Neutralizing Antibodies in Naïve and Previously Infected Recipients (9 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-06-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.12.21258815</id><title>Intersections between pneumonia, lowered oxygen saturation percentage and immune activation mediate depression, anxiety and chronic fatigue syndrome-like symptoms due to COVID-19: a nomothetic network approach (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.807539+00:00</updated><author><name>Hawraa Kadhem Al-Jassas</name></author><author><name>Hussein Kadhem Al-Hakeim</name></author><author><name>Michael Maes</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 is associated with neuropsychiatric symptoms including increased depressive, anxiety and chronic fatigue-syndrome (CFS)-like physiosomatic (previously known as psychosomatic) symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aims&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To delineate the associations between affective and CFS-like symptoms in COVID-19 and chest CT-scan anomalies (CCTAs), oxygen saturation (SpO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;), interleukin (IL)-6, IL-10, C-Reactive Protein (CRP), albumin, calcium, magnesium, soluble angiotensin converting enzyme (ACE2) and soluble advanced glycation products (sRAGEs).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Method&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The above biomarkers were assessed in 60 COVID-19 patients and 30 heathy controls who had measurements of the Hamilton Depression (HDRS) and Anxiety (HAM-A) and the Fibromyalgia and Chronic Fatigue (FF) Rating Scales.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Partial Least Squares-SEM analysis showed that reliable latent vectors could be extracted from a) key depressive and anxiety and physiosomatic symptoms (the physio-affective or PA-core), b) IL-6, IL-10, CRP, albumin, calcium, and sRAGEs (the immune response core); and c) different CCTAs (including ground glass opacities, consolidation, and crazy paving) and lowered SpO2% (lung lesions). PLS showed that 70.0% of the variance in the PA-core was explained by the regression on the immune response and lung lesions latent vectors. Moreover, one common “infection-immune-inflammatory (III) core” underpins pneumonia-associated CCTAs, lowered SpO2 and immune activation, and this III core explains 70% of the variance in the PA core, and a relevant part of the variance in melancholia, insomnia, and neurocognitive symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Discussion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Acute SARS-CoV-2 infection is accompanied by lung lesions and lowered SpO2 which both may cause activated immune-inflammatory pathways, which mediate the effects of the former on the PA-core and other neuropsychiatric symptoms due to SARS-CoV-2 infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.12.21258815" rel="alternate" title="Intersections between pneumonia, lowered oxygen saturation percentage and immune activation mediate depression, anxiety and chronic fatigue syndrome-like symptoms due to COVID-19: a nomothetic network approach (7 tweets)"/><category term="Psychiatry and Clinical Psychology"/><published>2021-06-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.17.21259021</id><title>Survival of vaccine-induced human milk SARS-CoV-2 IgG and IgA immunoglobulins across simulated human infant gastrointestinal digestion (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.807932+00:00</updated><author><name>Myrtani Pieri</name></author><author><name>Vicky Nicolaidou</name></author><author><name>Irene Paphiti</name></author><author><name>Spyros Pipis</name></author><author><name>Kyriacos Felekkis</name></author><author><name>Christos Papaneophytou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Four vaccines have been approved to date by the European Medicines Agency for the management of the COVID-19 pandemic in Europe, with all four being targeted to adults over 18 years of age. One way to protect the younger population such as infants or younger children until pediatric vaccines are licensed is through passive immunity via breastfeeding. Recent evidence points to the fact that human milk contains immunoglobulins (Ig) against the SARS-CoV-2 virus, both after natural infection or vaccination, but it is not known whether these antibodies can resist enzymatic degradation during digestion in the infant gastrointestinal (GI) tract or indeed protect the consumers. Here, we describe our preliminary experiments where we validated commercially available ELISA kits to detect IgA and IgG antibodies in human milk from two lactating mothers vaccinated with either the Pfizer/BioNTech or the Astra Zeneca vaccine, and the effect of a static in vitro digestion protocol on the IgA and IgG concentrations. Our data, even preliminary, provide an indication that the IgA antibodies produced after vaccination with the Pfizer/BioNTech vaccine resist the gastric phase but are degraded during the intestinal phase of infant digestion, whereas the IgGs are more prone to degradation in both phases of digestion. We are in the process of recruiting more individuals to further evaluate the vaccine-induced immunoglobulin profile of breastmilk, and the extent to which these antibodies can resist digestion in the infant GI tract.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.17.21259021" rel="alternate" title="Survival of vaccine-induced human milk SARS-CoV-2 IgG and IgA immunoglobulins across simulated human infant gastrointestinal digestion (6 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.16.448642</id><title>Ceylon cinnamon and its major compound Cinnamaldehyde can limit overshooting inflammatory signaling and angiogenesis in vitro: implications for COVID-19 treatment (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.808375+00:00</updated><author><name>Kurt Lucas</name></author><author><name>Maximilian Ackermann</name></author><author><name>Anna Lena Leifke</name></author><author><name>William W. Li</name></author><author><name>Ulrich Pöschl</name></author><author><name>Janine Fröhlich-Nowoisky</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Overshooting immune reactions can occur during inflammatory responses that accompany severe infections, such as COVID-19. Cytokines, damage-associated molecular patterns (DAMPs), and reactive oxygen and nitrogen species can generate positive feedback loops of inflammation, leading to long-term complications such as vascular endothelialitis, thrombosis, endothelial dysfunction, neurological impairments, and chronic fatigue. Dexamethasone can limit inflammation by inhibiting the activation of pro-inflammatory transcription factors. High dose dexamethasone, however, has undesirable side effects. Here, we show that Ceylon cinnamon and its major compound cinnamaldehyde can mitigate inflammatory signaling &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. Cinnamaldehyde interferes with the dimerization of toll-like receptor 4 (TLR4), which can be activated by DAMPs like HSP60 and HMGB1. Our results suggest that supplementary treatment with Ceylon cinnamon may allow administration of lower doses of dexamethasone to avoid high dose steroid side effects. Moreover, preliminary results indicate that Ceylon cinnamon modulates angiogenesis, which is a reactive phenomenon in COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.16.448642" rel="alternate" title="Ceylon cinnamon and its major compound Cinnamaldehyde can limit overshooting inflammatory signaling and angiogenesis in vitro: implications for COVID-19 treatment (6 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-06-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.15.21258502</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 variant of concern B.1.1.7: diagnostic accuracy of three antigen-detecting rapid tests (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.808788+00:00</updated><author><name>Andreas K. Lindner</name></author><author><name>Lisa J. Krüger</name></author><author><name>Olga Nikolai</name></author><author><name>Julian A.F. Klein</name></author><author><name>Heike Rössig</name></author><author><name>Paul Schnitzler</name></author><author><name>Victor M. Corman</name></author><author><name>Terry C. Jones</name></author><author><name>Frank Tobian</name></author><author><name>Mary Gaeddert</name></author><author><name>Susen Burock</name></author><author><name>Jilian A. Sacks</name></author><author><name>Joachim Seybold</name></author><author><name>Frank P. Mockenhaupt</name></author><author><name>Claudia M. Denkinger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Virus mutations have the potential to impact the accuracy of diagnostic tests. The SARS-CoV-2 B.1.1.7 lineage is defined by a large number of mutations in the spike gene and four in the nucleocapsid (N) gene. Most commercially available SARS-CoV-2 antigen-detecting rapid tests (Ag-RDTs) target the viral N-protein, encoded by the N-gene.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted a manufacturer-independent, prospective diagnostic accuracy study of three SARS-CoV-2 Ag-RDTs that are currently under review by the WHO Emergency Use Listing Procedure (Espline -Fujirebio Inc.; Sure Status -Premier Medical Corporation Private Limited; Mologic -Mologic Ltd.) and report here on an additional sub-analysis regarding the B.1.1.7 lineage. During the study, in Berlin and Heidelberg, Germany, from 20 January to 15 April 2021, B.1.1.7 rapidly became the dominant SARS-CoV-2 lineage at the testing sites and was detected in 220 (62%) of SARS-CoV-2 RT-PCR positive patients. All three Ag-RDTs yielded comparable sensitivities irrespective of an infection with the B.1.1.7 lineage or not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is only limited data on how N-gene mutations in variants of concern may impact Ag-RDTs. Currently, no major changes to test performance are anticipated. However, test developers and health authorities should assess and monitor the impact of emerging variants on the accuracy of Ag-RDTs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.15.21258502" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 variant of concern B.1.1.7: diagnostic accuracy of three antigen-detecting rapid tests (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.15.448583</id><title>Structural Modeling of the TMPRSS Subfamily of Host Cell Proteases Reveals Potential Binding Sites (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.809559+00:00</updated><author><name>Diego E. Escalante</name></author><author><name>Austin Wang</name></author><author><name>David M. Ferguson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The transmembrane protease serine subfamily (TMPRSS) has at least eight members with known protein sequence: TMPRSS2, TMPRRS3, TMPRSS4, TMPRSS5, TMPRSS6, TMPRSS7, TMPRSS9, TMPRSS11, TMPRSS12 and TMPRSS13. A majority of these TMPRSS proteins have key roles in human hemostasis as well as promoting certain pathologies, including several types of cancer. In addition, TMPRSS proteins have been shown to facilitate the entrance of respiratory viruses into human cells, most notably TMPRSS2 and TMPRSS4 activate the spike protein of the SARS-CoV-2 virus. Despite the wide range of functions that these proteins have in the human body, none of them have been successfully crystallized. The lack of structural data has significantly hindered any efforts to identify potential drug candidates with high selectivity to these proteins. In this study, we present homology models for all members of the TMPRSS family including any known isoform (the homology model of TMPRSS2 is not included in this study as it has been previously published). The atomic coordinates for all homology models have been refined and equilibrated through molecular dynamic simulations. The structural data revealed potential binding sites for all TMPRSS as well as key amino acids that can be targeted for drug selectivity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.15.448583" rel="alternate" title="Structural Modeling of the TMPRSS Subfamily of Host Cell Proteases Reveals Potential Binding Sites (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.17.21259077</id><title>Determination of IgG1 and IgG3 SARS-CoV-2 spike protein and nucleocapsid binding. Who is binding who and why? (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.809858+00:00</updated><author><name>Jason K Iles</name></author><author><name>Raminta Zmuidinaite</name></author><author><name>Christoph Sadee</name></author><author><name>Anna Gardiner</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Lacey</name></author><author><name>Stephen Harding</name></author><author><name>Gregg Wallis</name></author><author><name>Roshani Patel</name></author><author><name>Debra Roblett</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Luke Heeney</name></author><author><name>Dr HE Baxendale</name></author><author><name>Raymond Kruse Iles</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The involvement of IgG3 within the humoral immune response to SARS-CoV2 infection has been implicated in the pathogenesis of ARDS in COVID-19. The exact molecular mechanism is unknown but is thought to involve this IgG subtypes differential ability to fix complement and stimulate cytokine release. We examined convalescent patients antibodies binding to immobilised nucleocapsid and spike protein by MALDI-ToF mass spectrometry. IgG3 was a major immunoglobulin found in all samples. Differential analysis of the spectral signatures found for nucleocapsid versus spike protein demonstrated that the predominant humoral immune response to nucleocapsid was IgG3, whilst against spike it was IgG1. However, the spike protein displayed a strong affinity for IgG3 itself which it would bind from control plasma samples as well as from those previously infected with SARS-CoV2, much in the way Protein-G binds IgG1. Furthermore, detailed spectral analysis indicated a mass shift consistent with hyper-glycosylation or glycation was a characteristic of the IgG3 captured by the spike protein.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.17.21259077" rel="alternate" title="Determination of IgG1 and IgG3 SARS-CoV-2 spike protein and nucleocapsid binding. Who is binding who and why? (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>