<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.315486+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21267966</id><title>Vaccine effectiveness against SARS-CoV-2 infection with the Omicron or Delta variants following a two-dose or booster BNT162b2 or mRNA-1273 vaccination series: A Danish cohort study (36827 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.316166+00:00</updated><author><name>Christian Holm Hansen</name></author><author><name>Astrid Blicher Schelde</name></author><author><name>Ida Rask Moustsen-Helm</name></author><author><name>Hanne-Dorthe Emborg</name></author><author><name>Tyra Grove Krause</name></author><author><name>Kåre Mølbak</name></author><author><name>Palle Valentiner-Branth</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In this brief communication we are showing original research results with early estimates from Danish nationwide databases of vaccine effectiveness (VE) against the novel SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant (B.1.1.529) up to five months after a primary vaccination series with the BNT162b2 or mRNA-1273 vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our study provides evidence of protection against infection with the Omicron variant after completion of a primary vaccination series with the BNT162b2 or mRNA-1273 vaccines; in particular, we found a VE against the Omicron variant of 55.2% (95% confidence interval (CI): 23.5 to 73.7%) and 36.7% (95% CI: 69.9 to 76.4%) for the BNT162b2 and mRNA-1273 vaccines, respectively, in the first month after primary vaccination. However, the VE is significantly lower than that against Delta infection and declines rapidly over just a few months. The VE is re-established upon revaccination with the BNT162b2 vaccine (54.6%, 95% CI: 30.4 to 70.4%).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21267966" rel="alternate" title="Vaccine effectiveness against SARS-CoV-2 infection with the Omicron or Delta variants following a two-dose or booster BNT162b2 or mRNA-1273 vaccination series: A Danish cohort study (36827 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.18.21268018</id><title>Analytical sensitivity of seven SARS-CoV-2 antigen-detecting rapid tests for Omicron variant (929 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.316828+00:00</updated><author><name>Meriem Bekliz</name></author><author><name>Kenneth Adea</name></author><author><name>Catia Alvarez</name></author><author><name>Manel Essaidi-Laziosi</name></author><author><name>Camille Escadafal</name></author><author><name>Laurent Kaiser</name></author><author><name>Isabella Eckerle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The emergence of novel SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (VOCs) requires investigation of a potential impact on diagnostic performance, such as Antigen-detecting rapid diagnostic tests (Ag-RDT). Although anecdotal reports have been circulating that Omicron is in principle detectable by Ag-RDTs, no published data are a yet available for the newly emerged Omicron variant. Here, we have performed an analytical sensitivity testing with cultured virus in seven Ag-RDTs for their sensitivity to Omicron compared to data earlier obtained on VOCs Alpha, Beta, Gamma and Delta and a pre-VOC isolate of SARS-CoV-2. Overall, we have found a tendency towards lower sensitivity for Omicron compared to pre-VOC SARS-CoV-2 and the other VOCs across tests. Importantly, while analytical testing with cultured virus may be a proxy for clinical sensitivity, is not a replacement for clinical evaluations which are urgently needed for Ag-RDT performance in Omicron-infected individuals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.18.21268018" rel="alternate" title="Analytical sensitivity of seven SARS-CoV-2 antigen-detecting rapid tests for Omicron variant (929 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473248</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 Omicron spike mediated immune escape, infectivity and cell-cell fusion (646 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.317455+00:00</updated><author><name>Bo Meng</name></author><author><name>Isabella A.T.M Ferreira</name></author><author><name>Adam Abdullahi</name></author><author><name>Akatsuki Saito</name></author><author><name>Izumi Kimura</name></author><author><name>Daichi Yamasoba</name></author><author><name>Steven A. Kemp</name></author><author><name>Niluka Goonawardane</name></author><author><name>Guido Papa</name></author><author><name>Saman Fatihi</name></author><author><name>Surabhi Rathore</name></author><author><name>Terumasa Ikeda</name></author><author><name>Mako Toyoda</name></author><author><name>Toong Seng Tan</name></author><author><name>Jin Kuramochi</name></author><author><name>Shigeki Mitsunaga</name></author><author><name>Takamasa Ueno</name></author><author><name>Oscar J. Charles</name></author><author><name>Kenneth G.C. Smith</name></author><author><name>John Bradley</name></author><author><name>Jinwook Choi</name></author><author><name>Elo Madissoon</name></author><author><name>Kerstin Meyer</name></author><author><name>Petra Mlcochova</name></author><author><name>Rainer Doffinger</name></author><author><name>Sarah A. Teichmann</name></author><author><name>Leo James</name></author><author><name>Joo Hyeon Lee</name></author><author><name>Lipi Thukral</name></author><author><name>Kei Sato</name></author><author><name>Ravindra K. Gupta</name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The SARS-CoV-2 Omicron BA.1 variant emerged in late 2021 and is characterised by multiple spike mutations across all spike domains. Here we show that compared to the Delta variant, Omicron BA.1 confers very significant evasion of therapeutic monoclonal and vaccine-elicited polyclonal neutralising antibodies after two doses. mRNA vaccination as a third vaccine dose rescues and broadens neutralisation in the short term. Importantly, antiviral drugs remdesevir and molnupiravir retain efficacy against Omicron BA.1. Despite three mutations predicted to favour spike S1/S2 cleavage, observed cleavage efficiency is substantially lower than for Delta. Omicron spike pseudotyped virus (PV) entry into lower airway organoids and Calu-3 lung cells was impaired. This defect for Omicron, but not Delta spike PV, correlated with higher cellular expression of TMPRSS2 transcripts, as determined by single cell RNA seq. Indeed we showed that in lung cells expressing TMPRSS2, live Omicron virus demonstrated significantly lower replication in comparison to Delta. This phenotype was reflected in cells where TMPRSS2 expression could be manipulated, with Omicron showing no change in entry in the presence of TMPRSS2. Cell-cell fusion mediated by spike glycoprotein is known require S1/S2 cleavage, but is also dependent on presence of TMPRSS2; fusogenicity of the Omicron BA.1 spike was severely impaired despite TMPRSS2 expression, leading to marked reduction in syncytium formation compared to Delta spike. These &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; data indicate that suboptimal Omicron S1/S2 cleavage reduces efficient infection of lower airway cells expressing TMPRSS2, but not TMPRSS2 negative cells such as those found in the upper airway. Overall, Omicron appears to have gained significant immune evasion properties whilst modulating viruscell interactions that alter tropism with implications for &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; disease progression and transmission.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473248" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 Omicron spike mediated immune escape, infectivity and cell-cell fusion (646 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268134</id><title>Activity of convalescent and vaccine serum against a B.1.1.529 variant SARS-CoV-2 isolate (577 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.318659+00:00</updated><author><name>Juan Manuel Carreño</name></author><author><name>Hala Alshammary</name></author><author><name>Johnstone Tcheou</name></author><author><name>Gagandeep Singh</name></author><author><name>Ariel Raskin</name></author><author><name>Hisaaki Kawabata</name></author><author><name>Levy Sominsky</name></author><author><name>Jordan Clark</name></author><author><name>Daniel C. Adelsberg</name></author><author><name>Dominika Bielak</name></author><author><name>Ana Silvia Gonzalez-Reiche</name></author><author><name>Komal Srivastava</name></author><author><name>Emilia Mia Sordillo</name></author><author><name>Goran Bajic</name></author><author><name>Harm van Bakel</name></author><author><name>Viviana Simon</name></author><author><name>Florian Krammer</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The B.1.1.529 (Omicron) variant of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) was identified in November of 2021 in South Africa and Botswana as well as in a sample of a traveler from South Africa in Hong Kong.&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt; Since then, B.1.1.529 has been detected in many countries globally. This variant seems to be more infectious than B.1.617.2 (Delta), has already caused super spreader events&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; and has outcompeted Delta within weeks in several countries and metropolitan areas. B.1.1.529 hosts an unprecedented number of mutations in its spike gene and early reports have provided evidence for extensive immune escape and reduced vaccine effectiveness.&lt;sup&gt;2,4-6&lt;/sup&gt; Here, we investigated the neutralizing and binding activity of sera from convalescent, mRNA double vaccinated, mRNA boosted as well as convalescent double vaccinated and convalescent boosted individuals against wild type, B.1.351 and B.1.1.529 SARS-CoV-2 isolates. Neutralizing activity of sera from convalescent and double vaccinated participants was undetectable to very low against B.1.1.529 while neutralizing activity of sera from individuals who had been exposed to spike three or four times was maintained, albeit at strongly reduced levels. Binding to the B.1.1.529 receptor binding domain (RBD) and N-terminal domain (NTD) was reduced in convalescent not vaccinated but was mostly retained in vaccinated individuals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268134" rel="alternate" title="Activity of convalescent and vaccine serum against a B.1.1.529 variant SARS-CoV-2 isolate (577 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473584</id><title>Neutralization against Omicron SARS-CoV-2 from previous non-Omicron infection (504 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.319085+00:00</updated><author><name>Jing Zou</name></author><author><name>Hongjie Xia</name></author><author><name>Xuping Xie</name></author><author><name>Chaitanya Kurhade</name></author><author><name>Rafael R. G. Machado</name></author><author><name>Scott C. Weaver</name></author><author><name>Ping Ren</name></author><author><name>Pei-Yong Shi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The explosive spread of the Omicron SARS-CoV-2 variant underscores the importance of analyzing the cross-protection from previous non-Omicron infection. We developed a high-throughput neutralization assay for Omicron SARS-CoV-2 by engineering the Omicron spike gene into an mNeonGreen USA-WA1/2020 SARS-CoV-2 (isolated in January 2020). Using this assay, we determined the neutralization titers of patient sera collected at 1- or 6-months after infection with non-Omicron SARS-CoV-2. From 1- to 6-month post-infection, the neutralization titers against USA-WA1/2020 decreased from 601 to 142 (a 4.2-fold reduction), while the neutralization titers against Omicron-spike SARS-CoV-2 remained low at 38 and 32, respectively. Thus, at 1- and 6-months after non-Omicron SARS-CoV-2 infection, the neutralization titers against Omicron were 15.8- and 4.4-fold lower than those against USA-WA1/2020, respectively. The low cross-neutralization against Omicron from previous non-Omicron infection supports vaccination of formerly infected individuals to mitigate the health impact of the ongoing Omicron surge.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473584" rel="alternate" title="Neutralization against Omicron SARS-CoV-2 from previous non-Omicron infection (504 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.21268008</id><title>Fluvoxamine for Outpatient COVID-19 to Prevent Hospitalization: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis (475 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.319646+00:00</updated><author><name>Todd C. Lee</name></author><author><name>Simone Vigod</name></author><author><name>Émilie Bortolussi-Courval</name></author><author><name>Ryan Hanula</name></author><author><name>David R. Boulware</name></author><author><name>Eric J. Lenze</name></author><author><name>Angela M. Reiersen</name></author><author><name>Emily G. McDonald</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Widely available and affordable options for the outpatient management of COVID-19 are needed, particularly therapies that prevent hospitalization.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Perform a meta-analysis of the available randomized clinical trial evidence for fluvoxamine in the outpatient management of COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data Sources&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;World Health Organization International Clinical Trials Registry Platform and ClinicalTrials.gov.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Study Selection&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Completed outpatient trials with available results which compared fluvoxamine to placebo.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data Extraction and Synthesis&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We followed the PRISMA 2020 guidelines. We extracted study details in terms of inclusion criteria, trial demographics and the pre-specified outcome of all-cause hospitalization. Risk of bias was assessed by the Cochrane Risk of Bias 2 tool. We conducted a frequentist random effects meta-analysis, as well as two sensitivity analyses using a Bayesian random effects meta-analysis with different estimates of prior probability: a weakly neutral prior (50% chance of efficacy with 95% confidence interval for Risk Ratio [RR] between 0.5 and 2) and a moderately optimistic prior (85% chance of efficacy). We contextualized the results by estimating the probability of any effect (RR ≤1) and moderate effect (RR ≤0.9) on reducing hospitalization.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Outcome(s) and Measure(s)&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;All cause hospitalization.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;2196 participants were included from 3 identified trials. The risk ratios for hospitalization were 0.75 (95%CI, 0.57-0.97) for the frequentist analysis, 0.78 (95%CI 0.58-1.08) for the Bayesian weakly neutral prior, and 0.73 (95%CI, 0.53-1.01) for the Bayesian moderately optimistic prior. Depending on the scenario, the probability of any effect on hospitalization ranged from 94.1% to 98.3% and a moderate effect from 81.6% to 91.1%.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions and Relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under a variety of assumptions, fluvoxamine shows a high probability of preventing hospitalization in outpatients with COVID-19. While ongoing randomized trials are important to evaluate alternative doses, explore the effectiveness in vaccinated patients, and provide further refinement to these estimates, fluvoxamine could be recommended as a treatment option, particularly in resource-limited settings or persons without access to SARS-CoV-2 monoclonal antibody therapy or direct antivirals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key Points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Question&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Does early administration of fluvoxamine prevent hospitalization in symptomatic adult outpatients with confirmed COVID-19?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this meta-analysis with Bayesian sensitivity analyses that accounted for varying prior probabilities, there was a high probability (94.1% to 98.3%) that fluvoxamine reduces hospitalization with frequentist risk ratio of 0.75 (95%CI 0.57-0.97).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Meaning&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fluvoxamine is a widely available and inexpensive option that prevents hospitalization in patients with early COVID-19 based on randomized controlled trial evidence to date.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.21268008" rel="alternate" title="Fluvoxamine for Outpatient COVID-19 to Prevent Hospitalization: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis (475 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473557</id><title>mRNA-1273 and BNT162b2 mRNA vaccines have reduced neutralizing activity against the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant (125 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.320211+00:00</updated><author><name>Venkata-Viswanadh Edara</name></author><author><name>Kelly E. Manning</name></author><author><name>Madison Ellis</name></author><author><name>Lilin Lai</name></author><author><name>Kathryn M. Moore</name></author><author><name>Stephanie L. Foster</name></author><author><name>Katharine Floyd</name></author><author><name>Meredith E. Davis-Gardner</name></author><author><name>Grace Mantus</name></author><author><name>Lindsay E. Nyhoff</name></author><author><name>Sarah Bechnak</name></author><author><name>Ghina Alaaeddine</name></author><author><name>Amal Naji</name></author><author><name>Hady Samaha</name></author><author><name>Matthew Lee</name></author><author><name>Laurel Bristow</name></author><author><name>Laila Hussaini</name></author><author><name>Caroline Rose Ciric</name></author><author><name>Phuong-Vi Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Matthew Gagne</name></author><author><name>Jesmine Roberts-Torres</name></author><author><name>Amy R. Henry</name></author><author><name>Sucheta Godbole</name></author><author><name>Arash Grakoui</name></author><author><name>Marybeth Sexton</name></author><author><name>Anne Piantadosi</name></author><author><name>Jesse J. Waggoner</name></author><author><name>Daniel C. Douek</name></author><author><name>Evan J. Anderson</name></author><author><name>Nadine Rouphael</name></author><author><name>Jens Wrammert</name></author><author><name>Mehul S. Suthar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The BNT162b2 (Pfizer-BioNTech) and mRNA-1273 (Moderna) vaccines generate potent neutralizing antibodies against severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). However, the global emergence of SARS-CoV-2 variants with mutations in the spike protein, the principal antigenic target of these vaccines, has raised concerns over the neutralizing activity of vaccine-induced antibody responses. The Omicron variant, which emerged in November 2021, consists of over 30 mutations within the spike protein. Here, we used an authentic live virus neutralization assay to examine the neutralizing activity of the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant against mRNA vaccine-induced antibody responses. Following the 2nd dose, we observed a 30-fold reduction in neutralizing activity against the omicron variant. Through six months after the 2nd dose, none of the sera from naïve vaccinated subjects showed neutralizing activity against the Omicron variant. In contrast, recovered vaccinated individuals showed a 22-fold reduction with more than half of the subjects retaining neutralizing antibody responses. Following a booster shot (3rd dose), we observed a 14-fold reduction in neutralizing activity against the omicron variant and over 90% of boosted subjects showed neutralizing activity against the omicron variant. These findings show that a 3rd dose is required to provide robust neutralizing antibody responses against the Omicron variant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473557" rel="alternate" title="mRNA-1273 and BNT162b2 mRNA vaccines have reduced neutralizing activity against the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant (125 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473528</id><title>Immune escape of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant from mRNA vaccination-elicited RBD-specific memory B cells (92 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.321269+00:00</updated><author><name>Aurélien Sokal</name></author><author><name>Matteo Broketa</name></author><author><name>Annalisa Meola</name></author><author><name>Giovanna Barba-Spaeth</name></author><author><name>Ignacio Fernández</name></author><author><name>Slim Fourati</name></author><author><name>Imane Azzaoui</name></author><author><name>Andrea de La Selle</name></author><author><name>Alexis Vandenberghe</name></author><author><name>Anais Roeser</name></author><author><name>Magali Bouvier-Alias</name></author><author><name>Etienne Crickx</name></author><author><name>Laetitia Languille</name></author><author><name>Marc Michel</name></author><author><name>Bertrand Godeau</name></author><author><name>Sébastien Gallien</name></author><author><name>Giovanna Melica</name></author><author><name>Yann Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Virginie Zarrouk</name></author><author><name>Florence Canoui-Poitrine</name></author><author><name>France Noizat-Pirenne</name></author><author><name>Jérôme Megret</name></author><author><name>Jean-Michel Pawlotsky</name></author><author><name>Simon Fillatreau</name></author><author><name>Etienne Simon-Lorière</name></author><author><name>Jean-Claude Weill</name></author><author><name>Claude-Agnès Reynaud</name></author><author><name>Félix A. Rey</name></author><author><name>Pierre Bruhns</name></author><author><name>Pascal Chappert</name></author><author><name>Matthieu Mahévas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Memory B cells (MBCs) represent a second layer of immune protection against SARS-CoV-2. Whether MBCs elicited by mRNA vaccines can recognize the Omicron variant is of major concern. We used bio-layer interferometry to assess the affinity against the receptor-binding-domain (RBD) of Omicron spike of 313 naturally expressed monoclonal IgG that were previously tested for affinity and neutralization against VOC prior to Omicron. We report here that Omicron evades recognition from a larger fraction of these antibodies than any of the previous VOCs. Additionally, whereas 30% of these antibodies retained high affinity against Omicron-RBD, our analysis suggest that Omicron specifically evades antibodies displaying potent neutralizing activity against the D614G and Beta variant viruses. Further studies are warranted to understand the consequences of a lower memory B cell potency on the overall protection associated with current vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473528" rel="alternate" title="Immune escape of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant from mRNA vaccination-elicited RBD-specific memory B cells (92 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.21268007</id><title>Outpatient therapies for COVID-19: How do we choose? (71 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.322505+00:00</updated><author><name>Todd C. Lee</name></author><author><name>Andrew M. Morris</name></author><author><name>Steven A. Grover</name></author><author><name>Srinivas Murthy</name></author><author><name>Emily G. McDonald</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Several outpatient COVID-19 therapies have reduced hospitalization in randomized controlled trials. The choice of therapy may depend on drug efficacy, toxicity, pricing, availability, and access to administration infrastructure. To facilitate comparative decision making, we evaluated the efficacy of each treatment in clinical trials and then estimated the associated cost per hospitalization prevented.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wherever possible, we obtained relative risk for hospitalization from published randomized controlled trials. Otherwise, we extracted data from press releases, conference abstracts, government submissions, or preprints. If more than one study was published, the results were meta-analyzed. Using relative risk, we estimated the number needed to treat (NNT), assuming a baseline hospitalization risk of 5%. Drug pricing was based on Canadian formularies, government purchases, or manufacturer estimates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Administrative and societal costs were not included. Results will be updated online as new studies emerge or final publication numbers become available.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a 5% risk of hospitalization the estimated NNTs were: 87 for colchicine, 80 for fluvoxamine, 72 for inhaled corticosteroids, 24 for nirmatrelvir/ritonavir, 25 for sotrovimab, 24 for remdesivir, 29 for casirivimab/imdevimab, 29 for bamlanivimab/etesevimab and 52 for molnupiravir. Colchicine, fluvoxamine, inhaled corticosteroids, and nirmatrelvir/ritonavir had cost per hospitalization prevented point estimates below the CIHI estimated cost of hospitalization ($23000).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Canada is fortunate to have access to several effective outpatient therapies to prevent COVID-19 hospitalization. Given differences in efficacy, toxicity, cost and administration complexities, this assessment serves as one tool to help guide policy makers and clinicians in their treatment selection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.21268007" rel="alternate" title="Outpatient therapies for COVID-19: How do we choose? (71 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.21268070</id><title>Effectiveness of different booster regimens for preventing infection and adverse outcomes in Puerto Rico (68 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.322873+00:00</updated><author><name>M.M. Robles-Fontán</name></author><author><name>R.A. Irizarry</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent laboratory and observational studies have demonstrated that the COVID-19 vaccine effectiveness wanes over time. In response, several jurisdictions have authorized the administration of booster doses. Since August 13, 2021, Puerto Rico has administered 540,140 booster shots. We used data collected and made public by the Puerto Rico Department of Health (PRDH) to evaluate the effectiveness of four different booster regimens at preventing SARS-CoV-2 laboratory confirmed infections and adverse COVID-19 outcomes. Specifically, we analyzed data from all 115,995 SARS-CoV-2 infections occurring since the vaccination process commenced on December 15, 2020. We combined vaccination status, SARS-CoV-2 test results, and COVID-19 hospitalizations and deaths data, and fit a statistical model that adjusted for time-varying incidence rates and age group, to estimate time-varying vaccine effectiveness against infection and adverse outcomes. We find that, after 6 months, the mRNA-1273 and BNT162b2 effectiveness against infection wanes substantially to 61% (58%-63%) and 36% (34%-39%), respectively, while the Ad26.COV2.S wanes to 35% (31%-39%) after two months. However, after a booster shot of the corresponding initial vaccine manufacturer, effectiveness increased to 87% (83%-91%) and 82% (79%-85%) for mRNA-1273 and BNT162b2, respectively. The effectiveness for Ad26.COV2.S followed by either a mRNA-1273 or BNT162b2 booster increased to 88% (71%-100%), substantially higher than 65% (59%-70%), the peak effectiveness reached with just one shot. We also found that heterologous booster regimens restored effectiveness. Furthermore, we did not observe waning after two months of the booster shot. Finally, we found that all booster regimens provided increased protection against COVID-19 hospitalizations and deaths. Code and data to reproduce the analyses are provided here: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/rafalab/booster-eff-pr"&gt;https://github.com/rafalab/booster-eff-pr&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.21268070" rel="alternate" title="Effectiveness of different booster regimens for preventing infection and adverse outcomes in Puerto Rico (68 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473447</id><title>Blockade of TMPRSS2-mediated priming of SARS-CoV-2 by the N-terminal peptide of lactoferrin (55 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.323145+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna Ohradanova-Repic</name></author><author><name>Laura Gebetsberger</name></author><author><name>Gabor Tajti</name></author><author><name>Gabriela Ondrovičová</name></author><author><name>Romana Praženicová</name></author><author><name>Rostislav Skrabana</name></author><author><name>Peter Baráth</name></author><author><name>Hannes Stockinger</name></author><author><name>Vladimir Leksa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In addition to vaccines, there is an urgent need for supplemental antiviral therapeutics to dampen the persistent COVID-19 pandemic caused by the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-2 (SARS–CoV-2). The transmembrane protease serine 2 (TMPRSS2), which is responsible for the proteolytic processing of the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein as virus priming for cell entry, appears as a rational therapeutic target for the clearance of SARS-CoV-2 infection. Accordingly, selective inhibitors of TMPRSS2 represent potential tools for prevention and treatment of COVID-19. Here, we tested the inhibitory capacities of the human milk glycoprotein lactoferrin and its N-terminal peptide pLF1, which we identified as inhibitors of plasminogen, a serine protease homologous to TMPRSS2. &lt;italic&gt;In vitro&lt;/italic&gt; proteolysis assays revealed that, unlike full-length lactoferrin, pLF1 significantly inhibited the proteolytic activity of TMPRSS2. pLF1 inhibited both the proteolytic processing of the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein and the SARS-CoV-2 infection of simian Vero cells. Because lactoferrin is a natural product and several biologically active peptides, such as the N-terminally derived lactoferricins, are produced naturally by pepsin-mediated digestion, natural or synthetic peptides from lactoferrin represent well-achievable candidates for supporting prevention and treatment of COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473447" rel="alternate" title="Blockade of TMPRSS2-mediated priming of SARS-CoV-2 by the N-terminal peptide of lactoferrin (55 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473679</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 Omicron Spike recognition by plasma from individuals receiving BNT162b2 mRNA vaccination with a 16-weeks interval between doses (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.323647+00:00</updated><author><name>Debashree Chatterjee</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Tauzin</name></author><author><name>Lorie Marchitto</name></author><author><name>Shang Yu Gong</name></author><author><name>Marianne Boutin</name></author><author><name>Catherine Bourassa</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Beaudoin-Bussieres</name></author><author><name>Yuxia Bo</name></author><author><name>Shilei Ding</name></author><author><name>Annemarie Laumaea</name></author><author><name>Dani Vezina</name></author><author><name>Josee Perreault</name></author><author><name>Laurie Gokool</name></author><author><name>Chantal Morrisseau</name></author><author><name>Pascale Arlotto</name></author><author><name>Eric Fournier</name></author><author><name>Aurelie Guilbault</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Delisle</name></author><author><name>Ines Levade</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Goyette</name></author><author><name>Gabrielle Gendron-Lepage</name></author><author><name>Halima Medjahed</name></author><author><name>Gaston De Serres</name></author><author><name>Cecile Tremblay</name></author><author><name>Valerie Martel-Laferriere</name></author><author><name>Daniel E Kaufmann</name></author><author><name>Renee Bazin</name></author><author><name>Jeremie Prevost</name></author><author><name>Sandrine Moreira</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Richard</name></author><author><name>Marceline Cote</name></author><author><name>Andres Finzi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Continuous emergence of SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (VOC) is fueling the COVID-19 pandemic.  Omicron (B.1.1.529), is rapidly spreading worldwide.  The large number of mutations in its Spike raised concerns about a major antigenic drift that could significantly decrease vaccine efficacy and infection-induced immunity.  A long interval between BNT162b2 mRNA doses was shown to elicit antibodies that efficiently recognize Spikes from different VOCs.  Here we evaluated the recognition of Omicron Spike by plasma from a cohort of SARS-CoV-2 naive and previously-infected individuals that received their BNT162b2 mRNA vaccine 16-weeks apart.  Omicron Spike was recognized less efficiently than D614G, Alpha, Beta, Gamma and Delta Spikes. We compared to plasma activity from participants receiving a short (4-weeks) interval regimen.  Plasma from individuals of the long interval cohort neutralized better the Omicron Spike compared to those that received a short interval. Whether this difference confers any clinical benefit against Omicron remains unknown.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473679" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 Omicron Spike recognition by plasma from individuals receiving BNT162b2 mRNA vaccination with a 16-weeks interval between doses (37 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.21268044</id><title>The Place of Fluvoxamine in the Treatment of Non-critically ill Patients with COVID-19: A Living Systematic Review and Meta-analysis (32 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.324574+00:00</updated><author><name>Salah Eddine Oussama Kacimi</name></author><author><name>Elona Greca</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Amine Haireche</name></author><author><name>Ahmed Sallam ElHawary</name></author><author><name>Mounir Ould Setti</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Caruana</name></author><author><name>Sahar Rizwan</name></author><author><name>Hidayet Benyettou</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Yasir Essar</name></author><author><name>Jaffer Shah</name></author><author><name>Sherief Ghozy</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fluvoxamine is a selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor that is known to be used as antidepressant. Repurposing of Fluvoxamine for the treatment of COVID-19 is theorized to help in the prevention of the clinical deterioration of SARS CoV-2 patients. In our systematic review and meta-analysis, we aim to assess the safety and efficacy of the drug under study in terms of its effect on the mortality and the risk of hospitalization and mechanical ventilation in non-critically ill COVID-19 patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We performed a systematic search of seven electronic databases. The search results were screened based on the previously determined inclusion and exclusion criteria. We determined the data related to our objectives. The mortality rates, rates of hospitalization, risk of mechanical ventilation and serious side effects were extracted from the studies that successfully met our inclusion and exclusion criteria. Then, the extracted data from the included studies was included in the meta-analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Three studies, two randomized clinical trials and one observational cohort study, with 1762 patients, were the final outcome of our search and screening processes. Among all participants, 886 patients received Fluvoxamine while 876 were controls. Follow up periods ranged from 7 days to 28 days. There was no significant difference in the intention-to-treat mortality rates between the two groups (RR = 0.66; 95% CI: 0.36 - 1.21, p-value = 0.18; &lt;italic&gt;I&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; = 0%). However, Fluvoxamine decreased the per-protocol mortality compared to both placebo alone or placebo/standard care (RR = 0.09; 95% CI: 0.01 - 0.64, p-value = 0.02; &lt;italic&gt;I&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; = 0% and RR = 0.09; 95% CI: 0.01 - 0.72, respectively). As compared to placebo or standard care, the all-cause hospitalization was significantly reduced in the fluvoxamine group (RR = 0.71; 95% CI: 0.54 - 0.93, p-value = 0.01; &lt;italic&gt;I&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; = 61%). This risk reduction was not significant when compared to placebo alone (RR = 0.76; 95% CI: 0.57 - 1.00; p-value = 0.051; &lt;italic&gt;I&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; = 48%). Furthermore, the risk of mechanical ventilation was not improved in the fluvoxamine group as compared to placebo (RR = 0.71; 95% CI: 0.43 - 1.16, p-value = 0.17; &lt;italic&gt;I&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; = 0%). The serious adverse effects were almost the same in the treatment group and the control (13% and 12% respectively).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fluvoxamine does not significantly reduce the mortality rates or the risk of mechanical ventilation in SARS CoV-2 patients. Nonetheless, it was found to have a good impact on reducing all cause hospitalization among patients with COVID-19 disease. Therefore, further clinical studies are needed to determine the effectiveness of the drug and its mechanisms of action.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.21268044" rel="alternate" title="The Place of Fluvoxamine in the Treatment of Non-critically ill Patients with COVID-19: A Living Systematic Review and Meta-analysis (32 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.18.21267628</id><title>RESISTANCE CONFERRING MUTATIONS IN SARS-CoV-2 DELTA FOLLOWING SOTROVIMAB INFUSION (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.325163+00:00</updated><author><name>Rebecca J Rockett</name></author><author><name>Kerri Basile</name></author><author><name>Susan Maddocks</name></author><author><name>Winkie Fong</name></author><author><name>Jessica E Agius</name></author><author><name>Jessica Johnson Mackinnon</name></author><author><name>Alicia Arnott</name></author><author><name>Shona Chandra</name></author><author><name>Mailie Gall</name></author><author><name>Jenny Draper</name></author><author><name>Elena Martinez</name></author><author><name>Eby M Sim</name></author><author><name>Clement Lee</name></author><author><name>Christine Ngo</name></author><author><name>Marc Ramsperger</name></author><author><name>Andrew N Ginn</name></author><author><name>Qinning Wang</name></author><author><name>Michael Fennell</name></author><author><name>Danny Ko</name></author><author><name>H Ling Lim</name></author><author><name>Nicky Gilroy</name></author><author><name>Matthew V N O’Sullivan</name></author><author><name>Sharon C-A Chen</name></author><author><name>Jen Kok</name></author><author><name>Dominic E Dwyer</name></author><author><name>Vitali Sintchenko</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Several Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) neutralising monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) have received emergency use authorisation by regulatory agencies for treatment and prevention of Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19), including in patients at risk for progression to severe disease. Here we report the persistence of viable SARS-CoV-2 in patients treated with sotrovimab and the rapid development of spike gene mutations that have been shown to confer high level resistance to sotrovimab &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. We highlight the need for SARS-CoV-2 genomic surveillance in at risk individuals to inform stewardship of mAbs use and prevent potential treatment failures.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.18.21267628" rel="alternate" title="RESISTANCE CONFERRING MUTATIONS IN SARS-CoV-2 DELTA FOLLOWING SOTROVIMAB INFUSION (19 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268124</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 vaccine effectiveness and breakthrough infections in maintenance dialysis patients (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.326064+00:00</updated><author><name>Harold J. Manley</name></author><author><name>Gideon N. Aweh</name></author><author><name>Caroline M. Hsu</name></author><author><name>Daniel E. Weiner</name></author><author><name>Dana Miskulin</name></author><author><name>Antonia M. Harford</name></author><author><name>Doug Johnson</name></author><author><name>Eduardo K. Lacson</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 vaccine effectiveness during the Delta period and immunogenicity threshold associated with protection against COVID-19 related hospitalization or death in the dialysis population is unknown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A retrospective, observational study assessed SARS-CoV-2 vaccine effectiveness and immunogenicity threshold in all adult maintenance dialysis patients without COVID-19 history treated between February 1 and October 2, 2021. All COVID-19 infections, composite of hospitalization or death following COVID-19 and available SARS-CoV-2 anti-spike immunoglobulin (Ig) G values were extracted from electronic medical record. COVID-19 cases per 10,000 days at risk and vaccine effectiveness during pre-Delta and Delta periods were determined.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of 15,718 patients receiving dialysis during the study period, 11,191 (71%) were fully vaccinated, 733 (5%) were partially vaccinated and 3,794 (24%) were unvaccinated. 967 COVID-19 were cases identified: 511 (53%) occurred in unvaccinated patients and 579 (60%) occurred during the Delta period. COVID-19 related hospitalization or death was less likely among vaccinated versus unvaccinated patients for all vaccines (adjusted HR 0.19 [0.12, 0.30]) and for BNT162b2/Pfizer, mRNA-1273/Moderna, and Ad26.COV2.S/Janssen (adjusted HR=0.25 [0.16, 0.40], 0.14 [0.08, 0.22], and 0.34 [0.17, 0.68] respectively). Among those with anti-spike IgG levels, those with IgG level ≥ 7 had significantly lower risk of a COVID-19 diagnosis (HR=0.25 [0.15, 0.42]) and none experienced a COVID-related hospitalization or death.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among maintenance dialysis patients, SARS-CoV-2 vaccination was associated with a lower risk of COVID-19 diagnosis and associated hospitalization or death. Among vaccinated patients, low anti-spike IgG level is associated with worse COVID-19 related outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 vaccine effectiveness and association between antibody levels and clinical outcomes in maintenance dialysis patients is not known. Between February 1 and October 2, 2021, vaccine effectiveness was 85% against COVID-19 infection and 81% against composite of COVID-related hospitalization or death. COVID-19 case rates and severe outcomes were higher during the Delta dominant period (June 27-October 2, 2021). Increasing time (weeks) since full vaccination status was associated with increased risk for COVID-19 related hospitalization or death. Anti-spike IgG level ≥ 7 had lower risk of a COVID-19 diagnosis and no COVID-related hospitalization or death. Our findings supports utilization of SARS-CoV-2 vaccination and suggests that monitoring SARS-CoV-2 antibody levels and administering additional vaccine doses to maintain adequate immunity will be beneficial.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268124" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 vaccine effectiveness and breakthrough infections in maintenance dialysis patients (17 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.21267983</id><title>GB0139, an inhaled small molecule inhibitor of galectin-3, in COVID-19 pneumonitis: a randomised, controlled, open-label, phase 2a experimental medicine trial of safety, pharmacokinetics, and potential therapeutic value (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.326695+00:00</updated><author><name>Erin Gaughan</name></author><author><name>Tariq Sethi</name></author><author><name>Tom Quinn</name></author><author><name>Nikhil Hirani</name></author><author><name>Andrew Mills</name></author><author><name>Annya M. Bruce</name></author><author><name>Alison MacKinnon</name></author><author><name>Vassilios Aslanis</name></author><author><name>Feng Li</name></author><author><name>Richard O’Connor</name></author><author><name>Richard A. Parker</name></author><author><name>John Norrie</name></author><author><name>James Dear</name></author><author><name>Ahsan R. Akram</name></author><author><name>Oliver Koch</name></author><author><name>Jie Wang-Jairaj</name></author><author><name>Robert J. Slack</name></author><author><name>Lise Gravelle</name></author><author><name>Bertil Lindmark</name></author><author><name>Kevin Dhaliwal</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Rationale&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;High galectin-3 levels predict poor outcomes in patients with COVID-19. Galectin-3 activates monocytes and macrophages which are directly implicated in COVID-19 immunopathology and the cytokine storm. GB0139 is a potent thiodigalactoside galectin-3 inhibitor and may reduce the severe effects of the disease. We report safety and pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of the inhaled galectin-3 inhibitor, GB0139, and assess clinical outcomes and key systemic inflammatory biomarkers in hospitalised patients with COVID-19 (ClinicalTrials.gov/EudraCT identifier: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT04473053"&gt;NCT04473053&lt;/ext-link&gt;/2020-002230-32).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adults with COVID-19 requiring oxygen, and with pneumonitis on x-ray, were randomised to receive standard of care (SOC; including dexamethasone; n=21) or SOC plus 10 mg GB0139 twice daily for 48 hours, then once daily for ≤14 days (n=20).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients aged 27–87 years were enrolled from July 2020; the final patient completed the 90-day follow-up in April 2021. GB0139+SOC was well tolerated with no treatment-related serious adverse events reported. Incidences of adverse events were similar between treatment arms (40 with GB0139+SOC &lt;italic&gt;vs&lt;/italic&gt; 35 with SOC). Plasma GB0139 was measurable in all patients after inhaled exposure, with moderate interpatient variability, and demonstrated target engagement with decreased circulating galectin (overall treatment effect post-hoc over days 2–7: p=0·0099 &lt;italic&gt;vs&lt;/italic&gt; SOC). Rate of decline in fraction of inspired oxygen (%) requirement was significantly greater in the GB0139+SOC arm with a posterior mean difference of -1·51 (95% highest posterior density: -2·90, -0·189) versus SOC. Plasma levels of biomarkers associated with inflammation, coagulopathy, major organ function and fibrosis showed a downward trend versus SOC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;GB0139+SOC was well tolerated and achieved clinically relevant plasma concentrations and target engagement. This, and the reduction in markers associated with inflammatory, coagulation, fibrosis, and reduction in inspired oxygen (%) over SOC alone, indicates the therapeutic potential for inhaled GB0139 in hospitalised patients with COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.21267983" rel="alternate" title="GB0139, an inhaled small molecule inhibitor of galectin-3, in COVID-19 pneumonitis: a randomised, controlled, open-label, phase 2a experimental medicine trial of safety, pharmacokinetics, and potential therapeutic value (17 tweets)"/><category term="Respiratory Medicine"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.21268103</id><title>Neutralization of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron pseudovirus by BNT162b2 vaccine-elicited human sera (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.327484+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Muik</name></author><author><name>Bonny Gaby Lui</name></author><author><name>Ann-Kathrin Wallisch</name></author><author><name>Maren Bacher</name></author><author><name>Julia Muehl</name></author><author><name>Jonas Reinholz</name></author><author><name>Orkun Ozhelvaci</name></author><author><name>Nina Beckmann</name></author><author><name>Ramon de la Caridad Guimil Garcia</name></author><author><name>Asaf Poran</name></author><author><name>Svetlana Shpyro</name></author><author><name>Hui Cai</name></author><author><name>Qi Yang</name></author><author><name>Kena Anne Swanson</name></author><author><name>Oezlem Tuereci</name></author><author><name>Ugur Sahin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A new severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) lineage, B.1.1.529, was recently detected in Botswana and South Africa and is now circulating globally. Just two days after it was first reported to the World Health Organization (WHO), this strain was classified as a variant of concern (VOC) and named Omicron. Omicron has an unusually large number of mutations, including up to 39 amino acid modifications in the spike (S) protein, raising concerns that its recognition by neutralizing antibodies from convalescent and vaccinated individuals may be severely compromised. In this study, we tested pseudoviruses carrying the SARS-CoV-2 spike glycoproteins of either the Wuhan reference strain, the Beta, the Delta or the Omicron variants of concern with sera of 51 participants that received two doses or a third dose (≥6 months after dose 2) of the mRNA-based COVID-19 vaccine BNT162b2. Immune sera from individuals who received two doses of BNT162b2 had more than 22-fold reduced neutralizing titers against the Omicron as compared to the Wuhan pseudovirus. One month after a third dose of BNT162b2, the neutralization titer against Omicron was increased 23-fold compared to two doses and antibody titers were similar to those observed against the Wuhan pseudovirus after two doses of BNT162b2. These data suggest that a third dose of BNT162b2 may protect against Omicron-mediated COVID-19, but further analyses of longer-term antibody persistence and real-world effectiveness data are needed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.21268103" rel="alternate" title="Neutralization of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron pseudovirus by BNT162b2 vaccine-elicited human sera (15 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.21267898</id><title>Diminished neutralization responses towards SARS-CoV-2 Omicron VoC after mRNA or vector-based COVID-19 vaccinations (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.328077+00:00</updated><author><name>Henning Jacobsen</name></author><author><name>Monika Strengert</name></author><author><name>Henrike Maaß</name></author><author><name>Mario Alberto Ynga Durand</name></author><author><name>Barbora Kessel</name></author><author><name>Manuela Harries</name></author><author><name>Ulfert Rand</name></author><author><name>Leila Abassi</name></author><author><name>Yeonsu Kim</name></author><author><name>Tatjana Lüddecke</name></author><author><name>Pilar Hernandez</name></author><author><name>Julia Ortmann</name></author><author><name>Jana-Kristin Heise</name></author><author><name>Stefanie Castell</name></author><author><name>Daniela Gornyk</name></author><author><name>Stephan Glöckner</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Melhorn</name></author><author><name>Berit Lange</name></author><author><name>Alex Dulovic</name></author><author><name>Julia Häring</name></author><author><name>Daniel Junker</name></author><author><name>Nicole Schneiderhan-Marra</name></author><author><name>Markus Hoffmann</name></author><author><name>Stefan Pöhlmann</name></author><author><name>Gérard Krause</name></author><author><name>Luka Cicin-Sain</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 variants accumulating immune escape mutations provide a significant risk to vaccine-induced protection. The novel variant of concern Omicron (B.1.1.529) has to date the largest number of amino acid alterations in its Spike protein. Thus, it may efficiently escape recognition by neutralizing antibodies, allowing breakthrough infections in convalescent and vaccinated individuals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aims&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We analysed neutralization activity of all mRNA-, vector- or heterologous immunization schemes currently approved in Europe at peak response and in a longitudinal follow-up with BNT162b2 vaccinees to define immune escape potential of the Omicron VoC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We tested sera by &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; pseudotype particle neutralization assay towards SARS-CoV-2 B.1, Omicron, Beta and Delta Spike proteins.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;All vaccines apart from Ad26.CoV2.S showed high levels of responder rates (93-100%) towards SARS-CoV-2 wild-type, but some reductions in neutralizing Beta and Delta VoC pseudotypes. The novel Omicron variant had the biggest impact, both in terms of response rates and neutralization titres among responders. Only mRNA-1273 showed a 100% response rate to Omicron and induced the highest titres of neutralizing antibodies, followed by heterologous prime-boost approaches. Homologous BNT162b2 vaccination or vector-based formulations with AZD1222 or Ad26.CoV2.S performed less well with peak responder rates of 33%, 50% and 9%, respectively. However, Omicron responder rates in BNT162b2 recipients were maintained in our six month longitudinal follow-up and even slightly increased to 47%, indicating Omicron cross-protection is maintained over time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our data strongly argues for urgent booster doses particularly for those who were previously vaccinated with BNT162b2 or a vector-based immunization scheme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.21267898" rel="alternate" title="Diminished neutralization responses towards SARS-CoV-2 Omicron VoC after mRNA or vector-based COVID-19 vaccinations (15 tweets)"/><category term="Allergy and Immunology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473613</id><title>The Geometry of ATG-Walks of the Omicron SARS CoV-2 Virus RNAs (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.328764+00:00</updated><author><name>Guennadi A. Kouzaev</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In this message, the complete RNA sequences (GISAID) of Omicron (BA.1 and BA.2) SARS CoV-2 viruses are studied using the genomic ATG-walks. These walks are compared visually and numerically with a reference RNA (Wuhan, China, 2020), and the deviation levels are estimated. Statistical characteristics of these distributions are compared, including the fractal dimension values of coding-word length distributions. Most of the 17 RNA ATG walks studied here show relatively small deviations of their characteristics and resistance to forming a new virus family.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473613" rel="alternate" title="The Geometry of ATG-Walks of the Omicron SARS CoV-2 Virus RNAs (15 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268098</id><title>Therapies for Long COVID in non-hospitalised individuals - from symptoms, patient-reported outcomes, and immunology to targeted therapies (The TLC Study): Study protocol (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.328977+00:00</updated><author><name>Shamil Haroon</name></author><author><name>Krishnarajah Nirantharakumar</name></author><author><name>Sarah E Hughes</name></author><author><name>Anuradhaa Subramanian</name></author><author><name>Olalekan Lee Aiyegbusi</name></author><author><name>Elin Haf Davies</name></author><author><name>Puja Myles</name></author><author><name>Tim Williams</name></author><author><name>Grace M Turner</name></author><author><name>Joht Singh Chandan</name></author><author><name>Christel McMullan</name></author><author><name>Janet Lord</name></author><author><name>David Wraith</name></author><author><name>Kirsty McGee</name></author><author><name>Alastair Denniston</name></author><author><name>Tom Taverner</name></author><author><name>Louise Jackson</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Sapey</name></author><author><name>Georgios Gkoutos</name></author><author><name>Krishna Gokhale</name></author><author><name>Edward Leggett</name></author><author><name>Clare Iles</name></author><author><name>Christopher Frost</name></author><author><name>Gary McNamara</name></author><author><name>Amy Bamford</name></author><author><name>Tom Marshall</name></author><author><name>Dawit Zemedikun</name></author><author><name>Gary Price</name></author><author><name>Steven Marwaha</name></author><author><name>Nikita Simms-Williams</name></author><author><name>Kirsty Brown</name></author><author><name>Anita Walker</name></author><author><name>Karen Jones</name></author><author><name>Karen Matthews</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Camaradou</name></author><author><name>Michael Saint-Cricq</name></author><author><name>Sumita Kumar</name></author><author><name>Yvonne Alder</name></author><author><name>David E. Stanton</name></author><author><name>Lisa Agyen</name></author><author><name>Megan Baber</name></author><author><name>Hannah Blaize</name></author><author><name>Melanie Calvert</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individuals with COVID-19 frequently experience symptoms and impaired quality of life beyond 4-12 weeks, commonly referred to as Long COVID. Whether Long COVID is one or several distinct syndromes is unknown. Establishing the evidence base for appropriate therapies is needed. We aim to evaluate the symptom burden and underlying pathophysiology of Long COVID syndromes in non-hospitalised individuals and evaluate potential therapies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods and analysis&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A cohort of 4000 non-hospitalised individuals with a past COVID-19 diagnosis and 1000 matched controls will be selected from anonymised primary care records from the Clinical Practice Research Datalink (CPRD) and invited by their general practitioners to participate on a digital platform (Atom5™). Individuals will report symptoms, quality of life, work capability, and patient reported outcome measures. Data will be collected monthly for one year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Statistical clustering methods will be used to identify distinct Long COVID symptom clusters. Individuals from the four most prevalent clusters and two control groups will be invited to participate in the BioWear sub-study which will further phenotype Long COVID symptom clusters by measurement of immunological parameters and actigraphy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We will review existing evidence on interventions for post-viral syndromes and Long COVID to map and prioritise interventions for each newly characterised Long COVID syndrome. Recommendations will be made using the cumulated evidence in an expert consensus workshop. A virtual supportive intervention will be coproduced with patients and health service providers for future evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individuals with lived experience of Long COVID will be involved throughout this programme through a patient and public involvement group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Ethics and dissemination&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ethical approval was obtained from the Solihull Research Ethics Committee, West Midlands (21/WM/0203). The study is registered on the ISRCTN Registry (1567490). Research findings will be presented at international conferences, in peer-reviewed journals, to Long COVID patient support groups and to policymakers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Article Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Strengths and limitations of the study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study will generate a nationally representative cohort of individuals with Long COVID recruited from primary care.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We will recruit controls matched on a wide range of demographic and clinical factors to assess differences in symptoms between people with Long COVID and similar individuals without a history of COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We will use a newly developed electronic patient reported outcome measure (Symptom Burden Questionnaire™) for Long COVID to comprehensively assess a wide range of symptoms highlighted by existing literature, patients, and clinicians.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Immunological, proteomic, genetic, and wearable data captured in the study will allow deep phenotyping of Long COVID syndromes to help better target therapies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;A limitation is that a significant proportion of non-hospitalised individuals affected by COVID-19 in the first wave of the pandemic will lack confirmatory testing and will be excluded from recruitment to the study.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268098" rel="alternate" title="Therapies for Long COVID in non-hospitalised individuals - from symptoms, patient-reported outcomes, and immunology to targeted therapies (The TLC Study): Study protocol (13 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21267967</id><title>Safety of the single-dose Ad26.CoV2.S vaccine among healthcare workers in the phase 3b Sisonke study in South Africa (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.329767+00:00</updated><author><name>Simbarashe Takuva</name></author><author><name>Azwidhwi Takalani</name></author><author><name>Ishen Seocharan</name></author><author><name>Nonhlanhla Yende-Zuma</name></author><author><name>Tarylee Reddy</name></author><author><name>Imke Engelbrecht</name></author><author><name>Mark Faesen</name></author><author><name>Kentse Khuto</name></author><author><name>Carmen Whyte</name></author><author><name>Veronique Bailey</name></author><author><name>Valentina Trivella</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Peter</name></author><author><name>Jessica Opie</name></author><author><name>Vernon Louw</name></author><author><name>Pradeep Rowji</name></author><author><name>Barry Jacobson</name></author><author><name>Pamela Groenewald</name></author><author><name>Rob E. Dorrington</name></author><author><name>Ria Laubscher</name></author><author><name>Debbie Bradshaw</name></author><author><name>Harry Moultrie</name></author><author><name>Lara Fairall</name></author><author><name>Ian Sanne</name></author><author><name>Linda Gail-Bekker</name></author><author><name>Glenda Gray</name></author><author><name>Ameena Goga</name></author><author><name>Nigel Garrett</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Sisonke open-label phase 3b implementation study aimed to assess the safety and effectiveness of the Janssen Ad26.CoV2.S vaccine among health care workers (HCWs) in South Africa. Here, we present the safety data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We monitored adverse events (AEs) at vaccination sites, through self-reporting triggered by text messages after vaccination, health care provider reports and by active case finding. The frequency and incidence rate of non-serious and serious AEs were evaluated from day of first vaccination (17 February 2021) until 28 days after the final vaccination (15 June 2021). COVID-19 breakthrough infections, hospitalisations and deaths were ascertained via linkage of the electronic vaccination register with existing national databases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of 477,234 participants, 10,279 (2.2%) reported AEs, of which 139 (1.4%) were serious. Women reported more AEs than men (2.3% vs. 1.6%). AE reports decreased with increasing age (3.2% for 18–30, 2.1% for 31-45, 1.8% for 46-55 and 1.5% in &amp;gt;55-year-olds). Participants with previous COVID-19 infection reported slightly more AEs (2.6% vs. 2.1%). The commonest reactogenicity events were headache and body aches, followed by injection site pain and fever, and most occurred within 48 hours of vaccination. Two cases of Thrombosis with Thrombocytopenia Syndrome and four cases of Guillain-Barre Syndrome were reported post-vaccination. Serious AEs and AEs of special interest including vascular and nervous system events, immune system disorders and deaths occurred at lower than the expected population rates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The single-dose Ad26.CoV2.S vaccine had an acceptable safety profile supporting the continued use of this vaccine in our setting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Funding was provided by the National Treasury of South Africa, the National Department of Health, Solidarity Response Fund NPC, The Michael &amp;amp; Susan Dell Foundation, The Elma Vaccines and Immunization Foundation - Grant number 21-V0001, and the Bill &amp;amp; Melinda Gates Foundation – grant number INV-030342.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21267967" rel="alternate" title="Safety of the single-dose Ad26.CoV2.S vaccine among healthcare workers in the phase 3b Sisonke study in South Africa (12 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.21268171</id><title>Breakthrough Covid-19 infections during periods of circulating Beta, Delta and Omicron variants of concern, among health care workers in the Sisonke Ad26.COV2.S vaccine trial, South Africa (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.330653+00:00</updated><author><name>Ameena Goga</name></author><author><name>Linda-Gail Bekker</name></author><author><name>Nigel Garrett</name></author><author><name>Tarylee Reddy</name></author><author><name>Nonhlanhla Yende-Zuma</name></author><author><name>Lara Fairall</name></author><author><name>Harry Moultrie</name></author><author><name>Azwidihwi Takalani</name></author><author><name>Valentina Trivella</name></author><author><name>Mark Faesen</name></author><author><name>Veronique Bailey</name></author><author><name>Ishen Seocharan</name></author><author><name>Glenda E Gray</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We report breakthrough infections (BTIs) during periods of circulating Beta, Delta and Omicron variants of concern, among health care workers (HCW) participating in the Sisonke phase 3B Ad26.COV2.S vaccine trial (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov"&gt;ClinicalTrials.gov&lt;/ext-link&gt; number, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT04838795"&gt;NCT04838795&lt;/ext-link&gt;). Data were gathered between 17 February and 15 December 2021. Duration of each period in this study was 89 days for Beta, 180 days or Delta and 30 days for Omicron.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A total of 40 538 BTIs were observed, with 609 during Beta, 22 279 during Delta and 17 650 during Omicron. By 15 December, daily infections during Omicron were three times that seen during the peak observed during Delta. However, unlike the Delta period, with Omicron there was a clear and early de-coupling of hospitalisation from cases as a percentage of the Delta peak curves. Omicron significantly infected a greater proportion of HCW in the 18-30 year age-group, compared with the 55+ age group. There were 1 914 BTI-related hospitalisations - 77, 1 429 and 408 in the Beta (89 days), Delta (180 days) and Omicron (30 days) periods, respectively. During Omicron, 91% hospitalized HCWs required general ward care, 6% high care and 3% intensive care, compared with 89% general ward care, 4% high care and 7% intensive care, during Delta and 78% general care, 7% high care and 16% intensive care during Beta (p&amp;lt;0.001). During Beta and Beta 43% of hospitalized HCW needed supplementary oxygen and 7-8% needed ventilation, compared with 16% and 0.2% respectively during the Omicron period (p&amp;lt;0.001). Median length of hospitalization was significantly lower with Omicron compared with Beta and Delta (3 days compared with 5-6 days, p&amp;lt;0.001).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We illustrate more BTIs but reassuringly less severe Covid-19 with Omicron. Re-infections and Omicron-driven primary infections were likely driven by high population SARS-CoV-2 seroprevalence, waning vaccine effectiveness over time, increased Omicron infectivity, Omicron immune evasion or a combination of these and need further investigation. Follow-up of this cohort will continue and reports will be updated, as time and infections accrue.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.21268171" rel="alternate" title="Breakthrough Covid-19 infections during periods of circulating Beta, Delta and Omicron variants of concern, among health care workers in the Sisonke Ad26.COV2.S vaccine trial, South Africa (12 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473774</id><title>Longitudinal characterisation of phagocytic and neutralisation functions of anti-Spike antibodies in plasma of patients after SARS-CoV-2 infection (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.330989+00:00</updated><author><name>Anurag Adhikari</name></author><author><name>Arunasingam Abayasingam</name></author><author><name>Chaturaka Rodrigo</name></author><author><name>David Agapiou</name></author><author><name>Elvis Pandzic</name></author><author><name>Nicholas A Brasher</name></author><author><name>Bentotage Samitha Madushan Fernando</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Keoshkerian</name></author><author><name>Hui Li</name></author><author><name>Ha Na Kim</name></author><author><name>Megan Lord</name></author><author><name>Gordona Popovic</name></author><author><name>William Rawlinson</name></author><author><name>Michael Mina</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey J Post</name></author><author><name>Bernard Hudson</name></author><author><name>Nicole Gilroy</name></author><author><name>Adam W. Bartlett</name></author><author><name>Golo Ahlenstiel</name></author><author><name>Branka Grubor-Bauk</name></author><author><name>Dominic Dwyer</name></author><author><name>Pamela Konecny</name></author><author><name>Andrew R Lloyd</name></author><author><name>Marianne Martinello</name></author><author><name>Rowena A Bull</name></author><author><name>Nicodemus Tedla</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Phagocytic responses by effector cells to antibody or complement-opsonised viruses have been recognized to play a key role in anti-viral immunity. These include antibody dependent cellular phagocytosis mediated via Fc-receptors, phagocytosis mediated by classically activated complement-fixing IgM or IgG1 antibodies and antibody independent phagocytosis mediated via direct opsonisation of viruses by complement products activated via the mannose-binding lectin pathway. Limited data suggest these phagocytic responses by effector cells may contribute to the immunological and inflammatory responses in SARS-CoV-2 infection, however, their development and clinical significance remain to be fully elucidated. In this cohort of 62 patients, acutely ill individuals were shown to mount phagocytic responses to autologous plasma-opsonised SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein-coated microbeads as early as 10 days post symptom onset. Heat inactivation of the plasma prior to use as an opsonin caused 77-95% abrogation of the phagocytic response, and pre-blocking of Fc-receptors on the effector cells showed only 18-60% inhibition. These results suggest that SARS-CoV-2 can provoke early phagocytosis, which is primarily driven by heat labile components, likely activated complements, with variable contribution from anti-Spike antibodies. During convalescence, phagocytic responses correlated significantly with anti-Spike IgG titers. Older patients and patients with severe disease had significantly higher phagocytosis and neutralisation functions when compared to younger patients or patients with asymptomatic, mild, or moderate disease. A longitudinal study of a subset of these patients over 12 months showed preservation of phagocytic and neutralisation functions in all patients, despite a drop in the endpoint antibody titers by more than 90%. Interestingly, surface plasmon resonance showed a significant increase in the affinity of the anti-Spike antibodies over time correlating with the maintenance of both the phagocytic and neutralisation functions suggesting that improvement in the antibody quality over the 12 months contributed to the retention of effector functions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Limited data suggest antibody dependent effector functions including phagocytosis may contribute to the immunological and inflammatory responses in SARS CoV-2 infection, however, their development, maintenance, and clinical significance remain unknown. In this study we show:
&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients with acute SARS CoV-2 infection can mount phagocytic responses as early as 10 days post symptom onset and these responses were primarily driven by heat labile components of the autologous plasma. These results indicate that the current approach of studying phagocytosis using purified or monoclonal antibodies does not recapitulate contribution by all components in the plasma.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;In convalescent patients, high phagocytic responses significantly correlated with increasing age, increasing disease severity, high neutralisation functions and high anti-Spike antibody titers, particularly IgG1.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Longitudinal study of convalescent patients over a 12-month period showed maintenance of phagocytic and neutralisation functions, despite a drop in the anti-Spike endpoint antibody titers by more than 90%. However, we found significant increase in the affinity of the anti-Spike antibodies over the 12-month period and these correlated with the maintenance of functions suggesting that improvement in the antibody quality over time contributed to the retention of effector functions. Clinically, measuring antibody titers in sera but not the quality of antibodies is considered a gold standard indicator of immune protection following SARS-CoV 2 infection or vaccination. Our results challenge this notion and recommends change in the current clinical practice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473774" rel="alternate" title="Longitudinal characterisation of phagocytic and neutralisation functions of anti-Spike antibodies in plasma of patients after SARS-CoV-2 infection (10 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21267978</id><title>VaxiMap: optimal delivery of vaccinations for housebound patients (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.331632+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas F. Kirk</name></author><author><name>Adam J. Barker</name></author><author><name>Armen Bodossian</name></author><author><name>Robert Staruch</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Throughout the UK’s Covid-19 vaccination campaign, responsibility for vaccinating housebound patients has rested with individual GP surgeries, posing them a difficult logistical challenge (the travelling salesman problem). In response to demand from GPs, and a lack of existing solutions tailored specifically to vaccination, VaxiMap was created. This tool provides optimal routes for vaccine delivery and has been free to all users since its inception in January 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;VaxiMap generates optimal routes subject to the constraint that the number of patients per route should be fixed. This ensures that a known quantity of vaccine can be set aside for each route and minimises wastage. The user need only upload an Excel spreadsheet of patient postcodes to be visited. A divide-and-conquer approach of iterative &lt;italic&gt;k&lt;/italic&gt;-means clustering followed by within-cluster route optimisation is used to generate the routes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We find substantial savings in the time taken to plan vaccinations, as well as savings in the time taken to visit housebound patients. We estimate total savings to date of 4,700 hours of practitioner time, equivalent to 2.5 work-years, or approximately £91k at typical practitioner salaries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The adoption of VaxiMap yielded both time and cost savings for GP surgeries and accelerated the UK’s Covid-19 vaccination campaign at a critical moment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Financial support for VaxiMap was provided by Magdalen College, Oxford, Oxford University Innovation, and JHubMed, part of UK Strategic Command. These parties were not involved in the preparation of this manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21267978" rel="alternate" title="VaxiMap: optimal delivery of vaccinations for housebound patients (10 tweets)"/><category term="Health Systems and Quality Improvement"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268102</id><title>Systematic review of spontaneous reports of myocarditis and pericarditis in transplant recipients and immunocompromised patients following COVID-19 mRNA vaccination (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.331848+00:00</updated><author><name>Samantha Lane</name></author><author><name>Alison Yeomans</name></author><author><name>Saad Shakir</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To determine whether spontaneous reporting rates of myocarditis and pericarditis differed in immunocompromised patients compared to the whole population overall, and in terms of demographics, vaccine dose, and time-to-onset.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Systematic review of spontaneously reported data from the European Union/European Economic Area (EU/EEA) and the United States (US).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data Sources&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;EudraVigilance (EU/EEA) and Vaccine Adverse Event Reporting System (VAERS; US) spontaneous reporting databases were searched from date of vaccine launch to 30 November 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Eligibility criteria&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Publicly available spontaneous reporting data for “Myocarditis” and “Pericarditis” from EU/EEA and US following COVID-19 mRNA vaccines. Reports with comorbidities or concurrent medication indicative of transplantation, HIV infection, or cancer (“immunocompromised” population) were compared with each overall database population.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data extraction and synthesis&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two researchers extracted data. Spontaneously reported events of myocarditis and pericarditis were presented for immunocompromised populations for each data source, stratified by age, sex, dose, and time-to-onset (where available). Seriousness of each event was determined according to the ICH E2A definition. Proportional Reporting Ratio (PRR) was calculated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There were 106 reports of myocarditis and pericarditis amongst immunocompromised individuals overall. Seriousness was comparable between the immunocompromised and overall populations in both databases. No trends in age or sex were observed amongst immunocompromised individuals. Most reports (54.4%) to VAERS followed a second vaccine dose and 70.2% of events occurred within 14 days. The frequency of reporting was similar to the wider population (PRR=1.36 [95% CI= 0.89-1.82] for VAERS population).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Myocarditis and pericarditis following COVID-19 vaccination are very rare, and benefits of COVID-19 vaccination continue to outweigh any perceived risks. Reporting rates of myocarditis and pericarditis were similar in immunocompromised individuals, however defining characteristics differed compared to the whole population; therefore, continued monitoring of adverse events following vaccination remains vital to understand differences between population subgroups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Strengths and Limitations of the Study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the first study to investigate the frequency and characteristics of reported events of myocarditis and pericarditis in immunocompromised individuals compared with the population as a whole, bringing together data from two regions (Europe and the United States).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Results from this study demonstrate that myocarditis and pericarditis are not more frequently reported following COVID-19 mRNA vaccines for immunocompromised individuals, however age and sex distributions are less clear, and clinical course may differ compared with the overall population.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;As with all analyses using spontaneously reported data, results may have been subject to underreporting and missing information, including information on comorbidities and concomitant medications. It is possible that some immunocompromised were incorrectly classified as immunocompetent. Further biases may have influenced results, including differences in vaccination strategies between the two regions examined, differences in data collected via spontaneous reporting systems, and serious events more likely to be reported.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is not possible to estimate incidence rates using spontaneous reports due to a lack of data on the exposed population, and there is no unexposed comparison group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further monitoring of myocarditis and pericarditis events in immunocompromised populations is needed as booster vaccination programmes progress. Pharmacoepidemiological studies are urgently needed to provide more accurate estimates of the frequency and clinical course of myocarditis and pericarditis following COVID-19 mRNA vaccination amongst immunocompromised people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268102" rel="alternate" title="Systematic review of spontaneous reports of myocarditis and pericarditis in transplant recipients and immunocompromised patients following COVID-19 mRNA vaccination (10 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473421</id><title>Virus-like particles (VLPs) are efficient tools for boosting mRNA-induced antibodies (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.332109+00:00</updated><author><name>Anne-Cathrine S. Vogt</name></author><author><name>Lukas Jörg</name></author><author><name>Byron Martina</name></author><author><name>Pascal S. Krenger</name></author><author><name>Xinyue Chang</name></author><author><name>Andris Zeltins</name></author><author><name>Monique Vogel</name></author><author><name>Mona O. Mohsen</name></author><author><name>Martin F. Bachmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;mRNA based vaccines against COVID-19 have proven most successful at keeping the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic at bay in many countries. Recently, there is an increased interest in heterologous prime-boost vaccination strategies for COVID-19 to maintain antibody response for the control of continuously emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (VoCs) and to overcome other obstacles such as supply shortage, costs and reduced safety issues or inadequate induced immune-response. In this study, we investigate the antibody responses induced by heterologous prime-boost with vaccines based on mRNA and virus-like particles (VLPs). The VLP-based mCuMV&lt;sub&gt;TT&lt;/sub&gt;-RBM vaccine candidate and the approved mRNA-1273 vaccine were used for this purpose. We find that homologous prime boost regimens with either mRNA or VLP induced high levels of high avidity antibodies. Optimal antibody responses were, however, induced by heterologous regimens both for priming with mRNA and boosting with VLP and vice versa, priming with VLP and boosting with mRNA. Thus, heterologous prime boost strategies may be able to optimize efficacy and economics of novel vaccine strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473421" rel="alternate" title="Virus-like particles (VLPs) are efficient tools for boosting mRNA-induced antibodies (9 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473880</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 Omicron neutralization by therapeutic antibodies, convalescent sera, and post-mRNA vaccine booster (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.332744+00:00</updated><author><name>Sabrina Lusvarghi</name></author><author><name>Simon D. Pollett</name></author><author><name>Sabari Nath Neerukonda</name></author><author><name>WEI WANG</name></author><author><name>Richard Wang</name></author><author><name>Russell Vassell</name></author><author><name>Nusrat J. Epsi</name></author><author><name>Anthony C. Fries</name></author><author><name>Brian K Agan</name></author><author><name>David A. Lindholm</name></author><author><name>Tahaniyat Lalani</name></author><author><name>Rupal Mody</name></author><author><name>Evan C. Ewers</name></author><author><name>Tahaniyat Lalani</name></author><author><name>Anuradha Ganesan</name></author><author><name>Emilie Goguet</name></author><author><name>Monique Hollis-Perry</name></author><author><name>Si'Ana A. Coggins</name></author><author><name>Mark P. Simons</name></author><author><name>Leah C. Katzelnick</name></author><author><name>Gregory Wang</name></author><author><name>Christopher C. Broder</name></author><author><name>David R. Tribble</name></author><author><name>Lisa Marie Bentley</name></author><author><name>Ann E. Eakin</name></author><author><name>Karl J. Erlandson</name></author><author><name>Eric D. Laing</name></author><author><name>Timothy H. Burgess</name></author><author><name>Edward Mitre</name></author><author><name>Carol D. Weiss</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The rapid spread of the highly contagious Omicron variant of SARS-CoV-2 along with its high number of mutations in the spike gene has raised alarm about the effectiveness of current medical countermeasures. To address this concern, we measured neutralizing antibodies against Omicron in three important settings: (1) post-vaccination sera after two and three immunizations with the Pfizer/BNT162b2 vaccine, (2) convalescent sera from unvaccinated individuals infected by different variants, and (3) clinical-stage therapeutic antibodies. Using a pseudovirus neutralization assay, we found that titers against Omicron were low or undetectable after two immunizations and in most convalescent sera. A booster vaccination significantly increased titers against Omicron to levels comparable to those seen against the ancestral (D614G) variant after two immunizations. Neither age nor sex were associated with differences in post-vaccination antibody responses. Only three of 24 therapeutic antibodies tested retained their full potency against Omicron and high-level resistance was seen against fifteen. These findings underscore the potential benefit of booster mRNA vaccines for protection against Omicron and the need for additional therapeutic antibodies that are more robust to highly mutated variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473880" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 Omicron neutralization by therapeutic antibodies, convalescent sera, and post-mRNA vaccine booster (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473706</id><title>Anti-SARS-CoV-2 human antibodies retaining neutralizing activity against SARS-CoV-2 B.1.1.529 (omicron) (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.333577+00:00</updated><author><name>Maya Imbrechts</name></author><author><name>Winnie Kerstens</name></author><author><name>Madina Rasulova</name></author><author><name>Thomas Vercruysse</name></author><author><name>Wim Maes</name></author><author><name>Louanne Ampofo</name></author><author><name>Karen Ven</name></author><author><name>Jeroen Lammertyn</name></author><author><name>Karen Vanhoorelbeke</name></author><author><name>Nico Callewaert</name></author><author><name>Johan Neyts</name></author><author><name>Kai Dallmeier</name></author><author><name>Paul Declerck</name></author><author><name>Hendrik Jan Thibaut</name></author><author><name>Nick Geukens</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 B.1.1.529, designated omicron, was recently identified as a new variant of concern by WHO and is rapidly replacing SARS-CoV-2 delta as the most dominant variant in many countries. Unfortunately, because of the high number of mutations present in the spike of SARS-CoV-2 omicron, most monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) currently approved for treatment of COVID-19 lose their in vitro neutralizing activity against this variant. We recently described a panel of human anti-SARS-CoV-2 mAbs that potently neutralize SARS-CoV-2 Wuhan, D614G and variants alpha, beta, gamma and delta. In this work, we evaluated our mAb panel for potential in vitro activity against SARS-CoV-2 delta and omicron. Three mAbs from our panel retain neutralizing activity against both delta and omicron, with mAb 3B8 still resulting in complete neutralization at a concentration as low as 0.02 ug/ml for both variants. Overall, our data indicate that mAb 3B8 may have the potential to become a game-changer in the fight against the continuously evolving SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473706" rel="alternate" title="Anti-SARS-CoV-2 human antibodies retaining neutralizing activity against SARS-CoV-2 B.1.1.529 (omicron) (9 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.21268285</id><title>Dynamics of immune recall following SARS-CoV-2 vaccination or breakthrough infection (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.334872+00:00</updated><author><name>Marios Koutsakos</name></author><author><name>Wen Shi Lee</name></author><author><name>Arnold Reynaldi</name></author><author><name>Hyon-Xhi Tan</name></author><author><name>Grace Gare</name></author><author><name>Paul Kinsella</name></author><author><name>Kwee Chin Liew</name></author><author><name>Deborah A Williamson</name></author><author><name>Helen E Kent</name></author><author><name>Eva Stadler</name></author><author><name>Deborah Cromer</name></author><author><name>David S Khoury</name></author><author><name>Adam K Wheatley</name></author><author><name>Jennifer A Juno</name></author><author><name>Miles P Davenport</name></author><author><name>Stephen J Kent</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Vaccination against SARS-CoV-2 results in protection from acquisition of infection as well as improved clinical outcomes even if infection occurs, likely reflecting a combination of residual vaccine-elicited immunity and the recall of immunological memory. Here, we define the early kinetics of spike-specific humoral and T cell immunity after vaccination of seropositive individuals, and after breakthrough infection in vaccinated individuals. Intensive and early longitudinal sampling reveals the timing and magnitude of recall, with the phenotypic activation of B cells preceding an increase in neutralizing antibody titres. In breakthrough infections, the delayed kinetics of humoral immune recall provides a mechanism for the lack of early control of viral replication but likely underpins accelerated viral clearance and the protective effects of vaccination against severe COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.21268285" rel="alternate" title="Dynamics of immune recall following SARS-CoV-2 vaccination or breakthrough infection (9 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268141</id><title>Field evaluation of Rapid SARS-Cov2 Antigen screening test on self-collected deep throat saliva samples in Malaysia (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.335500+00:00</updated><author><name>Noorliza Mohamad Noordin</name></author><author><name>Steven Chee Loon Lim</name></author><author><name>Zhuo-zhi Lim</name></author><author><name>Teck-Onn Lim</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Low cost Rapid Antigen Tests are widely used in Malaysia and the government has also mandated worksite screening as a condition for reopening. Numerous RAT kits have been approved by the Malaysian Medical Device Authority. However, it remains uncertain how these kits would perform in the field.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We enrolled workers between June and September 2021 from 23 worksites. They were trained and experienced in performing RAT selftest by virtue of their worksite participation in routine screening program. These workers also had reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction tests in the course of mass screening or contact tracing. We also enrolled patients with PCR confirmed Covid19 from a quarantine centre. These patients were instructed on selftesting and then immediately perform RAT under supervision. Two manufacturers donated RAT for this study.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A total of 340 participants were enrolled, 130 were from quarantine centre and 210 from worksites. The overall sensitivity of RAT compared to PCR was 70 percent. The specificity was 91 percent. Sensitivity decreased with increasing PCR cycle threshold values. Sensitivity is also lower among untrained subjects at each level of Ct. Logistic regression analysis confirmed false negative result is associated with Ct and participants prior training and experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study shows that in the real world, RAT performance were markedly lower than that reported by the manufacturers. The test sensitivity is dependent on the operator training and experience, as well as on viral load as measured by Ct. User training and repeated testing for screening purpose is necessary to mitigate the low sensitivity of RAT.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268141" rel="alternate" title="Field evaluation of Rapid SARS-Cov2 Antigen screening test on self-collected deep throat saliva samples in Malaysia (8 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473542</id><title>Structural flexibility of the SARS-CoV-2 genome relevant to variation, replication, pathogenicity, and immune evasion (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.335856+00:00</updated><author><name>Roberto Patarca</name></author><author><name>William A. Haseltine</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The SARS-CoV-2 pandemic continues to be driven by viral variants. Most research has focused on structural proteins and on site-specific mutations. Here, we describe recombination events involving genomic terminal sequences in SARS-CoV-2 and related viruses leading to structural rearrangements in terminal and coding regions and discuss their potential contributions to viral variation, replication, pathogenicity, and immune evasion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473542" rel="alternate" title="Structural flexibility of the SARS-CoV-2 genome relevant to variation, replication, pathogenicity, and immune evasion (8 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473359</id><title>Pentosan polysulfate inhibits attachment and infection by SARS-CoV-2 in vitro: insights into structural requirements for binding (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.336088+00:00</updated><author><name>Sabrina Bertini</name></author><author><name>Anna Alekseeva</name></author><author><name>Stefano Elli</name></author><author><name>Isabel Pagani</name></author><author><name>Serena Zanzoni</name></author><author><name>Giorgio Eisele</name></author><author><name>Ravi Krishnan</name></author><author><name>Klaus P Maag</name></author><author><name>Christian Reiter</name></author><author><name>Dominik Lenhart</name></author><author><name>Rudolf Gruber</name></author><author><name>Edwin A Yates</name></author><author><name>Elisa Vicenzi</name></author><author><name>Annamaria Naggi</name></author><author><name>Antonella Bisio</name></author><author><name>Marco Guerrini</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Two years since the outbreak of the novel coronavirus SARS-CoV-2 pandemic, there remain few clinically effective drugs to complement vaccines. One is the anticoagulant, heparin, which in 2004 was found able to inhibit invasion of SARS CoV (CoV-1) and which has been employed during the current pandemic to prevent thromboembolic complications and moderate potentially damaging inflammation. Heparin has also been shown experimentally to inhibit SARS-CoV-2 attachment and infection in susceptible cells. At high therapeutic doses however, heparin increases the risk of bleeding and prolonged use can cause heparin-induced thrombocytopenia, a serious side-effect. One alternative, with structural similarities to heparin is the plant-derived, semi-synthetic polysaccharide, pentosan polysulfate (PPS). PPS is an established drug for the oral treatment of interstitial cystitis, is well-tolerated and exhibits weaker anticoagulant effects than heparin. In an established Vero cell model, PPS and its fractions of varying molecular weights, inhibited invasion by SARS-CoV-2. Intact PPS and its size-defined fractions were characterized by molecular weight distribution and chemical structure using NMR spectroscopy and LC-MS, then employed to explore the structural basis of interactions with SARS-CoV-2 spike protein receptor-binding domain (S1 RBD) and the inhibition of Vero cell invasion. PPS was as effective as unfractionated heparin, but more effective at inhibiting cell infection than low molecular weight heparin (on a weight/volume basis). Isothermal titration calorimetry and viral plaque-forming assays demonstrated size-dependent binding to S1 RBD and inhibition of Vero cell invasion, suggesting the potential application of PPS as a novel inhibitor of SARS-CoV-2 infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473359" rel="alternate" title="Pentosan polysulfate inhibits attachment and infection by SARS-CoV-2 in vitro: insights into structural requirements for binding (8 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473223</id><title>ACE2-containing defensosomes serve as decoys to inhibit SARS-CoV-2 infection (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.336582+00:00</updated><author><name>Krystal L Ching</name></author><author><name>Maren de Vries</name></author><author><name>Juan Gago</name></author><author><name>Kristen Dancel-Manning</name></author><author><name>Joseph Sall</name></author><author><name>William J Rice</name></author><author><name>Clea Barnett</name></author><author><name>Feng-Xia Liang</name></author><author><name>Lorna E Thorpe</name></author><author><name>Bo Shopsin</name></author><author><name>Leopoldo N Segal</name></author><author><name>Meike Dittmann</name></author><author><name>Victor J Torres</name></author><author><name>Ken Cadwell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Extracellular vesicles of endosomal origin, exosomes, mediate intercellular communication by transporting substrates with a variety of functions related to tissue homeostasis and disease. Their diagnostic and therapeutic potential has been recognized for diseases such as cancer in which signaling defects are prominent. However, it is unclear to what extent exosomes and their cargo inform the progression of infectious diseases. We recently defined a subset of exosomes termed defensosomes that are mobilized during bacterial infection in a manner dependent on autophagy proteins. Through incorporating protein receptors on their surface, defensosomes mediated host defense by binding and inhibiting pore-forming toxins secreted by bacterial pathogens. Given this capacity to serve as decoys that interfere with surface protein interactions, we investigated the role of defensosomes during infection by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), the etiological agent of COVID-19. Consistent with a protective function, exosomes containing high levels of the viral receptor ACE2 in bronchioalveolar lavage fluid from critically ill COVID-19 patients was associated with reduced ICU and hospitalization times. We found ACE2+ exosomes were induced by SARS-CoV-2 infection and activation of viral sensors in cell culture, which required the autophagy protein ATG16L1, defining these as defensosomes. We further demonstrate that ACE2+ defensosomes directly bind and block viral entry. These findings suggest that defensosomes may contribute to the antiviral response against SARS-CoV-2 and expand our knowledge on the regulation and effects of extracellular vesicles during infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473223" rel="alternate" title="ACE2-containing defensosomes serve as decoys to inhibit SARS-CoV-2 infection (8 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473268</id><title>Efficacy of antiviral drugs against the omicron variant of SARS-CoV-2. (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.337335+00:00</updated><author><name>Agnieszka Dabrowska</name></author><author><name>Artur Szczepanski</name></author><author><name>Pawel Botwina</name></author><author><name>Natalia Mazur-Panasiuk</name></author><author><name>Helena Jirincova</name></author><author><name>Lukasz Rabalski</name></author><author><name>Tomas Zajic</name></author><author><name>Grzegorz Popowicz</name></author><author><name>Krzysztof Pyrc</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Omicron variant of the SARS-CoV-2 virus was first detected in South Africa in November 2021. The analysis of the sequence data in the context of earlier variants suggested that it may show very different characteristics, including immune evasion and increased transmission. These assumptions were partially confirmed, and the reduction in protection in convalescent patients and vaccinated individuals have been confirmed. Here, we have evaluated the efficacy of antivirals against SARS-CoV-2 variants, Omicron, Delta, and the early 2020 isolate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473268" rel="alternate" title="Efficacy of antiviral drugs against the omicron variant of SARS-CoV-2. (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473804</id><title>Engineered ACE2 counteracts vaccine-evading SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.338572+00:00</updated><author><name>Nariko Ikemura</name></author><author><name>Shunta Taminishi</name></author><author><name>Tohru Inaba</name></author><author><name>Takao Arimori</name></author><author><name>Daisuke Motooka</name></author><author><name>Kazutaka Katoh</name></author><author><name>Yuhei Kirita</name></author><author><name>Yusuke Kirita</name></author><author><name>Songling Li</name></author><author><name>Yumi Itoh</name></author><author><name>Yuki Ozaki</name></author><author><name>Shota Nakamura</name></author><author><name>Satoaki Matoba</name></author><author><name>Daron M Standley</name></author><author><name>Toru Okamoto</name></author><author><name>Junichi Takagi</name></author><author><name>Atsushi Hoshino</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The novel SARS-CoV-2 variant, Omicron (B.1.1.529) contains an unusually high number of mutations (&amp;gt;30) in the spike protein, raising concerns of escape from vaccines, convalescent sera and therapeutic drugs. Here we analyze the alteration of neutralizing titer with Omicron pseudovirus. Sera of 3 months after double BNT162b2 vaccination exhibit approximately 18-fold lower neutralization titers against Omicron. Convalescent sera from Alpha and Delta patients allow similar levels of breakthrough by Omicron. However, some Delta patients have relatively preserved neutralization efficacy, comparable to 3-month double BNT162b2 vaccination. Domain-wise analysis using chimeric spike revealed that this efficient evasion was, at least in part, caused by multiple mutations in the N-terminal domain. Omicron escapes the therapeutic cocktail of imdevimab and casirivimab, whereas sotrovimab, which targets a conserved region to avoid viral mutation, remains effective against Omicron. The ACE2 decoy is another virus-neutralizing drug modality that is free, at least in theory, from mutational escape. Deep mutational analysis demonstrated that, indeed, the engineered ACE2 overcomes every single-residue mutation in the receptor-binding domain, similar to immunized sera. Like previous SARS-CoV-2 variants, Omicron and some other sarbecoviruses showed high sensitivity against engineered ACE2, confirming the therapeutic value against diverse variants, including those that are yet to emerge.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473804" rel="alternate" title="Engineered ACE2 counteracts vaccine-evading SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473564</id><title>MERS-CoV endoribonuclease and accessory proteins jointly evade host innate immunity during infection of lung and nasal epithelial cells (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.339353+00:00</updated><author><name>Courtney E. Comar</name></author><author><name>Clayton J. Otter</name></author><author><name>Jessica Pfannenstiel</name></author><author><name>Ethan Doerger</name></author><author><name>David M. Renner</name></author><author><name>Li Hui Tan</name></author><author><name>Stanley Perlman</name></author><author><name>Noam A. Cohen</name></author><author><name>Anthony R. Fehr</name></author><author><name>Susan R. Weiss</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) emerged into humans in 2012, causing highly lethal respiratory disease. The severity of disease may be in part because MERS-CoV is adept at antagonizing early innate immune pathways – interferon (IFN) production and signaling, protein kinase R (PKR), and oligoadenylate synthetase ribonuclease L (OAS/RNase L) – generated in response to viral double-stranded (ds)RNA generated during genome replication. This is in contrast to SARS-CoV-2, which we recently reported activates PKR and RNase L and to some extent, IFN signaling. We previously found that MERS-CoV accessory proteins NS4a (dsRNA binding protein) and NS4b (phosphodiesterase) could weakly suppress these pathways, but ablation of each had minimal effect on virus replication. Here we investigated the antagonist effects of the conserved coronavirus endoribonuclease (EndoU), in combination with NS4a or NS4b. Inactivation of EndoU catalytic activity alone in a recombinant MERS-CoV caused little if any effect on activation of the innate immune pathways during infection. However, infection with recombinant viruses containing combined mutations with inactivation of EndoU and deletion of NS4a or inactivation of the NS4b phosphodiesterase promoted robust activation of the dsRNA-induced innate immune pathways. This resulted in ten-fold attenuation of replication in human lung derived A549 and primary nasal cells. Furthermore, replication of these recombinant viruses could be rescued to the level of WT MERS-CoV by knockout of host immune mediators MAVS, PKR, or RNase L. Thus, EndoU and accessory proteins NS4a and NS4b together suppress dsRNA-induced innate immunity during MERS-CoV infection in order to optimize viral replication.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Middle East Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus (MERS-CoV) causes highly lethal respiratory disease. MERS-CoV encodes several innate immune antagonists, accessory proteins NS4a and NS4b unique to the merbeco lineage and the nsp15 protein endoribonuclease (EndoU), conserved among all coronaviruses. While mutation of each antagonist protein alone has little effect on innate immunity, infections with recombinant MERS-CoVs with mutations of EndoU in combination with either NS4a or NS4b, activate innate signaling pathways and are attenuated for replication. Our data indicate that EndoU and accessory proteins NS4a and NS4b together suppress innate immunity during MERS-CoV infection, to optimize viral replication. This is in contrast to SARS-CoV-2 which activates these pathways and consistent with greater mortality observed during MERS-CoV infection compared to SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473564" rel="alternate" title="MERS-CoV endoribonuclease and accessory proteins jointly evade host innate immunity during infection of lung and nasal epithelial cells (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473949</id><title>Rapid longitudinal SARS-CoV-2 intra-host emergence of novel haplotypes regardless of immune deficiencies (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.339915+00:00</updated><author><name>Laura Manuto</name></author><author><name>Marco Grazioli</name></author><author><name>Andrea Spitaleri</name></author><author><name>Paolo Fontana</name></author><author><name>Luca Bianco</name></author><author><name>Luigi Bertolotti</name></author><author><name>Martina Bado</name></author><author><name>Giorgia Mazzotti</name></author><author><name>Federico Bianca</name></author><author><name>Francesco Onelia</name></author><author><name>Giovanni Lorenzin</name></author><author><name>Fabio Simeoni</name></author><author><name>Dejan Lazarevic</name></author><author><name>Elisa Franchin</name></author><author><name>Claudia Del Vecchio</name></author><author><name>Ilaria Dorigatti</name></author><author><name>Giovanni Tonon</name></author><author><name>daniela Cirillo</name></author><author><name>Enrico Lavezzo</name></author><author><name>Andrea Crisanti</name></author><author><name>Stefano Toppo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;On February 2020, the municipality of Vo’, a small town near Padua (Italy), was quarantined due to the first coronavirus disease 19 (COVID-19)-related death detected in Italy. The entire population was swab tested in two sequential surveys. Here we report the analysis of the viral genomes, which revealed that the unique ancestor haplotype introduced in Vo’ belongs to lineage B and, more specifically, to the subtype found at the end of January 2020 in two Chinese tourists visiting Rome and other Italian cities, carrying mutations G11083T and G26144T. The sequences, obtained for 87 samples, allowed us to investigate viral evolution while being transmitted within and across households and the effectiveness of the non-pharmaceutical interventions implemented in Vo’. We report, for the first time, evidence that novel viral haplotypes can naturally arise intra-host within an interval as short as two weeks, in approximately 30% of the infected individuals, regardless of symptoms severity or immune system deficiencies. Moreover, both phylogenetic and minimum spanning network analyses converge on the hypothesis that the viral sequences evolved from a unique common ancestor haplotype, carried by an index case. The lockdown extinguished both viral spread and the emergence of new variants, confirming the efficiency of this containment strategy. The information gathered from household was used to reconstructs possible transmission events.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473949" rel="alternate" title="Rapid longitudinal SARS-CoV-2 intra-host emergence of novel haplotypes regardless of immune deficiencies (6 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473702</id><title>Tutorial: Investigating SARS-CoV-2 evolution and phylogeny using MNHN-Tree-Tools (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.340680+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas Haschka</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Covid-19 pandemic has caused at more than 3 million deaths by Mai this year. It had a significant impact on the daily life and the global economy. The virus has since its first recorded outbreak in China mutated into new strains. The Nextstrain project has so far been monitoring the evolution of the virus. At the same time we were developing in our lab the MNHN-Tree-Tools toolkit, primarily for the investigation of DNA repeat sequences. We have further extended MNHN-Tree-Tools to guide phylogenetics. As such the toolkit has evolved into a high performance code, allowing for a fast investigation of millions of sequences. Given the context of the pandemic it became evident that we will use our versatile tool to investigate the evolution of SARS-CoV-2 sequences. Our efforts have cumulated in this tutorial that we share with the scientific community.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473702" rel="alternate" title="Tutorial: Investigating SARS-CoV-2 evolution and phylogeny using MNHN-Tree-Tools (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473733</id><title>Monospecific and bispecific monoclonal SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibodies that maintain potency against B.1.617 (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.340923+00:00</updated><author><name>Lei Peng</name></author><author><name>Yingxia Hu</name></author><author><name>Madeleine Mankowski</name></author><author><name>Ping Ren</name></author><author><name>Rita Chen</name></author><author><name>Jin Wei</name></author><author><name>Min Zhao</name></author><author><name>Tongqing Li</name></author><author><name>Therese Tripler</name></author><author><name>Lupeng Ye</name></author><author><name>Ryan Chow</name></author><author><name>Zhenhao Fang</name></author><author><name>Chunxiang Wu</name></author><author><name>Matthew Dong</name></author><author><name>Matthew Cook</name></author><author><name>Guilin Wang</name></author><author><name>Paul Clark</name></author><author><name>Bryce Nelson</name></author><author><name>Daryl Klein</name></author><author><name>Richard Sutton</name></author><author><name>Michael Diamond</name></author><author><name>Craig Wilen</name></author><author><name>Yong Xiong</name></author><author><name>Sidi Chen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 pathogen SARS-CoV-2 has infected hundreds of millions and caused over 5 million deaths to date. Although multiple vaccines are available, breakthrough infections occur especially by emerging variants. Effective therapeutic options such as monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) are still critical. Here, we report the development, cryo-EM structures, and functional analyses of mAbs that potently neutralize SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern. By high-throughput single cell sequencing of B cells from spike receptor binding domain (RBD) immunized animals, we identified two highly potent SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing mAb clones that have single-digit nanomolar affinity and low-picomolar avidity, and generated a bispecific antibody. Lead antibodies showed strong inhibitory activity against historical SARS-CoV-2 and several emerging variants of concern. We solved several cryo-EM structures at ~3 Angstrom resolution of these neutralizing antibodies in complex with prefusion spike trimer ectodomain, and revealed distinct epitopes, binding patterns, and conformations. The lead clones also showed potent efficacy in vivo against authentic SARS-CoV-2 in both prophylactic and therapeutic settings. We also generated and characterized a humanized antibody to facilitate translation and drug development. The humanized clone also has strong potency against both the original virus and the B.1.617.2 Delta variant. These mAbs expand the repertoire of therapeutics against SARS-CoV-2 and emerging variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473733" rel="alternate" title="Monospecific and bispecific monoclonal SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibodies that maintain potency against B.1.617 (5 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.470882</id><title>COVID-19: Salient Aspects of Coronavirus Infection, Vaccines and Vaccination Testing and their Implications (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.341904+00:00</updated><author><name>Pradeep K. Pasricha</name></author><author><name>Arun K. Upadhayaya</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the present study, three basic aspects related to COVID-19 are presented. 
(a) The occurrence of coronavirus infection is analyzed statistically as number of coronaviruses infected alveolar cells compared to normal alveolar cells in human lungs. The mole concept is used to estimate the number of normal alveolar cells per human lung. The number of coronavirus infections in infected alveolar cells is estimated from the published Lower Respiratory Tract (LRT) load data. The Poisson probability distribution is aptly applied to imply the incubation period of the coronavirus infection to be within day-3 to day-7, with the cumulative probability of 75%. The incubation period within day-0 to day-10 has a cumulative probability of 98%. It implies a 10-day quarantine to isolate an uninfected individual as a precautionary measure. 
(b) Three vaccines to combat COVID-19, which adopt distinct paradigms while preparing them, are analyzed. These are Moderna's mRNA-1273, Oxford-AstraZeneca's ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 and Bharat BioTech's COVAXIN. The mole concept is used to estimate the antigen mass density per dose of each of these vaccines as 10, 0.1 and 1 (g per cubic-cm), respectively. The vaccines are deemed to be compatible to neutralize the infection.
(c) A statistical analysis is performed of the Moderna's mRNA-1273 vaccine efficacy of 94.1% and Oxford's ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 vaccine efficacy of 62.1% in terms of groups of volunteers testing negative to vaccine by chance. In the Moderna vaccination testing scenario, since the probability of negative response of vaccine is small, the Poisson probability distribution for 95% cumulative probability is used to describe the vaccination testing in 300 samples of 47 volunteers each. Thus, 87% of samples have average group of 3 volunteers testing negative to vaccine. About 6% of samples have all volunteers testing positive to vaccine. In the Oxford vaccination testing scenario, since the probability of negative response of vaccine is finite, the Gaussian probability distribution for 95% probability is used to describe the vaccination testing in 75 samples of 120 volunteers each. Thus, 68% of samples have average group of 45 volunteers testing negative to vaccine. No sample has all volunteers testing positive to vaccine. A vaccine, irrespective of its efficacy being high or low, is necessary for mass immunization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.470882" rel="alternate" title="COVID-19: Salient Aspects of Coronavirus Infection, Vaccines and Vaccination Testing and their Implications (5 tweets)"/><category term="Scientific Communication and Education"/><published>2021-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.21267766</id><title>High-Quality and Easy-to-Regenerate Personal Filter (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.342234+00:00</updated><author><name>Max Fraenkl</name></author><author><name>Milos Krbal</name></author><author><name>Jakub Houdek</name></author><author><name>Zuzana Olmrova Zmrhalova</name></author><author><name>Borivoj Prokes</name></author><author><name>Petr Hejda</name></author><author><name>Stanislav Slang</name></author><author><name>Jan Prikryl</name></author><author><name>Jakub Ondracek</name></author><author><name>Otakar Makes</name></author><author><name>Juraj Kostyk</name></author><author><name>Petr Nasadil</name></author><author><name>Pavel Malcik</name></author><author><name>Vladimir Zdimal</name></author><author><name>Miroslav Vlcek</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Proper respiratory tract protection is the key factor to limiting the rate of COVID-19 spread and providing a safe environment for health care workers. Traditional N95 (FFP2) respirators are not easy to regenerate and thus create certain financial and ecological burdens; moreover, their quality may vary significantly. A solution that would overcome these disadvantages is desirable. In this study a commercially available knit polyester fleece fabric was selected as the filter material, and a total of 25 filters of different areas and thicknesses were prepared. Then, the size-resolved filtration efficiency (40–400 nm) and pressure drop were evaluated at a volumetric flow rate of 95 L/min. We showed the excellent synergistic effect of expanding the filtration area and increasing the number of filtering layers on the filtration efficiency; a filter cartridge with 8 layers of knit polyester fabric with a surface area of 900 cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; and sized 25 × 14 × 8 cm achieved filtration efficiencies of 98 % at 95 L/min and 99.5 % at 30 L/min. The assembled filter kit consists of a filter cartridge (14 Pa) carried in a small backpack connected to a half mask with a total pressure drop of 84 Pa at 95 L/min. In addition, it is reusable, and the filter material can be regenerated at least ten times by simple methods, such as boiling. We have demonstrated a novel approach for creating high-quality and easy-to-breathe-through respiratory protective equipment that reduces operating costs and is a green solution because it is easy to regenerate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.21267766" rel="alternate" title="High-Quality and Easy-to-Regenerate Personal Filter (5 tweets)"/><category term="Occupational and Environmental Health"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.21268060</id><title>Orthostatic intolerance in adults with long COVID was not associated with postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.342931+00:00</updated><author><name>Ann Monaghan</name></author><author><name>Glenn Jennings</name></author><author><name>Feng Xue</name></author><author><name>Lisa Byrne</name></author><author><name>Eoin Duggan</name></author><author><name>Roman Romero-Ortuno</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In this observational cross-sectional study, we investigated predictors of orthostatic intolerance (OI) in adults with long COVID. Participants underwent a 3-minute active stand (AS) with Finapres® NOVA, followed by a 10-minute unmedicated 70-degree head-up tilt test. 85 participants were included (mean age 46 years, range 25-78; 74% women), of which 56 (66%) reported OI during AS (OI&lt;sub&gt;AS&lt;/sub&gt;). OI&lt;sub&gt;AS&lt;/sub&gt; seemed associated with female sex, more fatigue and depressive symptoms, and greater inability to perform activities of daily living (ADL), as well as a higher heart rate (HR) at the lowest systolic blood pressure (SBP) point before the 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; minute post-stand (mean HR&lt;sub&gt;nadir&lt;/sub&gt;: 88 vs 75 bpm, P=0.004). In a regression model also including age, sex, fatigue, depression, ADL inability, and peak HR after the nadir SBP, HR&lt;sub&gt;nadir&lt;/sub&gt; was the only OI&lt;sub&gt;AS&lt;/sub&gt; predictor (OR=1.09, 95% CI: 1.01-1.18, P=0.027). 22 participants had initial (iOH) and 5 classical (cOH) orthostatic hypotension, but neither correlated with OI&lt;sub&gt;AS&lt;/sub&gt;. 71 participants proceeded to tilt, of which 28 had OI during tilt (OI&lt;sub&gt;tilt&lt;/sub&gt;). Of the 53 who had a 10-minute tilt, 7 (13%) fulfilled hemodynamic postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome (POTS) criteria, but 6 did not report OI&lt;sub&gt;tilt&lt;/sub&gt;. OI&lt;sub&gt;AS&lt;/sub&gt; was associated with a higher initial HR on AS, which after 1 minute equalized with the non-OI&lt;sub&gt;AS&lt;/sub&gt; group. Despite these initial orthostatic HR differences, POTS was infrequent and largely asymptomatic. &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov"&gt;ClinicalTrials.gov&lt;/ext-link&gt; Identifier: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT05027724"&gt;NCT05027724&lt;/ext-link&gt; (retrospectively registered on August 30, 2021).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.21268060" rel="alternate" title="Orthostatic intolerance in adults with long COVID was not associated with postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cardiovascular Medicine"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.21268078</id><title>Real-world clinical outcomes of treatment with casirivimab-imdevimab among patients with mild-to-moderate coronavirus disease 2019 during the Delta variant pandemic (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.343638+00:00</updated><author><name>Yasuhito Suzuki</name></author><author><name>Yoko Shibata</name></author><author><name>Hiroyuki Minemura</name></author><author><name>Takefumi Nikaido</name></author><author><name>Yoshinori Tanino</name></author><author><name>Atsuro Fukuhara</name></author><author><name>Ryuzo Kanno</name></author><author><name>Hiroyuki Saito</name></author><author><name>Shuzo Suzuki</name></author><author><name>Taeko Ishii</name></author><author><name>Yayoi Inokoshi</name></author><author><name>Eiichiro Sando</name></author><author><name>Hirofumi Sakuma</name></author><author><name>Tatsuho Kobayashi</name></author><author><name>Hiroaki Kume</name></author><author><name>Masahiro Kamimoto</name></author><author><name>Hideko Aoki</name></author><author><name>Akira Takama</name></author><author><name>Takamichi Kamiyama</name></author><author><name>Masaru Nakayama</name></author><author><name>Kiyoshi Saito</name></author><author><name>Koichi Tanigawa</name></author><author><name>Masahiko Sato</name></author><author><name>Toshiyuki Kanbe</name></author><author><name>Norio Kanzaki</name></author><author><name>Teruhisa Azuma</name></author><author><name>Keiji Sakamoto</name></author><author><name>Yuichi Nakamura</name></author><author><name>Hiroshi Otani</name></author><author><name>Mitsuru Waragai</name></author><author><name>Shinsaku Maeda</name></author><author><name>Tokiya Ishida</name></author><author><name>Keishi Sugino</name></author><author><name>Yasuhiko Tsukada</name></author><author><name>Ryuki Yamada</name></author><author><name>Riko Sato</name></author><author><name>Takumi Omuna</name></author><author><name>Hikaru Tomita</name></author><author><name>Mikako Saito</name></author><author><name>Natsumi Watanabe</name></author><author><name>Mami Rikimaru</name></author><author><name>Takaya Kawamata</name></author><author><name>Takashi Umeda</name></author><author><name>Julia Morimoto</name></author><author><name>Ryuichi Togawa</name></author><author><name>Yuki Sato</name></author><author><name>Junpei Saito</name></author><author><name>Kenya Kanazawa</name></author><author><name>Ken Iseki</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mutations of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) may reduce the efficacy of neutralizing monoclonal antibody therapy against coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). We here evaluated the efficacy of casirivimab-imdevimab in patients with mild-to-moderate COVID-19 during the Delta variant surge in Fukushima Prefecture, Japan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We enrolled 949 patients with mild-to-moderate COVID-19 who were admitted to hospital between July 24, 2021 and September 30, 2021. Clinical deterioration after admission was compared between casirivimab-imdevimab users (n = 314) and non-users (n = 635).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The casirivimab-imdevimab users were older (P &amp;lt; 0.0001), had higher body temperature (≥ 38°C) (P &amp;lt; 0.0001) and greater rates of history of cigarette smoking (P = 0.0068), hypertension (P = 0.0004), obesity (P &amp;lt; 0.0001), and dyslipidemia (P &amp;lt; 0.0001) than the non-users. Multivariate logistic regression analysis demonstrated that receiving casirivimab-imdevimab was an independent factor for preventing deterioration (odds ratio 0.448; 95% confidence interval 0.263–0.763; P = 0.0023). Furthermore, in 222 patients who were selected from each group after matching on the propensity score, deterioration was significantly lower among those receiving casirivimab-imdevimab compared to those not receiving casirivimab-imdevimab (7.66% vs 14.0%; p = 0.021).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This real-world study demonstrates that casirivimab-imdevimab contributes to the prevention of deterioration in COVID-19 patients after hospitalization during a Delta variant surge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This real-world retrospective study demonstrates the contribution of treatment with casirivimab-imdevimab to the prevention of deterioration in patients with mild-to-moderate coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) even during the Delta variant pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.21268078" rel="alternate" title="Real-world clinical outcomes of treatment with casirivimab-imdevimab among patients with mild-to-moderate coronavirus disease 2019 during the Delta variant pandemic (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21267829</id><title>KNOWLEDGE, ATTITUDES AND PRACTICE AMONG HEALTHCARE WORKERS TOWARDS COVID-19 PREVENTIVE MEASURES AT WOMEN AND NEW-BORN HOSPITAL, UNIVERSITY TEACHING HOSPITAL, LUSAKA, ZAMBIA (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.344629+00:00</updated><author><name>Joyce Nambela Shampile</name></author><author><name>Godfrey Lingenda</name></author><author><name>Mowa Zambwe</name></author><author><name>Peter J. Chipimo</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To assess the knowledge, attitude and Practices among healthcare workers towards covid-19 preventive measures at Women and New-born Hospital of the University Teaching Hospitals in Lusaka.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cross-sectional study conducted at WNH-UTH, Lusaka. Convenient sample of 264 frontline healthcare workers responded to self-administered questionnaire to determine their knowledge, attitudes and practices on COVID-19 preventive measures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Majority (31.9%) of the respondents were aged 25 – 29 years. The study revealed that 63.4% had a good knowledge, 60.3% had positive attitudes and 59.9% had a good practice. Attitude was positively related with practice (&lt;italic&gt;r&lt;/italic&gt; = 0.524, p &amp;lt; 0.001) and knowledge (&lt;italic&gt;r&lt;/italic&gt; = 0.469; p &amp;lt; 0.001). Further, knowledge was positively correlated with practice (&lt;italic&gt;r&lt;/italic&gt; = 0.51; p &amp;lt; 0.001). Bivariate analysis results showed that only high knowledge score (75.6%; p &amp;lt; 0.001) and high attitude score (77.6%; p &amp;lt; 0.001) was associated with an increase in good practice among healthcare workers towards Covid-19 preventive measures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study showed the need for continued assessment of Knowledge Attitude and Practice among healthcare workers towards Covid-19 preventive measures. It further showed the need of designing interventions aimed at encouraging sustained compliance to preventive measures among healthcare workers to prevent COVID-19 transmission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;ARTICLE SUMMARY&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Strengths and Limitations&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study was conducted at Women and Newborn Hospital of the University of Zambia and described the Knowledge, Attitude and Practice among Healthcare workers towards Covid-109 preventive measures. The study showed the need for continued assessment of Knowledge Attitude and Practice among healthcare workers towards Covid-19 preventive measures. This study has the potential to yield significant benefits for the participants and the community at large. The study is reproducible and feasible with results which can be used in designing interventions aimed at encouraging use of preventive measures available to healthcare workers to prevent COVID-19 transmission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study was a cross-sectional study which limits our ability to make causal inferences. Further the study was conducted at only one hospital which is located in the capital city and so the findings cannot be generalized to HCW in other parts of Zambia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21267829" rel="alternate" title="KNOWLEDGE, ATTITUDES AND PRACTICE AMONG HEALTHCARE WORKERS TOWARDS COVID-19 PREVENTIVE MEASURES AT WOMEN AND NEW-BORN HOSPITAL, UNIVERSITY TEACHING HOSPITAL, LUSAKA, ZAMBIA (5 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268113</id><title>A nationwide deep learning pipeline to predict stroke and COVID-19 death in atrial fibrillation (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.344906+00:00</updated><author><name>Alex Handy</name></author><author><name>Angela Wood</name></author><author><name>Cathie Sudlow</name></author><author><name>Christopher Tomlinson</name></author><author><name>Frank Kee</name></author><author><name>Johan H Thygesen</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Mamouei</name></author><author><name>Reecha Sofat</name></author><author><name>Richard Dobson</name></author><author><name>Samantha Ip</name></author><author><name>Spiros Denaxas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Deep learning (DL) and machine learning (ML) models trained on long-term patient trajectories held as medical codes in electronic health records (EHR) have the potential to improve disease prediction. Anticoagulant prescribing decisions in atrial fibrillation (AF) offer a use case where the benchmark stroke risk prediction tool (CHA&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;DS&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-VASc) could be meaningfully improved by including more information from a patient’s medical history. In this study, we design and build the first DL and ML pipeline that uses the routinely updated, linked EHR data for 56 million people in England accessed via NHS Digital to predict first ischaemic stroke in people with AF, and as a secondary outcome, COVID-19 death. Our pipeline improves first stroke prediction in AF by 17% compared to CHA&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;DS&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-VASc (0.61 (0.57-0.65) vs 0.52 (0.52-0.52) area under the receiver operating characteristics curves, 95% confidence interval) and provides a generalisable, opensource framework that other researchers and developers can build on.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268113" rel="alternate" title="A nationwide deep learning pipeline to predict stroke and COVID-19 death in atrial fibrillation (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cardiovascular Medicine"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268150</id><title>Statistical Forecasting : Third Wave of COVID-19-With an Application to India (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.345518+00:00</updated><author><name>Sabara Parshad Rajeshbhai</name></author><author><name>Subhra Sankar Dhar</name></author><author><name> Shalabh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The pandemic due to the SARS-CoV-2 virus impacted the entire world in different waves. An important question that arise after witnessing the first and second waves of COVID-19 is - Will the third wave also arrive and if yes, then when. Various types of methodologies are being used to explore the arrival of third wave. A statistical methodology based on the fitting of mixture of Gaussian distributions is explored in this paper and the aim is to forecast the third wave using the data on the first two waves of pandemic. Utilizing the data of different countries that are already facing the third wave, modelling of their daily cases data and predicting the impact and timeline for the third wave in India is attempted in this paper. The Gaussian mixture model based on algorithm for clustering is used to estimate the parameters.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268150" rel="alternate" title="Statistical Forecasting : Third Wave of COVID-19-With an Application to India (5 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.21268319</id><title>Surveillance and correlation of SARS-CoV-2 viral RNA, antigen, virus isolation, and self-reported symptoms in a longitudinal study with daily sampling (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.345819+00:00</updated><author><name>Gaston Bonenfant</name></author><author><name>Jessica Deyoe</name></author><author><name>Terianne Wong</name></author><author><name>Carlos G. Grijalva</name></author><author><name>H. Keipp Talbot</name></author><author><name>Natasha Halasa</name></author><author><name>James Chappell</name></author><author><name>Dan Cui</name></author><author><name>Norman Hassell</name></author><author><name>Natalie J. Thornburg</name></author><author><name>Melissa A. Rolfes</name></author><author><name>David Wentworth</name></author><author><name>Bin Zhou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The novel coronavirus pandemic incited unprecedented demand for assays that detect viral nucleic acids, viral proteins, and corresponding antibodies. The 320 molecular diagnostics in receipt of FDA emergency use authorization mainly focus on viral detection; however, no currently approved test can be used to infer infectiousness, i.e., the presence of replicable virus. As the number of tests conducted increased, persistent SARS-CoV-2 RNA positivity by RT-PCR in some individuals led to concerns over quarantine guidelines. To this end, we attempted to design an assay that reduces the frequency of positive test results from individuals who do not shed culturable virus. We describe multiplex quantitative RT-PCR (qRT-PCR) assays that detect genomic RNA (gRNA) and subgenomic RNA (sgRNA) species of SARS-CoV-2, including spike (S), nucleocapsid (N), membrane (M), envelope (E), and ORF8. The absolute copy number of each RNA target was determined in longitudinal specimens from a household transmission study. Calculated viral RNA levels over the 14-day follow up period were compared with antigen testing and self-reported symptoms to characterize the clinical and molecular dynamics of infection and infer predictive values of these qRT-PCR assays relative to culture isolation. When detection of sgS RNA was added to the CDC 2019-Novel Coronavirus Real-Time RT-PCR Diagnostic Panel, we found a qRT-PCR positive result was 98% predictive of a positive culture (negative predictive value was 94%). Our findings suggest sgRNA presence correlates with active infection, may help identify individuals shedding culturable virus, and that similar multiplex assays can be adapted to current and future variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.21268319" rel="alternate" title="Surveillance and correlation of SARS-CoV-2 viral RNA, antigen, virus isolation, and self-reported symptoms in a longitudinal study with daily sampling (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473523</id><title>Conjunctival epithelial cells resist productive SARS-CoV-2 infection (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.346395+00:00</updated><author><name>Robert M Jackson</name></author><author><name>Catherine F Hatton</name></author><author><name>Jarmila Stremenova Spegarova</name></author><author><name>Maria Georgiou</name></author><author><name>Joseph Collin</name></author><author><name>Emily Stephenson</name></author><author><name>Bernard Verdon</name></author><author><name>Iram J Haq</name></author><author><name>Rafiqul Hussain</name></author><author><name>Jonathan M Coxhead</name></author><author><name>Hardeep-Singh Mudhar</name></author><author><name>Bart Wagner</name></author><author><name>Megan Hasoon</name></author><author><name>Tracey Davey</name></author><author><name>Paul Rooney</name></author><author><name>C.M. Anjam Khan</name></author><author><name>Chris Ward</name></author><author><name>Malcolm Brodlie</name></author><author><name>Muzlifah Haniffa</name></author><author><name>Sophie Hambleton</name></author><author><name>Lyle Armstrong</name></author><author><name>Francisco Figueiredo</name></author><author><name>Rachel Queen</name></author><author><name>Christopher J A Duncan</name></author><author><name>Majlinda Lako</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Although tropism of SARS-CoV-2 for respiratory tract epithelial cells is well established, an open question is whether the conjunctival epithelium is also a target for SARS-CoV-2. Conjunctival epithelial cells, which express viral entry receptors ACE2 and TMPRSS2, constitute the largest exposed epithelium of the ocular surface tissue, and may represent a relevant viral entry route. To address this question, we generated an organotypic air-liquid-interface model of conjunctival epithelium, composed of progenitor, basal and superficial epithelial cells and fibroblasts, which could be maintained successfully up to day 75 of differentiation. Using single-cell RNA Seq, with complementary imaging and virological assays, we observed that while all conjunctival cell types were permissive to SARS-CoV-2 genome expression, a productive infection did not ensue. The early innate immune response to SARS-CoV-2 infection in conjunctival cells was characterised by a robust autocrine and paracrine NF-Kβ activity, without activation of antiviral interferon signalling. Collectively, these data enrich our understanding of SARS-CoV-2 infection at the human ocular surface, with potential implications for the design of preventive strategies and conjunctival transplants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473523" rel="alternate" title="Conjunctival epithelial cells resist productive SARS-CoV-2 infection (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.21267362</id><title>The role of airborne transmission in a large single source outbreak of SARS-CoV-2 in a Belgian nursing home in 2020 (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.347046+00:00</updated><author><name>Bea Vuylsteke</name></author><author><name>Lize Cuypers</name></author><author><name>Guy Baele</name></author><author><name>Marianne Stranger</name></author><author><name>Sarah Lima Paralovo</name></author><author><name>Emmanuel André</name></author><author><name>Joke Dirks</name></author><author><name>Piet Maes</name></author><author><name>Marie Laga</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To better understand the conditions which have led to one of the largest COVID-19 outbreaks in Belgian nursing homes in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A nursing home in Flanders, Belgium, which experienced a massive outbreak of COVID-19 after a cultural event. An external volunteer who dressed as a legendary figure visited consecutively the 4 living units and tested positive for SARS-CoV-2 the next day. Within days, residents started to display symptoms and the outbreak spread rapidly within the nursing home.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We interviewed key informants and collected standardized data from all residents retrospectively. A batch of 115 positive samples with a Ct value of &amp;lt;37 by qRT-PCR were analysed using whole-genome sequencing. Six months after the outbreak, ventilation assessment of gathering rooms in the nursing home was done using a tracer gas test with calibrated CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; sensors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Timeline of diagnoses and symptom onsets clearly pointed to the cultural event as the start of the outbreak, with the volunteer as index case. The genotyping of positive samples depicted the presence of one large cluster, suggesting a single source outbreak.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The global attack rate among residents was 77% with a significant association between infection and presence at the event. Known risk factors such as short distance to or physical contact with the volunteer, and wearing of a mask during the event were not associated with early infection. The ventilation assessment showed a high background average CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; level in four main rooms varying from 657 ppm to 846 ppm.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our investigation shows a rapid and widespread single source outbreak of SARS-CoV-2 in a nursing home, in which airborne transmission was the most plausible explanation for the massive intra-facility spread. Our results underscore the importance of ventilation and air quality for the prevention of future outbreaks in closed facilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.21267362" rel="alternate" title="The role of airborne transmission in a large single source outbreak of SARS-CoV-2 in a Belgian nursing home in 2020 (4 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473668</id><title>Engineered High-Affinity ACE2 Peptide Mitigates ARDS and Death Induced by Multiple SARS-CoV-2 Variants (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.347431+00:00</updated><author><name>Lianghui Zhang</name></author><author><name>Soumajit Dutta</name></author><author><name>Shiqin Xiong</name></author><author><name>Matthew Chan</name></author><author><name>Kui K. Chan</name></author><author><name>Timothy M. Fan</name></author><author><name>Keith L. Bailey</name></author><author><name>Matthew Lindeblad</name></author><author><name>Laura M. Cooper</name></author><author><name>Lijun Rong</name></author><author><name>Anthony F. Gugliuzza</name></author><author><name>Diwakar Shukla</name></author><author><name>Erik Procko</name></author><author><name>Jalees Rehman</name></author><author><name>Asrar B. Malik</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Vaccine hesitancy and continuing emergence of SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern that may escape vaccine-induced immune responses highlight the urgent need for effective COVID-19 therapeutics. Monoclonal antibodies used in the clinic have varying efficacies against distinct SARS-CoV-2 variants; thus, there is considerable interest in engineered ACE2 peptides with augmented binding affinities for SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein. These could have therapeutic benefit against multiple viral variants. Using molecular dynamics simulations, we show how three amino acid substitutions in an engineered soluble ACE2 peptide (sACE2&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;.v2.4-IgG1) markedly increase affinity for the SARS-CoV-2 Spike (S) protein. We demonstrate high binding affinity to S protein of the early SARS-CoV-2 WA-1/2020 isolate and also to multiple variants of concern: B.1.1.7 (Alpha), B.1.351 (Beta), P.1 (Gamma), and B.1.617.2 (Delta) SARS-CoV-2 variants. In humanized K18-hACE2 mice, prophylactic and therapeutic administration of sACE2&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;.v2.4-IgG1 peptide prevented acute lung vascular endothelial injury and lung edema (essential features of ARDS) and significantly improved survival after infection by SARS-CoV-2 WA-1/2020 as well as P.1 variant of concern. These studies demonstrate for the first time broad efficacy &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; of an ACE2 decoy peptide against multiple SARS-CoV-2 variants and point to its therapeutic potential.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473668" rel="alternate" title="Engineered High-Affinity ACE2 Peptide Mitigates ARDS and Death Induced by Multiple SARS-CoV-2 Variants (4 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.21267955</id><title>Immunity acquired by a minority active fraction of the population could explain COVID-19 spread in Greater Buenos Aires (June-November 2020) (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.348078+00:00</updated><author><name>Gabriel Fabricius</name></author><author><name>Rodolfo A. Borzi</name></author><author><name>José Caminos</name></author><author><name>Tomás S. Grigera</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic had an uneven development in different countries. In Argentina, the pandemic began in march 2020 and, during the first 3 months, the vast majority of cases were concentrated in a densely populated region that includes the city of Buenos Aires (country capital) and the Greater Buenos Aires area that surrounds it. This work focuses on the spread of COVID-19 between June and November 2020 in Greater Buenos Aires. Within this period of time there was no vaccine, basically only the early wild strain of SARS-CoV-2 was present, and the official restriction and distancing measures in this region remained more or less constant. Under these particular conditions, the incidences show a sharp rise from June 2020 and begin to decrease towards the end of August until the end of November 2020. In this work we study, through mathematical modelling and available epidemiological information, the spread of COVID-19 in this region and period of time. We show that a coherent explanation of the evolution of incidences can be obtained assuming that only a minority fraction of the population got involved in the spread process, so that the incidences decreased as this group of people was becoming immune. The observed evolution of the incidences could then be a consequence at the population level of lasting immunity conferred by SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.21267955" rel="alternate" title="Immunity acquired by a minority active fraction of the population could explain COVID-19 spread in Greater Buenos Aires (June-November 2020) (4 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21267832</id><title>PREVALENCE AND PREDICTORS OF STRESS AMONG COVID-19 HEALTH WORKERS IN KABWE DISTRICT- A CROSS SECTIONAL STUDY (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.348842+00:00</updated><author><name>L. L Mukwasa</name></author><author><name>R. Mutemwa</name></author><author><name>M. Zambwe</name></author><author><name>E. Nkhama</name></author><author><name>P.J Chipimo</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;OBJECTIVE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study aimed at determining the magnitude of stress among COVID-19 health workers in Kabwe district.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;METHODS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study was a cross-sectional study which recruited 138 health care workers managing COVID-19 cases in Kabwe. Data were collected through structured questionnaires and in-depth interviews. Quantitative data was analyzed using SPSS version 16 while qualitative data was analyzed using Nvivo8.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;RESULTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study obtained 100% responses from the respondents and the prevalence of stress among the respondents was 73%. The nurses were more perceived to experience stress compared to the pharmacy personnel (28% vs. 3%). Similarly, women displayed a higher likelihood of experiencing stress compared to men. Lack of support, increased workload and fear were among the factors leading to stress.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study went out to determine stress among healthcare workers in Kabwe district. It was established that nurses were more vulnerable than groups. And women were found to be more stressed than men. It is therefore recommended that effective and meaningful interventions be put in place to mitigate the impact of long-term psychological distress and physical well-being in healthcare workers during the COVID-19 pandemic and future outbreaks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;ARTICLE SUMMARY&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Strengths and limitations of the study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;A cross-sectional study method was employed; it does not assist in determining the cause and effect, in addition, the timing of the snapshot may not guarantee representation of the situation overtime. Therefore, there may be need to evaluate the effects of the COVID-19 pandemic on health workers mental requirements using a longitudinal study design.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;There might have been bias from respondents as the outcomes were self-reported. However, irrespective of the aforementioned limitations, this is a novel study in Kabwe describing stress among health workers in the district during the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study grants access to initial evidence on stress among health workers managing the COVID-19 pandemic in Kabwe district, with the expectation of drawing the attention to legislators, health facility supervisors and those involved in the response to COVID-19 or impending epidemics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21267832" rel="alternate" title="PREVALENCE AND PREDICTORS OF STRESS AMONG COVID-19 HEALTH WORKERS IN KABWE DISTRICT- A CROSS SECTIONAL STUDY (4 tweets)"/><category term="Emergency Medicine"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268081</id><title>Economic burden and catastrophic health expenditure associated with COVID-19 hospitalisations in Kerala, South India (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.349272+00:00</updated><author><name>Ronnie Thomas</name></author><author><name>Quincy Mariam Jacob</name></author><author><name>Sharon Raj Eliza</name></author><author><name>Malathi Mini</name></author><author><name>Jobinse Jose</name></author><author><name>A Sobha</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Catastrophic health expenditure during COVID-19 hospitalization has altered the economic picture of households especially in low resource settings with high rates of COVID-19 infection. This study aimed to estimate the Out of Pocket (OOP) expenditure and the proportion of households that incurred catastrophic health expenditures due to COVID-19 hospitalisation in Kerala, South India.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Materials and Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A cross-sectional study was conducted among a representative sample of 155 COVID-19 hospitalised patients in Kottayam district over four months, using a pretested interview schedule. The direct medical and non-medical costs incurred by the study participant during hospitalisation and the total monthly household expenditure were obtained from the respective COVID-19 affected households. Catastrophic health expenditure was defined as direct medical expenditure exceeding 40% of effective household income.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;From the study, median and mean Out of Pocket (OOP) expenditures were obtained as USD 93.57 and USD 502.60 respectively. The study revealed that 49.7% of households had Catastrophic health expenditure, with 32.9% having incurred Distress financing. Multivariate analysis revealed being Below poverty line, hospitalisation in private healthcare facility and presence of co-morbid conditions as significant determinants of Catastrophic health expenditure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;High levels of Catastrophic health expenditure and distress financing revealed by the study unveils major unaddressed challenges in the road to Universal health coverage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268081" rel="alternate" title="Economic burden and catastrophic health expenditure associated with COVID-19 hospitalisations in Kerala, South India (4 tweets)"/><category term="Health Economics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268140</id><title>Spatiotemporal patterns and progression of the Delta variant of COVID-19 and their health intervention linkages in Southeast Asia (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.349742+00:00</updated><author><name>Luo Wei</name></author><author><name>Liu Zhaoyin</name></author><author><name>Zhou Yuxuan</name></author><author><name>Zhao Yumin</name></author><author><name>Li Yunyue Elita</name></author><author><name>Arif Masrur</name></author><author><name>Manzhu Yu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The global pandemic of COVID-19 presented an unprecedented challenge to all countries in the world, among which Southeast Asia (SEA) countries managed to maintain and mitigate the first wave of COVID-19 in 2020. However, these countries were caught in the crisis after the Delta variant was introduced to SEA, though many countries had immediately implemented non-pharmaceutical intervention (NPI) measures along with vaccination in order to contain the disease spread. To investigate the potential linkages between epidemic dynamics and public health interventions, we adopted a prospective space-time scan method to conduct spatiotemporal analysis at the district level in the seven selected countries in SEA from June 2021 to October 2021. Results reveal the spatial and temporal propagation and progression of COVID-19 risks relative to public health measures implemented by different countries. Our research benefits continuous improvements of public health strategies in preventing and containing this pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268140" rel="alternate" title="Spatiotemporal patterns and progression of the Delta variant of COVID-19 and their health intervention linkages in Southeast Asia (4 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473887</id><title>Allosteric Determinants of the SARS-CoV-2 Spike Protein Binding with Nanobodies: Examining Mechanisms of Mutational Escape and Sensitivity of the Omicron Variant (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.350133+00:00</updated><author><name>Gennady Verkhivker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Structural and biochemical studies have recently revealed a range of rationally engineered nanobodies with efficient neutralizing capacity against SARS-CoV-2 virus and resilience against mutational escape. In this study, we performed a comprehensive computational analysis of the SARS-CoV-2 spike trimer complexes with Nb6, VHH E and bi-paratopic VHH VE nanobodies. We combined atomistic dynamics and collective motions analysis with binding free energy scanning, perturbation-response scanning and network centrality analysis to examine mechanisms of nanobody-induced allosteric modulation and cooperativity in the SARS-CoV-2 spike trimer complexes with these nanobodies. By quantifying energetic and allosteric determinants of the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein binding with nanobodies, we also examined nanobody-induced modulation of escaping mutations and the effect of the Omicron variant on nanobody binding. The mutational scanning analysis supported the notion that E484A mutation can have a significant detrimental effect on nanobody binding and result in Omicron-induced escape from nanobody neutralization. Our findings showed that SARS-CoV-2 spike protein may exploit plasticity of specific allosteric hotspots to generate escape mutants that alter response to binding without compromising activity. The network analysis supported these findings showing that VHH VE nanobody binding can induce long-range couplings between the cryptic binding epitope and ACE2-binding site through a broader ensemble of communication paths that is less dependent on specific mediating centers and therefore may be less sensitive to mutational perturbations of functional residues. The results suggest that binding affinity and long-range communications of the SARS-CoV-2 complexes with nanobodies can be determined by structurally stable regulatory centers and conformationally adaptable hotspots that are allosterically coupled and collectively control resilience to mutational escape.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473887" rel="alternate" title="Allosteric Determinants of the SARS-CoV-2 Spike Protein Binding with Nanobodies: Examining Mechanisms of Mutational Escape and Sensitivity of the Omicron Variant (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268100</id><title>Analysis of cutoff point estimation for determining seropositivity in the context of SARS-CoV-2 infections (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.350371+00:00</updated><author><name>Tiago Dias Domingues</name></author><author><name>Helena Mouriño</name></author><author><name>Nuno Sepúlveda</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In this work will apply mixture models based on distributions from the SMSN family to antibody data against four SARS-CoV-2 virus antigens. Furthermore, since the true infection status of individuals is known &lt;italic&gt;a priori&lt;/italic&gt;, performance measures will be calculated for the methods proposed for cutoff point estimation such as sensitivity, specificity and accuracy. The results of a simulation study will also be presented.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268100" rel="alternate" title="Analysis of cutoff point estimation for determining seropositivity in the context of SARS-CoV-2 infections (3 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268095</id><title>Worldwide clustering and infection cycles as universal features of multiscale stochastic processes in the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.350862+00:00</updated><author><name>Marija Mitrović Dankulov</name></author><author><name>Bosiljka Tadić</name></author><author><name>Roderick Melnik</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Predicting the evolution of the current epidemic depends significantly on understanding the nature of the underlying stochastic processes. To unravel the global features of these processes, we analyse the world data of SARS-CoV-2 infection events, scrutinising two eight-month periods associated with the epidemic’s outbreak and initial immunisation phase. Based on the correlation-network mapping, K-means clustering, and multifractal time series analysis, our results reveal universal patterns, suggesting potential predominant drivers of the pandemic. More precisely, the Laplacian eigenvectors localisation has revealed robust communities of different countries and regions that then cluster according to similar shapes of infection fluctuations. Apart from quantitative measures, the immunisation phase differs significantly from the epidemic outbreak by the countries and regions constituting each cluster. While the similarity grouping possesses some regional components, the appearance of large clusters spanning different geographic locations is persevering. Furthermore, cyclic trends are characteristic of the identified clusters, dominating large temporal fluctuations of infection evolution, which are prominent in the immunisation phase. Meanwhile, persistent fluctuations around the local trend occur in intervals smaller than 14 days. These results provide a basis for further research into the interplay between biological and social factors as the primary cause of infection cycles and a better understanding of the impact of socio-economical and environmental factors at different phases of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21268095" rel="alternate" title="Worldwide clustering and infection cycles as universal features of multiscale stochastic processes in the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic (3 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21267724</id><title>Factors associated with COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy in Senegal: a mixed study (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.351107+00:00</updated><author><name>Mouhamadou Faly Ba</name></author><author><name>Adama Faye</name></author><author><name>Babacar Kane</name></author><author><name>Amadou Ibra Diallo</name></author><author><name>Amandine Junot</name></author><author><name>Ibrahima Gaye</name></author><author><name>Emmanuel Bonnet</name></author><author><name>Valéry Ridde</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most effective way to control the COVID-19 pandemic in the long term is through vaccination. Two of the important components that can hinder it are vaccine hesitancy and vaccine refusal. This study, conducted before the arrival of the vaccines in Senegal, aims to assess and identify factors associated with hesitancy to the COVID-19 vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study was an explanatory, sequential, mixed-methods design. We collected quantitative data from December 24, 2020, to January 16, 2021, and qualitative data from February 19 to March 30, 2021. We conducted a marginal quota sampling nationwide. We used a structured questionnaire to collect data for the quantitative phase and an interview guide with a telephone interview for the qualitative phase. We performed descriptive, bivariate, and multivariate analyses with R software version 4.0.5 for the quantitative phase; and performed manual content analyses for the qualitative phase.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We surveyed 607 people for the quantitative phase, and interviewed 30 people for the qualitative phase. Individuals who hesitated or refused to be vaccinated represented 12.9% and 32.8%, respectively. Vaccine hesitancy was related to gender, living in large cities, having a poor attitude towards the vaccine, thinking that the vaccine would not help protect them from the virus, being influenced by people important to them, and lacking information from health professionals. Vaccine refusal was related to living in large cities, having a poor attitude towards the vaccine, thinking that the vaccine would not help protect them from the virus, thinking that the vaccine could endanger their health, trusting opinions of people who were important to them, and lacking information from health professionals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The results of the study show that the factors associated with hesitancy and refusal to be vaccinated against COVID-19 are diverse and complex. Reducing them will help to ensure better vaccination coverage if the current challenges of vaccine accessibility are addressed. Therefore, governments and health authorities should intensify their efforts to promote vaccine confidence and reduce misinformation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21267724" rel="alternate" title="Factors associated with COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy in Senegal: a mixed study (3 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.21268052</id><title>Time Between Viral Loads for People with HIV during the COVID-19 Pandemic (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.351694+00:00</updated><author><name>Walid G. El-Nahal</name></author><author><name>Nicola M. Shen</name></author><author><name>Jeanne C. Keruly</name></author><author><name>Joyce L. Jones</name></author><author><name>Anthony T. Fojo</name></author><author><name>Yukari C. Manabe</name></author><author><name>Richard D. Moore</name></author><author><name>Kelly A. Gebo</name></author><author><name>Geetanjali Chander</name></author><author><name>Catherine R. Lesko</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the COVID-19 pandemic, patients experienced significant care disruptions, including lab monitoring. We investigated changes in the time between viral load (VL) checks for people with HIV associated with the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was an observational analysis of VLs of people with HIV in routine care at a large subspecialty clinic. At pandemic onset, the clinic temporarily closed its onsite laboratory. The exposure was time period (time-varying): pre-pandemic (January 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; 2019-March 15&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;, 2020); pandemic lab-closed (March 16&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;-July 12&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;, 2020); and pandemic lab-open (July 13&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;-December 31&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt;, 2020). We estimated time from an index VL to a subsequent VL, stratified by whether the index VL was suppressed (≤200 copies/mL). We also calculated cumulative incidence of a non-suppressed VL following a suppressed index VL, and of re-suppression following a loss of viral suppression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compared to pre-pandemic, hazard ratios for next VL check were: 0.34 (95% CI: 0.30, 0.37, lab-closed) and 0.73 (CI: 0.68, 0.78, lab-open) for suppressed patients; 0.56 (CI: 0.42, 0.79, lab-closed) and 0.92 (95% CI: 0.76, 1.10, lab-open) for non-suppressed patients. The 12-month cumulative incidence of loss of suppression was the same in the pandemic lab-open (4%) and pre-pandemic period (4%). The hazard of re-suppression following loss of suppression was lower during the pandemic lab-open versus the pre-pandemic period (hazard ratio: 0.68, 95% CI: 0.50, 0.92).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Early pandemic restrictions and lab closure significantly delayed VL monitoring. Once the lab re-opened, non-suppressed patients resumed normal monitoring. Suppressed patients still had a delay, but no significant loss of suppression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the early COVID-19 pandemic, people with HIV experienced disruptions in viral load monitoring due to lab closure and pandemic restrictions. Loosening restrictions resolved delays for non-suppressed, but not suppressed patients. Delays did not significantly increase proportion of non-suppressed patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.21268052" rel="alternate" title="Time Between Viral Loads for People with HIV during the COVID-19 Pandemic (3 tweets)"/><category term="HIV/AIDS"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.21267927</id><title>Evaluation of the Roche SARS-CoV-2 Rapid Antibody Test in samples from vaccinated individuals (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.352114+00:00</updated><author><name>Johannes Hayer</name></author><author><name>Eva Urlaub</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study aimed to establish the performance of the SARS-CoV-2 Rapid Antibody Test (IgG and IgM) and the Elecsys&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; Anti-SARS-CoV-2 S assay in vaccinated individuals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A panel of serum samples from Boca Biolistics was utilized to assess antibodies following vaccination, consisting of samples drawn prior to vaccination, after the first dose, or at least 14 days after the second dose of Moderna mRNA-1273 or Pfizer-BioNTech BNT162b2 COVID-19 vaccines. Agreement between the two methods was measured and stratified by test evaluator and assay lot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Agreement between the SARS-CoV-2 Rapid Antibody Test (IgG) and Elecsys Anti-SARS-CoV-2 S assay qualitative measurements at the different assessment points for both mRNA-1273 and BNT162b2 ranged between 97.06% (95% confidence interval [CI] 84.67, 99.93) to 100% (95% CI 82.35, 100). Agreement of the SARS-CoV-2 Rapid Antibody Test (IgG) with the Elecsys Anti-SARS-CoV-2 S assay was not highly influenced by either lot or evaluator. There was a medium-to-strong correlation between the semi-quantitative SARS-CoV-2 Rapid Antibody Test (IgG) result and quantitative Elecsys Anti-SARS-CoV-2 S assay in samples taken after both doses of the vaccines, with higher intensity bands being associated with higher total anti-S antibody titer (mRNA-1273, p=0.0019; BNT162b2, p&amp;lt;0.0001).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Semi-quantitative SARS-CoV-2 Rapid Antibody Test (IgG) and quantitative Elecsys Anti-SARS-CoV-2 S assay correlated well, suggesting that the SARS-CoV-2 Rapid Antibody Test (IgG) is helpful in understanding the immune response post-vaccination. The current data support the use of the SARS-CoV-2 Rapid Antibody Test (IgG) in the vaccinated population.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Serologic assays are an essential tool for quality control of vaccines and to determine the response to vaccination. Although a correlate of immunity has not yet been established for COVID-19 vaccines, antibody titers after natural infection and vaccination have been associated with protection from symptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection. Rapid point-of-care assays can potentially be of use in this context with advantages over centralized testing, such as speed and ease of use. The point-of-care SARS-CoV-2 Rapid Antibody Test (IgG) compared favorably to the Elecsys Anti-SARS-CoV-2 S assay with agreement rates above 97.06%, after one or two doses of Moderna mRNA-1273 or Pfizer-BioNTech BNT162b2. Semi-quantitative SARS-CoV-2 Rapid Antibody Test (IgG) and quantitative Elecsys Anti-SARS-CoV-2 S assay results correlated well, suggesting that SARS-CoV-2 Rapid Antibody Test (IgG) is helpful in understanding the immune response post-vaccination. The current data support the use of the SARS-CoV-2 Rapid Antibody Test (IgG) in the vaccinated population.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.21267927" rel="alternate" title="Evaluation of the Roche SARS-CoV-2 Rapid Antibody Test in samples from vaccinated individuals (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.21268155</id><title>Variability in physical inactivity responses of university students during COVID-19 pandemic: A monitoring of daily step counts using a smartphone application (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.352657+00:00</updated><author><name>Shoji Konda</name></author><author><name>Issei Ogasawara</name></author><author><name>Kazuki Fujita</name></author><author><name>Chisa Aoyama</name></author><author><name>Teruki Yokoyama</name></author><author><name>Takuya Magome</name></author><author><name>Chen Yulong</name></author><author><name>Ken Hashizume</name></author><author><name>Tomoyuki Matsuo</name></author><author><name>Ken Nakata</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This study investigated the changes in physical inactivity of university students during the COVID-19 pandemic, with reference to their academic calendar. We used the daily step counts recorded by a smartphone application (iPhone Health App) from April 2020 to January 2021 (287 days) for 603 students. The data for 287 days were divided into five periods based on their academic calendar. The median value of daily step counts across each period was calculated. A k-means clustering analysis was performed to classify the 603 participants into subgroups to demonstrate the variability in the physical inactivity responses. The median daily step counts, with a 7-days moving average, dramatically decreased from 5,000 to 2,000 steps/day in early April. It remained at a lower level (less than 2,000 steps/day) during the first semester, then increased to more than 5,000 steps/day at the start of summer vacation. The clustering analysis demonstrated the variability in physical inactivity responses. Independent of the academic calendar, many inactive students did not recover their original daily step counts after its dramatic decrement. Consequently, promoting physical activity is recommended for inactive university students over the course of the whole semester.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.21268155" rel="alternate" title="Variability in physical inactivity responses of university students during COVID-19 pandemic: A monitoring of daily step counts using a smartphone application (3 tweets)"/><category term="Sports Medicine"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473990</id><title>Designing multi-epitope based peptide vaccine targeting spike protein SARS-CoV-2 B1.1.529 (Omicron) variant using computational approaches. (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.353246+00:00</updated><author><name>Meet Parmar</name></author><author><name>Ritik Thumar</name></author><author><name>Jigar Sheth</name></author><author><name>Dhaval Patel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Since the SARS-CoV-2 outbreak in 2019, millions of people have been infected with the virus, and due to its high human-to-human transmission rate, there is a need for a vaccine to protect people. Although some vaccines are in use, due to the high mutation rate in the SARS-CoV-2 multiple variants, the current vaccines may not be sufficient to immunize people against new variant threats. One of the emerging variants of concern is B1.1.529 (Omicron), which carries ~30 mutations in the Spike protein of SARS-CoV-2 is predicted to evade antibodies recognition even from vaccinated people. We used a structure-based approach along with an epitope prediction server to develop a Multi-Epitope based Subunit Vaccine (MESV) involving SARS-CoV-2 B1.1.529 variant spike glycoprotein. The predicted epitope with better antigenicity and non-toxicity were used for designing and predicting vaccine construct features and structure models. The MESV construct In-silico cloning in pET28a expression vector predicted the construct to be highly translational. The proposed MESV vaccine construct was also subjected to immune simulation prediction and was found to be highly antigenic and elicit a cell-mediated immune response. The proposed MESV in the present study has the potential to be evaluated further for vaccine production against the newly identified B1.1.529 (Omicron) variant of concern.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473990" rel="alternate" title="Designing multi-epitope based peptide vaccine targeting spike protein SARS-CoV-2 B1.1.529 (Omicron) variant using computational approaches. (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.21268226</id><title>A systematic review of observational methods used to quantify personal protective behaviours among members of the public during the COVID-19 pandemic, and the concordance between observational and self-report measures in infectious disease health protection (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.353692+00:00</updated><author><name>Rachel Davies</name></author><author><name>Fiona Mowbray</name></author><author><name>Alex F Martin</name></author><author><name>Louise E Smith</name></author><author><name>G James Rubin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Objectives: To assess the quantity and quality of studies using an observational measure of behaviour during the COVID-19 pandemic, and to narratively describe the association between self-report and observational data for behaviours relevant to controlling an infectious disease outbreak. 
Design:  Systematic review and narrative synthesis of observational studies. 
Data sources:  We searched Medline, Embase, PsychInfo, Publons, Scopus and the Public Health England behavioural science LitRep database from inception to 17th September 2021 for relevant studies. 
Study selection: We included studies which collected observational data of at least one of three health protective behaviours (hand hygiene, face covering use and maintaining physical distance from others (social distancing) during the COVID-19 pandemic. Studies where observational data were compared to self-report data in relation to any infectious disease were also included.
Data extraction and synthesis: We evaluated the quality of studies using the NIH quality assessment scale for observational studies, extracted data on sample size, setting and adherence to health protective behaviours, and synthesized results narratively.  
Results: Of 27,279 published papers on COVID-19 relevant health protective behaviours that included one or more terms relating to hand hygiene, face covering and social distancing, we identified 48 studies that included an objective observational measure. Of these, 35 assessed face covering use, 17 assessed hand hygiene behaviour and seven assessed physical distancing. The general quality of these studies was good. When expanding the search to all infectious diseases, we included 21 studies that compared observational versus self-report data. These almost exclusively studied hand hygiene. The difference in outcomes was striking, with self-report over-estimating observed adherence by up to a factor of five in some settings. In only four papers did self-report match observational data in any domains. 
Conclusions: Despite their importance in controlling the pandemic, we found remarkably few studies assessing protective behaviours by observation, rather than self-report, though these studies tended to be of reasonably good quality. Observed adherence tends to be substantially lower than estimates obtained via self-report. Accurate assessment of levels of personal protective behaviour, and evaluation of interventions to increase this, would benefit from the use of observational methods.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.21268226" rel="alternate" title="A systematic review of observational methods used to quantify personal protective behaviours among members of the public during the COVID-19 pandemic, and the concordance between observational and self-report measures in infectious disease health protection (3 tweets)"/><category term="Public and Global Health"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>