<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:02.968912+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.02.21264267</id><title>Year-long COVID-19 infection reveals within-host evolution of SARS-CoV-2 in a patient with B cell depletion (39 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:02.969583+00:00</updated><author><name>Veronique Nussenblatt</name></author><author><name>Allison E Roder</name></author><author><name>Sanchita Das</name></author><author><name>Emmie de Wit</name></author><author><name>Jung-Ho Youn</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Banakis</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Mushegian</name></author><author><name>Christopher Mederos</name></author><author><name>Wei Wang</name></author><author><name>Matthew Chung</name></author><author><name>Lizzette Pérez-Pérez</name></author><author><name>Tara Palmore</name></author><author><name>Jennifer N. Brudno</name></author><author><name>James N. Kochenderfer</name></author><author><name>Elodie Ghedin</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;B-cell depleting therapies may lead to protracted disease and prolonged viral shedding in individuals infected with SARS-CoV-2. Viral persistence in the setting of immunosuppression raises concern for viral evolution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amplification of sub-genomic transcripts for the E gene (sgE) was done on nasopharyngeal samples over the course of 355 days in a patient infected with SARS-CoV-2 who had previously undergone CAR T cell therapy and had persistently positive SARS-CoV-2 nasopharyngeal swabs. Whole genome sequencing was performed on samples from the patient’s original presentation and 10 months later.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the course of almost a year, the virus accumulated a unique in-frame deletion in the amino-terminal domain of the spike protein, and complete deletion of ORF7b and ORF8, the first report of its kind in an immunocompromised patient. Also, minority variants that were identified in the early samples—reflecting the heterogeneity of the initial infection—were found to be fixed late in the infection. Remdesivir and high-titer convalescent plasma treatment were given, and the infection was eventually cleared after 335 days of infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The unique viral mutations found in this study highlight the importance of analyzing viral evolution in protracted SARS-CoV-2 infection, especially in immunosuppressed hosts, and the implication of these mutations in the emergence of viral variants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We report an immunocompromised patient with persistent symptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection for 335 days. During this time, the virus accumulated a unique in-frame deletion in the spike, and a complete deletion of ORF7b and ORF8 which is the first report of its kind in an immunocompromised patient.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.02.21264267" rel="alternate" title="Year-long COVID-19 infection reveals within-host evolution of SARS-CoV-2 in a patient with B cell depletion (39 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.06.21264535</id><title>Analytical performance of eleven SARS-CoV-2 antigen-detecting rapid tests for Delta variant (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:02.970348+00:00</updated><author><name>Meriem Bekliz</name></author><author><name>Kenneth Adea</name></author><author><name>Manel Essaidi-Laziosi</name></author><author><name>Camille Escadafal</name></author><author><name>Jilian A Sacks</name></author><author><name>Laurent Kaiser</name></author><author><name>Isabella Eckerle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Global concerns arose as the emerged and rapidly spreading SARS-CoV-2 Delta variant. To date, few data on routine diagnostic performance for Delta are available. Here, we investigate the analytical performance of eleven commercially available antigen-detecting rapid diagnostic tests (Ag-RDTs) for Delta VOC in comparison with current and earlier VOCs (Alpha, Beta and Gamma) and early pandemic variant using cultured SARS-CoV-2. Comparable sensitivity was observed for Delta for the majority of Ag-RDTs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.06.21264535" rel="alternate" title="Analytical performance of eleven SARS-CoV-2 antigen-detecting rapid tests for Delta variant (37 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.04.21264500</id><title>Increase in preterm stillbirths and reduction in iatrogenic preterm births for fetal compromise: a multi-centre cohort study of COVID-19 lockdown effects in Melbourne, Australia (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:02.970643+00:00</updated><author><name>Lisa Hui</name></author><author><name>Melvin Barrientos Marzan</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Potenza</name></author><author><name>Daniel L. Rolnik</name></author><author><name>Natasha Pritchard</name></author><author><name>Joanne M. Said</name></author><author><name>Kirsten R Palmer</name></author><author><name>Clare L. Whitehead</name></author><author><name>Penelope M. Sheehan</name></author><author><name>Jolyon Ford</name></author><author><name>Ben W. Mol</name></author><author><name>Susan P. Walker</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic has been associated with a worsening of perinatal outcomes in many settings due to the combined impacts of maternal COVID-19 disease, disruptions to maternity care, and overloaded health systems. In 2020, Melbourne endured a unique natural experiment where strict lockdown conditions were accompanied by very low COVID-19 case numbers and the maintenance of health service capacity. The aim of this study was to compare stillbirth and preterm birth rates in women who were exposed or unexposed to lockdown restrictions during pregnancy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Retrospective multi-centre cohort study of perinatal outcomes before and during COVID-19 lockdown&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Birth outcomes from all 12 public maternity hospitals in metropolitan Melbourne&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Inclusion criteria&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Singleton births without congenital anomalies from 24 weeks’ gestation. The lockdown-exposed cohort were those women for whom weeks 20- 40 of gestation would have occurred during the lockdown period of 23 March 2020 to 14 March 2021. The control cohort comprised all pregnancies in the corresponding periods one and two years prior to the exposed cohort.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main outcome measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Odds of stillbirth, preterm birth (PTB), birth weight &amp;lt; 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; centile, and iatrogenic PTB for fetal compromise, adjusting for multiple covariates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There were 24,017 births in the exposed and 50,017 births in the control group. There was a significantly higher risk of preterm, but not term, stillbirth in the exposed group compared with the control group (0.26% vs 0.18%, aOR 1.49, 95%CI 1.08 to 2.05, P = 0.015). There was also a significant reduction in preterm birth &amp;lt; 37 weeks (5.93% vs 6.23%, aOR 0.93, 95%CI 0.87 to 0.99, P=0.03), largely mediated by a reduction in iatrogenic PTB for live births (3.01% vs 3.27%, aOR 0.89, 95%CI 0.81 to 0.98, P = 0.015), including iatrogenic PTB for suspected fetal compromise (1.25% vs 1.51%, aOR 0.79, 95%CI 0.69 to 0.91, P= 0.001). There was no significant difference in the spontaneous PTB rate between the exposed and control groups (2.69% vs 2.82%, aOR 0.94, 95%CI 0.86 to 0.1.03, P=0.25).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lockdown restrictions in a high-income setting, in the absence of high rates of COVID-19 disease, were associated with a significant increase in preterm stillbirths, and a significant reduction in iatrogenic PTB for suspected fetal compromise.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Trial registration&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study was registered as an observational study with the Australian and New Zealand Clinical Trials Registry (ACTRN12620000878976).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.04.21264500" rel="alternate" title="Increase in preterm stillbirths and reduction in iatrogenic preterm births for fetal compromise: a multi-centre cohort study of COVID-19 lockdown effects in Melbourne, Australia (22 tweets)"/><category term="Obstetrics and Gynecology"/><published>2021-10-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463402</id><title>Inhibition of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein palmitoylation reduces virus infectivity (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:02.970950+00:00</updated><author><name>Ahmed A. Ramadan</name></author><author><name>Karthick Mayilsamy</name></author><author><name>Andrew R. McGill</name></author><author><name>Anandita Ghosh</name></author><author><name>Marc A. Giulianotti</name></author><author><name>Haley M. Donow</name></author><author><name>Shyam S. Mohapatra</name></author><author><name>Subhra Mohapatra</name></author><author><name>Bala Chandran</name></author><author><name>Robert J. Deschenes</name></author><author><name>Arunava Roy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spike glycoproteins of almost all enveloped viruses are known to undergo post-translational attachment of palmitic acid moieties. The precise role of such palmitoylation of the spike protein in membrane fusion and infection is not completely understood. Here, we report that palmitoylation of the first five cysteine residues of the c-terminal cysteine-rich domain of the SARS-CoV-2 spike are indispensable for infection, and palmitoylation deficient spike mutants are defective in trimerization and subsequent membrane fusion. The DHHC9 palmitoyltransferase interacts with and palmitoylates the spike protein in the ER and Golgi, and knockdown of DHHC9 results in reduced fusion and infection of SARS-CoV-2. Two bis-piperazine backbone-based DHHC9 inhibitors inhibit SARS-CoV-2 spike protein palmitoylation and the resulting progeny virion particles released are defective in fusion and infection. This establishes these palmitoyltransferase inhibitors as potential new intervention strategies against SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463402" rel="alternate" title="Inhibition of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein palmitoylation reduces virus infectivity (7 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463234</id><title>High-throughput Activity Assay for Screening Inhibitors of the SARS-CoV-2 Mac1 Macrodomain (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:02.971244+00:00</updated><author><name>Morgan Dasovich</name></author><author><name>Junlin Zhuo</name></author><author><name>Jack A. Goodman</name></author><author><name>Ajit Thomas</name></author><author><name>Robert Lyle McPherson</name></author><author><name>Aravinth Kumar Jayabalan</name></author><author><name>Veronica F. Busa</name></author><author><name>Shang-Jung Cheng</name></author><author><name>Brennan A. Murphy</name></author><author><name>Karli R. Redinger</name></author><author><name>Takashi Tsukamoto</name></author><author><name>Barbara Slusher</name></author><author><name>Jürgen Bosch</name></author><author><name>Huijun Wei</name></author><author><name>Anthony K. L. Leung</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Macrodomains are a class of conserved ADP-ribosylhydrolases expressed by viruses of pandemic concern, including coronaviruses and alphaviruses. Viral macrodomains are critical for replication and virus-induced pathogenesis; therefore, these enzymes are a promising target for antiviral therapy. However, no potent or selective viral macrodomain inhibitors currently exist, in part due to the lack of a high-throughput assay for this class of enzymes. Here, we developed a high-throughput ADP-ribosylhydrolase assay using the SARS-CoV-2 macrodomain Mac1. We performed a pilot screen which identified dasatinib and dihydralazine as ADP-ribosylhydrolase inhibitors. Importantly, dasatinib does not inhibit MacroD2, the closest Mac1 homolog in humans. Our study demonstrates the feasibility of identifying selective inhibitors based on ADP-ribosylhydrolase activity, paving the way for screening large compound libraries to identify improved macrodomain inhibitors and explore their potential as antiviral therapies for SARS-CoV-2 and future viral threats.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463234" rel="alternate" title="High-throughput Activity Assay for Screening Inhibitors of the SARS-CoV-2 Mac1 Macrodomain (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.09.21264771</id><title>Taste loss as a distinct symptom of COVID-19: A systematic review and meta-analysis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:02.971539+00:00</updated><author><name>Mackenzie R Hannum</name></author><author><name>Riley Koch</name></author><author><name>Vicente Ramirez</name></author><author><name>Sarah Marks</name></author><author><name>Aurora Toskala</name></author><author><name>Riley Herriman</name></author><author><name>Cailu Lin</name></author><author><name>Paule Valery Joseph</name></author><author><name>Danielle R Reed</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chemosensory scientists have been skeptical that reports of COVID–19 taste loss are genuine, in part because, before COVID–19, taste loss was rare and often confused with smell loss. Therefore, to establish the predicted prevalence rate of taste loss in COVID–19 patients, we conducted a systematic review and meta–analysis of 376 papers published in 2020 and 2021, with 241 of the papers meeting all inclusion criteria. Additionally, we explored how methodological differences (direct vs. self-report measures) may affect these estimates. We hypothesized that direct prevalence measures of taste loss would be the most valid because they avoid the taste/smell confusion of self-report. The meta–analysis showed that, among 138,897 COVID–19–positive patients, 39.2% reported taste dysfunction (95% CI: 35.34–43.12%), and the prevalence estimates were slightly but not significantly higher from studies using direct (n = 18) versus self-report (n = 223) methodologies (Q = 0.57, df = 1, p = 0.45). Generally, males reported lower rates of taste loss than did females and taste loss was highest in middle-aged groups. Thus, taste loss is a bona fide symptom COVID–19, meriting further research into the most appropriate direct methods to measure it and its underlying mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.09.21264771" rel="alternate" title="Taste loss as a distinct symptom of COVID-19: A systematic review and meta-analysis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Allergy and Immunology"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>