<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.952683+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.02.474743</id><title>Reduced Pathogenicity of the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron Variant in Hamsters (1198 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.953271+00:00</updated><author><name>Katherine McMahan</name></author><author><name>Victoria Giffin</name></author><author><name>Lisa H. Tostanoski</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Chung</name></author><author><name>Mazuba Siamatu</name></author><author><name>Mehul S. Suthar</name></author><author><name>Peter Halfmann</name></author><author><name>Yoshihiro Kawaoka</name></author><author><name>Cesar Piedra-Mora</name></author><author><name>Amanda J. Martinot</name></author><author><name>Swagata Kar</name></author><author><name>Hanne Andersen</name></author><author><name>Mark G. Lewis</name></author><author><name>Dan H. Barouch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The SARS-CoV-2 Omicron (B.1.1.529) variant has proven highly transmissible and has outcompeted the Delta variant in many regions of the world&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. Early reports have also suggested that Omicron may result in less severe clinical disease in humans. Here we show that Omicron is less pathogenic than prior SARS-CoV-2 variants in Syrian golden hamsters. Infection of hamsters with the SARS-CoV-2 WA1/2020, Alpha, Beta, or Delta strains led to 4-10% weight loss by day 4 and 10-17% weight loss by day 6, as expected&lt;sup&gt;2,3&lt;/sup&gt;. In contrast, infection of hamsters with two different Omicron challenge stocks did not result in any detectable weight loss, even at high challenge doses. Omicron infection still led to substantial viral replication in both the upper and lower respiratory tracts and pulmonary pathology, but with a trend towards higher viral loads in nasal turbinates and lower viral loads in lung parenchyma compared with WA1/2020 infection. These data suggest that the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant may result in more robust upper respiratory tract infection but less severe lower respiratory tract clinical disease compared with prior SARS-CoV-2 variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.02.474743" rel="alternate" title="Reduced Pathogenicity of the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron Variant in Hamsters (1198 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474561</id><title>Melatonin drugs inhibit SARS-CoV-2 entry into the brain and virus-induced damage of cerebral small vessels (680 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.953706+00:00</updated><author><name>Erika Cecon</name></author><author><name>Daniela Fernandois</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Renault</name></author><author><name>Caio Fernando Ferreira Coelho</name></author><author><name>Jan Wenzel</name></author><author><name>Corentin Bedart</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Izabelle</name></author><author><name>Sarah Gallet Wimez</name></author><author><name>Sophie Le Poder</name></author><author><name>Bernard Klonjkowski</name></author><author><name>Markus Schwaninger</name></author><author><name>Vincent Prevot</name></author><author><name>Julie Dam</name></author><author><name>Ralf Jockers</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 is a complex disease with short- and long-term respiratory, inflammatory and neurological symptoms that are triggered by the infection with SARS-CoV-2. Invasion of the brain by SARS-CoV-2 has been observed in humans and is postulated to be involved in post COVID condition. Brain infection is particularly pronounced in the K18-&lt;italic&gt;hACE2&lt;/italic&gt; mouse model of COVID-19. Here, we show that treatment of K18-&lt;italic&gt;hACE2&lt;/italic&gt; mice with melatonin and two melatonin-derived marketed drugs, agomelatine and ramelteon, prevent SARS-CoV-2 entry in the brain thereby reducing virus-induced damage of small cerebral vessels, immune cell infiltration and brain inflammation. Brain entry of SARS-CoV-2 through endothelial cells is prevented by melatonin through allosteric binding to human angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2), which interferes with the cell entry receptor function of ACE2 for SARS-CoV-2. Our findings open new perspectives for the repurposing of melatonergic drugs in the prevention of brain infection by SARS-CoV-2 and COVID-19-related long-term neurological symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474561" rel="alternate" title="Melatonin drugs inhibit SARS-CoV-2 entry into the brain and virus-induced damage of cerebral small vessels (680 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.21268586</id><title>T cell reactivity to the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant is preserved in most but not all prior infected and vaccinated individuals (526 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.954049+00:00</updated><author><name>Vivek Naranbhai</name></author><author><name>Anusha Nathan</name></author><author><name>Clarety Kaseke</name></author><author><name>Cristhian Berrios</name></author><author><name>Ashok Khatri</name></author><author><name>Shawn Choi</name></author><author><name>Matthew A. Getz</name></author><author><name>Rhoda Tano-Menka</name></author><author><name>Onosereme Ofoman</name></author><author><name>Alton Gayton</name></author><author><name>Fernando Senjobe</name></author><author><name>Kerri J. St Denis</name></author><author><name>Evan C. Lam</name></author><author><name>Wilfredo F. Garcia-Beltran</name></author><author><name>Alejandro B. Balazs</name></author><author><name>Bruce D. Walker</name></author><author><name>A. John Iafrate</name></author><author><name>Gaurav D. Gaiha</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant (B.1.1.529) contains mutations that mediate escape from infection and vaccine-induced antibody responses, although the extent to which these substitutions in spike and non-spike proteins affect T cell recognition is unknown. Here we show that T cell responses in individuals with prior infection, vaccination, both prior infection and vaccination, and boosted vaccination are largely preserved to Omicron spike and non-spike proteins. However, we also identify a subset of individuals (∼21%) with a &amp;gt;50% reduction in T cell reactivity to the Omicron spike. Evaluation of functional CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; memory T cell responses confirmed these findings and reveal that reduced recognition to Omicron spike is primarily observed within the CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cell compartment. Booster vaccination substantially enhanced T cell responses to Omicron spike. In contrast to neutralizing immunity, these findings suggest preservation of T cell responses to the Omicron variant, although with reduced reactivity in some individuals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.21268586" rel="alternate" title="T cell reactivity to the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant is preserved in most but not all prior infected and vaccinated individuals (526 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474825</id><title>Structural basis of Omicron neutralization by affinity-matured public antibodies (486 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.954532+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel J. Sheward</name></author><author><name>Pradeepa Pushparaj</name></author><author><name>Hrishikesh Das</name></author><author><name>Changil Kim</name></author><author><name>Sungyong Kim</name></author><author><name>Leo Hanke</name></author><author><name>Robert Dyrdak</name></author><author><name>Gerald McInerney</name></author><author><name>Jan Albert</name></author><author><name>Ben Murrell</name></author><author><name>Gunilla B. Karlsson Hedestam</name></author><author><name>B. Martin Hällberg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The SARS-CoV-2 Omicron&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Variant of Concern (B.1.1.529) has spread rapidly in many countries. With a spike that is highly diverged from that of the pandemic founder, it escapes most available monoclonal antibody therapeutics&lt;sup&gt;2,3&lt;/sup&gt; and erodes vaccine protection&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;. A public class of IGHV3-53-using SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibodies&lt;sup&gt;5,6&lt;/sup&gt; typically fails to neutralize variants carrying mutations in the receptor-binding motif&lt;sup&gt;7–11&lt;/sup&gt;, including Omicron. As antibodies from this class are likely elicited in most people following SARS-CoV-2 infection or vaccination, their subsequent affinity maturation is of particular interest. Here, we isolated IGHV3-53-using antibodies from an individual seven months after infection and identified several antibodies capable of broad and potent SARS-CoV-2 neutralization, extending to Omicron without loss of potency. By introducing select somatic hypermutations into a germline-reverted form of one such antibody, CAB-A17, we demonstrate the potential for commonly elicited antibodies to develop broad cross-neutralization through affinity maturation. Further, we resolved the structure of CAB-A17 Fab in complex with Omicron spike at an overall resolution of 2.6 Å by cryo-electron microscopy and defined the structural basis for this breadth. Thus, public SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibodies can, without modified spike vaccines, mature to cross-neutralize exceptionally antigenically diverged SARS-CoV-2 variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474825" rel="alternate" title="Structural basis of Omicron neutralization by affinity-matured public antibodies (486 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.31.474653</id><title>The SARS-CoV-2 variant, Omicron, shows rapid replication in human primary nasal epithelial cultures and efficiently uses the endosomal route of entry (362 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.954803+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas P. Peacock</name></author><author><name>Jonathan C. Brown</name></author><author><name>Jie Zhou</name></author><author><name>Nazia Thakur</name></author><author><name>Joseph Newman</name></author><author><name>Ruthiran Kugathasan</name></author><author><name>Ksenia Sukhova</name></author><author><name>Myrsini Kaforou</name></author><author><name>Dalan Bailey</name></author><author><name>Wendy S. Barclay</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;At the end of 2021 a new SARS-CoV-2 variant, Omicron, emerged and quickly spread across the world. It has been demonstrated that Omicron’s high number of Spike mutations lead to partial immune evasion from even polyclonal antibody responses, allowing frequent re-infection and vaccine breakthroughs. However, it seems unlikely these antigenic differences alone explain its rapid growth; here we show Omicron replicates rapidly in human primary airway cultures, more so even than the previously dominant variant of concern, Delta. Omicron Spike continues to use human ACE2 as its primary receptor, to which it binds more strongly than other variants. Omicron Spike mediates enhanced entry into cells expressing several different animal ACE2s, including various domestic avian species, horseshoe bats and mice suggesting it has an increased propensity for reverse zoonosis and is more likely than previous variants to establish an animal reservoir of SARS-CoV-2. Unlike other SARS-CoV-2 variants, however, Omicron Spike has a diminished ability to induce syncytia formation. Furthermore, Omicron is capable of efficiently entering cells in a TMPRSS2-independent manner, via the endosomal route. We posit this enables Omicron to infect a greater number of cells in the respiratory epithelium, allowing it to be more infectious at lower exposure doses, and resulting in enhanced intrinsic transmissibility.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.31.474653" rel="alternate" title="The SARS-CoV-2 variant, Omicron, shows rapid replication in human primary nasal epithelial cultures and efficiently uses the endosomal route of entry (362 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474580</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 entry sites are present in all structural elements of the human glossopharyngeal and vagal nerves: clinical implications (80 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.955101+00:00</updated><author><name>L. Vitale-Cross</name></author><author><name>I Szalayova</name></author><author><name>A Scoggins</name></author><author><name>M. Palkovits</name></author><author><name>E Mezey</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) infections result in the temporary loss of smell and taste (anosmia and dysgeusia) in about one third of confirmed cases. Several investigators have reported that the viral spike protein receptor is present in olfactory neurons. However, no study has been published to date showing the presence of viral entry sites angiotensinconverting enzyme 2 (ACE2), neuropilin1 (NRP1), and TMPRSS2, the serine protease necessary for priming the viral proteins, in human nerves that are responsible for taste sensation (cranial nerves: VII, IX and X). We used immunocytochemistry to examine three postmortem donor samples of the IXth (glossopharyngeal) and Xth (vagal) cranial nerves where they leave/join the medulla from three donors to confirm the presence of ACE2, NRP1 and TMPRSS2. Two samples were paraffin embedded; one was a frozen sample. In addition to staining sections from the latter, we isolated RNA from it, made cDNA, and performed PCR to confirm the presence of the mRNAs that encode the proteins visualized. All three of the proteins required for SARS-CoV-2 infections appear to be present in the human IXth and Xth nerves near the medulla. Direct infection of these nerves by the COVID-19 virus is likely to cause the loss of taste experienced by many patients. In addition, potential viral spread through these nerves into the adjacent brainstem respiratory centers might also aggravate the respiratory problems patients are experiencing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474580" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 entry sites are present in all structural elements of the human glossopharyngeal and vagal nerves: clinical implications (80 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.21268536</id><title>Prevalence, characteristics, and predictors of Long COVID among diagnosed cases of COVID-19 (69 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.955303+00:00</updated><author><name>Arjun M C</name></author><author><name>Arvind Kumar Singh</name></author><author><name>Debkumar Pal</name></author><author><name>Kajal Das</name></author><author><name>Alekhya Gajjala</name></author><author><name>Mahalingam Venkateshan</name></author><author><name>Baijayantimala Mishra</name></author><author><name>Binod Kumar Patro</name></author><author><name>Prasanta Raghab Mohapatra</name></author><author><name>Sonu Hangma Subba</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Long COVID or long-term complication after COVID-19 has the ability to affect health and quality of life. Knowledge about the burden and predictors could aid in their prevention and management. Most of the studies are from high-income countries and focus on severe cases. We did this study to estimate the prevalence and identify the characteristics and predictors of Long COVID among our patients. 
Methodology: We recruited adult (≥18 years) patients who were diagnosed as Reverse Transcription Polymerase Chain Reaction (RTPCR) confirmed SARS-COV-2 infection and were either hospitalized or tested on outpatient basis.  Eligible participants were followed up telephonically after four weeks of diagnosis of SARS-COV-2 infection to collect data on sociodemographic, clinical history, vaccination history, Cycle threshold (Ct) values during diagnosis and other variables. Characteristic of Long COVID were elicited, and multivariable logistic regression was done to find the predictors of Long COVID. 
Results: We have analyzed 487 individual data with a median follow-up of 44 days (Inter quartile range (IQR): 39,47). Overall, Long COVID was reported by 29.2% (95% Confidence interval (CI): 25.3%,33.4%) participants. Prevalence of Long COVID among patients with mild/moderate disease (n = 415) was 23.4% (95% CI: 19.5%,27.7%) as compared to 62.5% (95% CI: 50.7%,73%) in severe/critical cases(n=72). The most common Long COVID symptom was fatigue (64.8%) followed by cough (32.4%). Statistically significant predictors of Long COVID were - Pre-existing medical conditions (Adjusted Odds ratio (aOR)=2.00, 95% CI: 1.16,3.44), having a more significant number of symptoms during acute phase of COVID-19 disease (aOR=11.24, 95% CI: 4.00,31.51), two doses of COVID-19 vaccination (aOR=2.32, 95% CI: 1.17,4.58), the severity of illness (aOR=5.71, 95% CI: 3.00,10.89) and being admitted to hospital (Odds ratio (OR)=3.89, 95% CI: 2.49,6.08).
Conclusion: A considerable proportion of COVID-19 cases reported Long COVID symptoms. More research is needed in Long COVID to objectively assess the symptoms and find the biological and radiological markers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.21268536" rel="alternate" title="Prevalence, characteristics, and predictors of Long COVID among diagnosed cases of COVID-19 (69 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2022-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.01.474639</id><title>In vitro evaluation of therapeutic antibodies against a SARS-CoV-2 Omicron B.1.1.529 isolate (51 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.955550+00:00</updated><author><name>Franck Touret</name></author><author><name>Cécile Baronti</name></author><author><name>Hawa Sophia Bouzidi</name></author><author><name>Xavier de Lamballerie</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The emergence and rapid spread of the Omicron variant of SARS-CoV-2, which has more than 30 substitutions in the spike glycoprotein, compromises the efficacy of currently available vaccines and therapeutic antibodies. Using a clinical strain of the Omicron variant, we analyzed the neutralizing power of eight currently used monoclonal antibodies compared to the ancestral B.1 BavPat1 D614G strain. We observed that six of these antibodies have lost their ability to neutralize the Omicron variant. Of the antibodies still having neutralizing activity, Sotrovimab/Vir-7831 shows the smallest reduction in activity, with a factor change of 3.1. Cilgavimab/AZD1061 alone shows a reduction in efficacy of 15.8, resulting in a significant loss of activity for the Evusheld cocktail (42.6 fold reduction) in which the other antibody, Tixagevimab, does not retain significant activity against Omicron. Our results suggest that the clinical efficacy of the initially proposed doses should be rapidly evaluated and the possible need to modify doses or propose combination therapies should be considered.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.01.474639" rel="alternate" title="In vitro evaluation of therapeutic antibodies against a SARS-CoV-2 Omicron B.1.1.529 isolate (51 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.22268742</id><title>COVID-19-Associated Hospitalizations Among Children Less Than 12 Years of Age in the United States (48 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.955753+00:00</updated><author><name>Manuela Di Fusco</name></author><author><name>Shailja Vaghela</name></author><author><name>Mary M Moran</name></author><author><name>Jay Lin</name></author><author><name>Jessica E Atwell</name></author><author><name>Deepa Malhotra</name></author><author><name>Thomas Scassellati Sforzolini</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Cane</name></author><author><name>Jennifer L Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Leah J McGrath</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To describe the characteristics, healthcare resource use and costs associated with initial hospitalization and readmissions among pediatric patients with COVID-19 in the US.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hospitalized pediatric patients, 0-11 years of age, with a primary or secondary discharge diagnosis code for COVID-19 (ICD-10 code U07.1) were selected from 1 April 2020 through 30 September 2021 in the US Premier Healthcare Database Special Release (PHD SR). Patient characteristics, hospital length of stay (LOS), in-hospital mortality, hospital costs, hospital charges, and COVID-19-associated readmission outcomes were evaluated and stratified by age groups (0-4, 5-11), four COVID-19 disease progression states based on intensive care unit (ICU) and invasive mechanical ventilation (IMV) usage, and three sequential calendar periods. Sensitivity analyses were performed using the US HealthVerity claims database and restricting the analyses to primary discharge code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among 4,573 hospitalized pediatric patients aged 0-11 years, 68.0% were 0-4 years and 32.0% were 5-11 years, with a mean (median) age of 3.2 (1) years; 56.0% were male, and 67.2% were covered by Medicaid. Among the overall study population, 25.7% had immunocompromised condition(s), 23.1% were admitted to the ICU and 7.3% received IMV. The mean (median) hospital LOS was 4.3 (2) days, hospital costs and charges were $14,760 ($6,164) and $58,418 ($21,622), respectively; in-hospital mortality was 0.5%. LOS, costs, charges, and in-hospital mortality increased with ICU admission and/or IMV usage. In total, 2.1% had a COVID-19-associated readmission. Study outcomes appeared relatively more frequent and/or higher among those 5-11 than those 0-4. Results using the HealthVerity data source were generally consistent with main analyses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Limitations&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This retrospective administrative database analysis relied on coding accuracy and inpatient admissions with validated hospital costs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;These findings underscore that children aged 0-11 years can experience severe COVID-19 illness requiring hospitalization and substantial hospital resource use, further supporting recommendations for COVID-19 vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.22268742" rel="alternate" title="COVID-19-Associated Hospitalizations Among Children Less Than 12 Years of Age in the United States (48 tweets)"/><category term="Health Economics"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.21268499</id><title>Safety and immunogenicity of a heterologous boost with a recombinant vaccine, NVSI-06-07, in the inactivated vaccine recipients from UAE: a phase 2 randomised, double-blinded, controlled clinical trial (37 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.956029+00:00</updated><author><name>Nawal AlKaabi</name></author><author><name>Yun Kai Yang</name></author><author><name>Jing Zhang</name></author><author><name>Ke Xu</name></author><author><name>Yu Liang</name></author><author><name>Yun Kang</name></author><author><name>Ji Guo Su</name></author><author><name>Tian Yang</name></author><author><name>Salah Hussein</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Saif ElDein</name></author><author><name>Shuai Shao</name></author><author><name>Sen Sen Yang</name></author><author><name>Wenwen Lei</name></author><author><name>Xue Jun Gao</name></author><author><name>Zhiwei Jiang</name></author><author><name>Hui Wang</name></author><author><name>Meng Li</name></author><author><name>Hanadi Mekki Mekki</name></author><author><name>Walid Zaher</name></author><author><name>Sally Mahmoud</name></author><author><name>Xue Zhang</name></author><author><name>Chang Qu</name></author><author><name>Dan Ying Liu</name></author><author><name>Jing Zhang</name></author><author><name>Mengjie Yang</name></author><author><name>Islam ElTantawy</name></author><author><name>Peng Xiao</name></author><author><name>Zhao Nian Wang</name></author><author><name>Jin Liang Yin</name></author><author><name>Xiao Yan Mao</name></author><author><name>Jin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Ning Liu</name></author><author><name>Fu Jie Shen</name></author><author><name>Liang Qu</name></author><author><name>Yun Tao Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xiao Ming Yang</name></author><author><name>Guizhen Wu</name></author><author><name>Qi Ming Li</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The increased coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) breakthrough cases pose the need of booster vaccinations. In this study, we reported the safety and immunogenicity of a heterologous boost with a recombinant COVID-19 vaccine (CHO cells), named NVSI-06-07, as a third dose in participants who have previously received two doses of the inactivated vaccine (BBIBP-CorV) at pre-specified time intervals. Using homologous boost with BBIBP-CorV as control, the safety and immunogenicity of the heterologous boost with NVSI-06-07 against various SARS-CoV-2 strains, including Omicron, were characterized.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study is a single-center, randomised, double-blinded, controlled phase 2 trial for heterologous boost of NVSI-06-07 in BBIBP-CorV recipients from the United Arab Emirates (UAE). Healthy adults (aged ≥18 years) were enrolled and grouped by the specified prior vaccination interval of BBIBP-CorV, i.e., 1-3 months, 4-6 months or ≥6 months, respectively, with 600 individuals per group. For each group, participants were randomly assigned at 1:1 ratio to receive either a heterologous boost of NVSI-06-07 or a homologous booster dose of BBIBP-CorV. The primary outcome was to comparatively assess the immunogenicity between heterologous and homologous boosts at 14 and 28 days post-boosting immunization, by evaluation of the geometric mean titers (GMTs) of IgG and neutralizing antibodies as well as the corresponding seroconversion rate (≥4-fold rise in antibody titers). The secondary outcomes were the safety profile of the boosting strategies within 30 days post vaccination. The exploratory outcome was the immune efficacy against Omicron and other variants of concern (VOCs) of SARS-CoV-2. This trial is registered with &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov"&gt;ClinicalTrials.gov&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT05033847"&gt;NCT05033847&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A total of 1800 individuals who have received two doses of BBIBP-CorV were enrolled, of which 899 participants received a heterologous boost of NVSI-06-07 and 901 received a homologous boost for comparison. No vaccine-related serious adverse event (SAE) and no adverse events of special interest (AESI) were reported. 184 (20·47%) participants in the heterologous boost groups and 177 (19·64%) in the homologous boost groups reported at least one adverse reaction within 30 days. Most of the local and systemic adverse reactions reported were grades 1 (mild) or 2 (moderate), and there was no significant difference in the overall safety between heterologous and homologous boosts. Immunogenicity assays showed that the seroconversion rates in neutralizing antibodies against prototype SARS-CoV-2 elicited by heterologous boost were 89·96% - 97·52% on day 28 post-boosting vaccination, which was much higher than what was induced by homologous boost (36·80% - 81·75%). Similarly, in heterologous NVSI-06-07 booster groups, the neutralizing geometric mean titers (GMTs) against the prototype strain increased by 21·01 - 63·85 folds from baseline to 28 days post-boosting vaccination, whereas only 4·20 - 16·78 folds of increases were observed in homologous BBIBP-CorV booster group. For Omicron variant, the neutralizing antibody GMT elicited by the homologous boost of BBIBP-CorV was 37·91 (95%CI, 30·35-47·35), however, a significantly higher level of neutralizing antibodies with GMT 292·53 (95%CI, 222·81-384·07) was induced by the heterologous boost of NVSI-06-07, suggesting that it may serve as an effective boosting strategy combating the pandemic of Omicron. The similar results were obtained for other VOCs, including Alpha, Beta and Delta, in which the neutralizing response elicited by the heterologous boost was also significantly greater than that of the homologous boost. In the participants primed with BBIBP-CorV over 6 months, the largest increase in the neutralizing GMTs was obtained both in the heterologous and homologous boost groups, and thus the booster vaccination with over 6 months intervals was optimal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our findings indicated that the heterologous boost with NVSI-06-07 was safe, well-tolerated and immunogenic in adults primed with a full regimen of BBIBP-CorV. Compared to homologous boost with a third dose of BBIBP-CorV, incremental increases in immune responses were achieved by the heterologous boost with NVSI-06-07 against SARS-CoV-2 prototype strain, Omicron variant, and other VOCs. The heterologous BBIBP-CorV/NVSI-06-07 prime-boosting vaccination may be valuable in preventing the pandemic of Omicron. The optimal booster strategy was the heterologous boost with NVSI-06-07 over 6 months after a priming with two doses of BBIBP-CorV.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Research in context&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Evidence before this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We searched PubMed for clinical trials or prospective/cohort studies involving heterologous booster vaccination in non-immunocompromised population published up to Dec 25, 2021, using the term “(COVID) AND (vaccin*) AND (clinical trial OR cohort OR prospective) AND (heterologous) AND (booster OR prime-boost OR third dose)” with no language restrictions. Nine studies of heterologous prime-boost vaccinations with adenovirus-vector vaccines (ChAdOx1 nCov-19, Oxford-AstraZeneca, Ad26.COV2.S, Janssen) and mRNA vaccines (BNT162b2, Pfizer-BioNtech; mRNA1273, Moderna) were identified. The adenovirus-vector and mRNA heterologous prime-boost vaccination was found to be well tolerated and immunogenic. In individuals primed with adenovirus-vector vaccine, mRNA booster vaccination led to greater immune response than homologous boost. However, varied results were obtained on whether heterologous boost was immunogenically superior to the homologous mRNA prime-boost vaccination. Besides that, A preprint trial in population previously immunized with inactivated vaccines (CoronaVac, Sinovac Biotech) showed that the heterologous boost with adenovirus-vector vaccine (Convidecia, CanSino Biologicals) was safe and induced higher level of live-virus neutralizing antibodies than by the homogeneous boost. A pilot study reported that boosting with BNT162b2 in individuals primed with two doses of inactivated vaccines (BBIBP-CorV) was significantly more immunogenic than homologous vaccination with two-dose of BNT162b2. In addition, a preprint paper demonstrated that heterologous boost of ZF2001, a recombinant protein subunit vaccine, after CoronaVac or BBIBP-CorV vaccination potently improved the immunogenicity. But only a small size of samples was tested in this study and the live-virus neutralization was not detected. Till now, it is still lacking a formal clinical trial to evaluate the immunogenicity and safety of the heterologous prime-boost vaccination with an inactivated vaccine followed by a recombinant protein subunit-based vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Added value of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To our knowledge, this is the first reported result of a large-scale randomised, controlled clinical trial of heterologous prime-boost vaccination with an inactivated vaccine followed by a recombinant protein subunit vaccine. This trial demonstrated that the heterologous prime-booster vaccination with BBIBP-CorV/NVSI-06-07 is safe and immunogenic. Its immunoreactivity is similar to that of homologous vaccination with BBIBP-CorV. Compared to homologous boost, heterologous boost with NVSI-06-07 in BBIBP-CorV recipients elicited significantly higher immunogenicity not only against the SARS-CoV-2 prototype strain but also against Omicron and other variants of concern (VOCs).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Implications of all the available evidence&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Booster vaccination is considered an effective strategy to improve the protection efficacy of COVID-19 vaccines and control the epidemic waves of SARS-CoV-2. Data from our trial suggested that the booster vaccination of NVSI-06-07 in BBIBP-CorV recipients significantly improved the immune responses against various SARS-CoV-2 strains, including Omicron. Due to no Omicron-specific vaccine available currently, the BBIBP-CorV/NVSI-06-07 heterologous prime-boost might serve as an effective strategy combating Omicron variant. Besides that, BBIBP-CorV has been widely inoculated in population, and thus further boosting vaccination with NVSI-06-07 is valuable in preventing the COVID-19 pandemic. But further studies are needed to assess the long-term protection of BBIBP-CorV/NVSI-06-07 prime-booster vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.21268499" rel="alternate" title="Safety and immunogenicity of a heterologous boost with a recombinant vaccine, NVSI-06-07, in the inactivated vaccine recipients from UAE: a phase 2 randomised, double-blinded, controlled clinical trial (37 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475107</id><title>Autophagy and evasion of immune system by SARS-CoV-2. Structural features of the Non-structural protein 6 from Wild Type and Omicron viral strains interacting with a model lipid bilayer (30 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.956584+00:00</updated><author><name>Emmanuelle Bignon</name></author><author><name>Marco Marazzi</name></author><author><name>Stéphanie Grandemange</name></author><author><name>Antonio Monari</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The viral cycle of SARS-CoV-2 is based on a complex interplay with the cellular machinery, which is mediated by specific proteins eluding or hijacking the cellular defense mechanisms. Among the complex pathways called by the viral infection autophagy is particularly crucial and is strongly influenced by the action of the non-structural protein 6 (Nsp6) interacting with the endoplasmic reticulum membrane. Importantly, differently from other non-structural proteins Nsp6 is mutated in the recently emerged Omicron variant, suggesting a possible different role of autophagy. In this contribution we explore, for the first time, the structural property of Nsp6 thanks to long-time scale molecular dynamic simulations and machine learning analysis, identifying the interaction patterns with the lipid membrane. We also show how the mutation brought by the Omicron variant may indeed modify some of the specific interactions, and more particularly help anchoring the viral protein to the lipid bilayer interface.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;TOC GRAPHICS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="475107v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475107" rel="alternate" title="Autophagy and evasion of immune system by SARS-CoV-2. Structural features of the Non-structural protein 6 from Wild Type and Omicron viral strains interacting with a model lipid bilayer (30 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.21268323</id><title>Lineage replacement and evolution captured by the United Kingdom Covid Infection Survey (21 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.956793+00:00</updated><author><name>Katrina A. Lythgoe</name></author><author><name>Tanya Golubchik</name></author><author><name>Matthew Hall</name></author><author><name>Thomas House</name></author><author><name>George MacIntyre-Cockett</name></author><author><name>Helen Fryer</name></author><author><name>Laura Thomson</name></author><author><name>Anel Nurtay</name></author><author><name>David Buck</name></author><author><name>Angie Green</name></author><author><name>Amy Trebes</name></author><author><name>Paolo Piazza</name></author><author><name>Lorne J Lonie</name></author><author><name>Ruth Studley</name></author><author><name>Emma Rourke</name></author><author><name>Duncan Cook</name></author><author><name>Darren Smith</name></author><author><name>Matthew Bashton</name></author><author><name>Andrew Nelson</name></author><author><name>Matthew Crown</name></author><author><name>Clare McCann</name></author><author><name>Gregory R Young</name></author><author><name>Rui Andre Nunes dos Santos</name></author><author><name>Zack Richards</name></author><author><name>Adnan Tariq</name></author><author><name>Christophe Fraser</name></author><author><name>Ian Diamond</name></author><author><name>Jeff Barrett</name></author><author><name>Sarah Walker</name></author><author><name>David Bonsall</name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Office for National Statistics COVID-19 Infection Survey is a large household-based surveillance study based in the United Kingdom. Here, we report on the epidemiological and evolutionary dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 determined by analysing sequenced samples collected up until 13th November 2021. We observed four distinct sweeps or partial-sweeps, by lineages B.1.177, B.1.1.7/Alpha, B.1.617.2/Delta, and finally AY.4.2, a sublineage of B.1.617.2, with each sweeping lineage having a distinct growth advantage compared to their predecessors. Evolution was characterised by steady rates of evolution and increasing diversity within lineages, but with step increases in divergence associated with each sweeping major lineage, leading to a faster overall rate of evolution and fluctuating levels of diversity. These observations highlight the value of viral sequencing integrated into community surveillance studies to monitor the viral epidemiology and evolution of SARS-CoV-2, and potentially other pathogens, particularly as routine PCR testing is phased out or in settings where large-scale sequencing is not feasible.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.21268323" rel="alternate" title="Lineage replacement and evolution captured by the United Kingdom Covid Infection Survey (21 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.22268599</id><title>Antibody response to SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccine in lung cancer patients: Reactivity to vaccine antigen and variants of concern (21 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.957482+00:00</updated><author><name>Rajesh M Valanparambil</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Carlisle</name></author><author><name>Susanne L. Linderman</name></author><author><name>Akil Akthar</name></author><author><name>Ralph Linwood Millett</name></author><author><name>Lilin Lai</name></author><author><name>Andres Chang</name></author><author><name>Ashley A. McCook</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey Switchenko</name></author><author><name>Tahseen H. Nasti</name></author><author><name>Manpreet Saini</name></author><author><name>Andreas Wieland</name></author><author><name>Kelly E. Manning</name></author><author><name>Madison Ellis</name></author><author><name>Kathryn M. Moore</name></author><author><name>Stephanie L. Foster</name></author><author><name>Katharine Floyd</name></author><author><name>Meredith E. Davis-Gardner</name></author><author><name>Venkata-Viswanadh Edara</name></author><author><name>Mit Patel</name></author><author><name>Conor Steur</name></author><author><name>Ajay K. Nooka</name></author><author><name>Felicia Green</name></author><author><name>Margaret A. Johns</name></author><author><name>Fiona O’Brein</name></author><author><name>Uma Shanmugasundaram</name></author><author><name>Veronika I Zarnitsyna</name></author><author><name>Hasan Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Lindsay E. Nyhoff</name></author><author><name>Grace Mantus</name></author><author><name>Michael Garett</name></author><author><name>Srilatha Edupuganti</name></author><author><name>Madhusmita Behra</name></author><author><name>Rustom Antia</name></author><author><name>Jens Wrammert</name></author><author><name>Mehul S. Suthar</name></author><author><name>Madhav V. Dhodapkar</name></author><author><name>Suresh Ramalingam</name></author><author><name>Rafi Ahmed</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Purpose&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We investigated SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccine-induced binding and live-virus neutralizing antibody response in NSCLC patients to the SARS-CoV-2 wild type strain and the emerging Delta and Omicron variants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;82 NSCLC patients and 53 healthy adult volunteers who received SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccines were included in the study. Blood was collected longitudinally, and SARS-CoV-2-specific binding and live-virus neutralization response to 614D (WT), B.1.617.2 (Delta), B.1.351 (Beta) and B.1.1.529 (Omicron) variants were evaluated by Meso Scale Discovery (MSD) assay and Focus Reduction Neutralization Assay (FRNT) respectively. We determined the longevity and persistence of vaccine-induced antibody response in NSCLC patients. The effect of vaccine-type, age, gender, race and cancer therapy on the antibody response was evaluated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Binding antibody titer to the mRNA vaccines were lower in the NSCLC patients compared to the healthy volunteers (P=&amp;lt;0.0001). More importantly, NSCLC patients had reduced live-virus neutralizing activity compared to the healthy vaccinees (P=&amp;lt;0.0001). Spike and RBD-specific binding IgG titers peaked after a week following the second vaccine dose and declined after six months (P=&amp;lt;0.001). While patients &amp;gt;70 years had lower IgG titers (P=&amp;lt;0.01), patients receiving either PD-1 monotherapy, chemotherapy or a combination of both did not have a significant impact on the antibody response. Binding antibody titers to the Delta and Beta variants were lower compared to the WT strain (P=&amp;lt;0.0001). Importantly, we observed significantly lower FRNT&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; titers to Delta (6-fold), and Omicron (79-fold) variants (P=&amp;lt;0.0001) in NSCLC patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Binding and live-virus neutralizing antibody titers to SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccines in NSCLC patients were lower than the healthy vaccinees, with significantly lower live-virus neutralization of B.1.617.2 (Delta), and more importantly, the B.1.1.529 (Omicron) variant compared to the wild-type strain. These data highlight the concern for cancer patients given the rapid spread of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.22268599" rel="alternate" title="Antibody response to SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccine in lung cancer patients: Reactivity to vaccine antigen and variants of concern (21 tweets)"/><category term="Oncology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474779</id><title>Host kinase CSNK2 is a target for inhibition of pathogenic β-coronaviruses including SARS-CoV-2 (19 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.958696+00:00</updated><author><name>Xuan Yang</name></author><author><name>Rebekah J. Dickmander</name></author><author><name>Armin Bayati</name></author><author><name>Sharon A. Taft-Benz</name></author><author><name>Jeffery L. Smith</name></author><author><name>Jason W. Brown</name></author><author><name>Erik M. Lenarcic</name></author><author><name>Boyd L. Yount</name></author><author><name>Edcon Chang</name></author><author><name>Alison D. Axtman</name></author><author><name>Ralph S. Baric</name></author><author><name>Mark T. Heise</name></author><author><name>Peter S. McPherson</name></author><author><name>Nathaniel J. Moorman</name></author><author><name>Timothy M. Willson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Inhibition of the protein kinase CSNK2 with any of 30 specific and selective inhibitors representing different chemotypes, blocked replication of pathogenic human and murine β-coronaviruses (β-CoV). The potency of in-cell CSNK2A target engagement across the set of inhibitors correlated with antiviral activity and genetic knockdown confirmed the essential role of the CSNK2 holoenzyme in β-CoV replication. Spike protein uptake was blocked by CSNK2A inhibition, indicating that antiviral activity was due in part to a suppression of viral entry. CSNK2A inhibition may be a viable target for development of new broad spectrum anti-β-CoV drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474779" rel="alternate" title="Host kinase CSNK2 is a target for inhibition of pathogenic β-coronaviruses including SARS-CoV-2 (19 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.22268755</id><title>Heterologous immunization with inactivated vaccine followed by mRNA booster elicits strong humoral and cellular immune responses against the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant (18 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.959213+00:00</updated><author><name>Fanglei Zuo</name></author><author><name>Hassan Abolhassani</name></author><author><name>Likun Du</name></author><author><name>Antonio Piralla</name></author><author><name>Federico Bertoglio</name></author><author><name>Leire de Campos-Mata</name></author><author><name>Hui Wan</name></author><author><name>Maren Schubert</name></author><author><name>Yating Wang</name></author><author><name>Rui Sun</name></author><author><name>Irene Cassaniti</name></author><author><name>Stelios Vlachiotis</name></author><author><name>Makiko Kumagai-Braesch</name></author><author><name>Juni Andréll</name></author><author><name>Zhaoxia Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yintong Xue</name></author><author><name>Esther Veronika Wenzel</name></author><author><name>Luigi Calzolai</name></author><author><name>Luca Varani</name></author><author><name>Nima Rezaei</name></author><author><name>Zahra Chavoshzadeh</name></author><author><name>Fausto Baldanti</name></author><author><name>Michael Hust</name></author><author><name>Lennart Hammarström</name></author><author><name>Harold Marcotte</name></author><author><name>Qiang Pan-Hammarström</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There has been an unprecedented global effort to produce safe and effective vaccines against SARS-CoV-2. However, production challenges, supply shortages and unequal global reach, together with an increased number of breakthrough infections due to waning of immunity and the emergence of new variants of concern (VOC), have prolonged the pandemic. To boost the immune response, several heterologous vaccination regimes have been tested and have shown increased antibody responses compared to homologous vaccination. Here we evaluated the effect of mRNA vaccine booster on immunogenicity in individuals who had been vaccinated with two doses of inactivated vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The levels of specific antibodies against the receptor-binding domain (RBD) of the spike protein from wild-type virus and the Beta, Delta and Omicron variants were measured in healthy individuals who had received two doses of homologous inactivated (BBIBP-CorV or CoronoVac) or mRNA (BNT162b2 or mRNA-1273) vaccines, and in donors who were given an mRNA vaccine boost after two doses of either vaccine. Pre-vaccinated healthy donors, or individuals who had been infected and subsequently received the mRNA vaccine were also included as controls. In addition, specific memory B and T cell responses were measured in a subset of samples.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A booster dose of an mRNA vaccine significantly increased the level of specific antibodies that bind to the RBD domain of the wild-type (6-fold) and VOCs including Delta (8-fold) and Omicron (14-fold), in individuals who had previously received two doses of inactivated vaccines. The level of specific antibodies in the heterologous vaccination group was furthermore similar to that in individuals receiving a third dose of homologous mRNA vaccines or boosted with mRNA vaccine after natural infection. Moreover, this heterologous vaccination regime significantly enhanced the specific memory B and T cell responses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heterologous prime-boost immunization with inactivated vaccine followed by an mRNA vaccine boost markedly increased the levels of specific antibodies and B and T cell responses and may thus increase protection against emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants including Omicron.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.22268755" rel="alternate" title="Heterologous immunization with inactivated vaccine followed by mRNA booster elicits strong humoral and cellular immune responses against the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant (18 tweets)"/><category term="Allergy and Immunology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474974</id><title>Sequence assignment validation in cryo-EM models with checkMySequence (18 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.959816+00:00</updated><author><name>Grzegorz Chojnowski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The availability of new AI-based protein structure prediction tools radically changed the way cryo-EM maps are interpreted, but it has not eliminated the challenges of map interpretation faced by a microscopist. Models will continue to be locally rebuilt and refined using interactive tools. This inevitably results in occasional errors, among which register-shifts remain one of the most difficult to identify and correct. Here we introduce &lt;italic&gt;checkMySequence&lt;/italic&gt;; a fast, fully automated and parameter-free method for detecting register-shifts in protein models built into cryo-EM maps. We show that the method can assist model building in cases where poorer map resolution hinders visual interpretation. We also show that &lt;italic&gt;checkMySequence&lt;/italic&gt; could have helped avoid a widely discussed sequence register error in a model of SARS-CoV-2 RNA-dependent RNA polymerase that was originally detected thanks to a visual residue-by-residue inspection by members of the structural biology community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Synopsis&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present a new method, &lt;italic&gt;checkMySequence&lt;/italic&gt;, for fast and automated detection of register errors in protein models built into cryo-EM reconstructions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474974" rel="alternate" title="Sequence assignment validation in cryo-EM models with checkMySequence (18 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474592</id><title>The runaway evolution of SARS-CoV-2 leading to the highly evolved Delta strain (16 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.960119+00:00</updated><author><name>Yongsen Ruan</name></author><author><name>Mei Hou</name></author><author><name>Xiaolu Tang</name></author><author><name>Xionglei He</name></author><author><name>Xuemei Lu</name></author><author><name>Jian Lu</name></author><author><name>Chung-I Wu</name></author><author><name>Haijun Wen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In new epidemics after the host shift, the pathogens may experience accelerated evolution driven by novel selective pressures. When the accelerated evolution enters a positive feedback loop with the expanding epidemics, the pathogen’s runaway evolution may be triggered. To test this possibility in COVID-19, we analyze the extensive databases and identify 5 major waves of strains, one replacing the previous one in 2020 – 2021. The mutations differ entirely between waves and the number of mutations continues to increase, from 3-4 to 21-31. The latest wave is the Delta strain which accrues 31 new mutations to become highly prevalent. Interestingly, these new mutations in Delta strain emerge in multiple stages with each stage driven by 6 – 12 coding mutations that form a fitness group. In short, the evolution of SARS-CoV-2 from the oldest to the youngest wave, and from the earlier to the later stages of the Delta wave, is a process of acceleration with more and more mutations. The global increase in the viral population size (&lt;italic&gt;M&lt;/italic&gt;(&lt;italic&gt;t&lt;/italic&gt;), at time &lt;italic&gt;t&lt;/italic&gt;) and the mutation accumulation (&lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;(&lt;italic&gt;t&lt;/italic&gt;)) may have indeed triggered the runaway evolution in late 2020, leading to the highly evolved Alpha and then Delta strain. To suppress the pandemic, it is crucial to break the positive feedback loop between &lt;italic&gt;M&lt;/italic&gt;(&lt;italic&gt;t&lt;/italic&gt;) and &lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;(&lt;italic&gt;t&lt;/italic&gt;), neither of which has yet to be effectively dampened by late 2021. New waves beyond Delta, hence, should not be surprising.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474592" rel="alternate" title="The runaway evolution of SARS-CoV-2 leading to the highly evolved Delta strain (16 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474769</id><title>Omicron variant escapes therapeutic mAbs contrary to eight prior main VOC (16 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.960427+00:00</updated><author><name>Céline Boschi</name></author><author><name>Philippe Colson</name></author><author><name>Audrey Bancod</name></author><author><name>Valérie Moal</name></author><author><name>Bernard La Scola</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Monocolonal antibodies (mAbs) are currently used for active immunization of COVID-19 in immunocompromised patients. We herein show that in spite there are variations in susceptibility to available mAbs that are authorized for clinical use in France tested on the original B.1.1 virus and 9 variants of concern or of interest, the cocktail casirivimab/imdevimab (REGN-CoV-2) showed a major synergistic effect. However, none of the four mAbs either alone or in combination neutralized the new Omicron variant. Our data strongly warrant a reinforcement of protective measures against infection for immunocompromised patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474769" rel="alternate" title="Omicron variant escapes therapeutic mAbs contrary to eight prior main VOC (16 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.31.474032</id><title>Analysis of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron Neutralization Data up to 2021-12-22 (15 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.960651+00:00</updated><author><name>Antonia Netzl</name></author><author><name>Sina Tureli</name></author><author><name>Eric LeGresley</name></author><author><name>Barbara Mühlemann</name></author><author><name>Samuel H. Wilks</name></author><author><name>Derek J. Smith</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The rapid spread of the Omicron SARS-CoV-2 variant (B.1.1.529) resulted in international efforts to quickly assess its escape from immunity generated by vaccines and previous infections. Numerous laboratories published Omicron neutralization data as preprints and reports. The understandable limitations and variability in such rapid reporting of early results however made it difficult to make definitive statements about the data. Here, we aggregate and analyze Omicron neutralization data from 23 reporting laboratories up to 2021-12-22. There are enough data to identify multiple trends and make two definitive points. First, in twice-vaccinated individuals, titer fold drop of Omicron relative to wild type is more than 19x, likely substantially more given the number of measurements below the limit of detection of the assay. Second, out to one month post third vaccination with an mRNA vaccine, or twice vaccinated after an earlier infection, the titer fold drop to Omicron is substantially less at approximately 7x. This substantially lower fold drop and somewhat higher titers after 3rd vaccination are strong early evidence for the utility of booster vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.31.474032" rel="alternate" title="Analysis of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron Neutralization Data up to 2021-12-22 (15 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.22268771</id><title>Detection of fecal coliforms and SARS-CoV-2 RNA in sewage and recreational waters in the Ecuadorian Coast: a call for improving water quality regulation (12 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.960977+00:00</updated><author><name>Maritza Cárdenas-Calle</name></author><author><name>Leandro Patiño</name></author><author><name>Beatríz Pernia</name></author><author><name>Roberto Erazo</name></author><author><name>Carlos Muñoz</name></author><author><name>Magaly Valencia-Avellan</name></author><author><name>Mariana Lozada</name></author><author><name>Mary Regato-Arrata</name></author><author><name>Miguel Barrera</name></author><author><name>Segundo Aquino</name></author><author><name>Stalyn Moyano</name></author><author><name>Stefania Fuentes</name></author><author><name>Javier Duque</name></author><author><name>Luis Velazquez-Araque</name></author><author><name>Bertha Carpio</name></author><author><name>Carlos Méndez-Roman</name></author><author><name>Carlos Calle</name></author><author><name>Guillermo Cárdenas</name></author><author><name>David Guizado-Herrera</name></author><author><name>Clara Lucía Tello</name></author><author><name>Veronica Bravo-Basantes</name></author><author><name>Josué Zambranod</name></author><author><name>Jhannelle Francis</name></author><author><name>Miguel Uyaguari</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Wastewater surveillance represents an alternative approach for the diagnosis and early detection of infectious agents of public health importance. This study aimed to evaluate SARS-CoV-2 and other quality markers in oxidation lagoons, estuarine areas and seawater at Guayas and Santa Elena in Ecuador. Sample collections were conducted twice at 42 coastal sites and 2 oxidation lagoons during dry and rainy seasons (2020-2021). Physico-chemical and microbiological parameters were evaluated to determine organic pollution. Quantitative reverse transcription PCR was conducted to detect SARS-CoV-2. Results showed high levels of &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; and low dissolved oxygen concentrations. SARS-CoV-2 was detected in sea-waters and estuaries with salinity levels between 34.2-36.4 PSU and 28.8 °C-31.3 °C. High amounts of fecal coliforms were detected and correlated with the SARS-CoV-2 shedding. We recommend to decentralized autonomous governments in developing countries such as Ecuador to implement corrective actions and establish medium-term mechanisms to minimize a potential contamination route.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;HIGHLIGHTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 RNA was detected in estuaries, bays and the wastewater treatment systems in Playas and Santa Elena.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;High levels of fecal coliforms were detected along shorelines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Water quality parameters revealed a negative impact on the beaches studied associated with human activities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.22268771" rel="alternate" title="Detection of fecal coliforms and SARS-CoV-2 RNA in sewage and recreational waters in the Ecuadorian Coast: a call for improving water quality regulation (12 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474721</id><title>Hydrodynamics of spike proteins dictate a transport-affinity competition for SARS-CoV-2 and other enveloped viruses (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.961563+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicolas Moreno</name></author><author><name>Daniela Moreno-Chaparro</name></author><author><name>Florencio Balboa Usabiaga</name></author><author><name>Marco Ellero</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many viruses, such as SARS-CoV-2 or Influenza, possess spike-decorated envelopes. Depending on the virus type, a large variability is present in spikes number, morphology and reactivity, which remains generally unexplained. Since viruses’ transmissibility depend on features beyond their genetic sequence, new tools are required to discern the effects of spikes functionality, interaction, and morphology. Here, we postulate the relevance of hydrodynamic interactions in the viral infectivity of enveloped viruses and propose micro-rheological characterization as a platform for viruses differentiation. To understand how the spikes affect virion mobility and infectivity, we investigate the diffusivity of spike-decorate structures using mesoscopic-hydrodynamic simulations. Furthermore, we explored the interplay between affinity and passive viral transport. Our results revealed that the diffusional mechanism of SARS-CoV-2 is strongly influenced by the size and distribution of its spikes. We propose and validate a universal mechanism to explain the link between optimal virion structure and maximal infectivity for many virus families.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474721" rel="alternate" title="Hydrodynamics of spike proteins dictate a transport-affinity competition for SARS-CoV-2 and other enveloped viruses (11 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475095</id><title>Structure-based identification of naphthoquinones and derivatives as novel inhibitors of main protease Mpro and papain-like protease PLpro of SARS-CoV-2 (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.961803+00:00</updated><author><name>Lucianna H. Santos</name></author><author><name>Thales Kronenberger</name></author><author><name>Renata G. Almeida</name></author><author><name>Elany B. Silva</name></author><author><name>Rafael E. O. Rocha</name></author><author><name>Joyce C. Oliveira</name></author><author><name>Luiza V. Barreto</name></author><author><name>Danielle Skinner</name></author><author><name>Pavla Fajtová</name></author><author><name>Miriam A. Giardini</name></author><author><name>Brendon Woodworth</name></author><author><name>Conner Bardine</name></author><author><name>André Luiz Lourenço</name></author><author><name>Charles S. Craik</name></author><author><name>Antti Poso</name></author><author><name>Larissa M. Podust</name></author><author><name>James H. McKerrow</name></author><author><name>Jair L. Siqueira-Neto</name></author><author><name>Anthony J. O’Donoghue</name></author><author><name>Eufrânio N. da Silva Júnior</name></author><author><name>Rafaela S. Ferreira</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The worldwide COVID-19 pandemic caused by the coronavirus SARS-CoV-2 urgently demands novel direct antiviral treatments. The main protease (Mpro) and papain-like protease (PLpro) are attractive drug targets among coronaviruses due to their essential role in processing the polyproteins translated from the viral RNA. In the present work, we virtually screened 688 naphthoquinoidal compounds and derivatives against Mpro of SARS-CoV-2. Twenty-four derivatives were selected and evaluated in biochemical assays against Mpro using a novel fluorogenic substrate. In parallel, these compounds were also assayed with SARS-CoV-2 PLpro. Four compounds inhibited Mpro with half-maximal inhibitory concentration (IC&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;) values between 0.41 µM and 66 µM. In addition, eight compounds inhibited PLpro with IC&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; ranging from 1.7 µM to 46 µM. Molecular dynamics simulations suggest stable binding modes for Mpro inhibitors with frequent interactions with residues in the S1 and S2 pockets of the active site. For two PLpro inhibitors, interactions occur in the S3 and S4 pockets. In summary, our structure-based computational and biochemical approach identified novel naphthoquinonal scaffolds that can be further explored as SARS-CoV-2 antivirals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475095" rel="alternate" title="Structure-based identification of naphthoquinones and derivatives as novel inhibitors of main protease Mpro and papain-like protease PLpro of SARS-CoV-2 (8 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.22268750</id><title>Cell-mediated and humoral immune response to SARS-CoV-2 vaccination and booster dose in immunosuppressed patients (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.962410+00:00</updated><author><name>Lu M. Yang</name></author><author><name>Cristina Costales</name></author><author><name>Muthukumar Ramanathan</name></author><author><name>Philip L. Bulterys</name></author><author><name>Kanagavel Murugesan</name></author><author><name>Joseph Schroers-Martin</name></author><author><name>Ash A. Alizadeh</name></author><author><name>Scott D. Boyd</name></author><author><name>Janice M. Brown</name></author><author><name>Kari C. Nadeau</name></author><author><name>Sruti S. Nadimpalli</name></author><author><name>Aileen X. Wang</name></author><author><name>Stephan Busque</name></author><author><name>Benjamin A. Pinsky</name></author><author><name>Niaz Banaei</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Data on the humoral and cellular immune response to primary and booster SARS-CoV-2 vaccination in immunosuppressed patients is limited.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To determine humoral and cellular response to primary and booster vaccination in immunosuppressed patients and identify variables associated with poor response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Retrospective observational cohort study.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Large healthcare system in Northern California.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study included patients fully vaccinated against SARS-CoV-2 (mRNA-1273, BNT162b2, or Ad26.COV2.S) who underwent clinical testing for anti-SARS-SoV-2 S1 IgG ELISA (anti-S1 IgG) and SARS-CoV-2 interferon gamma release assay (IGRA) from January 1, 2021 through November 15, 2021. A cohort of 18 immunocompetent volunteer healthcare workers were included as reference. No participants had a prior diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2 infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Exposure(s)&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Immunosuppressive diseases and therapies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Outcome(s) and Measure(s)&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Humoral and cellular SARS-CoV-2 vaccine response as measured by anti-S1 IgG and SARS-CoV-2 IGRA, respectively, after primary and booster vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;496 patients (54% female; median age 50 years) were included in this study. Among immunosuppressed patients after primary vaccination, 62% (261/419) had positive anti-S1 IgG and 71% (277/389) had positive IGRA. After booster, 69% (81/118) had positive anti-S1 IgG and 73% (91/124) had positive IGRA. Immunosuppressive factors associated with low rates of humoral response after primary vaccination included anti-CD20 monoclonal antibodies (&lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;&amp;lt;.001), sphingosine 1-phsophate (S1P) receptor modulators (&lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;&amp;lt;.001), mycophenolate (&lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;=.002), and B cell lymphoma (&lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;=.004); those associated with low rates of cellular response included S1P receptor modulators (&lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;&amp;lt;.001) and mycophenolate (&lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;&amp;lt;.001). Of patients who responded poorly to primary vaccination, 16% (4/25) with hematologic malignancy or primary immunodeficiency developed a significantly increased humoral response after the booster dose, while 52% (14/27) with solid malignancy, solid organ transplantation, or autoimmune disease developed an increased response (&lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;=.009). Only 5% (2/42) of immunosuppressed patients developed a significantly increased cellular response following the booster dose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions and Relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cellular vaccine response rates were higher than humoral response rates in immunosuppressed individuals after primary vaccination, particularly among those undergoing B cell targeting therapies. However, humoral response can be increased with booster vaccination, even in patients on B cell targeting therapies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.22268750" rel="alternate" title="Cell-mediated and humoral immune response to SARS-CoV-2 vaccination and booster dose in immunosuppressed patients (8 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.474231</id><title>Genomic Perspectives on the Emerging SARS-CoV-2 Omicron Variant (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.962838+00:00</updated><author><name>Wentai Ma</name></author><author><name>Jing Yang</name></author><author><name>Haoyi Fu</name></author><author><name>Chao Su</name></author><author><name>Caixia Yu</name></author><author><name>Qihui Wang</name></author><author><name>Ana Tereza Ribeiro de Vasconcelos</name></author><author><name>Georgii A. Bazykin</name></author><author><name>Yiming Bao</name></author><author><name>Mingkun Li</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A new variant of concern for SARS-CoV-2, Omicron (B.1.1.529), was designated by the World Health Organization on November 26, 2021. This study analyzed the viral genome sequencing data of 108 samples collected from patients infected with Omicron. First, we found that the enrichment efficiency of viral nucleic acids was reduced due to mutations in the region where the primers anneal to. Second, the Omicron variant possesses an excessive number of mutations compared to other variants circulating at the same time (62 &lt;italic&gt;vs&lt;/italic&gt;. 45), especially in the &lt;italic&gt;Spike&lt;/italic&gt; gene. Mutations in the &lt;italic&gt;Spike&lt;/italic&gt; gene confer alterations in 32 amino acid residues, which was more than those observed in other SARS-CoV-2 variants. Moreover, a large number of nonsynonymous mutations occur in the codons for the amino acid residues located on the surface of the Spike protein, which could potentially affect the replication, infectivity, and antigenicity of SARS-CoV-2. Third, there are 53 mutations between the Omicron variant and its closest sequences available in public databases. Many of those mutations were rarely observed in the public database and had a low mutation rate. In addition, the linkage disequilibrium between these mutations were low, with a limited number of mutations (6) concurrently observed in the same genome, suggesting that the Omicron variant would be in a different evolutionary branch from the currently prevalent variants. To improve our ability to detect and track the source of new variants rapidly, it is imperative to further strengthen genomic surveillance and data sharing globally in a timely manner.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.474231" rel="alternate" title="Genomic Perspectives on the Emerging SARS-CoV-2 Omicron Variant (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.02.474028</id><title>A dual-receptor mechanism between integrins and ACE2 widens SARS-CoV-2 tissue tropism (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.963415+00:00</updated><author><name>Danielle Nader</name></author><author><name>Timothy E. Gressett</name></author><author><name>Md Lokman Hossen</name></author><author><name>Prem Chapagain</name></author><author><name>Steven W. Kerrigan</name></author><author><name>Gregory Bix</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In addition to the ACE2 receptor, SARS-CoV-2 binds to integrins to gain host cell entry and trigger pro-inflammatory integrin-mediated signalling cascades. Integrins, therefore, are likely candidates for a dual-receptor mechanism with ACE2 to explain the increased infectivity seen in SARS-CoV-2 models. As integrins are primarily expressed in vasculature and persistent vasculopathy is seen in COVID-19, examining the role of endothelial integrin involvement is crucial in uncovering the pathophysiology of SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.02.474028" rel="alternate" title="A dual-receptor mechanism between integrins and ACE2 widens SARS-CoV-2 tissue tropism (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.02.474750</id><title>An in vitro and in vivo approach for the isolation of Omicron variant from human clinical specimens (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.963811+00:00</updated><author><name>Pragya D. Yadav</name></author><author><name>Nivedita Gupta</name></author><author><name>Varsha Potdar</name></author><author><name>Sreelekshmy Mohandas</name></author><author><name>Rima R. Sahay</name></author><author><name>Prasad Sarkale</name></author><author><name>Anita M. Shete</name></author><author><name>Alpana Razdan</name></author><author><name>Deepak Y. Patil</name></author><author><name>Dimpal A. Nyayanit</name></author><author><name>Yash Joshi</name></author><author><name>Savita Patil</name></author><author><name>Triparna Majumdar</name></author><author><name>Hitesh Dighe</name></author><author><name>Bharti Malhotra</name></author><author><name>Jayanthi Shastri</name></author><author><name>Priya Abraham</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Due to failure of virus isolation of Omicron variant in Vero CCL-81 from the clinical specimen’s of COVID-19 cases, we infected Syrian hamsters and then passage into Vero CCL-81 cells. The Omicron sequences were studied to assess if hamster could incorporate any mutation to changes its susceptibility. L212C mutation, Tyrosine 69 deletion, and C25000T nucleotide change in spike gene and absence of V17I mutation in E gene was observed in sequences of hamster passage unlike human clinical specimen and Vero CCL-81 passages. No change was observed in the furin cleavage site in any of the specimen sequence which suggests usefulness of these isolates in future studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.02.474750" rel="alternate" title="An in vitro and in vivo approach for the isolation of Omicron variant from human clinical specimens (8 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474610</id><title>Robust expansion of phylogeny for fast-growing genome sequence data (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.964243+00:00</updated><author><name>Yongtao Ye</name></author><author><name>Marcus H. Shum</name></author><author><name>Joseph L. Tsui</name></author><author><name>Guangchuang Yu</name></author><author><name>David K. Smith</name></author><author><name>Huachen Zhu</name></author><author><name>Joseph T. Wu</name></author><author><name>Yi Guan</name></author><author><name>Tommy T. Lam</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Massive sequencing of SARS-CoV-2 genomes has led to a great demand for adding new samples to a reference phylogeny instead of building the tree from scratch. To address such challenge, we proposed an algorithm ‘TIPars’ by integrating parsimony analysis with pre-computed ancestral sequences. Compared to four state-of-the-art methods on four benchmark datasets (SARS-CoV-2, Influenza virus, Newcastle disease virus and 16S rRNA genes), TIPars achieved the best performance in most tests. It took only 21 seconds to insert 100 SARS-CoV-2 genomes to a 100k-taxa reference tree using near 1.4 gigabytes of memory. Its efficient and accurate phylogenetic placements and incrementation for phylogenies with highly similar and divergent sequences suggest that it will be useful in a wide range of studies including pathogen molecular epidemiology, microbiome diversity and systematics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474610" rel="alternate" title="Robust expansion of phylogeny for fast-growing genome sequence data (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474855</id><title>Structural and computational insights into the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron RBD-ACE2 interaction (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.964518+00:00</updated><author><name>Jun Lan</name></author><author><name>Xinheng He</name></author><author><name>Yifei Ren</name></author><author><name>Ziyi Wang</name></author><author><name>Huan Zhou</name></author><author><name>Shilong Fan</name></author><author><name>Chenyou Zhu</name></author><author><name>Dongsheng Liu</name></author><author><name>Bin Shao</name></author><author><name>Tie-Yan Liu</name></author><author><name>Qisheng Wang</name></author><author><name>Linqi Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jiwan Ge</name></author><author><name>Tong Wang</name></author><author><name>Xinquan Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Since SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant (B.1.1.529) was reported in November 2021, it has quickly spread to many countries and outcompeted the globally dominant Delta variant in several countries. The Omicron variant contains the largest number of mutations to date, with 32 mutations located at spike (S) glycoprotein, which raised great concern for its enhanced viral fitness and immune escape&lt;sup&gt;[1–4]&lt;/sup&gt;. In this study, we reported the crystal structure of the receptor binding domain (RBD) of Omicron variant S glycoprotein bound to human ACE2 at a resolution of 2.6 Å. Structural comparison, molecular dynamics simulation and binding free energy calculation collectively identified four key mutations (S477N, G496S, Q498R and N501Y) for the enhanced binding of ACE2 by the Omicron RBD compared to the WT RBD. Representative states of the WT and Omicron RBD-ACE2 systems were identified by Markov State Model, which provides a dynamic explanation for the enhanced binding of Omicron RBD. The effects of the mutations in the RBD for antibody recognition were analyzed, especially for the S371L/S373P/S375F substitutions significantly changing the local conformation of the residing loop to deactivate several class IV neutralizing antibodies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474855" rel="alternate" title="Structural and computational insights into the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron RBD-ACE2 interaction (7 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.31.474593</id><title>Cell culture model system utilizing engineered A549 cells to express high levels of ACE2 and TMPRSS2 for investigating SARS-CoV-2 infection and antivirals (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.964874+00:00</updated><author><name>Ching-Wen Chang</name></author><author><name>Krishna Mohan Parsi</name></author><author><name>Mohan Somasundaran</name></author><author><name>Emma Vanderleeden</name></author><author><name>John Cruz</name></author><author><name>Alyssa Cousineau</name></author><author><name>Ping Liu</name></author><author><name>Qi Li</name></author><author><name>Yang Wang</name></author><author><name>Rene Maehr</name></author><author><name>Jennifer P. Wang</name></author><author><name>Robert W. Finberg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Novel pathogenic severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) continues to pose an imminent global threat since its initial outbreak in December 2019. A simple in vitro model system using cell lines highly susceptible to SARS-CoV-2 infection are critical to facilitate the study of the virus cycle and to discover effective antivirals against the virus. Human lung alveolar A549 cells are regarded as a useful and valuable model for respiratory virus infection. However, SARS-CoV-2 uses the ACE2 as receptor for viral entry and the TMPRSS2 to prime the Spike protein, both of which are negligibly expressed in A549 cells. Here, we report the generation of a robust human lung epithelial cell-based model by transducing ACE2 and TMPRSS2 into A549 cells and show that the ACE2 enriched A549&lt;sup&gt;ACE2/TMPRSS2&lt;/sup&gt; cells (ACE2plus) and its single-cell-derived subclone (ACE2plusC3) are highly susceptible to SARS-CoV-2 infection. These engineered ACE2plus showed higher &lt;italic&gt;ACE2&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;TMPRSS2&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA expression levels than currently used Calu3 and commercial A549&lt;sup&gt;ACE2/TMPRSS2&lt;/sup&gt; cells. ACE2 and TMPRSS2 proteins were also highly and ubiquitously expressed in ACE2plusC3 cells. Additionally, antiviral drugs like Camostat mesylate, EIDD-1931, and Remdesivir strongly inhibited SARS-CoV-2 replication. Notably, multinucleated syncytia, a clinical feature commonly observed in severe COVID-19 patients was induced in ACE2plusC3 cells either by virus infection or by overexpressing the Spike proteins of different variants of SARS-CoV-2. Syncytial process was effectively blocked by the furin protease inhibitor, Decanoyl-RVKR-CMK. Taken together, we have developed a robust human A549 lung epithelial cell-based model that can be applied to probe SARS-CoV-2 replication and to facilitate the discovery of SARS-CoV-2 inhibitors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.31.474593" rel="alternate" title="Cell culture model system utilizing engineered A549 cells to express high levels of ACE2 and TMPRSS2 for investigating SARS-CoV-2 infection and antivirals (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.22268754</id><title>Validation of a novel fluorescent lateral flow assay for rapid qualitative and quantitative assessment of total anti-SARS-CoV-2 S-RBD binding antibody units (BAU) from plasma or fingerstick whole-blood of COVID-19 vaccinees (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.965412+00:00</updated><author><name>Nadin Younes</name></author><author><name>Duaa W. Al-Sadeq</name></author><author><name>Farah M. Shurrab</name></author><author><name>Hadeel T. Zidan</name></author><author><name>Haissam Abou-Saleh</name></author><author><name>Bushra Y. Abo Halawa</name></author><author><name>Fatima M. AlHamaydeh</name></author><author><name>Amira E. Elsharafi</name></author><author><name>Hanin I. Daas</name></author><author><name>Swapna Thomas</name></author><author><name>Sahar Aboalmaaly</name></author><author><name>Afra Al Farsi</name></author><author><name>Reeham Al-Buainain</name></author><author><name>Samar Ataelmannan</name></author><author><name>Jiji Paul</name></author><author><name>Amana Salih Al Saadi</name></author><author><name>Hadi M. Yassine</name></author><author><name>Amin F. Majdalawieh</name></author><author><name>Ahmed Ismail</name></author><author><name>Laith J. Abu-Raddad</name></author><author><name>Gheyath K. Nasrallah</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Limited commercial LFA assays are available to provide a reliable quantitative measurement of the total binding antibody units (BAU/mL) against the receptor-binding domain of the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein (S-RBD).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aim&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To evaluate the performance of FinecareTM2019-nCoV S-RBD LFA and its fluorescent reader (FinecareTM-FIA Meter) against the following reference methods (i) The FDA-approved Genscript surrogate virus-neutralizing assay (sVNT), and (ii) three highly performing automated immunoassays: BioMérieux VIDAS®3, Ortho VITROS®, and Mindray CL-900i®.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plasma from 488 vaccinees were tested by all aforementioned assays. Fingerstick whole-blood samples from 156 vaccinees were also tested by FinecareTM.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results and conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;FinecareTM showed 100% specificity as none of the pre-pandemic samples tested positive. Equivalent FinecareTM results were observed among the samples taken from fingerstick or plasma (Pearson correlation &lt;italic&gt;r&lt;/italic&gt;=0.9, p&amp;lt;0.0001), suggesting that fingerstick samples are sufficient to quantitate the S-RBD BAU/mL. A moderate correlation was observed between FinecareTM and sVNT (&lt;italic&gt;r=&lt;/italic&gt;0.5, p&amp;lt;0.0001), indicating that FinecareTM can be used for rapid prediction of the neutralization antibody post-vaccination. FinecareTM BAU results showed strong correlation with VIDAS®3 (&lt;italic&gt;r=&lt;/italic&gt;0.6, p&amp;lt;0.0001), and moderate correlation with VITROS® (&lt;italic&gt;r&lt;/italic&gt;=0.5, p&amp;lt;0.0001), and CL-900i® (&lt;italic&gt;r&lt;/italic&gt;=0.4, p&amp;lt;0.0001), suggesting that FinecareTM be used as a surrogate for the advanced automated assays to measure S-RBD BAU/mL.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.22268754" rel="alternate" title="Validation of a novel fluorescent lateral flow assay for rapid qualitative and quantitative assessment of total anti-SARS-CoV-2 S-RBD binding antibody units (BAU) from plasma or fingerstick whole-blood of COVID-19 vaccinees (6 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.22268646</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 Genetic diversity and lineage dynamics of in Egypt (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.965881+00:00</updated><author><name>Wael H. Roshdy</name></author><author><name>Mohamed K. khalifa</name></author><author><name>James Emmanuel San</name></author><author><name>Houriiyah Tegally</name></author><author><name>Eduan Wilkinson</name></author><author><name>Shymaa Showky</name></author><author><name>Daren Patrick Martin</name></author><author><name>Monika Moir</name></author><author><name>Amel Naguib</name></author><author><name>Nancy Elguindy</name></author><author><name>Mokhtar R. Gomaa</name></author><author><name>Manal Fahim</name></author><author><name>Hanaa Abu Elsood</name></author><author><name>Amira Mohsen</name></author><author><name>Ramy Galal</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Hassany</name></author><author><name>Richard J Lessells</name></author><author><name>Ahmed A. Al-Karmalawy</name></author><author><name>Rabeh EL-Shesheny</name></author><author><name>Ahmed M. Kandeil</name></author><author><name>Mohamed A. Ali</name></author><author><name>Tulio de Oliveira</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 was first diagnosed in Egypt on 14 February 2020. By the end of November 2021, over 333,840 cases and 18,832 deaths had been reported. As part of national genomic surveillance, 1,027 SARS-CoV-2 near whole-genomes had been generated and published by the end of May 2021. Here we describe the genomic epidemiology of SARS-CoV-2 in Egypt over this period using a subset of 976 high-quality Egyptian genomes analysed together with a representative set of global sequences within a phylogenetic framework. We show that a single lineage, C.36, introduced early in the pandemic was responsible for most cases in Egypt. Furthermore, we show that to remain dominant in the face of mounting immunity from previous infection and vaccination, this lineage evolved into various sub-lineages acquiring several mutations known to confer adaptive advantage and pathogenic properties. These results highlight the value of continuous genomic surveillance in regions where VOCs are not predominant and enforcement of public health measures to prevent expansion of existing lineages.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.22268646" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 Genetic diversity and lineage dynamics of in Egypt (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.22268786</id><title>Narrowing gap in regional and age-specific excess mortality in the first year and a half of COVID-19 in Hungary (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.966858+00:00</updated><author><name>Csaba G. Tóth</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the first year and a half of the pandemic, the excess mortality in Hungary was 28,400, which was 1,700 lower than the official statistics on COVID-19 deaths. This discrepancy can be partly explained by protective measures instated during the COVID-19 pandemic that decreased the intensity of the seasonal flu outbreak, which caused on average 3,000 deaths per year. Compared to the second wave of the COVID-19 pandemic, the third wave showed a reduction in the differences in excess mortality between age groups and regions. The excess mortality rate for people aged 75+ fell significantly in the third wave, partly due to the vaccination schedule and the absence of a normal flu season. For people aged 40–77, the excess mortality rate rose slightly in the third wave. Between regions, excess mortality was highest in Northern Hungary and Western Transdanubia, and much lower in Central Hungary, where the capital is located. The excess mortality rate for men was almost twice as high as that for women in almost all age groups.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.22268786" rel="alternate" title="Narrowing gap in regional and age-specific excess mortality in the first year and a half of COVID-19 in Hungary (5 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.22268637</id><title>Personal Resilience, Social Support, and Organizational Support Impact Burnout among Nurses During COVID-19 (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.967349+00:00</updated><author><name>Hanan Daghash</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nurses have been under heavy workloads since the outbreak of COVID-19 and are at a high risk of infection, leading to a high level of psychosocial risk. This can adversely affect nurses both psychologically and physically. Burnout is caused by prolonged stress during work. In the nursing profession, burnout is common, potentially affecting the well-being of nurses and their productivity. The identification of factors that may contribute to maintaining mental health and reducing burnout among frontline nurses during a pandemic is essential.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Purpose&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to explore how personal resilience, social support, and organizational support impact burnout among frontline staff nurses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study involved 129 registered nurses from a COVID-19 designated hospital using four standardized scales.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The mean age of the respondents was 29.46 years (standard deviation = 4.89). The mean number of years respondents worked in this organization was 5.60 years and the nursing profession was 4.16 years. Most of the respondents were female and held a bachelor’s degree in nursing. Multiple regression analysis was performed to predict burnout. Burnout was statistically significantly predicted by the multiple regression model (&lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; = .420, &lt;italic&gt;F&lt;/italic&gt; (3, 125) = 10.941, &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt; &amp;lt; .0001; adjusted &lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; = .406). Personal resilience, social support, and organizational support added statistically significantly to the prediction of burnout (&lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt; &amp;lt; .05).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Findings from multiple regression analysis showed that nurses with low resilience and those who perceived inadequate social and organizational support had a higher risk of reporting more burnout. As a result of a bivariate analysis, there was no significant correlation between nurse variables and burnout level, except for age, which was negatively correlated with burnout level. Accordingly, young nurses tend to experience burnout, and nurse directors and managers must address this problem.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.22268637" rel="alternate" title="Personal Resilience, Social Support, and Organizational Support Impact Burnout among Nurses During COVID-19 (4 tweets)"/><category term="Nursing"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474814</id><title>Duplication and overexpression of the genes encoding a beta 1,3-glucan synthase confer the intrinsic resistance to echinocandin in Mucor circinelloides (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.968027+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexis Garcia</name></author><author><name>Eun Young Huh</name></author><author><name>Soo Chan Lee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Procedures such as solid organ transplants and cancer treatments can leave many patients in an immunocompromised state resulting in an increased susceptibility to opportunistic diseases including fungal infections. Mucormycosis infections are continually emerging and pose a serious threat to immunocompromised patients. Currently there has been a sharp increase in mucormycosis cases as a secondary infection in patients battling SARS-CoV-2 infections. Mucorales fungi are notorious for presenting resistance to most antifungal drugs. The absence of effective means to treat these infections results in mortality rates approaching 100% in cases of disseminated infection. One of the most effective antifungal drug classes currently available are echinocandins. Echinocandins seem to be efficacious in treatment of many other fungal infections. Unfortunately, susceptibility testing has found that echinocandins have no to little effect on Mucorales. In this study, we found that the model Mucorales &lt;italic&gt;Mucor circinelloides&lt;/italic&gt; genome carries three copies of the genes encoding for the echinocandin β-(1,3)-D-glucan synthase (&lt;italic&gt;fks&lt;/italic&gt;A, &lt;italic&gt;fksB&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;fksC&lt;/italic&gt;). Interestingly, we revealed that exposing &lt;italic&gt;M. circinelloides&lt;/italic&gt; to micafungin significantly increased the expression of the &lt;italic&gt;fksA&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;fksB&lt;/italic&gt; genes when compared to an untreated control. We further uncovered that the serine/threonine phosphatase calcineurin is responsible for the overexpression of &lt;italic&gt;fksA&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;fksB&lt;/italic&gt; as deletion of calcineurin results in a decrease in expression of all three &lt;italic&gt;fks&lt;/italic&gt; genes and a lower minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC) to micafungin. Taken together, this study demonstrates that the &lt;italic&gt;fks&lt;/italic&gt; gene duplication and overexpression by calcineurin contribute to the intrinsic resistance to echinocandins in &lt;italic&gt;Mucor&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The recent emergence of mucormycosis cases in immunocompromised patients has become a more prevalent issue. The Mucorales fungi that cause these infections are known to be highly drug resistant, thus treatment options are limited and the mortalities of these types of infections remain unacceptably high. Echinocandins are one of the latest antifungal drugs developed to successfully treat fungal infections, but it remains unclear why Mucorales fungi are resistant to these treatments. In our study, we uncovered three copies of the genes (&lt;italic&gt;fks&lt;/italic&gt;) encoding the drug target for echinocandins. Furthermore, we discovered that the serine-threonine phosphatase calcineurin is regulating the over-expression of these genes, which confers resistance. By inhibiting calcineurin we found that the expression of these drug targets decreases resulting in an increase in susceptibility to echinocandins both &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474814" rel="alternate" title="Duplication and overexpression of the genes encoding a beta 1,3-glucan synthase confer the intrinsic resistance to echinocandin in Mucor circinelloides (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.21268549</id><title>Seroresponse to third doses of SARS-CoV-2 vaccine among patients receiving maintenance dialysis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.968776+00:00</updated><author><name>Caroline M. Hsu</name></author><author><name>Eduardo K. Lacson</name></author><author><name>Harold J. Manley</name></author><author><name>Gideon N. Aweh</name></author><author><name>Dana Miskulin</name></author><author><name>Doug Johnson</name></author><author><name>Daniel E. Weiner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Given the increased morbidity and mortality from COVID-19 among patients undergoing maintenance dialysis, we examined the seroresponse to an additional dose of SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccine, using a hypothesized protective anti-spike protein IgG antibody threshold of 7 based on prior work. Among 395 patients, 384 (97%) had seroresponse ≥7 following administration of the third dose. Among those with suboptimal (peak &amp;lt;7) and minimal (peak &amp;lt;1) seroresponse to an initial mRNA vaccine regimen, the rate of seroresponse ≥7 following a third dose was 97% (36 of 37) and 64% (14 of 22), respectively. Given ongoing high rates of COVID-19 and rapidly waning immunity after an initial vaccine series, we recommend a third mRNA vaccine dose be standard for all patients receiving maintenance dialysis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.21268549" rel="alternate" title="Seroresponse to third doses of SARS-CoV-2 vaccine among patients receiving maintenance dialysis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Nephrology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.22268766</id><title>Effects of Varying Approaches to Lifting COVID-19 Pandemic Restrictions in the United States (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.969672+00:00</updated><author><name>Jessica E. Galarraga</name></author><author><name>Daniel Popovsky</name></author><author><name>Kevin Delijani</name></author><author><name>Hannah Hanson</name></author><author><name>Mark Hanlon</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Policy approaches to lifting COVID-19 restrictions have varied significantly across the United States. An evaluation of the effects of state reopening policies on population health outcomes can inform ongoing and future pandemic responses. This study evaluates the approaches to lifting social distancing restrictions based on adherence to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) guidance established during the first wave of the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We performed a retrospective study using difference-in-differences analyses to examine the effects of reopening policies on COVID-19 outcomes with risk-adjustment for population density, temporal changes, and concurrent mask policy implementation. We examined the effects of reopening policies on per capita case rates and rates of severe COVID-19 outcomes, including hospitalizations and deaths.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adherence to the CDC’s reopening gating metrics and phased social distancing guidelines resulted in fewer COVID-19 cases, hospitalizations, and deaths. Phase one adherent states exhibited a 50-fold reduction in daily new cases and a 3-fold reduction in daily new deaths after reopening. Phase two adherent states experienced improvements in COVID-19 outcomes after reopening, while non-adherent states had a resurgence of worsening outcomes after lifting restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our study findings indicate that adherence to the CDC’s reopening guidance after implementing social distancing restrictions during the COVID-19 pandemic substantially prevents new cases, hospitalizations, and deaths. Following a stepwise reopening strategy and ensuring a sustained decline in case rates and test positivity rates before lifting restrictions can mitigate on a large scale the negative effects of a pandemic on population health outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.22268766" rel="alternate" title="Effects of Varying Approaches to Lifting COVID-19 Pandemic Restrictions in the United States (4 tweets)"/><category term="Health Policy"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.22268749</id><title>Factors Associated with COVID-19 Testing among People who Inject Drugs: Missed Opportunities for Reaching those Most at Risk (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.970489+00:00</updated><author><name>Samantha Yeager</name></author><author><name>Daniela Abramovitz</name></author><author><name>Alicia Harvey-Vera</name></author><author><name>Carlos F. Vera</name></author><author><name>Angel B. Algarin</name></author><author><name>Laramie R. Smith</name></author><author><name>Gudelia Rangel</name></author><author><name>Irina Artamonova</name></author><author><name>Thomas L. Patterson</name></author><author><name>Angela R. Bazzi</name></author><author><name>Emma L. Brugman</name></author><author><name>Steffanie A. Strathdee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;People who inject drugs (PWID) are vulnerable to SARS-CoV-2 infection. We examined correlates of COVID-19 testing among PWID in the U.S.-Mexico border region and described encounters with services or venues representing potential opportunities (i.e., ‘touchpoints’) where COVID-19 testing could have been offered. Between October, 2020 and September, 2021, participants aged ≥18 years from San Diego, California, USA and Tijuana, Baja California, Mexico who injected drugs within the last month completed surveys and SARS-CoV-2, HIV, and HCV serologic testing. Logistic regression was used to identify factors associated with COVID-19 testing prior to enrollment. Of 583 PWID, 30.5% previously had a COVID-19 test. Of 172 PWID who tested SARS-CoV-2 seropositive in our study (30.1%), 50.3% encountered at least one touchpoint within the prior six months where COVID-19 testing could have been offered. Factors independently associated with at least two fold higher odds of COVID-19 testing were living in San Diego (versus Tijuana), having recently been incarcerated or attending substance use disorder (SUD) treatment and having at least one chronic health condition. In addition, recent homelessness, having had at least one COVID-19 vaccine dose and having been tested for HIV or HCV since the pandemic began were independently associated with COVID-19 testing. We identified several factors independently associated with COVID-19 testing and multiple touchpoints where COVID-19 testing could be scaled up for PWID, such as SUD treatment programs and syringe service programs. Integrated health services are needed to improve access to rapid, free COVID-19 testing in this vulnerable population.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.22268749" rel="alternate" title="Factors Associated with COVID-19 Testing among People who Inject Drugs: Missed Opportunities for Reaching those Most at Risk (3 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>