<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.659463+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.30.21257971</id><title>Heterologous ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 and BNT162b2 prime-boost vaccination elicits potent neutralizing antibody responses and T cell reactivity (703 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.660023+00:00</updated><author><name>Rüdiger Groß</name></author><author><name>Michelle Zanoni</name></author><author><name>Alina Seidel</name></author><author><name>Carina Conzelmann</name></author><author><name>Andrea Gilg</name></author><author><name>Daniela Krnavek</name></author><author><name>Sümeyye Erdemci-Evin</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Mayer</name></author><author><name>Markus Hoffmann</name></author><author><name>Stefan Pöhlmann</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Beil</name></author><author><name>Joris Kroschel</name></author><author><name>Bernd Jahrsdörfer</name></author><author><name>Hubert Schrezenmeier</name></author><author><name>Frank Kirchhoff</name></author><author><name>Jan Münch</name></author><author><name>Janis A. Müller</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heterologous prime-boost schedules with vector- and mRNA-based COVID-19 vaccines are already administered, but immunological responses and elicited protection have not been reported.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We here analyzed a cohort of 26 individuals aged 25-46 (median 30.5) years that received a ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 prime followed by a BNT162b2 boost after an 8-week interval for reactogenicity, antibody responses and T cell reactivity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Self-reported solicited symptoms after ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 prime were in line with previous reports and less severe after the BNT162b2 boost. Antibody titers increased significantly over time resulting in strong neutralization titers 2 weeks after the BNT162b2 boost. Neutralizing activity against the prevalent strain B.1.1.7 was 3.9-fold higher than in individuals receiving homologous BNT162b2 vaccination, only 2-fold reduced for variant of concern B.1.351, and similar for variant B.1.617. In addition, CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells reacted to SARS-CoV-2 spike peptide stimulus 2 weeks after the full vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The heterologous ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 / BNT162b2 prime-boost vaccination regimen is not associated with serious adverse events and results in a potent humoral immune response and elicits T cell reactivity. Variants of concern B.1.1.7, B.1.351 and B.1.617 are potently neutralized by sera of all participants. These results suggest that this heterologous vaccination regimen is at least as immunogenic and protective as homologous vaccinations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.30.21257971" rel="alternate" title="Heterologous ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 and BNT162b2 prime-boost vaccination elicits potent neutralizing antibody responses and T cell reactivity (703 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.21257993</id><title>The UGT2A1/UGT2A2 locus is associated with COVID-19-related anosmia (161 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.660616+00:00</updated><author><name>Janie F. Shelton</name></author><author><name>Anjali J. Shastri</name></author><author><name>Stella Aslibekyan</name></author><author><name>Adam Auton</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Loss of sense of smell is a characteristic symptom of infection with SARS-CoV-2. However, specific mechanisms linking infection with loss of smell are poorly understood. Using self-reported symptom data from the 23andMe COVID-19 study, we describe the demographic patterns associated with COVID-19 related anosmia, and find the symptom is more often reported in women and younger respondents, and less often by those of East Asian and African American ancestry compared to those of European ancestry. We ran a trans-ethnic genome-wide association study (GWAS) comparing loss of smell or taste (n=47,298) with no loss of smell or taste (n=22,543) among those with a positive SARS-CoV-2 test result. We identified an association (rs7688383) in the vicinity of the &lt;italic&gt;UGT2A1 and UGT2A2&lt;/italic&gt; genes (OR=1.115, p-value=4×10&lt;sup&gt;−15&lt;/sup&gt;), which have been linked to olfactory function. These results may shed light on the biological mechanisms underlying COVID-19 related anosmia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.21257993" rel="alternate" title="The UGT2A1/UGT2A2 locus is associated with COVID-19-related anosmia (161 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.445667</id><title>Revealing the host antiviral protein ZAP-S as an inhibitor of SARS-CoV-2 programmed ribosomal frameshifting (76 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.661480+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthias M. Zimmer</name></author><author><name>Anuja Kibe</name></author><author><name>Ulfert Rand</name></author><author><name>Lukas Pekarek</name></author><author><name>Luka Cicin-Sain</name></author><author><name>Neva Caliskan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Programmed ribosomal frameshifting (PRF) is a fundamental gene expression event in many viruses including SARS-CoV-2, which allows production of essential structural and replicative enzymes from an alternative reading frame. Despite the importance of PRF for the viral life cycle, it is still largely unknown how and to what extent cellular factors alter mechanical properties of frameshifting RNA molecules and thereby impact virulence. This prompted us to comprehensively dissect the interplay between the host proteome and the SARS-CoV-2 frameshift element. Here, we reveal that zinc-finger antiviral protein (ZAP-S) is a direct and specific regulator of PRF in SARS-CoV-2 infected cells. ZAP-S overexpression strongly impairs frameshifting and viral replication. Using &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; ensemble and single-molecule techniques, we further demonstrate that ZAP-S directly interacts with the SARS-CoV-2 RNA and ribosomes and interferes with the folding of the frameshift RNA. Together these data illuminate ZAP-S as &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; host-encoded specific inhibitor of SARS-CoV-2 frameshifting and expand our understanding of RNA-based gene regulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.445667" rel="alternate" title="Revealing the host antiviral protein ZAP-S as an inhibitor of SARS-CoV-2 programmed ribosomal frameshifting (76 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.30.446357</id><title>Complete protection by a single dose skin patch delivered SARS-CoV-2 spike vaccine (69 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.662185+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher L.D. McMillan</name></author><author><name>Jovin J.Y. Choo</name></author><author><name>Adi Idris</name></author><author><name>Aroon Supramaniam</name></author><author><name>Naphak Modhiran</name></author><author><name>Alberto A. Amarilla</name></author><author><name>Ariel Isaacs</name></author><author><name>Stacey T.M. Cheung</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Liang</name></author><author><name>Helle Bielefeldt-Ohmann</name></author><author><name>Armira Azuar</name></author><author><name>Dhruba Acharya</name></author><author><name>Gabrielle Kelly</name></author><author><name>Germain J.P. Fernando</name></author><author><name>Michael J. Landsberg</name></author><author><name>Alexander A. Khromykh</name></author><author><name>Daniel Watterson</name></author><author><name>Paul R. Young</name></author><author><name>Nigel A.J. McMillan</name></author><author><name>David A. Muller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 has infected over 160 million people and resulted in more than 3.3 million deaths, and we still face many challenges in the rollout of vaccines. Here, we use the high-density microarray patch to deliver a SARS-CoV-2 spike subunit vaccine directly to the skin. We show the vaccine, dry-coated on the patch is thermostable, and delivery of spike via HD-MAP induced greater cellular and antibody immune responses, with serum able to potently neutralize clinically relevant isolates including those from the B.1.1.7 and B.1.351 lineages. Finally, a single dose of HD-MAP-delivered spike provided complete protection from a lethal virus challenge, demonstrating that HD-MAP delivery of a SARS-CoV-2 vaccine is superior to traditional needle-and-syringe vaccination and has the potential to greatly impact the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.30.446357" rel="alternate" title="Complete protection by a single dose skin patch delivered SARS-CoV-2 spike vaccine (69 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.21257989</id><title>UV-A and UV-B Can Neutralize SARS-CoV-2 Infectivity (32 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.663466+00:00</updated><author><name>Mara Biasin</name></author><author><name>Sergio Strizzi</name></author><author><name>Andrea Bianco</name></author><author><name>Alberto Macchi</name></author><author><name>Olga Utyro</name></author><author><name>Giovanni Pareschi</name></author><author><name>Alessia Loffreda</name></author><author><name>Adalberto Cavalleri</name></author><author><name>Manuela Lualdi</name></author><author><name>Daria Trabattoni</name></author><author><name>Carlo Tacchetti</name></author><author><name>Davide Mazza</name></author><author><name>Mario Clerici</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We performed an in-depth analysis of the virucidal effect of discrete wavelengths: UV-C (278 nm), UV-B (308 nm), UV-A (366 nm) and violet (405 nm) on SARS-CoV-2. By using a highly infectious titer of SARS-CoV-2 we observed that the violet light-dose resulting in a 2-log viral inactivation is only 10&lt;sup&gt;−4&lt;/sup&gt; times less efficient than UV-C light. Moreover, by qPCR and fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) approach we verified that the viral titer typically found in the sputum of COVID-19 patients can be completely inactivated by the long UV-wavelengths corresponding to UV-A and UV-B solar irradiation. The comparison of the UV action spectrum on SARS-CoV-2 to previous results obtained on other pathogens suggests that RNA viruses might be particularly sensitive to long UV wavelengths. Our data extend previous results showing that SARS-CoV-2 is highly susceptible to UV light and offer an explanation to the reduced incidence of SARS-CoV-2 infection seen in the summer season.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SYNOPSIS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;UV-A, UV-B and violet wavelengths kill SARS-CoV-2, supporting the sterilizing effects of the solar pump on human pathogens and the explanation of the seasonality of the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.21257989" rel="alternate" title="UV-A and UV-B Can Neutralize SARS-CoV-2 Infectivity (32 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.26.21257441</id><title>Emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern evade humoral immune responses from infection and vaccination (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.663791+00:00</updated><author><name>Tom G. Caniels</name></author><author><name>Ilja Bontjer</name></author><author><name>Karlijn van der Straten</name></author><author><name>Meliawati Poniman</name></author><author><name>Judith A. Burger</name></author><author><name>Brent Appelman</name></author><author><name>Ayesha H.A. Lavell</name></author><author><name>Melissa Oomen</name></author><author><name>Gert-Jan Godeke</name></author><author><name>Coralie Valle</name></author><author><name>Ramona Mögling</name></author><author><name>Hugo D.G. van Willigen</name></author><author><name>Elke Wynberg</name></author><author><name>Michiel Schinkel</name></author><author><name>Lonneke A. van Vught</name></author><author><name>Denise Guerra</name></author><author><name>Jonne L. Snitselaar</name></author><author><name>Devidas N. Chaturbhuj</name></author><author><name>Isabel Cuella Martin</name></author><author><name>John P. Moore</name></author><author><name>Menno D. de Jong</name></author><author><name>Chantal Reusken</name></author><author><name>Jonne J. Sikkens</name></author><author><name>Marije K. Bomers</name></author><author><name>Godelieve J. de Bree</name></author><author><name>Marit J. van Gils</name></author><author><name>Dirk Eggink</name></author><author><name>Rogier W. Sanders</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants pose a threat to human immunity induced by natural infection and vaccination. We assessed the recognition of three variants of concern (B.1.1.7, B.1.351 and P.1) in cohorts of COVID-19 patients ranging in disease severity (n = 69) and recipients of the Pfizer/BioNTech vaccine (n = 50). Spike binding and neutralization against all three VOC was substantially reduced in the majority of samples, with the largest 4-7-fold reduction in neutralization being observed against B.1.351. While hospitalized COVID-19 patients and vaccinees maintained sufficient neutralizing titers against all three VOC, 39% of non-hospitalized patients did not neutralize B.1.351. Moreover, monoclonal neutralizing antibodies (NAbs) show sharp reductions in their binding kinetics and neutralizing potential to B.1.351 and P.1, but not to B.1.1.7. These data have implications for the degree to which pre-existing immunity can protect against subsequent infection with VOC and informs policy makers of susceptibility to globally circulating SARS-CoV-2 VOC.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.26.21257441" rel="alternate" title="Emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern evade humoral immune responses from infection and vaccination (30 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.01.446640</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 infection studies in lung organoids identify TSPAN8 as novel mediator (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.664215+00:00</updated><author><name>Lisiena Hysenaj</name></author><author><name>Samantha Little</name></author><author><name>Kayla Kulhanek</name></author><author><name>Oghenekevwe M. Gbenedio</name></author><author><name>Lauren Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Alan Shen</name></author><author><name>Jean-Christophe Lone</name></author><author><name>Leonard C. Lupin-Jimenez</name></author><author><name>Luke R. Bonser</name></author><author><name>Nina K. Serwas</name></author><author><name>Kriti Bahl</name></author><author><name>Eran Mick</name></author><author><name>Jack Z. Li</name></author><author><name>Vivianne W. Ding</name></author><author><name>Shotaro Matsumoto</name></author><author><name>Mazharul Maishan</name></author><author><name>Camille Simoneau</name></author><author><name>Gabriela Fragiadakis</name></author><author><name>David M. Jablons</name></author><author><name>Charles R. Langelier</name></author><author><name>Michael Matthay</name></author><author><name>Melanie Ott</name></author><author><name>Matthew Krummel</name></author><author><name>Alexis J. Combes</name></author><author><name>Anita Sil</name></author><author><name>David J. Erle</name></author><author><name>Johannes R. Kratz</name></author><author><name>Jeroen P. Roose</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) is causing a global pandemic with large variation in COVID-19 disease spectrum. SARS-CoV-2 infection requires host receptor ACE2 on lung epithelium, but epithelial underpinnings of variation are largely unknown. We capitalized on comprehensive organoid assays to report remarkable variation in SARS-CoV-2 infection rates of lung organoids from different subjects. Tropism is highest for TUBA- and MUC5AC-positive organoid cells, but levels of TUBA-, MUC5A-, or ACE2-positive cells do not predict infection rate. We identify surface molecule Tetraspanin 8 (TSPAN8) as novel mediator of SARS-CoV-2 infection, which is not downregulated by this specific virus. TSPAN8 levels, prior to infection, strongly correlate with infection rate and TSPAN8-blocking antibodies diminish SARS-CoV-2 infection. We propose TSPAN8 as novel functional biomarker and potential therapeutic target for COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.01.446640" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 infection studies in lung organoids identify TSPAN8 as novel mediator (27 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.21258011</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 infectious virus, viral RNA in nasopharyngeal swabs, and serostatus of symptomatic COVID-19 outpatients in the United States (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.664801+00:00</updated><author><name>Katie R. Mollan</name></author><author><name>Joseph J. Eron</name></author><author><name>Taylor J. Krajewski</name></author><author><name>Wendy Painter</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth R. Duke</name></author><author><name>Caryn G. Morse</name></author><author><name>Erin A. Goecker</name></author><author><name>Lakshmanane Premkumar</name></author><author><name>Cameron R. Wolfe</name></author><author><name>Laura J. Szewczyk</name></author><author><name>Paul L. Alabanza</name></author><author><name>Amy James Loftis</name></author><author><name>Emily J. Degli-Angeli</name></author><author><name>Ariane J. Brown</name></author><author><name>Joan A. Dragavon</name></author><author><name>John J. Won</name></author><author><name>Jessica Keys</name></author><author><name>Michael G. Hudgens</name></author><author><name>David A. Wohl</name></author><author><name>Myron S. Cohen</name></author><author><name>Ralph S. Baric</name></author><author><name>Robert W. Coombs</name></author><author><name>Timothy P. Sheahan</name></author><author><name>William A. Fischer</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 infectious virus isolation in the upper airway of COVID-19 patients is associated with higher levels of viral RNA. However, comprehensive evaluation of the relationships between host and disease factors and infectious, replication competent virus is needed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Symptomatic COVID-19 outpatients were enrolled from the United States. Clinical symptoms were recorded via patient diary. Nasopharyngeal swabs were collected to quantitate SARS-CoV-2 RNA by reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction and for infectious virus isolation in Vero E6-cells. SARS-CoV-2 antibodies were measured in serum using a validated ELISA assay.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among 204 participants within one week of reported symptom onset (median=5, IQR 4-5 days), median age was 40 (min-max: 18-82 years), median nasopharyngeal viral RNA was 6.5 (IQR 4.7-7.6 log&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;/sub&gt; copies/mL), and 26% had detectable SARS-CoV-2 antibodies at baseline. Infectious virus was recovered in 7% of participants with antibodies compared to 58% of participants without antibodies (probability ratio (PR)=0.12, 95% CI: 0.04, 0.36; p=0.00016). Infectious virus isolation was also associated with higher levels of viral RNA (mean RNA difference +2.6 log&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;/sub&gt;, 95% CI: 2.2, 3.0; p&amp;lt;0.0001) and fewer days since symptom onset (PR=0.79, 95% CI: 0.71, 0.88 per day; p&amp;lt;0.0001).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The presence of SARS-CoV-2 antibodies is strongly associated with clearance of infectious virus isolation. Seropositivity and viral RNA are likely more reliable markers of infectious virus suppression than subjective measure of COVID-19 symptoms. Virus-targeted treatment and prevention strategies should be administered as early as possible and ideally before seroconversion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ridgeback Biotherapeutics, LP and NIH&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov"&gt;ClinicalTrials.gov&lt;/ext-link&gt; Identifier&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;NCT04405570&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Research in Context&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Evidence before this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A deeper understanding of the viral and host factors associated with infectious virus detection is essential to accurately identify and quarantine contagious individuals. Several studies have reported associations between SARS-CoV-2 virus isolation and viral RNA levels or time from symptom onset. However, little is known about which host factors (i.e. demographics, comorbidities, SARS-CoV-2 seropositivity, symptomatology etc.) are associated with infectious virus detection. A search of PubMed on 12 April 2021 using keywords “COVID-19” or “SARS-CoV-2” and “infectious virus isolation” yielded 14 publications that evaluated virus isolation from respiratory samples of SARS-CoV-2 infected individuals. Five of these studies were case reports or case series that included up to 5 individuals. Seven studies included cohorts of both outpatients and hospitalized individuals and found strong associations between virus isolation and time from symptom onset and viral RNA level. Of these seven, only two studies evaluated the association between SARS-CoV-2-specific antibodies and virus isolation, but were limited by the late timing of collection (&amp;gt;10 days after symptom onset) or the small number of participants included. The remaining two articles compared virus isolation with antigen and molecular based diagnostics and reviewed prior literature respectively. Collectively, these studies suggest that infectious virus isolation from nasopharyngeal swab samples is possible up to 10 days from symptom onset in individuals with mild disease and for longer in those with severe illness or an underlying immune deficiency. No study has systematically evaluated host, disease, and viral factors associated with infectious virus isolation in the same cohort.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Added value of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To better understand the host, disease, and viral factors associated with virus isolation in ambulatory individuals with COVID-19, we analyzed demographic, symptom, virologic, and SARS-CoV-2-specific antibody data at baseline entry to outpatient care from 204 individuals enrolled in a randomized placebo-controlled study of a novel oral therapeutic. Host characteristics were self-reported and viral RNA quantitation, virus isolation, and SARS-2 specific antibody testing (IgG, IgM, IgA and total Ig) were performed at central laboratories. This represents the largest evaluation of virus isolation from symptomatic outpatients with COVID-19 reported to date, and affords an important opportunity to understand which host, virus, and disease factors are associated with the presence and clearance of infectious virus in the nasopharynx. Consistent with prior studies, we found that isolation of replication competent SARS-CoV-2 &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; strongly correlated with both higher nasal viral qRT-PCR RNA levels and shorter time since symptom onset. Importantly, we also found that SARS-CoV-2 antibodies are strongly associated with the clearance of infectious virus, with virus isolation in 7% of seropositive individuals compared to 58% of seronegative individuals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Implications of all the available evidence&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our findings provide a comprehensive analysis of key virus, host, and disease factors associated with infectious virus isolation and suggest that antibody detection appears to be a more reliable marker of infectious virus clearance than patient-reported symptom duration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.21258011" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 infectious virus, viral RNA in nasopharyngeal swabs, and serostatus of symptomatic COVID-19 outpatients in the United States (27 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.29.21257760</id><title>Genomic epidemiology and associated clinical outcomes of a SARS-CoV-2 outbreak in a general adult hospital in Quebec (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.665342+00:00</updated><author><name>Bastien Paré</name></author><author><name>Marieke Rozendaal</name></author><author><name>Sacha Morin</name></author><author><name>Raphaël Poujol</name></author><author><name>Fatima Mostefai</name></author><author><name>Jean-Christophe Grenier</name></author><author><name>Léa Kaufmann</name></author><author><name>Henry Xing</name></author><author><name>Miguelle Sanchez</name></author><author><name>Ariane Yechouron</name></author><author><name>Ronald Racette</name></author><author><name>Julie Hussin</name></author><author><name>Guy Wolf</name></author><author><name>Ivan Pavlov</name></author><author><name>Martin A. Smith</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The first confirmed case of COVID-19 in Quebec, Canada, occurred at Verdun Hospital on February 25, 2020. A month later, a localized outbreak was observed at this hospital. We performed tiled amplicon whole genome nanopore sequencing on nasopharyngeal swabs from all SARS-CoV-2 positive samples from 31 March to 17 April 2020 in 2 local hospitals to assess the viral diversity of the outbreak. We report 264 viral genomes from 242 individuals (both staff and patients) with associated clinical features and outcomes, as well as longitudinal samples, technical replicates and the first publicly disseminated SARS-CoV-2 genomes in Quebec. Viral lineage assessment identified multiple subclades in both hospitals, with a predominant subclade in the Verdun outbreak, indicative of hospital-acquired transmission. Dimensionality reduction identified two subclades that evaded supervised lineage assignment methods, including Pangolin, and identified certain symptoms (headache, myalgia and sore throat) that are significantly associated with favorable patient outcomes. We also address certain limitations of standard SARS-CoV-2 bioinformatics procedures, notably when presented with multiple viral haplotypes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.29.21257760" rel="alternate" title="Genomic epidemiology and associated clinical outcomes of a SARS-CoV-2 outbreak in a general adult hospital in Quebec (18 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.21258007</id><title>Temporal stability and detection sensitivity of the dry swab-based diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2 (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.665828+00:00</updated><author><name>CG Gokulan</name></author><author><name>Uday Kiran</name></author><author><name>Santosh Kumar Kuncha</name></author><author><name>Rakesh K Mishra</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The rapid spread and evolution of various strains of SARS-CoV-2, the virus responsible for COVID-19, continues to challenge the disease controlling measures globally. Alarming concern is, the number of second wave infections surpassed the first wave and the onset of severe symptoms manifesting rapidly. In this scenario, testing of maximum population in less time and minimum cost with existing diagnostic amenities is the only possible way to control the spread of the virus. The previously described RNA extraction-free methods using dry swab have been shown to be advantageous in these critical times by different studies. In this work, we show the temporal stability and performance of the dry swab viral detection method at two different temperatures. Contrived dry swabs holding serially diluted SARS-CoV-2 strains A2a and A3i at 25°C (room temperature; RT) and 4°C were subjected to direct RT-PCR and compared with standard VTM-RNA based method. The results clearly indicate that dry swab method of RNA detection is as efficient as VTM-RNA-based method in both strains, when checked for up to 72 hours. The lesser C&lt;sub&gt;T&lt;/sub&gt; values of dry swab samples in comparison to that of the VTM-RNA samples suggest better sensitivity of the method within 48 hours of time. The results collectively suggest that dry swab samples are stable at RT for 24 hours and the detection of SARS-CoV-2 RNA by RT-PCR do not show variance from VTM-RNA. This extraction free, direct RT-PCR method holds phenomenal standing in the present life-threatening circumstances due to SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.21258007" rel="alternate" title="Temporal stability and detection sensitivity of the dry swab-based diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2 (10 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.29.445137</id><title>Functional characterization of SARS-CoV-2 vaccine elicited antibodies in immunologically naïve and pre-immune humans (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.667034+00:00</updated><author><name>David Forgacs</name></author><author><name>Hyesun Jang</name></author><author><name>Rodrigo B. Abreu</name></author><author><name>Hannah B. Hanley</name></author><author><name>Jasper L. Gattiker</name></author><author><name>Alexandria M. Jefferson</name></author><author><name>Ted M. Ross</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;As the COVID-19 pandemic continues, the authorization of vaccines for emergency use has been crucial in slowing down the rate of infection and transmission of the SARS-CoV-2 virus that causes COVID-19. In order to investigate the longitudinal serological responses to SARS-CoV-2 natural infection and vaccination, a large-scale, multi-year serosurveillance program entitled SPARTA (SARS SeroPrevalence and Respiratory Tract Assessment) was initiated at 4 locations in the U.S. The serological assay presented here measuring IgG binding to the SARS-CoV-2 receptor binding domain (RBD) detected antibodies elicited by SARS-CoV-2 infection or vaccination with a 95.5% sensitivity and a 95.9% specificity. We used this assay to screen more than 3100 participants and selected 20 previously infected pre-immune and 32 immunologically naïve participants to analyze their antibody binding to RBD and viral neutralization (VN) responses following vaccination with two doses of either the Pfizer-BioNTech BNT162b2 or the Moderna mRNA-1273 vaccine. Vaccination not only elicited a more robust immune reaction than natural infection, but the level of neutralizing and anti-RBD antibody binding after vaccination is also significantly higher in pre-immune participants compared to immunologically naïve participants (&lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt;&amp;lt;0.0033). Furthermore, the administration of the second vaccination did not further increase the neutralizing or binding antibody levels in pre-immune participants (&lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt;=0.69). However, ~46% of the immunologically naïve participants required both vaccinations to seroconvert.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.29.445137" rel="alternate" title="Functional characterization of SARS-CoV-2 vaccine elicited antibodies in immunologically naïve and pre-immune humans (9 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.02.21258218</id><title>Whole blood-based measurement of SARS-CoV-2-specific T cell responses reveals asymptomatic infection and vaccine efficacy in healthy subjects and patients with solid organ cancers (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.667469+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin J. Scurr</name></author><author><name>Wioleta M. Zelek</name></author><author><name>George Lippiatt</name></author><author><name>Michelle Somerville</name></author><author><name>Stephanie E. A. Burnell</name></author><author><name>Lorenzo Capitani</name></author><author><name>Kate Davies</name></author><author><name>Helen Lawton</name></author><author><name>Thomas Tozer</name></author><author><name>Tara Rees</name></author><author><name>Kerry Roberts</name></author><author><name>Mererid Evans</name></author><author><name>Amanda Jackson</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Young</name></author><author><name>Lucy Fairclough</name></author><author><name>Mark Wills</name></author><author><name>Andrew D. Westwell</name></author><author><name>B. Paul Morgan</name></author><author><name>Awen Gallimore</name></author><author><name>Andrew Godkin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Accurate assessment of SARS-CoV-2 immunity in the population is critical to evaluating vaccine efficacy and devising public health policies. Whilst the exact nature of effective immunity remains incompletely defined, SARS-CoV-2-specific T cell responses are a critical feature of the immune response that will likely form a key correlate of protection against COVID-19. Here, we developed and optimised a high-throughput whole blood-based assay to determine the T cell response associated with prior SARS-CoV-2 infection and/or vaccination amongst 156 healthy donors and 67 cancer patients. Following overnight &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; stimulation with SARS-CoV-2-specific peptides, blood plasma samples were harvested and analysed for T&lt;sub&gt;H&lt;/sub&gt;1-type effector cytokines (IFN-γ and IL-2). Amongst healthy donors, highly significant differential IFN-γ&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;/IL-2&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; SARS-CoV-2-specific T cell responses were seen amongst vaccinated or previously infected COVID-19-positive individuals in comparison to unknown/naïve individuals (P &amp;lt; 0.0001). IL-2 production from T cells in response to SARS-CoV-2 derived antigens was a highly predictive diagnostic assay (P &amp;lt; 0.0001; 96.0% sensitivity, 93.9% specificity); measurement of IFN-γ&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; SARS-CoV-2 specific T cell responses was equally effective at identifying asymptomatic (antibody and T cell positive) participants. A single dose of COVID-19 vaccine induced IFN-γ and/or IL-2 SARS-CoV-2-specific T cell responses in 28/29 (96.6%) of healthy donors, reducing significantly to 27/56 (48.2%) when measured in cancer patients (P = 0.0003). Overall, this cost-effective standardisable test ensures accurate and comparable assessments of SARS-CoV-2-specific T cell responses amenable to widespread population immunity testing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.02.21258218" rel="alternate" title="Whole blood-based measurement of SARS-CoV-2-specific T cell responses reveals asymptomatic infection and vaccine efficacy in healthy subjects and patients with solid organ cancers (6 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.21257591</id><title>Chronic SARS-CoV-2 infection and viral evolution in a hypogammaglobulinaemic individual. (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.667894+00:00</updated><author><name>Maia Kavanagh Williamson</name></author><author><name>Fergus Hamilton</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Hutchings</name></author><author><name>Hannah M Pymont</name></author><author><name>Mark Hackett</name></author><author><name>David Arnold</name></author><author><name>Nick Maskell</name></author><author><name>Alasdair P MacGowan</name></author><author><name>mahableshwar Albur</name></author><author><name>Megan Jenkins</name></author><author><name>Izak Heys</name></author><author><name>Francesca Knapper</name></author><author><name>Mustafa Elsayed</name></author><author><name>Rachel Milligan</name></author><author><name>Peter Muir</name></author><author><name>Barry Vipond</name></author><author><name>David A Matthews</name></author><author><name>Ed Moran</name></author><author><name>Andrew D. D. Davidson</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;There is widespread interest in the capacity for SARS-CoV-2 evolution in the face of selective pressures from host immunity, either naturally acquired post-exposure or from vaccine acquired immunity. Allied to this is the potential for long perm persistent infections within immune compromised individuals to allow a broader range of viral evolution in the face of sub-optimal immune driven selective pressure. Here we report on an immunocompromised individual who is hypogammaglobulinaemic and was persistently infected with SARS-CoV-2 for over 290 days, the longest persistent infection recorded in the literature to date. During this time, nine samples of viral nucleic acid were obtained and analysed by next-generation sequencing. Initially only a single mutation (L179I) was detected in the spike protein relative to the prototypic SARS-CoV-2 Wuhan-Hu-1 isolate, with no further changes identified at day 58. However, by day 155 the spike protein had acquired a further four amino acid changes, namely S255F, S477N, H655Y and D1620A and a two amino acid deletion (ΔH69/ΔV70). Infectious virus was cultured from a nasopharyngeal sample taken on day 155 and next-generation sequencing confirmed that the mutations in the virus mirrored those identified by sequencing of the corresponding swab sample. The isolated virus was susceptible to remdesivir in vitro, however a 17-day course of remdesivir started on day 213 had no effect on the viral RT-PCR cycle threshold (Ct) value. On day 265 the patient was treated with the combination of casirivimab and imdevimab. The patient experienced progressive resolution of all symptoms over the next 8 weeks and by day 311 the virus was no longer detectable by RT-PCR. The ΔH69/ΔV70 deletion in the N-terminus of the spike protein which arose in our patient is also present in the B.1.1.7 variant of concern and has been associated with viral escape mutagenesis after treatment of another immunocompromised patient with convalescent plasma. Our data confirms the significance of this deletion in immunocompromised patients but illustrates it can arise independently of passive antibody transfer, suggesting the deletion may be an enabling mutation that compensates for distant changes in the spike protein that arise under selective pressure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.21257591" rel="alternate" title="Chronic SARS-CoV-2 infection and viral evolution in a hypogammaglobulinaemic individual. (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.03.447023</id><title>Immunological profiling of COVID-19 patients with pulmonary sequelae (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.668305+00:00</updated><author><name>Jianghua Wu</name></author><author><name>Lu Tang</name></author><author><name>Yanling Ma</name></author><author><name>Yu Li</name></author><author><name>Dong-Mei Zhang</name></author><author><name>Qian Li</name></author><author><name>Heng Mei</name></author><author><name>Yu Hu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cellular immunity may be involved in organ damage and rehabilitation in patients with coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). We aimed to delineate immunological features of COVID-19 patients with pulmonary sequelae (PS) one year after discharge. 50 COVID-19 survivors were recruited and classified according to radiological characteristics: 24 patients with PS and 26 patients without PS. Phenotypic and functional characteristics of immune cells were evaluated by multiparametric flow cytometry. Patients with PS had an increased proportion of natural killer (NK) cells and lower percentage of B cells compared to patients without PS. Phenotypic and functional features of T cells in patients with PS were predominated by the accumulation of CD4+ T cells secreting IL-17A, short-lived effector-like CD8+ T cells (CD27-CD62L-) and senescent T cells with excessive secretion of granzyme-B/perforin/IFN-γ. NK cells were characterized by the excessive secretion of granzyme-B and perforin and the downregulation of NKP30 and NKP46; highly activated NKT and γδ T cells exhibited NKP30 and TIM-3 upregulation and NKB1 downregulation in patients with PS. However, immunosuppressive cells were comparable between the two groups. The interrelation of immune cells in COVID-19 was intrinsically identified, whereby T cells secreting IL-2, IL-4 and IL-17A were enriched among CD28+ and CD57- cells and cells secreting perforin/granzyme-B/IFN-γ/TNF-α expressed markers of terminal differentiation. CD57+NK cells, CD4+perforin+ T cells and CD8+CD27+CD62L+ T cells were identified as the independent predictors for residual lesions. Overall, our findings unveil the profound imbalance of immune landscape that may correlate with organ damage and rehabilitation in COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.03.447023" rel="alternate" title="Immunological profiling of COVID-19 patients with pulmonary sequelae (5 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>