<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>BioRxiv or medRxiv preprints about COVID posted in the last week with at least 5 tweets</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.186186+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.21257107</id><title>The Impact of Universal Transport Media and Viral Transport Media Liquid Samples on a SARS-CoV-2 Rapid Antigen Test (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.268596+00:00</updated><author><name>J Mayfield</name></author><author><name>P Hesse</name></author><author><name>D Ledden</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The impact of universal transport media (UTM) and viral transport media (VTM) liquid samples on the performance of the Healgen Scientific Rapid COVID-19 Antigen Test was investigated. Twelve different UTM/VTM liquid samples were added at different dilutions to the extraction buffer, and 2 of 12 generated false-positive results. To understand the cause of these false-positive results, the effect of extraction buffer dilution on sample pH, surfactant concentration, and ionic strength were investigated. The most important factor in UTM/VTM liquid sample dilution of the extraction buffer was ionic strength as measured by conductivity. Dilutions with conductivity below ∼17 mS/cm can induce a false-positive result. It was also noted that the ionic strength of UTM/VTMs can vary, and those with low ionic strength can be problematic. To rule out the effect of other common components found in UTMs/VTMs, several materials were mixed with extraction buffer and tested at high concentrations. None was shown to produce false-positive results.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.21257125</id><title>COVID-19 Serology in New York State Using a Multiplex Microsphere Immunoassay (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.267504+00:00</updated><author><name>Danielle T. Hunt</name></author><author><name>Jennifer L. Yates</name></author><author><name>Karen E. Kulas</name></author><author><name>Kyle Carson</name></author><author><name>Theresa Lamson</name></author><author><name>Valerie Demarest</name></author><author><name>Andrea Furuya</name></author><author><name>Kelly Howard</name></author><author><name>Mary Marchewka</name></author><author><name>Randy Stone</name></author><author><name>Heidi Tucker</name></author><author><name>Casey Warszycki</name></author><author><name>Jim Yee</name></author><author><name>He S. Yang</name></author><author><name>Sabrina Racine-Brzostek</name></author><author><name>Zhen Zhao</name></author><author><name>Monir Ejemel</name></author><author><name>Qi Li</name></author><author><name>Yang Wang</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Fernando</name></author><author><name>Francesca La Carpia</name></author><author><name>Eldad A. Hod</name></author><author><name>Kathleen A. McDonough</name></author><author><name>William T. Lee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The emergence of SARS-CoV-2, leading to COVID-19, necessitated the development of new molecular and serological tests.  Here, we describe a multiplexed serological assay developed as the global pandemic moved into New York State in the spring of 2020.  The original microsphere immunoassay used a target antigen from the SARS-CoV-1 virus responsible for the 2003 SARS outbreak, but evolved to incorporate multiple SARS-CoV-2 protein antigens (nucleocapsid, spike and spike domains, spike and nucleocapsid proteins from seasonal human coronaviruses).  Besides being highly versatile due to multiplex capabilities, the assay was highly specific and sensitive and adaptable to measuring both total antibodies and antibody isotypes. While determining the assay performance characteristics,  we were able to identify antibody production patterns (e.g., kinetics of isotypes, individual variations) for total antibodies and individual antibody classes.  Overall, the results provide insights into the laboratory response to new serology needs, and how the evolution and fine-tuning of a serology assay helped contribute to a better understanding of the antibody response to SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.21256995</id><title>Magnetofluidic platform for rapid multiplexed screening of SARS-CoV-2 variants and respiratory pathogens (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.266502+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Y. Trick</name></author><author><name>Fan-En Chen</name></author><author><name>Liben Chen</name></author><author><name>Pei-Wei Lee</name></author><author><name>Alexander C. Hasnain</name></author><author><name>Heba H. Mostafa</name></author><author><name>Karen C. Carroll</name></author><author><name>Tza-Huei Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The rise of highly transmissible SARS-CoV-2 variants brings new challenges and concerns with vaccine efficacy, diagnostic sensitivity, and public health responses in the fight to end the pandemic. Widespread detection of variant strains will be critical to inform policy decisions to mitigate further spread, and post-pandemic multiplexed screening of respiratory viruses will be necessary to properly manage patients presenting with similar respiratory symptoms. In this work, we have developed a portable, magnetofluidic cartridge platform for automated PCR testing in &amp;lt;30 min. Cartridges were designed for multiplexed detection of SARS-CoV-2 with either distinctive variant mutations or with Influenza A and B. The platform demonstrated a limit of detection down to 2 copies/µL SARS-CoV-2 RNA with successful identification of B.1.1.7 and B.1.351 variants. The multiplexed SARS-CoV-2/Flu assay was validated using archived clinical nasopharyngeal swab eluates (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; = 116) with an overall sensitivity/specificity of 98.1%/95.2%, 85.7%/100%, 100%/98.2%, respectively, for SARS-CoV-2, Influenza A, and Influenza B. Further testing with saliva (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; = 14) demonstrated successful detection of all SARS-CoV-2 positive samples with no false-positives.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443289</id><title>Hyperinflammation evokes different antiviral TMPRSS2 and ADAM17 expression responses in human gut xenograft versus host mouse gut although overall genomic responses are similar (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.265380+00:00</updated><author><name>Lorna Morris</name></author><author><name>Einat Nisim-Eliraz</name></author><author><name>Iftach Schouten</name></author><author><name>François Bergey</name></author><author><name>Nigel Dyer</name></author><author><name>Hiroshi Momiji</name></author><author><name>Eilam Nir</name></author><author><name>Noga Marsiano</name></author><author><name>Raheleh Sheibani Tezerji</name></author><author><name>Simcha Yagel</name></author><author><name>Philip Rosenstiel</name></author><author><name>David Rand</name></author><author><name>Vitor A.P. Martins dos Santos</name></author><author><name>Nahum Y. Shpigel</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The global spread of the newly emerged severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) has led to the pandemic outbreak of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), an inflammatory disease that is primarily affecting the respiratory system. However, gastrointestinal symptoms in COVID-19 patients suggests that the gut may present another viral target organ. Disease development and severity is dependent on viral interaction with two cell surface human proteins, ACE2 and TMPRSS2, and on antiviral response which may lead to systemic hyperinflammatory syndrome and multiorgan dysfunction. Understanding the host response to SARS-CoV-2 infection and the pathology of the disease will be greatly enhanced by the development of appropriate animal models. Laboratory mice have been the mainstay of therapeutic and vaccine development, however, the virus does not grow in wild type mice and only induced mild disease in transgenic animals expressing human ACE2. As there are known differences between immune response in laboratory mice and humans we evaluated the response of human gut developed as xenografts and host mouse gut following systemic LPS injections as a hyperinflammation model system. The orthologous gene expression levels in the mouse and human gut were highly correlated (Spearman’s rank correlation coefficient: 0.28–0.76) and gene set enrichment analysis of significantly upregulated human and mouse genes revealed that a number of inflammatory and immune response pathways are commonly regulated in the two species. However, species differences were also observed, most importantly, in the inflamed human gut but not in the mouse gut, there was clear upregulation of mRNAs coding for TMPRSS2, ADAM17 and for RIG-I-like receptors, which are involved in the recognition of viruses and in antiviral innate immune response. Moreover, using species-specific immunofluorescence microscopy, we demonstrated the expression and localization of human ACE2 and TMPRSS2 proteins, which are essential elements of the molecular machinery that enables SARS-CoV-2 to infect and replicate in human gut cells. Our findings demonstrate that the intestinal immune response to inflammation in humans and mice are generally very similar. However, certain human-specific diseases, such as COVID-19, can only be successfully studied in an experimental model of human tissue, such as the gut xenograft.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.04.21255000</id><title>COVID-19 Compromises in the Medical Practice and the Consequential Effect on Endometriosis Patients (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.264676+00:00</updated><author><name>Shaked Ashkenazi</name></author><author><name>Ole Linvåg Huseby</name></author><author><name>Gard Kroken</name></author><author><name>Adrian Soto-Mota</name></author><author><name>Marius Pents</name></author><author><name>Alessandra Loschiavo</name></author><author><name>Roksana Lewandowska</name></author><author><name>Grace Tran</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Kwiatkowski</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background and purpose&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to the ongoing coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic, self-isolation practices aimed to curb the spread of COVID-19 have severely complicated the medical management of patients suffering from endometriosis and their physical and mental well- being. Endometriosis, the main cause for chronic pelvic pain (CPP), is a highly prevalent disease characterized by the presence of endometrial tissue in locations outside the uterine cavity that affects up to 10% of women in their reproductive age. This study aimed to explore the effects of the global COVID-19 pandemic on patients suffering from endometriosis across multiple countries, and to investigate the different approaches to the medical management of these patients based on their self-reported experiences.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A cross-sectional survey, partially based on validated quality of life questionnaires for endometriosis patients, was initially created in English, which was then reviewed by experts. Through the process of assessing face and content validity, the questionnaire was then translated to fifteen different languages following the WHO recommendations for medical translation. After evaluation, the questionnaire was converted into a web form and distributed across different platforms. An analysis of 2964 responses of participants from 59 countries suffering from self-reported endometriosis was then conducted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The data shows an association between COVID-19 imposed compromises with the reported worsening of the mental state of the participants, as well as with the aggravation of their symptoms. For the 1174 participants who had their medical appointments cancelled, 43.7% (n=513) reported that their symptoms had been aggravated, and 49.3% (n=579) reported that their mental state had worsened. In comparison, of the 1180 participants who kept their appointments, only 29.4% (n=347) stated that their symptoms had been aggravated, and 27.5% (n=325) stated their mental health had worsened. 610 participants did not have medical appointments scheduled, and these participants follow a similar pattern as the participants who kept their appointments, with 29.0% (n=177) reporting aggravation of symptoms and 28.2% (n=172) reporting that their mental state had worsened.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;These findings suggest that COVID-19 pandemic has had a clinically significant negative effect on the mental and physical well-being of participants suffering from endometriosis based on their self-reported experiences. Thus, they show the importance of further assessment and reevaluation of the current and future management of this condition in medical practices worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.06.21256773</id><title>Risk of COVID-19 infection and work place exposure of front-line mass media professionals (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.264377+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarabon Tahura</name></author><author><name>Bilkis Banu</name></author><author><name>Nasrin Akter</name></author><author><name>Sarder Mahmud Hossain</name></author><author><name>Rashidul Alam Mahumud</name></author><author><name>Md Rishad Ahmed</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mass media plays a crucial role in creating awareness and knowledge sharing in this Corona virus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic. However, the risk of exposure and extent of COVID-19 infection among media professional are less elucidated yet. Therefore, this study was intended to investigate the workplace-related risk of COVID-19 exposure and the association between exposure to COVID-19 and participant’s characteristics, including various forms of respiratory protection for mass-media professionals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This closed web-based cross-sectional survey was conducted among 199 mass-media professionals in Bangladesh by snowball sampling approach. A multivariate logistic regression model was used for the analytical exploration. Adjusted and Unadjusted Odds Ratio (OR) with 95% confidence intervals (95% CI) were calculated for the specified exposures. Chi-square test was used to observe the association. Ethical issues were maintained according to the guidance of the declaration of the Helsinki.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of all, 39.2% of mass-media professionals were tested positive for COVID-19, whereas 6% of symptomatic or suspected participants did not do the test. Mass media professionals who worked in electronic media reported more COVID-19 infection (adjusted odds ratio, AOR= 6.25; 95% Confidence interval: Lower limit 1.43, upper limit 27.43; P =0.02). However, no significant relationship was found between the type of job role and COVID-19 infection. Furthermore, infected colleagues (OR/P=1.92/0.04) were identified as significant contact of acquiring infection. However, the study result showed that reused/new medical mask, homemade/cloth-made mask (vs. use of respirator mask) was not significantly (p=0.82) associated with mass media professional’s infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Professionals working in electronic media were at higher risk of being infected by COVID-19 and mostly acquired from infected colleagues. Using a respirator mask was not associated with a lower risk of test positive infection in mass media professionals. This study will aid the policy maker and public health authorities during the COVID-19 pandemic to make proper implementation strategies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.07.21256743</id><title>Effect of using personal protective equipment during the COVID-19 pandemic on the quality indicators of screening colonoscopies (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.264087+00:00</updated><author><name>Subin Chirayath</name></author><author><name>Janak Bahirwani</name></author><author><name>Parampreet Kaur</name></author><author><name>Noel Martins</name></author><author><name>Ronak Modi</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background and Aims&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) has affected many facets of the practice of medicine including screening colonoscopies. Our study looks to observe if there has been an effect on the quality of colonoscopies, as indicated by quality measures such as cecal intubation rate (CIR), cecal intubation time (CIT), scope withdrawal time (SWT) and adenoma detection rate (ADR) with the adoption of standard COVID-19 precautions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted a retrospective chart review to analyze the effects of the COVID-19 pandemic on screening colonoscopies. The study utilized data on CIR, CIT, SWT and ADR from outpatient, non-emergent procedures conducted at 3 endoscopy suites of St Luke’s University Health Network. All inpatient and emergent procedures were excluded. Data was obtained by performing chart review on EPIC electronic health record.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our study demonstrated that the total number of screening colonoscopies was decreased between 2019 to 2020 (318 in 2019 vs 157 in 2020, p= 0.005). CIT (320±105 seconds in 2019 vs 392±107 seconds in 2020, p=0.001) and SWT (706±232 seconds in 2019 vs 830±241 seconds in 2020, p=0.001) were increased while CIR (98.2% in 2019 vs 96.6% in 2020, p=0.04) was decreased between 2019 and 2020 likely due to PPE introduction. ADR was similar between the two groups (38.23 (12.50-66.66) in 2019 vs 38.18(16.66-66.00) in 2020, p=0.8).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our study showed that quality indices for screening colonoscopies like cecal intubation rate, cecal intubation time and scope withdrawal time were negatively impacted during the initial COVID time period compared to pre-COVID time. The study also displayed that though there was a significant decline in both screening and diagnostic colonoscopies during pandemic, adenoma detection rates were comparable. Thus, the efficiency of the procedures was affected by the use of PPE but it did not affect the colonoscopy’s clinical benefit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.21256935</id><title>Identifying risk factors for COVID-19 severity and mortality in the UK Biobank (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.263153+00:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Madakkatel</name></author><author><name>Catherine King</name></author><author><name>Ang Zhou</name></author><author><name>Anwar Mulugeta</name></author><author><name>Amanda Lumsden</name></author><author><name>Mark McDonnell</name></author><author><name>Elina Hyppönen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus has infected over 114 million people worldwide as of March 2021, with worldwide mortality rates ranging between 1-10%. We use information on up to 421,111 UK Biobank participants to identify possible predictors for long-term susceptibility to severe COVID-19 infection (&lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt; =1,088) and mortality (&lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt; =376). We include 36,168 predictors in our analyses and use a gradient boosting decision tree (GBDT) algorithm and feature attribution based on Shapley values, together with traditional epidemiological approaches to identify possible risk factors. Our analyses show associations between socio-demographic factors (e.g. age, sex, ethnicity, education, material deprivation, accommodation type) and lifestyle indicators (e.g. smoking, physical activity, walking pace, tea intake, and dietary changes) with risk of developing severe COVID-19 symptoms. Blood (cystatin C, C-reactive protein, gamma glutamyl transferase and alkaline phosphatase) and urine (microalbuminuria) biomarkers measured more than 10 years earlier predicted severe COVID-19. We also confirm increased risks for several pre-existing disease outcomes (e.g. lung diseases, type 2 diabetes, hypertension, circulatory diseases, anemia, and mental disorders). Analyses on mortality were possible within a sub-group testing positive for COVID-19 infection (&lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt; =1,953) with our analyses confirming association between age, smoking status, and prior primary diagnosis of urinary tract infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our hypothesis-free approach combining machine learning with traditional epidemiological methods finds a number of risk factors (sociodemographic, lifestyle, and psychosocial factors, biomarkers, disease outcomes and treatments) associated with developing severe COVID-19 symptoms and COVID-19 mortality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.07.21256742</id><title>INDIA’S PRAGMATIC VACCINATION STRATEGY AGAINST COVID-19: A MATHEMATICAL
                    MODELLING BASED ANALYSIS (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.262556+00:00</updated><author><name>Sandip Mandal</name></author><author><name>Nimalan Arinaminpathy</name></author><author><name>Balram Bhargava</name></author><author><name>Samiran Panda</name></author><content>
                &lt;sec&gt;
                    &lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;To investigate the impact of targeted vaccination strategies on
                        morbidity and mortality due to COVID-19, as well as on the incidence of
                        SARS-CoV-2, in India.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/sec&gt;
                &lt;sec&gt;
                    &lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Mathematical modelling.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/sec&gt;
                &lt;sec&gt;
                    &lt;title&gt;Settings&lt;/title&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Indian epidemic of COVID-19 and vulnerable population.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/sec&gt;
                &lt;sec&gt;
                    &lt;title&gt;Data sources&lt;/title&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Country specific and age-segregated pattern of social contact, case
                        fatality rate and demographic data obtained from peer-reviewed literature
                        and public domain.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/sec&gt;
                &lt;sec&gt;
                    &lt;title&gt;Model&lt;/title&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;An age-structured dynamical model describing SARS-CoV-2 transmission in
                        India incorporating uncertainty in natural history parameters was
                        constructed.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/sec&gt;
                &lt;sec&gt;
                    &lt;title&gt;Interventions&lt;/title&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Comparison of different vaccine strategies by targeting priority groups
                        such as key workers including health care professionals, individuals with
                        comorbidities (24 – 60 year), and all above 60.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/sec&gt;
                &lt;sec&gt;
                    &lt;title&gt;Main outcome measures&lt;/title&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Incidence reduction and averted deaths in different scenarios, assuming
                        that the current restrictions are fully lifted as vaccination is
                        implemented.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/sec&gt;
                &lt;sec&gt;
                    &lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;The priority groups together account for about 18% of India’s
                        population. An infection preventing vaccine with 60% efficacy covering all
                        these groups would reduce peak symptomatic incidence by 20.6% (95%
                        uncertainty intervals (CrI) 16.7 - 25.4), and cumulative mortality by 29.7%
                        (95% CrI 25.8-33.8). A similar vaccine with ability to prevent symptoms (but
                        not infection) will reduce peak incidence of symptomatic cases by 10.4% (95%
                        CrI 8.4 – 13.0), and cumulative mortality by 32.9% (95% CrI 28.6 - 37.3). In
                        the event of insufficient vaccine supply to cover all priority groups, model
                        projections suggest that after keyworkers, vaccine strategy should
                        prioritise all who are &amp;gt; 60, and subsequently individuals with
                        comorbidities. In settings with weakest transmission, such as
                        sparsely-populated rural areas, those with comorbidities should be
                        prioritised after keyworkers.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/sec&gt;
                &lt;sec&gt;
                    &lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;An appropriately targeted vaccination strategy would witness substantial
                        mitigation of impact of COVID-19 in a country like India with wide
                        heterogenity. ‘Smart vaccination’, based on public health considerations,
                        rather than mass vaccination, appears prudent.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/sec&gt;
                &lt;sec&gt;
                    &lt;label /&gt;
                    &lt;boxed-text id="box1" position="float" orientation="portrait"&gt;
                        &lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;Strengths and limitation of this
                            study&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                        &lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;
                            &lt;list-item&gt;
                                &lt;p&gt;The model in this study is informed by age-dependent risk
                                    factors for SARS-CoV-2 infection among contacts, and is
                                    stratified by co-morbidities (diabetes and/or hypertension), and
                                    vaccination status.&lt;/p&gt;
                            &lt;/list-item&gt;
                            &lt;list-item&gt;
                                &lt;p&gt;Data on mortality and large-scale contact tracing from
                                    within India, and the recent national sero-survey results were
                                    used, which constituted a major strength of this
                                    investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
                            &lt;/list-item&gt;
                            &lt;list-item&gt;
                                &lt;p&gt;Distinguishing between ‘infection’ and ‘symptomatic disease
                                    ‘ preventing vaccines, the model was simulated under a range of
                                    scenarios for the basic reproduction number (R0).&lt;/p&gt;
                            &lt;/list-item&gt;
                            &lt;list-item&gt;
                                &lt;p&gt;Should they have been available, real life country-specific
                                    data on excess risks of deaths due to comorbidities would have
                                    added strength to the presented model.&lt;/p&gt;
                            &lt;/list-item&gt;
                            &lt;list-item&gt;
                                &lt;p&gt;Key priority group-specific data on social mixing and
                                    potential associated transmission was not available, and
                                    remained as a limitation.&lt;/p&gt;
                            &lt;/list-item&gt;
                        &lt;/list&gt;
                    &lt;/boxed-text&gt;
                &lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.06.21256769</id><title>Pharmacogenomic and drug interaction risk associations with hospital length of stay among Medicare Advantage members with COVID-19 (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.261980+00:00</updated><author><name>Kristine Ashcraft</name></author><author><name>Chad Moretz</name></author><author><name>Chantelle Schenning</name></author><author><name>Susan Rojahn</name></author><author><name>Kae Vines Tanudtanud</name></author><author><name>Gwyn Omar Magoncia</name></author><author><name>Justine Reyes</name></author><author><name>Bernardo Marquez</name></author><author><name>Yinglong Guo</name></author><author><name>Elif Tokar Erdemir</name></author><author><name>Taryn O. Hall</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 has severely impacted older populations and strained healthcare resources, with many patients requiring long periods of hospitalization. Reducing the hospital length of stay (LOS) reduces patient and hospital burden. Given that adverse drug reactions are known to prolong LOS, unmanaged pharmacogenomic risk and drug interactions among COVID-19 patients may be a risk factor for longer hospital stays.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The objective of this study was to determine if pharmacogenomic and drug interaction risks were associated with longer lengths of stay among high-risk patients hospitalized with COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Retrospective cohort study of medical and pharmacy claims&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Administrative database from a large U.S. health insurance company&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Medicare Advantage members with a first COVID-19 hospitalization between January 2020 and June 2020, who did not die during the stay.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Exposures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;(1) Pharmacogenetic interaction probability (PIP) of ≤25% (low), 26%–50% (moderate), or &amp;gt;50% (high), which indicate the likelihood that one or more clinically actionable gene-drug or gene-drug-drug interactions would be identified with testing; (2) drug-drug interaction (DDI) severity of minimal, minor, moderate, major, or contraindicated, which indicate the severity of an interaction between two or more active medications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Outcomes and Measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The primary outcome was hospital length of stay. Results were stratified by hierarchical condition categories (HCC) counts and chronic conditions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A total of 6,025 patients hospitalized with COVID-19 were included in the study. Patients with moderate or high PIP were hospitalized for 9% (CI: 4%–15%; p &amp;lt; 0.001) and 16% longer (CI: 8%–24%; p &amp;lt; 0.001), respectively, compared to those with low PIP, whereas RAF score was not associated with LOS. High PIP was significantly associated with 12%–22% longer lengths of stay compared to low PIP in patients with hypertension, hyperlipidemia, diabetes, or COPD. Finally, among patients with 2 or 3 HCCs, a 10% longer length of stay was observed among patients with moderate or more severe DDI compared to minimal or minor DDI.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions and Relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Proactively mitigating pharmacogenomic risk has the potential to reduce length of stay in patients hospitalized with COVID-19 especially those with COPD, diabetes, hyperlipidemia, and hypertension.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key Points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Question&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;What is the impact of unmanaged pharmacogenomic risk among patients hospitalized with COVID-19?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among 6,025 patients hospitalized with COVID-19, those with greater unmanaged pharmacogenomic risk for adverse drug reactions had longer hospital stays than those with lower risk, both within the entire cohort and within groups matched by number and type of chronic conditions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Meaning&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preemptive pharmacogenomic testing may shorten hospital stay by reducing adverse drug reactions among seriously ill patients and more broadly improve patient risk classification, care utilization predictions, and health system performance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.21256929</id><title>INFLUENCE OF NOVEL CORONAVIRUS DISEASE (COVID-19) ON PARKINSON’S DISEASE: SYSTEMATIC REVIEW (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.261560+00:00</updated><author><name>Vikash Jaiswal</name></author><author><name>Danah Alquraish</name></author><author><name>Shavy Nagpal</name></author><author><name>Dattatreya Mukherjee</name></author><author><name>Prakriti Singh Shrestha</name></author><author><name>Diana Sanchez Velazco</name></author><author><name>Prathima Guntipalli</name></author><author><name>Arushee Bhatnagar</name></author><author><name>Saloni Savani</name></author><author><name>Eldamhalji Halilaj</name></author><author><name>Samir Ruxmohan</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1.&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The novel Coronavirus (COVID-19) infection has affected the population with various medical issues including the underlying neurological comorbidities such as Parkinson disease. COVID – 19 is found to bind with the host angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) receptors for viral entry. ACE2 receptors are normally expressed in various body surfaces as well as in the neurons and glial cells where they act as an entry port to SARS-CoV-2 infection to invade the central nervous system (CNS). ACE2 are also highly expressed in dopamine neurons which might worsen the outcome in terms of motor symptoms in PD with the treatment course. It may lead to an indirect response via immune-mediated cytokine storms and propagate through CNS leading to damage. Parkinson’s disease has also been noticed due to certain post-viral infections apart from COVID-19 such as, HSV, Influenza virus A, Measles virus, Cytomegalovirus and Mumps (Olsen et al, 2018). We aim to provide a thorough review on neurological outcomes and impact of COVID-19 in Parkinson disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A systematic review was conducted to analyze the impact of COVID-19 in patients with Parkinson disease (&amp;gt; 21 yo). Systematic literature search was done using PubMed, Science Direct, Google Scholar and Cochrane databases. PRISMA guidelines were followed summarized in Fig. 3 for study acquisition.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of the Parkinson’s patients that were tested positive for SARS-CoV-2, worsening of motor symptoms were reported along with other COVID-19 symptoms (Fig. 4 and 5). These symptoms include bradykinesia, tremors, gait disturbances, delirium and dementia and severe spasms of arms and legs. Encephalopathy was also one of the main symptoms presented in two of the studies. Increased mortality rates were identified for those who were hospitalized due to COVID-19 and PD when compared to other patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Parkinson’s disease may experience substantial worsening of motor and non -motor symptoms during COVID 19. Due to the novelty of the virus, studies were reported from recent years and further extensive studies are needed to explore more about the disease severity and neurological outcomes when compared to other non-PD patients. Authors identify this as a limitation for this paper. Additional studies are needed to understand the role of ACE2 in increasing vulnerability to viruses and role of ACE inhibitors as treatment modality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443474</id><title>Binding of SARS-CoV-2 fusion peptide to host membranes (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.261058+00:00</updated><author><name>Stefan L. Schaefer</name></author><author><name>Hendrik Jung</name></author><author><name>Gerhard Hummer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During infection the SARS-CoV-2 virus fuses its viral envelope with cellular membranes of its human host. Initial contact with the host cell and membrane fusion are both mediated by the viral spike (S) protein. Proteolytic cleavage of S at the S2′ site exposes its 40 amino acid long fusion peptide (FP). Binding of the FP to the host membrane anchors the S2 domain of S in both the viral and the host membrane. The reorganization of S2 then pulls the two membranes together. Here we use molecular dynamics (MD) simulations to study the two core functions of the SARS-CoV-2 FP: to attach quickly to cellular membranes and to form an anchor strong enough to withstand the mechanical force during membrane fusion. In eight 10 &lt;italic&gt;μ&lt;/italic&gt;s-long MD simulations of FP in proximity to endosomal and plasma membranes, we find that FP binds spontaneously to the membranes and that binding proceeds predominantly by insertion of two short amphipathic helices into the membrane interface. Connected via a flexible linker, the two helices can bind the membrane independently, yet binding of one promotes the binding of the other by tethering it close to the target membrane. By simulating mechanical pulling forces acting on the C-terminus of the FP we then show that the bound FP can bear forces up to 250 pN before detaching from the membrane. This detachment force is more than ten-fold higher than an estimate of the force required to pull host and viral membranes together for fusion. We identify a fully conserved disulfide bridge in the FP as a major factor for the high mechanical stability of the FP membrane anchor. We conclude, first, that the sequential binding of two short amphipathic helices allows the SARS-CoV-2 FP to insert quickly into the target membrane, before the virion is swept away after shedding the S1 domain connecting it to the host cell receptor. Second, we conclude that the double attachment and the conserved disulfide bridge establish the strong anchoring required for subsequent membrane fusion. Multiple distinct membrane-anchoring elements ensure high avidity and high mechanical strength of FP-membrane binding.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.21256920</id><title>Comparison of Mental Health Symptoms prior to and during COVID-19: Evidence from a Living Systematic Review and Meta-analysis (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.257586+00:00</updated><author><name>Ying Sun</name></author><author><name>Yin Wu</name></author><author><name>Olivia Bonardi</name></author><author><name>Ankur Krishnan</name></author><author><name>Chen He</name></author><author><name>Jill T. Boruff</name></author><author><name>Danielle B. Rice</name></author><author><name>Yutong Wang</name></author><author><name>Xiaowen Jiang</name></author><author><name>Kexin Li</name></author><author><name>Sarah Markham</name></author><author><name>Brooke Levis</name></author><author><name>Marleine Azar</name></author><author><name>Ian Thombs-Vite</name></author><author><name>Dipika Neupane</name></author><author><name>Tiffany Dal Santo</name></author><author><name>Amina Tasleem</name></author><author><name>Anneke Yao</name></author><author><name>Branka Agic</name></author><author><name>Christine Fahim</name></author><author><name>Michael S. Martin</name></author><author><name>Sanjeev Sockalingam</name></author><author><name>Gustavo Turecki</name></author><author><name>Andrea Benedetti</name></author><author><name>Brett D. Thombs</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The rapid pace, high volume, and limited quality of mental health evidence being generated during COVID-19 poses a barrier to effective decision-making. The objective of the present report is to compare mental health outcomes assessed during COVID-19 to outcomes prior to COVID-19 in the general population and other population groups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Living systematic review.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data Sources&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;MEDLINE (Ovid), PsycINFO (Ovid), CINAHL (EBSCO), EMBASE (Ovid), Web of Science Core Collection: Citation Indexes, China National Knowledge Infrastructure, Wanfang, medRxiv (preprints), and Open Science Framework Preprints (preprint server aggregator). The initial search was conducted on April 13, 2020 with ongoing weekly updates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Eligibility criteria for selecting studies&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;For this report, we included studies that compared general mental health, anxiety symptoms, or depression symptoms, assessed January 1, 2020 or later, to the same outcomes collected between January 1, 2018 and December 31, 2019. We required ≥ 90% of participants pre-COVID-19 and during COVID-19 to be the same or the use of statistical methods to address missing data. For population groups with continuous outcomes for at least three studies in an outcome domain, we conducted restricted maximum-likelihood random-effects meta-analyses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of March 22, 2021, we had identified 36 unique eligible studies with data from 33 cohorts. All reported COVID-19 outcomes between March and June 2020, and 3 studies also reported outcomes between September and November 2020. Estimates of changes in general mental health were close to zero in the general population (standardized mean difference [SMD] = 0.02, 95% CI -0.11 to 0.16, I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 94.6%; 4 studies, N = 19,707) and among older adults (SMD = 0.02, 95% CI -0.11 to 0.16, I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 90.4%; 4 studies, N = 5,520) and university students (SMD = -0.01, 95% CI -0.33 to 0.30, I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 92.0%; 3 studies, N = 3,372). Changes in anxiety symptoms were close to zero and not statistically significant in university students (SMD = 0.00, 95% CI - 0.35 to 0.36, I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 95.4%; 5 studies, N = 1,537); women or females (SMD = 0.02, 95% CI -0.35 to 0.39, I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 92.3%; 3 studies, N = 2,778); and men or males (SMD = 0.07, 95% CI -0.01 to 0.15; I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 0.01%; 3 studies, N = 1,250); anxiety symptoms increased, however, among people with pre-existing medical conditions (SMD = 0.27, 95% CI 0.01 to 0.54, I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 91.0%; 3 studies, N = 2,053). Changes in depression symptoms were close to zero or small and not statistically significant among university students (SMD = 0.19, 95% CI -0.08 to 0.45, I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 91.8%; 5 studies, N = 1,537); people with pre-existing medical conditions (SMD = 0.01, 95% CI -0.15 to 0.17, I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 14.9%; 3 studies, N = 2,006); women or females (SMD = 0.21, 95% CI -0.14 to 0.55, I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 91.2%; 3 studies, N = 2,843); and men or males (SMD = 0.00, 95% CI -0.21 to 0.22; I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 92.3%; 4 studies, N = 3,661). In 3 studies with data from both March to June 2020 and September to November 2020, symptoms were unchanged from pre-COVID-19 at both time points or there were increases at the first assessment that had largely dissipated by the second assessment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Evidence does not suggest a widespread negative effect on mental health symptoms in COVID-19, although it is possible that gaps in data have not allowed identification of changes in some vulnerable groups. Continued updating is needed as evidence accrues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CMS-171703; MS1-173070); McGill Interdisciplinary Initiative in Infection and Immunity Emergency COVID-19 Research Fund (R2-42).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Registration&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;PROSPERO (CRD42020179703); registered on April 17, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.07.443114</id><title>Following the Trail of One Million Genomes: Footprints of SARS-CoV-2 Adaptation to Humans (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.257181+00:00</updated><author><name>Saymon Akther</name></author><author><name>Edgaras Bezrucenkovas</name></author><author><name>Li Li</name></author><author><name>Brian Sulkow</name></author><author><name>Lia Di</name></author><author><name>Desiree Pante</name></author><author><name>Che L. Martin</name></author><author><name>Benjamin J. Luft</name></author><author><name>Weigang Qiu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) has accumulated genomic mutations at an approximately linear rate since it first infected human populations in late 2019. Controversies remain regarding the identity, proportion, and effects of adaptive mutations as SARS-CoV-2 evolves from a bat-to a human-adapted virus. The potential for vaccine-escape mutations poses additional challenges in pandemic control. Despite being of great interest to therapeutic and vaccine development, human-adaptive mutations in SARS-CoV-2 are masked by a genome-wide linkage disequilibrium under which neutral and even deleterious mutations can reach fixation by chance or through hitchhiking. Furthermore, genome-wide linkage equilibrium imposes clonal interference by which multiple adaptive mutations compete against one another. Informed by insights from microbial experimental evolution, we analyzed close to one million SARS-CoV-2 genomes sequenced during the first year of the COVID-19 pandemic and identified putative human-adaptive mutations according to the rates of synonymous and missense mutations, temporal linkage, and mutation recurrence. Furthermore, we developed a forward-evolution simulator with the realistic SARS-CoV-2 genome structure and base substitution probabilities able to predict viral genome diversity under neutral, background selection, and adaptive evolutionary models. We conclude that adaptive mutations have emerged early, rapidly, and constantly to dominate SARS-CoV-2 populations despite clonal interference and purifying selection. Our analysis underscores a need for genomic surveillance of mutation trajectories at the local level for early detection of adaptive and immune-escape variants. Putative human-adaptive mutations are over-represented in viral proteins interfering host immunity and binding host-cell receptors and thus may serve as priority targets for designing therapeutics and vaccines against human-adapted forms of SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443422</id><title>Rapid inactivation of SARS-CoV-2 variants by continuous and intermittent irradiation with a deep-ultraviolet light-emitting diode (DUV-LED) device (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.256819+00:00</updated><author><name>Hiroko Inagaki</name></author><author><name>Akatsuki Saito</name></author><author><name>Chiho Kaneko</name></author><author><name>Hironobu Sugiyama</name></author><author><name>Tamaki Okabayashi</name></author><author><name>Shouichi Fujimoto</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;More than 1 year has passed since social activities have been restricted due to the spread of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). More recently, novel SARS-CoV-2 variants have been spreading around the world, and there is growing concern of higher transmissibility of the variants and weaker protective efficacy of vaccine against the variants. Immediate measures are needed to reduce human exposure to the virus. In this study, the antiviral efficacy of deep-ultraviolet light-emitting diode (DUV-LED) irradiation (280 ± 5 nm, 3.75 mW/cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;) against three SARS-CoV-2 variants was evaluated. For the B.1.1.7, B.1.351, and P.1 strains, the infectious titer reduction rates of 96.3%, 94.6%, and 91.9%, respectively, were already recognized with the irradiation of virus stocks for 1 s, and the rates increased to 99.9%, 99.9%, and 99.8%, respectively, with irradiation for 5 s. We also tested the effect of pulsed DUV-LED irradiation (7.5 mW/cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, duty rate: 50%, frequency: 1 KHz) under the same output conditions as continuous irradiation, and found that the antiviral efficacy of pulsed and continuous irradiation was the same. These findings suggest that SARS-CoV-2 may be instantly inactivated by DUV-LED irradiation if the DUV-LED device is further developed and optimized to increase its output.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.06.21256766</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 RNA and antibody detection in human milk from a prospective multicenter study in Spain (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.253631+00:00</updated><author><name>Christine Bäuerl</name></author><author><name>Walter Randazzo</name></author><author><name>Gloria Sánchez</name></author><author><name>Marta Selma-Royo</name></author><author><name>Elia Garcia-Verdevio</name></author><author><name>Laura Martínez-Rodríguez</name></author><author><name>Anna Parra-Llorca</name></author><author><name>Carles Lerin</name></author><author><name>Victoria Fumadó</name></author><author><name>Francesca Crovetto</name></author><author><name>Fátima Crispi</name></author><author><name>Francisco J Pérez-Cano</name></author><author><name>Gerardo Rodríguez</name></author><author><name>Gema Ruíz-Redondo</name></author><author><name>Cristina Campoy</name></author><author><name>Cecilia Martínez-Costa</name></author><author><name>Maria Carmen Collado</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the COVID-19 pandemic in 2020, breastfeeding in women positive for SARS-CoV-2 was compromised due to contradictory data regarding potential viral transmission. However, growing evidence confirms the relevant role of breast milk in providing passive immunity by generating and transmitting specific antibodies against the virus. Thus, our study aimed to develop and validate a specific protocol to detect SARS-CoV-2 in breast milk matrix as well as to determine the impact of maternal SARS-CoV-2 infection on presence, concentration, and persistence of specific SARS-CoV-2 antibodies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Study design/Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A prospective multicenter longitudinal study in Spain was carried out from April to December 2020. A total of 60 mothers with SARS-CoV-2 infection and/or recovered from COVID-19 were included (n=52 PCR-diagnosed and n=8 seropositive). Data from maternal-infant clinical records and symptomatology were collected. A specific protocol was validated to detect SARS-CoV-2 RNA in breast milk, targeting the N1 region of the nucleocapsid gene and the envelope (E) gene. Presence and levels of SARS-CoV-2 specific immunoglobulins (Igs) -IgA, IgG, and IgM-in breast milk samples from COVID-19 patients and from 13 women before the pandemic were also evaluated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;All breast milk samples showed negative results for SARS-CoV-2 RNA presence. We observed high intra- and inter-individual variability in the antibody response to the receptor-binding domain (RBD) of the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein for each of the three isotypes IgA, IgM and IgG. Protease domain (MPro) antibodies were also detected in milk. In general, 82.9 % of the milk samples were positive for at least one of the three antibody isotypes, being 52.86 % of those positive for all three Igs. Positivity rate for IgA was relatively stable over time (65.2 – 87.5 %), whereas it raised continuously for IgG (47.8 % the first ten days to 87.5 % from day 41 up to day 206 post-PCR confirmation).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Considering the lack of evidence for SARS-CoV-2 transmission through breast milk, our study confirms the safety of breastfeeding practices and highlights the relevance of virus-specific SARS-CoV-2 antibody transfer, that would provide passive immunity to breastfed infants and protect them against COVID-19 disease. This study provides crucial data to support official breastfeeding recommendations based on scientific evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.04.21256650</id><title>Importance of E484K and N501Y mutations in SARS-CoV-2 for genomic surveillance: rapid detection by restriction enzyme analysis (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.252274+00:00</updated><author><name>Rossana C Jaspe</name></author><author><name>Yoneira Sulbaran</name></author><author><name>Carmen L Loureiro</name></author><author><name>Pierina D’Angelo</name></author><author><name>Lieska Rodríguez</name></author><author><name>Domingo J Garzaro</name></author><author><name>Héctor R Rangel</name></author><author><name>Flor H Pujol</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Variants of Concern of SARS-CoV-2 (VOCs), the new coronavirus responsible for COVID-19, have emerged in several countries. Two mutations in the gene coding for the Spike protein of the viral genome are particularly important and associated with some of these variants: E484K and N501Y. Restriction enzyme analysis is proposed as a rapid method to detect these two mutations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methodology&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A search on GISAID was performed in April 2021 to detect the frequency of these two mutations in the sequence available and their association with other lineages. A small amplicon from the Spike gene was digested with two enzymes: HpyAV, which allows detecting E484K mutation, and MseI, for detecting the N501Y one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The mutations E484K and N501Y, associated with VOCs, have emerged in several other lineages, particularly E484K. A 100% correlation was observed with sequencing results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The proposed methodology, which allows screening a great number of samples, will probably help to provide more information on the prevalence and epidemiology of these mutations worldwide, to select the candidates for whole-genome sequencing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.06.21256751</id><title>COVID-19 wastewater based epidemiology: long-term monitoring of 10 WWTP in France reveals the importance of the sampling context (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.251812+00:00</updated><author><name>A. Lazuka</name></author><author><name>C. Arnal</name></author><author><name>E. Soyeux</name></author><author><name>M. Sampson</name></author><author><name>A.-S. Lepeuple</name></author><author><name>Y. Deleuze</name></author><author><name>S. Pouradier Duteil</name></author><author><name>S. Lacroix</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 wastewater-based epidemiology (WBE) has been advancedas a relevant indicator of distribution of COVID-19 in communities, supporting classical testing and tracing epidemiological approaches. An extensive sampling campaign, including ten municipal wastewater treatment plants, has been conducted in different cities of France over a 20-weeks period, encompassing the second peak of COVID-19 outbreak in France. A well-recognised ultrafiltration - RNA extraction - RT-qPCR protocol was used and qualified, showing 5.5 +/-0.5% recovery yield on heat-inactivated SARS-CoV-2. Importantly the whole, solid and liquid, fraction of wastewater was used for virus concentration in this study.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Campaign results showed medium- to strong-correlation between SARS-CoV-2 WBE data and COVID-19 prevalence. To go further, WWTP inlet flow rate and raining statistical relationships were studied and taken into account for each WWTP in order to calculate contextualized SARS-CoV-2 loads. This metric presented improved correlation strengths with COVID-19 prevalence for WWTP particularly submitted and sensitive to rain. Such findings highlighted that SARS-CoV-2 WBE data ultimately require to be contextualised for relevant interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;First study monitoring inlet of 10 WWTPs located in France for SARS-CoV-2 RNA quantification over a 20-weeks period encompassing the second peak of COVID-19 outbreak&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Viral recovery yield was 5.5 % +/-0.5% using heat-inactivated SARS-CoV-2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Medium to high Spearman’s correlation strength was observed between SARS-CoV-2 WBE and COVID-19 prevalence data&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Considering sampling context (ei. rain events) improved data consistency and correlation strength&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="21256751v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.21257033</id><title>COVID-19: A comparative study of severity of patients hospitalized during the first and the second wave in South Africa (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.251020+00:00</updated><author><name>Caroline Maslo</name></author><author><name>Angeliki Messina</name></author><author><name>Anchen Laubscher</name></author><author><name>Mande Toubkin</name></author><author><name>Liza Sitharam</name></author><author><name>Charles Feldman</name></author><author><name>Guy A Richards</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;South Africa has experienced two waves of COVID-19 infections, the second of which was inter alia attributed to the emergence of a novel SARS-CoV2 variant, 501Y.V2. This variant possibly has increased virulence and may be associated with increased mortality. The objective of this study was to determine if patients admitted in the second wave had more severe illness and higher mortality than those admitted in the first.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We analysed and compared the characteristics, biological severity markers, treatments, level of care and outcomes of patients hospitalised in a private hospital in the Eastern Cape Province, South Africa.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compared to the first wave, patients admitted in the second were older and less likely to have co-morbidities. In contrast, the D-dimer and interleukin-6 (IL-6) levels were significantly higher. Despite this, significantly less patients were admitted to ICU and/or were mechanically ventilated. The total length of hospital stay was identical in both groups. Whereas the overall mortality was not significantly higher during the second wave, the ICU mortality was. Those that died in the second wave were older than those in the first wave. Multivariable logistic regression showed that being admitted during the second wave was an independent risk factor for mortality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study appears to confirm previous reports that the 501Y.V2 variant is possibly more virulent as indicated by the higher levels of D-dimer and IL-6, the slight increase in mortality of hospitalised patients and the higher ICU mortality in the second wave.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.07.21256388</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 antibody prevalence among homeless people, sex workers and shelter workers in Denmark: a nationwide cross-sectional study (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.250091+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexandra R Röthlin Eriksen</name></author><author><name>Kamille Fogh</name></author><author><name>Rasmus B Hasselbalch</name></author><author><name>Henning Bundgaard</name></author><author><name>Susanne D Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Charlotte S Jørgensen</name></author><author><name>Bibi FSS Scharff</name></author><author><name>Christian Erikstrup</name></author><author><name>Susanne G. Sækmose</name></author><author><name>Dorte K Holm</name></author><author><name>Bitten Aagaard</name></author><author><name>Jonas H Kristensen</name></author><author><name>Cecilie A Bødker</name></author><author><name>Jakob Norsk</name></author><author><name>Pernille Brok Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Lars Østergaard</name></author><author><name>Svend Ellermann-Eriksen</name></author><author><name>Berit Andersen</name></author><author><name>Henrik Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Isik S. Johansen</name></author><author><name>Lothar Wiese</name></author><author><name>Lone Simonsen</name></author><author><name>Thea K.Fischer</name></author><author><name>Fredrik Folke</name></author><author><name>Freddy Lippert</name></author><author><name>Sisse R Ostrowski</name></author><author><name>Steen Ethelberg</name></author><author><name>Anders Koch</name></author><author><name>Anne-Marie Vangsted</name></author><author><name>Tyra Krause</name></author><author><name>Anders Fomsgaard</name></author><author><name>Claus Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Henrik Ullum</name></author><author><name>Robert Skov</name></author><author><name>Kasper Iversen</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;People experiencing homelessness (PEH) and associated shelter workers may be at higher risk of infection with “Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2” (SARS-CoV-2). The aim of this study was to determine the prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 among PEH and shelter workers in Denmark.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design and methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In November 2020, we conducted a nationwide cross-sectional seroprevalence study among PEH and shelter workers at 21 recruitment sites in Denmark. The assessment included a point-of-care test for antibodies against SARS-CoV-2, followed by a questionnaire. The seroprevalence was compared to that of geographically matched blood donors considered as a proxy for the background population, tested using a total Ig ELISA assay.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We included 827 participants in the study, of whom 819 provided their SARS-CoV-2 antibody results. Of those, 628 were PEH (median age 50.8 (IQR 40.9-59.1) years, 35.5% female) and 191 were shelter workers (median age 46.6 (IQR 36.1-55.0) years and 74.5% female). The overall seroprevalence was 6.7% and was similar among PEH and shelter workers (6.8% vs 6.3%, p=0.87); and 12.2% among all participants who engaged in sex work. The overall participant seroprevalence was significantly higher than that of the background population (2.9%, p &amp;lt;0.001). When combining all participants who reported sex work or were recruited at designated safe havens, we found a significantly increased risk of seropositivity compared to other participants (RR 2.1, 95% CI 1.16-3.75, p=0.02). Seropositive and seronegative participants reported a similar presence of at least one SARS-CoV-2 associated symptom (49% and 54%, respectively).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretations&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 antibodies was more than twice as high among PEH and associated shelter workers, compared to the background population. The subset of the study participants who were also sex workers were at particularly high risk of COVID-19 infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;TrygFonden and HelseFonden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.21256975</id><title>Inferring the COVID-19 IFR with a simple Bayesian evidence synthesis of seroprevalence study data and imprecise mortality data (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.249166+00:00</updated><author><name>Harlan Campbell</name></author><author><name>Paul Gustafson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Estimating the COVID-19 infection fatality rate (IFR) has proven to be particularly challenging --and rather controversial-- due to the fact that both the data on deaths and the data on the number of individuals infected are subject to many different biases.  We consider a Bayesian evidence synthesis approach which, while simple enough for researchers to understand and use, accounts for many important sources of uncertainty inherent in both the seroprevalence and mortality data.  We estimate the COVID-19 IFR to be 0.38% (95% prediction interval of (0.03%, 1.19%)) for a typical population where the proportion of those aged over 65 years old is 9% (the approximate worldwide value). Our results suggest that, despite immense efforts made to better understand the COVID-19 IFR, there remains a large amount of uncertainty and unexplained heterogeneity surrounding this important statistic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.06.21256781</id><title>Characterizing cellular and molecular variabilities of peripheral immune cells in healthy inactivated SARS-CoV-2 vaccine recipients by single-cell RNA sequencing (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.246878+00:00</updated><author><name>Renyang Tong</name></author><author><name>Jianmei Zhong</name></author><author><name>Ronghong Li</name></author><author><name>Yifan Chen</name></author><author><name>Liuhua Hu</name></author><author><name>Zheng Li</name></author><author><name>Jianfeng Shi</name></author><author><name>Guanqiao Lin</name></author><author><name>Yuyan Lyu</name></author><author><name>Li Hu</name></author><author><name>Xiao Guo</name></author><author><name>Qi Liu</name></author><author><name>Tian Shuang</name></author><author><name>Chenjie Zhang</name></author><author><name>Ancai Yuan</name></author><author><name>Minchao Zhang</name></author><author><name>Wei Lin</name></author><author><name>Jun Pu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We systematically investigated the transcriptomes of the peripheral immune cells from 6 inactivated vaccine, BBIBP-CorV recipients at 4 pivotal time points using single-cell RNA-seq technique. First, the significant variation of the canonical immune-responsive signals of both humoral and cellular immunity, as well as other possible symptom-driver signals were evaluated in the specific cell types. Second, we described and compared the common and distinct variation trends across COVID-19 vaccination, disease progression, and flu vaccination to achieve in-depth understandings of the manifestation of immune response in peripheral blood under different stimuli. Third, the expanded T cell and B cell clones were correlated to the specific phenotypes which allowed us to characterize the antigen-specific ones much easier in the future. At last, other than the coagulopathy, the immunogenicity of megakaryocytes in vaccination were highlighted in this study. In brief, our study provided a rich data resource and the related methodology to explore the details of the classical immunity scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443477</id><title>Viral shedding and transmission after natural infection and vaccination in an animal model of SARS-CoV-2 propagation (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.245488+00:00</updated><author><name>Caroline J. Zeiss</name></author><author><name>Jennifer L. Asher</name></author><author><name>Brent Vander Wyk</name></author><author><name>Heather G. Allore</name></author><author><name>Susan Compton</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;At present, global immunity to SARS-CoV-2 resides within a heterogeneous combination of susceptible, naturally infected and vaccinated individuals. The extent to which viral shedding and transmission occurs on re-exposure to SARS-CoV-2 after prior natural exposure or vaccination is an emerging area of understanding. We used Sialodacryoadenitis Virus (SDAV) in rats to model the extent to which immune protection afforded by prior natural infection via high risk (inoculation; direct contact) or low risk (fomite) exposure, or by vaccination, influenced viral shedding and transmission on re-exposure. On initial infection, we confirmed that amount, duration and consistency of viral shedding were correlated with exposure risk. Animals were reinfected after 3.7-5.5 months using the same exposure paradigm. Amount and duration of viral shedding were correlated with re-exposure type and serologic status. 59% of seropositive animals shed virus. Previously exposed seropositive reinfected animals were able to transmit virus to 25% of naive recipient rats after 24-hour exposure by direct contact. Rats vaccinated intranasally with a related virus (Parkers Rat Coronavirus) were able to transmit SDAV to only 4.7% of naive animals after a 7-day direct contact exposure, despite comparable viral shedding. Observed cycle threshold values associated with transmission in both groups ranged from 29-36 cycles, however observed shedding was not a prerequisite for transmission. Results indicate that low-level shedding in both naturally infected and vaccinated seropositive animals can propagate infection in susceptible individuals. Extrapolated to COVID-19, our results suggest that continued propagation of SARS-CoV-2 by seropositive previously infected or vaccinated individuals is possible.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.08.21256792</id><title>Yet another lockdown? A large-scale study on people’s unwillingness to be confined during the first 5 months of the COVID-19 pandemic in Spain (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.244835+00:00</updated><author><name>Marina Martinez-Garcia</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Rabasa</name></author><author><name>Xavier Barber</name></author><author><name>Kristina Polotskaya</name></author><author><name>Kristof Roomp</name></author><author><name>Nuria Oliver</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Population confinements have been one of the most widely adopted non-pharmaceutical interventions (NPIs) implemented by governments across the globe to help contain the spread of the SARS-CoV-2 virus. While confinement measures have been proven to be effective to reduce the number of infections, they entail significant economic and social costs. Thus, different policy makers and social groups have exhibited varying levels of acceptance of this type of measures. In this context, understanding the factors that determine the willingness of individuals to be confined during a pandemic is of paramount importance, particularly, to policy and decision-makers. In this paper, we study the factors that influence the unwillingness to be confined during the COVID-19 pandemic by means of a large-scale, online population survey deployed in Spain. We apply both quantitative (logistic regression) and qualitative (automatic pattern discovery) methods and consider socio-demographic, economic and psychological factors, together with the 14-day cumulative incidence per 100,000 inhabitants. Our analysis of 109,515 answers to the survey covers data spanning over a 5-month time period to shed light on the impact of the passage of time. We find evidence of &lt;italic&gt;pandemic fatigue&lt;/italic&gt; as the percentage of those who report an unwillingness to be in confinement increases over time; we identify significant &lt;italic&gt;gender&lt;/italic&gt; differences, with women being generally less likely than men to be able to sustain long-term confinement of at least 6 months; we uncover that the &lt;italic&gt;psychological impact&lt;/italic&gt; was the most important factor to determine the willingness to be in confinement at the beginning of the pandemic, to be replaced by the &lt;italic&gt;economic impact&lt;/italic&gt; as the most important variable towards the end of our period of study. Our results highlight the need to design gender and age specific public policies, to implement psychological and economic support programs and to address the evident pandemic fatigue as the success of potential future confinements will depend on the population’s willingness to comply with them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443377</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 receptor ACE2 identifies immuno-hot tumors in breast cancer (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.243645+00:00</updated><author><name>Jie Mei</name></author><author><name>Yun Cai</name></author><author><name>Rui Xu</name></author><author><name>Xinqian Yu</name></author><author><name>Lingyan Chen</name></author><author><name>Tao Ma</name></author><author><name>Tianshu Gao</name></author><author><name>Fei Gao</name></author><author><name>Yichao Zhu</name></author><author><name>Yan Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) is known as a host cell receptor for Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), which is identified to be dysregulated in multiple tumors. Although the characterization of abnormal ACE2 expression in malignancies has been preliminarily explored, in-depth analysis of ACE2 in breast cancer (BRCA) has not been elucidated. A systematic pan-cancer analysis was conducted to assess the expression pattern and immunological role of ACE2 based on RNA-sequencing (RNA-seq) data downloaded from The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA). Next, correlations between ACE2 expression immunological characteristics in the BRCA tumor microenvironment (TME) were evaluated. Also, the role of ACE2 in predicting the clinical features and the response to therapeutic options in BRCA was estimated. These findings were subsequently validated in another public transcriptomic cohort as well as a recruited cohort. ACE2 was lowly expressed in most cancers compared with adjacent tissues. ACE2 was positively correlated with immunomodulators, tumor-infiltrating immune cells (TIICs), cancer immunity cycles, immune checkpoints, and tumor mutation burden (TMB). Besides, high ACE2 levels indicated the triple-negative breast cancer (TNBC) subtype of BRCA, lower response to endocrine therapy and higher response to chemotherapy, anti-ERBB therapy, antiangiogenic therapy and immunotherapy. To sum up, ACE2 correlates with an inflamed TME and identifies immuno-hot tumors, which may be used as an auxiliary biomarker for the identification of immunological characteristics in BRCA.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443519</id><title>Dynamic Interactions of Fully Glycosylated SARS-CoV-2 Spike Protein with Various Antibodies (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.243160+00:00</updated><author><name>Yiwei Cao</name></author><author><name>Yeol Kyo Choi</name></author><author><name>Martin Frank</name></author><author><name>Hyeonuk Woo</name></author><author><name>Sang-Jun Park</name></author><author><name>Min Sun Yeom</name></author><author><name>Chaok Seok</name></author><author><name>Wonpil Im</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The spread of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) presents a public health crisis, and the vaccines that can induce highly potent neutralizing antibodies are essential for ending the pandemic. The spike (S) protein on the viral envelope mediates human angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) binding and thus is the target of a variety of neutralizing antibodies. In this work, we built various S trimer-antibody complex structures on the basis of the fully glycosylated S protein models described in our previous work, and performed all-atom molecular dynamics simulations to get insight into the structural dynamics and interactions between S protein and antibodies. Investigation of the residues critical for S-antibody binding allows us to predict the potential influence of mutations in SARS-CoV-2 variants. Comparison of the glycan conformations between S-only and S-antibody systems reveals the roles of glycans in S-antibody binding. In addition, we explored the antibody binding modes, and the influences of antibody on the motion of S protein receptor binding domains. Overall, our analyses provide a better understanding of S-antibody interactions, and the simulation-based S-antibody interaction maps could be used to predict the influences of S mutation on S-antibody interactions, which will be useful for the development of vaccine and antibody-based therapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443331</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 ferritin nanoparticle vaccines elicit broad SARS coronavirus immunogenicity (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.237921+00:00</updated><author><name>M. Gordon Joyce</name></author><author><name>Wei-Hung Chen</name></author><author><name>Rajeshwer S. Sankhala</name></author><author><name>Agnes Hajduczki</name></author><author><name>Paul V. Thomas</name></author><author><name>Misook Choe</name></author><author><name>William Chang</name></author><author><name>Caroline E. Peterson</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Martinez</name></author><author><name>Elaine B. Morrison</name></author><author><name>Clayton Smith</name></author><author><name>Aslaa Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Lindsay Wieczorek</name></author><author><name>Alexander Anderson</name></author><author><name>Rita E. Chen</name></author><author><name>James Brett Case</name></author><author><name>Yifan Li</name></author><author><name>Therese Oertel</name></author><author><name>Lorean Rosado</name></author><author><name>Akshaya Ganesh</name></author><author><name>Connor Whalen</name></author><author><name>Joshua M. Carmen</name></author><author><name>Letzibeth Mendez-Rivera</name></author><author><name>Christopher Karch</name></author><author><name>Neelakshi Gohain</name></author><author><name>Zuzana Villar</name></author><author><name>David McCurdy</name></author><author><name>Zoltan Beck</name></author><author><name>Jiae Kim</name></author><author><name>Shikha Shrivastava</name></author><author><name>Ousman Jobe</name></author><author><name>Vincent Dussupt</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Molnar</name></author><author><name>Ursula Tran</name></author><author><name>Chandrika B. Kannadka</name></author><author><name>Michelle Zemil</name></author><author><name>Htet Khanh</name></author><author><name>Weimin Wu</name></author><author><name>Matthew A. Cole</name></author><author><name>Debra K. Duso</name></author><author><name>Larry W. Kummer</name></author><author><name>Tricia J. Lang</name></author><author><name>Shania E. Muncil</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey R. Currier</name></author><author><name>Shelly J. Krebs</name></author><author><name>Victoria R. Polonis</name></author><author><name>Saravanan Rajan</name></author><author><name>Patrick M. McTamney</name></author><author><name>Mark T. Esser</name></author><author><name>William W. Reiley</name></author><author><name>Morgane Rolland</name></author><author><name>Natalia de Val</name></author><author><name>Michael S. Diamond</name></author><author><name>Gregory D. Gromowski</name></author><author><name>Gary R. Matyas</name></author><author><name>Mangala Rao</name></author><author><name>Nelson L. Michael</name></author><author><name>Kayvon Modjarrad</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The need for SARS-CoV-2 next-generation vaccines has been highlighted by the rise of variants of concern (VoC) and the long-term threat of other coronaviruses. Here, we designed and characterized four categories of engineered nanoparticle immunogens that recapitulate the structural and antigenic properties of prefusion Spike (S), S1 and RBD. These immunogens induced robust S-binding, ACE2-inhibition, and authentic and pseudovirus neutralizing antibodies against SARS-CoV-2 in mice. A Spike-ferritin nanoparticle (SpFN) vaccine elicited neutralizing titers more than 20-fold higher than convalescent donor serum, following a single immunization, while RBD-Ferritin nanoparticle (RFN) immunogens elicited similar responses after two immunizations. Passive transfer of IgG purified from SpFN- or RFN-immunized mice protected K18-hACE2 transgenic mice from a lethal SARS-CoV-2 virus challenge. Furthermore, SpFN- and RFN-immunization elicited ACE2 blocking activity and neutralizing ID50 antibody titers &amp;gt;2,000 against SARS-CoV-1, along with high magnitude neutralizing titers against major VoC. These results provide design strategies for pan-coronavirus vaccine development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;HIGHLIGHTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iterative structure-based design of four Spike-domain Ferritin nanoparticle classes of immunogens&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;SpFN-ALFQ and RFN-ALFQ immunization elicits potent neutralizing activity against SARS-CoV-2, variants of concern, and SARS-CoV-1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Passively transferred IgG from immunized C57BL/6 mice protects K18-hACE2 mice from lethal SARS-CoV-2 challenge&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.21256912</id><title>Household overcrowding and risk of SARS-CoV-2: analysis of the Virus Watch prospective community cohort study in England and Wales (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.237353+00:00</updated><author><name>Robert W Aldridge</name></author><author><name>Helen Pineo</name></author><author><name>Ellen Fragaszy</name></author><author><name>Max Eyre</name></author><author><name>Jana Kovar</name></author><author><name>Vincent Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Sarah Beale</name></author><author><name>Thomas Byrne</name></author><author><name>Anna Aryee</name></author><author><name>Colette Smith</name></author><author><name>Delanjathan Devakumar</name></author><author><name>Jonathon Taylor</name></author><author><name>Srinivasa Vittal Katikireddi</name></author><author><name>Wing Lam Erica Fong</name></author><author><name>Cyril Geismar</name></author><author><name>Parth Patel</name></author><author><name>Madhumita Shrotri</name></author><author><name>Isobel Braithwaite</name></author><author><name>Annalan M D Navaratnam</name></author><author><name>Anne M Johnson</name></author><author><name>Andrew Hayward</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Household overcrowding is associated with increased risk of infectious diseases across contexts and countries. Limited data exist linking household overcrowding and risk of COVID-19. We used data collected from the Virus Watch cohort to examine the association between overcrowded households and SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Virus Watch study is a household community cohort of acute respiratory infections in England &amp;amp; Wales that began recruitment in June 2020. We calculated the persons per room for each household and classified accommodation as overcrowded when the number of rooms□was fewer than the number of people. We considered two primary outcomes - PCR-confirmed positive SARS-CoV-2 antigen tests and laboratory confirmed SARS-CoV-2 antibodies (Roche Elecsys anti-N total immunoglobulin assay). We used mixed effects logistic regression models that accounted for household structure to estimate the association between household overcrowding and SARS-CoV-2 infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The proportion of participants with a positive SARS-CoV-2 PCR result was highest in the overcrowded group (6.6%; 73/1,102) and lowest in the under-occupied group (2.9%; 682/23,219). In a mixed effects logistic regression model that included age, sex, ethnicity, household income and geographical region, we found strong evidence of an increased odds of having a positive PCR SARS-CoV-2 antigen result (Odds Ratio 3.72; 95% CI: 1.92, 7.13; p-value &amp;lt; 0.001) and increased odds of having a positive SARS-CoV-2 antibody result in individuals living in overcrowded houses (2.96; 95% CI: 1.13, 7.74; p-value =0.027) compared to people living in under-occupied houses. The proportion of variation at the household level was 9.91% and 9.97% in the PCR and antibody models respectively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Discussion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Public health interventions to prevent and stop the spread of SARS-CoV-2 should consider the much greater risk of infection for people living in overcrowded households and pay greater attention to reducing household transmission. There is an urgent need to better recognise housing as a leading determinant of health in the context of a pandemic and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.06.21256768</id><title>Antibody Response to COVID-19 vaccination in Patients Receiving Dialysis (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.236159+00:00</updated><author><name>Shuchi Anand</name></author><author><name>Maria E. Montez-Rath</name></author><author><name>Jialin Han</name></author><author><name>Pablo Garcia</name></author><author><name>LinaCel Cadden</name></author><author><name>Patti Hunsader</name></author><author><name>Russell Kerschmann</name></author><author><name>Paul Beyer</name></author><author><name>Mary Dittrich</name></author><author><name>Geoffrey A Block</name></author><author><name>Scott D Boyd</name></author><author><name>Julie Parsonnet</name></author><author><name>Glenn M Chertow</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients receiving dialysis may mount impaired responses to COVID19 vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We report antibody response to vaccination from 1140 patients without, and 493 patients with pre-vaccination SARS-CoV-2 RBD antibody. We used commercially available assays (Siemens) to test remainder plasma monthly in association with vaccination date and type, and assess prevalence of absent total receptor binding antibody, and absent or attenuated (index value &amp;lt; 10) semiquantitative receptor binding domain IgG index values. We used Poisson regression to evaluate risk factors for absent or attenuated response to vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among patients who were seronegative versus seropositive before vaccination, 62% and 56% were ≥65 years old, 20% and 24% were Hispanic, and 22% and 23% were Black. Median IgG index values rose steadily over time, and were higher among the seropositive than in the seronegative patients after completing vaccination (150 [25&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;, 75&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; percentile 23.2, 150.0] versus 41.6 [11.3, 150.0]). Among 610 patients who completed vaccination (assessed ≥14 days later, median 29 days later), the prevalence of absent total RBD response, and absent and attenuated semiquantitative IgG response was 4.4% (95% CI 3.1, 6.4%), 3.4% (2.4, 5.2%), and 14.3% (11.7, 17.3%) respectively. Risk factors for absent or attenuated response included longer vintage of end-stage kidney disease, and lower pre-vaccination serum albumin.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;More than one in five patients receiving dialysis had evidence of an attenuated immune response to COVID19 vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients receiving dialysis face high likelihood of severe COVID19; at the same time, vaccination may be less efficacious, as prior data indicate impaired immune responses to influenza and Hepatitis B vaccination. We found that 22% of patients receiving dialysis had suboptimal responses to vaccination, irrespective of whether or not they had evidence of prior SARS-CoV-2 infection. Poorer health status and longer duration of end-stage kidney disease increased likelihood of suboptimal response. Ongoing vigilance for COVID19 in dialysis facilities and studies of modified vaccination dosing schedules will be critical to protecting patients receiving dialysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.05.21256710</id><title>Evolution of COVID-19 symptoms during the first 9 months after illness onset (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.235479+00:00</updated><author><name>Elke Wynberg</name></author><author><name>Hugo van Willigen</name></author><author><name>Maartje Dijkstra</name></author><author><name>Anders Boyd</name></author><author><name>Neeltje A. Kootstra</name></author><author><name>Joost G. van den Aardweg</name></author><author><name>Marit J. van Gils</name></author><author><name>Amy Matser</name></author><author><name>Marije R. de Wit</name></author><author><name>Tjalling Leenstra</name></author><author><name>Godelieve de Bree</name></author><author><name>Menno D. de Jong</name></author><author><name>Maria Prins</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Few longitudinal data on COVID-19 symptoms across the full spectrum of disease severity are available. We evaluated symptom onset, severity and recovery up to nine months after illness onset.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The RECoVERED Study is a prospective cohort study based in Amsterdam, the Netherlands. Participants aged&amp;gt;18 years were recruited following SARS-CoV-2 diagnosis via the local Public Health Service and from hospitals. Standardised symptom questionnaires were completed at recruitment, at one week and month after recruitment, and monthly thereafter. Clinical severity was defined according to WHO criteria. Kaplan-Meier methods were used to compare time from illness onset to symptom recovery, by clinical severity. We examined determinants of time to recovery using multivariable Cox proportional hazards models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Between 11 May 2020 and 31 January 2021, 301 COVID-19 patients (167[55%] male) were recruited, of whom 99/301(32.9%) had mild, 140/301(46.5%) moderate, 30/301(10.0%) severe and 32/301(10.6%) critical disease. The proportion of symptomatic participants who reported at least one persistent symptom at 12 weeks after illness onset was greater in those with severe/critical disease (81.7%[95%CI=68.7-89.7%]) compared to those with mild or moderate disease (33.0%[95%CI=23.0-43.3%] and 63.8%[95%CI=54.8-71.5%]). Even at nine months after illness onset, almost half of all participants (42.1%[95%CI=35.6-48.5]) overall continued to report ≥1 symptom. Recovery was slower in participants with BMI≥30kg/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; (HR 0.51[95%CI=0.30-0.87]) compared to those with BMI&amp;lt;25kg/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, after adjusting for age, sex and number of comorbidities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 symptoms persisted for nine months after illness onset, even in those with mild disease. Obesity was the most important determinant of speed of recovery from symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.08.21256619</id><title>Characterization of the emerging B.1.621 variant of interest of SARS-CoV-2 (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.226005+00:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Laiton-Donato</name></author><author><name>Carlos Franco-Muñoz</name></author><author><name>Diego A. Álvarez-Díaz</name></author><author><name>Hector Alejandro Ruiz-Moreno</name></author><author><name>Jose A. Usme-Ciro</name></author><author><name>Diego Andrés Prada</name></author><author><name>Jhonnatan Reales-González</name></author><author><name>Sheryll Corchuelo</name></author><author><name>María T. Herrera-Sepúlveda</name></author><author><name>Julian Naizaque</name></author><author><name>Gerardo Santamaría</name></author><author><name>Jorge Rivera</name></author><author><name>Paola Rojas</name></author><author><name>Juan Hernández Ortiz</name></author><author><name>Andrés Cardona</name></author><author><name>Diana Malo</name></author><author><name>Franklin Prieto-Alvarado</name></author><author><name>Fernando Ruiz Gómez</name></author><author><name>Magdalena Wiesner</name></author><author><name>Martha Lucia Ospina Martínez</name></author><author><name>Marcela Mercado-Reyes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 genetic diversity has the potential to impact the virus transmissibility and the escape from natural infection- or vaccine-elicited neutralizing antibodies. Here, we report the emergence of the B.1.621 lineage, considered a variant of interest (VOI) with the accumulation of several mutations affecting the Spike protein, including the amino acid changes I95I, Y144T, Y145S and the insertion 146N in the N-terminal domain, R346K, E484K and N501Y in the Receptor Binding Domain and P681H in the S1/S2 cleavage site of the Spike protein. The rapid increase in frequency and fixation in a relatively short time in some cities that were near the theoretical herd immunity suggests an epidemiologic impact. Further studies will be required to assess the biological and epidemiologic roles of the substitution pattern found in the B.1.621 lineage.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.444076</id><title>The Spike Proteins of SARS-CoV-2 B.1.617 and B.1.618 Variants Identified in India Provide Partial Resistance to Vaccine-elicited and Therapeutic Monoclonal Antibodies. (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.223890+00:00</updated><author><name>Takuya Tada</name></author><author><name>Hao Zhou</name></author><author><name>Belinda M Dcosta</name></author><author><name>Marie I Samanovic</name></author><author><name>Mark J Mulligan</name></author><author><name>Nathaniel R Landau</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Highly transmissible SARS-CoV-2 variants recently identified in India designated B.1.617 and B.1.618 have mutations within the spike protein that may contribute to their increased transmissibility and that could potentially result in re-infection or resistance to vaccine-elicited antibody. B.1.617 encodes a spike protein with mutations L452R, E484Q, D614G and P681R while the B.1.618 spike has mutations Δ145-146, E484K and D614G. We generated lentiviruses pseudotyped by the variant proteins and determined their resistance to neutralization by convalescent sera, vaccine-elicited antibodies and therapeutic monoclonal antibodies. Viruses with B.1.617 and B.1.618 spike were neutralized with a 2-5-fold decrease in titer by convalescent sera and vaccine-elicited antibodies. The E484Q and E484K versions were neutralized with a 2-4-fold decrease in titer. Virus with the B.1.617 spike protein was neutralized with a 4.7-fold decrease in titer by the Regeneron monoclonal antibody cocktail as a result of the L452R mutation. The modest neutralization resistance of the variant spike proteins to vaccine elicited antibody suggests that current vaccines will remain protective against the B.1.617 and B.1.618 variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.06.21256753</id><title>A Direct Capture Method for Purification and Detection of Viral Nucleic Acid Enables Epidemiological Surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.223309+00:00</updated><author><name>Subhanjan Mondal</name></author><author><name>Nathan Feirer</name></author><author><name>Michael Brockman</name></author><author><name>Melanie A. Preston</name></author><author><name>Sarah J. Teter</name></author><author><name>Dongping Ma</name></author><author><name>Said A. Goueli</name></author><author><name>Sameer Moorji</name></author><author><name>Brigitta Saul</name></author><author><name>James J. Cali</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Studies have demonstrated that SARS-CoV-2 RNA can be detected in the feces of infected individuals. This finding spurred investigation into using wastewater-based epidemiology (WBE) to monitor SARS-CoV-2 RNA and track the appearance and spread of COVID-19 in communities. SARS-CoV-2 is present at low levels in wastewater, making sample concentration a prerequisite for sensitive detection and utility in WBE. Whereas common methods for isolating viral genetic material are biased toward intact virus isolation, it is likely that a relatively low percentage of the total SARS-CoV-2 RNA genome in wastewater is contained within intact virions. Therefore, we hypothesized that a direct unbiased total nucleic acid extraction method could overcome the cumbersome protocols, variability and low recovery rates associated with the former methods. This led to development of a simple, rapid, and modular alternative to existing purification methods. In an initial concentration step, chaotropic agents are added to raw sewage allowing binding of nucleic acid from free nucleoprotein complexes, partially intact, and intact virions to a silica matrix. The eluted nucleic acid is then purified using manual or semi-automated methods. RT-qPCR enzyme mixes were formulated that demonstrate substantial inhibitor resistance. In addition, multiplexed probe-based RT-qPCR assays detecting the N1, N2 (nucleocapsid) and E (envelope) gene fragments of SARS-CoV-2 were developed. The RT-qPCR assays also contain primers and probes to detect Pepper Mild Mottle Virus (PMMoV), a fecal indicator RNA virus present in wastewater, and an exogenous control RNA to measure effects of RT-qPCR inhibitors. Using this workflow, we monitored wastewater samples from three wastewater treatment plants (WWTP) in Dane County, Wisconsin. We also successfully sequenced a subset of samples to ensure compatibility with a SARS-CoV-2 amplicon panel and demonstrated the potential for SARS-CoV-2 variant detection. Data obtained here underscore the potential for wastewater surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 and other infectious agents in communities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.21256886</id><title>Lack of evidence for infectious SARS-CoV-2 in feces and sewage (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.223028+00:00</updated><author><name>Sandra Albert</name></author><author><name>Alba Ruíz</name></author><author><name>Javier Pemán</name></author><author><name>Miguel Salavert</name></author><author><name>Pilar Domingo-Calap</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Purpose&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The SARS-CoV-2 coronavirus is a respiratory virus whose primary route of transmission is airborne. However, it has been shown that the virus can replicate in gastrointestinal cells, can be excreted in feces, and can reach sewage systems. Although viral RNA has been found in patient feces and sewage, little is known about the potential fecal-oral transmission of the coronavirus. Determining the presence of infective viral particles in feces and sewage is necessary to take adequate control measures and to discover new routes of coronavirus transmission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Feces and urine of COVID-19 patients, and wastewater samples at the time of high prevalence in the region under study (Valencia, Spain), have been analyzed both by molecular methods and cell culture.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Presence of SARS-CoV-2 in feces of COVID-19 patients has been detected, even in patients without gastrointestinal symptoms, suggesting that viral shedding though stool is common. In addition, we have developed a sample concentration methodology that allows us to maintain the infectivity of the viral particles present in the samples. Finally, inoculation of cell cultures with fecal and sewage concentrated samples do not evidence the presence of infective viral particles.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is no evidence of the presence of infectious SARS-CoV-2 in feces and sewage, suggesting that fecal-oral transmission is not a primary route. However, larger-scale efforts are needed to elucidate whether the fecal-oral transmission should be considered, especially with the emergence of new viral variants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.08.21256879</id><title>Prevalence and source analysis of COVID-19 misinformation of 138 countries (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.222755+00:00</updated><author><name>Md. Sayeed Al-Zaman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This study analyzed 9,657 pieces of misinformation that originated in 138 countries and fact-checked by 94 organizations. Collected from Poynter Institute’s official website and following a quantitative content analysis method along with descriptive statistical analysis, this research produces some novel insights regarding COVID-19 misinformation. The findings show that India (15.94%), the US (9.74%), Brazil (8.57%), and Spain (8.03%) are the four most misinformation-affected countries. Based on the results, it is presumed that the prevalence of COVID-19 misinformation can have a positive association with the COVID-19 situation. Social media (84.94%) produces the highest amount of misinformation, and the internet (90.5%) as a whole is responsible for most of the COVID-19 misinformation. Moreover, Facebook alone produces 66.87% misinformation among all social media platforms. Of all countries, India (18.07%) produced the highest amount of social media misinformation, perhaps thanks to the country’s higher internet penetration rate, increasing social media consumption, and users’ lack of internet literacy. On the other hand, countries like Turkey, the US, Brazil, and the Philippines where either political control over media is intense or political conservatism is apparent, experienced a higher amount of misinformation from mainstream media, political figures, and celebrities. Although the prevalence of misinformation was the highest in March 2020, given the present trends, it may likely to increase slightly in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.21256634</id><title>Humoral immunogenicity of the seasonal influenza vaccine before and after CAR-T-cell therapy (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.221945+00:00</updated><author><name>Carla S. Walti</name></author><author><name>Andrea N. Loes</name></author><author><name>Kiel Shuey</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth M. Krantz</name></author><author><name>Jim Boonyaratanakornkit</name></author><author><name>Jacob Keane-Candib</name></author><author><name>Tillie Loeffelholz</name></author><author><name>Caitlin R. Wolf</name></author><author><name>Justin J. Taylor</name></author><author><name>Rebecca A. Gardner</name></author><author><name>Damian J. Green</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Cowan</name></author><author><name>David G. Maloney</name></author><author><name>Cameron J. Turtle</name></author><author><name>Steven A. Pergam</name></author><author><name>Helen Y. Chu</name></author><author><name>Jesse D. Bloom</name></author><author><name>Joshua A. Hill</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recipients of chimeric antigen receptor-modified T (CAR-T) cell therapies for B-cell malignancies are immunocompromised and at risk for serious infections. Vaccine immunogenicity is unknown in this population. We conducted a prospective observational study of the humoral immunogenicity of 2019-2020 inactivated influenza vaccines (IIV) in children and adults immediately prior to (n=7) or 13-57 months after (n=15) CD19-, CD20-, or BCMA-targeted CAR-T-cell therapy, as well as controls (n=8). Individuals post-CAR-T-cell therapy were in remission. We tested for antibodies to 4 vaccine strains at baseline and ≥1 time point after IIV using neutralization and hemagglutination inhibition assays. An antibody response was defined as a ≥4-fold titer increase from baseline at the first post-vaccine time point. Baseline A(H1N1) titers in the CAR-T cohorts were significantly lower compared to controls. Antibody responses to ≥1 vaccine strain occurred in 2 (29%) individuals before CAR-T-cell therapy; one individual maintained a response for &amp;gt;3 months post-CAR-T-cell therapy. Antibody responses to ≥1 vaccine strain occurred in 6 (40%) individuals vaccinated after CAR-T-cell therapy. An additional 2 (29%) and 6 (40%) individuals had ≥2-fold increases (at any time) in the pre- and post-CAR-T cohorts, respectively. There were no identified clinical or immunologic predictors of antibody responses. Neither severe hypogammaglobulinemia nor B-cell aplasia precluded antibody responses. These data support consideration for vaccination before and after CAR-T-cell therapy for influenza and other relevant pathogens such as SARS-CoV-2, irrespective of hypogammaglobulinemia or B-cell aplasia. Larger studies are needed to determine correlates of vaccine immunogenicity and durability in CAR-T-cell therapy recipients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key Points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Influenza vaccination was immunogenic pre- and post-CAR-T-cell therapy, despite hypogammaglobulinemia and B-cell aplasia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vaccination with inactivated vaccines can be considered before CAR-T-cell therapy and in individuals with remission after therapy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443592</id><title>Design and immunogenicity of a Pan-SARS-CoV-2 synthetic DNA vaccine (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.221409+00:00</updated><author><name>Charles C. Reed</name></author><author><name>Katherine Schultheis</name></author><author><name>Viviane M. Andrade</name></author><author><name>Richa Kalia</name></author><author><name>Jared Tur</name></author><author><name>Blake Schouest</name></author><author><name>Dustin Elwood</name></author><author><name>Jewell N. Walters</name></author><author><name>Igor Maricic</name></author><author><name>Arthur Doan</name></author><author><name>Miguel Vazquez</name></author><author><name>Zeena Eblimit</name></author><author><name>Patrick Pezzoli</name></author><author><name>Dinah Amante</name></author><author><name>Maria Yang</name></author><author><name>Joseph Fader</name></author><author><name>Roi Ferrer</name></author><author><name>David B. Weiner</name></author><author><name>J. Joseph Kim</name></author><author><name>Laurent M. Humeau</name></author><author><name>Stephanie J. Ramos</name></author><author><name>Trevor R.F. Smith</name></author><author><name>Kate E. Broderick</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;First generation COVID-19 vaccines matched to the original Wuhan-Hu-1 (WT) strain are showing reduced efficacy against emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern (VOC). In response, next generation vaccines either matched to a single variant or designed to provide broader coverage across the VOC group are being developed. The latter pan-SARS-CoV-2 approach may offer substantial advantages in terms of cross-strain protection, immune coverage, reduced susceptibility to escape mutants, and non-restricted geographical use. Here we have employed our SynCon&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; design technology to construct a DNA vaccine expressing a pan-Spike immunogen (INO-4802) to induce broad immunity across SARS-CoV-2 variants. Compared to WT and VOC-matched vaccines which showed limited cross-neutralizing activity, INO-4802 induced potent neutralizing antibodies and T cell responses against WT as well as B.1.1.7, P.1, and B.1.351 VOCs in a murine model. In addition, a hamster vaccination model showed enhanced humoral responses against VOCs in a heterologous pWT prime/INO-4802 boost setting. These results demonstrate the potential of the pan-SARS-CoV-2 vaccine, INO-4802 to induce cross-reactive immune responses against emerging VOCs as either a standalone vaccine, or as a potential boost for individuals previously immunized with WT-matched vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.05.21256384</id><title>Genomic and epidemiological analysis of SARS-CoV-2 viruses in Sri Lanka (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.220804+00:00</updated><author><name>Chandima Jeewandara</name></author><author><name>Deshni Jayathilaka</name></author><author><name>Diyanath Ranasinghe</name></author><author><name>Nienyun Sharon Hsu</name></author><author><name>Dinuka Ariyaratne</name></author><author><name>Tibutius Thanesh Jayadas</name></author><author><name>Deshan Madushanka</name></author><author><name>Benjamin B. Lindsey</name></author><author><name>Laksiri Gomes</name></author><author><name>Matthew D. Parker</name></author><author><name>Ananda Wijewickrama</name></author><author><name>Malika Karunaratne</name></author><author><name>Graham S. Ogg</name></author><author><name>Thushan I. de Silva</name></author><author><name>Gathsaurie Neelika Malavige</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Since identification of the first Sri Lankan individual with the SARS-CoV-2 in early March 2020, small clusters that occurred were largely contained until the current extensive outbreak that started in early October 2020. In order to understand the molecular epidemiology of SARS-CoV-2 in Sri Lanka, we carried out genomic sequencing overlaid on available epidemiological data. The B.1.411 lineage was most prevalent, which was established in Sri Lanka and caused outbreaks throughout the country. The estimated time of the most recent common ancestor of this lineage was 10&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; August 2020 (95% lower and upper bounds 6&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; July to 7&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; September), suggesting cryptic transmission may have occurred, prior to a large epidemic starting in October 2020. Returning travellers were identified with infections caused by lineage B.1.258, as well as the more transmissible B.1.1.7 lineage. Ongoing genomic surveillance in Sri Lanka is vital as vaccine roll-out increases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Article summary line&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following repeated successful control of small outbreaks early in the pandemic caused by multiple lineages, the subsequent spread of a single lineage established in Sri Lanka (B.1.411) appears to be the cause of the large outbreak that started in early October 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443948</id><title>Plasmacytoid dendritic cells produce type I interferon and reduce viral replication in airway epithelial cells after SARS-CoV-2 infection (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.220419+00:00</updated><author><name>Luisa Cervantes-Barragan</name></author><author><name>Abigail Vanderheiden</name></author><author><name>Charlotte J. Royer</name></author><author><name>Meredith E. Davis-Gardner</name></author><author><name>Philipp Ralfs</name></author><author><name>Tatiana Chirkova</name></author><author><name>Larry J. Anderson</name></author><author><name>Arash Grakoui</name></author><author><name>Mehul S. Suthar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Infection with SARS-CoV-2 has caused a pandemic of unprecedented dimensions. SARS-CoV-2 infects airway and lung cells causing viral pneumonia. The importance of type I interferon (IFN) production for the control of SARS-CoV-2 infection is highlighted by the increased severity of COVID-19 in patients with inborn errors of type I IFN response or auto-antibodies against IFN-α. Plasmacytoid dendritic cells (pDCs) are a unique immune cell population specialized in recognizing and controlling viral infections through the production of high concentrations of type I IFN. In this study, we isolated pDCs from healthy donors and showed that pDCs are able to recognize SARS-CoV-2 and rapidly produce large amounts of type I IFN. Sensing of SARS-CoV-2 by pDCs was independent of viral replication since pDCs were also able to recognize UV-inactivated SARS-CoV-2 and produce type I IFN. Transcriptional profiling of SARS-CoV-2 and UV-SARS-CoV-2 stimulated pDCs also showed a rapid type I and III IFN response as well as induction of several chemokines, and the induction of apoptosis in pDCs. Moreover, we modeled SARS-CoV-2 infection in the lung using primary human airway epithelial cells (pHAEs) and showed that co-culture of pDCs with SARS-CoV-2 infected pHAEs induces an antiviral response and upregulation of antigen presentation in pHAE cells. Importantly, the presence of pDCs in the co-culture results in control of SARS-CoV-2 replication in pHAEs. Our study identifies pDCs as one of the key cells that can recognize SARS-CoV-2 infection, produce type I and III IFN and control viral replication in infected cells.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Type I interferons (IFNs) are a major part of the innate immune defense against viral infections. The importance of type I interferon (IFN) production for the control of SARS-CoV-2 infection is highlighted by the increased severity of COVID-19 in patients with defects in the type I IFN response. Interestingly, many cells are not able to produce type I IFN after being infected with SARS-CoV-2 and cannot control viral infection. In this study we show that plasmacytoid dendritic cells are able to recognize SARS-CoV-2 and produce type I IFN, and that pDCs are able to help control viral infection in SARS-CoV-2 infected airway epithelial cells.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.21257083</id><title>Background rates of five thrombosis with thrombocytopenia syndromes of special interest for COVID-19 vaccine safety surveillance: incidence between 2017 and 2019 and patient profiles from 20.6 million people in six European countries (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.219994+00:00</updated><author><name>Edward Burn</name></author><author><name>Xintong Li</name></author><author><name>Kristin Kostka</name></author><author><name>Henry Morgan Stewart</name></author><author><name>Christian Reich</name></author><author><name>Sarah Seager</name></author><author><name>Talita Duarte-Salles</name></author><author><name>Sergio Fernandez-Bertolin</name></author><author><name>María Aragón</name></author><author><name>Carlen Reyes</name></author><author><name>Eugenia Martinez-Hernandez</name></author><author><name>Edelmira Marti</name></author><author><name>Antonella Delmestri</name></author><author><name>Katia Verhamme</name></author><author><name>Peter Rijnbeek</name></author><author><name>Daniel Prieto-Alhambra</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thrombosis with thrombocytopenia syndrome (TTS) has been reported among individuals vaccinated with adenovirus-vectored COVID-19 vaccines. In this study we describe the background incidence of TTS in 6 European countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electronic medical records from France, Netherlands, Italy, Germany, Spain, and the United Kingdom informed the study. Incidence rates of cerebral venous sinus thrombosis (CVST), splanchnic vein thrombosis (SVT), deep vein thrombosis (DVT), pulmonary embolism (PE), and stroke, all with concurrent thrombocytopenia, were estimated among the general population between 2017 to 2019. A range of additional adverse events of special interest for COVID-19 vaccinations were also studied in a similar manner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A total of 20,599,134 individuals were included. Background rates ranged from 1.0 (0.7 to 1.4) to 1.5 (1.0 to 2.0) per 100,000 person-years for DVT with thrombocytopenia, from 0.5 (0.3 to 0.6) to 1.4 (1.1 to 1.8) for PE with thrombocytopenia, from 0.1 (0.0 to 0.1) to 0.7 (0.5 to 0.9) for SVT with thrombocytopenia, and from 0.2 (0.0 to 0.4) to 4.4 (3.9 to 5.0) for stroke with thrombocytopenia. CVST with thrombocytopenia was only identified in one database, with incidence rate of 0.1 (0.0 to 0.2) per 100,000 person-years. The incidence of TTS increased with age, with those affected typically having more comorbidities and greater medication use than the general population. TTS was also more often seen in men than women. A sizeable proportion of those affected were seen to have been taking antithrombotic and anticoagulant therapies prior to their TTS event.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although rates vary across databases, TTS has consistently been seen to be a very rare event among the general population. While still very rare, rates of TTS are typically higher among older individuals, and those affected were also seen to generally be male and have more comorbidities and greater medication use than the general population.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study was funded by the European Medicines Agency (EMA/2017/09/PE Lot 3).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Research in context&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Evidence before this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We searched PubMed to identify studies that have previously described the background incidence of the study outcomes. Estimates of the incidence of cerebral venous sinus thrombosis (CVST) among the general population have ranged from 0.3 to 2 per 100,000 person-years. The background incidence of splanchnic vein thrombosis (SVT) is not well-known, although the incidence of portal vein thrombosis, the most commonly involved vein, has been estimated at around 3 per 100,000 person-years. Deep vein thrombosis (DVT) and pulmonary embolism (PE) are far more common with estimates of their incidence among the general population typically around 100 and 60 per 100,000 person-years respectively, while the incidence of stroke is typically estimated to be above 100 per 100,000 person-years. The background incidence of these events with concurrent thrombocytopenia has not, however, previously been described in detail.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Added value of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on spontaneous reports from the US, the United Kingdom, and the European Union, thrombosis with thrombocytopenia syndrome (TTS) has been raised as a serious, albeit rare, adverse event that may be caused by adenovirus-vectored COVID-19 vaccines. Assessing this safety signal requires a consideration of whether the rates of TTS being reported after vaccinations against SARS-CoV-2 differ from those normally seen among the general population in the absence of any such vaccinations. This study brings together data from six European countries to estimate the background incidence of TTS. We used six large databases of routinely-collected data allowing for sufficient sample size to study TTS across multiple study populations and in different age and sex strata. Additionally, we characterised patients affected by TTS in historical data, describing their comorbidities and prior medication use.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Implications of all the available evidence&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;TTS is very rare and based on the highest estimates among the databases included in this study, one would normally expect approximately 1 case of CVST with thrombocytopenia, 5 of SVT with thrombocytopenia, 11 of DVT with thrombocytopenia, 11 of PE with thrombocytopenia, and 34 of stroke with thrombocytopenia among a general population of 10 million individuals per 28 days. Expected events would however be higher for an older cohort, as patients with TTS are typically older than the general population. Patients with TTS are more often men and appear to typically have more comorbidities and greater medication use, including prior use of antithrombotic and anticoagulant therapies, than the general population.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not only do the rates of TTS being reported among those who had received an adenovirus-based vaccine against SARS-CoV-2 raise a concern, but early evidence from spontaneous reports suggests that TTS among those vaccinated has been more commonly been seen among women and younger persons. While this might be in part explained by potential biases in spontaneous reporting, it also underlines the importance of further evaluation of the safety signal for TTS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As with other adverse events of special interest for COVID-19 vaccines, estimates of TTS vary depending on the data source used. Comparison of observed versus expected TTS rates during the monitoring of COVID-19 vaccines should ideally be done using the same databases for the estimation of post-vaccine (observed) and background (expected) rates, with adjustment for patient characteristics (such as age and sex) done as part of the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.07.21256826</id><title>A quantitative risk-benefit analysis of ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 vaccine among people under 60 in Italy (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.219664+00:00</updated><author><name>Raffaele Palladino</name></author><author><name>Daniele Ceriotti</name></author><author><name>Damiano De Ambrosi</name></author><author><name>Marta De Vito</name></author><author><name>Marco Farsoni</name></author><author><name>Giuseppina Seminara</name></author><author><name>Francesco Barone-Adesi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 is a vaccine against the COVID-19 infection that was granted a conditional marketing authorization by the European Commission in January 2021. However, following a report from the Pharmacovigilance Risk Assessment Committee (PRAC) of European Medicines Agency, which reported an association with thrombo-embolic events (TEE), in particular Disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC) and Cerebral venous sinus thrombosis (CVST), many European countries either limited to individuals older than 55-60 years or suspended its use. We used publicly available data to carry out a quantitative risk-benefit analysis of the vaccine among people under 60 in Italy. Specifically, we used data from PRAC, Eudravigilance and ECDC to estimate the excess number of deaths for TEE, DIC and CVST expected in vaccine users, stratified by age groups. We then used data from the National Institute of Health to calculate age-specific COVID-19 mortality rates in Italy. Preventable deaths were calculated assuming a 72% vaccine efficacy over an 8-month period. Finally, benefit-risk ratio of ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 vaccination was calculated as the ratio between preventable COVID-19 deaths and vaccine-related deaths, using Monte-Carlo simulations. We found that among subjects aged 20-29 years the benefit-risk [B-R] ratio was not clearly favorable (0.70; 95% Uncertainty Interval [UI]: 0.27-2.11). However, in the other age groups the benefits of vaccination largely exceeded the risks (for age 30-49, B-R ratio: 22.9: 95%UI: 10.1-186.4). For age 50-59, B-R ratio: 1577.1: 95%UI: 1176.9-2121.5). Although many countries have limited the use of the ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 vaccine, the benefits of using this vaccine clearly outweigh the risks in people older than 30 years. The use of this vaccine should be a strategic and fundamental part of the immunization campaign considering its safety and efficacy in preventing COVID-19 and its complications.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443384</id><title>Structure and mechanism of SARS-CoV-2 Spike N679-V687 deletion variant elucidate cell-type specific evolution of viral fitness (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.219247+00:00</updated><author><name>Kapil Gupta</name></author><author><name>Christine Toelzer</name></author><author><name>Maia Kavanagh Williamson</name></author><author><name>Deborah K. Shoemark</name></author><author><name>A. Sofia F. Oliveira</name></author><author><name>David A. Matthews</name></author><author><name>Abdulaziz Almuqrin</name></author><author><name>Oskar Staufer</name></author><author><name>Sathish K.N. Yadav</name></author><author><name>Ufuk Borucu</name></author><author><name>Frederic Garzoni</name></author><author><name>Daniel Fitzgerald</name></author><author><name>Joachim Spatz</name></author><author><name>Adrian J. Mulholland</name></author><author><name>Andrew D. Davidson</name></author><author><name>Christiane Schaffitzel</name></author><author><name>Imre Berger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;As the global burden of SARS-CoV-2 infections escalates, so does the evolution of viral variants which is of particular concern due to their potential for increased transmissibility and pathology. In addition to this entrenched variant diversity in circulation, RNA viruses can also display genetic diversity within single infected hosts with co-existing viral variants evolving differently in distinct cell types. The BriSΔ variant, originally identified as a viral subpopulation by passaging SARS-CoV-2 isolate hCoV-19/England/02/2020, comprises in the spike glycoprotein an eight amino-acid deletion encompassing the furin recognition motif and S1/S2 cleavage site. Here, we analyzed the structure, function and molecular dynamics of this variant spike, providing mechanistic insight into how the deletion correlates to viral cell tropism, ACE2 receptor binding and infectivity, allowing the virus to probe diverse trajectories in distinct cell types to evolve viral fitness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Teaser&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 can exploit different cell types to diversify and evolve virus variants distinct in infectivity and structure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443555</id><title>Mechanism of molnupiravir-induced SARS-CoV-2 mutagenesis (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.218922+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Kabinger</name></author><author><name>Carina Stiller</name></author><author><name>Jana Schmitzová</name></author><author><name>Christian Dienemann</name></author><author><name>Hauke S. Hillen</name></author><author><name>Claudia Höbartner</name></author><author><name>Patrick Cramer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Molnupiravir is an orally available antiviral drug candidate that is in phase III trials for the treatment of COVID-19 patients&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt;. Molnupiravir increases the frequency of viral RNA mutations&lt;sup&gt;3,4&lt;/sup&gt; and impairs SARS-CoV-2 replication in animal models&lt;sup&gt;4-6&lt;/sup&gt; and in patients&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. Here we establish the molecular mechanisms that underlie molnupiravir-induced RNA mutagenesis by the RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp) of the coronavirus SARS-CoV-2. Biochemical assays show that the RdRp readily uses the active form of molnupiravir, β-D-N4-hydroxycytidine (NHC) triphosphate, as a substrate instead of CTP or UTP. Incorporation of NHC monophosphate into nascent RNA does not impair further RdRp progression. When the RdRp uses the resulting RNA as a template, NHC directs incorporation of either G or A, leading to mutated RNA products. Structural analysis of RdRp-RNA complexes containing mutagenesis products shows that NHC can form stable base pairs with either G or A in the RdRp active center, explaining how the polymerase escapes proofreading and synthesizes mutated RNA. This two-step mutagenesis mechanism likely applies to various viral polymerases and can explain the broad-spectrum antiviral activity of molnupiravir.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.443734</id><title>CV2CoV, an enhanced mRNA-based SARS-CoV-2 vaccine candidate, supports higher protein expression and improved immunogenicity in rats (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.218586+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicole Roth</name></author><author><name>Jacob Schön</name></author><author><name>Donata Hoffmann</name></author><author><name>Moritz Thran</name></author><author><name>Andreas Thess</name></author><author><name>Stefan O. Mueller</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Petsch</name></author><author><name>Susanne Rauch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;More than a year after emergence of the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic, multiple first-generation vaccines are approved and available for vaccination. Still, many challenges remain. The ongoing vaccination programs across the globe suffer from insufficient vaccine supply. The virus is adapting to the human host and novel variants are circulating that are neutralised less efficiently by antibodies raised against ancestral SARS-CoV-2 variants. Here, we describe CV2CoV, a second-generation mRNA vaccine developed for enhanced protein expression and immunogenicity. CV2CoV supports increased levels of protein expression in cell culture compared to our clinical candidate CVnCoV. Vaccination with CV2CoV induces high levels of virus neutralising antibodies with accelerated kinetics in rats. Robust antibody responses are reflected in significant cross-neutralisation of circulating SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern, i.e. B.1.1.7 and B.1.351. Together, these results underline the value of CV2CoV as next-generation SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.08.21256775</id><title>Intra-host evolution provides for continuous emergence of SARS-CoV-2 variants (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.218162+00:00</updated><author><name>Justin T. Landis</name></author><author><name>Razia Moorad</name></author><author><name>Linda J. Pluta</name></author><author><name>Carolina Caro-Vegas</name></author><author><name>Ryan P McNamara</name></author><author><name>Anthony B. Eason</name></author><author><name>Aubrey Bailey</name></author><author><name>Femi Cleola S. Villamor</name></author><author><name>Angelica Juarez</name></author><author><name>Jason P. Wong</name></author><author><name>Brian Yang</name></author><author><name>Grant S. Broussard</name></author><author><name>Blossom Damania</name></author><author><name>Dirk P. Dittmer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Variants of concern (VOC) in SARS-CoV-2 refer to viral genomes that differ significantly from the ancestor virus and that show the potential for higher transmissibility and/or worse clinical progression. VOC have the potential to disrupt ongoing public health measures and vaccine efforts. Yet, little is known regarding how frequently different viral variants emerge and under what circumstances. We report a longitudinal study to determine the degree of SARS-CoV-2 sequence evolution in 94 COVID-19 cases and to estimate the frequency at which highly diverse variants emerge. 2 cases accumulated ≥9 single-nucleotide variants (SNVs) over a two-week period and 1 case accumulated 23 SNVs over a three-week period, including three non-synonymous mutations in the Spike protein (D138H, E554D, D614G). We estimate that in 2% of COVID cases, viral variants with multiple mutations, including in the Spike glycoprotein, can become the dominant strains in as little as one month of persistent in patient virus replication. This suggests the continued local emergence of VOC independent of travel patterns. Surveillance by sequencing for (i) viremic COVID-19 patients, (ii) patients suspected of re-infection, and (iii) patients with diminished immune function may offer broad public health benefits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.21256933</id><title>Fixed dosing of tocilizumab in ICU admitted COVID-19 patients is a superior choice compared to bodyweight based dosing; an observational population pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic study (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.217282+00:00</updated><author><name>Dirk Jan A.R. Moes</name></author><author><name>David J. van Westerloo</name></author><author><name>Sandra M. Arend</name></author><author><name>Jesse J. Swen</name></author><author><name>Annick de Vries</name></author><author><name>Henk-Jan Guchelaar</name></author><author><name>Simone A. Joosten</name></author><author><name>Mark G.J. de Boer</name></author><author><name>Teun van Gelder</name></author><author><name>Judith van Paassen</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tocilizumab improves outcome, including survival, in intensive care unit (ICU) admitted COVID-19 patients. The currently applied dosage of 8 mg/kg is based on use of this drug for other indications, however is has not formally been investigated for COVID-19. In this study pharmacokinetics and dynamics of tocilizumab were investigated in ICU admitted COVID-19 patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was an open-label, single-center observational pharmacokinetic and -dynamic evaluation study. Enrolled patients, with polymerase chain reaction confirmed Covid-19 were admitted to the ICU for mechanical ventilation or high flow nasal canula oxygen support. All patients were 18 years of age or older and received tocilizumab within 24 hours after admission to the ICU and received 6 mg dexamethasone daily as concomitant therapy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;29 patients were enrolled between 15 December 2020 and 15 March 2021. A total of 139 tocilizumab plasma samples were obtained covering the pharmacokinetic curve of day 0 up to day 20 after tocilizumab initiation. A population pharmacokinetic model with parallel linear and non-linear clearance was developed and validated. Average AUC&lt;sub&gt;0-inf 1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;DOSE&lt;/sub&gt; was 938 [±190] ug/mL*days. Tocilizumab half-life was estimated to be 4·15 [±0·24] days. All patients had tocilizumab exposure above 1 ug/ml for at least 15 days.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study provides evidence to support a fixed dose of 600 mg tocilizumab in COVID-19 patients. Furthermore our findings suggest that alternative cost saving regimens with even lower doses are likely to be as effective as the current 8 mg/kg recommendation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;No external funding was received for this work&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the randomized controlled trial REMAP-CAP, the IL-6 receptor antagonist tocilizumab was shown to improve outcome, including survival in ICU admitted COVID-19 patients. Because obesity is a risk factor for development of severe COVID-19, concerns have been raised about overtreatment as well as undertreatment through weight-based dosing of tocilizumab. Furthermore pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic parameters of medications are often found to be different in severely ill patients when compared to mild or moderately ill patients. However, the effects of different dosing schedules were only investigated to a very limited extent in non-randomized observational studies. Hence, evaluation of the PK/PD parameters of tocilizumab in severely ill patients – is warranted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Added value of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study provides valuable information about the population pharmacokinetics and dynamics of tocilizumab in dexamethasone cotreated ICU admitted COVID-19 patients. This research shows that there is no rationale for the 8 mg/kg dosing recommendation in ICU patients. Fixed dosing of 600 mg tocilizumab is a cost saving, logistically attractive and safe alternative without losing efficacy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Implications of all the evidence&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Due to the ongoing pandemic, shortages of tocilizumab and other IL-6 receptor antagonists may be anticipated. A fixed tocilizumab dose regimen has many practical and safety advantages, e.g. it will reduce dosing errors and avoid unnecessary wastage of medication. More importantly, according to the data presented in this study, relative underdosing of patients with low, or low-normal bodyweight compared to patients with high bodyweight will be avoided. Last but not least, in view of the large number of patients currently being treated with these agents, a significant cost saving can also be expected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.21255146</id><title>A population-level analysis of the protective effects of androgen deprivation therapy against COVID-19 disease incidence and severity (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.216881+00:00</updated><author><name>Kyung Min Lee</name></author><author><name>Kent Heberer</name></author><author><name>Anthony Gao</name></author><author><name>Daniel J Becker</name></author><author><name>Stacy Loeb</name></author><author><name>Danil V. Makarov</name></author><author><name>Barbara Gulanski</name></author><author><name>Scott L DuVall</name></author><author><name>Mihaela Aslan</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Lee</name></author><author><name>Richard Hauger</name></author><author><name>Mei-Chiung Shih</name></author><author><name>Julie Lynch</name></author><author><name>Matthew Rettig</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The incidence and severity of coronavirus disease 19 (COVID-19) is higher in men. Sex hormones potentially offer one explanation for differences by sex.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To determine whether men exposed to androgen deprivation therapy (ADT) have lower incidence and severity of COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted an observational study of male Veterans treated in the Veterans Health Administration from February 15th to July 15th, 2020. We developed a propensity score model to predict the likelihood to undergo Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) testing. We performed multivariable logistic regression modeling adjusted with inverse probability weighting to examine the relationship between ADT and COVID-19 incidence. We conducted logistic regression analysis among COVID-19 patients to test the association between ADT and COVID-19 severity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study sample consisted of 6,250,417 male Veterans who were alive as of February 15, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Exposure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Exposure to ADT was defined as having any prescription for a luteinizing hormone releasing hormone analogue or an antiandrogen in the six months prior to the index date.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main Outcomes and Measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To assess incidence, we used a binary variable indicating any positive reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction SARS-CoV-2 test result through July 15, 2020. To measure severity, we constructed a binary variable indicating whether a patient was admitted to the intensive care unit, placed on mechanical ventilation, or dead in the 60 days following a positive test up to July 15, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We identified 246,087 patients who had been tested for SARS-CoV-2, of whom 3,057 were exposed to ADT, and 36,096 patients with cancer and no ADT exposure. Of these, 295 ADT patients and 2,427 other cancer patients had COVID-19 illness. In the primary, propensity-weighted comparison of ADT patients to cancer patients not on ADT, ADT was associated with decreased likelihood of testing positive for SARS-CoV-2 (adjusted OR, 0.88 [95% CI, 0.81-0.95]; p=0.001). ADT was associated with fewer severe COVID-19 outcomes (OR 0.72 [95% CI 0.53-0.96]; p=0.03).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions and Relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;ADT is associated with reduced incidence and severity of COVID-19 amongst male Veterans. Repurposing of drugs that modulate androgen production and/or action may represent viable potential treatments for COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;KEY POINTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Question&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Does androgen deprivation therapy (ADT) lower incidence and severity of COVID-19?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this observational study of male Veterans treated in the Veterans Healthcare System, ADT was associated with decreased likelihood of testing positive for SARS-CoV-2 (adjusted OR, 0.88 [95% CI, 0.81-0.95]; p=0.001). ADT was also associated with fewer severe COVID-19 outcomes (OR 0.72 [95% CI 0.53-0.96]; p=0.03).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Meaning&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The use of androgen deprivation therapy may be protective against SARS-CoV-2 infection and modulate severity of COVID-19 outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.05.21256690</id><title>A new SARS-CoV-2 variant poorly detected by RT-PCR on nasopharyngeal samples, with high lethality (33 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.216202+00:00</updated><author><name>Pierre Fillatre</name></author><author><name>Marie-José Dufour</name></author><author><name>Sylvie Behillil</name></author><author><name>Remi Vatan</name></author><author><name>Pascale Reusse</name></author><author><name>Alice Gabellec</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Velmans</name></author><author><name>Catherine Montagne</name></author><author><name>Sophie Geffroy</name></author><author><name>Edith Droumaguet</name></author><author><name>Véronique Merour</name></author><author><name>Vincent Enouf</name></author><author><name>Rodolphe Buzele</name></author><author><name>Marion Valence</name></author><author><name>Elena Guillotel</name></author><author><name>Bertrand Gagniere</name></author><author><name>Artem Baidaluk</name></author><author><name>Anna Zhukova</name></author><author><name>Mathieu Tourdjman</name></author><author><name>Vincent Thibault</name></author><author><name>Claire Grolhier</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Pronier</name></author><author><name>Xavier Lescure</name></author><author><name>Etienne Simon-Loriere</name></author><author><name>Dominique Costagliola</name></author><author><name>Sylvie Van Der Werf</name></author><author><name>Pierre Tattevin</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Massart</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In early January 2021, an outbreak of nosocomial cases of COVID-19 emerged in Western France, with RT-PCR tests repeatedly negative on nasopharyngeal samples but positive on lower respiratory tract samples. Whole genome sequencing (WGS) revealed a new variant, currently defining a novel SARS-CoV-2 lineage: B.1.616. In March, WHO classified this variant as ‘under investigation’ (VUI). We analyzed the characteristics and outcomes of COVID-19 cases related to this new variant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clinical, virological, and radiological data were retrospectively collected from medical charts in the two hospitals involved. We enrolled patients with at least one of the following: i) positive SARS-CoV-2 RT-PCR on a respiratory sample; ii) seroconversion with anti-SARS-CoV-2 IgG/IgM; iii) suggestive symptoms and typical features of COVID-19 on chest CT scan. Cases were categorized as either: i) B.1.616; ii) variant of concern (VOC); iii) unknown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;From January 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; to March 24&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;, 2021, 114 patients fulfilled the inclusion criteria: B.1.616 (n=34), VOC (n=32), and unknown (n=48). B.1.616-related cases were older than VOC-related cases (81 years [73-88], vs 73 years [67-82], &lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;&amp;lt;0.05) and their first RT-PCR tests were less often positive (5/34, 15% vs 31/32, 97%, &lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;&amp;lt;0.05). The B.1.616 variant was independently associated with severe disease (multivariable Cox model HR 4.2 [1.3– 13.5], &lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;=0.018), and increased lethality (logrank test &lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;=0.01): 28-day mortality 15/34 (44%) with B.1.616, vs. 5/32 (16%) for VOC, &lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;=0.036.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We report a nosocomial outbreak of COVID-19 cases related to a new variant, B.1.616, poorly detected by RT-PCR on nasopharyngeal samples, with high lethality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Research in context&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Evidence before this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among the numerous SARS-CoV-2 variants described worldwide, only 3 are currently classified as Variant of Concern (VOC) by the WHO, since they are associated with either an increased risk in transmissibility, severity, or significant reduction in neutralization by antibodies: B.1.1.7, B.1.351 and P.1 (Pango lineage nomenclature). With the ongoing circulation of SARS-CoV-2 in many places worldwide, the emergence of new variants may reduce the efficacy of vaccines and jeopardize our prospects to control the pandemic. In early January 2021, an outbreak of cases highly suggestive of COVID-19 despite negative RT-PCR tests on repeated nasopharyngeal (NP) samples was reported in Western France, leading to several nosocomial clusters. Whole-genome sequencing (WGS) from lower respiratory tract samples identified a new lineage of SARS-CoV-2 virus, classified as B1.616. Consequently, the French public health agency (Santé publique France) and the WHO classified B.1.616 as ‘variant under investigation’ (VUI).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Added value of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our observational study, conducted from January 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; to March 24&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; 2021 in the B.1.616 identified area, provides the first clinical and virological description of B.1.616-associated COVID-19. The 34 cases had clinical, biological and radiological findings in line with classical features of COVID-19, while RT-PCR tests on nasopharyngeal (NP) samples failed to detect SARS-CoV-2 in most patients. Indeed, this gold-standard test was positive in only 15% of the first tests in B.1.616-related COVID-19 patients. Of note, the diagnostic performance of RT-PCR tests was satisfactory on lower respiratory tract samples, suggesting that failure to detect B.1.616 on NP samples would be due to a viral load below the limit of detection in the upper respiratory tract, rather than to genomic mismatches between routine RT-PCR targets and this variant. In our cohort, B.1.616 was independently associated with worse clinical outcome, with high 28-day mortality (44%).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Implications of all the available evidence&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diagnosis of B.1.616-related COVID-19 cases should not rely on RT-PCR tests on NP samples. In the epidemic area, strict infection control measures must be maintained as long as COVID-19 diagnosis is not ruled out, in order to limit nosocomial clusters and case fatality. Further studies are needed to confirm and investigate the association between genomic characteristics of B.1.616, and i) poor detection by RT-PCR tests on NP samples; ii) prognosis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.21256192</id><title>High Dose Convalescent Plasma in COVID-19: Results from the Randomized Trial CAPSID (34 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.215350+00:00</updated><author><name>Sixten Körper</name></author><author><name>Manfred Weiss</name></author><author><name>Daniel Zickler</name></author><author><name>Thomas Wiesmann</name></author><author><name>Kai Zacharowski</name></author><author><name>Victor M.Corman</name></author><author><name>Beate Grüner</name></author><author><name>Lucas Ernst</name></author><author><name>Peter Spieth</name></author><author><name>Philipp M. Lepper</name></author><author><name>Martin Bentz</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Zinn</name></author><author><name>Gregor Paul</name></author><author><name>Johannes Kalbhenn</name></author><author><name>Matthias Dollinger</name></author><author><name>Peter Rosenberger</name></author><author><name>Thomas Kirschning</name></author><author><name>Thomas Thiele</name></author><author><name>Thomas Appl</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Mayer</name></author><author><name>Michael Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Christian Drosten</name></author><author><name>Hinnerk Wulf</name></author><author><name>Jan Matthias Kruse</name></author><author><name>Bettina Jungwirth</name></author><author><name>Erhard Seifried</name></author><author><name>Hubert Schrezenmeier</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Rationale&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 convalescent plasma (CCP) has been considered a treatment option in COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To assess the efficacy of neutralizing antibody containing high-dose CCP in hospitalized adults with COVID-19 requiring respiratory support or intensive care treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients (n=105) were randomized 1:1 to either receive standard treatment and 3 units of CCP or standard treatment alone. Control group patients with progress on day 14 could cross over to the CCP group. Primary outcome was a dichotomous composite outcome of survival and no longer fulfilling criteria for severe COVID-19 on day 21. The trial is registered: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov"&gt;clinicaltrials.gov&lt;/ext-link&gt; #&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT04433910"&gt;NCT04433910&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Measurements and main results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The primary outcome occurred in 43.4% of patients in the CCP and 32.7% in the control group (p=0.32). The median time to clinical improvement was 26 days (IQR 15-not reached (n.r.)) in the CCP group and 66 days (IQR 13-n.r.) in the control group (p=0.27). Median time to discharge from hospital was 31 days (IQR 16-n.r.) in the CCP and 51 days (IQR 20–n.r.) in the control group (p=0.24). In the subgroup that received a higher cumulative amount of neutralizing antibodies the primary outcome occurred in 56.0% (versus 32.1%), with a shorter interval to clinical improvement, shorter time to hospital discharge and better survival compared to the control group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;CCP added to standard treatment did not result in a significant difference in the primary and secondary outcomes. A pre-defined subgroup analysis showed a significant benefit for CCP among those who received a larger amount of neutralizing antibodies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.444111</id><title>CD147 antibody specifically and effectively inhibits infection and cytokine storm of SARS-CoV-2 variants (36 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.213404+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhi-Nan Chen</name></author><author><name>Ping Zhu</name></author><author><name>Huijie Bian</name></author><author><name>Jiejie Geng</name></author><author><name>Liang Chen</name></author><author><name>Yufeng Yuan</name></author><author><name>Ruo Chen</name></author><author><name>Ke Wang</name></author><author><name>Yongqiang Deng</name></author><author><name>Peng Du</name></author><author><name>Jiangning Liu</name></author><author><name>Guizhen Wu</name></author><author><name>Youchun Wang</name></author><author><name>Xiuxuan Sun</name></author><author><name>Ting Guo</name></author><author><name>Xu Yang</name></author><author><name>Jiao Wu</name></author><author><name>Jianli Jiang</name></author><author><name>Ling Li</name></author><author><name>Kui Zhang</name></author><author><name>Hua Zhu</name></author><author><name>Zhaohui Zheng</name></author><author><name>Xianghui Fu</name></author><author><name>Fengfan Yang</name></author><author><name>Xiaochun Chen</name></author><author><name>Hao Tang</name></author><author><name>Zheng Zhang</name></author><author><name>Ding Wei</name></author><author><name>Yang Zhang</name></author><author><name>Ying Shi</name></author><author><name>Yumeng Zhu</name></author><author><name>Zhuo Pei</name></author><author><name>Fei Huo</name></author><author><name>Shirui Chen</name></author><author><name>Qingyi Wang</name></author><author><name>Wen Xie</name></author><author><name>Yirong Li</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 and its variants are raging worldwide. Unfortunately, the global vaccination is not efficient enough to attain a vaccine-based herd-immunity and yet no special and effective drug is developed to contain the spread of the disease. Previously we have identified CD147 as a novel receptor for SARS-CoV-2 infection. Here, we demonstrated that CD147 antibody effectively inhibits infection and cytokine storm caused by SARS-CoV-2 variants. In CD147KO VeroE6 cells, infections of SARS-CoV-2, its variants (B.1.1.7, B.1.351) and pseudovirus mutants (B.1.1.7, B.1.351, B.1.525, B.1.526 (S477N), B.1.526 (E484K), P.1, P.2, B.1.617.1, B.1.617.2) were decreased. Meanwhile, CD147 antibody effectively blocked the entry of variants and pseudomutants in VeroE6 cells, and inhibited the expression of cytokines. A model of SARS-CoV-2-infected hCD147 transgenic mice was constructed, which recapitulated the features of exudative diffuse alveolar damage and dynamic immune responses of COVID-19. CD147 antibody could effectively clear the virus and alveolar exudation, resolving the pneumonia. We found the elevated level of cyclophilin A (CyPA) in plasma of severe/critical cases, and identified CyPA as the most important proinflammatory intermediate causing cytokine storm. Mechanistically, spike protein of SARS-CoV-2 bound to CD147 and initiated the JAK-STAT pathway, which induced expression of CyPA. CyPA reciprocally bound to CD147, triggered MAPK pathway and consequently mediated the expression of cytokine and chemokine. In conclusion, CD147 is a critical target for SARS-CoV-2 variants and CD147 antibody is a promising drug to control the new wave of COVID-19 epidemic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.06.21256705</id><title>Estimated Spike Evolution and Impact of Emerging SARS-CoV-2 Variants (36 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.213174+00:00</updated><author><name>Yong Lu</name></author><author><name>Kun Han</name></author><author><name>Gang Xue</name></author><author><name>Ningbo Zheng</name></author><author><name>Guangxu Jin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), the virus that causes COVID-19, has been mutating and thus variants emerged. This suggests that SARS-CoV-2 could mutate at an unsteady pace. Supportive evidence comes from the accelerated evolution which was revealed by tracking mutation rates of the genomic location of Spike protein. This process is sponsored by a small portion of the virus population but not the largest viral clades. Moreover, it generally took one to six months for current variants that caused peaks of COVID-19 cases and deaths to survive selection pressure. Based on this statistic result and the above speedy Spike evolution, another upcoming peak would come around July 2021 and disastrously attack Africa, Asia, Europe, and North America. This is the prediction generated by a mathematical model on evolutionary spread. The reliability of this model and future trends out of it comes from the comprehensive consideration of factors mainly including mutation rate, selection course, and spreading speed. Notably, if the prophecy is true, then the new wave will be the first determined by accelerated Spike evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.21256876</id><title>The Impact of Control and Mitigation Strategies during the Second Wave of COVID-19 Infections in Spain and Italy (44 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.212849+00:00</updated><author><name>Marco De Nadai</name></author><author><name>Kristof Roomp</name></author><author><name>Bruno Lepri</name></author><author><name>Nuria Oliver</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;European countries struggled to fight against the second and the third waves of the COVID-19 pandemic, as the Test-Trace-Isolate (TTI) strategy widely adopted over the summer and early fall failed to effectively contain the spread of the disease. In this paper, we shed light on the effectiveness of such a strategy in two European countries (Spain and Italy) by analysing data from June to December 2020, collected via a large-scale online citizen survey with 95,251 answers in Spain and 43,393 answers in Italy. Through our analysis, we identify several weaknesses in each of the three pillars of the TTI strategy: testing, tracing and isolating. Moreover, we analyse the respondents’ self-reported behaviour before and after the mitigation strategies were deployed during the second wave of infections. We find that the changes in the participants’ behaviour were more pronounced in Italy than in Spain, whereas in both countries, respondents reported being very compliant with individual protection measures, such as wearing facial masks or frequently disinfecting their hands. Finally, we analyse the participants’ perceptions about their government’s measures and the safety of everyday activities and places regarding the risk of getting an infection. We find that the perceived risk is often gender- and age-dependent and not aligned with the risk level identified by the literature. This finding emphasises the importance of deploying public-health communication campaigns to debunk misconceptions about SARS-CoV-2. Overall, our work shows the value of online citizen surveys to quickly and cheaply collect large-scale data to support and evaluate policy decisions to contrast the spread of the disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.07.21256834</id><title>Description of a University COVID-19 Outbreak and Interventions to Disrupt Transmission, Wisconsin, August – October 2020 (54 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.212179+00:00</updated><author><name>Dustin W. Currie</name></author><author><name>Gage K. Moreno</name></author><author><name>Miranda J. Delahoy</name></author><author><name>Ian W. Pray</name></author><author><name>Amanda Jovaag</name></author><author><name>Katarina M. Braun</name></author><author><name>Devlin Cole</name></author><author><name>Todd Shechter</name></author><author><name>Geroncio C. Fajardo</name></author><author><name>Carol Griggs</name></author><author><name>Brian S. Yandell</name></author><author><name>Steve Goldstein</name></author><author><name>Dena Bushman</name></author><author><name>Hannah E. Segaloff</name></author><author><name>G. Patrick Kelly</name></author><author><name>Collin Pitts</name></author><author><name>Christine Lee</name></author><author><name>Katarina M. Grande</name></author><author><name>Amanda Kita-Yarbro</name></author><author><name>Brittany Grogan</name></author><author><name>Sara Mader</name></author><author><name>Jake Baggott</name></author><author><name>Allen C. Bateman</name></author><author><name>Ryan P. Westergaard</name></author><author><name>Jacqueline E. Tate</name></author><author><name>Thomas C. Friedrich</name></author><author><name>Hannah L. Kirking</name></author><author><name>David H. O’Connor</name></author><author><name>Marie E. Killerby</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;University settings have demonstrated potential for COVID-19 outbreaks, as they can combine congregate living, substantial social activity, and a young population predisposed to mild illness. Using genomic and epidemiologic data, we describe a COVID-19 outbreak at the University of Wisconsin (UW)–Madison. During August – October 2020, 3,485 students tested positive, including 856/6,162 students living in residence halls. Case counts began rising during move-in week for on-campus students (August 25-31, 2020), then rose rapidly during September 1-11, 2020. UW-Madison initiated multiple prevention efforts, including quarantining two residence halls; a subsequent decline in cases was observed. Genomic surveillance of cases from Dane County, where UW-Madison is located, did not find evidence of transmission from a large cluster of cases in the two residence halls quarantined during the outbreak. Coordinated implementation of prevention measures can effectively reduce SARS-CoV-2 spread in university settings and may limit spillover to the community surrounding the university.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.08.21256868</id><title>Monitors to Improve Indoor Carbon Dioxide Concentrations in the Hospital: Background, Rationale and Protocol for a Randomized, Sham-controlled, Cross-Over, Open Label Trial (60 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.211893+00:00</updated><author><name>Michaël R. Laurent</name></author><author><name>Johan Frans</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) has caused considerably morbidity and mortality worldwide, mainly among older adults. Hospital outbreaks contribute to the burden of this disease, despite optimal hand hygiene and personal protective equipment such as masks and face shields. Ventilation with fresh outdoor air has emerged as an important strategy to reduce indoor aerosol transmission of COVID-19. Carbon dioxide (CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) monitors are increasingly advocated to facilitate ventilation in schools, long-term care facilities, offices and public buildings. Moreover, several health authorities have issued guidelines for target CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; values in work as well as clinical environments. Given that modern hospitals have superior indoor air quality control systems, it remains however unknown whether feedback from CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; monitors is needed and/or effective to improve ventilation further. Here, we describe the rationale and protocol for a randomized, sham-controlled, crossover, open label trial of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; monitors in double-bed hospital rooms in two acute geriatric wards. Based on pilot data, Aranet4 Home&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; monitors will be used to alert nurses and other staff to raised indoor CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; concentrations. Practical limitations in implementing CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; monitors are discussed, and will be surveyed among staff as additional study outcomes. The Monitors to Improve Indoor Carbon Dioxide (CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) Concentrations in the Hospital (MICH) trial is registered at ClinicalTrials.gov, identifier: &lt;underline&gt;NCT04770597&lt;/underline&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.06.21256706</id><title>Saudi Arabian SARS-CoV-2 genomes implicate a mutant Nucleocapsid protein in modulating host interactions and increased viral load in COVID-19 patients (94 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.208089+00:00</updated><author><name>Tobias Mourier</name></author><author><name>Muhammad Shuaib</name></author><author><name>Sharif Hala</name></author><author><name>Sara Mfarrej</name></author><author><name>Fadwa Alofi</name></author><author><name>Raeece Naeem</name></author><author><name>Afrah Alsomali</name></author><author><name>David Jorgensen</name></author><author><name>Amit Kumar Subudhi</name></author><author><name>Fathia Ben Rached</name></author><author><name>Qingtian Guan</name></author><author><name>Rahul P Salunke</name></author><author><name>Amanda Ooi</name></author><author><name>Luke Esau</name></author><author><name>Olga Douvropoulou</name></author><author><name>Raushan Nugmanova</name></author><author><name>Sadhasivam Perumal</name></author><author><name>Huoming Zhang</name></author><author><name>Issaac Rajan</name></author><author><name>Awad Al-Omari</name></author><author><name>Samer Salih</name></author><author><name>Abbas Shamsan</name></author><author><name>Abbas Al Mutair</name></author><author><name>Jumana Taha</name></author><author><name>Abdulaziz Alahmadi</name></author><author><name>Nashwa Khotani</name></author><author><name>Abdelrahman Alhamss</name></author><author><name>Ahmed Mahmoud</name></author><author><name>Khaled Alquthami</name></author><author><name>Abdullah Dageeg</name></author><author><name>Asim Khogeer</name></author><author><name>Anwar M. Hashem</name></author><author><name>Paula Moraga</name></author><author><name>Eric Volz</name></author><author><name>Naif Almontashiri</name></author><author><name>Arnab Pain</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Monitoring SARS-CoV-2 spread and evolution through genome sequencing is essential in handling the COVID-19 pandemic. The availability of patient hospital records is crucial for linking the genomic sequence information to virus function during the course of infections. Here, we sequenced 892 SARS-CoV-2 genomes collected from patients in Saudi Arabia from March to August 2020. From the assembled sequences, we estimate the SARS-CoV-2 effective population size and infection rate and outline the epidemiological dynamics of import and transmission events during this period in Saudi Arabia. We show that two consecutive mutations (R203K/G204R) in the SARS-CoV-2 nucleocapsid (N) protein are associated with higher viral loads in COVID-19 patients. Our comparative biochemical analysis reveals that the mutant N protein displays enhanced viral RNA binding and differential interaction with key host proteins. We found hyper-phosphorylation of the adjacent serine site (S206) in the mutant N protein by mass-spectrometry analysis. Furthermore, analysis of the host cell transcriptome suggests that the mutant N protein results in dysregulated interferon response genes. We provide crucial information in linking the R203K/G204R mutations in the N protein as a major modulator of host-virus interactions and increased viral load and underline the potential of the nucleocapsid protein as a drug target during infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.21256877</id><title>A blood atlas of COVID-19 defines hallmarks of disease severity and specificity (106 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.204065+00:00</updated><author><name> </name></author><author><name>David J Ahern</name></author><author><name>Zhichao Ai</name></author><author><name>Mark Ainsworth</name></author><author><name>Chris Allan</name></author><author><name>Alice Allcock</name></author><author><name>Azim Ansari</name></author><author><name>Carolina V Arancibia-Carcamo</name></author><author><name>Dominik Aschenbrenner</name></author><author><name>Moustafa Attar</name></author><author><name>J. Kenneth Baillie</name></author><author><name>Eleanor Barnes</name></author><author><name>Rachael Bashford-Rogers</name></author><author><name>Archana Bashyal</name></author><author><name>Sally Beer</name></author><author><name>Georgina Berridge</name></author><author><name>Amy Beveridge</name></author><author><name>Sagida Bibi</name></author><author><name>Tihana Bicanic</name></author><author><name>Luke Blackwell</name></author><author><name>Paul Bowness</name></author><author><name>Andrew Brent</name></author><author><name>Andrew Brown</name></author><author><name>John Broxholme</name></author><author><name>David Buck</name></author><author><name>Katie L Burnham</name></author><author><name>Helen Byrne</name></author><author><name>Susana Camara</name></author><author><name>Ivan Candido Ferreira</name></author><author><name>Philip Charles</name></author><author><name>Wentao Chen</name></author><author><name>Yi-Ling Chen</name></author><author><name>Amanda Chong</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Clutterbuck</name></author><author><name>Mark Coles</name></author><author><name>Christopher P Conlon</name></author><author><name>Richard Cornall</name></author><author><name>Adam P Cribbs</name></author><author><name>Fabiola Curion</name></author><author><name>Emma E Davenport</name></author><author><name>Neil Davidson</name></author><author><name>Simon Davis</name></author><author><name>Calliope Dendrou</name></author><author><name>Julie Dequaire</name></author><author><name>Lea Dib</name></author><author><name>James Docker</name></author><author><name>Christina Dold</name></author><author><name>Tao Dong</name></author><author><name>Damien Downes</name></author><author><name>Alexander Drakesmith</name></author><author><name>Susanna J Dunachie</name></author><author><name>David A Duncan</name></author><author><name>Chris Eijsbouts</name></author><author><name>Robert Esnouf</name></author><author><name>Alexis Espinosa</name></author><author><name>Rachel Etherington</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Fairfax</name></author><author><name>Rory Fairhead</name></author><author><name>Hai Fang</name></author><author><name>Shayan Fassih</name></author><author><name>Sally Felle</name></author><author><name>Maria Fernandez Mendoza</name></author><author><name>Ricardo Ferreira</name></author><author><name>Roman Fischer</name></author><author><name>Thomas Foord</name></author><author><name>Aden Forrow</name></author><author><name>John Frater</name></author><author><name>Anastasia Fries</name></author><author><name>Veronica Gallardo Sanchez</name></author><author><name>Lucy Garner</name></author><author><name>Clementine Geeves</name></author><author><name>Dominique Georgiou</name></author><author><name>Leila Godfrey</name></author><author><name>Tanya Golubchik</name></author><author><name>Maria Gomez Vazquez</name></author><author><name>Angie Green</name></author><author><name>Hong Harper</name></author><author><name>Heather A Harrington</name></author><author><name>Raphael Heilig</name></author><author><name>Svenja Hester</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Hill</name></author><author><name>Charles Hinds</name></author><author><name>Clare Hird</name></author><author><name>Ling-Pei Ho</name></author><author><name>Renee Hoekzema</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Hollis</name></author><author><name>Jim Hughes</name></author><author><name>Paula Hutton</name></author><author><name>Matthew Jackson</name></author><author><name>Ashwin Jainarayanan</name></author><author><name>Anna James-Bott</name></author><author><name>Kathrin Jansen</name></author><author><name>Katie Jeffery</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Jones</name></author><author><name>Luke Jostins</name></author><author><name>Georgina Kerr</name></author><author><name>David Kim</name></author><author><name>Paul Klenerman</name></author><author><name>Julian C Knight</name></author><author><name>Vinod Kumar</name></author><author><name>Piyush Kumar Sharma</name></author><author><name>Prathiba Kurupati</name></author><author><name>Andrew Kwok</name></author><author><name>Angela Lee</name></author><author><name>Aline Linder</name></author><author><name>Teresa Lockett</name></author><author><name>Lorne Lonie</name></author><author><name>Maria Lopopolo</name></author><author><name>Martyna Lukoseviciute</name></author><author><name>Jian Luo</name></author><author><name>Spyridoula Marinou</name></author><author><name>Brian Marsden</name></author><author><name>Jose Martinez</name></author><author><name>Philippa Matthews</name></author><author><name>Michalina Mazurczyk</name></author><author><name>Simon McGowan</name></author><author><name>Stuart McKechnie</name></author><author><name>Adam Mead</name></author><author><name>Alexander J Mentzer</name></author><author><name>Yuxin Mi</name></author><author><name>Claudia Monaco</name></author><author><name>Ruddy Montadon</name></author><author><name>Giorgio Napolitani</name></author><author><name>Isar Nassiri</name></author><author><name>Alex Novak</name></author><author><name>Darragh O'Brien</name></author><author><name>Daniel O'Connor</name></author><author><name>Denise O'Donnell</name></author><author><name>Graham Ogg</name></author><author><name>Lauren Overend</name></author><author><name>Inhye Park</name></author><author><name>Ian Pavord</name></author><author><name>Yanchun Peng</name></author><author><name>Frank Penkava</name></author><author><name>Mariana Pereira Pinho</name></author><author><name>Elena Perez</name></author><author><name>Andrew J Pollard</name></author><author><name>Fiona Powrie</name></author><author><name>Bethan Psaila</name></author><author><name>T. Phuong Quan</name></author><author><name>Emmanouela Repapi</name></author><author><name>Santiago Revale</name></author><author><name>Laura Silva-Reyes</name></author><author><name>Jean-Baptiste Richard</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Rich-Griffin</name></author><author><name>Thomas Ritter</name></author><author><name>Christine S Rollier</name></author><author><name>Matthew Rowland</name></author><author><name>Fabian Ruehle</name></author><author><name>Mariolina Salio</name></author><author><name>Stephen N Sansom</name></author><author><name>Alberto Santos Delgado</name></author><author><name>Tatjana Sauka-Spengler</name></author><author><name>Ron Schwessinger</name></author><author><name>Giuseppe Scozzafava</name></author><author><name>Gavin Screaton</name></author><author><name>Anna Seigal</name></author><author><name>Malcolm G Semple</name></author><author><name>Martin Sergeant</name></author><author><name>Christina Simoglou Karali</name></author><author><name>David Sims</name></author><author><name>Donal Skelly</name></author><author><name>Hubert Slawinski</name></author><author><name>Alberto Sobrinodiaz</name></author><author><name>Nikolaos Sousos</name></author><author><name>Lizzie Stafford</name></author><author><name>Lisa Stockdale</name></author><author><name>Marie Strickland</name></author><author><name>Otto Sumray</name></author><author><name>Bo Sun</name></author><author><name>Chelsea Taylor</name></author><author><name>Stephen Taylor</name></author><author><name>Adan Taylor</name></author><author><name>Supat Thongjuea</name></author><author><name>Hannah Thraves</name></author><author><name>John A Todd</name></author><author><name>Adriana Tomic</name></author><author><name>Orion Tong</name></author><author><name>Amy Trebes</name></author><author><name>Dominik Trzupek</name></author><author><name>Felicia A Tucci</name></author><author><name>Lance Turtle</name></author><author><name>Irina Udalova</name></author><author><name>Holm Uhlig</name></author><author><name>Erinke van Grinsven</name></author><author><name>Iolanda Vendrell</name></author><author><name>Marije Verheul</name></author><author><name>Alexandru Voda</name></author><author><name>Guanlin Wang</name></author><author><name>Lihui Wang</name></author><author><name>Dapeng Wang</name></author><author><name>Peter Watkinson</name></author><author><name>Robert Watson</name></author><author><name>Michael Weinberger</name></author><author><name>Justin Whalley</name></author><author><name>Lorna Witty</name></author><author><name>Katherine Wray</name></author><author><name>Luzheng Xue</name></author><author><name>Hing Yuen Yeung</name></author><author><name>Zixi Yin</name></author><author><name>Rebecca K Young</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Youngs</name></author><author><name>Ping Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yasemin-Xiomara Zurke</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Treatment of severe COVID-19 is currently limited by clinical heterogeneity and incomplete understanding of potentially druggable immune mediators of disease. To advance this, we present a comprehensive multi-omic blood atlas in patients with varying COVID-19 severity and compare with influenza, sepsis and healthy volunteers. We identify immune signatures and correlates of host response. Hallmarks of disease severity revealed cells, their inflammatory mediators and networks as potential therapeutic targets, including progenitor cells and specific myeloid and lymphocyte subsets, features of the immune repertoire, acute phase response, metabolism and coagulation. Persisting immune activation involving AP-1/p38MAPK was a specific feature of COVID-19. The plasma proteome enabled sub-phenotyping into patient clusters, predictive of severity and outcome. Tensor and matrix decomposition of the overall dataset revealed feature groupings linked with disease severity and specificity. Our systems-based integrative approach and blood atlas will inform future drug development, clinical trial design and personalised medicine approaches for COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.06.21256788</id><title>Rapid detection of neutralizing antibodies to SARS-CoV-2 variants in post-vaccination sera (115 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.203154+00:00</updated><author><name>Kei Miyakawa</name></author><author><name>Sundararaj Stanleyraj Jeremiah</name></author><author><name>Hideaki Kato</name></author><author><name>Yutaro Yamaoka</name></author><author><name>Hirofumi Go</name></author><author><name>Takeharu Yamanaka</name></author><author><name>Akihide Ryo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The uncontrolled spread of the COVID-19 pandemic has led to the emergence of different SARS-CoV-2 variants across the globe. The ongoing global vaccination strategy to curtail the COVID-19 juggernaut, is threatened by the rapidly spreading Variants of Concern (VOC) and other regional mutants, which are less responsive to neutralization by infection or vaccine derived antibodies. We have previously developed the hiVNT system which detects SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibodies in sera in less than three hours. In this study, we modify the hiVNT for rapid qualitative screening of neutralizing antibodies (nAb) to multiple variants of concern (VOC) of SARS-CoV-2, and assess the neutralizing efficacy of the BNT162b2 mRNA vaccine on seven epidemiologically relevant SARS-CoV-2 variants. Here we show that the BNT162b2 mRNA vaccine can activate humoral immunity against the major SARS-CoV-2 mutants that are currently in circulation. Albeit a small sample size, we observed that one dose of vaccine was sufficient to elicit a protective humoral response in previously infected people. Using a panel of seven SARS-CoV-2 variants and a single prototype virus, our modified hiVNT would be useful for large-scale community wide testing to detect protective immunity that may confer vaccine/immune passport in the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.08.21256866</id><title>Antibody Responses After a Single Dose of ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 Vaccine in Healthcare Workers Previously Infected with SARS-CoV-2 (133 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.202404+00:00</updated><author><name>Sebastian Havervall</name></author><author><name>Ulrika Marking</name></author><author><name>Nina Greilert-Norin</name></author><author><name>Henry Ng</name></author><author><name>Ann-Christin Salomonsson</name></author><author><name>Cecilia Hellström</name></author><author><name>Elisa Pin</name></author><author><name>Kim Blom</name></author><author><name>Sara Mangsbo</name></author><author><name>Mia Phillipson</name></author><author><name>Jonas Klingström</name></author><author><name>Mikael Åberg</name></author><author><name>Sophia Hober</name></author><author><name>Peter Nilsson</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Thålin</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recent reports demonstrate robust serological responses to a single dose of messenger RNA (mRNA) vaccines in individuals previously infected with SARS-CoV-2. Data on immune responses following a single-dose adenovirus-vectored vaccine expressing the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein (ChAdOx1 nCoV-19) in individuals with previous SARS-CoV-2 infection are however limited, and current guidelines recommend a two-dose regime regardless of preexisting immunity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We compared spike-specific IgG and pseudo-neutralizing spike-ACE2 blocking antibodies against SARS-CoV-2 wild type and variants B.1.1.7, B.1.351, and P1 following two doses of the mRNA vaccine BNT162b2 and a single dose of the adenovector vaccine ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 in 232 healthcare workers with and without previous COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The post-vaccine levels of spike-specific IgG and neutralizing antibodies against the SARS-CoV-2 wild type and all three variants of concern were similar or higher in participants receiving a single dose of ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 vaccine post SARS-CoV-2 infection (both &amp;lt; 11 months post infection (n=37) and ≥ 11 months infection (n=46)) compared to participants who received two doses of BNT162b2 vaccine (n=149).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our data support that a single dose ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 vaccine serves as an effective immune booster after priming with natural SARS-CoV-2 infection up to at least 11 months post infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.21257037</id><title>Mental health of Adolescents in the Pandemic: Long-COVID19 or Long-Pandemic Syndrome? (247 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.202007+00:00</updated><author><name>Judith Blankenburg</name></author><author><name>Magdalena K. Wekenborg</name></author><author><name>Jörg Reichert</name></author><author><name>Carolin Kirsten</name></author><author><name>Elisabeth Kahre</name></author><author><name>Luise Haag</name></author><author><name>Leonie Schumm</name></author><author><name>Paula Czyborra</name></author><author><name>Reinhard Berner</name></author><author><name>Jakob P. Armann</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Backround&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Post-COVID19 complications such as pediatric inflammatory multisystem syndrome (PIMS) and Long-COVID19 move increasingly into focus, potentially causing more harm in this age group than the acute infection. To better understand the symptoms of long-COVID19 in adolescents and to distinguish infection-associated symptoms from pandemic-associated symptoms, we conducted a Long-COVID19 survey, comparing responses from seropositive and seronegative adolescents. To our knowledge, data of Long-COVID19 surveys with seronegative control groups have not been published yet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since May 2020 students grade 8-12 in fourteen secondary schools in Eastern Saxony were enrolled in the SchoolCovid19 study. Seroprevalence was assessed via serial SARS-CoV-2 antibody testing in all participants. Furthermore, during the March/April 2021 study visit all participants were asked to complete a 12 question Long-COVID19 survey regarding the occurrence and frequency of difficulties concentrating, memory loss, listlessness, headache, abdominal pain, myalgia/ arthralgia, fatigue, insomnia and mood (sadness, anger, happiness and tenseness).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;1560 students with a median age of 15 years participated in this study. 1365 (88%) were seronegative, 188 (12%) were seropositive. Each symptom was present in at least 35% of the students within the last seven days before the survey. However, there was no statistical difference comparing the reported symptoms between seropositive students and seronegative students. Whether the infection was known or unknown to the participant did not influence the prevalence of symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The lack of differences comparing the reported symptoms between seropositive and seronegative students suggests that Long-COVID19 might be less common than previously thought and emphasizing the impact of pandemic-associated symptoms regarding the well-being and mental health of young adolescents.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study was supported by a grant by the Federal State of Saxony. M.K.W. was supported by the Else Kröner-Fresenius Center for Digital Health (EKFZ), TU Dresden, Germany.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.21257080</id><title>A year of genomic surveillance reveals how the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic unfolded in Africa (251 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.195625+00:00</updated><author><name>Eduan Wilkinson</name></author><author><name>Marta Giovanetti</name></author><author><name>Houriiyah Tegally</name></author><author><name>James E. San</name></author><author><name>Richard Lessels</name></author><author><name>Diego Cuadros</name></author><author><name>Darren P. Martin</name></author><author><name>Abdel-Rahman N. Zekri</name></author><author><name>Abdoul K. Sangare</name></author><author><name>Abdoul-Salam Ouedraogo</name></author><author><name>Abdul K. Sesay</name></author><author><name>Adnène Hammami</name></author><author><name>Adrienne A. Amuri</name></author><author><name>Ahmad Sayed</name></author><author><name>Ahmed Rebai</name></author><author><name>Aida Elargoubi</name></author><author><name>Alexander J. Trotter</name></author><author><name>Alpha K. Keita</name></author><author><name>Amadou A. Sall</name></author><author><name>Amadou Kone</name></author><author><name>Amal Souissi</name></author><author><name>Ana V. Gutierrez</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Page</name></author><author><name>Arash Iranzadeh</name></author><author><name>Arnold Lambisia</name></author><author><name>Augustina Sylverken</name></author><author><name>Azeddine Ibrahimi</name></author><author><name>Beatrice Dhaala</name></author><author><name>Bourema Kouriba</name></author><author><name>Bronwyn Kleinhans</name></author><author><name>Cara Brook</name></author><author><name>Carolyn Williamson</name></author><author><name>Catherine B. Pratt</name></author><author><name>Chantal G. Akoua-Koffi</name></author><author><name>Charles N. Agoti</name></author><author><name>Collins M. Morang’a</name></author><author><name>D. James Nokes</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Bridges</name></author><author><name>Daniel L. Bugembe</name></author><author><name>David Baker</name></author><author><name>Deelan Doolabh</name></author><author><name>Deogratius Ssemwanga</name></author><author><name>Derek Tshabuila</name></author><author><name>Diarra Bassirou</name></author><author><name>Dominic S.Y. Amuzu</name></author><author><name>Dominique Goedhals</name></author><author><name>Dorcas Maruapula</name></author><author><name>Ebenezer Foster-Nyarko</name></author><author><name>Eddy K. Lusamaki</name></author><author><name>Edgar Simulundu</name></author><author><name>Edidah Moraa</name></author><author><name>Edith N. Ngabana</name></author><author><name>Elmostafa El Fahime</name></author><author><name>Emerald Jacob</name></author><author><name>Emmanuel Lokilo</name></author><author><name>Enatha Mukantwari</name></author><author><name>Essia Belarbi</name></author><author><name>Etienne Simon-Loriere</name></author><author><name>Etilé A. Anoh</name></author><author><name>Fabian Leendertz</name></author><author><name>Faida Ajili</name></author><author><name>Fares Wasfi</name></author><author><name>Faustinos T. Takawira</name></author><author><name>Fawzi Derrar</name></author><author><name>Feriel Bouzid</name></author><author><name>Francisca M. Muyembe</name></author><author><name>Frank Tanser</name></author><author><name>Gabriel K. Mbunsu</name></author><author><name>Gaetan Thilliez</name></author><author><name>Gemma Kay</name></author><author><name>George Githinji</name></author><author><name>Gert van Zyl</name></author><author><name>Gordon A. Awandare</name></author><author><name>Grit Schubert</name></author><author><name>Gugu P. Maphalala</name></author><author><name>Hafaliana C. Ranaivoson</name></author><author><name>Hajar Lemriss</name></author><author><name>Haruka Abe</name></author><author><name>Hela H. Karray</name></author><author><name>Hellen Nansumba</name></author><author><name>Hesham A. Elgahzaly</name></author><author><name>Hlanai Gumbo</name></author><author><name>Ibtihel Smeti</name></author><author><name>Ikhlas B. Ayed</name></author><author><name>Ilhem Boutiba-Ben Boubaker</name></author><author><name>Imed Gaaloul</name></author><author><name>Inbal Gazy</name></author><author><name>Isaac Ssewanyana</name></author><author><name>Jean B. Lekana-Douk</name></author><author><name>Jean-Claude C. Makangara</name></author><author><name>Jean-Jacques M. Tamfum</name></author><author><name>Jean-Michel Heraud</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey G. Shaffer</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Giandhari</name></author><author><name>Jingjing Li</name></author><author><name>Jiro Yasuda</name></author><author><name>Joana Q. Mends</name></author><author><name>Jocelyn Kiconco</name></author><author><name>John Morobe</name></author><author><name>John N. Nkengasong</name></author><author><name>John O. Gyapong</name></author><author><name>John T. Kayiwa</name></author><author><name>Johnathan A. Edwards</name></author><author><name>Jones Gyamfi</name></author><author><name>Jouali Farah</name></author><author><name>Joyce M. Ngoi</name></author><author><name>Joyce Namulondo</name></author><author><name>Julia C. Andeko</name></author><author><name>Julius J. Lutwama</name></author><author><name>Justin O’Grady</name></author><author><name>Kefentse A. Tumedi</name></author><author><name>Khadija M. Said</name></author><author><name>Kim Hae-Young</name></author><author><name>Kwabena O. Duedu</name></author><author><name>Lahcen Belyamani</name></author><author><name>Lavanya Singh</name></author><author><name>Leonardo de O. Martins</name></author><author><name>Madisa Mine</name></author><author><name>Magalutcheemee Ramuth</name></author><author><name>Maha Mastouri</name></author><author><name>Mahjoub Aouni</name></author><author><name>Mahmoud el Hefnawi</name></author><author><name>Maitshwarelo I. Matsheka</name></author><author><name>Malebogo Kebabonye</name></author><author><name>Manel Turki</name></author><author><name>Martin M. Nyaga</name></author><author><name>Mathabo Mareka</name></author><author><name>Matoke Damaris</name></author><author><name>Matthew Cotten</name></author><author><name>Maureen W. Mburu</name></author><author><name>Maximillian Mpina</name></author><author><name>Michael Owusu</name></author><author><name>Michael R. Wiley</name></author><author><name>Mohamed A. Ali</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Abouelhoda</name></author><author><name>Mohamed G. Seadawy</name></author><author><name>Mohamed K. Khalifa</name></author><author><name>Mooko Sekhele</name></author><author><name>Mouna Ouadghiri</name></author><author><name>Mulenga Mwenda</name></author><author><name>Mushal Allam</name></author><author><name>My V.T. Phan</name></author><author><name>Nabil Abid</name></author><author><name>Nadia Touil</name></author><author><name>Najla Kharrat</name></author><author><name>Nalia Ismael</name></author><author><name>Nedio Mabunda</name></author><author><name>Nei-yuan Hsiao</name></author><author><name>Nelson B. Silochi</name></author><author><name>Ngonda Saasa</name></author><author><name>Nicola Mulder</name></author><author><name>Patrice Combe</name></author><author><name>Patrick Semanda</name></author><author><name>Paul E. Oluniyi</name></author><author><name>Paulo Arnaldo</name></author><author><name>Peter K. Quashie</name></author><author><name>Philip A. Bester</name></author><author><name>Philippe Dussart</name></author><author><name>Placide K. Mbala</name></author><author><name>Pontiano Kaleebu</name></author><author><name>Reuben Ayivor-Djanie</name></author><author><name>Richard Njouom</name></author><author><name>Richard O. Phillips</name></author><author><name>Richmond Gorman</name></author><author><name>Robert A. Kingsley</name></author><author><name>Rosina A.A. Carr</name></author><author><name>Saâd El Kabbaj</name></author><author><name>Saba Gargouri</name></author><author><name>Saber Masmoudi</name></author><author><name>Samar Kassim</name></author><author><name>Sameh Trabelsi</name></author><author><name>Sami Kammoun</name></author><author><name>Sanaâ Lemriss</name></author><author><name>Sara H. Agwa</name></author><author><name>Sébastien Calvignac-Spencer</name></author><author><name>Seydou Doumbia</name></author><author><name>Sheila M. Mandanda</name></author><author><name>Sherihane Aryeetey</name></author><author><name>Shymaa S. Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Sikhulile Moyo</name></author><author><name>Simani Gaseitsiwe</name></author><author><name>Sonia Lekana-Douki</name></author><author><name>Sophie Prosolek</name></author><author><name>Soumeya Ouangraoua</name></author><author><name>Steve A. Mundeke</name></author><author><name>Steven Rudder</name></author><author><name>Sumir Panji</name></author><author><name>Sureshnee Pillay</name></author><author><name>Susan Engelbrecht</name></author><author><name>Susan Nabadda</name></author><author><name>Sylvie Behillil</name></author><author><name>Sylvie L. Budiaki</name></author><author><name>Sylvie van der Werf</name></author><author><name>Tapfumanei Mashe</name></author><author><name>Tarik Aanniz</name></author><author><name>Thabo Mohale</name></author><author><name>Thanh Le-Viet</name></author><author><name>Tobias Schindler</name></author><author><name>Ugochukwu J. Anyaneji</name></author><author><name>Upasana Ramphal</name></author><author><name>Vagner Fonseca</name></author><author><name>Vincent Enouf</name></author><author><name>Vivianne Gorova</name></author><author><name>Wael H. Roshdy</name></author><author><name>William K. Ampofo</name></author><author><name>Wolfgang Preiser</name></author><author><name>Wonderful T. Choga</name></author><author><name>Yaw Bediako</name></author><author><name>Yenew K Tebeje</name></author><author><name>Yeshnee Naidoo</name></author><author><name>Zaydah R. de Laurent</name></author><author><name>Sofonias K. Tessema</name></author><author><name>Tulio de Oliveira</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The progression of the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic in Africa has so far been heterogeneous and the full impact is not yet well understood. Here, we describe the genomic epidemiology using a dataset of 8746 genomes from 33 African countries and two overseas territories. We show that the epidemics in most countries were initiated by importations, predominantly from Europe, which diminished following the early introduction of international travel restrictions. As the pandemic progressed, ongoing transmission in many countries and increasing mobility led to the emergence and spread within the continent of many variants of concern and interest, such as B.1.351, B.1.525, A.23.1 and C.1.1. Although distorted by low sampling numbers and blind-spots, the findings highlight that Africa must not be left behind in the global pandemic response, otherwise it could become a breeding ground for new variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.06.21256755</id><title>Clinical coding of long COVID in English primary care: a federated analysis of 58 million patient records in situ using OpenSAFELY (280 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.193962+00:00</updated><author><name> </name></author><author><name>Alex J Walker</name></author><author><name>Brian MacKenna</name></author><author><name>Peter Inglesby</name></author><author><name>Christopher T Rentsch</name></author><author><name>Helen J Curtis</name></author><author><name>Caroline E Morton</name></author><author><name>Jessica Morley</name></author><author><name>Amir Mehrkar</name></author><author><name>Seb Bacon</name></author><author><name>George Hickman</name></author><author><name>Chris Bates</name></author><author><name>Richard Croker</name></author><author><name>David Evans</name></author><author><name>Tom Ward</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Cockburn</name></author><author><name>Simon Davy</name></author><author><name>Krishnan Bhaskaran</name></author><author><name>Anna Schultze</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth J Williamson</name></author><author><name>William J Hulme</name></author><author><name>Helen I McDonald</name></author><author><name>Laurie Tomlinson</name></author><author><name>Rohini Mathur</name></author><author><name>Rosalind M Eggo</name></author><author><name>Kevin Wing</name></author><author><name>Angel YS Wong</name></author><author><name>Harriet Forbes</name></author><author><name>John Tazare</name></author><author><name>John Parry</name></author><author><name>Frank Hester</name></author><author><name>Sam Harper</name></author><author><name>Shaun O’Hanlon</name></author><author><name>Alex Eavis</name></author><author><name>Richard Jarvis</name></author><author><name>Dima Avramov</name></author><author><name>Paul Griffiths</name></author><author><name>Aaron Fowles</name></author><author><name>Nasreen Parkes</name></author><author><name>Ian J Douglas</name></author><author><name>Stephen JW Evans</name></author><author><name>Liam Smeeth</name></author><author><name>Ben Goldacre</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Long COVID is a term to describe new or persistent symptoms at least four weeks after onset of acute COVID-19. Clinical codes to describe this phenomenon were released in November 2020 in the UK, but it is not known how these codes have been used in practice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Working on behalf of NHS England, we used OpenSAFELY data encompassing 96% of the English population. We measured the proportion of people with a recorded code for long COVID, overall and by demographic factors, electronic health record software system, and week. We also measured variation in recording amongst practices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Long COVID was recorded for 23,273 people. Coding was unevenly distributed amongst practices, with 26.7% of practices having not used the codes at all. Regional variation was high, ranging between 20.3 per 100,000 people for East of England (95% confidence interval 19.3-21.4) and 55.6 in London (95% CI 54.1-57.1). The rate was higher amongst women (52.1, 95% CI 51.3-52.9) compared to men (28.1, 95% CI 27.5-28.7), and higher amongst practices using EMIS software (53.7, 95% CI 52.9-54.4) compared to TPP software (20.9, 95% CI 20.3-21.4).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Long COVID coding in primary care is low compared with early reports of long COVID prevalence. This may reflect under-coding, sub-optimal communication of clinical terms, under-diagnosis, a true low prevalence of long COVID diagnosed by clinicians, or a combination of factors. We recommend increased awareness of diagnostic codes, to facilitate research and planning of services; and surveys of clinicians’ experiences, to complement ongoing patient surveys.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.21256578</id><title>Live virus neutralisation testing in convalescent patients and subjects vaccinated against 19A, 20B, 20I/501Y.V1 and 20H/501Y.V2 isolates of SARS-CoV-2 (295 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.193088+00:00</updated><author><name>Claudia Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Carla Saade</name></author><author><name>Antonin Bal</name></author><author><name>Martine Valette</name></author><author><name>Kahina Saker</name></author><author><name>Bruno Lina</name></author><author><name>Laurence Josset</name></author><author><name>Mary-Anne Trabaud</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Thiery</name></author><author><name>Elisabeth Botelho-Nevers</name></author><author><name>Stéphane Paul</name></author><author><name>Paul Verhoeven</name></author><author><name>Thomas Bourlet</name></author><author><name>Sylvie Pillet</name></author><author><name>Florence Morfin</name></author><author><name>Sophie Trouillet-Assant</name></author><author><name>Bruno Pozzetto</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 mutations appeared recently and can lead to conformational changes in the spike protein and probably induce modifications in antigenicity. In this study, we wanted to assess the neutralizing capacity of antibodies to prevent cell infection, using a live virus neutralisation test.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sera samples were collected from different populations: two-dose vaccinated COVID-19-naïve healthcare workers (HCWs; Pfizer-BioNTech BNT161b2), 6-months post mild COVID-19 HCWs, and critical COVID-19 patients. We tested various clades such as 19A (initial one), 20B (B.1.1.241 lineage), 20I/501Y.V1 (B.1.1.7 lineage), and 20H/501Y.V2 (B.1.351 lineage).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;No significant difference was observed between the 20B and 19A isolates for HCWs with mild COVID-19 and critical patients. However, a significant decrease in neutralisation ability was found for 20I/501Y.V1 in comparison with 19A isolate for critical patients and HCWs 6-months post infection. Concerning 20H/501Y.V2, all populations had a significant reduction in neutralising antibody titres in comparison with the 19A isolate. Interestingly, a significant difference in neutralisation capacity was observed for vaccinated HCWs between the two variants whereas it was not significant for the convalescent groups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neutralisation capacity was slightly reduced for critical patients and HCWs 6-months post infection. No neutralisation escape could be feared concerning the two variants of concern in both populations. The reduced neutralising response observed towards the 20H/501Y.V2 in comparison with the 19A and 20I/501Y.V1 isolates in fully immunized subjects with the BNT162b2 vaccine is a striking finding of the study.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.07.21256539</id><title>Immune profile of children with post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection (Long Covid) (312 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T02:24:51.188446+00:00</updated><author><name>Gabriele Di Sante</name></author><author><name>Danilo Buonsenso</name></author><author><name>Cristina De Rose</name></author><author><name>Piero Valentini</name></author><author><name>Francesco Ria</name></author><author><name>Maurizio Sanguinetti</name></author><author><name>Michela Sali</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;There is increasing reporting by patients’ organization and researchers of long covid (or post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 - PASC), characterized by symptoms such as fatigue, dyspnea, chest pain, cognitive and sleeping disturbances, arthralgia and decline in quality of life. Immune system dysregulation with a hyperinflammatory state, direct viral toxicity, endothelial damage and microvascular injury have been proposed as pathologenic mechanisms. Recently, cohorts of children with PASC have been reported in Italy, Sweden and Russia. However, immunological studies of children with PASC have never been performed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this study, we documented significant immunologic differences between children that completely recovered from acute infection and those with PASC, providing the first objective laboratory sign of the existence of PASC in children.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>