<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.915969+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.23.449568</id><title>Increased lung cell entry of B.1.617.2 and evasion of antibodies induced by infection and BNT162b2 vaccination (196 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.916699+00:00</updated><author><name>Prerna Arora</name></author><author><name>Amy Kempf</name></author><author><name>Inga Nehlmeier</name></author><author><name>Anzhalika Sidarovich</name></author><author><name>Nadine Krüger</name></author><author><name>Luise Graichen</name></author><author><name>Anna-Sophie Moldenhauer</name></author><author><name>Martin S. Winkler</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Schulz</name></author><author><name>Hans-Martin Jäck</name></author><author><name>Metodi V. Stankov</name></author><author><name>Georg M. N. Behrens</name></author><author><name>Stefan Pöhlmann</name></author><author><name>Markus Hoffmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The delta variant of SARS-CoV-2, B.1.617.2, emerged in India and has subsequently spread to over 80 countries. B.1.617.2 rapidly replaced B.1.1.7 as the dominant virus in the United Kingdom, resulting in a steep increase in new infections, and a similar development is expected for other countries. Effective countermeasures require information on susceptibility of B.1.617.2 to control by antibodies elicited by vaccines and used for COVID-19 therapy. We show, using pseudotyping, that B.1.617.2 evades control by antibodies induced upon infection and BNT162b2 vaccination, although with lower efficiency as compared to B.1.351. Further, we found that B.1.617.2 is resistant against Bamlanivimab, a monoclonal antibody with emergency use authorization for COVID-19 therapy. Finally, we show increased Calu-3-lung cell entry and enhanced cell-to-cell fusion of B.1.617.2, which may contribute to augmented transmissibility and pathogenicity of this variant. These results identify B.1.617.2 as an immune evasion variant with increased capacity to enter and fuse lung cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.23.449568" rel="alternate" title="Increased lung cell entry of B.1.617.2 and evasion of antibodies induced by infection and BNT162b2 vaccination (196 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-06-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.21.449205</id><title>One viral sequence for each host? – The neglected within-host diversity as the main stage of SARS-CoV-2 evolution (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.917268+00:00</updated><author><name>Yongsen Ruan</name></author><author><name>Mei Hou</name></author><author><name>Jiarui Li</name></author><author><name>Yangzi Song</name></author><author><name>Hurng-YI Wang</name></author><author><name>Xionglei He</name></author><author><name>Hui Zeng</name></author><author><name>Jian Lu</name></author><author><name>Haijun Wen</name></author><author><name>Chen Chen</name></author><author><name>Chung-I Wu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The standard practice of presenting one viral sequence for each infected individual implicitly assumes low within-host genetic diversity. It places the emphasis on the viral evolution between, rather than within, hosts. To determine this diversity, we collect SARS-CoV-2 samples from the same patient multiple times. Our own data in conjunction with previous reports show that two viral samples collected from the same individual are often very different due to the substantial within-host diversity. Each sample captures only a small part of the total diversity that is transiently and locally released from infected cells. Hence, the global SARS-CoV-2 population is a meta-population consisting of the viruses in all the infected hosts, each of which harboring a genetically diverse sub-population. Advantageous mutations must be present first as the within-host diversity before they are revealed as between-host polymorphism. The early detection of such diversity in multiple hosts could be an alarm for potentially dangerous mutations. In conclusion, the main forces of viral evolution, i.e., mutation, drift, recombination and selection, all operate within hosts and should be studied accordingly. Several significant implications are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.21.449205" rel="alternate" title="One viral sequence for each host? – The neglected within-host diversity as the main stage of SARS-CoV-2 evolution (26 tweets)"/><category term="Evolutionary Biology"/><published>2021-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.15.21258669</id><title>COMPARATIVE IMMUNOGENICITY OF BNT162b2 mRNA VACCINE WITH NATURAL COVID-19 INFECTION (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.917794+00:00</updated><author><name>Mina Psichogiou</name></author><author><name>Andreas Karabinis</name></author><author><name>Garyphallia Poulakou</name></author><author><name>Anastasia Antoniadou</name></author><author><name>Anastasia Kotanidou</name></author><author><name>Dimitrios Degiannis</name></author><author><name>Ioanna D. Pavlopoulou</name></author><author><name>Antigoni Chaidaroglou</name></author><author><name>Sotirios Roussos</name></author><author><name>Elpida Mastrogianni</name></author><author><name>Irene Eliadi</name></author><author><name>Dimitrios Basoulis</name></author><author><name>Konstantinos Petsios</name></author><author><name>Konstantinos Leontis</name></author><author><name>Eleni Kakkalou</name></author><author><name>Konstantinos Protopapas</name></author><author><name>Edison Jahaj</name></author><author><name>Maria Pratikaki</name></author><author><name>Konstantinos N. Syrigos</name></author><author><name>Pagona Lagiou</name></author><author><name>Helen Gogas</name></author><author><name>Sotirios Tsiodras</name></author><author><name>Gkikas Magiorkinis</name></author><author><name>Dimitrios Paraskevis</name></author><author><name>Vana Sypsa</name></author><author><name>Angelos Hatzakis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mRNA vaccine BNT162b2 has proven highly effective and currently many millions are being vaccinated. There are limited and conflicting data from immunogenicity studies on the effects of age, gender, vaccination side effects (VSE), risk factors for severe COVID-19 (RFS-COV), obesity (BMI) and previous SARS-CoV-2 (Pr-CoV) Moreover, immunogenicity data from COVID-19 patients comparing various disease categories of natural infection i.e. asymptomatic vs mild vs moderate vs severe infection are sparse, and include limited number of individuals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study included 871 vaccinated health care workers (HCW) and 181 patients with natural infection. Immunogenicity was assessed by a quantative assay measuring anti-SARS-CoV-2 against the RBD domain of the spike protein (anti-RBD) and anti-SARS-CoV-2 against nucleocapsid protein (anti-N). Samples were collected 1-2 weeks after completion of the 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; dose in the vaccinated HCWs and 15-59 days post symptoms onset in patients with natural infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The concentration of anti-RBD in vaccinated individuals after multivariable analysis was significantly associated with age, gender, VSE and Pr-CoV. Specifically, anti-RBD median levels (95% CI) were lower by 2,466 (651-5,583), 6,228 (3,254-9,203) and 7,651 (4,479-10,823) AU/ml in 35-44, 45-54, 55-70 yrs respectively, compared with 18-34 yrs group. In females, median levels of anti-RBD were higher by 2,823 (859-4,787) compared with males, in individuals with VSE were higher by 5,024 (3,122-6,926) compared with no VSE, and in HCWs with Pr-CoV were higher by 9,971 (5,158-14,783) AU/ml compared with HCWs without Pr-CoV.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among individuals with natural infection, the median anti-RBD levels were 14.8 times higher in patients with critical COVID-19 infection compared with non-hospitalized individuals. The ratio of anti-RBD in vaccinated individuals versus those with natural infection varied from 1.0 up to 19.4 according to the clinical subgroup of natural infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study proves the high immunogenicity of BNT162b2 vaccine although its sustainability remains to be seen. The use of comparative data from natural infection serological panels, expressing the clinical heterogeneity of natural infection may facilitate early decisions for vaccine evaluation in clinical trials.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.15.21258669" rel="alternate" title="COMPARATIVE IMMUNOGENICITY OF BNT162b2 mRNA VACCINE WITH NATURAL COVID-19 INFECTION (18 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.14.21258882</id><title>Inequalities in initiation of COVID19 vaccination by age and population group in Israel-December 2020-April 2021 (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.919043+00:00</updated><author><name>Yanay Gorelik</name></author><author><name>Michael Edelstein</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Israel, COVID19 vaccination coverage varies widely by population group and age. Despite the vaccine being locally and freely available in the entire country. Comparing crude coverage between localities and population groups is misleading because of differing age structures in different population groups. In order to describe inequalities in COVID19 vaccine initiation we determined differences in age-specific dose 1 vaccine coverage between the main population groups in Israel, and characterised the influence of age on vaccine coverage within each of these groups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We obtained daily doses administered by municipality and age from the Ministry of Health, and demographic data from the Central Bureau of Statistics. We determined whether the relative proportion of people vaccinated in each age group (15-19, 20-29, 30-39, 40-49, 50-59, 60+) changed by population group (General Jewish, Ultra-Orthodox and Arab) using ANOVA and quantified association between age, population group and vaccine coverage using binomial regression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;8,507,723 individuals in 268 localities were included. Compared with the General Jewish population, vaccine coverage was lower among the Arab and Ultra-Orthodox populations and lowest in the Ultra-Orthodox population in all age groups. Gaps between population groups differed according to age group (p&amp;lt;0.001). In all populations, coverage decreased with decreasing age (p&amp;lt;0.001). The Ultra-orthodox population was the least vaccinated in all age groups relatively to those aged 60 and over&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In all age groups, the Ultra-Orthodox population had the lowest vaccine coverage. The younger the age group, the more Ultra-Orthodox Jews are diverging from their age peers in terms of initiating COVID19 vaccination. These findings suggest generational differences in terms of vaccination behaviour in this group. Qualitative studies understanding the causes behind this divergence can inform tailored vaccination strategies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.14.21258882" rel="alternate" title="Inequalities in initiation of COVID19 vaccination by age and population group in Israel-December 2020-April 2021 (8 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.23.449558</id><title>Unsupervised classification of SARS-CoV-2 genomic sequences uncovers hidden genetic diversity and suggests an efficient strategy for genomic surveillance (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.919482+00:00</updated><author><name>Matteo Chiara</name></author><author><name>David S. Horner</name></author><author><name>Erika Ferrandi</name></author><author><name>Carmela Gissi</name></author><author><name>Graziano Pesole</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Accurate and timely monitoring of emerging genomic diversity is crucial for limiting the spread of potentially more transmissible/pathogenic strains of SARS-CoV-2. At the time of writing, over 1.8M distinct viral genome sequences have been made publicly available, and a sophisticated nomenclature system based on phylogenetic evidence and expert manual curation has allowed the relatively rapid classification of emerging lineages of potential concern.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we propose a complementary approach that integrates fine-grained spatiotemporal estimates of allele frequency with unsupervised clustering of viral haplotypes, and demonstrate that multiple highly frequent genetic variants, arising within large and/or rapidly expanding SARS-CoV-2 lineages, have highly biased geographic distributions and are not adequately captured by current SARS-CoV-2 nomenclature standards.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our results advocate a partial revision of current methods used to track SARS-CoV-2 genomic diversity and highlight the importance of the application of strategies based on the systematic analysis and integration of regional data. Here we provide a complementary, completely automated and reproducible framework for the mapping of genetic diversity in time and across different geographic regions, and for the prioritization of virus variants of potential concern. We believe that the approach outlined in this study will contribute to relevant advances to current genomic surveillance methods.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.23.449558" rel="alternate" title="Unsupervised classification of SARS-CoV-2 genomic sequences uncovers hidden genetic diversity and suggests an efficient strategy for genomic surveillance (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-06-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.17.21258666</id><title>Predicting COVID-19 incidence in French hospitals using human contact network analytics (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.919836+00:00</updated><author><name>Christian Selinger</name></author><author><name>Marc Choisy</name></author><author><name>Samuel Alizon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) was detected in Wuhan, China in 2019 and spread worldwide within few weeks. The COVID-19 epidemic started to gain traction in France in March 2020. Sub-national hospital admissions and deaths were then recorded daily and served as the main policy indicators. Concurrently, mobile phone positioning data have been curated to determine the frequency of users being colocalized within a given distance. Contrarily to individual tracking data, these can provide a proxy of human contact networks between subnational administrative units. Motivated by numerous studies correlating human mobility data and disease incidence, we developed predictive time series models of hospital incidence between July 2020 and April 2021. Adding human contact network analytics such as clustering coefficients, contact network strength, null links or curvature as regressors, we found that predictions can be improved substantially (more than 50%) both at the national and sub-national for up to two weeks. Our sub-national analysis also revealed the importance of spatial structure, as incidence in colocalized administrative units improved predictions. This original application of network analytics from co-localisation data to epidemic spread opens new perspectives for epidemics forecasting and public health.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We use novel human contact network analytics based on colocation data of mobile app users to follow the dynamics of disease incidence and interventions of COVID-19 in France.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Time series predictions of hospital incidence are greatly improved by adding these analytics as regressors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sub-national analysis highlights both spatial correlations of incidence and network analytics to obtain high-precision predictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.17.21258666" rel="alternate" title="Predicting COVID-19 incidence in French hospitals using human contact network analytics (6 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-06-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.14.21258886</id><title>The majority of the variation in COVID-19 rates between nations is explained by median age, obesity rate, and island status (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.920209+00:00</updated><author><name>Joseph B. Fraiman</name></author><author><name>Ethan Ludwin-Peery</name></author><author><name>Sarah Ludwin-Peery</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Since the World Health Organization declared SARS-CoV-2 to be a global pandemic on March 11, 2020, nearly every nation on earth has reported infections. Incidence and prevalence of COVID-19 case rates have demonstrated extreme geospatial and temporal variability across the globe. The outbreaks in some countries are extreme and devastating, while other countries face outbreaks that are relatively minor. The causes of these differences between nations remain poorly understood, and identifying the factors that underlie this variation is critical to understand the dynamics of this disease in order to better respond to this and future pandemics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we examine four factors that we anticipated would explain much of the variation in COVID-19 rates between nations: median age, obesity rate, island status, and strength of border closure measures. Clinical evidence suggests that age and obesity increase both the likelihood of infection and transmission in individual patients, which make them plausible demographic factors. The third factor, whether or not each country is an island nation, was selected because the geographical isolation of islands is expected to influence COVID-19 transmission. The fourth factor of border closure was selected because of its anticipated interaction with island nation status.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Together, these four variables are able to explain a majority of the international variance in COVID-19 case rates. Using a dataset of 190 countries, simple modeling based on these four factors and their interactions explains more than 70% of the total variance between countries. With additional covariates, more complex modeling and higher-order interactions explains more than 80% of the variance. These novel findings offer a solution to explain the unusual global variation of COVID-19 that has remained largely elusive throughout the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.14.21258886" rel="alternate" title="The majority of the variation in COVID-19 rates between nations is explained by median age, obesity rate, and island status (6 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.23.449535</id><title>Integrative COVID-19 Biological Network Inference with Probabilistic Core Decomposition (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.920560+00:00</updated><author><name>Yang Guo</name></author><author><name>Fatemeh Esfahani</name></author><author><name>Xiaojian Shao</name></author><author><name>Venkatesh Srinivasan</name></author><author><name>Alex Thomo</name></author><author><name>Li Xing</name></author><author><name>Xuekui Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The SARS-CoV-2 coronavirus is responsible for millions of deaths around the world. To help contribute to the understanding of crucial knowledge and to further generate new hypotheses relevant to SARS-CoV-2 and human protein interactions, we make use of the information abundant Biomine probabilistic database and extend the experimentally identified SARS-CoV-2-human protein-protein interaction (PPI) network &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt;. We generate an extended network by integrating information from the Biomine database and the PPI network. To generate novel hypotheses, we focus on the high-connectivity sub-communities that overlap most with the PPI network in the extended network. Therefore, we propose a new data analysis pipeline that can efficiently compute core decomposition on the extended network and identify dense subgraphs. We then evaluate the identified dense subgraph and the generated hypotheses in three contexts: literature validation for uncovered virus targeting genes and proteins, gene function enrichment analysis on subgraphs, and literature support on drug repurposing for identified tissues and diseases related to COVID-19. The majority types of the generated hypotheses are proteins with their encoding genes and we rank them by sorting their connections to known PPI network nodes. In addition, we compile a comprehensive list of novel genes, and proteins potentially related to COVID-19, as well as novel diseases which might be comorbidities. Together with the generated hypotheses, our results provide novel knowledge relevant to COVID-19 for further validation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.23.449535" rel="alternate" title="Integrative COVID-19 Biological Network Inference with Probabilistic Core Decomposition (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.17.21258371</id><title>ADESSO detects SARS-CoV-2 and its variants: extensive clinical validation of an optimised CRISPR-Cas13-based COVID-19 test (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.920910+00:00</updated><author><name>Beatrice Casati</name></author><author><name>J.P. Verdi</name></author><author><name>A. Hempelmann</name></author><author><name>Maximilian Kittel</name></author><author><name>Andrea Gutierrez Klaebisch</name></author><author><name>Sybille Welker</name></author><author><name>Sonal Asthana</name></author><author><name>Pavle Boskovic</name></author><author><name>Ka Hou Man</name></author><author><name>Bernhard Radlwimmer</name></author><author><name>C. Erec Stebbins</name></author><author><name>Thomas Miethke</name></author><author><name>F. Nina Papavasiliou</name></author><author><name>Riccardo Pecori</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;With the coronavirus disease 19 (COVID-19) pandemic now deep into its second year, widespread testing for the detection of the causative severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) is fundamental. The gold standard reverse transcription quantitative PCR (RT-qPCR) cannot keep up with the high demand alone, therefore alternative diagnostic tests are needed. Here we present ADESSO (Accurate Detection of Evolving SARS-CoV-2 through SHERLOCK Optimisation), an optimised version of the CRISPR-based SHERLOCK (Specific High-sensitivity Enzymatic Reporter unLOCKing) assay. After an extensive validation on 983 clinical samples, we demonstrated that ADESSO has a sensitivity of 96% and a specificity of 100% on extracted RNA, comparable to RT-qPCR. Its performance on unextracted samples still allows the detection of the more infectious 75% of the COVID-19 positive population, making it suitable for point-of-care (POC) testing. Interestingly, our in parallel comparison of 390 matching swab and gargle samples showed consistently lower viral loads in gargle specimens. We also validated ADESSO for the detection of the B.1.1.7 variant and demonstrated that ADESSO is adaptable to any variant of concern in less than one week, a critical feature now that worrisome SARS-CoV-2 variants are spreading all around the world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.17.21258371" rel="alternate" title="ADESSO detects SARS-CoV-2 and its variants: extensive clinical validation of an optimised CRISPR-Cas13-based COVID-19 test (5 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>