<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv/medRxiv COVID preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.100650+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/covid/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.03.21263103</id><title>The prevalence of adaptive immunity to COVID-19 and reinfection after recovery – a comprehensive systematic review and meta-analysis of 12 011 447 individuals (170 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.101328+00:00</updated><author><name>Tawanda Chivese</name></author><author><name>Joshua T. Matizanadzo</name></author><author><name>Omran A. H. Musa</name></author><author><name>George Hindy</name></author><author><name>Luis Furuya-Kanamori</name></author><author><name>Nazmul Islam</name></author><author><name>Rafal Al-Shebly</name></author><author><name>Rana Shalaby</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Habibullah</name></author><author><name>Talal Al-Marwani</name></author><author><name>Rizeq F Hourani</name></author><author><name>Ahmed D Nawaz</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Z Haider</name></author><author><name>Mohamed M. Emara</name></author><author><name>Farhan Cyprian</name></author><author><name>Suhail A. R. Doi</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study aims to estimate the prevalence and longevity of detectable SARS-CoV-2 antibodies as well as memory cells T and B after recovery. In addition, the prevalence of COVID-19 reinfection, and the preventive efficacy of previous infection with SARS-CoV-2 were investigated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods and analyses&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A synthesis of existing research was conducted. The Cochrane Library for COVID-19 resources, the China Academic Journals Full Text Database, PubMed, and Scopus as well as preprint servers were searched for studies conducted between 1 January 2020 to 1 April 2021. We included studies with the relevant outcomes of interest. All included studies were assessed for methodological quality and pooled estimates of relevant outcomes were obtained in a meta-analysis using a bias adjusted synthesis method. Proportions were synthesized with the Freeman-Tukey double arcsine transformation and binary outcomes using the odds ratio (OR). Heterogeneity between included studies was assessed using the I2 and Cochran’s Q statistics and publication bias was assessed using Doi plots.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fifty-four studies, from 18 countries, with a total of 12 011 447 individuals, followed up to 8 months after recovery were included. At 6-8 months after recovery, the prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 specific immunological memory remained high; IgG – 90.4% (95%CI 72.2-99.9, I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;=89.0%, 5 studies), CD4+ - 91.7% (95%CI 78.2 – 97.1, one study), and memory B cells 80.6% (95%CI 65.0-90.2, one study) and the pooled prevalence of reinfection was 0.2% (95%CI 0.0 – 0.7, I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 98.8, 9 studies). Individuals previously infected with SARS-CoV-2 had an 81% reduction in odds of a reinfection (OR 0.19, 95% CI 0.1 - 0.3, I&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 90.5%, 5 studies).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Around 90% of people previously infected with SARS-CoV-2 had evidence of immunological memory to SARS-CoV-2, which was sustained for at least 6-8 months after recovery, and had a low risk of reinfection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Registration&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;PROSPERO: CRD42020201234&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What is already known on this topic&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individuals who recover from COVID-19 may have immunity against future infection but the proportion who develop immunity is uncertain. Further, there is uncertainty about the proportion of individuals who get reinfected with COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What this study adds&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using data from 54 studies with follow up time up to 8 months after recovery, during the period February 2020-February 2021, we found that, post-COVID-19, up to 90% of individuals had antibodies and memory T and B cells against SARS-CoV-2. We also found a pooled prevalence of reinfection of 0.2%, and that infection conferred an 81% decrease in odds of reinfection with SARS-CoV-2, compared to unimmunized individuals without previous COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This review of 12 million individuals presents evidence that most individuals who recover from COVID-19 develop immunological memory to SARS-CoV-2, which was still detectable for up to 8 months. Further, reinfection after recovery from COVID-19 was rare during the first 8 months after recovery, with a prevalence below 1%, while prior infection confers protection with an odds ratio of 0.19 and a preventive efficacy of 80% at a baseline prevalence of 5% for COVID-19 in a community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Implications of all the available evidence&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individuals with a history of COVID-19 infection have immunity against the disease for up to 8 months, although this period could be longer. These individuals could be prioritized last for COVID-19 vaccinations or considered for single dose vaccinations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Strengths&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This comprehensive review addresses key questions on prevalent immunological memory and risk of reinfection in individuals with prior confirmed COVID-19 using robust systematic review methods.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Limitations&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some of the included studies which examined prevalent immunological memory were small studies which were affected by loss to follow up. The review did not examine evidence for immunity against the new divergent variants, which may be more likely to have immune evasion behaviour and may present a higher risk of reinfection. Lastly, the review did not examine the effect of the severity of COVID-19 on both immunological memory and the risk of reinfection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.03.21263103" rel="alternate" title="The prevalence of adaptive immunity to COVID-19 and reinfection after recovery – a comprehensive systematic review and meta-analysis of 12 011 447 individuals (170 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-09-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.04.21263115</id><title>Durability analysis of the highly effective BNT162b2 vaccine against COVID-19 (101 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.101915+00:00</updated><author><name>Arjun Puranik</name></author><author><name>Patrick J. Lenehan</name></author><author><name>John C. O’Horo</name></author><author><name>Michiel J.M. Niesen</name></author><author><name>Abinash Virk</name></author><author><name>Melanie D. Swift</name></author><author><name>Walter Kremers</name></author><author><name>A.J. Venkatakrishnan</name></author><author><name>Joel E. Gordon</name></author><author><name>Holly L. Geyer</name></author><author><name>Leigh Lewis Speicher</name></author><author><name>Venky Soundararajan</name></author><author><name>Andrew D. Badley</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 breakthrough infections have been increasingly reported in fully vaccinated individuals. We conducted a test-negative case-control study to assess the durability of protection after full vaccination with BNT162b2, defined as 14 days after the second dose, against polymerase chain reaction (PCR)-confirmed symptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection, in a national medical practice between February 1, 2021 and August 22, 2021. We fit conditional logistic regression (CLR) models stratified on residential county and calendar time of testing to assess the association between time elapsed since vaccination and the odds of symptomatic infection or non-COVID-19 hospitalization (negative control), adjusted for several covariates. The primary population included 652 individuals who had a positive symptomatic test after full vaccination with BNT162b2 (cases) and 5,946 individuals with at least one negative symptomatic test after full vaccination (controls). The adjusted odds of symptomatic infection were higher 120 days after full vaccination versus at the date of full vaccination (Odds Ratio [OR]: 3.21, 95% confidence interval [CI]: 1.33-7.74). Importantly, the odds of infection were still lower 150 days after the first BNT162b2 dose as compared to 4 days after the first dose (OR: 0.3, 95% CI: 0.19-0.45), when immune protection approximates the unvaccinated status. Low rates of COVID-19 associated hospitalization or death in this cohort precluded analyses of these severe outcomes. The odds of experiencing a non-COVID-19 hospitalization decreased with time since vaccination, suggesting a possible underestimation of waning protection by this approach due to confounding factors. Taken together, these data constitute an early signal for waning protection against symptomatic illness while also providing reassurance that BNT162b2 continues to protect against symptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection several months after full vaccination. Continued surveillance of COVID-19 vaccine durability, particularly against severe disease, is critical to guide effective and equitable strategies to respond to the pandemic, including distribution of booster doses, development of new vaccines, and implementation of both pharmaceutical and nonpharmaceutical interventions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.04.21263115" rel="alternate" title="Durability analysis of the highly effective BNT162b2 vaccine against COVID-19 (101 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-09-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.04.21263123</id><title>Assessment of COVID-19 intervention strategies in the Nordic countries using genomic epidemiology (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.102505+00:00</updated><author><name>Sebastian Duchene</name></author><author><name>Leo Featherstone</name></author><author><name>Birgitte Freiesleben de Blasio</name></author><author><name>Edward C. Holmes</name></author><author><name>Jon Bohlin</name></author><author><name>John H.-O. Pettersson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Nordic countries, defined here as Norway, Sweden, Denmark, Finland and Iceland, are known for their comparable demographics and political systems. Since these countries implemented different COVID-19 intervention strategies, they provide a natural laboratory for examining how COVID-19 policies and mitigation strategies affected the propagation, evolution and spread of the SARS-CoV-2 virus. We explored how the duration, the size and number of transmission clusters, defined as country-specific monophyletic groups in a SARS-CoV-2 phylogenetic tree, differed between the Nordic countries. We found that Sweden had the largest number of COVID-19 transmission clusters followed by Denmark, Norway, Finland and Iceland. Moreover, Sweden and Denmark had the largest, and most enduring, transmission clusters followed by Norway, Finland and Iceland. In addition, there was a significant positive association between transmission cluster size and duration, suggesting that the size of transmission clusters could be reduced by rapid and effective contact tracing. Thus, these data indicate that to reduce the general burden of COVID-19 there should be a focus on limiting dense gatherings and their subsequent contacts to keep the number, size and duration of transmission clusters to a minimum. Our results further suggest that although geographical connectivity, population density and openness influence the spread and the size of SARS-CoV-2 transmission clusters, country-specific intervention strategies had the largest single impact.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.04.21263123" rel="alternate" title="Assessment of COVID-19 intervention strategies in the Nordic countries using genomic epidemiology (12 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-09-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.459641</id><title>Targeting Stem-loop 1 of the SARS-CoV-2 5’UTR to suppress viral translation and Nsp1 evasion (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.102876+00:00</updated><author><name>Setu M. Vora</name></author><author><name>Pietro Fontana</name></author><author><name>Valerie Leger</name></author><author><name>Ying Zhang</name></author><author><name>Tian-Min Fu</name></author><author><name>Judy Lieberman</name></author><author><name>Lee Gehrke</name></author><author><name>Ming Shi</name></author><author><name>Longfei Wang</name></author><author><name>Hao Wu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 is a highly pathogenic virus that evades anti-viral immunity by interfering with host protein synthesis, mRNA stability, and protein trafficking. The SARS-CoV-2 nonstructural protein 1 (Nsp1) uses its C-terminal domain to block the mRNA entry channel of the 40S ribosome to inhibit host protein synthesis. However, how SARS-CoV-2 circumvents Nsp1-mediated suppression for viral protein synthesis and if the mechanism can be targeted therapeutically remain unclear. Here we show that N- and C-terminal domains of Nsp1 coordinate to drive a tuned ratio of viral to host translation, likely to maintain a certain level of host fitness while maximizing replication. We reveal that the SL1 region of the SARS-CoV-2 5’ UTR is necessary and sufficient to evade Nsp1-mediated translational suppression. Targeting SL1 with locked nucleic acid antisense oligonucleotides (ASOs) inhibits viral translation and makes SARS-CoV-2 5’ UTR vulnerable to Nsp1 suppression, hindering viral replication in vitro at a nanomolar concentration. Thus, SL1 allows Nsp1 to switch infected cells from host to SARS-CoV-2 translation, presenting a therapeutic target against COVID-19 that is conserved among immune-evasive variants. This unique strategy of unleashing a virus’ own virulence mechanism against itself could force a critical trade off between drug resistance and pathogenicity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.459641" rel="alternate" title="Targeting Stem-loop 1 of the SARS-CoV-2 5’UTR to suppress viral translation and Nsp1 evasion (8 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459280</id><title>TET1 controls Cxcl1 induction by DNA demethylation and promotes neutrophil recruitment during acute lung injury (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.103756+00:00</updated><author><name>Kathleen M. Yee</name></author><author><name>Richard W. Shuai</name></author><author><name>Bin Liu</name></author><author><name>Christian A. Huynh</name></author><author><name>Chao Niu</name></author><author><name>Hailey R. Lee</name></author><author><name>Min S. Lee</name></author><author><name>Jirui Wen</name></author><author><name>Jian Zou</name></author><author><name>Jiang Wu</name></author><author><name>Ke Shuai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neutrophils are rapidly recruited from the peripheral blood to the inflammatory site to initiate inflammatory response against pathogenic infections. The process to recruit neutrophils must be properly regulated since the abnormal accumulation of neutrophils can cause organ damage and dysfunction. The acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS)/acute lung injury (ALI) is a common cause of respiratory failure that is characterized by the infiltration of neutrophils and epithelial integrity disruption. Indeed, recent studies suggest a pathogenic role of neutrophils in the clinic severity of the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) ARDS. The chemokine CXCL1, which is rapidly induced by inflammatory stimuli, plays a key role in neutrophil influx during lung inflammation. The molecular basis of &lt;italic&gt;Cxcl1&lt;/italic&gt; induction is not fully understood. Here we report that TET1, a member of the ten eleven translocation (TET) methylcytosine dioxygenase protein family, displays a striking specificity in the regulation of gene expression in macrophages. RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) analysis showed that &lt;italic&gt;Tet1&lt;/italic&gt; disruption significantly altered the expression of only 48 genes that include &lt;italic&gt;Cxcl1&lt;/italic&gt; and several other genes known to be important for cell migration and trafficking in bone marrow derived macrophages (BMDMs) in response to LPS stimulation. TET1 regulates the induction of &lt;italic&gt;Cxcl1&lt;/italic&gt; by facilitating the DNA demethylation of the &lt;italic&gt;Cxcl1&lt;/italic&gt; promoter. In &lt;italic&gt;Tet1&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;−/−&lt;/sup&gt; mice, the induction of &lt;italic&gt;Cxcl1&lt;/italic&gt; was suppressed, resulting in defective neutrophil recruitment to the lung during LPS-induced acute lung injury. Our results identify a novel epigenetic mechanism that selectively controls &lt;italic&gt;Cxcl1&lt;/italic&gt; induction and neutrophil recruitment during acute lung injury.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key Points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;TET1 has a striking specificity in macrophage gene regulation and controls &lt;italic&gt;Cxcl1&lt;/italic&gt; induction by inflammatory stimuli via DNA demethylation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neutrophil recruitment is defective in &lt;italic&gt;Tet1&lt;/italic&gt; deficient mice during acute lung injury&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459280" rel="alternate" title="TET1 controls Cxcl1 induction by DNA demethylation and promotes neutrophil recruitment during acute lung injury (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>