<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.141915+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462180</id><title>Extracellular Electron Transfer Enables Cellular Control of Cu(I)-catalyzed Alkyne-Azide Cycloaddition (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.146643+00:00</updated><author><name>Gina Partipilo</name></author><author><name>Austin J. Graham</name></author><author><name>Brian Belardi</name></author><author><name>Benjamin K. Keitz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Extracellular electron transfer (EET) is an anaerobic respiration process that couples carbon oxidation to the reduction of metal species. In the presence of a suitable metal catalyst, EET allows for cellular metabolism to control a variety of synthetic transformations. Here, we report the use of EET from the model electroactive bacterium &lt;italic&gt;Shewanella oneidensis&lt;/italic&gt; for metabolic and genetic control over Cu(I)-catalyzed Alkyne-Azide Cycloaddition (CuAAC). CuAAC conversion under anaerobic and aerobic conditions was dependent on live, actively respiring &lt;italic&gt;S. oneidensis&lt;/italic&gt; cells. In addition, reaction progress and kinetics could be further manipulated by tailoring the central carbon metabolism of &lt;italic&gt;S. oneidensis&lt;/italic&gt;. Similarly, CuAAC activity was dependent on specific EET pathways and could be manipulated using inducible genetic circuits controlling the expression of EET-relevant proteins including MtrC, MtrA, and CymA. EET-driven CuAAC also exhibited modularity and robustness in ligand tolerance and substrate scope. Furthermore, the living nature of this system could be exploited to perform multiple reaction cycles without requiring regeneration, something inaccessible to traditional chemical reductants. Finally, &lt;italic&gt;S. oneidensis&lt;/italic&gt; enabled bioorthogonal CuAAC membrane labelling on live mammalian cells without affecting cell viability, suggesting that &lt;italic&gt;S. oneidensis&lt;/italic&gt; can act as a dynamically tunable biocatalyst in complex environments. In summary, our results demonstrate how EET can expand the reaction scope available to living systems by enabling cellular control of CuAAC.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462180" rel="alternate" title="Extracellular Electron Transfer Enables Cellular Control of Cu(I)-catalyzed Alkyne-Azide Cycloaddition (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462277</id><title>The use of barcoded Asaia bacteria in mosquito in vivo screens for identification of systemic insecticides and inhibitors of malaria transmission (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.147055+00:00</updated><author><name>Angelika Sturm</name></author><author><name>Martijn W. Vos</name></author><author><name>Rob Henderson</name></author><author><name>Maarten Eldering</name></author><author><name>Karin M.J. Koolen</name></author><author><name>Avinash Sheshachalam</name></author><author><name>Guido Favia</name></author><author><name>Kirandeep Samby</name></author><author><name>Esperanza Herreros</name></author><author><name>Koen J. Dechering</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This work addresses the need for new chemical matter in product development for control of pest insects and vector-borne diseases. We present a barcoding strategy that enables phenotypic screens of blood-feeding insects against small molecules in microtiter plate-based arrays and apply this to discovery of novel systemic insecticides and compounds that block malaria parasite development in the mosquito vector. Encoding of the bloodmeals was achieved through recombinant DNA-tagged &lt;italic&gt;Asaia&lt;/italic&gt; bacteria that successfully colonized &lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Anopheles&lt;/italic&gt; mosquitoes. An arrayed screen of a collection of pesticides showed that chemical classes of avermectins, phenylpyrazoles and neonicotinoids were enriched for compounds with systemic adulticide activity against &lt;italic&gt;Anopheles&lt;/italic&gt;. Using a luminescent &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; reporter strain, barcoded screens identified 48 drug-like transmission blocking compounds from a 400-compound antimicrobial library. The approach significantly increases the throughput in phenotypic screening campaigns using adult insects, and identifies novel candidate small molecules for disease control.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462277" rel="alternate" title="The use of barcoded Asaia bacteria in mosquito in vivo screens for identification of systemic insecticides and inhibitors of malaria transmission (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>