<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.975166+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467796</id><title>Gender Imbalance in the Editorial Activities of a Researcher-led Journal (130 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.975351+00:00</updated><author><name>Tal Seidel Malkinson</name></author><author><name>Devin B. Terhune</name></author><author><name>Mathew Kollamkulam</name></author><author><name>Maria J. Guerreiro</name></author><author><name>Dani S. Bassett</name></author><author><name>Tamar R. Makin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Editorial decision-making is a fundamental element of the scientific enterprise. We examined whether contributions to editorial decisions at various stages of the publication process is subject to gender disparity, based on analytics collected by the biomedical researcher-led journal eLife. Despite efforts to increase women representation, the board of reviewing editors (BRE) was men-dominant (69%). Moreover, authors suggested more men from the BRE pool, even after correcting for men’s numerical over-representation. Although women editors were proportionally involved in the initial editorial process, they were under-engaged in editorial activities involving reviewers and authors. Additionally, converging evidence showed gender homophily in manuscripts assignment, such that men Senior Editors over-engaged men Reviewing Editors. This tendency was stronger in more gender-balanced scientific disciplines. Together, our findings confirm that gender disparities exist along the editorial process and suggest that merely increasing the proportion of women might not be sufficient to eliminate this bias.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467796" rel="alternate" title="Gender Imbalance in the Editorial Activities of a Researcher-led Journal (130 tweets)"/><category term="Scientific Communication and Education"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467960</id><title>Characterization of scar tissue biomechanics during adult murine flexor tendon healing (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.975527+00:00</updated><author><name>Antonion Korcari</name></author><author><name>Mark R. Buckley</name></author><author><name>Alayna E. Loiselle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tendon injuries are very common and result in significant impairments in mobility and quality of life. During healing, tendons produce a scar at the injury site, characterized by abundant and disorganized extracellular matrix and by permanent deficits in mechanical integrity compared to healthy tendon. Although a significant amount of work has been done to understand the healing process of tendons and to develop potential therapeutics for tendon regeneration, there is still a significant gap in terms of assessing the direct effects of therapeutics on the functional and material quality specifically of the scar tissue, and thus, on the overall tendon healing process. In this study, we focused on characterizing the mechanical properties of only the scar tissue in flexor digitorum longus (FDL) tendons during the proliferative and remodeling healing phases and comparing these properties with the mechanical properties of the composite healing tissue. Our method was sensitive enough to identify significant differences in structural and material properties between the scar and tendon-scar composite tissues. To account for possible inaccuracies due to the small aspect ratio of scar tissue, we also applied inverse finite element analysis (iFEA) to compute mechanical properties based on simulated tests with accurate specimen geometries and boundary conditions. We found that the scar tissue linear tangent moduli calculated from iFEA were not significantly different from those calculated experimentally at all healing timepoints, validating our experimental findings, and suggesting the assumptions in our experimental calculations were accurate. Taken together, this study first demonstrates that due to the presence of uninjured stubs, testing composite healing tendons without isolating the scar tissue overestimates the material properties of the scar itself. Second, our scar isolation method promises to enable more direct assessment of how different treatment regimens (e.g., cellular ablation, biomechanical and/or biochemical stimuli, tissue engineered scaffolds) affect scar tissue function and material quality in multiple different types of tendons.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467960" rel="alternate" title="Characterization of scar tissue biomechanics during adult murine flexor tendon healing (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468427</id><title>Homology mediated end joining enables efficient non-viral targeted integration of large DNA templates in primary human T cells (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.975664+00:00</updated><author><name>Beau R Webber</name></author><author><name>Matthew J Johnson</name></author><author><name>Nicholas S Slipek</name></author><author><name>Walker S Lahr</name></author><author><name>Anthony P DeFeo</name></author><author><name>Joseph G Skeate</name></author><author><name>Xiaohong Qiu</name></author><author><name>Blaine Rathmann</name></author><author><name>Miechaleen D Diers</name></author><author><name>Bryce Wick</name></author><author><name>Tom Henley</name></author><author><name>Modassir Choudhry</name></author><author><name>R. Scott McIvor</name></author><author><name>Branden S Moriarity</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Adoptive cellular therapy using genetically engineered immune cells holds tremendous promise for the treatment of advanced cancers. While the number of available receptors targeting tumor specific antigens continues to grow, the current reliance on viral vectors for clinical production of engineered immune cells remains a significant bottleneck limiting translation of promising new therapies. Here, we describe an optimized methodology for efficient CRISPR-Cas9 based, non-viral engineering of primary human T cells that overcomes key limitations of previous approaches. By synergizing temporal optimization of reagent delivery, reagent composition, and integration mechanism, we achieve targeted integration of large DNA cargo at efficiencies nearing those of viral vector platforms with minimal toxicity. CAR-T cells generated using our approach are highly functional and elicit potent anti-tumor cytotoxicity in vitro and in vivo. Importantly, our method is readily adaptable to cGMP compliant manufacturing and clinical scale-up, offering a near-term alternative to the use of viral vectors for production of genetically engineered T cells for cancer immunotherapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468427" rel="alternate" title="Homology mediated end joining enables efficient non-viral targeted integration of large DNA templates in primary human T cells (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468096</id><title>Efficient multi-gene expression in cell-free droplet microreactors (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.975867+00:00</updated><author><name>Ana Maria Restrepo Sierra</name></author><author><name>Stefan T. Arold</name></author><author><name>Raik Grünberg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cell-free transcription and translation systems promise to accelerate and simplify the engineering of proteins, biological circuits and metabolic pathways. Their encapsulation on microfluidic platforms can generate millions of cell-free reactions in picoliter volume droplets. However, current methods struggle to create DNA diversity between droplets while also reaching sufficient protein expression levels. In particular, efficient multi-gene expression has remained elusive. We here demonstrate that co-encapsulation of DNA-coated beads with a defined cell-free system allows high protein expression while also supporting genetic diversity between individual droplets. We optimize DNA loading on commercially available microbeads through direct binding as well as through the sequential coupling of up to three genes via a solid-phase Golden Gate assembly or BxB1 integrase-based recombineering. Encapsulation with an off-the-shelf microfluidics device allows for single or multiple protein expression from a single DNA-coated bead per 14 pL droplet. We envision that this approach will help to scale up and parallelize the rapid prototyping of more complex biological systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468096" rel="alternate" title="Efficient multi-gene expression in cell-free droplet microreactors (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467852</id><title>Glomerular function and urinary biomarker changes between vancomycin and vancomycin plus piperacillin-tazobactam in a translational rat model (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.976002+00:00</updated><author><name>Jack Chang</name></author><author><name>Gwendolyn Pais</name></author><author><name>Kimberly Valdez</name></author><author><name>Sylwia Marianski</name></author><author><name>Erin F. Barreto</name></author><author><name>Marc H. Scheetz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Clinical studies have reported additive nephrotoxicity associated with the combination of vancomycin (VAN) and piperacillin-tazobactam (TZP). This study assessed differences in glomerular filtration rate (GFR) and urinary biomarkers between rats receiving VAN and those receiving VAN+TZP. Male Sprague-Dawley rats (n=26) were randomized to receive 96 hours of intravenous VAN at 150mg/kg/day, intraperitoneal TZP at 1400 mg/kg/day, or VAN+TZP. Kidney function was evaluated using fluorescein-isothiocyanate sinistrin and a transdermal sensor to estimate real-time glomerular filtration rate (GFR). Kidney injury was evaluated via urinary biomarkers including kidney injury molecule-1 (KIM-1), clusterin, and osteopontin. Compared to a saline control, only rats in the VAN group showed significant declines in GFR by day 4 (−0.39 mL/min/100 g body weight, 95% CI: -0.68 to -0.10, p=0.008). When the VAN+TZP and VAN alone treatment groups were compared, significantly higher urinary KIM-1 was observed in the VAN alone group on day 1 (18.4 ng, 95% CI: 1.4 to 35.3, p=0.03), day 2 (27.4 ng, 95% CI: 10.4 to 44.3, p=0.002), day 3 (18.8 ng, 95% CI: 1.9 to 35.8, p=0.03), and day 4 (23.2 ng, 95% CI: 6.3 to 40.2, p=0.007). KIM-1 was the urinary biomarker that most correlated with decreasing GFR on day 3 (Spearman’s rho: -0.45, p = 0.022) and day 4 (Spearman’s rho: - 0.41, p = 0.036). Kidney function decline and increased KIM-1 were observed among rats that received VAN only, but not TZP or VAN+TZP. Addition of TZP to VAN does not worsen kidney function or injury in a validated translational rat model.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467852" rel="alternate" title="Glomerular function and urinary biomarker changes between vancomycin and vancomycin plus piperacillin-tazobactam in a translational rat model (5 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467799</id><title>Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor Inhibition Prevents Caveolin-1-dependent Calcifying Extracellular Vesicle Biogenesis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.976222+00:00</updated><author><name>Amirala Bakhshian Nik</name></author><author><name>Hooi Hooi Ng</name></author><author><name>Patrick Sun</name></author><author><name>Francesco Iacoviello</name></author><author><name>Paul R. Shearing</name></author><author><name>Sergio Bertazzo</name></author><author><name>Deniel Mero</name></author><author><name>Bohdan B. Khomtchouk</name></author><author><name>Joshua D. Hutcheson</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chronic kidney disease (CKD) increases the risk of cardiovascular disease, including vascular calcification, leading to higher mortality. Release of calcifying extracellular vesicles (EVs) by vascular smooth muscle cells (VSMCs) promotes the ectopic mineralization of vessel walls. Caveolin-1 (CAV1) protein plays a key role in formation of calcifying EVs in VSMCs. Epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) co-localizes with and influences the intracellular trafficking of CAV1.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We computationally analyzed 7651 individuals in the Multi-Ethnic Study of Atherosclerosis (MESA) and Framingham cohorts to assess potential correlations between coronary artery calcium and single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) associated with elevated serum levels of EGFR. Using a diet-induced mouse model of CKD, we measured serum EGFR and assessed the potential of EGFR inhibition to prevent vascular calcification.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individuals in the MESA and Framingham cohorts with SNPs associated with increased serum EGFR exhibit elevated coronary artery calcium. Mice with CKD developed widespread vascular calcification, which associated with increased serum levels of EGFR. In both the CKD mice and human VSMC culture, EGFR inhibition significantly reduced vascular calcification by mitigating the release of CAV1-positive calcifying EVs. EGFR inhibition also increased bone mineral density in CKD mice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given that EGFR inhibitors exhibit clinical safety and efficacy in other pathologies, the current data suggest that EGFR may be an ideal target to prevent pathological vascular calcification.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Subject terms&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Growth Factors, Vascular Biology, Vascular Disease, Translational Study&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467799" rel="alternate" title="Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor Inhibition Prevents Caveolin-1-dependent Calcifying Extracellular Vesicle Biogenesis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.467741</id><title>Soft, dynamic hydrogel confinement improves kidney organoid lumen morphology and reduces epithelial–mesenchymal transition in culture (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.976409+00:00</updated><author><name>Floor A.A. Ruiter</name></author><author><name>Francis L.C. Morgan</name></author><author><name>Nadia Roumans</name></author><author><name>Anika Schumacher</name></author><author><name>Gisela G. Slaats</name></author><author><name>Lorenzo Moroni</name></author><author><name>Vanessa L.S. LaPointe</name></author><author><name>Matthew B. Baker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pluripotent stem cell–derived kidney organoids offer a promising solution to renal failure, yet current organoid protocols often lead to off-target cells and phenotypic alterations, preventing maturity. Here, we created various dynamic hydrogel architectures, conferring a controlled and biomimetic environment for organoid encapsulation. We investigated how hydrogel stiffness and stress relaxation affect renal phenotype and undesired fibrotic markers. We observed stiff hydrogel encapsulation led to an absence of certain renal cell types and signs of an epithelial– mesenchymal transition (EMT), whereas encapsulation in soft-stress-relaxing hydrogels led to all major renal segments, fewer fibrosis/EMT associated proteins, apical proximal tubule enrichment, and primary cilia formation, representing a significant improvement over current approaches to culture kidney organoids. Our findings show that engineering hydrogel mechanics and dynamics has a decided benefit for organoid culture. These structure–property– function relationships can enable rational design of materials, bringing us closer to functional engraftments and disease-modelling applications.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.467741" rel="alternate" title="Soft, dynamic hydrogel confinement improves kidney organoid lumen morphology and reduces epithelial–mesenchymal transition in culture (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468191</id><title>A novel non-genetic murine model of hyperglycemia and hyperlipidemia-associated accelerated atherosclerosis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.976578+00:00</updated><author><name>Susanne Gaul</name></author><author><name>Khurrum Shahzad</name></author><author><name>Rebekka Medert</name></author><author><name>Ishan Gadi</name></author><author><name>Christina Meader</name></author><author><name>Dagmar Schumacher</name></author><author><name>Angela Wirth</name></author><author><name>Saira Ambreen</name></author><author><name>Sameen Fatima</name></author><author><name>Jes-Niels Boeckel</name></author><author><name>Hamzah Khawaja</name></author><author><name>Jan Haas</name></author><author><name>Maik Brune</name></author><author><name>Peter Paul Nawroth</name></author><author><name>Berend Isermann</name></author><author><name>Ulrich Laufs</name></author><author><name>Marc Freichel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Objective: Atherosclerosis, the main pathology underlying cardiovascular diseases is accelerated in diabetic patients. Genetic mouse models require breeding efforts which are time-consuming and costly. To establish a new non-genetic model of inducible metabolic risk factors mimicking hyperlipidemia, hyperglycemia, or both and allowing to detect phenotypic differences dependent on the metabolic stressor(s). Methods and Results: Wild type mice were injected with gain-of-function PCSK9D377Y (proprotein convertase subtilisin/kexin type 9) mutant adeno-associated viral particles (AAV) and streptozotocin and fed either a high-fat diet (HFD) or high-cholesterol/high fat-diet (Paigen diet, PD). Combined hyperlipidemic and hyperglycemic (HGHCi) mice, but not hyperlipidemia (HCi) alone, display characteristic features of accelerated atherosclerosis. Atherosclerotic plaques of HGHCi animals were larger, showed a less stable phenotype, contained more macrophages and less smooth muscle cells. These findings were observed both at early (12 weeks) and late (20 weeks) time points on both HFD or PD diet. Differences between the HGHCi and HCi model were confirmed using RNAseq analysis revealing that significantly more genes are dysregulated in mice with combined hyperlipidemia and hyperglycemia as compared to the hyperlipidemia only group. The HGHCi-associated genes were related to pathways regulating inflammation, cellular metabolism and collagen degradation. PD accelerates atherosclerosis in mice and shows plaque formation already after 8 weeks, therefore, representing a fast direct inducible hyperglycemic atherosclerosis model. Conclusion: We established a non-genetic inducible mouse model allowing comparative analyses of atherosclerosis in HCi and HGHCi conditions and its modification by diet, allowing analyses of multiple metabolic hits in mice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468191" rel="alternate" title="A novel non-genetic murine model of hyperglycemia and hyperlipidemia-associated accelerated atherosclerosis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467687</id><title>Open Access publishing in Medicine: lights and shadows (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.976802+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicola Bernabò</name></author><author><name>Luca Valbonetti</name></author><author><name>Alessandra Ordinelli</name></author><author><name>Rosa Ciccarelli</name></author><author><name>Barbara Barboni</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The widespread use of internet has had enormous consequences in changing the way of accessing to scientific literature in all domains of knowledge and, in particular, in medicine. One of the most important related factors is the idea of making research output freely available: the so-called Open Access (OA) option. OA is considered very important in spreading of knowledge, breaking down barriers in benefit of research, and increasing the impact of research outputs within the scientific community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we carried out a comparison between Non-Open Access (NOA) and OA medical Journals in terms of growing rate, geographical distribution, and the impact on scientific community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We collected the bibliometric data on the scientific Journals indexed in Scopus starting from 2001 to 2016 published either as NOA or OA. Then, we analysed the number of Journals, their geolocalization, their impact on the scientific community, and the parameters as SJR, &lt;italic&gt;H&lt;/italic&gt; index, and cites for document (2 years).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a result, we found that while the number of NOA Journals is virtually stable, that of OA is dramatically increasing, with a growing rate higher than 400% in 2016. Then, the majority of OA Journals are published in developing Countries (Brazil, India, South Africa, South Korea, New Zealand, Serbia, and Poland) and their impact within researchers is lower compared to the NOA Journals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, our data provide an updated and unprecedented picture of OA adoption in medical field, with its lights and shadows.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Article Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are seeing in medicine a huge increase in the number of Journals that use OA;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;This trend is mainly due to the increase in publishing Journals in Countries with emergent economies;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The use of OA for Journals in the medical field, did not guarantee a vantage in term of bibliometric parameters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;MCS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;92C99&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;JEL&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;I30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467687" rel="alternate" title="Open Access publishing in Medicine: lights and shadows (3 tweets)"/><category term="Scientific Communication and Education"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>