<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.282372+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472419</id><title>Generative Language Modeling for Antibody Design (35 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.282558+00:00</updated><author><name>Richard W. Shuai</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey A. Ruffolo</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey J. Gray</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Successful development of monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) for therapeutic applications is hindered by developability issues such as low solubility, low thermal stability, high aggregation, and high immunogenicity. The discovery of more developable mAb candidates relies on high-quality antibody libraries for isolating candidates with desirable properties. We present Immunoglobulin Language Model (IgLM), a deep generative language model for generating synthetic libraries by re-designing variable-length spans of antibody sequences. IgLM formulates anti-body design as an autoregressive sequence generation task based on text-infilling in natural language. We trained IgLM on approximately 558M antibody heavy- and light-chain variable sequences, conditioning on each sequence’s chain type and species-of-origin. We demonstrate that IgLM can be applied to generate synthetic libraries that may accelerate the discovery of therapeutic antibody candidates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472419" rel="alternate" title="Generative Language Modeling for Antibody Design (35 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472674</id><title>Qualifying a human Liver-Chip for predictive toxicology: Performance assessment and economic implications (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.282709+00:00</updated><author><name>Lorna Ewart</name></author><author><name>Athanasia Apostolou</name></author><author><name>Skyler A. Briggs</name></author><author><name>Christopher V. Carman</name></author><author><name>Jake T. Chaff</name></author><author><name>Anthony R. Heng</name></author><author><name>Sushma Jadalannagari</name></author><author><name>Jeshina Janardhanan</name></author><author><name>Kyung-Jin Jang</name></author><author><name>Sannidhi R. Joshipura</name></author><author><name>Mahika Kadam</name></author><author><name>Marianne Kanellias</name></author><author><name>Ville J. Kujala</name></author><author><name>Gauri Kulkarni</name></author><author><name>Christopher Y. Le</name></author><author><name>Carolina Lucchesi</name></author><author><name>Dimitris V. Manatakis</name></author><author><name>Kairav K. Maniar</name></author><author><name>Meaghan E. Quinn</name></author><author><name>Joseph S. Ravan</name></author><author><name>Ann Catherine Rizos</name></author><author><name>John F.K. Sauld</name></author><author><name>Josiah Sliz</name></author><author><name>William Tien-Street</name></author><author><name>Dennis Ramos Trinidad</name></author><author><name>James Velez</name></author><author><name>Max Wendell</name></author><author><name>Prathap Kumar Mahalingaiah</name></author><author><name>Donald E. Ingber</name></author><author><name>Daniel Levner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human organ-on-a-chip (Organ-Chip) technology has the potential to disrupt preclinical drug discovery and improve success in drug development pipelines as it can recapitulate organ-level pathophysiology and clinical responses. The Innovation and Quality (IQ) consortium formed by multiple pharmaceutical and biotechnology companies, however, systematic and quantitative evaluation of the predictive value of Organ-Chips has not yet been reported. Here, 780 Liver-Chips were analyzed to determine their ability to predict drug-induced liver injury (DILI) caused by small molecules identified as benchmarks by the IQ consortium. The Liver-Chip met the qualification guidelines across a blinded set of 27 known hepatotoxic and non-toxic drugs with a sensitivity of 80% and a specificity of 100%. With this performance, a computational economic value analysis suggests that the Liver-Chip could generate $3 billion annually for the pharmaceutical industry due to increased R&amp;amp;D productivity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472674" rel="alternate" title="Qualifying a human Liver-Chip for predictive toxicology: Performance assessment and economic implications (20 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472296</id><title>Personalized models of breast cancer desmoplasia reveal biomechanical determinants of drug penetration (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.282991+00:00</updated><author><name>Giovanni S. Offeddu</name></author><author><name>Kristina Haase</name></author><author><name>Zhengpeng Wan</name></author><author><name>Luca Possenti</name></author><author><name>Huu Tuan Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Mark R. Gillrie</name></author><author><name>Dean Hickman</name></author><author><name>Charles G. Knutson</name></author><author><name>Roger D. Kamm</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Breast cancer desmoplasia heterogeneity contributes to high disease mortality due to discrepancies in treatment efficacy between patients. Personalized &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; breast cancer models can be used for high throughput testing and ranking of therapeutic strategies to normalize the aberrant microenvironment in a patient-specific manner. Here, tumoroids assembled from patient-derived cells cultured in microphysiological systems including perfusable microvasculature reproduce key aspects of stromal and vascular dysfunction. Increased hyaluronic acid and collagen deposition, loss of vascular glycocalyx and reduced perfusion, and elevated interstitial fluid pressure in the models result in impaired drug distribution to tumor cells. We demonstrate the application of these personalized models as tools to rank molecular therapies for the normalization of the tumoroid microenvironment and to discover new therapeutic targets such as IL8 and CD44, which may ultimately improve drug efficacy in breast cancer patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472296" rel="alternate" title="Personalized models of breast cancer desmoplasia reveal biomechanical determinants of drug penetration (17 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472418</id><title>Modelling biochemical gradients in vitro to control cell compartmentalization in a microengineered 3D model of the intestinal epithelium (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.283150+00:00</updated><author><name>Gizem Altay</name></author><author><name>Aina Abad-Lázaro</name></author><author><name>Emilio J. Gualda</name></author><author><name>Jordi Folch</name></author><author><name>Claudia Insa</name></author><author><name>Sébastien Tosi</name></author><author><name>Xavier Hernando-Momblona</name></author><author><name>Eduard Batlle</name></author><author><name>Pablo Loza-Álvarez</name></author><author><name>Vanesa Fernández-Majada</name></author><author><name>Elena Martinez</name></author><author><name>Matteo Bernardello</name></author><author><name>Gustavo Castro</name></author><author><name>Jordi Andilla</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gradients of signaling pathways within the intestinal stem cell (ISC) niche are instrumental for cellular compartmentalization and tissue function, yet how are they formed and sensed by the epithelium is still not fully understood. Here we present a new in vitro model of the small intestine based on primary epithelial cells (i), apically accessible (ii), with native tissue mechanical properties and controlled mesh size (iii), 3D villus-like architecture (iv), and biomolecular gradients of the ISC niche (v). Biochemical gradients are formed through the hydrogel-based scaffolds by free diffusion from a source to a sink chamber. To confirm the establishment of precise spatiotemporally controlled gradients, we employ light-sheet fluorescence microscopy and in-silico modelling. The ISC niche biochemical gradients applied along the villus axis lead to the in vivo-like compartmentalization of the proliferative and differentiated cells, while changing the composition and concentration of the biochemical factors affects the cellular organization along the villus axis. This novel 3D in vitro intestinal model derived from organoids recapitulates both the villus-like architecture and the gradients of ISC biochemical factors, thus opening the possibility to study in vitro the nature of such gradients and the resulting cellular response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Table of contents (ToC)&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="472418v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;p&gt;Biomolecular gradients are fundamental in intestinal epithelial tissue organization and function. The microengineered platform developed, with well-controlled spatiotemporal gradients of intestinal stem cell niche factors, 3D architecture and organoid-derived cells retrieves an in vivo-like cell compartmentalization. The system is easily incorporated in standard cell culture inserts where one can systematically test factors critical for intestinal tissue dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472418" rel="alternate" title="Modelling biochemical gradients in vitro to control cell compartmentalization in a microengineered 3D model of the intestinal epithelium (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.11.472230</id><title>Peptide Aggregation Induced Immunogenic Rupture (PAIIR) (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.283336+00:00</updated><author><name>Gokhan Gunay</name></author><author><name>Seren Hamsici</name></author><author><name>Gillian A. Lang</name></author><author><name>Mark L. Lang</name></author><author><name>Susan Kovats</name></author><author><name>Handan Acar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Under the influence of stress and membrane damage, cells undergo immunogenic cell death (ICD), which involves the release of damage associated molecular patterns (DAMPs), natural adjuvants for enhancing an immune response. In the presence of an antigen, released DAMPs can determine the type and magnitude of the immune response, and therefore the longevity and efficacy of an antigen-specific immunity. In the last decade, the immune response effect of ICD has been shown, yet there is no tool that can induce controlled ICD with predictable results, regardless of the cell type. We designed a peptide-based tool, called [II], for controlled damage to cell membrane to induce ICD and DAMPs release. Herein we describe a series of experiments that determine that the mechanism of action of [II] includes a caspase-dependent ICD and subsequent release of immune stimulating DAMPs, on various cell types. Moreover, we tested the hypothesis that controlled DAMP release via [II] in vivo was associated with enhancement of antigen-specific adaptive immunity with influenza hemagglutinin (HA) subunit vaccine. HA and [II] showed significantly higher HA specific IgG1 and IgG2a antibodies, compared to HA-only immunized mice, while the peptide itself did not elicit antibodies. In this paper, we demonstrate the first peptide-aggregation induced immunogenic rupture (PAIIR) approach as vaccine adjuvants for increasing both humoral and cellular immunity. In consideration of its ability to enhance IgG2a responses that are associated with heterosubtypic influenza virus protection, PAIIR is a promising adjuvant to promote universal protection upon influenza HA vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.11.472230" rel="alternate" title="Peptide Aggregation Induced Immunogenic Rupture (PAIIR) (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472696</id><title>Epigenetic remodeling during monolayer cell expansion reduces therapeutic potential (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.283479+00:00</updated><author><name>Adrienne Scott</name></author><author><name>Eduard Casas</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Ellyse Schneider</name></author><author><name>Alison Swearingen</name></author><author><name>Courtney Van Den Elzen</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Seelbinder</name></author><author><name>Jeanne Barthold</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Kugel</name></author><author><name>Josh Lewis Stern</name></author><author><name>Kyla Foster</name></author><author><name>Nancy Emery</name></author><author><name>Justin Brumbaugh</name></author><author><name>Corey Neu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding how cells remember previous mechanical environments to influence their fate, or mechanical memory, informs the design of biomaterials and therapies in medicine. Current regeneration therapies require two-dimensional (2D) cell expansion processes to achieve large cell populations critical for the repair of damaged (e.g. connective and musculoskeletal) tissues. However, the influence of mechanical memory on cell fate following expansion is unknown, and mechanisms defining how physical environments influence the therapeutic potential of cells remain poorly understood. Here, we show that the organization of histone H3 trimethylated at lysine 9 (H3K9me3) and expression of tissue-identifying genes in primary cartilage cells (chondrocytes) transferred to three-dimensional (3D) hydrogels depends on the number of previous population doublings on tissue culture plastic during 2D cell expansion. Decreased levels of H3K9me3 occupying promoters of dedifferentiation genes after the 2D culture were also retained in 3D culture. Suppression of H3K9me3 during expansion of cells isolated from a murine model similarly resulted in the loss of the chondrocyte phenotype and global remodeling of nuclear architecture. In contrast, increasing levels of H3K9me3 through inhibiting H3K9 demethylases partially rescued the chondrogenic nuclear architecture and gene expression, which has important implications for tissue repair therapies, where expansion of large numbers of phenotypically-suitable cells is required. Overall, our findings indicate mechanical memory in primary cells is encoded in the chromatin architecture, which impacts cell fate and the phenotype of expanded cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472696" rel="alternate" title="Epigenetic remodeling during monolayer cell expansion reduces therapeutic potential (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473085</id><title>Amino acid substitutions in human growth hormone affect coiled-coil content and receptor binding (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.283657+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrei Rajkovic</name></author><author><name>Sandesh Kanchugal</name></author><author><name>Eldar Abdurakhmanov</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Howard</name></author><author><name>Astrid Gräslund</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Wärmländer</name></author><author><name>Joseph Erwin</name></author><author><name>Helena Ursula Danielson</name></author><author><name>Samuel Coulbourn Flores</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The interaction between human Growth Hormone (hGH) and hGH Receptor (hGHR) has great relevance to human diseases such as acromegaly and cancer. HGH has been extensively engineered by other workers to improve binding and other properties. We used a computational screen to select substitutions at single hGH positions within the hGHR-binding site. We find that, while many successfully slow down dissociation of the hGH-hGHR complex once bound, they also slow down the association of hGH to hGHR. We are particularly interested in E174 which belongs to the hGH zinc-binding triad, and which spans coiled-coil helices and obeys the coiled-coil heptad pattern. Surprisingly, substituting E174 with A leads to substantial increase in an experimental measure of coiled-coil content. E174A is known to increase affinity of hGH against hGHR; here we show that this is simply because the off-rate is slowed down more than the on-rate, in line with what has been found for other affinity-improving mutations. For E174Y (and mutations at other sites) the slowdown in on-rate was greater, leading to decreased affinity. The results point to a link between coiled-coiling, zinc binding, and hGHR-binding affinity in hGH, and also suggest rules for choosing affinity-increasing substitutions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473085" rel="alternate" title="Amino acid substitutions in human growth hormone affect coiled-coil content and receptor binding (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473072</id><title>Optimal spatial allocation of enzymes as an investment problem (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.283815+00:00</updated><author><name>Giovanni Giunta</name></author><author><name>Filipe Tostevin</name></author><author><name>Sorin Tanase-Nicola</name></author><author><name>Ulrich Gerland</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Given a limited number of molecular components, cells face various allocation problems demanding decisions on how to distribute their resources. For instance, cells decide which enzymes to produce at what quantity, but also where to position them. Here we focus on the spatial allocation problem of how to distribute enzymes such as to maximize the total reaction flux produced by them in a system with given geometry and boundary conditions. So far, such distributions have been studied by computational optimization, but a deeper theoretical understanding was lacking. We derive an optimal allocation principle, which demands that the available enzymes are distributed such that the marginal flux returns at each occupied position are equal. This ‘homogeneous marginal returns criterion’ (HMR criterion) corresponds to a portfolio optimization criterion in a scenario where each investment globally feeds back onto all payoffs. The HMR criterion allows us to analytically understand and characterize a localization-delocalization transition in the optimal enzyme distribution that was previously observed numerically. In particular, our analysis reveals the generality of the transition, and produces a practical test for the optimality of enzyme localization by comparing the reaction flux to the influx of substrate. Based on these results, we devise an additive construction algorithm, which builds up optimal enzyme arrangements systematically rather than by trial and error. Taken together, our results reveal a common principle in allocation problems from biology and economics, which can also serve as a design principle for synthetic biomolecular systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473072" rel="alternate" title="Optimal spatial allocation of enzymes as an investment problem (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>