<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-09T06:15:39.400616+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.02.454472</id><title>Microbial community of recently discovered Auka vent field sheds light on vent biogeography and evolutionary history of thermophily (57 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-09T06:15:39.401028+00:00</updated><author><name>Daan R Speth</name></author><author><name>Feiqiao B Yu</name></author><author><name>Stephanie A Connon</name></author><author><name>Sujung Lim</name></author><author><name>John S Magyar</name></author><author><name>Manet E Peña</name></author><author><name>Stephen R Quake</name></author><author><name>Victoria J Orphan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hydrothermal vents have been key to our understanding of the limits of life, and the metabolic and phylogenetic diversity of thermophilic organisms. Here we used environmental metagenomics combined with analysis of physico-chemical data and 16S rRNA amplicons to characterize the diversity, temperature optima, and biogeographic distribution of sediment-hosted microorganisms at the recently discovered Auka vents in the Gulf of California, the deepest known hydrothermal vent field in the Pacific Ocean. We recovered 325 metagenome assembled genomes (MAGs) representing 54 phyla, over 1/3 of the currently known phylum diversity, showing the microbial community in Auka hydrothermal sediments is highly diverse. Large scale 16S rRNA amplicon screening of 227 sediment samples across the vent field indicates that the MAGs are largely representative of the microbial community. Metabolic reconstruction of a vent-specific, deeply branching clade within the Desulfobacterota (Tharpobacteria) suggests these organisms metabolize sulfur using novel octaheme cytochrome-c proteins related to hydroxylamine oxidoreductase. Community-wide comparison of the average nucleotide identity of the Auka MAGs with MAGs from the Guaymas Basin vent field, found 400 km to the Northwest, revealed a remarkable 20% species-level overlap between vent sites, suggestive of long-distance species transfer and sediment colonization. An adapted version of a recently developed model for predicting optimal growth temperature to the Auka and Guaymas MAGs indicates several of these uncultured microorganisms could grow at temperatures exceeding the currently known upper limit of life. Extending this analysis to reference data shows that thermophily is a trait that has evolved frequently among Bacteria and Archaea. Combined, our results show that Auka vent field offers new perspectives on our understanding of hydrothermal vent microbiology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.02.454472" rel="alternate" title="Microbial community of recently discovered Auka vent field sheds light on vent biogeography and evolutionary history of thermophily (57 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.01.454633</id><title>Regulatory perturbations of ribosome allocation results in a trade-off between fast growth and adaptation capacity (32 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-09T06:15:39.401304+00:00</updated><author><name>David Hidalgo</name></author><author><name>César A. Martínez-Ortiz</name></author><author><name>Bernhard O. Palsson</name></author><author><name>José I. Jiménez</name></author><author><name>José Utrilla</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacteria regulate their cellular resource allocation to enable their fast growth-adaptation to a variety of environmental niches. We studied the ribosomal allocation, growth and expression profile of two sets of fast-growing mutants of &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; K-12 MG1655. Mutants with 3 copies of the stronger ribosomal RNA operons grew faster than the wild-type strain in minimal media and show similar phenotype to previously studied &lt;italic&gt;rpoB&lt;/italic&gt; mutants. All of them displayed increased ribosomal content, a longer diauxic shift and a reduced activity of the &lt;italic&gt;aceBAK&lt;/italic&gt; operon, indicative of repressed gluconeogenic pathways. Transcriptomic profiles of fast-growing mutants showed common downregulation of hedging functions and upregulated growth functions. Proteome allocation estimations showed an increase in the growth-related proteome for fast-growing strains, but not an increased cellular budget for recombinant protein production. These results show that two different regulatory perturbations (rRNA promoters or &lt;italic&gt;rpoB&lt;/italic&gt; mutations) increasing ribosomal allocation optimize the proteome for growth with a concomitant fitness cost.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strains with the 3 stronger ribosomal operons grow faster than the wild-type&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fast-growing strains show higher ribosomal content&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Comparison among &lt;italic&gt;rrn&lt;/italic&gt; and RNAP mutants shows commonalities&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fast-growing strains show adaptation trade-offs&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mutant’s proteome is larger and optimized for growth&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.01.454633" rel="alternate" title="Regulatory perturbations of ribosome allocation results in a trade-off between fast growth and adaptation capacity (32 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.04.455085</id><title>GEPSi: A Python Library to Simulate GWAS Phenotype Data (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-09T06:15:39.401614+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel A Reidenbach</name></author><author><name>Avantika Lal</name></author><author><name>Lotfi Slim</name></author><author><name>Ohad Mosafi</name></author><author><name>Johnny Israeli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many computational methods aim to identify genetic variants associated with diseases and complex traits. Due to the absence of ground truth data, simulated genotype and phenotype data is needed to benchmark these methods. However, phenotypes are frequently simulated as an additive function of randomly selected variants, neglecting biological complexity such as non-random occurrence of causal SNPs, epistatic effects, heritability and dominance. Including such features would improve benchmarking studies and accelerate the development of methods for genetic analysis. Here, we describe GEPSi (GWAS Epistatic Phenotype Simulator), a user-friendly python package to simulate phenotype data based on user-supplied genotype data for a population. GEPSi incorporates diverse biological parameters such as heritability, dominance, population stratification and epistatic interactions between SNPs. We demonstrate the use of this package to compare machine learning methods for GWAS analysis.
GEPSi is freely available under an Apache 2.0 license, and can be downloaded from https://github.com/clara-parabricks/GEPSi.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.04.455085" rel="alternate" title="GEPSi: A Python Library to Simulate GWAS Phenotype Data (11 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.02.454837</id><title>Broadening the toolkit for quantitatively evaluating noncanonical amino acid incorporation in yeast (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-09T06:15:39.402022+00:00</updated><author><name>J.T. Stieglitz</name></author><author><name>K.A. Potts</name></author><author><name>J.A. Van Deventer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genetic code expansion is a powerful approach for advancing critical fields such as biological therapeutic discovery. However, the machinery for genetically encoding noncanonical amino acids (ncAAs) is only available in limited plasmid formats, constraining potential applications. In extreme cases, the introduction of two separate plasmids, one containing an orthogonal translation system (OTS) to facilitate ncAA incorporation and a second for expressing a ncAA-containing protein of interest, is not possible due to lack of convenient selection markers. One strategy to circumvent this challenge is to express the OTS and protein of interest from a single vector. For what we believe is the first time in yeast, we describe here several sets of single plasmid systems (SPSs) for performing genetic code manipulation and compare the ncAA incorporation capabilities of these plasmids against the capabilities of previously described dual plasmid systems (DPSs). For both dual fluorescent protein reporters and yeast display reporters tested with multiple OTSs and ncAAs, measured ncAA incorporation efficiencies with SPSs were determined to be equal to or improved relative to efficiencies determined with DPSs. Click chemistry on yeast cells displaying ncAA-containing proteins was also shown to be feasible in both formats, although differences in reactivity between formats suggest the need for caution when using such approaches. Additionally, we investigated whether these reporters would support separation of yeast strains known to exhibit distinct ncAA incorporation efficiencies. Model sorts conducted with mixtures of two strains transformed with the same SPS or DPS led to enrichment of a strain known to support higher efficiency ncAA incorporation, suggesting that these reporters will be suitable for conducting screens for strains exhibiting enhanced ncAA incorporation efficiencies. Overall, our results confirm that SPSs are well-behaved in yeast and provide a convenient alternative to DPSs. In particular, SPSs are expected to be invaluable for conducting high-throughput investigations of the effects of genetic or genomic changes on ncAA incorporation efficiency and, more fundamentally, the eukaryotic translation apparatus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract Figure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="454837v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.02.454837" rel="alternate" title="Broadening the toolkit for quantitatively evaluating noncanonical amino acid incorporation in yeast (10 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.02.454535</id><title>Myth-busting the provider-user relationship for digital sequence information (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-09T06:15:39.402369+00:00</updated><author><name>Amber Hartman Scholz</name></author><author><name>Matthias Lange</name></author><author><name>Pia Habekost</name></author><author><name>Paul Oldham</name></author><author><name>Ibon Cancio</name></author><author><name>Guy Cochrane</name></author><author><name>Jens Freitag</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The United Nations Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD) formally recognized the sovereign rights of nations over their biological diversity. Implicit within the treaty is the idea that mega-biodiverse countries will provide genetic resources and grant access to them and scientists in high-income countries will use these resources and share back benefits. However, little research has been conducted on how this framework is reflected in real-life scientific practice. Currently, parties to the CBD) are debating whether or not digital sequence information (DSI) should be regulated under a new benefit-sharing framework. At this critical time point in the upcoming international negotiations, we test the fundamental hypothesis of provision and use by looking at the global patterns of access and use in scientific publications. Our data reject the provider-user relationship and suggest far more complex information flow for digital sequence information. Therefore, any new policy decisions on digital sequence information should be aware of the high level of use of DSI across low- and middle-income countries and seek to preserve open access to this crucial common good.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.02.454535" rel="alternate" title="Myth-busting the provider-user relationship for digital sequence information (9 tweets)"/><category term="Scientific Communication and Education"/><published>2021-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.07.455331</id><title>Homeobox transcription factor MNX1 is crucial for restraining the expression of pan-neuronal genes in motor neurons (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-09T06:15:39.402718+00:00</updated><author><name>Ming-an Sun</name></author><author><name>Sherry Ralls</name></author><author><name>Warren Wu</name></author><author><name>Justin Demmerle</name></author><author><name>Jiayao Jiang</name></author><author><name>Carson Miller</name></author><author><name>Gernot Wolf</name></author><author><name>Todd Macfarlan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Motor neurons (MNs) control muscle movement and are essential for breathing, walking and fine motor skills. Motor Neuron and Pancreas Homeobox 1 (MNX1) has long been recognized as a key marker of the MN lineage. Deficiency of the Mnx1 gene in mice results in early postnatal lethality - likely by causing abnormal MN development and respiratory malfunction. However, the genome-wide targets and exact regulatory function of Mnx1 in MNs remains unresolved. Using an in vitro model for efficient MN induction from mouse embryonic stem cells, we identified about six thousand MNX1-bound loci, of which half are conserved enhancers co-bound by the core MN-inducing factors ISL1 and LHX3, while the other half are promoters for housekeeping-like genes. Despite its widespread binding, disruption of Mnx1 affects the activity of only a few dozen MNX1-bound loci, and causes mis-regulation of about one hundred genes, the majority of which are up-regulated pan-neuronal genes with relatively higher expression in the brain compared to MNs. Integration of genome-wide binding, transcriptomic and epigenomic data in the wild-type and Mnx1-disrupted MNs predicts that Pbx3 and Pou6f2 are two putative direct targets of MNX1, and both are homeobox transcription factors highly expressed in the central nervous system. Our results suggest that MNX1 is crucial for restraining the expression of many pan-neuronal genes in MNs, likely in an indirect fashion. Further, the rarity of direct targets in contrast to the widespread binding of MNX1 reflects a distinctive mode of transcriptional regulation by homeobox transcriptional factors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.07.455331" rel="alternate" title="Homeobox transcription factor MNX1 is crucial for restraining the expression of pan-neuronal genes in motor neurons (7 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-08-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.03.21261494</id><title>Mapping genetic determinants of 184 circulating proteins in 26,494 individuals to connect proteins and disease. (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-09T06:15:39.403549+00:00</updated><author><name>Erin Macdonald-Dunlop</name></author><author><name>Lucija Klarić</name></author><author><name>Lasse Folkersen</name></author><author><name>Paul R.H.J. Timmers</name></author><author><name>Stefan Gustafsson</name></author><author><name>Jing Hua Zhao</name></author><author><name>Niclas Eriksson</name></author><author><name>Anne Richmond</name></author><author><name>Stefan Enroth</name></author><author><name>Niklas Mattsson-Carlgren</name></author><author><name>Daria Zhernakova</name></author><author><name>Anette Kalnapenkis</name></author><author><name>Martin Magnusson</name></author><author><name>Eleanor Wheeler</name></author><author><name>Shih-Jen Hwang</name></author><author><name>Yan Chen</name></author><author><name>Andrew Morris</name></author><author><name>Bram Prins</name></author><author><name>Urmo Võsa</name></author><author><name>Nicholas J. Wareham</name></author><author><name>John Danesh</name></author><author><name>Johan Sundstrom</name></author><author><name>Bruna Gigante</name></author><author><name>Damiano Baldassarre</name></author><author><name>Rona J Strawbridge</name></author><author><name>Harry Campbell</name></author><author><name>Ulf Gyllensten</name></author><author><name>Chen Yao</name></author><author><name>Daniela Zanetti</name></author><author><name>Themistocles L Assimes</name></author><author><name>Per Eriksson</name></author><author><name>Daniel Levy</name></author><author><name>Claudia Langenberg</name></author><author><name>J. Gustav Smith</name></author><author><name>Tõnu Esko</name></author><author><name>Jingyuan Fu</name></author><author><name>Oskar Hansson</name></author><author><name>Åsa Johansson</name></author><author><name>Caroline Hayward</name></author><author><name>Lars Wallentin</name></author><author><name>Agneta Siegbahn</name></author><author><name>Lars Lind</name></author><author><name>Adam S Butterworth</name></author><author><name>Karl Michaëlsson</name></author><author><name>James E Peters</name></author><author><name>Anders Mälarstig</name></author><author><name>Peter K Joshi</name></author><author><name>James F Wilson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We performed the largest genome-wide meta-analysis (GWAMA) (Max N=26,494) of the levels of 184 cardiovascular-related plasma protein levels to date and reported 592 independent loci (pQTL) associated with the level of at least one protein (1308 significant associations, median 6 per protein). We estimated that only between 8-37% of testable pQTL overlap with established expression quantitative trait loci (eQTL) using multiple methods, while 132 out of 1064 lead variants show evidence for transcription factor binding, and found that 75% of our pQTL are known DNA methylation QTL. We highlight the variation in genetic architecture between proteins and that proteins share genetic architecture with cardiometabolic complex traits. Using cis-instrument Mendelian randomisation (MR), we infer causal relationships for 11 proteins, recapitulating the previously reported relationship between PCSK9 and LDL cholesterol, replicating previous pQTL MR findings and discovering 16 causal relationships between protein levels and disease. Our MR results highlight IL2-RA as a candidate for drug repurposing for Crohn's Disease as well as 2 novel therapeutic targets: IL-27 (Crohn's disease) and TNFRSF14 (Inflammatory bowel disease, Multiple sclerosis and Ulcerative colitis). We have demonstrated the discoveries possible using our pQTL and highlight the potential of this work as a resource for genetic epidemiology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.03.21261494" rel="alternate" title="Mapping genetic determinants of 184 circulating proteins in 26,494 individuals to connect proteins and disease. (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genetic and Genomic Medicine"/><published>2021-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.04.455067</id><title>A Self-Limiting Circuit Regulates Mammary Cap Cell Plasticity Through TGF-beta Signaling (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-09T06:15:39.404556+00:00</updated><author><name>Armelle M Le Guelte</name></author><author><name>Ian G Macara</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The organization and maintenance of complex tissues requires emergent properties driven by self-organizing and self-limiting cell-cell interactions. We examined these interactions in the murine mammary gland. Luminal and myoepithelial subpopulations of the postnatal mammary gland arise from unipotent progenitors, but the destiny of cap cells, which enclose terminal end buds (TEB) in pubertal mice, remains controversial. Using a transgenic strain (Tg11.5kb-GFP) that specifically marks cap cells, we found ~50% of these cells undergo divisions perpendicular to the TEB surface, suggesting they might contribute to the underlying luminal cell population. To address their stemness potential we developed a lineage tracing mouse driven from the s-SHIP (11.5 kb) promoter. Induction of tdTomato (tdTom) from this promoter in vivo demonstrated that all cap cell progeny are myoepithelial, with no conversion to luminal lineage. Organoid cultures also exhibited unipotency. However, isolated cap cells cultured as mammospheres generated mixed luminal/myoepithelial spheres. Moreover, ablation of luminal cells in vivo using diphtheria toxin triggered repopulation by progeny of tdTom+ cap cells. A signaling inhibitor screen identified the TGFb pathway as a potential regulator of multipotency. TGFbR inhibitors or gene deletion blocked conversion to the luminal lineage, consistent with an autocrine loop in which cap cells secrete TGFb to activate the receptor and promote luminal transdifferentiation. Ductal tree regeneration in vivo from isolated cap cells was much more efficient when they were pre-treated with inhibitor, consistent with more cells retaining cap cell potential prior to transplantation. Notably, in vitro transdifferentiation of cap cells was blocked by co-culture with luminal cells. Overall, these data reveal a self-limiting cell circuit through which mammary luminal cells suppress cap cell conversion to the luminal lineage.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.04.455067" rel="alternate" title="A Self-Limiting Circuit Regulates Mammary Cap Cell Plasticity Through TGF-beta Signaling (6 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.29.452310</id><title>Are flexible school start times associated with higher academic grades? A 4-year longitudinal study (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-09T06:15:39.405058+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna M. Biller</name></author><author><name>Carmen Molenda</name></author><author><name>Fabian Obster</name></author><author><name>Giulia Zerbini</name></author><author><name>Christian Förtsch</name></author><author><name>Till Roenneberg</name></author><author><name>Eva C. Winnebeck</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mismatch between teenagers’ late sleep phase and early school start time results in acute and chronic sleep reductions. This is not only harmful for students’ learning in the short-term but may impact on students’ career prospects and widen social inequalities. Delaying school start times has been shown to improve sleep but whether this translates to better achievement is unresolved. The current evidence is limited due to a plethora of outcome measures and the many factors influencing sleep and grade/score trajectories. Here, we studied whether 0.5-1.5 years of exposure to a &lt;italic&gt;flexible&lt;/italic&gt; school start system, with the &lt;italic&gt;daily&lt;/italic&gt; choice of an 8AM or 8:50AM-start (intervention), allowed secondary school students (n=63-157, 14-19 years) to improve their quarterly school grades in a 4-year longitudinal pre-post design. We investigated whether sleep, changes in sleep or frequency of later starts predicted grade improvements in the flexible system. Our mixed model regressions with 5,111-16,724 official grades as outcomes did not indicate meaningful grade improvements in the flexible system &lt;italic&gt;per se&lt;/italic&gt; or with previously observed sleep variables (nor their changes) – the covariates academic quarter, discipline and grade level had a greater, more systematic effect in our sample. Importantly, this finding does not preclude improvements in learning and cognition in our sample. However, at the ‘dose’ received here, intermittent sleep benefits did not obviously translate into detectable grade changes, which is in line with several other studies and highlights that grades are suboptimal to evaluate timetabling interventions despite their importance for future success.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Early school start times worldwide clash with teenagers’ delayed sleep-wake rhythms. This mismatch results in sleep restrictions below healthy amounts, which compromises health and performance and further aggravates social disparities. Since adequate sleep is important for learning and concentration, there is the strong expectation that counteracting sleep deprivation with delayed school starts results in better academic achievement. We add important high-resolution, longitudinal data to this unresolved scientific debate. When controlling for confounders, our results do not support that improved sleep leads to grade changes within 1.5 years in a flexible start system. While grades are suboptimal to measure later school start effects on performance, they nevertheless open doors to higher education worldwide and thus determine future trajectories.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.29.452310" rel="alternate" title="Are flexible school start times associated with higher academic grades? A 4-year longitudinal study (5 tweets)"/><category term="Scientific Communication and Education"/><published>2021-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>