<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.026866+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463746</id><title>Deep-Learning Super-Resolution Microscopy Reveals Nanometer-Scale Intracellular Dynamics at the Millisecond Temporal Resolution (56 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.027089+00:00</updated><author><name>Rong Chen</name></author><author><name>Xiao Tang</name></author><author><name>Zeyu Shen</name></author><author><name>Yusheng Shen</name></author><author><name>Tiantian Li</name></author><author><name>Ji Wang</name></author><author><name>Binbin Cui</name></author><author><name>Yusong Guo</name></author><author><name>Shengwang Du</name></author><author><name>Shuhuai Yao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single-molecule localization microscopy (SMLM) can be used to resolve subcellular structures and achieve a tenfold improvement in spatial resolution compared to that obtained by conventional fluorescence microscopy. However, the separation of single-molecule fluorescence events in thousands of frames dramatically increases the image acquisition time and phototoxicity, impeding the observation of instantaneous intracellular dynamics. Based on deep learning networks, we develop a single-frame super-resolution microscopy (SFSRM) approach that reconstructs a super-resolution image from a single frame of a diffraction-limited image to support live-cell super-resolution imaging at a ~20 nm spatial resolution and a temporal resolution of up to 10 ms over thousands of time points. We demonstrate that our SFSRM method enables the visualization of the dynamics of vesicle transport at a millisecond temporal resolution in the dense and vibrant microtubule network in live cells. Moreover, the well-trained network model can be used with different live-cell imaging systems, such as confocal and light-sheet microscopes, making super-resolution microscopy accessible to nonexperts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463746" rel="alternate" title="Deep-Learning Super-Resolution Microscopy Reveals Nanometer-Scale Intracellular Dynamics at the Millisecond Temporal Resolution (56 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.05.463266</id><title>Engineered endosymbionts capable of directing mammalian cell gene expression (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.027335+00:00</updated><author><name>Cody S. Madsen</name></author><author><name>Ashley V. Makela</name></author><author><name>Emily M. Greeson</name></author><author><name>Jonathan W. Hardy</name></author><author><name>Christopher H. Contag</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Modular methods for directing mammalian gene expression would enable advances in tissue regeneration, enhance cell-based therapeutics and improve modulation of immune responses. To address this challenge, engineered endosymbionts (EES) that escape endosomal destruction, reside in the cytoplasm of mammalian cells, and secrete proteins that are transported to the nucleus to control host cell gene expression were developed. Microscopy confirmed that EES escape phagosomes, replicate within the cytoplasm, and can secrete reporter proteins into the cytoplasm that were then transported to the nucleus. Synthetic operons encoding the mammalian transcription factors, &lt;italic&gt;Stat-1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Klf6&lt;/italic&gt; or &lt;italic&gt;Klf4&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Gata-3&lt;/italic&gt; were recombined into the EES genome. Using controlled induction, these EES were shown to direct gene expression in J774A.1 macrophage/monocyte cells and modulate the host cell fates. Expressing mammalian transcription factors from engineered intracellular bacteria as endosymbionts comprises a new tool for directing host cell gene expression for therapeutic and research purposes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="463266v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.05.463266" rel="alternate" title="Engineered endosymbionts capable of directing mammalian cell gene expression (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>