<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv other-biological-sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.760736+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453379</id><title>AlphaPept, a modern and open framework for MS-based proteomics (57 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.761002+00:00</updated><author><name>Maximilian T. Strauss</name></author><author><name>Isabell Bludau</name></author><author><name>Wen-Feng Zeng</name></author><author><name>Eugenia Voytik</name></author><author><name>Constantin Ammar</name></author><author><name>Julia Schessner</name></author><author><name>Rajesh Ilango</name></author><author><name>Michelle Gill</name></author><author><name>Florian Meier</name></author><author><name>Sander Willems</name></author><author><name>Matthias Mann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In common with other omics technologies, mass spectrometry (MS)-based proteomics produces ever-increasing amounts of raw data, making their efficient analysis a principal challenge. There is a plethora of different computational tools that process the raw MS data and derive peptide and protein identification and quantification. During the last decade, there has been dramatic progress in computer science and software engineering, including collaboration tools that have transformed research and industry. To leverage these advances, we developed AlphaPept, a Python-based open-source framework for efficient processing of large high-resolution MS data sets. Using Numba for just-in-time machine code compilation on CPU and GPU, we achieve hundred-fold speed improvements while maintaining clear syntax and rapid development speed. AlphaPept uses the Python scientific stack of highly optimized packages, reducing the code base to domain-specific tasks while providing access to the latest advances in machine learning. We provide an easy on-ramp for community validation and contributions through the concept of literate programming, implemented in Jupyter Notebooks of the different modules. A framework for continuous integration, testing, and benchmarking enforces solid software engineering principles. Large datasets can rapidly be processed as shown by the analysis of hundreds of cellular proteomes in minutes per file, many-fold faster than the data acquisiton. The AlphaPept framework can be used to build automated processing pipelines using efficient HDF5 based file formats, web-serving functionality and compatibility with downstream analysis tools. Easy access for end-users is provided by one-click installation of the graphical user interface, for advanced users via a modular Python library, and for developers via a fully open GitHub repository.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453379" rel="alternate" title="AlphaPept, a modern and open framework for MS-based proteomics (57 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453492</id><title>Delineating Medical Education: Bibliometric Research Approach(es) (52 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.761242+00:00</updated><author><name>Lauren A. Maggio</name></author><author><name>Anton Ninkov</name></author><author><name>Jason R. Frank</name></author><author><name>Joseph A. Costello</name></author><author><name>Anthony R. Artino</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The field of medical education remains poorly delineated such that there is no broad consensus of the articles and journals that comprise “the field.” This lack of consensus has implications for conducting bibliometric studies and other research designs (e.g., systematic reviews); it also challenges the field to compare citation scores in the field and across others and for an individual to identify themselves as “a medical education researcher.” Other fields have utilized bibliometric field delineation, which is the assigning of articles or journals to a certain field in an effort to define that field.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Process&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this &lt;italic&gt;Research Approach&lt;/italic&gt;, three bibliometric field delineation approaches -- information retrieval, core journals, and journal co-citation -- are introduced. For each approach, the authors describe their attempt to apply it in the medical education context and identify related strengths and weaknesses. Based on co-citation, the authors propose the Medical Education Journal List 24 (MEJ-24), as a starting point for delineating medical education and invite the community to collaborate on improving and potentially expanding this list.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Pearls&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a research approach, field delineation is complicated, and there is no clear best way to delineate the field of medical education. However, recent advances in information and computer science provide potentially more fruitful approaches to deal with the complexity of the field. When considering these emerging approaches, researchers should consider collaborating with bibliometricians.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bibliometric approaches rely on available metadata for articles and journals, which necessitates that researchers examine the metadata prior to analysis to understand its strengths and weaknesses, and to assess how this might affect their data interpretation. While using bibliometric approaches for field delineation is valuable, it is important to remember that these techniques are only as good as the research team’s interpretation of the data, which suggests that an expanded research approach is needed to better delineate medical education, an approach that includes active discussion within the medical education community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453492" rel="alternate" title="Delineating Medical Education: Bibliometric Research Approach(es) (52 tweets)"/><category term="Scientific Communication and Education"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453605</id><title>Identifying cell-state associated alternative splicing events and their co-regulation (51 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.761409+00:00</updated><author><name>Carlos F. Buen Abad Najar</name></author><author><name>Prakruthi Burra</name></author><author><name>Nir Yosef</name></author><author><name>Liana F. Lareau</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Alternative splicing shapes the transcriptome and contributes to each cell’s unique identity, but single-cell RNA sequencing has struggled to capture the impact of alternative splicing. We previously showed that low recovery of mRNAs from single cells led to erroneous conclusions about the cell-to-cell variability of alternative splicing (1). Here, we present a method, Psix, to confidently identify splicing that changes across a landscape of single cells, using a probabilistic model that is robust against the data limitations of scRNA-seq. Its autocorrelation-inspired approach finds patterns of alternative splicing that correspond to patterns of cell identity, such as cell type or developmental stage, without the need for explicit cell clustering, labeling, or trajectory inference. Applying Psix to data that follow the trajectory of mouse brain development, we identify exons whose alternative splicing patterns cluster into modules of co-regulation. We show that the exons in these modules are enriched for binding by distinct neuronal splicing factors, and that their changes in splicing correspond to changes in expression of these splicing factors. Thus, Psix reveals cell-type-dependent splicing patterns and the wiring of the splicing regulatory networks that control them. Our new method will enable scRNA-seq analysis to go beyond transcription to understand the roles of post-transcriptional regulation in determining cell identity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453605" rel="alternate" title="Identifying cell-state associated alternative splicing events and their co-regulation (51 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453478</id><title>Mechanosensitivity of nucleocytoplasmic transport (44 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.761568+00:00</updated><author><name>Ion Andreu</name></author><author><name>Ignasi Granero-Moya</name></author><author><name>Nimesh R. Chahare</name></author><author><name>Kessem Clein</name></author><author><name>Marc Molina Jordàn</name></author><author><name>Amy E. M. Beedle</name></author><author><name>Alberto Elosegui-Artola</name></author><author><name>Xavier Trepat</name></author><author><name>Barak Raveh</name></author><author><name>Pere Roca-Cusachs</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mechanical force controls fundamental cellular processes in health and disease, and increasing evidence shows that the nucleus both experiences and senses applied forces. Here we show that nuclear forces differentially control both passive and facilitated nucleocytoplasmic transport, setting the rules for the mechanosensitivity of shuttling proteins. We demonstrate that nuclear force increases permeability across nuclear pore complexes, with a dependence on molecular weight that is stronger for passive than facilitated diffusion. Due to this differential effect, force leads to the translocation into or out of the nucleus of cargoes within a given range of molecular weight and affinity for nuclear transport receptors. Further, we show that the mechanosensitivity of several transcriptional regulators can be both explained by this mechanism, and engineered exogenously by introducing appropriate nuclear localization signals. Our work sets a novel framework to understand mechanically induced signalling, with potential general applicability across signalling pathways and pathophysiological scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Force application to the nucleus leads to nuclear accumulation of proteins by differentially affecting passive versus facilitated nucleocytoplasmic transport.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453478" rel="alternate" title="Mechanosensitivity of nucleocytoplasmic transport (44 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453573</id><title>Strong and opponent contributions of dorsomedial striatal pathways to behavior depends on cognitive demands and task strategy (43 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.761762+00:00</updated><author><name>Scott S. Bolkan</name></author><author><name>Iris R. Stone</name></author><author><name>Lucas Pinto</name></author><author><name>Zoe C. Ashwood</name></author><author><name>Jorge M. Iravedra Garcia</name></author><author><name>Alison L. Herman</name></author><author><name>Priyanka Singh</name></author><author><name>Akhil Bandi</name></author><author><name>Julia Cox</name></author><author><name>Christopher A. Zimmerman</name></author><author><name>Jounhong Ryan Cho</name></author><author><name>Ben Engelhard</name></author><author><name>Sue A. Koay</name></author><author><name>Jonathan W. Pillow</name></author><author><name>Ilana B. Witten</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A classic view of the striatum holds that activity in direct and indirect pathways oppositely modulates motor output. Whether this involves direct control of movement, or reflects a cognitive process underlying movement, has remained unresolved. Here we find that strong, opponent control of behavior by the two pathways of the dorsomedial striatum (DMS) depends on a task’s cognitive demands. Furthermore, a latent state model (a hidden markov model with generalized linear model observations) reveals that—even within a single task—the contribution of the two pathways to behavior is state-dependent. Specifically, the two pathways have large contributions in one of two states associated with a strategy of evidence accumulation, compared to a state associated with a strategy of repeating previous choices. Thus, both the cognitive demands imposed by a task, as well as the strategy that mice pursue within a task, determine whether DMS pathways provide strong and opponent control of behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453573" rel="alternate" title="Strong and opponent contributions of dorsomedial striatal pathways to behavior depends on cognitive demands and task strategy (43 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.453458</id><title>Epithelial-mesenchymal plasticity determines estrogen receptor positive (ER+) breast cancer dormancy and reacquisition of an epithelial state drives awakening (41 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.761985+00:00</updated><author><name>Patrick Aouad</name></author><author><name>Yueyun Zhang</name></author><author><name>Céline Stibolt</name></author><author><name>Sendurai A. Mani</name></author><author><name>George Sflomos</name></author><author><name>Cathrin Brisken</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Estrogen receptor α-positive (ER+) breast cancers (BCs) represent more than 70% of all breast cancers and pose a particular clinical challenge because they recur up to decades after initial diagnosis and treatment. The mechanisms governing tumor cell dormancy and latent disease remain elusive due to a lack of adequate models. Here, we compare tumor progression of ER+ and triple-negative (TN) BC subtypes with a clinically relevant mouse intraductal xenografting approach (MIND). Both ER+ and TN BC cells disseminate already during the &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt;stage. However, TN disseminated tumor cells (DTCs) proliferate at the same rate as cells at the primary site and give rise to macro-metastases. ER+ DTCs have low proliferative indices, form only micro-metastases and lose epithelial characteristics. Expression of &lt;italic&gt;CDH1&lt;/italic&gt; is decreased whereas the mesenchymal marker &lt;italic&gt;VIM&lt;/italic&gt; and the transcription factors, &lt;italic&gt;ZEB1&lt;/italic&gt;/&lt;italic&gt;ZEB2,&lt;/italic&gt; which control epithelial-mesenchymal plasticity (EMP) are increased. EMP is not detected earlier during ER+ BC development and not required for invasion or metastasis. &lt;italic&gt;In vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, forced transition to the epithelial state through ectopic E-cadherin expression overcomes dormancy with increased growth of lung metastases. We conclude that EMP is essential for the generation of a dormant cell state and the development of latent disease. Targeting exit from EMP is of therapeutic potential.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.453458" rel="alternate" title="Epithelial-mesenchymal plasticity determines estrogen receptor positive (ER+) breast cancer dormancy and reacquisition of an epithelial state drives awakening (41 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.21.453258</id><title>Retrosplenial cortex is necessary for spatial and non-spatial latent learning in mice (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.762154+00:00</updated><author><name>Ana Carolina Bottura de Barros</name></author><author><name>Liad J. Baruchin</name></author><author><name>Marios C. Panayi</name></author><author><name>Nils Nyberg</name></author><author><name>Veronika Samborska</name></author><author><name>Mitchell T. Mealing</name></author><author><name>Thomas Akam</name></author><author><name>Jeehyun Kwag</name></author><author><name>David M. Bannerman</name></author><author><name>Michael M. Kohl</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Latent learning occurs when associations are formed between stimuli in the absence of explicit reinforcement. Traditionally, latent learning in rodents has been associated with the creation internal models of space. However, increasing evidence points to roles of internal models also in non-spatial decision making. Whether the same brain structures and processes support the creation of spatially-anchored or non-spatial internal models via latent learning, is an open question. To address this question, we developed a novel operant box task that allows to test spatial and non-spatial versions of a flavour-based sensory preconditioning paradigm. We probed the role of the retrosplenial cortex, a brain area associated with spatial cognition and subjective value representation, in this task using precise, closed-loop optogenetic silencing during different task phases. We show that the retrosplenial cortex is necessary for both spatial and non-spatial latent learning in mice. We further demonstrate that the requirement of retrosplenial cortex is limited to the preconditioning phase of the task. Our results provide insight into the specific role of the retrosplenial cortex in latent learning, demonstrate that latent learning plays a general part in the creation of internal models, independent of spatial anchors, and provide a novel avenue for studying model-based decision making.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.21.453258" rel="alternate" title="Retrosplenial cortex is necessary for spatial and non-spatial latent learning in mice (30 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.27.453460</id><title>Extracellular mechanical forces drive endocardial cell volume decrease during cardiac valve morphogenesis (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.762341+00:00</updated><author><name>Julien Vermot</name></author><author><name>Helene Vignes</name></author><author><name>Christina Vagena-Pantoula</name></author><author><name>Mangal Prakash</name></author><author><name>Caren Norden</name></author><author><name>Florian Jug</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Organ morphogenesis involves dynamic changes of tissue properties at the cellular scale. In addition, cells need to adapt to their mechanical environment through mechanosensitive pathways. How mechanical cues influence cell behaviors during morphogenesis, however, remains poorly understood. Here we studied the influence of mechanical forces during the formation of the atrioventricular canal (AVC) where cardiac valves develop. We show that in zebrafish the AVC forms within a zone of tissue convergence between the atrium and the ventricle which is associated with increased activation of the actomyosin meshwork and endocardial cell orientation changes. We demonstrate that tissue convergence occurs with a major reduction of endocardial cell volume triggered by mechanical forces and the mechanosensitive channels TRPP2/TRPV4. In addition, we show that the extracellular matrix component hyaluronic acid controls cell volume changes. Together, our data suggest that cell volume change is a key cellular feature activated by mechanical forces during cardiovascular morphogenesis. This work further unravels how mechanical forces and
extracellular matrix can influence tissue remodeling in developing organs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.27.453460" rel="alternate" title="Extracellular mechanical forces drive endocardial cell volume decrease during cardiac valve morphogenesis (29 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453816</id><title>Synaptic Mechanisms of Top-Down Control by The Auditory Cortico-Collicular Pathway (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.762508+00:00</updated><author><name>Hannah M. Oberle</name></author><author><name>Alex Ford</name></author><author><name>Jordyn Czarny</name></author><author><name>Pierre F. Apostolides</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Corticofugal projections to evolutionarily ancient, sub-cortical structures are ubiquitous across mammalian sensory systems. These “descending” pathways enable the neocortex to control ascending sensory representations in a predictive or feedback manner, but the underlying cellular mechanisms are poorly understood. Here we combine optogenetic approaches with &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; patch-clamp electrophysiology to study the projection from auditory cortex to the inferior colliculus (IC), a major descending auditory pathway that controls IC neuron feature selectivity, plasticity and auditory perceptual learning. Although individual auditory cortico-collicular synapses were generally weak, IC neurons often integrated inputs from multiple corticofugal axons that generated reliable, tonic depolarizations even during prolonged presynaptic activity. Latency measurements &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; showed that descending signals reach the IC within 30 ms of sound onset, which in IC neurons corresponded to the peak of synaptic depolarizations evoked by short sounds. Activating ascending and descending pathways at latencies expected &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; caused a NMDA receptor dependent, supra-linear EPSP summation, indicating that descending signals can non-linearly amplify IC neurons’ moment-to-moment acoustic responses. Our results shed light upon the synaptic bases of descending sensory control, and imply that heterosynaptic cooperativity contributes to the auditory cortico-collicular pathway’s role in plasticity and perceptual learning.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453816" rel="alternate" title="Synaptic Mechanisms of Top-Down Control by The Auditory Cortico-Collicular Pathway (23 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453747</id><title>ABlooper: Fast accurate antibody CDR loop structure prediction with accuracy estimation (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.762664+00:00</updated><author><name>Brennan Abanades</name></author><author><name>Guy Georges</name></author><author><name>Alexander Bujotzek</name></author><author><name>Charlotte M. Deane</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antibodies are a key component of the immune system and have been extensively used as biotherapeutics. Accurate knowledge of their structure is central to understanding their function. The key area for antigen binding and the main area of structural variation in antibodies are concentrated in their six complementarity determining regions (CDRs), with the most variable being the CDR-H3 loop. The sequence and structure variability of CDR-H3 make it particularly challenging to model. Recently, deep learning methods have offered a step change in our ability to predict protein structures. In this work we present ABlooper, an end-to-end equivariant deep-learning based CDR loop structure prediction tool. ABlooper predicts the structure of CDR loops with high accuracy and provides a confidence estimate for each of its predictions. On the models of the Rosetta Antibody Benchmark, ABlooper makes predictions with an average H3 RMSD of 2.45Å, which drops to 2.02Å when considering only its 76% most confident predictions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453747" rel="alternate" title="ABlooper: Fast accurate antibody CDR loop structure prediction with accuracy estimation (23 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453647</id><title>Oncogenic c-Myc induces replication stress by increasing cohesins chromatin occupancy (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.762817+00:00</updated><author><name>Silvia Peripolli</name></author><author><name>Tanya Singh</name></author><author><name>Harshil Patel</name></author><author><name>Leticia Meneguello</name></author><author><name>Koshiro Kiso</name></author><author><name>Peter Thorpe</name></author><author><name>Cosetta Bertoli</name></author><author><name>Robertus A.M. de Bruin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Oncogene-induced replication stress is a major driver of genomic instability in cancer cells, with a central role in both cancer initiation and progression (1). Despite its critical role in cancer development, the mechanisms that lay at the basis of oncogene-induced replication stress remains poorly understood. Here, we investigate the mechanism of c-Myc-induced replication stress. Our data shows that c-Myc induces replication stress by increasing the amount of cohesins bound to chromatin in the G1 phase of the cell cycle. This is independent of previously suggested mechanisms involving deregulation of replication initiation and transcriptional interference. Restoring the amount of chromatin-bound cohesins to control levels, or preventing the accumulation of cohesins at CTCF sites, in cells experiencing oncogenic c-Myc activity prevents replication stress. Increased cohesins chromatin occupancy correlates with a c-Myc-dependent increase in the levels of the cohesion loader Mau2. Preventing c-Myc-induced increase in Mau2 reduces oncogene-induced replication stress. Together our data support a novel mechanism for oncogene-induced replication stress. Since c-Myc activation is a crucial event in many human cancers (2), identifying the mechanisms through which this oncogene promotes replication stress provides critical insights into cancer biology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453647" rel="alternate" title="Oncogenic c-Myc induces replication stress by increasing cohesins chromatin occupancy (20 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453678</id><title>Reward-dependent selection of feedback gains impacts rapid motor decisions (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.763050+00:00</updated><author><name>Antoine De Comite</name></author><author><name>Frédéric Crevecoeur</name></author><author><name>Philippe Lefèvre</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Expected reward is known to affect planning strategies through modulation of movement vigor. Strikingly, although current theories suggest that movement planning consists in selecting a goal-directed control policy, the influence of reward on feedback control strategies remains unknown. Here we investigated this question in three human reaching experiments. First, we varied the explicit reward associated with the goal target and found an overall increase in movement vigor for higher reward targets, highlighted by larger velocities, feedback responses to external loads, and background muscle activity. Then, assuming that larger feedback gains were used to reject perturbations, we sought to investigate whether this effect hindered online decisions to switch to a new target in the presence of multiple successful goals. We indeed observed idiosyncratic switching strategies dependent on both target rewards and movement vigor, such that the more vigorous movements were less likely to switch to a new goal following perturbations. To gain further insight into a causal influence of movement vigor on rapid motor decisions, we demonstrated that biasing the baseline activity and reflex gains by means of a background load evoked a larger proportion of target switches in the direction opposite to the background load associated with lower muscle activity. Our results highlight the competition between movement vigor and flexibility to switch target during movement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Humans can modulate their movement vigor based on the expected reward. However, a potential influence of reward on feedback control has not been documented. Here we investigated reaching control strategies in different contexts associated with explicit rewards for one or multiple goals, while exposed to external perturbations. We report two strategies: reward could either invigorate feedback gains, or promote flexible switches between goals. The engagement of peripheral circuits in the modulation of feedback gains was confirmed by the application of a background load that biased feedback vigor directionally, which evoked differences in switching behavior in the opposite direction. We conclude that feedback vigor and flexible changes in goal are two competing mechanisms to be selected when one interacts with a dynamic environment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453678" rel="alternate" title="Reward-dependent selection of feedback gains impacts rapid motor decisions (16 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453634</id><title>Crowding-induced phase separation of nuclear transport receptors in FG nucleoporin assemblies (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.763342+00:00</updated><author><name>Luke K. Davis</name></author><author><name>Ian J. Ford</name></author><author><name>Bart W. Hoogenboom</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The rapid (&amp;lt; 1 ms) transport of biological material to and from the cell nucleus is regulated by the nuclear pore complex (NPC). At the core of the NPC is a permeability barrier consisting of intrinsically disordered Phe-Gly (FG) nucleoporins (FG Nups). Various types of nuclear transport receptors (NTRs) facilitate transport by partitioning in the FG Nup assembly, overcoming the barrier by their affinity to the FG Nups, and comprise a significant fraction of proteins in the NPC barrier. In previous work, we revealed that the experimental binding of the NTRs NTF2 and – the larger – Imp&lt;italic&gt;β&lt;/italic&gt; to different planar assemblies of FG Nups follows a universal physical law defined by negative cooperativity, which was further validated by a minimal physical model that treated the FG Nups as flexible homopolymers and the NTRs as uniformly cohesive spheres &lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Zahn et al. (2016&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt;). Here, we build upon our original study by first parametrizing our model to experimental data, and next to predict the effects of crowding by different types of NTRs. We show how varying the amounts of one type of NTR modulates how the other NTR penetrates the FG Nup assembly. Notably, at similar and physiologically relevant NTR concentrations, our model predicts demixed phases of NTF2 and Imp&lt;italic&gt;β&lt;/italic&gt; within the FG Nup assembly. The functional implication of NTR phase separation is that NPCs may sustain separate transport pathways that are determined by inter-NTR competition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453634" rel="alternate" title="Crowding-induced phase separation of nuclear transport receptors in FG nucleoporin assemblies (14 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453674</id><title>Role of non-specific interactions in the phase-separation and maturation of macromolecules (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.763634+00:00</updated><author><name>Rakesh Krishnan</name></author><author><name>Srivastav Ranganathan</name></author><author><name>Samir K Maji</name></author><author><name>Ranjith Padinhateeri</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Phase separation of biomolecules could be mediated by both specific and non-specific interactions. How the interplay between non-specific and specific interactions along with polymer entropy influences phase separation is an open question. We address this question by simulating self-associating molecules as polymer chains with a short core stretch that forms the specifically interacting functional interface, and longer non-core regions that participate in non-specific/promiscuous interactions. Our results show that the interplay of specific (strength, &lt;italic&gt;ϵ&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;sp&lt;/sub&gt;) and non-specific interactions (strength, &lt;italic&gt;ϵ&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;ns&lt;/sub&gt;) could result in phase separation of polymers and its transition to solid-like aggregates (mature state). In the absence of &lt;italic&gt;ϵ&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;ns&lt;/sub&gt;, the polymer chains do not dwell long enough in the vicinity of each other to undergo phase separation and transition into a mature state. On the other hand, in the limit of strong &lt;italic&gt;ϵ&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;ns&lt;/sub&gt;, the assemblies cannot transition into the mature state because they get kinetically trapped, suggesting an optimal range of interactions favoring mature multimers. In the scenario where only a fraction (N&lt;sub&gt;frac&lt;/sub&gt;) of the non-core regions participate in attractive interactions, we find that a slight modifications to either &lt;italic&gt;ϵ&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;ns&lt;/sub&gt; or N&lt;sub&gt;frac&lt;/sub&gt; can result in a dramatically altered self-assembled states. Using a combination of heterogeneous and homogeneous mix of polymers, we establish how this interplay between interaction energies dictates the propensity of biomolecules to find the correct binding partner at dilute concentrations in crowded environments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453674" rel="alternate" title="Role of non-specific interactions in the phase-separation and maturation of macromolecules (12 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.18.21259977</id><title>Altered functional connectome hierarchy with gene expression signatures in newly-diagnosed focal epilepsy (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.764180+00:00</updated><author><name>Christophe E de Bézenac</name></author><author><name>Lorenzo Caciagli</name></author><author><name>Batil K Alonazi</name></author><author><name>Boris C Bernhardt</name></author><author><name>Anthony G Marson</name></author><author><name>Simon S Keller</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neuroimaging research is providing insights into epilepsy as a disorder of brain connectivity linked to functional impairments which may have an identifiable genetic component. This case-control study aims to identify imbalances in a functional connectome dimension spanning from unimodal to transmodal networks and explore the potential genetic basis of such alterations in patients with newly diagnosed focal epilepsy (NDfE).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used gradient-based analysis of resting-sate fMRI data comparing cortical gradient maps in patients with NDfE (n = 27) to age and sex-matched controls (n = 36). Using a brain-wide gene expression dataset, gene combinations associated with altered brain regions were then entered into an enrichment analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found an increased differentiation of connectivity profiles between unimodal and transmodal networks in NDfE, which was particularly pronounced in the patients with persistent seizures at 12-months follow-up (n=10). Differences corresponded to gradient score reductions in a visual network and increases in limbic and default mode systems which subserve higher-level cognition. Cortical difference maps were spatially correlated with regional expression of a weighted gene combination. These genes were enriched for disease and ontology terms and pathways previously associated with epilepsy and seizure susceptibility.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretations&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Large-scale functional hierarchy may be altered from in focal epilepsy from diagnosis and correlate with response to treatment. Combining functional neuroimaging and transcriptional data analysis may provide a framework for understanding the wide-ranging impairments associated with the disorder and mechanistic insight into how gene processes may drive alterations in brain function mediating the genetic risk of epilepsy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.18.21259977" rel="alternate" title="Altered functional connectome hierarchy with gene expression signatures in newly-diagnosed focal epilepsy (12 tweets)"/><category term="Neurology"/><published>2021-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.452477</id><title>Trial-wise exposure to visual appetitive cues increases physiological arousal but not temporal discounting (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.764862+00:00</updated><author><name>Kilian Knauth</name></author><author><name>Jan Peters</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Humans and many animals devalue future rewards as a function of time (temporal discounting). Increased discounting has been linked to various psychiatric conditions, including substance-use-disorders, behavioral addictions and obesity. Despite its high intra-individual stability, temporal discounting is partly under contextual control. One prominent manipulation that has been linked to increases in discounting is the exposure to highly arousing appetitive cues. However, results from trial-wise cue exposure studies appear highly mixed, and changes in physiological arousal were not adequately controlled. Here we tested the effects of appetitive (erotic), aversive and neutral visual cues on temporal discounting in thirty-five healthy male participants. The contribution of single-trial physiological arousal was assessed using comprehensive monitoring of autonomic activity (pupil size, heart rate, electrodermal activity). Physiological arousal was elevated following aversive and in particular erotic cues. In contrast to our pre-registered hypothesis, if anything, we observed &lt;italic&gt;decreased&lt;/italic&gt; temporal discounting following erotic cue exposure. Aversive cues tended to increase decision noise. Computational modeling revealed that trial-wise arousal only accounted for minor variance over and above aversive and erotic condition effects, arguing against a general effect of physiological arousal on temporal discounting.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.452477" rel="alternate" title="Trial-wise exposure to visual appetitive cues increases physiological arousal but not temporal discounting (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453671</id><title>MetaBinner: a high-performance and stand-alone ensemble binning method to recover individual genomes from complex microbial communities (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.765121+00:00</updated><author><name>Ziye Wang</name></author><author><name>Pingqin Huang</name></author><author><name>Ronghui You</name></author><author><name>Fengzhu Sun</name></author><author><name>Shanfeng Zhu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Binning is an essential procedure during metagenomic data analysis. However, the available individual binning methods usually do not simultaneously fully use different features or biological information. Furthermore, it is challenging to integrate multiple binning results efficiently and effectively. Therefore, we developed an ensemble binner, MetaBinner, which generates component results with multiple types of features and utilizes single-copy gene (SCG) information for k-means initialization. It then utilizes a two-step ensemble strategy based on SCGs to integrate the component results. Extensive experimental results over three large-scale simulated datasets and one real-world dataset demonstrate that MetaBinner outperforms other state-of-the-art individual binners and ensemble binners. MetaBinner is freely available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/ziyewang/MetaBinner"&gt;https://github.com/ziyewang/MetaBinner&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453671" rel="alternate" title="MetaBinner: a high-performance and stand-alone ensemble binning method to recover individual genomes from complex microbial communities (10 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453355</id><title>Inhibition of striatal SEZ6 by miR-3594-5p is a drug-specific marker for late-stage heroin intake escalation (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.765400+00:00</updated><author><name>Magalie Lenoir</name></author><author><name>Isabella Bondi</name></author><author><name>Loïc Clemenceau</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Nondier</name></author><author><name>Margaux Ballé</name></author><author><name>Sébastien Jacques</name></author><author><name>Angéline Duché</name></author><author><name>Corinne Canestrelli</name></author><author><name>Séverine Martin-Lannerée</name></author><author><name>Sophie Mouillet-Richard</name></author><author><name>Jenny M. Gunnersen</name></author><author><name>Serge H. Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Marie</name></author><author><name>Florence Noble</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Escalation of drug use is a hallmark stage in the transition to addiction and uncovering its underlying brain molecular mechanisms constitutes a considerable challenge. Here, we report in rats with extended access to heroin for self-administration that miR-3594-5p was upregulated in the dorsal striatum at late, but not early, stages during escalation when excessive heroin intake plateaued. Striatal miR-3594-5p bound directly to the 3’UTR region of &lt;italic&gt;Sez6&lt;/italic&gt; transcript and inhibited its expression, thereby decreasing the mature form of the translated SEZ6 protein. This miR-3594-5p/&lt;italic&gt;Sez6&lt;/italic&gt; interaction was specific to heroin, as it was not observed with cocaine, and correlated with the severity of heroin intake escalation. Our findings reveal that miRNA alterations during escalation of drug self-administration are spatially and temporally regulated and drug-specific.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453355" rel="alternate" title="Inhibition of striatal SEZ6 by miR-3594-5p is a drug-specific marker for late-stage heroin intake escalation (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453449</id><title>Heat-inactivated modified vaccinia virus Ankara boosts Th1-biased cellular and humoral immune responses as a vaccine adjuvant by activating the STING-mediated cytosolic DNA-sensing pathway (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.765906+00:00</updated><author><name>Ning Yang</name></author><author><name>Aitor Garzia</name></author><author><name>Cindy Meyer</name></author><author><name>Thomas Tuschl</name></author><author><name>Taha Merghoub</name></author><author><name>Jedd D. Wolchok</name></author><author><name>Liang Deng</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Protein or peptide-based subunit vaccines are promising platforms for combating human cancers and infectious diseases. However, one primary concern regarding subunit vaccines is the relatively weak immune responses induced by proteins or peptides. Therefore, developing novel and effective vaccine adjuvants is critical for the success of subunit vaccines. Modified vaccinia virus (MVA) is a safe and effective vaccine against smallpox and monkeypox. In this study, we explored the potential of heat-inactivated MVA (heat-iMVA) as a novel vaccine adjuvant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We co-administered heat-iMVA with a model antigen, chicken ovalbumin (OVA), either intramuscularly or subcutaneously twice, two weeks apart, and analyzed anti-OVA specific CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells in the spleens and skin draining lymph nodes (dLNs) and serum anti-OVA IgG1 and IgG2c antibodies. We also compared the adjuvanticity of heat-iMVA with several known vaccine adjuvants, including complete Freund’s adjuvant (CFA) and AddaVax, an MF59-like preclinical grade nano-emulsion. In addition, we tested whether co-administration of heat-iMVA plus tumor neoantigen peptides or irradiated tumor cells improves antitumor efficacy in a B16-F10 therapeutic vaccination model. Using Stimulator of Interferon Genes (STING) or Batf3-deficient mice, we evaluated the contribution of the STING pathway and Batf3-dependent CD103&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;/CD8α DCs in heat-iMVA-induced immunity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Co-administration of protein- or peptide-based immunogens with heat-iMVA dramatically enhances Th1-biased cellular and humoral immune responses. This adjuvant effect of heat-iMVA is dependent on the STING-mediated cytosolic DNA-sensing pathway, and the antigen-specific CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cell response requires Batf3-dependent CD103&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;/CD8α&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; dendritic cells (DCs). Heat-iMVA infection of bone marrow-derived DCs (BMDCs) promoted antigen cross-presentation, whereas live MVA infection did not. RNA-seq analyses revealed that heat-iMVA is a more potent activator of the STING pathway than live MVA. Additionally, combining tumor neoantigen peptides or irradiated tumor cells with heat-iMVA delayed tumor growth and extended the median survival in B16-F10 therapeutic vaccination models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heat-iMVA induces type I interferon (IFN) production and antigen cross-presentation via a STING-dependent mechanism in DCs. Co-administration of heat-iMVA with peptide antigen generates strong Th1-biased cellular and humoral immunity. Collectively, our results demonstrate that heat-iMVA is a safe and potent vaccine adjuvant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453449" rel="alternate" title="Heat-inactivated modified vaccinia virus Ankara boosts Th1-biased cellular and humoral immune responses as a vaccine adjuvant by activating the STING-mediated cytosolic DNA-sensing pathway (8 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453512</id><title>In vitro and in vivo analysis of microvesicle-mediated metastasis using a bright, red-shifted bioluminescent reporter protein of extracellular vesicles (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.766101+00:00</updated><author><name>Ahmed A. Zarea</name></author><author><name>Gloria I. Perez</name></author><author><name>David Broadbent</name></author><author><name>Benedikt Dolgikh</name></author><author><name>Matthew P. Bernard</name></author><author><name>Alicia Withrow</name></author><author><name>Amelia McGill</name></author><author><name>Victoria Toomajian</name></author><author><name>Lukose K. Thampy</name></author><author><name>Jack Harkema</name></author><author><name>Joel R. Walker</name></author><author><name>Thormas A. Kirkland</name></author><author><name>Michael H. Bachmann</name></author><author><name>Jens Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Masamitsu Kanada</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cancer cells produce heterogeneous extracellular vesicles (EVs) as mediators of intercellular communication. Our study focused on a novel method to image EV subtypes and their biodistribution &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Regardless of injection routes, we established that reporter EVs isolated from murine mammary carcinoma cells expressing PalmReNL, which utilizes bioluminescence resonance energy transfer (BRET), localized to the lungs. This new EV reporter allowed highly sensitive EV tracking &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and enabled us to begin studies to understand the commonalities and functional differences of the EV subtypes. We demonstrated the early appearance of metastatic foci in the lungs of mammary tumor-bearing mice following multiple injections of the microvesicle (MV)-enriched fraction derived from mammary carcinoma cells. In addition, the results we present here show that tumor cell-derived MVs act on distant tissues through upregulating LC3 expression within the lung.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453512" rel="alternate" title="In vitro and in vivo analysis of microvesicle-mediated metastasis using a bright, red-shifted bioluminescent reporter protein of extracellular vesicles (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453739</id><title>Connectivity between the hippocampus and default mode network during the relief – but not elicitation – of curiosity supports curiosity-enhanced memory enhancements (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.766327+00:00</updated><author><name>Charlotte Murphy</name></author><author><name>Charan Ranganath</name></author><author><name>Matthias J. Gruber</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Consistent with the idea that curiosity enhances information seeking, it has been shown that activity within both the dopaminergic circuit and hippocampus supports curiosity-enhanced learning. However, the role of whole-brain mechanisms involved in cognitive control (fronto-parietal network; FPN) and memory integration (default mode network; DMN) that might underpin curiosity states and their effects on memory remain elusive. We hypothesised that the FPN and DMN should distinguish between high- and low-curiosity conditions and be recruited more heavily for later remembered information associated with high-curiosity. Here, we used functional magnetic resonance imaging whilst participants completed a trivia paradigm, in which we presented trivia questions associated with high- and low-curiosity, followed by the associated answer. After a short delay, we tested memory for trivia answers. We adopted a network-based parcellation of the brain into subnetworks of the FPN and DMN to examine how neural activity within, and functional connectivity between, each subnetwork predicts curiosity-enhanced memory. Across elicitation and relief of curiosity, we found focal recruitment of FPNA and widespread recruitment of DMN subnetworks in support of curiosity and curiosity-enhanced memory. Most importantly, during the elicitation of curiosity, functional subcortical connectivity and across cortical networks, but not subcortical-cortical coupling, correlated with curiosity-enhanced memory. However, during the relief of curiosity, coupling between subcortical regions and DMNA emerged in support of curiosity-enhanced memory. Taken together, our results provide the first evidence about how neuromodulatory mechanisms via the hippocampal-dopaminergic circuit trigger states of curiosity and thereby communicate to higher-order cortical regions to facilitate curiosity-enhanced memory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significant statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Does neural activity within, and functional connectivity between, the dopaminergic-hippocampal network, fronto-parietal network (FPN), and default mode network (DMN) underpin curiosity states and their effects on memory? Here, we show how the dopaminergic system together with the hippocampus interact specifically with subnetwork DMNA potentially reflecting how subcortical regions support the enhancement of memory intergration of semantic information associated with curiosity. As DMNA (the core DMN subnetwork) was also functionally coupled with the whole DMN network and the semantic control network (FPNA), these findings provide a plausible neuromodulatory mechanism through which hippocampal-dopaminergic input triggers curiosity and then communicates to higher-order brain regions via DMNA to facilitate curiosity-enhanced memory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453739" rel="alternate" title="Connectivity between the hippocampus and default mode network during the relief – but not elicitation – of curiosity supports curiosity-enhanced memory enhancements (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453271</id><title>Understanding associative false memories in aging using multivariate analyses (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.766481+00:00</updated><author><name>Nancy A. Dennis</name></author><author><name>Amy A. Overman</name></author><author><name>Catherine M. Carpenter</name></author><author><name>Courtney R. Gerver</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Associative memory declines in aging arise, in part, from age-related increases in false memories to recombined lures. Studies have shown that there is a benefit to associative memory if the configural context of associative pairs is maintained from encoding to retrieval. The current study aimed to examine whether this benefit of contextual congruency is reduced in aging, and whether the neural similarity of memory representations between targets and lures underlies age- related increases in false memories. Behaviorally, both age groups benefited from target pairs presented in a visual format that was congruent with how the pair was learned. While no age difference was observed in hits, the typical age-related increase in false alarms was found. Congruent with behavioral results, neither the relationship between target-related patterns of neural activity across memory phases (as measured by ERS) nor the discriminability of target classification as a function of condition at retrieval (as measured by MVPA). However, with regard to false memories, older adults exhibited overall lower pattern similarity for hits and FAs compared to hits and CRs (as measured by RSA). Additionally, Hit-FA RSA correlated with age- related increases in associative FAs across visual, frontal, and parietal cortices. Results suggest that while neural processes supporting associative memory retrieval are dependent on configural congruency between encoding and retrieval, there is no difference as to how congruency affects these processes in aging. Additionally, similarity of target and lure processing may reflect reduced diagnosticity of information processing in aging.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453271" rel="alternate" title="Understanding associative false memories in aging using multivariate analyses (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453649</id><title>Important Docking study of Structure of Plasmodium falciparum thioredoxin reductase-thioredoxin complex: the case of potent drug Telatinib, a small molecule angiogenesis inhibitor (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.766635+00:00</updated><author><name>Ivan Vito Ferrari</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the last decades, malaria parasites have been rapidly developing resistance against antimalarial drugs, which underlines the need for novel drug targets. Thioredoxin reductase (TrxR) is crucially involved in redox homeostasis and essential for Plasmodium falciparum. In this communication, we report first time important Docking study by in Silico approach, using AutoDock Vina. After a selective analysis of over 300 drugs, processed with Pyrx (a Virtual Screening software into the active site of protein (ID PDB 4J56 Thioredoxin reductase 2 Chain A), we noticed excellent value of Binding Energy of Telatinib estimated by Pyrx software. These results are comparable to the crystallized ligand FAD (FLAVIN-ADENINE DINUCLEOTIDE) completed in the above-mentioned protein. Indeed, from the results of Autodock Vina, Telatinib an inhibitor of tyrosine kinases, has excellent a Binding affinity value, ca. −12 kcal/mol.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453649" rel="alternate" title="Important Docking study of Structure of Plasmodium falciparum thioredoxin reductase-thioredoxin complex: the case of potent drug Telatinib, a small molecule angiogenesis inhibitor (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453750</id><title>EMDA: A Python package for Electron Microscopy Data Analysis (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.766772+00:00</updated><author><name>Rangana Warshamanage</name></author><author><name>Keitaro Yamashita</name></author><author><name>Garib N. Murshudov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;An open-source Python library EMDA for cryo-EM map and model manipulation is presented with a specific focus on validation. The architecture of the library and its programmable and command-line interfaces are presented. The use of several functionalities in the library is presented through several examples. The utility of local correlation as a metric for identifying model errors and unmodeled regions in maps, and how it is used as a metric of map-model validation is demonstrated. The mapping of local correlation to individual atoms, and its use to draw insights on local signal variations are discussed. EMDA’s likelihood-based map overlay is demonstrated by carrying out a superposition of two domains in two related structures. The overlay is carried out globally to bring both maps into the same coordinate frame and then locally to estimate the relative movement of domains. Finally, the map magnification refinement in EMDA is presented with an example to highlight the importance of correcting map magnification in structural comparison studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453750" rel="alternate" title="EMDA: A Python package for Electron Microscopy Data Analysis (7 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.453456</id><title>Fast transcriptional activation of developmental signalling pathways during wound healing of the calcareous sponge Sycon ciliatum (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.766919+00:00</updated><author><name>Cüneyt Caglar</name></author><author><name>Alexander Ereskovsky</name></author><author><name>Mary Laplante</name></author><author><name>Daria Tokina</name></author><author><name>Sven Leininger</name></author><author><name>Ilya Borisenko</name></author><author><name>Genevieve Aisbett</name></author><author><name>Di Pan</name></author><author><name>Marcin Adamski</name></author><author><name>Maja Adamska</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ability to regenerate lost or damaged body parts is an ancient animal characteristic with a wide yet variable distribution across all phyla. Sponges, likely the sister group to all other animals, have remarkable regenerative abilities including whole body regeneration and re-development from dissociated cells. The calcareous sponge &lt;italic&gt;Sycon ciliatum&lt;/italic&gt; has been subject to various regeneration studies since the beginning of the last century. However, the early steps of wound healing of &lt;italic&gt;S. ciliatum&lt;/italic&gt; have not been addressed from the molecular perspective.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this study, we combined electron microscopy with gene expression analysis to investigate wound healing after transverse sectioning of &lt;italic&gt;S. ciliatum&lt;/italic&gt;. Microscopic analysis revealed massive transdifferentiation and collective migration behaviour of choanocytes and pinacocytes early upon injury (6-12h) as the main mechanisms for quick closure of the wound surface. RNA-sequencing identified upregulation of components of the conserved metazoan Wnt and TGFβ signalling pathways within 3h, preceding morphologically detectable wound healing events. De novo upregulation after a decline in expression coincides with morphologically visible polarity establishment. Moreover, by integrating the new wound healing data set with previously published data derived from intact sponge, we demonstrate similarity between gene activity during early wound healing and osculum maintenance. Whole mount &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; hybridisation of the TGFβ signalling pathway ligand SciTGFβU and signal transducer SciSmadRa show that the early activation of both is initially encompassing a large area surrounding the cut surface with gradual restriction to the edge of the forming regenerative membrane as wound healing progresses. While SciTGFβU transcripts are localised to exo- and endopinacocytes, SciSmadRa expression appears across all cell types. Using an EdU cell proliferation assay, we found that a global increase in cell proliferation is not visible before 12h into wound healing. Hence, the initial stages to cover the injury site including cell transdifferentiation and migration seem to be executed by cells remaining after injury. Gene expression clustering coupled with GO term enrichment analysis confirmed that expression of genes involved in processes related to cell proliferation, DNA repair as well as apoptotic processes at 3 and 6h of wound healing was not upregulated. On the other hand, genes associated with positive regulation of transcription, signal transduction, actin filament and chromatin organisation, as well as the Wnt signalling pathway are upregulated at early wound healing stages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have analysed wound healing in the calcareous sponge &lt;italic&gt;Sycon ciliatum&lt;/italic&gt; using microscopic and genomic methods. This study highlights a remarkable mechanism of interplay between cell transdifferentiation and collective migration we hypothesise to be regulated by conserved metazoan developmental pathways and numerous taxonomically restricted genes. Expression of these genes in regenerating and intact sponges sheds light on the long-standing question whether embryonic developmental pathways are redeployed in regeneration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.453456" rel="alternate" title="Fast transcriptional activation of developmental signalling pathways during wound healing of the calcareous sponge Sycon ciliatum (7 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453293</id><title>Age- and sex-related topological organisation of human brain functional networks and their relationship to cognition (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.767111+00:00</updated><author><name>Heidi Foo</name></author><author><name>Anbupalam Thalamuthu</name></author><author><name>Jiyang Jiang</name></author><author><name>Forrest Koch</name></author><author><name>Karen A. Mather</name></author><author><name>Wei Wen</name></author><author><name>Perminder S. Sachdev</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Age and sex associated with changes in functional brain network topology and cognition in large population of older adults have been poorly understood. We explored this question further by examining differences in 11 resting-state graph theory measures with respect to age, sex, and their relationships with cognitive performance in 17,127 UK Biobank participants (mean=62.83±7.41 years).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;METHODS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Brain connectivity toolbox was used to derive the graph theory measures that assessed network integration, segregation, and strength. Multiple linear regression was performed the relationship between age, sex, cognition, and network measures. Subsequently, multivariate analysis was done to further examine the joint effect of the network measures on cognitive functions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;RESULTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Age was associated with an overall decrease in the effectiveness of network communication (i.e. integration) and loss of functional specialisation (i.e. segregation) of specific brain regions. Sex differences were also observed, with women showing more efficient networks which were less segregated than in men (FDR adjusted &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt;&amp;lt;.05). Age-related changes were also more apparent in men than women, which suggests that men may be more vulnerable to cognitive decline with age. Interestingly, while network segregation and strength of limbic network were only nominally associated with cognitive performance, the network measures collectively were significantly associated with cognition (FDR adjusted &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt;≤.002). This may imply that individual measures may be inadequate to capture much of the variance in neural activity or its output and need further refinement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The complexity of the functional brain organisation may be shaped by an individual’s age and sex, which ultimately may influence cognitive performance of older adults. Age and sex stratification may be used to inform clinical neuroscience research to identify older adults at risk of cognitive dysfunction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453293" rel="alternate" title="Age- and sex-related topological organisation of human brain functional networks and their relationship to cognition (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453533</id><title>Decoding the Neural Signatures of Valence and Arousal From Portable EEG Headset (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.767284+00:00</updated><author><name>Nikhil Garg</name></author><author><name>Rohit Garg</name></author><author><name>NS Parrivesh</name></author><author><name>Apoorv Anand</name></author><author><name>V.A.S. Abhinav</name></author><author><name>Veeky Baths</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This paper focuses on classifying emotions on the valence-arousal plane using various feature extraction, feature selection and machine learning techniques. Emotion classification using EEG data and machine learning techniques has been on the rise in the recent past. We evaluate different feature extraction techniques, feature selection techniques and propose the optimal set of features and electrodes for emotion recognition. The images from the OASIS image dataset were used for eliciting the valence and arousal emotions, and the EEG data was recorded using the Emotiv Epoc X mobile EEG headset. The analysis is additionally carried out on publicly available datasets: DEAP and DREAMER. We propose a novel feature ranking technique and incremental learning approach to analyze the dependence of performance on the number of participants. Leave-one-subject-out cross-validation was carried out to identify subject bias in emotion elicitation patterns. The importance of different electrode locations was calculated, which could be used for designing a headset for emotion recognition. Our study achieved root mean square errors (RMSE) of less than 0.75 on DREAMER, 1.76 on DEAP, and 2.39 on our dataset.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453533" rel="alternate" title="Decoding the Neural Signatures of Valence and Arousal From Portable EEG Headset (6 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453650</id><title>A network-based approach reveals the dysregulated transcriptional regulation in non-alcohol fatty liver disease (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.767449+00:00</updated><author><name>Hong Yang</name></author><author><name>Muhammad Arif</name></author><author><name>Meng Yuan</name></author><author><name>Xiangyu Li</name></author><author><name>Ko Eun Shong</name></author><author><name>Hasan Turkez</name></author><author><name>Jens Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Mathias Uhlén</name></author><author><name>Jan Borén</name></author><author><name>Zhang Cheng</name></author><author><name>Adil Mardinoglu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Non-alcohol-related fatty liver disease (NAFLD) is a leading cause of chronic liver disease worldwide. We performed network analysis to investigate the dysregulated biological processes in the disease progression and revealed the molecular mechanism underlying NAFLD. Based on network analysis, we identified a highly conserved disease-associated gene module across three different NAFLD cohorts and highlighted the predominant role of key transcriptional regulators associated with lipid and cholesterol metabolism. In addition, we revealed the detailed metabolic differences between heterogenous NAFLD patients through integrative systems analysis of transcriptomic data and liver-specific genome-scale metabolic model. Furthermore, we identified transcription factors (TFs), including SREBF2, HNF4A, SREBF1, YY1 and KLF13, showing regulation of hepatic expression of genes in the NAFLD-associated modules and validated the TFs using data generated from a mouse NAFLD model. In conclusion, our integrative analysis facilitated our understanding of the regulatory mechanism of these perturbed TFs and associated biological processes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453650" rel="alternate" title="A network-based approach reveals the dysregulated transcriptional regulation in non-alcohol fatty liver disease (6 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.21260947</id><title>Prospective validation of host transcriptomic biomarkers for pulmonary tuberculosis by real-time PCR (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.767647+00:00</updated><author><name>Simon C Mendelsohn</name></author><author><name>Stanley Kimbung Mbandi</name></author><author><name>Andrew Fiore-Gartland</name></author><author><name>Adam Penn-Nicholson</name></author><author><name>Munyaradzi Musvosvi</name></author><author><name>Humphrey Mulenga</name></author><author><name>Michelle Fisher</name></author><author><name>Katie Hadley</name></author><author><name>Mzwandile Erasmus</name></author><author><name>Onke Nombida</name></author><author><name>Michele Tameris</name></author><author><name>Gerhard Walzl</name></author><author><name>Kogielium Naidoo</name></author><author><name>Gavin Chruchyard</name></author><author><name>Mark Hatherill</name></author><author><name>Thomas Scriba</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We tested performance of host-blood transcriptomic tuberculosis (TB) signatures for active case-finding. Among 20,207 HIV-uninfected and 963 HIV-infected adults screened; 2,923 and 861 were enrolled from five South African communities. Eight signatures were measured by microfluidic RT-qPCR and participants were microbiologically-investigated for pulmonary TB at baseline, and actively surveilled for incident disease through 15 months. Diagnostic AUCs for 61 HIV-uninfected (weighted-prevalence 1.1%) and 10 HIV-infected (prevalence 1.2%) prevalent TB cases for the 8 signatures were 0.63-0.79 and 0.65-0.88, respectively. Thereafter, 24 HIV-uninfected and 9 HIV-infected participants progressed to incident TB (1.1 and 1.0 per 100 person-years, respectively). Prognostic AUCs through 15-months follow-up were 0.49-0.66 and 0.54-0.81, respectively. Prognostic performance for incident TB occurring within 6-12 months in HIV-negative participants was higher for all signatures. None of the signatures met WHO Target Product Profile criteria for a triage test to diagnose asymptomatic TB; most signatures met the criteria for symptomatic TB. Prognostic accuracy of most signatures for incident TB within six months of testing met the criteria for an incipient TB test.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.21260947" rel="alternate" title="Prospective validation of host transcriptomic biomarkers for pulmonary tuberculosis by real-time PCR (6 tweets)"/><category term="Respiratory Medicine"/><published>2021-07-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453736</id><title>Towards an integrative multi-omics workflow (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.767868+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Jeanneret</name></author><author><name>Stéphane Gazut</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The advent of high-throughput techniques has greatly enhanced biological discovery. Last years, analysis of multi-omics data has taken the front seat to improve physiological understanding. Handling functional enrichment results from various biological data raises practical questions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We propose an integrative workflow to better interpret biological process insights in a multi-omics approach applied to breast cancer data from The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) related to Invasive Ductal Carcinoma (IDC) and Invasive Lobular Carcinoma (ILC). Pathway enrichment by Over Representation Analysis (ORA) and Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (GSEA) has been conducted with both features information from differential expression analysis or selected features from multi-block sPLS-DA methods. Then, comprehensive comparisons of enrichment results have been carried out by looking at classical enrichment analysis, probabilities pooling by Stouffer’s Z scores method and pathways clustering in biological themes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our work shows that ORA enrichment with selected sPLS-DA features and pathways probabilities pooling by Stouffer’s method lead to enrichment maps highly associated to physiological knowledge of IDC or ILC phenotypes, better than ORA and GSEA with differential expression driven features.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453736" rel="alternate" title="Towards an integrative multi-omics workflow (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.28.454213</id><title>Mitochondria dysfunction in Charcot Marie Tooth 2B Peripheral Sensory Neuropathy (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.768012+00:00</updated><author><name>Yingli Gu</name></author><author><name>Flora Guerra</name></author><author><name>Mingzheng Hu</name></author><author><name>Alexander Pope</name></author><author><name>Kijung Sung</name></author><author><name>Wanlin Yang</name></author><author><name>Simone Jetha</name></author><author><name>Thomas A. Shoff</name></author><author><name>Tessanya Gunatilake</name></author><author><name>Owen Dahlkamp</name></author><author><name>Linda Zhixia Shi</name></author><author><name>Fiore Manganelli</name></author><author><name>Maria Nolano</name></author><author><name>Yue Zhou</name></author><author><name>Jianqing Ding</name></author><author><name>Cecilia Bucci</name></author><author><name>Chengbiao Wu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent evidence has uncovered an important role of Rab7 in regulating mitochondrial morphology and function. Missense mutation(s) of Rab7 underlies the pathogenesis of Charcot Marie Tooth 2B (CMT2B) peripheral neuropathy. Herein, we investigated how mitochondrial morphology and function were impacted by the CMT2B associated Rab7V162M mutation in fibroblasts from human CMT2B patients as well as in a knockin mouse model. In contrast to recently published results from studies of using heterologous overexpression systems, our results have demonstrated significant mitochondrial fragmentation in fibroblasts of both human CMT2B patients and CMT2B mouse embryonic fibroblasts (MEFs). Furthermore, we have shown that mitochondria were fragmented and axonal mitochondrial movement was dysregulated in primary cultured E18 dorsal root ganglion (DRG) sensory neurons, but not in E18 hippocampal and cortical primary neurons. We also show that inhibitors to either the mitochondrial fission protein Drp1 or to the nucleotide binding to Rab7 normalized the mitochondrial deficits in both MEFs and E18 cultured DRG neurons. Our study has revealed, for the first time, that expression of CMT2B Rab7 mutation at physiological level enhances Drp1 activity to promote mitochondrial fission, that may potentially underlie selective vulnerability of peripheral sensory neurons in CMT2B pathogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.28.454213" rel="alternate" title="Mitochondria dysfunction in Charcot Marie Tooth 2B Peripheral Sensory Neuropathy (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453290</id><title>PCRMS: a database of predicted cis-regulatory modules and constituent transcription factor binding sites in genomes (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.768239+00:00</updated><author><name>Pengyu Ni</name></author><author><name>Zhengchang Su</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;More accurate and more complete predictions of &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-regulatory modules (CRMs) and constituent transcriptional factor (TF) binding sites (TFBSs) in genomes can facilitate characterizing functions of regulatory sequences. Here, we developed a database PCRMS (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cci-bioinfo.uncc.edu"&gt;https://cci-bioinfo.uncc.edu&lt;/ext-link&gt;) that stores highly accurate and unprecedentedly complete maps of predicted CRMs and TFBSs in the human and mouse genomes. The web interface allows the user to browse CRMs and TFBSs in an organism, find the closest CRMs to a gene, search CRMs around a gene, and find all TFBSs of a TF. PCRMS can be a useful resource for the research community to characterize regulatory genomes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453290" rel="alternate" title="PCRMS: a database of predicted cis-regulatory modules and constituent transcription factor binding sites in genomes (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453632</id><title>PTEN mutant NSCLC require ATM to suppress pro-apoptotic signalling and evade radiotherapy (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.768383+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas Fischer</name></author><author><name>Oliver Hartmann</name></author><author><name>Michaela Reissland</name></author><author><name>Cristian Prieto-Garcia</name></author><author><name>Kevin Klann</name></author><author><name>Christina Schülein-Völk</name></author><author><name>Bülent Polat</name></author><author><name>Elena Gerhard-Hartmann</name></author><author><name>Mathias Rosenfeldt</name></author><author><name>Christian Münch</name></author><author><name>Michael Flentje</name></author><author><name>Markus E. Diefenbacher</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite advances in treatment of patients with non-small cell lung cancer, carriers of certain genetic alterations are prone to failure. One such factor frequently mutated, is the tumor suppressor PTEN. These tumors are supposed to be more resistant to radiation, chemo- and immunotherapy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using CRISPR genome editing, we deleted PTEN in a human tracheal stem cell-like cell line as well generated primary murine NSCLC, proficient or deficient for &lt;italic&gt;Pten&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. These models were used to verify the impact of PTEN loss &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; by immunohistochemical staining, western blot and RNA-Sequencing. Radiation sensitivity was assessed by colony formation and growth assays. To elucidate putative treatment options, identified via the molecular characterisation, PTEN pro- and deficient cells were treated with PI3K/mTOR/DNA-PK-inhibitor PI-103 or the ATM-inhibitors KU-60019 und AZD 1390. Changes in radiation sensitivity were assessed by colony-formation assay, FACS, western-blot, phospho-proteomic mass spectrometry and &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; lung slice cultures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We demonstrate that loss of PTEN led to altered expression of transcriptional programs which directly regulate therapy resistance, resulting in establishment of radiation resistance. While PTEN-deficient tumor cells were not dependent on DNA-PK for IR resistance nor activated ATR during IR, they showed a significant dependence for the DNA damage kinase ATM. Pharmacologic inhibition of ATM, via KU-60019 and AZD1390 at non-toxic doses, restored and even synergized with IR in PTEN-deficient human and murine NSCLC cells as well in a multicellular organotypic &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; tumor model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;PTEN tumors are addicted to ATM to detect and repair radiation induced DNA damage. This creates an exploitable bottleneck. At least &lt;italic&gt;in cellulo&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; we show that low concentration of ATM inhibitor is able to synergise with IR to treat PTEN-deficient tumors in genetically well-defined IR resistant lung cancer models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453632" rel="alternate" title="PTEN mutant NSCLC require ATM to suppress pro-apoptotic signalling and evade radiotherapy (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.27.454001</id><title>Endorsement and Phylogenetic Analysis of some Fabaceae Plants based on DNA Barcoding gene MatK (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.768584+00:00</updated><author><name>Nader R. Abdelsalam</name></author><author><name>Mohamed E. Hasan</name></author><author><name>Samar M.A. Rabie</name></author><author><name>Houssam El-Din M.F. El-wakeel</name></author><author><name>Amera F. Zaitoun</name></author><author><name>Rehab Y. Ghareeb</name></author><author><name>Aly Z. Abdelsalam</name></author><author><name>Hesham M. Aly</name></author><author><name>Amira A. Ibrahim</name></author><author><name>Alaa A. Hemeida</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;DNA barcodes have been considered as a tool to facilitate species identification based on their simplicity and high-level accuracy compression to the complexity and subjective biases linked to morphological identification of taxa. MaturaseK gene “  MatK”  of the chloroplast is very crucial in the plant system which is involved in the group II intron splicing. The main objective of this current study is determining the relative utility of the “  MatK”  chloroplast gene for barcoding in fifteen legume trees by both single region and multiregional approaches. The chloroplast “  MatK”  gene sequences were submitted to GenBank and accession numbers (GenBank: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC602060"&gt;LC602060&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC602154"&gt;LC602154&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC602263"&gt;LC602263&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC603347"&gt;LC603347&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC603655"&gt;LC603655&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC603845"&gt;LC603845&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC603846"&gt;LC603846&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC603847"&gt;LC603847&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC604717"&gt;LC604717&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC604718"&gt;LC604718&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC605994"&gt;LC605994&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC604799"&gt;LC604799&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC605995"&gt;LC605995&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC606468"&gt;LC606468&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC606469"&gt;LC606469&lt;/ext-link&gt;) were obtained with sequence length ranging from 730 to 1545 nucleotides. These DNA sequences were aligned with database sequence using PROMALS server  ,  Clustal Omega server and Bioedit program. Also,  the maximum likelihood and neighbor-joining algorithms for phylogenetic reconstruction using the MEGA-X program were employed. Overall, these results indicated that  the phylogenetic tree  analysis and the evolutionary distances of an individual dataset of each species were agreed with a phylogenetic tree of all each other consisting of two clades, the first clade comprising  (Enterolobium contortisiliquum, Albizia lebbek), Acacia saligna  ,  Leucaena leucocephala,  Dichrostachys Cinerea, (Delonix regia, Parkinsonia aculeata), (Senna surattensis, Cassia fistula, Cassia javanica)  and  Schotia brachypetala  were more closely to each other, respectively. The remaining four species of  Erythrina humeana, (Sophora secundiflora, Dalbergia Sissoo, Tipuana Tipu)  constituted the second clade. Therefore,  MatK  gene is considered promising a candidate for DNA barcoding in plant family Fabaceae and providing a clear relationship between the families. Moreover, their sequences could be successfully utilized in single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) or part of the sequence as DNA fragment analysis utilizing polymerase chain reaction (PCR) in plant systematic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.27.454001" rel="alternate" title="Endorsement and Phylogenetic Analysis of some Fabaceae Plants based on DNA Barcoding gene MatK (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453582</id><title>Taxonomic repositioning of twelve Xanthomonas campestris, seven Xanthomonas axonopodis and one Pseudomonas cissicola reference pathovars to Xanthomonas citri (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.768775+00:00</updated><author><name>Kanika Bansal</name></author><author><name>Sanjeet Kumar</name></author><author><name>Prabhu B. Patil</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Here on the basis of phylo-taxonogenomics criteria we present amended description of 20 pathovars to &lt;italic&gt;Xanthomonas citri&lt;/italic&gt; majority (18/20) of which were first reported from India. 7/20 are currently classified as &lt;italic&gt;X. axonopodis&lt;/italic&gt;, 12/20 as &lt;italic&gt;X. campestris&lt;/italic&gt; and 1/20 as &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas cissicola&lt;/italic&gt;. Here, we have generated genome sequence data for 4 pathovars and genomes of remaining 16 were used from the published data. Genome based investigation reveals that all these pathovars belong to &lt;italic&gt;X. citri&lt;/italic&gt; and not to &lt;italic&gt;X. axonopodis&lt;/italic&gt; or &lt;italic&gt;X. campestris&lt;/italic&gt; as previously reported. Present proposal is to aid in resolving the taxonomic confusion of the &lt;italic&gt;X. ctiri&lt;/italic&gt; pathovars and prevent future usage of invalid names.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453582" rel="alternate" title="Taxonomic repositioning of twelve Xanthomonas campestris, seven Xanthomonas axonopodis and one Pseudomonas cissicola reference pathovars to Xanthomonas citri (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453552</id><title>Emotional states as distinct configurations of functional brain networks (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.768925+00:00</updated><author><name>Rotem Dan</name></author><author><name>Marta Weinstock</name></author><author><name>Gadi Goelman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The conceptualization of emotional states as patterns of interactions between large-scale brain networks has recently gained support. Yet, few studies have directly examined the brain’s network structure during emotional experiences. Here, we investigated the brain’s functional network organization during experiences of sadness, amusement, and neutral states elicited by movies, in addition to a resting-state. We tested the effects of the experienced emotion on individual variability in the brain’s functional connectome. Next, for each state, we defined a modular organization of the brain and quantified its segregation and integration. Our results show that emotional states increase the similarity between and within individuals in the brain’s functional connectome. Second, in the brain’s modular organization, sadness, relative to amusement, was associated with higher integration and increased connectivity of cognitive control networks: the salience and fronto-parietal networks. Modular metrics of brain segregation and integration were further associated with reported emotional valence. Last, in both the functional connectome and emotional report, a higher similarity was found among women. Our results suggest that the experience of emotion is linked to a reconfiguration of whole-brain distributed, not emotion-specific, functional brain networks and that the topological structure carries information about the subjective emotional experience.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453552" rel="alternate" title="Emotional states as distinct configurations of functional brain networks (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.27.453123</id><title>Electrophysiological measures of visual suppression (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.769070+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel H Baker</name></author><author><name>Greta Vilidaite</name></author><author><name>Alex R Wade</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the early visual system, suppression occurs between neurons representing different stimulus properties. This includes features such as orientation (cross-orientation suppression), eye-of-origin (interocular suppression) and spatial location (surround suppression), which are thought to involve distinct anatomical pathways. We asked if these separate routes to suppression can be differentiated by their pattern of gain control on the contrast response function measured in human participants using steady-state electroencephalography. Changes in contrast gain shift the contrast response function laterally, whereas changes in response gain scale the function vertically. We used a Bayesian hierarchical model to summarise the evidence for each type of gain control. A computational meta-analysis of 16 previous studies found the most evidence for contrast gain effects with overlaid masks, but no clear evidence favouring either response gain or contrast gain for other mask types. We then conducted two new experiments, comparing suppression from four mask types (monocular and dichoptic overlay masks, and aligned and orthogonal surround masks) on responses to sine wave grating patches flickering at 5Hz. At the occipital pole, there was strong evidence for contrast gain effects in all four mask types at the first harmonic frequency (5Hz). Suppression generally became stronger at more lateral electrode sites, but there was little evidence of response gain effects. At the second harmonic frequency (10Hz) suppression was stronger overall, and involved both contrast and response gain effects. Although suppression from different mask types involves distinct anatomical pathways, gain control processes appear to serve a common purpose, which we suggest might be to suppress less reliable inputs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.27.453123" rel="alternate" title="Electrophysiological measures of visual suppression (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453693</id><title>Hoslundia opposita and other Nigerian plants inhibit sickle hemoglobin polymerization and prevent erythrocyte sickling: a virtual screening-guided identification of bioactive plants. (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.769217+00:00</updated><author><name>Eric O. Olori</name></author><author><name>Olujide Oludayo Olubiyi</name></author><author><name>Chinedum Peace Babalola</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In sickle cell disease, a hereditary hemoglobinopathy, clinically observed disease presentations are the endpoint of a point mutation involving the substitution of glutamic acid with valine at the position 6 of the beta globin chain. With about 4.4 million people globally being affected, and another 43 million people bearing the sickle cell trait, several research efforts have been made to discover new and affordable treatment and possibly cure for the disease. Africa is endowed with a large flora population and traditional healers and citizens have over time depended on the use of herbs in folkloric medicine for different ailments including sickle cell disease (SCD). Such native knowledge has often formed the basis for different research exploration into the anti-sickling activities of selected African plants. These plants that have been so far investigated for their anti-sickling properties represent about 0.05 % of the 45,000 plant species enriching the flora landscape in Sub-Saharan Africa. Some of these have yielded potent anti-sickling profiles. In the current work we seek to achieve a more extensive search of the African plant diversity with anti-sickling properties: for this we have adopted a hybrid computational-cum-experimental protocol that employed computer-aided drug design (CADD) means for identifying plants with at least one constituent capable of interacting with the sickle hemoglobin, followed by extractive procedures and anti-sickling experiments for validating the predictions. Over two thousand (or 2,000) African natural products, representing over 200 plant species, were first virtually screened against the crystal structure of the dimerized human sickle hemoglobin. The natural products with the best computed sickle hemoglobin interaction energetics were found to belong to five plant species including Catharanthus roseus, Rauvolfia vomitoria, Hoslundia opposita, Lantana camara and Euphorbia hirta. The leaves of these plants were each collected subsequently and subjected to standard processing and extraction procedures. Using both HbSS polymerization inhibition and sickling reversal tests significant reductions in polymerization of erythrocyte hemolysate of the HbSS genotype were observed with the methanolic extracts of the plants, as well as sickling reversal levels of up to 68.50 % (H. opposita) was observed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453693" rel="alternate" title="Hoslundia opposita and other Nigerian plants inhibit sickle hemoglobin polymerization and prevent erythrocyte sickling: a virtual screening-guided identification of bioactive plants. (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453762</id><title>Effect of stimulation time on the expression of human macrophage polarization markers (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.769364+00:00</updated><author><name>Duygu Unuvar Purcu</name></author><author><name>Asli Korkmaz</name></author><author><name>Sinem Gunalp</name></author><author><name>Derya Goksu Helvaci</name></author><author><name>Yonca Erdal</name></author><author><name>Yavuz Dogan</name></author><author><name>Gerhard Wingender</name></author><author><name>Duygu Sag</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Macrophages are highly plastic cells that can polarize into functionally distinct subsets &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; in response to environmental signals. The development of protocols to model macrophage polarization &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; greatly contributes to our understanding of macrophage biology. Macrophages are divided into two main groups: Pro-inflammatory M1 macrophages (classically activated) and anti-inflammatory M2 macrophages (alternatively activated), based on several key surface markers and the production of inflammatory mediators. However, the expression of these common macrophage polarization markers is greatly affected by the stimulation time used. Unfortunately, there is no consensus yet regarding the optimal stimulation times for particular macrophage polarization markers in &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; experiments. This situation is problematic, (i) as analysing a particular marker at a suboptimal time point can lead to false-negative results, and (ii) as it clearly impedes the comparison of different studies. Using human monocyte-derived macrophages (MDMs) &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, we analysed how the expression of the main polarization markers for M1 (CD64, CD86, CXCL9, CXCL10, HLA-DR, IDO1, IL1β, IL12p70, TNF), M2a (CD200R, CD206, CCL17, CCL22, IL-10, TGM2), and M2c (CD163, IL-10, TGFβ) macrophages changes over time at mRNA and protein levels. Our data establish the most appropriate stimulation time for the analysis of the expression of human macrophage polarization markers &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. Providing such a reference guide will likely facilitate the investigation of macrophage polarization and its reproducibility.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453762" rel="alternate" title="Effect of stimulation time on the expression of human macrophage polarization markers (5 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.452189</id><title>The first crested duck genome reveals clues to genetic compensation and crest cushion formation (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.769812+00:00</updated><author><name>Guobin Chang</name></author><author><name>Xiaoya Yuan</name></author><author><name>Qixin Guo</name></author><author><name>Hao Bai</name></author><author><name>Xiaofang Cao</name></author><author><name>Meng Liu</name></author><author><name>Zhixiu Wang</name></author><author><name>Bichun Li</name></author><author><name>Shasha Wang</name></author><author><name>Yong Jiang</name></author><author><name>Zhiquan Wang</name></author><author><name>Yang Zhang</name></author><author><name>Qi Xu</name></author><author><name>Qianqian Song</name></author><author><name>Rui Pan</name></author><author><name>Shenghan Zheng</name></author><author><name>Lingling Qiu</name></author><author><name>Tiantian Gu</name></author><author><name>Xinsheng Wu</name></author><author><name>Yulin Bi</name></author><author><name>Zhengfeng Cao</name></author><author><name>Yu Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yang Chen</name></author><author><name>Hong Li</name></author><author><name>Jianfeng Liu</name></author><author><name>Wangcheng Dai</name></author><author><name>Guohong Chen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Chinese crested (CC) duck is a unique indigenous waterfowl breed with a phenotypic crest trait that affects its high survival rate. Therefore, the CC duck is an ideal model to investigate the genetic compensation response to maintain genetic stability. In the present study, we first generated a chromosome-level genome of CC ducks. Comparative genomics revealed genes related to tissue repair, immune function, and tumors were under strong positive selection, which suggested that these adaptive changes might enhance cancer resistance and immune response to maintain the genetic stability of CC ducks. We sub-assembled a Chinese spot-billed duck genome and detected genome-assembled structure variants among three ducks. Functional analysis revealed that a large number of structural variants were related to the immune system, which strongly suggests the occurrence of genetic compensation in the anti-tumor and immune systems to further support the survival of CC ducks. Moreover, we confirmed that the CC duck originated from the mallard ducks. Finally, we revealed the physiological and genetic basis of crest traits and identified a causative mutation in &lt;italic&gt;TAS2R40&lt;/italic&gt; that leads to crest formation. Overall, the findings of this study provide new insights into the role of genetic compensation in adaptive evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.452189" rel="alternate" title="The first crested duck genome reveals clues to genetic compensation and crest cushion formation (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.452934</id><title>Modelling time evolution of in blood alcohol concentration (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.770142+00:00</updated><author><name>Antoni Oliver Gelabert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A theoretical model based on mass conservation is proposed to predict blood alcohol concentration (BAC) over time. The proposed model takes as input the body parameters, the data timing for each drink, as well as his alcoholic strength and ingested amount. Three test cases with variations are presented and discussed. The results given are obtained by solving numerically the equation proposed. The solution predicts a well located alcohol peak and a reasonable time of alcohol body cleaning. This model represents a first order approach to a complex problem. Similar scenarios, like, for instance, drug concentrations can be modelled by using the same concept. The proposed model has been implemented on easy-to-use program COGORZA, which source code is available online at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/tonibois/Cogorza"&gt;https://github.com/tonibois/Cogorza&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.452934" rel="alternate" title="Modelling time evolution of in blood alcohol concentration (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453568</id><title>Global, Low Amplitude Cortical State Predicts Response Outcomes in a Selective Detection Task (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.770290+00:00</updated><author><name>Krista Marrero</name></author><author><name>Krithiga Aruljothi</name></author><author><name>Behzad Zareian</name></author><author><name>Chengchun Gao</name></author><author><name>Zhaoran Zhang</name></author><author><name>Edward Zagha</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spontaneous neuronal activity strongly impacts stimulus encoding and behavioral responses. We sought to determine the effects of neocortical prestimulus activity on stimulus detection. We trained mice in a selective whisker detection task, in which they learned to respond (lick) to target stimuli in one whisker field and ignore distractor stimuli in the contralateral whisker field. During expert task performance, we used widefield Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; imaging to assess prestimulus and post-stimulus neuronal activity broadly across frontal and parietal cortices. We found that lower prestimulus activity correlated with enhanced stimulus detection: lower prestimulus activity predicted response versus no response outcomes and faster reaction times. The activity predictive of trial outcome was distributed through dorsal neocortex, rather than being restricted to whisker or licking regions. Using principal component analysis, we demonstrate that response trials are associated with a distinct and less variable prestimulus neuronal subspace. For single units, prestimulus choice probability was weak yet distributed broadly, with lower than chance choice probability correlating with stronger sensory and motor encoding. These findings support a low amplitude, low variability, optimal prestimulus cortical state for stimulus detection that presents globally and predicts response outcomes for both target and distractor stimuli.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453568" rel="alternate" title="Global, Low Amplitude Cortical State Predicts Response Outcomes in a Selective Detection Task (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.27.453915</id><title>HyperChIP for identifying hypervariable signals across ChIP/ATAC-seq samples (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.770460+00:00</updated><author><name>Haojie Chen</name></author><author><name>Shiqi Tu</name></author><author><name>Chongze Yuan</name></author><author><name>Feng Tian</name></author><author><name>Yijing Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yihua Sun</name></author><author><name>Zhen Shao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;With the reduction in sequencing costs, studies become prevalent that profile the chromatin landscape for tens or even hundreds of human individuals by using ChIP/ATAC-seq techniques. Identifying genomic regions with hypervariable ChIP/ATAC-seq signals across given samples is essential for such studies. In particular, the hypervariable regions (HVRs) across tumors from different patients indicate their heterogeneity and can contribute to revealing potential cancer subtypes and the associated epigenetic markers. We present HyperChIP as the first complete statistical tool for the task. HyperChIP uses scaled variances that account for the mean-variance dependence to rank genomic regions, and it increases the statistical power by diminishing the influence of true HVRs on model fitting. Applying it to a large pan-cancer ATAC-seq data set, we found that the identified HVRs not only provided a solid basis to uncover the underlying similarity structure among the involved tumor samples, but also led to the identification of transcription factors pertaining to the similarity structure when coupled with a motif-scanning analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.27.453915" rel="alternate" title="HyperChIP for identifying hypervariable signals across ChIP/ATAC-seq samples (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453642</id><title>Molecular Learning of a Soft-Disks Fluid (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.770632+00:00</updated><author><name>Luca Zammataro</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This work is based on the Equivalence between Molecular Dynamics and Neural Network. It provides learning proofs in a Lennard-Jones (LJ) fluid, presented as a network of particles having non-bonded interactions. I describe the fluid’s learning as the property of an order that emerges as an adaptation in establishing equilibrium with energy and thermal conservation. The experimental section demonstrates the fluid can be trained with logic-gates patterns. The work goes beyond Molecular Computing’s application, explaining how this model uses its intrinsic minimizing properties in learning and predicting outputs. Finally, it gives hints for a theory on real chemistry’s computational universality.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453642" rel="alternate" title="Molecular Learning of a Soft-Disks Fluid (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.21260946</id><title>Association between prenatal alcohol exposure and children's facial shape. A prospective population-based cohort study (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.770766+00:00</updated><author><name>Xianjing Liu</name></author><author><name>Manfred Kayser</name></author><author><name>Steven A. Kushner</name></author><author><name>Henning Tiemeier</name></author><author><name>Fernando Rivadeneira</name></author><author><name>Vincent W. V. Jaddoe</name></author><author><name>Wiro Niessen</name></author><author><name>Eppo B. Wolvius</name></author><author><name>Gennady V. Roshchupkin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;IMPORTANCE: Children exposed to a high level of prenatal alcohol exposure (PAE) are more likely to develop fetal alcohol spectrum disorder with adverse phenotypes on their faces. However, it is still poorly understood, which level of PAE is associated with facial manifestation and if such associations persist during childhood. 
OBJECTIVE: To examine the association between PAE and children facial phenotype in a prospective multi-ethnic population-based study.
DESIGN, SETTING, AND PARTICIPANTS: This study was based on the Generation R Study, a prospective cohort from fetal life onwards with maternal and offspring data. Children had a 3D facial image taken at ages 9 (n=3160) and 13 years (n=2492). 
EXPOSURES: We defined 6 levels of PAE based on the frequency and dose of alcohol consumption, and defined three tiers based on the timing of alcohol exposure of the unborn child.
MAIN OUTCOMES AND MEASURES:  For image analysis, we used 3D graph convolutional networks for non-linear dimensionality reduction, which compressed the high-dimensional images into 200 endophenotypes representing facial morphology. These facial endophenotypes were used as dependent variables in a linear regression analysis to search for associations with PAE. Finally, to detect specific facial components associated with PAE, we mapped statistically significant endophenotypes back to the 3D facial shape. We generated heatmaps to display the facial changes associated with PAE. PAE prediction based on facial shape was also performed; the prediction accuracy was estimated by area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUC).
RESULTS: A significant association between PAE and facial shape was found in the 9-year-old children, at all levels of alcohol exposure: the higher the level of exposure, the stronger the association. Moreover, PAE before and during pregnancy was associated with facial shape. The most common detected facial phenotypes included turned-up nose tip, shortened nose, turned-out jaw and turned-in lower-eyelid-related regions. For the 13-year-old children, the associations were weaker and the AUCs lower than those of the 9-years-old children.
CONCLUSIONS AND RELEVANCE: PAE before and during pregnancy, even at low level, is associated with the facial shape of children, and these associations become weaker as children grow older.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.21260946" rel="alternate" title="Association between prenatal alcohol exposure and children's facial shape. A prospective population-based cohort study (4 tweets)"/><category term="Pediatrics"/><published>2021-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453662</id><title>Population colonization history influences behavioral responses of European starlings in personality tests (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.770949+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexandra Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Martine Hausberger</name></author><author><name>Patricia Le Quilliec</name></author><author><name>Philippe Clergeau</name></author><author><name>Laurence Henry</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To understand the processes involved in biological invasions, the genetic, morphological, physiological and behavioral characteristics of invasive populations need to be understood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many invasive species have been reported to be flying species. In birds, both invaders and migrants encounter novel situations, therefore one could expect that both groups might react similarly to novelty.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we analyzed the behavioral responses of individuals from three populations of European starling &lt;italic&gt;Sturnus vulgaris&lt;/italic&gt;: a population settled for centuries in a rural region, a population that recently colonized an urban area, and a population of winter migrant birds. We conducted a social isolation test, a novel environment test, a novel food test and a novel object test to explore their reactions towards novelty. We identified and characterized different behavioral profiles for each test.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The group of migratory adults appeared to be less anxious in social isolation than the group of urban young. Urban and migrant groups entered the novel environment sooner than rural birds. Shy, bold and intermediate individuals were observed in all three groups when presented with novel food. Finally, the proportion of shy individuals which did not touch the novel object was higher than the proportion of bold individuals in the rural group. Our study emphasizes that neophilia or boldness present in migrant and invasive populations may facilitate the occupation of novel habitats. Our analysis also suggests that mixed reactions of neophobia ensure behavioral flexibility in a gregarious invasive species.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significant statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we show that an invasive species like European starling, &lt;italic&gt;Sturnus vulgaris&lt;/italic&gt;, presents an important flexibility in neophobia and in reaction towards social isolation. These variations depend on the settlement history of populationseven when the birds had been wild-caught as nestlings and hand-raised in standard conditions. This is significant because it highlights possible scenarios of colonization processes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We believe that this manuscript is appropriate for publication by Behavioral Ecology and Sociobiology because it places individuals’ behavior in the core mechanisms of an ecological phenomenom as biological invasions. Our manuscript enlarges the paradigms related to the ways of coping with novelty in animals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This manuscript has not been published and is not under consideration for publication elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453662" rel="alternate" title="Population colonization history influences behavioral responses of European starlings in personality tests (4 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453685</id><title>SegmA: Residue Segmentation of cryo-EM density maps (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.771650+00:00</updated><author><name>Mark Rozanov</name></author><author><name>Haim J. Wolfson</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cryo-EM resolution revolution enables the development of algorithms for direct de-novo modelling of protein structures from given cryo-EM density maps. Deep Learning tools have been applied to locate structure patterns, such as rotamers, secondary structures and C&lt;italic&gt;α&lt;/italic&gt; atoms. We present a deep neural network (nicknamed SegmA) for the residue type segmentation of a cryo-EM density map. The network labels voxels in a cryo-EM map by the residue type (amino acid type or nucleic acid) of the sampled macromolecular structure. It also provides a visual representation of the density map by coloring the different types of voxels by their assgned colors. SegmA’s algorithm combines a rotation equivariant group convolutional network with a traditional U-net network in a cascade. In addition SegmA estimates the labeling accuracy and reports only labels assigned with high confidence. At resolution of 3&lt;italic&gt;Å&lt;/italic&gt; SegmAs accuracy is 80% for nucleotides. Amino acids which can be seen by eye, such as LEU, ARG and PHE, are detected by Segma with about 70% accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A web server of the application is under development at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dev.dcsh7cbr3o89e.amplifyapp.com"&gt;https://dev.dcsh7cbr3o89e.amplifyapp.com&lt;/ext-link&gt;. The SegmA open code is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Mark-Rozanov/SegmA_3A/tree/master"&gt;https://github.com/Mark-Rozanov/SegmA_3A/tree/master&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453685" rel="alternate" title="SegmA: Residue Segmentation of cryo-EM density maps (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453636</id><title>IRI-CCE: A Platform for Evaluating CRISPR-based Genome Editing Tools and Its Components (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.772049+00:00</updated><author><name>Rahul Mahadev Shelake</name></author><author><name>Dibyajyoti Pramanik</name></author><author><name>Jae-Yean Kim</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Rapid assessment of Clustered Regularly Interspaced Short Palindromic Repeats (CRISPR)-based tools and validation of cloned CRISPR-plasmid vectors are critical aspects for the successful application of genome editing (GE) in different organisms, including plants. Also, the selection of active guide RNAs (gRNAs) is a determining factor to achieve efficient GE at the targeted locus. Incidentally, plasmid vectors capable of ectopic expression of Cas enzyme and sgRNAs in bacteria will facilitate the quick screening and reliability of cloned plasmids and the functionality of designed gRNAs. We report a platform for in vivo rapid investigation of CRISPR components in &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; (IRI-CCE), which is compatible with plant-transforming binary vectors comprising plant promoters/terminators. Besides, IRI-CCE analyses reveal distinct features of cytidine (PmCDA1, evoCDA1, APOBEC3A) and adenine (ABE8e) base editors. Finally, we show the IRI-CCE platform as a reliable and rapid method for screening functional gRNAs to achieve successful GE outcomes. Base editor-based CRISPR components expressed by promoters of different strengths led to the establishment of IRI-CCE platform for three major applications: optimization of novel CRISPR tools, validation of cloned CRISPR plasmids, and to know gRNA functionality.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453636" rel="alternate" title="IRI-CCE: A Platform for Evaluating CRISPR-based Genome Editing Tools and Its Components (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453664</id><title>Habituation, task solving and memorization may facilitate biological invasions: the Starling example (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.772384+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexandra Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Martine Hausberger</name></author><author><name>Philippe Clergeau</name></author><author><name>Laurence Henry</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Invasions ecology deals more and more with behavioural characteristics of invasive species. Particularly, research have focused on the personality of invaders and on their way of coping with novelty in new habitats. Traits of neophobia may limit individuals in their exploration of novel objects or the consumption of novel foods, they may stop the access to valuable ressources. Actually, in novel environments like cities, food can be unreachable in throwaway dishes with lids or hidden in the garbage or even close to frightening objects. Animals may either left the place and waste these resources, or they can express low neophobia from the beginning and manipulate the objects to reach food. They may also habituate progressively to the context and use the ressources.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we analyzed the behavioural responses of individuals from three populations of European starling &lt;italic&gt;Sturnus vulgaris&lt;/italic&gt;: a population anciently settled in a rural region, a population that has recently colonized a urban area and a population of wintering migrant birds.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used a series of tests in order to explore if individuals would habituate to a novel object and if they could remember it eight months later. We explored if individuals would be less neophobic when confronted to two novel objects successively and we tested them in a learning task involving a novel object and an attractive food. Our results show that &lt;italic&gt;Sturnus vulgaris&lt;/italic&gt; habituates rapidly to novel objects and that categorization facilitates neophobia lost when confronted to two different novel objects. Initially young birds appeared to be more skilled than adults in the learning task. Individuals from this species seem to be able to remember an object durably. We suggest that habituation, task solving and memorization are three mechanisms enhancing biological invasions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453664" rel="alternate" title="Habituation, task solving and memorization may facilitate biological invasions: the Starling example (3 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453821</id><title>PEGR: a flexible management platform for reproducible epigenomic and genomic research (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.772571+00:00</updated><author><name>Danying Shao</name></author><author><name>Gretta D. Kellogg</name></author><author><name>Ali Nematbakhsh</name></author><author><name>Prashant Kuntala</name></author><author><name>Shaun Mahony</name></author><author><name>B. Franklin Pugh</name></author><author><name>William KM Lai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Reproducibility is a significant challenge in (epi)genomic research due to the complexity of experiments composed of traditional biochemistry and informatics. Recent advances have exacerbated this challenge as high-throughput sequencing data is generated at an unprecedented pace. Here we report on our development of a &lt;underline&gt;P&lt;/underline&gt;latform for &lt;underline&gt;E&lt;/underline&gt;pi-&lt;underline&gt;G&lt;/underline&gt;enomic &lt;underline&gt;R&lt;/underline&gt;esearch (PEGR), a web-based project management platform that tracks and quality controls experiments from conception to publication-ready figures, compatible with multiple assays and bioinformatic pipelines. It supports rigor and reproducibility for biochemists working at the wet bench, while continuing to fully support reproducibility and reliability for bioinformaticians through integration with the Galaxy platform.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453821" rel="alternate" title="PEGR: a flexible management platform for reproducible epigenomic and genomic research (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453858</id><title>Crosstalk with keratinocytes causes GNAQ oncogene specificity in melanoma (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.772753+00:00</updated><author><name>Oscar Urtatiz</name></author><author><name>Amanda Haage</name></author><author><name>Guy Tanentzapf</name></author><author><name>Catherine D. Van Raamsdonk</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Different melanoma subtypes exhibit specific and non-overlapping sets of oncogene and tumor suppressor mutations, despite a common cell of origin in melanocytes. For example, activation of the Gα&lt;sub&gt;q/11&lt;/sub&gt; signaling pathway is a characteristic initiating event in primary melanomas that arise in the dermis, uveal tract or central nervous system. It is rare in melanomas arising in the epidermis. Here, we present evidence that in the mouse, crosstalk with the epidermal microenvironment actively impairs the survival of melanocytes expressing the GNAQ&lt;sup&gt;Q209L&lt;/sup&gt; oncogene, providing a new model for oncogene specificity in cancer. The presence of epidermal cells inhibited cell division and fragmented dendrites of melanocytes expressing GNAQ&lt;sup&gt;Q209L&lt;/sup&gt; in culture, while they promoted the growth of normal melanocytes. Differential gene expression analysis of FACS sorted epidermal melanocytes showed that cells expressing GNAQ&lt;sup&gt;Q209L&lt;/sup&gt; exhibit an oxidative stress and apoptosis signature previously linked to vitiligo. Furthermore, PLCB4, the direct downstream effector of Gα&lt;sub&gt;q/11&lt;/sub&gt; signaling, is frequently mutated in cutaneous melanoma alongside P53 and NF1. Our results suggest that a deficiency of PLCB4 promotes cutaneous melanomagenesis by reducing GNAQ driven signaling. Hence, our studies reveal the flip side of the GNAQ/PLCB4 signaling pathway, which was hitherto unsuspected. In the future, understanding how epidermal crosstalk restrains the GNAQ&lt;sup&gt;Q209L&lt;/sup&gt; oncogene could suggest novel melanoma therapies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453858" rel="alternate" title="Crosstalk with keratinocytes causes GNAQ oncogene specificity in melanoma (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453903</id><title>3D Convolutional Neural Networks for Classification of Alzheimer's and Parkinson's Disease with T1-Weighted Brain MRI (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.772910+00:00</updated><author><name>Nikhil J. Dhinagar</name></author><author><name>Sophia I. Thomopoulos</name></author><author><name>Conor Owens-Walton</name></author><author><name>Dimitris Stripelis</name></author><author><name>Jose-Luis Ambite</name></author><author><name>Greg Ver Steeg</name></author><author><name>Daniel Weintraub</name></author><author><name>Philip Cook</name></author><author><name>Corey McMillan</name></author><author><name>Paul M. Thompson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Parkinson's disease (PD) and Alzheimer's disease (AD) are progressive neurodegenerative disorders that affect millions of people worldwide. In this work, we propose a deep learning approach to classify these diseases based on 3D T1-weighted brain MRI. We analyzed several datasets including the Parkinson's Progression Markers Initiative (PPMI), an independent dataset from the University of Pennsylvania School of Medicine (UPenn), the Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging Initiative (ADNI), and the Open Access Series of Imaging Studies (OASIS) dataset. PPMI and ADNI were partitioned to train (70%), validate (20%), and test (10%) a 3D convolutional neural network (CNN) for PD and AD classification. The UPenn and OASIS datasets were used as independent test sets to evaluate the model performance during inference. We also implemented a random forest classifier as a baseline model by extracting key radiomics features from the same T1-weighted MRI scans. The proposed 3D CNN model was trained from scratch for the classification tasks. For AD classification, the 3D CNN model achieved an ROC-AUC of 0.878 on the ADNI test set and an average ROC-AUC of 0.789 on the OASIS dataset. For PD classification, the proposed 3D CNN model achieved an ROC-AUC of 0.667 on the PPMI test set and an average ROC-AUC of 0.743 on the UPenn dataset. We also found that model performance was largely maintained when using only 25% of the training dataset. The 3D CNN outperformed the random forest classifier for both the PD and AD tasks. The 3D CNN also generalized better on unseen MRI data from different imaging centers. Our results show that the proposed 3D CNN model was less prone to overfitting for AD than for PD classification. This approach shows promise for screening of PD and AD patients using only T1-weighted brain MRI, which is relatively widely available. This model with additional validation could also be used to help differentiate between challenging cases of AD and PD when they present with similarly subtle motor and non-motor symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453903" rel="alternate" title="3D Convolutional Neural Networks for Classification of Alzheimer's and Parkinson's Disease with T1-Weighted Brain MRI (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453696</id><title>Artificial Intelligence Resolves Kinetic Pathways of Magnesium Binding to RNA (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.773104+00:00</updated><author><name>Jan Neumann</name></author><author><name>Nadine Schwierz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Magnesium is an indispensable cofactor in countless vital processes. In order to understand its functional role, the characterization of the binding pathways to biomolecules such as RNA is crucial. Despite the importance, a molecular description is still lacking since the transition from the water-mediated outer-sphere to the direct inner-sphere conformation is on the millisecond timescale and therefore out of reach for conventional simulation techniques. To fill this gap, we use transition path sampling to resolve the binding pathways and to elucidate the role of the solvent in the reaction. The results reveal that the molecular void provoked by the leaving phosphate oxygen of the RNA is immediately filled by an entering water molecule. In addition, water molecules from the first and second hydration shell couple to the concerted exchange. To capture the intimate solute-solvent coupling, we perform a committor analysis as basis for a machine learning algorithm that derives the optimal deep learning model from thousands of scanned architectures using hyperparameter tuning. The results reveal that the properly optimized deep network architecture recognizes the important solvent structures, extracts the relevant information and predicts the commitment probability with high accuracy. Our results provide a quantitative description of solute-solvent coupling which is ubiquitous for kosmotropic ions and governs a large variety of biochemical reactions in aqueous solutions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453696" rel="alternate" title="Artificial Intelligence Resolves Kinetic Pathways of Magnesium Binding to RNA (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453697</id><title>Specialized subsets of innate-like T cells and dendritic cells protect from lethal pneumococcal infection in the lung (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.773247+00:00</updated><author><name>Mallory Paynich Murray</name></author><author><name>Catherine M. Crosby</name></author><author><name>Paola Marcovecchio</name></author><author><name>Nadine Hartmann</name></author><author><name>Shilpi Chandra</name></author><author><name>Meng Zhao</name></author><author><name>Archana Khurana</name></author><author><name>Sonja P. Zahner</name></author><author><name>Björn E. Clausen</name></author><author><name>Fadie T. Coleman</name></author><author><name>Joseph P. Mizgerd</name></author><author><name>Zbigniew Mikulski</name></author><author><name>Mitchell Kronenberg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Innate-like T cells, including invariant natural killer T (iNKT) cells, mucosal-associated invariant T (MAIT) cells and γδ T cells, are present in various barrier tissues, including the lung. They carry out protective responses during infections, but the mechanisms for protection are not completely understood. Here, we investigated their roles during pulmonary infection with &lt;italic&gt;Streptococcus pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt;. Following infection, innate-like T cells rapidly increased in lung tissue, in part through recruitment, but TCR activation and cytokine production occurred mostly in IL-17-producing NKT17 and γδ T cells. NKT17 cells were preferentially located outside the vasculature prior to infection, as were CD103&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; dendritic cells (cDC1), which were important both for antigen presentation to NKT17 cells and γδ T cell activation. Whereas IL-17A-producing γδ T cells also were numerous, GM-CSF was exclusive to NKT17 cells and contributed to iNKT cell-mediated protection. These studies demonstrate how particular cellular interactions and responses of functional subsets of innate-like T cells contribute to protection from pathogenic lung infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453697" rel="alternate" title="Specialized subsets of innate-like T cells and dendritic cells protect from lethal pneumococcal infection in the lung (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453707</id><title>Opposing roles of blood-borne monocytes and tissue-resident macrophages in limbal stem cell damage after ocular injury (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.773465+00:00</updated><author><name>Chengxin Zhou</name></author><author><name>Fengyang Lei</name></author><author><name>Mirja Mittermaier</name></author><author><name>Bruce Ksander</name></author><author><name>Reza Dana</name></author><author><name>Claes H. Dohlman</name></author><author><name>Demetrios G. Vavvas</name></author><author><name>James Chodosh</name></author><author><name>Eleftherios I. Paschalis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Limbal stem cell (LSC) deficiency is a frequent and severe complication after chemical injury to the eye. Previous studies have assumed that this is mediated by direct chemical injury. Here we show that LSC loss can occur even without direct chemical injury to LSCs. Elevation of anterior chamber (AC) pH causes acute uveal stress, release of inflammatory cytokines at the basal limbal tissue, and subsequent LSC death. In particular, peripherally-derived CCR2&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;CX3CR1&lt;sup&gt;−-&lt;/sup&gt;monocytes cause upregulation of tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF-α) at the limbus, causing LSC loss. In contrast to peripherally-derived monocytes, CX3CR1&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;CCR2&lt;sup&gt;−-&lt;/sup&gt;tissue-resident macrophages are protective. Pharmacological depletion of tissue-resident macrophages prior to injury exacerbates LSC loss and increases LSC vulnerability to apoptosis following exposure to TNF-α, despite reduced CCR2&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;cell infiltration into the tissue. Consistently, repopulation of the cornea by new tissue-resident macrophages after depletion reverse LSC susceptibility to inflammatory cell death. This findings have important implication in LSC protection after chemical injury.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Limbal stem cell (LSC) loss after chemical burn is a significant clinical problem that has long been thought to be the result of direct chemical injury. This study demonstrates the existence of competing inflammatory mechanism responsible for LSC death, mediated by infiltrating peripheral monocytes that antagonize and overcome the protective role of tissue-resident macrophages. Thus, enhancing the role of tissue-resident macrophages while suppressing that of infiltrating monocytes could be a novel therapeutic strategy for LSC survival.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453707" rel="alternate" title="Opposing roles of blood-borne monocytes and tissue-resident macrophages in limbal stem cell damage after ocular injury (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453746</id><title>EXPRESSION OF A SECRETABLE, CELL-PENETRATING CDKL5 PROTEIN ENHANCES THE EFFICACY OF AAV VECTOR-MEDIATED GENE THERAPY FOR CDKL5 DEFICIENCY DISORDER (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.773651+00:00</updated><author><name>Giorgio Medici</name></author><author><name>Marianna Tassinari</name></author><author><name>Giuseppe Galvani</name></author><author><name>Stefano Bastianini</name></author><author><name>Laura Gennaccaro</name></author><author><name>Manuela Loi</name></author><author><name>Claudia Fuchs</name></author><author><name>Nicola Mottolese</name></author><author><name>Sara Alvente</name></author><author><name>Chiara Berteotti</name></author><author><name>Helen Rappe Baggett</name></author><author><name>Giovanna Zoccoli</name></author><author><name>Maurizio Giustetto</name></author><author><name>Alysson Muotri</name></author><author><name>Hiroyuki Nakai</name></author><author><name>Stefania Trazzi</name></author><author><name>Elisabetta Ciani</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;No therapy is currently available for CDKL5 (cyclin-dependent kinase-like 5) deficiency disorder (CDD), a severe neurodevelopmental disorder caused by mutations in the CDKL5 gene. Although delivery of a wild-type copy of the mutated gene to cells represents the most curative approach for a monogenic disease, proof-of-concept studies highlight significant efficacy caveats for brain gene therapy. Herein, we used a secretable TATk-CDKL5 protein to enhance the efficiency of a gene therapy for CDD. We found that, although AAVPHP.B_Igk-TATk-CDKL5 and AAVPHP.B_CDKL5 vectors had similar brain infection efficiency, the AAVPHP.B_Igk-TATk-CDKL5 vector led to a higher CDKL5 protein replacement due to secretion and transduction of the TATk-CDKL5 protein into the neighboring cells. Importantly, &lt;italic&gt;Cdkl5&lt;/italic&gt; KO mice treated with the AAVPHP.B_Igk-TATk-CDKL5 vector showed a behavioral and neuroanatomical improvement in comparison with vehicle-treated &lt;italic&gt;Cdkl5&lt;/italic&gt; KO mice or &lt;italic&gt;Cdkl5&lt;/italic&gt; KO mice treated with the AAVPHP.B_CDKL5 vector, indicating that a gene therapy based on a secretable recombinant TATk-CDKL5 protein is more effective at compensating &lt;italic&gt;Cdkl5&lt;/italic&gt;-null brain defects than gene therapy based on the expression of the native CDKL5.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453746" rel="alternate" title="EXPRESSION OF A SECRETABLE, CELL-PENETRATING CDKL5 PROTEIN ENHANCES THE EFFICACY OF AAV VECTOR-MEDIATED GENE THERAPY FOR CDKL5 DEFICIENCY DISORDER (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.21.21251509</id><title>Incidence of Lyme disease in the United Kingdom and association with fatigue: a population-based, historical cohort study (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.773879+00:00</updated><author><name>Florence Brellier</name></author><author><name>Mar Pujades-Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Emma Powell</name></author><author><name>Kathleen Mudie</name></author><author><name>Eliana Lacerda</name></author><author><name>Luis Nacul</name></author><author><name>Kevin Wing</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To evaluate incidence rates of Lyme disease in the UK and to investigate a possible association with subsequent fatigue&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Population-based historical cohort study with a comparator cohort matched by age, sex, and general practice&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients treated in UK general practices contributing to IQVIA Medical Research Data&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Participants&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;2,130 patients with a first diagnosis of Lyme disease between 2000 and 2018, and 8,510 randomly-sampled matched comparators, followed-up for a median time of 3 years and 8 months.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main outcome measures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Time from Lyme disease diagnosis to consultation for any fatigue-related symptoms or diagnosis and for myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome (ME/CFS). Adjusted hazard ratios (HRs) were estimated from Cox models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Average incidence rate for Lyme disease across the UK was 5.18 per 100,000 py between 2000 and 2018, increasing from 2.55 in 2000 to 9.33 in 2018. In total 929 events of any types of fatigue were observed, i.e. an incidence rate of 307.90 per 10,000 py in the Lyme cohort (282 events) and 165.60 in the comparator cohort (647 events). Effect of Lyme disease on any subsequent fatigue varied by index season with highest adjusted HRs in autumn [3.14 (95%CI: 1.92 to 5.13)] and winter [2.23 (1.21 to 4.11)]. Incidence rates of ME/CFS were 11.16 per 10,000 py in Lyme patients (12 events) and 1.20 in comparators (5 events), corresponding to an adjusted HR of 16.95 (5.17 to 55.60). Effect on any types of fatigue and ME/CFS was attenuated 6 months after diagnosis but still clearly visible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;UK primary care records provided strong evidence that Lyme disease was associated with acute and chronic fatigue. Albeit weaker, these effects persisted beyond 6 months, suggesting that patients and healthcare providers should remain alert to fatigue symptoms months to years following Lyme disease diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key messages box&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What is already known on this topic&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Incidence rates of Lyme disease in the UK are increasing but estimations vary according to data sources used.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reports investigating the association between Lyme disease and long-term fatigue are contradictory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What this study adds&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Average incidence rate for Lyme disease across the UK was estimated at 5.18 per 100,000 py between 2000 and 2018, and followed an increasing trend.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In patients with Lyme disease, a 2- and 3-fold increase in any subsequent fatigue was observed in winter and autumn, respectively, and a 16-fold increase in ME/CFS (all seasons combined), compared to a non-Lyme cohort matched by sex, age, and general practice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.21.21251509" rel="alternate" title="Incidence of Lyme disease in the United Kingdom and association with fatigue: a population-based, historical cohort study (3 tweets)"/><category term="Infectious Diseases (except HIV/AIDS)"/><published>2021-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.453424</id><title>Mechanisms of phosphatidylserine influence on viral production: a computational model of Ebola virus matrix protein assembly (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.774050+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiao Liu</name></author><author><name>Ethan J. Pappas</name></author><author><name>Monica L. Husby</name></author><author><name>Robert V. Stahelin</name></author><author><name>Elsje Pienaar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ebola virus (EBOV) infections continue to pose a global public health threat, with high mortality rates and sporadic outbreaks in Central and Western Africa. A quantitative understanding of the key processes driving EBOV assembly and budding could provide valuable insights to inform drug development. Here we used a computational model to evaluate EBOV matrix assembly. Our model focused on the assembly kinetics of VP40, the matrix protein in EBOV, and its interaction with phosphatidylserine (PS) in the host cell membrane. Human cells transfected with VP40-expressing plasmids are capable of producing virus-like particles (VLPs) that closely resemble EBOV virions. We used data from this in vitro VP40 system to calibrate our computational model. PS levels in the host cell membrane had been shown to affect VP40 dynamics as well as VLP production through recruiting VP40 dimers to plasma membrane inner leaflet. Our computational results indicated that PS may have direct influence on VP40 filament growth and affect multiple steps in the assembly and budding of VP40 VLPs. We also proposed that the assembly of VP40 filaments may follow the nucleation-elongation theory where initialization and oligomerization of VP40 are two separate and distinct steps in the assembly process. This work illustrated how computational and experimental approaches can be combined to allow for additional analysis and hypothesis generation. Our findings advanced understanding of the molecular process of EBOV assembly and budding processes and may help the development of new EBOV treatments targeting VP40 matrix assembly.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.453424" rel="alternate" title="Mechanisms of phosphatidylserine influence on viral production: a computational model of Ebola virus matrix protein assembly (3 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453477</id><title>Generative Adversarial Network augmented the gut microbiome-based health index by profoundly improved discrimination power (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.774208+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuxue Li</name></author><author><name>Gang Xie</name></author><author><name>Yuguo Zha</name></author><author><name>Kang Ning</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gut microbiome-based health index (GMHI) has been applied with success, while the discrimination powers of GMHI varied for different diseases, limiting its utility on a broad spectrum of diseases. In this work, a Generative Adversarial Network (GAN) model is proposed to improve the discrimination power of GMHI. Built based on the batch corrected data through GAN (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/HUST-NingKang-Lab/GAN-GMHI"&gt;https://github.com/HUST-NingKang-Lab/GAN-GMHI&lt;/ext-link&gt;), GAN-GMHI has largely reduced the batch effects, and profoundly improved the performance for distinguishing healthy individuals and different diseases. GAN-GMHI has provided results to support the strong association of gut microbiome and diseases, and indicated a more accurate venue towards microbiome-based disease monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability and implementation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;GAN-GMHI is publicly available on GitHub: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/HUST-NingKang-Lab/GAN-GMHI"&gt;https://github.com/HUST-NingKang-Lab/GAN-GMHI&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contact&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;email&gt;ningkang@hust.edu.cn&lt;/email&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Supplementary information&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453477" rel="alternate" title="Generative Adversarial Network augmented the gut microbiome-based health index by profoundly improved discrimination power (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453588</id><title>Accelerated epigenetic aging and inflammatory/immunological profile (ipAGE) in patients with chronic kidney disease (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.774420+00:00</updated><author><name>Igor Yusipov</name></author><author><name>Elena Kondakova</name></author><author><name>Alena Kalyakulina</name></author><author><name>Mikhail Krivonosov</name></author><author><name>Nadezhda Lobanova</name></author><author><name>Maria Giulia Bacalini</name></author><author><name>Claudio Franceschi</name></author><author><name>Maria Vedunova</name></author><author><name>Mikhail Ivanchenko</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chronic kidney disease (CKD) is defined by reduced estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR). This failure can be related to a phenotype of accelerated aging. In this work we considered 76 subjects with end-stage renal disease (ESRD) and 83 healthy controls. We evaluated two measures that can be informative of the rate of aging, i.e. whole blood DNA methylation using the Illumina Infinium EPIC array and plasma levels of a selection of inflammatory/immunological proteins using Multiplex Immunoassays. We demonstrated accelerated aging in terms of the most common epigenetic age estimators in CKD patients. We developed a new predictor of age based on inflammatory/immunological profile (ipAGE) and confirmed age acceleration in CKD patients. Finally, we evaluated the relationship between epigenetic age predictors and ipAGE and further identified the inflammatory/immunological biomarkers differentially expressed between cases and controls. In summary, our data show an accelerated aging phenotype in CKD patients sustained by inflammatory processes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453588" rel="alternate" title="Accelerated epigenetic aging and inflammatory/immunological profile (ipAGE) in patients with chronic kidney disease (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21260986</id><title>A plasma metabolite score of three eicosanoids predicts incident type 2 diabetes – a prospective study in three independent cohorts (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.774627+00:00</updated><author><name>Karolina Tuomisto</name></author><author><name>Joonatan Palmu</name></author><author><name>Tao Long</name></author><author><name>Jeramie D. Watrous</name></author><author><name>Kysha Mercader</name></author><author><name>Kim A. Lagerborg</name></author><author><name>Allen Andres</name></author><author><name>Marko Salmi</name></author><author><name>Sirpa Jalkanen</name></author><author><name>Ramachandran S. Vasan</name></author><author><name>Michael Inouye</name></author><author><name>Aki S. Havulinna</name></author><author><name>Pekka Jousilahti</name></author><author><name>Teemu J. Niiranen</name></author><author><name>Susan Cheng</name></author><author><name>Mohit Jain</name></author><author><name>Veikko Salomaa</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aim&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Peptide markers of inflammation have been associated with the development of type 2 diabetes. The role of upstream, lipid-derived mediators of inflammation such as eicosanoids, remains less clear. The aim was to examine whether eicosanoids are associated with incident type 2 diabetes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the FINRISK 2002 study, a population-based sample of Finnish men and women aged 25-74 years, we used directed, non-targeted liquid chromatography – mass spectrometry to identify 545 eicosanoids and related oxylipins in the participants’ plasma samples (n=8,292). We used multivariable-adjusted Cox regression to examine associations between eicosanoids and incident type 2 diabetes. The findings were replicated in the Framingham Heart Study (FHS, n=2,886) and DILGOM 2007 (n=3,905). Together, these three cohorts had 1070 cases of incident type 2 diabetes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;76 eicosanoids were associated individually with incident type 2 diabetes. We identified three eicosanoids independently associated with incident type 2 diabetes using stepwise Cox regression with forward selection and a Bonferroni-corrected inclusion threshold. A three-eicosanoid risk score produced a hazard ratio (HR) of 1.56 (95% confidence interval 1.41-1.72) per one standard deviation (SD) increment for risk of incident diabetes. The HR for comparing the top quartile to the lowest was 2.80 (2.53-3.07). Meta-analysis of the three cohorts yielded a pooled HR per SD of 1.31 (1.05-1.56).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plasma eicosanoid profiles predict incident type 2 diabetes and the clearest signals replicate in three independent cohorts. Our findings give new information on the biology underlying type 2 diabetes and suggest opportunities for early identification of people at risk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21260986" rel="alternate" title="A plasma metabolite score of three eicosanoids predicts incident type 2 diabetes – a prospective study in three independent cohorts (3 tweets)"/><category term="Epidemiology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453511</id><title>PatchPerPixMatch for Automated 3d Search of Neuronal Morphologies in Light Microscopy (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.774927+00:00</updated><author><name>Lisa Mais</name></author><author><name>Peter Hirsch</name></author><author><name>Claire Managan</name></author><author><name>Kaiyu Wang</name></author><author><name>Konrad Rokicki</name></author><author><name>Robert R. Svirskas</name></author><author><name>Barry J. Dickson</name></author><author><name>Wyatt Korff</name></author><author><name>Gerald M. Rubin</name></author><author><name>Gudrun Ihrke</name></author><author><name>Geoffrey W. Meissner</name></author><author><name>Dagmar Kainmueller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Studies of individual neurons in the Drosophila nervous system are facilitated by transgenic lines that sparsely and repeatably label respective neurons of interest. Sparsity can be enhanced by means of intersectional approaches like the split-GAL4 system, which labels the positive intersection of the expression patterns of two (denser) GAL4 lines. To this end, two GAL4 lines have to be identified as labelling a neuron of interest. Current approaches to tackling this task include visual inspection, as well as automated search in 2d projection images, of single cell multi-color flip-out (MCFO) acquisitions of GAL4 expression patterns. There is to date no automated method available that performs full 3d search in MCFO imagery of GAL4 lines, nor one that leverages automated reconstructions of the labelled neuron morphologies. To close this gap, we propose PatchPerPixMatch, a fully automated approach for finding a given neuron morphology in MCFO acquisitions of Gen1 GAL4 lines. PatchPerPixMatch performs automated instance segmentation of MCFO acquisitions, and subsequently searches for a target neuron morphology by minimizing an objective that aims at covering the target with a set of well-fitting segmentation fragments. Patch-PerPixMatch is computationally efficient albeit being full 3d, while also highly robust to inaccuracies in the automated neuron instance segmentation. We are releasing PatchPerPixMatch search results for ~30,000 neuron morphologies from the Drosophila &lt;italic&gt;hemibrain&lt;/italic&gt; in ~20,000 MCFO acquisitions of ~3,500 Gen1 GAL4 lines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Code&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Kainmueller-Lab/PatchPerPixMatch"&gt;https://github.com/Kainmueller-Lab/PatchPerPixMatch&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pppm.janelia.org"&gt;https://pppm.janelia.org&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453511" rel="alternate" title="PatchPerPixMatch for Automated 3d Search of Neuronal Morphologies in Light Microscopy (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261034</id><title>Running related biomechanical risk factors for overuse injuries in distance runners: A systematic review considering injury specificity and the potentials for future research (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.775130+00:00</updated><author><name>Steffen Willwacher</name></author><author><name>Markus Kurz</name></author><author><name>Johanna Robbin</name></author><author><name>Matthias Thelen</name></author><author><name>Joseph Hamill</name></author><author><name>Luke Kelly</name></author><author><name>Patrick Mai</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To identify and evaluate the evidence of the most relevant running-related risk factors (RRRFs) for running-related overuse injuries (ROIs) and to suggest future research directions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Systematic review considering prospective and retrospective studies. (PROSPERO_ID: 236832)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data sources&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pubmed. Connected Papers. The search was performed in February 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Eligibility criteria&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;English language. Studies on participants whose primary sport is running addressing the risk for the seven most common ROIs and at least one kinematic, kinetic (including pressure measurements), or electromyographic RRRF. An RRRF needed to be identified in at least one prospective or two retrospective studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sixty-two articles fulfilled our eligibility criteria. Levels of evidence for specific ROIs ranged from conflicting to moderate evidence. Running populations and methods applied varied considerably between studies. While some RRRFs appeared for several ROIs, most RRRFs were specific for a particular ROI. The biomechanical measurements performed in many studies would have allowed for consideration of many more RRRFs than have been reported, highlighting a potential for more effective data usage in the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study offers a comprehensive overview of RRRFs for the most common ROIs, which might serve as a starting point to develop ROI-specific risk profiles of individual runners. Future work should use macroscopic (big data) approaches involving long-term data collections in the real world and microscopic approaches involving precise stress calculations using recent developments in biomechanical modelling. However, consensus on data collection standards (including the quantification of workload and stress tolerance variables and the reporting of injuries) is warranted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.21261034" rel="alternate" title="Running related biomechanical risk factors for overuse injuries in distance runners: A systematic review considering injury specificity and the potentials for future research (3 tweets)"/><category term="Orthopedics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>