<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.820306+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463746</id><title>Deep-Learning Super-Resolution Microscopy Reveals Nanometer-Scale Intracellular Dynamics at the Millisecond Temporal Resolution (56 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.820509+00:00</updated><author><name>Rong Chen</name></author><author><name>Xiao Tang</name></author><author><name>Zeyu Shen</name></author><author><name>Yusheng Shen</name></author><author><name>Tiantian Li</name></author><author><name>Ji Wang</name></author><author><name>Binbin Cui</name></author><author><name>Yusong Guo</name></author><author><name>Shengwang Du</name></author><author><name>Shuhuai Yao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single-molecule localization microscopy (SMLM) can be used to resolve subcellular structures and achieve a tenfold improvement in spatial resolution compared to that obtained by conventional fluorescence microscopy. However, the separation of single-molecule fluorescence events in thousands of frames dramatically increases the image acquisition time and phototoxicity, impeding the observation of instantaneous intracellular dynamics. Based on deep learning networks, we develop a single-frame super-resolution microscopy (SFSRM) approach that reconstructs a super-resolution image from a single frame of a diffraction-limited image to support live-cell super-resolution imaging at a ~20 nm spatial resolution and a temporal resolution of up to 10 ms over thousands of time points. We demonstrate that our SFSRM method enables the visualization of the dynamics of vesicle transport at a millisecond temporal resolution in the dense and vibrant microtubule network in live cells. Moreover, the well-trained network model can be used with different live-cell imaging systems, such as confocal and light-sheet microscopes, making super-resolution microscopy accessible to nonexperts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463746" rel="alternate" title="Deep-Learning Super-Resolution Microscopy Reveals Nanometer-Scale Intracellular Dynamics at the Millisecond Temporal Resolution (56 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>