<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.781777+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460215</id><title>Dinosaur bonebed amber from an original swamp forest soil (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.781998+00:00</updated><author><name>Sergio Álvarez-Parra</name></author><author><name>Ricardo Pérez-de la Fuente</name></author><author><name>Enrique Peñalver</name></author><author><name>Eduardo Barrón</name></author><author><name>Luis Alcalá</name></author><author><name>Jordi Pérez-Cano</name></author><author><name>Carles Martín-Closas</name></author><author><name>Khaled Trabelsi</name></author><author><name>Nieves Meléndez</name></author><author><name>Rafael López Del Valle</name></author><author><name>Rafael P Lozano</name></author><author><name>David Peris</name></author><author><name>Ana Rodrigo</name></author><author><name>Víctor Sarto i Monteys</name></author><author><name>Carlos A Bueno-Cebollada</name></author><author><name>César Menor-Salván</name></author><author><name>Marc Philippe</name></author><author><name>Alba Sánchez-García</name></author><author><name>Constanza Peña-Kairath</name></author><author><name>Antonio Arillo</name></author><author><name>Eduardo Espílez</name></author><author><name>Luis Mampel</name></author><author><name>Xavier Delclòs</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Dinosaur bonebeds with amber content, yet scarce, offer a superior wealth and quality of data on ancient terrestrial ecosystems. However, the preserved palaeodiversity and/or taphonomic characteristics of these exceptional localities had hitherto limited their palaeobiological potential. Here we describe the amber from the Lower Cretaceous dinosaur bonebed of Ariño (Teruel, Spain) using a multidisciplinary approach. Amber is found in both a root layer with amber strictly in situ and a litter layer namely composed of aerial pieces unusually rich in bioinclusions, encompassing 11 insect orders, arachnids, and a few plant and vertebrate remains, including a feather. Additional palaeontological data ‒ charophytes, palynomorphs, ostracods‒ are provided. Ariño arguably represents the most prolific and palaeobiologically diverse locality in which fossiliferous amber and a dinosaur bonebed have been found in association, and the only one known where the vast majority of the palaeontological assemblage suffered no or low-grade pre-burial transport. That has enabled unlocking unprecedentedly complete and reliable palaeoecological data out of two complementary windows of preservation from the same site.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460215" rel="alternate" title="Dinosaur bonebed amber from an original swamp forest soil (4 tweets)"/><category term="Paleontology"/><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460266</id><title>Investigation of a derived adverse outcome pathway (AOP) network for endocrine-mediated perturbations (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.782285+00:00</updated><author><name>Janani Ravichandran</name></author><author><name>Bagavathy Shanmugam Karthikeyan</name></author><author><name>Areejit Samal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;An adverse outcome pathway (AOP) is a compact representation of the available mechanistic information on observed adverse effects upon environmental exposure. Sharing of events across individual AOPs has led to the emergence of AOP networks. Since AOP networks are expected to be functional units of toxicity prediction, there is current interest in their development tailored to specific research question or regulatory problem. To this end, we have developed a detailed workflow to construct a comprehensive endocrine-specific AOP (ED-AOP) network. Connectivity analysis of the ED-AOP network comprising 48 AOPs reveals 7 connected components and 12 isolated AOPs. Subsequently, we apply standard network measures to perform an in-depth analysis of the two largest connected components of the ED-AOP network. Notably, the graph-theoretic analyses led to the identification of important events including points of convergence or divergence in the ED-AOP network. Detailed analysis of the largest component in the ED-AOP network gives insights on the systems-level perturbations caused by endocrine disruption, emergent paths, and stressor-event associations. In sum, the derived ED-AOP network can be used to address the current knowledge gaps in the existing regulatory framework and aid in better risk assessment of environmental chemicals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460266" rel="alternate" title="Investigation of a derived adverse outcome pathway (AOP) network for endocrine-mediated perturbations (3 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460053</id><title>Dysregulation of the Tweak/Fn14 pathway in skeletal muscle of spinal muscular atrophy mice (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.782436+00:00</updated><author><name>Katharina E. Meijboom</name></author><author><name>Emily McFall</name></author><author><name>Daniel Anthony</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Edwards</name></author><author><name>Sabrina Kubinski</name></author><author><name>Gareth Hazell</name></author><author><name>Nina Ahlskog</name></author><author><name>Peter Claus</name></author><author><name>Kay E. Davies</name></author><author><name>Rashmi Kothary</name></author><author><name>Matthew J.A. Wood</name></author><author><name>Melissa Bowerman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spinal muscular atrophy (SMA) is a childhood neuromuscular disorder caused by depletion of the survival motor neuron (SMN) protein. SMA is characterized by the selective death of spinal cord motor neurons, leading to progressive muscle wasting. Loss of skeletal muscle in SMA is a combination of denervation-induced muscle atrophy and intrinsic muscle pathologies. Elucidation of the pathways involved is essential to identify the key molecules that contribute to and sustain muscle pathology. The tumor necrosis factor-like weak inducer of apoptosis (TWEAK)/TNF receptor superfamily member fibroblast growth factor inducible 14 (Fn14) pathway has been shown to play a critical role in the regulation of denervation-induced muscle atrophy as well as muscle proliferation, differentiation and metabolism in adults. However, it is not clear whether this pathway would be important in highly dynamic and developing muscle. We thus investigated the potential role of the TWEAK/Fn14 pathway in SMA muscle pathology, using the severe Taiwanese &lt;italic&gt;Smn&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;;SMN2&lt;/italic&gt; and the less severe &lt;italic&gt;Smn&lt;sup&gt;2B/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; SMA mice, which undergo a progressive neuromuscular decline in the first three post-natal weeks. Here, we report significantly dysregulated expression of the TWEAK/Fn14 pathway during disease progression in skeletal muscle of the two SMA mouse models. In addition, siRNA-mediated &lt;italic&gt;Smn&lt;/italic&gt; knockdown in C2C12 myoblasts suggests a genetic interaction between Smn and the TWEAK/Fn14 pathway. Further analyses of SMA, &lt;italic&gt;Tweak&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Fn14&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice revealed dysregulated myopathy, myogenesis and glucose metabolism pathways as a common skeletal muscle feature, and providing further evidence in support of a relationship between the TWEAK/Fn14 pathway and Smn. Finally, a pharmacological intervention (Fc-TWEAK) to upregulate the activity of the TWEAK/Fn14 pathway improved disease phenotypes in the two SMA mouse models. Our study provides novel mechanistic insights into the molecular players that contribute to muscle pathology in SMA and into the role of the TWEAK/Fn14 pathway in developing muscle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460053" rel="alternate" title="Dysregulation of the Tweak/Fn14 pathway in skeletal muscle of spinal muscular atrophy mice (3 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>