<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.546924+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.02.454535</id><title>Myth-busting the provider-user relationship for digital sequence information (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.547418+00:00</updated><author><name>Amber Hartman Scholz</name></author><author><name>Matthias Lange</name></author><author><name>Pia Habekost</name></author><author><name>Paul Oldham</name></author><author><name>Ibon Cancio</name></author><author><name>Guy Cochrane</name></author><author><name>Jens Freitag</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The United Nations Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD) formally recognized the sovereign rights of nations over their biological diversity. Implicit within the treaty is the idea that mega-biodiverse countries will provide genetic resources and grant access to them and scientists in high-income countries will use these resources and share back benefits. However, little research has been conducted on how this framework is reflected in real-life scientific practice. Currently, parties to the CBD) are debating whether or not digital sequence information (DSI) should be regulated under a new benefit-sharing framework. At this critical time point in the upcoming international negotiations, we test the fundamental hypothesis of provision and use by looking at the global patterns of access and use in scientific publications. Our data reject the provider-user relationship and suggest far more complex information flow for digital sequence information. Therefore, any new policy decisions on digital sequence information should be aware of the high level of use of DSI across low- and middle-income countries and seek to preserve open access to this crucial common good.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.02.454535" rel="alternate" title="Myth-busting the provider-user relationship for digital sequence information (9 tweets)"/><category term="Scientific Communication and Education"/><published>2021-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.07.455331</id><title>Homeobox transcription factor MNX1 is crucial for restraining the expression of pan-neuronal genes in motor neurons (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.547921+00:00</updated><author><name>Ming-an Sun</name></author><author><name>Sherry Ralls</name></author><author><name>Warren Wu</name></author><author><name>Justin Demmerle</name></author><author><name>Jiayao Jiang</name></author><author><name>Carson Miller</name></author><author><name>Gernot Wolf</name></author><author><name>Todd Macfarlan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Motor neurons (MNs) control muscle movement and are essential for breathing, walking and fine motor skills. Motor Neuron and Pancreas Homeobox 1 (MNX1) has long been recognized as a key marker of the MN lineage. Deficiency of the Mnx1 gene in mice results in early postnatal lethality - likely by causing abnormal MN development and respiratory malfunction. However, the genome-wide targets and exact regulatory function of Mnx1 in MNs remains unresolved. Using an in vitro model for efficient MN induction from mouse embryonic stem cells, we identified about six thousand MNX1-bound loci, of which half are conserved enhancers co-bound by the core MN-inducing factors ISL1 and LHX3, while the other half are promoters for housekeeping-like genes. Despite its widespread binding, disruption of Mnx1 affects the activity of only a few dozen MNX1-bound loci, and causes mis-regulation of about one hundred genes, the majority of which are up-regulated pan-neuronal genes with relatively higher expression in the brain compared to MNs. Integration of genome-wide binding, transcriptomic and epigenomic data in the wild-type and Mnx1-disrupted MNs predicts that Pbx3 and Pou6f2 are two putative direct targets of MNX1, and both are homeobox transcription factors highly expressed in the central nervous system. Our results suggest that MNX1 is crucial for restraining the expression of many pan-neuronal genes in MNs, likely in an indirect fashion. Further, the rarity of direct targets in contrast to the widespread binding of MNX1 reflects a distinctive mode of transcriptional regulation by homeobox transcriptional factors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.07.455331" rel="alternate" title="Homeobox transcription factor MNX1 is crucial for restraining the expression of pan-neuronal genes in motor neurons (7 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-08-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.04.455067</id><title>A Self-Limiting Circuit Regulates Mammary Cap Cell Plasticity Through TGF-beta Signaling (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.548200+00:00</updated><author><name>Armelle M Le Guelte</name></author><author><name>Ian G Macara</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The organization and maintenance of complex tissues requires emergent properties driven by self-organizing and self-limiting cell-cell interactions. We examined these interactions in the murine mammary gland. Luminal and myoepithelial subpopulations of the postnatal mammary gland arise from unipotent progenitors, but the destiny of cap cells, which enclose terminal end buds (TEB) in pubertal mice, remains controversial. Using a transgenic strain (Tg11.5kb-GFP) that specifically marks cap cells, we found ~50% of these cells undergo divisions perpendicular to the TEB surface, suggesting they might contribute to the underlying luminal cell population. To address their stemness potential we developed a lineage tracing mouse driven from the s-SHIP (11.5 kb) promoter. Induction of tdTomato (tdTom) from this promoter in vivo demonstrated that all cap cell progeny are myoepithelial, with no conversion to luminal lineage. Organoid cultures also exhibited unipotency. However, isolated cap cells cultured as mammospheres generated mixed luminal/myoepithelial spheres. Moreover, ablation of luminal cells in vivo using diphtheria toxin triggered repopulation by progeny of tdTom+ cap cells. A signaling inhibitor screen identified the TGFb pathway as a potential regulator of multipotency. TGFbR inhibitors or gene deletion blocked conversion to the luminal lineage, consistent with an autocrine loop in which cap cells secrete TGFb to activate the receptor and promote luminal transdifferentiation. Ductal tree regeneration in vivo from isolated cap cells was much more efficient when they were pre-treated with inhibitor, consistent with more cells retaining cap cell potential prior to transplantation. Notably, in vitro transdifferentiation of cap cells was blocked by co-culture with luminal cells. Overall, these data reveal a self-limiting cell circuit through which mammary luminal cells suppress cap cell conversion to the luminal lineage.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.04.455067" rel="alternate" title="A Self-Limiting Circuit Regulates Mammary Cap Cell Plasticity Through TGF-beta Signaling (6 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.29.452310</id><title>Are flexible school start times associated with higher academic grades? A 4-year longitudinal study (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.548358+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna M. Biller</name></author><author><name>Carmen Molenda</name></author><author><name>Fabian Obster</name></author><author><name>Giulia Zerbini</name></author><author><name>Christian Förtsch</name></author><author><name>Till Roenneberg</name></author><author><name>Eva C. Winnebeck</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mismatch between teenagers’ late sleep phase and early school start time results in acute and chronic sleep reductions. This is not only harmful for students’ learning in the short-term but may impact on students’ career prospects and widen social inequalities. Delaying school start times has been shown to improve sleep but whether this translates to better achievement is unresolved. The current evidence is limited due to a plethora of outcome measures and the many factors influencing sleep and grade/score trajectories. Here, we studied whether 0.5-1.5 years of exposure to a &lt;italic&gt;flexible&lt;/italic&gt; school start system, with the &lt;italic&gt;daily&lt;/italic&gt; choice of an 8AM or 8:50AM-start (intervention), allowed secondary school students (n=63-157, 14-19 years) to improve their quarterly school grades in a 4-year longitudinal pre-post design. We investigated whether sleep, changes in sleep or frequency of later starts predicted grade improvements in the flexible system. Our mixed model regressions with 5,111-16,724 official grades as outcomes did not indicate meaningful grade improvements in the flexible system &lt;italic&gt;per se&lt;/italic&gt; or with previously observed sleep variables (nor their changes) – the covariates academic quarter, discipline and grade level had a greater, more systematic effect in our sample. Importantly, this finding does not preclude improvements in learning and cognition in our sample. However, at the ‘dose’ received here, intermittent sleep benefits did not obviously translate into detectable grade changes, which is in line with several other studies and highlights that grades are suboptimal to evaluate timetabling interventions despite their importance for future success.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Early school start times worldwide clash with teenagers’ delayed sleep-wake rhythms. This mismatch results in sleep restrictions below healthy amounts, which compromises health and performance and further aggravates social disparities. Since adequate sleep is important for learning and concentration, there is the strong expectation that counteracting sleep deprivation with delayed school starts results in better academic achievement. We add important high-resolution, longitudinal data to this unresolved scientific debate. When controlling for confounders, our results do not support that improved sleep leads to grade changes within 1.5 years in a flexible start system. While grades are suboptimal to measure later school start effects on performance, they nevertheless open doors to higher education worldwide and thus determine future trajectories.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.29.452310" rel="alternate" title="Are flexible school start times associated with higher academic grades? A 4-year longitudinal study (5 tweets)"/><category term="Scientific Communication and Education"/><published>2021-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>