<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.852406+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.463948</id><title>Prion-like α-synuclein pathology in the brains of infants: Krabbe disease as a novel seed-competent α-synucleinopathy (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.852792+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher Hatton</name></author><author><name>Simona S. Ghanem</name></author><author><name>David J. Koss</name></author><author><name>Ilham Y. Abdi</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Gibbons</name></author><author><name>Rita Guerreiro</name></author><author><name>Jose Bras</name></author><author><name>Lauren Walker</name></author><author><name>Ellen Gelpi</name></author><author><name>Wendy Heywood</name></author><author><name>Tiago F. Outeiro</name></author><author><name>Johannes Attems</name></author><author><name>Bobby McFarland</name></author><author><name>Rob Forsyth</name></author><author><name>Omar M. El-Agnaf</name></author><author><name>Daniel Erskine</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Krabbe disease (KD) is an infantile neurodegenerative disorder resulting from pathogenic variants in the &lt;italic&gt;GALC&lt;/italic&gt; gene which causes accumulation of the toxic sphingolipid psychosine. &lt;italic&gt;GALC&lt;/italic&gt; variants are associated with increased risk of Lewy body diseases (LBD), an umbrella term for age-associated neurodegenerative diseases in which the protein α-synuclein aggregates into Lewy bodies. To explore whether α-synuclein in KD has pathological similarities to that in LBD, we compared &lt;italic&gt;post-mortem&lt;/italic&gt; KD tissue to that of infant control cases and identified alterations to α-synuclein localisation and expression of modifications associated with LBD. To determine whether α-synuclein in KD displayed pathogenic properties associated with LBD we evaluated its seeding capacity using the real-time quaking-induced conversion assay. Strikingly, seeded aggregation of α-synuclein resulted in the formation of fibrillar aggregates similar to those observed in LBD, confirming the prion-like capacity of KD-derived α-synuclein. These observations constitute the first report of prion-like α-synuclein in the brain tissue of infants and challenge the putative view that α-synuclein pathology is merely an age-associated phenomenon, instead suggesting it can result from alterations to biological processes such as sphingolipid homeostasis. Our findings have important implications for understanding the mechanisms underlying Lewy body formation in LBD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.463948" rel="alternate" title="Prion-like α-synuclein pathology in the brains of infants: Krabbe disease as a novel seed-competent α-synucleinopathy (19 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2021-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.16.464646</id><title>Pharmacological mechanisms on the anti-breast cancer property of Coix lacryma-jobi: A network-based analysis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.853123+00:00</updated><author><name>Angelu Mae A Ferrer</name></author><author><name>Janella Rayne A David</name></author><author><name>Arvin A Taquiqui</name></author><author><name>Arci A Bautista</name></author><author><name>Custer C Deocaris</name></author><author><name>Malona Velasco Alinsug</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Breast cancer is considered as one of the three most common cancers around the world and the second leading cause of cancer deaths among women. Coix lachrymal jobi, commonly known as Jobs tears or adlay has been reported to possess anti-cancer properties. Despite evidences provided by clinical data, the usage of Coix lacryma-jobi in treating cancer, particularly breast cancer, has been scarce. Thus, this study was conducted to determine the pharmacological mechanisms underlying its anti-breast cancer property using various network pathway analyses. Bioactive compounds from Coix lacryma-jobi and its potential target genes were obtained from SymMap. Breast cancer-related target genes were collected from CTD. Protein-protein interaction network was analyzed using the STRING database. GO and KEGG pathway enrichment analyses were performed using DAVID to further explore the mechanisms of Coix lacryma-jobi in treating breast cancer. PPI and compound-target-pathway were visualized using Cytoscape. A total of 26 bioactive compounds, 201 corresponding targets, 36625 breast cancer-associated targets were obtained, and 200 common targets were considered potential therapeutic targets. The 9 bioactive compounds identified were berberine, oleic acid, beta-sitosterol, sitosterol, linoleic acid, berberrubine, jatrorrhizine, thalifendine, and stigmasterol. The identified 5 core targets were ESR1, JUN, MAPK14, and RXRA.  Coix lacryma-jobi targets enriched in GO terms were mostly involved in regulation of transcription from RNA polymerase II promoter, drug response, steroid hormone receptor activity, and protein binding. This study elucidates on the pharmacological underpinnings on the potency of adlay against breast cancer.  Its subsequent drug development will be worth a step forward for a breast cancer-free society.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.16.464646" rel="alternate" title="Pharmacological mechanisms on the anti-breast cancer property of Coix lacryma-jobi: A network-based analysis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>