<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.853425+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455048</id><title>The longitudinal dynamics and natural history of clonal haematopoiesis (98 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.853739+00:00</updated><author><name>Margarete A. Fabre</name></author><author><name>José Guilherme de Almeida</name></author><author><name>Edoardo Fiorillo</name></author><author><name>Emily Mitchell</name></author><author><name>Aristi Damaskou</name></author><author><name>Justyna Rak</name></author><author><name>Valeria Orrù</name></author><author><name>Michele Marongiu</name></author><author><name>MS Vijayabaskar</name></author><author><name>Joanna Baxter</name></author><author><name>Claire Hardy</name></author><author><name>Federico Abascal</name></author><author><name>Michael Spencer Chapman</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Williams</name></author><author><name>Jyoti Nangalia</name></author><author><name>Iñigo Martincorena</name></author><author><name>Peter J. Campbell</name></author><author><name>Eoin F. McKinney</name></author><author><name>Francesco Cucca</name></author><author><name>Moritz Gerstung</name></author><author><name>George S. Vassiliou.</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human cells acquire somatic mutations throughout life, some of which can drive clonal expansion. Such expansions are frequent in the haematopoietic system of healthy individuals and have been termed clonal haematopoiesis (CH). While CH predisposes to myeloid neoplasia and other diseases, we have limited understanding of how and when CH develops, what factors govern its behaviour, how it interacts with ageing and how these variables relate to malignant progression. Here, we track 697 CH clones from 385 individuals aged 55 or older over a median of 13 years. We find that 92.4% of clones expanded at a stable exponential rate over the study period, with different mutations driving substantially different growth rates, ranging from 5% (&lt;italic&gt;DNMT3A&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;TP53&lt;/italic&gt;) to over 50%/yr (&lt;italic&gt;SRSF2-&lt;/italic&gt;P95H). Growth rates of clones with the same mutation differed by approximately +/−5%/yr, proportionately impacting “slow” drivers more substantially. By combining our time-series data with phylogenetic analysis of 1,731 whole genome-sequenced haematopoietic colonies from 7 older individuals, we reveal distinct patterns of lifelong clonal behaviour. &lt;italic&gt;DNMT3A&lt;/italic&gt;-mutant clones preferentially expanded early in life and displayed slower growth in old age, in the context of an increasingly competitive oligoclonal landscape. By contrast, splicing gene mutations only drove expansion later in life, while growth of &lt;italic&gt;TET2&lt;/italic&gt;-mutant clones showed minimal age-dependency. Finally, we show that mutations driving faster clonal growth carry a higher risk of malignant progression. Our findings characterise the lifelong natural history of CH and give fundamental insights into the interactions between somatic mutation, ageing and clonal selection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455048" rel="alternate" title="The longitudinal dynamics and natural history of clonal haematopoiesis (98 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456042</id><title>MorphoGraphX 2.0: Providing context for biological image analysis with positional information (79 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.854097+00:00</updated><author><name>Sören Strauss</name></author><author><name>Adam Runions</name></author><author><name>Brendan Lane</name></author><author><name>Dennis Eschweiler</name></author><author><name>Namrata Bajpai</name></author><author><name>Nicola Trozzi</name></author><author><name>Anne-Lise Routier-Kierzkowska</name></author><author><name>Saiko Yoshida</name></author><author><name>Sylvia Rodrigues da Silveira</name></author><author><name>Athul Vijayan</name></author><author><name>Rachele Tofanelli</name></author><author><name>Mateusz Majda</name></author><author><name>Emillie Echevin</name></author><author><name>Constance Le Gloanec</name></author><author><name>Hana Bertrand-Rakusova</name></author><author><name>Milad Adibi</name></author><author><name>Kay Schneitz</name></author><author><name>George Bassel</name></author><author><name>Daniel Kierzkowski</name></author><author><name>Johannes Stegmaier</name></author><author><name>Miltos Tsiantis</name></author><author><name>Richard S Smith</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Positional information is a central concept in developmental biology. In developing organs, positional information can be idealized as a local coordinate system that arises from morphogen gradients controlled by organizers at key locations. This offers a plausible mechanism for the integration of the molecular networks operating in individual cells into the spatially-coordinated multicellular responses necessary for the organization of emergent forms. Understanding how positional cues guide morphogenesis requires the quantification of gene expression and growth dynamics in the context of their underlying coordinate systems. Here we present recent advances in the MorphoGraphX software (Barbier de Reuille et al. eLife 2015;4:e05864) that implement a generalized framework to annotate developing organs with local coordinate systems. These coordinate systems introduce an organ-centric spatial context to microscopy data, allowing gene expression and growth to be quantified and compared in the context of the positional information thought to control them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456042" rel="alternate" title="MorphoGraphX 2.0: Providing context for biological image analysis with positional information (79 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455846</id><title>Structural basis for context-specific inhibition of translation by oxazolidinone antibiotics (34 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.854362+00:00</updated><author><name>Kaitlyn Tsai</name></author><author><name>Vanja Stojković</name></author><author><name>D. John Lee</name></author><author><name>Iris D. Young</name></author><author><name>Teresa Szal</name></author><author><name>Nora Vazquez-Laslop</name></author><author><name>Alexander S. Mankin</name></author><author><name>James S. Fraser</name></author><author><name>Danica Galonić Fujimori</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The antibiotic linezolid, the first clinically approved member of the oxazolidinone class, inhibits translation of bacterial ribosomes by binding to the peptidyl transferase center. Recent work has demonstrated that linezolid does not inhibit peptide bond formation at all sequences but rather acts in a context-specific manner, namely when alanine occupies the penultimate position of the nascent chain. In this study, we determined that the second-generation oxazolidinone radezolid also induces stalling with alanine at the penultimate position. However, the molecular basis for context-specificity of these inhibitors has not been elucidated. In this study, we determined high-resolution cryo-EM structures of both linezolid and radezolid-stalled ribosome complexes. These structures reveal that the alanine side chain fits within a small hydrophobic crevice created by oxazolidinone, resulting in improved ribosome binding. Modification of the ribosome by the antibiotic resistance enzyme Cfr disrupts stalling by forcing the antibiotic to adopt a conformation that narrows the hydrophobic alanine pocket. Together, the structural and biochemical findings presented in this work provide molecular understanding of context-specific inhibition of translation by clinically important oxazolidinone antibiotics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455846" rel="alternate" title="Structural basis for context-specific inhibition of translation by oxazolidinone antibiotics (34 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455294</id><title>Assessment of 3D MINFLUX data for quantitative structural biology in cells (32 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.854548+00:00</updated><author><name>Kirti Prakash</name></author><author><name>Alistair P. Curd</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;MINFLUX is a promising new development in single-molecule localization microscopy, claiming a resolution of 1-3 nm in living and fixed biological specimens. While MINFLUX can achieve very high localisation precision, quantitative analysis of reported results leads us to dispute the resolution claim and question reliability for imaging sub-100-nm structural features, in its current state.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455294" rel="alternate" title="Assessment of 3D MINFLUX data for quantitative structural biology in cells (32 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456204</id><title>Nrf2 is a central regulator of the metabolic landscape in macrophages and finetunes their inflammatory response (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.854690+00:00</updated><author><name>Dylan Gerard Ryan</name></author><author><name>Elena V Knatko</name></author><author><name>Alva Casey</name></author><author><name>Jens L Hukelmann</name></author><author><name>Alejandro J Brenes</name></author><author><name>Sharadha Dayalan Naidu</name></author><author><name>Maureen Higgins</name></author><author><name>Laura Tronci</name></author><author><name>Efterpi Nikitopoulou</name></author><author><name>Luke AJ O'Neill</name></author><author><name>Angus I Lamond</name></author><author><name>Andrey Y Abramov</name></author><author><name>Doreen A Cantrell</name></author><author><name>Michael P Murphy</name></author><author><name>Albena T Dinkova-Kostova</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To overcome oxidative, inflammatory, and metabolic stress, cells have evolved networks of cytoprotective proteins controlled by nuclear factor erythroid 2 p45-related factor 2 (Nrf2) and its main negative regulator the Kelch-like ECH associated protein 1 (Keap1). Here, we used high-resolution mass-spectrometry to characterize the proteomes of macrophages with genetically altered Nrf2 status. Our analysis revealed significant differences among the genotypes in cellular metabolism and redox homeostasis, which we validated with respirometry and metabolomics, as well as in anti-viral immune pathways and the cell cycle. Nrf2 status significantly affected the proteome following lipopolysaccharide (LPS) stimulation, with alterations in redox, carbohydrate and lipid metabolism, and innate immunity observed. Of note, Nrf2 activation was found to promote mitochondrial fusion in inflammatory macrophages. The Keap1 inhibitor, 4-octyl itaconate (4-OI), a derivative of the mitochondrial immunometabolite itaconate, remodeled the inflammatory macrophage proteome, increasing redox and suppressing anti-viral immune effectors in a Nrf2-dependent manner. These data suggest that Nrf2 activation facilitates metabolic reprogramming and mitochondrial adaptation, and finetunes the innate immune response in macrophages.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456204" rel="alternate" title="Nrf2 is a central regulator of the metabolic landscape in macrophages and finetunes their inflammatory response (27 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456039</id><title>DEVELOPMENTAL AND EVOLUTIONARY COMPARATIVE ANALYSIS OF A HOXD REGULATORY LANDSCAPE IN MAMMALS AND BIRDS (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.854902+00:00</updated><author><name>Aurélie Hintermann</name></author><author><name>Isabel Guerreiro</name></author><author><name>Christopher Chase Bolt</name></author><author><name>Sandra Gitto</name></author><author><name>Denis Duboule</name></author><author><name>Leonardo Beccari</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Modifications in gene regulation during development are considered to be a driving force in the evolution of organisms. Part of these changes involve rapidly evolving &lt;italic&gt;cis-&lt;/italic&gt;regulatory elements (CREs), which interact with their target genes through higher-order 3D chromatin structures. How such 3D architectures and variations in CREs contribute to transcriptional evolvability nevertheless remains elusive. During vertebrate evolution, &lt;italic&gt;Hox&lt;/italic&gt; genes were redeployed in different organs in a class-specific manner, while maintaining the same basic function in organizing the primary body axis. Since a large part of the relevant enhancers are located in a conserved regulatory landscape, this gene cluster represents an interesting paradigm to study the emergence of regulatory innovations. In this work, we analyzed &lt;italic&gt;Hoxd&lt;/italic&gt; gene regulation in both murine vibrissae and chicken feather primordia, two mammalian- and avian-specific skin appendages which express different subsets of &lt;italic&gt;Hoxd&lt;/italic&gt; genes, and compared their regulatory modalities with the regulations at work during the elongation of the posterior trunk, a mechanism highly conserved in amniotes. We show that in the former two structures, distinct subsets of &lt;italic&gt;Hoxd&lt;/italic&gt; genes are contacted by different lineage-specific enhancers, likely as a result of using an ancestral chromatin topology as an evolutionary playground, whereas the regulations implemented in the mouse and chicken embryonic trunk rely more on conserved CREs. Nevertheless, a high proportion of these non-coding sequences active in the trunk appear to have functionally diverged between the two species, suggesting that transcriptional robustness is maintained despite a considerable divergence in CREs’ sequence, an observation supported by a genome-wide comparative approach.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456039" rel="alternate" title="DEVELOPMENTAL AND EVOLUTIONARY COMPARATIVE ANALYSIS OF A HOXD REGULATORY LANDSCAPE IN MAMMALS AND BIRDS (24 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456308</id><title>Structural transitions in the GTP cap visualized by cryo-EM of catalytically inactive microtubules (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.855068+00:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin J LaFrance</name></author><author><name>Johanna Roostalu</name></author><author><name>Gil Henkin</name></author><author><name>Basil J Greber</name></author><author><name>Rui Zhang</name></author><author><name>Davide Normanno</name></author><author><name>Chloe McCollum</name></author><author><name>Thomas Surrey</name></author><author><name>Eva Nogales</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microtubules (MTs) are polymers of alphabeta-tubulin heterodimers that stochastically switch between growth and shrinkage phases. This dynamic instability is critically important for MT function. It is believed that GTP hydrolysis within the MT lattice is accompanied by destabilizing conformational changes, and that MT stability depends on a transiently existing GTP cap at the growing MT end. Here we use cryo-EM and TIRF microscopy of GTP hydrolysis-deficient MTs assembled from mutant recombinant human tubulin to investigate the structure of a GTP-bound MT lattice. We find that the GTP-MT lattice of two mutants in which the catalytically active glutamate in α-tubulin was substituted by inactive amino acids (E254A and E254N) is remarkably plastic. Undecorated E254A and E254N MTs with 13 protofilaments both have an expanded lattice, but display opposite protofilament twists, making these lattices distinct from the compacted lattice of wildtype GDP-MTs. End binding proteins of the EB family have the ability to compact both mutant GTP-lattices and to stabilize a negative twist, suggesting that they promote this transition also in the GTP cap of wildtype MTs, thereby contributing to the maturation of the MT structure. We also find that the MT seam appears to be stabilized in mutant GTP-MTs and destabilized in GDP-MTs, supporting the proposal that the seam plays an important role in MT stability. Together, these first high-resolution structures of truly GTP-bound MTs add mechanistic insight to our understanding of MT dynamic instability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456308" rel="alternate" title="Structural transitions in the GTP cap visualized by cryo-EM of catalytically inactive microtubules (24 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.454869</id><title>Integrated annotation and analysis of genomic features reveal new types of functional elements and large-scale epigenetic phenomena in the developing zebrafish (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.855244+00:00</updated><author><name>Damir Baranasic</name></author><author><name>Matthias Hoertenhuber</name></author><author><name>Piotr Balwierz</name></author><author><name>Tobias Zehnder</name></author><author><name>Abdul Kadir Mukarram</name></author><author><name>Chirag Nepal</name></author><author><name>Csilla Varnai</name></author><author><name>Yavor Hadzhiev</name></author><author><name>Ada Jimenez-Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Nan Li</name></author><author><name>Joseph W. Wragg</name></author><author><name>Fabio D'Orazio</name></author><author><name>Noelia Diaz</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Hernandez-Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Zelin Chen</name></author><author><name>Marcus Stoiber</name></author><author><name>Michael Dong</name></author><author><name>Irene Stevens</name></author><author><name>Samuel E. Ross</name></author><author><name>Anne Eagle</name></author><author><name>Ryan Martin</name></author><author><name>Pelumi Obasaju</name></author><author><name>Sepand Rastegar</name></author><author><name>Alison C. McGarvey</name></author><author><name>Wolfgang Kopp</name></author><author><name>Emily Chambers</name></author><author><name>Dennis Wang</name></author><author><name>Hyejeong Kim Kim</name></author><author><name>Rafael D. Acemel</name></author><author><name>Silvia Naranjo</name></author><author><name>Maciej Lapinski</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Chong-Morrison</name></author><author><name>Sinnakaruppan Mathavan</name></author><author><name>Bernard Peers</name></author><author><name>Tatjana Sauka-Spengler</name></author><author><name>Martin Vingron</name></author><author><name>Piero Carninci</name></author><author><name>Uwe Ohler</name></author><author><name>Scott Allen Lacadie</name></author><author><name>Shawn Burgess</name></author><author><name>Cecilia Winata</name></author><author><name>Freek van Eeden</name></author><author><name>Juan M. Vaquerizas</name></author><author><name>Jose Luis Gomez-Skarmeta</name></author><author><name>Daria Onichtchouk</name></author><author><name>Ben James Brown</name></author><author><name>Ozren Bogdanovic</name></author><author><name>Monte Westerfield</name></author><author><name>Fiona C. Wardle</name></author><author><name>Carsten O. Daub</name></author><author><name>Boris Lenhard</name></author><author><name>Ferenc Mueller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Zebrafish, a popular model for embryonic development and for modelling human diseases, has so far lacked a systematic functional annotation programme akin to those in other animal models. To address this, we formed the international DANIO-CODE consortium and created the first central repository to store and process zebrafish developmental functional genomic data. Our Data Coordination Center (https://danio-code.zfin.org) combines a total of 1,802 sets of unpublished and reanalysed published genomics data, which we used to improve existing annotations and show its utility in experimental design. We identified over 140,000 cis-regulatory elements in development, including novel classes with distinct features dependent on their activity in time and space. We delineated the distinction between regulatory elements active during zygotic genome activation and those active during organogenesis, identifying new aspects of how they relate to each other. Finally, we matched regulatory elements and epigenomic landscapes between zebrafish and mouse and predict functional relationships between them beyond sequence similarity, extending the utility of zebrafish developmental genomics to mammals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.454869" rel="alternate" title="Integrated annotation and analysis of genomic features reveal new types of functional elements and large-scale epigenetic phenomena in the developing zebrafish (23 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-08-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456048</id><title>Bending-torsional elasticity and energetics of the plus-end microtubule tip (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.855723+00:00</updated><author><name>Maxim Igaev</name></author><author><name>Helmut Grubmueller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microtubules (MTs), mesoscopic cellular filaments, grow primarily by the addition of GTP-bound tubulin dimers at their dynamic flaring plus-end tips. They operate as chemomechanical energy transducers with stochastic transitions to an astounding shortening motion upon hydrolyzing GTP to GDP. Time-resolved dynamics of the MT tip - a key determinant of this behavior - as a function of nucleotide state, internal lattice strain, and stabilizing lateral interactions have not been fully understood. Here, we use atomistic simulations to study the spontaneous relaxation of complete GTP-MT and GDP-MT tip models from unfavorable straight to relaxed splayed conformations and to comprehensively characterize the elasticity of MT tips. Our simulations reveal the dominance of viscoelastic dynamics of MT protofilaments during the relaxation process, driven by the stored bending-torsional strain and counterbalanced by the inter-protofilament interactions. We show that the post-hydrolysis MT tip is exposed to higher activation energy barriers for straight lattice formation, which translates into its inability to elongate. Our study provides an 'information ratchet' mechanism for the elastic energy conversion and release by MT tips and offers new insights into the mechanoenzymatics of MTs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456048" rel="alternate" title="Bending-torsional elasticity and energetics of the plus-end microtubule tip (18 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456007</id><title>Simultaneous infection with porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome and influenza viruses abrogates clinical protection induced by live attenuated porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome vaccination (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.855873+00:00</updated><author><name>Tiphany Chrun</name></author><author><name>Emmanuel A. Maze</name></author><author><name>Eleni Vatzia</name></author><author><name>Veronica Martini</name></author><author><name>Basu Paudyal</name></author><author><name>Matthew Edmans</name></author><author><name>Adam McNee</name></author><author><name>Tanuja Manjegowda</name></author><author><name>Francisco J. Salguero</name></author><author><name>Nanchaya Wanasen</name></author><author><name>Surapong Koonpaew</name></author><author><name>Simon P. Graham</name></author><author><name>Elma Tchilian</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The porcine respiratory disease complex (PRDC) is responsible for significant economic losses in the pig industry worldwide. Porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome virus (PRRSV) and swine influenza virus are major viral contributors to PRDC. Vaccines are cost-effective measures for controlling PRRS, however, their efficacy in the context of co-infections has been poorly investigated. In this study, we aimed to determine the effect of PRRSV-2 and swine influenza H3N2 virus co-infection on the efficacy of PRRSV modified live virus (MLV) vaccination, which is widely used in the field. Following simultaneous challenge with contemporary PRRSV-2 and H3N2 field isolates, we found that the protective effect of PRRS MLV vaccination on clinical disease and pathology was abrogated, although viral load was unaffected and antibody responses were enhanced. In contrast, co-infection in non-immunized animals reduced PRRSV-2 viremia and H3N2 virus load in the upper respiratory tract and potentiated T cell responses against both PRRSV-2 and H3N2 in the lung. Further analysis suggested that an upregulation of inhibitory cytokines gene expression in the lungs of vaccinated pigs may have influenced responses to H3N2 and PRRSV-2. These findings provide important insights into the effect of viral co-infections on PRRS vaccine efficacy that may help identity more effective vaccination strategies against PRDC in the field.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456007" rel="alternate" title="Simultaneous infection with porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome and influenza viruses abrogates clinical protection induced by live attenuated porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome vaccination (18 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456249</id><title>The Zip4 protein directly couples meiotic crossover formation to synaptonemal complex assembly (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.856076+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexandra Pyatnitskaya</name></author><author><name>Jessica Andreani</name></author><author><name>Raphael Guerois</name></author><author><name>Arnaud De Muyt</name></author><author><name>Valerie Borde</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Meiotic recombination is triggered by programmed double-strand breaks (DSBs), a subset of these being repaired as crossovers, promoted by eight evolutionarily conserved proteins, named ZMM. Crossover formation is functionally linked to synaptonemal complex (SC) assembly between homologous chromosomes, but the underlying mechanism is unknown. Here we show that Ecm11, a SC central element protein, localizes on both DSB sites and sites that attach chromatin loops to the chromosome axis, which are the starting points of SC formation, in a way that strictly requires the ZMM protein Zip4. Furthermore, Zip4 directly interacts with Ecm11 and point mutants that specifically abolish this interaction lose Ecm11 binding to chromosomes and exhibit defective SC assembly. This can be partially rescued by artificially tethering interaction-defective Ecm11 to Zip4. Mechanistically, this direct connection ensuring SC assembly from CO sites could be a way for the meiotic cell to shut down further DSB formation once enough recombination sites have been selected for crossovers, thereby preventing excess crossovers. Finally, the mammalian ortholog of Zip4, TEX11, also interacts with the SC central element TEX12, suggesting a general mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456249" rel="alternate" title="The Zip4 protein directly couples meiotic crossover formation to synaptonemal complex assembly (17 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456026</id><title>Live imaging YAP signaling in vivo with fusion reporter mice (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.856232+00:00</updated><author><name>Bin Gu</name></author><author><name>Brian Bradshaw</name></author><author><name>Min Zhu</name></author><author><name>Yu Sun</name></author><author><name>Sevan Hopyan</name></author><author><name>Janet Rossant</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;YAP protein is a critical regulator of mammalian embryonic development. By generating a near-infrared fusion YAP reporter mouse line, we have achieved high-resolution live imaging of YAP localization during mouse embryonic development. We have validated the reporter by demonstrating its predicted responses to blocking Lats kinase activity or blocking cell polarity. The YAP fusion reporter mice and imaging methods will open new opportunities for understanding dynamic YAP signaling &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; in many different situations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456026" rel="alternate" title="Live imaging YAP signaling in vivo with fusion reporter mice (9 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455910</id><title>Hippocampal place cells as a cryptographic tool that enables animals to secretly cache and retrieve their food (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.856391+00:00</updated><author><name>Oren Forkosh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;For animals, the ability to hide and retrieve valuable information, such as the location of food, can mean the difference between life and death. Here, we propose that to achieve this, their brain uses spatial cells similarly to how we utilize encryption for data security. Some animals are able to cache hundreds of thousands of food items annually by each individual and later retrieve most of what they themselves stashed. Rather than memorizing their cache locations as previously suggested, we propose that they use a single cryptographic-like mechanism during both caching and retrieval. The model we developed is based on hippocampal spatial cells, which respond to an animal’s positional attention, such as when the animal enters a specific region (place-cells) or gazes at a particular location (spatial-view-cells). We know that the region that activates each spatial cell remains consistent across subsequent visits to the same area but not between areas. This remapping, combined with the uniqueness of cognitive maps, produces a persistent crypto-hash function for both food caching and retrieval. We also show that the model stores temporal information that helps animals in food caching order preference as previously observed. This behavior, which we refer to as crypto-taxis, might also explain consistent differences in decision-making when animals are faced with a large number of alternatives such as in foraging.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455910" rel="alternate" title="Hippocampal place cells as a cryptographic tool that enables animals to secretly cache and retrieve their food (9 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456232</id><title>Two parallel sRNA amplification cycles contribute to RNAi inheritance in C. elegans (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.856523+00:00</updated><author><name>John Paul Tsu Ouyang</name></author><author><name>Wenyan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Geraldine Seydoux</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;RNA-mediated interference (RNAi) is a conserved mechanism that uses small RNAs (sRNAs) to tune gene expression. In C. elegans, exposure to dsRNA induces the production of gene-specific sRNAs that are propagated to progeny not exposed to the dsRNA trigger. We present evidence that RNAi inheritance is mediated by two parallel sRNA amplification loops. The first loop, dependent on the nuclear Argonaute HRDE-1, targets nascent transcripts, and reduces but does not eliminate productive transcription at the locus. The second loop, dependent on the conserved helicase ZNFX-1, targets mature transcripts and concentrates them in perinuclear condensates (nuage). Each amplification loop generates a distinct class of sRNAs, with the ZNFX-1 loop responsible for the bulk of sRNA production on the region targeted by the trigger. By independently targeting nascent and mature transcripts, the HRDE-1 and ZNFX-1 loops ensure maximum silencing in progeny not exposed to the trigger.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456232" rel="alternate" title="Two parallel sRNA amplification cycles contribute to RNAi inheritance in C. elegans (9 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456199</id><title>Light-controlled elimination of PD-L1+ cells (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.856664+00:00</updated><author><name>Judith Jing Wen Wong</name></author><author><name>Paal K. Selbo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The programmed death ligand-1 (PD-L1), also known as CD274 or B7-H1, is mainly expressed on cancer cells and/or immunosuppressive cells in the tumor microenvironment (TME) and plays an essential role in tumor progression and immune escape. Immune checkpoint inhibitors (ICIs) of the PD-1/PD-L1 axis have shown impressive clinical success, however, the majority of the patients do not respond to immune checkpoint therapy (ICT). Thus, to overcome ICT resistance there is a high need for potent and novel strategies that simultaneously target both tumor cells and immunosuppressive cells in the TME. In this study, we show that the intracellular light-controlled drug delivery method photochemical internalization (PCI) induce specific and strongly enhanced cytotoxic effects of the PD-L1-targeting immunotoxin, anti-PD-L1-saporin (Anti-PDL1-SAP), in the PD-L1+ triple-negative breast cancer MDA-MB-231 cell line, while no enhanced efficacy was obtained in the PD-L1 negative control cell line MDA-MB-453. Using fluorescence microscopy, we reveal that the anti-PD-L1 antibody binds to PD-L1 on the surface of the MDA-MD-231 cells and overnight accumulates in late endosomes and lysosomes where it co-localizes with the PCI photosensitizer fimaporfin (TPCS2a). Moreover, light-controlled endosomal/lysosomal escape of the anti-PD-L1 antibody and fimaporfin into the cytosol was obtained. We also confirm that the breast MDA-MB-468 and the prostate PC-3 and DU-145 cancer cell lines have subpopulations with PD-L1 expression. In addition, we show that interferon-gamma strongly induce PD-L1 expression in the per se PD-L1 negative CT26.WT cells and enhance the PD-L1 expression in MC-38 cells, of which both are murine colon cancer cell lines. In conclusion, our work provides an in vitro proof-of-concept of PCI-enhanced targeting and eradication of PD-L1 positive immunosuppressive cells. This light-controlled combinatorial strategy has a potential to advance cancer immunotherapy and should be explored in preclinical studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456199" rel="alternate" title="Light-controlled elimination of PD-L1+ cells (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455556</id><title>Phase transition specified by a binary code patterns the vertebrate eye cup (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.856802+00:00</updated><author><name>Revathi Balasubramanian</name></author><author><name>Xuanyu Min</name></author><author><name>Peter M.J. Quinn</name></author><author><name>Quentin Lo Giudice</name></author><author><name>Chenqi Tao</name></author><author><name>Karina Polanco</name></author><author><name>Neoklis Makrides</name></author><author><name>John Peregrin</name></author><author><name>Michael Bouaziz</name></author><author><name>Yingyu Mao</name></author><author><name>Qian Wang</name></author><author><name>Bruna L Costa</name></author><author><name>Diego Buenaventura</name></author><author><name>Fen Wang</name></author><author><name>Liang Ma</name></author><author><name>Stephen H Tsang</name></author><author><name>Pierre J. Fabre</name></author><author><name>Xin Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The developing vertebrate eye cup is partitioned into the neural retina (NR), the retinal pigmented epithelium (RPE) and the ciliary margin (CM). By single cell analysis, we showed that a gradient of FGF signaling regulates demarcation and subdivision of the CM and controls its stem cell-like property of self-renewal, differentiation and survival. This regulation by FGF is balanced by an evolutionarily conserved Wnt signaling gradient induced by the lens ectoderm and the periocular mesenchyme, which specifies the CM and the distal RPE. These two morphogen gradients converge in the CM where FGF signaling promotes Wnt signaling by stabilizing β-catenin in a GSK3β-independent manner. We further showed that activation of Wnt signaling converts the NR to either the CM or the RPE depending on the level of FGF signaling. Conversely, activation of FGF transforms the RPE to the NR or CM dependent on Wnt activity. We demonstrated that the default fate of the eye cup is the NR, but synergistic FGF and Wnt signaling promotes CM formation both in vivo and in retinal organoid culture of human iPS cells. Our study reveals that the vertebrate eye develops through phase transition determined by a combinatorial code of FGF and Wnt signaling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455556" rel="alternate" title="Phase transition specified by a binary code patterns the vertebrate eye cup (7 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455998</id><title>Mapping the peptide binding groove of MHC class I (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.857027+00:00</updated><author><name>Janine-Denise Kopicki</name></author><author><name>Ankur Saikia</name></author><author><name>Stephan Niebling</name></author><author><name>Christian G&amp;uumlnther</name></author><author><name>Maria M. Garcia-Alai</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Springer</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Uetrecht</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;An essential element of adaptive immunity is the selective binding of peptide antigens by major histocompatibility complex (MHC) class I proteins and their presentation to cytotoxic T lymphocytes on the cell surface. Using native mass spectrometry, we here analyze the binding of peptides to an empty disulfide-stabilized HLA-A*02:01 molecule. This novel approach allows us to examine the binding properties of diverse peptides. The unique stability of our MHC class I even enables us to determine the binding affinity of complexes, which are suboptimally loaded with truncated or charge-reduced peptides. Notably, a unique erucamide adduct decouples affinity analysis from peptide identity alleviating issues usually attributed to clustering. We discovered that two anchor positions at the binding surface between MHC and peptide can be stabilized independently and further analyze the contribution of other peptidic amino acids on the binding. We propose this as an alternative, likely universally applicable method to artificial prediction tools to estimate the binding strength of peptides to MHC class I complexes quickly and efficiently. This newly described MHC class I-peptide binding affinity quantitation represents a much needed orthogonal, confirmatory approach to existing computational affinity predictions and has the potential to eliminate binding affinity biases and thus accelerate drug discovery in infectious diseases autoimmunity, vaccine design, and cancer immunotherapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455998" rel="alternate" title="Mapping the peptide binding groove of MHC class I (7 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455968</id><title>Forgetting Enhances Episodic Control with Structured Memories (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.857195+00:00</updated><author><name>Annik Yalnizyan-Carson</name></author><author><name>Blake A. Richards</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Forgetting is a normal process in healthy brains, and evidence suggests that the mammalian brain forgets more than is required based on limitations of mnemonic capacity. Episodic memories, in particular, are liable to be forgotten over time. Researchers have hypothesized that it may be beneficial for decision making to forget episodic memories over time. Reinforcement learning offers a normative framework in which to test such hypotheses. Here, we show that a reinforcement learning agent that uses an episodic memory cache to find rewards in maze environments can forget a large percentage of older memories without any performance impairments, if they utilize mnemonic representations that contain structural information about space. Moreover, we show that some forgetting can actually provide a benefit in performance compared to agents with unbounded memories. Our analyses of the agents show that forgetting reduces the influence of outdated information and states which are not frequently visited on the policies produced by the episodic control system. These results support the hypothesis that some degree of forgetting can be beneficial for decision making, which can help to explain why the brain forgets more than is required by capacity limitations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455968" rel="alternate" title="Forgetting Enhances Episodic Control with Structured Memories (6 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456071</id><title>Uncertainty avoidance versus conditioned reinforcement: exploring paradoxical choice in rats (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.857334+00:00</updated><author><name>Victor Ajuwon</name></author><author><name>Andrés Ojeda</name></author><author><name>Robin A. Murphy</name></author><author><name>Tiago Monteiro</name></author><author><name>Alex Kacelnik</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Paying a cost to reduce uncertainty can be adaptive, because better informed decision-makers can align their preferences to opportunities. However, birds and mammals display an appetite for information that they cannot use to functionally alter behaviour or its outcomes. We explore two putative motivational mechanisms for this paradoxical behaviour. The information hypothesis proposes that reducing uncertainty is reinforcing &lt;italic&gt;per se&lt;/italic&gt;, consistent with the concept of curiosity: a motivation to know, in the absence of instrumental benefits. In contrast, the conditioned reinforcement hypothesis sees information-seeking as a consequence of asymmetries in secondarily acquired reinforcement: responding increments caused by post-choice stimuli announcing positive outcomes (S&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;) exceed decrements caused by stimuli signalling absence of reward (S&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt;). We contrast these hypotheses experimentally. Rats chose between two equally profitable options delivering food probabilistically after a fixed delay. In the informative option (&lt;italic&gt;Info&lt;/italic&gt;), the outcome (food/no food) was signalled immediately after choice, whereas in the non-informative option (&lt;italic&gt;NoInfo&lt;/italic&gt;) outcomes were uncertain until the delay lapsed. Subjects preferred (&lt;italic&gt;Info&lt;/italic&gt;) when (1) outcomes were signalled by salient auditory cues, (2) only the absence of reward was signalled, and (3) only reward was signalled, though acquisition was slower when rewards were not explicitly signalled. Our results show that a salient good news signal is not required as a conditioned reinforcer to generate paradoxical preferences. Terminal preferences support the information hypothesis but the slower acquisition of (&lt;italic&gt;Info&lt;/italic&gt;) preference when S&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; is not present is consistent with the conditioning account. We conclude that both uncertainty reduction and conditioned reinforcement influence choice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456071" rel="alternate" title="Uncertainty avoidance versus conditioned reinforcement: exploring paradoxical choice in rats (6 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455638</id><title>Construction of competing endogenous RNA interaction networks as prognostic markers in metastatic melanoma (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.857486+00:00</updated><author><name>Zan He</name></author><author><name>Zijuan Xin</name></author><author><name>Yongfei Peng</name></author><author><name>Hua Zhao</name></author><author><name>Xiangdong Fang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Malignant melanoma (MM) is a highly aggressive, metastatic cancer originating from melanocytes. These tumors have an extremely poor prognosis. MM accounts for 4% of skin cancers with an 80% mortality rate. The median survival of patients with metastatic melanoma is approximately six months, with a five-year survival rate of less than 10%. In recent years, the incidence of melanoma has gradually increased and has become one of the deadliest cancers. Competitive endogenous RNA (ceRNA) models the mechanism by which long chain non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs) play a regulatory role in the disease. LncRNAs can act as a sponge, competitively attracting small RNAs (micoRNAs; miRNAs) and interfering with miRNA function. This can affect the expression of target gene messenger RNAs (mRNAs), ultimately promoting tumorigenesis and tumor progression. Bioinformatics analysis may identify potentially prognostic and therapeutically-relevant differentially expressed genes in MM, as well as lncRNAs, miRNAs and mRNAs that are interconnected through the ceRNA network. This may provide further insight into gene regulation and the prognosis of metastatic melanoma. Weighted co-expression networks were used to identify lncRNA and mRNA modules associated with the metastatic phenotype, as well as the co-expression genes contained in the modules. We used 17 lncRNAs, six miRNAs, and 11 mRNAs to construct a ceRNA interaction network with a regulatory role in patients with metastatic melanoma. The prognostic risk model was used as a sorter to classify the survival prognosis of melanoma patients. Four groups of ceRNA interaction triplets were obtained, and miR-3662 may be used in the treatment of metastatic melanoma patients. Experiments confirmed the regulating relationship and phenotype of this assumption. This study provides new targets to regulate the metastatic process, predict metastatic potential and determine that miR-3662 may be used in the treatment of melanoma.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455638" rel="alternate" title="Construction of competing endogenous RNA interaction networks as prognostic markers in metastatic melanoma (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-08-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456067</id><title>Paramecium Polycomb Repressive Complex 2 physically interacts with the small RNA binding PIWI protein to repress transposable elements (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.857637+00:00</updated><author><name>Caridad Miró Pina</name></author><author><name>Takayuki Kawaguchi</name></author><author><name>Olivia Charmant</name></author><author><name>Audrey Michaud</name></author><author><name>Isadora Cohen</name></author><author><name>Adeline Humbert</name></author><author><name>Yan Jaszczyszyn</name></author><author><name>Laurence Del Maestro</name></author><author><name>Daniel Holoch</name></author><author><name>Slimane Ait-Si-Ali</name></author><author><name>Olivier Arnaiz</name></author><author><name>Raphaël Margueron</name></author><author><name>Sandra Duharcourt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Polycomb Repressive Complex 2 (PRC2) maintains transcriptionally silent genes in a repressed state via deposition of histone H3 K27 trimethyl (me3) marks. PRC2 has also been implicated in silencing transposable elements (TEs) yet how PRC2 is targeted to TEs remains unclear. To address this question, we performed tandem affinity purification combined with mass spectrometry and identified proteins that physically interact with the &lt;italic&gt;Paramecium&lt;/italic&gt; Enhancer-of-zeste Ezl1 enzyme, which catalyzes H3K9me3 and H3K27me3 deposition at TEs. We show that the &lt;italic&gt;Paramecium&lt;/italic&gt; PRC2 core complex comprises four subunits, each required &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; for catalytic activity. We also identify PRC2 cofactors, including the RNA interference (RNAi) effector Ptiwi09, which are necessary to target H3K9me3 and H3K27me3 to TEs. We find that the physical interaction between PRC2 and the RNAi pathway is mediated by a RING finger protein and that small RNA recruitment of PRC2 to TEs is analogous to the small RNA recruitment of H3K9 methylation SU(VAR)3-9 enzymes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456067" rel="alternate" title="Paramecium Polycomb Repressive Complex 2 physically interacts with the small RNA binding PIWI protein to repress transposable elements (6 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456046</id><title>Escaping from multiple visual threats: Modulation of escape responses in Pacific staghorn sculpin (Leptocottus armatus). (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.857837+00:00</updated><author><name>Hibiki Kimura</name></author><author><name>Tilo Pfalzgraff</name></author><author><name>Marie Levet</name></author><author><name>Yuuki Kawabata</name></author><author><name>John F Steffensen</name></author><author><name>Jacob L Johansen</name></author><author><name>Paolo Domenici</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fish perform rapid escape responses to avoid sudden predatory attacks. During escape responses, fish bend their bodies into a C-shape and quickly turn away from the predator and accelerate. The escape trajectory is determined by the initial turn (Stage 1) and a contralateral bend (Stage 2). Previous studies have used a single threat or model predator as a stimulus. In nature, however, multiple predators may attack from different directions simultaneously or in close succession. It is unknown whether fish are able to change the course of their escape response when startled by multiple stimuli at various time intervals. Pacific staghorn sculpin (&lt;italic&gt;Leptocottus armatus&lt;/italic&gt;) were startled with a left and right visual stimulus in close succession. By varying the timing of the second stimulus, we were able to determine when and how a second stimulus could affect the escape response direction. Four treatments were used: a single visual stimulus (control); or two stimuli coming from opposite sides separated by a 0 ms (simultaneous treatment); a 33 ms; or a 83 ms time interval. The 33 ms and 83 ms time intervals were chosen to occur shortly before and after a predicted 60 ms visual escape latency (i.e. during Stage 1). The 0 ms and 33 ms treatments influenced both the escape trajectory and the Stage 1 turning angle, compared to a single stimulation, whereas the 83 ms treatment had no effect on the escape response. We conclude that Pacific staghorn sculpin can modulate their escape response only between stimulation and the onset of the response, but that escape responses are ballistic after the body motion has started.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456046" rel="alternate" title="Escaping from multiple visual threats: Modulation of escape responses in Pacific staghorn sculpin (Leptocottus armatus). (6 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456130</id><title>Structurally distinct polymorphs of Tau aggregates revealed by nanoscale infrared spectroscopy (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.858003+00:00</updated><author><name>Siddhartha Banerjee</name></author><author><name>Ayanjeet Ghosh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aggregation of the tau protein plays a central role in several neurodegenerative diseases collectively known as tauopathies, including Alzheimers and Parkinsons disease. Tau misfolds into fibrillar beta sheet structures that constitute the paired helical filaments found in Neurofibrillary tangles. It is known that there can be significant structural heterogeneities in tau aggregates associated with different diseases. However, while structures of mature fibrils have been studied, the structural distributions in early stage tau aggregates is not well understood. In the present study, we use AFM-IR to investigate nanoscale spectra of individual tau fibrils at different stages of aggregation and demonstrate the presence of multiple fibrillar polymorphs that exhibit different secondary structures. We further show that mature fibrils contain significant amounts of antiparallel beta sheets. Our results are the very first application of nanoscale infrared spectroscopy to tau aggregates and underscore the promise of spatially resolved infrared spectroscopy for investigating protein aggregation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456130" rel="alternate" title="Structurally distinct polymorphs of Tau aggregates revealed by nanoscale infrared spectroscopy (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456082</id><title>Effect of A-tract-mediated linker histone orientation on trinucleosome compaction (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.858141+00:00</updated><author><name>Madhura De</name></author><author><name>Martin Wuertz</name></author><author><name>Gabriele Mueller</name></author><author><name>Katalin Toth</name></author><author><name>Rebecca C. Wade</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Linker histones (LH) have been shown to preferentially bind to AT-rich DNA, and specifically to A-tracts, contiguous stretches of adenines. Recently, using spFRET (single pair Foerster/Fluorescence Resonance Energy Transfer), we showed that the globular domain (gH) of Xenopus laevis H1.0b LH  orients towards A-tracts present on the linker-DNA (L-DNA) in LH:mononucleosome complexes. We investigated the impact of this A-tract mediated orientation of the gH on the compaction of higher-order structures by studying trinucleosomes as minimal models for chromatin. Two 600 bp DNA sequences were constructed containing three Widom 601 core sequences separated by about 40 bp linkers and A-tracts inserted on either the outer or the inner L-DNAs flanking the 1st and the 3rd Widom 601 sequences. The two inner L-DNAs were fluorescently labelled at their midpoints. Trinucleosomes were reconstituted using the doubly-labelled 600 bp DNA, core histone octamers and the full-length H1.0b LH. SpFRET was performed for a range of NaCl concentrations. While the LH compacted the trinucleosomes, surprisingly, the extent of compaction was similar for trinucleosomes with A-tracts either on the two outer or on the two inner L-DNAs. Modeling constrained by the FRET efficiency suggests that the trinucleosomes adopt a zig-zagged conformation with the 1st and 3rd nucleosomes stacked on top of each other. Even though we expect that the gH of neighbouring (1st and 3rd) LHs are oriented towards the A-tracts, our models suggest that they are not sufficiently close to dimerize and affect compaction. Thus, despite differences in A-tract placements, the LH compacts trinucleosomes similarly.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456082" rel="alternate" title="Effect of A-tract-mediated linker histone orientation on trinucleosome compaction (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455992</id><title>Experimental evidence that chronic outgroup conflict reduces reproductive success in a cooperatively breeding fish (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.858295+00:00</updated><author><name>Ines Braga Goncalves</name></author><author><name>Andrew N. Radford</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Conflicts with conspecific outsiders are common in group-living species, from ants to primates, and are argued to be an important selective force in social evolution. However, whilst an extensive empirical literature exists on the behaviour exhibited during and immediately after interactions with rivals, only very few observational studies have considered the cumulative fitness consequences of outgroup conflict. Using a cooperatively breeding fish, the daffodil cichlid (&lt;italic&gt;Neolamprologus pulcher&lt;/italic&gt;), we conducted the first experimental test of the effects of chronic outgroup conflict on reproductive investment and output. ‘Intruded’ groups received long-term simulated territorial intrusions by neighbours that generated consistent group-defence behaviour; matched ‘Control’ groups (each the same size and with the same neighbours as an Intruded group) received no intrusions in the same period. Intruded groups had longer inter-clutch intervals and produced eggs with less protein than Control groups. Despite this lower egg investment, Intruded groups provided more parental care, achieving similar hatching success to Control groups. Ultimately, however, Intruded groups had fewer and smaller surviving offspring than Control groups at 1-month post-hatching. We therefore provide experimental evidence that outgroup conflict can decrease fitness via cumulative effects on reproductive success, confirming the selective potential of this empirically neglected aspect of sociality.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455992" rel="alternate" title="Experimental evidence that chronic outgroup conflict reduces reproductive success in a cooperatively breeding fish (5 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456166</id><title>Autoimmune Alleles at the Major Histocompatibility Locus Modify Melanoma Susceptibility (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.858432+00:00</updated><author><name>James Talwar</name></author><author><name>David Laub</name></author><author><name>Meghana Pagadala</name></author><author><name>Andrea Castro</name></author><author><name>McKenna Lewis</name></author><author><name>Georg E. Luebeck</name></author><author><name>Gerald P. Morris</name></author><author><name>Rany M. Salem</name></author><author><name>Wesley K. Thompson</name></author><author><name>Kit Curtius</name></author><author><name>Maurizio Zanetti</name></author><author><name>Hannah Carter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Autoimmunity and cancer represent two different aspects of immune dysfunction. Autoimmunity is characterized by breakdowns in immune self-tolerance, while impaired immune surveillance can allow for tumorigenesis. The class I major histocompatibility complex (MHC-I), which displays derivatives of the cellular peptidome for immune surveillance by CD8+ T cells, serves as a common genetic link between these conditions. As melanoma-specific CD8+ T-cells have been shown to target melanocyte-specific peptide antigens more often than melanoma-specific antigens, we investigated whether vitiligo and psoriasis predisposing MHC-I alleles conferred a melanoma protective effect. In individuals with cutaneous melanoma from both The Cancer Genome Atlas (N = 451) and an independent validation cohort (N = 586), MHC-I autoimmune allele carriers are significantly associated with a later age of melanoma diagnosis. MHC-I autoimmune allele contributions to melanoma risk are not captured by current polygenic risk scores (PRS) and incorporation of autoimmune MHC allele presence can improve relative risk stratification. Mechanisms of autoimmune protection were neither associated with improved melanoma-driver mutation association nor improved gene-level conserved antigen presentation relative to common alleles (population frequency &amp;gt; 1%). However, autoimmune alleles showed a marked affinity relative to common alleles for particular windows of melanocyte conserved antigens suggesting a potential relationship between antigen processing, binding, and cell-surface presentation. Overall, this study presents evidence that MHC-I autoimmune risk alleles modulate melanoma risk currently unaccounted for by current PRS.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456166" rel="alternate" title="Autoimmune Alleles at the Major Histocompatibility Locus Modify Melanoma Susceptibility (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456159</id><title>How big should this object be? Perceptual influences on viewing-size preferences (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.858625+00:00</updated><author><name>Yi-Chia Chen</name></author><author><name>Arturo Deza</name></author><author><name>Talia Konkle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;When viewing objects depicted in a frame, observers prefer to view large objects like cars in larger sizes and smaller objects like cups in smaller sizes. That is, the visual size of an object that "looks best" is linked to its typical physical size in the world. Why is this the case? One intuitive possibility is that these preferences are driven by semantic knowledge: For example, when we recognize a sofa, we access our knowledge about its real-world size, and this influences what size we prefer to view the sofa within a frame. However, might visual processing play a role in this phenomenon--that is, do visual features that are related to big and small objects look better at big and small visual sizes, respectively, even when observers do not have explicit access to semantic knowledge about the objects? To test this possibility, we used "texform" images, which are synthesized versions of recognizable objects, which critically retain local perceptual texture and coarse form information, but are no longer explicitly recognizable. To test for visual size preferences, we used a two-interval forced choice task, in which each texform was presented at the preferred visual size of its corresponding original image, and a visual size slightly bigger or smaller. Observers consistently selected the texform presented at the canonical visual size as the more aesthetically pleasing one. These results suggest that the preferred visual size of an object depends not only on explicit knowledge of its real-world size, but also can be evoked by mid-level visual features that systematically covary with an object's real-world size.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456159" rel="alternate" title="How big should this object be? Perceptual influences on viewing-size preferences (4 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455610</id><title>The role of viscoelasticity in long-time cell rearrangement (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.858770+00:00</updated><author><name>Ivana Pajic-Lijakovic</name></author><author><name>Milan Milivojevic</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Although collective cell migration (CCM) is a highly coordinated and ordered migratory mode, perturbations in the form of mechanical waves appear even in 2D. These perturbations caused by the viscoelastic nature of cell rearrangement are involved in various biological processes, such as embryogenesis, wound healing and cancer invasion. The mechanical waves, as a product of the active turbulence occurred at low Reynolds number, represent an oscillatory change in cell velocity and the relevant rheological parameters. The velocity oscillations, in the form of forward and backward flows, are driven by: viscoelastic force, surface tension force, and traction force. The viscoelastic force represents a consequence of inhomogeneous distribution of cell residual stress accumulated during CCM. This cause-consequence relation is considered on a model system such as the cell monolayer free expansion. The collision of forward and backward flows causes an increase in cell packing density which has a feedback impact on the tissue viscoelasticity and on that base influences the tissue stiffness. The evidence of how the tissue stiffness is changed near the cell jamming is conflicting. To fill this gap, we discussed the density driven change in the tissue viscoelasticity by accounting for the cell pseudo-phase transition from active (contractile) to passive (non-contractile) state appeared near cell jamming in the rheological modeling consideration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455610" rel="alternate" title="The role of viscoelasticity in long-time cell rearrangement (4 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-08-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456133</id><title>A B cell actomyosin arc network couples integrin co-stimulation to mechanical force-dependent immune synapse formation (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.858908+00:00</updated><author><name>Jia C Wang</name></author><author><name>Yang-In Yim</name></author><author><name>Xufeng Wu</name></author><author><name>Valentin Jaumouillé</name></author><author><name>Clare M Waterman</name></author><author><name>John H Kehrl</name></author><author><name>John A Hammer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;B-cell activation and immune synapse (IS) formation with membrane-bound antigens are actin-dependent processes that scale positively with the strength of antigen-induced signals. Importantly, ligating the B-cell integrin, LFA-1, with ICAM-1 promotes IS formation when antigen is limiting. Whether the actin cytoskeleton plays a specific role in integrin-dependent IS formation is unknown. Here we show using super-resolution imaging of primary B cells that LFA-1: ICAM-1 interactions promote the formation of an actomyosin network that dominates the B-cell IS. This network is created by the formin mDia1, organized into concentric, contractile arcs by myosin 2A, and flows inward at the same rate as B-cell receptor (BCR): antigen clusters. Consistently, individual BCR microclusters are swept inward by individual actomyosin arcs. Under conditions where integrin is required for synapse formation, inhibiting myosin impairs synapse formation, as evidenced by reduced antigen centralization, diminished BCR signaling, and defective signaling protein distribution at the synapse. Together, these results argue that a contractile actomyosin arc network plays a key role in the mechanism by which LFA-1 co-stimulation promotes B-cell activation and IS formation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456133" rel="alternate" title="A B cell actomyosin arc network couples integrin co-stimulation to mechanical force-dependent immune synapse formation (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455816</id><title>Light-sheet photonic force optical coherence elastography for high-throughput quantitative 3D micromechanical imaging (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.859072+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuechuan Lin</name></author><author><name>Nichaluk Leartprapun</name></author><author><name>Justin C. Luo</name></author><author><name>Steven G. Adie</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microscale mechanical properties of the extracellular matrix (ECM) and dynamic cell-ECM interactions play an important role in physiological processes and disease. However, it remains a challenge for current mechanical characterization methods to combine quantitative 3D imaging of ECM mechanics with cellular-scale resolution and dynamic monitoring of cell-mediated changes to pericellular viscoelasticity. Here, we present light-sheet photonic force optical coherence elastography (LS-pfOCE) to address these challenges by leveraging a light-sheet for parallelized, non-invasive, and localized mechanical loading. We demonstrate the capabilities of LS-pfOCE by imaging the micromechanical heterogeneity of fibrous 3D collagen matrices and perform a live-cell study to image micromechanical heterogeneity induced by NIH-3T3 cells seeded in 3D fibrin constructs. We also show that LS-pfOCE is able to quantify temporal variations in pericellular viscoelasticity in response to altered cellular activity. By providing access to the spatiotemporal variations in the micromechanical properties of 3D complex biopolymer constructs and engineered cellular systems, LS-pfOCE has the potential to drive new discoveries in the rapidly growing field of mechanobiology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455816" rel="alternate" title="Light-sheet photonic force optical coherence elastography for high-throughput quantitative 3D micromechanical imaging (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455991</id><title>Cancer cell hyper-proliferation disrupts the topological invariance of epithelial monolayers (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.859220+00:00</updated><author><name>Daria S. Roshal</name></author><author><name>Marianne Martin</name></author><author><name>Kirill Fedorenko</name></author><author><name>Virginie MOLLE</name></author><author><name>Stephen Baghdiguian</name></author><author><name>Sergey B. Rochal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Although the polygonal shape of epithelial cells has drawn the attention of scientists for several centuries, only recently, it has been demonstrated that distributions of polygon types (DOPTs) are similar in proliferative epithelia of many different plant and animal species. In this study we show that hyper-proliferation of cancer cells disrupts this universality paradigm and results in random epithelial structures. Examining non-synchronized and synchronized HeLa cervix cells, we suppose that the cell size spread is the single parameter controlling the DOPT in these monolayers. We test this hypothesis by considering morphologically similar random polygonal packings. By analyzing the differences between tumoral and non-tumoral epithelial monolayers, we uncover that the latter have more ordered structures and argue that the relaxation of mechanical stresses associated with cell division induces more effective ordering in the epithelia with lower proliferation rates. The proposed theory also explains the specific highly ordered structures of some post-mitotic unconventional epithelia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455991" rel="alternate" title="Cancer cell hyper-proliferation disrupts the topological invariance of epithelial monolayers (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456231</id><title>Across functional boundaries: making non-neutralizing antibodies to neutralize HIV-1 and mediate Fc-mediated effector killing of infected cells (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.859378+00:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Richard</name></author><author><name>Dung Nguyen</name></author><author><name>William D. Tolbert</name></author><author><name>Romain Gasser</name></author><author><name>shilei ding</name></author><author><name>Dani Vezina</name></author><author><name>Shang Yu Gong</name></author><author><name>Jeremie Prevost</name></author><author><name>Gabrielle Gendron-Lepage</name></author><author><name>Halima Medjahed</name></author><author><name>Suneetha Gottumukkala</name></author><author><name>Andres Finzi</name></author><author><name>Marzena Pazgier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In HIV-1 infection, many antibodies (Abs) are elicited to Envelope (Env) epitopes that are conformationally masked in the native trimer and are only available for antibody recognition after the trimer binds host cell CD4. Among these are epitopes within the Co-Receptor Binding Site (CoRBS) and the constant region 1 and 2 (C1-C2 or Cluster A region). In particular, C1-C2 epitopes map to the gp120 face interacting with gp41 in the native, closed Env trimer present on HIV-1 virions or expressed on HIV-1 infected cells. Antibodies targeting this region are therefore non-neutralizing and their potential as mediators of antibody depended cellular cytoxicity (ADCC) of HIV-1 infected cells diminished by a lack of available binding targets.  Here we present the design of Ab-CD4 chimeric proteins that consist of the Ab-IgG1 of a CoRBS or Cluster A specificity to the extracellular domain 1 and 2 of human CD4. Our Ab-CD4 hybrids induce potent ADCC against infected primary CD4+ T cells and neutralize tier 1 and 2 HIV-1 viruses. Furthermore, competition binding experiments reveal that the observed biological activities rely on both the antibody and CD4 moieties confirming their cooperativity in triggering conformational rearrangements of Env. Our data indicate the utility of these Ab-CD4 hybrids as antibody therapeutics effective in eliminating HIV-1 through the combined mechanisms of neutralization and ADCC. This is also the first report of single-chain-Ab-based molecules capable of opening closed Env trimers on HIV-1 particles/infected cells to expose the Cluster A region and activate ADCC and neutralization against these non-neutralizing targets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456231" rel="alternate" title="Across functional boundaries: making non-neutralizing antibodies to neutralize HIV-1 and mediate Fc-mediated effector killing of infected cells (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455895</id><title>Performance of Core Genome Multilocus Sequence Typing Compared to Capillary-Electrophoresis PCR Ribotyping and SNP Analysis of Clostridioides difficile (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.859578+00:00</updated><author><name>A Baktash</name></author><author><name>J Corver</name></author><author><name>C Harmanus</name></author><author><name>WK Smits</name></author><author><name>W Fawley</name></author><author><name>MH Wilcox</name></author><author><name>N Kumar</name></author><author><name>DW Eyre</name></author><author><name>A Indra</name></author><author><name>A Mellmann</name></author><author><name>EJ Kuijper</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Clostridioides difficile&lt;/italic&gt; is the most common cause of antibiotic-associated gastrointestinal infections. Capillary-electrophoresis (CE)-PCR ribotyping is currently the gold standard for &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; typing but lacks discriminatory power to study transmission and outbreaks in detail. New molecular methods have the capacity to differentiate better, but backward compatibility with CE-PCR ribotyping must be assessed. Using a well-characterized collection of diverse strains (N=630; 100 unique ribotypes [RTs]), we aimed to investigate PCR ribotyping prediction from core genome multilocus sequence typing (cgMLST). Additionally, we compared the discriminatory power of cgMLST (SeqSphere &amp;amp; EnteroBase) and whole genome MLST (wgMLST) (EnteroBase) with single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) analysis). A unique cgMLST profile (&amp;gt;6 allele differences) was observed in 82/100 ribotypes, indicating sufficient backward compatibility. Intra-RT allele difference varied per ribotype and MLST clade. Application of cg/wgMLST and SNP analysis in two outbreak settings with ribotypes RT078 and RT181 (known with a low intra-ribotype allele difference) showed no distinction between outbreak- and non-outbreak strains, in contrast to wgMLST and SNP analysis. We conclude that cgMLST has the potential to be an alternative to CE-PCR ribotyping. The method is reproducible, easy to standardize and offers higher discrimination. However, in some ribotype complexes adjusted cut-off thresholds and epidemiological data are necessary to recognize outbreaks. We propose to decrease the current threshold of 6 to 3 alleles to better identify outbreaks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455895" rel="alternate" title="Performance of Core Genome Multilocus Sequence Typing Compared to Capillary-Electrophoresis PCR Ribotyping and SNP Analysis of Clostridioides difficile (4 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455931</id><title>DNAJB1-PRKACA in HEK293T cells induces LINC00473 overexpression that depends on PKA signaling (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.859765+00:00</updated><author><name>Stephanie S. Kim</name></author><author><name>Ina Kycia</name></author><author><name>Michael Karski</name></author><author><name>Rosanna K. Ma</name></author><author><name>Evan A. Bordt</name></author><author><name>Julian Kwan</name></author><author><name>Anju Karki</name></author><author><name>Elle Winter</name></author><author><name>Ranan G. Aktas</name></author><author><name>Yuxuan Wu</name></author><author><name>Andrew Emili</name></author><author><name>Daniel E. Bauer</name></author><author><name>Praveen Sethupathy</name></author><author><name>Khashayar Vakili</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fibrolamellar carcinoma (FLC) is a primary liver cancer that most commonly arises in adolescents and young adults in a background of normal liver tissue and has an poor prognosis due to lack of effective chemotherapeutic agents. The &lt;italic&gt;DNAJB1-PRKACA&lt;/italic&gt; gene fusion (DP) has been reported in the majority of FLC tumors, however its oncogenic mechanisms remain unclear. Given the paucity of cellular models, in particular FLC tumor cell lines, we hypothesized that engineering the DP fusion gene in HEK293T cells would provide insight into the cellular effects of the fusion gene. We used CRISPR/Cas9 to engineer HEK293T clones expressing DP fusion gene (HEK-DP) and performed transcriptomic, proteomic, and mitochondrial studies to characterize this cellular model. Proteomic analysis of DP interacting partners identified mitochondrial proteins as well as proteins in other subcellular compartments. HEK-DP cells demonstrated significantly elevated mitochondrial fission, which suggests a role for DP in altering mitochondrial dynamics. Transcriptomic analysis of HEK-DP cells revealed a significant increase in &lt;italic&gt;LINC00473&lt;/italic&gt; expression, similar to what has been observed in primary FLC samples. &lt;italic&gt;LINC00473&lt;/italic&gt; overexpression was reversible with siRNA targeting of &lt;italic&gt;PRKACA&lt;/italic&gt; as well as pharmacologic targeting of PKA and Hsp40 in HEK-DP cells. Therefore, our model suggests that &lt;italic&gt;LINC00473&lt;/italic&gt; is a candidate marker for DP activity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455931" rel="alternate" title="DNAJB1-PRKACA in HEK293T cells induces LINC00473 overexpression that depends on PKA signaling (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455957</id><title>NSUN6, an RNA methyltransferase of 5-mC controls glioblastoma response to Temozolomide (TMZ) via NELFB and RPS6KB2 interaction (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.860015+00:00</updated><author><name>Chidiebere U Awah</name></author><author><name>Jan Winter</name></author><author><name>Claudiane M Mazdoom</name></author><author><name>Olorunseun O. Ogunwobi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nop2/Sun RNA methyltransferase (NSUN6) is an RNA 5 - methyl cytosine (5mC) transferase with little information known of its function in cancer and response to cancer therapy. Here, we show that NSUN6 methylates both large and small RNA in glioblastoma and controls glioblastoma response to temozolomide with or without influence of the MGMT promoter status, with high NSUN6 expression conferring survival benefit to glioblastoma patients and in other cancers. Mechanistically, our results show that NSUN6 controls response to TMZ therapy via 5mC mediated regulation of NELFB and RPS6BK2. Taken together, we present evidence that show that NSUN6 mediated 5mC deposition regulates transcriptional pause (by accumulation of NELFB and the general transcription factor complexes (POLR2A, TBP, TFIIA, TFIIE) on the preinitiation complex at TATA binding site to control translation machinery in glioblastoma response to alkylating agents. Our findings open a new frontier into controlling of transcriptional regulation by RNA methyltransferase and 5mC.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455957" rel="alternate" title="NSUN6, an RNA methyltransferase of 5-mC controls glioblastoma response to Temozolomide (TMZ) via NELFB and RPS6KB2 interaction (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456108</id><title>Identification and validation of E3 ubiquitin ligase XIAP as a novel substrate of deubiquitinase USP7 (HAUSP) - Implication towards oncogenesis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.860169+00:00</updated><author><name>Gouranga Saha</name></author><author><name>Sibani Sarkar</name></author><author><name>Partha S Mohanta</name></author><author><name>Krishna Kumar</name></author><author><name>Saikat Chakraborty</name></author><author><name>Mrinal K Ghosh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The induction of apoptosis upon USP7 (HAUSP) inhibition is established in cancers that contain a wild-type p53 (p53&lt;sup&gt;Wt&lt;/sup&gt;) through the ‘USP7-Mdm2-p53’ axis, but no clear explanation has yet been reported for the same to occur in cancers containing mutant 53 (p53&lt;sup&gt;Mut&lt;/sup&gt;) or even p53 null (p53&lt;sup&gt;Null&lt;/sup&gt;) systems. Instead of this ‘USP7-Mdm2-p53’ axis USP7 also works through an alternative new pathway identified in this study. Here in this study, we observed that the magnitude of apoptosis induction in response to USP7 inhibition was remarkably similar between cancer cells showing p53&lt;sup&gt;Null&lt;/sup&gt; or p53&lt;sup&gt;Mut&lt;/sup&gt; and those with p53&lt;sup&gt;Wt&lt;/sup&gt;. Through a proteomics-based approach, we were able to identify XIAP as a novel interacting partner for USP7. XIAP is a potent and well-characterized member of the inhibitor of apoptosis proteins (IAPs), which function through caspase inhibition. We successfully identified USP7 as a positive regulator of XIAP at post-translational but not at its transcriptional level. Using molecular modelling coupled with domain deletion studies, we show that the first three Ubl domains in association with the catalytic domain of USP7 interact with the BIR2 and the linker region between BIR2 and BIR3 domains of XIAP. Modulation of expression and catalytic activity of USP7 in multiple type of cancer cell lines showed that USP7 stabilizes XIAP through its deubiquitinase activity. We have also observed that USP7 sensitizes cells against chemotherapeutic drugs through stabilization of XIAP. Thus, USP7 promotes tumorigenesis in multiple cancers, &lt;italic&gt;via&lt;/italic&gt; stabilization of XIAP that results in apoptosis inhibition in caspase dependent pathway. Moreover, we observed that combinatorial inhibition of USP7 and XIAP can induce cellular apoptosis in a higher magnitude than their individual inhibition. Additionally, our results indicates that nanoformulated P5091 and P22077 showed higher potency for killing C6 cells in comparison to normal drugs. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first report on identification and validation of XIAP, a crucial E3 ubiquitin ligase, as a novel substrate of the deubiquitinase USP7 and they together involve in empowerment of the tumorigenic potential of cancer cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456108" rel="alternate" title="Identification and validation of E3 ubiquitin ligase XIAP as a novel substrate of deubiquitinase USP7 (HAUSP) - Implication towards oncogenesis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455932</id><title>SATB1 undergoes isoform-specific phase transitions in T cells (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.860331+00:00</updated><author><name>Tomas Zelenka</name></author><author><name>Petros Tzerpos</name></author><author><name>George Panagopoulos</name></author><author><name>Konstantinos C. Tsolis</name></author><author><name>Dionysios-Alexandros Papamatheakis</name></author><author><name>Vassilis M. Papadakis</name></author><author><name>David Stanek</name></author><author><name>Charalampos Spilianakis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Intracellular space is demarcated into functional membraneless organelles and nuclear bodies via the process of phase separation. Phase transitions are involved in many functions linked to such bodies as well as in gene expression regulation and other cellular processes. In this work we describe how the genome organizer SATB1 utilizes its prion-like domains to undergo phase transitions. We have identified two SATB1 isoforms with distinct biophysical behavior and showed how phosphorylation and interaction with nuclear RNA, impact their phase transitions. Moreover, we show that SATB1 is associated with transcription and splicing, both of which evinced deregulation in &lt;italic&gt;Satb1&lt;/italic&gt; knockout mice. Thus, the tight regulation of different SATB1 isoforms levels and their post-translational modifications are imperative for SATB1’s physiological roles in T cell development while their deregulation may be linked to disorders such as cancer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455932" rel="alternate" title="SATB1 undergoes isoform-specific phase transitions in T cells (4 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456060</id><title>The cell surface hyaluronidase TMEM2 plays an essential role in mouse neural crest cell development and survival (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.860504+00:00</updated><author><name>Toshihiro Inubushi</name></author><author><name>Yuichiro Nakanishi</name></author><author><name>Makoto Abe</name></author><author><name>Yoshifumi Takahata</name></author><author><name>Riko Nishimura</name></author><author><name>Hiroshi Kurosaka</name></author><author><name>Fumitoshi Irie</name></author><author><name>Takashi Yamashiro</name></author><author><name>Yu Yamaguchi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neural crest cells (NCCs) are a migratory population that gives rise to a diverse cell lineage, including the craniofacial complex, the peripheral nervous system, and a part of the heart. Hyaluronan (HA) is a major component of the extracellular matrix, and its tissue levels are dynamically regulated in during development. Although the synthesis of HA has been shown to exert substantial influence on embryonic morphogenesis, the functional importance of the catabolic side of HA turnover is poorly understood. Here, we demonstrate that the transmembrane hyaluronidase TMEM2 plays an essential role in NCC development and the morphogenesis of their derivatives. &lt;italic&gt;Wnt1-Cre&lt;/italic&gt;–mediated &lt;italic&gt;Tmem2&lt;/italic&gt; knockout (&lt;italic&gt;Tmem2&lt;sup&gt;CKO&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt;) mice exhibit severe craniofacial and cardiovascular abnormalities. Analysis of &lt;italic&gt;Tmem2&lt;/italic&gt; expression using &lt;italic&gt;Tmem2&lt;/italic&gt; knock-in reporter mice reveals that &lt;italic&gt;Tmem2&lt;/italic&gt; is expressed at the site of NCC delamination in the neural tube and in Sox9-positive emigrating NCCs, suggesting that &lt;italic&gt;Tmem2&lt;/italic&gt; is critical for NCC development. Consistent with this possibility, linage tracing analysis reveals that the contribution of &lt;italic&gt;Wnt1-Cre&lt;/italic&gt;–labeled cells to NCC derivatives is significantly reduced in a &lt;italic&gt;Tmem2&lt;/italic&gt;-deficient background. Moreover, the emigration of NCCs from the neural tube is greatly reduced in &lt;italic&gt;Tmem2&lt;sup&gt;CKO&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice. &lt;italic&gt;In vitro&lt;/italic&gt; assays demonstrate that &lt;italic&gt;Tmem2&lt;/italic&gt; expression is essential for the ability of mouse O9-1 NCCs to form focal adhesion on and migrate into HA-containing substrates. &lt;italic&gt;Tmem2&lt;sup&gt;CKO&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice also exhibit increased apoptotic cell death in NCC-derived tissues. Collectively, our data demonstrate that &lt;italic&gt;Tmem2&lt;/italic&gt; is essential for normal development of NCC-derivatives, including the craniofacial complex, and that TMEM2-mediated HA degradation allows NCCs to generate a tissue environment suitable for efficient focal adhesion assembly and migration. This study reveals the hitherto unrecognized functional importance of the catabolic side of HA metabolism in embryonic development and highlights the pivotal role of &lt;italic&gt;Tmem2&lt;/italic&gt; in the process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The functional significance of hyaluronan (HA) in embryonic developmental processes has been demonstrated by studies using genetic manipulation of HA synthesis. However, the expression of HA is regulated not only by its synthesis, but also by its degradation. This issue is of particular importance due to the extremely rapid metabolic turnover of HA. Curiously, mice with mutations/ablations of known hyaluronidase molecules, such as the lysosomal hyaluronidases HYAL1 and HYAL2, exhibit little embryonic phenotypes. This suggests the existence of yet another hyaluronidase molecule that plays a key role in regulating extracellular HA balance in developing tissues. In this context, transmembrane protein 2 (TMEM2) is a novel hyaluronidase that functions on the cell surface. Here, we demonstrate that TMEM2 is expressed at the site of neural crest development and in neural crest cell (NSC)-derived craniofacial tissue, and that NCC-targeted &lt;italic&gt;Tmem2&lt;/italic&gt; conditional knockout mice develop severe craniofacial defects, which attests to a requirement for TMEM2-mediated extracellular HA degradation in neural crest development. Our &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; analyses on the underlying mechanisms of the phenotype demonstrate that TMEM2 is essential for generating a tissue environment suitable for efficient focal adhesion formation by NCCs. This paper reveals for the first time that the catabolic machinery for HA exerts a specific regulatory role in embryonic morphogenesis, and that its dysregulation of HA degradation leads to severe developmental defects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456060" rel="alternate" title="The cell surface hyaluronidase TMEM2 plays an essential role in mouse neural crest cell development and survival (3 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456129</id><title>Loss of the extracellular matrix protein DIG-1 causes glial fragmentation, dendrite breakage, and dendrite extension defects (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.860681+00:00</updated><author><name>Megan K. Chong</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth R. Cebul</name></author><author><name>Karolina Mizeracka</name></author><author><name>Maxwell G. Heiman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The extracellular matrix (ECM) guides and constrains the shape of the nervous system. In &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt;, DIG-1 is a giant ECM component that is required for fasciculation of sensory dendrites during development and for maintenance of axon positions throughout life. We identified four novel alleles of &lt;italic&gt;dig-1&lt;/italic&gt; in three independent screens for mutants affecting disparate aspects of neuronal and glial morphogenesis. First, we find that disruption of DIG-1 causes fragmentation of the amphid sheath glial cell in larvae and young adults. Second, it causes severing of the BAG sensory dendrite from its terminus at the nose tip, apparently due to breakage of the dendrite as animals reach adulthood. Third, it causes embryonic defects in dendrite fasciculation in inner labial (IL2) sensory neurons, as previously reported, as well as rare defects in IL2 dendrite extension that are enhanced by loss of the apical ECM component DYF-7, suggesting that apical and basolateral ECM contribute separately to dendrite extension. Our results highlight novel roles for DIG-1 in maintaining the cellular integrity of neurons and glia, possibly by creating a barrier between structures in the nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456129" rel="alternate" title="Loss of the extracellular matrix protein DIG-1 causes glial fragmentation, dendrite breakage, and dendrite extension defects (3 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456119</id><title>Ecdysone exerts biphasic control of regenerative signaling, coordinating the completion of regeneration with developmental progression (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.860833+00:00</updated><author><name>Faith Karanja</name></author><author><name>Subhshri Sahu</name></author><author><name>Sara Weintraub</name></author><author><name>Rajan Bhandari</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Jaszczak</name></author><author><name>Jason Sitt</name></author><author><name>Adrian Halme</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt;, loss of regenerative capacity in wing imaginal discs coincides with an increase in systemic levels of the steroid hormone ecdysone, a key coordinator of their developmental progression. Regenerating discs release the relaxin hormone Dilp8, which limits ecdysone synthesis and extends the regenerative period. Here, we describe how regenerating tissues produce a biphasic response to ecdysone levels: lower concentrations of ecdysone promote local and systemic regenerative signaling, whereas higher concentrations suppress regeneration through the expression of broad splice isoforms. Ecdysone also promotes the expression of Wingless during both regeneration and normal development through a distinct regulatory pathway. This dual role for ecdysone explains how regeneration can still be completed successfully in dilp8-mutant larvae: higher ecdysone levels increase the regenerative activity of tissues, allowing regeneration to reach completion in a shorter time. From these observations, we propose that ecdysone hormone signaling functions to coordinate regeneration with developmental progression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456119" rel="alternate" title="Ecdysone exerts biphasic control of regenerative signaling, coordinating the completion of regeneration with developmental progression (3 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456206</id><title>“Playing mysterious”: occurrence of Bio-duck calls in Brazil reveals a complex acoustic behaviour for the Antarctic minke whale (Balaenoptera bonaerensis) (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.861000+00:00</updated><author><name>Marcos Rossi-Santos</name></author><author><name>Diego Filun</name></author><author><name>William Soares-Filho</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Paro</name></author><author><name>Leonardo Wedekin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Acoustic methods can provide important data on the occurrence and distribution of migratory species. Information about Antarctic Minke whale (Balaenoptera bonaerensis) occurrence in the winter breeding grounds is scarce, mostly limited to old records from whaling stations before 1960’s international moratory, such as Costinha Station in Northeastern Brazil (6° S / 34° W). This work describes the occurrence of the Antarctic minke whale (AMW) through Bio-duck acoustic detections in the Santos Basin, South-Southeastern Brazil (22º and 28º S / 42º and 48º W), registered between November 12 and December 19, 2015. AMW calls were detected for 12 days. We detected and classified 9 different Bio-duck calls in Brazilian coast waters, evidencing a high diverse acoustic behaviour for the minke whale breeding ground. This is the first study to describe the acoustic diversity of AMW vocalizations in lower latitudes, constituting important information to the conservation and management of cetaceans and their habitat. Therefore, our study presents the foremost acoustic evidence of the Antarctic minke whale in Brazil, utilizing high technological passive acoustic methods, such as autonomous underwater vehicle (SeaGlider) sampling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456206" rel="alternate" title="“Playing mysterious”: occurrence of Bio-duck calls in Brazil reveals a complex acoustic behaviour for the Antarctic minke whale (Balaenoptera bonaerensis) (3 tweets)"/><category term="Animal Behavior and Cognition"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455914</id><title>The Microtubule Associated Protein Tau Regulates KIF1A Pausing Behavior and Motility (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.861156+00:00</updated><author><name>DV Lessard</name></author><author><name>CL Berger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many neurodegenerative diseases result from dysfunction of axonal transport, a highly regulated cellular process responsible for site-specific neuronal cargo delivery. The kinesin-3 family member KIF1A is a key mediator of this process by facilitating long-distance cargo delivery in a spatiotemporally regulated manner. While misregulation of KIF1A cargo delivery is observed in many neurodegenerative diseases, the regulatory mechanisms responsible for KIF1A cargo transport are largely unexplored. Our lab has recently characterized a mechanism for a unique pausing behavior of KIF1A in between processive segments on the microtubule. This behavior, mediated through an interaction between the KIF1A K-loop and the polyglutamylated C-terminal tails of tubulin, helps us further understand how KIF1A conducts long-range cargo transport. However, how this pausing behavior is influenced by other regulatory factors on the microtubule is an unexplored concept. The microtubule associated protein Tau is one potential regulator, as altered Tau function is a pathological marker in many neurodegenerative diseases. However, while the effect of Tau on kinesin-1 and -2 has been extensively characterized, its role in regulating KIF1A transport is greatly unexplored at the behavioral level. Using single-molecule imaging, we have identified Tau-mediated regulation of KIF1A pausing behavior and motility. Specifically, our findings imply a competitive interaction between Tau and KIF1A for the C-terminal tails of tubulin. We introduce a new mechanism of Tau-mediated kinesin regulation by inhibiting the ability of KIF1A to use C-terminal tail reliant pauses to connect multiple processive segments into a longer run length. Moreover, we have correlated this regulatory mechanism to the behavioral dynamics of Tau, further elucidating the function of Tau diffusive and static behavioral state on the microtubule surface. In summary, we introduce a new mechanism of Tau-mediated motility regulation, providing insight on how disruptions in axonal transport can lead to disease state pathology.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SIGNIFICANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;KIF1A mediated cargo transport is essential in many cellular processes such as axonal transport and neuronal development. Defects in KIF1A transport have been implicated in neurodegenerative diseases including Alzheimer’s disease and frontotemporal dementia. However, the mechanism of KIF1A’s pathological misregulation remains elusive, highlighting the importance of identifying regulators of KIF1A function. The microtubule associated protein Tau is an attractive potential regulator of KIF1A motility as Tau dysfunction is a hallmark of these neurodegenerative diseases. Here, we demonstrate a direct connection between Tau and KIF1A motility, revealing a unique form of Tau-mediated regulation of axonal transport. Our results provide a molecular foundation for understanding the role of motor protein misregulation in neurodegenerative disease progression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455914" rel="alternate" title="The Microtubule Associated Protein Tau Regulates KIF1A Pausing Behavior and Motility (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455964</id><title>Role of YAP in early ectodermal specification and a Huntington’s Disease model of human neurulation (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.861294+00:00</updated><author><name>Francesco M. Piccolo</name></author><author><name>Nathaniel R. Kastan</name></author><author><name>Tomomi Haremaki</name></author><author><name>Qingyun Tian</name></author><author><name>Tiago L. Laundos</name></author><author><name>Riccardo De Santis</name></author><author><name>Thomas S. Carroll</name></author><author><name>Ji-Dung Luo</name></author><author><name>Ksenia Gnedeva</name></author><author><name>Fred Etoc</name></author><author><name>A. J. Hudspeth</name></author><author><name>Ali H. Brivanlou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Hippo pathway, a highly conserved signaling cascade that functions as an integrator of molecular signals and biophysical states, ultimately impinges upon the transcription coactivator Yes-associated protein 1 (YAP). Hippo-YAP signaling has been shown to play key roles both at the early embryonic stages of implantation and gastrulation, and later during neurogenesis. To explore YAP’s potential role in neurulation, we used self-organizing neuruloids grown from human embryonic stem cells on micropatterned substrates. We identified YAP activation as a key lineage determinant, first between neuronal ectoderm and non-neuronal ectoderm, and later between epidermis and neural crest, indicating that YAP activity can enhance the effect of BMP4 stimulation and therefore affect ectodermal specification at this developmental stage. Because aberrant Hippo-YAP signaling has been implicated in the pathology of Huntington’s Disease (HD), we used isogenic mutant neuruloids to explore the relationship between signaling and the disease. We found that HD neuruloids demonstrate ectopic activation of gene targets of YAP and that pharmacological reduction of YAP’s transcriptional activity can partially rescue the HD phenotype.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455964" rel="alternate" title="Role of YAP in early ectodermal specification and a Huntington’s Disease model of human neurulation (3 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455976</id><title>A temporally controlled sequence of X-chromosome
inactivation and reactivation defines female mouse in vitro germ cells with meiotic potential (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.861510+00:00</updated><author><name>Jacqueline Severino</name></author><author><name>Moritz Bauer</name></author><author><name>Tom Mattimoe</name></author><author><name>Niccolo Arecco</name></author><author><name>Luca Cozzuto</name></author><author><name>Patricia Lorden</name></author><author><name>Norio Hamada</name></author><author><name>Yoshiaki Nosaka</name></author><author><name>So Nagaoka</name></author><author><name>Holger Heyn</name></author><author><name>Katsuhiko Hayashi</name></author><author><name>Mitinori Saitou</name></author><author><name>Bernhard Payer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The early mammalian germ cell lineage is characterized by extensive epigenetic reprogramming, which is required for the maturation into functional eggs and sperm. In particular, the epigenome needs to be reset before parental marks can be established and then transmitted to the next generation. In the female germ line, reactivation of the inactive X chromosome is one of the most prominent epigenetic reprogramming events, and despite its scale involving an entire chromosome affecting hundreds of genes, very little is known about its kinetics and biological function.
Here we investigate X-chromosome inactivation and reactivation dynamics by employing a tailor-made &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; system to visualize the X-status during differentiation of primordial germ cell-like cells (PGCLCs) from female mouse embryonic stem cells (ESCs). We find that the degree of X-inactivation in PGCLCs is moderate when compared to somatic cells and characterized by a large number of genes escaping full inactivation. Nevertheless, PGCLCs that fail to undergo X-inactivation show an abnormal gene expression signature and deficiencies in meiotic entry. Subsequent to X-inactivation we observe gradual step-wise X-reactivation, which is mostly completed by the end of meiotic prophase I. Cells deviating from these progressive kinetics and undergoing X-reactivation too rapidly fail to enter a meiotic trajectory. Our data reveals that a fine-tuned X-inactivation and -reactivation cycle is a critical feature of female germ cell developmental competence towards meiosis and oogenesis&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455976" rel="alternate" title="A temporally controlled sequence of X-chromosome&#10;inactivation and reactivation defines female mouse in vitro germ cells with meiotic potential (3 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456223</id><title>Ras/MAPK signalling intensity defines subclonal fitness in a mouse model of primary and metastatic hepatocellular carcinoma (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.861716+00:00</updated><author><name>Anthony Lozano</name></author><author><name>Francois-Regis Souche</name></author><author><name>Christel Ramirez</name></author><author><name>Serena Vegna</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Desandre</name></author><author><name>Anais Riviere</name></author><author><name>Valerie Dardalhon</name></author><author><name>Amal Zine El Aabidine</name></author><author><name>Philippe Fort</name></author><author><name>Leila Akkari</name></author><author><name>Urszula Hibner</name></author><author><name>Damien Gregoire</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Quantitative differences in signal transduction are to date an understudied feature of tumour heterogeneity. The MAPK Erk pathway, which is activated in a large proportion of human tumours, is a prototypic example of distinct cell fates being driven by signal intensity. We have used primary hepatocyte precursors transformed with different dosages of an oncogenic form of Ras to model subclonal variations in MAPK signalling. Orthotopic allografts of Ras-transformed cells in immunocompromised mice gave rise to fast-growing aggressive tumours, both at the primary location and in the peritoneal cavity. Fluorescent labelling of cells expressing different oncogene levels, and consequently varying levels of MAPK Erk activation, highlighted the selection processes operating at the two sites of tumour growth. Indeed, significantly higher Ras expression was observed in primary as compared to metastatic tumours, despite the evolutionary trade-off of increased apoptotic death in the liver that correlated with high Ras dosage. Analysis of the immune tumoral microenvironment at the two locations suggests that fast metastatic growth in the immunocompromised setting is abrogated in immunocompetent animals due to efficient antigen presentation by peritoneal dendritic cells. Furthermore, our data indicate that, in contrast to the metastatic outgrowth,  strong MAPK signalling is required in the primary liver tumours to resist elimination by NK cells. Overall, this study describes a quantitative aspect of tumour heterogeneity and highlights potential vulnerability of a subtype of hepatocellular carcinoma as a function of MAPK Erk signalling intensity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456223" rel="alternate" title="Ras/MAPK signalling intensity defines subclonal fitness in a mouse model of primary and metastatic hepatocellular carcinoma (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>