<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.070343+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.468552</id><title>Proteolysis Targeting Chimeras With Reduced Off-targets (35 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.070659+00:00</updated><author><name>Tuan M Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Arghya Deb</name></author><author><name>Praveen Kokkonda</name></author><author><name>Vedagopuram Sreekanth</name></author><author><name>Praveen K Tiwari</name></author><author><name>Veronika M Shoba</name></author><author><name>Sophia Lai</name></author><author><name>Santosh K Chaudhary</name></author><author><name>Jaron A.M. Mercer</name></author><author><name>Max Jan</name></author><author><name>David R Liu</name></author><author><name>Benjamin L Ebert</name></author><author><name>Amit Choudhary</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Proteolysis Targeting Chimeras (PROTACs), a class of heterobifunctional molecules that recruit target proteins to E3 ligases, have gained traction for targeted protein degradation. However, pomalidomide, a widely used E3 ligase recruiter in PROTACs, can independently degrade other targets, such as zinc-finger (ZF) proteins, that hold key functions in normal development and disease progression. This off-target degradation of pomalidomide-based PROTACs raises concerns about their therapeutic applicability and long-term side effects. Therefore, there is a crucial need to develop rules for PROTAC design that minimize off-target degradation. In this study, we developed a high-throughput platform that interrogates the off-target degradation of ZF domains and discovered, using this platform, that PROTACs with the current design paradigm induce significant degradation of several ZF proteins. To identify new rules for PROTAC design, we generated a rationalized library of pomalidomide analogs with distinct exit vector modifications on the C4 and C5 positions of the phthalimide ring and profiled their propensities for ZF protein degradation. We found that modifications on the C5 position with nucleophilic aromatic substitution (S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;Ar) reduce off-target ZF degradation. We applied our newfound design principles on a previously developed ALK oncoprotein-targeting PROTAC and generated PROTACs with enhanced potency and minimal off-target degradation. We envision the reported off-target profiling platform and pomalidomide analogs will find utility in the design of specific PROTACs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.468552" rel="alternate" title="Proteolysis Targeting Chimeras With Reduced Off-targets (35 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469020</id><title>Effects of crude oil on juvenile threespine stickleback somatic and immune development (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.070951+00:00</updated><author><name>Kelly S Ireland</name></author><author><name>Kathryn Milligan-Myhre</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aquatic oil spills have resounding effects on surrounding ecosystems, and thus significant resources are committed to oil spill responses to remove the oil from the environment as quickly as possible. Oil has immunotoxic effects and may be particularly harmful to larval and juvenile fish as it can cause a number of developmental defects and stunt growth. In spite of significant efforts to clean oil, it is unclear whether larval and juvenile fish can recover from the effects of oil and no work has been done on the effect crude oil has on developing threespine stickleback (Gasterosteus aculeatus) fish. Threespine stickleback are a ubiquitous sentinel species in the northern hemisphere and are an important food source for many larger, economically valuable fish. As fish with fully marine, anadromous, and freshwater populations, stickleback are exposed to oil in a variety of aquatic environments. We hypothesized that oil exposure would suppress both growth and immunity of developing stickleback, but that fish health could be recovered by removal of the crude oil. Fish were exposed to Alaska North Slope crude oil and then were moved to water without crude oil for two weeks (depuration).  Measurements of growth and immunity were taken before and after the depuration. We found that crude oil effected different developmental pathways independently, significantly impacting some but not others. This is the first study to examine the effect crude oil has on early stages of stickleback development, and that stickleback fish are unable to recover from exposure after being transferred to clean water for two-weeks, suggesting larval/juvenile stickleback exposed to crude oil need longer than two-weeks to recover if they are able to recover at all.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469020" rel="alternate" title="Effects of crude oil on juvenile threespine stickleback somatic and immune development (20 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469435</id><title>Biomechanics of aging and osteoarthritic human knee ligaments (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.071089+00:00</updated><author><name>Abby E Peters</name></author><author><name>Brendan Geraghty</name></author><author><name>Karl T Bates</name></author><author><name>Riaz Akhtar</name></author><author><name>Rosti Readioff</name></author><author><name>Eithne Comerford</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background. Ligaments work to stabilize the human knee joint and prevent excessive movement. Whilst ligaments are known to decline in structure and function with aging, there has been no systematic effort to study changes in gross mechanical properties in the four major human knee ligaments due to osteoarthritis (OA). This study aims to collate material properties for the anterior (ACL) and posterior (PCL) cruciate ligaments, medial (MCL) and lateral (LCL) collateral ligaments. Our cadaveric samples come from a diverse demographic from which the effects of aging and OA on bone and cartilage material properties have already been quantified. Therefore, by combining our previous bone and cartilage data with the new ligament data from this study we are facilitating subject-specific whole-joint modelling studies.

Methods. The demographics of the collected cadaveric knee joints were diverse with age range between 31 to 88 years old, and OA International Cartilage Repair Society grade 0 to 4. Twelve cadaveric human knee joints were dissected, and bone-ligament-bone specimens were extracted for mechanical loading to failure. Ligament material properties were determined from the load-extension curves, namely: linear and ultimate (failure) stress and strain, secant modulus, tangent modulus, and stiffness.

Results. There were significant negative correlations between age and ACL linear force (p=0.01), stress (p=0.03) and extension (p=0.05), ACL failure force (p=0.02), stress (p=0.02) and extension (p=0.02), PCL secant (p=0.02) and tangent (p=0.02) modulus, and LCL stiffness (p=0.05). Significant negative correlations were also found between OA grades and ACL linear force (p=0.05), stress (p=0.02), extension (p=0.01) and strain (p=0.03), and LCL failure stress (p=0.05). However, changes in age or OA grade did not show a statistically significant correlation with the MCL tensile parameters. Trends showed that almost all the tensile parameters of the ACL and PCLs decreased with increasing age and progression of OA. Due to small sample size, the combined effect of age and presence of OA could not be statistically derived.

Conclusions. This research is the first to correlate changes in tensile properties of the four major human knee ligaments to aging and OA. The current ligament study when combined with our previous findings on bone and cartilage for the same twelve knee cadavers, supports conceptualization of OA as a whole-joint disease that impairs the integrity of many peri-articular tissues within the knee. The subject-specific data pool consisting of the material properties of the four major knee ligaments, subchondral and trabecular bones and articular cartilage will aid reconstruction and graft replacements and advance knee joint finite element models, whilst knowledge of aged or diseased mechanics may direct future therapeutic interventions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469435" rel="alternate" title="Biomechanics of aging and osteoarthritic human knee ligaments (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469120</id><title>Genotyping strategies for detecting CRISPR mutations in polyploid species: a case study-based approach in hexaploid wheat (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.071242+00:00</updated><author><name>Ajay Gupta</name></author><author><name>Wanlong Li</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;As a versatile tool for genome engineering, CRISPR-Cas9 has been revolutionizing the field of molecular biology, biotechnology, and crop improvement. By precisely targeting pre-selected genomic sites, CRISPR-Cas9 primarily induces insertions or deletions (indels) of variable size. Despite the significant advance in the technology per se, detecting these indels is the major and difficult part of the CRISPR program in polyploid species, like wheat, with relatively low mutation rates. A plethora of methods are available for detecting mutations, but no method is perfect for all mutation types. In this case study, we demonstrated a new, protocol for capturing length polymorphism from small indels using a nested PCR approach. This new method is tractable, efficient, and cost-effective in detecting and genotyping indels &amp;gt;3-bp. We also discussed the major genotyping platforms used in our wheat CRISPR projects, such as mismatch cleavage assay, restriction enzyme assay, ribonucleoprotein assay, and Sanger sequencing, for their advantages and pitfalls in wheat CRISPR mutation detection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469120" rel="alternate" title="Genotyping strategies for detecting CRISPR mutations in polyploid species: a case study-based approach in hexaploid wheat (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.468631</id><title>High diversity of pimpline parasitoid wasps (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Pimplinae) from the lowermost Eocene Fur Formation (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.071367+00:00</updated><author><name>Seraina Klopfstein</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;With an estimated 100,000 extant species, Darwin wasps (Ichneumonidae) are more specious than all vertebrates together. However, only 288 fossil species have been described to date, with hundreds more awaiting formal description in palaeontological collections. One of the largest gaps in our knowledge concerns the ~12 million years between the K-PG mass extinction and the late Ypresian, from which only two species have been formally described, including Pimpla stigmatica Henriksen from the Danish Fur Formation (~55 Ma). Ie here redescribe and reclassify this species in the genus Epitheronia Gupta, n. comb., and describe nine new species from this fossil locality that are consistent with a placement in Pimplinae: Crusopimpla collina n. sp., C. elongata n. sp., C. minuta n. sp., C. rettigi n. sp., C. violina n. sp., Theronia? furensis n. sp.,  T. nigriscutum n. sp., Xanthopimpla ciboisae n. sp., and X. crescendae n. sp. The diagnosis of the genus Crusopimpla Kopylov, Spasojevic &amp;amp; Klopfstein is amend in the light of the new species. By comparing the preserved colouration between and within specimens of different species, we draw conclusions about the taxonomic usefulness of colour patterns observed in Fur Formation ichneumonids. The number of described species of pimpline parasitoid wasps from Fur is very high when compared to any other fossil deposit, but low with respect to numbers of extant species. Further study and excavation of Fur ichneumonids will certainly reveal an even higher diversity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.468631" rel="alternate" title="High diversity of pimpline parasitoid wasps (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Pimplinae) from the lowermost Eocene Fur Formation (4 tweets)"/><category term="Paleontology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469179</id><title>evSeq: Cost-Effective Amplicon Sequencing of Every Variant in a Protein Library (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.071483+00:00</updated><author><name>Bruce J. Wittmann</name></author><author><name>Kadina E. Johnston</name></author><author><name>Patrick J. Almhjell</name></author><author><name>Frances H. Arnold</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Widespread availability of protein sequence-fitness data would revolutionize both our biochemical understanding of proteins and our ability to engineer them. Unfortunately, even though thousands of protein variants are generated and evaluated for fitness during a typical protein engineering campaign, most are never sequenced, leaving a wealth of potential sequence-fitness information untapped. This largely stems from the fact that sequencing is unnecessary for many protein engineering strategies; the added cost and effort of sequencing is thus unjustified. Here, we present every variant sequencing (evSeq), an efficient protocol for sequencing a variable region within every variant gene produced during a protein engineering campaign at a cost of cents per variant. Execution of evSeq is simple, requires no sequencing experience to perform, relies only on resources and services typically available to biology labs, and slots neatly into existing protein engineering workflows. Analysis of evSeq data is likewise made simple by its accompanying software (found at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/fhalab/evSeq"&gt;github.com/fhalab/evSeq&lt;/ext-link&gt;, documentation at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://fhalab.github.io/evSeq"&gt;fhalab.github.io/evSeq&lt;/ext-link&gt;), which can be run on a personal laptop and was designed to be accessible to users with no computational experience. Low-cost and easy to use, evSeq makes collection of extensive protein variant sequence-fitness data practical.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469179" rel="alternate" title="evSeq: Cost-Effective Amplicon Sequencing of Every Variant in a Protein Library (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469250</id><title>Preclinical and Toxicology Studies of BRD5529, a Selective Inhibitor of CARD9 (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.071617+00:00</updated><author><name>Theodore Kottom</name></author><author><name>Kyle Schaefbauer</name></author><author><name>Eva M Carmona</name></author><author><name>Joanne E Yi</name></author><author><name>Andrew Limper</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Exuberant inflammation during Pneumocystis pneumonia leads to lung injury. CARD9 is a central mediator of inflammatory signaling mediated by C-type lectin receptors. CARD9 inhibitor BRD5529 has been shown to be an effective in vitro inhibitor of Pneumocystis Beta-glucan-induced proinflammatory signaling and downstream TNF-alpha production, suggesting its viability as a candidate for preliminary drug testing as an anti-inflammatory agent in the rodent Pneumocystis pneumonia model (PCP).
Methods: To assess for potential toxicity, mice were injected intraperitoneally (IP) daily either with vehicle or BRD5529 at 0.1 mg/kg or 1.0 mg/kg for two weeks. Mouse weights were taken daily. At day 14, mice were euthanized, weighed, and analyzed by flexiVent for lung stiffness. Lungs, liver, and kidney were then harvested for H&amp;amp;E staining and pathology scoring. Lung samples were further analyzed for proinflammatory cytokines via ELISA and extracellular matrix generation via quantitative PCR (q-PCR). Blood collection postmortem was performed for blood chemistry analysis.
Results: BRD5529 at both doses of IP administration resulted in no significant changes in daily or final weight gain. Analysis of lung stiffness by flexiVent showed no significant differences between the control or treated groups. Furthermore, ELISA results for proinflammatory IL-1 Beta, IL-6, and TNF-alpha showed no major differences in the respective groups. qPCR analysis of extracellular matrix transcripts collagen type I, alpha 1 (Col1a1) and fibronectin (Fn) were statically similar as well in the treated and control groups. Examination and pathology scoring of H&amp;amp;E slides from lung, liver, and kidney from the each of the mice in all groups and subsequent pathology scoring showed no significant change. Blood chemistry analysis revealed similar, non-significant patterns.
Conclusions: BRD5529 in our initial general safety and toxicology assessments displayed no inherent safety concerns in the analyzed parameters. These data support broader in vivo testing of the inhibitor as a timed adjunct therapy to the deleterious proinflammatory host immune response often associated with anti-Pneumocystis therapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469250" rel="alternate" title="Preclinical and Toxicology Studies of BRD5529, a Selective Inhibitor of CARD9 (4 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.468912</id><title>Validity of freehand three-dimensional ultrasound system in measurement of three-dimensional surface shape of shoulder muscles (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.071756+00:00</updated><author><name>Jun Umehara</name></author><author><name>Norio Fukuda</name></author><author><name>Shoji Konda</name></author><author><name>Masaya Hirashima</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Accurate measurement of muscle morphology is crucial for assessing skeletal muscle capacity. Although the freehand three-dimensional ultrasound (3DUS) system is a promising technique for assessing muscle morphology, its accuracy has been validated mainly in terms of volume by examining lower limb muscles. The purpose of this study was to validate 3DUS in the measurements of 3D surface shape and volume by comparing them with MRI measurements while ensuring the reproducibility of participant posture by focusing on the shoulder muscles. The supraspinatus, infraspinatus, and posterior deltoid muscles of 10 healthy males were scanned using 3DUS and MRI while secured by an immobilization support customized for each participant. A 3D surface model of each muscle was created from the 3DUS and MRI methods, and the agreement between them was assessed. For the muscle volume, the mean difference between the two models was within 0.51 cm&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; for all muscles. For the surface shape, the distances between the closest points of the two models was calculated for every point on the 3DUS surface model. The results showed that the median (third quartile) of the distances was less than 1.21 mm (1.89 mm) for all muscles. These results suggest that, given the above error is permitted, 3DUS can be used as an alternative to MRI in measuring volume and surface shape, even for the shoulder muscles.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.468912" rel="alternate" title="Validity of freehand three-dimensional ultrasound system in measurement of three-dimensional surface shape of shoulder muscles (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469268</id><title>A Comparison Study between Autism Spectrum Disorder and Typically Control in Graph Frequency Bands Using Graph and Triadic Interaction Metrics (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.071889+00:00</updated><author><name>Alireza Talesh Jafadideh</name></author><author><name>Babak Mohammadzadeh Asl</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many researchers using many different approaches have attempted to find features discriminating between autism spectrum disorder (ASD) and typically control (TC) subjects. In this study, this attempt has been continued by analyzing global metrics of functional graphs and metrics of functional triadic interactions of the brain in the low, middle, and high-frequency bands (LFB, MFB, and HFB) of the structural graph. The graph signal processing (GSP) provided the combinatorial usage of the functional graph of resting-state fMRI and structural graph of DTI. In comparison to TCs, ASDs had significantly higher clustering coefficients in the MFB, higher efficiencies and strengths in the MFB and HFB, and lower small-world propensity in the HFB. These results show over-connectivity, more global integration, and probably decreased local specialization in ASDs compared to TCs. Triadic analysis showed that the numbers of unbalanced triads were significantly lower for ASDs in the MFB. This finding may show the reason for restricted and repetitive behavior in ASDs. Also, in the MFB and HFB, the numbers of balanced triads and the energies of triadic interactions were significantly higher and lower for ASDs, respectively. These findings may reflect the disruption of the optimum balance between functional integration and specialization. All of these results demonstrated that the significant differences between ASDs and TCs existed in the MFB and HFB of the structural graph when analyzing the global metrics of the functional graph and triadic interaction metrics. In conclusion, the results demonstrate the promising perspective of GSP for attaining discriminative features and new knowledge, especially in the case of ASD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469268" rel="alternate" title="A Comparison Study between Autism Spectrum Disorder and Typically Control in Graph Frequency Bands Using Graph and Triadic Interaction Metrics (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>