<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.499623+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466210</id><title>Selective inhibition of PfATP6 by artemisinins and identification of new classes of inhibitors after expression in yeast (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.500391+00:00</updated><author><name>Catherine M. Moore</name></author><author><name>Jigang Wang</name></author><author><name>Qingsong Lin</name></author><author><name>Pedro Ferreira</name></author><author><name>Mitchell A. Avery</name></author><author><name>Khaled Elokely</name></author><author><name>Henry M. Staines</name></author><author><name>Sanjeev Krishna</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Treatment failures with artemisinin combination therapies (ACTs) threaten global efforts to eradicate malaria. They highlight the importance of identifying drug targets and new inhibitors and of studying how existing antimalarial classes work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Herein we report the successful development of an heterologous expression-based compound screening tool. Validated drug target &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; calcium ATPase6 (PfATP6) and a mammalian ortholog (SERCA1a) were functionally expressed in yeast providing a robust, sensitive, and specific screening tool. Whole-cell and &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; assays consistently demonstrated inhibition and labelling of PfATP6 by artemisinins. Mutations in PfATP6 resulted in fitness costs that were ameliorated in the presence of artemisinin derivatives when studied in the yeast model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As previously hypothesised, PfATP6 is a target of artemisinins. Mammalian SERCA1a can be mutated to become more susceptible to artemisinins. The inexpensive, low technology yeast screening platform has identified unrelated classes of druggable PfATP6 inhibitors. Resistance to artemisinins may depend on mechanisms that can concomitantly address multi-targeting by artemisinins and fitness costs of mutations that reduce artemisinin susceptibility.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466210" rel="alternate" title="Selective inhibition of PfATP6 by artemisinins and identification of new classes of inhibitors after expression in yeast (8 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466240</id><title>FITTING OF HYPERELASTIC CONSTITUTIVE MODELS IN DIFFERENT SHEEP HEART REGIONS BASED ON BIAXIAL MECHANICAL PROPERTIES (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.501556+00:00</updated><author><name>Fulufhelo Nemavhola</name></author><author><name>Thanyani Pandelani</name></author><author><name>Harry Ngwangwa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Heart failure remains one of the leading causes of death especially among people over the age of 60 years worldwide. To develop effective therapy and suitable replacement materials for the heart muscle it is necessary to understand its biomechanical behaviour under load. This paper investigates the passive mechanical response of the sheep myocardia excised from three different regions of the heart. Due to the relatively higher cost and huge ethical demands in acquisition and testing of real animal heart models, this paper evaluates the fitting performances of five different constitutive models on the myocardial tissue responses. Ten sheep were sacrificed, and their hearts excised and transported within 3h to the testing biomechanical laboratory. The upper sections of the hearts above the short axes were carefully dissected out. Tissues were dissected from the mid-sections of the left ventricle, mid-wall and right ventricle for each heart. The epicardia and endocardia were then carefully sliced off each tissue to leave the myocardia. Stress-strain curves were calculated, filtered and resampled. The results show that Choi-Vito model was found to provide the best fit to the LV, the polynomial (Anisotropic) model to RV, the Four-Fiber Family model to RV, Holzapfel (2000) to RV, Holzapfel (2005) to RV and the Fung model to LV.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466240" rel="alternate" title="FITTING OF HYPERELASTIC CONSTITUTIVE MODELS IN DIFFERENT SHEEP HEART REGIONS BASED ON BIAXIAL MECHANICAL PROPERTIES (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466295</id><title>Repeated exposure to chlorpyrifos is associated with a dose-dependent chronic neurobehavioral deficit in adult rats (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.502109+00:00</updated><author><name>Ana CR Ribeiro</name></author><author><name>Elisa H Hawkins</name></author><author><name>Fay M Jahr</name></author><author><name>Joseph L McClay</name></author><author><name>Laxmikant S Deshpande</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Organophosphate (OP) chemicals include commonly used pesticides and also chemical warfare agents, and mechanistically they are potent inhibitors of the cholinesterase (ChE) enzyme. While a chronic low-dose OP exposure does not produce acute cholinergic crises, epidemiological studies report long-term neuropsychiatric issues including depression and cognitive impairments in OP-exposed individuals. Chlorpyrifos (CPF) is one of the most widely used pesticides worldwide. Multiple laboratory studies have reported on either the long-term behavioral effect of a single, high-dose CPF or studied sub-chronic behavioral effects particularly the motor and cognitive effects of repeated low-dose CPF exposure. However, studies on chronic mood and depression-related morbidities following repeated sub-threshold CPF doses that would mimic occupationally-relevant OP exposures are lacking. Here, adult male rats were injected with CPF (1, 3, 5, or 10 mg/kg/d, s.c.) for 21-days. Dependent on the CPF dose, ChE activity was inhibited approximately 60-80% in the blood and about 20-50% in the hippocampus at 2-days after the end of CPF exposures. Following an 11-week washout period, CPF-treated rats exhibited a dose-dependent increase in signs of anhedonia (sucrose preference test), anxiety (open-field and elevated plus-maze), and despair (forced swim test) despite a complete recovery of ChE activity at this stage. We speculate that both cholinergic and non-cholinergic mechanisms could play a role in the development of chronic OP-related depressive outcomes. The proposed CPF exposure paradigm could provide an ideal model to further study molecular mechanisms underlying cause and effect relationships between environmental OP exposures and the development of chronic behavioral deficits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466295" rel="alternate" title="Repeated exposure to chlorpyrifos is associated with a dose-dependent chronic neurobehavioral deficit in adult rats (3 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>