<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.517229+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471190</id><title>High School Science Fair: Ethnicity Trends in Student Participation and Experience (35 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.517434+00:00</updated><author><name>Frederick Grinnell</name></author><author><name>Simon Dalley</name></author><author><name>Joan Reisch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we report ethnicity trends in student participation and experience in high school science and engineering fairs (science fairs). Science fair participation showed significant ethnic diversity. For survey students, the approximate distribution was Asian-32%; Black-11%; Hispanic-20%; White-33%; Other-3%. Black students made up only 4.5% of the students who participated in science fairs beyond the school-only level, whereas students from other ethnic groups were more equally represented. The lower percentage of Black students resulted from a combination of lower science fair participation and lower percentage of students advancing to science fairs beyond the school-only level. Students who advanced to science fairs beyond the school-only level frequently received help from scientists, coaching for the interview, and were not required to participate in science fair. Black students received the least help from scientists and were most likely to be required to do science fair. They also were most likely to receive no help from parents, teachers, or scientists. Asian and Hispanic students (63.8% and 56.8%) indicated greater interest in careers in science and engineering (S&amp;amp;E) compared to Black and White students (43.7% &amp;amp; 50.7%). In addition to career interest, the most important experiences that correlated with students indicating that science fair increased their interests in S&amp;amp;E were getting help from the internet and/or books and magazines; getting help fine tuning the report; and overcoming obstacles by doing more background research, making a timeline, and perseverance. Black students did not report a positive effect of any of these strategies but experienced time pressure as more of an obstacle than did other students. Our findings identify a wide range of student experiences associated with positive science fair outcomes that could be enhanced for all students but especially Black students. More involvement of scientists in helping science fair students would be particularly valuable.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471190" rel="alternate" title="High School Science Fair: Ethnicity Trends in Student Participation and Experience (35 tweets)"/><category term="Scientific Communication and Education"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.470764</id><title>EpyNN: Educational python for Neural Networks (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.517588+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Malard</name></author><author><name>Laura Danner</name></author><author><name>Emilie Rouzies</name></author><author><name>Jesse G Meyer</name></author><author><name>Ewen Lescop</name></author><author><name>Stéphanie Olivier-Van Stichelen</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Artificial Neural Networks (ANNs) have achieved unequaled performance for numerous problems in many areas of Science, Business, Public Policy, and more. While experts are familiar with performance-oriented software and underlying theory, ANNs are difficult to comprehend for non-experts because it requires skills in programming, background in mathematics and knowledge of terminology and concepts. In this work, we release EpyNN, an educational python resource meant for a public willing to understand key concepts and practical implementation of scalable ANN architectures from concise, homogeneous and idiomatic source code. EpyNN contains an educational Application Programming Interface (API), educational workflows from data preparation to ANN training and a documentation website setting side-by-side code, mathematics, graphical representation and text to facilitate learning and provide teaching material. Overall, EpyNN provides basics for python-fluent individuals who wish to learn, teach or develop from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;EpyNN documentation is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://epynn.net"&gt;https://epynn.net&lt;/ext-link&gt; and repository can be retrieved from &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/synthaze/epynn"&gt;https://github.com/synthaze/epynn&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contact&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stéphanie Olivier-Van-Stichelen, &lt;email&gt;solivier@mcw.edu&lt;/email&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Supplementary Information&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supplementary files and listings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.470764" rel="alternate" title="EpyNN: Educational python for Neural Networks (31 tweets)"/><category term="Scientific Communication and Education"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471663</id><title>A predictive microfluidic model of human glioblastoma to assess trafficking of blood-brain barrier penetrant nanoparticles (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.517735+00:00</updated><author><name>Joelle P. Straehla</name></author><author><name>Cynthia Hajal</name></author><author><name>Hannah C. Safford</name></author><author><name>Giovanni S. Offeddu</name></author><author><name>Natalie Boehnke</name></author><author><name>Tamara G. Dacoba</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey Wyckoff</name></author><author><name>Roger D. Kamm</name></author><author><name>Paula T. Hammond</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The blood-brain barrier represents a significant challenge for the treatment of high-grade gliomas, and our understanding of drug transport across this critical biointerface remains limited. To advance preclinical therapeutic development for gliomas, there is an urgent need for predictive &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; models with realistic blood-brain barrier vasculature. Here, we report a vascularized human glioblastoma (GBM) model in a microfluidic device that accurately recapitulates brain tumor vasculature with self-assembled endothelial cells, astrocytes, and pericytes to investigate the transport of targeted nanotherapeutics across the blood-brain barrier and into GBM cells. Using modular layer-by-layer assembly, we functionalized the surface of nanoparticles with GBM-targeting motifs to improve trafficking to tumors. We directly compared nanoparticle transport in our &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; platform with transport across mouse brain capillaries using intravital imaging, validating the ability of the platform to model &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; blood-brain barrier transport. We investigated the therapeutic potential of functionalized nanoparticles by encapsulating cisplatin and showed improved efficacy of these GBM-targeted nanoparticles both &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and in an &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; orthotopic xenograft model. Our vascularized GBM model represents a significant biomaterials advance, enabling in-depth investigation of brain tumor vasculature and accelerating the development of targeted nanotherapeutics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The blood-brain barrier represents a major therapeutic challenge for the treatment of glioblastoma, and there is an unmet need for &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; models that recapitulate human biology and are predictive of &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; response. Here we present a new microfluidic model of vascularized glioblastoma featuring a tumor spheroid in direct contact with self-assembled vascular networks comprised of human endothelial cells, astrocytes, and pericytes. This model was designed to accelerate the development of targeted nanotherapeutics, and enabled rigorous assessment of a panel of surface-functionalized nanoparticles designed to exploit a receptor overexpressed in tumor-associated vasculature. Trafficking and efficacy data in the &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; model compared favorably to parallel &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; data, highlighting the utility of the vascularized glioblastoma model for therapeutic development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471663" rel="alternate" title="A predictive microfluidic model of human glioblastoma to assess trafficking of blood-brain barrier penetrant nanoparticles (12 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471790</id><title>Functional modulation of PTH1R activation and signalling by RAMP2 (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.517907+00:00</updated><author><name>Katarina Nemec</name></author><author><name>Hannes Schihada</name></author><author><name>Gunnar Kleinau</name></author><author><name>Ulrike Zabel</name></author><author><name>Eugene O. Grushevskyi</name></author><author><name>Patrick Scheerer</name></author><author><name>Martin J. Lohse</name></author><author><name>Isabella Maiellaro</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Receptor-activity-modifying proteins (RAMPs) are ubiquitously expressed membrane proteins that associate with different G protein-coupled receptors (GPCRs) including the parathyroid hormone 1 receptor (PTH1R), a class B GPCR, and an important modulator of mineral ion homeostasis and bone metabolism. However, it is unknown whether and how RAMP proteins may affect PTH1R function. Using different optical biosensors to measure the activation of PTH1R and its downstream signalling, we describe here that RAMP2 acts as a specific allosteric modulator of PTH1R, shifting PTH1R to a unique pre-activated state that permits faster activation in a ligand-specific manner. Moreover, RAMP2 modulates PTH1R downstream signalling in an agonist-dependent manner, most notably increasing the PTH-mediated Gi3 signalling sensitivity. Additionally, RAMP2 increases both PTH- and PTHrP-triggered β-arrestin2 recruitment to PTH1R. Employing homology modelling we describe the putative structural molecular basis underlying our functional findings. These data uncover a critical role of RAMPs in the activation and signalling of a GPCR that may provide a new venue for highly specific modulation of GPCR function and advanced drug design.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471790" rel="alternate" title="Functional modulation of PTH1R activation and signalling by RAMP2 (12 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.470803</id><title>Imaging-Guided Bioreactor for De-Epithelialization and Long-Term Cultivation of Ex Vivo Rat Trachea (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.518066+00:00</updated><author><name>Seyed Mohammad Mir</name></author><author><name>Jiawen Chen</name></author><author><name>Meghan R. Pinezich</name></author><author><name>John D. O’Neill</name></author><author><name>Sarah X.L. Huang</name></author><author><name>Gordana Vunjak-Novakovic</name></author><author><name>Jinho Kim</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent synergistic advances in organ-on-chip and tissue engineering technologies offer opportunities to create &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;-grown tissue or organ constructs that can faithfully recapitulate their &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; counterparts. Such &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; tissue or organ constructs can be utilized in multiple applications, including rapid drug screening, high-fidelity disease modeling, and precision medicine. Here, we report an imaging-guided bioreactor that allows &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; monitoring of the lumen of &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; airway tissues during controlled &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; tissue manipulation and cultivation of isolated rat trachea. Using this platform, we demonstrated selective removal of the rat tracheal epithelium (i.e., de-epithelialization) without disrupting the underlying subepithelial cells and extracellular matrix. Through different tissue evaluation assays, such as immunofluorescent staining, DNA/protein quantification, and electron beam microscopy, we showed that the epithelium of the tracheal lumen can be effectively removed with negligible disruption in the underlying tissue layers, such as cartilage and blood vessel. Notably, using a custom-built micro-optical imaging device integrated with the bioreactor, the trachea lumen was visualized at the cellular level in real time, and removal of the endogenous epithelium and distribution of locally delivered exogenous cells were demonstrated &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt;. Moreover, the de-epithelialized trachea supported on the bioreactor allowed attachment and growth of exogenous cells seeded topically on its denuded tissue surface. Collectively, the results suggest that our imaging-enabled rat trachea bioreactor and selective cell replacement method can facilitate creating of bioengineered &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; airway tissue that can be used in different biomedical applications.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.470803" rel="alternate" title="Imaging-Guided Bioreactor for De-Epithelialization and Long-Term Cultivation of Ex Vivo Rat Trachea (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471279</id><title>Fast off-rate CD229 chimeric antigen receptor T cells efficiently target multiple myeloma, spare T cells, and exhibit reduced trogocytosis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.518209+00:00</updated><author><name>Erica R. Vander Mause</name></author><author><name>Jillian M. Baker</name></author><author><name>Sabarinath V. Radhakrishnan</name></author><author><name>Patricia Davis</name></author><author><name>Jens Panse</name></author><author><name>James E. Marvin</name></author><author><name>Michael L. Olson</name></author><author><name>Mary Steinbach</name></author><author><name>David P. Ng</name></author><author><name>Carol S. Lim</name></author><author><name>Djordje Atanackovic</name></author><author><name>Tim Luetkens</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;T cells expressing chimeric antigen receptors have shown remarkable therapeutic activity against different types of cancer. However, their wider use has been hampered by the potential for life-threatening toxicities due to the unintended targeting of healthy cells expressing low levels of the targeted antigen. We have now developed an affinity-tuning approach for the generation of minimally modified, low-affinity antibody variants derived from existing high-affinity antibodies. Using this approach, we engineered low affinity variants of the fully human CD229-specific antibody 2D3. Parental 2D3 originally efficiently targeted multiple myeloma cells but also healthy T cells expressing low levels of CD229. We demonstrate that CAR T cells based on a low affinity variant of 2D3 maintain the parental antibody’s anti-tumor activity, but lack its targeting of healthy T cells. In addition, variant CD229 CAR T cells show reduced trogocytosis potentially augmenting CAR T cell persistence. The fast off-rate CAR produced using our affinity tuning approach eliminates a key liability of CD229 CAR T cells and paves the way for the effective and safe treatment of patients with multiple myeloma.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Affinity tuning approach yields low affinity CD229 CAR binding domain maintaining the parental clone’s anti-tumor activity while eliminating killing of healthy T cells, increasing CAR T cell expansion, and decreasing trogocytosis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471279" rel="alternate" title="Fast off-rate CD229 chimeric antigen receptor T cells efficiently target multiple myeloma, spare T cells, and exhibit reduced trogocytosis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471211</id><title>Modeling implanted metals in electrical stimulation applications (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.518378+00:00</updated><author><name>Borja Mercadal</name></author><author><name>Ricardo Salvador</name></author><author><name>Maria Chiara Biagi</name></author><author><name>Fabrice Bartolomei</name></author><author><name>Fabrice Wendling</name></author><author><name>Giulio Ruffini</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Metal implants impact the dosimetry assessment in electrical stimulation techniques. Therefore, they need to be included in numerical models. While currents in the body are ionic, metals only allow electron transport. In fact, charge transfer between tissues and metals requires electric fields to drive the electrochemical reactions at the interface. Thus, metal implants may act as insulators or as conductors depending on the scenario.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective/Hypothesis&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The aim of this paper is to provide a theoretical argument that guides the choice of the correct representation of metal implants using purely electrical models but considering the electrochemical nature of the problem in the technology of interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We built a simple model of a metal implant exposed to a homogeneous electric field of various magnitudes to represent both weak (e.g., tDCS), medium (TMS) or strong field stimulation. The same geometry was solved using two different models: a purely electric one (with different conductivities for the implant), and an electrochemical one. As an example of application, we also modeled a transcranial electrical stimulation (tES) treatment in a realistic head model with a skull plate using a high and low conductivity value for the plate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Metal implants generally act as electric insulators when exposed to electric fields up to around 100 V/m (tES and TMS range) and they only resemble a perfect conductor for fields in the order of 1000 V/m and above. The results are independent of the implant’s metal, but they depend on its geometry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion(s)&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Metal implants can be accurately represented by a simple electrical model of constant conductivity, but an incorrect model choice can lead to large errors in the dosimetry assessment. In particular, tES modeling with implants incorrectly treated as conductors can lead to errors of 50% in induced fields or more. Our results can be used as a guide to select the correct model in each scenario.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471211" rel="alternate" title="Modeling implanted metals in electrical stimulation applications (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>