<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.322114+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469715</id><title>Contractile force of transplanted cardiomyocytes contributes to heart function after injury (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.322437+00:00</updated><author><name>Tim Stüdemann</name></author><author><name>Judith Rössinger</name></author><author><name>Christoph Manthey</name></author><author><name>Birgit Geertz</name></author><author><name>Rajiven Srikantharajah</name></author><author><name>Constantin von Bibra</name></author><author><name>Aya Shibamiya</name></author><author><name>Maria Köhne</name></author><author><name>Antonius Wiehler</name></author><author><name>J. Simon Wiegert</name></author><author><name>Thomas Eschenhagen</name></author><author><name>Florian Weinberger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Transplantation of pluripotent stem cell-derived cardiomyocytes represents an innovative therapeutic strategy for heart failure. Studies in small and large animals have demonstrated functional recovery of left ventricular function after cardiomyocyte transplantation&lt;sup&gt;1–4&lt;/sup&gt;, and first clinical studies are currently underway&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;. Yet, the mechanism of action underlying graft-induced benefit is unknown&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;. Here we demonstrate that transplanted cardiomyocytes actively contribute to heart function. We transplanted cardiomyocytes with an optogenetic off-on switch in a guinea pig cardiac injury model. Light-induced inhibition of engrafted cardiomyocyte contractility resulted in a rapid decrease of left ventricular function that was fully reversible with the offset of photostimulation. Hence, our optogenetic approach demonstrated that transplanted cardiomyocytes actively participate in heart function, supporting the hypothesis that the delivery of new force-generating myocardium can serve as a regenerative therapeutic strategy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469715" rel="alternate" title="Contractile force of transplanted cardiomyocytes contributes to heart function after injury (17 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469570</id><title>Polyelectrolyte Nanocomplex Formation Combined with Electrostatic Self-Assembly Enables the Co-Delivery of Synergistic Antimicrobials to Treat Bacterial Biofilms (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.322725+00:00</updated><author><name>Joel A. Finbloom</name></author><author><name>Preethi Raghavan</name></author><author><name>Bhushan N. Kharbikar</name></author><author><name>Michelle A. Yu</name></author><author><name>Tejal A. Desai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;New approaches are needed to treat bacterial biofilm infections, particularly those of &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; (PA). PA biofilms have high rates of antimicrobial resistance and are commonly found in chronic wound and cystic fibrosis lung infections. The use of combination therapeutics that act synergistically is a promising treatment strategy; however, the delivery of multiple therapeutics at relevant dosages is challenging in the clinic. We therefore developed a new nanoscale drug carrier by combining approaches from both polyelectrolyte nanocomplex (NC) formation and layer-by-layer electrostatic self-assembly. This strategy led to NC drug carriers functionalized with both tobramycin antibiotics and antimicrobial silver nanoparticles with high loading efficiencies. AgTob-NCs displayed synergistic enhancements in antimicrobial activity against planktonic and biofilm PA cultures, with positively charged NCs demonstrating complete biofilm eradication. Overall, this approach shows promise in the co-delivery of diverse classes of antimicrobials to overcome antimicrobial resistance and treat bacterial biofilm infections.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469570" rel="alternate" title="Polyelectrolyte Nanocomplex Formation Combined with Electrostatic Self-Assembly Enables the Co-Delivery of Synergistic Antimicrobials to Treat Bacterial Biofilms (11 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469541</id><title>Quantification of vascular networks in photoacoustic mesoscopy (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.322866+00:00</updated><author><name>Emma L. Brown</name></author><author><name>Thierry L. Lefebvre</name></author><author><name>Paul W. Sweeney</name></author><author><name>Bernadette J. Stolz</name></author><author><name>Janek Gröhl</name></author><author><name>Lina Hacker</name></author><author><name>Ziqiang Huang</name></author><author><name>Dominique-Laurent Couturier</name></author><author><name>Heather A. Harrington</name></author><author><name>Helen M. Byrne</name></author><author><name>Sarah E. Bohndiek</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mesoscopic photoacoustic imaging (PAI) enables non-invasive visualisation of tumour vasculature and has the potential to assess prognosis and therapeutic response. Currently, evaluating vasculature using mesoscopic PAI involves visual or semi-quantitative 2D measurements, which fail to capture 3D vessel network complexity, and lack robust ground truths for assessment of segmentation accuracy. Here, we developed an &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt;, phantom, &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt;-validated end-to-end framework to quantify 3D vascular networks captured using mesoscopic PAI. We applied our framework to evaluate the capacity of rule-based and machine learning-based segmentation methods, with or without vesselness image filtering, to preserve blood volume and network structure by employing topological data analysis. We first assessed segmentation performance against ground truth data of &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; synthetic vasculatures and a photoacoustic string phantom. Our results indicate that learning-based segmentation best preserves vessel diameter and blood volume at depth, while rule-based segmentation with vesselness image filtering accurately preserved network structure in superficial vessels. Next, we applied our framework to breast cancer patient-derived xenografts (PDXs), with corresponding &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; immunohistochemistry. We demonstrated that the above segmentation methods can reliably delineate the vasculature of 2 breast PDX models from mesoscopic PA images. Our results underscore the importance of evaluating the choice of segmentation method when applying mesoscopic PAI as a tool to evaluate vascular networks &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469541" rel="alternate" title="Quantification of vascular networks in photoacoustic mesoscopy (9 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469463</id><title>Jointly Optimized Spatial Histogram UNET Architecture (JOSHUA) for Adipose Tissue Segmentation (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.323038+00:00</updated><author><name>Joshua K. Peeples</name></author><author><name>Julie F. Jameson</name></author><author><name>Nisha M. Kotta</name></author><author><name>Jonathan M. Grasman</name></author><author><name>Whitney L. Stoppel</name></author><author><name>Alina Zare</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We quantify adipose tissue deposition at surgical sites as a function of biomaterial implantation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Impact Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To our knowledge, this study is the first investigation to apply convolutional neural network (CNN) models to identify and segment adipose tissue in histological images from silk fibroin biomaterial implants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;When designing biomaterials for the treatment of various soft tissue injuries and diseases, one must consider the extent of adipose tissue deposition. In this work, we implant silk fibroin biomaterials in a rodent subcutaneous injury model. Current strategies for quantifying adipose tissue after biomaterial implantation are often tedious and prone to human bias during analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used CNN models with novel spatial histogram layer(s) that can more accurately identify and segment regions of adipose tissue in hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;amp;E) and Masson’s Trichrome stained images, allowing for determination of the optimal biomaterial formulation. We compared the method, Jointly Optimized Spatial Histogram UNET Architecture (JOSHUA), to the baseline UNET model and an extension of the baseline model, Attention UNET, as well as to versions of the models with a supplemental “attention”-inspired mechanism (JOSHUA+ and UNET+).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The inclusion of histogram layer(s) in our models shows improved performance through qualitative and quantitative evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our results demonstrate that the proposed methods, JOSHUA and JOSHUA+, are highly beneficial for adipose tissue identification and localization. The new histological dataset and code for our experiments are publicly available.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469463" rel="alternate" title="Jointly Optimized Spatial Histogram UNET Architecture (JOSHUA) for Adipose Tissue Segmentation (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469508</id><title>Effect of therapeutic ultrasound on the mechanical and biological properties of fibroblasts (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.323177+00:00</updated><author><name>Rosy P. Cárdenas-Sandoval</name></author><author><name>Homero F. Pastrana-Rendón</name></author><author><name>Alba G. Ávila-Bernal</name></author><author><name>Angélica M. Ramírez-Martínez</name></author><author><name>Myriam L. Navarrete-Jimenez</name></author><author><name>Alejandro O. Ondo-Mendez</name></author><author><name>Diego A. Garzón-Alvarado</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Conventional doses of therapeutic ultrasound alter the mechanical behavior of ligament fibroblasts to improve the regenerative and remodeling stages of the wound healing process. Using a multidisciplinary approach, we applied ultrasound doses of 1.0 and 2.0 W/cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; at 1 MHz frequency for five days on ligament fibroblasts. Atomic force microscopy showed a decrease in cell elastic modulus for both doses, but the treated cells were still viable based on flow cytometry. Finite element method analysis exhibited visible cytoskeleton displacements and decreased harmonics in treated cells. Colorimetric assay revealed increased cell proliferation, while scratch assay showed increased migration at low doses. An increase in collagen and fibronectin was detected by enzyme-linked immunoassay at high doses, and β-actin expression for both treatments was visualized through immunofluorescence imaging. Both doses of ultrasound altered the fibroblast mechanical properties due to cytoskeletal reorganization and enhanced the early and late stages of cell repair.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469508" rel="alternate" title="Effect of therapeutic ultrasound on the mechanical and biological properties of fibroblasts (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470055</id><title>Bagaza virus in wild birds, Portugal, 2021 (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.323320+00:00</updated><author><name>Joao Queiros</name></author><author><name>Silvia Barros</name></author><author><name>Alberto Sanchez-Cano</name></author><author><name>Margarida Henriques</name></author><author><name>Teresa Fagulha</name></author><author><name>Fabio Abade dos Santos</name></author><author><name>Margarida Duarte</name></author><author><name>Catarina Goncalves</name></author><author><name>David Goncalves</name></author><author><name>Marisa Rodrigues</name></author><author><name>Teresa Cardona Cabrera</name></author><author><name>Isabel G. Fernandez de Mera</name></author><author><name>Christian Gortazar</name></author><author><name>Ursula Hofle</name></author><author><name>Paulo Celio Alves</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bagaza virus (BAGV) emerged in Spain, in 2010. Since then, BAGV was not reported in other European countries until September 2021, when BAGV was diagnosed by molecular methods in one corn bunting and several red-legged partridges, after abnormal mortality in Southern Portugal. Sequencing revealed high similarity with strains reported previously.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470055" rel="alternate" title="Bagaza virus in wild birds, Portugal, 2021 (3 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469732</id><title>Directed Evolution of Aptamer Discovery Technologies (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.323508+00:00</updated><author><name>Diana Wu</name></author><author><name>Chelsea K.L. Gordon</name></author><author><name>John H. Shin</name></author><author><name>Michael Eisenstein</name></author><author><name>H. Tom Soh</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conspectus&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although antibodies are a powerful tool for molecular biology and clinical diagnostics, there are many emerging applications for which nucleic acid-based aptamers can be advantageous. However, generating high-quality aptamers with sufficient affinity and specificity for biomedical applications is a challenging feat for most research laboratories. In this &lt;italic&gt;Account&lt;/italic&gt;, we describe four techniques developed in our lab to accelerate the discovery of high quality aptamer reagents that can achieve robust binding even for challenging molecular targets. The first method is particle display, in which we convert solution-phase aptamers into aptamer particles that can be screened via fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) to quantitatively isolate individual aptamer particles based on their affinity. This enables the efficient isolation of high-affinity aptamers in fewer selection rounds than conventional methods, thereby minimizing selection biases and reducing the emergence of artifacts in the final aptamer pool. We subsequently developed the multi-parametric particle display (MPPD) method, which employs two-color FACS to isolate aptamer particles based on both affinity and specificity, yielding aptamers that exhibit excellent target binding even in complex matrices like serum. The third method is a click chemistry-based particle display (click-PD) that enables the generation and high-throughput screening of “non-nattural” aptamers with a wide range of base modifications. We have shown that these base-modified aptamers can achieve robust affinity and specificity for targets that have proven challenging or inaccessible with natural nucleotide-based aptamer libraries. Lastly, we describe the non-natural aptamer array (N2A2) platform, in which a modified benchtop sequencing instrument is used to characterize base-modified aptamers in a massively parallel fashion, enabling the efficient identification of molecules with excellent affinity and specificity for their targets. This system first generates aptamer clusters on the flow-cell surface that incorporate alkyne-modified nucleobases, and then performs a click reaction to couple those nucleobases to an azide-modified chemical moiety. This yields a sequence-defined array of tens of millions of base-modified sequences, which can then be characterized in a high-throughput fashion. Collectively, we believe that these advancements are helping to make aptamer technology more accessible, efficient, and robust, thereby enabling the use of these affinity reagents for a wider range of molecular recognition and detection-based applications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469732" rel="alternate" title="Directed Evolution of Aptamer Discovery Technologies (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469540</id><title>Interferometric imaging of thermal expansion for temperature control in retinal laser therapy (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.323640+00:00</updated><author><name>David Veysset</name></author><author><name>Tong Ling</name></author><author><name>Yueming Zhuo</name></author><author><name>Daniel Palanker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Precise control of the temperature rise is a prerequisite for proper photothermal therapy. In retinal laser therapy, the heat deposition is primarily governed by the melanin concentration, which can significantly vary across the retina and from patient to patient. In this work, we present a method for determining the optical and thermal properties of layered materials, directly applicable to the retina, using low-energy laser heating and phase-resolved optical coherence tomography (pOCT). The method is demonstrated on a polymer-based tissue phantom heated with a laser pulse focused onto an absorbing layer buried below the phantom’s surface. Using a line-scan spectral-domain pOCT, optical path length changes induced by the thermal expansion were extracted from sequential B-scans. The material properties were then determined by matching the optical path length changes to a thermo-mechanical model developed for fast computation. This method determined the absorption coefficient with a precision of 2.5% and the temperature rise with a precision of about 0.2°C from a single laser exposure, while the peak did not exceed 8°C during 1 ms pulse, which is well within the tissue safety range and significantly more precise than other methods.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469540" rel="alternate" title="Interferometric imaging of thermal expansion for temperature control in retinal laser therapy (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>