<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.383457+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476248</id><title>OrganoID: a versatile deep learning platform for organoid image analysis (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.383543+00:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan M Matthews</name></author><author><name>Brooke Schuster</name></author><author><name>Sara Saheb Kashaf</name></author><author><name>Ping Liu</name></author><author><name>Mustafa Bilgic</name></author><author><name>Andrey Rzhetsky</name></author><author><name>Savas Tay</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Organoids are three-dimensional in vitro tissue models that closely represent the native heterogeneity, microanatomy, and functionality of an organ or diseased tissue. Analysis of organoid morphology, growth, and drug response is challenging due to the diversity in shape and size of organoids, movement through focal planes, and limited options for live-cell staining. Here, we present OrganoID, an open-source image analysis platform that automatically recognizes, labels, and tracks single organoids in brightfield and phase-contrast microscopy. The platform identifies organoid morphology pixel by pixel without the need for fluorescence or transgenic labeling and accurately analyzes a wide range of organoid types in time-lapse microscopy experiments. OrganoID uses a modified u-net neural network with minimal feature depth to encourage model generalization and allow fast execution. The network was trained on images of human pancreatic cancer organoids and was validated on images from pancreatic, lung, colon, and adenoid cystic carcinoma organoids with a mean intersection-over-union of 0.76. OrganoID measurements of organoid count and individual area concurred with manual measurements at 96% and 95% agreement respectively. Tracking accuracy remained above 89% over the duration of a four-day validation experiment. Automated single-organoid morphology analysis of a dose-response experiment identified significantly different organoid circularity after exposure to different concentrations of gemcitabine. The OrganoID platform enables straightforward, detailed, and accurate analysis of organoid images to accelerate the use of organoids as physiologically relevant models in high-throughput research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476248" rel="alternate" title="OrganoID: a versatile deep learning platform for organoid image analysis (10 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476124</id><title>BlenderPhotonics – a versatile environment for 3-D complex bio-tissue modeling and light transport simulations based on Blender (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.383632+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuxuang Zhang</name></author><author><name>Qianqian Fang</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rapid advances in biophotonics techniques require quantitative, model-based computational approaches to obtain functional and structural information from increasingly complex and multi-scaled anatomies. The lack of efficient tools to accurately model tissue structures and subsequently perform quantitative multi-physics modeling greatly impedes the clinical translation of these modalities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aim&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;While the mesh-based Monte Carlo (MMC) method expands our capabilities in simulating complex tissues by using tetrahedral meshes, the generation of such domains often requires specialized meshing tools such as Iso2Mesh. Creating a simplified and intuitive interface for tissue anatomical modeling and optical simulations is essential towards making these advanced modeling techniques broadly accessible to the user community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Approach&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We responded to the above challenge by combining the powerful, open-source 3-D modeling software, Blender, with state-of-the-art 3-D mesh generation and MC simulation tools, utilizing the interactive graphical user interface (GUI) in Blender as the front-end to allow users to create complex tissue mesh models, and subsequently launch MMC light simulations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have developed a Python-based Blender add-on – BlenderPhotonics – to interface with Iso2Mesh and MMC, allowing users to create, configure and refine complex simulation domains and run hardware-accelerated 3-D light simulations with only a few clicks. In this tutorial, we provide a comprehensive introduction to this new tool and walk readers through 5 examples, ranging from simple shapes to sophisticated realistic tissue models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;BlenderPhotonics is user-friendly and open-source, leveraging the vastly rich ecosystem of Blender. It wraps advanced modeling capabilities within an easy-to-use and interactive interface. The latest software can be downloaded at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mcx.space/bp"&gt;http://mcx.space/bp&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476124" rel="alternate" title="BlenderPhotonics – a versatile environment for 3-D complex bio-tissue modeling and light transport simulations based on Blender (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475658</id><title>Sensitive protein detection using site-specifically oligonucleotide-conjugated nanobodies (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.383692+00:00</updated><author><name>Rasel A. Al-Amin</name></author><author><name>Phathutshedzo M. Muthelo</name></author><author><name>Eldar Abdurakhmanov</name></author><author><name>Cécile Vincke</name></author><author><name>Serge Muyldermans</name></author><author><name>U. Helena Danielson</name></author><author><name>Ulf Landegren</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;High-quality affinity probes are critical for sensitive and specific protein detection, in particular to detect protein biomarkers at early phases of disease development. Clonal affinity reagents can offer advantages over the commonly used polyclonal antibodies (pAbs) in terms of reproducibility and standardization of such assays. In particular, clonal reagents offer opportunities for site-directed attachment of exactly one modification per affinity reagent at a site designed not to interfere with target binding to help standardize assays. The proximity extension assays (PEA) is a widely used protein assay where pairs of protein-binding reagents are modified with oligonucleotides (oligos), so that their proximal binding to a target protein generates a reporter DNA strand for DNA-assisted readout. The assays have been used for high-throughput multiplexed protein detection of up to a few thousand different proteins in one or a few microliters of plasma. Here we explore nanobodies (Nb) as an alternative to polyclonal antibodies pAbs as affinity reagents for PEA. We describe an efficient site-specific approach for preparing high-quality oligo-conjugated Nb probes via Sortase A (SrtA) enzyme coupling. The procedure allows convenient removal of unconjugated affinity reagents after conjugation. The purified high-grade Nb probes were used in PEA and the reactions provided an efficient means to select optimal pairs of binding reagents from a group of affinity reagents. We demonstrate that Nb-based PEA for interleukin-6 (IL6) detection can augment assay performance, compared to the use of pAb probes. We identify and validate Nb combinations capable of binding in pairs without competition for IL6 antigen detection by PEA.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475658" rel="alternate" title="Sensitive protein detection using site-specifically oligonucleotide-conjugated nanobodies (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476283</id><title>Ehrlichia SLiM ligand mimetic activates Notch signaling in human monocytes (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.383772+00:00</updated><author><name>LaNisha L. Patterson</name></author><author><name>Thangam Sudha Velayutham</name></author><author><name>Caitlan D. Byerly</name></author><author><name>Duc Cuong Bui</name></author><author><name>Jignesh Patel</name></author><author><name>Veljko Veljkovic</name></author><author><name>Slobodan Paessler</name></author><author><name>Jere W. McBride</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Ehrlichia chaffeensis&lt;/italic&gt; evades innate host defenses by reprogramming the mononuclear phagocyte through mechanisms that involve exploitation of multiple evolutionarily conserved cellular signaling pathways including Notch. This immune evasion strategy is directed in part by tandem repeat protein (TRP) effectors. Specifically, the TRP120 effector activates and regulates Notch signaling through interactions with the Notch receptor and the negative regulator, F-Box and WD repeat domain-containing 7 (FBW7). However, the specific molecular interactions and motifs required for E. chaffeensis TRP120-Notch receptor interaction and activation have not been defined. To investigate the molecular basis of TRP120 Notch activation, we compared TRP120 with endogenous canonical/non-canonical Notch ligands and identified a short region of sequence homology within the tandem repeat (TR) domain. TRP120 was predicted to share biological function with Notch ligands, and a function-associated sequence in the TR domain was identified. To investigate TRP120-Notch receptor interactions, colocalization between TRP120 and endogenous Notch-1 was observed. Moreover, direct interactions between full length TRP120, the TRP120 TR domain containing the putative Notch ligand sequence, and the Notch receptor LBR were demonstrated. To molecularly define the TRP120 Notch activation motif, peptide mapping was used to identify an 11-amino acid short linear motif (SLiM) located within the TRP120 TR that activated Notch signaling and downstream gene expression. Peptide mutants of the Notch SLiM or anti-Notch SLiM antibody reduced or eliminated Notch activation and NICD nuclear translocation. This investigation reveals a novel molecularly defined pathogen encoded Notch SLiM mimetic that activates Notch signaling consistent with endogenous ligands.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476283" rel="alternate" title="Ehrlichia SLiM ligand mimetic activates Notch signaling in human monocytes (5 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476011</id><title>No One Is Leaving This Time: Appraisal of Awareness and Knowledge of Port Health Officers on International Health Regulation IHR (2005) (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.383860+00:00</updated><author><name>Yusuf Babatunde Adiama</name></author><author><name>Solomon Olayinka Adewoye</name></author><author><name>Opasola Afolabi Olaniyi</name></author><author><name>Habeeb Modupe Lateefat</name></author><author><name>Abdullahi Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Morufu Olalekan Raimi</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Historically, ships have played an important role in transmitting infectious diseases around the world. The spread of cholera pandemics in the 19&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century was thought to be linked to trade routes and facilitated by merchant shipping. The international maritime traffic of people and goods has often contributed to the spread of pathogens affecting public health.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To assess level of awareness and knowledge of international Health regulation (IHR 2005) content among port health officer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study design was descriptive cross-sectional evaluation, questionnaires were used to capture the respondents’ knowledge, awareness and sanitary condition of ship in accordance with (IHR 2005)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;On awareness and knowledge, Majority of the respondent (77.1 %) demonstrate good awareness of the IHR (2005), while 22.9% had not and some even testified of hearing the said document for the first time. Despite the fact that majority of respondent were aware but only 24.6% of them can actually demonstrate good knowledge of IHR (2005) and its intent to protect and prevent spread of disease along the international route.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is need to improve the knowledge of port health officers by expand training and guidance on application of the IHR’s to frontline officer at point of entries. Also ensure more thorough inspection and avoid influence of ship agent during inspection of ship.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476011" rel="alternate" title="No One Is Leaving This Time: Appraisal of Awareness and Knowledge of Port Health Officers on International Health Regulation IHR (2005) (4 tweets)"/><category term="Scientific Communication and Education"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475795</id><title>Optimized cell culture conditions promote ex-vivo manipulation and expansion of primitive hematopoietic stem cells for therapeutic gene editing (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.383938+00:00</updated><author><name>Rajeev Rai</name></author><author><name>Winston Vetharoy</name></author><author><name>Asma Naseem</name></author><author><name>Zohar Steinberg</name></author><author><name>Adrian J Thrasher</name></author><author><name>Giorgia Santilli</name></author><author><name>Alessia Cavazza</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During the last few years, gene editing has emerged as a powerful tool for the therapeutic correction of monogenic diseases. CRISPR/Cas9 applied to hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells (HSPCs) has shown great promise in proof-of-principle preclinical studies to treat haematological disorders, and clinical trials using these tools are now underway. Nonetheless, there remain important challenges that need to be addressed, such as the efficiency of targeting primitive, long-term repopulating HSPCs and expand them &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; for clinical purposes. Here we have tested the effect exerted by different culture media compositions on the ability of HSPCs to proliferate and undergo homology directed repair-mediated knock-in of a reporter gene, while preserving their stemness features during &lt;italic&gt;ex-vivo&lt;/italic&gt; culture. We tested different combinations of compounds and demonstrated that by supplementing the culture media with inhibitors of histone deacetylases, and/or by fine-tuning its cytokine composition it is possible to achieve high levels of gene targeting in long-term repopulating HSPCs both &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, with a beneficial balance between preservation of stemness and cell expansion, thus allowing to obtain a significant amount of edited, primitive HSPCs compared to established, state-of-the-art culture conditions. Overall, the implantation of this optimized ex vivo HSPC culture protocol will improve the efficacy, feasibility and applicability of gene editing and will likely provide one step further to unlock the full therapeutic potential of such powerful technology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475795" rel="alternate" title="Optimized cell culture conditions promote ex-vivo manipulation and expansion of primitive hematopoietic stem cells for therapeutic gene editing (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476227</id><title>Transverse and axial resolution of femtosecond laser ablation (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.384011+00:00</updated><author><name>Yao L. Wang</name></author><author><name>Noa W. F. Grooms</name></author><author><name>Samuel H Chung</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Femtosecond lasers are capable of precise ablation that produce surgical dissections &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. The transverse and axial resolution of the laser damage inside the bulk are important parameters of ablation. The transverse resolution is routinely quantified, but the axial resolution is more difficult to measure and is less commonly performed. In some &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; samples, fine dissections can also be difficult to visualize, but &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; samples may allow clear imaging. Using a 1040-nm, 400-fs pulsed laser, we performed ablation inside agarose and glass, producing clear and persistent damage spots. Near the ablation threshold of both media, we found that the axial resolution is similar to the transverse resolution. We also ablated neuron cell bodies and fibers in &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; and demonstrate submicrometer resolution in both the transverse and axial directions, consistent with our results in agarose and glass. Using simple yet rigorous methods, we define the resolution of laser ablation in transparent media along all directions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476227" rel="alternate" title="Transverse and axial resolution of femtosecond laser ablation (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.17.476579</id><title>piggyBac-system-mediated genomic integration of large variant libraries for deep mutational scanning in mammalian cells (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.384072+00:00</updated><author><name>Yanjie Zhao</name></author><author><name>Yifan Li</name></author><author><name>Yi Wang</name></author><author><name>Weijun Su</name></author><author><name>Shuai Li</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;There is a need of introducing large variant libraries into mammalian cells to facilitate deep mutational scanning (DMS). In this study, we develop an approach to integrate in-vitro ligation dsDNA variant library into cultured mammalian cell genome via the piggyBac transposon system. T4 DNA ligase was employed to produce dsDNA ligation products containing variant library sequence flanked by piggyBac inverted terminal repeat sequences (ITRs) at both ends. The ligation products were then cotransfected with a piggyBac transposase expression vector into mammalian cells for library integration. The clone formation assay results showed that about 29,000 resistance clones were generated from a single well of 6-well-plate transfected HEK293T cells. As a proof of principle of using the strategy for DMS, a GFP chromophore random variant library was integrated into the HEK293T cell genome. By FACS selection, we enriched GFP-positive cells. The next-generation sequencing (NGS) results showed that the GFP-chromophore amino acid sequences were restored after selection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.17.476579" rel="alternate" title="piggyBac-system-mediated genomic integration of large variant libraries for deep mutational scanning in mammalian cells (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.476543</id><title>An efficient simplified method for the generation of corneal epithelial cells from human pluripotent stem cells (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.384145+00:00</updated><author><name>Rodi Abdalkader</name></author><author><name>Ken-ichiro Kamei</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Corneal epithelial cells derived from human pluripotent stem cells (hPSCs) are an important cell source for preclinical models to test ophthalmic drugs. However, current differentiation protocols lack instructions regarding optimal culturing conditions, which hinders the quality of cells and limits scale-up. Here, we introduce a simplified small molecule-based corneal induction method (SSM-CI) to generate corneal epithelial cells from hPSCs. SSM-CI provides the advantage of minimizing cell culturing time using two defined culturing media containing TGFβ, and Wnt/β-catenin pathway inhibitors, and bFGF growth factor over 25 days. Compared to the conventional human corneal epithelial cell line (HCE-T) and human primary corneal epithelial cells (hPCEpCs), corneal epithelial cells generated by SSM-CI are well-differentiated and express relevant maturation markers, including PAX6 and CK12. RNA-seq analysis indicated the faithful differentiation of hPSCs into corneal epithelia, with significant upregulation of corneal progenitor and adult corneal epithelial phenotypes. Furthermore, despite the initial inhibition of TGF-β and Wnt/β-catenin, upregulation of these pathway-related transcripts was observed in the later stages, indicating their necessity in the generation of mature corneal epithelial cells. Moreover, we observed a shift in gene signatures associated with the metabolic characteristics of mature corneal epithelial cells, involving a decrease in glycolysis- and an increase in fatty acid oxidation. This was also attributed to the overexpression of metabolic enzymes and transporter-related transcripts responsible for fatty acid metabolism. Thus, SSM-CI provides a comprehensive method for the generation of functional corneal epithelial cells for use in preclinical models.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.476543" rel="alternate" title="An efficient simplified method for the generation of corneal epithelial cells from human pluripotent stem cells (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476044</id><title>Automated bioprocess feedback operation in a high throughput facility via the integration of a mobile robotic lab assistant (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.384200+00:00</updated><author><name>Lucas Kaspersetz</name></author><author><name>Saskia Waldburger</name></author><author><name>M.-Therese Schermeyer</name></author><author><name>Sebastian L. Riedel</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Groß</name></author><author><name>Peter Neubauer</name></author><author><name>M.-Nicolas Cruz-Bournazou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Biotechnological processes development is challenging due to the sheer variety of process parameters. For efficient upstream development parallel cultivation systems have proven to reduce costs and associated timelines successfully, while offering excellent process control. However, the degree of automation of such small scale systems is comparably low and necessary sample analysis requires manual steps. Although the subsequent analysis can be performed in a high-throughput manner, the integration of analytic devices remains challenging. Especially, when cultivation and analysis laboratories are spatially separated. Mobile robots offer a potential solution, but the implementation in research laboratories is not widely adopted. Our approach demonstrates the integration of a small scale cultivation system into a liquid handling station for an automated sample procedure. The samples are transferred via a mobile robotic lab assistant and subsequently analysed by a high-throughput analyzer. The process data is stored in a centralized database. The mobile robotic workflow guarantees a flexible solution for device integration and facilitates automation. Restrictions regarding spatial separation of devices are circumvented, enabling a modular platform throughout different laboratories. The presented cultivation platform is evaluated based on industrial relevant &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; BW25113 high cell density fed-batch cultivation. Here its suitability for accelerating bioprocess development is proven. The necessary magnesium addition for reaching high cell densities in mineral salt medium is automated via a feedback operation loop. The feedback operation loop demonstrates the possibility for advanced control options. This study sets the foundation for a fully integrated facility with different cultivation scales sharing the same data infrastructure, where the mobile robotic lab assistant physically connects the devices.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476044" rel="alternate" title="Automated bioprocess feedback operation in a high throughput facility via the integration of a mobile robotic lab assistant (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>