<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.685308+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474555</id><title>A nanopore interface for high bandwidth DNA computing (55 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.685730+00:00</updated><author><name>Karen Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yuan-Jyue Chen</name></author><author><name>Kathryn Doroschak</name></author><author><name>Karin Strauss</name></author><author><name>Luis Ceze</name></author><author><name>Georg Seelig</name></author><author><name>Jeff Nivala</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;DNA has emerged as a powerful substrate for programming information processing machines at the nanoscale. Among the DNA computing primitives used today, DNA strand displacement (DSD) is arguably the most popular, with DSD-based circuit applications ranging from disease diagnostics to molecular artificial neural networks. The outputs of DSD circuits are generally read using fluorescence spectroscopy. However, due to the spectral overlap of typical small-molecule fluorescent reporters, the number of unique outputs that can be detected in parallel is limited, requiring complex optical setups or spatial isolation of reactions to make output bandwidths scalable. Here, we present a multiplexable sequencing-free readout method that enables real-time, kinetic measurement of DSD circuit activity through highly parallel, direct detection of barcoded output strands using nanopore sensor array technology (Oxford Nanopore Technologies' MinION device). We show that engineered reporter probes can be detected and classified with high accuracy at the single-molecule level directly from raw nanopore signals using deep learning. We then demonstrate this method's utility in multiplexed detection of clinically relevant microRNA sequences. These results increase DSD output bandwidth by an order of magnitude over what is possible with fluorescence spectroscopy, laying the foundations for a new paradigm in DNA circuit readout and programmable multiplexed molecular diagnostics using portable nanopore devices.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474555" rel="alternate" title="A nanopore interface for high bandwidth DNA computing (55 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474357</id><title>A Musculoskeletal Model of the Hand and Wrist Capable of Simulating Functional Tasks (20 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.686021+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Clinton McFarland</name></author><author><name>Benjamin I Binder-Markey</name></author><author><name>Jennifer A Nichols</name></author><author><name>Sarah J Wohlman</name></author><author><name>Marije de Bruin</name></author><author><name>Wendy M Murray</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Objective: The purpose of this work was to develop an open-source musculoskeletal model of the hand and wrist and to evaluate its performance during simulations of functional tasks. Methods: The musculoskeletal model was developed by adapting and expanding upon existing musculoskeletal models. An optimal control theory framework that combines forward-dynamics simulations with a simulated-annealing optimization was used to simulate maximum grip and pinch force. Active and passive hand opening were simulated to evaluate coordinated kinematic hand movements. Results: The model's maximum grip force production matched experimental measures of grip force, force distribution amongst the digits, and displayed sensitivity to wrist flexion. Simulated lateral pinch strength fell within variability of in vivo palmar pinch strength data. Additionally, predicted activation for 7 of 8 muscles fell within variability of EMG data during palmar pinch. The active and passive hand opening simulations predicted reasonable activations and demonstrated passive motion mimicking tenodesis, respectively. Conclusion: This work advances simulation capabilities of hand and wrist models and provides a foundation for future work to build upon. Significance: This is the first open-source musculoskeletal model of the hand and wrist to be implemented during both functional kinetic and kinematic tasks. We provide a novel simulation framework to predict maximal grip and pinch force which can be used to evaluate how potential surgical and rehabilitation interventions influence these functional outcomes while requiring minimal experimental data.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474357" rel="alternate" title="A Musculoskeletal Model of the Hand and Wrist Capable of Simulating Functional Tasks (20 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474546</id><title>Bioprinting the Tumor Microenvironment with an Upgraded Consumer Stereolithographic 3D Printer (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.686332+00:00</updated><author><name>Louise Breideband</name></author><author><name>Kaja Nicole Wächtershäuser</name></author><author><name>Levin Hafa</name></author><author><name>Konstantin Wieland</name></author><author><name>Achilleas Frangakis</name></author><author><name>Ernst H.K. Stelzer</name></author><author><name>Francesco Pampaloni</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A widespread application of three-dimensional (3D) bioprinting in basic and translational research requires the accessibility to affordable printers able to produce physiologically relevant tissue models. To facilitate the use of bioprinting as a standard technique in biology, an open-source device based on a consumer-grade 3D stereolithographic (SL) printer was developed. This SL bioprinter can produce complex constructs that preserve cell viability and recapitulate the physiology of tissues. The detailed documentation of the modifications apported to the printer as well as a throughout performance analysis allow for a straightforward adoption of the device in other labs and its customization for specific applications. Given the low cost, several modified bioprinters could be simultaneously operated for a highly parallelized tissue production. To showcase the capability of the bioprinter, we produced constructs consisting of patient-derived cholangiocarcinoma organoids encapsulated in a gelatin methacrylate (GelMA)/polyethylene glycol diacrylate (PEGDA) hydrogel. A thorough characterization of different GelMA/PEGDA ratios revealed that the mechanical properties of the bioprinted tumor model can be accurately fine-tuned to mimic a specific tumor micro-environment. Immunofluorescence and gene expression analyses of tumor markers confirmed that the bioprinted synthetic hydrogel provides a flexible and adequate replacement of animal-derived reconstituted extracellular matrix.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474546" rel="alternate" title="Bioprinting the Tumor Microenvironment with an Upgraded Consumer Stereolithographic 3D Printer (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>