<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.924392+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467528</id><title>Large-scale discovery of recombinases for integrating DNA into the human genome (307 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.925250+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew G Durrant</name></author><author><name>Alison Fanton</name></author><author><name>Josh Tycko</name></author><author><name>Michaela Hinks</name></author><author><name>Sita Chandrasekaran</name></author><author><name>Nicholas T Perry</name></author><author><name>Julia Schaepe</name></author><author><name>Peter P Du</name></author><author><name>Lacramioara Bintu</name></author><author><name>Michael C Bassik</name></author><author><name>Ami S Bhatt</name></author><author><name>Patrick D. Hsu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent microbial genome sequencing efforts have revealed a vast reservoir of mobile genetic elements containing integrases that could be useful genome engineering tools. Large serine recombinases (LSRs), such as Bxb1 and PhiC31, are bacteriophage-encoded integrases that can facilitate the insertion of phage DNA into bacterial genomes. However, only a few LSRs have been previously characterized and they have limited efficiency in human cells. Here, we developed a systematic computational discovery workflow that searches across the bacterial tree of life to expand the diversity of known LSRs and their cognate DNA attachment sites by &amp;gt;100-fold. We validated this approach via experimental characterization of LSRs, leading to three classes of LSRs distinguished from one another by their efficiency and specificity. We identify landing pad LSRs that efficiently integrate into native attachment sites in a human cell context, human genome-targeting LSRs with computationally predictable pseudosites, and multi-targeting LSRs that can unidirectionally integrate cargos with similar efficiency and superior specificity to commonly used transposases. LSRs from each category were functionally characterized in human cells, overall achieving up to 7-fold higher plasmid recombination than Bxb1 and genome insertion efficiencies of 40-70% with cargo sizes over 7 kb. Overall, we establish a paradigm for the large-scale discovery of microbial recombinases directly from sequencing data and the reconstruction of their target sites. This strategy provided a rich resource of over 60 experimentally characterized LSRs that can function in human cells and thousands of additional candidates for large-payload genome editing without double-stranded DNA breaks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467528" rel="alternate" title="Large-scale discovery of recombinases for integrating DNA into the human genome (307 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.466680</id><title>Vertex protein PduN tunes encapsulated pathway performance by dictating bacterial metabolosome morphology (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.925720+00:00</updated><author><name>Carolyn E. Mills</name></author><author><name>Curt Waltmann</name></author><author><name>Andre G. Archer</name></author><author><name>Nolan W. Kennedy</name></author><author><name>Charlotte H. Abrahamson</name></author><author><name>Alexander D. Jackson</name></author><author><name>Eric W. Roth</name></author><author><name>Sasha Shirman</name></author><author><name>Michael C. Jewett</name></author><author><name>Niall M. Mangan</name></author><author><name>Monica Olvera de la Cruz</name></author><author><name>Danielle Tullman-Ercek</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Engineering subcellular organization in microbes shows great promise in addressing bottlenecks in metabolic engineering efforts; however, rules guiding selection of an organization strategy or platform are lacking. Here, we study compartment morphology as a factor in mediating encapsulated pathway performance. Using the 1,2-propanediol utilization microcompartment (Pdu MCP) system from &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella enterica&lt;/italic&gt; serovar Typhimurium LT2, we find that we can shift the morphology of this protein nanoreactor from polyhedral to tubular by removing vertex protein PduN. Analysis of the metabolic function between these Pdu microtubes (MTs) shows that they provide a diffusional barrier capable of shielding the cytosol from a toxic pathway intermediate, similar to native MCPs. However, kinetic modeling suggests that the different surface area to volume ratios of MCP and MT structures alters encapsulated pathway performance. Finally, we report a microscopy-based assay that permits rapid assessment of Pdu MT formation to enable future engineering efforts on these structures.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.466680" rel="alternate" title="Vertex protein PduN tunes encapsulated pathway performance by dictating bacterial metabolosome morphology (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467225</id><title>Spread of Xanthomonas vasicola pv. musacearum within banana mats: implications for Xanthomonas wilt management (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.926129+00:00</updated><author><name>Walter Ocimati</name></author><author><name>Anthony F Tazuba</name></author><author><name>Guy Blomme</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Xanthomonas wilt (XW) of banana caused by Xanthomonas vasicola pv. musacearum (Xvm) does not spread to all plants physically interconnected through the rhizome when one or a few are diseased. However, the factors behind this incomplete systemic spread of Xvm are not fully known yet could inform XW management. This study explored the effect of Xvm inoculum amounts, number and size of suckers, sucker positioning on mother plant corms and other mother plant corm attributes on sucker colonization. A shorter (p &amp;lt;0.05) incubation period (17.9 vs 21.1 days) and higher (p&amp;lt;.001) cumulative number of symptomatic leaves (5.2 vs 1.6 leaves) was observed when all (high inoculum) compared to two leaves (low inoculum) were inoculated. Xvm was recovered in corms at 29 days post inoculation (dpi) in both treatments with no differences (p &amp;gt;0.05) in proportions of corms with Xvm between the treatments. However, Xvm was recovered earlier and at a higher frequency in suckers when all leaves were inoculated. Lower Xvm recoveries occurred in the lower corm sections to which most suckers were attached relative to the middle and upper corm sections. Xvm incidence in corms increased with the number of attached maiden suckers, and the dpi while it declined with increasing mother plant and corm height. Thus, Xvm spread within mats is influenced by the amount of inoculum and the physiological stage (e.g., height) of the plant and attached suckers. The position of suckers, predominantly at the bottom of corms also protects them from infection. Measures that reduce Xvm inoculum build-up in mats are thus crucial for minimizing within mat XW spread.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467225" rel="alternate" title="Spread of Xanthomonas vasicola pv. musacearum within banana mats: implications for Xanthomonas wilt management (4 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.465885</id><title>Generation and Culture of Cardiac Microtissues in a Microfluidic Chip with a Reversible Open Top Enables Electrical Pacing, Dynamic Drug Dosing and Endothelial Cell Co-Culture (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.926449+00:00</updated><author><name>Aisen Vivas</name></author><author><name>Camilo IJspeert</name></author><author><name>Jesper Yue Pan</name></author><author><name>Kim Vermeul</name></author><author><name>Albert van den Berg</name></author><author><name>Robert Passier</name></author><author><name>Stephan Sylvest Keller</name></author><author><name>Andries D. van der Meer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cardiovascular disease morbidity has increased worldwide in recent years while drug development has been affected by failures in clinical trials and lack of physiologically relevant models. Organs-on-chips and human pluripotent stem cell technologies aid to overcome some of the limitations in cardiac &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; models. Here, a bi-compartmental, monolithic heart-on-chip device that facilitates porous membrane integration in a single fabrication step is presented. Moreover, the device includes open-top compartments that allow facile co-culture of human pluripotent stem cell-derived cardiomyocytes and human adult cardiac fibroblast into geometrically defined cardiac microtissues. The device can be reversibly closed with a glass seal or a lid with fully customized 3D-printed pyrolytic carbon electrodes allowing electrical stimulation of cardiac microtissues. A subjacent microfluidic channel allowed localized and dynamic drug administration to the cardiac microtissues, as demonstrated by a chronotropic response to isoprenaline. Moreover, the microfluidic channel could also be populated with human induced pluripotent stem-derived endothelial cells allowing co-culture of heterotypic cardiac cells in one device. Overall, this study demonstrates a unique heart-on-chip model that systematically integrates the structure and electromechanical microenvironment of cardiac tissues in a device that enables active perfusion and dynamic drug dosing. Advances in the engineering of human heart-on-chip models represent an important step towards making organ-on-a-chip technology a routine aspect of preclinical cardiac drug development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.465885" rel="alternate" title="Generation and Culture of Cardiac Microtissues in a Microfluidic Chip with a Reversible Open Top Enables Electrical Pacing, Dynamic Drug Dosing and Endothelial Cell Co-Culture (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467322</id><title>AlphaFold Models Illuminate Half of Dark Human Proteins (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.927149+00:00</updated><author><name>Jessica L Binder</name></author><author><name>Joel Berendzen</name></author><author><name>Amy O Stevens</name></author><author><name>Yi He</name></author><author><name>Jian Wang</name></author><author><name>Nikolay V Dokholyan</name></author><author><name>Tudor I Oprea</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We investigate the use of confidence scores to predict the accuracy of a given AlphaFold model for drug discovery. Predicted accuracy is improved by eliminating confidence scores below 80, due to effects of disorder. 95% of models corresponding to a set of recent crystal structures are accurate at the fold level. Conformational discordance in the training set has a more significant effect on accuracy than sequence divergence. We propose criteria for models and residues that are possibly useful for virtual screening, by which AlphaFold provides models for half of understudied (dark) human proteins and two-thirds of residues in those models.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467322" rel="alternate" title="AlphaFold Models Illuminate Half of Dark Human Proteins (3 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467190</id><title>Detection of pseudouridine modifications and type I/II hypermodifications in human mRNAs using direct, long-read sequencing (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.927597+00:00</updated><author><name>Sepideh Tavakoli</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Nabizadehmashhadtoroghi</name></author><author><name>Amr Makhamreh</name></author><author><name>Howard Gamper</name></author><author><name>Neda Rezapour</name></author><author><name>Ya-MIng Hou</name></author><author><name>Meni Wanunu</name></author><author><name>Sara H Rouhanifard</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Enzyme-mediated chemical modifications to mRNAs have the potential to fine-tune gene expression in response to environmental stimuli. Notably, pseudouridine-modified mRNAs are more resistant to RNase-mediated degradation, more responsive to cellular stress, and have the potential to modulate immunogenicity and enhance translation in vivo. However, the precise biological functions of pseudouridine modification on mRNAs remain unclear due to the lack of sensitive and accurate tools for mapping. We developed a semi-quantitative method for mapping pseudouridylated sites with high confidence directly on mammalian mRNA transcripts via direct RNA, long-read nanopore sequencing. By analysis of a modification-free transcriptome, we demonstrate that the depth of coverage and intrinsic errors associated with specific k-mer sequences are critical parameters for accurate base-calling. We adjust these parameters for high-confidence U-to-C base-calling errors that occur at pseudouridylated sites, which are benchmarked against sites that were identified previously by biochemical methods. We also uncovered new pseudouridylated sites, many of which fall on genes that encode RNA binding proteins and on uridine-rich k-mers. Sites identified by U-to-C base calling error were verified using 1000mer synthetic RNA controls bearing a single pseudouridine in the center position, demonstrating that 1. the U-to-C base-calling error occurs at the site of pseudouridylation, and 2. the basecalling error is systematically under-calling the pseudouridylated sites. High-occupancy sites with &amp;gt;40% U-to-C basecalling error are classified as sites of hyper modification type I, whereas genes with more than one site of pseudouridylation are classified as having type II hyper modification which is confirmed by single-molecule analysis. We report the discovery of mRNAs with up to 7 unique sites of pseudouridine modification. Here we establish an innovative pipeline for direct identification, quantification, and detection of pseudouridine modifications and type I/II hypermodifications on native RNA molecules using long-read sequencing without resorting to RNA amplification, chemical reactions on RNA, enzyme-based replication, or DNA sequencing steps.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467190" rel="alternate" title="Detection of pseudouridine modifications and type I/II hypermodifications in human mRNAs using direct, long-read sequencing (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466993</id><title>Laser-driven Wireless Deep Brain Stimulation using Temporal Interference and Organic Electrolytic Photocapacitors (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.928094+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian MISSEY</name></author><author><name>Mary Jocelyn DONAHUE</name></author><author><name>Pascal WEBER</name></author><author><name>Ibrahima NGOM</name></author><author><name>Emma ACERBO</name></author><author><name>Boris BOTZANOWSKI</name></author><author><name>Ludovico MIGLIACCIO</name></author><author><name>Viktor Jirsa</name></author><author><name>Eric Daniel GLOWACKI</name></author><author><name>Adam Williamson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Deep brain stimulation (DBS) is a technique commonly used both in clinical and fundamental neurosciences. Classically, brain stimulation requires an implanted and wired electrode system to deliver stimulation directly to the target area. Although techniques such as temporal interference (TI) can provide stimulation at depth without involving any implanted electrodes, these methods still rely on a wired apparatus which limits free movement. Herein we report organic photocapacitors as untethered light-driven electrodes which convert deep-red light into electric current. Pairs of these ultrathin devices can be driven using lasers at two different frequencies to deliver stimulation at depth via temporally interfering fields. We validate this concept of laser TI stimulation using numerical modeling, ex vivo tests with phantom samples, and finally in vivo tests. Wireless organic photocapacitors are placed on the cortex and elicit stimulation in the hippocampus, while not delivering off-target stimulation in the cortex. This laser-driven wireless TI evoked a neuronal response at depth that is comparable to control experiments induced with deep brain stimulation protocols using implanted electrodes. Our work shows that a combination of these two techniques, temporal interference and organic electrolytic photocapacitors, provides a reliable way to target brain structures requiring neither deeply implanted electrodes nor tethered stimulator devices. The laser TI protocol demonstrated here address two of the most important drawbacks in the field of deep brain stimulation and thus holds potential to solve many issues in freely-moving animal experiments or for clinical chronic therapy application.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466993" rel="alternate" title="Laser-driven Wireless Deep Brain Stimulation using Temporal Interference and Organic Electrolytic Photocapacitors (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466776</id><title>Coiled Coil Crosslinked Alginate Hydrogels Dampen Macrophage-Driven Inflammation (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.929146+00:00</updated><author><name>Zain Clapacs</name></author><author><name>Conor L O'Neill</name></author><author><name>Paresh Shrimali</name></author><author><name>Giriraj Lokhande</name></author><author><name>Megan Files</name></author><author><name>Darren D Kim</name></author><author><name>Akhilesh Gaharwar</name></author><author><name>Jai S Rudra</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Alginate hydrogels are widely used for tissue engineering and regenerative medicine due to their excellent biocompatibility. A facile and commonly used strategy to crosslink alginate is the addition of Ca2+ that leads to hydrogelation. However, extracellular Ca2+ is a secondary messenger in activating inflammasome pathways following physical injury or pathogenic insult leading to persistent inflammation and scaffold rejection. Here we present graft copolymers of charge complementary heterodimeric coiled coil (CC) peptides and alginate that undergo supramolecular self-assembly to form Ca2+ free alginate hydrogels. The formation of heterodimeric CCs was confirmed using circular dichroism spectroscopy and scanning electron microscopy revealed a significant difference in pore size between Ca2+ and CC crosslinked gels. The resulting hydrogels were self-supporting and display shear-thinning and shear-recovery properties. In response to lipopolysaccharide (LPS) stimulation, peritoneal macrophages and bone marrow derived dendritic cells cultured in the CC crosslinked gels exhibited a 10-fold  reduction in secretion of the proinflammatory cytokine IL-1β compared to Ca2+ crosslinked gels. A similar respose was also observed in vivo upon peritoneal delivery of Ca2+ or CC crosslinked gels. Analysis of peritoneal lavage showed that macrophages in mice injected with Ca2+ crosslinked gels display a more inflammatory phenotype compared to macrophages from mice injected with CC crosslinked gels. These results suggest that CC peptides by virtue of their tunable sequence-structure-function relationship and mild gelation conditions are promising alternative crosslinkers for alginate and other biopolymer scaffolds used in tissue engineering.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466776" rel="alternate" title="Coiled Coil Crosslinked Alginate Hydrogels Dampen Macrophage-Driven Inflammation (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466780</id><title>A system for multiplexed selection of aptamers with exquisite specificity without counter-selection (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.929637+00:00</updated><author><name>Alex M. Yoshikawa</name></author><author><name>Leighton Wan</name></author><author><name>Liwei Zheng</name></author><author><name>Michael Eisenstein</name></author><author><name>H. Tom Soh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aptamers have proven to be valuable tools for the detection of small molecules due to their remarkable ability to specifically discriminate between structurally similar molecules. Most aptamer selection efforts have relied on counter-selection to eliminate aptamers that exhibit unwanted cross-reactivity to interferents or structurally similar relatives to the target of interest. However, because the affinity and specificity characteristics of an aptamer library are fundamentally unknowable &lt;italic&gt;a priori&lt;/italic&gt;, it is not possible to determine the optimal counter-selection parameters. As a result, counter-selection experiments require trial-and-error approaches that are inherently inefficient and may not result in aptamers with the best combination of affinity and specificity. In this work, we describe a high-throughput screening process for generating high-specificity aptamers to multiple targets in parallel, while also eliminating the need for counter-selection. We employ a platform based on a modified benchtop sequencer to conduct a massively-parallel aptamer screening process that enables the selection of highly-specific aptamers against multiple structurally similar molecules in a single experiment, without any counter-selection. As a demonstration, we have selected aptamers with high affinity and exquisite specificity for three structurally similar kynurenine metabolites that differ by a single hydroxyl group in a single selection experiment. This process can easily be adapted to other small-molecule analytes, and should greatly accelerate the development of aptamer reagents that achieve exquisite specificity for their target analytes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aptamers offer the exciting potential to discriminate between structurally similar small molecules. However, generating such highly specific aptamers has been proven challenging using the conventional process of counter-selection. In this work, we describe a high-throughput screening platform that can characterize the specificity of millions of aptamers towards a group of structurally related molecules in a single experiment and generate exquisitely specific aptamers without any counter-selection. As exemplars, we generated aptamers with high affinity and specificity towards three structurally related kynurenine metabolites using our platform. Our platform can be readily adapted to other small molecule targets and should therefore accelerate the development of aptamer reagents with exquisite specificity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466780" rel="alternate" title="A system for multiplexed selection of aptamers with exquisite specificity without counter-selection (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467069</id><title>Biofabrication of development-inspired scaffolds for regeneration of the annulus fibrosus macro- and microarchitecture (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.930655+00:00</updated><author><name>Nadine Kluser</name></author><author><name>Christoph Sprecher</name></author><author><name>Gion Ursin Alig</name></author><author><name>Sonja Haeckel</name></author><author><name>Christoph E Albers</name></author><author><name>Mauro Alini</name></author><author><name>Sibylle Grad</name></author><author><name>David Eglin</name></author><author><name>Andrea J Vernengo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Annulus fibrosus (AF) tissue engineering is a promising strategy for repairing the degenerated intervertebral disc (IVD) and a research area that could benefit from improved tissue models to drive translation. AF tissue is composed of concentric layers of aligned collagen bundles arranged in an angle-ply pattern, an architecture which is challenging to recapitulate with current scaffold design strategies. In response to this need, we developed a strategy to print 3D scaffolds that induce cell and tissue organization into oriented patterns mimicking the AF. Polycaprolactone (PCL) was printed in an angle-ply macroarchitecture possessing microscale aligned topographical cues. The topography was achieved by extrusion through custom-designed printer nozzles which were either round or possessing circumferential sinusoidal peaks. Whereas the round nozzle produced extruded filaments with a slight uniaxial texture, patterned nozzles with peak heights of 60 or 120 μm produced grooves, 10.87 ± 3.09 μm or 17.77 ± 4.91 μm wide, respectively. Bone marrow derived mesenchymal stem cells (BM-MSCs) cultured on the scaffolds for four weeks exhibited similar degrees of alignment within ± 10 ° of the printing direction and upregulation of outer AF markers (COL1, COL12, SFRP, MKX, MCAM, SCX and TAGLN), with no statistically significant differences as a function of topography. Interestingly, the grooves generated by the patterned nozzles induced longitudinal end-to-end alignment of cells, capturing the arrangement of cells during fibrillogenesis. In contrast, topography produced from the round nozzle induced a continuous web of elongated cells without end-to-end alignment. Extracellular collagen I, decorin and fibromodulin were detected in patterns closely following cellular organization. Taken together, we present a single-step biofabrication strategy to induce anisotropic cellular alignments in x-, y-, and z-space, with potential application as an in vitro model for studying AF tissue morphogenesis and growth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467069" rel="alternate" title="Biofabrication of development-inspired scaffolds for regeneration of the annulus fibrosus macro- and microarchitecture (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>