<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.258338+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.22.457271</id><title>Vapor cannabis exposure generationally affects male reproductive functions in mice (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.258582+00:00</updated><author><name>Mingxin Shi</name></author><author><name>Esther M. Langholt</name></author><author><name>Logan C. Butler</name></author><author><name>Madeleine E. Harvey</name></author><author><name>Emma C. Wheeler</name></author><author><name>Liang Zhao</name></author><author><name>James A. MacLean</name></author><author><name>Yeongseok Oh</name></author><author><name>Emily Sabrowsky</name></author><author><name>Sue Yu</name></author><author><name>Shane Watson</name></author><author><name>Jon F. Davis</name></author><author><name>Kanako Hayashi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This study was performed to examine whether vapor exposure to cannabis plant matter negatively impacts male reproductive functions and testis development in mice. Adult CD-1 male mice (F0) were exposed to air (control) or 200 mg of vaporized cannabis plant matter 3x/day over a 10 day period. Subsequently, F0 males were bred with drug naïve CD-1 females to generate F1 males, and F1 offspring were used to generate F2 males. Cannabis vapor exposure decreased sperm count and/or motility in F0 and F1 males and disrupted the progression of germ cell development, as morphometric analyses exhibited an abnormal distribution of the stages of spermatogenesis in F0 males. Although plasma levels of testosterone were not affected by cannabis exposure in any ages or generations of males, dysregulated steroidogenic enzymes, &lt;italic&gt;Cyp11a1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Cyp19a1&lt;/italic&gt;, were observed in F0 testis. In the neonatal testis from F1 males, while apoptosis was not altered, DNA damage and DNMT1, but not DNMT3A and DNMT3B, were increased in germ cells following cannabis exposure. In contrast, the alterations of DNA damage and DNMT1 expression were not observed in F2 neonatal males. These results suggest that cannabis vapor exposure generationally affects male reproductive functions, probably due to disruption of spermatogenesis in the developing testis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;GRAPHICAL ABSTRACT&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="457271v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;HIGHLIGHTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cannabis vapor exposure to adult males impairs sperm counts, motility and spermatogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cannabis vapor exposure to F0 males causes reduced sperm counts in F1, but not in F2 males.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plasma testosterone levels are not affected in F0, F1 and F2 males by cannabis exposure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cannabis increases DNA damage and the expression of DNA methyltransferase (DNMT) 1 in the F1 neonatal testis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.22.457271" rel="alternate" title="Vapor cannabis exposure generationally affects male reproductive functions in mice (3 tweets)"/><category term="Pharmacology and Toxicology"/><published>2021-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.23.457415</id><title>Time Evolution of the Stroke Symptom-Herb Networks Based on TCM Prescriptions (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.258840+00:00</updated><author><name>Xing Fu</name></author><author><name>Qianqian Li</name></author><author><name>Feng Yang</name></author><author><name>Ranran Zhou</name></author><author><name>Ran Li</name></author><author><name>Jianchen Hou</name></author><author><name>Xiaohua Tao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Traditional Chinese Medicine (TCM) has its origins in distant antiquity and has piled up over a long time with much knowledge about diseases, especially stroke. Different combinations of symptom variables yield different combinations of herbs to form a myriad of prescriptions, and they have undergone repeated confirmation and are worthy objects of excavation and analysis. Herbal studies on stroke have developed from genomics to transcriptomics, proteomics and metabolomics, yet more thought is needed on putting time in a wider perspective of the symptoms and herbs for stroke in Chinese medicine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Due to this, we studied the dynamic structure of TCM prescriptions on stroke, using over 270 TCM prescription books containing 2231 prescriptions related to stroke recorded from 341 to 2000 CE. We labeled the functions of the prescriptions with the symptoms based on subject terms in MESH &lt;italic&gt;Neurologic Manifestations&lt;/italic&gt;, then standardized the herbs in the prescriptions, and finally connected the co-occurring symptoms and herbs in the prescriptions to build an undirected complex network. The Stroke Symptom-Herb Networks (SSHNs) can be seen from its network characteristics that it is not a random network and has small-world characteristics. It has experienced two peaks in its nearly 1700-year history, during the Song dynasty, the Ming and Qing dynasties. From 600 years onwards, the core herb cluster has been initially formed. The comparison of sub-network similarities allowed us to identify several symptoms with similar herb clusters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We divided the community based on modularity, and by analyzing the community evolution, we found a more fixed historical evolutionary trend with &lt;italic&gt;Hemiplegia&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Sialorrhea&lt;/italic&gt; nodes and their associated symptom and herb nodes. In the time series analysis, we found many symptom-herb combinations that were consistently closely related to historic time depends on assessing the similarity between the symptoms and the herbs. The complex network provides a distinctive perspective for understanding the symptom-herb relationships embedded in TCM prescriptions in remote antiquity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.23.457415" rel="alternate" title="Time Evolution of the Stroke Symptom-Herb Networks Based on TCM Prescriptions (3 tweets)"/><category term="Scientific Communication and Education"/><published>2021-08-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>