<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.561942+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461850</id><title>Optogenetic perturbations of RNA expression in tissue space (103 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.562427+00:00</updated><author><name>Ivano Legnini</name></author><author><name>Lisa Emmenegger</name></author><author><name>Ricardo Wurmus</name></author><author><name>Alessandra Zappulo</name></author><author><name>Anna Oliveras Martinez</name></author><author><name>Cledi Cerda Jara</name></author><author><name>Anastasiya Boltengagen</name></author><author><name>Talé Hessler</name></author><author><name>Guido Mastrobuoni</name></author><author><name>Agnieszka Rybak-Wolf</name></author><author><name>Stefan Kempa</name></author><author><name>Robert Zinzen</name></author><author><name>Andrew Woehler</name></author><author><name>Nikolaus Rajewsky</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Quantifying gene expression in space, for example by spatial transcriptomics, is essential for describing the biology of cells and their interactions in complex tissues. Perturbation experiments, at single-cell resolution and conditional on both space and time, are necessary for dissecting the molecular mechanisms of these interactions. To this aim, we combined optogenetics and CRISPR technologies to activate or knock-down RNA of target genes, at single-cell resolution and in programmable spatial patterns. As a proof of principle, we optogenetically induced Sonic Hedgehog (SHH) signaling at a distinct spatial location within human neural organoids. This robustly induced known SHH spatial domains of gene expression – cell-autonomously and across the entire organoid. In principle, our approach can be used to induce or knock down RNAs from any gene of interest in specific spatial locations or patterns of complex biological systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461850" rel="alternate" title="Optogenetic perturbations of RNA expression in tissue space (103 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.19.460985</id><title>The apportionment of citations: A scientometric analysis of Lewontin, 1972 (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.563927+00:00</updated><author><name>Jedidiah Carlson</name></author><author><name>Kelley Harris</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;“The Apportionment of Human Diversity” (1972) is the most highly cited research article published by geneticist Richard Lewontin in his career. This study’s primary result—that most genetic diversity in humans can be accounted for by within-population differences, not between-population differences—along with Lewontin’s outspoken, politically-charged interpretations thereof, has become foundational to the scientific and cultural discourse pertaining to human genetic variation. The article has an unusual bibliometric trajectory in that it is much more salient in the bibliographic record today compared to the first 20 years after its publication. Here, we show how the paper’s fame was shaped by four factors: 1) citations in influential publications across several disciplines; 2) Lewontin’s own popular books and media appearances; 3) the renaissance of population genetics research of the early 1990s; and 4) the serendipitous collision of scientific progress, influential books/papers, and heated controversies in the year 1994. We conclude with an analysis of Twitter data to characterize the communities and conversations that continue to keep this study at the epicenter of discussions about race and genetics, prompting new challenges for scientists who have inherited Lewontin’s legacy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.19.460985" rel="alternate" title="The apportionment of citations: A scientometric analysis of Lewontin, 1972 (27 tweets)"/><category term="Scientific Communication and Education"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461415</id><title>Peptide fusion improves prime editing efficiency (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.564220+00:00</updated><author><name>Minja Velimirovic</name></author><author><name>Larissa C. Zanetti</name></author><author><name>Max W. Shen</name></author><author><name>James D. Fife</name></author><author><name>Lin Lin</name></author><author><name>Minsun Cha</name></author><author><name>Ersin Akinci</name></author><author><name>Danielle Barnum</name></author><author><name>Tian Yu</name></author><author><name>Richard I. Sherwood</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Prime editing enables search-and-replace genome editing but is limited by low editing efficiency. We present a high-throughput approach, PepSEq, to measure how fusion of 12,000 85-amino acid peptides derived from human DNA repair-related proteins influences prime editing efficiency. We show that peptide fusion can enhance prime editing, prime-enhancing peptides combine productively, and a top dual peptide-prime editor increases prime editing significantly in multiple cell lines across dozens of target sites.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461415" rel="alternate" title="Peptide fusion improves prime editing efficiency (14 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461256</id><title>Quantitative single-cell transcriptome-based ranking of engineered AAVs in human retinal explants (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.564612+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhouhuan Xi</name></author><author><name>Bilge E. Öztürk</name></author><author><name>Molly E. Johnson</name></author><author><name>William R. Stauffer</name></author><author><name>Leah C. Byrne</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gene therapy is a rapidly developing field, and adeno-associated virus (AAV) is a leading viral vector candidate for therapeutic gene delivery. Newly engineered AAVs with improved abilities are now entering the clinic. It has proven challenging, however, to predict the translational potential of gene therapies developed in animal models, due to cross-species differences. Human retinal explants are the only available model of fully developed human retinal tissue, and are thus important for the validation of candidate AAV vectors. In this study, we evaluated 18 wildtype and engineered AAV capsids in human retinal explants using a recently developed single-cell RNA-Seq AAV engineering pipeline (scAAVengr). Human retinal explants retained the same major cell types as fresh retina, with similar expression of cell-specific markers, except for a cone population with altered expression of cone-specific genes. The efficiency and tropism of AAVs in human explants were quantified, with single-cell resolution. The top performing serotypes, K91, K912, and 7m8, were further validated in non-human primate and human retinal explants. Together, this study provides detailed information about the transcriptome profiles of retinal explants, and quantifies the infectivity of leading AAV serotypes in human retina, accelerating the translation of retinal gene therapies to the clinic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphic abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="461256v2_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461256" rel="alternate" title="Quantitative single-cell transcriptome-based ranking of engineered AAVs in human retinal explants (14 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461696</id><title>Fabrication and delivery of mechano-actived microcapsules containing osteogenic factors in a large animal model of osteochondral injury (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.564904+00:00</updated><author><name>Hannah M. Zlotnick</name></author><author><name>Ryan C. Locke</name></author><author><name>Sanjana Hemdev</name></author><author><name>Brendan D. Stoeckl</name></author><author><name>Sachin Gupta</name></author><author><name>Ana P. Peredo</name></author><author><name>David R. Steinberg</name></author><author><name>James L. Carey</name></author><author><name>Daeyeon Lee</name></author><author><name>George R. Dodge</name></author><author><name>Robert L. Mauck</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chondral and osteochondral repair strategies are limited by adverse bony changes that occur after injury. Bone resorption can cause entire scaffolds, engineered tissues, or even endogenous repair tissues to subside below the cartilage surface. To address this translational issue, we fabricated poly(D,L-lactide-co-glycolide) (PLGA) microcapsules containing the pro-osteogenic agents triiodothyronine and ß-glycerophosphate, and delivered these microcapsules in a large animal model of osteochondral injury to preserve bone structure. We demonstrate that developed microcapsules ruptured &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; under increasing mechanical loads, and readily sink within a liquid solution, allowing for gravity-based positioning onto the osteochondral surface. In a large animal, these mechano-active microcapsules (MAMCs) were assessed through two different delivery strategies. Intra-articular injection of control MAMCs enabled fluorescent quantification of MAMC rupture and cargo release in a synovial joint setting over time in vivo. This joint-wide injection also confirmed that the MAMCs do not elicit an inflammatory response. In the contralateral hindlimbs, chondral defects were created, MAMCs were locally administered, and nanofracture (Nfx), a clinically utilized method to promote cartilage repair, was performed. The NFx holes enabled marrow-derived stromal cells to enter the defect area and served as repeatable bone injury sites to monitor over time. Animals were evaluated 1 and 2 weeks after injection and surgery. Analysis of injected MAMCs showed that bioactive cargo was released in a controlled fashion over 2 weeks. A bone fluorochrome label injected at the time of surgery displayed maintenance of mineral labeling in the therapeutic group, but resorption in both control groups. Alkaline phosphatase (AP) staining at the osteochondral interface revealed higher AP activity in defects treated with therapeutic MAMCs. Overall, this study establishes a new micro-fluidically generated delivery platform that releases therapeutic factors in an articulating joint, and reduces this to practice in the delivery of therapeutics that preserve bone structure after osteochondral injury.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461696" rel="alternate" title="Fabrication and delivery of mechano-actived microcapsules containing osteogenic factors in a large animal model of osteochondral injury (13 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461639</id><title>Bio-hybrid Soft Robotic Bioreactors for Mimicking Multi-Axial Femoropopliteal Artery Mechanobiology (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.565281+00:00</updated><author><name>Cody Fell</name></author><author><name>Trent L Brooks-Richards</name></author><author><name>Maria Ann Woodruff</name></author><author><name>Mark C Allenby</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The emerging field of soft robotics aims to emulate dynamic physiological locomotion. Soft robotics’ mimicry of naturally complex biomechanics makes them ideal platforms for exerting mechanical stimuli for patient-specific tissue maturation and disease modeling applications. Such platforms are essential for emulating highly flexible tissues such as the kneecap’s femoropopliteal artery (FPA), one of the most flexible arteries in the body, which flexes and bends during walking, standing, and crouching movements. The FPA is a frequent site of disease, where 80% of all peripheral artery diseases manifest, affecting over 200 million people worldwide. The complex biomechanical and hemodynamic forces within the FPA have been implicated in the frequent occurrence of PAD and lead to debilitating morbidities, such as limb-threatening ischemia. To better mimic these complex biomechanics, we developed an &lt;italic&gt;in-vitro&lt;/italic&gt; bio-hybrid soft robot (BSR). First, Platsil OO-20 was identified as an ideal hyperelastomer for both cell culture and BSR fabrication using 3D printed molds. Then, employing a simulation-based design workflow, we integrated pneumatic network (PneuNet) actuators cast with Platsil OO-20, which extend in angular, longitudinal, and radial dimensions. Pressurizing the BSR PneuNets enabled a range of mechanical stimuli to be dynamically applied during tissue culture to mimic normal and diseased FPA flexions during daily walking and sitting poses, the most extreme being radial distensions of 20% and angular flexions of 140°. Finally, these designed, manufactured, and programmed vascular BSRs were seeded with mesenchymal stem cells and conditioned for 24 hours to highlight the effect of dynamic conditioning on cultured cell alignment, as well as type IV collagen production and the upregulation of smooth muscle phenotypes. Soft robotic bioreactor platforms that accurately mimic patient-, disease-, and lifestyle-specific mechanobiology will develop fundamental disease understanding, preoperative laboratory simulations for existing therapeutics, and biomanufacturing platforms for tissue-engineered implants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461639" rel="alternate" title="Bio-hybrid Soft Robotic Bioreactors for Mimicking Multi-Axial Femoropopliteal Artery Mechanobiology (11 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.460915</id><title>Glucosyltransferase-dependent and independent effects of Clostridioides difficile toxins during infection (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.565663+00:00</updated><author><name>F. Christopher Peritore-Galve</name></author><author><name>John A. Shupe</name></author><author><name>Rory J. Cave</name></author><author><name>M. Kay Washington</name></author><author><name>Sarah A. Kuehne</name></author><author><name>D. Borden Lacy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Clostridioides difficile&lt;/italic&gt; infection (CDI) is the leading cause of nosocomial diarrhea and pseudomembranous colitis in the USA. In addition to these symptoms, patients with CDI can develop severe inflammation and tissue damage, resulting in life-threatening toxic megacolon. CDI is mediated by two large homologous protein toxins, TcdA and TcdB, that bind and hijack receptors to enter host cells where they use glucosyltransferase (GT) enzymes to inactivate Rho family GTPases. GT-dependent intoxication elicits cytopathic changes, cytokine production, and apoptosis. At higher concentrations TcdB induces GT-independent necrosis in cells and tissue by stimulating production of reactive oxygen species via recruitment of the NADPH oxidase complex. Although GT-independent necrosis has been observed &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, the relevance of this mechanism during CDI has remained an outstanding question in the field. In this study we generated novel &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; toxin mutants in the hypervirulent BI/NAP1/PCR-ribotype 027 R20291 strain to test the hypothesis that GT-independent epithelial damage occurs during CDI. Using the mouse model of CDI, we observed that epithelial damage occurs through a GT-independent process that is does not involve immune cell influx. The GT-activity of either toxin was sufficient to cause severe edema and inflammation, yet GT activity of both toxins was necessary to produce severe watery diarrhea. These results indicate that both TcdA and TcdB contribute to infection when present. Further, while inactivating GT activity of &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; toxins may suppress diarrhea and deleterious GT-dependent immune responses, the potential of severe GT-independent epithelial damage merits consideration when developing toxin-based therapeutics against CDI.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SIGNIFICANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Clostridioides difficile&lt;/italic&gt; is the leading cause of antibiotic-associated diarrhea in hospitals worldwide. This bacterium produces two virulence factors, TcdA and TcdB, which are large protein toxins that enter host colon cells to cause inflammation, fluid secretion, and cell death. The enzymatic domain of TcdB is a target for novel &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; infection (CDI) therapeutics since it is considered the major factor in causing severe CDI. However, necrotic cell death due to non-enzymatic TcdB-host interactions have been reported in cell culture and intoxicated tissue. Here, we generated &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; strains with enzyme-inactive toxins to evaluate the role of each toxin in an animal model of CDI. We observe an additive role for TcdA and TcdB in disease and both glucosyltransferase-dependent and independent phenotypes. These findings are expected to inform the development of toxin-based CDI therapeutics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.460915" rel="alternate" title="Glucosyltransferase-dependent and independent effects of Clostridioides difficile toxins during infection (9 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462180</id><title>Extracellular Electron Transfer Enables Cellular Control of Cu(I)-catalyzed Alkyne-Azide Cycloaddition (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.565990+00:00</updated><author><name>Gina Partipilo</name></author><author><name>Austin J. Graham</name></author><author><name>Brian Belardi</name></author><author><name>Benjamin K. Keitz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Extracellular electron transfer (EET) is an anaerobic respiration process that couples carbon oxidation to the reduction of metal species. In the presence of a suitable metal catalyst, EET allows for cellular metabolism to control a variety of synthetic transformations. Here, we report the use of EET from the model electroactive bacterium &lt;italic&gt;Shewanella oneidensis&lt;/italic&gt; for metabolic and genetic control over Cu(I)-catalyzed Alkyne-Azide Cycloaddition (CuAAC). CuAAC conversion under anaerobic and aerobic conditions was dependent on live, actively respiring &lt;italic&gt;S. oneidensis&lt;/italic&gt; cells. In addition, reaction progress and kinetics could be further manipulated by tailoring the central carbon metabolism of &lt;italic&gt;S. oneidensis&lt;/italic&gt;. Similarly, CuAAC activity was dependent on specific EET pathways and could be manipulated using inducible genetic circuits controlling the expression of EET-relevant proteins including MtrC, MtrA, and CymA. EET-driven CuAAC also exhibited modularity and robustness in ligand tolerance and substrate scope. Furthermore, the living nature of this system could be exploited to perform multiple reaction cycles without requiring regeneration, something inaccessible to traditional chemical reductants. Finally, &lt;italic&gt;S. oneidensis&lt;/italic&gt; enabled bioorthogonal CuAAC membrane labelling on live mammalian cells without affecting cell viability, suggesting that &lt;italic&gt;S. oneidensis&lt;/italic&gt; can act as a dynamically tunable biocatalyst in complex environments. In summary, our results demonstrate how EET can expand the reaction scope available to living systems by enabling cellular control of CuAAC.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462180" rel="alternate" title="Extracellular Electron Transfer Enables Cellular Control of Cu(I)-catalyzed Alkyne-Azide Cycloaddition (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461497</id><title>Models as games: a novel approach for ‘gamesourcing’ parameter data and communicating complex models (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.566284+00:00</updated><author><name>Jeroen Minderman</name></author><author><name>A. Bradley Duthie</name></author><author><name>Isabel L. Jones</name></author><author><name>Laura Thomas-Walters</name></author><author><name>Adrian Bach</name></author><author><name>Matthew Nuttall</name></author><author><name>Nils Bunnefeld</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Models have become indispensable tools in conservation science in the face of increasingly rapid loss of biodiversity through anthropogenic habitat loss and natural resource exploitation. In addition to their ecological components, accurately representing human decision-making processes in such models is vital to maximise their utility. This can be problematic as modelling complexity increases, making them challenging to communicate and parameterise.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Games have a long history of being used as science communication tools, but are less widely used as data collection tools, particularly in videogame form. We propose a novel approach to (1) aid communication of complex social-ecological models, and (2) “gamesource” human decision-making data, by explicitly casting an existing modelling framework as an interactive videogame.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present players with a natural resource management game as a front-end to a social-ecological modelling framework (Generalised Management Strategy Evaluation, GMSE). Players’ actions replace a model algorithm making management decisions about a population of wild animals, which graze on crops and can thus lower agricultural yield. A number of non-player agents (farmers) respond through modelled algorithms to the player’s management, taking actions that may affect their crop yield as well as the animal population. Players are asked to set their own management goal (e.g. maintain the animal population at a certain level or improve yield) and make decisions accordingly. Trial players were also asked to provide any feedback on both gameplay and purpose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We demonstrate the utility of this approach by collecting and analysing game play data from a sample of trial plays, in which we systematically vary two model parameters, and allowing trial players to interact with the model through the game interface. As an illustration, we show how variations in land ownership and the number of farmers in the system affects decision-making patterns as well as population trajectories (extinction probabilities).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We discuss the potential and limitations of this model-game approach in the light of trial player feedback received. In particular, we highlight how a common concern about the game framework (perceived lack of “realism” or relevance to a specific context) are actually criticisms of the underlying model, as opposed to the game itself. This further highlights both the parallels between games and models, as well as the utility of model-games to aid in communicating complex models. We conclude that videogames may be an effective tool for conservation and natural resource management, and that although they provide a promising means to collect data on human decision-making, it is vital to carefully consider both external validity and potential biases when doing so.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461497" rel="alternate" title="Models as games: a novel approach for ‘gamesourcing’ parameter data and communicating complex models (5 tweets)"/><category term="Scientific Communication and Education"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461661</id><title>Cell-adaptable dynamic hydrogel reinforced with stem cells improves the functional repair of spinal cord injury by alleviating neuroinflammation (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.567153+00:00</updated><author><name>Xin Yuan</name></author><author><name>Weihao Yuan</name></author><author><name>Lu Ding</name></author><author><name>Ming Shi</name></author><author><name>Liang Luo</name></author><author><name>Yong Wan</name></author><author><name>Jiwon Oh</name></author><author><name>Yanfang Zhou</name></author><author><name>Liming Bian</name></author><author><name>David Y.B. Deng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spinal cord injury (SCI) is one of the most challenging clinical issues. It is characterized by the disruption of neural circuitry and connectivity, resulting in neurological disability. Adipose-derived stem cells (ADSCs) serve as a promising source of therapeutic cells for SCI treatment. However, the therapeutic outcomes of direct ADSCs transplantation are limited in the presence of an inflammatory microenvironment. Herein, a cell-adaptable neurogenic (CaNeu) hydrogel was developed as a delivery vehicle for ADSCs to promote neuronal regeneration after SCI. The dynamic network of CaNeu hydrogel loaded with ADSCs provides a cell-infiltratable matrix that enhances axonal growth and eventually leads to improved motor evoked potential, hindlimb strength, and coordination of complete spinal cord transection in rats. Furthermore, the CaNeu hydrogel also establishes an anti-inflammatory microenvironment by inducing a shift in the polarization of the recruited macrophages toward the pro-regeneration (M2) phenotype. Our study showed that the CaNeu-hydrogel‒mediated ADSCs delivery resulted in significantly suppressed neuroinflammation and apoptosis, and that this phenomenon involved the PI3K/Akt signaling pathway. Our findings indicate that the CaNeu hydrogel is a valuable delivery vehicle to assist stem cell therapy for SCI, providing a promising strategy for central nervous system diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461661" rel="alternate" title="Cell-adaptable dynamic hydrogel reinforced with stem cells improves the functional repair of spinal cord injury by alleviating neuroinflammation (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461306</id><title>Hyperconcentrated Mucus Unifies Submucosal Gland and Superficial Airway Dysfunction in Cystic Fibrosis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.567488+00:00</updated><author><name>Takafumi Kato</name></author><author><name>Giorgia Radicioni</name></author><author><name>Micah J. Papanikolas</name></author><author><name>Georgi V. Stoychev</name></author><author><name>Matthew R. Markovetz</name></author><author><name>Kazuhiro Aoki</name></author><author><name>Mindy Porterfield</name></author><author><name>Kenichi Okuda</name></author><author><name>Selene M. Barbosa Cardenas</name></author><author><name>Rodney C. Gilmore</name></author><author><name>Cameron B. Morrison</name></author><author><name>Camille Ehre</name></author><author><name>Kimberlie A. Burns</name></author><author><name>Kristen K. White</name></author><author><name>Henry P. Goodell</name></author><author><name>Holly Thacker</name></author><author><name>Henry T. Loznev</name></author><author><name>Lawrence J. Forsberg</name></author><author><name>Takahide Nagase</name></author><author><name>Michael Rubinstein</name></author><author><name>Scott H. Randell</name></author><author><name>Michael Tiemeyer</name></author><author><name>David B. Hill</name></author><author><name>Mehmet Kesimer</name></author><author><name>Wanda K. O’Neal</name></author><author><name>Stephen T. Ballard</name></author><author><name>Ronit Freeman</name></author><author><name>Brian Button</name></author><author><name>Richard C. Boucher</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cystic fibrosis (CF) is characterized by abnormal transepithelial ion transport. However, a description of CF lung disease pathophysiology unifying superficial epithelial and submucosal gland (SMG) dysfunctions has remained elusive. We hypothesized that biophysical abnormalities associated with CF mucus hyperconcentration provide a unifying mechanism. Studies of the anion secretion-inhibited pig airway CF model revealed elevated SMG mucus concentrations, osmotic pressures, and SMG mucus accumulation. Human airway studies revealed hyperconcentrated CF SMG mucus with raised osmotic pressures and cohesive forces predicted to limit SMG mucus secretion/release. Utilizing proline-rich protein 4 (PRR4) as a biomarker of SMG secretion, proteomics analyses of CF sputum revealed markedly lower PRR4 levels compared to healthy and bronchiectasis controls, consistent with a failure of CF SMGs to secrete mucus onto airway surfaces. Raised mucus osmotic/cohesive forces, reflecting mucus hyperconcentration, provide a unifying mechanism that describes disease-initiating mucus accumulation on airway surfaces and within SMGs of the CF lung.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hyperconcentrated Mucus Unifies Submucosal Gland and Superficial Airway Dysfunction in Cystic Fibrosis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461306" rel="alternate" title="Hyperconcentrated Mucus Unifies Submucosal Gland and Superficial Airway Dysfunction in Cystic Fibrosis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461422</id><title>Microbial Biotextiles for a Circular Materials Economy (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.567902+00:00</updated><author><name>Theanne N. Schiros</name></author><author><name>Romare Antrobus</name></author><author><name>Delfina Farias</name></author><author><name>Yueh-Ting Chiu</name></author><author><name>Christian Tay Joseph</name></author><author><name>Shanece Esdaille</name></author><author><name>Gwen Karen Sanchiricco</name></author><author><name>Grace Miquelon</name></author><author><name>Dong An</name></author><author><name>Sebastian T. Russell</name></author><author><name>Adrian M. Chitu</name></author><author><name>Susanne Goetz</name></author><author><name>Anne Marika Verploegh Chassé</name></author><author><name>Colin Nuckolls</name></author><author><name>Sanat K. Kumar</name></author><author><name>Helen H. Lu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Harnessing microbial biofabrication and inspired by indigenous practices, we engineer high-performance microbial nanocellulose (MC) biotextiles with a sustainable circular life cycle. Specifically, our plant-based lecithin phosphocholine treatment modulates cellulose cross-linking through phosphate and methylene groups, to yield a biodegradable material with superior mechanical and flame-retardant properties. Coloration is achieved using natural dyes and waste-to-resource strategies. Life cycle impact assessment reveals MC biotextiles mitigate the carcinogenics of leather by a factor of 10&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; and the carbon footprint of synthetic leather and cotton by ∼97%, for widespread application in fashion, interiors, and construction. The translational potential of this approach is tremendous, as using microbes and green chemistry to engineer regenerative, high-performance products will disrupt linear production models and mitigate its environmental threats in a circular economy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We engineer high-performance, microbial biotextiles which mitigate the climate and toxicity impacts of conventional textiles.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461422" rel="alternate" title="Microbial Biotextiles for a Circular Materials Economy (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461967</id><title>Validity and sensitivity of an inertial measurement unit-driven biomechanical model of motor variability for gait (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.568145+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher A. Bailey</name></author><author><name>Thomas K. Uchida</name></author><author><name>Julie Nantel</name></author><author><name>Ryan B. Graham</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Motor variability in gait is frequently linked to fall risk, yet field-based biomechanical joint evaluations are scarce. We evaluated the validity and sensitivity of an inertial measurement unit (IMU)-driven biomechanical model of joint angle variability for gait. Fourteen healthy young adults completed seven-minute trials of treadmill gait at several speeds and arm swing amplitudes. Joint kinematics were estimated by IMU- and optoelectronic-based models using &lt;italic&gt;OpenSim&lt;/italic&gt;. We calculated range of motion (ROM), magnitude of variability (meanSD), local dynamic stability (λ&lt;sub&gt;max&lt;/sub&gt;), persistence of ROM fluctuations (DFAα), and regularity (SaEn) of each angle over 200 continuous strides, and evaluated model accuracy (e.g., RMSD: root mean square difference), consistency (ICC&lt;sub&gt;2,1&lt;/sub&gt;: intraclass correlation), biases, limits of agreement, and sensitivity to within-participant gait responses (effects of Speed and Swing). RMSDs of joint angles were 1.7–7.5° (pooled mean of 4.8°), excluding ankle inversion. ICCs were mostly good– excellent in the primary plane of motion for ROM and in all planes for meanSD and λ&lt;sub&gt;max&lt;/sub&gt;, but were poor–moderate for DFAα and SaEn. Modeled Speed and Swing responses for ROM, meanSD, and λ&lt;sub&gt;max&lt;/sub&gt; were similar. Results suggest that the IMU-driven model is valid and sensitive for field-based assessments of joint angles and several motor variability features.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461967" rel="alternate" title="Validity and sensitivity of an inertial measurement unit-driven biomechanical model of motor variability for gait (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.460629</id><title>PcGCE is a potent elicitor of defense responses in aspen (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.568306+00:00</updated><author><name>Evgeniy N. Donev</name></author><author><name>Marta Derba-Maceluch</name></author><author><name>Xiao-Kun Liu</name></author><author><name>Henri Colyn Bwanika</name></author><author><name>Izabela Dobrowolska</name></author><author><name>Mohit Thapa</name></author><author><name>Joanna Leśniewska</name></author><author><name>Jan Šimura</name></author><author><name>Alex Yi-Lin Tsai</name></author><author><name>Dan Boström</name></author><author><name>Leszek A. Kleczkowski</name></author><author><name>Maria E. Eriksson</name></author><author><name>Karin Ljung</name></author><author><name>Emma R. Master</name></author><author><name>Ewa J. Mellerowicz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Using microbial enzymes in transgenesis is a powerful means to introduce new functionalities in plants. Glucuronoyl esterase (GCE) is a microbial enzyme hydrolyzing the ester bond between lignin and 4-O-methyl-α-D-glucuronic acid present as a side chain of glucuronoxylan. This bond mediates lignin-carbohydrate complex (LCC) formation, considered as crucial factor of lignocellulose recalcitrance to saccharification. Previous studies showed that hybrid aspen (&lt;italic&gt;Populus tremula&lt;/italic&gt; L. x &lt;italic&gt;tremuloides&lt;/italic&gt; Michx.) constitutively expressing &lt;italic&gt;Phanerochaete carnosa&lt;/italic&gt; Burt GCE (&lt;italic&gt;Pc&lt;/italic&gt;GCE) had better efficiency of cellulose-to-glucose conversion but were stunned and had lower cellulose content indicating that more studies are needed to design strategy for deployment of this enzyme &lt;italic&gt;in planta&lt;/italic&gt;. Here we report that the transgenic plants exhibit premature leaf senescence, increased accumulation of calcium oxalate crystals, tyloses and necrotic lesions and have strongly activated immune defense reactions as revealed by their altered profiles of transcriptomes, metabolomes and hormones in the leaves. To elucidate if these effects are triggered by damage-associated molecular patterns (DAMPs) or by &lt;italic&gt;Pc&lt;/italic&gt;GCE protein perceived as a pathogen-associated molecular pattern (PAMP), we ectopically expressed in aspen an enzymatically inactive &lt;italic&gt;Pc&lt;/italic&gt;GCE&lt;sup&gt;S217A&lt;/sup&gt;. The mutated &lt;italic&gt;Pc&lt;/italic&gt;GCE induced similar growth retardation, leaf necrosis and premature senescence as the active one, providing evidence that &lt;italic&gt;Pc&lt;/italic&gt;GCE protein is recognized as PAMP. Transcriptomics analysis of young expanding leaves of &lt;italic&gt;35S:PcGCE&lt;/italic&gt; plants identified several candidates for receptors of &lt;italic&gt;Pc&lt;/italic&gt;GCE, which were not expressed in developing wood tissues. Grafting experiments showed that &lt;italic&gt;Pc&lt;/italic&gt;GCE transcripts are not cell-to-cell mobile and that leaves augment systemic responses. In agreement, expressing &lt;italic&gt;Pc&lt;/italic&gt;GCE in developing wood by using the woodspecific promoter (WP), avoided all off-target effects. Moreover, &lt;italic&gt;WP:PcGCE&lt;/italic&gt; lines grew better than control plants providing evidence that this strategy can be used in transgenic crops dedicated for biorefinery.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.460629" rel="alternate" title="PcGCE is a potent elicitor of defense responses in aspen (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.460996</id><title>Sensing Local Field Potentials with a Directional and Scalable Depth Array: DISC (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.568535+00:00</updated><author><name>Amada Abrego Mancilla</name></author><author><name>Wasif Khan</name></author><author><name>Christopher E. Wright</name></author><author><name>Neela Prajapati</name></author><author><name>M. Rabiul Islam</name></author><author><name>Mohammad H. Ghajar</name></author><author><name>Xiaokang Bai</name></author><author><name>Nitin Tandon</name></author><author><name>John P. Seymour</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A variety of electrophysiology tools are available to the neurosurgeon for diagnosis, functional therapy, and neural prosthetics. However, no tool can currently address these three critical recording needs: (i) a surgical method that can reach any cortical region in a minimally invasive manner; (ii) record microscale, mesoscale, and macroscale resolutions simultaneously; and (iii) enable recording from multiple brain regions. This work presents a novel device for recording local field potentials (LFPs) whose form is based on state-of-the-art stereo-electroencephalogram (sEEG). Using quasi-static electromagnetic modeling, the lead body is shown to shield LFP sources and this enables &lt;italic&gt;&lt;underline&gt;di&lt;/underline&gt;&lt;/italic&gt;rectional sensitivity and &lt;italic&gt;&lt;underline&gt;sc&lt;/underline&gt;&lt;/italic&gt;alability when microelectrodes are positioned radially, which we refer to as a DISC array. As predicted, DISC demonstrated significantly improved signal-to-noise, directional sensitivity, and decoding accuracy in the rat barrel cortex during whisker stimulation. Critically, DISC also demonstrated equivalent fidelity at the macroscale and, uniquely, performs current source density in stereo. Directional sensitivity of LFPs may significantly improve brain-computer interfaces and many diagnostic procedures, including epilepsy foci detection and deep brain targeting.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.460996" rel="alternate" title="Sensing Local Field Potentials with a Directional and Scalable Depth Array: DISC (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461282</id><title>Computationally-guided tuning of ligand sensitivity in a GPCR-based sensor (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.568740+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Keri</name></author><author><name>Reto B. Cola</name></author><author><name>Zacharoula Kagiampaki</name></author><author><name>Patriarchi Tommaso</name></author><author><name>Patrick Barth</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genetically-encoded fluorescent sensors for neuromodulators are increasingly used molecular tools in neuroscience. However, these protein-based biosensors are often limited by the sensitivity of the protein scaffold towards endogenous ligands. Here, we explored the possibility of applying computational design approaches for enhancing sensor sensitivity. Using the dopamine sensor dLight1 as proof of concept, we designed two variants that boost the sensor’s potency (EC50) for dopamine and norepinephrine by up to 5- and 15-fold, respectively. Interestingly, the largest effects were obtained through improved designed allosteric transmission in the transmembrane region of the sensor. Our approach should prove generally useful for enhancing sensing capabilities of a large variety of neuromodulator sensors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461282" rel="alternate" title="Computationally-guided tuning of ligand sensitivity in a GPCR-based sensor (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461208</id><title>Bioactive Hydrogel Microcapsules for Guiding Stem Cell Fate Decisions by Release and Reloading of Growth Factors (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.568900+00:00</updated><author><name>Kihak Gwon</name></author><author><name>Hye Jin Hong</name></author><author><name>Alan M. Gonzalez-Suarez</name></author><author><name>Michael Q. Slama</name></author><author><name>Daheui Choi</name></author><author><name>Jinkee Hong</name></author><author><name>Harihara Baskaran</name></author><author><name>Gulnaz Stybayeva</name></author><author><name>Quinn P. Peterson</name></author><author><name>Alexander Revzin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human pluripotent stem cells (hPSC) hold considerable promise as a source of adult cells for treatment of diseases ranging from diabetes to liver failure. Some of the challenges that limit the clinical/translational impact of hPSCs are high cost and difficulty in scaling-up of existing differentiation protocols. In this paper, we sought to address these challenges through the development of bioactive microcapsules. A co-axial flow focusing microfluidic device was used to encapsulate hPSCs in microcapsules comprised of an aqueous core and a hydrogel shell. Importantly, the shell contained heparin moieties for growth factor (GF) binding and release. The aqueous core enabled rapid aggregation of hPSCs into 3D spheroids while the bioactive hydrogel shell was used to load inductive cues driving pluripotency maintenance and endodermal differentiation. Specifically, we demonstrated that one-time 1h long loading of pluripotency signals, fibroblast growth factor (FGF)-2 and transforming growth factor (TGF)-β1, into bioactive microcapsules was sufficient to induce and maintain pluripotency of hPSCs over the course of 5 days at levels similar to or better than a standard protocol with soluble GFs. Furthermore, stem cell-carrying microcapsules that previously contained pluripotency signals could be reloaded with an endodermal cue, Nodal, resulting in higher levels of endodermal markers compared to stem cells differentiated in a standard protocol. Overall, bioactive heparin-containing core-shell microcapsules decreased GF usage five-fold while improving stem cell phenotype and are well suited for 3D cultivation of hPSCs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461208" rel="alternate" title="Bioactive Hydrogel Microcapsules for Guiding Stem Cell Fate Decisions by Release and Reloading of Growth Factors (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462404</id><title>Localization free super-resolution microbubble velocimetry using a long short-term memory neural network (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.569085+00:00</updated><author><name>Xi Chen</name></author><author><name>Matthew R. Lowerison</name></author><author><name>Zhijie Dong</name></author><author><name>Nathiya Chandra Sekaran</name></author><author><name>Chengwu Huang</name></author><author><name>Shigao Chen</name></author><author><name>Timothy M. Fan</name></author><author><name>Daniel A. Llano</name></author><author><name>Pengfei Song</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ultrasound localization microscopy is a super-resolution imaging technique that exploits the unique characteristics of contrast microbubbles to side-step the fundamental trade-off between imaging resolution and penetration depth. However, the conventional reconstruction technique is confined to low microbubble concentrations to avoid localization and tracking errors. Several research groups have introduced sparsity- and deep learning-based approaches to overcome this constraint to extract useful vascular structural information from overlapping microbubble signals, but these solutions have not been demonstrated to produce blood flow velocity maps of the microcirculation. Here, we introduce Deep-SMV, a localization free super-resolution microbubble velocimetry technique, based on a long short-term memory neural network, that provides high imaging speed and robustness to high microbubble concentrations, and directly outputs blood velocity measurements at a super-resolution. Deep-SMV is trained efficiently using microbubble flow simulation on real &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; vascular data and demonstrates real-time velocity map reconstruction suitable for functional vascular imaging at super-resolution. The technique is successfully applied to a wide variety of imaging scenarios, include flow channel phantoms, chicken embryo chorioallantoic membranes, and mouse kidney, tumor, and brain imaging.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462404" rel="alternate" title="Localization free super-resolution microbubble velocimetry using a long short-term memory neural network (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>