<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.057697+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475103</id><title>The role of collegiality in academic review, promotion, and tenure (27 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.058109+00:00</updated><author><name>Diane Dawson</name></author><author><name>Esteban Morales</name></author><author><name>Erin C. McKiernan</name></author><author><name>Lesley A. Schimanski</name></author><author><name>Meredith T. Niles</name></author><author><name>Juan Pablo Alperin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Review, promotion, and tenure (RPT) processes at universities typically assess candidates along three dimensions: research, teaching, and service. In recent years, some have argued for the inclusion of a controversial fourth criterion: collegiality. While collegiality plays a role in the morale and effectiveness of academic departments, it is amorphic and difficult to assess, and could be misused to stifle dissent or enforce homogeneity. Despite this, some institutions have opted to include this additional element in their RPT documents and processes, but it is unknown the extent of this practice and how it varies across institution type and disciplinary units. This study is based on two sets of data: survey data collected as part of a project that explored the publishing decisions of faculty and how these related to perceived importance in RPT processes, and 864 RPT documents collected from 129 universities from the United States and Canada. We analysed these RPT documents to determine the degree to which collegiality and related terms are mentioned, if they are defined, and if and how they may be assessed during the RPT process. Results show that when collegiality and related terms appear in these documents they are most often just briefly &lt;italic&gt;mentioned&lt;/italic&gt;. It is less common for collegiality and related terms to be &lt;italic&gt;defined&lt;/italic&gt; or &lt;italic&gt;assessed&lt;/italic&gt; in RPT documents. Although the terms are &lt;italic&gt;mentioned&lt;/italic&gt; across all types of institutions, there is a statistically significant difference in how prevalent they are at each. Collegiality is more commonly mentioned in the documents of doctoral research-focused universities (60%), than of master’s universities and colleges (31%) or baccalaureate colleges (15%). Results from the accompanying survey of faculty also support this finding: individuals from R-Types were more likely to perceive collegiality to be a factor in their RPT processes. We conclude that collegiality likely plays an important role in RPT processes, whether it is explicitly acknowledged in policies and guidelines or not, and point to several strategies in how it might be best incorporated in the assessment of academic careers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475103" rel="alternate" title="The role of collegiality in academic review, promotion, and tenure (27 tweets)"/><category term="Scientific Communication and Education"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474944</id><title>A Low-Cost, 3D-Printed Biosensor for Rapid Detection of Escherichia coli (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.058406+00:00</updated><author><name>Samir Malhotra</name></author><author><name>Dang Song Pham</name></author><author><name>Michael P.H. Lau</name></author><author><name>Anh H. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Hung Cao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Detection of bacterial pathogens is significant in the fields of food safety, medicine, public health, etc. If bacterial pathogens are not treated promptly, antimicrobial resistance is possible and can lead to morbidity and mortality. Current bacterial detection methodologies rely on laboratory-based techniques that pose limitations such as long turnaround detection times, expensive costs, inadequate accuracy, and required trained specialists. Here, we describe a cost-effective and portable 3D-printed electrochemical biosensor that facilitates rapid detection of certain &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;) strains (DH5α, BL21, TOP10, and JM109) within 15 minutes using 500 μL of sample and costs $2.50 per test. The sensor displayed an excellent limit of detection (LOD) of 53 cfu, limit of quantification (LOQ) of 270 cfu, and showed cross-reactivity with strains BL21 and JM109 due to shared epitopes. This advantageous diagnostic device is a potential candidate for high-frequency testing at point of care as well as applicable to various fields where pathogen detection is of interest.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474944" rel="alternate" title="A Low-Cost, 3D-Printed Biosensor for Rapid Detection of Escherichia coli (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.475008</id><title>Metabolic rescue ameliorates mitochondrial encephalo-cardiomyopathy in murine and human iPSC models of Leigh syndrome (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.058605+00:00</updated><author><name>Jin-Young Yoon</name></author><author><name>Nastaran Daneshgar</name></author><author><name>Yi Chu</name></author><author><name>Biyi Chen</name></author><author><name>Marco Hefti</name></author><author><name>Kaikobad Irani</name></author><author><name>Long-Sheng Song</name></author><author><name>Charles Brenner</name></author><author><name>E. Dale Abel</name></author><author><name>Barry London</name></author><author><name>Dao-Fu Dai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mice with deletion of complex I subunit Ndufs4 develop mitochondrial encephalomyopathy resembling Leigh syndrome (LS). We report that LS mice also develop severe cardiac bradyarrhythmia and diastolic dysfunction. Human induced pluripotent stem cell-derived cardiomyocytes (iPS-CMs) with Ndufs4 deletion recapitulate LS cardiomyopathy. Mechanistically, we demonstrate a direct link between complex I deficiency, decreased intracellular NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;/ NADH and bradyarrhythmia, mediated by hyperacetylation of the cardiac sodium channel Na&lt;sub&gt;V&lt;/sub&gt;1.5, particularly at K1479 site. Neuronal apoptosis in the cerebellar and midbrain regions in LS mice was associated with hyperacetylation of p53 and activation of microglia. Targeted metabolomics revealed increases in several amino acids and citric acid cycle intermediates, likely due to impairment of NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;-dependent dehydrogenases, and a substantial decrease in reduced Glutathione (GSH). Metabolic rescue by nicotinamide riboside (NR) supplementation increased intracellular NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;/ NADH, restored metabolic derangement, reversed protein hyperacetylation through NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;-dependent Sirtuin deacetylase, and ameliorated cardiomyopathic phenotypes, concomitant with improvement of Na&lt;sub&gt;V&lt;/sub&gt;1.5 current and SERCA2a function measured by Ca2&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;- transients. NR also attenuated neuronal apoptosis and microglial activation in the LS brain and human iPS-derived neurons with Ndufs4 deletion. Our study reveals direct mechanistic explanations of the observed cardiac bradyarrhythmia, diastolic dysfunction and neuronal apoptosis in mouse and human iPSC models of LS.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.475008" rel="alternate" title="Metabolic rescue ameliorates mitochondrial encephalo-cardiomyopathy in murine and human iPSC models of Leigh syndrome (4 tweets)"/><category term="Pathology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474983</id><title>Embracing enzyme promiscuity with activity-based compressed biosensing (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.058853+00:00</updated><author><name>Brandon Alexander Holt</name></author><author><name>Hong Seo Lim</name></author><author><name>Melanie Su</name></author><author><name>McKenzie Tuttle</name></author><author><name>Haley Liakakos</name></author><author><name>Peng Qiu</name></author><author><name>Gabriel A. Kwong</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genome-scale activity-based profiling of proteases requires identifying substrates that are specific to each individual protease. However, this process becomes increasingly difficult as the number of target proteases increases because most substrates are promiscuously cleaved by multiple proteases. We introduce a method – &lt;bold&gt;S&lt;/bold&gt;ubstrate &lt;bold&gt;Li&lt;/bold&gt;braries for &lt;bold&gt;C&lt;/bold&gt;ompressed sensing of &lt;bold&gt;E&lt;/bold&gt;nzymes (SLICE) – for selecting complementary sets of promiscuous substrates to compile libraries that classify complex protease samples (1) without requiring deconvolution of the compressed signals and (2) without the use of highly specific substrates. SLICE ranks substrate libraries according to two features: substrate orthogonality and protease coverage. To quantify these features, we design a compression score that was predictive of classification accuracy across 140 &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; libraries (Pearson &lt;italic&gt;r&lt;/italic&gt; = 0.71) and 55 &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; libraries (Pearson &lt;italic&gt;r&lt;/italic&gt; = 0.55) of protease substrates. We demonstrate that a library comprising only two protease substrates selected with SLICE can accurately classify twenty complex mixtures of 11 enzymes with perfect accuracy. We envision that SLICE will enable the selection of peptide libraries that capture information from hundreds of enzymes while using fewer substrates for applications such as the design of activity-based sensors for imaging and diagnostics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474983" rel="alternate" title="Embracing enzyme promiscuity with activity-based compressed biosensing (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>