<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.469512+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.25.474038</id><title>Ultra-high-speed multi-parametric photoacoustic microscopy (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.469897+00:00</updated><author><name>Song Hu</name></author><author><name>Fenghe Zhong</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Multi-parametric photoacoustic microscopy (PAM) is uniquely capable of simultaneous, high-resolution mapping of blood hemoglobin concentration, oxygenation, and flow in vivo. However, its speed has been limited by the dense sampling required for blood flow quantification. To overcome this limitation, we have developed an ultra-high-speed multi-parametric PAM system, which enables simultaneous acquisition of ~500 densely sampled B-scans by superposing the rapid laser scanning across the line-shaped focus of a cylindrically focused ultrasonic transducer over the conventional mechanical scan of the optical-acoustic dual foci. A novel optical-acoustic combiner is designed and implemented to accommodate the short working distance of the transducer, enabling convenient confocal alignment of the dual foci in the reflection mode. This new system enables continuous monitoring of microvascular hemoglobin concentration, blood oxygenation, and flow over a 4.5 x 3 mm2 area in the awake mouse brain with high spatial and temporal resolution (6.9 μm and 0.3 Hz, respectively).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.25.474038" rel="alternate" title="Ultra-high-speed multi-parametric photoacoustic microscopy (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473478</id><title>Accelerating manufacturing to start large-scale supply of a new adenovirus-vectored vaccine within 100 days (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.470134+00:00</updated><author><name>Carina CD Joe</name></author><author><name>Rameswara R Segireddy</name></author><author><name>Cathy Oliveira</name></author><author><name>Adam Berg</name></author><author><name>Yuanyuan Li</name></author><author><name>Dimitrios Doultsinos</name></author><author><name>Nitin Chopra</name></author><author><name>Steffi Scholze</name></author><author><name>Asma Ahmad</name></author><author><name>Piergiuseppe Nestola</name></author><author><name>Julia Niemann</name></author><author><name>Alexander Douglas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Coalition for Epidemic Preparedness Innovations &amp;amp;rsquo  &amp;amp;lsquo 100-day moonshot &amp;amp;rsquo aspires to launch a new vaccine within 100 days of pathogen identification. Here, we describe work to optimize adenovirus vector manufacturing for rapid response, by minimizing time to clinical trial and first large-scale supply, and maximizing the output from the available manufacturing footprint. We describe a rapid viral seed expansion workflow that allows vaccine release to clinical trials within 60 days of antigen sequence identification, followed by vaccine release from globally distributed sites within a further 40 days. We also describe a new perfusion-based upstream production process, designed to maximize output while retaining simplicity and suitability for existing manufacturing facilities. This improves upstream volumetric productivity of ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 by around four-fold and remains compatible with the existing downstream process, yielding drug substance sufficient for 10000 doses from each liter of bioreactor capacity. Transition to a new production process across a large manufacturing network is a major task. In the short term, the rapid seed generation workflow could be used with the existing production process. We also use techno-economic modelling to show that, if linear scale-up were achieved, a single cleanroom containing two 2000 L bioreactors running our new perfusion-based process could supply bulk drug substance for around 120 million doses each month, costing &amp;lt;0.20 EUR/dose. We estimate that a manufacturing network with 32000 L of bioreactor capacity could release around 1 billion doses of a new vaccine within 130 days of genomic sequencing of a new pathogen, in a hypothetical surge campaign with suitable prior preparation and resources, including adequate fill-and-finish capacity. This accelerated manufacturing process, along with other advantages such as thermal stability, supports the ongoing value of adenovirus-vectored vaccines as a rapidly adaptable and deployable platform for emergency response.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473478" rel="alternate" title="Accelerating manufacturing to start large-scale supply of a new adenovirus-vectored vaccine within 100 days (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473715</id><title>Using antibody synergy to engineer a high potency biologic cocktail against C. difficile (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.470420+00:00</updated><author><name>Hui Zhao</name></author><author><name>Michael Tasch</name></author><author><name>Michael Dodds</name></author><author><name>Mesfin Gewe</name></author><author><name>Anissa Martinez</name></author><author><name>Melanie Hutton</name></author><author><name>Kristie Keeney</name></author><author><name>Alex Pollock</name></author><author><name>Ben Jester</name></author><author><name>Nhi Khuong</name></author><author><name>Mia Zhang</name></author><author><name>Colin Brady</name></author><author><name>Mark Heinnickel</name></author><author><name>Hannah Tabakh</name></author><author><name>Nathan Sanjaya</name></author><author><name>Kendra Cruickshank</name></author><author><name>Troy Paddock</name></author><author><name>Stacey Ertel</name></author><author><name>Sarah Struyvenberg</name></author><author><name>Jason Dang</name></author><author><name>Chelsea Shanitta</name></author><author><name>David Fletcher</name></author><author><name>Lauren Goetsch</name></author><author><name>Caitlin Gamble</name></author><author><name>Steven J. Mileto</name></author><author><name>Ryan Heselpoth</name></author><author><name>Dena Lyras</name></author><author><name>Craig A. Behnke</name></author><author><name>Vincent Fischetti</name></author><author><name>Brian Finrow</name></author><author><name>James M. Roberts</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We applied a mathematical framework originally used to model the effects of multiple inhibitors on enzyme activity to guide the development a therapeutic antibody cocktail, LMN-201, to prevent and treat &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; infection (CDI). CDI causes hundreds of thousands of cases of severe, often recurrent diarrhea and colitis in the United States annually and is associated with significant morbidity and mortality worldwide. Current therapies for preventing recurrent CDI are only partially successful, and there are no options available to prevent initial bouts of CDI in at-risk populations. Almost all antibody therapies have been developed and administered as monotherapies. Antibody cocktails are relatively rare even though they have the potential to greatly increase efficacy. One reason for this is our limited understanding of how antibody interactions can enhance potency, which makes it difficult to identify and develop antibodies that can be assembled into optimally effective cocktails. In contrast to the view that antibody synergies depend on unusual instances of cooperativity or allostery, we show that synergistic efficacy requires nothing more than that the antibodies bind independently to distinct epitopes on a common target. Therefore, synergy may be achieved much more readily than is generally appreciated. Due to synergy the LMN-201 antibody cocktail, which targets the &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; exotoxin B (TcdB), is 300- to 3000-fold more potent at neutralizing the most clinically prevalent TcdB toxin types than bezlotoxumab, the only monoclonal antibody currently approved for treatment or prevention of CDI. The efficacy of LMN-201 is further enhanced by inclusion of a phage-derived endolysin that destroys the C. difficile bacterium, and which therefore has a complementary mechanism of action to the antibody cocktail. These observations may serve as a paradigm for the development of high potency biologic cocktails against targets that have proven challenging for single-agent therapies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473715" rel="alternate" title="Using antibody synergy to engineer a high potency biologic cocktail against C. difficile (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.18.473289</id><title>Reversable deformation of artificial cell colony for muscle behavior mimicry triggered by actin polymerization (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.470839+00:00</updated><author><name>Chao Li</name></author><author><name>Xiangxiang Zhang</name></author><author><name>Boyu Yang</name></author><author><name>Feng Wei</name></author><author><name>Yongshuo Ren</name></author><author><name>Wei Mu</name></author><author><name>Xiaojun Han</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mimicry of living tissues from artificial cells is beneficial to understanding the interaction mechanism among cells, as well as holding great potentials in the tissue engineering field. Self-powered artificial cells capable of reversible deformation are developed by encapsulating living mitochondria, actin proteins, and methylcellulose. Upon the addition of pyruvate molecules, the mitochondria produce ATP molecules as energy sources to trigger the polymerization of actin. ATP molecules were produced by mitochondria (2.76×10&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;/ml) with the concentrations of 35.8±3.2 µM, 158.2±19.3 µM and 200.7±20.1 μM by adding pyruvate molecules with the concentration of 3 μM, 12 μM and 21 μM, respectively. The reversible deformation of artificial cells is experienced with spindle shape resulting from the polymerization of actins to form filaments adjacent to the lipid bilayer, subsequently back to spherical shape resulting from the depolymerization of actin filaments upon laser irradiations. The linear colonies composed of these artificial cells exhibit collective contraction and relaxation behavior to mimic muscle tissues. At the stage of maximum contraction, the long axis of each GUV is in parallel to each other. All colonies are synchronized in the contraction phase. The deformation of each GUV in the colonies is influenced by its adjacent GUVs. The muscle-like artificial cell colonies paved the path to develop sustainably self-powered artificial tissues in the field of tissue engineering.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.18.473289" rel="alternate" title="Reversable deformation of artificial cell colony for muscle behavior mimicry triggered by actin polymerization (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473705</id><title>Deep Learning-powered Bessel-beam Multi-parametric Photoacoustic Microscopy (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.471044+00:00</updated><author><name>Yifeng Zhou</name></author><author><name>Naidi Sun</name></author><author><name>Song Hu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Enabling simultaneous and high resolution quantification of the total concentration of hemoglobin (CHb), oxygen saturation of hemoglobin (sO2), and cerebral blood flow (CBF), multi parametric photoacoustic microscopy (PAM) has emerged as a promising tool for functional and metabolic imaging of the live mouse brain. However, due to the limited depth of focus imposed by the Gaussian beam excitation, the quantitative measurements become inaccurate when the imaging object is out of focus. To address this problem, we have developed a hardware-software combined approach by integrating Bessel beam excitation and conditional generative adversarial network (cGAN) based deep learning. Side by side comparison of the new cGAN powered Bessel-beam multi parametric PAM against the conventional Gaussian beam multi parametric PAM shows that the new system enables high resolution, quantitative imaging of CHb, sO2, and CBF over a depth range of ~600 μm in the live mouse brain, with errors 13 to 58 times lower than those of the conventional system. Better fulfilling the rigid requirement of light focusing for accurate hemodynamic measurements, the deep learning powered Bessel beam multi parametric PAM may find applications in large field functional recording across the uneven brain surface and beyond (e.g., tumor imaging).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473705" rel="alternate" title="Deep Learning-powered Bessel-beam Multi-parametric Photoacoustic Microscopy (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.471878</id><title>Photothermal Dye-based Subcellular-sized Heat Spot Enabling the Modulation of Local Cellular Activities (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.471215+00:00</updated><author><name> Ferdinandus</name></author><author><name>Madoka Suzuki</name></author><author><name>Yoshie Harada</name></author><author><name>Satya Ranjan Sarker</name></author><author><name>Shin’ichi Ishiwata</name></author><author><name>Tetsuya Kitaguchi</name></author><author><name>Satoshi Arai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Thermal engineering at microscale such as the control and measurement of temperature is a key technology in basic biological research and biomaterials development, which remains challenge yet. Here, we engineered the polymeric nanoparticle, in which a fluorescent temperature sensory dye and a photothermal dye were embedded in its polymer matrices, termed &lt;bold&gt;nanoHT&lt;/bold&gt;. When a near infrared laser at 808 nm is illuminated to the particle, it enables to create the subcellular-sized heat spot in a live cell, where fluorescence thermometry allows the read out of the temperature increment concurrently at individual heat spots. Owing to the controlled local heating, we found that the cell death of HeLa cells was induced at the certain temperature at rate of a few seconds. It should be also noted that the cell death was triggered from the very local heat spot at subcellular level. Furthermore, &lt;bold&gt;nanoHT&lt;/bold&gt; was applied for the induction of muscle contraction of the C2C12 myotube by heat. We successfully showed that the heat-induced contraction took place at the limited area of a single myotube according to the alteration of protein-protein interactions related to the contraction event. These studies demonstrated that even a single heat spot provided by a photothermal material could be very effective in altering cellular functions, paving the way for novel photothermal therapies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.471878" rel="alternate" title="Photothermal Dye-based Subcellular-sized Heat Spot Enabling the Modulation of Local Cellular Activities (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.474044</id><title>Homogeneity of antibody-drug conjugates critically impacts the therapeutic efficacy in brain tumors (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.471453+00:00</updated><author><name>Yasuaki Anami</name></author><author><name>Yoshihiro Otani</name></author><author><name>Wei Xiong</name></author><author><name>Summer Y. Y. Ha</name></author><author><name>Aiko Yamaguchi</name></author><author><name>Ningyan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Zhiqiang An</name></author><author><name>Balveen Kaur</name></author><author><name>Kyoji Tsuchikama</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glioblastoma multiforme (GBM) is characterized by aggressive growth and the poorest prognosis of all brain tumor types. Most therapies rarely provide clinically meaningful improvements in outcomes of patients with GBM. Antibody-drug conjugates (ADCs) are emerging chemotherapeutics with stunning success in cancer management. Although promising, clinical studies of three ADCs for treating GBM, including Depatux-M, have been discontinued because of safety concerns and limited therapeutic benefits. Here, we report that ADC homogeneity is a critical parameter to maximize the therapeutic potential in GBM therapy. We demonstrate that homogeneous conjugates generated using our linker show enhanced drug delivery to intracranial brain tumors. Notably, compared to heterogeneous ADCs, including a Depatux-M analog, our ADCs provide greatly improved antitumor effects and survival benefits in orthotopic brain tumor models, including a patient-derived xenograft model of GBM. Our findings warrant the future development of homogeneous ADCs as promising molecular entities toward cures for intractable brain tumors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.474044" rel="alternate" title="Homogeneity of antibody-drug conjugates critically impacts the therapeutic efficacy in brain tumors (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473402</id><title>Self-confocal NIR-II fluorescence microscopy for in vivo imaging (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.471693+00:00</updated><author><name>Jing Zhou</name></author><author><name>Tianxiang Wu</name></author><author><name>Liang Zhu</name></author><author><name>Yifei Li</name></author><author><name>Liying Chen</name></author><author><name>Jun Qian</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Benefiting from low scatter of NIR-II light in biological tissues and high spatial resolution of confocal microscopy, NIR-II fluorescence confocal microscopy has been developed recently and achieve deep imaging in vivo. However, independence of excitation point and detection point makes this system difficult to be adjusted. New, improved, self-confocal NIR-II fluorescence confocal systems are created in this work. Based on a shared pinhole for excitation light and fluorescence, the system is easy and controlled to be adjusted. The fiber-pinhole confocal system is constructed for cerebrovascular and hepatocellular NIR-II fluorescence intensity imaging. The air-pinhole confocal system is constructed for cerebrovascular NIR-II fluorescence intensity imaging, hepatic NIR-II fluorescence lifetime imaging, and hepatic multiphoton imaging.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473402" rel="alternate" title="Self-confocal NIR-II fluorescence microscopy for in vivo imaging (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473340</id><title>Process engineering of biopharmaceutical production in moss bioreactors via model-based description and evaluation of phytohormone impact (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.471891+00:00</updated><author><name>Natalia Ruiz-Molina</name></author><author><name>Juliana Parsons</name></author><author><name>Sina Schroeder</name></author><author><name>Clemens Posten</name></author><author><name>Ralf Reski</name></author><author><name>Eva L. Decker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The moss Physcomitrella is an interesting production host for recombinant biopharmaceuticals. Here we produced MFHR1, a synthetic complement regulator which has been proposed for the treatment of diseases associated to the complement system as part of human innate immunity. We studied the impact of different operation modes for the production process in 5 L stirred-tank photobioreactors. The total amount of recombinant protein was doubled by using fed-batch or batch compared to semi-continuous operation, although the maximum specific productivity (mg MFHR1/g FW) increased just by 35%. We proposed an unstructured kinetic model which fits accurately with the experimental data in batch and semi-continuous operation under autotrophic conditions with 2% CO2 enrichment. The model is able to predict recombinant protein production, nitrate uptake and biomass growth, which is useful for process control and optimization. We investigated strategies to further increase MFHR1 production. While mixotrophic and heterotrophic conditions decreased the MFHR1-specific productivity compared to autotrophic conditions, addition of the phytohormone auxin (NAA, 10 μM) to the medium enhanced it by 470% in shaken flasks and up to 230% and 260%, in batch and fed-batch bioreactors, respectively. Supporting this finding, the auxin-synthesis inhibitor L-Kynurenine (100 μM) decreased MFHR1 production significantly by 110% and 580% at day 7 and 18, respectively. Expression analysis revealed that the MFHR1 transgene, driven by the Physcomitrella actin5 (PpAct5) promoter, was upregulated 16 hours after NAA addition and remained enhanced over the whole process, whereas the auxin-responsive gene PpIAA1A was upregulated within the first two hours, indicating that the effect of auxin on PpAct5 promoter-driven expression is indirect. Furthermore, the day of NAA supplementation was crucial, leading to an up to 8-fold increase of MFHR1-specific productivity (0.82 mg MFHR1/ g fresh weight, 150 mg accumulated over 7 days) compared to the productivity reported previously. Our findings are likely to be applicable to other plant-based expression systems to increase biopharmaceutical production and yields.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473340" rel="alternate" title="Process engineering of biopharmaceutical production in moss bioreactors via model-based description and evaluation of phytohormone impact (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473721</id><title>Comprehensive Fitness Landscape of a Multi-Geometry Protein Capsid Informs Machine Learning Models of Assembly (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.472087+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel D. Brauer</name></author><author><name>Celine B. Santiago</name></author><author><name>Zoe N. Merz</name></author><author><name>Esther McCarthy</name></author><author><name>Danielle Tullman-Ercek</name></author><author><name>Matthew B. Francis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Virus-like  particles  (VLPs)  are  non-infections  viral-derived  nanomaterials  poised for biotechnological applications due to their well-defined, modular self-assembling architecture.   Although  progress  has  been  made  in  understanding  the  complex  effects that  mutations  may  have  on  VLPs,  nuanced  understanding  of  the  influence  particle  mutability has on quaternary structure has yet to be achieved.  Here, we generate and compare the apparent fitness landscapes of two capsid geometries (T=3 and T=1 icosahedral) of the bacteriophage MS2 VLP. We find significant shifts in mutability at the symmetry interfaces of the T=1 capsid when compared to the wildtype T=3 assembly. Furthermore, we use the generated landscapes to benchmark the performance of &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; mutational scanning tools in capturing the effect of missense mutation on complex particle assembly.  Finding that predicted stability effects correlated relatively poorly with assembly phenotype, we used a combination of &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; features in tandem with &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; results to train machine learning algorithms for the classification of variant effects on assembly.  Our findings not only reveal ways that assembly geometry affects the mutable landscape of a self-assembled particle,  but also establish a template for the generation of predictive mutational models of self-assembled capsids using minimal empirical training data.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473721" rel="alternate" title="Comprehensive Fitness Landscape of a Multi-Geometry Protein Capsid Informs Machine Learning Models of Assembly (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>