<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular other biological sciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.210373+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/other-biological-sciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469897</id><title>Increasing Animal Cognition Research in Zoos (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.210688+00:00</updated><author><name>Elias Garcia-Pelegrin</name></author><author><name>Fay E. Clark</name></author><author><name>Rachael Miller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Animal cognition covers various mental processes including perception, learning, decision-making and memory, and animal behavior is often used as a proxy for measuring cognition. Animal cognition/behavior research has multiple benefits; it provides fundamental knowledge on animal biology and evolution but can also have applied conservation and welfare applications. Zoos provide an excellent yet relatively untapped resource for animal cognition research, because they house a wide variety of species - many of which are under threat - and allow close observation and relatively high experimental control compared to the wild. Multi-zoo collaboration leads to increased sample size and species representation, which in turn leads to more robust science. However, there are salient challenges associated with zoo-based cognitive research, which are subject-based (e.g., small sample sizes at single zoos, untrained/unhabituated subjects, site effects) and human-based (e.g., time restrictions, safety concerns, and perceptions of animals interacting with unnatural technology or apparatus). We aim to increase the understanding and subsequent uptake of animal cognition research in zoos, by transparently outlining the main benefits and challenges. Importantly, we use our own research (1) a study on novelty responses in hornbills, and (2) a multi-site collaboration called the ‘ManyBirds’ project to demonstrate how challenges may be overcome. These potential options include using ‘drop and go’ apparatuses that require no training, close human contact or animal separation. This article is aimed at zoo animal care and research staff, as well as external researchers interested in zoo-based studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;RESEARCH HIGHLIGHTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zoos are an excellent yet relatively untapped resource for animal cognition research.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zoo cognition research has historically been challenging, and traditional laboratory paradigms often do not translate well to the majority of zoos.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Salient challenges of zoo-based cognitive research can be overcome by using less restrictive test apparatuses, limiting animal training and isolation, and subscribing to multi-zoo collaborative programs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469897" rel="alternate" title="Increasing Animal Cognition Research in Zoos (24 tweets)"/><category term="Scientific Communication and Education"/><published>2021-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470714</id><title>An in vitro, in utero and in silico framework of oxygen diffusion in intricate vascular networks of the placenta (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.210883+00:00</updated><author><name>Nikhilesh Bappoo</name></author><author><name>Lachlan J. Kelsey</name></author><author><name>Yutthapong Tongpob</name></author><author><name>Kirk W. Feindel</name></author><author><name>Harrison Caddy</name></author><author><name>Caitlin S. Wyrwoll</name></author><author><name>Barry J. Doyle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The placenta is a temporary and complex organ critical for fetal development through its subtle but convoluted harmonization of endocrine, vascular, haemodynamic and exchange adaptations. Yet, due to experimental, technological and ethical constraints, this unique organ remains poorly understood. &lt;italic&gt;In silico&lt;/italic&gt; tools are emerging as a powerful means to overcome these challenges and have the potential to actualize novel breakthroughs. Here, we present an interdisciplinary framework combining &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; experiments used to develop an elegant and scalable &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; model of oxygen diffusion. We then use &lt;italic&gt;in utero&lt;/italic&gt; imaging of placental perfusion and oxygenation in both control and growth-restricted rodent placentas for validation of our &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; model. Our framework revealed the structure-function relationship in the feto-placental vasculature; oxygen diffusion is impaired in growth-restricted placentas, due to the diminished arborization of growth-restricted feto-placental vasculature and the lack of decelerated flow for adequate oxygen diffusion and exchange. We highlight the mechanisms of impairment in a rat model of growth restriction, underpinned by placental vascular impairment. Our framework reports and validates the prediction of blood flow deceleration impairment in growth restricted placentas with the placenta’s oxygen transfer capability being significantly impaired, both globally and locally.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470714" rel="alternate" title="An in vitro, in utero and in silico framework of oxygen diffusion in intricate vascular networks of the placenta (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioengineering"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.469764</id><title>The Importance of Mentors and How to Handle More Than One Mentor (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.211068+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrea G. Marshall</name></author><author><name>Lillian J. Brady</name></author><author><name>Caroline B. Palavicino-Maggio</name></author><author><name>Kit Neirkirk</name></author><author><name>Zer Vue</name></author><author><name>Heather Beasley</name></author><author><name>Edgar Garza-Lopez</name></author><author><name>Sandra Murray</name></author><author><name>Denise Martinez</name></author><author><name>Haysetta Shuler</name></author><author><name>Elsie C. Spencer</name></author><author><name>Derrick Morton</name></author><author><name>Antentor Hinton</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Working with multiple mentors is a critical way for students to expand their network, gain opportunities, and better prepare for future scholastic or professional ventures. However, students from underrepresented groups (UR) are less likely to be mentored or have access to mentors, particularly in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) fields. We developed and implemented a workshop, to provide the necessary foundation for students to be better prepared for establishing future mentorships throughout graduate and professional school.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Faculty well-versed in the area of effective mentorship from multiple universities developed and delivered a 1.5-hour workshop to address the roles of a mentor, especially when it comes to UR students, and how students may effectively work with multiple mentors. This workshop was delivered to a group of students from the HBCU Winston Salem State University, and a pre/post-Likert scale-based survey was administered.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We analyzed the raw data with nonparametric tests for comparison within paired samples. Wilcoxon matched-pairs and signed-rank tests showed statistically significant growth in student self-ratings related to the workshop learning objectives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The “How to Handle More than One Mentor to Achieve Excellence” workshop was well received as a component of pre-graduate and pre-professional training. Incorporating workshops like this may increase student preparedness around developing and cultivating healthy mentorship relationships throughout STEM training.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;EDUCATIONAL OBJECTIVES&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;By the end of this workshop, learners will be able to:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Describe the role of mentors in developing the next generation of trainees.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Describe current research on mentorship among underrepresented populations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Apply skills on effective communication needed in the development of successful mentorship relationships.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work with multiple mentors at one time while maintaining solid professional and personal relationships.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.469764" rel="alternate" title="The Importance of Mentors and How to Handle More Than One Mentor (5 tweets)"/><category term="Scientific Communication and Education"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>