<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv cancer-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.608995+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443157</id><title>O-GlcNAc transferase regulates glioblastoma acetate metabolism via regulation of CDK5-dependent ACSS2 phosphorylation (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.609291+00:00</updated><author><name>Lorela Ciraku</name></author><author><name>Zachary A. Bacigalupa</name></author><author><name>Jing Ju</name></author><author><name>Rebecca A. Moeller</name></author><author><name>Rusia H. Lee</name></author><author><name>Michael D. Smith</name></author><author><name>Christina M. Ferrer</name></author><author><name>Sophie Trefely</name></author><author><name>Mary T. Doan</name></author><author><name>Wiktoria A. Gocal</name></author><author><name>Luca D’Agostino</name></author><author><name>Wenyin Shi</name></author><author><name>Joshua G. Jackson</name></author><author><name>Christos D. Katsetos</name></author><author><name>Nathaniel W. Snyder</name></author><author><name>Mauricio J. Reginato</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glioblastomas (GBMs) preferentially generate acetyl-CoA from acetate as a fuel source to promote tumor growth. O-GlcNAcylation has been shown to be elevated by increasing O-GlcNAc transferase (OGT) in many cancers and reduced O-GlcNAcylation can block cancer growth. Here, we identify a novel mechanism whereby OGT regulates acetate-dependent acetyl-CoA production by regulating phosphorylation of acetyl-CoA synthetase 2 (ACSS2) by cyclin-dependent kinase 5 (CDK5). OGT is required and sufficient for GBM cell growth and regulates acetate conversion to acetyl-CoA. Elevating O-GlcNAcylation in GBM cells increases phosphorylation of ACSS2 on Ser-267 in a CDK5-dependent manner. Importantly, we show that ACSS2 Ser-267 phosphorylation regulates its stability by reducing polyubiquitination and degradation. ACSS2 Ser-267 is critical for OGT-mediated GBM growth as overexpression of ACSS2 Ser-267 phospho-mimetic rescues growth &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in&lt;/italic&gt; vivo. Importantly, we show that pharmacologically targeting OGT and CDK5 reduces GBM growth &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Thus, the OGT/CDK5/ACSS2 pathway may be a way to target altered metabolic dependencies in brain tumors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443157" rel="alternate" title="O-GlcNAc transferase regulates glioblastoma acetate metabolism via regulation of CDK5-dependent ACSS2 phosphorylation (11 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443282</id><title>Dual G9A and EZH2 inhibition stimulates an anti-tumour immune response in ovarian high-grade serous carcinoma (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.609588+00:00</updated><author><name>Pavlina Spiliopoulou</name></author><author><name>Sarah Spear</name></author><author><name>Hasan Mirza</name></author><author><name>Ian Garner</name></author><author><name>Lynn McGarry</name></author><author><name>Fabio Grundland-Freile</name></author><author><name>Zhao Cheng</name></author><author><name>Darren P. Ennis</name></author><author><name>Sophie McNamara</name></author><author><name>Marina Natoli</name></author><author><name>Susan Mason</name></author><author><name>Karen Blyth</name></author><author><name>Peter D. Adams</name></author><author><name>Patricia Roxburgh</name></author><author><name>Matthew J. Fuchter</name></author><author><name>Bob Brown</name></author><author><name>Iain A. McNeish</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ovarian high-grade serous carcinoma (HGSC) prognosis correlates directly with presence of intratumoral lymphocytes. However, cancer immunotherapy has yet to achieve meaningful survival benefit in patients with HGSC. Epigenetic silencing of immunostimulatory genes is implicated in immune evasion in HGSC and re-expression of these genes could promote tumour immune clearance. We discovered that simultaneous inhibition of the histone methyltransferases G9A and EZH2 activates the CXCL10-CXCR3 axis and increases homing of intratumoral effector lymphocytes and natural killer cells whilst suppressing tumour-promoting FoxP3&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; CD4 T cells. The dual G9A/EZH2 inhibitor HKMTI-1-005 induced chromatin changes that resulted in the transcriptional activation of immunostimulatory gene networks, including the re-expression of elements of the ERV-K endogenous retroviral family. Importantly, treatment with HKMTI-1-005 improved the survival of mice bearing &lt;italic&gt;Trp53&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;-/-&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;null ID8 ovarian tumours and resulted in tumour burden reduction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These results indicate that inhibiting G9A and EZH2 in ovarian cancer alters the immune microenvironment and reduces tumour growth and therefore positions dual inhibition of G9A/EZH2 as a strategy for clinical development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract Figure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="443282v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443282" rel="alternate" title="Dual G9A and EZH2 inhibition stimulates an anti-tumour immune response in ovarian high-grade serous carcinoma (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443240</id><title>Multimodal Analysis Reveals Differential Immuno-Metabolic Features in Lung Squamous Cell Carcinoma and Adenocarcinoma (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.609815+00:00</updated><author><name>Brooks P. Leitner</name></author><author><name>Shyryn Ospanova</name></author><author><name>Aray Beisenbayeva</name></author><author><name>Kevin B. Givechian</name></author><author><name>Katerina Politi</name></author><author><name>Rachel J. Perry</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The relationship between systemic metabolism, immune function, and lung cancer is complex and remains poorly defined. Seemingly paradoxically, overweight and obesity confer an improved response to immune checkpoint inhibition in non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC); however, it is not known whether excess body weight or adiposity impacts the immunometabolic tumor microenvironment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Utilizing three complementary National Cancer Institute-funded open-source databases containing &lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;F-fluorodeoxyglucose positron-emission tomography/computed tomography (PET-CT) images for tumor and tissue glucose uptake, adipose tissue and skeletal muscle mass, histology annotated with tumor infiltrating leukocytes, and tumor RNA sequencing, we performed a retrospective cross-sectional analysis to examine phenotypic, metabolic, and genomic intersections of adiposity and tumor immune-metabolism in patients with lung adenocarcinoma (LUAD) versus squamous cell carcinoma (LUSC).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our data reveal distinct immunometabolomic features of LUSC as compared to LUAD: visceral fat content was negatively correlated with both tumor glucose uptake and leukocyte infiltration. Subcutaneous and visceral adiposity conferred different effects on the tumor genetic landscapes in both tumor types. LUSC tumors showed greater gene expression pathways related to pyruvate, glucose, amino acid, and lipid metabolism, in addition to significantly greater &lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;F-FDG uptake compared with LUAD, suggesting deeper metabolic regulation within the LUSC tumor microenvironment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Several immunometabolomic characteristics of LUSC and LUAD differ, including tumor glucose uptake and the associated metabolic pathways in the tumor, as well as the impact of visceral adiposity on tumor metabolism. These data may highlight opportunities to advance mechanistically targeted precision medicine approaches by better understanding the interplay between metabolic, immunologic, and genomic factors in lung cancer treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443240" rel="alternate" title="Multimodal Analysis Reveals Differential Immuno-Metabolic Features in Lung Squamous Cell Carcinoma and Adenocarcinoma (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>