<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv cancer-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.775780+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.449991</id><title>Spatial epitope barcoding reveals subclonal tumor patch behaviors (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.776235+00:00</updated><author><name>Xavier Rovira-Clavé</name></author><author><name>Alexandros P. Drainas</name></author><author><name>Sizun Jiang</name></author><author><name>Yunhao Bai</name></author><author><name>Maya Baron</name></author><author><name>Bokai Zhu</name></author><author><name>Maxim Markovic</name></author><author><name>Garry L. Coles</name></author><author><name>Michael C. Bassik</name></author><author><name>Julien Sage</name></author><author><name>Garry P. Nolan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Intratumoral variability is a seminal feature of human tumors contributing to tumor progression and response to treatment. Current technologies are unsuitable to accurately track phenotypes and subclonal evolution within tumors, especially in response to genetic manipulations. Here, we developed epitope combinatorial tags (EpicTags), which we coupled to multiplexed ion beam imaging (EpicMIBI) for &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; tracking of barcodes within tissue microenvironments. Using this platform, we dissected the spatial component of cell lineages and phenotypes in a xenograft model of small-cell lung cancer. We observed emergent properties from mixed clones leading to the preferential expansion of subclonal patches for both neuroendocrine and non-neuroendocrine cancer cell states in this model. In tumors harboring a fraction of PTEN-deficient cancer cells, we uncovered a non-autonomous increase of subclonal patch size in PTEN wildtype cancer cells. EpicMIBI can facilitate &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; interrogation of cell-intrinsic and cell-extrinsic processes involved in intratumoral heterogeneity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.449991" rel="alternate" title="Spatial epitope barcoding reveals subclonal tumor patch behaviors (24 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.28.450088</id><title>A novel small molecule that induces cytotoxicity in lung cancer cells inhibits disulfide reductases GSR and TXNRD1 (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.776560+00:00</updated><author><name>Fraser D. Johnson</name></author><author><name>John Ferrarone</name></author><author><name>Alvin Liu</name></author><author><name>Christina Brandstädter</name></author><author><name>Ravi Munuganti</name></author><author><name>Dylan Farnsworth</name></author><author><name>Daniel Lu</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Luu</name></author><author><name>Tianna Sihota</name></author><author><name>Sophie Jansen</name></author><author><name>Amy Nagelberg</name></author><author><name>Rocky Shi</name></author><author><name>Giovanni C. Forcina</name></author><author><name>Xu Zhang</name></author><author><name>Grace S. W. Cheng</name></author><author><name>Sandra E. Spencer Miko</name></author><author><name>Georgia de Rappard-Yuswack</name></author><author><name>Poul H. Sorensen</name></author><author><name>Scott J. Dixon</name></author><author><name>Udayan Guha</name></author><author><name>Katja Becker</name></author><author><name>Hakim Djaballah</name></author><author><name>Romel Somwar</name></author><author><name>Harold Varmus</name></author><author><name>Gregg B. Morin</name></author><author><name>William W. Lockwood</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;High-throughput phenotype-based screening of large libraries of novel compounds without known targets can identify small molecules that elicit a desired cellular response, but additional approaches are required to find and characterize their targets and mechanisms of action. Here we show that a compound termed lung cancer screen 3 (LCS3), previously selected for its ability to impair the growth of human lung adenocarcinoma (LUAD) cell lines, but not normal lung cells, induces oxidative stress and activates the NRF2 signaling pathway by generating reactive oxygen species (ROS) in sensitive LUAD cell lines. To identify the target that mediates this effect, we applied thermal proteome profiling (TPP) and uncovered the disulfide reductases GSR and TXNRD1 as LCS3 targets. Through enzymatic assays using purified protein, we confirmed that LCS3 inhibits disulfide reductase activity through a reversible, uncompetitive mechanism. Further, we demonstrate that LCS3-sensitive LUAD cells are correspondingly sensitive to the synergistic inhibition of glutathione and thioredoxin pathways. Lastly, a genome-wide CRISPR knockout screen identified the loss of NQO1 as a mechanism of LCS3 resistance. This work highlights the ability of TPP to uncover targets of small molecules identified by high-throughput screens and demonstrates the potential utility of inhibiting disulfide reductases as a therapeutic strategy for LUAD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.28.450088" rel="alternate" title="A novel small molecule that induces cytotoxicity in lung cancer cells inhibits disulfide reductases GSR and TXNRD1 (7 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>