<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv cancer-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.668132+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453512</id><title>In vitro and in vivo analysis of microvesicle-mediated metastasis using a bright, red-shifted bioluminescent reporter protein of extracellular vesicles (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.668827+00:00</updated><author><name>Ahmed A Zarea</name></author><author><name>Gloria I Perez</name></author><author><name>David Broadbent</name></author><author><name>Benedikt Dolgikh</name></author><author><name>Matthew P Bernard</name></author><author><name>Alicia Withrow</name></author><author><name>Amelia McGill</name></author><author><name>Victoria Toomajian</name></author><author><name>Lukose K Thampy</name></author><author><name>Jack Harkema</name></author><author><name>Joel R Walker</name></author><author><name>Thomas A Kirkland</name></author><author><name>Michael H Bachmann</name></author><author><name>Jens Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Masamitsu Kanada</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cancer cells produce heterogeneous extracellular vesicles (EVs) as mediators of intercellular communication. Our study focused on a novel method to image EV subtypes and their biodistribution in vivo. Regardless of injection routes, we established that reporter EVs isolated from murine mammary carcinoma cells expressing PalmReNL, which utilizes bioluminescence resonance energy transfer (BRET), localized to the lungs. This new EV reporter allowed highly sensitive EV tracking in vitro and in vivo and enabled us to begin studies to understand the commonalities and functional differences of the EV subtypes. We demonstrated the early appearance of metastatic foci in the lungs of mammary tumor-bearing mice following multiple injections of the microvesicle (MV)-enriched fraction derived from mammary carcinoma cells. In addition, the results we present here show that tumor cell-derived MVs act on distant tissues through upregulating LC3 expression within the lung.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453512" rel="alternate" title="In vitro and in vivo analysis of microvesicle-mediated metastasis using a bright, red-shifted bioluminescent reporter protein of extracellular vesicles (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.453458</id><title>Epithelial-mesenchymal plasticity determines estrogen receptor positive (ER+) breast cancer dormancy and reacquisition of an epithelial state drives awakening (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.669767+00:00</updated><author><name>Aouad Patrik</name></author><author><name>Zhang Yueyun</name></author><author><name>Celine Stibolt</name></author><author><name>Mani Sendurai</name></author><author><name>Georgios Sflomos</name></author><author><name>Cathrin Brisken</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Estrogen receptor α-positive (ER+) breast cancers (BCs) represent more than 70% of all breast cancers and pose a particular clinical challenge because they recur up to decades after initial diagnosis and treatment. The mechanisms governing tumor cell dormancy and latent disease remain elusive due to a lack of adequate models. Here, we compare tumor progression of ER+ and triple-negative (TN) BC subtypes with a clinically relevant mouse intraductal  xenografting approach (MIND). Both ER+ and TN BC cells disseminate already during the in situstage. However, TN disseminated tumor cells (DTCs) proliferate at the same rate as cells at the primary site and give rise to macro-metastases. ER+ DTCs have low proliferative indices, form only micro-metastases and lose epithelial characteristics. Expression of CDH1 is decreased whereas the mesenchymal marker VIM and the transcription factors, ZEB1/ZEB2, which control epithelial-mesenchymal plasticity (EMP) are increased. EMP is not detected earlier during ER+ BC development and not required for invasion or metastasis. In vivo, forced transition to the epithelial state through ectopic E-cadherin expression overcomes dormancy with increased growth of lung metastases. We conclude that EMP is essential for the generation of a dormant cell state and the development of latent disease. Targeting exit from EMP is of therapeutic potential.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.453458" rel="alternate" title="Epithelial-mesenchymal plasticity determines estrogen receptor positive (ER+) breast cancer dormancy and reacquisition of an epithelial state drives awakening (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453632</id><title>PTEN mutant NSCLC require ATM to suppress pro-apoptotic signalling and evade radiotherapy (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.670345+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas Fischer</name></author><author><name>Oliver Hartmann</name></author><author><name>Michaela Reissland</name></author><author><name>Cristian Prieto-Garcia</name></author><author><name>Kevin Klann</name></author><author><name>Christina Schuelein-Voelk</name></author><author><name>Buelent Polat</name></author><author><name>Elena Gebhard-Hartmann</name></author><author><name>Mathias Rosenfeldt</name></author><author><name>Christian Muench</name></author><author><name>Michael Flentje</name></author><author><name>Markus Elmar Diefenbacher</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Despite advances in treatment of patients with non-small cell lung cancer, carriers of certain genetic alterations are prone to failure. One such factor frequently mutated, is the tumor suppressor PTEN. These tumors are supposed to be more resistant to radiation, chemo- and immunotherapy. Methods: Using CRISPR genome editing, we deleted PTEN in a human tracheal stem cell-like cell line as well generated primary murine NSCLC, proficient or deficient for Pten, in vivo. These models were used to verify the impact of PTEN loss in vitro and in vivo by immunohistochemical staining, western blot and RNA-Sequencing. Radiation sensitivity was assessed by colony formation and growth assays. To elucidate putative treatment options, identified via the molecular characterisation, PTEN pro- and deficient cells were treated with PI3K/mTOR/DNA-PK-inhibitor PI-103 or the ATM-inhibitors KU-60019 und AZD 1390. Changes in radiation sensitivity were assessed by colony-formation assay, FACS, western-blot, phospho-proteomic mass spectrometry and ex vivo lung slice cultures. Results: We demonstrate that loss of PTEN led to altered expression of transcriptional programs which directly regulate therapy resistance, resulting in establishment of radiation resistance. While PTEN-deficient tumor cells were not dependent on DNA PK for IR resistance nor activated ATR during IR, they showed a significant dependence for the DNA damage kinase ATM. Pharmacologic inhibition of ATM, via KU-60019 and AZD1390 at non-toxic doses, restored and even synergized with IR in PTEN-deficient human and murine NSCLC cells as well in a multicellular organotypic ex vivo tumor model. Conclusion: PTEN tumors are addicted to ATM to detect and repair radiation induced DNA damage. This creates an exploitable bottleneck. At least in cellulo and ex vivo we show that low concentration of ATM inhibitor is able to synergise with IR to treat PTEN-deficient tumors in genetically well-defined IR resistant lung cancer models.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453632" rel="alternate" title="PTEN mutant NSCLC require ATM to suppress pro-apoptotic signalling and evade radiotherapy (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>