<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv immunology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.607371+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/immunology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443590</id><title>Natural killer cell immunosuppressive function requires CXCR3-dependent redistribution within lymphoid tissues (33 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.607685+00:00</updated><author><name>Ayad Ali</name></author><author><name>Laura M. Canaday</name></author><author><name>H. Alex Feldman</name></author><author><name>Hilal Cevik</name></author><author><name>Michael T. Moran</name></author><author><name>Sanjeeth Rajaram</name></author><author><name>Nora Lakes</name></author><author><name>Jasmine A. Tuazon</name></author><author><name>Harsha Seelamneni</name></author><author><name>Durga Krishnamurthy</name></author><author><name>Eryn Blass</name></author><author><name>Dan H. Barouch</name></author><author><name>Stephen N. Waggoner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Natural killer (NK) cell suppression of T cells is a key determinant of viral pathogenesis and vaccine efficacy. This process involves perforin-dependent elimination of activated CD4 T cells during the first three days of infection. Although this mechanism requires cell-cell contact, NK cells and T cells typically reside in different compartments of lymphoid tissues at steady state. Here, we show that NK-cell suppression of T cells is associated with a transient accumulation of NK cells within T cell-rich sites of the spleen during lymphocytic choriomeningitis virus infection. The chemokine receptor CXCR3 is required for relocation to T-cell zones and suppression of antiviral T cells. Accordingly, this NK-cell migration is mediated by type I interferon (IFN)-dependent promotion of CXCR3 ligand expression. In contrast, adenoviral vectors that weakly induce type I IFN and do not stimulate NK-cell inhibition of T cells also do not promote measurable redistribution of NK cells to T-cell zones. Provision of supplemental IFN could rescue NK-cell migration during adenoviral vector immunization. Thus, type I IFN and CXCR3 are critical for properly positioning NK cells to constrain antiviral T-cell responses. Development of strategies to curtail migration of NK cells between lymphoid compartments may enhance vaccine-elicited immune responses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443590" rel="alternate" title="Natural killer cell immunosuppressive function requires CXCR3-dependent redistribution within lymphoid tissues (33 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443508</id><title>Expanding the Potential Genes of Inborn Errors of Immunity through Protein Interactions (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.607951+00:00</updated><author><name>Humza A. Khan</name></author><author><name>Manish J. Butte</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Inborn errors of immunity (IEI) are a group of genetic disorders that impair the immune system, with over 400 genes described so far, and hundreds more to be discovered. To facilitate the search for new genes, we need a way to prioritize among all the genes in the genome those most likely to play an important role in immunity. Here we identify a new list of genes by linking known IEI genes to new ones by using open-source databases of protein-protein interactions, post-translational modifications, and transcriptional regulation. We analyze this new set of 2,530 IEI-related genes for their tolerance of genetic variation and by their expression levels in various immune cell types.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443508" rel="alternate" title="Expanding the Potential Genes of Inborn Errors of Immunity through Protein Interactions (15 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443916</id><title>IL-31 uncouples skin inflammation from itch sensation in allergic dermatitis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.608115+00:00</updated><author><name>Marlys S. Fassett</name></author><author><name>Joao M. Braz</name></author><author><name>Carlos A. Castellanos</name></author><author><name>Andrew W. Schroeder</name></author><author><name>Mahsa Sadeghi</name></author><author><name>Darryl J. Mar</name></author><author><name>Connie J. Zhou</name></author><author><name>Jeoung-Sook Shin</name></author><author><name>Allan I. Basbaum</name></author><author><name>K. Mark Ansel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite a robust literature associating IL-31 with pruritic inflammatory skin diseases, its influence on cutaneous inflammation and on the interplay between inflammatory and neurosensory pathways remain unmapped. Here, we examined the effects of IL-31 and its receptor IL31RA on both inflammation and pruritus in mouse models of dermatitis, including chronic topical house dust mite (HDM) exposure. Unexpectedly, &lt;italic&gt;Il31&lt;/italic&gt; deficiency increased cutaneous adaptive type 2 cytokine-producing cells and serum IgE. In addition, M2-like macrophages capable of fueling feedforward pro-inflammatory loops were selectively enriched in &lt;italic&gt;Il31ra&lt;/italic&gt;-deficient skin. Thus, IL-31 is not strictly a pro-inflammatory cytokine, but rather an immunoregulatory factor that limits the magnitude of allergic skin inflammation. In contrast, &lt;italic&gt;Il31&lt;/italic&gt;-deficient mice displayed a deficit in HDM-induced scratching. Itch reduction occurred despite intact – and in some cases increased – responsiveness of sensory neurons to other pruritogens released during HDM challenge, highlighting the non-redundant contribution of IL-31-receptive sensory afferents to pruritus in environmental allergen-induced dermatitis. When present, therefore, IL-31 uncouples circuits driven by sensory neurons and immune cells that converge in inflamed skin.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443916" rel="alternate" title="IL-31 uncouples skin inflammation from itch sensation in allergic dermatitis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>