<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv immunology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.704470+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/immunology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.01.446527</id><title>A co-opted ISG15-USP18 binding mechanism normally reserved for deISGylation controls type I IFN signalling (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.704806+00:00</updated><author><name>Andri Vasou</name></author><author><name>Katie Nightingale</name></author><author><name>Vladimíra Cetkovská</name></author><author><name>Connor G.G. Bamford</name></author><author><name>Jelena Andrejeva</name></author><author><name>Richard E. Randall</name></author><author><name>John McLauchlan</name></author><author><name>Michael P. Weekes</name></author><author><name>David J Hughes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Type I interferon (IFN) signalling induces the expression of several hundred IFN-stimulated genes that provide an unfavourable environment for viral replication. To prevent an overexuberant response and autoinflammatory disease, IFN signalling requires tight control. One critical regulator is the ubiquitin-like protein ISG15, evidenced by autoinflammatory disease in patients with inherited ISG15 deficiencies. Current models suggest that ISG15 stabilises USP18, a well-established negative regulator of IFN signalling. USP18 also functions as an ISG15-specific peptidase, however its catalytic activity is dispensable for controlling IFN signalling. Here, we show that the ISG15-dependent stabilisation of USP18 is necessary but not sufficient for regulation of IFN signalling and that USP18 requires non-covalent interactions with ISG15 to enhance its regulatory function. Intriguingly, this trait has been acquired through co-option of a binding mechanism normally reserved for deISGylation, identifying an unexpected new function for ISG15.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.01.446527" rel="alternate" title="A co-opted ISG15-USP18 binding mechanism normally reserved for deISGylation controls type I IFN signalling (18 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.03.446738</id><title>The timing of differentiation and potency of CD8 effector function is set by RNA binding proteins (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.705075+00:00</updated><author><name>Georg Petkau</name></author><author><name>Twm J. Mitchell</name></author><author><name>Krishnendu Chakraborty</name></author><author><name>Sarah E. Bell</name></author><author><name>Vanessa D’Angeli</name></author><author><name>Louise Matheson</name></author><author><name>David J. Turner</name></author><author><name>Fiamma Salerno</name></author><author><name>Peter D. Katsikis</name></author><author><name>Martin Turner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;CD8 T cell differentiation into effector cells is initiated early after antigen encounter by signals from the T cell antigen receptor and costimulatory molecules. The molecular mechanisms that determine the timing and rate of differentiation however are not defined. Here we show that the RNA binding proteins (RBP) ZFP36 and ZFP36L1 limit the rate of differentiation of activated naïve CD8 T cells and the potency of the resulting cytotoxic lymphocytes. The RBP act in an early and short temporal window to enforce dependency on costimulation via CD28 for full T cell activation and effector differentiation by directly binding mRNA of NF-κB, IRF8 and NOTCH1 transcription factors and IL2. Their absence in T cells, or the adoptive transfer of a small numbers of CD8 T cells lacking the RBP, promotes resilience to influenza A virus infection without immunopathology. These findings highlight ZFP36 and ZFP36L1 as nodes for the integration of the early T cell activation signals determining the speed and quality of the CD8 response.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.03.446738" rel="alternate" title="The timing of differentiation and potency of CD8 effector function is set by RNA binding proteins (15 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.03.446763</id><title>Single cell clonal analysis identifies an AID-dependent pathway of plasma cell differentiation (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.705303+00:00</updated><author><name>Carmen Gómez-Escolar</name></author><author><name>Alvaro Serrano-Navarro</name></author><author><name>Alberto Benguria</name></author><author><name>Ana Dopazo</name></author><author><name>Fátima Sánchez-Cabo</name></author><author><name>Almudena R Ramiro</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Germinal centers (GC) are microstructures where B cells that have been activated by antigen can improve the affinity of their B cell receptors and differentiate into memory B cells (MBCs) or antibody secreting plasma cells. Activation Induced Deaminase (AID) initiates antibody diversification in GCs by somatic hypermutation and class switch recombination. Here we have addressed the role of AID in the terminal differentiation of GC B cells by combining single cell transcriptome and immunoglobulin clonal analysis in a mouse model that traces AID-experienced cells. We identified 8 transcriptional clusters that include dark zone and light zone GC subsets, plasmablasts/plasma cells (PB), 4 subsets of MBCs and a novel prePB subset, which shares the strongest clonal relationships with PBs. Mice lacking AID have various alterations in the size and expression profiles of these transcriptional clusters. We find that AID deficiency leads to a reduced proportion of prePB cells and severely impairs transitions between the prePB and the PB subsets. Thus, AID shapes the differentiation fate of GC B cells by enabling PB generation from a prePB state.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.03.446763" rel="alternate" title="Single cell clonal analysis identifies an AID-dependent pathway of plasma cell differentiation (10 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>