<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>BioRxiv preprints in immunology posted in the last week with at least 5 tweets</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.469843+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/immunology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.02.442353</id><title>Fine-tuning of β-catenin in thymic epithelial cells is required for postnatal T cell development (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.470903+00:00</updated><author><name>Sayumi Fujimori</name></author><author><name>Izumi Ohigashi</name></author><author><name>Hayato Abe</name></author><author><name>Makoto M. Taketo</name></author><author><name>Yousuke Takahama</name></author><author><name>Shinji Takada</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the thymus, the thymic epithelium provides a microenvironment essential for the development of functionally competent and self-tolerant T cells. Previous findings showed that modulation of Wnt/β-catenin signaling in thymic epithelial cells (TECs) disrupts embryonic thymus organogenesis. However, the role of β-catenin in TECs for postnatal T cell development remains to be elucidated. Here, we analyzed gain-of-function (GOF) and loss-of-function (LOF) of β-catenin highly specific in TECs. We found that GOF of β-catenin in TECs results in severe thymic dysplasia and T cell deficiency beginning from the embryonic period. By contrast, LOF of β-catenin in TECs reduces the number of cortical TECs and thymocytes modestly and only postnatally. These results indicate that fine-tuning of β-catenin expression within a permissive range is required for TECs to generate an optimal microenvironment to support postnatal T cell development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.02.442324</id><title>Protective pan-ebolavirus combination therapy by two multifunctional human antibodies (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.470213+00:00</updated><author><name>Pavlo Gilchuk</name></author><author><name>Charles D. Murin</name></author><author><name>Robert W. Cross</name></author><author><name>Philipp A. Ilinykh</name></author><author><name>Kai Huang</name></author><author><name>Natalia Kuzmina</name></author><author><name>Viktoriya Borisevich</name></author><author><name>Krystle N. Agans</name></author><author><name>Joan B. Geisbert</name></author><author><name>Robert H. Carnahan</name></author><author><name>Rachel S. Nargi</name></author><author><name>Rachel E Sutton</name></author><author><name>Naveenchandra Suryadevara</name></author><author><name>Seth J. Zost</name></author><author><name>Robin G. Bombardi</name></author><author><name>Alexander Bukreyev</name></author><author><name>Thomas W. Geisbert</name></author><author><name>Andrew B. Ward</name></author><author><name>James E. Crowe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ebolaviruses cause a severe and often fatal illness with the potential for global spread. Monoclonal antibody-based treatments that have become available recently have a narrow therapeutic spectrum and are ineffective against ebolaviruses other than Ebola virus (EBOV), including medically important Bundibugyo (BDBV) and Sudan (SUDV) viruses. Here we report the development of a therapeutic cocktail comprising two broadly neutralizing human antibodies rEBOV-515 and rEBOV-442 that recognize non-overlapping sites on the ebolavirus glycoprotein (GP). Antibodies in the cocktail exhibited synergistic neutralizing activity and resisted viral escape, and they were optimized for their Fc-mediated effector function activities. The cocktail protected non-human primates from ebolavirus disease caused by EBOV, BDBV, or SUDV with high therapeutic effectiveness. High-resolution structures of the cocktail antibodies in complex with GP revealed the molecular determinants for neutralization breadth and potency. This study provides advanced preclinical data to support clinical development of this cocktail for pan-ebolavirus therapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>