<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular immunology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-16T10:55:16.529673+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/immunology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456204</id><title>Nrf2 is a central regulator of the metabolic landscape in macrophages and finetunes their inflammatory response (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T10:55:16.530048+00:00</updated><author><name>Dylan Gerard Ryan</name></author><author><name>Elena V Knatko</name></author><author><name>Alva Casey</name></author><author><name>Jens L Hukelmann</name></author><author><name>Alejandro J Brenes</name></author><author><name>Sharadha Dayalan Naidu</name></author><author><name>Maureen Higgins</name></author><author><name>Laura Tronci</name></author><author><name>Efterpi Nikitopoulou</name></author><author><name>Luke AJ O'Neill</name></author><author><name>Angus I Lamond</name></author><author><name>Andrey Y Abramov</name></author><author><name>Doreen A Cantrell</name></author><author><name>Michael P Murphy</name></author><author><name>Albena T Dinkova-Kostova</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To overcome oxidative, inflammatory, and metabolic stress, cells have evolved networks of cytoprotective proteins controlled by nuclear factor erythroid 2 p45-related factor 2 (Nrf2) and its main negative regulator the Kelch-like ECH associated protein 1 (Keap1). Here, we used high-resolution mass-spectrometry to characterize the proteomes of macrophages with genetically altered Nrf2 status. Our analysis revealed significant differences among the genotypes in cellular metabolism and redox homeostasis, which we validated with respirometry and metabolomics, as well as in anti-viral immune pathways and the cell cycle. Nrf2 status significantly affected the proteome following lipopolysaccharide (LPS) stimulation, with alterations in redox, carbohydrate and lipid metabolism, and innate immunity observed. Of note, Nrf2 activation was found to promote mitochondrial fusion in inflammatory macrophages. The Keap1 inhibitor, 4-octyl itaconate (4-OI), a derivative of the mitochondrial immunometabolite itaconate, remodeled the inflammatory macrophage proteome, increasing redox and suppressing anti-viral immune effectors in a Nrf2-dependent manner. These data suggest that Nrf2 activation facilitates metabolic reprogramming and mitochondrial adaptation, and finetunes the innate immune response in macrophages.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456204" rel="alternate" title="Nrf2 is a central regulator of the metabolic landscape in macrophages and finetunes their inflammatory response (27 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456007</id><title>Simultaneous infection with porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome and influenza viruses abrogates clinical protection induced by live attenuated porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome vaccination (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T10:55:16.530337+00:00</updated><author><name>Tiphany Chrun</name></author><author><name>Emmanuel A. Maze</name></author><author><name>Eleni Vatzia</name></author><author><name>Veronica Martini</name></author><author><name>Basu Paudyal</name></author><author><name>Matthew Edmans</name></author><author><name>Adam McNee</name></author><author><name>Tanuja Manjegowda</name></author><author><name>Francisco J. Salguero</name></author><author><name>Nanchaya Wanasen</name></author><author><name>Surapong Koonpaew</name></author><author><name>Simon P. Graham</name></author><author><name>Elma Tchilian</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The porcine respiratory disease complex (PRDC) is responsible for significant economic losses in the pig industry worldwide. Porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome virus (PRRSV) and swine influenza virus are major viral contributors to PRDC. Vaccines are cost-effective measures for controlling PRRS, however, their efficacy in the context of co-infections has been poorly investigated. In this study, we aimed to determine the effect of PRRSV-2 and swine influenza H3N2 virus co-infection on the efficacy of PRRSV modified live virus (MLV) vaccination, which is widely used in the field. Following simultaneous challenge with contemporary PRRSV-2 and H3N2 field isolates, we found that the protective effect of PRRS MLV vaccination on clinical disease and pathology was abrogated, although viral load was unaffected and antibody responses were enhanced. In contrast, co-infection in non-immunized animals reduced PRRSV-2 viremia and H3N2 virus load in the upper respiratory tract and potentiated T cell responses against both PRRSV-2 and H3N2 in the lung. Further analysis suggested that an upregulation of inhibitory cytokines gene expression in the lungs of vaccinated pigs may have influenced responses to H3N2 and PRRSV-2. These findings provide important insights into the effect of viral co-infections on PRRS vaccine efficacy that may help identity more effective vaccination strategies against PRDC in the field.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456007" rel="alternate" title="Simultaneous infection with porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome and influenza viruses abrogates clinical protection induced by live attenuated porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome vaccination (18 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456133</id><title>A B cell actomyosin arc network couples integrin co-stimulation to mechanical force-dependent immune synapse formation (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T10:55:16.530542+00:00</updated><author><name>Jia C Wang</name></author><author><name>Yang-In Yim</name></author><author><name>Xufeng Wu</name></author><author><name>Valentin Jaumouillé</name></author><author><name>Clare M Waterman</name></author><author><name>John H Kehrl</name></author><author><name>John A Hammer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;B-cell activation and immune synapse (IS) formation with membrane-bound antigens are actin-dependent processes that scale positively with the strength of antigen-induced signals. Importantly, ligating the B-cell integrin, LFA-1, with ICAM-1 promotes IS formation when antigen is limiting. Whether the actin cytoskeleton plays a specific role in integrin-dependent IS formation is unknown. Here we show using super-resolution imaging of primary B cells that LFA-1: ICAM-1 interactions promote the formation of an actomyosin network that dominates the B-cell IS. This network is created by the formin mDia1, organized into concentric, contractile arcs by myosin 2A, and flows inward at the same rate as B-cell receptor (BCR): antigen clusters. Consistently, individual BCR microclusters are swept inward by individual actomyosin arcs. Under conditions where integrin is required for synapse formation, inhibiting myosin impairs synapse formation, as evidenced by reduced antigen centralization, diminished BCR signaling, and defective signaling protein distribution at the synapse. Together, these results argue that a contractile actomyosin arc network plays a key role in the mechanism by which LFA-1 co-stimulation promotes B-cell activation and IS formation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456133" rel="alternate" title="A B cell actomyosin arc network couples integrin co-stimulation to mechanical force-dependent immune synapse formation (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456231</id><title>Across functional boundaries: making non-neutralizing antibodies to neutralize HIV-1 and mediate Fc-mediated effector killing of infected cells (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T10:55:16.530707+00:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Richard</name></author><author><name>Dung Nguyen</name></author><author><name>William D. Tolbert</name></author><author><name>Romain Gasser</name></author><author><name>shilei ding</name></author><author><name>Dani Vezina</name></author><author><name>Shang Yu Gong</name></author><author><name>Jeremie Prevost</name></author><author><name>Gabrielle Gendron-Lepage</name></author><author><name>Halima Medjahed</name></author><author><name>Suneetha Gottumukkala</name></author><author><name>Andres Finzi</name></author><author><name>Marzena Pazgier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In HIV-1 infection, many antibodies (Abs) are elicited to Envelope (Env) epitopes that are conformationally masked in the native trimer and are only available for antibody recognition after the trimer binds host cell CD4. Among these are epitopes within the Co-Receptor Binding Site (CoRBS) and the constant region 1 and 2 (C1-C2 or Cluster A region). In particular, C1-C2 epitopes map to the gp120 face interacting with gp41 in the native, closed Env trimer present on HIV-1 virions or expressed on HIV-1 infected cells. Antibodies targeting this region are therefore non-neutralizing and their potential as mediators of antibody depended cellular cytoxicity (ADCC) of HIV-1 infected cells diminished by a lack of available binding targets.  Here we present the design of Ab-CD4 chimeric proteins that consist of the Ab-IgG1 of a CoRBS or Cluster A specificity to the extracellular domain 1 and 2 of human CD4. Our Ab-CD4 hybrids induce potent ADCC against infected primary CD4+ T cells and neutralize tier 1 and 2 HIV-1 viruses. Furthermore, competition binding experiments reveal that the observed biological activities rely on both the antibody and CD4 moieties confirming their cooperativity in triggering conformational rearrangements of Env. Our data indicate the utility of these Ab-CD4 hybrids as antibody therapeutics effective in eliminating HIV-1 through the combined mechanisms of neutralization and ADCC. This is also the first report of single-chain-Ab-based molecules capable of opening closed Env trimers on HIV-1 particles/infected cells to expose the Cluster A region and activate ADCC and neutralization against these non-neutralizing targets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456231" rel="alternate" title="Across functional boundaries: making non-neutralizing antibodies to neutralize HIV-1 and mediate Fc-mediated effector killing of infected cells (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>