<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv immunology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.953431+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/immunology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.21.448937</id><title>Inflammation induces pro-NETotic neutrophils via TNFR2 signaling (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.953704+00:00</updated><author><name>Friederike Neuenfeldt</name></author><author><name>Jan Christoph Schumacher</name></author><author><name>Ricardo Grieshaber-Bouyer</name></author><author><name>Jüri Habicht</name></author><author><name>Jutta Schröder-Braunstein</name></author><author><name>Annika Gauss</name></author><author><name>Beate Niesler</name></author><author><name>Niko Heineken</name></author><author><name>Alexander Dalpke</name></author><author><name>Matthias M. Gaida</name></author><author><name>Thomas Giese</name></author><author><name>Stefan Meuer</name></author><author><name>Yvonne Samstag</name></author><author><name>Guido Wabnitz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cytokines released during chronic inflammatory diseases induce pro-inflammatory properties in polymorphonuclear neutrophils (PMN). Here we show that &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; cytokine treatment leads to the development of a subgroup of human PMN expressing CCR5, termed CCR5&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; cytokine-induced PMN (CCR5&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; cPMN). Auto/paracrine TNF signaling increases intracellular neutrophil elastase (ELANE) abundance and induces NETosis in CCR5&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; cPMN. Triggering of CCR5 amplifies NETosis. Membranous TNF (mTNF) outside-in signaling induces the formation of reactive oxygen species, a known activator of NETosis. &lt;italic&gt;In vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, we find an increased number of CCR5&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; cPMN in the peripheral blood and inflamed lamina propria of patients with ulcerative colitis (UC) but not Crohn’s disease (CD). Notably, failure of anti-TNF therapy is associated with higher frequencies of CCR5&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; cPMN. In conclusion, we identify a phenotype of pro-NETotic, CCR5 positive PMN present in inflamed tissue &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and inducible &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. These cells may reflect an important component of tissue damage during chronic inflammation and could be of diagnostic value.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.21.448937" rel="alternate" title="Inflammation induces pro-NETotic neutrophils via TNFR2 signaling (6 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.23.449596</id><title>P2Y6 receptor signaling in natural killer cells impairs insulin sensitivity in obesity (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.953996+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna Sieben</name></author><author><name>Anne Christine Hausen</name></author><author><name>Paul Klemm</name></author><author><name>Alexander Jais</name></author><author><name>Christian Heilinger</name></author><author><name>Jens Alber</name></author><author><name>Kat Folz-Donahue</name></author><author><name>Lena Schumacher</name></author><author><name>Janine Altmüller</name></author><author><name>Marek Franitza</name></author><author><name>Patrick Giavalisco</name></author><author><name>Yvonne Hinze</name></author><author><name>Susanne Brodesser</name></author><author><name>Christian Kukat</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Theurich</name></author><author><name>Jens C. Brüning</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Natural killer (NK) cells contribute to the development of obesity-associated insulin resistance and have previously been shown to up-regulate the expression of the P2Y purinoreceptor 6 (P2Y6R) upon high fat diet (HFD)-induced obesity. Here, we reveal that NK cell-specific inactivation of the P2Y6R gene improves insulin sensitivity in obese mice and reduces the expression of chemokines in adipose tissue infiltrating NK-cells. Obese mice lacking P2Y6R specifically in NK cells exhibited a reduction in adipose tissue inflammation, exhibited improved insulin-stimulated suppression of lipolysis in adipose tissue and a reduction in hepatic glucose production, leading to an overall improvement of systemic insulin sensitivity. In contrast, myeloid lineage specific P2Y6R inactivation does not affect energy or glucose homeostasis in obesity. Collectively, we show that P2Y6R signaling in NK cells contributes to the development of obesity-associated insulin resistance and thus might be a future target for the treatment of obesity-associated insulin resistance and type 2 diabetes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.23.449596" rel="alternate" title="P2Y6 receptor signaling in natural killer cells impairs insulin sensitivity in obesity (5 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>