<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv immunology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.772892+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/immunology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.28.450116</id><title>Pseudomonas aeruginosa infection reveals a Caspase-1-dependent neutrophil pyroptosis pathway that restrains damaging Histone release (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.773360+00:00</updated><author><name>Rémi Planès</name></author><author><name>Karin Santoni</name></author><author><name>Salimata Bagayoko</name></author><author><name>David Pericat</name></author><author><name>Pierre-Jean Bordignon</name></author><author><name>Audrey Hessel</name></author><author><name>Miriam Pinilla</name></author><author><name>Stephen-Andonai Leon-Icaza</name></author><author><name>Elisabeth Bellard</name></author><author><name>Serge Mazères</name></author><author><name>Rim Abdderrahim</name></author><author><name>Emilie Doz-Deblauwe</name></author><author><name>Frances Aylward</name></author><author><name>Yoann Rombouts</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Winter</name></author><author><name>Jean-Philippe Girard</name></author><author><name>Odile Burlet-Schiltz</name></author><author><name>Christine T.N. Pham</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Lamkanfi</name></author><author><name>Christophe Paget</name></author><author><name>Céline Cougoule</name></author><author><name>Anne Gonzalez-De-Peredo</name></author><author><name>Renaud Poincloux</name></author><author><name>Emma Lefrançais</name></author><author><name>Etienne Meunier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neutrophils mediate essential immune and microbicidal processes. Consequently, to counteract neutrophil attack, pathogens have developed various virulence strategies. Here, we showed that &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;P. aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt;) phospholipase ExoU drives pathological NETosis in neutrophils. Surprisingly, inhibition of ExoU activity uncovered a fully functional Caspase-1-driven pyroptosis pathway in neutrophils. Mechanistically, activated NLRC4 inflammasome promoted Caspase-1-dependent Gasdermin-D activation, IL-1β cytokine release and neutrophil pyroptosis. Whereas both pyroptotic and netotic neutrophils released alarmins, only NETosis liberated the destructive DAMPs Histones, which exacerbated &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/italic&gt;-induced mouse lethality. To the contrary, subcortical actin allowed pyroptotic neutrophils to physically limit poisonous inflammation by keeping Histones intracellularly. Finally, mouse models of infection highlighted that both NETosis and neutrophil Caspase-1 contributed to &lt;italic&gt;P. aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; spreading. Overall, we established the host deleterious consequences of &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/italic&gt;-induced-NETosis but also uncovered an unsuspected ability of neutrophils to undergo Caspase-1-dependent pyroptosis, a process where neutrophils exhibit a self-regulatory function that limit Histone release.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;P.aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;ExoU&lt;/sup&gt; (right) triggers phospholipid degradation and subsequent neutrophil lysis that associates to NETosis through F-Actin collapse/degradation and PAD4-dependent DNA decondensation. &lt;italic&gt;P.aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;ExoU-&lt;/sup&gt; (left) triggers NLRC4-dependent pyroptosis in neutrophils, which leads to PAD4- depndent DNA decondensation but not expulsion due to a still function subcortical F- Actin network. Created with Biorender.com.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="450116v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.28.450116" rel="alternate" title="Pseudomonas aeruginosa infection reveals a Caspase-1-dependent neutrophil pyroptosis pathway that restrains damaging Histone release (12 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450355</id><title>Single-cell analyses of immune thrombocytopenic patients reveal multiorgan dissemination of high-affinity autoreactive plasma cells (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.774017+00:00</updated><author><name>Pablo Canales-Herrerias</name></author><author><name>Etienne Crickx</name></author><author><name>Matteo Broketa</name></author><author><name>Aurélien Sokal</name></author><author><name>Guilhem Chenon</name></author><author><name>Imane Azzaoui</name></author><author><name>Alexis Vandenberghe</name></author><author><name>Angga Perima</name></author><author><name>Bruno Iannascoli</name></author><author><name>Odile Richard-Le Goff</name></author><author><name>Carlos Castrillon</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Mottet</name></author><author><name>Delphine Sterlin</name></author><author><name>Ailsa Robbins</name></author><author><name>Marc Michel</name></author><author><name>Patrick England</name></author><author><name>Gael A. Millot</name></author><author><name>Klaus Eyer</name></author><author><name>Jean Baudry</name></author><author><name>Matthieu Mahevas</name></author><author><name>Pierre Bruhns</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The major therapeutic goal for immune thrombocytopenia (ITP) is to restore normal platelet counts using drugs to promote platelet production or by interfering with mechanisms responsible for platelet destruction. 80% of patients possess anti-integrin αIIbβ3 (GPIIbIIIa) IgG autoantibodies causing platelet opsonization and phagocytosis. The spleen is considered the primary site of autoantibody production by autoreactive B cells and platelet destruction. The immediate failure in ~50% of patients to recover a normal platelet count after anti-CD20 Rituximab-mediated B cell depletion and splenectomy suggest that autoreactive, rituximab-resistant, IgG-secreting B cells (IgG-SC) reside in other anatomical compartments. We analyzed &amp;gt;3,300 single IgG-SC from spleen, bone marrow and/or blood of 27 patients with ITP revealing high inter-individual variability in affinity for GPIIbIIIa with variations over 3 logs. IgG-SC dissemination and range of affinities were however similar per patient. Longitudinal analysis of autoreactive IgG-SC upon treatment with anti-CD38 mAb daratumumab demonstrated variable outcomes, from complete remission to failure with persistence of high-affinity anti-GPIIbIIIa IgG-SC in the bone marrow. This study demonstrates the existence and dissemination of high-affinity autoreactive plasma cells in multiple anatomical compartments of patients with ITP that may cause the failure of current therapies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450355" rel="alternate" title="Single-cell analyses of immune thrombocytopenic patients reveal multiorgan dissemination of high-affinity autoreactive plasma cells (11 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450285</id><title>Clonally expanded virus-specific CD8 T cells acquire diverse transcriptional phenotypes during acute, chronic, and latent infections (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.774372+00:00</updated><author><name>Raphael Kuhn</name></author><author><name>Ioana Sandu</name></author><author><name>Andreas Agrafiotis</name></author><author><name>Kai-Lin Huang</name></author><author><name>Daniel Neumeier</name></author><author><name>Doron Merkler</name></author><author><name>Annette Oxenius</name></author><author><name>Sai T. Reddy</name></author><author><name>Alexander Yermanos</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;CD8+ T cells play a crucial role in the control and resolution of viral infections and can adopt a wide range of phenotypes and effector functions depending on the inflammatory context and the duration and extent of antigen exposure. Similarly, viral infections can exert diverse selective pressures on populations of clonally related T cells. Technical limitations have nevertheless made it challenging to investigate the relationship between clonal selection and transcriptional phenotypes of virus-specific T cells. We therefore performed single-cell T cell receptor (TCR) repertoire and transcriptome sequencing of virus-specific CD8 T cells in murine models of acute, chronic and latent infection. We observed clear infection-specific populations corresponding to memory, effector, exhausted, and inflationary phenotypes. We further uncovered a mouse-specific and polyclonal T cell response, despite all T cells sharing specificity to a single viral epitope, which was accompanied by stereotypic TCR germline gene usage in all three infection types. Persistent antigen exposure during chronic and latent viral infections resulted in a higher proportion of clonally expanded T cells relative to acute infection. We furthermore observed a relationship between transcriptional heterogeneity and clonal expansion for all three infections, with highly expanded clones having distinct transcriptional phenotypes relative to lowly expanded clones. Finally, we developed and utilized a bioinformatic pipeline integrating pseudotime and clonality, termed Clonotyme, to further support a model in which expanded virus-specific CD8+ T cells adopt heterogenic, yet preferentially, effector-like phenotypes. Together our work relates clonal selection to gene expression in the context of viral infection and further provides a dataset and accompanying software for the immunological community.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450285" rel="alternate" title="Clonally expanded virus-specific CD8 T cells acquire diverse transcriptional phenotypes during acute, chronic, and latent infections (6 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>