<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv immunology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.615037+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/immunology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.07.447379</id><title>Hypoxia is a dominant remodeler of the CD8+ T cell surface proteome relative to activation and regulatory T cell-mediated suppression (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.615409+00:00</updated><author><name>James R. Byrnes</name></author><author><name>Amy M. Weeks</name></author><author><name>Eric Shifrut</name></author><author><name>Julia Carnevale</name></author><author><name>Lisa Kirkemo</name></author><author><name>Alan Ashworth</name></author><author><name>Alexander Marson</name></author><author><name>James A. Wells</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Immunosuppressive factors in the tumor microenvironment (TME) impair T cell function and limit the anti-tumor immune response. T cell surface receptors that influence interactions and function in the TME are already proven targets for cancer immunotherapy. However, surface proteome remodeling of primary human T cells in response to suppressive forces in the TME has never been characterized systematically. Using a reductionist cell culture approach with primary human T cells and SILAC-based quantitative cell surface capture glycoproteomics, we examined how two immunosuppressive TME factors, regulatory T cells (Tregs) and hypoxia, globally affect the activated CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; surface proteome (surfaceome). Surprisingly, the CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;/Treg co-culture only modestly affected the CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; surfaceome, but did reverse several activation-induced surfaceomic changes. In contrast, hypoxia dramatically altered the CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; surfaceome in a manner consistent with both metabolic reprogramming and induction of an immunosuppressed state. The CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cell surfaceome similarly responded to hypoxia, revealing a novel hypoxia-induced surface receptor program. Our findings are consistent with the premise that hypoxic environments create a metabolic challenge for T cell activation, which may underlie the difficulty encountered in treating solid tumors with immunotherapies. Together, the data presented here provide insight into how suppressive TME factors remodel the T cell surfaceome and represent a valuable resource to inform future therapeutic efforts to enhance T cell function in the TME.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.07.447379" rel="alternate" title="Hypoxia is a dominant remodeler of the CD8+ T cell surface proteome relative to activation and regulatory T cell-mediated suppression (22 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.07.447462</id><title>A personalized anti-cancer vaccine for melanoma based on an approved vaccine against measles, mumps, and rubella (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.615662+00:00</updated><author><name>Erkko Ylösmäki</name></author><author><name>Manlio Fusciello</name></author><author><name>Arttu Uoti</name></author><author><name>Sara Feola</name></author><author><name>Beatriz Martins</name></author><author><name>Karri Aalto</name></author><author><name>Firas Hamdan</name></author><author><name>Jacopo Ciaro</name></author><author><name>Tapani Viitala</name></author><author><name>Vincenzo Cerullo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Common vaccines for infectious diseases have been repurposed as cancer immunotherapies. Intratumoural administration of these repurposed vaccines can induce immune cell infiltration into the treated tumour. Here, we have used an approved trivalent live attenuated measles, mumps, and rubella (MMR) vaccine in our previously developed PeptiENV anti-cancer vaccine platform. Intratumoural administration of this novel MMR-containing PeptiENV anti-cancer vaccine significantly increased both intratumoural as well as systemic tumour-specific T cell responses. In addition, PeptiENV therapy, in combination with immune checkpoint inhibitor therapy, significantly improved tumour growth control and survival as well as increased the number of mice responsive to immune checkpoint inhibitor therapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.07.447462" rel="alternate" title="A personalized anti-cancer vaccine for melanoma based on an approved vaccine against measles, mumps, and rubella (9 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-06-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.12.448210</id><title>Multimodal Single-Cell Characterization of the Human Granulocyte Lineage (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.615910+00:00</updated><author><name>Jingjing Qi</name></author><author><name>Darwin D'Souza</name></author><author><name>Travis Dawson</name></author><author><name>Daniel Geanon</name></author><author><name>Hiyab Stefanos</name></author><author><name>Robert Marvin</name></author><author><name>Laura Walker</name></author><author><name>Adeeb H Rahman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;High throughput single cell transcriptomics (scRNA-seq) has been successfully applied to characterize immune cell heterogeneity across a diverse range of settings; however, analysis of human granulocytes remains a significant challenge due to their low gene expression transcript detection. Consequently, granulocytes are typically either absent or highly under-represented and inaccurately enumerated in most human scRNA-seq datasets. Here, we apply multi-modal CITE-seq profiling to characterize granulocytes in human whole blood and bone marrow, and we show that these populations can be accurately detected and analyzed using the antibody-based modality, and that their frequencies and phenotype align well with antibody-based characterization of the same samples using CyTOF. These analyses also clearly highlight extremely low gene transcript detection across the entire granulocyte lineage including the earliest neutrophil progenitor populations when using the 10X Genomics platform. By contrast, when performing parallel analyses of the same samples using the BD Rhapsody platform, we recovered a much higher proportion of granulocyte gene transcripts, enabling true multi-modal characterization of human granulocyte heterogeneity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.12.448210" rel="alternate" title="Multimodal Single-Cell Characterization of the Human Granulocyte Lineage (5 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>