<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv immunology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.445687+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/immunology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.29.445691</id><title>Synthetic Antigen Presenting cells reveal the diversity and functional specialization of extracellular vesicles composing the fourth signal of T cell immunological synapses. (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.445936+00:00</updated><author><name>Pablo F. Céspedes</name></author><author><name>Ashwin K. Jainarayanan</name></author><author><name>Lola Fernández-Messina</name></author><author><name>Salvatore Valvo</name></author><author><name>David G. Saliba</name></author><author><name>Audun Kvalvaag</name></author><author><name>Elke Kurz</name></author><author><name>Huw Colin-York</name></author><author><name>Marco Fritzsche</name></author><author><name>Peng Yanchun</name></author><author><name>Tao Dong</name></author><author><name>Jesús A. Siller-Farfán</name></author><author><name>Omer Dushek</name></author><author><name>Michal Maj</name></author><author><name>Erdinc Sezgin</name></author><author><name>Ben Peacock</name></author><author><name>Alice Law</name></author><author><name>Dimitri Aubert</name></author><author><name>Simon Engledow</name></author><author><name>Moustafa Attar</name></author><author><name>Francisco Sánchez-Madrid</name></author><author><name>Svenja Hester</name></author><author><name>Roman Fisher</name></author><author><name>Michael L. Dustin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The T cell Immunological Synapse (IS) is a pivotal hub for the regulation of adaptive immunity by endowing the exchange of information between cells engaged in physical contacts. Beyond the integration of antigen (signal one), co-stimulation (signal two), and cytokines (signal three), the IS facilitates the delivery of T-cell effector assemblies including supramolecular attack particles (SMAPs) and extracellular vesicles (EVs). How these particulate outputs differ among T -cell subsets and how subcellular compartments and signals exchanged at the synapse contribute to their composition is not fully understood. Here we harnessed bead-supported lipid bilayers (BSLBs) as a tailorable and versatile technology for the study of synaptic particle biogenesis and composition in different T-cell subsets, including CART. These synthetic antigen-presenting cells (APCs) facilitated the characterisation of synaptic vesicles (SVs) as a heterogeneous population of EVs comprising among others PM-derived synaptic ectosomes and CD63+ exosomes. We harnessed BSLB to unveil the factors influencing the vesicular release of CD40L, as a model effector, identifying CD40 trans presentation, T-cell activation, ESCRT upregulation/recruitment, antigen density/potency, co-repression by PD-1 ligands, and its processing by ADAM10 as major determinants. Further, BSLB made possible the comparison of microRNA (miR) species associated with SVs and steadily shed EVs (sEVs). Altogether, our data provide evidence for a higher specialisation of SVs which are enriched not only in effector immune receptors but also in miR and RNA-binding proteins. Considering the molecular uniqueness and functional complexity of the SV output, which is also accompanied by SMAPs, we propose their classification as signal four.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.29.445691" rel="alternate" title="Synthetic Antigen Presenting cells reveal the diversity and functional specialization of extracellular vesicles composing the fourth signal of T cell immunological synapses. (17 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.446215</id><title>Transcriptional analysis of peripheral memory T cells reveals Parkinson's disease-specific gene signatures (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.446358+00:00</updated><author><name>Rekha Dhanwani</name></author><author><name>Joao Rodrigues Lima-Junior</name></author><author><name>Ashu Sethi</name></author><author><name>John Pham</name></author><author><name>Gregory Williams</name></author><author><name>April Frazier</name></author><author><name>Yaqian Xu</name></author><author><name>Amy W Amara</name></author><author><name>David G Standaert</name></author><author><name>Jennifer G Goldman</name></author><author><name>Irene Litvan</name></author><author><name>Roy N Alcalay</name></author><author><name>Bjoern Peters</name></author><author><name>David Sulzer</name></author><author><name>Cecilia S Lindestam Arlehamn</name></author><author><name>Alessandro Sette</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Parkinson's disease (PD) is a multi-stage neurodegenerative disorder with largely unknown etiology. Recent findings have identified PD-associated autoimmune features including roles for T cells. To further characterize the role of T cells in PD, we performed RNA sequencing on PBMC and peripheral CD4 and CD8 memory T cell subsets derived from PD patients and age-matched healthy controls. When the groups were stratified by their T cell responsiveness to alpha-synuclein (α-syn) as a proxy for ongoing inflammatory autoimmune response, the study revealed a broad differential gene expression profile in memory T cell subsets and a specific PD associated gene signature. We identified a significant enrichment of transcriptomic signatures previously associated with PD, including for oxidative stress, phosphorylation, autophagy of mitochondria, cholesterol metabolism and inflammation, and the chemokine signaling proteins CX3CR1, CCR5 and CCR1. In addition, we identified genes in these peripheral cells that have previously been shown to be involved in PD pathogenesis and expressed in neurons, such as LRRK2, LAMP3, and aquaporin. Together, these findings suggest that features of circulating T cells with α-syn-specific responses in PD patients provide insights into the interactive processes that occur during PD pathogenesis and suggest potential intervention targets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.446215" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptional analysis of peripheral memory T cells reveals Parkinson's disease-specific gene signatures (7 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>