<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv immunology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.500762+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/immunology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444409</id><title>T Cell Receptor Beta (TRB) Germline Variability is Revealed by Inference From Repertoire Data (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.501100+00:00</updated><author><name>Aviv Omer</name></author><author><name>Ayelet Peres</name></author><author><name>Oscar L Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Corey T Watson</name></author><author><name>William Lees</name></author><author><name>Pazit Polak</name></author><author><name>Andrew M Collins</name></author><author><name>Gur Yaari</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;T and B cell repertoires constitute the foundation of adaptive immunity. Adaptive immune receptor repertoire sequencing (AIRR-seq) is a common approach to study immune system dynamics. Understanding the genetic factors influencing the composition and dynamics of these repertoires is of major scientific and clinical importance. The chromosomal loci encoding for the variable regions of T and B cell receptors (TCRs and BCRs, respectively) are challenging to decipher due to repetitive elements and undocumented structural variants. To confront this challenge, AIRR-seq-based methods have been developed recently for B cells, enabling genotype and haplotype inference and discovery of undocumented alleles. Applying these methods to AIRR-seq data reveals a plethora of undocumented genomic variations. However, this approach relies on complete coverage of the receptors’ variable regions, and most T cell studies sequence only a small fraction of the variable region. Here, we adapted BCR inference methods to full and partial TCR sequences, and identified 38 undocumented polymorphisms in TRBV, 15 of them were also observed in genomic data assemblies. Further, we identified 31 undocumented 5’ UTR sequences. A subset of these inferences was also observed using independent genomic approaches. We found the two documented TRBD2 alleles to be equally abundant in the population, and show that the single nucleotide that differentiates them is strongly associated with dramatic changes in the expressed repertoire. Our findings expand the knowledge of genomic variation in the TRB (T Cell Receptor Beta) locus and provide a basis for annotation of TCR repertoires for future basic and clinical studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444409" rel="alternate" title="T Cell Receptor Beta (TRB) Germline Variability is Revealed by Inference From Repertoire Data (23 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.444843</id><title>Predicting T cell receptor antigen specificity from structural features derived from homology models of receptor-peptide-major histocompatibility complexes (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.501389+00:00</updated><author><name>Martina Milighetti</name></author><author><name>John Shawe-Taylor</name></author><author><name>Benjamin M Chain</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The physical interaction between the T cell receptor (TCR) and its cognate antigen causes T cells to activate and participate in the immune response. Understanding this physical interaction is important in predicting TCR binding to a target epitope, as well as potential cross-reactivity. Here, we propose a way of collecting informative features of the binding interface from homology models of T cell receptor-peptide-major histocompatibility complex (TCR-pMHC) complexes. The information collected from these structures is sufficient to discriminate binding from non-binding TCR-pMHC pairs in multiple independent datasets. The classifier is limited by the number of crystal structures available for the homology modelling and by the size of the training set. However, the classifier shows comparable performance to sequence-based classifiers requiring much larger training sets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.444843" rel="alternate" title="Predicting T cell receptor antigen specificity from structural features derived from homology models of receptor-peptide-major histocompatibility complexes (19 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.444191</id><title>Sequence and functional characterization of a public HIV-specific antibody clonotype (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.501668+00:00</updated><author><name>Amyn A. Murji</name></author><author><name>Nagarajan Raju</name></author><author><name>Juliana S Qin</name></author><author><name>Haajira Kaldine</name></author><author><name>Katarzyna Janowska</name></author><author><name>Emilee Friedman Fechter</name></author><author><name>Rutendo Mapengo</name></author><author><name>Cathrine Scheepers</name></author><author><name>Ian Setliff</name></author><author><name>Priyamvada Acharya</name></author><author><name>Lynn Morris</name></author><author><name>Ivelin S. Georgiev</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Public antibody clonotypes shared among multiple individuals have been identified for several pathogens. However, little is known about the limits of what constitutes a public clonotype. Here, we characterize the sequence and functional properties of antibodies from a public HIV-specific clonotype comprising sequences from 3 individuals. Our results showed that antigen specificity for the public antibodies was modulated by the V&lt;sub&gt;H&lt;/sub&gt;, but not V&lt;sub&gt;L&lt;/sub&gt;, germline gene. Non-native pairing of public heavy and light chains from different donors resulted in antibodies with consistent antigen specificity, suggesting functional complementation of sequences within the public antibody clonotype. The strength of antigen recognition appeared to be dependent on the specific antibody light chain used, but not on other sequence features such as germline or native-antibody sequence identity. Understanding the determinants of antibody clonotype “publicness” can provide insights into the fundamental rules of host-pathogen interactions at the population level, with implications for clonotype-specific vaccine development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.444191" rel="alternate" title="Sequence and functional characterization of a public HIV-specific antibody clonotype (7 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>