<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.214899+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.20.465155</id><title>Human milk oligosaccharides reduce murine group B Streptococcus vaginal colonization with minimal impact on the vaginal microbiota (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.215354+00:00</updated><author><name>Marlyd E Mejia</name></author><author><name>Samantha Ottinger</name></author><author><name>Alison Vrbanac</name></author><author><name>Priyanka Babu</name></author><author><name>Jacob Zulk</name></author><author><name>David Moorshead</name></author><author><name>Lars Bode</name></author><author><name>Victor Nizet</name></author><author><name>Kathryn Patras</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Group B Streptococcus (GBS) colonizes the vaginal mucosa of a significant percentage of healthy women and is a leading cause of neonatal bacterial infections. Currently, pregnant women are screened in the last month of pregnancy and GBS-positive women are given antibiotics during parturition to prevent bacterial transmission to the neonate. Recently, human milk oligosaccharides (HMOs) isolated from breastmilk were found to inhibit GBS growth and biofilm formation in vitro, and women that make certain HMOs are less likely to be vaginally colonized with GBS. Using in vitro human vaginal epithelial cells and a murine vaginal colonization model, we tested the impact of HMO treatment on GBS burdens and the composition of the endogenous microbiota by 16S rRNA amplicon sequencing. HMO treatment reduced GBS vaginal burdens in vivo with minimal alterations to the vaginal microbiota. HMOs displayed potent inhibitory activity against GBS in vitro, but HMO pretreatment did not alter adherence of GBS or the probiotic Lactobacillus rhamnosus to human vaginal epithelial cells. Additionally, disruption of a putative GBS glycosyltransferase (Δsan_0913) rendered the bacterium largely resistant to HMO inhibition in vitro and in vivo but did not compromise its adherence, colonization, or biofilm formation in the absence of HMOs. We conclude that HMOs are a promising therapeutic bioactive to limit GBS vaginal colonization with minimal impacts on the vaginal microenvironment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.20.465155" rel="alternate" title="Human milk oligosaccharides reduce murine group B Streptococcus vaginal colonization with minimal impact on the vaginal microbiota (22 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.22.465537</id><title>Amplicon sequencing of single-copy protein-coding genes reveals accurate diversity for sequence-discrete microbiome populations (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.215818+00:00</updated><author><name>Chengfeng Yang</name></author><author><name>Qinzhi Su</name></author><author><name>Min Tang</name></author><author><name>Shiqi Luo</name></author><author><name>Hao Zheng</name></author><author><name>Xue Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xin Zhou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;An in-depth understanding of microbial function and the division of ecological niches requires accurate delineation and identification of microbes at a fine taxonomic resolution. Microbial phylotypes are typically defined using a 97% small subunit (16S) rRNA threshold. However, increasing evidence has demonstrated the ubiquitous presence of taxonomic units of distinct functions within phylotypes. These so-called sequence-discrete populations (SDPs) have used to be mainly delineated by disjunct sequence similarity at the whole-genome level. However, gene markers that could accurately identify and quantify SDPs are lacking in microbial community studies. Here we developed a pipeline to screen single-copy protein-coding genes that could accurately characterize SDP diversity via amplicon sequencing of microbial communities. Fifteen candidate marker genes were evaluated using three criteria (extent of sequence divergence, phylogenetic accuracy, and conservation of primer regions) and the selected genes were subject to test the efficiency in differentiating SDPs within Gilliamella, a core honeybee gut microbial phylotype, as a proof-of-concept. The results showed that the 16S V4 region failed to report accurate SDP diversities due to low taxonomic resolution and changing copy numbers. In contrast, the single-copy genes recommended by our pipeline were able to successfully quantify Gilliamella SDPs for both mock samples and honeybee guts, with results highly consistent with those of metagenomics. The pipeline developed in this study is expected to identify single-copy protein coding genes capable of accurately quantifying diverse bacterial communities at the SDP level.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.22.465537" rel="alternate" title="Amplicon sequencing of single-copy protein-coding genes reveals accurate diversity for sequence-discrete microbiome populations (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.23.465551</id><title>Retraction ATPase motors are promiscuous among type IVa pilus systems (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.216304+00:00</updated><author><name>Evan Couser</name></author><author><name>Jennifer L Chlebek</name></author><author><name>Ankur B Dalia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial surface appendages called type IVa pili (T4aP) promote diverse activities including DNA uptake, twitching motility, and virulence. These activities rely on the ability of T4aP to dynamically extend and retract from the cell surface. Dynamic extension relies on a motor ATPase commonly called PilB. Most T4aP also rely on specific motor ATPases, commonly called PilT and PilU, to dynamically and forcefully retract. Here, we systematically assess whether motor ATPases from 4 distinct T4aP could functionally complement Vibrio cholerae mutants that lacked their endogenous motors. We found that the retraction ATPases PilT and PilU are highly promiscuous and promote retraction of the V. cholerae competence T4aP despite a high degree of sequence divergence. In contrast, orthologous extension ATPases were not able to mediate extension of the V. cholerae competence T4aP despite a similar degree of sequence divergence. Also, we show that one of the PilT orthologs characterized does not support PilU-dependent retraction and we attributed this loss of activity to the 3' end of the gene, which suggests that the C-terminus of PilT plays an important role in promoting PilU-dependent retraction. Together, our data suggest that retraction ATPases have maintained a high degree of promiscuity for promoting retraction of diverse T4aP, while extension ATPases have evolved to become highly specific for their cognate systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.23.465551" rel="alternate" title="Retraction ATPase motors are promiscuous among type IVa pilus systems (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.19.465067</id><title>Phospho-regulation accommodates Type III secretion and assembly of a tether of ER-Chlamydia inclusion membrane contact sites (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.216763+00:00</updated><author><name>Rebecca L. Murray</name></author><author><name>Rachel J. Ende</name></author><author><name>Samantha K. D’Spain</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Derré</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Membrane contact sites (MCS) are crucial for non-vesicular trafficking-based inter-organelle communication. ER-organelle tethering occurs in part through the interaction of the ER resident protein VAP with FFAT-motif containing proteins. FFAT motifs are characterized by a seven amino acidic core surrounded by acid tracks. We have previously shown that the human intracellular bacterial pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Chlamydia trachomatis&lt;/italic&gt; establishes MCS between its vacuole (the inclusion) and the ER through expression of a bacterial tether, IncV, displaying molecular mimicry of eukaryotic FFAT motif cores. Here, we show that multiple layers of host cell kinase-mediated phosphorylation events govern the assembly of the IncV-VAP tethering complex. CK2-mediated phosphorylation of a C-terminal region of IncV enables IncV hyperphosphorylation of a phospho- FFAT motif core and serine-rich tracts immediately upstream of IncV FFAT motif cores. Phosphorylatable serine tracts, rather than genetically-encoded acidic tracts, accommodate Type III-mediated translocation of IncV to the inclusion membrane, while achieving full mimicry of FFAT motifs. Thus, regulatory components and post-translational modifications are integral to MCS biology, and intracellular pathogens such as &lt;italic&gt;C. trachomatis&lt;/italic&gt; have evolved complex molecular mimicry of these eukaryotic features.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.19.465067" rel="alternate" title="Phospho-regulation accommodates Type III secretion and assembly of a tether of ER-Chlamydia inclusion membrane contact sites (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>