<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.857737+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467152</id><title>DeepBacs: Bacterial image analysis using open-source deep learning approaches (146 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.858626+00:00</updated><author><name>Christoph Spahn</name></author><author><name>Romain F. Laine</name></author><author><name>Pedro Matos Pereira</name></author><author><name>Estibaliz Gómez-de-Mariscal</name></author><author><name>Lucas von Chamier</name></author><author><name>Mia Conduit</name></author><author><name>Mariana Gomes de Pinho</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Jacquemet</name></author><author><name>Séamus Holden</name></author><author><name>Mike Heilemann</name></author><author><name>Ricardo Henriques</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Deep Learning (DL) is rapidly changing the field of microscopy, allowing for efficient analysis of complex data while often out-performing classical algorithms. This revolution has led to a significant effort to create user-friendly tools allowing biomedical researchers with little background in computer sciences to use this technology effectively. Thus far, these approaches have mainly focused on analysing microscopy images from eukaryotic samples and are still underused in microbiology. In this work, we demonstrate how to use a range of state-of-the-art artificial neural-networks particularly suited for the analysis of bacterial microscopy images, using our recently developed ZeroCostDL4Mic platform. We showcase different DL approaches for segmenting bright field and fluorescence images of different bacterial species, use object detection to classify different growth stages in time-lapse imaging data, and carry out DL-assisted phenotypic profiling of antibiotic-treated cells. To also demonstrate the DL capacity to enhance low-phototoxicity live-cell microscopy, we showcase how image denoising can allow researchers to attain high-fidelity data in faster and longer imaging. Finally, artificial labelling of cell membranes and predictions of super-resolution images allow for accurate mapping of cell shape and intracellular targets. To aid in the training of novice users, we provide a purposefully-built database of training and testing data, enabling bacteriologists to quickly explore how to analyse their data through DL. We hope this lays a fertile ground for the efficient application of DL in microbiology and fosters the creation of novel tools for bacterial cell biology and antibiotic research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467152" rel="alternate" title="DeepBacs: Bacterial image analysis using open-source deep learning approaches (146 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467097</id><title>A drug repurposing screen identifies altiratinib as a selective inhibitor of a key regulatory splicing kinase and a potential therapeutic for toxoplasmosis and malaria (44 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.859473+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher Swale</name></author><author><name>Valeria Bellini</name></author><author><name>Matthew W. Bowler</name></author><author><name>Nardella Flore</name></author><author><name>Marie-Pierre Brenier-Pinchart</name></author><author><name>Dominique Cannella</name></author><author><name>Lucid Belmudes</name></author><author><name>Caroline Mas</name></author><author><name>Yohann Couté</name></author><author><name>Fabrice Laurent</name></author><author><name>Artur Scherf</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Bougdour</name></author><author><name>Mohamed-Ali Hakimi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The apicomplexa comprise a large phylum of single-celled, obligate intracellular protozoa that infect humans and animals and cause severe parasitic diseases. Available therapeutics against these devastating diseases are limited by suboptimal efficacy and frequent side effects, as well as the emergence and spread of resistance. Here, we use a drug repurposing strategy and identify altiratinib, a compound originally developed to treat glioblastoma, as a promising drug candidate with broad spectrum activity against apicomplexans. Altiratinib is parasiticidal and blocks the development of intracellular zoites in the nanomolar range and with a high selectivity index. We have identified &lt;italic&gt;Tg&lt;/italic&gt;PRP4K of &lt;italic&gt;T. gondii&lt;/italic&gt; as the primary target of altiratinib by genetic target deconvolution, highlighting key residues within the kinase catalytic site that, when mutated, confer resistance to the drug. We have further elucidated the molecular basis of the inhibitory mechanism and species selectivity of altiratinib for &lt;italic&gt;Tg&lt;/italic&gt;PRP4K as well as for its &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; counterpart &lt;italic&gt;Pf&lt;/italic&gt;CLK3. Our data also point to structural features critical for binding of the other &lt;italic&gt;Pf&lt;/italic&gt;CLK3 inhibitor, TCMDC-135051. Consistent with the role of this kinase family in splicing in a broad spectrum of eukaryotes, we have shown that altiratinib causes global disruption of splicing, primarily through intron retention in both &lt;italic&gt;T. gondii&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt;. Thus, our data establish parasitic PRP4K/CLK3 as a promising pan-apicomplexan target whose repertoire of inhibitors can be expanded by the addition of altiratinib.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467097" rel="alternate" title="A drug repurposing screen identifies altiratinib as a selective inhibitor of a key regulatory splicing kinase and a potential therapeutic for toxoplasmosis and malaria (44 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.466924</id><title>Organization and composition of apicomplexan kinetochores reveal plasticity in chromosome segregation across parasite modes of division (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.859986+00:00</updated><author><name>Lorenzo Brusini</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Dos Santos Pacheco</name></author><author><name>Dominique Soldati-Favre</name></author><author><name>Mathieu Brochet</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Kinetochores are multiprotein assemblies directing mitotic spindle attachment and chromosome segregation. In apicomplexan parasites, most known kinetochore components and associated regulators are apparently missing, suggesting a minimal structure with limited control over chromosome segregation. In this study, we use interactomics combined with deep homology searches to identify six divergent eukaryotic components, in addition to a set of eight apicomplexan kinetochore proteins (AKiTs) that bear no detectable sequence similarity to known proteins. The nanoscale organization of the apicomplexan kinetochore includes four subdomains, each displaying different evolutionary rates across the phylum. Functional analyses confirm AKiTs are essential for mitosis and reveal architectures parallel to biorientation at metaphase. Furthermore, we identify a homolog of MAD1 at the apicomplexan kinetochore, suggesting conserved spindle assembly checkpoint signaling. Finally, we show unexpected plasticity in kinetochore composition and segregation throughout the parasite lifecycle, indicating diverse requirements to maintain fidelity of chromosome segregation across apicomplexan modes of division.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.466924" rel="alternate" title="Organization and composition of apicomplexan kinetochores reveal plasticity in chromosome segregation across parasite modes of division (37 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.467002</id><title>Detection of velogenic avian paramyxoviruses in rock doves in New York City, New York (34 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.860200+00:00</updated><author><name>Isabel Francisco</name></author><author><name>Shatoni Bailey</name></author><author><name>Teresa Bautista</name></author><author><name>Djenabou Diallo</name></author><author><name>Jesus Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Joel Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Ericka Kirkpatrick Roubidoux</name></author><author><name>Paul K. Ajayi</name></author><author><name>Randy A. Albrecht</name></author><author><name>Rita McMahon</name></author><author><name>Florian Krammer</name></author><author><name>Christine Marizzi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Avian paramyxovirus 1 (APMV-1), also known as Newcastle disease virus (NDV), causes severe and economically important disease in poultry around the globe. Although a limited amount of APMV-1 strains in urban areas have been characterized, the role of the urban wild bird population as an APMV-1 reservoir is unclear. Since urban birds may have an important role for long-term circulation of the virus, fecal and swab samples were collected by community scientists from wild birds in New York City (NYC), New York, United States. These samples were screened for APMV-1 and genotypically characterized by sequencing of the complete genome. A total of 885 samples were collected from NYC parks and from a local wildlife rehabilitation clinic from October 2020 through June 2021. Eight birds (1.1 %) screened positive for the APMV-1 nucleoprotein gene by conventional reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR), and two live viruses were isolated via egg culture. The F protein cleavage site, an indicator of pathogenicity, was present in the two samples fully sequenced by next generation sequencing, and positioned &lt;sup&gt;112&lt;/sup&gt;R R K K R F&lt;sup&gt;117&lt;/sup&gt;. Phylogenetic analysis of the F gene coding sequence classified both isolates into genotype VI, a diverse and predominant genotype responsible for NDV outbreaks in pigeon and dove species worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we describe the first large-scale effort to screen for APMV-1 in New York City’s wild bird population as part of the New York City Virus Hunters program, a community science initiative. We have characterized two isolates of NDV, with phylogenetic analyses suggesting diversity in established and circulating strains of pigeon paramyxoviruses. Our isolates are also domestic reference strains for future APMV-1 vaccine developments. Future surveillance in this region may contribute to our understanding of NDV’s evolution and genetic diversity, as well as inform poultry husbandry and vaccination practices in New York State.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.467002" rel="alternate" title="Detection of velogenic avian paramyxoviruses in rock doves in New York City, New York (34 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466829</id><title>Single molecule tracking of bacterial cell surface cytochromes reveals dynamics that impact long-distance electron transport (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.861174+00:00</updated><author><name>Grace W. Chong</name></author><author><name>Sahand Pirbadian</name></author><author><name>Yunke Zhao</name></author><author><name>Lori A. Zacharoff</name></author><author><name>Fabien Pinaud</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Y. El-Naggar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Using a series of multiheme cytochromes, the metal-reducing bacterium &lt;italic&gt;Shewanella oneidensis&lt;/italic&gt; MR-1 can perform extracellular electron transfer (EET) to respire redox-active surfaces, including minerals and electrodes outside the cell. While the role of multiheme cytochromes in transporting electrons across the cell wall is well established, these cytochromes were also recently found to facilitate long-distance (micrometer-scale) redox conduction along outer membranes and across multiple cells bridging electrodes. Recent studies proposed that long-distance conduction arises from the interplay of electron hopping and cytochrome diffusion, which allows collisions and electron exchange between cytochromes along membranes. However, the diffusive dynamics of the multiheme cytochromes have never been observed or quantified &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, making it difficult to assess their hypothesized contribution to the collision-exchange mechanism. Here we use quantum dot labeling, total internal reflection fluorescence microscopy, and single-particle tracking to quantify the lateral diffusive dynamics of the outer membrane-associated decaheme cytochromes MtrC and OmcA, two key components of EET in &lt;italic&gt;S. oneidensis&lt;/italic&gt;. We observe confined diffusion behavior for both quantum dot-labeled MtrC and OmcA along cell surfaces (diffusion coefficients &lt;italic&gt;D&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;MtrC&lt;/sub&gt; = 0.0192 ± 0.0018 μm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;/s, &lt;italic&gt;D&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;OmcA&lt;/sub&gt; = 0.0125 ± 0.0024 μm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;/s) and the membrane extensions thought to function as bacterial nanowires. We find that these dynamics can trace a path for electron transport via overlap of cytochrome trajectories, consistent with the long-distance conduction mechanism. The measured dynamics inform kinetic Monte Carlo simulations that combine direct electron hopping and redox molecule diffusion, revealing significant electron transport rates along cells and membrane nanowires.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Multiheme cytochromes in &lt;italic&gt;Shewanella oneidensis&lt;/italic&gt; MR-1 transport electrons across the cell wall, in a process called extracellular electron transfer. These electron conduits can also enable electron transport along and between cells. While the underlying mechanism is thought to involve a combination of electron hopping and lateral diffusion of cytochromes along membranes, these diffusive dynamics have never been observed &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Here, we observe the mobility of quantum dot-labeled cytochromes on living cell surfaces and membrane nanowires, quantify their diffusion with single-particle tracking techniques, and simulate the contribution of these dynamics to electron transport. This work reveals the impact of redox molecule dynamics on bacterial electron transport, with implications for understanding and harnessing this process in the environment and bioelectronics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466829" rel="alternate" title="Single molecule tracking of bacterial cell surface cytochromes reveals dynamics that impact long-distance electron transport (22 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.06.467543</id><title>Malaria transmission relies on concavin-mediated maintenance of Plasmodium sporozoite cell shape (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.861556+00:00</updated><author><name>Jessica Kehrer</name></author><author><name>Pauline Formaglio</name></author><author><name>Julianne Mendi Muthinja</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Weber</name></author><author><name>Danny Baltissen</name></author><author><name>Christopher Lance</name></author><author><name>Johanna Ripp</name></author><author><name>Janessa Grech</name></author><author><name>Markus Meissner</name></author><author><name>Charlotta Funaya</name></author><author><name>Rogerio Amino</name></author><author><name>Friedrich Frischknecht</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During transmission of malaria-causing parasites from mosquitoes to mammals, &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium&lt;/italic&gt; sporozoites migrate rapidly in the skin to search for a blood vessel. The high migratory speed and narrow passages taken by the parasites suggest considerable strain on the sporozoites to maintain their shape. Here we report on a newly identified protein, concavin, that is important for maintenance of the sporozoite shape inside salivary glands of mosquitoes and during migration in the skin. Concavin-GFP localized at the cytoplasmic periphery of sporozoites and &lt;italic&gt;concavin(-)&lt;/italic&gt; sporozoites progressively rounded up upon entry of salivary glands. These rounded &lt;italic&gt;concavin(-)&lt;/italic&gt; sporozoites failed to pass through the narrow salivary ducts and were hence rarely ejected by mosquitoes. However, normally shaped &lt;italic&gt;concavin(-)&lt;/italic&gt; sporozoites could be transmitted and migrated in the skin or skin like environments. Strikingly, motile &lt;italic&gt;concavin(-)&lt;/italic&gt; sporozoites could disintegrate while migrating through narrow strictures in the skin leading to parasite arrest or death and decreased transmission efficiency. We suggest that concavin contributes to cell shape maintenance by riveting the plasma membrane to the subtending inner membrane complex.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.06.467543" rel="alternate" title="Malaria transmission relies on concavin-mediated maintenance of Plasmodium sporozoite cell shape (17 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467004</id><title>Discordance between different bioinformatic methods for identifying resistance genes from short-read genomic data, with a focus on Escherichia coli (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.861791+00:00</updated><author><name>Timothy J Davies</name></author><author><name>Jeremy Swan</name></author><author><name>Anna E Sheppard</name></author><author><name>Hayleah Pickford</name></author><author><name>Samuel Lipworth</name></author><author><name>Manal AbuOun</name></author><author><name>Matthew Ellington</name></author><author><name>Philip W Fowler</name></author><author><name>Susan Hopkins</name></author><author><name>Katie L Hopkins</name></author><author><name>Derrick W Crook</name></author><author><name>Tim EA Peto</name></author><author><name>Muna F Anjum</name></author><author><name>A Sarah Walker</name></author><author><name>Nicole Stoesser</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;2.&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Several bioinformatics genotyping algorithms are now commonly used to characterise antimicrobial resistance (AMR) gene profiles in whole genome sequencing (WGS) data, with a view to understanding AMR epidemiology and developing resistance prediction workflows using WGS in clinical settings. Accurately evaluating AMR in Enterobacterales, particularly &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt;, is of major importance, because this is a common pathogen. However, robust comparisons of different genotyping approaches on relevant simulated and large real-life WGS datasets are lacking. Here, we used both simulated datasets and a large set of real &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; WGS data (n=1818 isolates) to systematically investigate genotyping methods in greater detail.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Simulated constructs and real sequences were processed using four different bioinformatic programs (ABRicate, ARIBA, KmerResistance, and SRST2, run with the ResFinder database) and their outputs compared. For simulations tests where 3,092 AMR gene variants were inserted into random sequence constructs, KmerResistance was correct for all 3,092 simulations, ABRicate for 3,082 (99.7%), ARIBA for 2,927 (94.7%) and SRST2 for 2,120 (68.6%). For simulations tests where two closely related gene variants were inserted into random sequence constructs, ABRicate identified the correct alleles in 11,382/46,279 (25%) of simulations, ARIBA in 2494/46,279 (5%), SRST in 2539/46,279 (5%) and KmerResistance in 38,826/46,279 (84%). In real data, across all methods, 1392/1818 (76%) isolates had discrepant allele calls for at least one gene.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our evaluations revealed poor performance in scenarios that would be expected to be challenging (e.g. identification of AMR genes at &amp;lt;10x coverage, discriminating between closely related AMR gene sequences), but also identified systematic sequence classification (i.e. naming) errors even in straightforward circumstances, which contributed to 1081/3092 (35%) errors in our most simple simulations and at least 2530/4321 (59%) discrepancies in real data. Further, many of the remaining discrepancies were likely “artefactual” with reporting cut-off differences accounting for at least 1430/4321 (33%) discrepants. Comparing outputs generated by running multiple algorithms on the same dataset can help identify and resolve these artefacts, but ideally new and more robust genotyping algorithms are needed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;label&gt;3.&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Impact statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whole-genome sequencing is widely used for studying the epidemiology of antimicrobial resistance (AMR) genes in bacteria; however, there is some concern that outputs are highly dependent on the bioinformatics methods used. This work evaluates these concerns in detail by comparing four different, commonly used AMR gene typing methods using large simulated and real datasets. The results highlight performance issues for most methods in at least one of several simulated and real-life scenarios. However most discrepancies between methods were due to differential labelling of the same sequences related to the assumptions made regarding the underlying structure of the reference resistance gene database (i.e. that resistance genes can be easily classified in well-defined groups). This study represents a major advance in quantifying and evaluating the nature of discrepancies between outputs of different AMR typing algorithms, with relevance for historic and future work using these algorithms. Some of the discrepancies can be resolved by choosing methods with fewer assumptions about the reference AMR gene database and manually resolving outputs generated using multiple programs. However, ideally new and better methods are needed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;label&gt;1.5&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Repositories&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sequencing data are available at the following NCBI BioProject accession number: PRJNA540750.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467004" rel="alternate" title="Discordance between different bioinformatic methods for identifying resistance genes from short-read genomic data, with a focus on Escherichia coli (15 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467112</id><title>Time-dependent regulation of cytokine production by RNA binding proteins defines T cell effector function (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.862576+00:00</updated><author><name>Branka Popović</name></author><author><name>Aurélie Guislain</name></author><author><name>Sander Engels</name></author><author><name>Benoît P. Nicolet</name></author><author><name>Anouk P. Jurgens</name></author><author><name>Natali Paravinja</name></author><author><name>Julian J. Freen-van Heeren</name></author><author><name>Floris P.J. van Alphen</name></author><author><name>Maartje van den Biggelaar</name></author><author><name>Fiamma Salerno</name></author><author><name>Monika C. Wolkers</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Effective T cell responses against target cells require controlled production of the key pro-inflammatory cytokines IFN-γ, TNF and IL-2. Post-transcriptional events determine the magnitude and duration of cytokine production in T cells, a process that is largely regulated by RNA binding proteins (RBPs). Here we studied the identity and mode of action of RBPs interacting with cytokine mRNAs. With an RNA aptamer-based capture assay from human T cell lysates, we identified &amp;gt;130 RBPs interacting with the full length 3’untranslated regions of &lt;italic&gt;IFNG&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;TNF&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;IL2.&lt;/italic&gt; The RBP landscape altered upon T cell activation. Furthermore, RBPs display temporal activity profiles to control cytokine production. Whereas HuR promotes early cytokine production, the peak production levels and response duration is controlled by ZFP36L1, ATXN2L and ZC3HAV1. Importantly, ZFP36L1 deletion boosts T cell responses against tumors &lt;italic&gt;in vivo,&lt;/italic&gt; revealing the potential of the RBP map to identify critical modulators of T cell responses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467112" rel="alternate" title="Time-dependent regulation of cytokine production by RNA binding proteins defines T cell effector function (11 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467329</id><title>Cooperativity mediates drug resistance and metabolism in Plasmodium falciparum malaria parasites (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.862951+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew J Jezewski</name></author><author><name>Ann M Guggisberg</name></author><author><name>Dana M Hodge</name></author><author><name>Naomi Ghebremichael</name></author><author><name>Lisa K. McLellan</name></author><author><name>Audrey Ragan Odom John</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Efforts to control the global malaria health crisis are undermined by antimalarial resistance. Identifying mechanisms of resistance will uncover the underlying biology of the &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; malaria parasites that allow evasion of our most promising therapeutics and may reveal new drug targets. We utilized fosmidomycin (FSM) as a chemical inhibitor of plastidial isoprenoid biosynthesis through the methylerythritol phosphate (MEP) pathway. We have thus identified an unusual metabolic regulation scheme in the malaria parasite through the essential glycolytic enzyme, glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH). Two parallel genetic screens converged on independent but functionally analogous resistance alleles in GAPDH. Metabolic profiling of FSM-resistant gapdh mutant parasites indicates that neither of these mutations disrupt overall glycolytic output. While FSM-resistant GAPDH variant proteins are catalytically active, they have reduced assembly into the homotetrameric state favored by wild-type GAPDH. Disrupted oligomerization of FSM-resistant GAPDH variant proteins is accompanied by altered enzymatic cooperativity and reduced susceptibility to inhibition by free heme. Together, our data identifies a new genetic biomarker of FSM-resistance and reveals the central role of GAPDH cooperativity in MEP pathway control and antimalarial sensitivity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467329" rel="alternate" title="Cooperativity mediates drug resistance and metabolism in Plasmodium falciparum malaria parasites (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467513</id><title>Single-Cell Multiomics Defines Tolerogenic Extrathymic Aire-Expressing Populations with Unique Homology to Thymic Epithelium (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.863373+00:00</updated><author><name>Jiaxi Wang</name></author><author><name>Caleb A Lareau</name></author><author><name>Jhoanne L Bautista</name></author><author><name>Alexander R Gupta</name></author><author><name>Katalin Sandor</name></author><author><name>Joe Germino</name></author><author><name>Yajie Yin</name></author><author><name>Matthew P Arvedson</name></author><author><name>Gabriella C Reeder</name></author><author><name>Nathan T Cramer</name></author><author><name>Fang Xie</name></author><author><name>Vasilis Ntranos</name></author><author><name>Ansuman T Satpathy</name></author><author><name>Mark S Anderson</name></author><author><name>James M Gardner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Autoimmune Regulator (Aire) gene, well defined for its role in medullary thymic epithelial cells (mTECs) and immune self-tolerance, is also expressed in extrathymic Aire-expressing cells (eTACs) in the secondary lymphoid organs. eTACs have been shown to be hematopoietic antigen presenting cells (APCs) and potent inducers of immune tolerance. However, the precise identity and function of these cells remain unclear. Here, we use high-dimensional single-cell multiomics and functional approaches to define eTACs at the transcriptional, genomic, and proteomic level. We find that eTACs consist of two similar cell types: CCR7+ Aire-expressing migratory dendritic cells (AmDCs) and a unique Aire-hi population co-expressing Aire and RAR-related orphan receptor gamma-t (RORγt). The latter, which have significant transcriptional and genomic homology to migratory dendritic cells (migDCs) and mTECs, we term Janus cells (JCs). All eTACs, and JCs in particular, have a highly accessible chromatin structure and high levels of broad gene expression, including tissue-specific antigens, as well as remarkable transcriptional and genomic homology to thymic medullary epithelium. As in the thymus, Aire expression in eTACs is also dependent on RANK-RANK-ligand interactions. Furthermore, lineage-tracing shows that JCs are not precursors to the majority of AmDCs. Finally, self-antigen expression by eTACs is sufficient to mediate negative selection of T cells escaping thymic selection and can prevent autoimmune diabetes in non-obese diabetic mice. This transcriptional, genomic, and functional symmetry between a hematopoietic Aire-expressing population in the periphery and an epithelial Aire-expressing population in the thymus suggests that a core biological program may influence self-tolerance and self-representation across the spectrum of immune development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467513" rel="alternate" title="Single-Cell Multiomics Defines Tolerogenic Extrathymic Aire-Expressing Populations with Unique Homology to Thymic Epithelium (10 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.467029</id><title>Analysis of sex-specific lipid metabolism in P. falciparum gametocytes points to importance of sphingomyelin for gametocytogenesis (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.863779+00:00</updated><author><name>Melanie C. Ridgway</name></author><author><name>Daniela Cihalova</name></author><author><name>Simon H.J. Brown</name></author><author><name>Phuong Tran</name></author><author><name>Todd W. Mitchell</name></author><author><name>Alexander G. Maier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Male and female &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; gametocytes are the parasite lifecycle stage responsible for transmission of malaria from the human host to mosquito vector. Not only are gametocytes able to survive in radically different host environments, but they are also precursors for male and female gametes that reproduce sexually soon after ingestion by the mosquito. Here we investigate the sex-specific lipid metabolism of gametocytes within their host red blood cell and poised for ingestion by the mosquito vector and subsequent sexual reproduction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Comparison of the male and female lipidome identifies cholesteryl esters and dihydrosphingomyelin enrichment in female gametocytes. Chemical inhibition of each of these lipid types in mature gametocytes suggests dihydrosphingomyelin synthesis but not cholesteryl ester synthesis is important for sex-specific gametocyte viability. Genetic disruption of each of the two sphingomyelin synthase gene points towards sphingomyelin synthesis contributing to gametocytogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study shows that gametocytes are not only distinct from asexual stages, but that the lipid composition is also vastly different between male and female gametocytes, reflecting the different cellular roles these stages play. Together our results highlight the sex-specific nature of gametocyte lipid metabolism that has the potential to be targeted to block malaria transmission.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.467029" rel="alternate" title="Analysis of sex-specific lipid metabolism in P. falciparum gametocytes points to importance of sphingomyelin for gametocytogenesis (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467490</id><title>Bacterial chemotaxis to saccharides is governed by a trade-off between sensing and uptake (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.864097+00:00</updated><author><name>Noele Norris</name></author><author><name>Uria Alcolombri</name></author><author><name>Johannes M Keegstra</name></author><author><name>Yutaka Yawata</name></author><author><name>Filippo Menolascina</name></author><author><name>Emilio Frazzoli</name></author><author><name>Naomi M Levine</name></author><author><name>Vicente I Fernandez</name></author><author><name>Roman Stocker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To swim up gradients of nutrients, E. coli senses nutrient concentrations within its periplasm. For small nutrient molecules, periplasmic concentrations typically match extracellular concentrations. However, this is not necessarily the case for saccharides, such as maltose, which is transported into the periplasm via a specific porin. Previous observations have shown that under various conditions E. coli limits maltoporin abundance so that, for extracellular micromolar concentrations of maltose, there are predicted to be only nanomolar concentrations of free maltose in the periplasm. Thus, in the micromolar regime, the total uptake of maltose from the external environment into the cytoplasm is limited not by the abundance of cytoplasmic transport proteins but by the abundance of maltoporins. Here we present results from experiments and modeling showing that this porin-limited transport enables E. coli to sense micromolar gradients of maltose despite having a high-affinity ABC transport system that is saturated at these micromolar levels. We used microfluidic assays to study chemotaxis of E. coli in various gradients of maltose and methyl-aspartate and leveraged our experimental observations to develop a mechanistic transport-and-sensing chemotaxis model. Incorporating this model into agent-based simulations, we discover a trade-off between uptake and sensing: although high-affinity transport enables higher uptake rates at low nutrient concentrations, it severely limits dynamic sensing range. We thus propose that E. coli may limit periplasmic uptake to increase its chemotactic sensitivity, enabling it to use maltose as an environmental cue.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467490" rel="alternate" title="Bacterial chemotaxis to saccharides is governed by a trade-off between sensing and uptake (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466889</id><title>Maize AFP1 confers antifungal activity by inhibiting chitin deacetylases from a broad range of fungi (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.864434+00:00</updated><author><name>Lay-Sun Ma</name></author><author><name>Wei-Lun Tsai</name></author><author><name>Raviraj M. Kalunke</name></author><author><name>Meng-Yun Xu</name></author><author><name>Yu-Han Lin</name></author><author><name>Florensia Ariani Damei</name></author><author><name>Hui-Chun Lee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Adapted plant pathogenic fungi deacetylate chitin to chitosan to avoid host perception and disarm the chitin-triggered plant immunity. Whether plants have evolved factors to counteract this fungal evasion mechanism in the plant-pathogen interface remains obscure. Here, we decipher the underlying mechanism of maize cysteine-rich receptor-like secreted proteins (CRRSPs)-AFP1, which exhibits mannose-binding dependent antifungal activity. AFP1 initials the action by binding to specific sites on the surface of yeast-like cells, filaments, and germinated spores of the biotrophic fungi &lt;italic&gt;Ustilago maydis&lt;/italic&gt;. This could result in fungal cell growth and cell budding inhibition, delaying spore germination and subsequently reducing fungal viability in a mannose-binding dependence manner. The antifungal activity of AFP1 is conferred by its interaction with the PMT-dependent mannosylated chitin deacetylases (CDAs) and interfering with the conversion of chitin. Our finding that AFP1 targets CDAs from pathogenic fungi and nonpathogenic budding yeast suggests a potential application of the CRRSP in combating fungal diseases and reducing threats posed by the fungal kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466889" rel="alternate" title="Maize AFP1 confers antifungal activity by inhibiting chitin deacetylases from a broad range of fungi (8 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466972</id><title>Creatine utilization as a sole nitrogen source in Pseudomonas putida KT2440 is transcriptionally regulated by CahR (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.864696+00:00</updated><author><name>Lauren A. Hinkel</name></author><author><name>Graham G. Willsey</name></author><author><name>Sean M. Lenahan</name></author><author><name>Korin Eckstrom</name></author><author><name>Kristin C. Schutz</name></author><author><name>Matthew J. Wargo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glutamine amidotransferase-1 domain-containing AraC-family transcriptional regulators (GATRs) are present in the genomes of many bacteria, including all &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/italic&gt; species. The involvement of several characterized GATRs in amine-containing compound metabolism has been determined, but the full scope of GATR ligands and regulatory networks are still unknown. Here, we characterize &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas putida’&lt;/italic&gt;s detection of the animal-derived amine compound, creatine, a compound particularly enriched in muscle and ciliated cells by a creatine-specific GATR, PP_3665, here named CahR (&lt;underline&gt;C&lt;/underline&gt;reatine &lt;underline&gt;a&lt;/underline&gt;mido&lt;underline&gt;h&lt;/underline&gt;ydrolase &lt;underline&gt;R&lt;/underline&gt;egulator). &lt;italic&gt;cahR&lt;/italic&gt; is necessary for transcription of the gene encoding creatinase (&lt;italic&gt;PP_3667/creA&lt;/italic&gt;) in the presence of creatine and is critical for &lt;italic&gt;P. putida&lt;/italic&gt;’s ability to utilize creatine as a sole source of nitrogen. The CahR/creatine regulon is small and electrophoretic mobility shift demonstrates strong and specific CahR binding only at the &lt;italic&gt;creA&lt;/italic&gt; promoter, supporting the conclusion that much of the regulon is dependent on downstream metabolites. Phylogenetic analysis of creA orthologs associated with cahR orthologs highlights a strain distribution and organization supporting likely horizontal gene transfer, particularly evident within the genus &lt;italic&gt;Acinetobacter&lt;/italic&gt;. This study identifies and characterizes the GATR that transcriptionally controls &lt;italic&gt;P. putida&lt;/italic&gt; metabolism of creatine, broadening the scope of known GATR ligands and suggesting GATR diversification during evolution of metabolism for aliphatic nitrogen compounds.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466972" rel="alternate" title="Creatine utilization as a sole nitrogen source in Pseudomonas putida KT2440 is transcriptionally regulated by CahR (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.466697</id><title>Microbiome restructuring: dominant coral bacterium Endozoicomonas species display differential adaptive capabilities to environmental changes (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.865209+00:00</updated><author><name>Kshitij Tandon</name></author><author><name>Yu-Jing Chiou</name></author><author><name>Sheng-Ping Yu</name></author><author><name>Hernyi Justin Hsieh</name></author><author><name>Chih-Ying Lu</name></author><author><name>Ming-Tsung Hsu</name></author><author><name>Pei-Wen Chiang</name></author><author><name>Hsing-Ju Chen</name></author><author><name>Naohisa Wada</name></author><author><name>Sen-Lin Tang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacteria in the coral microbiome play a crucial role in determining coral health and fitness, and the coral host often restructures its microbiome composition in response to external factors. An important but often neglected factor determining this microbiome restructuring is the capacity of microbiome members to adapt to a new environment. To address this issue, we examined how the microbiome structure of &lt;italic&gt;Acropora muricata&lt;/italic&gt; corals changed over 9 months following a reciprocal transplant experiment. Using a combination of metabarcoding, genomics, and comparative genomics approaches, we found that coral colonies separated by a small distance harbored different dominant &lt;italic&gt;Endozoicomonas related phylotypes belonging to two different&lt;/italic&gt; species, including a novel species, &lt;italic&gt;Candidatus&lt;/italic&gt; Endozoicomonas penghunesis 4G, whose chromosome level (complete) genome was also sequenced in this study. Furthermore, the two dominant &lt;italic&gt;Endozoicomonas&lt;/italic&gt; species showed varied adaptation capabilities when coral colonies were transplanted in a new environment. The differential adaptation capabilities of dominant members of the microbiome can a) provide distinct advantages to coral hosts when subjected to changing environmental conditions and b) have positive implications for future reefs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.466697" rel="alternate" title="Microbiome restructuring: dominant coral bacterium Endozoicomonas species display differential adaptive capabilities to environmental changes (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467536</id><title>Construction of lux-based promoter-reporter platforms in Mycobacterium bovis BCG for screening of drug repurposing small-molecule compounds as new anti-tuberculosis drugs (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.865914+00:00</updated><author><name>Li Zhu</name></author><author><name>Annie Wing-tung Lee</name></author><author><name>Kelvin Ka-Lok WU</name></author><author><name>Peng GAO</name></author><author><name>Kingsley King-Gee Tam</name></author><author><name>Rahim Rajwani</name></author><author><name>Galata Chala CHABURTE</name></author><author><name>Timothy Ting-Leung NG</name></author><author><name>Chloe Toi Mei Chan</name></author><author><name>Hiu-Yin Lao</name></author><author><name>Wing-Cheong Yam</name></author><author><name>Richard Yi-Tsun Kao</name></author><author><name>Gilman Kit Hang Siu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The emergence of multidrug-resistant strains and hyper-virulent strains of Mycobacterium tuberculosis are big therapeutic challenges for tuberculosis (TB) control. Repurposing bioactive small-molecule compounds has recently become a new therapeutic approach against TB. This study aimed to construct a rapid screening system to identify novel anti-TB agents from a library of small-molecule compounds. In this study, a total of 320 small-molecule compounds were used to screen for their ability to suppress the expression of a key virulence gene, phoP, of M. tuberculosis complex using luminescence (lux)-based promoter-reporter platforms. The minimum inhibitory and bactericidal concentrations on drug-resistant M. tuberculosis and cytotoxicity to human macrophage were determined. RNA-sequencing (RNA-seq) was conducted to determine the drug mechanisms of the selected compounds as novel antibiotics or anti-virulent agents against the M. tuberculosis complex. Six compounds displayed bactericidal activity against M. bovis BCG, in which Ebselen demonstrated the lowest cytotoxicity to macrophage and was considered as a potential antibiotic for TB. Another ten compounds did not inhibit the in vitro growth of the M. tuberculosis complex but down-regulated the expression of phoP specifically. Of them, ST-193 and ST-193 (hydrochloride) showed low cytotoxicity and could dysregulate the entire phoP-associated gene network, and thus identified as potential anti-virulence agents for M. tuberculosis. This study provides a rapid screening platform coupled with a systematic validation and eventually suggested one potential antibiotic and two anti-virulence agents for M. tuberculosis infections.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467536" rel="alternate" title="Construction of lux-based promoter-reporter platforms in Mycobacterium bovis BCG for screening of drug repurposing small-molecule compounds as new anti-tuberculosis drugs (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.467040</id><title>Discrimination of species within the Enterobacter cloacae complex using MALDI-TOF Mass Spectrometry and Fourier-Transform Infrared Spectroscopy coupled with Machine Learning tools (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.866245+00:00</updated><author><name>Ana Candela</name></author><author><name>Miriam Mateos</name></author><author><name>Alicia Gómez-Asenjo</name></author><author><name>Manuel J. Arroyo</name></author><author><name>Marta Hernandez-García</name></author><author><name>Rosa del Campo</name></author><author><name>Emilia Cercenado</name></author><author><name>Gema Méndez</name></author><author><name>Luis Mancera</name></author><author><name>Juan de Dios Caballero</name></author><author><name>Laura Martínez-García</name></author><author><name>Desirée Gijón</name></author><author><name>María Isabel Morosini</name></author><author><name>Patricia Ruiz-Garbajosa</name></author><author><name>Rafael Cantón</name></author><author><name>Patricia Muñoz</name></author><author><name>David Rodríguez-Temporal</name></author><author><name>Belén Rodríguez-Sánchez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Enterobacter cloacae&lt;/italic&gt; complex (ECC) encompasses heterogenic genetic clusters of species that have been associated with nosocomial outbreaks. These species may host different acquired antimicrobial susceptibility patterns and their identification is challenging. DNA-based techniques are laborious and require specific equipment. MALDI-TOF MS has showed low accuracy for the discrimination of ECC species. The aim of this study is to develop machine learning predictive models using MALDI-TOF MS and new diagnostic technologies like Fourier-Transform Infrared Spectroscopy (FTIR-S) for species-level identification of these species.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A total of 163 ECC clinical isolates were included in the study: 47 for the predictive model development and internal validation and 126 for external validation. All spectra obtained by MALDI-TOF MS and FTIR-S were processed using Clover MS Data Analysis software. Two models were created: Model A for differentiate six ECC species and Model B for &lt;italic&gt;E. hormaechei&lt;/italic&gt; subspecies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For MALDI-TOF MS spectra, Model A identified correctly 96.0% of isolates using Random Forest (RF) algorithm, and Model B identified 94.1% using Support Vector Machine (SVM). Regarding FTIR-S, Model A identified 73.0% of isolates by RF and Model B 72.5%. Two new predictive models were created for FTIR-S: Model C for discrimination of &lt;italic&gt;E. hormaechei&lt;/italic&gt; from non-&lt;italic&gt;E. hormaechei&lt;/italic&gt; (87.3% identification, RF) and Model D for differentiation among non-&lt;italic&gt;E. hormaechei&lt;/italic&gt; species (62.7% identification, RF).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;MALDI-TOF MS combined with machine learning tools could be a rapid and accurate method for species-level identification within the ECC. FTIR-S differentiated general groups of the ECC although discrimination of non-&lt;italic&gt;E. hormaechei&lt;/italic&gt; species was poor.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.467040" rel="alternate" title="Discrimination of species within the Enterobacter cloacae complex using MALDI-TOF Mass Spectrometry and Fourier-Transform Infrared Spectroscopy coupled with Machine Learning tools (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466922</id><title>Pseudomonas zeiradicis from corn and Pseudomonas soyae from soybean, two new Pseudomonas species and endophytes from agricultural crops (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.866978+00:00</updated><author><name>Jacqueline Lemaire</name></author><author><name>Sarah Seaton</name></author><author><name>Patrik Inderbitzin</name></author><author><name>Martha E. Trujillo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Two novel &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/italic&gt; species associated with healthy plants and other habitats are described from the United States. They are &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas zeiradicis&lt;/italic&gt; strain PI116 from corn in Missouri, compost from Massachusetts, urban soil from Iowa and water of Lake Erie; and &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas soyae&lt;/italic&gt; strain JL117 from soybean in Indiana and Wisconsin, and soil in Wyoming. No plant pathogenic strains are known for any of the novel species based on genome comparisons to assemblies in GenBank.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466922" rel="alternate" title="Pseudomonas zeiradicis from corn and Pseudomonas soyae from soybean, two new Pseudomonas species and endophytes from agricultural crops (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467116</id><title>Detection of the HIV-1 accessory proteins Nef and Vpu by flow cytometry represents a new tool to study their functional interplay within a single infected CD4+ T cell (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.868116+00:00</updated><author><name>Jérémie Prévost</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Richard</name></author><author><name>Romain Gasser</name></author><author><name>Halima Medjahed</name></author><author><name>Frank Kirchhoff</name></author><author><name>Beatrice H. Hahn</name></author><author><name>John C. Kappes</name></author><author><name>Christina Ochsenbauer</name></author><author><name>Ralf Duerr</name></author><author><name>Andrés Finzi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The HIV-1 Nef and Vpu accessory proteins are known to protect infected cells from antibody-dependent cellular cytotoxicity (ADCC) responses by limiting exposure of CD4-induced (CD4i) envelope (Env) epitopes at the cell surface. Although both proteins target the host receptor CD4 for degradation, the extent of their functional redundancy is unknown. Here, we developed an intracellular staining technique that permits the intracellular detection of both Nef and Vpu in primary CD4+ T cells by flow cytometry. Using this method, we show that the combined expression of Nef and Vpu predicts the susceptibility of HIV-1-infected primary CD4+ T cells to ADCC by HIV+ plasma. We also show that Vpu cannot compensate for the absence of Nef, thus providing an explanation for why some infectious molecular clones that carry a LucR reporter gene upstream of Nef render infected cells more susceptible to ADCC responses. Our method thus represents a new tool to dissect the biological activity of Nef and Vpu in the context of other host and viral proteins within single infected CD4+ T cells.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;HIV-1 Nef and Vpu exert several biological functions that are important for viral immune evasion, release and replication. Here, we developed a new method allowing simultaneous detection of these accessory proteins in their native form together with some of their cellular substrates. This allowed us to show that Vpu cannot compensate the lack of a functional Nef, which has implication for studies that use Nef-defective viruses to study ADCC responses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467116" rel="alternate" title="Detection of the HIV-1 accessory proteins Nef and Vpu by flow cytometry represents a new tool to study their functional interplay within a single infected CD4+ T cell (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466980</id><title>Aryl hydrocarbon receptor (AhR) activation by 2,3,7,8-tetrachlorodibenzo-p-dioxin (TCDD) dose-dependently shifts the gut microbiome consistent with the progression of steatosis to steatohepatitis with fibrosis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.869016+00:00</updated><author><name>Russell R. Fling</name></author><author><name>Tim R. Zacharewski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gut dysbiosis with disrupted enterohepatic bile acid metabolism is commonly associated with non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) and recapitulated in a NAFLD-phenotype elicited by 2,3,7,8-tetrachlorodibenzo-p-dioxin (TCDD) in mice. TCDD induces hepatic fat accumulation and increases levels of secondary bile acids including taurolithocholic acid and deoxycholic acid, microbial modified bile acids involved in host bile acid regulation signaling pathways. To investigate the effects of TCDD on the gut microbiota, cecum contents of male C57BL/6 mice orally gavaged with sesame oil vehicle or 0.3, 3, or 30 µg/kg TCDD were examined using shotgun metagenomic sequencing. Taxonomic analysis identified dose-dependent increases in Lactobacillus species (i.e., &lt;italic&gt;Lactobacillus reuteri&lt;/italic&gt;). Increased species were also associated with dose-dependent increases in bile salt hydrolase sequences, responsible for deconjugation reactions in secondary bile acid metabolism. Increased &lt;italic&gt;L. reuteri&lt;/italic&gt; levels were further associated with mevalonate-dependent isopentenyl diphosphate (IPP) biosynthesis and menaquinone biosynthesis genes. Analysis of gut microbiomes from cirrhosis patients identified increased abundance of these pathways as identified in the mouse cecum metagenomic analysis. These results extend the association of lactobacilli with the AhR/intestinal axis in NAFLD progression and highlight the similarities between TCDD-elicited phenotypes in mice to human NAFLD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466980" rel="alternate" title="Aryl hydrocarbon receptor (AhR) activation by 2,3,7,8-tetrachlorodibenzo-p-dioxin (TCDD) dose-dependently shifts the gut microbiome consistent with the progression of steatosis to steatohepatitis with fibrosis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467100</id><title>Microniches in biofilm depth are hot-spots for antibiotic resistance acquisition in response to in situ stress (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.869337+00:00</updated><author><name>Linda Tlili</name></author><author><name>Marie-Cécile Ploy</name></author><author><name>Sandra Da Re</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Class 1 integrons play a major role in antibiotic resistance dissemination among Gram-negative bacteria. They are genetic platforms able to capture, exchange and express antibiotic resistance gene cassettes. The integron integrase, whose expression is regulated by the bacterial SOS response, is the key element of the integron catalyzing insertion/excision/shuffling of gene cassettes. We previously demonstrated that the basal level of integrase expression and in consequence, its activity, is increased &lt;italic&gt;via&lt;/italic&gt; the starvation-induced stringent response in the biofilm population. However, biofilms are heterogeneous environments where bacteria are under various physiological states. Here we thus analyzed at the bacterial level, the SOS response and integrase expression within the biofilm, using confocal microscopy and flow cytometry. We showed that in the absence of exogenous stress, only a small number of bacteria (~ 1%) located in the depth of the biofilm induce the SOS-response leading to a high level of integrase expression, through both a stringent response-dependent and -independent manner. Our results thus indicate that few bacteria located in microniches of the biofilm depth undergo sufficient endogenous stress to promote the acquisition of antibiotic resistance, forming a reservoir of bacteria ready to rapidly resist antibiotic treatments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467100" rel="alternate" title="Microniches in biofilm depth are hot-spots for antibiotic resistance acquisition in response to in situ stress (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466809</id><title>Yersinia pseudotuberculosis doxycycline tolerance strategies include modulating expression of genes involved in cell permeability and tRNA modifications (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.869610+00:00</updated><author><name>Hector S. Alvarez-Manzo</name></author><author><name>Robert K. Davidson</name></author><author><name>Jasper Van Cauwelaert de Wyels</name></author><author><name>Katherine L. Cotten</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Zeyu Zhu</name></author><author><name>Jon Anthony</name></author><author><name>Tim van Opijnen</name></author><author><name>Kimberly M. Davis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antibiotic tolerance is typically associated with a phenotypic change within a bacterial population, resulting in a transient decrease in antibiotic susceptibility that can contribute to treatment failure and recurrent infections. Although tolerant cells may emerge prior to treatment, the stress of prolonged antibiotic exposure can also promote tolerance. Here, we sought to determine how &lt;italic&gt;Yersinia pseudotuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; responds to doxycycline exposure, to then verify if these gene expression changes could promote doxycycline tolerance in culture and in our mouse model of infection. Only four genes were differentially regulated in response to a physiologically-relevant dose of doxycycline: &lt;italic&gt;osmB&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;ompF&lt;/italic&gt; were upregulated&lt;italic&gt;, tusB&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;cnfy&lt;/italic&gt; were downregulated; differential expression also occurred during doxycycline treatment in the mouse. &lt;italic&gt;ompF, tusB&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;cnfy&lt;/italic&gt; were also differentially regulated in response to chloramphenicol, indicating these could be general responses to ribosomal inhibition. &lt;italic&gt;cnfy&lt;/italic&gt; has previously been associated with persistence and was not a major focus here. We found deletion of the OmpF porin resulted in increased antibiotic accumulation, suggesting expression may promote diffusion of doxycycline out of the cell, while OsmB lipoprotein had a minor impact on antibiotic permeability. Overexpression of &lt;italic&gt;tusB&lt;/italic&gt; significantly impaired bacterial survival in culture and in the mouse, suggesting that tRNA modification by &lt;italic&gt;tusB&lt;/italic&gt;, and the resulting impacts on translational machinery, may play an important role in promoting tolerance. We believe this is the first observation of bactericidal activity of doxycycline, which was revealed by reversing &lt;italic&gt;tusB&lt;/italic&gt; downregulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466809" rel="alternate" title="Yersinia pseudotuberculosis doxycycline tolerance strategies include modulating expression of genes involved in cell permeability and tRNA modifications (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.06.467582</id><title>specificity	: an R package for generalized specificity analysis, with example analyses of Hawaiian foliar endophytic Fungi, human gut microbiome bacteria, and Antarctic glacier bacteria. (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.870193+00:00</updated><author><name>John L Darcy</name></author><author><name>Anthony S Amend</name></author><author><name>Sean O I Swift</name></author><author><name>Pacifica S Sommers</name></author><author><name>Catherine A Lozupone</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the factors that influence microbes' environmental distributions is important for determining drivers of microbial community composition. Species distributions are governed by parameters that influence their dispersal or survival. These include environmental variables like temperature and pH, and higher-dimensional variables like geographic distance and host species phylogenies. In microbial ecology, "specificity" is often described in the context of symbiotic or host parasitic interactions, but specificity can be more broadly used to describe the extent to which a species occupies a narrower range of an environmental variable than expected by chance. Using a standardization we describe here, Rao's (1982, 2010) Quadratic Entropy can be conveniently applied to calculate specificity of a focal species to many different environmental variables, including 1-dimensional variables (vectors), dissimilarity matrices, phylogenies, and ontologies. We present our R package "&lt;italic&gt;specificity&lt;/italic&gt;" for performing the above analyses, and apply it to four real-life microbial datasets to demonstrate its application: fungi living within the leaves of native Hawaiian plants, bacteria from the human gut microbiome, bacteria living within Antarctic glacier ice, and the Earth Microbiome Project data set. Finally, we present an interactive visualization and data exploration tool for these analyses, available as a companion R-package called "&lt;italic&gt;specificity.shiny&lt;/italic&gt;".&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.06.467582" rel="alternate" title="specificity&#9;: an R package for generalized specificity analysis, with example analyses of Hawaiian foliar endophytic Fungi, human gut microbiome bacteria, and Antarctic glacier bacteria. (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467511</id><title>Natural variation in root exudation of GABA and DIMBOA impacts the maize root endosphere and rhizosphere microbiomes (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.870638+00:00</updated><author><name>Peng Wang</name></author><author><name>Lucas Dantes Lopez</name></author><author><name>Sophie Alvarez</name></author><author><name>Martha Lopez-Guerrero</name></author><author><name>Karin van Dijk</name></author><author><name>Jean-Jack Riethoven</name></author><author><name>Daniel Schachtman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Root exudates are important for shaping root-associated microbiomes. However, studies on a wider range of metabolites in exudates are required for a comprehensive understanding about their influence on microbial communities. We identified maize inbred lines that differ in exudate concentrations of DIMBOA and GABA using a semi-hydroponic system. These lines were grown in the field to determine the changes in microbial diversity and gene expression due to varying concentrations of DIMBOA and GABA in exudates using 16S rRNA amplicon sequencing and metatranscriptomics. Results showed individual and interaction effects of DIMBOA and GABA on the rhizosphere and root endosphere beta-diversity, most strongly at the V10 growth stage. The main bacterial families affected by both compounds were Ktedonobacteraceae and Xanthomonadaceae. Higher concentrations of DIMBOA in exudates affected the rhizosphere metatranscriptome, enriching for KEGG pathways associated with plant disease. This study validated the use of natural variation within plant species as a powerful approach for understanding the role of root exudates on microbiome selection. We also showed that a semi-hydroponic system can be used to identify maize genotypes that differ in GABA and DIMBOA exudate concentrations under field conditions. The impact of GABA exudation on root-associated microbiomes was shown for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467511" rel="alternate" title="Natural variation in root exudation of GABA and DIMBOA impacts the maize root endosphere and rhizosphere microbiomes (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467339</id><title>Chromosome splitting of Plasmodium berghei using the CRISPR/Cas9 system. (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.871581+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Addo-Gyan</name></author><author><name>Haruka Matsushita</name></author><author><name>Enya Sora</name></author><author><name>Tsubasa Nishi</name></author><author><name>Naoaki Shinzawa</name></author><author><name>Masao Yuda</name></author><author><name>Shiroh Iwanaga</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spatial arrangement of chromosomes is responsible for gene expression in  Plasmodium  parasites. However, methods for rearranging chromosomes have not been established, which makes it difficult to investigate its role in detail. Here, we report a method for splitting chromosome in rodent malaria parasite by CRISPR/Cas9 system using fragments in which a telomere and a centromere were incorporated. The resultant split chromosomes segregated accurately into daughter parasites by the centromere. In addition, elongation of  de novo  telomeres were observed, indicating its proper function. Furthermore, chromosome splitting had no effect on development of parasites. Splitting of the chromosome is expected to alter its spatial arrangement, and our method will thus be useful for investigating its biological role related with gene expression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467339" rel="alternate" title="Chromosome splitting of Plasmodium berghei using the CRISPR/Cas9 system. (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>