<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.926181+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.18.448987</id><title>The ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase from Melainabacteria: a comparative study between photosynthetic and non-photosynthetic bacterial sources (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.926555+00:00</updated><author><name>María V. Ferretti</name></author><author><name>Rania A. Hussien</name></author><author><name>Miguel A. Ballicora</name></author><author><name>Alberto A. Iglesias</name></author><author><name>Carlos M. Figueroa</name></author><author><name>Matías D. Asencion Diez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Until recently, all members of the cyanobacterial phylum were considered capable of performing oxygenic photosynthesis. This view has been questioned after the discovery of a group of presumed non-photosynthetic cyanobacteria named &lt;italic&gt;Melainabacteria&lt;/italic&gt;. Using metagenomic data, we identified sequences encoding putative ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase (EC 2.7.7.27, ADP-GlcPPase) from free-living and intestinal &lt;italic&gt;Melainabacteria&lt;/italic&gt;. These genes were &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; synthesized and overexpressed in &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt;. The purified recombinant proteins from the free-living and the intestinal &lt;italic&gt;Melainabacteria&lt;/italic&gt; showed ADP-GlcPPase activity, with &lt;italic&gt;V&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;max&lt;/sub&gt; values of 2.3 and 7.1 U/mg, respectively. Both enzymes had similar affinities towards ATP (&lt;italic&gt;S&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;0.5&lt;/sub&gt; ∼0.3 mM) although the one from the intestinal source displayed a 6-fold higher affinity for glucose-1P. Both recombinant ADP-GlcPPases were sensitive to allosteric activation by glucose-6P (&lt;italic&gt;A&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;0.5&lt;/sub&gt; ∼0.3 mM), and to inhibition by Pi and ADP (&lt;italic&gt;I&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;0.5&lt;/sub&gt; between 0.2 to 3 mM). Interestingly, the enzymes from &lt;italic&gt;Melainabacteria&lt;/italic&gt; were insensitive to 3-phosphoglycerate, which is the principal activator of ADP-GlcPPases from photosynthetic cyanobacteria. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first biochemical characterization of an active enzyme from &lt;italic&gt;Melainabacteria&lt;/italic&gt;, offering further data to discussions regarding their phylogenetic position. This work contributes to a better understanding regarding the evolution of allosteric mechanisms in ADP-GlcPPases, an essential enzyme for the synthesis of glycogen in prokaryotes and starch in plants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.18.448987" rel="alternate" title="The ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase from Melainabacteria: a comparative study between photosynthetic and non-photosynthetic bacterial sources (14 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.20.449199</id><title>Differential ubiquitination as an effective strategy employed by Blood-Brain Barrier for prevention of bacterial transcytosis (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.926815+00:00</updated><author><name>Smita Bhutda</name></author><author><name>Sourav Ghosh</name></author><author><name>Akash Raj Sinha</name></author><author><name>Shweta Santra</name></author><author><name>Aishwarya Hiray</name></author><author><name>Anirban Banerjee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The protective mechanisms of blood-brain barrier (BBB) prohibiting entry of blood borne pathogens and toxins into the central nervous system (CNS) is critical for maintenance of homeostasis in the brain. These include various forms of intracellular defence mechanisms which are vital to block bacterial transcytosis, the major route of trafficking adopted by meningeal pathogens to transit into the CNS. However, mechanistic details of the defence mechanisms and their exploitation to prevent bacterial meningitis remain unexplored. In this study, we established that brain endothelium driven ubiquitination acts as a major intracellular defence mechanism for clearance of &lt;italic&gt;S. pneumoniae,&lt;/italic&gt; a critical neurotropic pathogen, during its transit through BBB. Our findings suggest that brain endothelium employs differential ubiquitination with either K48 or K63-Ub chain topologies as an effective strategy to target SPN towards diverse killing pathways. While K63-Ub decoration triggers autophagic killing, K48-Ub directs pneumococcus exclusively to the proteasome machinery. Indeed, time lapse fluorescence imaging involving proteasomal marker LMP2 revealed that in BBB, majority of the ubiquitinated SPN were cleared by proteasome. Fittingly, pharmacological inhibition of proteasome and autophagy pathway not only led to exclusive accumulation of K48-Ub and K63-Ub marked SPN, respectively, but also triggered significant increment in intracellular SPN burden. Moreover, genetic impairment of formation of either K48 or K63-Ub chain topology demonstrated that though both chain types play important roles in disposal of intracellular SPN, K48-Ub chains and subsequent proteasomal degradation has more pronounced contribution towards ubiquitinated SPN killing in brain endothelium. Collectively, these observations for the first time illustrated a pivotal role of differential ubiquitination in orchestrating a symphony of intracellular defence mechanisms blocking pathogen trafficking into the brain which could be further exploited to prevent bacterial CNS infections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among the different cellular barriers present in the human body, Blood-Brain Barrier (BBB) is unique as it not only provides structural integrity but also protects the central nervous system (CNS) from pathogen invasion. In recent past, ubiquitination, which is known to be involved in protein quality control and cellular homeostasis, has been proven to be critically involved in pathogen clearance. In this study, employing &lt;italic&gt;S. pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; as a model CNS pathogen, we wanted to decipher the critical contribution of ubiquitination in protective mechanism of BBB while tackling bacterial entry into the CNS. Our results suggest, that BBB deploys differential ubiquitination as an effective strategy to prevent neurotropic bacterial trafficking into the brain. By portraying a comprehensive picture of ubiquitin coat on SPN, we figured out that different ubiquitin chain topologies formed on the pneumococcus dictated the selection of downstream degradative pathways, namely, autophagy and proteasomal machinery. Amongst these, contribution of proteasomal system in clearance of pneumococcus was found to be more pronounced. Overall our study revealed how BBB deploys differential ubiquitination as a strategy to trigger autophagy and proteasomal system, which work in tandem to ensure brain’s identity as an immunologically sterile site.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.20.449199" rel="alternate" title="Differential ubiquitination as an effective strategy employed by Blood-Brain Barrier for prevention of bacterial transcytosis (12 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>