<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.519919+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.30.458270</id><title>Global distribution of anaerobic dichloromethane degradation potential (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.520478+00:00</updated><author><name>Robert W. Murdoch</name></author><author><name>Gao Chen</name></author><author><name>Fadime Kara Murdoch</name></author><author><name>E. Erin Mack</name></author><author><name>Manuel I. Villalobos Solis</name></author><author><name>Robert L. Hettich</name></author><author><name>Frank E. Löffler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Anthropogenic activities and natural processes release dichloromethane (DCM), a toxic chemical with substantial ozone-depleting capacity. Specialized anaerobic bacteria metabolize DCM; however, the genetic basis for this process has remained elusive. Comparative genomics of the three known anaerobic DCM-degrading bacterial species revealed a homologous gene cluster, designated the methylene chloride catabolism (&lt;italic&gt;mec&lt;/italic&gt;) gene cassette, comprising eight to ten genes with predicted 79.6 – 99.7% amino acid identity. Functional annotation identified genes encoding a corrinoid-dependent methyltransferase system, and shotgun proteomics applied to two DCM-catabolizing cultures revealed high expression of proteins encoded on the &lt;italic&gt;mec&lt;/italic&gt; gene cluster during anaerobic growth with DCM. In a DCM-contaminated groundwater plume, the abundance of &lt;italic&gt;mec&lt;/italic&gt; genes strongly correlated with DCM concentrations (R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 0.71 – 0.85) indicating their value as process-specific bioremediation biomarkers. &lt;italic&gt;mec&lt;/italic&gt; gene clusters were identified in metagenomes representing peat bogs, the deep subsurface, and marine ecosystems including oxygen minimum zones (OMZs), suggesting DCM turnover in diverse habitats. The broad distribution of anaerobic DCM catabolic potential suggests a relevant control function for emissions to the atmosphere, and a role for DCM as a microbial energy source in critical zone environments. The findings imply that the global DCM flux might be far greater than emission measurements suggest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dichloromethane (DCM) is an increasing threat to stratospheric ozone with both anthropogenic and natural emission sources. Anaerobic bacterial metabolism of DCM has not yet been taken into consideration as a factor in the global DCM cycle. The discovery of the &lt;italic&gt;mec&lt;/italic&gt; gene cassette associated with anaerobic bacterial DCM metabolism and its widespread distribution in environmental systems highlight a strong attenuation potential for DCM. Knowledge of the &lt;italic&gt;mec&lt;/italic&gt; cassette offers new opportunities to delineate DCM sources, enables more robust estimates of DCM fluxes, supports refined DCM emission modeling and simulation of the stratospheric ozone layer, reveals a novel, ubiquitous C&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; carbon metabolic system, and provides prognostic and diagnostic tools supporting bioremediation of groundwater aquifers impacted by DCM.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.30.458270" rel="alternate" title="Global distribution of anaerobic dichloromethane degradation potential (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.02.458731</id><title>Macrophages in the uterus are functionally specialised and continually replenished from the circulation (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.521291+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas A Scott</name></author><author><name>Lamiya Mohiyiddeen</name></author><author><name>Livia Lacerda Mariano</name></author><author><name>Peter T Ruane</name></author><author><name>John D Aplin</name></author><author><name>Olivia C Moran</name></author><author><name>Daniel R Brison</name></author><author><name>Molly A Ingersoll</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth R Mann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Macrophages are innate immune cells that fight infection but also regulate tissue regeneration and remodelling. In the uterus, although tissue remodelling is essential for establishment and maintenance of pregnancy, the specialisation of macrophages is not well characterised compared to other mucosal tissues. Here we show that uterine macrophages are functionally specialised, expressing multiple markers of alternative activation associated with tissue remodelling and repair, and responding more highly to the type 2 cytokine IL-4 than other mucosal tissue macrophages. Uterine macrophages were continuously replenished from circulating bone marrow-derived CCR2+ monocytes that fluctuated dramatically in number throughout the reproductive cycle, and had properties distinct from the macrophages that they became, including differential responses to microbial stimulation. Importantly, many of these properties of uterine monocytes and macrophages were conserved between mice and humans. These findings further our understanding of immune regulation of uterine tissue integrity and have important implications for differences in immune responses to infections at different phases of the reproductive cycle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.02.458731" rel="alternate" title="Macrophages in the uterus are functionally specialised and continually replenished from the circulation (5 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>