<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.815252+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.15.448505</id><title>Norwegian Kveik brewing yeasts are adapted to higher temperatures and produce fewer off-flavours under heat stress than commercial Saccharomyces cerevisiae American Ale yeast (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.815608+00:00</updated><author><name>Dimitri Kits</name></author><author><name>Lars Marius Garshol</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Norwegian kveik are a recently described family of domesticated &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; brewing yeasts used by farmhouse brewers in western Norway for generations to produce traditional Norwegian farmhouse ale. Kveik ale yeasts have been domesticated by farmhouse brewers through serial repitching of the yeast in warm wort (&amp;gt;30°C) punctuated by long periods of dry storage. Kveik yeasts are alcohol tolerant, flocculant, capable of utilizing maltose/maltotriose, phenolic off flavour negative, and exhibit elevated thermotolerance when compared to other modern brewer’s yeasts belonging to the ‘Beer 1’ clade. However, the optimal fermentation and growth temperatures (T&lt;sub&gt;opt&lt;/sub&gt;) for kveik ale yeasts and the influence of fermentation temperature of the production of flavour-active metabolites like fusel alcohols and sulfur compounds (H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;S, SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) are not known. Here we show that kveik ale yeasts have an elevated optimal fermentation temperature (T&lt;sub&gt;opt&lt;/sub&gt;) when compared to commercial American Ale yeast (SafAle™ US-05) and that they produce fewer off-flavours at high temperatures (&amp;gt;30°C) when compared to commercial American Ale yeasts. The tested kveik yeasts show significantly higher maximum fermentation rates than American Ale yeast not only at elevated temperatures (&amp;gt;30°C), but also at ‘typical’ ale fermentation temperatures (20°C-25°C). Finally, we demonstrate that kveik ale yeasts are heterogeneous in their T&lt;sub&gt;opt&lt;/sub&gt; and that they attenuate standard wort robustly above their T&lt;sub&gt;opt&lt;/sub&gt; unlike our control American Ale yeast which showed very poor apparent attenuation in our standard wort at temperatures ≫ T&lt;sub&gt;opt&lt;/sub&gt;. Our results provide further support that kveik yeasts may possess favourable fermentation kinetics and sensory properties compared to American Ale yeasts. The observations here provide a roadmap for brewers to fine tune their commercial fermentations using kveik ale yeasts for optimal performance and/or flavour impact.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.15.448505" rel="alternate" title="Norwegian Kveik brewing yeasts are adapted to higher temperatures and produce fewer off-flavours under heat stress than commercial Saccharomyces cerevisiae American Ale yeast (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.14.448304</id><title>VirClust – a tool for hierarchical clustering, core gene detection and annotation of (prokaryotic) viruses (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.815820+00:00</updated><author><name>Cristina Moraru</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent years have seen major changes in the classification criteria and taxonomy of viruses. The current classification scheme, also called “megataxonomy of viruses”, recognizes five different viral realms, defined based on the presence of viral hallmark genes. Within the realms, viruses are classified into hierarchical taxons, ideally defined by their shared genes. Therefore, there is currently a need for virus classification tools based on such shared genes / proteins. Here, VirClust is presented – a novel tool capable of performing i) hierarchical clustering of viruses based on intergenomic distances calculated from their protein cluster content, ii) identification of core proteins and iii) annotation of viral proteins. VirClust groups proteins into clusters both based on BLASTP sequence similarity, which identifies more related proteins, and also based on hidden markow models (HMM), which identifies more distantly related proteins. Furthermore, VirClust provides an integrated visualization of the hierarchical clustering tree and of the distribution of the protein content, which allows the identification of the genomic features responsible for the respective clustering. By using different intergenomic distances, the hierarchical trees produced by VirClust can be split into viral genome clusters of different taxonomic ranks. VirClust is freely available, as web-service (virclust.icbm.de) and stand-alone tool.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.14.448304" rel="alternate" title="VirClust – a tool for hierarchical clustering, core gene detection and annotation of (prokaryotic) viruses (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>