<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.924447+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457082</id><title>A nitrite-oxidizing bacterium constitutively consumes atmospheric hydrogen (44 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.924863+00:00</updated><author><name>Pok Man Leung</name></author><author><name>Anne Daebeler</name></author><author><name>Eleonora Chiri</name></author><author><name>Paul R. F. Cordero</name></author><author><name>Iresha Hanchapola</name></author><author><name>David L. Gillett</name></author><author><name>Ralf B Schittenhelm</name></author><author><name>Holger Daims</name></author><author><name>Chris Greening</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chemolithoautotrophic nitrite-oxidizing bacteria (NOB) of the genus Nitrospira contribute to nitrification in diverse natural environments and engineered systems. Nitrospira are thought to be well-adapted to substrate limitation owing to their high affinity for nitrite and capacity to use alternative energy sources. Here, we demonstrate that the canonical nitrite oxidizer Nitrospira moscoviensis oxidizes hydrogen (H2) below atmospheric levels using a high-affinity group 2a nickel-iron hydrogenase [Km(app) = 32 nM]. Atmospheric H2 oxidation occurred under both nitrite-replete and nitrite-deplete conditions, suggesting low-potential electrons derived from H2 oxidation promote nitrite-dependent growth and enable survival during nitrite limitation. Proteomic analyses confirmed the hydrogenase was abundant under both conditions and indicated extensive metabolic changes occur to reduce energy expenditure and growth under nitrite-deplete conditions. Respirometry analysis indicates the hydrogenase and nitrite oxidoreductase are bona fide components of the aerobic respiratory chain of N. moscoviensis, though they transfer electrons to distinct electron carriers in accord with the contrasting redox potentials of their substrates. Collectively, this study suggests atmospheric H2 oxidation enhances the growth and survival of NOB in amid variability of nitrite supply. These findings also extend the phenomenon of atmospheric H2 oxidation to a seventh phylum (Nitrospirota) and reveal unexpected new links between the global hydrogen and nitrogen cycles.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457082" rel="alternate" title="A nitrite-oxidizing bacterium constitutively consumes atmospheric hydrogen (44 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.17.456620</id><title>Immunopeptidomic analysis of influenza A virus infected human tissues identifies internal proteins as a rich source of HLA ligands (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.925383+00:00</updated><author><name>Ben Nicholas</name></author><author><name>Alistair Bailey</name></author><author><name>Karl J Staples</name></author><author><name>Tom Wilkinson</name></author><author><name>Tim Elliott</name></author><author><name>Paul Skipp</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;CD8+ and CD4+ T cells provide cell-mediated cross-protection against multiple influenza strains by recognising epitopes bound as peptides to human leukocyte antigen (HLA) class I and -II molecules respectively. Two challenges in identifying the immunodominant epitopes needed to generate a universal T cell influenza vaccine are: A lack of cell models susceptible to influenza infection which present population-prevalent HLA allotypes, and an absence of a reliable in-vitro method of identifying class II HLA peptides. Here we present a mass spectrometry-based proteomics strategy for identifying viral peptides derived from the A/H3N2/X31 and A/H3N2/Wisconsin/67/2005 strains of influenza. We compared the HLA-I and -II immunopeptidomes presented by ex-vivo influenza challenged human lung tissues. We then compared these with directly infected immortalised macrophage-like cell line (THP1) and primary dendritic cells fed apoptotic influenza-infected respiratory epithelial cells. In each of the three experimental conditions we identified novel influenza class I and II HLA peptides with motifs specific for the host allotype. Ex-vivo infected lung tissues yielded few class-II HLA peptides despite significant numbers of alveolar macrophages, including directly infected ones, present within the tissues. THP1 cells presented HLA-I viral peptides derived predominantly from internal proteins. Primary dendritic cells presented predominantly viral envelope-derived HLA class II peptides following phagocytosis of apoptotic infected cells. The most frequent viral source protein for HLA-I and -II was matrix 1 protein (M1). This work confirms that internal influenza proteins, particularly M1, are a rich source of CD4+ and CD8+ T cell epitopes. Moreover, we demonstrate the utility of two ex-vivo fully human infection models which enable direct HLA-I and -II immunopeptide identification without significant viral tropism limitations. Application of this epitope discovery strategy in a clinical setting will provide more certainty in rational vaccine design against influenza and other emergent viruses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Influenza infections present a significant global health challenge. High rates of mutation require reformulation of vaccines annually. Vaccines are designed to induce antibody responses to the surface proteins of the influenza virus, but the contribution of T cells to overall immunity is unclear. Here, we used several totally human laboratory models to show how the viral proteins are presented to the T cells to induce immunity. We found that CD8 T cells, which kill infected cells, and CD4 T cells which support the CD8 T cells as well as the antibody-producing B cells, mainly see proteins from inside the viral particle, not the surface ones which are targeted by antibodies. These internal viral proteins are more similar between different viral strains than the surface proteins, and therefore suggest that vaccines designed to induce T cell responses could be better protective if they target internal viral proteins.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.17.456620" rel="alternate" title="Immunopeptidomic analysis of influenza A virus infected human tissues identifies internal proteins as a rich source of HLA ligands (16 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456482</id><title>Particle Uptake Driven Phagocytosis in Macrophages and Neutrophils Enhances Bacterial Clearance (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.925860+00:00</updated><author><name>Preeti Sharma</name></author><author><name>Anjali Vijaykumar</name></author><author><name>Jayashree Vijaya Raghavan</name></author><author><name>Supriya Rajendra Rananaware</name></author><author><name>Alakesh Alakesh</name></author><author><name>Janhavi Bodele</name></author><author><name>Junaid Ur Rehman</name></author><author><name>Shivani Shukla</name></author><author><name>Virta Wagde</name></author><author><name>Savitha Nadig</name></author><author><name>Sveta Chakrabarti</name></author><author><name>Sandhya S. Visweswariah</name></author><author><name>Dipankar Nandi</name></author><author><name>Balasubramanian Gopal</name></author><author><name>Siddharth Jhunjhunwala</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Humans are exposed to numerous synthetic foreign particulates in the form of environmental pollutants and diagnostic or therapeutic agents. Specialized immune cells (phagocytes) clear these particulates by phagocytosing and attempting to degrade them. The process of recognition and internalization of the particulates may trigger changes in the function of phagocytes. Some of these changes, especially the ability of a particle-loaded phagocyte to take up and neutralize pathogens, remains poorly studied. Herein, we demonstrate that the uptake of non-stimulatory cargo-free particles enhances the phagocytic ability of monocytes, macrophages and neutrophils. The enhancement in phagocytic ability was independent of particle properties, such as size or the base material constituting the particle. Additionally, we show that the increased phagocytosis was not a result of cellular activation or cellular heterogeneity but was driven by changes in cell membrane fluidity and cellular compliance. A consequence of the enhanced phagocytic activity was that particulate-laden immune cells neutralize &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; faster in culture. Moreover, when administered in mice as a prophylactic, particulates enable faster clearance of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;S. epidermidis&lt;/italic&gt;. Together, we demonstrate that the process of uptake induces cellular changes that favor additional phagocytic events. This study provides insights into using non-stimulatory cargo-free particles to engineer immune cell functions for applications involving faster clearance of phagocytosable particulates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456482" rel="alternate" title="Particle Uptake Driven Phagocytosis in Macrophages and Neutrophils Enhances Bacterial Clearance (15 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.18.456644</id><title>Intracellular Salmonella Paratyphi A is motile and differs in the expression of flagella-chemotaxis, SPI-1 and carbon utilization pathways in comparison to Intracellular S. Typhimurium (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.926410+00:00</updated><author><name>Helit Cohen</name></author><author><name>Claire Hoede</name></author><author><name>Felix Scharte</name></author><author><name>Charles Coluzzi</name></author><author><name>Emiliano Cohen</name></author><author><name>Inna Shomer</name></author><author><name>Ludovic Mallet</name></author><author><name>Remy Felix Serre</name></author><author><name>Thomas Schiex</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Virlogeux-Payant</name></author><author><name>Guntram Grassl</name></author><author><name>Michael Hensel</name></author><author><name>Helene Chiapello</name></author><author><name>Ohad Gal-Mor</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Although Salmonella Typhimurium (STM) and Salmonella Paratyphi A (SPA) belong to the same phylogenetic species, share large portion of their genome and express many common virulence factors, they differ vastly in their host specificity, the immune response they elicit, and the clinical manifestations they cause. In this work, we compared for the first time their intracellular trascriptomic architecture and cellular phenotypes during epithelial cell infection. While transcription induction of many metal transport systems, purines, biotin, PhoPQ and SPI-2 regulons was common in both intracellular SPA and STM, we identified 234 differentially expressed genes that showed distinct expression patterns in intracellular SPA vs. STM. Surprisingly, clear expression differences were found in SPI-1, motility and chemotaxis, and carbon (mainly citrate, galactonate and ethanolamine) utilization pathways, indicating that these pathways are regulated and possibly function differently, during their intracellular phase. Moreover, we show that the induction of flagella genes by intracellular SPA leads to cytosolic motility, a conserved trait specific to SPA. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first report of a flagellum-dependent intracellular motility of any Salmonella serovar in living host cells. Importantly, we demonstrate that the elevated expression of SPI-1 and motility genes by intracellular SPA results in increased invasiveness of SPA, following exit from host cells. We propose that such changes prime SPA towards new cycles of host cell infection and contribute to the ability of SPA to disseminate beyond the intestinal lamina propria of the human host, during enteric fever.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.18.456644" rel="alternate" title="Intracellular Salmonella Paratyphi A is motile and differs in the expression of flagella-chemotaxis, SPI-1 and carbon utilization pathways in comparison to Intracellular S. Typhimurium (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.18.456889</id><title>Does plant diversity determine the diversity of the rhizosphere microbial community? (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.926704+00:00</updated><author><name>Aleksei Zverev</name></author><author><name>Arina Kichko</name></author><author><name>Vasiliy Shapkin</name></author><author><name>Aleksandr Pinaev</name></author><author><name>Nikolay Provorov</name></author><author><name>Evgeny Andronov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The rhizosphere community represents an “ecological interface” between plant and soil, providing the plant with a number of advantages. Close connection and mutual influence in this communication allow to talk about the self-adjusting “plant-rhizosphere community” system, which should be be studied in connection. Diversity estimation is one of the ways of describing both bacterial and plant communities. Based on the literature, there are two assumptions of how the diversity of plant communities related to the diversity of bacterial communities: 1) an increase in the species richness of plants leads to an increase in the number of available micro-niches, and increasing of microbial diversity, 2) an increase in the species richness of plants is accompanied by the predominant development of bacteria from highly productive specific taxa and decreasing in the diversity of microorganisms. Experimental studies show controversial results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We analyzed field sites (rye crop field and two fallow sites), using DNA isolation of both the plant root mass (followed by sequencing of the ITS1 region) and rhizosphere microorganisms (followed by sequencing of the 16s rDNA V4 region). This allowed us to 1) accurately determine the abundance and taxonomic position of plant communities; 2) extract information about both plant and microbial communities from the same sample.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was no correlation between alpha-diversity indices of plants and rhizosphere communities. Alpha-diversity connection should be explored in similar plant communities, such as synusia. We hypothesize, that the significant differences in plant abundances lead to significant changes in exudation profiles, and the loss of diversity connection. The beta-diversity between rhizosphere communities and plant communities is highly correlated, in particular in terms of the abundance of taxa. This can be explained by a potential correlation (as reported in the literature) or by the presence of statistical artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.18.456889" rel="alternate" title="Does plant diversity determine the diversity of the rhizosphere microbial community? (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.18.456900</id><title>A bacterial genome and culture collection of gut microbial in weanling piglet (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.927074+00:00</updated><author><name>Bo Dong</name></author><author><name>Xiaoqian Lin</name></author><author><name>Xiaohuan Jing</name></author><author><name>Tuanyuan Hu</name></author><author><name>Jianwei Zhou</name></author><author><name>Jianwei Chen</name></author><author><name>Liang Xiao</name></author><author><name>Bo Wang</name></author><author><name>Zhuang Chen</name></author><author><name>Jing Liu</name></author><author><name>Yiyin Hu</name></author><author><name>Guilin Liu</name></author><author><name>Shanshan Liu</name></author><author><name>Junnian Liu</name></author><author><name>Wenkang Wei</name></author><author><name>Yuanqiang Zou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The microbiota hosted in the pig gastrointestinal tract are important for productivity of livestock. However, the individual species and functional repertoires that make up the pig gut microbiome remain largely undefined. Here we comprehensively investigated the genomes and functions of the piglet gut microbiome using culture-based and metagenomics approaches. A collection included 266 cultured genomes and 482 metagenome-assembled genomes (MAGs) that were clustered to 428 species across 10 phyla was established. Among these clustered species, 333 genomes represent potential new species. Less matches between cultured genomes and MAGs revealed a substantial bias for the acquisition of reference genomes by the two strategies. Glycoside hydrolases was the dominant category of carbohydrate-active enzymes. 445 secondary metabolite biosynthetic genes were predicted from 292 genomes with bacteriocin being the most. Pan genome analysis of &lt;italic&gt;Limosilactobacillus reuteri&lt;/italic&gt; uncover the biosynthesis of reuterin was strain-specific and the production was experimentally determined. These genomic resources will enable a comprehensive characterization of the microbiome composition and function of pig gut.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.18.456900" rel="alternate" title="A bacterial genome and culture collection of gut microbial in weanling piglet (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>