<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.291925+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.18.460796</id><title>Antigen identification and high-throughput interaction mapping by reprogramming viral entry (95 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.292945+00:00</updated><author><name>Connor S. Dobson</name></author><author><name>Anna N. Reich</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Gaglione</name></author><author><name>Blake E. Smith</name></author><author><name>Ellen J. Kim</name></author><author><name>Jiayi Dong</name></author><author><name>Larance Ronsard</name></author><author><name>Vintus Okonkwo</name></author><author><name>Daniel Lingwood</name></author><author><name>Michael Dougan</name></author><author><name>Stephanie K. Dougan</name></author><author><name>Michael E. Birnbaum</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Deciphering immune recognition is critical for understanding a broad range of diseases and for the development of effective vaccines and immunotherapies. Efforts to do so are limited by a lack of technologies capable of simultaneously capturing the complexity of adaptive immune receptor repertoires and the landscape of potential antigens. To address this, we present RAPTR (&lt;bold&gt;R&lt;/bold&gt;eceptor-&lt;bold&gt;A&lt;/bold&gt;ntigen &lt;bold&gt;P&lt;/bold&gt;airing by &lt;bold&gt;T&lt;/bold&gt;argeted &lt;bold&gt;R&lt;/bold&gt;etroviruses). RAPTR combines viral pseudotyping and molecular engineering approaches to enable one-pot library on library interaction screens by displaying antigens on the surface of lentiviruses and encoding their identity in the viral genome. Antigen-specific viral infection of cells allows readout of both antigen and receptor identities via single-cell sequencing. The resulting system is modular, scalable, and compatible with any cell type, making it easily implemented. These techniques provide a suite of new tools for targeted viral entry, molecular engineering, and interaction screens with broad potential applications.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.18.460796" rel="alternate" title="Antigen identification and high-throughput interaction mapping by reprogramming viral entry (95 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461432</id><title>Reclassification of Shigella species as later heterotypic synonyms of Escherichia coli in the Genome Taxonomy Database (56 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.293434+00:00</updated><author><name>Donovan H. Parks</name></author><author><name>Maria Chuvochina</name></author><author><name>Peter R. Reeves</name></author><author><name>Scott A. Beatson</name></author><author><name>Philip Hugenholtz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Members of the genus &lt;italic&gt;Shigella&lt;/italic&gt; have high genomic similarity to &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; and are often considered to be atypical members of this species. In an attempt to retain &lt;italic&gt;Shigella&lt;/italic&gt; species as recognizable entities, they were reclassified as &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia&lt;/italic&gt; species in the Genome Taxonomy Database (GTDB) using an operational average nucleotide identity (ANI)-based approach nucleated around type strains. This resulted in nearly 80% of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; genomes being reclassified to new species including the common laboratory strain &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; K-12 (to ‘&lt;italic&gt;E. flexneri’&lt;/italic&gt;) because it is more closely related to the type strain of &lt;italic&gt;Shigella flexneri&lt;/italic&gt; than it is to the type strain of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;. Here we resolve this conundrum by treating &lt;italic&gt;Shigella&lt;/italic&gt; species as later heterotypic synonyms of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;, present evidence supporting this reclassification, and show that assigning &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;/&lt;italic&gt;Shigella&lt;/italic&gt; strains to a single species is congruent with the GTDB-adopted genomic species definition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461432" rel="alternate" title="Reclassification of Shigella species as later heterotypic synonyms of Escherichia coli in the Genome Taxonomy Database (56 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461816</id><title>Expansion microsopy reveals Plasmodium falciparum blood-stage parasites undergo anaphase with a chromatin bridge in the absence of mini-chromosome maintenance complex binding protein (47 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.293713+00:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Liffner</name></author><author><name>Sabrina Absalon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mitosis in the malaria parasite &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; undergoes closed mitosis, which occurs within an intact nuclear envelope, and differs significantly from its human host. Mitosis is underpinned by the dynamics of microtubules and the nuclear envelope. To date, our ability to study &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; mitosis by microscopy has been hindered by the small size of &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; nuclei. Ultrastructure expansion microscopy (U-ExM) has recently been developed for &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt;, allowing visualization of mitosis at the individual nucleus level. Using U-ExM, three intranuclear microtubule structures are observed: hemispindles, mitotic spindles and interpolar spindles. A previous study demonstrated that the mini-chromosome maintenance complex binding-protein (MCMBP) depletion caused abnormal nuclear morphology and microtubule defects. To investigate the role of microtubules following MCMBP depletion and study the nuclear envelope in these parasites, we developed the first nuclear stain enabled by U-ExM in &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt;. MCMBP deficient parasites show aberrant hemispindles and mitotic spindles. Moreover, anaphase chromatin bridges, and individual nuclei containing multiple microtubule structures were observed following MCMBP knockdown. Collectively, this study refines our model for the phenotype of MCMBP-deficient parasites and highlights the utility of U-ExM coupled with a nuclear envelope stain for studying mitosis in &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461816" rel="alternate" title="Expansion microsopy reveals Plasmodium falciparum blood-stage parasites undergo anaphase with a chromatin bridge in the absence of mini-chromosome maintenance complex binding protein (47 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462013</id><title>The DarTG toxin-antitoxin system provides phage defense by ADP-ribosylating viral DNA (35 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.293941+00:00</updated><author><name>Michele LeRoux</name></author><author><name>Sriram Srikant</name></author><author><name>Megan H. Littlehale</name></author><author><name>Gabriella Teodoro</name></author><author><name>Shany Doron</name></author><author><name>Mohsen Badiee</name></author><author><name>Anthony K. L. Leung</name></author><author><name>Rotem Sorek</name></author><author><name>Michael T. Laub</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Toxin-antitoxin (TA) systems are broadly distributed, yet poorly conserved, genetic elements whose biological functions are unclear and controversial. Some TA systems may provide bacteria with immunity to infection by their ubiquitous viral predators, the bacteriophage. To identify TA systems that protect &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; MG1655 against phage, we searched for those frequently encoded near known phage defense genes in bacterial genomes. Two of the systems tested provide strong protection against phage infection and are homologs of DarTG, a recently discovered family of TA systems whose biological functions and natural activating conditions were unclear. We demonstrate that phage infection triggers the release of DarT toxin, a DNA ADP-ribosyltransferase, to modify viral DNA and prevent replication, thereby blocking the production of mature virions. Phages can evolve to overcome DarTG defense either through mutations to their DNA polymerase or to an anti-DarT factor, gp61.2, encoded by many T-even phages. Collectively, our results indicate that phage defense may be a common function for TA systems and reveal the mechanism by which DarTG systems inhibit phage infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462013" rel="alternate" title="The DarTG toxin-antitoxin system provides phage defense by ADP-ribosylating viral DNA (35 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461451</id><title>Label-free Raman microspectroscopy for identifying virocells (34 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.294218+00:00</updated><author><name>Indra Monsees</name></author><author><name>Victoria Turzynski</name></author><author><name>Sarah P. Esser</name></author><author><name>André Soares</name></author><author><name>Lara I. Timmermann</name></author><author><name>Katrin Weidenbach</name></author><author><name>Jarno Banas</name></author><author><name>Michael Kloster</name></author><author><name>Bánk Beszteri</name></author><author><name>Ruth A. Schmitz</name></author><author><name>Alexander J. Probst</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Raman microspectroscopy has been thoroughly used to assess growth dynamics and heterogeneity of prokaryotic cells. Yet, little is known about how the chemistry of individual cells changes during infection with lytic viruses, resulting in so-called virocells. Here, we investigate biochemical changes of bacterial and archaeal cells of three different species in laboratory cultures before and after addition of their respective viruses using single-cell Raman microspectroscopy. By applying multivariate statistics, we identified significant differences in the spectra of single cells and cells after addition of lytic phage (&lt;italic&gt;phi6&lt;/italic&gt;) for &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas syringae&lt;/italic&gt;. A general ratio of wavenumbers that contributed the greatest differences in the recorded spectra was defined as an indicator for virocells. Based on reference spectra, this difference is likely attributable to an increase in nucleic acid vs. protein ratio of virocells. This method proved also successful for identification of &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; cells infected with &lt;italic&gt;phi29&lt;/italic&gt; displaying a decrease in respective ratio but failed for archaeal virocells (&lt;italic&gt;Methanosarcina mazei&lt;/italic&gt; with Methanosarcina Spherical Virus) due to autofluorescence. Multivariate and univariate analyses suggest that Raman spectral data of infected cells can also be used to explore the complex biology behind viral infections of bacteria. Using this method, we confirmed the previously described two-stage infection of &lt;italic&gt;P. syringae&lt;/italic&gt;’s &lt;italic&gt;phi6&lt;/italic&gt; and that infection of &lt;italic&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; by &lt;italic&gt;phi29&lt;/italic&gt; results in a stress response within single cells. We conclude that Raman microspectroscopy is a promising tool for chemical identification of Gram-positive and Gram-negative virocells undergoing infection with lytic DNA or RNA viruses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Viruses are highly diverse biological entities shaping many ecosystems across Earth. Yet, understanding the infection of individual microbial cells and the related biochemical changes remains limited. Using Raman microspectroscopy in conjunction with univariate and unsupervised machine learning approaches, we established a marker for identification of infected Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria. This non-destructive, label-free analytical method at single-cell resolution paves the way for future studies geared towards analyzing complex biological changes of virus-infected cells in pure culture and natural ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461451" rel="alternate" title="Label-free Raman microspectroscopy for identifying virocells (34 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461418</id><title>Structural Mechanics of the Alpha-2-Macroglobulin Transformation (33 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.294661+00:00</updated><author><name>Yasuhiro Arimura</name></author><author><name>Hironori Funabiki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Alpha-2-Macroglobulin (A2M) is the critical pan-protease inhibitor of the innate immune system. When proteases cleave the A2M bait region, global structural transformation of the A2M tetramer is triggered to entrap the protease. The structural basis behind the cleavage-induced transformation and the protease entrapment remains unclear. Here, we report cryo-EM structures of native- and intermediate-forms of the &lt;italic&gt;Xenopus laevis&lt;/italic&gt; egg A2M homolog (A2Moo or ovomacroglobulin) tetramer at 3.7-4.1 Å and 6.4 Å resolution, respectively. In the native A2Moo tetramer, two pairs of dimers arrange into a cross-like configuration with four 60 Å-wide bait-exposing grooves. Each bait in the native form threads into an aperture formed by three macroglobulin domains (MG2, MG3, MG6). The bait is released from the narrowed aperture in the induced protomer of the intermediate form. We propose that the intact bait region works as a “latch-lock” to block futile A2M transformation until its protease-mediated cleavage.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461418" rel="alternate" title="Structural Mechanics of the Alpha-2-Macroglobulin Transformation (33 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461819</id><title>Comparative genomics reveals electron transfer and syntrophic mechanisms differentiating methanotrophic and methanogenic archaea (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.295122+00:00</updated><author><name>Grayson L Chadwick</name></author><author><name>Connor T Skennerton</name></author><author><name>Rafael Laso-Pérez</name></author><author><name>Andy O Leu</name></author><author><name>Daan R Speth</name></author><author><name>Hang Yu</name></author><author><name>Connor Morgan-Lang</name></author><author><name>Roland Hatzenpichler</name></author><author><name>Danielle Goudeau</name></author><author><name>Rex Malmstrom</name></author><author><name>William J Brazelton</name></author><author><name>Tanja Woyke</name></author><author><name>Steven J Hallam</name></author><author><name>Gene W Tyson</name></author><author><name>Gunter Wegener</name></author><author><name>Antje Boetius</name></author><author><name>Victoria J Orphan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The anaerobic oxidation of methane coupled to sulfate reduction is a microbially mediated process requiring a syntrophic partnership between anaerobic methanotrophic (ANME) archaea and sulfate reducing bacteria (SRB). Based on genome taxonomy, ANME lineages are polyphyletic within the phylum &lt;italic&gt;Halobacterota&lt;/italic&gt;, none of which have been isolated in pure culture. Here we reconstruct 28 ANME genomes from environmental metagenomes and flow sorted syntrophic consortia. Together with a reanalysis of previously published datasets, these genomes enable a comparative analysis of all marine ANME clades. We review the genomic features which separate ANME from their methanogenic relatives and identify what differentiates ANME clades. Large multiheme cytochromes and bioenergetic complexes predicted to be involved in novel electron bifurcation reactions are well-distributed and conserved in the ANME archaea, while significant variations in the anabolic C1 pathways exists between clades. Our analysis raises the possibility that methylotrophic methanogenesis may have evolved from a methanotrophic ancestor.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461819" rel="alternate" title="Comparative genomics reveals electron transfer and syntrophic mechanisms differentiating methanotrophic and methanogenic archaea (31 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461960</id><title>A new sugar for an old phage: A c-di-GMP dependent polysaccharide pathway sensitizes E. coli for bacteriophage infection (25 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.295848+00:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Sellner</name></author><author><name>Rūta Prakapaitė</name></author><author><name>Margo van Berkum</name></author><author><name>Matthias Heinemann</name></author><author><name>Alexander Harms</name></author><author><name>Urs Jenal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacteriophages are ubiquitous parasites of bacteria and major drivers of bacterial ecology and evolution. Despite an ever-growing interest in their biotechnological and therapeutic applications, detailed knowledge of the molecular mechanisms underlying phage-host interactions remains scarce. Here, we show that bacteriophage N4 exploits a novel surface glycan, NGR, as a receptor to infect its host &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt;. We demonstrate that this process is regulated by the second messenger c-di-GMP and that N4 infection is specifically stimulated by the diguanylate cyclase DgcJ while the phosphodiesterase PdeL effectively protects &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; from N4-mediated killing. PdeL-mediated protection requires its catalytic activity to reduce c-di-GMP and includes a secondary role as a transcriptional repressor. We demonstrate that PdeL binds to and represses the promoter of the &lt;italic&gt;wec&lt;/italic&gt; operon, which encodes components of the ECA exopolysaccharide pathway. However, only the acetylglucosamine epimerase WecB but none of the other ECA components is required for N4 infection. Based on this, we postulate that NGR is an N-acetylmannosamine-based carbohydrate polymer that is produced and exported to the cell surface of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; in a c-di-GMP dependent manner where it serves as a receptor for N4. This novel carbohydrate pathway is conserved in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; and other bacterial pathogens, serves as the primary receptor for a range of N4-like bacteriophages, and is induced at elevated temperature and by specific amino acid-based nutrients. These studies provide an entry point into understanding how bacteria use specific regulatory mechanisms to balance costs and benefits of highly conserved surface structures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because bacterial surface glycans are in direct contact with the environment they can provide essential protective functions during infections or against competing bacteria. But such structures are also ‘Achilles heels’ as they can serve as primary receptors for bacteriophages. Bacteria thus need to carefully control the exposure of conserved surface glycans to balance costs and benefits. Here, we identify a novel exopolysaccharide that is widely conserved in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; and is used by N4 and related bacteriophages as primary receptor. We demonstrate that the synthesis of NGR (N4 glycan receptor) is tightly controlled by the second messenger c-di-GMP in a highly specific manner and by a single diguanylate cyclase. These studies provide an example of how bacteria can alleviate the strong selective pressure imposed on them by bacteriophages entering through conserved surface structures by carefully regulating their synthesis and secretion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461960" rel="alternate" title="A new sugar for an old phage: A c-di-GMP dependent polysaccharide pathway sensitizes E. coli for bacteriophage infection (25 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461078</id><title>Cryo-electron tomography of ASC signalling sites in pyroptotic cells (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.296630+00:00</updated><author><name>Yangci Liu</name></author><author><name>Haoming Zhai</name></author><author><name>Helen Alemayehu</name></author><author><name>Lee J. Hopkins</name></author><author><name>Alicia C. Borgeaud</name></author><author><name>Christina Heroven</name></author><author><name>Jonathan D. Howe</name></author><author><name>Jérôme Boulanger</name></author><author><name>Clare E. Bryant</name></author><author><name>Yorgo Modis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Inflammasomes induce cell death in response to infection, chemical entities and cell damage. Human genetics and animal models have identified the NLRP3 inflammasome as a gatekeeper of caspase-1-dependent pyroptosis. NLRP3 activation induces polymerization of ASC into a single, micron-scale perinuclear punctum, where caspase-1 is activated. These puncta have yet to be imaged at sufficient resolution to resolve their ultrastructure. Here, we apply correlative cryo-light microscopy and cryo-electron tomography to visualize ASC/caspase-1 puncta and mitochondrial membrane remodelling within NLRP3-activated cells. The puncta are composed primarily of branched ASC filaments. The N-terminal pyrin domain forms an 8-10 nm-diameter tubular core, which is decorated by the flexibly linked C-terminal caspase recruitment domain. The variable filament density allows ribosomes and &lt;italic&gt;trans&lt;/italic&gt;-Golgi-like vesicles to permeate the network. We propose this provides structural integrity while allowing macromolecules and vesicles to diffuse in or bind with the necessary density, timing and localization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461078" rel="alternate" title="Cryo-electron tomography of ASC signalling sites in pyroptotic cells (22 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461800</id><title>The PhoPQ two-component system promotes carbapenem tolerance in Enterobacterales (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.297182+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew N. Murtha</name></author><author><name>Misha I. Kazi</name></author><author><name>Richard D. Schargel</name></author><author><name>Trevor Cross</name></author><author><name>Conrad Fihn</name></author><author><name>Erin E. Carlson</name></author><author><name>Joseph M. Boll</name></author><author><name>Tobias Dörr</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antibiotic tolerance is an understudied potential contributor to antibiotic treatment failure and the emergence of multidrug-resistant bacteria. The molecular mechanisms governing tolerance remain poorly understood. A prominent type of β-lactam tolerance relies on the formation of cell wall-deficient spheroplasts, which maintain structural integrity via their outer membrane (OM), an asymmetric lipid bilayer consisting of phospholipids on the inner leaflet and a lipid-linked polysaccharide (lipopolysaccharide, LPS) enriched in the outer monolayer on the cell surface. How a membrane structure like LPS, with its reliance on mere electrostatic interactions to maintain stability, is capable of countering internal turgor pressure is unknown. Here, we have uncovered a novel role for the PhoPQ two-component system in tolerance to the β-lactam antibiotic meropenem in Enterobacterales. We found that PhoPQ is induced by meropenem treatment and promotes an increase in 4-amino-4-deoxy-L-aminoarabinose [L-Ara4N] modification of lipid A, the membrane anchor of LPS. L-Ara4N modifications enhance structural integrity, and consequently tolerance to meropenem, in several Enterobacterales species. Importantly, mutational inactivation of the negative PhoPQ regulatory element &lt;italic&gt;mgrB&lt;/italic&gt; (commonly selected for during clinical therapy with the last-resort antibiotic colistin, an antimicrobial peptide [AMP]) results in dramatically enhanced tolerance, suggesting that AMPs can collaterally select for meropenem tolerance via stable overactivation of PhoPQ. Lastly, we identify histidine kinase inhibitors (including an FDA-approved drug) that inhibit PhoPQ-dependent LPS modifications and consequently potentiate meropenem to enhance killing of tolerant cells. In summary, our results suggest that PhoPQ-mediated LPS modifications play a significant role in stabilizing the OM, promoting survival when the primary integrity maintenance structure, the cell wall, is removed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Treating an infection with an antibiotic often fails, resulting in a tremendous public health burden. One understudied likely reason for treatment failure is the development of “antibiotic tolerance”, the ability of bacteria to survive normally lethal exposure to an antibiotic. Here, we describe a molecular mechanism promoting tolerance. A bacterial stress sensor (PhoPQ) is activated in response to antibiotic (meropenem) treatment and consequently strengthens a bacterial protective “shell” to enhance survival. We also identify inhibitors of this mechanism, opening the door to developing compounds that help antibiotics work better against tolerant bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461800" rel="alternate" title="The PhoPQ two-component system promotes carbapenem tolerance in Enterobacterales (21 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.17.460124</id><title>Non-lesional and Lesional Lupus Skin Share Inflammatory Phenotypes that Drive Activation of CD16+ Dendritic Cells (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.297474+00:00</updated><author><name>Allison C. Billi</name></author><author><name>Feiyang Ma</name></author><author><name>Olesya Plazyo</name></author><author><name>Mehrnaz Gharaee-Kermani</name></author><author><name>Rachael Wasikowski</name></author><author><name>Grace A. Hile</name></author><author><name>Xianying Xing</name></author><author><name>Christine M. Yee</name></author><author><name>Syed M. Rizvi</name></author><author><name>Mitra P. Maz</name></author><author><name>Fei Wen</name></author><author><name>Lam C. Tsoi</name></author><author><name>Matteo Pellegrini</name></author><author><name>Robert L. Modlin</name></author><author><name>Johann E. Gudjonsson</name></author><author><name>J. Michelle Kahlenberg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cutaneous lupus erythematosus (CLE) is a disfiguring and poorly understood condition frequently associated with systemic lupus. Studies to date suggest that non-lesional keratinocytes play a role in disease predisposition, but this has not been investigated in a comprehensive manner or in the context of other cell populations. To investigate CLE immunopathogenesis, normal-appearing skin, lesional skin, and circulating immune cells from lupus patients were analyzed via integrated single-cell RNA-sequencing and spatial-seq. We demonstrate that normal-appearing skin of lupus patients represents a type I interferon-rich, ‘prelesional’ environment that skews gene transcription in all major skin cell types and dramatically distorts cell-cell communication. Further, we show that lupus-enriched CD16+ dendritic cells undergo robust interferon education in the skin, thereby gaining pro-inflammatory phenotypes. Together, our data provide a comprehensive characterization of lesional and non-lesional skin in lupus and identify a role for skin education of CD16+ dendritic cells in CLE pathogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.17.460124" rel="alternate" title="Non-lesional and Lesional Lupus Skin Share Inflammatory Phenotypes that Drive Activation of CD16+ Dendritic Cells (21 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461611</id><title>High-throughput functionalization of the Toxoplasma kinome uncovers a novel regulator of invasion and egress (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.297815+00:00</updated><author><name>Tyler A. Smith</name></author><author><name>Gabriella S. Lopez-Perez</name></author><author><name>Emily Shortt</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Lourido</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protein kinases regulate fundamental aspects of cell biology in all eukaryotes, making them attractive chemotherapeutic targets in Apicomplexan parasites such as the causative agents of malaria (&lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium&lt;/italic&gt; spp.) and toxoplasmosis (&lt;italic&gt;Toxoplasma gondii&lt;/italic&gt;). However, the precise roles of individual parasite kinases cannot be inferred simply from sequence identity, due to rewiring of signaling pathways and the shifting repertoire of kinases across species. To systematically examine the parasite kinome, we developed a high-throughput (HiT) CRISPR-mediated tagging strategy to endogenously label all predicted cytosolic protein kinases with a synthetic sequence encoding the minimal auxin-inducible degron (mAID) linked to a fluorophore and epitope tag. The system enables the assembly of thousands of tagging vectors from synthetic sequences in a single reaction and the pooled generation of mutants to examine kinase localization and function. We examined the phenotypes associated with kinase knock-down in 1,160 arrayed clones by replica-plating in the presence or absence of auxin and found broad defects across the lytic cycle for 109 clonal isolates, assigning localizations to 39 proteins, and associating 15 kinases within 6 distinct morphological phenotypes. The relative fitness of tagged alleles was also examined by tracking the relative abundance of individual guide RNAs as parasite populations progressed through the lytic cycle, in the presence or absence of auxin. Pooled screening had a high predictive value and differentiated between delayed and acute death. Demonstrating the value of this resource, we identified a novel kinase associated with delayed death as a novel regulator of invasion and egress. We call the previously unstudied kinase Store Potentiating/Activating Regulatory Kinase (SPARK), based on its impact on intracellular Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; stores at key moments during the lytic cycle. Despite having a similar kinase domain to the mammalian PDK1, SPARK lacks the canonical lipid-binding domain and we find no indication SPARK positively regulates other AGC kinases, suggesting a rewiring of signaling pathways to accommodate parasite adaptations. The HiT vector screening system extends the applications of genome-wide screens into complex cellular phenotypes, providing a scalable and versatile platform for the dissection of apicomplexan cell biology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461611" rel="alternate" title="High-throughput functionalization of the Toxoplasma kinome uncovers a novel regulator of invasion and egress (18 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461821</id><title>Transient dendritic cell activation diversifies the T cell response to acute infection (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.298012+00:00</updated><author><name>Kamir J. Hiam-Galvez</name></author><author><name>Rachel DeBarge</name></author><author><name>Caleb A. Lareau</name></author><author><name>Nam Woo Cho</name></author><author><name>Jacqueline L. Yee</name></author><author><name>Trine Line H. Okholm</name></author><author><name>Matthew H. Spitzer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The precise timing of T cell priming during infection remains unclear. Here, we mapped the cellular dynamics of all immune lineages during acute infection with &lt;italic&gt;Listeria monocytogenes&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Lm&lt;/italic&gt;). We identified highly transient DC activation 2 days post-infection that functions as a critical time window for priming effector T cells. Regulation of this transient state was mediated by DC extrinsic IFNγ provided by lymphocytes. Furthermore, antigen-specific T cells that arrive late to the site of priming and miss peak DC activation acquire only memory T cell fates. This temporal regulation of fate is recapitulated by CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; DCs &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, suggesting that shifts in activation state of a single antigen presenting cell population alter T cell fates. These results uncover a novel mechanism for temporal regulation of T cell differentiation during a dynamic immune response to acute infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The immune system generates a balanced protective response through rapidly shifting activation states and recruitment of new cells into an ongoing inflammatory landscape.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461821" rel="alternate" title="Transient dendritic cell activation diversifies the T cell response to acute infection (17 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461389</id><title>Regional and clonal T cell dynamics at single cell resolution in immune checkpoint blockade (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.298206+00:00</updated><author><name>Joy A. Pai</name></author><author><name>Andrew Chow</name></author><author><name>Jennifer L. Sauter</name></author><author><name>Marissa Mattar</name></author><author><name>Hira Rizvi</name></author><author><name>Hyung Jun Woo</name></author><author><name>Nisargbhai Shah</name></author><author><name>Fathema Uddin</name></author><author><name>Alvaro Quintanal-Villalonga</name></author><author><name>Joseph M. Chan</name></author><author><name>Parvathy Manoj</name></author><author><name>Viola Allaj</name></author><author><name>Marina Baine</name></author><author><name>Jamie Chaft</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Plodkowski</name></author><author><name>Helen Won</name></author><author><name>Daniel Wells</name></author><author><name>Mark T.A. Donoghue</name></author><author><name>Elisa de Stanchina</name></author><author><name>Triparna Sen</name></author><author><name>Jedd D. Wolchok</name></author><author><name>Brian Houck-Loomis</name></author><author><name>Taha Merghoub</name></author><author><name>Charles M. Rudin</name></author><author><name>Ansuman T. Satpathy</name></author><author><name>Matthew D. Hellmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Paired T cell receptor and RNA single cell sequencing (scTCR/RNA-seq) has allowed for enhanced resolution of clonal T cell dynamics in cancer. Here, we report a scTCR/RNA-seq dataset of 162,062 single T cells from 31 tissue regions, including tumor, adjacent normal tissues, and lymph nodes (LN), from three patients who underwent resections for progressing lung cancers after immune checkpoint blockade (ICB). We found marked regional heterogeneity in tumor persistence that was associated with heterogeneity in CD4 and CD8 T cell phenotypes; regions with persistent cancer cells were enriched for follicular helper CD4 T cells (TFH), regulatory T cells (Treg), and exhausted CD8 T cells. Clonal analysis demonstrated that highly-expanded T cell clones were predominantly of the CD8 subtype, were ubiquitously present across all sampled regions, found in the peripheral circulation, and expressed gene signatures of ‘large’ and ‘dual-expanded’ clones that have been predictive of response to ICB. Longitudinal tracking of CD8 T cell clones in the peripheral blood revealed that the persistence of ubiquitous CD8 T cell clones, as well as phenotypically distinct clones with tumor-reactive features, correlated with systemic tumor control. Finally, tracking CD8 T cell clones across tissues revealed the presence of TCF-1&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; precursor exhausted CD8 T cells in tumor draining LNs that were clonally linked to expanded exhausted CD8 T cells in tumors. Altogether, this comprehensive scTCR/RNA-seq dataset with regional, longitudinal, and clonal resolution provides fundamental insights into the tissue distribution, persistence, and differentiation trajectories of ICB-responsive T cells that underlie clinical responses to ICB.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461389" rel="alternate" title="Regional and clonal T cell dynamics at single cell resolution in immune checkpoint blockade (17 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461619</id><title>A phenotypic screen using splitCas9 identifies essential genes required for actin regulation during host cell egress and invasion by Toxoplasma gondii (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.298526+00:00</updated><author><name>Wei Li</name></author><author><name>Janessa Grech</name></author><author><name>Johannes Felix Stortz</name></author><author><name>Matthew Gow</name></author><author><name>Javier Periz</name></author><author><name>Markus Meissner</name></author><author><name>Elena Jimenez-Ruiz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Apicomplexan parasites, such as &lt;italic&gt;Toxoplasma gondii&lt;/italic&gt;, possess unique organelles, cytoskeletal structures, signalling cascades, replicate by internal budding within a specialised compartment and actively invade and exit the host cell, to name a few aspects of the unique biology that characterise this phylum. Due to their huge phylogenetic distance from well established model organisms, such as opisthokonts, comparative genomics has a limited capacity to infer gene functions and conserved proteins can fulfil different roles in apicomplexans. Indeed, approximately 30% of all genes are annotated as hypothetical and many had a crucial role during the asexual life cycle in genome-wide screens. While the current CRISPR/Cas9-based screens allow the identification of fitness conferring genes, only little information about the respective functions can be obtained. To overcome this limitation, and to group genes of interest into functional groups, we established a conditional Cas9-system in &lt;italic&gt;T. gondii&lt;/italic&gt; that allows phenotypic screens. Using an indicator strain for F-actin dynamics and apicoplast segregation, we identified critical genes required for defined steps during the asexual life cycle. The detailed characterisation of two of these candidates revealed them to be critical for host cell egress and invasion and to act at different time points in the disassembly of the intravacuolar F-actin network. While the signalling linking factor (SLF) is an integral part of a signalling complex required for early induction of egress, a novel conoid protein (conoid gliding protein, CGP) acts late during egress and is required for the activation of gliding motility.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461619" rel="alternate" title="A phenotypic screen using splitCas9 identifies essential genes required for actin regulation during host cell egress and invasion by Toxoplasma gondii (16 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461778</id><title>Direct reprogramming of the intestinal epithelium by parasitic helminths subverts type 2 immunity (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.298761+00:00</updated><author><name>Danielle Karo-Atar</name></author><author><name>Shaida Ouladan</name></author><author><name>Tanvi Javkar</name></author><author><name>Loick Joumier</name></author><author><name>Macy K. Matheson</name></author><author><name>Sydney Merritt</name></author><author><name>Susan Westfall</name></author><author><name>Annie Rochette</name></author><author><name>Maria E. Gentile</name></author><author><name>Ghislaine Fontes</name></author><author><name>Gregory J. Fonseca</name></author><author><name>Marc Parisien</name></author><author><name>Luda Diatchenko</name></author><author><name>Jakob von Moltke</name></author><author><name>Mohan Malleshaiah</name></author><author><name>Alex Gregorieff</name></author><author><name>Irah L. King</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Enteric helminths form intimate physical connections with the intestinal epithelium, yet their ability to directly alter epithelial stem cell fate has not been resolved. Here we demonstrate that infection of mice with the symbiotic parasite &lt;italic&gt;Heligmosomoides polygyrus bakeri&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Hbp&lt;/italic&gt;), reprograms the intestinal epithelium into a fetal-like state marked by the emergence of &lt;italic&gt;Clusterin&lt;/italic&gt;-expressing revival stem cells (revSCs). Organoid-based studies using parasite-derived excretory/secretory products reveal that &lt;italic&gt;Hpb&lt;/italic&gt;-mediated revSC generation occurs independent of host-derived immune signals and inhibits type 2 cytokine-driven differentiation of secretory epithelial lineages that promote their expulsion. Reciprocally, type 2 cytokine signals limit revSC differentiation and, consequently, &lt;italic&gt;Hpb&lt;/italic&gt; fitness indicating that helminths compete with their host for control of the intestinal stem cell niche to promote continuation of their life cycle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461778" rel="alternate" title="Direct reprogramming of the intestinal epithelium by parasitic helminths subverts type 2 immunity (15 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461509</id><title>Engineering CAR-NK cells to secrete IL15 sustains their anti-AML functionality, but is associated with systemic toxicities (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.299180+00:00</updated><author><name>Ilias Christodoulou</name></author><author><name>Won Jin Ho</name></author><author><name>Andrew Marple</name></author><author><name>Jonas W. Ravich</name></author><author><name>Ada Tam</name></author><author><name>Ruyan Rahnama</name></author><author><name>Adam Fearnow</name></author><author><name>Cambrynne Rietberg</name></author><author><name>Sean Yanik</name></author><author><name>Elena E. Solomou</name></author><author><name>Ravi Varadhan</name></author><author><name>Michael A. Koldobskiy</name></author><author><name>Challice L. Bonifant</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The prognosis of patients with recurrent/refractory acute myelogenous leukemia (AML) remains poor and cell-based immunotherapies hold promise to improve outcomes. NK cells can elicit an anti-leukemic response via a repertoire of activating receptors that bind AML surface ligands. NK cell adoptive transfer is safe but thus far has shown limited anti-AML efficacy. Here, we aimed to overcome this limitation by engineering NK cells to express chimeric antigen receptors (CARs) to boost their anti-AML activity, and interleukin-15 (IL15) to enhance their persistence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We characterized in detail NK cell populations expressing a panel of AML (CD123)-specific CARs and/or IL15 &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and in AML xenograft models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;CARs with 2B4.ζ or 4-1BB.ζ signaling domains demonstrated greater cell surface expression and endowed NK cells with improved anti-AML activity &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. Initial &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; testing revealed that only 2B4.ζ CAR-NK cells had improved anti-AML activity in comparison to untransduced (UTD) and 4-1BB.ζ CAR-NK cells. However, the benefit was transient due to limited CAR-NK cell persistence. Transgenic expression of secretory (s)IL15 in 2B4.ζ CAR and UTD NK cells improved their effector function in the setting of chronic antigen simulation &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. Multiparameter flow analysis after chronic antigen exposure identified the expansion of unique NK cell subsets. 2B4.ζ/sIL15 CAR and sIL15 NK cells maintained an overall activated NK cell phenotype. This was confirmed by transcriptomic analysis, which revealed a highly proliferative and activated signature in these NK cell groups. &lt;italic&gt;In vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, 2B4.ζ/sIL15 CAR-NK cells had potent anti-AML activity in one model, while 2B4.ζ/sIL15 CAR and sIL15 NK cells induced lethal toxicity in a second model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transgenic expression of CD123-CARs and sIL15 enabled NK cells to function in the setting of chronic antigen exposure but was associated with systemic toxicities. Thus, our study provides the impetus to explore inducible and controllable expression systems to provide cytokine signals to AML-specific CAR-NK cells before embarking on early phase clinical testing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract Figure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="461509v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;In Brief&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretion of IL15 from anti-CD123.2B4.CD3ζ CAR-NK cells enhances their activation and killing potential against Acute Myelogenous Leukemia, but carries the risk of severe systemic toxicity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461509" rel="alternate" title="Engineering CAR-NK cells to secrete IL15 sustains their anti-AML functionality, but is associated with systemic toxicities (14 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461566</id><title>Active Translation Control of CD4 T Cell Activation by Regulatory T Cells (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.299450+00:00</updated><author><name>Lomon So</name></author><author><name>Kazushige Obata-Ninomiya</name></author><author><name>Alex Hu</name></author><author><name>Virginia Muir</name></author><author><name>Ayako Takamori</name></author><author><name>Ram Savan</name></author><author><name>Steven F. Ziegler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Increased protein synthesis is a hallmark of lymphocyte activation. Regulatory T cells (Tregs) suppress the activation and subsequent effector functions of CD4 effector T cells (Teff). Molecular mechanisms that enforce suppression on CD4 Teff cell function are unclear. Control of CD4 Teff cell activation by Tregs has largely been defined at the transcriptional level, which does not reflect changes in post-transcriptional control. We found that Tregs suppressed activation-induced global protein synthesis in CD4 Teff cells prior to cell division. We analyzed genome-wide changes in the transcriptome and translatome of activated CD4 Teff cells using two independent approaches. We show that mRNAs encoding for the protein synthesis machinery are regulated at the level of translation in activated Teff cells. Strikingly, Tregs suppressed global protein synthesis of CD4 Teff cells by specifically inhibiting mRNAs of the translation machinery at the level of mTORC1-mediated translation control. Lastly, we found that the RNA helicase eIF4A inhibitor rocaglamide A (RocA) can suppress CD4 Teff activation &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; to alleviate inflammatory CD4 Teff activation caused by acute Treg depletion &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. These data provide evidence that peripheral tolerance is enforced by Tregs, mediated by IL-10, through mRNA translational control in CD4 Teff cells. Therefore, therapeutic targeting of the protein synthesis machinery can mitigate inflammatory responses invoked by Treg loss of function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461566" rel="alternate" title="Active Translation Control of CD4 T Cell Activation by Regulatory T Cells (14 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462010</id><title>Drivers and Determinants of Strain Dynamics Following Faecal Microbiota Transplantation (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.299693+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas SB Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Simone S Li</name></author><author><name>Oleksandr M Maistrenko</name></author><author><name>Wasiu Akanni</name></author><author><name>Luis Pedro Coelho</name></author><author><name>Sibasish Dolai</name></author><author><name>Anthony Fullam</name></author><author><name>Anna M Glazek</name></author><author><name>Rajna Hercog</name></author><author><name>Hilde Herrema</name></author><author><name>Ferris Jung</name></author><author><name>Stefanie Kandels</name></author><author><name>Askarbek Orakov</name></author><author><name>Thea Van Rossum</name></author><author><name>Vladimir Benes</name></author><author><name>Thomas J Borody</name></author><author><name>Willem M de Vos</name></author><author><name>Cyriel Y Ponsioen</name></author><author><name>Max Nieuwdorp</name></author><author><name>Peer Bork</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Faecal microbiota transplantation (FMT) is an efficacious therapeutic intervention, but its clinical mode of action and underlying microbiome dynamics remain poorly understood. Here, we analysed the metagenomes associated with 142 FMTs, in a time series-based meta-study across five disease indications. We quantified strain-level dynamics of 1,089 microbial species based on their pangenome, complemented with 47,548 newly constructed metagenome-assembled genomes. Using subsets of procedural-, host- and microbiome-based variables, LASSO-regularised regression models accurately predicted the colonisation and resilience of donor and recipient microbes, as well as turnover of individual species. Linking this to putative ecological mechanisms, we found these sets of variables to be informative of the underlying processes that shape the post-FMT gut microbiome. Recipient factors and complementarity of donor and recipient microbiomes, encompassing entire communities to individual strains, were the main determinants of individual strain population dynamics, and mostly independent of clinical outcomes. Recipient community state and the degree of residual strain depletion provided a neutral baseline for donor strain colonisation success, in addition to inhibitive priority effects between species and conspecific strains, as well as putatively adaptive processes. Our results suggest promising tunable parameters to enhance donor flora colonisation or recipient flora displacement in clinical practice, towards the development of more targeted and personalised therapies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462010" rel="alternate" title="Drivers and Determinants of Strain Dynamics Following Faecal Microbiota Transplantation (14 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462198</id><title>Influenza A virus undergoes compartmentalized replication in vivo dominated by stochastic bottlenecks (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.300037+00:00</updated><author><name>Katherine A. Amato</name></author><author><name>Luis A. Haddock</name></author><author><name>Katarina M. Braun</name></author><author><name>Victoria Meliopoulos</name></author><author><name>Brandi Livingston</name></author><author><name>Rebekah Honce</name></author><author><name>Grace A. Schaack</name></author><author><name>Emma Boehm</name></author><author><name>Christina A. Higgins</name></author><author><name>Gabrielle L. Barry</name></author><author><name>Katia Koelle</name></author><author><name>Stacey Schultz-Cherry</name></author><author><name>Thomas C. Friedrich</name></author><author><name>Andrew Mehle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Transmission of influenza A viruses (IAV) between hosts is subject to numerous physical and biological barriers that impose genetic bottlenecks, constraining viral diversity and adaptation. The presence of bottlenecks within individual hosts and their potential impacts on evolutionary pathways taken during infection and subsequent transmission are poorly understood. To address this knowledge gap, we created highly diverse IAV libraries bearing molecular barcodes on two independent gene segments, enabling high-resolution tracking and quantification of unique virus lineages within hosts. Here we show that IAV infection in lungs is characterized by multiple within-host bottlenecks that result in “islands” of infection in lung lobes, each with genetically distinct populations. We performed site-specific inoculation of barcoded IAV in the upper respiratory tract of ferrets and tracked viral diversity as infection spread to the trachea and lungs. We observed compartmentalized replication of discrete barcoded populations within the lobes of the lung. Bottlenecks stochastically sampled individual viruses from the upper respiratory tract or the trachea that became the dominant genotype in a particular lobe. These populations are shaped strongly by founder effects, with no evidence for positive selection. The segregated sites of replication highlight the jackpot-style events that contribute to within-host influenza virus evolution and may account for low rates of intrahost adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462198" rel="alternate" title="Influenza A virus undergoes compartmentalized replication in vivo dominated by stochastic bottlenecks (14 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461243</id><title>Local accessory gene sharing drives lineage-specific acquisition of antimicrobial resistance in Egyptian Campylobacter spp. (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.303125+00:00</updated><author><name>Shaimaa F. Mouftah</name></author><author><name>Ben Pascoe</name></author><author><name>Jessica K. Calland</name></author><author><name>Evangelos Mourkas</name></author><author><name>Naomi Tonkin</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Lefèvre</name></author><author><name>Danielle Deuker</name></author><author><name>Sunny Smith</name></author><author><name>Harry Wickenden</name></author><author><name>Matthew D. Hitchings</name></author><author><name>Samuel K. Sheppard</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Elhadidy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Campylobacter&lt;/italic&gt; is the most common cause of bacterial gastroenteritis worldwide and diarrheal disease is a major cause of child morbidity, growth faltering and mortality in low- and middle-income countries (LMICs). Despite evidence of high incidence and differences in disease epidemiology, there is limited genomic data from studies in developing countries. In this study, we characterised the genetic diversity and accessory genome content of a collection of &lt;italic&gt;Campylobacter&lt;/italic&gt; isolates from Cairo, Egypt. In total, 112 &lt;italic&gt;Campylobacter&lt;/italic&gt; isolates were collected from broiler carcasses (n=31), milk and dairy products (n=24) and patients (n=57) suffering from gastroenteritis. Among the most common sequence types (STs) we identified were the globally disseminated, host generalist ST-21 clonal complex (CC21) and the poultry specialist CC206, CC464 and CC48. Notably, CC45 and the cattle-specialist CC42 were under-represented with a total absence of CC61. Comparative genomics were used to quantify core and accessory genome sharing among isolates from the same country compared to sharing between countries. Lineage-specific accessory genome sharing was significantly higher among isolates from the same country, particularly CC21 which demonstrated greater local geographical clustering. In contrast, no geographic clustering was noted in either the core or accessory genomes of the CC828, suggesting a highly admixed population. A greater proportion of &lt;italic&gt;C. coli&lt;/italic&gt; isolates were multidrug resistant (MDR) compared to &lt;italic&gt;C. jejuni&lt;/italic&gt;. This is a significant public health concern as MDR food chain pathogens are difficult to treat and often pose increased mortality risk demanding enhanced prevention strategies in the Egyptian market to combat such a threat.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Impact statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Campylobacter&lt;/italic&gt; is the leading bacterial cause of gastroenteritis worldwide and despite high incidence in low- and middle-income countries, where infection can be fatal, culture-based isolation is rare and the genotypes responsible for disease are seldom identified. Here, we sequenced the genomes of a collection of isolates from clinical cases and potential infection reservoirs from Cairo in Egypt and characterised their genetic diversity. Among the most common genotypes we identified were globally disseminated lineages implicated in human disease worldwide, including the host generalist ST-21 clonal complex (CC21) and the poultry specialist genotypes CC206, CC464 and CC48. Notably however, some other globally common genotypes were under-represented or entirely absent from our collection, including those from cattle-specialist lineages, CC42 and CC61. By focussing on specific lineages, we demonstrate that there is increased accessory genome sharing in specific clonal complexes. This increased local sharing of genes may have contributed to a greater proportion of &lt;italic&gt;C. coli&lt;/italic&gt; isolates possessing antimicrobial resistance determinants that suggest they could be multidrug resistant (MDR). This is a significant public health concern as MDR food chain pathogens are difficult to treat and often pose increased mortality risk demanding enhanced prevention strategies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Short read data are available on the NCBI Sequence Read Archive, associated with BioProject PRJNA576513 (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/PRJNA576513"&gt;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/PRJNA576513&lt;/ext-link&gt;). Assembled genomes, supplementary material and additional analysis files are available from FigShare: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.9956597"&gt;https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.9956597&lt;/ext-link&gt;. Phylogenetic trees can be visualised and manipulated on Microreact for &lt;italic&gt;C. jejuni&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://next.microreact.org/project/Cjejuni_Egypt"&gt;https://next.microreact.org/project/Cjejuni_Egypt&lt;/ext-link&gt;) and &lt;italic&gt;C. coli&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://next.microreact.org/project/Ccoli_Egypt"&gt;https://next.microreact.org/project/Ccoli_Egypt&lt;/ext-link&gt;) separately, or combined Cairo and Oxford data with additional PopPunk network clustering (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://microreact.org/project/Campy-Egypt"&gt;https://microreact.org/project/Campy-Egypt&lt;/ext-link&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461243" rel="alternate" title="Local accessory gene sharing drives lineage-specific acquisition of antimicrobial resistance in Egyptian Campylobacter spp. (12 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461720</id><title>Global composition of the bacteriophage community in honeybees (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.303696+00:00</updated><author><name>Taylor J. Busby</name></author><author><name>Craig R. Miller</name></author><author><name>Nancy A. Moran</name></author><author><name>James T. Van Leuven</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The microbial communities in animal digestive systems are critical to host development and health. These assemblages of primarily viruses, bacteria, and fungi stimulate the immune system during development, synthesize important chemical compounds like hormones, aid in digestion, competitively exclude pathogens, etc. The bacteriophages in animal microbiomes are harder to characterize than the bacterial or fungal components of the microbiome and thus we know comparatively little about the temporal and spatial dynamics of bacteriophage communities in animal digestive systems. Recently, the bacteriophages of the honeybee gut were characterized in two European bee populations. Most of the bacteriophages described in these two reports were novel, encoded many metabolic genes in their genomes, and had a community structure that suggests coevolution with their bacterial hosts. To describe the conservation of bacteriophages in bees and begin to understand their role in the bee microbiome, we sequenced the virome of &lt;italic&gt;Apis mellifera&lt;/italic&gt; from Austin, Texas and compared bacteriophage composition between three locations around the world. We found that the majority of bacteriophages from Austin are novel, sharing no sequence similarity to anything in public repositories. However, many bacteriophages are shared among the three bee viromes, indicating specialization of bacteriophages in the bee gut. Our study along with the two previous bee virome studies shows that the bee gut bacteriophage community is simple compared to that of many animals, consisting of several hundred types of bacteriophages that primarily infect four of the dominant bacterial phylotypes in the bee gut.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461720" rel="alternate" title="Global composition of the bacteriophage community in honeybees (12 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461628</id><title>The mosquito microbiome includes habitat-specific but rare symbionts (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.303945+00:00</updated><author><name>Hans Schrieke</name></author><author><name>Loïs Maignien</name></author><author><name>Florentin Constancias</name></author><author><name>Florian Trigodet</name></author><author><name>Sarah Chakloute</name></author><author><name>Ignace Rakotoarivony</name></author><author><name>Albane Marie</name></author><author><name>Gregory L’Ambert</name></author><author><name>Patrick Makoundou</name></author><author><name>Nonito Pages</name></author><author><name>A. Murat Eren</name></author><author><name>Mylène Weill</name></author><author><name>Mathieu Sicard</name></author><author><name>Julie Reveillaud</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microbial communities are known to influence mosquito lifestyles by modifying essential metabolic and behavioral processes that affect reproduction, development, immunity, digestion, egg survival, and ability to transmit pathogens. Many studies have used 16S rRNA gene amplicons to characterize mosquito microbiota and investigate factors that influence host-microbiota dynamics. However, a relatively low taxonomic resolution due to clustering methods based on arbitrary threshold and the overall dominance of &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia or Asaia&lt;/italic&gt; populations obscured the investigation of rare members of mosquito microbiota in previous studies. Here, we used high resolution Shannon entropy-based oligotyping approaches to analyze the microbiota of &lt;italic&gt;Culex pipiens, Culex quinquefasciatus&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; individuals from continental and overseas regions in Southern France and Guadeloupe as well as from laboratories with or without antibiotics treatment. Our experimental design that resulted in a series of mosquito samples with a gradient of &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; density and relative abundance along with high-resolution analyses of amplicon sequences enabled the recovery of a robust signal from typically less accessible bacterial taxa. Our data confirm species-specific mosquito-bacteria associations with geography as a primary factor that influences bacterial community structure. But interestingly, they also reveal co-occurring symbiotic bacterial variants within single individuals for both &lt;italic&gt;Elizabethkingia&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Erwinia&lt;/italic&gt; genera, distinct and specific &lt;italic&gt;Asaia&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Chryseobacterium&lt;/italic&gt; in continental and overseas territories and a putative rare &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; variant. Overall, our study reveals the presence of previously-overlooked microdiversity and multiple closely related symbiotic strains within mosquito individuals with a remarkable habitat-specificity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461628" rel="alternate" title="The mosquito microbiome includes habitat-specific but rare symbionts (12 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462132</id><title>An anti-inflammatory activation sequence governs macrophage transcriptional dynamics during tissue injury (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.304178+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicolas Denans</name></author><author><name>Nhung T. T. Tran</name></author><author><name>Madeleine E. Swall</name></author><author><name>Daniel C. Diaz</name></author><author><name>Jillian Blanck</name></author><author><name>Tatjana Piotrowski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Macrophages are essential for tissue repair and regeneration. Yet, the molecular programs, as well as the timing of their activation during and after tissue injury are poorly defined. Using a high spatio-temporal resolution single cell analysis of macrophages coupled with live imaging after sensory hair cell death in zebrafish, we find that the same population of macrophages transitions through a sequence of three major anti-inflammatory activation states. Macrophages first show a signature of glucocorticoid activation, then IL10 signaling and finally the induction of oxidative phosphorylation by IL4/Polyamine signaling. Importantly, loss-of-function of glucocorticoid and IL10 signaling shows that each step of the sequence is independently activated. Our results provide the first evidence that macrophages, in addition to a switch from M1 to M2, sequentially and independently transition though three anti-inflammatory pathways &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; during tissue injury in a regenerating organ.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We show that macrophages are sequentially activated by three different anti-inflammatory pathways during tissue injury.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462132" rel="alternate" title="An anti-inflammatory activation sequence governs macrophage transcriptional dynamics during tissue injury (11 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461844</id><title>Widespread density dependence of bacterial growth under acid stress (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.304349+00:00</updated><author><name>Francesca Fiegna</name></author><author><name>Samay Pande</name></author><author><name>Hansrainer Peitz</name></author><author><name>Gregory J. Velicer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Benefits of cooperation intrinsically depend on density because biological interaction requires organismal proximity. Microbial cooperative traits are common, yet systematic tests for a shared cooperative phenotype across diverse species are rare, as are direct tests for the Allee effect - positive density dependence of fitness. Here we test for positive density dependence of growth under acid stress in five phylogenetically widespread bacterial species - three Gram-negative and two Gram-positive - and find the Allee effect in all five. However, social protection from acid stress appears to have evolved by different mechanisms across species. In &lt;italic&gt;Myxococcus xanthus&lt;/italic&gt;, the acid-stress Allee effect is found to be mediated by pH-regulated secretion of a diffusible molecule present in supernatant from high-density cultures. In contrast, growth from low density under acid stress by the other species was not enhanced by high-density supernatant. Additionally, density dependence of &lt;italic&gt;Myxococcus&lt;/italic&gt; fruiting-body formation during starvation is found to increase with acid stress, suggesting that abiotic stresses other than starvation shape the evolution of aggregative development. Our findings suggest that high cell density may protect against acid stress in most bacterial species and in &lt;italic&gt;Myxococcus&lt;/italic&gt; may promote predation on microbes that acidify their local environment by secretion of metabolic byproducts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461844" rel="alternate" title="Widespread density dependence of bacterial growth under acid stress (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462388</id><title>Klebsiella pneumoniae hijacks the Toll-IL-1R protein SARM1 in a type I IFN-dependent manner to antagonize host immunity (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.304503+00:00</updated><author><name>Claudia Feriotti</name></author><author><name>Joana Sa-Pessoa</name></author><author><name>Ricardo Calderón-González</name></author><author><name>Lili Gu</name></author><author><name>Brenda Morris</name></author><author><name>Ryoichi Sugisawa</name></author><author><name>Jose L. Insua</name></author><author><name>Michael Carty</name></author><author><name>Amy Dumigan</name></author><author><name>Rebecca J. Ingram</name></author><author><name>Adrien Kisenpfening</name></author><author><name>Andrew G. Bowie</name></author><author><name>José A. Bengoechea</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many bacterial pathogens antagonize host defence responses by translocating effector proteins into cells. It remains an open question how those pathogens not encoding effectors counteract anti-bacterial immunity. Here, we show that &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; hijacks the evolutionary conserved innate immune protein SARM1 to control cell intrinsic immunity. &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella&lt;/italic&gt; exploits SARM1 to regulate negatively MyD88 and TRIF-governed inflammation, and the activation of the MAP kinases ERK and JNK. SARM1 is required for &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella&lt;/italic&gt; induction of IL10 by fine-tuning the p38-type I IFN axis. SARM1 inhibits the activation of &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella&lt;/italic&gt;-induced absent in melanoma 2 inflammasome to limit IL1β production, suppressing further inflammation. &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella&lt;/italic&gt; exploits type I IFNs to induce SARM1 in a capsule and LPS O-polysaccharide-dependent manner via TLR4-TRAM-TRIF-IRF3-IFNAR1 pathway. Absence of SARM1 reduces the intracellular survival of &lt;italic&gt;K. pneumonaie&lt;/italic&gt; in macrophages whereas &lt;italic&gt;sarm1&lt;/italic&gt; deficient mice control the infection. Altogether, our results illustrate a hitherto unknown anti-immunology strategy deployed by a human pathogen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462388" rel="alternate" title="Klebsiella pneumoniae hijacks the Toll-IL-1R protein SARM1 in a type I IFN-dependent manner to antagonize host immunity (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462461</id><title>GpsB coordinates cell division and cell surface decoration by wall teichoic acids in Staphylococcus aureus (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.304791+00:00</updated><author><name>Lauren R. Hammond</name></author><author><name>Sebastian J. Khan</name></author><author><name>Michael D. Sacco</name></author><author><name>Catherine Spanoudis</name></author><author><name>Abigail Hough</name></author><author><name>Yu Chen</name></author><author><name>Prahathees J. Eswara</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial cell division is a complex and highly regulated process requiring the coordination of many different proteins. Despite substantial work in model organisms, our understanding of the systems regulating cell division in non-canonical organisms, including critical human pathogens, is far from complete. One such organism is &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/italic&gt;, a spherical bacterium that lacks known cell division regulatory proteins. Recent studies on GpsB, a protein conserved within the Firmicutes phylum, have provided insight into cell division regulation in &lt;italic&gt;S. aureus&lt;/italic&gt; and other related organisms. It has been revealed that GpsB coordinates cell division and cell wall synthesis in multiple species by interacting with Penicillin Binding Proteins (PBPs) and other partners. In &lt;italic&gt;S. aureus&lt;/italic&gt;, we have previously shown that GpsB directly regulates FtsZ polymerization. In this study, using &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; as a tool, we isolated intragenic and extragenic spontaneous suppressor mutants that abrogate the lethality of &lt;italic&gt;S. aureus&lt;/italic&gt; GpsB overproduction in &lt;italic&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/italic&gt;. Through characterization of these mutants, we identified several key residues important for the function of GpsB. Furthermore, we discovered an additional role for GpsB in wall teichoic acid (WTA) biosynthesis in &lt;italic&gt;S. aureus&lt;/italic&gt;. Specifically, we show that GpsB directly interacts with the wall teichoic acid export protein TarG using a bacterial two-hybrid analysis. We also identified a three-residue motif in GpsB that is crucial for this interaction. Based on the analysis of the localization of TagG in &lt;italic&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; and its homolog TarG in &lt;italic&gt;S. aureus&lt;/italic&gt;, it appears that WTA machinery is a part of the divisome complex. As such, we show additional evidence to the growing body of work that suggests that along with peptidoglycan synthesis, WTA biosynthesis and export may take place at the site of cell division. Taken together, this research illustrates how GpsB performs an essential function in &lt;italic&gt;S. aureus&lt;/italic&gt; by directly linking the tightly regulated cell cycle processes of cell division and WTA-mediated cell surface decoration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE/AUTHOR SUMMARY&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cytokinesis in bacteria involves an intricate orchestration of several key cell division proteins and other factors involved in building a robust cell envelope. One of the key factors that differentiates Gram-positive bacteria from Gram-negative bacteria is the presence of teichoic acids interlaced within the Gram-positive cell wall. By characterizing the role of &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/italic&gt; GpsB, an essential cell division protein in this organism, we have uncovered an additional role for GpsB in wall teichoic acids (WTA) biosynthesis. We show that GpsB directly interacts with TarG of the WTA export complex. We also show this function of GpsB may be conserved in other GpsB homologs as GpsB and the WTA exporter complex follow similar localization patterns. It has been suggested that WTA acts as a molecular signal to control the activity of autolytic enzymes, especially during the separation of conjoined daughter cells. Thus, our results reveal that GpsB, in addition to playing a role in cell division, may also help coordinate WTA biogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462461" rel="alternate" title="GpsB coordinates cell division and cell surface decoration by wall teichoic acids in Staphylococcus aureus (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461765</id><title>Human metapneumovirus P protein independently drives phase separation and recruits N protein to liquid-like inclusion bodies (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.304976+00:00</updated><author><name>Kerri Beth Boggs</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Cifuentes-Munoz</name></author><author><name>Kearstin Edmonds</name></author><author><name>Farah El Najjar</name></author><author><name>Conny Ossandón</name></author><author><name>McKenna Roe</name></author><author><name>Carole L. Moncman</name></author><author><name>Trevor Creamer</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Ellis Dutch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human metapneumovirus (HMPV) inclusion bodies (IBs) are dynamic structures required for efficient viral replication and transcription. The minimum components needed to form IB-like structures in cells are the nucleoprotein (N) and the tetrameric phosphoprotein (P). HMPV P binds to two versions of N protein in infected cells: C-terminal P residues interact with oligomeric, RNA-bound N (N-RNA), and N-terminal P residues interact with monomeric N (N&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt;) to maintain a pool of protein to encapsidate new RNA. Recent work on other negative-strand viruses has suggested that IBs are liquid-like organelles formed via liquid-liquid phase separation (LLPS). Here, HMPV IBs in infected or transfected cells were shown to possess liquid organelle properties, such as fusion and fission. Recombinant versions of HMPV N and P proteins were purified to analyze the interactions required to drive LLPS &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. Purified HMPV P was shown to form liquid droplets in the absence of other protein binding partners, a novel finding compared to other viral systems. Removal of nucleic acid from purified P altered phase separation dynamics, suggesting that nucleic acid interactions also play a role in IB formation. HMPV P also recruits monomeric N (N&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt;-P) and N-RNA to IBs &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. These findings suggest that, in contrast to what has been reported for other viral systems, HMPV P acts as a scaffold protein to mediate multivalent interactions with monomeric and oligomeric HMPV N to promote phase separation of IBs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Human metapneumovirus (HMPV) is a leading cause of respiratory disease among children, immunocompromised individuals, and the elderly. Currently, no vaccines or antivirals are available for treatment of HMPV infections. Cytoplasmic inclusion bodies (IBs), where HMPV replication and transcription occur, represent a promising target for the development of novel antivirals. The HMPV nucleoprotein (N) and phosphoprotein (P) are the minimal components needed for IB formation in eukaryotic cells. However, interactions that regulate the formation of these dynamic structures are poorly understood. Here, we showed that HMPV IBs possess the properties of liquid organelles and that purified HMPV P phase separates independently &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. Our work suggests that HMPV P phase separation dynamics are altered by nucleic acid. We provide strong evidence that, unlike results reported from other viral systems, HMPV P alone serves as a scaffold for multivalent interactions with monomeric (N&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt;) and oligomeric (N-RNA) HMPV N for IB formation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461765" rel="alternate" title="Human metapneumovirus P protein independently drives phase separation and recruits N protein to liquid-like inclusion bodies (8 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461452</id><title>Variable freshwater influences on the abundance of Vibrio vulnificus in a tropical urban estuary (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.305192+00:00</updated><author><name>Olivia D. Nigro</name></author><author><name>La’Toya I. James-Davis</name></author><author><name>Eric Heinen De Carlo</name></author><author><name>Yuan-Hui Li</name></author><author><name>Grieg F. Steward</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To better understand the controls on the opportunistic human pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Vibrio vulnificus&lt;/italic&gt; in warm tropical waters, we conducted a year-long investigation in the Ala Wai Canal, a channelized estuary in Honolulu, HI. The abundance of &lt;italic&gt;V. vulnificus&lt;/italic&gt; as determined by qPCR of the hemolysin gene (&lt;italic&gt;vvhA&lt;/italic&gt;), varied spatially and temporally nearly four orders of magnitude (≤ 3 to 14,000 mL&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;). Unlike in temperate and subtropical systems, temperatures were persistently warm (19–31°C) and explained little of the variability in &lt;italic&gt;V. vulnificus&lt;/italic&gt; abundance. Salinity (1–36 ppt) had a significant, but non-linear, relationship with &lt;italic&gt;V. vulnificus&lt;/italic&gt; abundance with highest &lt;italic&gt;vvhA&lt;/italic&gt; concentrations (&amp;gt; 2,500 mL&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) observed only at salinities from 7 to 22 ppt. &lt;italic&gt;V. vulnificus&lt;/italic&gt; abundances were lower on average in the summer dry season when waters were warmer but more saline. Highest canal-wide average abundances were observed during a time of modest rainfall when moderate salinities and elevated concentrations of reduced nitrogen species and silica suggested a groundwater influence. Distinguishing the abundances of two genotypes of &lt;italic&gt;V. vulnificus&lt;/italic&gt; (C-type and E-type) suggest that C-type strains, which are responsible for most human infections, were usually less abundant (25% on average), but their relative contribution was greater at higher salinities, suggesting a broader salinity tolerance. Generalized regression models suggested up to 67% of sample-to-sample variation in log-transformed &lt;italic&gt;V. vulnificus&lt;/italic&gt; abundance was explained (n = 202) using the measured environmental variables, and up to 97% of the monthly variation in canal-wide average concentrations (n = 13) was explained with the best subset of four variables.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our data illustrate that, in the absence of strong seasonal variation in water temperature in the tropics, variation in salinity driven by rainfall becomes a primary controlling variable on &lt;italic&gt;V. vulnificus&lt;/italic&gt; abundance. There is thus a tendency for a rainfall-driven seasonal cycle in &lt;italic&gt;V. vulnificus&lt;/italic&gt; abundance that is inverted from the temperature-driven seasonal cycle at higher latitudes. However, stochasticity in rainfall and its non-linear, indirect effects on &lt;italic&gt;V. vulnificus&lt;/italic&gt; concentration means that high abundances can occur at any location in the canal at any time of year, making it challenging to predict concentrations of this pathogen at high temporal or spatial resolution. Much of the variability in canal-wide average concentrations, on the other hand, was explained by a few variables that reflect the magnitude of freshwater input to the system, suggesting that relative risk of exposure to this pathogen could be predicted for the system as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461452" rel="alternate" title="Variable freshwater influences on the abundance of Vibrio vulnificus in a tropical urban estuary (8 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461933</id><title>HIV-1 hijacks the cell extracellular matrix to spread collectively and efficiently between T lymphocytes (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.305443+00:00</updated><author><name>C. Inizan</name></author><author><name>M. Caillet</name></author><author><name>A. Desrames</name></author><author><name>A. David</name></author><author><name>P. Bomme</name></author><author><name>A. Mallet</name></author><author><name>K. Bourdic</name></author><author><name>O. Lambotte</name></author><author><name>F. Boufassa</name></author><author><name>M. Mesel-Lemoine</name></author><author><name>F. Tangy</name></author><author><name>G. Pancino</name></author><author><name>H. Mouquet</name></author><author><name>T. Lagache</name></author><author><name>A. Dufour</name></author><author><name>J.- C. Olivo-Marin</name></author><author><name>F.A. Rey</name></author><author><name>A. Saez-Cirion</name></author><author><name>M.-I. Thoulouze</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Collective transmission &lt;italic&gt;via&lt;/italic&gt; structures containing several virions has recently emerged as a highly efficient mode of viral spread. Here, we demonstrate that HIV-1 spreads between T lymphocytes in the form of viral particles colonies that are concentrated and sheltered in an extracellular matrix (ECM) lattice enabling their collective transmission upon cell contacts. Intrinsically, ECM-clustered viruses infect T lymphocytes more efficiently than individual viral particles. They preserve HIV-1 transmission from antiretroviral treatment (ArT) and potent broadly neutralizing antibodies. We also show that collagen induced by HIV-1 infection controls the clustering of virions and their collective spread, thereby enhancing infectivity. CD4+ T cells from HIV-1-infected patients produce and transmit ECM-virus clusters, supporting that they could be involved &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. This study provides new insights into modes of HIV-1 transmission and identifies a novel fundamental role for collagen in this process. HIV-1 spread &lt;italic&gt;via&lt;/italic&gt; ECM-virus clusters may have important implications for viral dissemination and persistence, including during therapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461933" rel="alternate" title="HIV-1 hijacks the cell extracellular matrix to spread collectively and efficiently between T lymphocytes (8 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461865</id><title>Innate immune signaling drives late cardiac toxicity following DNA damaging cancer therapies (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.306254+00:00</updated><author><name>Achraf Shamseddine</name></author><author><name>Suchit H. Patel</name></author><author><name>Valery Chavez</name></author><author><name>Mutayyaba Adnan</name></author><author><name>Melody Di Bona</name></author><author><name>Jun Li</name></author><author><name>Chau T. Dang</name></author><author><name>Lakshmi V. Ramanathan</name></author><author><name>Kevin C. Oeffinger</name></author><author><name>Jennifer E. Liu</name></author><author><name>Richard M. Steingart</name></author><author><name>Alessandra Piersigilli</name></author><author><name>Nicholas D. Socci</name></author><author><name>Angel T. Chan</name></author><author><name>Anthony F. Yu</name></author><author><name>Samuel F. Bakhoum</name></author><author><name>Adam M. Schmitt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Late cardiac toxicity is a potentially lethal complication of cancer therapy, yet the pathogenic mechanism remains largely unknown, and few treatment options exist. Here we report DNA damaging agents such as radiation and anthracycline chemotherapies induce delayed cardiac inflammation following therapy due to activation of cGAS and STING-dependent type I interferon signaling. Genetic ablation of cGAS-STING-signaling in mice inhibits DNA damage induced cardiac inflammation, rescues late cardiac functional decline, and prevents death from cardiac events. Treatment with a STING antagonist suppresses cardiac interferon signaling following DNA damaging therapies and effectively mitigates cardiotoxicity. These results identify a therapeutically targetable, pathogenic mechanism for one of the most vexing treatment-related toxicities in cancer survivors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461865" rel="alternate" title="Innate immune signaling drives late cardiac toxicity following DNA damaging cancer therapies (8 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462096</id><title>Assessing the role of fungal diversity in decomposition: A meta-analysis (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.306702+00:00</updated><author><name>Sytske M. Drost</name></author><author><name>Annemieke van der Wal</name></author><author><name>Wietse de Boer</name></author><author><name>Paul. L.E. Bodelier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fungi play an important role in carbon - and nutrient cycling. It is, however, unclear if diversity of fungi is essential to fulfill this role. With this meta-analysis, we aim to understand the relationship between fungal diversity and decomposition of plant materials (leaf litter and wood) in terrestrial and aquatic environments. The selection criteria for papers were the presence of a fungal diversity gradient and quantification of decomposition as mass loss. In total 40 papers met the selection criteria. We hypothesized that increase of fungal species will result in stronger decomposition, especially in species poor communities. Both artificial inoculated and naturally assembled fungal communities were included in the analysis in order to assess whether manipulated experiments are representative for field situations. We found a significant positive effect of increased fungal diversity on decomposition. However, in manipulated experiments this relationship was only positive when a control treatment of one fungus was compared with multispecies communities. This relationship became negative when comparisons of higher initial richness (at least two fungal species as “control”) were included. In contrast, under natural field conditions increased fungal diversity coincided with increased decomposition. This suggests that manipulated experiments are not representative for field situations. Possible reasons for this are discussed. Yet, both in manipulated and field experiments, environmental factors can influence diversity – decomposition relationships as indicated by a negative relationship of increasing C:N ratio on the effect of fungal diversity on decomposition. Overall, our results show that fungal diversity can have an important role in decomposition, but that design of experiments (manipulated or field) and quality of the plant material should be taken into account for interpretation of this diversity-functioning relationship.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462096" rel="alternate" title="Assessing the role of fungal diversity in decomposition: A meta-analysis (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461875</id><title>Human neutrophils are not activated by Zika virus but reduce the infection of susceptible cells (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.306959+00:00</updated><author><name>Juliana Bernardi Aggio</name></author><author><name>Bárbara Nery Porto</name></author><author><name>Claudia Nunes Duarte dos Santos</name></author><author><name>Ana Luiza Pamplona Mosimann</name></author><author><name>Pryscilla Fanini Wowk</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Zika virus&lt;/italic&gt; (ZIKV) emergence highlighted the need for a deeper understanding on virus-host interaction to pave the development of antiviral therapies. The present work aimed to address the response of neutrophils during ZIKV infection. Neutrophils are an important effector cell in innate immunity involved in the host response to neurotropic arboviruses. Our results indicate that human neutrophils were not permissive to Asian or African ZIKV strains replication. Indeed, after stimulation with ZIKV, neutrophils were not primed against the virus as evaluated by the absence of CD11b modulation, secretion of inflammatory cytokines and granule content, production of reactive oxygen species and neutrophil extracellular traps formation. Overall, neutrophils did not affect ZIKV infectivity. Moreover, ZIKV infection of primary innate immune cells &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; did not trigger neutrophil migration. However, neutrophil co-cultured with ZIKV susceptible cells (A549) resulted in lower frequencies of infection on A549 cells by cell-to-cell contact. &lt;italic&gt;In vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, neutrophil depletion from immunocompetent mice did not affect ZIKV spreading to the draining lymph nodes. The data suggest human neutrophils do not play a &lt;italic&gt;per se&lt;/italic&gt; antiviral role against ZIKV, but these cells might participate in an infected environment shaping the ZIKV infection in other target cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461875" rel="alternate" title="Human neutrophils are not activated by Zika virus but reduce the infection of susceptible cells (7 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461265</id><title>Quantitative input-output dynamics of a c-di-GMP signal-transduction cascade in Vibrio cholerae (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.307154+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew A. Bridges</name></author><author><name>Jojo A. Prentice</name></author><author><name>Chenyi Fei</name></author><author><name>Ned S. Wingreen</name></author><author><name>Bonnie L. Bassler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial biofilms are multicellular communities that collectively overcome environmental threats and clinical treatments. To regulate the biofilm lifecycle, bacteria commonly transduce sensory information via the second-messenger molecule cyclic diguanylate (c-di-GMP). Using experimental and modeling approaches, we quantitatively capture c-di-GMP signal transmission via the bifunctional polyamine receptor NspS-MbaA, from ligand binding to output, in the pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Vibrio cholerae&lt;/italic&gt;. Upon binding of norspermidine or spermidine, NspS-MbaA synthesizes or degrades c-di-GMP, respectively, which in turn, drives alterations specifically to biofilm gene expression. A longstanding question is how output specificity is achieved via c-di-GMP, a diffusible molecule that regulates dozens of effectors. We show that NspS-MbaA signals locally to specific effectors, sensitizing &lt;italic&gt;V. cholerae&lt;/italic&gt; to polyamines. However, local signaling is not required for specificity, as changes to global cytoplasmic c-di-GMP levels can selectively regulate biofilm genes. This work establishes the input-output dynamics underlying c-di-GMP signaling, which could be useful for developing bacterial manipulation strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461265" rel="alternate" title="Quantitative input-output dynamics of a c-di-GMP signal-transduction cascade in Vibrio cholerae (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461995</id><title>Distinct cell adhesion signature defines glioblastoma myeloid-derived suppressor cell subsets (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.307391+00:00</updated><author><name>Defne Bayik</name></author><author><name>Cynthia F. Bartels</name></author><author><name>Katreya Lovrenert</name></author><author><name>Dionysios C. Watson</name></author><author><name>Duo Zhang</name></author><author><name>Kristen Kay</name></author><author><name>Adam Lauko</name></author><author><name>Sadie Johnson</name></author><author><name>Alice Lo</name></author><author><name>Mary McGraw</name></author><author><name>Matthew Grabowski</name></author><author><name>Alireza M. Mohammadi</name></author><author><name>Filippo Veglia</name></author><author><name>Yi Fan</name></author><author><name>Michael A. Vogelbaum</name></author><author><name>Peter Scacheri</name></author><author><name>Justin D. Lathia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Increased myeloid-derived suppressor cell (MDSC) frequency is associated with worse outcomes and poor therapeutic response in glioblastoma (GBM). Monocytic (m) MDSCs represent the predominant subset in the GBM microenvironment. However, the molecular basis of mMDSC enrichment in the tumor microenvironment compared to granulocytic (g) MDSCs has yet to be determined. Here, we report that mMDSCs and gMDSCs display differences in their tumoraccelerating ability, with mMDSCs driving tumor growth in GBM models. Epigenetic assessments indicate enhanced gene accessibility for cell adhesion programs in mMDSCs and higher cellsurface integrin expression in mouse and human mMDSCs. Integrin β1 blockage abrogated the tumor-promoting phenotype of mMDSCs and altered the immune profile in the tumor microenvironment. These findings suggest that integrin β1 expression underlies the enrichment of mMDSCs in tumors and represents a putative immunotherapy target to attenuate myeloid cell-driven immune suppression in GBM.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Myeloid-derived suppressor cells (MDSCs) drive glioblastoma growth; however, the function of specific MDSCs subsets is unclear. Bayik &lt;italic&gt;et al.&lt;/italic&gt; demonstrate that adhesion programs are enhanced in monocytic MDSCs and responsible for their GBM-promoting function.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461995" rel="alternate" title="Distinct cell adhesion signature defines glioblastoma myeloid-derived suppressor cell subsets (7 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462663</id><title>A gut commensal niche regulates stable association of a multispecies microbiota (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.307746+00:00</updated><author><name>Ren Dodge</name></author><author><name>Eric W. Jones</name></author><author><name>Haolong Zhu</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Obadia</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Martinez</name></author><author><name>Chenhui Wang</name></author><author><name>Andrés Aranda-Díaz</name></author><author><name>Kevin Aumiller</name></author><author><name>Zhexian Liu</name></author><author><name>Marco Voltolini</name></author><author><name>Eoin L. Brodie</name></author><author><name>Kerwyn Casey Huang</name></author><author><name>Jean M. Carlson</name></author><author><name>David A. Sivak</name></author><author><name>Allan C. Spradling</name></author><author><name>William B. Ludington</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The intestines of animals are typically colonized by a complex, relatively stable microbiota that influences health and fitness, but the underlying mechanisms of colonization remain poorly understood. As a typical animal, the fruit fly, &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; melanogaster, is associated with a consistent set of commensal bacterial species, yet the reason for this consistency is unknown. Here, we use gnotobiotic flies, microscopy, and microbial pulse-chase protocols to show that a commensal niche exists within the proventriculus region of the &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; foregut that selectively binds bacteria with exquisite strain-level specificity. Primary colonizers saturate the niche and exclude secondary colonizers of the same strain, but initial colonization by &lt;italic&gt;Lactobacillus&lt;/italic&gt; physically remodels the niche to favor secondary colonization by &lt;italic&gt;Acetobacter&lt;/italic&gt;. Our results provide a mechanistic framework for understanding the establishment and stability of an intestinal microbiome.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A strain-specific set of bacteria inhabits a defined spatial region of the &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; gut that forms a commensal niche.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462663" rel="alternate" title="A gut commensal niche regulates stable association of a multispecies microbiota (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461546</id><title>T cells modulate the microglial response to brain ischemia (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.308010+00:00</updated><author><name>Corinne Benakis</name></author><author><name>Alba Simats</name></author><author><name>Sophie Tritschler</name></author><author><name>Steffanie Heindl</name></author><author><name>Simon Besson-Girard</name></author><author><name>Gemma Llovera</name></author><author><name>Kelsey Pinkham</name></author><author><name>Anna Kolz</name></author><author><name>Fabian Theis</name></author><author><name>Özgün Gökce</name></author><author><name>Anneli Peters</name></author><author><name>Arthur Liesz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neuroinflammation after stroke is characterized by the activation of resident microglia and the invasion of circulating leukocytes into the brain. Although lymphocytes infiltrate the brain in small number, they have been consistently demonstrated to be the most potent leukocyte subpopulation contributing to secondary inflammatory brain injury. However, the exact mechanism how this minimal number of lymphocytes can profoundly affect stroke outcome is still largely elusive. Here, using a mouse model for ischemic stroke, we demonstrated that early activation of microglia in response to stroke is differentially regulated by distinct T cell subpopulations. Acute treatment with engineered T cells overexpressing IL-10 administered into the cisterna magna after stroke induces a switch of microglial gene expression to a profile associated with pro-regenerative functions. These findings substantiate the role of T cells in stroke with large impact on the cerebral inflammatory milieu by polarizing the microglial phenotype. Targeting T cell-microglia interactions can have direct translational relevance for further development of immune-targeted therapies for stroke and other neuroinflammatory conditions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The crosstalk between brain infiltrating T cells and microglia in response to stroke remains elusive. Benakis et al. report that transcriptional signature of the stroke-associated microglia is reprogrammed by distinct T cell subpopulations. Engineered T cells overexpressing IL-10 administered four hours after stroke reinitiate microglial function inducing a pro-regenerative environment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461546" rel="alternate" title="T cells modulate the microglial response to brain ischemia (6 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461182</id><title>Transcriptional dynamics of methane-cycling microbiomes are linked to seasonal CH4 fluxes in two hydromorphic and organic-rich grassland soils (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.308500+00:00</updated><author><name>Jana Täumer</name></author><author><name>Sven Marhan</name></author><author><name>Verena Groß</name></author><author><name>Corinna Jensen</name></author><author><name>Andreas W. Kuss</name></author><author><name>Steffen Kolb</name></author><author><name>Tim Urich</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Soil CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; fluxes are driven by CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-producing and -consuming microorganisms that determine whether soils are sources or sinks of this potent greenhouse gas. Using quantitative metatranscriptomics, we linked CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-cycling microbiomes to net surface CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; fluxes throughout a year in two drained peatland soils differing in grassland land-use intensity and physicochemical properties. CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; fluxes were highly dynamic; both soils were net CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; sources in autumn and winter and sinks in spring and summer. Despite similar net CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; emissions, methanogen and methanotroph loads, as determined by small subunit rRNA transcripts per gram soil, differed strongly between sites. In contrast, mRNA transcript abundances were similar in both soils and correlated well with CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; fluxes. The methane monooxygenase to methanogenesis mRNA ratio was higher in spring and summer, when the soils were net CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; sinks. CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; uptake was linked to an increased proportion of USCα and γ and pmoA2 &lt;italic&gt;pmoA&lt;/italic&gt; transcripts. We assume that methanogen transcript abundance may be useful to approximate changes in net surface CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; emissions from drained peat soils; high methanotroph to methanogen ratios would indicate CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; sink properties. Our study shows the strength of quantitative metatranscriptomics; mRNA transcript abundance holds promising indicator to link soil microbiome functions to ecosystem-level processes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461182" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptional dynamics of methane-cycling microbiomes are linked to seasonal CH4 fluxes in two hydromorphic and organic-rich grassland soils (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461956</id><title>Ecological stochasticity and phage induction diversify bacterioplankton communities at the microscale (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.308913+00:00</updated><author><name>Rachel E. Szabo</name></author><author><name>Sammy Pontrelli</name></author><author><name>Jacopo Grilli</name></author><author><name>Julia A. Schwartzman</name></author><author><name>Shaul Pollak</name></author><author><name>Uwe Sauer</name></author><author><name>Otto X. Cordero</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In many natural environments, microorganisms self-assemble around heterogeneously distributed resource patches. The growth and collapse of populations on resource patches can unfold within spatial ranges of a few hundred micrometers or less, making such microscale ecosystems hotspots of biological interactions and nutrient fluxes. Despite the potential importance of patch-level dynamics for the large-scale evolution and function of microbial communities, we have not yet been able to delineate the ecological processes that control natural populations at the microscale. Here, we addressed this challenge in the context of microbially-mediated degradation of particulate organic matter by characterizing the natural marine communities that assembled on over one thousand individual microscale chitin particles. Through shotgun metagenomics, we found significant variation in microscale community composition despite the similarity in initial species pools across replicates. Strikingly, a subset of particles was highly populated by rare chitin-degrading strains; we hypothesized that their conditional success reflected the impact of stochastic colonization and growth on community assembly. In contrast to the conserved functional structures that emerge in ecosystems at larger scales, this taxonomic variability translated to a wide range of predicted chitinolytic abilities and growth returns at the level of individual particles. We found that predation by temperate bacteriophages, especially of degrader strains, was a significant contributor to the variability in the bacterial compositions and yields observed across communities. Our study suggests that initial stochasticity in assembly states at the microscale, amplified through biotic interactions, may have significant consequences for the diversity and functionality of microbial communities at larger scales.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The biogeochemical consequences of the degradation of particulate organic matter by microorganisms represent the cumulative effect of microbial activity on individual microscale resource patches. The ecological processes controlling community dynamics in these highly localized microenvironments remain poorly understood. Here, we find that complex marine communities growing on microscale resource particles diverge both taxonomically and functionally despite assembling under identical abiotic conditions from a common species pool. We show that this variability stems from bacteriophage predation and history-dependent factors in community assembly, which create stochastic dynamics that are spatially structured at the microscale. This microscale stochasticity may have significant consequences for the coexistence, evolution, and function of diverse bacterial and viral populations in the global ocean.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461956" rel="alternate" title="Ecological stochasticity and phage induction diversify bacterioplankton communities at the microscale (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461737</id><title>Genetic interplay between type II topoisomerase enzymes and chromosomal ccdAB toxin-antitoxin in E. coli (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.309247+00:00</updated><author><name>Jay W. Kim</name></author><author><name>Vincent Blay</name></author><author><name>Portia Mira</name></author><author><name>Miriam Barlow</name></author><author><name>Manel Camps</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fluoroquinolones are one of the most widely used class of antibiotics. They target two type II topoisomerase enzymes: gyrase and topoisomerase IV. Resistance to these drugs, which is largely caused by mutations in their target enzymes, is on the rise and becoming a serious public health risk. In this work, we analyze the sequences of 352 extraintestinal &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; clinical isolates to gain insights into the selective pressures shaping the type II topoisomerase mutation landscape in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;. We identify both Quinolone Resistance-Determining Region (QRDR) and non-QRDR mutations, outline their mutation trajectories, and show that they are likely driven by different selective pressures. We confirm that ciprofloxacin resistance is specifically and strongly associated with QRDR mutations. By contrast, non-QRDR mutations are associated with the presence of the chromosomal version of &lt;italic&gt;ccdAB&lt;/italic&gt;, a toxin-antitoxin operon, where the toxin CcdB is known to target gyrase. We also find that &lt;italic&gt;ccdAB&lt;/italic&gt; and the evolution of QRDR mutation trajectories are partially incompatible. Finally, we identify partial deletions in CcdB and additional mutations that likely facilitate the compatibility between the presence of the &lt;italic&gt;ccdAB&lt;/italic&gt; operon and QRDR mutations. These “permissive” mutations are all found in ParC (a topoisomerase IV subunit). This, and the fact that CcdB-selected mutations frequently map to topoisomerase IV, strongly suggests that this enzyme (in addition to gyrase) is likely a target for the toxin CcdB in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;, although an indirect effect on global supercoiling cannot be excluded. This work opens the door for the use of the presence of &lt;italic&gt;ccdB&lt;/italic&gt; and of the proposed permissive mutations in the genome as genetic markers to assess the risk of quinolone resistance evolution and implies that certain strains may be genetically more refractory to evolving quinolone resistance through mutations in target enzymes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461737" rel="alternate" title="Genetic interplay between type II topoisomerase enzymes and chromosomal ccdAB toxin-antitoxin in E. coli (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461763</id><title>Rapid in vivo development of resistance to daptomycin in vancomycin-resistant Enterococcus faecium due to genomic rearrangements (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.312111+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah Mollerup</name></author><author><name>Christine Elmeskov</name></author><author><name>Heidi Gumpert</name></author><author><name>Mette Pinholt</name></author><author><name>Tobias Steen Sejersen</name></author><author><name>Martin Schou Pedersen</name></author><author><name>Peder Worning</name></author><author><name>Dorte Frees</name></author><author><name>Henrik Westh</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Daptomycin is a cyclic lipopeptide used in the treatment of vancomycin-resistant &lt;italic&gt;Enterococcus faecium&lt;/italic&gt; (VREfm). However, the development of daptomycin-resistant VREfm challenges the treatment of nosocomial VREfm infections. Resistance mechanisms of daptomycin are not fully understood. Here we analysed the genomic changes leading to a daptomycin-susceptible VREfm isolate becoming resistant after 40 days of daptomycin and linezolid combination therapy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two isogenic VREfm isolates (daptomycin-susceptible and daptomycin-resistant) were analysed using whole genome sequencing with Illumina and Nanopore.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whole genome comparative analysis identified the loss of a 46.5 kb fragment and duplication of a 29.7 kb fragment in the daptomycin-resistant isolate, with many implicated genes involved in cell wall synthesis. Two plasmids of the daptomycin-susceptible isolate were also found integrated in the chromosome of the resistant isolate. One nonsynonymous SNP in the &lt;italic&gt;rpoC&lt;/italic&gt; gene was identified in the daptomycin-resistant isolate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Daptomycin resistance developed through chromosomal rearrangements leading to altered cell wall structure. Such novel types of resistance mechanisms can only be identified by comparing closed genomes of isogenic isolates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461763" rel="alternate" title="Rapid in vivo development of resistance to daptomycin in vancomycin-resistant Enterococcus faecium due to genomic rearrangements (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461421</id><title>Firmicutes and Bacteroidetes explain mass gain variation in an obligate hibernator (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.315333+00:00</updated><author><name>Gina C. Johnson</name></author><author><name>Samuel Degregori</name></author><author><name>Paul H. Barber</name></author><author><name>Daniel T. Blumstein</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Body condition is an important life history challenge that directly impacts individual fitness and is particularly important for hibernating animals, whose maintenance of adequate body fat and mass is essential for survival.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is well documented that symbiotic microorganisms play a vital role in animal physiology and behaviour. Recent work demonstrates that gut microbes are associated with fat accumulation and obesity; &lt;italic&gt;Firmicutes&lt;/italic&gt; is consistently associated with obesity while &lt;italic&gt;Bacteroidetes&lt;/italic&gt; is associated with leanness both in humans and other animals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The focus of most microbiome studies has been on human health or involved lab reared animals used as a model system. However, these microbes likely are important for individual fitness in wild populations and provide potential mechanistic insights into the adaptability and survival of wildlife.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we test whether symbiotic microorganisms within the phyla of &lt;italic&gt;Firmicutes&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Bacteroidetes&lt;/italic&gt; are associated with summer mass gain in an exceptionally well-studied wild population of yellow-bellied marmots (&lt;italic&gt;Marmota flaviventer&lt;/italic&gt;) by quantifying microbial abundance over five years of fecal samples (2015 – 2019) collected during their summer active season.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Results show that marmots with higher mass gain rates have a greater abundance of &lt;italic&gt;Firmicutes&lt;/italic&gt;. In contrast, higher abundance of &lt;italic&gt;Bacteroidetes&lt;/italic&gt; was associated with lower mass gain rates, but only for marmots living in harsher environments. Similar patterns were found at the family level where &lt;italic&gt;Ruminococcaceae&lt;/italic&gt;, a member of &lt;italic&gt;Firmicutes&lt;/italic&gt;, was associated with higher mass gain rates, and &lt;italic&gt;Muribaculaceae&lt;/italic&gt;, a member of &lt;italic&gt;Bacteroidetes&lt;/italic&gt;, was associated with lower mass gain rates, and similarly in harsher environments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although correlative, these results highlight the importance of symbiotic gut microbiota to mass gain in the wild, a trait associated with survival and fitness in many taxonomic groups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461421" rel="alternate" title="Firmicutes and Bacteroidetes explain mass gain variation in an obligate hibernator (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461610</id><title>Alkaliphilus flagellata sp. nov., Butyricicoccus intestinisimiae sp. nov., Clostridium mobile sp. nov., Clostridium simiarum sp. nov., Dysosmobacter acutus sp. nov., Paenibacillus brevis sp. nov., Peptoniphilus ovalis sp. nov., and Tissierella simiarum sp. nov., isolated from monkey feces (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.315825+00:00</updated><author><name>Dan-Hua Li</name></author><author><name>Rexiding Abuduaini</name></author><author><name>Meng-Xuan Du</name></author><author><name>Yu-Jing Wang</name></author><author><name>Hong-He Chen</name></author><author><name>Nan Zhou</name></author><author><name>Hai-Zhen Zhu</name></author><author><name>Yong Lu</name></author><author><name>Pei-Jun Yu</name></author><author><name>Shu-Peng Yang</name></author><author><name>Cheng-Ying Jiang</name></author><author><name>Qiang Sun</name></author><author><name>Chang Liu</name></author><author><name>Shuang-Jiang Liu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Non-human primates harbor diverse microbiomes in their guts. As a part of China Microbiome Initiatives, we cultivated and characterized the gut microbiome of cynomolgus monkeys (&lt;italic&gt;Macaca fascicularis&lt;/italic&gt;). In this report, we communicate the characterization and taxonomy of 8 bacterial strains that were obtained from fecal samples of captive cynomolgus monkeys. The results revealed that they represented 8 novel bacterial species. The proposed names of the 8 novel species are &lt;italic&gt;Alkaliphilus flagellate&lt;/italic&gt; (type strain MSJ-5&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; =CGMCC 1.45007&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt;=KCTC 15974&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt;), &lt;italic&gt;Butyricicoccus intestinisimiae&lt;/italic&gt; MSJd-7&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; (type strain MSJd-7&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; =CGMCC 1.45013&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; =KCTC 25112&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt;), &lt;italic&gt;Clostridium mobile&lt;/italic&gt; (type strain MSJ-11&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; =CGMCC 1.45009&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt;=KCTC 25065&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt;), &lt;italic&gt;Clostridium simiarum&lt;/italic&gt; (type strain MSJ-4&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; =CGMCC 1.45006&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; =KCTC 15975&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt;), &lt;italic&gt;Dysosmobacter acutus&lt;/italic&gt; (type strain MSJ-2&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; =CGMCC 1.32896&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt;=KCTC 15976&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt;), &lt;italic&gt;Paenibacillus brevis&lt;/italic&gt; MSJ-6&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; (type strain MSJ-6&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; =CGMCC 1.45008&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt;=KCTC 15973&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt;), &lt;italic&gt;Peptoniphilus ovalis&lt;/italic&gt; (type strain MSJ-1&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; =CGMCC 1.31770&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt;=KCTC 15977&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt;), and &lt;italic&gt;Tissierella simiarum&lt;/italic&gt; (type strain MSJ-40&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; =CGMCC 1.45012&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt;=KCTC 25071&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461610" rel="alternate" title="Alkaliphilus flagellata sp. nov., Butyricicoccus intestinisimiae sp. nov., Clostridium mobile sp. nov., Clostridium simiarum sp. nov., Dysosmobacter acutus sp. nov., Paenibacillus brevis sp. nov., Peptoniphilus ovalis sp. nov., and Tissierella simiarum sp. nov., isolated from monkey feces (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462200</id><title>Flagellum and toxin phase variation impacts intestinal colonization and disease development in a mouse model of Clostridioides difficile infection (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.327609+00:00</updated><author><name>Dominika Trzilova</name></author><author><name>Mercedes A. H. Warren</name></author><author><name>Nicole C. Gadda</name></author><author><name>Caitlin L. Williams</name></author><author><name>Rita Tamayo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Clostridioides difficile&lt;/italic&gt; is a major nosocomial pathogen that can cause severe, toxin-mediated diarrhea and pseudomembranous colitis. Recent work has shown that &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; exhibits heterogeneity in swimming motility and toxin production &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; through phase variation by site-specific DNA recombination. The recombinase RecV reversibly inverts the flagellar switch sequence upstream of the &lt;italic&gt;flgB&lt;/italic&gt; operon, leading to the ON/OFF expression of flagellum and toxin genes. How this phenomenon impacts &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; virulence &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; remains unknown. We identified mutations in the right inverted repeat that reduced or prevented flagellar switch inversion by RecV. We introduced these mutations into &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; R20291 to create strains with the flagellar switch “locked” in either the ON or OFF orientation. These mutants exhibited a loss of flagellum and toxin phase variation during growth &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, yielding precisely modified mutants suitable for assessing virulence &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. In a hamster model of acute &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; infection, the phase-locked ON mutant caused greater toxin accumulation than the phase locked OFF mutant but did not differ significantly in the ability to cause acute disease symptoms. In contrast, in a mouse model, preventing flagellum and toxin phase variation affected the ability of &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; to colonize the intestinal tract and to elicit weight loss, which is attributable to differences in toxin production during infection. These results show that the ability of &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; to phase vary flagella and toxins influences colonization and disease development and suggest that the phenotypic variants generated by flagellar switch inversion have distinct capacities for causing disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462200" rel="alternate" title="Flagellum and toxin phase variation impacts intestinal colonization and disease development in a mouse model of Clostridioides difficile infection (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461897</id><title>Engaging the ‘A’ Class Antibody: Variable-Heavy (VH) region influencing IgA1&amp;2 engagement of FcαRI and superantigen proteins G, A, and L (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.328014+00:00</updated><author><name>Wei-Li Ling</name></author><author><name>Chinh Tran-To Su</name></author><author><name>Wai-Heng Lua</name></author><author><name>Joshua Yi Yeo</name></author><author><name>Jun-Jie Poh</name></author><author><name>Yuen-Ling Ng</name></author><author><name>Anil Wipat</name></author><author><name>Samuel Ken-En Gan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Interest in IgA as an alternative therapeutic and diagnostic antibody has increased over the years, yet much remains to be investigated especially given their importance in activating immune cells in blood and in mucosal immunity. Recent whole antibody-based investigations have shown significant distal effects between the variable (V) and constant (C)-regions that can be mitigated by the different hinge regions of the human IgA subtypes A1 and A2. Diving deeper into the mechanisms underlying this, systematic VH manipulations retaining the CDRs were performed on a panel of 28 IgA1s and A2s across the Trastuzumab and Pertuzumab models, revealed distal effects on FcαRI binding. Further insights from structural modelling showed these effects to also be mitigated by the differing glycosylation patterns in IgA1 and 2 to explain reversal of trends of IgA1s and 2s effected by slight changes in the CDRs. IgAs bound at the Fc showed similar trends but magnitudes better binding to Her2 with that bound by ppL, showing that ppL can sterically hinder Her2 antigen binding. Contrary to canonical knowledge, we found strong evidence of IgAs binding SpG that was narrowed to be at the CH2-3 region, and that the likely binding with SpA was beyond VH3 FWR and most likely at the CH1. VH1 was found to be the most suitable framework (FWRs) for CDR-grafting for both IgA1 and 2. With relevance to interactions with the microbiome at mucosal surfaces, mechanistic insight of how these IgAs can interact bacterial superantigens proteins G, A, and L are also discovered for potential future interventions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;An insight into the mechanism of distal V-region effects on FCAR and superantigens proteins G, A, and L by both IgA1 and A2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461897" rel="alternate" title="Engaging the ‘A’ Class Antibody: Variable-Heavy (VH) region influencing IgA1&amp;2 engagement of FcαRI and superantigen proteins G, A, and L (5 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462076</id><title>PD-1 checkpoint blockade activates germinal center follicular T cell programs that disrupt type 2 isotype-specific antibody homeostasis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.328492+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew G. Shuparski</name></author><author><name>Brett W. Higgins</name></author><author><name>Karen B. Miller</name></author><author><name>Louise J. McHeyzer-Williams</name></author><author><name>Michael G. McHeyzer-Williams</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Multiple CD4 T cell dependent tolerance mechanisms control adaptive B cell immunity to environmental antigens. We recently demonstrated a PD-1 checkpoint within steady-state splenic germinal centers (GC) that constrains the maturation of type 2 IgG1 isotype-specific antibody homeostasis. Here, we utilized single cell-indexed custom RNA-sequencing to probe the follicular T cell mechanisms directly targeted by acute PD-1 blockade. We find a pre-existing subset of follicular helper T (T&lt;sub&gt;FH&lt;/sub&gt;) cells that express type 2 immune response properties (T&lt;sub&gt;FH&lt;/sub&gt;2) with exaggerated pathways of TCR activation, cytokine signaling, and enhanced cell-cell contact upon acute PD-1 blockade. This selective amplification of the T&lt;sub&gt;FH&lt;/sub&gt;2 program significantly increases predicted molecular connections to type 2 IgG1 GC B cells that dominate limited changes in GC localized follicular regulatory T (GC T&lt;sub&gt;FR&lt;/sub&gt;) cell programs. These studies demonstrate how type 2 isotype-specific adaptive B cell tolerance is selectively disrupted by acute PD-1 blockade to reveal the modular regulatory mechanisms that control splenic GC dynamics at homeostasis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Acute PD-1 blockade alters the regulatory dynamic of the steady state germinal center to drive the maturation of IgG1 GC B cells towards PC differentiation in a process mediated by type 2 like TFH effector molecules.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;HIGHLIGHTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="simple"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;-&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Acute PD-1 blockade enhances the steady state splenic TFH program&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;-&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;PD-1 blockade selectively exaggerates a Type 2 like TFH module&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;-&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;GC TFR cells are minimally impacted by blockade&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;-&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;PD-1 restrains predicted TFH2 functional contacts with IgG1 GC B Cells&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462076" rel="alternate" title="PD-1 checkpoint blockade activates germinal center follicular T cell programs that disrupt type 2 isotype-specific antibody homeostasis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461991</id><title>Visualization of bacterial type 3 secretion system components down to the molecular level by MINFLUX nanoscopy (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.328903+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Carsten</name></author><author><name>Maren Rudolph</name></author><author><name>Tobias Weihs</name></author><author><name>Roman Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Christian A. Wurm</name></author><author><name>Andreas Diepold</name></author><author><name>Antonio Virgilio Failla</name></author><author><name>Manuel Wolters</name></author><author><name>Martin Aepfelbacher</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Type 3 secretion systems (T3SS) are essential virulence factors of numerous bacterial pathogens and inject effector proteins into host cells. The needle-like T3SS machinery consists of more than 20 components, has a length of around 100 nm and a diameter of up to 30 nm according to EM studies. Its intrabacterial components are highly dynamic and in permanent exchange with other bacterial structures. Therefore, a temporally and spatially resolved visualization of the T3SS using fluorescence microscopy techniques has been challenging. In the present study, novel labeling strategies were combined with super-resolution microscopy such as STED, STORM and MINFLUX. MINFLUX nanoscopy allowed to visualize components of the T3SS machinery such as the dynamic sorting platform component YscL and the extrabacterial pore protein YopD at unprecedented resolutions. The presented results represent the basis for an in depth investigation of T3SS structure and function and therefore gain new insights into the infection process of human pathogens in order to develop novel treatment and prevention strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461991" rel="alternate" title="Visualization of bacterial type 3 secretion system components down to the molecular level by MINFLUX nanoscopy (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461584</id><title>Phostensin Enables Lymphocyte Integrin Activation and Population of Peripheral Lymphoid Organs (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.329734+00:00</updated><author><name>Ho-Sup Lee</name></author><author><name>Hao Sun</name></author><author><name>Frédéric Lagarrigue</name></author><author><name>Jay W. Fox</name></author><author><name>Nicholas E. Sherman</name></author><author><name>Alexandre R. Gingras</name></author><author><name>Mark H. Ginsberg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Rap1 GTPase drives assembly of the Mig-10/RIAM/lamellipodin–Integrin–Talin (MIT) complex that enables integrin-dependent lymphocyte functions. Here we used tandem affinity tag-based proteomics to isolate and analyze the MIT complex and reveal that Phostensin (PTSN), a regulatory subunit of protein phosphatase 1, is a component of the complex. PTSN mediates de-phosphorylation of Rap1 thereby preserving the activity and membrane localization of Rap1 to stabilize the MIT complex. CRISPR/Cas9-induced deletion of &lt;italic&gt;PPP1R18,&lt;/italic&gt; which encodes PTSN, markedly suppresses integrin activation in Jurkat human T cells. We generated apparently healthy &lt;italic&gt;Ppp1r18&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice that manifest lymphocytosis and reduced population of peripheral lymphoid tissues ascribable to defective activation of integrins α&lt;sub&gt;L&lt;/sub&gt;β&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and α&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;β&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;. &lt;italic&gt;Ppp1r18&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; T cells exhibit reduced capacity to induce colitis in a murine adoptive transfer model. Thus, PTSN enables lymphocyte integrin-mediated functions by dephosphorylating Rap1 to stabilize the MIT complex. As a consequence, loss of PTSN ameliorates T cell-mediated colitis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Phostensin, a protein phosphatase 1 regulatory subunit, supports lymphocyte integrin-dependent functions by mediating dephosphorylation of Rap1 to stabilize the MIT complex thereby enabling the population of peripheral lymphoid organs and T cell-mediated colitis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461584" rel="alternate" title="Phostensin Enables Lymphocyte Integrin Activation and Population of Peripheral Lymphoid Organs (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461453</id><title>LON DELETION IMPAIRS PERSISTER CELL RESUSCITATION IN ESCHERICHIA COLI (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.330400+00:00</updated><author><name>Sayed Golam Mohiuddin</name></author><author><name>Aslan Massahi</name></author><author><name>Mehmet A. Orman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial persisters are non-growing cells that are highly tolerant to bactericidal antibiotics. However, this tolerance is reversible and not mediated by heritable genetic changes. Lon, an ATP-dependent protease, has repeatedly been shown to play a critical role in fluoroquinolone persistence. Although &lt;italic&gt;lon&lt;/italic&gt; deletion (Δ&lt;italic&gt;lon&lt;/italic&gt;) is thought to kill persister cells &lt;italic&gt;via&lt;/italic&gt; accumulation of the cell division inhibitor protein SulA, the exact mechanism underlying this phenomenon has yet to be elucidated. Here, we show that Lon is an important regulatory protein for the resuscitation of the fluoroquinolone persisters in &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;lon&lt;/italic&gt; deletion impairs the ability of persister cells to form colonies during recovery, without killing these cells, through a &lt;italic&gt;sulA-&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;ftsZ&lt;/italic&gt;-dependent mechanism. Notably, this observed non-culturable state of antibiotic-tolerant Δ&lt;italic&gt;lon&lt;/italic&gt; cells is transient, as environmental conditions, such as starvation, can restore their culturability. Our data further indicate that starvation-induced SulA degradation or expression of Lon during recovery facilitates Z-ring formation in Δ&lt;italic&gt;lon&lt;/italic&gt; persisters. Calculating the ratio of the cell length (L in µm) to the number of Z-rings (Z) for each ofloxacin-treated intact cell analyzed has revealed a strong correlation between persister resuscitation and calculated L/Z values, which represents a potential biomarker for Δ&lt;italic&gt;lon&lt;/italic&gt; persisters that are transitioning to the normal cell state under the conditions studied here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461453" rel="alternate" title="LON DELETION IMPAIRS PERSISTER CELL RESUSCITATION IN ESCHERICHIA COLI (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461484</id><title>Immune checkpoint expression on HIV-specific CD4+ T cells and response to their blockade are dependent on lineage and function (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.330711+00:00</updated><author><name>Elsa Brunet-Ratnasingham</name></author><author><name>Antigoni Morou</name></author><author><name>Mathieu Dubé</name></author><author><name>Julia Niessl</name></author><author><name>Amy E. Baxter</name></author><author><name>Olivier Tastet</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Brassard</name></author><author><name>Gloria Ortega-Delgado</name></author><author><name>Roxanne Charlebois</name></author><author><name>Gordon J. Freeman</name></author><author><name>Cécile Tremblay</name></author><author><name>Jean-Pierre Routy</name></author><author><name>Daniel E. Kaufmann</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Antigen-specific T cell impairment is observed in chronic infections. CD4+ T cells are diverse in phenotype and function; how their different lineages are impacted by inhibitory immune checkpoints (IC) is unknown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We examined IC expression and function in HIV-specific CD4+ T cells of viremic individuals prior to ART initiation and persons with spontaneous or therapy-induced viral suppression. We investigated IC patterns associated with exhaustion-related transcription factors and chemokine receptors using cytokine-independent activation-induced marker assays. We determined effector functions representative of T&lt;sub&gt;FH&lt;/sub&gt;, T&lt;sub&gt;H&lt;/sub&gt;1 and T&lt;sub&gt;H&lt;/sub&gt;17/T&lt;sub&gt;H&lt;/sub&gt;22 using ultra-sensitive RNA flow cytometric fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH), and their response to IC blockade.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The dysfunction-related transcription factor TOX was elevated in HIV-specific CD4+ T cells of viremic patients, and its expression was associated with lineage differentiation. We observed a hierarchy of PD-1, TIGIT and CD200 expression associated with both infection status and effector profile. &lt;italic&gt;In vitro&lt;/italic&gt; responsiveness to PD-L1 blockade varied with defined CD4+ T cell functions rather than IC expression levels: frequencies of cells with T&lt;sub&gt;H&lt;/sub&gt;1- and T&lt;sub&gt;H&lt;/sub&gt;17/T&lt;sub&gt;H&lt;/sub&gt;22-, but not T&lt;sub&gt;FH&lt;/sub&gt;-related functions, increased. Response to PD-L1 blockade was strongest in viremic participants and reduced after ART initiation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our data highlight a polarization-specific regulation of IC expression and differing sensitivities of antigen-specific Thelper subsets to PD-1-mediated inhibition. This heterogeneity may direct ICB efficacy on CD4+ T cells in HIV infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This work was supported by the National Institutes of Health, the Canadian Institutes for Health Research, the Canada Foundation for Innovation and the Fonds de Recherche du Québec-Santé.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Research in Context&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Evidence before this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Combination antiretroviral therapy (ART) is highly effective in controlling HIV but requires life-long medication due to the latent viral reservoir, and does not restore suppressive immune responses. In particular, there is no generation of effective HIV-specific T cell responses, which are thought to play an important role in controlling HIV in the rare individuals who can spontaneously control the virus. Inhibitory immune checkpoints (IC) such as PD-1 contribute to T cell dysfunction and failure to control viral infections, including HIV, and IC blockade (ICB) represents a potential adjuvant to ART through restoration of T cell functions. While most studies have focused on CD8+ T cells, increasing evidence shows that the remarkable impact of ICB therapy in a subset of cancer patients is enhanced by functional CD4+ T cell help, which can be directly affected by ICB. While effective virus-specific CD4+ T cell responses are also thought to be important for immune control of HIV, these cells are highly heterogenous. How IC expression and function differs across CD4+ T cell lineages and the consequences of this diversity for IC blockade (ICB) strategies are still poorly understood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Added value of this study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To compare various stages of immune dysfunction, we examined people living with HIV (PLWH) with different levels of viral control pre-ART (including elite controllers who spontaneously control virus) and followed a cohort longitudinally post-ART. We used a panel of assays to characterize HIV-specific CD4+ T cell subsets, including activation-induced marker (AIM) assays and flow cytometric detection of mRNAs coding for a wider variety of HIV-specific CD4+ T cell functions than what is detected by standard procedures. Our experiments indicate a hierarchy of IC (PD-1, TIGIT, CD200) expression on blood HIV-specific CD4+ T cells that depends not only on the person’s infection status but also on expression of lineage differentiation markers and effector functions representative of CD4+ T cell subsets critical for antiviral responses (T&lt;sub&gt;FH&lt;/sub&gt;, T&lt;sub&gt;H&lt;/sub&gt;1 and T&lt;sub&gt;H&lt;/sub&gt;17/T&lt;sub&gt;H&lt;/sub&gt;22 cells). This hierarchy was also present in the putatively functional cells of elite controllers. We characterized the expression of the dysfunction-related transcription factor TOX, and saw that its association with the key IC PD-1 in the setting of viremia varied across CD4+ T cell polarizations. Response to blockade of the PD-1 pathway resulted in increased antiviral and mucosal-protective functions, but did not affect T&lt;sub&gt;FH&lt;/sub&gt;-related functions. Response to ICB was most prominent in viremic patients, and subdued but not fully abrogated in the setting of viral suppression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Implications of all available evidence&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;These results highlight a previously unrecognized impact of ICB on mucosal immunity-related CD4+ functions, which are known to be depleted upon HIV infection and not restored by ART, and strong links between IC expression patterns and HIV-specific CD4+ T cell differentiation. The impact of ICB on CD4+ T cells in HIV infection has primarily been studied in the context of viral reservoir reactivation, which are preferentially harbored in IC+ cells. Our work emphasizes the importance of considering the differentiation profile of the virus-specific CD4+ T cells in studies of ICB blockade, as it may direct ICB efficacy in HIV infection. This data may also have implications for CD4+ T cell help in other infectious and non-infectious chronic human diseases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461484" rel="alternate" title="Immune checkpoint expression on HIV-specific CD4+ T cells and response to their blockade are dependent on lineage and function (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.459512</id><title>HIV-specific CD8 T cells from elite controllers have an epigenetic imprint that preserves effector functions (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.331062+00:00</updated><author><name>Adolfo B. Frias</name></author><author><name>Rachel L. Rutishauser</name></author><author><name>Ashish A. Sharma</name></author><author><name>Tian Mi</name></author><author><name>Hossam Abdelsamed</name></author><author><name>Caitlin Zebley</name></author><author><name>Christian M. Constantz</name></author><author><name>Mars Stone</name></author><author><name>Michael P. Busch</name></author><author><name>Steven G. Deeks</name></author><author><name>Rafick-Pierre Sékaly</name></author><author><name>Ben Youngblood</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Several lines of evidence support a central role for CD8 T cells as key determinants in the control of HIV, particularly in rare “elite controllers” who control the virus to undetectable levels in the blood in the absence of antiretroviral therapy (ART). While HIV-specific CD8 T cells isolated from elite controllers have enhanced antiviral cytokine production and proliferative capacity in response to antigen stimulation when compared to cells isolated from viremic or even aviremic ART-suppressed non-controllers, the cell-intrinsic mechanisms underlying the enhanced T cell memory-like function of HIV-specific CD8 T cells in elite controllers remain largely undefined. To identify the transcriptional and epigenetic pathways that regulate functional capacity in HIV-specific CD8 T cells in elite controllers, we performed genome-wide transcriptional and DNA methylation analysis of MHC Class I multimer+ CD8 T cells sorted from aviremic elite controllers compared to aviremic non-controllers on suppressive ART. Co-omics analysis revealed enrichment for gene signatures that support a multipotent differentiation state, cell survival, and a long-lived effector cell fate in HIV-specific CD8 T cells from elite controllers. Specifically, we observed DNA methylation programs at the transcription factor binding sites of the stem-associated factors TCF-1 and LEF1 that delineate HIV-specific CD8 T cells from elite controllers versus ART-treated individuals. HIV-specific CD8 T cells in elite controllers also maintain T cell receptor and IL-12/STAT4 pathway signaling and have suppressed pro-apoptotic TNFα pathway signaling. These findings show that HIV-specific CD8 T cells from elite controllers have enhanced expression and DNA methylation programs that maintain developmental potential and in turn promote long-term survival, proliferative potential, and effector capacity. These data also provide new insights into the relationship between stem-associated transcription factors and stable epigenetic restriction of T cell developmental capacity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.459512" rel="alternate" title="HIV-specific CD8 T cells from elite controllers have an epigenetic imprint that preserves effector functions (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462325</id><title>An international report on bacterial communities in esophageal squamous cell carcinoma (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.331499+00:00</updated><author><name>Jason Nomburg</name></author><author><name>Susan Bullman</name></author><author><name>Dariush Nasrollahzadeh</name></author><author><name>Eric A. Collisson</name></author><author><name>Behnoush Abedi-Ardekani</name></author><author><name>Larry O. Akoko</name></author><author><name>Joshua R. Atkins</name></author><author><name>Geoffrey C. Buckle</name></author><author><name>Satish Gopal</name></author><author><name>Nan Hu</name></author><author><name>Bongani Kaimila</name></author><author><name>Masoud Khoshnia</name></author><author><name>Reza Malekzadeh</name></author><author><name>Diana Menya</name></author><author><name>Blandina T. Mmbaga</name></author><author><name>Sarah Moody</name></author><author><name>Gift Mulima</name></author><author><name>Beatrice P. Mushi</name></author><author><name>Julius Mwaiselage</name></author><author><name>Ally Mwanga</name></author><author><name>Yulia Newton</name></author><author><name>Dianna L. Ng</name></author><author><name>Amie Radenbaugh</name></author><author><name>Deogratias S. Rwakatema</name></author><author><name>Msiba Selekwa</name></author><author><name>Joachim Schüz</name></author><author><name>Philip R. Taylor</name></author><author><name>Charles Vaske</name></author><author><name>Alisa Goldstein</name></author><author><name>Michael R. Stratton</name></author><author><name>Valerie McCormack</name></author><author><name>Paul Brennan</name></author><author><name>James A. DeCaprio</name></author><author><name>Matthew Meyerson</name></author><author><name>Elia J. Mmbaga</name></author><author><name>Katherine Van Loon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The incidence of esophageal squamous cell carcinoma (ESCC) is disproportionately high in the eastern corridor of Africa and parts of Asia. Emerging research has identified a potential association between poor oral health and ESCC. One proposed biological pathway linking poor oral health and ESCC involves the alteration of the microbiome. Thus, we performed an integrated analysis of four independent sequencing efforts of ESCC tumors from patients from high- and low-incidence regions of the world. Using whole genome sequencing (WGS) and RNA sequencing (RNAseq) of ESCC tumors and WGS of synchronous collections of saliva specimens from 61 patients in Tanzania, we identified a community of bacteria, including members of the genera &lt;italic&gt;Fusobacterium, Selenomonas, Prevotella, Streptococcus, Porphyromonas, Veillonella&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;Campylobacter&lt;/italic&gt;, present at high abundance in ESCC tumors. We then characterized the microbiome of 238 ESCC tumor specimens collected in two additional independent sequencing efforts consisting of patients from other high-ESCC incidence regions (Tanzania, Malawi, Kenya, Iran, China). This analysis revealed a similar tumor enrichment of the ESCC-associated bacterial community in these cancers. Because these genera are traditionally considered members of the oral microbiota, we explored if there is a relationship between the synchronous saliva and tumor microbiomes of ESCC patients in Tanzania. Comparative analyses revealed that paired saliva and tumor microbiomes are significantly similar with a specific enrichment of &lt;italic&gt;Fusobacterium&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Prevotella&lt;/italic&gt; in the tumor microbiome. Together, these data indicate that cancer-associated oral bacteria are associated with ESCC tumors at the time of diagnosis and support a model in which oral bacteria are present in high abundance in both saliva and tumors of ESCC patients. Longitudinal studies of the pre-diagnostic oral microbiome are needed to investigate whether these cross-sectional similarities reflect temporal associations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462325" rel="alternate" title="An international report on bacterial communities in esophageal squamous cell carcinoma (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462331</id><title>The kinesin KIF4 mediates HBV/HDV entry through regulation of surface NTCP localization and can be targeted by RXR agonists in vitro (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.332093+00:00</updated><author><name>Sameh A. Gad</name></author><author><name>Masaya Sugiyama</name></author><author><name>Masataka Tsuge</name></author><author><name>Kosho Wakae</name></author><author><name>Kento Fukano</name></author><author><name>Mizuki Oshima</name></author><author><name>Camille Sureau</name></author><author><name>Noriyuki Watanabe</name></author><author><name>Takanobu Kato</name></author><author><name>Asako Murayama</name></author><author><name>Yingfang Li</name></author><author><name>Ikuo Shoji</name></author><author><name>Kunitada Shimotohno</name></author><author><name>Kazuaki Chayama</name></author><author><name>Masamichi Muramatsu</name></author><author><name>Takaji Wakita</name></author><author><name>Tomoyoshi Nozaki</name></author><author><name>Hussein H. Aly</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Intracellular transport via microtubule-based dynein and kinesin family motors plays a key role in viral reproduction and transmission. We show here that Kinesin Family Member 4 (KIF4) plays an important role in HBV/HDV infection. We intended to explore host factors impacting the HBV life cycle that can be therapeutically addressed using siRNA library transfection and HBV/NLuc (HBV/NL) reporter virus infection in HepG2-hNTCP C4 cells. KIF4 silencing resulted in a 3-fold reduction in luciferase activity following HBV/NL infection and suppressed both wild-type HBV and HDV infection. Transient KIF4 depletion reduced surface and raised intracellular NTCP (HBV/HDV entry receptor) levels, according to both cellular fractionation and immunofluorescence analysis (IF). Overexpression of wild-type KIF4 but not ATPase-null KIF4 regains the surface localization of NTCP in these cells. Furthermore, immunofluorescence (IF) revealed KIF4 and NTCP colocalization across microtubule filaments, and a co-immunoprecipitation study showed that KIF4 physically binds to NTCP. KIF4 expression is regulated by FOXM1. Interestingly, we discovered that RXR agonists (Bexarotene, and Alitretinoin) down-regulated KIF4 expression via FOXM1-mediated suppression, resulting in a substantial decrease in HBV-Pre-S1 protein attachment to HepG2-hNTCP cell surface and subsequent suppression of HBV infection in HepG2-hNTCP and primary human hepatocytes (PXB) (Bexarotene, IC&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; 1.89 ± 0.98 μM). Overall, our findings show that human KIF4 is a critical regulator of NTCP surface transport and localization, which is required for NTCP to function as a receptor for HBV/HDV entry. Furthermore, small molecules that suppress or alleviate KIF4 expression would be potential antiviral candidates that target HBV and HDV entry phases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Understanding HBV/HDV entry machinery and the mechanism by which NTCP (HBV/HDV entry receptor) surface expression is regulated is crucial to develop antiviral entry inhibitors. We found that NTCP surface transport is mainly controlled by the motor kinesin KIF4. Surprisingly, KIF4 was negatively regulated by RXR receptors through FOXM1-mediated suppression&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study not only mechanistically correlated the role of RXR receptors in regulating HBV/HDV entry but also suggested a novel approach to develop therapeutic rexinoids for preventing HBV and/or HDV infections in important clinical situations, such as in patients undergoing liver transplantation or those who are at a high risk of HBV infection and unresponsive to HBV vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462331" rel="alternate" title="The kinesin KIF4 mediates HBV/HDV entry through regulation of surface NTCP localization and can be targeted by RXR agonists in vitro (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.460084</id><title>A new oomycete metabarcoding method using the rps10 gene (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.332439+00:00</updated><author><name>Zachary S. L. Foster</name></author><author><name>Felipe E. Albornoz</name></author><author><name>Valerie J. Fieland</name></author><author><name>Meredith M. Larsen</name></author><author><name>F. Andrew Jones</name></author><author><name>Brett M. Tyler</name></author><author><name>Hai D. T. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Treena I. Burgess</name></author><author><name>Carolyn Riddell</name></author><author><name>Hermann Voglmayr</name></author><author><name>Frank N. Martin</name></author><author><name>Niklaus J. Grünwald</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Oomycetes are a group of eukaryotes related to brown algae and diatoms, many of which cause diseases in plants and animals. Improved methods are needed for rapid and accurate characterization of oomycete communities using DNA metabarcoding. We have identified the mitochondrial 40S ribosomal protein S10 gene (&lt;italic&gt;rps10&lt;/italic&gt;) as a locus useful for oomycete metabarcoding and provide primers predicted to amplify all oomycetes based on available reference sequences from a wide range of taxa. We evaluated its utility relative to a popular barcode, the internal transcribed spacer 1 (ITS1), by sequencing environmental samples and a mock community using Illumina MiSeq. Amplified sequence variants (ASVs) and operational taxonomic units (OTUs) were identified per community. Both the sequence and predicted taxonomy of ASVs and OTUs were compared to the known composition of the mock community. Both &lt;italic&gt;rps10&lt;/italic&gt; and ITS yielded ASVs with sequences matching 21 of the 24 species in the mock community and matching all 24 when allowing for a 1 bp difference. Taxonomic classifications of ASVs included 23 members of the mock community for &lt;italic&gt;rps10&lt;/italic&gt; and 17 for ITS1. Sequencing results for the environmental samples suggest the proposed &lt;italic&gt;rps10&lt;/italic&gt; locus results in substantially less amplification of non-target organisms than the ITS1 method. The amplified &lt;italic&gt;rps10&lt;/italic&gt; region also has higher taxonomic resolution than ITS1, allowing for greater discrimination of closely related species. We present a new website with a searchable &lt;italic&gt;rps10&lt;/italic&gt; reference database for species identification and all protocols needed for oomycete metabarcoding. The &lt;italic&gt;rps10&lt;/italic&gt; barcode and methods described herein provide an effective tool for metabarcoding oomycetes using short-read sequencing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Interpretive summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oomycetes are a group of eukaryotes related to brown algae and diatoms, many of which cause diseases in plants and animals. Improved methods are needed to rapidly characterize the diversity of oomycete species found in environmental samples. We have identified the mitochondrial 40S ribosomal protein S10 gene (&lt;italic&gt;rps10&lt;/italic&gt;) as being useful for oomycete community sequencing. We evaluated its utility relative to a popular barcode, the internal transcribed spacer 1 (ITS1), by sequencing environmental samples and a community we synthesized in the laboratory. The amplified &lt;italic&gt;rps10&lt;/italic&gt; region is predicted to have a higher taxonomic resolution than ITS1, allowing for greater discrimination of closely related species. We present a new website with a searchable &lt;italic&gt;rps10&lt;/italic&gt; reference database for species identification and all protocols needed for oomycete community sequencing. The &lt;italic&gt;rps10&lt;/italic&gt; barcode and methods described herein provide an effective tool for characterizing oomycetes using environmental DNA sequencing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.460084" rel="alternate" title="A new oomycete metabarcoding method using the rps10 gene (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462426</id><title>New insights into the architecture and dynamics of archaella (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.332745+00:00</updated><author><name>Lavinia Gambelli</name></author><author><name>Michail N. Isupov</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Conners</name></author><author><name>Mathew McLaren</name></author><author><name>Annett Bellack</name></author><author><name>Vicki Gold</name></author><author><name>Reinhard Rachel</name></author><author><name>Bertram Daum</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Archaea swim by means of a unique molecular machine called the archaellum. The archaellum consists of an ATP-powered intracellular motor that drives the rotation of an extracellular filament, allowing the cell to rapidly propel itself through liquid media.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The archaellum filament comprises multiple copies of helically organised subunits named archaellins. While in many species several archaellin homologs are encoded in the same operon, structural studies conducted to date have suggested that archaella consist of only one protein species. Thus, the role of the remaining archaellin genes remains elusive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we present the structure of the &lt;italic&gt;Methanocaldococcus villosus&lt;/italic&gt; archaellum filament at 3.08 Å resolution. We find that the filament is composed of two alternating archaellins - ArlB1 and ArlB2, suggesting that the architecture and assembly of archaella is more complex than previously thought. Moreover, we identify two major structural elements that enable the archaellum filament to move.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our findings provide new insights into archaeal motility and challenge the current view on the archaellum architecture and assembly.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462426" rel="alternate" title="New insights into the architecture and dynamics of archaella (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462712</id><title>Mycobacterial resistance to zinc poisoning requires assembly of P-ATPase-containing membrane metal efflux platforms (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.333027+00:00</updated><author><name>Yves-Marie Boudehen</name></author><author><name>Marion Faucher</name></author><author><name>Xavier Maréchal</name></author><author><name>Roger Miras</name></author><author><name>Jérôme Rech</name></author><author><name>Olivier Sénèque</name></author><author><name>Maximilian Wallat</name></author><author><name>Pascal Demange</name></author><author><name>Jean-Yves Bouet</name></author><author><name>Olivier Saurel</name></author><author><name>Patrice Catty</name></author><author><name>Claude Gutierrez</name></author><author><name>Olivier Neyrolles</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Transition metals are toxic at high concentrations. The P&lt;sub&gt;1B&lt;/sub&gt;-ATPase metal exporter CtpC/Rv3270 is required for resistance to zinc poisoning in the human pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt;. Here, we discovered that zinc resistance also depends on the chaperone-like protein PacL1/Rv3269. PacL1 bound Zn&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;, but unlike PacL1 and CtpC, the PacL1 metal-binding motif (MBM) was required only at high zinc concentrations. PacL1 co-localized with CtpC in dynamic microdomains within the mycobacterial plasma membrane. Microdomain formation did not require flotillins nor the PacL1 MBM. Instead, loss of the PacL1 Glutamine/Alanine repeats led to loss of CtpC and sensitivity to zinc. PacL1 and CtpC are within the same operon, and homologous PacL1-P&lt;sub&gt;1B&lt;/sub&gt;-ATPase pairs are widely distributed within and across prokaryotes. PacL1 colocalized and functioned redundantly with PacL orthologs in &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt;. Overall, our study suggests that PacL proteins are scaffolds that assemble P-ATPase-containing metal efflux platforms, a novel type of functional membrane microdomain that underlies bacterial resistance to metal poisoning.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462712" rel="alternate" title="Mycobacterial resistance to zinc poisoning requires assembly of P-ATPase-containing membrane metal efflux platforms (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462733</id><title>A novel locally c-di-GMP-controlled exopolysaccharide synthase required for N4 phage infection of E. coli (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.333340+00:00</updated><author><name>Eike H. Junkermeier</name></author><author><name>Regine Hengge</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A major target of c-di-GMP signaling is the production of biofilm-associated extracellular polymeric substances (EPS), which in &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; K-12 include amyloid curli fibres, phosphoethanolamine-modified (pEtN-)cellulose and poly-N-acetyl-glucosamine (PGA). However, the characterized c-di-GMP-binding effector systems are largely outnumbered by the 12 diguanylate cyclases (DGCs) and 13 phosphodiesterases (PDEs), which synthetize and degrade c-di-GMP, respectively. &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; possesses a single protein with a potentially c-di-GMP-binding MshEN domain, NfrB, which – together with the outer membrane protein NfrA – is known to serve as a receptor system for phage N4. Here, we show that NfrB not only binds c-di-GMP with high affinity, but as a novel c-di-GMP-controlled glycosyltransferase synthesizes a secreted EPS, which can impede motility and is required as an initial receptor for phage N4 infection. In addition, a systematic screening of the 12 DGCs of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; K-12 revealed that specifically DgcJ is required for the infection with phage N4 and interacts directly with NfrB. This is in line with local signaling models, where specific DGCs and/or PDEs form protein complexes with particular c-di-GMP effector/target systems. Our findings thus provide further evidence that intracellular signaling pathways, which all use the same diffusible second messenger, can act in parallel in a highly specific manner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Key findings in model organisms led to the concept of ‘local’ signaling, challenging the dogma of a gradually increasing global intracellular c-di-GMP concentration driving the motile-sessile transition in bacteria. In our current model, bacteria dynamically combine global as well as local signaling modes, in which specific DGCs and/or PDEs team up with effector/target systems in multiprotein complexes. Our present study highlights a novel example of how specificity in c-di-GMP signaling can be achieved by showing NfrB as a novel c-di-GMP binding effector in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;, which is controlled in a local manner specifically by DgcJ. We further show that NfrB (which was initially found as a part of a receptor system for phage N4) is involved in the production of a novel exopolysaccharide. Finally, our data shine new light on host interaction of phage N4, which uses this exopolysaccharide as an initial receptor for adsorption.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462733" rel="alternate" title="A novel locally c-di-GMP-controlled exopolysaccharide synthase required for N4 phage infection of E. coli (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461887</id><title>A CRISPR-Cas9 screen reveals a role for WD repeat-containing protein 81 (WDR81) in the entry of late penetrating viruses (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.335428+00:00</updated><author><name>Anthony J. Snyder</name></author><author><name>Andrew T. Abad</name></author><author><name>Pranav Danthi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Successful initiation of infection by many different viruses requires their uptake into the endosomal compartment. While some viruses exit this compartment early, others must reach the degradative, acidic environment of the late endosome. Mammalian orthoreovirus (reovirus) is one such late penetrating virus. To identify host factors that are important for reovirus infection, we performed a CRISPR-Cas9 knockout (KO) screen that targets over 20,000 genes in fibroblasts derived from the embryos of C57/BL6 mice. We identified seven genes (WDR81, WDR91, RAB7, CCZ1, CTSL, GNPTAB, and SLC35A1) that were required for the induction of cell death by reovirus. Notably, CRISPR-mediated KO of WD repeat-containing protein 81 (WDR81) rendered cells resistant to reovirus infection. Susceptibility to reovirus infection was restored by complementing KO cells with human WDR81. Although the absence of WDR81 did not affect viral attachment efficiency or uptake into the endosomal compartments for initial disassembly, it delayed viral gene expression and diminished infectious virus production. Consistent with the role of WDR81 in impacting the maturation of endosomes, WDR81-deficiency led to the accumulation of reovirus particles in dead-end compartments. Though WDR81 was dispensable for infection by VSV (vesicular stomatitis virus), which exits the endosomal system at an early stage, it was required for VSV-EBO GP (VSV that expresses the Ebolavirus glycoprotein), which must reach the late endosome to initiate infection. These results reveal a broad, previously unappreciated role for WDR81 in promoting the replication of late penetrating viruses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;AUTHOR SUMMARY&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Viruses are obligate intracellular parasites that require the contributions of numerous host factors to complete the viral life cycle. Thus, the host-pathogen interaction can regulate cell death signaling and virus entry, replication, assembly, and egress. Functional genetic screens are useful tools to identify host factors that are important for establishing infection. Such information can also be used to understand cell biology. Notably, genome-scale CRISPR-Cas9 knockout screens are robust due to their specificity and the loss of host gene expression. Mammalian orthoreovirus (reovirus) is a tractable model system to investigate the pathogenesis of neurotropic and cardiotropic viruses. Using a CRISPR-Cas9 screen, we identified WD repeat-containing protein 81 (WDR81) as an essential host factor for reovirus infection of murine cells. Ablation of WDR81 blocked a late step in the viral entry pathway. Further, our work indicates that WDR81 is required for the entry of vesicular stomatitis virus that expresses the Ebolavirus glycoprotein.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461887" rel="alternate" title="A CRISPR-Cas9 screen reveals a role for WD repeat-containing protein 81 (WDR81) in the entry of late penetrating viruses (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461620</id><title>Identification of Immunodominant T-lymphocyte Epitope Peptides in HPV 1, 2 and 3 L1 Protein for Novel Cutaneous Wart Vaccine (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.336060+00:00</updated><author><name>Wu Han Toh</name></author><author><name>Chuang-Wei Wang</name></author><author><name>Wen-Hung Chung</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Common warts and flat warts are caused by the human papillomavirus (HPV). Peak incidence of wart infection occurs in schoolchildren aged 12-16, where prevalence can be as high as 20%. Traditional treatments aimed at destruction of wart tissue have low clearance rates and high recurrence rates. Occasional reports have even shown warts becoming malignant and progressing into verrucous carcinoma. Current licensed HPV vaccines largely target higher-risk oncogenic HPV types, but do not provide coverage of low-risk types associated with warts. To date, little attention has been given to the development of effective, anti-viral wart treatments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study aims to identify immunodominant T-lymphocyte epitopes from the L1 major capsid protein of HPV 1, 2 and 3, a foundational step in bioengineering a peptide-based vaccine for warts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cytotoxic T-cell and helper T-cell epitopes were predicted using an array of immunoinformatic tools against a reference panel of frequently observed MHC-I and MHC-II alleles. Predicted peptides were ranked based on IC&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; and IFN-γ Inducer Scores, respectively, and top performing epitopes were synthesized and subjected to &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; screening by IFN-γ enzyme-linked immunosorbent spot assay (ELISpot). Independent trials were conducted using PBMCs of healthy volunteers. Final chosen peptides were fused with flexible GS linkers in &lt;italic&gt;silico&lt;/italic&gt; to design a novel polypeptide vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seven immunodominant peptides screened from 44 predicted peptides were included in the vaccine design, selected to elicit specific immune responses across MHC class I and class II, and across HPV types. Evaluation of the vaccine’s properties suggest that the vaccine is stable, non-allergenic, and provides near complete global population coverage (&amp;gt;99%). Solubility prediction and rare codon analysis indicate that the DNA sequence encoding the vaccine is suitable for high level expression in &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In sum, this study demonstrates the potential and lays the framework for the development of a peptide-based vaccine against warts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461620" rel="alternate" title="Identification of Immunodominant T-lymphocyte Epitope Peptides in HPV 1, 2 and 3 L1 Protein for Novel Cutaneous Wart Vaccine (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462781</id><title>The Human STAT2 Coiled-Coil Domain Contains a Degron for Zika Virus Interferon Evasion (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.336527+00:00</updated><author><name>Jean-Patrick Parisien</name></author><author><name>Jessica J. Lenoir</name></author><author><name>Gloria Alvarado</name></author><author><name>Curt M. Horvath</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ability of viruses to evade the host antiviral immune system determines their level of replication fitness, species specificity, and pathogenic potential. Flaviviruses rely on the subversion of innate immune barriers including the type I and type III IFN antiviral systems. Zika virus infection induces the degradation of STAT2, an essential component of the IFN stimulated gene transcription factor, ISGF3. The mechanisms that lead to STAT2 degradation by Zika virus are poorly understood, but it is known to be mediated by the viral NS5 protein that binds to STAT2 and targets it for proteasome-mediated destruction. To better understand how NS5 engages and degrades STAT2, functional analysis of the protein interactions that lead to Zika virus and NS5-dependent STAT2 proteolysis were investigated. Data implicate the STAT2 coiled-coil domain as necessary and sufficient for NS5 interaction and proteasome degradation after Zika virus infection. Molecular dissection reveals that the first two α-helices of the STAT2 coiled-coil contain a specific targeting region for IFN antagonism. These functional interactions provide a more complete understanding of the essential protein-protein interactions needed for Zika virus evasion of the host antiviral response, and identifies new targets for antiviral therapeutic approaches.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zika virus infection can cause mild fever, rash, and muscle pain, and in rare cases lead to brain or nervous system diseases including Guillain–Barré syndrome. Infections in pregnant women can increase the risk of miscarriage or serious birth defects including brain anomalies and microcephaly. There are no drugs or vaccines for Zika disease. Zika virus is known to break down the host antiviral immune response, and this research project reveals how the virus suppresses interferon signaling, and may reveal therapeutic vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462781" rel="alternate" title="The Human STAT2 Coiled-Coil Domain Contains a Degron for Zika Virus Interferon Evasion (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461590</id><title>PplD is a de-N-acetylase of the cell wall linkage unit of streptococcal rhamnopolysaccharides (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.337190+00:00</updated><author><name>Jeffrey S. Rush</name></author><author><name>Prakash Parajuli</name></author><author><name>Alessandro Ruda</name></author><author><name>Jian Li</name></author><author><name>Amol A. Pohane</name></author><author><name>Svetlana Zamakhaeva</name></author><author><name>Mohammad M. Rahman</name></author><author><name>Jennifer C. Chang</name></author><author><name>Artemis Gogos</name></author><author><name>Cameron W. Kenner</name></author><author><name>Gérard Lambeau</name></author><author><name>Michael J. Federle</name></author><author><name>Konstantin V. Korotkov</name></author><author><name>Göran Widmalm</name></author><author><name>Natalia Korotkova</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The cell wall of the human bacterial pathogen Group A Streptococcus (GAS) consists of peptidoglycan decorated with the Lancefield group A carbohydrate (GAC). GAC is a promising target for the development of GAS vaccines. In this study, employing chemical, compositional, and NMR methods, we show that GAC is attached to peptidoglycan via glucosamine 1-phosphate. This structural feature makes the GAC-peptidoglycan linkage highly sensitive to cleavage by nitrous acid and resistant to mild acid conditions. Using this characteristic of the GAS cell wall, we identify PplD as a protein required for deacetylation of linkage &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;-acetylglucosamine (GlcNAc). X-ray structural analysis indicates that PplD performs catalysis via a modified acid/base mechanism. Genetic surveys &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; together with functional analysis indicate that PplD homologs deacetylate the polysaccharide linkage in many streptococcal species. We further demonstrate that introduction of positive charges to the cell wall by GlcNAc deacetylation protects GAS against host cationic antimicrobial proteins.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461590" rel="alternate" title="PplD is a de-N-acetylase of the cell wall linkage unit of streptococcal rhamnopolysaccharides (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461563</id><title>Lipoproteome screening of the Lyme disease agent identifies novel inhibitors of antibody-mediated complement killing (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.337485+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael J. Pereira</name></author><author><name>Beau Wager</name></author><author><name>Ryan J. Garrigues</name></author><author><name>Eva Gerlach</name></author><author><name>Joshua D. Quinn</name></author><author><name>Alex Dowdell</name></author><author><name>Marcia S. Osburne</name></author><author><name>Wolfram R. Zückert</name></author><author><name>Peter Kraiczy</name></author><author><name>Brandon L. Garcia</name></author><author><name>John M. Leong</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spirochetal pathogens such as the causative agent of Lyme disease, &lt;italic&gt;Borrelia burgdorferi&lt;/italic&gt; sensu lato, encode an abundance of lipoproteins; however, due in part to their evolutionary distance from more well-studied bacteria such as Proteobacteria and Firmicutes, very few spirochetal lipoproteins have assigned functions. Indeed, &lt;italic&gt;B. burgdorferi&lt;/italic&gt; devotes almost 8% of its genome to lipoprotein genes and interacts with its environment primarily through the production of at least eighty surface-exposed lipoproteins throughout its tick vector-vertebrate host lifecycle (57). Several &lt;italic&gt;B. burgdorferi&lt;/italic&gt; lipoproteins have been shown to serve diverse roles, such as cellular adherence or immune evasion, but the functions for most &lt;italic&gt;B. burgdorferi&lt;/italic&gt; surface lipoproteins remain unknown. In this study, we developed a &lt;italic&gt;B. burgdorferi&lt;/italic&gt; lipoproteome screening platform utilizing intact spirochetes that enables the identification of previously unrecognized host interactions. As spirochetal survival in the bloodstream is essential for dissemination, we targeted our screen to C1, the first component of the classical (antibody-mediated) complement pathway. We identified two high-affinity C1 interactions by the paralogous lipoproteins, ErpB and ErpQ. Using biochemical, microbiological, and biophysical approaches, we demonstrated that ErpB and ErpQ inhibit the activated forms of the C1 proteases, C1r and C1s, and represent a new mechanistic class of C1 inhibitors that protect the spirochete from antibody-mediated complement killing by allosteric regulation. In addition to identifying a novel mode of complement inhibition, our study establishes a lipoproteome screening methodology as a discovery platform for identifying direct host-pathogen interactions that are central to the pathogenesis of spirochetes, such as the Lyme disease agent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spirochetal pathogens encode an abundance of lipoproteins that can provide a critical interface with the host environment. For example, &lt;italic&gt;Borrelia burgdorferi&lt;/italic&gt;, the model species for spirochetal biology, must survive an enzootic life cycle defined by fluctuations between vector (tick) and vertebrate host. While &lt;italic&gt;B. burgdorferi&lt;/italic&gt; expresses over eighty surface lipoproteins— many of which likely contribute to host survival—the &lt;italic&gt;B. burgdorferi&lt;/italic&gt; lipoproteome is poorly characterized. Here, we generated a platform to rapidly identify targets of &lt;italic&gt;B. burgdorferi&lt;/italic&gt; surface lipoproteins and identified two orthologs that allosterically inhibit complement C1 subcomponents, conferring resistance to classical complement killing. This work expands our understanding of complement evasion mechanisms and points towards a discovery approach for identifying host-pathogen interactions that are central to spirochete pathogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461563" rel="alternate" title="Lipoproteome screening of the Lyme disease agent identifies novel inhibitors of antibody-mediated complement killing (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>