<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.431485+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473544</id><title>Stitchr: stitching coding TCR nucleotide sequences from V/J/CDR3 information (75 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.431940+00:00</updated><author><name>James M. Heather</name></author><author><name>Matthew J. Spindler</name></author><author><name>Marta Herrero Alonso</name></author><author><name>Yifang Ivana Shui</name></author><author><name>David G. Millar</name></author><author><name>David S. Johnson</name></author><author><name>Mark Cobbold</name></author><author><name>Aaron N. Hata</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The study and manipulation of T cell receptors (TCRs) is central to multiple fields across basic and translational immunology research. Produced by V(D)J recombination, TCRs are often only recorded in the literature and data repositories as a combination of their V and J gene symbols, plus their hypervariable CDR3 amino acid sequence. However, numerous applications require full-length coding nucleotide sequences. Here we present Stitchr, a software tool developed to specifically address this limitation. Given minimal V/J/CDR3 information, Stitchr produces complete coding sequences representing a fully spliced TCR cDNA. Due to its modular design, Stitchr can be used for TCR engineering using either published germline or novel/modified variable and constant region sequences. Sequences produced by Stitchr were validated by synthesizing and transducing TCR sequences into Jurkat cells, recapitulating the expected antigen specificity of the parental TCR. Using a companion script, Thimble, we demonstrate that Stitchr can process a million TCRs in under ten minutes using a standard desktop personal computer. By systemizing the production and modification of TCR sequences, we propose that Stitchr will increase the speed, repeatability, and reproducibility of TCR research. Stitchr is available on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473544" rel="alternate" title="Stitchr: stitching coding TCR nucleotide sequences from V/J/CDR3 information (75 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473537</id><title>Long-lasting germinal center responses to a priming immunization with continuous proliferation and somatic mutation (42 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.432291+00:00</updated><author><name>Jeong Hyun Lee</name></author><author><name>Henry Sutton</name></author><author><name>Christopher A. Cottrell</name></author><author><name>Ivy Phung</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Ozorowski</name></author><author><name>Leigh M. Sewall</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Nedellec</name></author><author><name>Catherine Nakao</name></author><author><name>Murillo Silva</name></author><author><name>Sara T. Richey</name></author><author><name>Jonathan L. Torres</name></author><author><name>Wen-Hsin Lee</name></author><author><name>Erik Georgeson</name></author><author><name>Michael Kubitz</name></author><author><name>Sam Hodges</name></author><author><name>Tina-Marie Mullen</name></author><author><name>Yumiko Adachi</name></author><author><name>Kimberly M. Cirelli</name></author><author><name>Amitinder Kaur</name></author><author><name>Carolina Allers-Hernandez</name></author><author><name>Marissa Fahlberg</name></author><author><name>Brooke F. Grasperge</name></author><author><name>Jason P. Dufour</name></author><author><name>Faith Schiro</name></author><author><name>Pyone P. Aye</name></author><author><name>Diane G. Carnathan</name></author><author><name>Guido Silvestri</name></author><author><name>Xiaoying Shen</name></author><author><name>David C. Montefiori</name></author><author><name>Ronald S. Veazey</name></author><author><name>Andrew B. Ward</name></author><author><name>Lars Hangartner</name></author><author><name>Dennis R. Burton</name></author><author><name>Darrell J. Irvine</name></author><author><name>William R. Schief</name></author><author><name>Shane Crotty</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Germinal centers (GCs) are the engines of antibody evolution. Using HIV Env protein immunogen priming in rhesus monkeys (RM) followed by a long period without further immunization, we demonstrate GC B cells (B&lt;sub&gt;GC&lt;/sub&gt;) lasted at least 6 months (29 weeks), all the while maintaining rapid proliferation. A 186-fold B&lt;sub&gt;GC&lt;/sub&gt; cell increase was present by week 10 compared to a conventional immunization. Single cell transcriptional profiling revealed that both light zone and dark zone GC states were sustained throughout the 6 months. Antibody somatic hypermutation (SHM) of B&lt;sub&gt;GC&lt;/sub&gt; cells continued to accumulate throughout the 29 week priming period, with evidence of selective pressure. Additionally, Env-binding B&lt;sub&gt;GC&lt;/sub&gt; cells were still 49-fold above baseline 29 weeks after immunization, suggesting that they could be active for significantly longer periods of time. High titers of HIV neutralizing antibodies were generated after a single booster immunization. Fully glycosylated HIV trimer protein is a complex antigen, posing significant immunodominance challenges for B cells, among other difficulties. Memory B cells (B&lt;sub&gt;Mem&lt;/sub&gt;) generated under these long priming conditions had higher levels of SHM, and both B&lt;sub&gt;Mem&lt;/sub&gt; cells and antibodies were more likely to recognize non-immunodominant epitopes. Numerous B&lt;sub&gt;GC&lt;/sub&gt; cell lineage phylogenies spanning the &amp;gt;6-month GC period were identified, demonstrating continuous GC activity and selection for at least 191 days, with no additional antigen exposure. A long prime, adjuvanted, slow delivery (12-day) immunization approach holds promise for difficult vaccine targets, and suggests that patience can have great value for tuning GCs to maximize antibody responses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473537" rel="alternate" title="Long-lasting germinal center responses to a priming immunization with continuous proliferation and somatic mutation (42 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473458</id><title>Re-evaluation of the phylogenetic diversity and global distribution of the genus Candidatus Accumulibacter (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.433028+00:00</updated><author><name>Francesca Petriglieri</name></author><author><name>Caitlin Singleton</name></author><author><name>Zivile Kondrotaite</name></author><author><name>Morten K. D. Dueholm</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth A. McDaniel</name></author><author><name>Katherine D. McMahon</name></author><author><name>Per H. Nielsen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Candidatus&lt;/italic&gt; Accumulibacter was the first microorganism identified as a polyphosphate-accumulating organism (PAO), important for phosphorus removal from wastewater. This genus is diverse, and the current phylogeny and taxonomic framework appears complicated, with the majority of publicly available genomes classified as “&lt;italic&gt;Candidatus&lt;/italic&gt; Accumulibacter phosphatis”, despite notable phylogenetic divergence. The &lt;italic&gt;ppk1&lt;/italic&gt; marker gene allows for a finer scale differentiation into different “types” and “clades”, nevertheless taxonomic assignments remain confusing and inconsistent across studies. Therefore, a comprehensive re-evaluation is needed to establish a common understanding of this genus, both in terms of naming and basic conserved physiological traits. Here, we provide this re-assessment using a comparison of genome, &lt;italic&gt;ppk1&lt;/italic&gt;, and 16S rRNA gene-based approaches from comprehensive datasets. We identified 15 novel species, along with the well-known &lt;italic&gt;Ca&lt;/italic&gt;. A. phosphatis, &lt;italic&gt;Ca&lt;/italic&gt;. A. deltensis and &lt;italic&gt;Ca&lt;/italic&gt;. A. aalborgensis. To compare the species &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt;, we designed new species-specific FISH probes and revealed their morphology and arrangement in activated sludge. Based on the MiDAS global survey, &lt;italic&gt;Ca&lt;/italic&gt;. Accumulibacter species were widespread in WWTPs with phosphorus removal, indicating the process design as a major driver for their abundance. Genome mining for PAO related pathways and FISH-Raman microspectroscopy confirmed the potential for the PAO metabolism in all &lt;italic&gt;Ca&lt;/italic&gt;. Accumulibacter species, with detection &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; of the typical PAO storage polymers. Genome annotation further revealed fine-scale differences in the nitrate/nitrite reduction pathways. This provides insights into the niche differentiation of these lineages, potentially explaining their coexistence in the same ecosystem while contributing to overall phosphorus and nitrogen removal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Candidatus&lt;/italic&gt; Accumulibacter is the most studied PAO organism, with a primary role in biological nutrient removal. However, the species-level taxonomy of this lineage is convoluted due to the use of different phylogenetic markers or genome sequencing. Here, we redefined the phylogeny of these organisms, proposing a comprehensive approach which could be used to address the classification of other diverse and uncultivated lineages. Using genome-resolved phylogeny, compared to 16S rRNA gene- and other phylogenetic markers phylogeny, we obtained a higher resolution taxonomy and established a common understanding of this genus. Furthermore, genome mining of gene and pathways of interest, validated &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; by application of a new set of FISH probes and Raman micromicrospectroscopy, provided additional high-resolution metabolic insights into these organisms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473458" rel="alternate" title="Re-evaluation of the phylogenetic diversity and global distribution of the genus Candidatus Accumulibacter (20 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473453</id><title>Single-Cell Atlas of Common Variable Immunodeficiency reveals germinal center-associated epigenetic dysregulation in B cell responses (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.433333+00:00</updated><author><name>Javier Rodríguez-Ubreva</name></author><author><name>Anna Arutyunyan</name></author><author><name>Marc Jan Bonder</name></author><author><name>Lucía Del Pino-Molina</name></author><author><name>Stephen J. Clark</name></author><author><name>Carlos de la Calle-Fabregat</name></author><author><name>Luz Garcia-Alonso</name></author><author><name>Louis-François Handfield</name></author><author><name>Laura Ciudad</name></author><author><name>Eduardo Andrés-León</name></author><author><name>Felix Krueger</name></author><author><name>Francesc Català-Moll</name></author><author><name>Virginia C. Rodríguez-Cortez</name></author><author><name>Krzysztof Polanski</name></author><author><name>Lira Mamanova</name></author><author><name>Stijn van Dongen</name></author><author><name>Vladimir Yu. Kiselev</name></author><author><name>María T. Martínez-Saavedra</name></author><author><name>Holger Heyn</name></author><author><name>Javier Martín</name></author><author><name>Klaus Warnatz</name></author><author><name>Eduardo López-Granados</name></author><author><name>Carlos Rodríguez-Gallego</name></author><author><name>Oliver Stegle</name></author><author><name>Gavin Kelsey</name></author><author><name>Roser Vento-Tormo</name></author><author><name>Esteban Ballestar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Common variable immunodeficiency (CVID), the most prevalent symptomatic primary immunodeficiency, is characterized by impaired terminal B-cell differentiation and defective antibody responses. Incomplete genetic penetrance and a wide range of phenotypic expressivity in CVID suggest the participation of additional pathogenic mechanisms. Monozygotic (MZ) twins discordant for CVID are uniquely valuable for studying the contribution of epigenetics to the disease. We used single-cell epigenomics and transcriptomics to create a cell census of naïve-to-memory B cell differentiation in a pair of CVID-discordant MZ twins. Our analysis identifies DNA methylation, chromatin accessibility and transcriptional defects in memory B cells that mirror defective cell-cell communication defects following activation. These findings were validated in a cohort of CVID patients and healthy donors. Our findings provide a comprehensive multi-omics map of alterations in naïve-to-memory B-cell transition in CVID and reveal links between the epigenome and immune cell cross-talk. Our resource, publicly available at the Human Cell Atlas, paves the way for future diagnosis and treatments of CVID patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473453" rel="alternate" title="Single-Cell Atlas of Common Variable Immunodeficiency reveals germinal center-associated epigenetic dysregulation in B cell responses (18 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473470</id><title>Single-cell RNA sequencing reveals micro-evolution of the stickleback immune system (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.433952+00:00</updated><author><name>Lauren E. Fuess</name></author><author><name>Daniel I. Bolnick</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pathogenic infection is an important driver of many ecological processes. Furthermore, variability in immune function is an important driver of differential infection outcomes. New evidence would suggest that immune variation extends to broad cellular structure of immune systems. However, variability at such broad levels is traditionally difficult to detect in non-model systems. Here we leverage single cell transcriptomic approaches to document signatures of microevolution of immune system structure in a natural system, the three-spined stickleback (&lt;italic&gt;Gasterosteus aculeatus&lt;/italic&gt;). We sampled nine adult fish from three populations with variability in resistance to a cestode parasite, &lt;italic&gt;Schistocephalus solidus&lt;/italic&gt;, to create the first comprehensive immune cell atlas for &lt;italic&gt;G. aculeatus&lt;/italic&gt;. Eight major immune cell types, corresponding to major vertebrate immune cells, were identified. We were also able to document significant variation in both abundance and expression profiles of the individual immune cell types, among the three populations of fish. This variability may contribute to observed variability in parasite susceptibility. Finally, we demonstrate that identified cell type markers can be used to reinterpret traditional transcriptomic data. Combined our study demonstrates the power of single cell sequencing to not only document evolutionary phenomena (i.e. microevolution of immune cells), but also increase the power of traditional transcriptomic datasets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473470" rel="alternate" title="Single-cell RNA sequencing reveals micro-evolution of the stickleback immune system (14 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473717</id><title>Human gut bifidobacteria inhibit the growth of the opportunistic fungal pathogen Candida albicans (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.434296+00:00</updated><author><name>Liviana Ricci</name></author><author><name>Joanna Mackie</name></author><author><name>Gillian E. Donachie</name></author><author><name>Ambre Chapuis</name></author><author><name>Kristýna Mezerová</name></author><author><name>Megan D. Lenardon</name></author><author><name>Alistair J. P. Brown</name></author><author><name>Sylvia H. Duncan</name></author><author><name>Alan W. Walker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The human gut microbiota protects the host from invading pathogens and the overgrowth of indigenous opportunistic species via mechanisms such as competition for nutrients and by production of antimicrobial compounds. Here, we investigated the antagonist activity of human gut bacteria towards &lt;italic&gt;Candida albicans&lt;/italic&gt;, an opportunistic fungal pathogen that can cause severe infections and mortality in susceptible patients. Co-culture batch incubations of &lt;italic&gt;C. albicans&lt;/italic&gt; in the presence of faecal microbiota from six different healthy individuals revealed varying levels of inhibitory activity against &lt;italic&gt;C. albicans&lt;/italic&gt;. 16S rRNA gene sequence profiling of these faecal co-culture bacterial communities showed that the &lt;italic&gt;Bifidobacteriaceae&lt;/italic&gt; family, and &lt;italic&gt;Bifidobacterium adolescentis&lt;/italic&gt; in particular, were most correlated with antagonistic activity against &lt;italic&gt;C. albicans&lt;/italic&gt;. Follow up mechanistic studies confirmed that culture supernatants of &lt;italic&gt;Bifidobacterium&lt;/italic&gt; species, particularly &lt;italic&gt;B. adolescentis&lt;/italic&gt;, inhibited &lt;italic&gt;C. albicans in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; under both aerobic and anaerobic conditions. Production of the fermentation acids acetate and lactate, together with the concomitant decrease in pH, were strong drivers of the inhibitory activity. Bifidobacteria may therefore represent attractive targets for the development of probiotics and prebiotic interventions tailored to enhance inhibitory activity against &lt;italic&gt;C. albicans in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473717" rel="alternate" title="Human gut bifidobacteria inhibit the growth of the opportunistic fungal pathogen Candida albicans (13 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473996</id><title>Direct RNA sequencing of Respiratory Syncytial Virus infected human cells generates a detailed overview of RSV polycistronic mRNA and transcript abundance (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.434584+00:00</updated><author><name>I'ah Donovan Banfield</name></author><author><name>Sophie Hall</name></author><author><name>Tianyi Gao</name></author><author><name>Eleanor Murphy</name></author><author><name>Jack Li</name></author><author><name>Ghada Shawli</name></author><author><name>Julian Alexander Hiscox</name></author><author><name>Rachel Fearns</name></author><author><name>David A Matthews</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To characterize species of viral mRNA transcripts generated during respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) infection, human fibroblast-like MRC5 lung cells were infected with subgroup A RSV for 6, 16 and 24 hours. Total RNA was harvested and polyadenylated mRNA was enriched and sequenced by direct RNA sequencing on an Oxford nanopore device. This yielded over 150,000 direct mRNA transcript reads which were mapped to the viral genome and analysed to determine relative mRNA levels of viral genes using our in-house ORF-centric pipeline. We were also able to examine frequencies with which polycistronic readthrough mRNAs were generated and to assess the length of the polyadenylated tails for each group of transcripts. We show that there is a general but non-linear decline in gene transcript abundance across the viral genome, as predicted by the model of RSV gene transcription. However, the decline in transcript abundance is not consistent. We show that the polyadenylate tails generated by the viral polymerase are similar in length to those generated by the host cells polyadenylation machinery and broadly declined in length for most transcripts as infection progressed. Finally, we observed that the steady state abundance of transcripts with very short polyadenylate tails is much less for N, SH and G transcripts compared to NS1, NS2, P, M, F and M2 which may reflect differences in mRNA stability and/or translation rates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473996" rel="alternate" title="Direct RNA sequencing of Respiratory Syncytial Virus infected human cells generates a detailed overview of RSV polycistronic mRNA and transcript abundance (13 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473591</id><title>Replication is the key barrier during the dual-host adaption of mosquito-borne flaviviruses (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.434825+00:00</updated><author><name>Yanan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Dening Liang</name></author><author><name>Fei Yuan</name></author><author><name>Yiran Yan</name></author><author><name>Zuoshu Wang</name></author><author><name>Pan Liu</name></author><author><name>Qi Yu</name></author><author><name>Xing Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xiangxi Wang</name></author><author><name>Aihua Zheng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mosquito-borne flaviviruses (MBFs) adapt to a dual-host transmission circle between mosquitoes and vertebrates. Dual-host affiliated insect-specific flaviviruses (dISFs), discovered from mosquitoes, are phylogenetically similar to MBFs but do not infect vertebrates. Thus, dISF-MBF chimeras could be an ideal model to study the dual-host adaption of MBFs. Using the pseudo-infectious reporter virus particle and reverse genetics systems, we found dISFs entered vertebrate cells as efficiently as the MBFs, but failed to initiate replication. Exchange of the un-translational regions (UTRs) of Donggang virus (DONV), an dISF, with those from Zika virus (ZIKV) rescued DONV replication in vertebrate cells and critical secondary RNA structures were further mapped. Essential UTR-binding host factors were screened for ZIKV replication in vertebrate cells, displaying different binding patterns. Therefore, our data demonstrate a post-entry cross-species transmission mechanism of MBFs, while UTR-host interaction is critical for dual-host adaption.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most viruses have a relatively narrow host range. In contrast, vector-borne flaviviruses, such as dengue virus and Zika virus, maintain their transmission cycle between arthropods and vertebrates, belonging to different phyla. How do these viruses adapt to the distinct cellular environments of two phyla? By comparing the single-host insect specific flavivirus and dual-host Zika virus, we identified three key molecular factors that determine MBF host tropism. This study will greatly increase the understanding of entry, replication, and cross-species evolution of mosquito-borne flaviviruses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473591" rel="alternate" title="Replication is the key barrier during the dual-host adaption of mosquito-borne flaviviruses (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473825</id><title>The ‘squalene route’ to carotenoid biosynthesis is widespread in Bacteria (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.435072+00:00</updated><author><name>Carlos Santana-Molina</name></author><author><name>Valentina Henriques</name></author><author><name>Damaso Hornero-Méndez</name></author><author><name>Damien P. Devos</name></author><author><name>Elena Rivas-Marin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Squalene is mostly associated with the biosynthesis of polycyclic triterpenes. Although there have been suggestions that squalene could be involved in the biosynthesis of carotenoids, functionally and evolutionarily related to polycyclic triterpenes, evidence of this ‘squalene route’ in nature was lacking. We demonstrate that planctomycetes synthesize C30 carotenoids via squalene and that this ‘squalene route’ is widely distributed in &lt;italic&gt;Bacteria&lt;/italic&gt;. We also investigated the functional roles of hopanoids and carotenoids in &lt;italic&gt;Planctomycetes&lt;/italic&gt; and show that their protective functions under stress conditions are complementary. Our evolutionary analyses suggest that the C30 carotenoid biosynthetic pathway is the most ancestral, with a potential origin in &lt;italic&gt;Firmicutes&lt;/italic&gt; or &lt;italic&gt;Planctomycetes&lt;/italic&gt;. In addition, we propose an evolutionary scenario to explain the diversification of the different carotenoid and squalene pathways. Together, these results improve the evolutionary contextualization of these molecules. Likewise, the widespread occurrence of the squalene route in bacteria increases the functional repertoire of squalene.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473825" rel="alternate" title="The ‘squalene route’ to carotenoid biosynthesis is widespread in Bacteria (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473798</id><title>Exploratory growth in Streptomyces venezuelae involves a unique transcriptional program, enhanced oxidative stress response, and profound acceleration in response to glycerol (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.435265+00:00</updated><author><name>Evan M. F. Shepherdson</name></author><author><name>Tina Netzker</name></author><author><name>Yordan Stoyanov</name></author><author><name>Marie A. Elliot</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Exploration is a recently discovered mode of growth and behaviour exhibited by some &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt; species that is distinct from their classical sporulating life cycle. While much has been uncovered regarding initiating environmental conditions and the phenotypic outcomes of exploratory growth, how this process is coordinated at a genetic level remains unclear. We used RNA-sequencing to survey global changes in the transcriptional profile of exploring cultures over time in the model organism &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces venezuelae&lt;/italic&gt;. Transcriptomic analyses revealed widespread changes in gene expression impacting diverse cellular functions. Investigations into differentially expressed regulatory elements revealed specific groups of regulatory factors to be impacted, including the expression of several extracytoplasmic function (ECF) sigma factors, second messenger signalling pathways, and members of the &lt;italic&gt;whiB&lt;/italic&gt;-like (&lt;italic&gt;wbl&lt;/italic&gt;) family of transcription factors. Dramatic changes were observed among primary metabolic pathways, especially among respiration-associated genes and the oxidative stress response; enzyme assays confirmed that exploring cultures exhibit an enhanced oxidative stress response compared with classically growing cultures. Changes in expression of the glycerol catabolic genes in &lt;italic&gt;S. venezuelae&lt;/italic&gt; led to the discovery that glycerol supplementation of the growth medium promotes a dramatic acceleration of exploration. This effect appears to be unique to glycerol as an alternative carbon source and this response is broadly conserved across other exploration-competent species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473798" rel="alternate" title="Exploratory growth in Streptomyces venezuelae involves a unique transcriptional program, enhanced oxidative stress response, and profound acceleration in response to glycerol (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.474031</id><title>Metabolic regulation by prostaglandin E2 impairs lung group 2 innate lymphoid cell responses (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.435561+00:00</updated><author><name>Calum Robb</name></author><author><name>You Zhou</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Felton</name></author><author><name>Birong Zhang</name></author><author><name>Marie Goepp</name></author><author><name>Privjyot Jheeta</name></author><author><name>Danielle Smyth</name></author><author><name>Richard Breyer</name></author><author><name>Shuh Narumiya</name></author><author><name>Henry McSorley</name></author><author><name>Rick Maizels</name></author><author><name>Jurgen Schwarze</name></author><author><name>Adriano Rossi</name></author><author><name>Chengcan Yao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Group 2 innate lymphoid cells (ILC2s) play a critical role in asthma pathogenesis. Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAID)-exacerbated respiratory disease (NERD) is associated with reduced signaling via EP2, a receptor for prostaglandin E2 (PGE2). However, the respective roles for the PGE2 receptors EP2 and EP4 (both share same downstream signaling) in the regulation of lung ILC2 responses has yet been deciphered. Here, we find that deficiency of EP2 rather than EP4 augments IL-33-induced lung ILC2 responses and eosinophilic inflammation in vivo. In contrast, exogenous agonism of EP4 but not EP2 markedly restricts IL-33- and Alternaria alternata-induced lung ILC2 responses and eosinophilic inflammation. Mechanistically, PGE2 directly suppresses IL-33-dependent ILC2 activation through the EP2/EP4-cAMP pathway, which downregulates STAT5 and MYC pathway gene expression and ILC2 energy metabolism. Blocking glycolysis diminishes IL-33-dependent ILC2 responses in mice lacking endogenous PG synthesis but not in PG-competent mice. Together, we have defined a mechanism for optimal suppression of lung ILC2 responses by endogenous PGE2-EP2 signaling which underpins the clinical findings of defective EP2 signaling in patients with NERD. Our findings also indicate that exogenously targeting the PGE2-EP4-cAMP and energy metabolic pathways may provide novel opportunities for treating ILC2-initiated lung inflammation in asthma and NERD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.474031" rel="alternate" title="Metabolic regulation by prostaglandin E2 impairs lung group 2 innate lymphoid cell responses (8 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473505</id><title>DNA replication dynamics during erythrocytic schizogony in the malaria parasites Plasmodium falciparum and Plasmodium knowlesi (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.435906+00:00</updated><author><name>Jennifer McDonald</name></author><author><name>Catherine J. Merrick</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Malaria parasites are unusual, early-diverging protozoans with non-canonical cell cycles. They do not undergo binary fission, but divide primarily by schizogony. This is a syncytial mode of replication involving asynchronous production of multiple nuclei within the same cytoplasm, culminating in a single mass cytokinesis event. The rate and efficiency of parasite replication is fundamentally important to malarial disease, which tends to be severe in hosts with high parasite loads. Here, we have studied for the first time the dynamics of schizogony in two human malaria parasite species, &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium knowlesi&lt;/italic&gt;. These differ in their cell-cycle length, the number of progeny produced and the genome composition, among other factors. Comparing them could therefore yield new information about the parameters and limitations of schizogony. We report that the dynamics of schizogony differ significantly between these two species, most strikingly in the gap phases between successive nuclear replications, which are longer in &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; and shorter, but more heterogenous, in &lt;italic&gt;P. knowlesi&lt;/italic&gt;. In both species, gaps become longer as schizogony progresses, whereas each period of active replication grows shorter. In both species there is also extreme variability between individual cells, with some schizonts producing many more nuclei than others, and some individual nuclei arresting their replication for many hours while adjacent nuclei continue to replicate. The efficiency of schizogony is probably influenced by a complex set of factors in both the parasite and its host cell.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473505" rel="alternate" title="DNA replication dynamics during erythrocytic schizogony in the malaria parasites Plasmodium falciparum and Plasmodium knowlesi (8 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.470774</id><title>Genetic and transcriptomic characteristics of RhlR-dependent quorum sensing in cystic fibrosis isolates of Pseudomonas aeruginosa (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.436112+00:00</updated><author><name>Kyle L. Asfahl</name></author><author><name>Nicole E. Smalley</name></author><author><name>Alexandria Chang</name></author><author><name>Ajai A. Dandekar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In people with the genetic disease cystic fibrosis (CF), bacterial infections involving the opportunistic pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; are a significant cause of morbidity and mortality. &lt;italic&gt;P. aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; uses a cell-cell signaling mechanism called quorum sensing (QS) to regulate many virulence functions. One type of QS consists of acyl-homoserine lactone (AHL) signals produced by LuxI-type signal synthases, which bind a cognate LuxR-type transcription factor. In laboratory strains and conditions, &lt;italic&gt;P. aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; employs two AHL synthase/receptor pairs arranged in a hierarchy, with the LasI/R system controlling the RhlI/R system and many downstream virulence factors. However, &lt;italic&gt;P. aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; isolates with inactivating mutations in &lt;italic&gt;lasR&lt;/italic&gt; are frequently isolated from chronic CF infections. We and others have shown that these isolates frequently use RhlR as the primary QS regulator. RhlR is rarely mutated in CF and environmental settings. We were interested if there were reproducible genetic characteristics of these isolates and if there was a central group of genes regulated by RhlR in all isolates. We examined five isolates and found signatures of adaptation common to CF isolates. We did not identify a common genetic mechanism to explain the switch from Las-to Rhl-dominated QS. We describe a core RhlR regulon encompassing 20 genes encoding 7 products. These results suggest a key group of QS-regulated factors important for pathogenesis of chronic infection, and position RhlR as a target for anti-QS therapeutics. Our work underscores the need to sample a diversity of isolates to understanding QS beyond what has been described in laboratory strains.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.470774" rel="alternate" title="Genetic and transcriptomic characteristics of RhlR-dependent quorum sensing in cystic fibrosis isolates of Pseudomonas aeruginosa (8 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473937</id><title>Molecular insights into antibody-mediated protection against the prototypic simian immunodeficiency virus (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.436328+00:00</updated><author><name>Fangzhu Zhao</name></author><author><name>Zachary T Berndsen</name></author><author><name>Nuria Pedreno-Lopez</name></author><author><name>Alison Burns</name></author><author><name>Joel D Allen</name></author><author><name>Shawn Barman</name></author><author><name>Wen-Hsin Lee</name></author><author><name>Srirupa Chakraborty</name></author><author><name>Sandrasegaram Gnanakaran</name></author><author><name>Leigh M Sewall</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Ozorowski</name></author><author><name>Oliver Limbo</name></author><author><name>Ge Song</name></author><author><name>Peter Yong</name></author><author><name>Sean Callaghan</name></author><author><name>Kim L Weisgrau</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey D Lifson</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Nedellec</name></author><author><name>Thomas B Voigt</name></author><author><name>Fernanda Laurino</name></author><author><name>Johan Louw</name></author><author><name>Brandon C Rosen</name></author><author><name>Michael Ricciardi</name></author><author><name>Max Crispin</name></author><author><name>Ronald C Desrosiers</name></author><author><name>Eva G Rakasz</name></author><author><name>David I Watkins</name></author><author><name>Raiees Andrabi</name></author><author><name>Andrew B Ward</name></author><author><name>Dennis R Burton</name></author><author><name>Devin Sok</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SIVmac239 infection of macaques is a favored model of human HIV infection. However, the SIVmac239 envelope (Env) trimer structure, glycan occupancy, and the targets and ability of neutralizing antibodies (nAbs) to protect against SIVmac239 remain unknown. Here, we report the isolation of SIVmac239 nAbs that recognize a glycan hole and the V1/V4 loop. A high-resolution structure of a SIVmac239 Env trimer-nAb complex shows many similarities to HIV and SIVcpz Envs, but with distinct V4 features and an extended V1 loop. Moreover, SIVmac239 Env has a higher glycan shield density than HIV Env that may contribute to poor or delayed nAb responses in SIVmac239-infected macaques. Passive transfer of a nAb protects macaques from repeated low dose intraveneous SIVmac239 challenge at serum titers comparable to those described for protection of humans against HIV infection. Our results provide structural insights for vaccine design and shed light on antibody-mediated protection in the SIV model.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473937" rel="alternate" title="Molecular insights into antibody-mediated protection against the prototypic simian immunodeficiency virus (8 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473182</id><title>Transcriptomes and metabolism define mouse and human MAIT cell heterogeneity (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.436920+00:00</updated><author><name>Shilpi Chandra</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Ascui</name></author><author><name>Thomas Riffelmacher</name></author><author><name>Ashu Chawla</name></author><author><name>Ciro Ramirez-Suastegui</name></author><author><name>Viankail Cedillo Castelan</name></author><author><name>Gregory Seumois</name></author><author><name>Hayley Simon</name></author><author><name>Mallory Paynich Murray</name></author><author><name>Goo-Young Seo</name></author><author><name>Ashmitaa Logandha Ramamoorthy Premlal</name></author><author><name>Greet Verstichel</name></author><author><name>Yingcong Li</name></author><author><name>Chia-Hao Lin</name></author><author><name>Jason Greenbaum</name></author><author><name>John Lamberti</name></author><author><name>Raghav Murthy</name></author><author><name>John Nigro</name></author><author><name>Hilde Cheroutre</name></author><author><name>Christian H. Ottensmeier</name></author><author><name>Stephen M. Hedrick</name></author><author><name>Li-Fan Lu</name></author><author><name>Pandurangan Vijayanand</name></author><author><name>Mitchell Kronenberg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mucosal-associated invariant T (MAIT) cells are a subpopulation of T lymphocytes that respond to microbial metabolites. We performed single-cell RNA sequencing and metabolic analyses of MAIT cell subsets in thymus and peripheral tissues from mice and humans to define the heterogeneity and developmental pathway of these innate-like lymphocytes. We show that the predominant mouse subset, which produces IL-17 (MAIT17), and the subset that produces IFNγ (MAIT1), have greatly different transcriptomes and metabolic states in the thymus and periphery. A splenic MAIT subset has a transcriptome similar to circulating lymphocytes, and in mice these also are found in recent thymic emigrants, suggesting partially mature cells emigrate from the thymus. Human MAIT cells are predominantly MAIT1 cells, but have a different metabolism from their mouse counterparts with increased fatty acid uptake and storage. Although mouse and human subsets are similar in thymus, in the periphery they diverge, likely reflecting environmental influences.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473182" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptomes and metabolism define mouse and human MAIT cell heterogeneity (7 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473386</id><title>IL-23 signaling prevents ferroptosis-driven renal immunopathology during candidiasis (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.437305+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicolas Millet</name></author><author><name>Norma V. Solis</name></author><author><name>Diane Aguilar</name></author><author><name>Michail S. Lionakis</name></author><author><name>Robert T. Wheeler</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Jendzjowsky</name></author><author><name>Marc Swidergall</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During infection the host relies on pattern-recognition receptors to sense invading fungal pathogens to launch immune defense mechanisms. While fungal recognition and immune effector responses are organ and cell type specific, during disseminated candidiasis myeloid cells exacerbate collateral tissue damage. However, the complex interplay between protective antifungal immunity and immunopathology remains incompletely understood. The β-glucan receptor ephrin type-A 2 receptor (EphA2) is required to initiate mucosal inflammatory responses during oral &lt;italic&gt;Candida&lt;/italic&gt; infection. Here we report that Epha2 promotes renal immunopathology during disseminated candidiasis. EphA2 deficiency leads to reduced renal inflammation and injury. Comprehensive analyses reveal that EphA2 limits IL-23 secretion in dendritic cells, while IL-23 signaling prevents ferroptotic myeloid cell death during infection. Further, ferroptosis aggravates inflammation during infection, while at the same time reducing the fungal killing capacity of macrophages. Thus, we identify ferroptotic cell death as a critical pathway of &lt;italic&gt;Candida-&lt;/italic&gt;mediated renal immunopathology that opens a new avenue to tackle &lt;italic&gt;Candida&lt;/italic&gt; infection and inflammation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473386" rel="alternate" title="IL-23 signaling prevents ferroptosis-driven renal immunopathology during candidiasis (7 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473954</id><title>MAVS mediates a protective immune response in the brain to Rift Valley fever virus (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.437635+00:00</updated><author><name>Dina R. Weilhammer</name></author><author><name>Nicholas R. Hum</name></author><author><name>Feliza A. Bourguet</name></author><author><name>Aimy Sebastian</name></author><author><name>Doris Lam</name></author><author><name>Ashlee M. Phillips</name></author><author><name>Kristina R. Sanchez</name></author><author><name>Amy Rasley</name></author><author><name>Gabriela G. Loots</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Rift Valley fever virus (RVFV) is a highly pathogenic mosquito-borne virus capable of causing hepatitis, encephalitis, blindness, hemorrhagic syndrome, and death in humans and livestock. Upon aerosol infection with RVFV, the brain is a major site of viral replication and tissue damage, yet pathogenesis in this organ has been understudied. Here, we investigated the immune response in the brain of RVFV infected mice. In response to infection, microglia initiate robust transcriptional upregulation of antiviral immune genes, as well as increased levels of activation markers and cytokine secretion that is dependent on mitochondrial antiviral-signaling protein (MAVS) and independent of toll-like receptors 3 and 7. In vivo, Mavs-/- mice displayed enhanced susceptibility to RVFV as determined by increased brain viral burden and higher mortality. Single-cell RNA sequence analysis identified microglia-specific defects in type I interferon and interferon responsive gene expression in Mavs-/- mice, as well as dysregulated lymphocyte infiltration. The results of this study provide a crucial step towards understanding the precise molecular mechanisms by which RVFV infection is controlled in the brain and will help inform the development of vaccines and antiviral therapies that are effective in preventing encephalitis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473954" rel="alternate" title="MAVS mediates a protective immune response in the brain to Rift Valley fever virus (7 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473623</id><title>Suicidal chemotaxis in bacteria (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.438065+00:00</updated><author><name>Nuno M. Oliveira</name></author><author><name>James H. R. Wheeler</name></author><author><name>Cyril Deroy</name></author><author><name>Sean C. Booth</name></author><author><name>Edmond J. Walsh</name></author><author><name>William M. Durham</name></author><author><name>Kevin R. Foster</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacteria commonly live in communities on surfaces where steep gradients of antibiotics and other chemical compounds routinely occur. While many species of bacteria can move on surfaces, we know surprisingly little about how such antibiotic gradients affect cell motility. Here we study the behaviour of the opportunistic pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; in stable spatial gradients of a range of antibiotics by tracking thousands of cells in microfluidic devices as they form biofilms. Unexpectedly, these experiments reveal that individual bacteria use pili-based (‘twitching’) motility to actively navigate towards regions with higher antibiotic concentrations. Our analyses suggest that this biased migration is driven, at least in part, by a direct response to the antibiotics. Migrating cells can reach antibiotic concentrations hundreds of times higher than their minimum inhibitory concentration in a few hours and remain highly motile. However, isolating these cells - using fluid-walled microfluidic devices that can be reconfigured in situ - suggests that these bacteria are terminal and not able to reproduce. In spite of moving towards their death, we show that migrating cells are capable of entering a suicidal program to release bacteriocins that are used to kill other bacteria. Our work suggests that bacteria respond to antibiotics as if they come from a competing colony growing in the neighbourhood, inducing them to invade and attack. As a result, clinical antibiotics have the potential to serve as a bait that lures bacteria to their death.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473623" rel="alternate" title="Suicidal chemotaxis in bacteria (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473675</id><title>Molecular features underlying Pseudomonas aeruginosa persistence in human plasma (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.438488+00:00</updated><author><name>Manon Janet-Maitre</name></author><author><name>Stéphane Pont</name></author><author><name>Frerich Masson</name></author><author><name>Julian Trouillon</name></author><author><name>Mylène Robert-Genthon</name></author><author><name>Chantal Dumestre-Perrard</name></author><author><name>Sylvie Elsen</name></author><author><name>Christine Moriscot</name></author><author><name>Bart Bardoel</name></author><author><name>Suzan Rooijakkers</name></author><author><name>François Cretin</name></author><author><name>Ina Attrée</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Persistence of bacterial pathogens is a main cause of treatment failure and establishment of chronic bacterial infection. &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt;, an opportunistic Gram-negative pathogen is a leading cause of bacteremia with high associated mortality. In a previous study, we found that plasma-sensitive &lt;italic&gt;P. aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; strains were able to form a persister-like sub-population named evaders. However, the molecular mechanisms underlying emergence and biology of evaders remained unknown. Here, using a gain-of-function genetic screen we examined the molecular determinants of persistence in plasma. In addition to known virulence factors (long O-specific antigens and exopolysaccharides), we found that ATP and biotin availability greatly impact bacterial survival in plasma. Mutants in genes of purine and biotin pathways display higher tolerance and persistence, respectively. Moreover, we identified a novel small protein named SrgA whose expression leads to 100-fold increase in survival in plasma. The analysis of different steps of complement activity and the use of outer-membrane impermeable drug nisin suggest that the mutants impede MAC activity &lt;italic&gt;per se&lt;/italic&gt;. Through this work we highlight the multifactorial origin of bacterial resilience to plasma and pave the way to a more comprehensive picture of the complex interplay between &lt;italic&gt;P. aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; and the complement system in the blood.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473675" rel="alternate" title="Molecular features underlying Pseudomonas aeruginosa persistence in human plasma (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473765</id><title>Plant growth promoting activity of bacteria isolated from Asian rice (Oryza sativa L.) are plant subspecies dependent (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.439075+00:00</updated><author><name>Nasim Maghboli Balasjin</name></author><author><name>James S. Maki</name></author><author><name>Michael R. Schläppi</name></author><author><name>Christopher W. Marshall</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Asian rice is one of the most important crops because it is a staple food for almost half of the world’s population. Rice has two subspecies, &lt;italic&gt;JAPONICA&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;INDICA&lt;/italic&gt;. To have production of rice keep pace with a growing world population, it is anticipated that the use of fertilizers will also need to increase, which may cause environmental damage through runoff impacts. An alternative strategy to increase crop yield is the use of plant growth promoting bacteria. Thousands of microbial species can exist in association with plant roots and shoots, and some are critical to the plant’s survival. We isolated 140 bacteria from rice and investigated whether &lt;italic&gt;JAPONICA&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;INDICA&lt;/italic&gt; rice subspecies were positively influenced by these isolates. The bacterial isolates were screened for their ability to solubilize phosphate, a known plant growth promoting characteristic, and 25 isolates were selected for further analysis. These 25 phosphate solubilizing isolates were also able to produce other potentially growth-promoting factors. Five of the most promising bacterial isolates were chosen for whole genome sequencing. Four of these bacteria, isolates related to &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas mosselii, Microvirga&lt;/italic&gt; sp., &lt;italic&gt;Paenibacillus rigui&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Paenibacillus graminis&lt;/italic&gt;, improved root and shoot growth, root to shoot ratio, and increased root dry weights of &lt;italic&gt;JAPONICA&lt;/italic&gt; plants but had no effect on growth and development of &lt;italic&gt;INDICA&lt;/italic&gt; plants. This indicates that while bacteria have several known plant growth promoting functions, their effects on growth parameters can be plant subspecies dependent and suggest close relationships between plants and their microbial partners.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473765" rel="alternate" title="Plant growth promoting activity of bacteria isolated from Asian rice (Oryza sativa L.) are plant subspecies dependent (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473556</id><title>Genomic diversity and biosynthetic capabilities of sponge-associated chlamydiae (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.439511+00:00</updated><author><name>Jennah E. Dharamshi</name></author><author><name>Natalia Gaarslev</name></author><author><name>Karin Steffen</name></author><author><name>Tom Martin</name></author><author><name>Detmer Sipkema</name></author><author><name>Thijs J. G. Ettema</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sponge microbiomes contribute to host health, nutrition, and defense through the production of secondary metabolites. Chlamydiae, a phylum of obligate intracellular bacteria ranging from animal pathogens to endosymbionts of microbial eukaryotes, are frequently found associated with sponges. However, sponge-associated chlamydial diversity has not yet been investigated at the genomic level and host-interactions remain thus far unexplored. Here, we sequenced the microbiomes of three sponge species and found high, though variable, Chlamydiae relative abundances of up to 21.2% of bacterial diversity. Using genome-resolved metagenomics 18 high-quality sponge-associated chlamydial genomes were reconstructed, covering four chlamydial families. Among these, Sorochlamydiaceae shares a common ancestor with Chlamydiaceae animal pathogens, suggesting long-term co-evolution with animals. Sponge-associated chlamydiae genomes mostly resembled environmental chlamydial endosymbionts, but not pathogens, and encoded genes for degrading diverse compounds associated with sponges, such as taurine. Unexpectedly, we identified widespread genetic potential for secondary metabolite biosynthesis across Chlamydiae, which may represent an explored reservoir of novel natural products. This finding suggests that chlamydiae may partake in defensive symbioses and that secondary metabolites play a wider role in mediating intracellular interactions. Furthermore, sponge-associated chlamydiae relatives were found in other marine invertebrates, pointing towards wider impacts of this phylum on marine ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473556" rel="alternate" title="Genomic diversity and biosynthetic capabilities of sponge-associated chlamydiae (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473518</id><title>GPR55 in B cells limits atherosclerosis development and regulates plasma cell maturation (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.439975+00:00</updated><author><name>Raquel Guillamat-Prats</name></author><author><name>Daniel Hering</name></author><author><name>Martina Rami</name></author><author><name>Carmen Härdtner</name></author><author><name>Donato Santovito</name></author><author><name>Petteri Rinne</name></author><author><name>Laura Bindila</name></author><author><name>Michael Hristov</name></author><author><name>Sabrina Pagano</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Vuilleumier</name></author><author><name>Sofie Schmid</name></author><author><name>Aleksandar Janjic</name></author><author><name>Wolfgang Enard</name></author><author><name>Christian Weber</name></author><author><name>Lars Maegdefessel</name></author><author><name>Alexander Faussner</name></author><author><name>Ingo Hilgendorf</name></author><author><name>Sabine Steffens</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Identifying novel pathways regulating the adaptive immune response in chronic inflammatory diseases such as atherosclerosis is of particular interest in view of developing new therapeutic drugs. Here we report that the lipid receptor GPR55 is highly expressed by splenic B cells and inversely correlates with atheroma plaque size in mice. In human carotid endarterectomy specimen, GPR55 transcript levels were significantly lower in unstable compared to stable carotid plaques. To study the impact of GPR55 deficiency in atherosclerosis, we crossed &lt;italic&gt;Gpr55&lt;/italic&gt; knockout mice with apolipoprotein E (&lt;italic&gt;ApoE&lt;/italic&gt;) knockout mice and subjected the mice to Western diet for 4 to 16 weeks. Compared to &lt;italic&gt;ApoE&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; controls, &lt;italic&gt;ApoE&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;Gpr55&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice developed larger plaques with increased necrotic core size, associated with elevated circulating and aortic leukocyte counts. Flow cytometry, immunofluorescence and RNA-sequencing analysis of splenic B cells in these mice revealed a hyperactivated B cell phenotype with disturbed plasma cell maturation and immunoglobulin (Ig)G antibody overproduction. The specific contribution of B cell GPR55 in atherosclerosis was further studied in mixed &lt;italic&gt;Gpr55&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt;/&lt;italic&gt;µMT&lt;/italic&gt; bone marrow chimeras on low density receptor deficiency (&lt;italic&gt;Ldlr&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt;) background, revealing that B-cell specific depletion of &lt;italic&gt;Gpr55&lt;/italic&gt; was sufficient to promote plaque development. Conversely, adoptive transfer of wildtype B cells into &lt;italic&gt;ApoE&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;Gpr55&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice blunted the proatherogenic phenotype. &lt;italic&gt;In vitro&lt;/italic&gt; stimulation of splenocytes with the endogenous GPR55 ligand LPI promoted plasma cell proliferation and enhanced B cell activation marker expression, which was inhibited by the GPR55 antagonist CID16020046. Collectively, these discoveries provide new evidence for GPR55 as key modulator of the adaptive immune response in atherosclerosis. Targeting GPR55 could be useful to limit inflammation and plaque progression in patients suffering from atherosclerosis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473518" rel="alternate" title="GPR55 in B cells limits atherosclerosis development and regulates plasma cell maturation (5 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473611</id><title>Molecular epidemiology of Animal African Trypanosomosis in southwest Burkina Faso (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.440688+00:00</updated><author><name>Robert Eustache Hounyèmè</name></author><author><name>Jacques Kaboré</name></author><author><name>Geoffrey Gimonneau</name></author><author><name>Martin Bienvenu Somda</name></author><author><name>Ernest Salou</name></author><author><name>Antoine Abel Missihoun</name></author><author><name>Zakaria Bengaly</name></author><author><name>Vincent Jamonneau</name></author><author><name>Alain Boulangé</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Animal African Trypanosomosis (AAT) is a parasitic disease of livestock that has a major socio-economic impact in the affected areas. It is caused by several species of uniflagellate extracellular protists of the genus &lt;italic&gt;Trypanosoma&lt;/italic&gt; mainly transmitted by tsetse flies: &lt;italic&gt;T. congolense, T. vivax&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;T. brucei brucei&lt;/italic&gt;. In Burkina Faso, AAT hampers the proper economic development of the southwestern part of the country, which is yet the best watered area particularly conducive to agriculture and animal production. It was therefore important to investigate the extend of the infection in order to better control the disease. The objective of the present study was to assess the prevalence of trypanosome infections and collect data on the presence of tsetse flies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Buffy coat, &lt;italic&gt;Trypanosoma&lt;/italic&gt; species-specific PCR, Indirect ELISA &lt;italic&gt;Trypanosoma sp&lt;/italic&gt; and trypanolysis techniques were used on 1898 samples collected. An entomological survey was also carried out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The parasitological prevalence of AAT was 1.1%, and all observed parasites were &lt;italic&gt;T. vivax&lt;/italic&gt;. In contrast, the molecular prevalence was 23%, of which &lt;italic&gt;T. vivax&lt;/italic&gt; was predominant (89%) followed by &lt;italic&gt;T. congolense&lt;/italic&gt; (12%) and &lt;italic&gt;T. brucei s.l&lt;/italic&gt;. (7.3%) with a sizable proportion as mixed infections (9.1%). &lt;italic&gt;T. brucei gambiense,&lt;/italic&gt; responsible of sleeping sickness in humans, was not detected. The serological prevalence reached 49%. Once again &lt;italic&gt;T. vivax&lt;/italic&gt; predominated (86.2%), but followed by &lt;italic&gt;T. brucei&lt;/italic&gt; (9.6%) and &lt;italic&gt;T. congolense&lt;/italic&gt; (4.2%), while 34.6% of positive samples tested positive for at least two trypanosome species. Seven samples, from six cattle and one pig, were found positive by trypanolysis. The density per trap of &lt;italic&gt;Glossina tachinoides&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;G. palpalis gambiensis&lt;/italic&gt; was about three flies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions/Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overall, our study showed a high prevalence of trypanosome infection in the area, pointing out an ongoing inadequacy of control measures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Authors summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Burkina Faso, like in most countries of sub-Saharan Africa, Animal African Trypanosomosis (AAT) is hampering economic development. It was therefore important to investigate the extent of trypanosome infections after years of control. This study examined circulating trypanosomes in domestic animals using parasitological, molecular and serological tools in southwest Burkina Faso. The prevalence levels observed show that the known epidemiological situation in the region has not really changed. The trypanosome species usually found in the area such as &lt;italic&gt;T. congolense, T. vivax&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;T. brucei s.l&lt;/italic&gt;. have remained the same, with a stronger presence of &lt;italic&gt;T. vivax&lt;/italic&gt;. The low occurrence of tsetse fly and the predominance of &lt;italic&gt;T. vivax&lt;/italic&gt; attests to the role of the mechanical vectors in maintaining the disease. Although no cases of &lt;italic&gt;T. brucei gambiense&lt;/italic&gt; infection was encountered in the animals examined, trypanolysis tests suggest that there are contact cases in this historical focus of sleeping sickness. Efforts are therefore necessary to reduce or even eliminate the trypanosome burden, and the data provided by this study can assist the decision making.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473611" rel="alternate" title="Molecular epidemiology of Animal African Trypanosomosis in southwest Burkina Faso (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473599</id><title>A role for CD4 helper cells in HIV control and progression (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.440982+00:00</updated><author><name>Igor M. Rouzine</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It remains unclear why HIV persists in most untreated individuals, and why a small minority of individuals can control the virus, either spontaneously or after an early treatment. The present work motivated by the striking differences in the functional avidity of CD4 T cells discovered between patient cohorts in a recent study [1] offers an experimentally–testable mathematical model that explains the diverse outcome of infection. The model predicts an arms race between viral dissemination and the proliferation of HIV-specific CD4 helper cells leading to one of two states: a low-viremia state or a high-viremia state. Helper CD4 cells with a higher avidity favor virus control. The parameter segregating spontaneous and post-treatment controllers is the infectivity asymmetry between activated and resting CD4 T cells. The predictions are found to be consistent with the data from [1] and with data on the avidity CD8 T cells [2]. I also analyze the alternative explanation of T cell exhaustion previously proposed to explain the diverse patient cohorts and demonstrate that it does not explain these and some other experimental data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why HIV persists in most untreated individuals, and why a minority can control the virus, either spontaneously or after short treatment, remains unknown. The present study offers a mathematical model of the immune response that explains the differences between the patient cohorts as a result of the arms race between viral dissemination and the proliferation of HIV-specific CD4 T cells. It offers testable predictions and personalized adjustment of early ART to a patient.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473599" rel="alternate" title="A role for CD4 helper cells in HIV control and progression (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473865</id><title>Copper Acts Synergistically with Fluconazole in Candida glabrata by Compromising Drug Efflux, Sterol Metabolism, and Zinc Homeostasis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.441146+00:00</updated><author><name>Ana Gaspar-Cordeiro</name></author><author><name>Catarina Amaral</name></author><author><name>Vania Pobre</name></author><author><name>Wilson Antunes</name></author><author><name>Ana Petronilho</name></author><author><name>Paulo Paixao</name></author><author><name>Antonio P. Alves de Matos</name></author><author><name>Catarina Pimentel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The synergistic combinations of drugs are promising strategies to boost the effectiveness of current antifungals and thus prevent the emergence of resistance. In this work, we show that copper and the antifungal fluconazole act synergistically against &lt;italic&gt;Candida glabrata&lt;/italic&gt;, an opportunistic pathogenic yeast intrinsically tolerant to fluconazole. Analyses of the transcriptomic profile of &lt;italic&gt;C. glabrata&lt;/italic&gt; after the combination of copper and fluconazole showed that the expression of the multidrug transporter gene &lt;italic&gt;CDR1&lt;/italic&gt; was decreased, suggesting that fluconazole efflux could be affected. In agreement, we observed that copper inhibits the transactivation of Pdr1, the transcription regulator of multidrug transporters, and leads to the intracellular accumulation of fluconazole. Copper also decreases the transcriptional induction of ergosterol biosynthesis (&lt;italic&gt;ERG&lt;/italic&gt;) genes by fluconazole, which culminates in the accumulation of toxic sterols. Co-treatment of cells with copper and fluconazole should affect the function of proteins located in the plasma membrane, as several ultrastructural alterations, including irregular cell wall and plasma membrane and loss of cell wall integrity, were observed. Finally, we show that the combination of copper and fluconazole downregulates the expression of the gene encoding the zinc-responsive transcription regulator Zap1, which possibly, together with the membrane transporters malfunction, generates zinc depletion. Supplementation with zinc reverts the toxic effect of combining copper with fluconazole, underscoring the importance of this metal in the observed synergistic effect. Overall, this work, while unveiling the molecular basis that supports the use of copper to enhance the effectiveness of fluconazole, paves the way for the development of new metal-based antifungal strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473865" rel="alternate" title="Copper Acts Synergistically with Fluconazole in Candida glabrata by Compromising Drug Efflux, Sterol Metabolism, and Zinc Homeostasis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473640</id><title>Biofilm matrix proteome of clinical strain of P. aeruginosa (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.441364+00:00</updated><author><name>Daria A. Egorova</name></author><author><name>Andrey A. Solovyev</name></author><author><name>Nikita B. Polyakov</name></author><author><name>Ksenya A. Danilova</name></author><author><name>Anastasya A. Scherbakova</name></author><author><name>Ivan N. Kravtsov</name></author><author><name>Maria A. Dmitrieva</name></author><author><name>Irina L. Tutykhina</name></author><author><name>Yulia M. Egorova</name></author><author><name>Alexander L. Gintsburg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Extracellular matrix plays a pivotal role in biofilm biology. Despite importance of matrix proteins as potential targets for development of antibacterial therapeutics little is known about matrix proteomes. While P. aeruginosa is one of the most important pathogens with emerging antibiotic resistance only few studies are devoted to matrix proteomes and there are no studies describing matrix proteome for any clinical isolates. As matrix responsible for some extracellular functions, it is expected that protein composition should be different in comparison with embedded in biofilm cells and this difference reflects possible active processes in matrix. Here we report the first matrix proteome for clinical isolate of P. aeruginosa in comparison with embedded cells. We have identified the largest number of proteins in matrix among all published studies. Ten proteins were unique for matrix and not present inside cells, but most of these proteins do not have well described function with respect to extracellular component of biofilm. Functional classification of enriched in matrix proteins resulted in several bioprocess groups of proteins. Top three groups were: oxidation-reduction processes, nucleoside metabolism and fatty acid synthesis. Finally, we discuss obtained data in prism of possible directions for antibiofilm therapeutic development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473640" rel="alternate" title="Biofilm matrix proteome of clinical strain of P. aeruginosa (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473593</id><title>Integrated metabolomic, molecular networking, and genome mining analyses uncover novel angucyclines from Streptomyces sp. RO-S4 strain isolated from Bejaia Bay, Algeria (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.441811+00:00</updated><author><name>Rima Ouchene</name></author><author><name>Didier Stien</name></author><author><name>Juliette Segret</name></author><author><name>Mouloud Kecha</name></author><author><name>Alice M. S. Rodrigues</name></author><author><name>Carole Veckerlé</name></author><author><name>Marcelino T. Suzuki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Multi-omic approaches have recently made big strides towards the effective exploration of microorganisms and accelerating the discovery of new bioactive compounds. We combined metabolomic, molecular networking, and genomic-based approaches to investigate the metabolic potential of the &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt; sp. RO-S4 strain isolated from the polluted waters of Bejaia Bay in Algeria. Antagonistic assays against &lt;italic&gt;methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/italic&gt; with RO-S4 organic extracts showed an inhibition zone of 20 mm by the agar diffusion method, and its minimum inhibitory concentration was 16 μg/mL. A molecular network was created using GNPS and annotated through the comparison of MS/MS spectra against several databases. The predominant compounds in the RO-S4 extract belonged to the angucyclines family. Three compounds were annotated as known metabolites, while all the others were putatively new to Science. Notably, all compounds had fridamycin-like aglycones, and several of them had a lactonized D ring analogous to that of urdamycin L. The whole genome of &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt; RO-S4 was sequenced to identify the biosynthetic gene cluster (BGC) encoding for these angucyclines, which yielded a draft genome of 7,497,846 bp with 72.4% G+C content. Subsequently, a genome mining analysis revealed 19 putative biosynthetic gene clusters, including a grincamycin-like BGC with a high similarity to that of &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt; sp. CZN-748 previously reported to also produce mostly open fridamycin-like aglycones. As the ring-opening process leading to these compounds is still not defined, we performed comparative analysis with other angucycline BGCs and advanced some hypotheses to explain the ring-opening and lactone formation, possibly linked to the uncoupling between the activity of GcnE and GcnM homologues in the RO-S4 strain. The combination of metabolomic and genomic approaches greatly improved the interpretation of the metabolic potential of the RO-S4 strain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473593" rel="alternate" title="Integrated metabolomic, molecular networking, and genome mining analyses uncover novel angucyclines from Streptomyces sp. RO-S4 strain isolated from Bejaia Bay, Algeria (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473610</id><title>Helminth infection modulates number and function of adipose tissue Tregs in high fat diet-induced obesity (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.442124+00:00</updated><author><name>Camila P. Queiroz-Glauss</name></author><author><name>Mariana S. Vieira</name></author><author><name>Marcela Helena Gonçalves-Pereira</name></author><author><name>Stephanie S. Almeida</name></author><author><name>Rachel H. Freire</name></author><author><name>Maria Aparecida Gomes</name></author><author><name>Jacqueline Isaura Alvarez-Leite</name></author><author><name>Helton C. Santiago</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Epidemiological and experimental studies have shown a protective effect of helminth infections in weight gain and against the development of metabolic dysfunctions in the host. However, the mechanisms induced by the parasite that regulate the development of metabolic diseases in the host are unclear. The present study aimed to verify the influence of &lt;italic&gt;Heligmosomoides polygyrus&lt;/italic&gt; infection in early stages of high fat diet-induced obesity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Principal Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The presence of infection was able to prevent exacerbated weight gain in mice fed with high fat diet when compared to non-infected controls. In addition, infected animals displayed improved insulin sensitivity and decreased fat accumulation in the liver. Obesity-associated inflammation was reduced in the presence of infection, demonstrated by higher levels of IL10 and adiponectin, increased infiltration of Th2 and eosinophils in adipose tissue of infected animals. Of note, the parasite infection was associated with increased Treg frequency in adipose tissue which showed higher expression of cell surface markers of function and activation, like LAP and CD134. The infection could also revert the loss of function in Tregs associated with high fat diet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;These data suggest that &lt;italic&gt;H. polygyrus&lt;/italic&gt; infection can prevent weight gain and metabolic syndrome in animals fed with high fat diet associated with modulations of adipose tissue Treg cells.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Helminth infections are known to modulate the immune system being responsible for protecting the host from developing allergic and autoimmune disorders (Hygiene Hypothesis). We hypothesized that the same immunomodulatory effect can have an impact on immunometabolic diseases, such as obesity and its linked diseases such as type 2 diabetes. Weight disorders have reached epidemic levels, nearly tripling since 1975 and being responsible for almost 5 million premature deaths each year. To test our hypothesis C57BL/6 male mice were fed control or high fat diet, for five weeks, in the presence or not of &lt;italic&gt;Heligmosomoides polygyrus&lt;/italic&gt; infection. Weight gain, development of metabolic disorders, inflammation and cellular migration to the adipose tissue were evaluated. In accordance with our hypothesis, we found that the presence of infection prevented the exacerbated weight gain and also improved metabolic parameters in animals fed a high fat diet. This was associated with the infection’s ability to modulate parameters of a cell responsible for regulatory functions: Tregs. In the light of these findings, helminth infection could be protective against weight gain and metabolic disturbances.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473610" rel="alternate" title="Helminth infection modulates number and function of adipose tissue Tregs in high fat diet-induced obesity (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473605</id><title>5-aminolevulinic acid-photodynamic therapy ameliorates cutaneous granuloma by killing drug-resistant Mycobacterium marinum (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.442455+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhiya Yang</name></author><author><name>Yahui Feng</name></author><author><name>Zhiping Pang</name></author><author><name>Dongmei Li</name></author><author><name>Sisi Wang</name></author><author><name>Huiqi Chen</name></author><author><name>Mingze Jiang</name></author><author><name>Hongxia Yan</name></author><author><name>Tianhang Li</name></author><author><name>Hongjun Fu</name></author><author><name>Hubao Xiong</name></author><author><name>Dongmei Shi</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although 5-aminolevulinic acid photodynamic therapy (ALA-PDT) has been extensively used to treat to various skin disease, the application of ALA-PDT on cutaneous infection caused by &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium marinum&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;M. marinum&lt;/italic&gt;), especially by drug-resistant &lt;italic&gt;M. marinum&lt;/italic&gt; is still not clear.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We evaluated the therapeutic efficacy of ALA-PDT on &lt;italic&gt;M. marinum in a&lt;/italic&gt; mouse infection model and tested its killing effect on &lt;italic&gt;M. marinum in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. Finally, we investigated the clinical effect of ALA-PDT in treating cutaneous granuloma caused by drug-resistant &lt;italic&gt;M. marinum&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Materials and methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We isolated total 9 strains of &lt;italic&gt;M. marinum&lt;/italic&gt; from patients and confirmed by morphological and molecular approaches. The strains were identified by anti-mycobacterial susceptibility. Then we evaluated the killing effect of ALA-PDT on &lt;italic&gt;M. marinum in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and in a mouse model to observe the antimycobacterial effect of ALA-PDT. Therapeutic efficacy was further assessed in patients with cutaneous granuloma caused by drug-resistant &lt;italic&gt;M. marinum&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We demonstrated that the ALA-PDT directly killed &lt;italic&gt;M. marinum in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. The paws cutaneous lesions of mice caused by &lt;italic&gt;M. marinum&lt;/italic&gt; were fully recovered 2 weeks after ALA-PDT treatment. However, there was no significant difference for immune cells in peripheral blood before and after ALA-PDT therapy. Finally, ALA-PDT proved to be effective in treat two patients with cutaneous infection caused by drug-resistant &lt;italic&gt;M. marinum&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The results suggest that ALA-PDT is effective in treating &lt;italic&gt;M. marinum&lt;/italic&gt; cutaneous infections by killing &lt;italic&gt;M. marinum&lt;/italic&gt; directly, independent of systemic immune responses. The data highlight the ALA-PDT as a promising therapeutic choice for &lt;italic&gt;M. marinum&lt;/italic&gt; infection, especially for drug-resistant strains.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473605" rel="alternate" title="5-aminolevulinic acid-photodynamic therapy ameliorates cutaneous granuloma by killing drug-resistant Mycobacterium marinum (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>