<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.400401+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445533</id><title>Cellular heterogeneity in DNA alkylation repair as a trade-off between cell survival and genetic plasticity (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.401031+00:00</updated><author><name>Maxence S. Vincent</name></author><author><name>Stephan Uphoff</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;DNA repair mechanisms fulfil a dual role, as they are essential for cell survival and genome maintenance. Here, we studied how cells regulate the interplay between DNA repair and mutation. We focused on the &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; adaptive response that increases resistance to DNA alkylation damage. Combination of single-molecule imaging and microfluidic-based single-cell microscopy showed that noise in the gene activation timing of the master regulator Ada is accurately propagated to generate a distinct subpopulation of cells in which all proteins of the adaptive response are absent. Although lack of these proteins causes extreme sensitivity to alkylation stress, cellular heterogeneity in DNA alkylation repair provides a functional benefit by increasing the evolvability of the whole population. We demonstrated this by monitoring the dynamics of nascent mutations during alkylation stress as well as the frequency of fixed mutations that are generated by the distinct subpopulations of the adaptive response. This highlighted that evolvability is a trade-off between mutability and cell survival. Stochastic modulation of DNA repair capacity by the adaptive response solves this trade-off through the generation of a viable hypermutable subpopulation of cells that acts as a source of genetic diversity in a clonal population.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445533" rel="alternate" title="Cellular heterogeneity in DNA alkylation repair as a trade-off between cell survival and genetic plasticity (29 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445430</id><title>The gut bacterial natural product colibactin triggers induction of latent viruses in diverse bacteria (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.401648+00:00</updated><author><name>Justin E. Silpe</name></author><author><name>Joel W. H. Wong</name></author><author><name>Siân V. Owen</name></author><author><name>Michael Baym</name></author><author><name>Emily P. Balskus</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Colibactin is a chemically unstable small molecule genotoxin produced by multiple different bacteria, including members of the human gut microbiome.&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt; While the biological activity of colibactin has been extensively investigated in mammalian systems,&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; little is known about its effects on other microorganisms. Here, we discover that colibactin targets bacteria carrying prophages, inducing lytic development via the bacterial SOS response. DNA, added exogenously, protects bacteria from colibactin, as does expressing a colibactin resistance protein (ClbS) in non-colibactin-producing cells. The prophage-inducing effects we observe apply broadly across taxonomically diverse phage-bacteria systems. Finally, we identify bacteria that possess colibactin resistance genes but lack colibactin biosynthetic genes. Many of these bacteria are infected with predicted prophages, and we show that the expression of their ClbS homologs provides immunity from colibactin-triggered induction. Our study reveals a mechanism by which colibactin production could impact microbiomes and highlights an underappreciated role for microbial natural products in influencing population-level events such as phage outbreaks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445430" rel="alternate" title="The gut bacterial natural product colibactin triggers induction of latent viruses in diverse bacteria (21 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.27.445954</id><title>Abiotic factors modulate interspecies competition mediated by the type VI secretion system effectors in Vibrio cholerae (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.402220+00:00</updated><author><name>Ming-Xuan Tang</name></author><author><name>Tong-Tong Pei</name></author><author><name>Zeng-Hang Wang</name></author><author><name>Han Luo</name></author><author><name>Xing-Yu Wang</name></author><author><name>Tao G. Dong</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Vibrio cholerae&lt;/italic&gt;, the etiological pathogen of cholera, relies on its type VI secretion system (T6SS) as an effective weapon to survive in highly competitive communities. The anti-bacterial and anti-eukaryotic functions of T6SS depend on its secreted effectors that target multiple essential cellular processes. However, the mechanisms that account for effector diversity and different effectiveness during interspecies competition remain elusive. Here, we report that environmental cations and temperature play a key role in dictating effector-mediated competition of &lt;italic&gt;Vibrio cholerae&lt;/italic&gt;. We found that &lt;italic&gt;V. cholerae&lt;/italic&gt; could employ its cell-wall-targeting effector TseH to outcompete the otherwise resistant &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; and the &lt;italic&gt;V. cholerae&lt;/italic&gt; immunity deletion mutant &lt;italic&gt;ΔtsiH&lt;/italic&gt; when Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; and Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; were supplemented. The &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; Δ&lt;italic&gt;phoQ&lt;/italic&gt; mutant was more sensitive to TseH-mediated killing during competition, suggesting the metal-sensing PhoPQ two-component system is protective to &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; from TseH activity. Using transcriptome analysis, we found multiple stress response systems, including acid stress response, oxidative stress response, and osmotic stress response, were activated in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; expressing TseH in comparison with &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; expressing the inactive mutant TseH&lt;sup&gt;H64A&lt;/sup&gt;. The membrane-targeting lipase effector TseL also exhibited reduced killing against &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; when divalent cations were removed. In addition, competition analysis of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; with &lt;italic&gt;V. cholerae&lt;/italic&gt; single-effector active strains reveals a temperature-dependent susceptibility of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; to effectors, VasX, VgrG3, and TseL. These findings suggest that abiotic factors, that &lt;italic&gt;V. cholerae&lt;/italic&gt; frequently encounters in natural habitats, play a crucial role in dictating the competitive fitness conferred by the type VI secretion system in complex multispecies communities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.27.445954" rel="alternate" title="Abiotic factors modulate interspecies competition mediated by the type VI secretion system effectors in Vibrio cholerae (13 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445453</id><title>Selection for cell yield does not reduce overflow metabolism in E. coli (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.402699+00:00</updated><author><name>Iraes Rabbers</name></author><author><name>Willi Gottstein</name></author><author><name>Adam Feist</name></author><author><name>Bas Teusink</name></author><author><name>Frank J. Bruggeman</name></author><author><name>Herwig Bachmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Overflow metabolism is ubiquitous in nature, and it is often considered inefficient because it leads to a relatively low biomass yield per consumed carbon. This metabolic strategy has been described as advantageous because it supports high growth rates during nutrient competition.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we experimentally evolved bacteria without nutrient competition by repeatedly growing and mixing millions of parallel batch cultures of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;. Each culture originated from a water-in-oil emulsion droplet seeded with a single cell. Unexpectedly we found that overflow metabolism (acetate production) did not change. Instead the numerical cell yield during the consumption of the accumulated acetate increased as a consequence of a reduction in cell size. Our experiments and a mathematical model show that fast growth and overflow metabolism followed by the consumption of the overflow metabolite, leads to a higher numerical cell yield and therefore a higher fitness compared to full respiration of the substrate. This provides an evolutionary scenario where overflow metabolism can be favourable even in the absence of nutrient competition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445453" rel="alternate" title="Selection for cell yield does not reduce overflow metabolism in E. coli (13 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.26.445777</id><title>Complex structure of the Bacillus subtilis CdaA c-di-AMP cyclase domain and the phosphoglucomutase GlmM (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.403235+00:00</updated><author><name>Monisha Pathania</name></author><author><name>Tommaso Tosi</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Millership</name></author><author><name>Fumiya Hoshiga</name></author><author><name>Rhodri M. L. Morgan</name></author><author><name>Paul S. Freemont</name></author><author><name>Angelika Gründling</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cyclic-di-adenosine monophosphate (c-di-AMP) is an important nucleotide signalling molecule, which plays a key role in osmotic regulation in bacteria. Cellular c-di-AMP levels are tightly regulated, as both high and low levels have a negative impact on bacterial growth. Here, we investigated how the activity of the main &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; c-di-AMP cyclase CdaA is regulated by the phosphoglucomutase GlmM. c-di-AMP is produced from two molecules of ATP by proteins containing a deadenylate cyclase (DAC) domain. CdaA is a membrane-linked cyclase with an N-terminal transmembrane domain followed by the cytoplasmic DAC domain. Here we show, using the soluble catalytic &lt;italic&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; CdaA&lt;sub&gt;CD&lt;/sub&gt; domain and purified full-length GlmM or the GlmM&lt;sub&gt;F369&lt;/sub&gt; variant lacking the C-terminal flexible domain 4, that the cyclase and phosphoglucomutase form a stable complex &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and that GlmM is a potent cyclase inhibitor. We determined the crystal structure of the individual &lt;italic&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; CdaA&lt;sub&gt;CD&lt;/sub&gt; and GlmM proteins, both of which form dimers in the structures, and of the CdaA&lt;sub&gt;CD&lt;/sub&gt;:GlmM&lt;sub&gt;F369&lt;/sub&gt; complex. In the complex structure, a CdaA&lt;sub&gt;CD&lt;/sub&gt; dimer is bound to a GlmM&lt;sub&gt;F369&lt;/sub&gt; dimer in such a manner that GlmM blocks the oligomerization of CdaA&lt;sub&gt;CD&lt;/sub&gt; and formation of active head-to-head cyclase oligomers, thus providing molecular details on how GlmM acts as cyclase inhibitor. The function of a key amino acid residue in CdaA&lt;sub&gt;CD&lt;/sub&gt; in complex formation was confirmed by mutagenesis analysis. As the amino acids at the CdaA&lt;sub&gt;CD&lt;/sub&gt;:GlmM interphase are conserved, we propose that the observed inhibition mechanism of CdaA by GlmM is conserved among Firmicutes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.26.445777" rel="alternate" title="Complex structure of the Bacillus subtilis CdaA c-di-AMP cyclase domain and the phosphoglucomutase GlmM (8 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445395</id><title>Standard Sample Storage Conditions Impact on Inferred Microbiome Composition and Antimicrobial Resistance Patterns (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.403687+00:00</updated><author><name>Casper Sahl Poulsen</name></author><author><name>Rolf Sommer Kaas</name></author><author><name>Frank M. Aarestrup</name></author><author><name>Sünje Johanna Pamp</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Storage of biological specimens is crucial in the life and medical sciences. The storage conditions for samples can be different for a number of reasons, and it is unclear which effect this can have on the inferred microbiome composition in metagenomics analyses. Here, we assess the effect of common storage temperatures (deep freezer: -80°C, freezer: -20°C, fridge: 5°C, room temperature: 22°C) and storage times, (immediate sample processing: 0h, next day: 16h, over weekend: 64h, and longer term: 4, 8, 12 months), as well as repeated sample freezing and thawing (2-4 freeze-thaw cycles). We examine two different pig feces and sewage samples, unspiked and spiked with a mock community, and in triplicates, respectively, amounting to a total of 438 samples (777 Gbp; 5.1 billion reads). Storage conditions had a significant and systematic effect on the taxonomic and functional composition of microbiomes. Distinct microbial taxa and antimicrobial resistance classes were in some situations similarly effected across samples, while others were not, suggesting an impact of individual inherent sample characteristics. With an increasing number of freeze-thaw cycles, an increasing abundance of Firmicutes, Actinobacteria, and eukaryotic microorganisms was observed. We include recommendations for sample storage, and strongly suggest including more detailed information in the metadata together with the DNA sequencing data in public repositories to better facilitate meta-analyses and reproducibility of findings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previous research has reported effects of DNA isolation, library preparation, and sequencing technology on metagenomics-based microbiome composition; however, the effect of biospecimen storage conditions has not been thoroughly assessed. We examined the effect of common sample storage conditions on metagenomics-based microbiome composition and find significant and, in part, systematic effects. Repeated freeze-thaw cycles could be used to improve the detection of microorganisms with more rigid cell walls, including parasites. We provide a dataset that could also be used for benchmarking algorithms to identify and correct for batch effects. Overall, the findings suggest that all samples of a microbiome study should be stored in the same way. Furthermore, there is a need to mandate more detailed information about sample storage and processing published together with the DNA sequencing data at INSDC (ENA/EBI, NCBI, DDBJ) or other repositories.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445395" rel="alternate" title="Standard Sample Storage Conditions Impact on Inferred Microbiome Composition and Antimicrobial Resistance Patterns (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445377</id><title>The mechanism underlying the organization of Borna disease virus inclusion bodies is unique among mononegaviruses (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.404205+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuya Hirai</name></author><author><name>Keizo Tomonaga</name></author><author><name>Masayuki Horie</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Inclusion bodies (IBs) are characteristic biomolecular condensates organized by mononegaviruses. Here, we characterize the IBs of Borna disease virus 1 (BoDV-1), a unique mononegavirus that forms IBs in the nucleus, in terms of liquid-liquid phase separation (LLPS). The BoDV-1 phosphoprotein (P) alone induces LLPS and the nucleoprotein (N) is incorporated into the P droplet &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. In contrast, co-expression of N and P is required for the formation of IB-like structure in cells. Furthermore, while BoDV-1 P binds to RNA, an excess amount of RNA dissolves the liquid droplets formed by N and P. Notably, the N-terminal intrinsically disordered region of BoDV-1 P is essential to drive LLPS and bind to RNA, suggesting that both abilities could compete with one another. These features are unique among mononegaviruses, and thus this study will contribute to a deeper understanding of LLPS-driven organization and RNA-mediated regulation of biomolecular condensates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445377" rel="alternate" title="The mechanism underlying the organization of Borna disease virus inclusion bodies is unique among mononegaviruses (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445428</id><title>Sex matters: effects of sex and mating in the presence and absence of a protective microbe (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.404672+00:00</updated><author><name>Anke Kloock</name></author><author><name>Lena Peters</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Rafaluk-Mohr</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In most animals, female investment in offspring production is greater than for males. Lifetime reproductive success (LRS) is predicted to be optimised in females through extended lifespans to maximise reproductive events. Extended lifespan can be achieved through increased investment in immunity. Males, however, maximise lifetime reproductive success by obtaining as many matings as possible. Microbe-mediated protection (MMP) is known to affect both immunity and reproduction, but whether the two sexes respond differently to the provision of MMP remains to be explored. Here, we investigated the sex-specific differences in host life history traits between female and male &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/italic&gt; following pathogenic infection with &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/italic&gt; with or without MMP by &lt;italic&gt;Enterococcus faecalis&lt;/italic&gt;. Overall, female survival decreased with increased mating. With MMP, females increased investment into offspring production, while males displayed higher behavioural activity. These results highlight the different strategies employed by the two sexes under pathogen infection with and without MMP.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445428" rel="alternate" title="Sex matters: effects of sex and mating in the presence and absence of a protective microbe (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.23.445362</id><title>A defined medium based on R2A for cultivation and exometabolite profiling of soil bacteria (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.405023+00:00</updated><author><name>Markus de Raad</name></author><author><name>Yifan Li</name></author><author><name>Peter Andeer</name></author><author><name>Suzanne M. Kosina</name></author><author><name>Nicholas R. Saichek</name></author><author><name>Amber Golini</name></author><author><name>La Zhen Han</name></author><author><name>Ying Wang</name></author><author><name>Benjamin P. Bowen</name></author><author><name>Romy Chakraborty</name></author><author><name>Trent R. Northen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Exometabolomics is an approach to assess how microorganisms alter their environments through the depletion and secretion of chemical compounds. Comparisons of inoculated with uninoculated media can be used to provide direct biochemical observations on depleted and secreted metabolites which can be used to predict resource competition, cross-feeding and secondary metabolite production in microbial isolates and communities. This approach is most powerful when used with defined media that enable tracking of all depleted metabolites. However, microbial growth media have traditionally been developed for the isolation and growth of microorganisms but not metabolite utilization profiling through LC-MS/MS. Here, we describe the construction of a defined medium, the Northen Lab Defined Medium (NLDM), that not only supports the growth of diverse bacteria but is defined and therefore suited for exometabolomic experiments. Metabolites included in NLDM were selected based on their presence in R2A medium and soil, elemental stoichiometry requirements, as well as knowledge of metabolite usage by different bacteria. We found that NLDM supported the growth of 53 phylogenetically diverse soil bacterial isolates and all of its metabolites were trackable through LC–MS/MS analysis. These results demonstrate the viability and utility of the constructed NLDM medium for cultivating and characterizing diverse microbial isolates and communities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Originality-Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We build a defined medium based on the metabolite composition of R2A medium and soil, elemental stoichiometry requirements, and knowledge of metabolite usage by different bacteria. The newly formulated defined medium was evaluated on its ability to support the growth of soil isolates and its application for metabolite utilization profiling. We found that of 53 phylogenetically diverse soil bacterial isolates grew on the defined medium and all of its metabolites were trackable through LC–MS/MS analysis. This demonstrates the viability and utility of the constructed defined medium for cultivating and characterizing diverse microbial isolates and communities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.23.445362" rel="alternate" title="A defined medium based on R2A for cultivation and exometabolite profiling of soil bacteria (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>