<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.945945+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468384</id><title>Phage-encoded sigma factors alter bacterial dormancy (53 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.946902+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel A Schwartz</name></author><author><name>Brent K Lehmkuhl</name></author><author><name>Jay T Lennon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;By entering a reversible state of reduced metabolic activity, dormant microorganisms are able to tolerate suboptimal conditions that would otherwise reduce their fitness. Dormancy may also benefit bacteria by serving as a refuge from parasitic infections. Here we focus on dormancy in the Firmicutes, where endospore development is transcriptionally regulated by the expression of sigma factors. A disruption of this process could influence the survivorship and reproduction of phages that infect spore-forming hosts with implications for coevolutionary dynamics. Here, we characterized the distribution and diversity of sigma factors in nearly 3,500 phage genomes. Homologs of sporulation-specific sigma factors were identified in phages that infect spore-forming hosts. Unlike sigma factors required for phage reproduction, the sporulation-like sigma factors were non-essential for lytic infection. However, when expressed in the spore-forming Bacillus subtilis, sigma factors from phages activated the bacterial sporulation gene network and reduced spore yield. Our findings suggest that the acquisition of host-like transcriptional regulators may allow phages to manipulate a complex and ancient trait in one of the most abundant cell types on Earth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468384" rel="alternate" title="Phage-encoded sigma factors alter bacterial dormancy (53 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.06.467345</id><title>Recurrent urinary tract infection and estrogen shape the taxonomic ecology and functional potential of the postmenopausal urobiome (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.947117+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael L. Neugent</name></author><author><name>Ashwani Kumar</name></author><author><name>Neha V. Hulyalkar</name></author><author><name>Kevin C. Lutz</name></author><author><name>Vivian H. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Jorge L. Fuentes</name></author><author><name>Cong Zhang</name></author><author><name>Amber Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Belle M. Sharon</name></author><author><name>Amy Kuprasertkul</name></author><author><name>Amanda P. Arute</name></author><author><name>Qiwei Li</name></author><author><name>Chao Xing</name></author><author><name>Vladimir Shulaev</name></author><author><name>Philippe E. Zimmern</name></author><author><name>Kelli L. Palmer</name></author><author><name>Nicole J. De Nisco</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Community-acquired urinary tract infection (UTI) is among the most common bacterial infections observed in humans. Postmenopausal women are a rapidly growing and underserved demographic group who are severely affected by rUTI with a &amp;gt;50% recurrence rate. In this population, rUTI can persist for years, reducing quality of life and imposing a significant healthcare burden. rUTI is most often treated by long-term antibiotic therapy, but development of antibiotic resistance and allergy leave physicians with fewer treatment options. The female urobiome has been identified as a key component of the urogenital environment. However, structural and functional changes in the urobiome underlying rUTI susceptibility in postmenopausal women are not well understood. Here, we used strictly curated, controlled cross-sectional human cohorts of postmenopausal women, urobiome whole genome (shotgun) metagenomic sequencing (WGMS), advanced urine culturing techniques, extensive biobanking of &amp;gt;900 patient-derived urinary bacterial and fungal isolates, and mass spectrometry-based estrogen profiling to survey the urobiome in rUTI patients during infection relapse and remission as well as healthy comparators with no lifetime history of UTI. Our results suggest that a history of rUTI strongly shapes the taxonomic and functional ecology of the urobiome. We also find a putative protective commensal population, consisting of species known to convey protection against bacterial vaginosis such as &lt;italic&gt;Lactobacillus crispatus&lt;/italic&gt;, within the urobiome of women who do not experience UTI. Integration of clinical metadata detected an almost exclusive enrichment of putative protective species belonging to the genus, &lt;italic&gt;Lactobacillus&lt;/italic&gt;, in women taking estrogen hormone therapy (EHT). We further show that the urobiome taxonomic ecology is shaped by EHT, with strong enrichments of putatively protective lactobacilli, such as &lt;italic&gt;L. crispatu&lt;/italic&gt;s and &lt;italic&gt;L. vaginalis&lt;/italic&gt;. Integrating quantitative metabolite profiling of urinary estrogens with WGMS, we observed robust associations between urobiome taxa, such as &lt;italic&gt;Bifidobacterium breve&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;L. crispatus&lt;/italic&gt;, and urinary estrogen conjugate concentrations, suggesting that EHT strongly alters the taxonomic composition of the female urobiome. We have further used functional metagenomic profiling and patient-derived isolate phenotyping to identify microbial metabolic pathways, antimicrobial resistance genes (ARGs), and clinically relevant antimicrobial resistance phenotypes enriched between disease-states. Our data suggest distinct metabolic and ARG signatures of the urobiome associated with current rUTI status and history. Taken together, our data suggests that rUTI history and estrogen use strongly shape the functional and taxonomic composition of the urobiome in postmenopausal women.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.06.467345" rel="alternate" title="Recurrent urinary tract infection and estrogen shape the taxonomic ecology and functional potential of the postmenopausal urobiome (23 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468108</id><title>tRNA anticodon cleavage by target-activated CRISPR-Cas13a effector (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.947368+00:00</updated><author><name>Ishita Jain</name></author><author><name>Matvey Kolesnik</name></author><author><name>Leonid Minakhin</name></author><author><name>Natalia Morozova</name></author><author><name>Anna Shiriaeva</name></author><author><name>Alexandr Kirillov</name></author><author><name>Sofia Medvedeva</name></author><author><name>Konstantin Kuznedelov</name></author><author><name>Sergei Borukhov</name></author><author><name>Kira S. Makarova</name></author><author><name>Eugene V. Koonin</name></author><author><name>Konstantin Severinov</name></author><author><name>Ekaterina Semenova</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Type VI CRISPR-Cas systems are the only CRISPR variety that cleaves exclusively RNA&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt;. In addition to the CRISPR RNA (crRNA)-guided, sequence-specific binding and cleavage of target RNAs, such as phage transcripts, the type VI effector, Cas13, causes collateral RNA cleavage, which induces bacterial cell dormancy, thus protecting the host population from phage spread&lt;sup&gt;3,4&lt;/sup&gt;. We show here that the principal form of collateral RNA degradation elicited by Cas13a protein from &lt;italic&gt;Leptotrichia shahii&lt;/italic&gt; upon target RNA recognition is the cleavage of anticodons of multiple tRNA species, primarily those with anticodons containing uridines. This tRNA cleavage is necessary and sufficient for bacterial dormancy induction by Cas13a. In addition, Cas13a activates the RNases of bacterial toxin-antitoxin modules, thus indirectly causing mRNA and rRNA cleavage, which could provide a back-up defense mechanism. The identified mode of action of Cas13a resembles that of bacterial anticodon nucleases involved in antiphage defense&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;, which is compatible with the hypothesis that type VI effectors evolved from an abortive infection module&lt;sup&gt;6,7&lt;/sup&gt; encompassing an anticodon nuclease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468108" rel="alternate" title="tRNA anticodon cleavage by target-activated CRISPR-Cas13a effector (22 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467819</id><title>Spatial relationships of intra-lesion heterogeneity in Mycobacterium tuberculosis microenvironment, replication status, and drug efficacy (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.947566+00:00</updated><author><name>Richard C. Lavin</name></author><author><name>Shumin Tan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A hallmark of &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; (Mtb) infection with critical impact on disease development and outcome is the marked heterogeneity that exists, spanning differences in lesion types to changes in microenvironment as the infection progresses&lt;sup&gt;1–7&lt;/sup&gt;. A mechanistic understanding of how this heterogeneity affects Mtb growth and treatment efficacy necessitates single bacterium-level studies in the context of intact host tissue architecture; however, such an evaluation has been technically challenging. Here, we exploit fluorescent reporter Mtb strains and the C3HeB/FeJ murine model in an integrated imaging approach to study microenvironment heterogeneity within a single lesion &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt;, and analyze how these differences relate to non-uniformity in Mtb replication state, activity, and drug efficacy. We show that the pH and chloride environments differ spatially in a caseous necrotic lesion, with increased acidity and chloride levels in the lesion cuff versus the necrotic core. Conversely, a higher percentage of Mtb in the necrotic core versus the lesion cuff were in an actively replicating state, and correspondingly active in transcription and translation. Finally, examination of three first-line anti-tubercular drugs showed that efficacy of isoniazid was strikingly poor against bacteria in the lesion cuff. Our study reveals spatial relationships of intra-lesion heterogeneity, sheds light on important considerations in the development of anti-tubercular treatment strategies, and establishes a foundational framework for Mtb infection heterogeneity analysis at the single cell level &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467819" rel="alternate" title="Spatial relationships of intra-lesion heterogeneity in Mycobacterium tuberculosis microenvironment, replication status, and drug efficacy (19 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.467495</id><title>Regulatory T cells suppress the formation of super-effector CD8 T cells by limiting IL-2 (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.947688+00:00</updated><author><name>Oksana Tsyklauri</name></author><author><name>Tereza Chadimova</name></author><author><name>Veronika Niederlova</name></author><author><name>Jirina Kovarova</name></author><author><name>Juraj Michalik</name></author><author><name>Iva Malatova</name></author><author><name>Sarka Janusova</name></author><author><name>Helene Rossez</name></author><author><name>Ales Drobek</name></author><author><name>Hana Vecerova</name></author><author><name>Virginie Galati</name></author><author><name>Marek Kovar</name></author><author><name>Ondrej Stepanek</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Regulatory T cells (Tregs) are indispensable for maintaining self-tolerance by suppressing conventional T cells. On the other hand, Tregs may promote tumor growth by inhibiting anti-cancer immunity. In this study, we identified that Tregs increase the quorum of self-reactive CD8+ T cells required for the induction of experimental autoimmune diabetes. Their major suppression mechanism is limiting available IL-2, a key cytokine for activated T cells. Specifically, Tregs inhibit the formation of a previously uncharacterized subset of antigen-stimulated CD8+ T cells. Since these T cells express high levels of IL-7 receptor and cytotoxic molecules (KLRK1, GZMB), and show superior cell killing abilities, we call them super-effector T cells. The administration of agonistic IL-2 immunocomplexes phenocopies the absence of Tregs, i.e., it induces super-effector T cells, promotes autoimmunity, and enhances anti-tumor responses. Counterparts of super-effector T cells were found in the human blood, revealing them as a potential target for immunotherapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.467495" rel="alternate" title="Regulatory T cells suppress the formation of super-effector CD8 T cells by limiting IL-2 (17 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.468512</id><title>Aerobic Bacteria Produce Nitric Oxide via Denitrification and Trigger Algal Population Collapse (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.947884+00:00</updated><author><name>Adi Abada</name></author><author><name>Martin Sperfeld</name></author><author><name>Raanan Carmieli</name></author><author><name>Shifra Ben-Dor</name></author><author><name>Irene Huang Zhang</name></author><author><name>Andrew R Babbin</name></author><author><name>Einat Segev</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microbial interactions govern marine biogeochemistry. These interactions are generally considered to rely on exchange of organic molecules. Here we report on a novel inorganic route of microbial communication, showing that algal-bacterial interactions are mediated through inorganic nitrogen exchange. Under oxygen-rich conditions, aerobic bacteria reduce algal-secreted nitrite to nitric oxide (NO) through denitrification, a well-studied anaerobic respiration mechanism. Bacteria secrete NO, triggering a cascade in algae akin to programmed cell death. During death, algae further generate NO, thereby propagating the signal in the algal population. Eventually, the algal population collapses, similar to the sudden demise of oceanic algal blooms. Our study suggests that the exchange of denitrification intermediates, particularly in oxygenated environments, is an overlooked yet ecologically significant route of microbial communication within and across kingdoms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.468512" rel="alternate" title="Aerobic Bacteria Produce Nitric Oxide via Denitrification and Trigger Algal Population Collapse (17 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468272</id><title>PHGDH is required for germinal center formation and is a therapeutic target in MYC-driven lymphoma (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.948032+00:00</updated><author><name>Annalisa D'Avola</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Legrave</name></author><author><name>Mylene Tajan</name></author><author><name>Probir Chakravarty</name></author><author><name>Ryan Shearer</name></author><author><name>Hamish King</name></author><author><name>Eric Cheung</name></author><author><name>Andrew Clear</name></author><author><name>Arief Gunawan</name></author><author><name>Lingling Zhang</name></author><author><name>Louisa James</name></author><author><name>James MacRae</name></author><author><name>John Gribben</name></author><author><name>Dinis Calado</name></author><author><name>Karen Vousden</name></author><author><name>John Riches</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The synthesis of serine from glucose is a key metabolic pathway supporting cellular proliferation in healthy and malignant cells. Despite this, the role that this aspect of metabolism plays in germinal center biology and pathology is not known. Here, we performed a comprehensive characterization of the role of the serine synthesis pathway in germinal center B cells and lymphomas derived from these cells. We demonstrate that upregulation of a functional serine synthesis pathway is a metabolic hallmark of B-cell activation and the germinal center reaction. Inhibition of phosphoglycerate dehydrogenase (PHGDH), the first and rate limiting enzyme in this pathway, leads to defective germinal formation and impaired high-affinity antibody production. In addition, overexpression of enzymes involved in serine synthesis is a characteristic of germinal center B-cell derived lymphomas, with high levels of expression being predictive of reduced overall survival in diffuse large B cell lymphoma. Inhibition of PHGDH induces apoptosis in lymphoma cells reducing disease progression. These findings establish PHGDH as a critical player in humoral immunity and a clinically relevant target in lymphoma.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468272" rel="alternate" title="PHGDH is required for germinal center formation and is a therapeutic target in MYC-driven lymphoma (15 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467952</id><title>Salmonella Outer Membrane Vesicles contain tRNA Fragments (tRFs) that Inhibit Bacteriophage P22 infection (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.948241+00:00</updated><author><name>Dominika Houserova</name></author><author><name>Yulong Huang</name></author><author><name>Mohan V. Kasukurthi</name></author><author><name>Brianna C. Watters</name></author><author><name>Fiza F. Khan</name></author><author><name>Raj V. Mehta</name></author><author><name>Neil Y. Chaudhary</name></author><author><name>Justin T. Roberts</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey D. DeMeis</name></author><author><name>Trevor K. Hobbs</name></author><author><name>Kanesha R. Ghee</name></author><author><name>Cameron H. McInnis</name></author><author><name>Nolan P. Johns</name></author><author><name>Abrianna J. Kegler</name></author><author><name>Alexander B. Coley</name></author><author><name>Cana L. Brown</name></author><author><name>Jenny L. Hewes</name></author><author><name>Marie M. McElyea</name></author><author><name>Monica N. Reeves</name></author><author><name>Tuan M. Tran</name></author><author><name>Natalie R. Bauer</name></author><author><name>Jingshan Huang</name></author><author><name>Jonathon P. Audia</name></author><author><name>John W. Foster</name></author><author><name>Glen M. Borchert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; Outer Membrane Vesicles (OMVs) were recently shown to inhibit P22 bacteriophage infection. Furthermore, despite there being several published reports now independently describing (1) the marked prevalence of tRFs within secreted vesicle transcriptomes and (2) roles for specific tRFs in facilitating/inhibiting viral replication, there have been no examinations of the effects of vesicle-secreted tRFs on viral infection reported to date. Notably, while specific tRFs have been reported in a number of bacteria, the tRFs expressed by salmonellae have not been previously characterized. As such, we recently screened small RNA-seq datasets for the presence of recurrent, specifically excised tRFs and identified 31 recurrent, relatively abundant tRFs expressed by &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella enterica&lt;/italic&gt; serovar Typhimurium (SL1344). What’s more, we find &lt;italic&gt;S&lt;/italic&gt;. Typhimurium OMVs contain significant levels of tRFs highly complementary to known &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella enterica&lt;/italic&gt;-infecting bacteriophage with 17 of 31 tRFs bearing marked complementarity to at least one known &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella enterica&lt;/italic&gt;-infecting phage (averaging 97.4% complementarity over 22.9 nt). Most notably, tRNA-Thr-CGT-1-1, 44-73, bears 100% sequence complementary over its entire 30 nt length to 29 distinct, annotated &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella enterica&lt;/italic&gt;-infecting bacteriophage including P22. Importantly, we find inhibiting this tRF in secreted OMVs improves P22 infectivity in a dose dependent manner whereas raising OMV tRF levels conversely inhibits P22 infectivity. Furthermore, we find P22 phage pre-incubation with OMVs isolated from naïve, control SL1344 &lt;italic&gt;S&lt;/italic&gt;. Typhimurium, successfully rescues the ability of &lt;italic&gt;S&lt;/italic&gt;. Typhimurium transformed with a specific tRNA-Thr-CGT-1-1, 44-73 tRF inhibitor to defend against P22. Collectively, these experiments confirm tRFs secreted in &lt;italic&gt;S&lt;/italic&gt;. Typhimurium OMVs are directly involved with and required for the ability of OMVs to defend against bacteriophage predation. As we find the majority of OMV tRFs are highly complementary to an array of known &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella enterica&lt;/italic&gt;-infecting bacteriophage, we suggest OMV tRFs may primarily function as a broadly acting, previously uncharacterized innate antiviral defense.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467952" rel="alternate" title="Salmonella Outer Membrane Vesicles contain tRNA Fragments (tRFs) that Inhibit Bacteriophage P22 infection (14 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467742</id><title>The bacterial actin-like cell division protein FtsA forms curved antiparallel double filaments upon binding of FtsN (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.948501+00:00</updated><author><name>Tim Nierhaus</name></author><author><name>Stephen H McLaughlin</name></author><author><name>Frank Bürmann</name></author><author><name>Danguole Kureisaite-Ciziene</name></author><author><name>Sarah Maslen</name></author><author><name>Mark J Skehel</name></author><author><name>Conny WH Yu</name></author><author><name>Stefan MV Freund</name></author><author><name>Louise FH Funke</name></author><author><name>Jason W Chin</name></author><author><name>Jan Löwe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cell growth and division of walled bacteria depend on the synthesis and remodelling of peptidoglycan (PG). These activities are carried out by two multiprotein complexes, the elongasome and the divisome during cell elongation and division, respectively. Filaments of tubulin-like FtsZ form the cytoplasmic scaffold for divisome assembly, the Z-ring. In &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;, the actin homologue FtsA anchors the Z-ring to the membrane and recruits downstream divisome components, including bitopic FtsN. FtsN is recruited late and activates the periplasmic PG synthase FtsWI. To start unravelling the activation mechanism involving FtsA and FtsN, we showed that &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; FtsA forms antiparallel double filaments on lipid monolayers when also binding FtsN’s cytoplasmic tail, and that &lt;italic&gt;Vibrio maritimus&lt;/italic&gt; FtsA crystallised as an equivalent double filament. We structurally located the FtsA-FtsN interaction site in FtsA’s IA-IC interdomain cleft and confirmed FtsA double filament formation &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; using site-specific cysteine cross-linking. FtsA-FtsN double filaments reconstituted on and in liposomes preferred negative Gaussian curvature, as was previously shown for the elongasome’s actin, MreB. MreB filaments serve as curvature-sensing “rudders”, orienting insertion of PG around the cell’s circumference. We propose that curved antiparallel FtsA double filaments function similarly in the divisome: FtsA filaments, together with dynamic FtsZ filaments orient and concentrate cell-constricting septal PG synthesis in the division plane.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467742" rel="alternate" title="The bacterial actin-like cell division protein FtsA forms curved antiparallel double filaments upon binding of FtsN (12 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.467955</id><title>Linking extreme seasonality and gene expression in arctic marine protists (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.948824+00:00</updated><author><name>Magdalena Wutkowska</name></author><author><name>Anna Vader</name></author><author><name>Ramiro Logares</name></author><author><name>Eric Pelletier</name></author><author><name>Tove M. Gabrielsen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;At high latitudes, strong seasonal differences in light availability affect marine organisms and restrict the timing of ecosystem processes. Marine protists are key players in Arctic aquatic ecosystems, yet little is known about their ecological roles over yearly cycles. This is especially true for the dark polar night period, which up until recently was assumed to be devoid of biological activity. A 12 million transcripts catalogue was built from 0.45-10 μm protist assemblages sampled over 13 months in a time series station in an arctic fjord in Svalbard. Community gene expression was correlated with seasonality, with light as the main driving factor. Transcript diversity and evenness were higher during polar night compared to polar day. Light-dependent functions had higher relative expression during polar day, except phototransduction. 64% of the most expressed genes could not be functionally annotated, yet up to 78% were identified in arctic samples from Tara Oceans, suggesting that arctic marine assemblages are distinct from those from other oceans. Our study increases understanding of the links between extreme seasonality and biological processes in pico- and nanoplanktonic protists. Our results set the ground for future monitoring studies investigating the seasonal impact of climate change on the communities of microbial eukaryotes in the High Arctic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.467955" rel="alternate" title="Linking extreme seasonality and gene expression in arctic marine protists (12 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468430</id><title>FoxP3 associates with enhancer-promoter loops to regulate Treg-specific gene expression (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.948974+00:00</updated><author><name>Ricardo N Ramirez</name></author><author><name>Kaitavjeet Chowdhary</name></author><author><name>Juliette Leon</name></author><author><name>Diane Mathis</name></author><author><name>Christophe Benoist</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gene expression programs are specified by higher-order chromatin structure and enhancer-promoter loops (EPL). T regulatory cells (Treg) identity is dominantly specified by the transcription factor FoxP3, whose mechanism of action is unclear. We applied proximity-ligation with chromatin immunoprecipitation (HiChIP) in Treg and closely related conventional CD4+ T cells (Tconv). EPL identified by H3K27Ac HiChIP showed a range of connection intensity, with some super-connected genes. TF-specific HiChIP showed that FoxP3 interacts with EPLs at a large number of genes, including some not differentially expressed in Treg vs Tconv, but enriched at the core Treg signature loci that it upregulates. FoxP3 association correlates with heightened H3H27Ac looping, as ascertained by analysis of FoxP3-deficient Treg-like cells. There was marked asymmetry in the loci where FoxP3 associated at the enhancer- or the promoter-side of EPLs, with enrichment for different transcriptional cofactors. FoxP3 EPL intensity distinguished gene clusters identified by single-cell ATAC-seq as co-varying between individual Tregs, supporting a direct transactivation model for FoxP3 in determining Treg identity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468430" rel="alternate" title="FoxP3 associates with enhancer-promoter loops to regulate Treg-specific gene expression (11 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468017</id><title>Vaccinia virus D10 has broad decapping activity that is regulated by mRNA splicing (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.949121+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael Ly</name></author><author><name>Hannah M. Burgess</name></author><author><name>Ian Mohr</name></author><author><name>Britt A. Glaunsinger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mRNA 5’ cap structure serves both to protect transcripts from degradation and promote their translation. Cap removal is thus an integral component of mRNA turnover that is carried out by cellular decapping enzymes, whose activity is tightly regulated and coupled to other stages of the mRNA decay pathway. The poxvirus vaccinia virus (VACV) encodes its own decapping enzymes, D9 and D10, that act on cellular and viral mRNA, but may be regulated differently than their cellular counterparts. Here, we evaluated the targeting potential of these viral enzymes using RNA sequencing from cells infected with wild-type and decapping mutant versions of VACV as well as in uninfected cells expressing D10. We found that D9 and D10 target an overlapping subset of viral transcripts but that D10 plays a dominant role in depleting the vast majority of human transcripts, although not in an indiscriminate manner. Unexpectedly, the splicing architecture of a gene influences how robustly its corresponding transcript is targeted by D10, as transcripts derived from intronless genes are less susceptible to enzymatic decapping by D10. As all VACV genes are intronless, preferential decapping of transcripts from intron-encoding genes provides an unanticipated mechanism for the virus to disproportionately deplete host transcripts and remodel the infected cell transcriptome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468017" rel="alternate" title="Vaccinia virus D10 has broad decapping activity that is regulated by mRNA splicing (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467865</id><title>Nitric Oxide Attenuates Human Cytomegalovirus Infection yet Disrupts Neural Cell Differentiation and Tissue Organization (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.949251+00:00</updated><author><name>Rebekah L. Mokry</name></author><author><name>Benjamin S. O’Brien</name></author><author><name>Jacob W. Adelman</name></author><author><name>Suzette Rosas</name></author><author><name>Allison D. Ebert</name></author><author><name>Scott S. Terhune</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human cytomegalovirus (HCMV) is a prevalent betaherpesvirus that is asymptomatic in healthy individuals but can cause serious disease in immunocompromised patients. HCMV is also the leading cause of viral-mediated birth defects. Many of these defects manifest within the central nervous system and include microcephaly, sensorineural hearing loss, and cognitive developmental delays. Nitric oxide is a critical effector molecule produced as a component of the innate immune response during infection. Using a 3-dimensional cortical organoid model, we demonstrate that nitric oxide inhibits HCMV spread and simultaneously disrupts neural rosette structures resulting in tissue disorganization. Nitric oxide also attenuates HCMV replication in 2-dimensional cultures of neural progenitor cells (NPCs), a prominent cell type in cortical organoids that differentiate into neurons and glial cells. The multipotency factor SOX2 was decreased during nitric oxide exposure, suggesting early neural differentiation is affected. Maximal mitochondrial respiration was also reduced in both uninfected and infected NPCs. We determined this reduction likely influences neural differentiation as neurons (Tuj1+GFAP-Nestin-) and glial populations (Tuj1-GFAP+Nestin-) were reduced following differentiation. We also observed changes in calcium signaling during exposure to nitric oxide with increased cellular response to ATP (purinergic receptors) and KCl (voltage gated calcium channels). Importantly, nitric oxide could not rescue HCMV-mediated defects in calcium response. Our studies indicate a prominent, immunopathogenic role of nitric oxide in promoting developmental defects within the brain despite its antiviral activity during congenital HCMV infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Human cytomegalovirus (HCMV) infection can result in serious disease to immunocompromised individuals. HCMV is also the leading cause of viral-mediated congenital birth defects. Congenitally-infected infants can have a variety of symptoms, including microcephaly, sensorineural hearing loss, and developmental delays. The use of 3-dimensional (3-D) cortical organoids to model infection of the fetal brain has advanced the current understanding of developmental defects and allowed a broader investigation of the mechanisms behind disease. Here, we investigate the effect of nitric oxide, a critical effector molecule, on cortical development and HCMV infection. We demonstrate that nitric oxide plays an antiviral role during infection yet results in significant disorganization to cortical tissue. Despite inhibiting viral replication in neural progenitor cells, nitric oxide contributes to differentiation defects of these cells and does not rescue functional consequences of HCMV infection on calcium signaling. Our results indicate that immunopathogenic consequences of nitric oxide during congenital infection promote developmental defects that undermine its antiviral activity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467865" rel="alternate" title="Nitric Oxide Attenuates Human Cytomegalovirus Infection yet Disrupts Neural Cell Differentiation and Tissue Organization (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468464</id><title>Ferric Citrate Uptake is a Virulence Factor in Uropathogenic Escherichia coli (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.949397+00:00</updated><author><name>Arwen E Frick-Cheng</name></author><author><name>Anna Sintsova</name></author><author><name>Sara N Smith</name></author><author><name>Ali Pirani</name></author><author><name>Evan S Snitkin</name></author><author><name>Harry L.T. Mobley</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;More than half of women will experience a urinary tract infection (UTI) with uropathogenic &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; (UPEC) causing ~80% of uncomplicated cases. Iron acquisition systems are essential for uropathogenesis, and UPEC encode functionally redundant iron acquisition systems, underlining their importance. However, a recent UPEC clinical isolate, HM7 lacks this functional redundancy and instead encodes a sole siderophore, enterobactin. To determine if &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; HM7 possesses unidentified iron acquisition systems, we performed RNA-sequencing under iron-limiting conditions and demonstrated that the ferric citrate uptake system (&lt;italic&gt;fecABCDE&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;fecIR&lt;/italic&gt;) was highly upregulated. Importantly, there are high levels of citrate within urine, some of which is bound to iron, and the &lt;italic&gt;fec&lt;/italic&gt; system is highly enriched in UPEC isolates compared to environmental or fecal strains. Therefore, we hypothesized that HM7 and other similar strains use the &lt;italic&gt;fec&lt;/italic&gt; system to acquire iron in the host. Deletion of both enterobactin biosynthesis and ferric citrate uptake (Δ&lt;italic&gt;entB&lt;/italic&gt;/Δ&lt;italic&gt;fecA&lt;/italic&gt;) abrogates use of ferric citrate as an iron source and &lt;italic&gt;fecA&lt;/italic&gt; provides an advantage in human urine in absence of enterobactin. However, in a UTI mouse model, &lt;italic&gt;fecA&lt;/italic&gt; is a fitness factor independent of enterobactin production, likely due to the action of host Lipocalin-2 chelating ferrienterobactin. These findings indicate that ferric citrate uptake is used as an iron source when siderophore efficacy is limited, such as in the host during UTI. Defining these novel compensatory mechanisms and understanding the nutritional hierarchy of preferred iron sources within the urinary tract are important in the search for new approaches to combat UTI.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468464" rel="alternate" title="Ferric Citrate Uptake is a Virulence Factor in Uropathogenic Escherichia coli (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467964</id><title>Platelets are dispensable for the ability of CD8+ T cells to accumulate, patrol, kill and reside in the liver (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.949539+00:00</updated><author><name>James H. O’Connor</name></author><author><name>Hayley A. McNamara</name></author><author><name>Yeping Cai</name></author><author><name>Lucy A. Coupland</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth E. Gardiner</name></author><author><name>Christopher R. Parish</name></author><author><name>Brendan J. McMorran</name></author><author><name>Vitaly V. Ganusov</name></author><author><name>Ian A. Cockburn</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Effector and memory CD8+ T cells accumulate in large numbers in the liver where they play key roles in the control of liver pathogens including &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium&lt;/italic&gt;. It has also been proposed that liver may act as the main place for elimination of effector CD8+ T cells at the resolution of immune responses. Platelets and the integrin LFA-1 have been proposed to be critical for the accumulation of protective CD8+ T cells in the liver; conversely, asialo-glycoprotein (ASGP) expression on the surface of CD8+ T cells has been proposed to assist in elimination of effector T cells in the liver. Here we investigated the contributions of these interactions in the accumulation of CD8+ T cells activated &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; or &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; by immunization with &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium&lt;/italic&gt; parasites. Using &lt;italic&gt;Mpl&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; mice with constitutive thrombocytopaenia and antibody-mediated platelet depletion models we found that severe reduction in platelet concentration in circulation did not strongly influence the accumulation and protective function of CD8+ T cells in the liver in these models. Surprisingly, inhibition of ASGP receptors did not inhibit the accumulation of effector cells in the liver, but instead prevented these cells from accumulating in the spleen. We further found that enforced expression of ASGP on effector CD8+ T cells using ST3GalI knockout cells lead to their loss from the spleen. These data suggest that platelets play a marginal role in CD8+ T cell function in the liver. Furthermore, ASGP-expressing effector CD8+ T cells are retained in the liver but are lost from the spleen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467964" rel="alternate" title="Platelets are dispensable for the ability of CD8+ T cells to accumulate, patrol, kill and reside in the liver (7 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467789</id><title>Host-associated phages disperse across the extraterrestrial analogue Antarctica (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.949776+00:00</updated><author><name>Janina Rahlff</name></author><author><name>Till L.V. Bornemann</name></author><author><name>Anna Lopatina</name></author><author><name>Konstantin Severinov</name></author><author><name>Alexander J. Probst</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Extreme Antarctic conditions provide one of the closest analogues of extraterrestrial environments. Since air and snow samples especially from polar regions yield DNA amounts in the lower picogram range, binning of prokaryotic genomes is challenging and renders studying the dispersal of biological entities across these environments difficult. Here, we hypothesized that dispersal of host-associated bacteriophages (adsorbed, replicating or prophages) across the Antarctic continent can be tracked via their genetic signatures and benefits our understanding of virus and host dispersal across long distances. Phage genome fragments (PGFs) reconstructed from surface snow metagenomes of three Antarctic stations were assigned to four host genomes, mainly Betaproteobacteria including &lt;italic&gt;Ralstonia&lt;/italic&gt; spp. Betaproteobacteria of this genus have been found in Antarctic snow as well as on space-related equipment. We reconstructed the complete genome of a temperate phage with near-complete alignment to a prophage in the reference genome of &lt;italic&gt;Ralstonia pickettii&lt;/italic&gt; 12D. PGFs from different stations were related to each other at the genus level and matched similar hosts. Metagenomic read mapping and nucleotide polymorphism analysis revealed a wide dispersal of highly identical PGFs, 13 of which appeared in seawater from the Western Antarctic Peninsula with up to 5538 km to the snow sampling stations. Our results suggest that host-associated phages, especially of &lt;italic&gt;Ralstonia&lt;/italic&gt; sp. disperse over long distances despite harsh conditions of the Antarctic continent. Due to the additional identification of 14 phages associated with two &lt;italic&gt;R. pickettii&lt;/italic&gt; draft genomes isolated from space equipment, we conclude implications for the spread of biological contaminants in extraterrestrial settings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Host-associated phages of the bacterium &lt;italic&gt;Ralstonia&lt;/italic&gt; identified in snow samples can be used to track microbial dispersal over thousands of kilometers across the Antarctic continent, which functions as an extraterrestrial analogue because of its harsh environmental conditions. Due to presence of this bacterial strain including genome-integrated prophages on space-related equipment, and the here demonstrated potential for dispersal of host-associated phages, our work has implications for Planetary Protection, a discipline in Astrobiology interested in preventing contamination of celestial bodies with alien biomolecules or forms of life.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467789" rel="alternate" title="Host-associated phages disperse across the extraterrestrial analogue Antarctica (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467302</id><title>A comparative analysis of memory B cell and antibody responses against Plasmodium falciparum merozoite surface protein 1 in children and adults from Uganda (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.949944+00:00</updated><author><name>S. Jake Gonzales</name></author><author><name>Kathleen N. Clarke</name></author><author><name>Gayani Batugedara</name></author><author><name>Ashley E. Braddom</name></author><author><name>Rolando Garza</name></author><author><name>Raphael A. Reyes</name></author><author><name>Isaac Ssewanyana</name></author><author><name>Kendra C. Garrison</name></author><author><name>Gregory C. Ippolito</name></author><author><name>Bryan Greenhouse</name></author><author><name>Sebastiaan Bol</name></author><author><name>Evelien M. Bunnik</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Memory B cells (MBCs) and plasma antibodies against &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; merozoite antigens are important components of the protective immune response against malaria. To gain understanding of how responses against &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; develop in these two arms of the humoral immune system, we evaluated MBC and antibody responses against the most abundant merozoite antigen, merozoite surface protein 1 (MSP1), in individuals from a region in Uganda with high &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; transmission. Our results showed that MSP1-specific B cells in adults with immunological protection against malaria were predominantly IgG&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; classical MBCs, while children with incomplete protection mainly harbored IgM&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; MSP1-specific classical MBCs. In contrast, anti-MSP1 plasma IgM reactivity was minimal in both children and adults. Instead, both groups showed high plasma IgG reactivity against MSP1 and whole merozoites, with broadening of the response against non-3D7 strains in adults. The antibodies encoded by MSP1-specific IgG&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; MBCs carried high levels of amino acid substitutions and recognized relatively conserved epitopes on the highly variable MSP1 protein. Proteomics analysis of MSP1&lt;sub&gt;19&lt;/sub&gt;-specific IgG in plasma of an adult revealed a limited repertoire of anti-MSP1 antibodies, most of which were IgG&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; or IgG&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;. Similar to MSP1- specific MBCs, anti-MSP1 IgGs had relatively high levels of amino acid substitutions and their sequences were predominantly found in classical MBCs, not atypical MBCs. Collectively, these results showed evolution of the MSP1-specific humoral immune response with cumulative &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; exposure, with a shift from IgM&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; to IgG&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; B cell memory, diversification of B cells from germline, and stronger recognition of MSP1 variants by the plasma IgG repertoire.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467302" rel="alternate" title="A comparative analysis of memory B cell and antibody responses against Plasmodium falciparum merozoite surface protein 1 in children and adults from Uganda (6 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467825</id><title>Water column stability as an important factor controlling nitrite-dependent anaerobic methane oxidation in stratified lake basins (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.950138+00:00</updated><author><name>Guangyi Su</name></author><author><name>Moritz F. Lehmann</name></author><author><name>Jana Tischer</name></author><author><name>Yuki Weber</name></author><author><name>Jean-Claude Walser</name></author><author><name>Helge Niemann</name></author><author><name>Jakob Zopfi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Anaerobic oxidation of methane (AOM) with nitrate/nitrite as the terminal electron acceptor may play an important role in mitigating methane emissions from lacustrine environments to the atmosphere. We investigated AOM in the water column of two connected but hydrodynamically contrasting basins of a south-alpine lake in Switzerland (Lake Lugano). The North Basin is permanently stratified with year-round anoxic conditions below 120 m water depth, while the South Basin undergoes seasonal stratification with the development of bottom water anoxia during summer. We show that below the redoxcline of the North Basin a substantial fraction of methane was oxidized coupled to nitrite reduction by &lt;italic&gt;Candidatus&lt;/italic&gt; Methylomirabilis. Incubation experiments with &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; and concentrated biomass from showed at least 43-52%-enhanced AOM rates with added nitrate/nitrite as electron acceptor. Multiannual time series data on the population dynamics of &lt;italic&gt;Candidatus&lt;/italic&gt; Methylomirabilis in the North Basin following an exceptional mixing event in 2005/2006 revealed their requirement for lasting stable low redox-conditions to establish. In the South Basin, on the other hand, we did not find molecular evidence for nitrite-dependent methane oxidizing bacteria. Our data suggest that here the dynamic mixing regime with fluctuating redox conditions is not conducive to the development of a stable population of relatively slow-growing &lt;italic&gt;Candidatus&lt;/italic&gt; Methylomirabilis, despite a hydrochemical framework that seems more favorable for nitrite-dependent AOM than in the North Basin. We predict that the importance of N-dependent AOM in freshwater lakes will likely increase in future because of longer thermal stratification periods and reduced mixing caused by global warming.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467825" rel="alternate" title="Water column stability as an important factor controlling nitrite-dependent anaerobic methane oxidation in stratified lake basins (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468388</id><title>Multiplexed detection of bacterial nucleic acids using Cas13 in droplet microarrays (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.950292+00:00</updated><author><name>Sri Gowtham Thakku</name></author><author><name>Cheri M Ackerman</name></author><author><name>Cameron Myhrvold</name></author><author><name>Roby P Bhattacharyya</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Livny</name></author><author><name>Peijun Ma</name></author><author><name>Giselle Isabella Gomez</name></author><author><name>Pardis Sabeti</name></author><author><name>Paul C Blainey</name></author><author><name>Deborah T Hung</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Rapid and accurate diagnosis of infections is fundamental to individual patient care and public health management. Nucleic acid detection methods are critical to this effort, but are limited either in the breadth of pathogens targeted or by the expertise and infrastructure required. We present here a high-throughput system that enables rapid identification of bacterial pathogens, bCARMEN, which utilizes: (1) modular CRISPR-Cas13-based nucleic acid detection with enhanced sensitivity and specificity; and (2) a droplet microfluidic system that enables thousands of simultaneous, spatially multiplexed detection reactions at nanoliter volumes; and (3) a novel pre-amplification strategy that further enhances sensitivity and specificity. We demonstrate bCARMEN is capable of detecting and discriminating 52 clinically relevant bacterial species and several key antibiotic resistance genes. We further develop a proof of principle system for use with stabilized reagents and a simple workflow with optical readout using a cell phone camera, opening up the possibility of a rapid point-of-care multiplexed bacterial pathogen identification and antibiotic susceptibility testing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468388" rel="alternate" title="Multiplexed detection of bacterial nucleic acids using Cas13 in droplet microarrays (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467407</id><title>ACPA-IgG variable domain glycosylation increases before the onset of rheumatoid arthritis and stabilizes thereafter; a cross-sectional study encompassing over 1500 samples (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.950463+00:00</updated><author><name>T. Kissel</name></author><author><name>L. Hafkenscheid</name></author><author><name>T.J. Wesemael</name></author><author><name>M. Tamai</name></author><author><name>S.Y. Kawashiri</name></author><author><name>A. Kawakami</name></author><author><name>H.S. El-Gabalawy</name></author><author><name>D. van Schaardenburg</name></author><author><name>S. Rantapää-Dahlqvist</name></author><author><name>M. Wuhrer</name></author><author><name>A.H.M. van der Helm-van Mil</name></author><author><name>C.F. Allaart</name></author><author><name>D. van der Woude</name></author><author><name>H.U. Scherer</name></author><author><name>R.E.M. Toes</name></author><author><name>T.W.J. Huizinga</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The autoimmune response in rheumatoid arthritis (RA) is marked by anti-citrullinated protein antibodies (ACPA). A remarkable feature of ACPA-IgG is the abundant expression of &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;-linked glycans in the variable domain. Nonetheless, the presence of ACPA variable domain glycans (VDG) across disease stages and its’ response to therapy is poorly described. To understand its dynamics, we investigated the abundance of ACPA-IgG VDG in 1574 samples from individuals in different clinical disease stages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using liquid chromatography, we analyzed ACPA-IgG VDG profiles of 7 different cohorts from Japan, Canada, the Netherlands and Sweden. We assessed 184 healthy, 228 pre-symptomatic, 277 arthralgia, 305 patients at RA-onset and 117 RA-patients 4, 8 and 12 months after disease onset. Additionally, we measured VDG of 234 samples from RA-patients that did or did not achieve long-term drug-free remission (DFR) during up to 16 years follow-up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our data show that ACPA-IgG VDG significantly increases (p&amp;lt;0.0001) towards disease-onset and associates with ACPA-levels and epitope spreading pre-diagnosis. A slight increase in VDG was observed in established RA and a moderate influence of treatment. Individuals who later achieved DFR displayed reduced ACPA-IgG VDG already at RA-onset.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The abundance of ACPA-IgG VDG rises towards RA-onset and correlates with maturation of the ACPA-response. Although, ACPA-IgG VDG levels are rather stable in established disease, a lower degree at RA-onset correlates with DFR. Even though the underlying biological mechanisms are still elusive, our data support the concept that VDG relates to an expansion of the ACPA-response pre-disease and contributes to disease-development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467407" rel="alternate" title="ACPA-IgG variable domain glycosylation increases before the onset of rheumatoid arthritis and stabilizes thereafter; a cross-sectional study encompassing over 1500 samples (6 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467953</id><title>LuxT is a Global Regulator of Low-Cell Density Behaviors Including Type III Secretion, Siderophore Production, and Aerolysin Secretion in Vibrio harveyi (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.950676+00:00</updated><author><name>Michaela J. Eickhoff</name></author><author><name>Chenyi Fei</name></author><author><name>Jian-Ping Cong</name></author><author><name>Bonnie L. Bassler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Quorum sensing (QS) is a chemical communication process in which bacteria produce, release, and detect extracellular signaling molecules called autoinducers. Via combined transcriptional and post-transcriptional regulatory mechanisms, QS allows bacteria to collectively alter gene expression on a population-wide scale. Recently, the LuxT transcription factor was shown to control &lt;italic&gt;V. harveyi qrr&lt;/italic&gt;1, encoding the Qrr1 small RNA that functions at the core of the QS regulatory cascade. Here, we use RNA-Sequencing to reveal that, beyond control of &lt;italic&gt;qrr&lt;/italic&gt;1, LuxT is a global regulator of 414 &lt;italic&gt;V. harveyi&lt;/italic&gt; genes including those involved in type III secretion, siderophore production, and aerolysin toxin biosynthesis. Importantly, LuxT directly represses &lt;italic&gt;swrZ&lt;/italic&gt;, encoding a transcription factor, and LuxT control of type III secretion, siderophore, and aerolysin genes occurs by two mechanisms, one that is SwrZ-dependent and one that is SwrZ-independent. All of these target genes specify QS-controlled behaviors that are enacted when &lt;italic&gt;V. harveyi&lt;/italic&gt; is at low cell density. Thus, LuxT and SwrZ function in parallel with QS to drive particular low cell density behaviors. Phylogenetic analyses reveal that &lt;italic&gt;luxT&lt;/italic&gt; is highly conserved among &lt;italic&gt;Vibrionaceae&lt;/italic&gt;, but &lt;italic&gt;swrZ&lt;/italic&gt; is less well conserved. In a test case to examine the relationship between LuxT and SwrZ, we find that in &lt;italic&gt;Aliivibrio fischeri&lt;/italic&gt;, LuxT also functions as a &lt;italic&gt;swrZ&lt;/italic&gt; repressor, and LuxT activates &lt;italic&gt;A. fischeri&lt;/italic&gt; siderophore production via &lt;italic&gt;swrZ&lt;/italic&gt; repression. Our results indicate that LuxT is a major regulator among &lt;italic&gt;Vibrionaceae&lt;/italic&gt;, and, in the species that also possess &lt;italic&gt;swrZ&lt;/italic&gt;, LuxT functions with SwrZ to control gene expression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bacteria precisely tune gene expression patterns to successfully react to changes that occur in the environment. Defining the mechanisms that enable bacteria to thrive in diverse and fluctuating habitats, including in host organisms, is crucial for a deep understanding of the microbial world and also for development of effective applications to promote or to combat particular bacteria. In this study, we show that a regulator called LuxT controls over 400 genes in the marine bacterium &lt;italic&gt;Vibrio harveyi&lt;/italic&gt; and, moreover, that LuxT is highly conserved among &lt;italic&gt;Vibrionaceae&lt;/italic&gt; species, ubiquitous marine bacteria that often cause disease. We characterize the mechanisms by which LuxT controls genes involved in virulence and nutrient acquisition. We show that LuxT functions in parallel with a set of regulators of the bacterial cell-to-cell communication process called quorum sensing to promote &lt;italic&gt;V. harveyi&lt;/italic&gt; behaviors at low cell density.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467953" rel="alternate" title="LuxT is a Global Regulator of Low-Cell Density Behaviors Including Type III Secretion, Siderophore Production, and Aerolysin Secretion in Vibrio harveyi (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.467892</id><title>Selective clonal persistence of human retroviruses in vivo: radial chromatin organization, integration site and host transcription (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.950813+00:00</updated><author><name>Anat Melamed</name></author><author><name>Tomas W Fitzgerald</name></author><author><name>Yuchuan Wang</name></author><author><name>Jian Ma</name></author><author><name>Ewan Birney</name></author><author><name>Charles R M Bangham</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The human retroviruses HTLV-1 and HIV-1 persist in vivo, despite the host immune response and antiretroviral therapy, as a reservoir of latently infected T-cell clones. It is poorly understood what determines which clones survive in the reservoir and which are lost. We compared &amp;gt;160,000 HTLV-1 integration sites from T-cells isolated ex vivo from naturally-infected subjects with &amp;gt;230,000 integration sites from in vitro infection, to identify the genomic features that determine selective clonal survival. Three factors explained &amp;gt;40% of the observed variance in clone survival of HTLV-1 in vivo: the radial intranuclear position of the provirus, its absolute genomic distance from the centromere, and the intensity of host genome transcription flanking the provirus. The radial intranuclear position of the provirus and its distance from the centromere also explained ~7% of clonal persistence of HIV-1 in vivo. Selection for transcriptionally repressive nuclear compartments favours clonal persistence of human retroviruses in vivo.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.467892" rel="alternate" title="Selective clonal persistence of human retroviruses in vivo: radial chromatin organization, integration site and host transcription (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468487</id><title>Vγ usage distinguishes pro- and anti-tumor intestinal γδ T cell subsets (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.950961+00:00</updated><author><name>Bernardo S Reis</name></author><author><name>Patrick W. Darcy</name></author><author><name>Iasha Z. Khan</name></author><author><name>Olawale Eleso</name></author><author><name>Caixia Zhu</name></author><author><name>Marina Schernthanner</name></author><author><name>Ainsley Lockhart</name></author><author><name>Aubrey Reed</name></author><author><name>Juliana Bortolatto</name></author><author><name>Tiago Castro</name></author><author><name>Angelina Bilate</name></author><author><name>Sergei Grivennikov</name></author><author><name>Daniel Mucida</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;γδ T cells physiologically scan the intestinal epithelium, representing a substantial fraction of infiltrating lymphocytes in colorectal cancer (CRC), albeit their role in CRC remains unclear. Using murine CRC models, we found that most γδ T cells in pre- or non-tumor colon express Vγ1+ or Vγ7+ and exhibit a cytotoxic profile. Targeting these γδ T cell subsets, as well as conditionally interfering with γδ T cell function at early stages of tumorigenesis led to heightened tumor development, suggesting anti-CRC functions for Vγ1+ and Vγ7+ subsets. In contrast, RORγt+ γδ T cell subsets, including Vg4+ and microbiota-dependent Vγ6+, accumulated during CRC progression. Conditional deletion of RORγt or Vγ chains revealed redundant roles for IL-17-producing Vγ4+ and Vγ6+ γδ T cells in promoting tumor growth. Our results uncover pro- and anti-tumor roles for γδ T cell subsets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468487" rel="alternate" title="Vγ usage distinguishes pro- and anti-tumor intestinal γδ T cell subsets (5 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467864</id><title>PRMT5 epigenetically regulates the E3 ubiquitin ligase ITCH to influence lipid accumulation during mycobacterial infection (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.951155+00:00</updated><author><name>Salik Miskat Borbora</name></author><author><name>R.S. Rajmani</name></author><author><name>Kithiganahalli Narayanaswamy Balaji</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; (Mtb), the causative agent of tuberculosis (TB), triggers enhanced accumulation of lipids to generate foamy macrophages (FMs). This process has been often attributed to the surge in the expression of lipid influx genes with a concomitant decrease in those involved in lipid efflux genes. Here, we define an Mtb-orchestrated modulation of the ubiquitination mechanism of lipid accumulation markers to enhance lipid accretion during infection. We find that Mtb infection represses the expression of the E3 ubiquitin ligase, ITCH, resulting in the sustenance of key lipid accrual molecules viz. ADRP and CD36, that are otherwise targeted by ITCH for proteasomal degradation. In line, overexpressing ITCH in Mtb-infected cells was found to suppress Mtb-induced lipid accumulation. Molecular analyses including loss-of-function and ChIP assays demonstrated a role for the concerted action of the transcription factor YY1 and the arginine methyl transferase PRMT5 in restricting the expression of &lt;italic&gt;Itch&lt;/italic&gt; gene by conferring repressive symmetrical H4R3me2 marks on its promoter. Consequently, siRNA-mediated depletion of YY1 or PRMT5 rescued ITCH expression, thereby compromising the levels of Mtb-induced ADRP and CD36 and limiting FM formation during infection. Accumulation of lipids within the host has been implicated as a pro-mycobacterial process that aids in pathogen persistence and dormancy. In our study, perturbation of PRMT5 enzyme activity resulted in compromised lipid levels and reduced mycobacterial survival in primary murine macrophages (&lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt;) and in a therapeutic mouse model of TB infection (&lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;). These findings provide new insights on the role of PRMT5 and YY1 in augmenting mycobacterial pathogenesis. Thus, we posit that our observations could help design novel adjunct therapies and combinatorial drug regimen for effective anti-TB strategies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; generates lipid-laden cells (foamy macrophages-FMs) that offer a favorable shelter for its persistence. During infection, we observe a significant reduction in the expression of the E3 ubiquitin ligase, ITCH. This repression allows the sustenance of key lipid accretion molecules (ADRP and CD36), by curbing their proteasomal degradation. Further, we show the repression of ITCH to be dependent on the concerted action of the bifunctional transcription factor, YY1 and the arginine methyl transferase, PRMT5. NOTCH signaling pathway was identified as a master-regulator of YY1 expression. &lt;italic&gt;In vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; analyses revealed the significance of PRMT5 in regulating FM formation and consequently mycobacterial burden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467864" rel="alternate" title="PRMT5 epigenetically regulates the E3 ubiquitin ligase ITCH to influence lipid accumulation during mycobacterial infection (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468441</id><title>Recombinant Group A Carbohydrate backbone embedded into Outer Membrane Vesicles is a potent vaccine candidate targeting Group A Streptococcus from Streptococcus pyogenes and Streptococcus dysgalactiae subsp. equisimilis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.951277+00:00</updated><author><name>Sowmya Ajay Castro</name></author><author><name>Sarah Thomson</name></author><author><name>Azul Zorzoli</name></author><author><name>Benjamin H Meyer</name></author><author><name>Mark Reglinski</name></author><author><name>Helge C Dorfmueller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Group A Streptococcus (GAS) are responsible for a wide range of human-exclusive infections, annually killing more than 500,000 people. Antibiotic resistance incidence of invasive GAS increased in the past decade and emphasises the need to develop a universal GAS vaccine. We have produced, for the first time, a recombinant polyrhamnose backbone (pRha), a validated universal GAS vaccine candidate. E. coli outer membrane vesicles (OMVs) carrying pRha were investigated for their immunogenicity and efficacy in an animal model. Our results suggest that pRha-OMVs induce specific antibodies which recognise Group A Carbohydrate (GAC) from S pyogenes and S. dysgalactiae subsp. equisimilis. Increased IgG levels correlate with increased bactericidal killing of the hypervirulent GAS M89 strain. Elevated IL-17a from pRha-OMV-immunised splenocytes indicates possible stimulation of long-term memory immune cells. We are the first to report efficacy and potency of this unique, exogenously produced polysaccharide, pRha, in the induction of humoral-mediated immune responses to GAS.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468441" rel="alternate" title="Recombinant Group A Carbohydrate backbone embedded into Outer Membrane Vesicles is a potent vaccine candidate targeting Group A Streptococcus from Streptococcus pyogenes and Streptococcus dysgalactiae subsp. equisimilis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.468003</id><title>Aspergillus fumigatus drives tissue damage via iterative assaults upon mucosal integrity and immune homeostasis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.951426+00:00</updated><author><name>Uju Joy Okaa</name></author><author><name>Margherita Bertuzzi</name></author><author><name>Rachael Fortune-Grant</name></author><author><name>Darren D. Thomson</name></author><author><name>David L. Moyes</name></author><author><name>Julian R. Naglik</name></author><author><name>Elaine Bignell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The human lung is constantly exposed to &lt;italic&gt;Aspergillus fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt; spores, the most prevalent worldwide cause of fungal respiratory disease. Pulmonary tissue damage is a unifying feature of &lt;italic&gt;Aspergillus&lt;/italic&gt;-related diseases; however, the mechanistic basis of damage is not understood. In the lungs of susceptible hosts &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt; undergoes an obligatory morphological switch involving spore germination and hyphal growth. We modelled &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt; infection in cultured A549 human pneumocytes, capturing phosphoactivation status of five host signalling pathways, nuclear translocation &amp;amp; DNA binding of eight host transcription factors, and expression of nine host response proteins over six time points encompassing exposures to live fungus and the secretome thereof. The resulting dataset, comprised of more than 1000 data points, reveals that pneumocytes mount differential responses to &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt; spores, hyphae and soluble secreted products via the NF-kB, JNK, and JNK + p38 pathways respectively. Importantly, via selective degradation of host pro-inflammatory (IL-6 and IL-8) cytokines and growth factors (FGF-2), fungal secreted products reorchestrate the host response to fungal challenge as well as driving multiparametric epithelial damage, culminating in cytolysis. Dysregulation of NF-kB signalling, involving iterative stimulation of canonical and non-canonical signalling, was identified as a significant feature of host damage both &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and in a mouse model of invasive aspergillosis. Our data demonstrate that composite tissue damage results from iterative exposures to different fungal morphotypes and secreted products and suggest that modulation of host responses to fungal challenge might represent a unified strategy for therapeutic control of pathologically distinct types of &lt;italic&gt;Aspergillus&lt;/italic&gt;-related disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pulmonary aspergillosis is a spectrum of diseases caused primarily by &lt;italic&gt;Aspergillus fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt;. This fungus is ubiquitous in the environment and grows as a mold, which harbors and disperses spores into the environment. Like other airborne pathogens, the lung mucosa is the first point of contact with the fungus post inhalation. The outcome and severity of disease depends on the host-fungal interaction at the lung interface. We studied how the human lung interacts with spore, germ tube and hyphae growth forms to understand the sequence and dynamics of the early events, which are critical drivers of disease development and progression. Our work is significant in identifying, in response to fungal secreted products, non-canonical NF-kB activation via RelB as being a driving factor in fungus-mediated lung damage. This process could be modulated therapeutically to protect the integrity of infected lung mucosae.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.468003" rel="alternate" title="Aspergillus fumigatus drives tissue damage via iterative assaults upon mucosal integrity and immune homeostasis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.465032</id><title>A vaccine targeting the L9 epitope of the malaria circumsporozoite protein confers protection from blood-stage infection in a mouse challenge model (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.951577+00:00</updated><author><name>Lucie Jelínková</name></author><author><name>Yevel Flores-Garcia</name></author><author><name>Sarah Shapiro</name></author><author><name>Bryce T. Roberts</name></author><author><name>Nikolai Petrovsky</name></author><author><name>Fidel Zavala</name></author><author><name>Bryce Chackerian</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pre-erythrocytic malaria vaccines that induce high-titer, durable antibody responses can potentially provide protection from infection. Here, we engineered a virus-like particle (VLP)-based vaccine targeting a recently described vulnerable epitope at the N-terminus of the central repeat region of the &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; circumsporozoite protein (CSP) that is recognized by the potently inhibitory monoclonal antibody L9 and show that immunization with L9 VLPs induces strong antibody responses that provide protection from blood-stage malaria in a mouse infection model.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.465032" rel="alternate" title="A vaccine targeting the L9 epitope of the malaria circumsporozoite protein confers protection from blood-stage infection in a mouse challenge model (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467288</id><title>A full-length infectious cDNA clone of a dsRNA totivirus-like virus (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.951799+00:00</updated><author><name>Han Wang</name></author><author><name>Kenta Okamoto</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Totivirus-like viruses are icosahedral non-enveloped double-stranded (ds)RNA viruses belonging to a group recently discovered and provisionally assigned in the &lt;italic&gt;Totiviridae&lt;/italic&gt; family. Unlike fungal and protozoan &lt;italic&gt;Totiviridae&lt;/italic&gt; viruses, these totivirus-like viruses infect a diverse spectrum of metazoan hosts and currently have enormous impacts on fisheries and agriculture. We developed the first totivirus-like virus Omono River virus (OmRV) infectious full-length DNA clone and produce the infectious particles using an RNA-transcript-based method. Unlike the parent wild-type particles from nature, the reverse-genetically-generated OmRV particles had an indistinguishable cytopathic effect, infectivity, and morphology. The established system is one of the few systems that have been reported for generating a non-segmented dsRNA virus DNA clone.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467288" rel="alternate" title="A full-length infectious cDNA clone of a dsRNA totivirus-like virus (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468056</id><title>Progressive enhancement of kinetic proofreading in T cell antigen discrimination from receptor activation to DAG generation (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.951924+00:00</updated><author><name>Derek M Britain</name></author><author><name>Orion David Weiner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;T cells use kinetic proofreading to discriminate antigens by converting small changes in antigen binding lifetime into large differences in cell activation, but where in the signaling cascade this computation is performed is unknown. Previously, we developed a light-gated immune receptor to probe the role of ligand kinetics in T cell antigen signaling. We found significant kinetic proofreading at the level of the signaling lipid diacylglycerol (DAG) but lacked the ability to determine where the multiple signaling steps required for kinetic discrimination originate in the upstream signaling cascade (Tischer and Weiner, 2019). Here we uncover where kinetic proofreading is executed by adapting our optogenetic system for robust activation of early signaling events. We find the strength of kinetic proofreading progressively increases from Zap70 recruitment to LAT clustering to downstream DAG generation. These data suggest a distributed kinetic proofreading mechanism, with proofreading steps both at the receptor and at downstream signaling events. Leveraging the ability of our system to rapidly disengage ligand binding, we measure slower reset rates for downstream signaling events. Our observations of distributed kinetic proofreading and slowed resetting of downstream steps suggest a basis of cooperativity between multiple active receptors with implications in tissue homeostasis, autoimmunity, and immunotherapy off-target effects.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468056" rel="alternate" title="Progressive enhancement of kinetic proofreading in T cell antigen discrimination from receptor activation to DAG generation (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.07.467618</id><title>Factors Influencing the Detection of Antibacterial Resistant Escherichia coli in Faecal Samples from Individual Cattle (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.952045+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrea Turner</name></author><author><name>Hannah Schubert</name></author><author><name>Emma F. Puddy</name></author><author><name>Jordan E. Sealey</name></author><author><name>Virginia C. Gould</name></author><author><name>Tristan A. Cogan</name></author><author><name>Matthew B. Avison</name></author><author><name>Kristen K. Reyher</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aims&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To investigate whether on-farm antibacterial usage (ABU), environmental antibacterial resistant (ABR) &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; prevalence, and sampling and sample handling methodologies are associated with ABR &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; positivity in individual faecal samples from dairy heifers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods and Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Three hundred and sixty-four heifers from 37 farms were sampled via rectal or faecal pat sampling. Samples were stored at -80°C for variable periods before microbiological analysis. Data analysis was through a multilevel, multivariable logistic regression approach.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individual rectal samples had increased odds of positivity for amoxicillin, cefalexin and tetracycline-resistant &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;. Sample storage for 6-12 month was associated with decreased odds of finding amoxicillin and tetracycline-resistant &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;. On-farm ABU had little influence, and environmental ABR &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; prevalence had no significant influence on on the odds of sample-level positivity for ABR &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sampling methodology and sample handling have a greater association than on-farm factors with the detection of ABR &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; in individual faecal samples from dairy heifers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance and Impact of the Study&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sampling and storage methodologies should be considered carefully at the point of designing ABR surveillance studies in livestock and their environments and, where possible, standardised between and within future studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.07.467618" rel="alternate" title="Factors Influencing the Detection of Antibacterial Resistant Escherichia coli in Faecal Samples from Individual Cattle (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468068</id><title>YAP1 Activation by Human Papillomavirus E7 Promotes Basal Cell Identity in Squamous Epithelia (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.952202+00:00</updated><author><name>Joshua Hatterschide</name></author><author><name>Paola Castagnino</name></author><author><name>Hee Won Kim</name></author><author><name>Steven M. Sperry</name></author><author><name>Kathleen T. Montone</name></author><author><name>Devraj Basu</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth A. White</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Persistent human papillomavirus (HPV) infection of stratified squamous epithelial cells causes nearly five percent of cancer cases worldwide. HPV-positive oropharyngeal cancers harbor few mutations in the Hippo signaling pathway compared to HPV-negative cancers at the same anatomical site, prompting the hypothesis that an HPV-encoded protein inactivates the Hippo pathway and activates the Hippo effector YAP1. The HPV E7 oncoprotein is required for HPV infection and for HPV-mediated oncogenic transformation. We investigated the effects of HPV oncoproteins on YAP1 and found that E7 activates YAP1, promoting YAP1 nuclear localization in basal epithelial cells. YAP1 activation by HPV E7 required that E7 bind and degrade the tumor suppressor PTPN14. E7 required YAP1 transcriptional activity to extend the lifespan of primary keratinocytes, indicating that YAP1 activation contributes to E7 carcinogenic activity. Maintaining infection in basal cells is critical for HPV persistence, and here we demonstrate that YAP1 activation causes HPV E7 expressing cells to be retained in the basal compartment of stratified epithelia. We propose that YAP1 activation resulting from PTPN14 inactivation is an essential, targetable activity of the HPV E7 oncoprotein relevant to HPV infection and carcinogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468068" rel="alternate" title="YAP1 Activation by Human Papillomavirus E7 Promotes Basal Cell Identity in Squamous Epithelia (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468026</id><title>Rapid antibiotic susceptibility testing and species identification for mixed infections (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.952433+00:00</updated><author><name>Vinodh Kandavalli</name></author><author><name>Praneeth Karempudi</name></author><author><name>Jimmy Larsson</name></author><author><name>Johan Elf</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antimicrobial resistance is an increasing problem globally. Rapid antibiotic susceptibility testing (AST) is urgently needed in the clinic to enable personalized prescription in high-resistance environments and limit the use of broad-spectrum drugs. Previously we have described a 30 min AST method based on imaging of individual bacterial cells. However, current phenotypic AST methods do not include species identification (ID), leaving time-consuming plating or culturing as the only available option when ID is needed to make the sensitivity call. Here we describe a method to perform phenotypic AST at the single-cell level in a microfluidic chip that allows subsequent genotyping by &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; FISH. By stratifying the phenotypic AST response on the species of individual cells, it is possible to determine the susceptibility profile for each species in a mixed infection sample in 1.5 h. In this proof-of-principle study, we demonstrate the operation with four antibiotics and a mixed sample with four species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468026" rel="alternate" title="Rapid antibiotic susceptibility testing and species identification for mixed infections (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468366</id><title>An interplay between viruses and bacteria associated with marine sponges from the White Sea revealed by metagenomics (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.952600+00:00</updated><author><name>Anastasiia Rusanova</name></author><author><name>Victor Fedorchuk</name></author><author><name>Stepan Toshchakov</name></author><author><name>Svetlana Dubiley</name></author><author><name>Dmitry Sutormin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sponges are remarkable holobionts harboring extremely diverse microbial and viral communities. However, the interactions between the components within holobionts and between a holobiont and environment are largely unknown, especially for polar organisms. To investigate possible interactions within the sponge-associated communities and between them, we probed the microbiomes and viromes of cold-water sympatric sponges Isodictya palmata, Halichondria panicea, and Halichondria sitiens by 16S and shotgun metagenomics. We showed that the bacterial and viral communities associated with these White Sea sponges are species-specific and different from the surrounding water. Extensive mining of bacterial antiphage defense systems in the metagenomes revealed a variety of defense mechanisms. The abundance of defense systems was comparable in the metagenomes of the sponges and the surrounding water, thus distinguishing the White Sea sponges from those inhabiting the tropical seas. We developed a network-based approach for the combined analysis of CRISPR-spacers and protospacers. Using this approach, we showed that the virus-host interactions within the sponge-associated community are typically more abundant than the inter-community interactions. Additionally, we detected the occurrence of viral exchanges between the communities. Our work provides the first insight into the metagenomics of the three cold-water sponge species from the White Sea and paves the way for a comprehensive analysis of the interactions between microbial communities and associated viruses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468366" rel="alternate" title="An interplay between viruses and bacteria associated with marine sponges from the White Sea revealed by metagenomics (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468188</id><title>Oxidative respiration through the bd-I and cbb3 oxidases is required for Vibrio cholerae pathogenicity and proliferation in vivo. (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.952747+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew John Van Alst</name></author><author><name>Lucas Maurice Demey</name></author><author><name>Victor DiRita</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Vibrio cholerae respires both aerobically and anaerobically and, while oxygen may be available to it during infection, other terminal electron acceptors are proposed for population expansion during infection. Unlike gastrointestinal pathogens that stimulate significant inflammation leading to elevated levels of oxygen or alternative terminal electron acceptors, V. cholerae  infections are not understood to induce a notable inflammatory response. To ascertain the respiration requirements of V. cholerae during infection, we used Multiplex Genome Editing by Natural Transformation (MuGENT) to create V. cholerae  strains lacking aerobic or anaerobic respiration. V. cholerae  strains lacking aerobic respiration were attenuated in infant mice 10  5  -fold relative to wild type, while strains lacking anaerobic respiration had no colonization defect, contrary to earlier work suggesting a role for anaerobic respiration during infection. Using several approaches, including one we developed for this work termed Comparative Multiplex PCR Amplicon Sequencing (CoMPAS), we determined that the bd-I and cbb3  oxidases are essential for small intestinal colonization of V. cholerae  in the infant mouse. The bd-I oxidase was also determined as the primary oxidase during growth outside the host, making  V. cholerae the only example of a Gram-negative bacterial pathogen in which a bd-type oxidase is the primary oxidase for energy acquisition inside and outside of a host.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468188" rel="alternate" title="Oxidative respiration through the bd-I and cbb3 oxidases is required for Vibrio cholerae pathogenicity and proliferation in vivo. (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468135</id><title>STAT1 Gain-of-Function Variants Drive Altered T Cell Prevalence, Metabolism, and Heightened IL-6 Sensitivity (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.952879+00:00</updated><author><name>Saara Kaviany</name></author><author><name>Todd Bartkowiak</name></author><author><name>Daniel E Dulek</name></author><author><name>Yasmin W Khan</name></author><author><name>Madeline J Hayes</name></author><author><name>Samuel K Schaefer</name></author><author><name>Debolanle O. Dahunsi</name></author><author><name>James A Connelly</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Michael Irish</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey C. Rathmell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Patients with Signal Transducer and Activator of Transcription 1 (STAT1) gain-of-function (GOF) pathogenic variants exhibit susceptibility to infections, autoimmunity, and cancer due to enhanced or prolonged STAT1 phosphorylation following cytokine stimulation.  While interferons (IFNs) are canonical STAT1 activators, other cytokines that may also contribute to pathology in STAT1 GOF patients have been less well defined.  Here we analyzed the immune profiles and cytokine responses of two patients with heterozygous GOF mutations in the STAT1 coiled-coil domain.  A systems immunology approach revealed major changes in the T cell compartment and minor changes in the B cells, NK cells, and myeloid cells.  Both patients with STAT1 GOF differed from healthy individuals in the abundance and phenotype of effector memory, Th17, and Treg populations.  STAT1 GOF T cells displayed a pattern of increased activation and had elevated markers of glycolysis and lipid oxidation.  Hypersensitivity of T cells to IL-6 was observed with intense, sustained STAT1 phosphorylation in memory T cell populations that exceeded that induced by IFNs.  Together, these results show a role for STAT1 in T cell metabolism and suggest that IL-6 may play a critical role to promote T cell memory formation and activation in patients with STAT1 GOF.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468135" rel="alternate" title="STAT1 Gain-of-Function Variants Drive Altered T Cell Prevalence, Metabolism, and Heightened IL-6 Sensitivity (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468120</id><title>Human gut derived Anaerotruncus colihominis ameliorates experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.953102+00:00</updated><author><name>Paola Bianchimano</name></author><author><name>Graham J. Britton</name></author><author><name>David S. Wallach</name></author><author><name>Emma M. Smith</name></author><author><name>Laura M. Cox</name></author><author><name>Shirong Liu</name></author><author><name>Howard L. Weiner</name></author><author><name>Jeremiah J. Faith</name></author><author><name>Jose C. Clemente</name></author><author><name>Stephanie K. Tankou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The gut microbiome plays an important role in autoimmunity including multiple sclerosis and its mouse model called experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis (EAE). The gut-brain axis refers to the complex interactions between the gut microbiota and the nervous and immune systems linking brain and gut functions. Prior studies have demonstrated that the multiple sclerosis gut microbiota can contribute to disease hence making it a potential therapeutic target. Other studies have reported that long-term antibiotic therapy in multiple sclerosis patients reduces relapse rate and gadolinium enhancing lesions as well as improves measures of disability. In addition, antibiotic treatment has been shown to ameliorate disease in the EAE mouse model of multiple sclerosis. Yet, to this date, the mechanisms mediating these antibiotics effects are not understood. Furthermore, there is no consensus on the gut derived bacterial strains that drive neuroinflammation in multiple sclerosis. Hence, it remains unclear how the gut microbiota can be targeted for therapeutic purposes in multiple sclerosis patients. Here we characterized the gut microbiome of untreated and vancomycin treated EAE mice over time to identify bacteria with neuroimmunomodulatory potential. We observed alterations in the gut microbiota composition following EAE induction. We found that vancomycin treatment ameliorates EAE and that this protective effect is mediated via the microbiota. Notably, we observed increase abundance of bacteria known to be strong inducers of regulatory T cells including members of Clostridium clusters XIVa and XVIII in vancomycin-treated mice during the presymptomatic phase of EAE as well as at disease peak. We identified 50 bacterial taxa that correlate with EAE severity. Interestingly, several of these taxa exist in the human gut and some of them have been implicated in multiple sclerosis including &lt;italic&gt;Anaerotruncus colihominis&lt;/italic&gt; which had a positive correlation with disease severity. Unexpectedly, we found that &lt;italic&gt;Anaerotruncus colihominis&lt;/italic&gt; ameliorates EAE and this is associated with induction of RORγt&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; regulatory T cells in the mesenteric lymph nodes. Together, our results identify vancomycin as a potent modulator of the gut-brain axis by promoting the proliferation of bacterial species that induce regulatory T cells. In addition, our findings reveal 50 gut commensals as regulator of the gut-brain axis that can be used to further characterize pathogenic and beneficial hostmicrobiota interactions in multiple sclerosis patients. Our findings suggest that elevated &lt;italic&gt;Anaerotruncus colihominis&lt;/italic&gt; in multiple sclerosis patients may represent a protective mechanism associated with recovery from the disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468120" rel="alternate" title="Human gut derived Anaerotruncus colihominis ameliorates experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467808</id><title>Microbial signals and lymphotoxin drive TNF-independent death of A20 and ABIN-1 deficient epithelium (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.953281+00:00</updated><author><name>Iulia Rusu</name></author><author><name>Elvira Mennillo</name></author><author><name>Zhongmei Li</name></author><author><name>Jared L. Bain</name></author><author><name>Xiaofei Sun</name></author><author><name>Kimberly Ly</name></author><author><name>Yenny Y. Rosli</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Naser</name></author><author><name>Zunqiu Wang</name></author><author><name>Rommel Advincula</name></author><author><name>Philip Achacoso</name></author><author><name>Ling Shao</name></author><author><name>Bahram Razani</name></author><author><name>Ophir D. Klein</name></author><author><name>Alexander Marson</name></author><author><name>Jessie A. Turnbaugh</name></author><author><name>Peter J. Turnbaugh</name></author><author><name>Barbara A. Malynn</name></author><author><name>Averil Ma</name></author><author><name>Michael G. Kattah</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Anti-TNF antibodies are effective for treating patients with inflammatory bowel disease (IBD), but many patients fail to respond to anti-TNF therapy, highlighting the importance of TNF-independent disease. We previously demonstrated that acute deletion of two IBD susceptibility genes, &lt;italic&gt;A20&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Tnfaip3&lt;/italic&gt;) and &lt;italic&gt;Abin-1&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Tnip1&lt;/italic&gt;), in intestinal epithelial cells (IECs) sensitizes mice to both TNF-dependent and TNF-independent death. Here we show that TNF-independent IEC death after &lt;italic&gt;A20&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Abin-1&lt;/italic&gt; deletion is rescued by germ-free derivation or deletion of &lt;italic&gt;MyD88&lt;/italic&gt;, while deletion of &lt;italic&gt;Trif&lt;/italic&gt; provides only partial protection. Combined deletion of &lt;italic&gt;Ripk3&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Casp8&lt;/italic&gt;, which inhibits both apoptotic and necroptotic death, completely protects against death after acute deletion of &lt;italic&gt;A20&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Abin-1&lt;/italic&gt; in IECs. &lt;italic&gt;A20&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Abin-1&lt;/italic&gt;-deficient IECs are sensitized to TNF-independent, TNFR-1-mediated death in response to lymphotoxin alpha (LTα) homotrimers. Blockade of LTα &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; reduces weight loss and improves survival when combined with partial deletion of &lt;italic&gt;MyD88&lt;/italic&gt;. These data show that microbial signals, &lt;italic&gt;MyD88&lt;/italic&gt;, and LTα all contribute to TNF-independent intestinal injury.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we show that germ-free derivation, MyD88 deletion, combined Ripk3 and Casp8 deletion, or anti-LTα, all reduce TNF-independent intestinal injury after &lt;italic&gt;A20&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Abin-1&lt;/italic&gt; deletion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467808" rel="alternate" title="Microbial signals and lymphotoxin drive TNF-independent death of A20 and ABIN-1 deficient epithelium (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468455</id><title>Biosorption potential and molecular characterization of metal resistant autochthonous microbes from tannery solid waste (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.953630+00:00</updated><author><name>Hajira Younas</name></author><author><name>Aisha Nazir</name></author><author><name>Zakia Latif</name></author><author><name>Janice E Thies</name></author><author><name>Muhammad Shafiq</name></author><author><name>Firdaus e Bareen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This study encompasses isolation and screening of heavy metal-resistant fungal and bacterial strains from tannery solid waste (TSW). Twelve fungal strains and twenty-five bacterial strains were isolated from TSW. The growth of fungal strains was observed against different heavy metals ranging from 10 mg L  -1  to 1050 mg L  -1  and the growth of bacteria was observed in metal concentrations ranging from 10 mg L  -1  to 1200 mg L  -1  . Five multi-metal resistant fungal isolates belonging to the genus  Trichoderma  and ten bacterial isolates belonging to the genus  Bacillus  showed good metal resistance and biosorption potential. They were identified through molecular techniques, fungi based on ITS region ribotyping, and bacteria based on 16S rRNA ribotyping. The fungal strains were characterized as  T. hamatum  (TSWF-06),  T. harzianum  (TSWF-11),  T. lixii  (TSWF-02) and  T. pseudokoningii  (TSWF-03, TSWF-10). The bacterial strains were characterized as  Bacillus xiamenensis  (TSW-02),  B. velezensis  (TSW-05),  B. piscis  (TSW-06),  B. safensis  (TSW-10),  B. subtilis  (TSW-14, TSW-15, TSW-17)  B. licheniformis  (TSW-19),  B. cereus  (TSW-20) and  B. thuringiensis  (TSW-22). The fungal strains namely,  T. pseudokoningii  (TSWF-03) and  T. harzianum  proved to be two multi-metal resistant strains with good biosorption efficiency. Unlike fungi, bacterial strains showed metal specific resistance. The strains  Bacillus xiamenensis  ,  B. subtilis  (TSW-14) and  B. subtilis  (TSW-15) showed good biosorption efficiency against Cr,  B. safensis  against Cu,  B. piscis and B. subtilis  (TSW-17) against Pb and  B. licheniformis  and  B. thuringiensis  against Zn. The autochthonous fungal and bacterial strains can therefore be employed to clean metal contaminated environments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468455" rel="alternate" title="Biosorption potential and molecular characterization of metal resistant autochthonous microbes from tannery solid waste (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>