<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.441396+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465200</id><title>Cell-extrinsic autophagy in mature adipocytes regulates anti-inflammatory response to intestinal tissue injury through lipid mobilization (52 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.442400+00:00</updated><author><name>Felix Clemens Richter</name></author><author><name>Matthias Friedrich</name></author><author><name>Mathilde Pohin</name></author><author><name>Ghada Alsaleh</name></author><author><name>Irina Guschina</name></author><author><name>Sarah Karin Wideman</name></author><author><name>Errin Johnson</name></author><author><name>Mariana Borsa</name></author><author><name>Klara Piletic</name></author><author><name>Paula Hahn</name></author><author><name>Henk Simon Schipper</name></author><author><name>Claire M. Edwards</name></author><author><name>Fiona Powrie</name></author><author><name>Anna Katharina Simon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Autophagy is a critical cellular recycling pathway which is genetically linked to the development of intestinal inflammation in humans. Inflammation drives adipose tissue breakdown and provision of major nutrients such as free fatty acids (FFA). However, the effect of autophagy-mediated FFA release by adipocytes in immune-mediated inflammatory diseases remains unexplored.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a mouse model of intestinal inflammation, we found that visceral adipocytes upregulate autophagy at peak inflammation. Adipocyte-specific loss of the key autophagy gene &lt;italic&gt;Atg7&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Atg7&lt;sup&gt;Ad&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt;) resulted in the exacerbation of intestinal inflammation. TNFα-induced lipolysis was impaired in &lt;italic&gt;Atg7&lt;/italic&gt;-deficient adipocytes leading to the reduced availability of several FFA species, and decreased expression of the FFA transporter CD36 on adipose tissue macrophages (ATMs). Visceral adipose tissues from &lt;italic&gt;Atg7&lt;sup&gt;Ad&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice released less IL-10 resulting in lower levels of circulating IL-10 in colitis. ATMs present the main source of adipose tissue-derived IL-10 during colitis. &lt;italic&gt;In vitro&lt;/italic&gt; assays confirmed that FFA restriction from macrophages reduced CD36 expression and diminished IL-10 production.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Taken together, our study demonstrates that autophagy-mediated FFA release from adipocytes directs anti-inflammatory responses in ATMs, which in turn conveys protective effects for distant intestinal inflammation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465200" rel="alternate" title="Cell-extrinsic autophagy in mature adipocytes regulates anti-inflammatory response to intestinal tissue injury through lipid mobilization (52 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465989</id><title>Evolutionary instability of collateral susceptibility networks in ciprofloxacin resistant clinical Escherichia coli strains (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.443418+00:00</updated><author><name>Vidar Sørum</name></author><author><name>Emma L. Øynes</name></author><author><name>Anna S. Møller</name></author><author><name>Klaus Harms</name></author><author><name>Ørjan Samuelsen</name></author><author><name>Nicole L. Podnecky</name></author><author><name>Pål J. Johnsen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Collateral sensitivity and resistance occur when resistance development towards one antimicrobial either potentiates or deteriorates the effect of others, respectively. Previous reports on collateral effects on susceptibility focus on newly acquired resistance determinants and propose that novel treatment guidelines informed by collateral networks may reduce the evolution, selection and spread of antimicrobial resistance. In this study, we investigate the evolutionary stability of collateral networks in five ciprofloxacin resistant, clinical &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; strains. After 300 generations of experimental evolution without antimicrobials, we show complete fitness restoration in four of five genetic backgrounds and demonstrate evolutionary instability in collateral networks of newly acquired resistance determinants. We show that compensatory mutations reducing efflux expression is the main driver destabilizing initial collateral networks and identify &lt;italic&gt;rpoS&lt;/italic&gt; as a putative target for compensatory evolution. Our results add another layer of complexity to future predictions and clinical application of collateral networks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465989" rel="alternate" title="Evolutionary instability of collateral susceptibility networks in ciprofloxacin resistant clinical Escherichia coli strains (37 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465810</id><title>Transmission of Klebsiella strains and plasmids within and between Grey-headed flying fox colonies (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.443751+00:00</updated><author><name>Ben Vezina</name></author><author><name>Louise M. Judd</name></author><author><name>Fiona K. McDougall</name></author><author><name>Wayne S.J. Boardman</name></author><author><name>Michelle L. Power</name></author><author><name>Jane Hawkey</name></author><author><name>Sylvain Brisse</name></author><author><name>Jonathan M. Monk</name></author><author><name>Kathryn E. Holt</name></author><author><name>Kelly L. Wyres</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Grey-headed flying fox (&lt;italic&gt;Pteropus poliocephalus&lt;/italic&gt;) is an endemic Australian fruit bat, known to carry pathogens with zoonotic potential. We recently showed these bats harbour the bacterial pathogens &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; and closely related species in the &lt;italic&gt;K. pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; species complex (&lt;italic&gt;Kp&lt;/italic&gt;SC). However, the dynamics of &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella&lt;/italic&gt; transmission and gene flow within flying fox colonies were not explored and remain poorly understood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we report a high-resolution genomic comparison of 39 &lt;italic&gt;Kp&lt;/italic&gt;SC isolates from Greyheaded flying foxes. Illumina whole genome sequences (n=39) were assembled &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; and the Kleborate genotyping tool was used to infer sequence types (STs). Oxford Nanopore sequences were generated for 13 isolates (one for each distinct ST) in order to generate high-quality completed reference genomes. Read mapping and variant calling was used to identify single nucleotide variants (SNVs) within each ST, using the relevant reference genome. &lt;italic&gt;In silico&lt;/italic&gt; genome-scale metabolic models were generated to predict and compare substrate usage to 59 previously published &lt;italic&gt;Kp&lt;/italic&gt;SC models for isolates from human and environmental sources, which indicated no distinction on the basis of metabolic capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;High-resolution genome comparisons identified five putative strain transmission clusters (four intra- and one inter-colony, n=2-15 isolates each, ≤25 pairwise SNVs). Inter-colony transmission of &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella africana&lt;/italic&gt; was found between two flying fox populations located within flying distance. The 13 completed genomes harboured 11 plasmids, all of which showed 37-98% coverage (mean 73%) and ≥95% identity to those previously reported from human-associated &lt;italic&gt;Kp&lt;/italic&gt;SC. Comparison of plasmids from different flying fox associated &lt;italic&gt;Kp&lt;/italic&gt;SC indicated an interspecies horizontal plasmid transmission between &lt;italic&gt;K. pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;K. africana&lt;/italic&gt; for a 98 kbp plasmid, pFF1003.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These data indicate that &lt;italic&gt;Kp&lt;/italic&gt;SC are able to transmit directly via flying fox populations or indirectly via a common source, and that these isolates can harbour plasmids with similarity to those found in human derived &lt;italic&gt;Kp&lt;/italic&gt;SC, indicating gene flow is occurring between isolates from Grey-headed flying fox &lt;italic&gt;Kp&lt;/italic&gt;SC and human clinical isolates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465810" rel="alternate" title="Transmission of Klebsiella strains and plasmids within and between Grey-headed flying fox colonies (37 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465843</id><title>Diversity, function and evolution of marine microbe genomes (25 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.444193+00:00</updated><author><name>Jianwei Chen</name></author><author><name>Yang Guo</name></author><author><name>Yangyang Jia</name></author><author><name>Guilin Liu</name></author><author><name>Denghui Li</name></author><author><name>Dayou Xu</name></author><author><name>Bing Wang</name></author><author><name>Li Zhou</name></author><author><name>Ling Peng</name></author><author><name>Fang Zhao</name></author><author><name>Yuanfang Zhu</name></author><author><name>Jiahui Sun</name></author><author><name>Chen Ye</name></author><author><name>Jun Wang</name></author><author><name>He Zhang</name></author><author><name>Shanshan Liu</name></author><author><name>Inge Seim</name></author><author><name>Xin Liu</name></author><author><name>Xun Xu</name></author><author><name>Huanming Yang</name></author><author><name>Karsten Kristiansen</name></author><author><name>Guangyi Fan</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Trillions of marine bacterial, archaeal and viral species contribute to the majority diversity of life on Earth. In the current study, we have done a comprehensive review of all the published studies of marine microbiome by re-analyzing most of the available high throughput sequencing data. We collected 17.59 Tb sequencing data from 8,165 metagenomic and prokaryotic samples, and systematically evaluated the genome characters, including genome size, GC content, phylogeny, and the functional and ecological roles of several typical phyla. A genome catalogue of 9,070 high quality genomes and a gene catalogue including 156,209,709 genes were constructed, representing the most integrate marine prokaryotic datasets till now. The genome size of Alphaproteobacteria and Actinobacteria was significant correlated to their GC content. A total of 44,322 biosynthetic gene clusters distributed in 53 types were detected from the reconstructed marine prokaryotic genome catalogue. Phylogenetic annotation of the 8,380 bacterial and 690 archaeal species revealed that most of the known bacterial phyla (99/111), including 62 classes and 181 orders, and four extra unclassified genomes from two candidate novel phyla were detected. In addition, taxonomically unclassified species represented a substantial fraction of 64.56% and 80.29% of the phylogenetic diversity of Bacteria and Archaea respectively. The genomic and ecological features of three groups of Cyanobacteria, luminous bacteria and methane-metabolizing archaea, including inhabitant preference, geolocation distribution and others were through discussed. Our database provides a comprehensive resource for marine microbiome, which would be a valuable reference for studies of marine life origination and evolution, ecology monitor and protection, bioactive compound development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465843" rel="alternate" title="Diversity, function and evolution of marine microbe genomes (25 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465934</id><title>Open chromatin analysis in Trypanosoma cruzi life forms highlights critical differences in genomic compartments and developmental regulation at tDNA loci (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.444896+00:00</updated><author><name>Alex Ranieri Jerônimo Lima</name></author><author><name>Saloe Bispo Poubel</name></author><author><name>Juliana Nunes Rosón</name></author><author><name>Loyze Paola Oliveira de Lima</name></author><author><name>Héllida Marina Costa-Silva</name></author><author><name>Herbert Guimarães de Sousa Silva</name></author><author><name>Camila Silva Gonçalves</name></author><author><name>Pedro A. F. Galante</name></author><author><name>Fabiola Holetz</name></author><author><name>Maria Cristina Machado M. Motta</name></author><author><name>Ariel M. Silber</name></author><author><name>M. Carolina Elias</name></author><author><name>Julia Pinheiro Chagas da Cunha</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Genomic organization and gene expression regulation in trypanosomes are remarkable because protein-coding genes are organized into codirectional gene clusters with unrelated functions. Moreover, there is no dedicated promoter for each gene, resulting in polycistronic gene transcription, with posttranscriptional control playing a major role. Nonetheless, these parasites harbor epigenetic modifications at critical regulatory genome features that dynamically change among parasite stages, which are not fully understood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we investigated the impact of chromatin changes in a scenario commanded by posttranscriptional control exploring the parasite &lt;italic&gt;Trypanosoma cruzi&lt;/italic&gt; and its differentiation program using genome-wide approaches supported by transmission electron microscopy. The integration of FAIRE and MNase-seq data, two complementary epigenomic approaches, enabled us to identify differences in &lt;italic&gt;T. cruzi&lt;/italic&gt; genome compartments, putative transcriptional start regions and virulence factors. In addition, we also detected developmental chromatin regulation at tRNA loci (tDNA), which seems to be linked to the translation regulatory mechanism required for parasite differentiation. Strikingly, a positive correlation was observed between active chromatin and steady-state transcription levels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Taken together, our results indicate that chromatin changes reflect the unusual gene expression regulation of trypanosomes and the differences among parasite developmental stages, even in the context of a lack of canonical transcriptional control of protein-coding genes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465934" rel="alternate" title="Open chromatin analysis in Trypanosoma cruzi life forms highlights critical differences in genomic compartments and developmental regulation at tDNA loci (23 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465990</id><title>Geological processes mediate a subsurface microbial loop in the deep biosphere (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.451866+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel A. Gittins</name></author><author><name>Pierre-Arnaud Desiage</name></author><author><name>Natasha Morrison</name></author><author><name>Jayne E. Rattray</name></author><author><name>Srijak Bhatnagar</name></author><author><name>Anirban Chakraborty</name></author><author><name>Jackie Zorz</name></author><author><name>Carmen Li</name></author><author><name>Oliver Horanszky</name></author><author><name>Margaret A. Cramm</name></author><author><name>Jamie Webb</name></author><author><name>Adam MacDonald</name></author><author><name>Martin Fowler</name></author><author><name>D. Calvin Campbell</name></author><author><name>Casey R. J. Hubert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The deep biosphere is the largest microbial habitat on Earth and features abundant bacterial endospores&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt;. Whereas dormancy and survival at theoretical energy minima are hallmarks of subsurface microbial populations&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;, the roles of fundamental ecological processes like dispersal and selection in these environments are poorly understood&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;. Here we combine geophysics, geochemistry, microbiology and genomics to investigate biogeography in the subsurface, focusing on bacterial endospores in a deep-sea setting characterized by thermogenic hydrocarbon seepage. Thermophilic endospores in permanently cold seabed sediments above petroleum seep conduits were correlated with the presence of hydrocarbons, revealing geofluid-facilitated cell migration pathways originating in deep oil reservoirs. Genomes of thermophilic bacteria highlight adaptations to life in anoxic petroleum systems and reveal that these dormant populations are closely related to oil reservoir microbiomes from around the world. After transport out of the subsurface and into the deep-sea, thermophilic endospores re-enter the geosphere by sedimentation. Viable thermophilic endospores spanning the top several metres of the seabed correspond with total endospore counts that are similar to or exceed the global average. Burial of dormant cells enables their environmental selection in sedimentary formations where new petroleum systems establish, completing a geological microbial loop that circulates living biomass in and out of the deep biosphere.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465990" rel="alternate" title="Geological processes mediate a subsurface microbial loop in the deep biosphere (17 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466428</id><title>Assassination Tango: An NLR/NLR-ID immune receptors pair of rapeseed co-operates inside the nucleus to activate cell death (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.452228+00:00</updated><author><name>Glykeria Mermigka</name></author><author><name>Argyro Amartolou</name></author><author><name>Adriani Mentzelopoulou</name></author><author><name>Niki Astropekaki</name></author><author><name>Panagiotis F. Sarris</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Plant immunity relies on cell-surface receptors and intracellular NLR immune receptors. Some plant NLRs carry integrated domains (IDs) that that mimic authentic pathogens effector targets. We report here the identification in Brassica napus of the genetically linked NLR/NLR-ID pair, BnRPR1 and BnRPR2. The NLR-ID carries two ID fusions and their mode of action conforms to the proposed integrated sensor/decoy model. The two NLRs interact and the heterocomplex localizes in the plant-cell nucleus and nucleolus. However, the BnRPRs pair does not operate through a negative regulation as it was previously reported for other NLR-IDs. Cell death is induced only upon co-expression of the two proteins and it is dependent on the helper genes EDS1 and NRG1. Truncations of the IDs of BnRPR1 results in cytoplasmic localization and compromises cell death activation. Expression, using the native promoter in Nicotiana species, led to a conditional cell death induction. However, this was not the case for the transgenic Arabidopsis, where no cell death was observed. In summary, we describe a new pair of NLR-IDs with interesting features in relation to its regulation and the cell death activation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466428" rel="alternate" title="Assassination Tango: An NLR/NLR-ID immune receptors pair of rapeseed co-operates inside the nucleus to activate cell death (12 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.22.465535</id><title>Rare modification in the ergosterol biosynthesis pathway leads to amphotericin B resistance in Candida auris clinical isolates (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.452429+00:00</updated><author><name>Milena Kordalewska</name></author><author><name>Kevin D. Guerrero</name></author><author><name>Timothy D. Mikulski</name></author><author><name>Tony N. Elias</name></author><author><name>Rocio Garcia-Rubio</name></author><author><name>Indira Berrío</name></author><author><name>Dianne Gardam</name></author><author><name>Christopher H. Heath</name></author><author><name>Anuradha Chowdhary</name></author><author><name>Nelesh Premapragasan Govender</name></author><author><name>David S Perlin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We determined amphotericin B (AmB) susceptibility and sequenced key genes of the ergosterol biosynthesis pathway implicated in AmB resistance (&lt;italic&gt;ERG2, ERG3, ERG6, ERG11&lt;/italic&gt;) of 321 clinical isolates of &lt;italic&gt;Candida auris&lt;/italic&gt;. In antifungal susceptibility testing, 19 (5.9%) isolates were categorized as AmB-resistant (MIC ≥2 mg/l). Only one AmB-resistant isolate presented a unique non-wild-type &lt;italic&gt;ERG6&lt;/italic&gt; genotype that was confirmed to confer amphotericin B resistance (MIC &amp;gt;32 mg/l) when introduced into a susceptible strain (MIC = 0.5 mg/l).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.22.465535" rel="alternate" title="Rare modification in the ergosterol biosynthesis pathway leads to amphotericin B resistance in Candida auris clinical isolates (12 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.466009</id><title>Total parenteral nutrition drives glucose metabolism disorders by modulating gut microbiota and its metabolites (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.452672+00:00</updated><author><name>Haifeng Sun</name></author><author><name>Peng Wang</name></author><author><name>Gulisudumu Maitiabula</name></author><author><name>Li Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jianbo Yang</name></author><author><name>Yupeng Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xuejin Gao</name></author><author><name>Jieshou Li</name></author><author><name>Bin Xue</name></author><author><name>Chao-Jun Li</name></author><author><name>Xinying Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The occurrence of glucose metabolism disorders is a potentially fatal complication of total parenteral nutrition (TPN). However, the mechanisms of TPN-associated glucose metabolism disorders remain unclarified. Given that the glucose metabolism was related to gut microbiome and TPN could induce the gut microbiota dysbiosis, we hypothesized that gut microbiota and its metabolites played the important roles in TPN-associated glucose metabolism disorders. By performing a cohort study of 256 type 2 IF patients given PN, we found that H-PN (PN&amp;gt;80%) patients exhibited insulin resistance and a higher risk of complications. Then, TPN and microbiome transfer mice model showed that TPN promoted glucose metabolism disorders by inducing gut microbiota dysbiosis; 16S rRNA sequencing demonstrated that the abundance of &lt;italic&gt;Lactobacillacea&lt;/italic&gt;e was decreased in mice model and negatively correlated with HOMA-IR and lipopolysaccharide level in TPN patients. Untargeted metabolomics found that indole-3-acetic acid (IAA) was decreased in TPN mice, and the serum level was also decreased in H-PN patients. Furthermore, GLP-1 secretion regulated by IAA and aryl hydrocarbon receptor was reduced in TPN mice and patients; IAA or liraglutide completely prevented glucose metabolism disorders in TPN mice. In conclusion, TPN drives glucose metabolism disorders by inducing alteration of gut microbiota and its metabolites.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.466009" rel="alternate" title="Total parenteral nutrition drives glucose metabolism disorders by modulating gut microbiota and its metabolites (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465851</id><title>Fungal auxin is a quorum-based modulator of blast disease severity (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.453021+00:00</updated><author><name>Lihong Dong</name></author><author><name>Qing Shen</name></author><author><name>Cheng-yen Chen</name></author><author><name>Lizheng Shen</name></author><author><name>Fan Yang</name></author><author><name>Naweed I. Naqvi</name></author><author><name>Yi Zhen Deng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Auxin is an important phytohormone regulating plant growth and development, and can also be produced by microbial pathogens including the rice-blast fungus &lt;italic&gt;Magnaporthe oryzae&lt;/italic&gt;. However, the detailed biosynthesis pathway, biological function(s), and cellular distribution of such fungal auxin in &lt;italic&gt;M. oryzae&lt;/italic&gt; remain largely unknown. Here, we report a sequential accumulation of intrinsic auxin in the three conidial cells, the infection structure (appressorium), and the invasive hyphae in &lt;italic&gt;M. oryzae&lt;/italic&gt;. Such fungus-derived auxin was also secreted out and perceived by the host plants. A mitochondria-associated Indole-3-pyruvate decarboxylase, Ipd1, is essential for auxin/Indole-3-acetic acid biosynthesis in &lt;italic&gt;M. oryzae&lt;/italic&gt;. The &lt;italic&gt;ipd1&lt;/italic&gt;Δ was defective in pathogenicity whereas overexpression of &lt;italic&gt;IPD1&lt;/italic&gt; led to enhanced virulence in rice. Chemical inhibition of fungal IAA biosynthesis, or its increase via external supplementation decreased or increased the severity of blast disease, respectively, in a dose-dependent manner. Furthermore, the IAA produced and secreted by &lt;italic&gt;M. oryzae&lt;/italic&gt; governed the incidence and severity of blast disease in a quorum-dependent manner. Appressorium formation, conidial cell death critical for appressorium function, and the transcription of infection-related genes, &lt;italic&gt;MPG1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;INV1&lt;/italic&gt;, directly correlated with cell density and/or IAA levels within the conidial population at the early stages of pathogenic development. Overall, our study revealed that the severity of blast disease is regulated via quorum sensing with intrinsic IAA serving as an associated signal transducer in rice blast.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465851" rel="alternate" title="Fungal auxin is a quorum-based modulator of blast disease severity (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466260</id><title>RACK1 associates with RNA-binding proteins Vigilin and SERBP1 to control dengue virus replication (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.453243+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexis Brugier</name></author><author><name>Mohamed-Lamine Hafirassou</name></author><author><name>Marie Pourcelot</name></author><author><name>Morgane Baldaccini</name></author><author><name>Laurine Couture</name></author><author><name>Vasiliya Kril</name></author><author><name>Beate Kuemmerer</name></author><author><name>Sarah Gallois-Montbrun</name></author><author><name>Lucie Bonnet-Madin</name></author><author><name>Sebastien Pfeffer</name></author><author><name>Pierre-Olivier Vidalain</name></author><author><name>Constance Delaugerre</name></author><author><name>Laurent Meertens</name></author><author><name>Ali Amara</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Dengue virus (DENV), a re-emerging virus transmitted by Aedes mosquitoes, causes severe pathogenesis in humans. No effective treatment is available against this virus. We recently identified the scaffold protein RACK1 as a component of the DENV replication complex, a macromolecular complex essential for viral genome amplification. Here, we show that RACK1 is important for DENV infection. RACK1 mediates DENV replication through binding to the 40S ribosomal subunit. Mass spectrometry analysis of RACK1 partners coupled to a loss-of-function screen identified the RNA binding proteins Vigilin and SERBP1 as DENV host dependency factors. Vigilin and SERBP1 interact with DENV viral RNA (vRNA), forming a ternary complex with RACK1 to mediate viral replication. Overall, our results indicate that RACK1 recruits Vigilin and SERBP1, linking the DENV vRNA to the translation machinery for optimal translation and replication.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466260" rel="alternate" title="RACK1 associates with RNA-binding proteins Vigilin and SERBP1 to control dengue virus replication (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466454</id><title>Steroid hormone catabolites activate the pyrin inflammasome through a non-canonical mechanism (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.453656+00:00</updated><author><name>Flora Magnotti</name></author><author><name>Daria Chirita</name></author><author><name>Sarah Dalmon</name></author><author><name>Amandine Martin</name></author><author><name>Pauline Bronnec</name></author><author><name>Jeremy Sousa</name></author><author><name>olivier Helynck</name></author><author><name>Wonyong Lee</name></author><author><name>Daniel Kastner</name></author><author><name>Jae Jin Chae</name></author><author><name>Michael McDermott</name></author><author><name>alexandre Belot</name></author><author><name>Michel Popoff</name></author><author><name>Pascal Seve</name></author><author><name>Sophie Georgin-Lavialle</name></author><author><name>Helene Munier-Lehmann</name></author><author><name>Tu anh TRAN</name></author><author><name>Ellen De Langhe</name></author><author><name>Carine Wouters</name></author><author><name>Yvan Jamilloux</name></author><author><name>Thomas Henry</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The pyrin inflammasome acts as a guard of RhoA GTPases and is central to immune defences against RhoA-manipulating pathogens. Pyrin activation proceeds in two steps. Yet, the second step is still poorly understood. Using cells constitutively activated for the pyrin step 1, a chemical screen identified etiocholanolone and pregnanolone, two catabolites of testosterone and progesterone, acting at low concentrations as specific step-2 activators. High concentrations of these metabolites fully and rapidly activated pyrin, in a human-specific, B30.2 domain-dependent manner and without inhibiting RhoA. Mutations in MEFV, encoding pyrin, cause two distinct autoinflammatory diseases (PAAND and FMF). Monocytes from PAAND patients, and to a lower extent from FMF patients, displayed increased responses to these metabolites. This study provides a new perspective on pyrin activation, indicates that endogenous steroid catabolites can drive autoinflammation, through the pyrin inflammasome, and explains the "steroid fever" described in the late 1950s, upon steroid injection in humans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466454" rel="alternate" title="Steroid hormone catabolites activate the pyrin inflammasome through a non-canonical mechanism (9 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465098</id><title>Adenovirus-α-defensin complexes induce NLRP3-associated maturation of human phagocytes via TLR4 engagement (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.454131+00:00</updated><author><name>Karsten Eichholz</name></author><author><name>Tuan Hiep Tran</name></author><author><name>Coraline Chéneau</name></author><author><name>Thi Thu Phuong Tran</name></author><author><name>Océane Paris</name></author><author><name>Martine Pugniere</name></author><author><name>Eric J Kremer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Intramuscular delivery of human adenovirus (HAdV)-based vaccines leads to rapid recruitment of neutrophils, which then release antimicrobial peptides/proteins (AMPs). How these AMPs influence vaccine efficacy over the subsequent 24 hr is poorly understood. In this study, we asked if human neutrophil protein 1 (HNP-1), an α-defensin that influences the direct and indirect innate immune responses to a range of pathogens, impacts the innate response of human phagocytes to three HAdV species/types (HAdV-C5, -D26, -B35). We show that HNP-1 binds to the capsids, redirects HAdV-C5, -D26, -B35 to Toll-like receptor 4 (TLR4), which leads to internalization, an NLRP3-mediated inflammasome response, and IL-1β release. Surprisingly, IL-1β release was not associated with notable disruption of plasma membrane integrity. These data further our understanding of HAdV innate immunogenicity and may provide pathways to extend HAdV-based vaccines efficacy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465098" rel="alternate" title="Adenovirus-α-defensin complexes induce NLRP3-associated maturation of human phagocytes via TLR4 engagement (7 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.465965</id><title>Impact of a 7-day homogeneous diet on interpersonal variation in human gut microbiomes and metabolomes (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.454444+00:00</updated><author><name>Leah Guthrie</name></author><author><name>Sean Spencer</name></author><author><name>Dalia Perelman</name></author><author><name>Will Van Treuren</name></author><author><name>Shuo Han</name></author><author><name>Feiqiao Brian Yu</name></author><author><name>Erica Sonnenburg</name></author><author><name>Michael A Fischbach</name></author><author><name>Timothy W. Meyer</name></author><author><name>Justin Sonnenburg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Metabolism of dietary compounds by the gut microbiota generates a vast array of microbiome-dependent metabolites (MDMs), which are highly variable between individuals. The uremic MDMs (uMDMs) phenylacetylglutamine (PAG), p-cresol sulfate (PCS) and indoxyl sulfate (IS) accumulate during renal failure and are associated with poor outcomes. Targeted dietary interventions may reduce toxic MDMs generation; however, it is unclear if interindividual differences in diet or gut microbiome dominantly contribute to MDM variance. Here we use a 7-day homogeneous average American diet to standardize dietary precursor availability in 21 healthy individuals. Notably, the coefficient of variation in three uMDMs of interest, PAG, PCS, and IS (primary outcome), did not significantly decrease. The majority of circulating MDMs maintained variation despite identical diets. These results highlight the highly personalized profile of MDMs and limited contribution of short-term dietary heterogeneity, suggesting that dietary modification may need to be paired with microbial therapies to control MDM profiles.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.465965" rel="alternate" title="Impact of a 7-day homogeneous diet on interpersonal variation in human gut microbiomes and metabolomes (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465908</id><title>HIV-1 envelope glycoproteins proteolytic cleavage protects infected cells from ADCC mediated by plasma from infected individuals (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.454698+00:00</updated><author><name>Jérémie Prévost</name></author><author><name>Halima Medjahed</name></author><author><name>Dani Vézina</name></author><author><name>Hung-Ching Chen</name></author><author><name>Beatrice H Hahn</name></author><author><name>Amos B. Smith</name></author><author><name>Andrés Finzi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The HIV-1 envelope glycoprotein (Env) is synthesized in the endoplasmic reticulum as a trimeric gp160 precursor, which requires proteolytic cleavage by a cellular furin protease to mediate virus-cell fusion. Env is conformationally flexible, but controls its transition from the unbound “closed” conformation (State 1) to downstream CD4-bound conformations (States 2/3), which are required for fusion. In particular, HIV-1 has evolved several mechanisms that reduce the premature “opening” of Env which exposes highly conserved epitopes recognized by non-neutralizing antibodies (nnAbs) capable of mediating antibody-dependent cellular cytotoxicity (ADCC). Env cleavage decreases its conformational transitions favoring the adoption of the “closed” conformation. Here we altered the gp160 furin cleavage site to impair Env cleavage and to examine its impact on ADCC responses mediated by plasma from HIV-1-infected individuals. We found that infected primary CD4+ T cells expressing uncleaved, but not wildtype, Env are efficiently recognized by nnAbs and become highly susceptible to ADCC responses mediated by plasma from HIV-1-infected individuals. Thus, HIV-1 limits the exposure of uncleaved Env at the surface of HIV-1-infected cells at least in part to escape ADCC responses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465908" rel="alternate" title="HIV-1 envelope glycoproteins proteolytic cleavage protects infected cells from ADCC mediated by plasma from infected individuals (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465873</id><title>LILRB1 and LILRB2 expression in peripheral blood immune cells at 18 and 24 months of age in infants born from mothers with placental malaria (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.454912+00:00</updated><author><name>Celia Dechavanne</name></author><author><name>Odilon Nouatin</name></author><author><name>Rafiou Adamou</name></author><author><name>Sofie Edslev</name></author><author><name>Anita Hansen</name></author><author><name>Florian Meurisse</name></author><author><name>Ibrahim Sadissou</name></author><author><name>Erasme Gbaguidi</name></author><author><name>Jacqueline Milet</name></author><author><name>Gilles Cottrell</name></author><author><name>Laure Gineau</name></author><author><name>Audrey Sabbagh</name></author><author><name>Achille Massougbodji</name></author><author><name>Kabirou Moutairou</name></author><author><name>Eduardo A. Donadi</name></author><author><name>Edgardo Carosella</name></author><author><name>Philippe Moreau</name></author><author><name>Ed Remarque</name></author><author><name>Michael Theisen</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Rouas-Freiss</name></author><author><name>André Garcia</name></author><author><name>Benoit Favier</name></author><author><name>David Courtin</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Placental malaria (PM) is associated with a higher susceptibility of infants to &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium falciparum (Pf)&lt;/italic&gt; malaria. A hypothesis of immune tolerance has been suggested but no clear explanation has been provided so far. Our goal was to investigate the involvement of inhibitory receptors LILRB1 and LILRB2, known to drive immune evasion upon ligation with pathogen and/or host ligands, in PM-induced immune tolerance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Infants of mothers with or without PM were enrolled in Allada, southern Benin, and followed-up for 24 months. Antibodies with specificity for five blood stage parasite antigens were quantified by ELISA, and the frequency of immune cell subsets was quantified by flow cytometry. LILRB1 or LILRB2 expression was assessed on cells collected at 18 and 24 months of age.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Infants born to PM-mothers had a higher risk of developing clinical malaria than those born to mothers without PM (IRR=1.53, p=0.040), and such infants displayed a lower frequency of non-classical monocytes (OR=0.74, p=0.01) that overexpressed LILRB2 (OR=1.36, p=0.002). Moreover, infants born to PM-mothers had lower levels of cytophilic IgG and higher levels of IL-10 during active infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Modulation of IgG and IL-10 levels could impair monocyte functions (opsonisation/phagocytosis) in infants born to PM-mothers, possibly contributing to their higher susceptibility to malaria. The long-lasting effect of PM on infants’ monocytes was notable, raising questions about the capacity of ligands such as Rifins or HLA-I molecules to bind to LILRB1 and LILRB2 and to modulate immune responses, and about the reprogramming of neonatal monocytes/macrophages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;KEY POINTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Infants of mothers with placental malaria were more susceptible to clinical malaria than those born to mothers without placental malaria and they displayed a lower frequency of non-classical monocytes that overexpressed LILRB2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465873" rel="alternate" title="LILRB1 and LILRB2 expression in peripheral blood immune cells at 18 and 24 months of age in infants born from mothers with placental malaria (6 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465825</id><title>Analysis of the Streptococcus mutans proteome during acid and oxidative stress reveals modules of co-expression and an expanded role for the TreR transcriptional regulator (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.455309+00:00</updated><author><name>Elizabeth L. Tinder</name></author><author><name>Roberta C. Faustoferri</name></author><author><name>Andrew A. Buckley</name></author><author><name>Robert G. Quivey</name></author><author><name>Jonathon L. Baker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Streptococcus mutans&lt;/italic&gt; promotes a tooth-damaging dysbiosis in the oral microbiota because it can form biofilms and survive acid stress better than most of its ecological competitors, which are typically health-associated. Many of these commensals produce hydrogen peroxide, therefore &lt;italic&gt;S. mutans&lt;/italic&gt; must manage both oxidative stress and acid stress with coordinated and complex physiological responses. In this study, the proteome of &lt;italic&gt;S. mutans&lt;/italic&gt; was examined during regulated growth in acid and oxidative stresses, as well as in deletion mutants with impaired oxidative stress phenotypes, Δ&lt;italic&gt;nox&lt;/italic&gt; and Δ&lt;italic&gt;treR.&lt;/italic&gt; 607 proteins exhibited significantly different abundance levels across the conditions tested, and correlation network analysis identified modules of co-expressed proteins that were responsive to the deletion of &lt;italic&gt;nox&lt;/italic&gt; and/or &lt;italic&gt;treR&lt;/italic&gt;, as well as acid and oxidative stress. The data provided evidence explaining the ROS-sensitive and mutacin-deficient phenotypes exhibited by the Δ&lt;italic&gt;treR&lt;/italic&gt; strain. SMU.1069-1070, a poorly understood LytTR system, had elevated abundance in the Δ&lt;italic&gt;treR&lt;/italic&gt; strain. &lt;italic&gt;S. mutans&lt;/italic&gt; LytTR systems regulate mutacin production and competence, which may explain how TreR affects mutacin production. Furthermore, the gene cluster that produces mutanobactin, a lipopeptide important in ROS tolerance, displayed reduced abundance in the Δ&lt;italic&gt;treR&lt;/italic&gt; strain. The role of Nox as a keystone in the oxidative stress response was also emphasized. Crucially, this dataset provides oral health researchers with a proteome atlas that will enable a more complete understanding of the &lt;italic&gt;S. mutans&lt;/italic&gt; stress responses that are required for pathogenesis, and facilitate the development of new and improved therapeutic approaches for dental caries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dental caries is the most common chronic infectious disease worldwide, and disproportionally affects marginalized socioeconomic groups. &lt;italic&gt;Streptococcus mutans&lt;/italic&gt; is a considered a primary etiologic agent of caries, with its pathogenicity dependent on coordinated physiologic stress responses that mitigate the damage caused by the oxidative and acid stress common within dental plaque. In this study, the proteome of &lt;italic&gt;S. mutans&lt;/italic&gt; was examined during growth in acidic and oxidative stresses, as well in &lt;italic&gt;nox&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;treR&lt;/italic&gt; deletion mutants. 607 proteins were differentially expressed across the strains/growth conditions, and modules of co-expressed proteins were identified, which enabled mapping the acid and oxidative stress responses across &lt;italic&gt;S. mutans&lt;/italic&gt; metabolism. The presence of TreR was linked to mutacin production via LytTR system signaling and to oxidative stress via mutanobactin production. The data provided by this study will guide future research elucidating &lt;italic&gt;S. mutans&lt;/italic&gt; pathogenesis and developing improved preventative and treatment modalities for dental caries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465825" rel="alternate" title="Analysis of the Streptococcus mutans proteome during acid and oxidative stress reveals modules of co-expression and an expanded role for the TreR transcriptional regulator (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465915</id><title>Hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells improve survival from sepsis by boosting immunomodulatory cells (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.455618+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel E. Morales-Mantilla</name></author><author><name>Bailee Kain</name></author><author><name>Duy Le</name></author><author><name>Anthony Flores</name></author><author><name>Silke Paust</name></author><author><name>Katherine King</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sepsis accounts for 1 in 5 deaths worldwide, and new therapeutic strategies to reduce sepsis- related mortality are urgently needed. Since hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells (HSPCs) are responsible for producing blood and immune cells, including in response to immunological stress, we explored their potential for treating sepsis. In a mouse model of Group A &lt;italic&gt;Streptococcus&lt;/italic&gt; (GAS)-induced sepsis, severe immunological stress was associated with significant depletion of bone marrow HSPCs and mortality within approximately 5-7 days. We hypothesized that the inflammatory environment of GAS infection drives rapid HSPC differentiation and depletion that can be rescued by infusion of donor HSPCs. Indeed, infusion of 10,000 naïve HSPCs into GAS-infected mice resulted in rapid myelopoiesis and a 50-60% increase in overall survival. Surprisingly, mice receiving donor HSPCs displayed a similar pathogen load compared to untreated mice. Flow cytometric analysis revealed a significantly increased number of myeloid-derived suppressor cells in HSPC-infused mice, which correlated with reduced inflammatory cytokine levels and restored HSPC levels. These findings suggest that HSPCs play an essential immunomodulatory role that may translate into new therapeutic strategies for sepsis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465915" rel="alternate" title="Hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells improve survival from sepsis by boosting immunomodulatory cells (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466382</id><title>Impact of antibiotic perturbation on intestinal viral communities in mice (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.455835+00:00</updated><author><name>Jacqueline Moltzau Anderson</name></author><author><name>Tim Lachnit</name></author><author><name>Simone Lipinski</name></author><author><name>Maren Falk-Paulsen</name></author><author><name>Philip Rosenstiel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Viruses and bacteriophages have a strong impact on intestinal barrier function and the composition and functional properties of commensal bacterial communities. To improve our understanding of the role of the enteric intestinal virome, we longitudinally characterized the virome in fecal samples from wild-type (WT) C57BL/6J and knock-out (KO) NOD2 mice in response to an antibiotic perturbation. Sequencing of viral-like-particles (VLPs) demonstrated both a high diversity and high inter-individual variation of the murine gut virome composed of eukaryotic viruses and bacteriophages. Antibiotics also had a significant impact on the gut murine virome causing a delayed resilience independent of genotype. However, compositional shifts in the virome and bacteriome were highly correlated, indicating a possible role of the virome in inflammatory bowel disease. Bacteriophage species may be playing an important role in either upregulating or downregulating the bacterial community, and restoring a healthy virome may therefore be a central goal of microbiota-targeted therapies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466382" rel="alternate" title="Impact of antibiotic perturbation on intestinal viral communities in mice (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.465406</id><title>Application of Cas12j for Streptomyces editing and cluster activation (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.456226+00:00</updated><author><name>Lee Ling Tan</name></author><author><name>Elena Heng</name></author><author><name>Nadiah Zulkarnain</name></author><author><name>Chuang Yan Leong</name></author><author><name>Veronica Ng</name></author><author><name>Lay Kien Yang</name></author><author><name>Deborah Chwee San Seow</name></author><author><name>Guangrong Peh</name></author><author><name>Yee Hwee Lim</name></author><author><name>Koduru Lokanand</name></author><author><name>Yoganathan Kanagasundaram</name></author><author><name>Siew Bee Ng</name></author><author><name>Fong Tian Wong</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In recent years, CRISPR-Cas toolboxes for Streptomyces editing have rapidly accelerated natural product discovery and engineering. However, Cas efficiencies are also oftentimes strain dependent, subsequently a variety of Cas proteins would allow for flexibility and enable genetic manipulation within a wider range of Streptomyces strains. In this work, we have further expanded the Cas toolbox by presenting the first example of Cas12j mediated editing in Streptomyces sp. A34053. In our study, we have also observed significantly improved editing efficiencies with Acidaminococcus sp. Cas12j compared to Cas12a, Francisella tularensis subsp. novicida U112's type V-A Cas (FnCpf1).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.465406" rel="alternate" title="Application of Cas12j for Streptomyces editing and cluster activation (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.23.465580</id><title>Identification and assessment of the antibacterial activity of ZnO nanoparticles produced by Vigna mungo and Rhizobacteria (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.456585+00:00</updated><author><name>Bharat Kwatra</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1.&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;ABSTRACTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;ZnO nanoparticles have received a lot of interest in recent years due to their unusual features. Antimicrobial properties of ZnO NPs However, the qualities of nanoparticles are determined by their size and form, making them suitable for a variety of applications. The current work looks at the synthesis, characterization, and antibacterial activity of ZnO NPs produced by Vigna Mungo and Rhizobacteria. Rhizobacteria isolated from V. mungo root nodule were morphologically, biochemically, and molecularly examined and identified as Rhizobium sp. strain P4 and Bacillus flexus strain IFO15715. The GC-MS analysis of methanol leaf extract of V. mungo was performed to detect and identify bioactive chemicals, and this indicated phytol as an antibacterial agent, while Squalene and Alpha – tocopherol had antioxidant and anti-tumour properties. Agar well diffusion experiment was used to determine the antibacterial properties of ZnO nanoparticles and Vigna Mungo leaf extract. This approach is widely documented, and standard zones of inhibition for sensitive and resistant values have been defined. The results demonstrated that both methanol extract and zinc oxide nanoparticles have strong antibacterial efficacy against the majority of the pathogens examined. he synthesized nanoparticles from Rhizobium sp. were characterized by analytical techniques like SEM, XRD, FTIR, and UV-Vis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.23.465580" rel="alternate" title="Identification and assessment of the antibacterial activity of ZnO nanoparticles produced by Vigna mungo and Rhizobacteria (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.22.464858</id><title>Conjugative transfer of naturally occurring plasmids in Mycolicibacterium sp (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.456764+00:00</updated><author><name>Sergio Morgado</name></author><author><name>Ana Carolina Vicente</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Conjugation is considered the main horizontal gene transfer (HGT) mechanism in bacterial adaptation and evolution. In the &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacteriaceae&lt;/italic&gt; family, &lt;italic&gt;Mycolicibacterium smegmatis&lt;/italic&gt; has been used as the model organism for the conjugative transfer of hybrid plasmids. However, the natural conjugation process in any bacteria would involve the transfer of naturally occurring plasmids. Currently, there is a gap in this regard in relation to this abundant environmental genus of &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacteriaceae&lt;/italic&gt;. Here, we performed conjugation experiments between wild &lt;italic&gt;Mycolicibacterium&lt;/italic&gt; sp. strains involving naturally occurring plasmids (sizes of 21 and 274 kb), and interestingly, evidence of conjugative transfer was obtained. Thus, it is likely that conjugation occurs in &lt;italic&gt;Mycolicibacterium&lt;/italic&gt; in the natural environment, representing a source of diversification and evolution in this genus of bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.22.464858" rel="alternate" title="Conjugative transfer of naturally occurring plasmids in Mycolicibacterium sp (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466258</id><title>DNA methylation patterns differ between free-living Rhizobium leguminosarum RCAM1026 and bacteroids formed in symbiosis with pea (Pisum sativum L.) (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.457517+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexey M. Afonin</name></author><author><name>Emma S. Gribchenko</name></author><author><name>Evgeni A. Zorin</name></author><author><name>Anton S. Sulima</name></author><author><name>Vladimir A. Zhukov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Rhizobium leguminosarum (Rl) is a common name for several genospecies of rhizobia able to form nitrogen-fixing nodules on the roots of pea (Pisum sativum L.) and undergo terminal differentiation into a symbiotic form called bacteroids. In this work, we compared the genomes of the free-living and differentiated forms of the Rl strain RCAM1026 using Oxford Nanopore long reads. No significant genome rearrangements were observed, but the relative abundances of replicons were different between the cell states. GANTC, GGCGCC and GATC methylated motifs have been found in the genome, along with genes for methyltransferases with matching predicted targets. Methylation patterns for the GANTC and GATC motives differed significantly depending on the cell state, which indicates their possible connection to the regulation of symbiotic differentiation. The GGCGCC motif was completely methylated in both bacteria states, and, apparently, is a target for the modification-restriction system. Currently, the methylation patterns in symbiotic bacteria are not extensively studied, so a further investigation of the topic coupled with gene expression data is needed to elucidate the function of differential methylation in terminal differentiation of R. leguminosarum and other rhizobia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466258" rel="alternate" title="DNA methylation patterns differ between free-living Rhizobium leguminosarum RCAM1026 and bacteroids formed in symbiosis with pea (Pisum sativum L.) (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466384</id><title>Combinatorial viral vector-based and live-attenuated vaccines without an adjuvant to generate broader immune responses to effectively combat pneumonic plague (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.457751+00:00</updated><author><name>Paul B Kilgore</name></author><author><name>Jian Sha</name></author><author><name>Emily Hendrix</name></author><author><name>Vladimir L Motin</name></author><author><name>Ashok K Chopra</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mice immunized with a combination of an adenovirus vector (Ad5-YFV) and live-attenuated (LMA)-based vaccines were evaluated for protective efficacy against pneumonic plague. While the Ad5-YFV vaccine harbors a fusion cassette of three genes encoding YscF, F1, and LcrV, LMA represents a mutant of parental &lt;italic&gt;Yersinia pestis&lt;/italic&gt; CO92 deleted for genes encoding Lpp, MsbB, and Ail. Ad5-YFV and LMA were either administered simultaneously (1-dose regimen) or 21 days apart in various order and route of administration combinations (2-dose regimen). The 2-dose regimen induced robust immune responses to provide full protection to animals against parental CO92 and its isogenic F1 (CAF&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;)-deletion mutant challenges during both short- and long-term studies. Mice intranasally (i.n.) immunized with Ad5-YFV first followed by LMA (i.n. or intramuscularly [i.m.]) had higher T- and B- cell proliferative responses and LcrV antibody titers than those in mice vaccinated with LMA (i.n. or i.m.) first ahead of Ad5-YFV (i.n.) during the long-term study. Specifically, the needle- and adjuvant- free vaccine combination (i.n.) is ideal for use in plague endemic regions. Conversely, with a 1-dose regimen, mice vaccinated with Ad5-YFV i.n. and LMA by the i.m. route provided complete protection to animals against CO92 and its CAF&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; mutant challenges, and elicited Th1/Th2, as well as Th17 responses, thus suitable for emergency vaccination during a plague outbreak or bioterrorist attack. This is a first study in which a viral vector-based and live-attenuated vaccines were effectively used in combination representing adjuvant- and/or needle- free immunization, with each vaccine triggering a distinct cellular immune response.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466384" rel="alternate" title="Combinatorial viral vector-based and live-attenuated vaccines without an adjuvant to generate broader immune responses to effectively combat pneumonic plague (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466435</id><title>Reproducible Propagation of Species-Rich Soil Microbiomes Suggests Robust Underlying Deterministic Principles of Community Formation (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.457975+00:00</updated><author><name>Senka Causevic</name></author><author><name>Janko Tackmann</name></author><author><name>Vladimir Sentchilo</name></author><author><name>Christian von Mering</name></author><author><name>Jan Roelof van der Meer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microbiomes are typically characterised by high species diversity but it is poorly understood how such system-level complexity can be generated and propagated. Here, we used soils as a relevant model to study microbiome development. Despite inherent stochastic variation in manipulating species-rich communities, both laboratory-mixed medium complexity (21 soil bacterial isolates in equal proportions) and high-diversity natural top-soil communities followed highly reproducible succession paths, maintaining distinct soil microbiome signatures. Development trajectories and compositional states were different for communities propagated in soils than in liquid suspension. Microbiome states were maintained over multiple renewed growth cycles but could be diverged by short-term pollutant exposure. The different but robust trajectories demonstrated that deterministic taxa-inherent characteristics underlie reproducible development and self-organized complexity of soil microbiomes within their environmental boundary conditions. Our findings also have direct implications for potential strategies to achieve controlled restoration of desertified land.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466435" rel="alternate" title="Reproducible Propagation of Species-Rich Soil Microbiomes Suggests Robust Underlying Deterministic Principles of Community Formation (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>