<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.034263+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468999</id><title>Reversible bacteriophage resistance by shedding the bacterial cell wall (79 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.034665+00:00</updated><author><name>Veronique Ongenae</name></author><author><name>Adam Sidi Mabrouk</name></author><author><name>Marjolein Crooijmans</name></author><author><name>Daniel Rozen</name></author><author><name>Ariane Briegel</name></author><author><name>Dennis Claessen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Phages are highly abundant in the environment and a major threat for bacteria. Therefore, bacteria have evolved sophisticated defense systems to withstand phage attacks. Here, we describe a previously unknown mechanism by which mono- and diderm bacteria survive infection with diverse lytic phages. Phage exposure leads to a rapid and near complete conversion of walled cells to a cell wall-deficient state, which remain viable in osmoprotective conditions and can revert to the walled state. While shedding the cell wall dramatically reduces the number of progeny phages produced by the host, it does not always preclude phage infection. Altogether, these results show that the formation of cell wall-deficient cells prevents complete eradication of the bacterial population and suggest that cell wall-deficiency may limit the efficacy of phage therapy, especially in highly osmotic environments or when used together with antibiotics that target the cell wall.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468999" rel="alternate" title="Reversible bacteriophage resistance by shedding the bacterial cell wall (79 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468770</id><title>Comparative genomics on cultivated and uncultivated, freshwater and marine Candidatus Manganitrophaceae species implies their worldwide reach in manganese chemolithoautotrophy (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.035587+00:00</updated><author><name>Hang Yu</name></author><author><name>Grayson L. Chadwick</name></author><author><name>Usha F. Lingappa</name></author><author><name>Jared R. Leadbetter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chemolithoautotrophic manganese oxidation has long been theorized, but only recently demonstrated in a bacterial co-culture. The majority member of the co-culture, &lt;italic&gt;Candidatus&lt;/italic&gt; Manganitrophus noduliformans, is a distinct but not yet isolated lineage in the phylum &lt;italic&gt;Nitrospirota&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Nitrospirae&lt;/italic&gt;). Here, we established two additional MnCO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-oxidizing cultures using inocula from Santa Barbara (USA) and Boetsap (South Africa). Both cultures were dominated by strains of a new species, designated &lt;italic&gt;Candidatus&lt;/italic&gt; Manganitrophus morganii. The next abundant members differed in the available cultures, suggesting that while &lt;italic&gt;Ca&lt;/italic&gt;. Manganitrophus species have not been isolated in pure culture, they may not require a specific syntrophic relationship with another species. Phylogeny of cultivated &lt;italic&gt;Ca&lt;/italic&gt;. Manganitrophus and related metagenome-assembled genomes revealed a coherent taxonomic family, &lt;italic&gt;Candidatus&lt;/italic&gt; Manganitrophaceae, from both freshwater and marine environments and distributed globally. Comparative genomic analyses support this family being Mn(II)-oxidizing chemolithoautotrophs. Among the 895 shared genes were a subset of those hypothesized for Mn(II) oxidation (Cyc2 and PCC_1) and oxygen reduction (TO_1 and TO_2) that could facilitate Mn(II) lithotrophy. An unusual, plausibly reverse Complex 1 containing 2 additional pumping subunits was also shared by the family, as were genes for the reverse TCA carbon fixation cycle, which could enable Mn(II) autotrophy. All members of the family lacked genes for nitrification found in &lt;italic&gt;Nitrospira&lt;/italic&gt; species. The results suggest that &lt;italic&gt;Ca&lt;/italic&gt;. Manganitrophaceae share a core set of candidate genes for the newly discovered manganese dependent chemolithoautotrophic lifestyle, and likely have a broad, global distribution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Manganese (Mn) is an abundant redox-active metal that cycled in many of Earth’s biomes. While diverse bacteria and archaea have been demonstrated to respire Mn(III/IV), only recently have bacteria been implicated in Mn(II) oxidation dependent growth. Here, two new Mn(II)-oxidizing enrichment cultures originated from two continents and hemispheres were examined. By comparing the community composition of the enrichments and performing phylogenomic analysis on the abundant &lt;italic&gt;Nitrospirota&lt;/italic&gt; therein, new insights are gleaned on cell interactions, taxonomy, and machineries that may underlie Mn(II)-based lithotrophy and autotrophy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468770" rel="alternate" title="Comparative genomics on cultivated and uncultivated, freshwater and marine Candidatus Manganitrophaceae species implies their worldwide reach in manganese chemolithoautotrophy (29 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468621</id><title>Mobilome-driven segregation of the resistome in biological wastewater treatment (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.035904+00:00</updated><author><name>Laura de Nies</name></author><author><name>Susheel Bhanu Busi</name></author><author><name>Benoit Josef Kunath</name></author><author><name>Patrick May</name></author><author><name>Paul Wilmes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Biological wastewater treatment plants (BWWTP) are considered to be hotspots of evolution and subsequent spread of antimicrobial resistance (AMR). Mobile genetic elements (MGEs) promote the mobilization and dissemination of antimicrobial resistance genes (ARGs) and are thereby critical mediators of AMR within the BWWTP microbial community. At present, it is unclear whether specific AMR categories are differentially disseminated via bacteriophages (phages) or plasmids. To understand the segregation of AMR in relation to MGEs, we analyzed meta-omic (metagenomic, metatranscriptomic and metaproteomic) data systematically collected over 1.5 years from a BWWTP. Our results showed a core group of fifteen AMR categories which were found across all timepoints. Some of these AMR categories were disseminated exclusively (bacitracin) or primarily (aminoglycoside, MLS, sulfonamide) via plasmids or phages (fosfomycin and peptide), whereas others were disseminated equally by both MGEs. Subsequent expression- and protein-level analyses further demonstrated that aminoglycoside, bacitracin and sulfonamide resistance genes were expressed more by plasmids, in contrast to fosfomycin and peptide AMR expression by phages, thereby validating our genomic findings. Longitudinal assessment further underlined these findings whereby the log2-fold changes of aminoglycoside, bacitracin and sulfonamide resistance genes were increased in plasmids, while fosfomycin and peptide resistance showed similar trends in phages. In the analyzed communities, the dominant taxon &lt;italic&gt;Candidatus&lt;/italic&gt; Microthrix parvicella was a major contributor to several AMR categories whereby its plasmids primarily mediated aminoglycoside resistance. Importantly, we also found AMR associated with ESKAPEE pathogens within the BWWTP, for which MGEs also contributed differentially to the dissemination of ARGs. Collectively our findings pave the way towards understanding the segmentation of AMR within MGEs, thereby shedding new light on resistome populations and their mediators, essential elements that are of immediate relevance to human health.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468621" rel="alternate" title="Mobilome-driven segregation of the resistome in biological wastewater treatment (22 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.467908</id><title>Tuning spherical cells into kinking helices in wall-less bacteria (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.036551+00:00</updated><author><name>Carole Lartigue</name></author><author><name>Bastien Lambert</name></author><author><name>Fabien Rideau</name></author><author><name>Marion Decossas</name></author><author><name>Mélanie Hillion</name></author><author><name>Jean-Paul Douliez</name></author><author><name>Julie Hardouin</name></author><author><name>Olivier Lambert</name></author><author><name>Alain Blanchard</name></author><author><name>Laure Béven</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In bacteria, cell shape is determined and maintained through a complex interplay between the peptidoglycan cell wall and cytoplasmic filaments made of polymerized MreB. &lt;italic&gt;Spiroplasma&lt;/italic&gt; species, members of the Mollicutes class, challenge this general understanding because they are characterized by a helical cell shape and motility without a cell wall. This specificity is thought to rely on five MreB isoforms and a specific fibril protein. In this study, combinations of these five MreBs and of the fibril from &lt;italic&gt;Spiroplasma citri&lt;/italic&gt; were expressed in another Mollicutes, &lt;italic&gt;Mycoplasma capricolum. Mycoplasma&lt;/italic&gt; cells that were initially pleomorphic, mostly spherical, turned into helices when MreBs and fibrils were expressed in this heterologous host. The fibril protein was essential neither for helicity nor for cell movements. The isoform MreB5 had a special role as it was sufficient to confer helicity and motility to the mycoplasma cells. Cryo-electron microscopy confirmed the association of MreBs and fibril-based cytoskeleton with the plasma membrane, suggesting a direct effect on the membrane curvature. Finally, the heterologous expression of these proteins, MreBs and fibril, made it possible to reproduce the kink-like motility of spiroplasmas without providing the ability of cell movement in liquid broth. We suggest that other &lt;italic&gt;Spiroplasma&lt;/italic&gt; components, not yet identified, are required for swimming, a hypothesis that could be evaluated in future studies using the same model.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.467908" rel="alternate" title="Tuning spherical cells into kinking helices in wall-less bacteria (21 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468248</id><title>Broadly-neutralizing antibodies that bind to the influenza hemagglutinin stalk domain enhance the effectiveness of neuraminidase inhibitors via Fc-mediated effector functions (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.036768+00:00</updated><author><name>Ali Zhang</name></author><author><name>Hanu Chaudhari</name></author><author><name>Yonathan Agung</name></author><author><name>Michael D'Agostino</name></author><author><name>Jann Ang</name></author><author><name>Matthew S Miller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The conserved hemagglutinin stalk domain is an attractive target for broadly effective antibody-based therapeutics and next generation universal influenza vaccines. Protection provided by hemagglutinin stalk binding antibodies is principally mediated through activation of immune effector cells. Titers of stalk-binding antibodies are highly variable on an individual level, and tend to increase with age as a result of increasing exposures to influenza virus. In our study, we show that stalk-binding antibodies cooperate with neuraminidase inhibitors to protect against influenza virus infection in an Fc-dependent manner. These data suggest that the effectiveness of neuraminidase inhibitors is likely influenced by an individual's titers of stalk-binding antibodies, and that neuraminidase inhibitors may enhance the effectiveness of future stalk-binding monoclonal antibody-based treatments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468248" rel="alternate" title="Broadly-neutralizing antibodies that bind to the influenza hemagglutinin stalk domain enhance the effectiveness of neuraminidase inhibitors via Fc-mediated effector functions (17 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468669</id><title>Spatially regulated protease activity in lymph nodes renders B cell follicles a sanctuary for retention of intact antigens (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.036911+00:00</updated><author><name>Aereas Aung</name></author><author><name>Ang Cui</name></author><author><name>Ava P. Soleimany</name></author><author><name>Maurice Bukenya</name></author><author><name>Heya Lee</name></author><author><name>Christopher A. Cottrell</name></author><author><name>Murillo Silva</name></author><author><name>Jesse D. Kirkpatrick</name></author><author><name>Parastoo Amlashi</name></author><author><name>Tanaka Remba</name></author><author><name>Shuhao Xiao</name></author><author><name>Leah Michelle Froehle</name></author><author><name>Wuhbet Abraham</name></author><author><name>Josetta Adams</name></author><author><name>Heikyung Suh</name></author><author><name>Phillip Huyett</name></author><author><name>Douglas S. Kwon</name></author><author><name>Nir Hacohen</name></author><author><name>William R. Schief</name></author><author><name>Sangeeta N. Bhatia</name></author><author><name>Darrell J. Irvine</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The structural integrity of vaccine antigens is critical, because antigen breakdown &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; could eliminate neutralizing epitopes and create competing B cell responses against irrelevant breakdown products. Using FRET imaging and imaging zymography, we found that protease activity and antigen breakdown are spatially heterogeneous in lymph nodes. Following protein immunization, antigens are rapidly degraded in the subcapsular sinus, paracortex, and interfollicular regions of the tissue. By contrast, the follicles and follicular dendritic cell (FDC) networks exhibit low protease activity and antigen degradation rates. Immunization regimens targeting antigen rapidly to FDCs led to germinal centers (GCs) where responses to intact antigen were highly dominant, while traditional bolus immunizations led to weaker GC responses where more GC B cells bound to breakdown products than intact antigen. Thus, spatially-compartmentalized antigen proteolysis impacts humoral immunity and can be exploited to enhance vaccine-induced production of antibody responses against key pathogen structural epitopes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468669" rel="alternate" title="Spatially regulated protease activity in lymph nodes renders B cell follicles a sanctuary for retention of intact antigens (16 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469141</id><title>Glacier-fed stream biofilms harbour diverse resistomes and biosynthetic gene clusters (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.037131+00:00</updated><author><name>Susheel Bhanu Busi</name></author><author><name>Laura de Nies</name></author><author><name>Paraskevi Pramateftaki</name></author><author><name>Massimo Bourquin</name></author><author><name>Leïla Ezzat</name></author><author><name>Tyler J. Kohler</name></author><author><name>Stilianos Fodelianakis</name></author><author><name>Grégoire Michoud</name></author><author><name>Hannes Peter</name></author><author><name>Michail Styllas</name></author><author><name>Matteo Tolosano</name></author><author><name>Vincent De Staercke</name></author><author><name>Martina Schön</name></author><author><name>Valentina Galata</name></author><author><name>Tom Battin</name></author><author><name>Paul Wilmes</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Antimicrobial resistance (AMR) is a universal phenomenon whose origins lay in natural ecological interactions such as competition within niches, within and between micro- to higher-order organisms. However, the ecological and evolutionary processes shaping AMR need to be better understood in view of better antimicrobial stewardship. Resolving antibiotic biosynthetic pathways, including biosynthetic gene clusters (BGCs), and corresponding antimicrobial resistance genes (ARGs) may therefore help in understanding the inherent mechanisms. However, to study these phenomena, it is crucial to examine the origins of AMR in pristine environments with limited anthropogenic influences. In this context, epilithic biofilms residing in glacier-fed streams (GFSs) are an excellent model system to study diverse, intra- and inter-domain, ecological crosstalk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We assessed the resistomes of epilithic biofilms from GFSs across the Southern Alps (New Zealand) and the Caucasus (Russia) and observed that both bacteria and eukaryotes encoded twenty-nine distinct AMR categories. Of these, beta-lactam, aminoglycoside, and multidrug resistance were both abundant and taxonomically distributed in most of the bacterial and eukaryotic phyla. AMR-encoding phyla included Bacteroidota and Proteobacteria among the bacteria, alongside Ochrophyta (algae) among the eukaryotes. Additionally, BGCs involved in the production of antibacterial compounds were identified across all phyla in the epilithic biofilms. Furthermore, we found that several bacterial genera (&lt;italic&gt;Flavobacterium, Polaromonas&lt;/italic&gt;, etc.) including representatives of the superphylum Patescibacteria encode both ARGs and BGCs within close proximity of each other, thereby demonstrating their capacity to simultaneously influence and compete within the microbial community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our findings highlight the presence and abundance of AMR in epilithic biofilms within GFSs. Additionally, we identify their role in the complex intra- and inter-domain competition and the underlying mechanisms influencing microbial survival in GFS epilithic biofilms. We demonstrate that eukaryotes may serve as AMR reservoirs owing to their potential for encoding ARGs. We also find that the taxonomic affiliation of the AMR and the BGCs are congruent. Importantly, our findings allow for understanding how naturally occurring BGCs and AMR contribute to the epilithic biofilms mode of life in GFSs. Importantly, these observations may be generalizable and potentially extended to other environments which may be more or less impacted by human activity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469141" rel="alternate" title="Glacier-fed stream biofilms harbour diverse resistomes and biosynthetic gene clusters (15 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468763</id><title>Disruption of vacuolin microdomains in the host Dictyostelium discoideum increases resistance to Mycobacterium marinum-induced membrane damage and infection (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.037323+00:00</updated><author><name>Cristina Bosmani</name></author><author><name>Angélique Perret</name></author><author><name>Florence Leuba</name></author><author><name>Aurélie Guého</name></author><author><name>Nabil Hanna</name></author><author><name>Thierry Soldati</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; (Mtb), the causative agent of tuberculosis, manipulates the host phagosome maturation pathway to replicate intracellularly. &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium marinum&lt;/italic&gt;, a closely-related species, and &lt;italic&gt;Dictyostelium discoideum&lt;/italic&gt;, a social amoeba and alternative phagocytic host, have been used as models to study host-pathogen interactions occurring during mycobacterial infections. Vacuolins, functional homologues of the mammalian flotillins, organize membrane microdomains and play a role in vesicular trafficking. Various pathogens have been reported to manipulate their membrane association and function. During infection of &lt;italic&gt;D&lt;/italic&gt;. &lt;italic&gt;discoideum&lt;/italic&gt; with &lt;italic&gt;M&lt;/italic&gt;. &lt;italic&gt;marinum&lt;/italic&gt;, Vacuolin C was specifically and highly induced and all three vacuolin isoforms were enriched at the mycobacteria-containing-vacuole (MCV). In addition, absence of vacuolins reduced escape from the MCV and conferred resistance to &lt;italic&gt;M&lt;/italic&gt;. &lt;italic&gt;marinum&lt;/italic&gt; infection. Moreover, ESAT-6, the membrane-disrupting virulence factor of &lt;italic&gt;M&lt;/italic&gt;. &lt;italic&gt;marinum&lt;/italic&gt;, was less associated with membranes when vacuolins were absent. Together, these results suggest that vacuolins are important host factors that are manipulated by mycobacteria to inflict membrane damage and escape from their compartment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468763" rel="alternate" title="Disruption of vacuolin microdomains in the host Dictyostelium discoideum increases resistance to Mycobacterium marinum-induced membrane damage and infection (14 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468714</id><title>NMR metabolomics of symbioses between bacterial vaginosis associated bacteria (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.037458+00:00</updated><author><name>Victoria Horrocks</name></author><author><name>Charlotte K. Hind</name></author><author><name>Matthew E. Wand</name></author><author><name>Joel Chan</name></author><author><name>Jade C. Hopkins</name></author><author><name>Georgina L. Houston</name></author><author><name>Rachel M. Tribe</name></author><author><name>J. Mark Sutton</name></author><author><name>A. James Mason</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial vaginosis (BV) is a dysbiosis of the vaginal microbiome, characterised by low levels of lacto-bacilli and overgrowth of a diverse group of bacteria, and associated with higher risk of a variety of infections, surgical complications, cancer and spontaneous preterm birth (PTB). Despite the lack of a consistently applicable aetiology, &lt;italic&gt;Prevotella&lt;/italic&gt; spp. are often associated with both BV and PTB and &lt;italic&gt;P. bivia&lt;/italic&gt; has known symbiotic relationships with both &lt;italic&gt;Peptostreptococcus anaerobius&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Gardnerella vaginalis&lt;/italic&gt;. Higher risk of PTB can also be predicted by a composite of metabolites linked to bacterial metabolism but their specific bacterial source remains poorly understood. Here we characterise diversity of metabolic strategies among BV associated bacteria and lactobacilli and the symbiotic metabolic relationships between &lt;italic&gt;P. bivia&lt;/italic&gt; and its partners and show how these influence the availability of metabolites associated with BV/PTB and/or pro- or anti-inflammatory immune responses. We confirm a commensal relationship between &lt;italic&gt;Pe. anaerobius&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;P. bivia&lt;/italic&gt;, refining its mechanism; &lt;italic&gt;P. bivia&lt;/italic&gt; supplies tyrosine, phenylalanine, methionine, uracil and proline, the last of which leads to a substantial increase in overall acetate production. In contrast, our data indicate the relationship between &lt;italic&gt;P. bivia&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;G. vaginalis&lt;/italic&gt; strains, with sequence variant G2, is mutualistic with outcome dependent on the metabolic strategy of the &lt;italic&gt;G. vaginalis&lt;/italic&gt; strain. Seven &lt;italic&gt;G. vaginalis&lt;/italic&gt; strains could be separated according to whether they performed mixed acid fermentation (MAF) or bifid shunt (BS). In co-culture, &lt;italic&gt;P. bivia&lt;/italic&gt; supplies all &lt;italic&gt;G. vaginalis&lt;/italic&gt; strains with uracil and received substantial amounts of asparagine in return. Acetate production, which is lower in BS strains, then matched that of MAF strains while production of aspartate increased for the latter. Taken together, our data show how knowledge of inter- and intra-species metabolic diversity and the effects of symbiosis may refine our understanding of the mechanism and approach to risk prediction in BV and/or PTB.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468714" rel="alternate" title="NMR metabolomics of symbioses between bacterial vaginosis associated bacteria (14 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469145</id><title>Cryo soft X-ray tomography to explore Escherichia coli nucleoid remodelling by Hfq master regulator (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.037607+00:00</updated><author><name>Antoine Cossa</name></author><author><name>Sylvain Trépout</name></author><author><name>Frank Wien</name></author><author><name>Etienne Le Brun</name></author><author><name>Florian Turbant</name></author><author><name>Eva Pereiro</name></author><author><name>Véronique Arluison</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial chromosomic DNA is packed within a membrane-less structure, the nucleoid, thanks to proteins called Nucleoid Associated Proteins (NAPs). The NAP composition of the nucleoid varies during the bacterial life cycle and is growth phase-dependent. Among these NAPs, Hfq is one of the most intriguing as it plays both direct and indirect roles on DNA structure. Indeed, Hfq is best known to mediate post-transcriptional regulation by using small noncoding RNA (sRNA). Although Hfq presence in the nucleoid has been demonstrated for years, its precise role is still unclear. Recently, it has been shown &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; that Hfq belongs to the bridging family of NAPs. Its bridging mechanism relies on the formation of the amyloid-like structure of Hfq C-terminal region. Here, using cryo soft X-ray tomography imaging of native unlabelled cells and using a semi-automatic analysis and segmentation procedure, we show that Hfq significantly remodels the &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; nucleoid, especially during the stationary growth phase. Hfq influences both nucleoid volume and absorbance. Hfq cumulates direct effects and indirect effects due to sRNA-based regulation of other NAPs. Taken together, our findings reveal a new role for this protein in nucleoid remodelling that may serve in response to stress conditions and in adapting to changing environments. This implies that Hfq regulates nucleoid compaction directly via its interaction with DNA, but also at the post-transcriptional level via its interaction with RNA.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469145" rel="alternate" title="Cryo soft X-ray tomography to explore Escherichia coli nucleoid remodelling by Hfq master regulator (14 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469103</id><title>Evasion of Toll-like Receptor Recognition by Escherichia coli is mediated via Population Level Regulation of Flagellin Production (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.037792+00:00</updated><author><name>M Lanz</name></author><author><name>C Birchall</name></author><author><name>L Drage</name></author><author><name>D Picton</name></author><author><name>C Mowbray</name></author><author><name>Q Alsenani</name></author><author><name>A. Tan</name></author><author><name>A Ali</name></author><author><name>C Harding</name></author><author><name>R Pickard</name></author><author><name>J Hall</name></author><author><name>PD Aldridge</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Uropathogenic &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; (UPEC) is a major cause of urinary tract infections. Analysis of the innate immune response in immortalised urothelial cells suggests that the bacterial flagellar subunit, flagellin, is key in inducing host defences. A panel of 39 clinical uro-associated &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; isolates recovered from either asymptomatic bacteruria (ASB), cystitis or pyelonephritis patients, were characterised for motility and their ability to induce an innate response in urothelial cells stably transfected with a NFκB luciferase reporter. Twenty-four isolates (60%) were identified as motile with strains recovered from cystitis patients exhibiting a bipolar motility distribution pattern (P &amp;lt; 0.005) and associated with a 2-5 fold increase in NFκB signalling. Although two isolates were associated with swarm sizes of &amp;gt;7 cm and NFκB activities of &amp;gt;30 fold (P = 0.029), data overall suggested bacterial motility and the NFκB signalling response were not directly correlated. To explore whether the signalling response reflected antigenic variation flagellin was purified from 11 different isolates and the urothelial cell challenges repeated. Purified flagellin filaments generated comparable (30.4±1.8 to 46.1±2.5 fold, P = NS) NFκB signalling responses, irrespective of either the source of the isolate or H-serotype. These data argued against any variability between isolates being related to flagellin itself. To determine the roles, if any, of flagellar abundance in inducing these responses flagellar hook numbers of a range of cystitis and ABU isolates were quantified using a plasmid encoded flagellar hook gene &lt;italic&gt;flgEA240C&lt;/italic&gt;. Foci data suggested isolates were averaging between 1 and 2 flagella per cell, while only 10 to 60% each isolates population exhibited foci. These data suggested selective pressures exist in the urinary tract that allow uro-associated &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; strains to maintain motility exploiting population heterogeneity to prevent host TLR5 recognition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469103" rel="alternate" title="Evasion of Toll-like Receptor Recognition by Escherichia coli is mediated via Population Level Regulation of Flagellin Production (13 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468584</id><title>Ly6Chi monocytes are metabolically reprogrammed in the blood during inflammatory stimulation allowing for macrophage lineage commitment (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.038079+00:00</updated><author><name>Gareth S.D. Purvis</name></author><author><name>Eileen McNeill</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Wright</name></author><author><name>Santiago Revale</name></author><author><name>Helen Lockstone</name></author><author><name>Keith M. Channon</name></author><author><name>David R. Greaves</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Acute inflammation is a rapid and dynamic process involving the recruitment and activation of multiple cell types in a co-ordinated and precise manner. Using cell tracking, linage tracing and single cell transcriptomics we investigated the origin and transcriptional reprogramming of monocytes and macrophages in acute inflammation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Monocyte trafficking and adoptive transfer experiments revealed that monocytes undergo rapid phenotypic change as they exit the blood and give rise to monocyte-derived macrophages that persist during the resolution of inflammation. Single cell transcriptomics revealed significant heterogeneity within the surface marker defined CD11b&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;Ly6G&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;Ly6C&lt;sup&gt;hi&lt;/sup&gt; monocyte population within the blood and at the site of inflammation. Lineage trajectory analysis revealed that Ly6C&lt;sup&gt;hi&lt;/sup&gt; monocytes in the blood are re-programmed into a defined differentiation pathway following inflammatory stimulus. We show that two major transcriptional reprogramming events occur during the initial 6 h of Ly6C&lt;sup&gt;hi&lt;/sup&gt; monocyte mobilisation, one in the blood priming monocytes for migration and a second at the site of inflammation. Pathway analysis revealed an important role for oxidative phosphorylation (OxPhos) during both these reprogramming events in a subset of M2-like cells. Experimentally we also demonstrate that OxPhos is essential for murine and human monocyte chemotaxis. These new findings opening up the possibility that altering monocyte metabolic capacity towards OxPhos could facilitate enhanced macrophage M2-like polarisation to aid inflammation resolution and tissue repair.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468584" rel="alternate" title="Ly6Chi monocytes are metabolically reprogrammed in the blood during inflammatory stimulation allowing for macrophage lineage commitment (13 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468835</id><title>Plasmodium-encoded murine IL-6 impairs liver stage infection and elicits long-lasting sterilizing immunity (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.038245+00:00</updated><author><name>Selma Belhimeur</name></author><author><name>Sylvie Briquet</name></author><author><name>Roger Peronet</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Pham</name></author><author><name>Pierre-Henri Commere</name></author><author><name>Rogerio Amino</name></author><author><name>Artur Scherf</name></author><author><name>Olivier Silvie</name></author><author><name>Salaheddine Mecheri</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium&lt;/italic&gt; sporozoites inoculated by &lt;italic&gt;Anopheles&lt;/italic&gt; mosquitoes into the skin of the mammalian host migrate to the liver before infecting hepatocytes. Previous work demonstrated that early production of IL-6 in the liver was found to be detrimental for the parasite growth, leading to the acquisition of a long-lasting immune protection. Considering IL-6 as a critical pro-inflammatory signal, we explored a novel approach whereby the parasite itself encodes for the murine IL-6 gene. We generated transgenic &lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;berghei&lt;/italic&gt; parasites that express murine IL-6 during liver stage development. Though IL-6 transgenic sporozoites develop into exo-erythrocytic forms in cultured hepatocytes &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, these parasites were not capable of inducing a blood stage infection in mice. Furthermore, immunization of mice with transgenic IL-6 sporozoites elicited a long-lasting CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cell-mediated protective immunity against a subsequent infectious sporozoite challenge. Collectively, this study demonstrates that parasite-encoded IL-6 impairs &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium&lt;/italic&gt; infection at the liver stage, forming the basis of a novel suicide vaccine strategy to elicit protective antimalarial immunity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468835" rel="alternate" title="Plasmodium-encoded murine IL-6 impairs liver stage infection and elicits long-lasting sterilizing immunity (13 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469063</id><title>Bacterial competition systems share a domain required for inner membrane transport of the nuclease bacteriocin pyocin G (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.038409+00:00</updated><author><name>Iva Atanaskovic</name></author><author><name>Connor Sharp</name></author><author><name>Cara Press</name></author><author><name>Renata Kaminska</name></author><author><name>Colin Kleanthous</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacteria exploit a variety of attack strategies to gain dominance within ecological niches. Prominent amongst these are contact-dependent inhibition (CDI), type VI secretion (T6SS) and bacteriocins. The cytotoxic endpoint of these systems is often the delivery of a nuclease to the cytosol. How such nucleases translocate across the cytoplasmic membrane of Gram-negative bacteria is unknown. Here, we identify a small, conserved, 15-kDa domain, which we refer to as the inner membrane translocation (IMT) domain that is common to T6SS and bacteriocins and linked to nuclease effector domains. Through fluorescence microscopy assays using intact and spheroplasted cells, we demonstrate that the IMT domain of the &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; specific bacteriocin pyocin G (PyoG) is required for import of the toxin nuclease domain to the cytoplasm. We also show that translocation of PyoG into the cytosol is dependent on inner membrane proteins FtsH, a AAA+ATPase/protease, and TonB1, the latter more typically associated with transport of bacteriocins across the outer membrane. Our study reveals that the IMT domain directs the cytotoxic nuclease of PyoG to cross the cytoplasmic membrane and, more broadly, has been adapted for the transport of other toxic nucleases delivered into Gram-negative bacteria by both contact dependent- and contact-independent means.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nuclease bacteriocins are potential antimicrobials for the treatment of antibiotic resistant bacterial infections. While the mechanism of outer membrane translocation is beginning to be understood, the mechanism of inner membrane transport is not known. This study uses PyoG as a model nuclease bacteriocin and defines a conserved domain which is essential for inner membrane translocation and which is widespread in other bacterial competition systems. Additionally, the presented data links two membrane proteins, FtsH and TonB1, with inner membrane translocation of PyoG. These findings point to the general importance of this domain to the cellular uptake mechanisms of nucleases delivered by otherwise diverse and distinct bacterial competition systems. The work is also of importance for the design of new protein antibiotics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469063" rel="alternate" title="Bacterial competition systems share a domain required for inner membrane transport of the nuclease bacteriocin pyocin G (12 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468962</id><title>Membrane adaptation in the hyperthermophilic archaeon Pyrococcus furiosus relies upon a novel strategy involving glycerol monoalkyl glycerol tetraether lipids (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.038544+00:00</updated><author><name>Maxime Tourte</name></author><author><name>Philippe Schaeffer</name></author><author><name>Vincent Grossi</name></author><author><name>Philippe M. Oger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microbes preserve membrane functionality under fluctuating environmental conditions by modulating their membrane lipid composition. Although several studies have documented membrane adaptations in Archaea, the influence of most biotic and abiotic factors on archaeal lipid compositions remains underexplored. Here, we studied the influence of temperature, pH, salinity, the presence/absence of elemental sulfur, the carbon source, and the genetic background on the core lipid composition of the hyperthermophilic neutrophilic marine archaeon &lt;italic&gt;Pyrococcus furiosus.&lt;/italic&gt; Every growth parameter tested affected the core lipid composition to some extent, the carbon source and the genetic background having the greatest influence. Surprisingly, &lt;italic&gt;P. furiosus&lt;/italic&gt; appeared to only marginally rely on the two major responses implemented by Archaea, i.e., the regulation of the ratio of diether to tetraether lipids and that of the number of cyclopentane rings in tetraethers. Instead, this species increased the ratio of glycerol monoalkyl glycerol tetraethers (GMGT, aka. H-shaped tetraethers) to glycerol dialkyl glycerol tetrathers (GDGT) in response to decreasing temperature and pH and increasing salinity, thus providing for the first time evidence of adaptive functions for GMGT. Besides &lt;italic&gt;P. furiosus&lt;/italic&gt;, numerous other species synthesize significant proportions of GMGT, which suggests that this unprecedented adaptive strategy might be common in Archaea.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We describe here the membrane adaptive strategies the hyperthermophilic, neutrophilic, and marine model archaeon &lt;italic&gt;Pyrococcus furiosus&lt;/italic&gt; implements in response to one of the largest sets of environmental stressors tested to date, including temperature, pH, salinity, presence/absence of elemental sulfur, carbon source, and genetic background. In contrast to the other archaea investigated so far, which response mainly involves the modulation of their diether/tetraether ratio and/or of their average number of cyclopentane rings, &lt;italic&gt;P. furiosus&lt;/italic&gt; regulates its monoalkyl (so called H-shaped) to dialkyl tetraether ratio. Our study thus provides for the first time evidence of adaptive functions of archaeal monoalkyl tetraethers towards low temperature and pH and high salinity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468962" rel="alternate" title="Membrane adaptation in the hyperthermophilic archaeon Pyrococcus furiosus relies upon a novel strategy involving glycerol monoalkyl glycerol tetraether lipids (12 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468908</id><title>The mycobacterial mutasome: composition and recruitment in live cells (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.038670+00:00</updated><author><name>Sophia Gessner</name></author><author><name>Zela Martin</name></author><author><name>Michael A. Reiche</name></author><author><name>Joana A. Santos</name></author><author><name>Neeraj Dhar</name></author><author><name>Ryan Dinkele</name></author><author><name>Timothy De Wet</name></author><author><name>Atondaho Ramudzuli</name></author><author><name>Saber Anoosheh</name></author><author><name>Dirk M. Lang</name></author><author><name>Jesse Aaron</name></author><author><name>Teng-Leong Chew</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Herrmann</name></author><author><name>Rolf Müller</name></author><author><name>John D. McKinney</name></author><author><name>Roger Woodgate</name></author><author><name>Valerie Mizrahi</name></author><author><name>Meindert H. Lamers</name></author><author><name>Digby F. Warner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A DNA damage-inducible mutagenic gene cassette has been implicated in the emergence of drug resistance in &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; during anti-tuberculosis (TB) chemotherapy. However, the molecular composition and operation of the encoded “mycobacterial mutasome” – minimally comprising DnaE2 polymerase and ImuA′ and ImuB accessory proteins – remain elusive. Following exposure of mycobacteria to DNA damaging agents, we observe that DnaE2 and ImuB co-localize with the DNA polymerase III β subunit (β clamp) in distinct intracellular foci. Notably, genetic inactivation of the mutasome in an &lt;italic&gt;imuB&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;AAAAGG&lt;/sup&gt; mutant containing a disrupted β clamp-binding motif abolishes ImuB-β clamp focus formation, a phenotype recapitulated pharmacologically by treating bacilli with griselimycin and in biochemical assays in which this β clamp-binding antibiotic collapses pre-formed ImuB-β clamp complexes. These observations establish the essentiality of the ImuB-β clamp interaction for mutagenic DNA repair in mycobacteria, identifying the mutasome as target for adjunctive therapeutics designed to protect anti-TB drugs against emerging resistance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468908" rel="alternate" title="The mycobacterial mutasome: composition and recruitment in live cells (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468767</id><title>Antenna modification leads to enhanced nitrogenase activity in a high light tolerant cyanobacterium (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.038968+00:00</updated><author><name>Anindita Bandyopadhyay</name></author><author><name>Zi Ye</name></author><author><name>Zuzana Benedikty</name></author><author><name>Martin Trtilek</name></author><author><name>Himadri B. Pakrasi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Biological nitrogen fixation is an energy intensive process that contributes significantly towards supporting life on this planet. Among nitrogen-fixing organisms, cyanobacteria remain unrivaled in their ability to fuel the energetically expensive nitrogenase reaction with photosynthetically harnessed solar energy. In heterocystous cyanobacteria light-driven, photosystem I (PSI)-mediated ATP synthesis plays a key role in propelling the nitrogenase reaction. Efficient light transfer to the photosystems rely on phycobilisomes (PBS), the major antenna protein complexes. PBS undergo degradation as a natural response to nitrogen starvation. Upon nitrogen availability, these proteins are resynthesized back to normal levels in vegetative cells, but their occurrence and function in heterocysts remains inconclusive. &lt;italic&gt;Anabaena&lt;/italic&gt; 33047 is a heterocystous cyanobacterium that thrives under high light, harbors higher amounts of PBS in its heterocysts and fixes nitrogen at higher rates compared to other heterocystous cyanobacteria. To assess the relationship between PBS in heterocysts and nitrogenase function, we engineered a strain that retains high amounts of the antenna proteins in its heterocysts. Intriguingly, under high light intensities the engineered strain exhibited unusually high rates of nitrogenase activity compared to the wild type. Spectroscopic analysis revealed altered PSI kinetics in the mutant, with increased cyclic electron flow around PSI, a route that contributes to ATP generation and nitrogenase activity in heterocysts. Retaining higher levels of PBS in heterocysts appears to be an effective strategy to enhance nitrogenase function in cyanobacteria that are equipped with the machinery to operate under high light intensities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The function of phycobilisomes, the large antenna protein complexes in heterocysts has long been debated. This study provides direct evidence of the involvement of these proteins in supporting nitrogenase activity in &lt;italic&gt;Anabaena&lt;/italic&gt; 33047, a heterocystous cyanobacterium that has affinity for very high light intensities. This strain was previously known to be recalcitrant to genetic manipulation and hence despite its many appealing traits, remained largely unexplored. We developed a genetic modification system for this strain and generated a Δ&lt;italic&gt;nblA&lt;/italic&gt; mutant that exhibited resistance to phycobilisome degradation upon nitrogen starvation. Physiological characterization of the strain indicated that PBS degradation is not essential for acclimation to nitrogen deficiency and retention of PBS is advantageous for nitrogenase function.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468767" rel="alternate" title="Antenna modification leads to enhanced nitrogenase activity in a high light tolerant cyanobacterium (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.465905</id><title>Aging and interferon gamma response drive the phenotype of neutrophils in the inflamed joint (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.039103+00:00</updated><author><name>Ricardo Grieshaber-Bouyer</name></author><author><name>Tarik Exner</name></author><author><name>Nicolaj S. Hackert</name></author><author><name>Felix A. Radtke</name></author><author><name>Scott A. Jelinsky</name></author><author><name>Olha Halyabar</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Wactor</name></author><author><name>Elham Karimizadeh</name></author><author><name>Jorge Schettini</name></author><author><name>A. Helena Jonsson</name></author><author><name>Deepak A. Rao</name></author><author><name>Lauren A. Henderson</name></author><author><name>Carsten Müller-Tidow</name></author><author><name>Hanns-Martin Lorenz</name></author><author><name>Guido Wabnitz</name></author><author><name>James A. Lederer</name></author><author><name>Angela Hadjipanayis</name></author><author><name>Peter A. Nigrovic</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neutrophils are typically the most abundant leukocyte in arthritic synovial fluid. We sought to understand changes that occur in neutrophils as they migrate from blood to joint.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We performed RNA sequencing of neutrophils from healthy human blood, arthritic blood, and arthritic synovial fluid, comparing transcriptional signatures with those from murine K/BxN serum transfer arthritis. We employed mass cytometry to quantify protein expression and sought to reproduce the synovial fluid phenotype &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; in cultured healthy blood neutrophils.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Blood neutrophils from healthy donors and patients with active arthritis exhibited largely similar transcriptional signatures. By contrast, synovial fluid neutrophils exhibited more than 1,600 differentially expressed genes. Gene signatures identified a prominent response to interferon gamma (IFNγ), as well as to tumor necrosis factor, interleukin 6, and hypoxia, in both humans and mice. Mass cytometry also found healthy and arthritic donor blood neutrophils largely indistinguishable but revealed a range of neutrophil phenotypes in synovial fluid defined by downregulation of CXCR1 and upregulation of FcγRI, HLA-DR, PD-L1, ICAM-1 and CXCR4. Reproduction of key elements of this signature in cultured blood neutrophils required both IFNγ and prolonged culture.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Circulating neutrophils from arthritis patients resemble those from healthy controls, but joint fluid cells exhibit a network of changes, conserved across species, that implicate IFNγ response and aging as complementary drivers of the synovial neutrophil phenotype.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;KEY MESSAGES&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What is already known about this subject?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neutrophils are central in the effector phase of inflammatory arthritis but their phenotypic heterogeneity in inflamed synovial fluid is poorly understood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;What does this study add?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;RNA-seq and mass cytometry identify a hallmark phenotype of neutrophils in synovial fluid consisting of upregulated ICAM-1, HLA-DR, PD-L1, Fc receptors and CXCR4.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transcriptomics highlight an IFNγ response signature conserved across humans and mice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;In vitro experiments implicate aging and IFNγ as complementary factors orchestrating the synovial fluid neutrophil phenotype.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;How might this impact on clinical practice or future developments?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Understanding the specific features of neutrophils in the arthritic joint may disclose opportunities for safe therapeutic targeting of this lineage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.465905" rel="alternate" title="Aging and interferon gamma response drive the phenotype of neutrophils in the inflamed joint (10 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468852</id><title>Structure of the rabies virus glycoprotein trimer bound to a pre-fusion specific neutralizing antibody (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.039429+00:00</updated><author><name>Heather M. Callaway</name></author><author><name>Dawid Zyla</name></author><author><name>Kathryn M. Hastie</name></author><author><name>Ruben Diaz Avalos</name></author><author><name>Alyssa Agarwal</name></author><author><name>Hervé Bourhy</name></author><author><name>Davide Corti</name></author><author><name>Erica Ollmann Saphire</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Rabies infection is nearly 100% lethal if untreated and kills over 50,000 people annually, many of them children. Existing rabies vaccines target the rabies virus glycoprotein (RABV-G) but generate short-lived immune responses, likely because the protein is heterogeneous under physiological conditions. Here, we report the 3.39Å cryo-EM structure of trimeric, pre-fusion RABV-G complexed with RVA122, a potently neutralizing human antibody. RVA122 binds to a quaternary epitope at the top of RABV-G, bridging domains and stabilizing RABV-G protomers in a prefusion state. RABV-G trimerization involves side-to-side interactions between the central α-helix and adjacent loops, rather than contacts between central helices, and interactions among the fusion loops at the glycoprotein base. These results provide a basis to develop improved rabies vaccines based on RABV-G stabilized in the prefusion conformation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We report the structure and trimeric interface of pre-fusion rabies virus glycoprotein bound to the neutralizing antibody RVA122.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468852" rel="alternate" title="Structure of the rabies virus glycoprotein trimer bound to a pre-fusion specific neutralizing antibody (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468953</id><title>An assessment of the evidence for antibacterial activity of stinging nettle (Urtica dioica) extracts (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.039681+00:00</updated><author><name>Freya Harrison</name></author><author><name>Jessica Furner-Pardoe</name></author><author><name>Erin Connelly</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Stinging nettles (&lt;italic&gt;Urtica&lt;/italic&gt; spp.) have been used in a diverse range of traditional and historical medicines from around the world for the treatment of skin diseases, wounds, urinary disorders, respiratory diseases, bone and joint pain, anaemia and other circulatory problems, as well as in cosmetic preparations for skin and haircare. As part of an interdisciplinary exploration of nettle-based remedies, we performed a systematic review of published evidence for the antimicrobial activity of &lt;italic&gt;Urtica&lt;/italic&gt; spp. extracts against bacteria and fungi that commonly cause skin, soft tissue and respiratory infections. We focussed on studies in which minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) assays of &lt;italic&gt;U. dioica&lt;/italic&gt; were conducted on the common bacterial opportunistic pathogens &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/italic&gt;. No studies used fresh leaves (all were dried prior to use), and no studies prepared nettles in weak acid (corresponding to vinegar) or in fats/oils, which are common combinations in historical and traditional preparations. We addressed this gap by conducting new antibacterial tests of extracts of fresh &lt;italic&gt;U. dioica&lt;/italic&gt; leaves prepared in vinegar, butter or olive oil against &lt;italic&gt;P. aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;S. aureus&lt;/italic&gt;. Our systematic review and additional experimental data leads us to conclude that there is no strong evidence for nettles containing molecules with clinically useful antimicrobial activity. It seems most likely that the utility of nettles in traditional topical preparations for wounds may simply be as a “safe” absorbent medium for keeping antibacterial (vinegar) or emollient (oils) ingredients at the treatment site.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;All data relating to the systematic review are supplied in the Datasets and Supplementary tables contained in the Supporting Data file.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468953" rel="alternate" title="An assessment of the evidence for antibacterial activity of stinging nettle (Urtica dioica) extracts (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468769</id><title>Effects of Chronic Intermittent Hypoxia and Chronic Sleep Fragmentation on Gut Microbiome, Serum Metabolome, Liver and Adipose Tissue Morphology (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.039879+00:00</updated><author><name>Fan Wang</name></author><author><name>Juanjuan Zou</name></author><author><name>Huajun Xu</name></author><author><name>Weijun Huang</name></author><author><name>Xiaoman Zhang</name></author><author><name>Zhicheng Wei</name></author><author><name>Xinyi Li</name></author><author><name>Yupu Liu</name></author><author><name>Jianyin Zou</name></author><author><name>Feng Liu</name></author><author><name>Huaming Zhu</name></author><author><name>Hongliang Yi</name></author><author><name>Jian Guan</name></author><author><name>Shankai Yin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chronic intermittent hypoxia (CIH) and chronic sleep fragmentation (CSF) are two cardinal pathological features of obstructive sleep apnea (OSA). Dietary obesity is a crucial risk intermediator for OSA and metabolic disorders. Gut microbiota affect hepatic and adipose tissue morphology under conditions of CIH or CSF through downstream metabolites. However, the exact relationship is unclear. Herein, chow and high-fat diet (HFD)-fed mice were subjected to CIH or CSF for 10 weeks each and compared to normoxia (NM) or normal sleep (NS) controls. 16S rRNA amplicon sequencing, untargeted liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry, and histological assessment of liver and adipose tissues were used to investigate the correlations between the microbiome, metabolome, and lipid metabolism under CIH or CSF condition. Our results demonstrated that CIH and CSF regulate the abundance of intestinal microbes (such as &lt;italic&gt;Akkermansia mucinphila&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;Clostridium spp.&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;Lactococcus spp.&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;and Bifidobacterium spp&lt;/italic&gt;.) and functional metabolites, such as tryptophan, free fatty acids, branched amino acids, and bile acids, which influence adipose tissue and hepatic lipid metabolism, and the level of lipid deposition in tissues and peripheral blood. In conclusion, CIH and CSF adversely affect fecal microbiota composition and function, and host metabolism; these findings provide new insight into the independent and synergistic effects of CIH, CSF, and HFD on lipid disorders.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468769" rel="alternate" title="Effects of Chronic Intermittent Hypoxia and Chronic Sleep Fragmentation on Gut Microbiome, Serum Metabolome, Liver and Adipose Tissue Morphology (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469056</id><title>A novel growth and isolation medium for exoelectrogenic bacteria (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.040167+00:00</updated><author><name>Zumaira Nazeer</name></author><author><name>Eustace Y. Fernando</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A microbiological isolation and growth medium that can effectively discriminate electrochemically active exoelectrogenic bacteria from other non-exoelectrogenic bacteria, is currently unavailable. In this study, we developed a novel chromogenic growth and isolation solid medium based on MnO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; that can selectively allow the growth of exoelectrogenic bacteria and change the medium colour in the process. Known exoelectrogenic bacteria such as &lt;italic&gt;Shewanella oneidensis&lt;/italic&gt; MR1 and other such bacteria from functional microbial fuel cell (MFC) anodes were capable of growing and changing colour in the novel growth medium. On the contrary, non-exoelectrogenic bacteria such as &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; ATCC 25922 were incapable of growing and inducing a colour change in the novel medium. Further biochemical characterisation of these isolated exoelectrogenic bacteria by Raman micro-spectroscopy demonstrated that these bacteria over express cytochrome proteins that are vital in extracellular electron transfer events. This medium is a convenient method to isolate exoelectrogenic bacteria from complex environmental samples.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469056" rel="alternate" title="A novel growth and isolation medium for exoelectrogenic bacteria (8 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468804</id><title>Whole-brain fluorescence-MRI coregistration for precise anatomical mapping of virus infection (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.040348+00:00</updated><author><name>Nunya Chotiwan</name></author><author><name>Stefanie M. A. Willekens</name></author><author><name>Erin Schexnaydre</name></author><author><name>Max Hahn</name></author><author><name>Federico Morini</name></author><author><name>Jianguo Zhang</name></author><author><name>Emma Nilsson</name></author><author><name>Lars-Anders Carlson</name></author><author><name>Ulf Ahlgren</name></author><author><name>Daniel Marcellino</name></author><author><name>Anna K. Överby</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neurotropic virus infections cause tremendous disease burden. Methods visualizing infection in the whole brain remain unavailable which greatly impedes understanding of viral neurotropism and pathogenesis. We devised an approach to visualize the distribution of neurotropic virus infection in whole mouse brain &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Optical projection tomography (OPT) signal was coregistered with a unique magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) brain template, enabling precise anatomical mapping of viral distribution, and the effect of type I interferon on distribution of infection was analyzed. Guided by OPT-MR, we show that Langat virus specifically targets sensory brain systems and the lack of type I interferon response results in an anatomical shift in infection patterns in the brain. We confirm this regional tropism, observed with whole brain OPT-MRI, by confocal and electron microscopy to provide unprecedented insight into viral neurotropism. This approach can be applied to any fluorescently labeled target in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468804" rel="alternate" title="Whole-brain fluorescence-MRI coregistration for precise anatomical mapping of virus infection (8 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469014</id><title>Mitochondrial dysfunction promotes alternative gasdermin D-mediated inflammatory cell death and susceptibility to infection (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.040627+00:00</updated><author><name>Chi G Weindel</name></author><author><name>Xiao Zhao</name></author><author><name>Eduardo Martinez</name></author><author><name>Samantha L Bell</name></author><author><name>Krystal J Vail</name></author><author><name>Aja K Coleman</name></author><author><name>Jordan J VanPortfliet</name></author><author><name>Baoyu Zhao</name></author><author><name>Cory Mabry</name></author><author><name>Pingwei Li</name></author><author><name>Phillip West</name></author><author><name>Jason Karpac</name></author><author><name>Kristin L Patrick</name></author><author><name>Robert O Watson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human mutations in mitochondrial-associated genes are associated with inflammatory diseases and susceptibility to infection. However, their mechanistic contributions to immune outcomes remain ill-defined.  We discovered that the disease-associated gain-of-function allele &lt;italic&gt;Lrrk2&lt;sup&gt;G2019S&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; (leucine-rich repeat kinase 2) promotes mitochondrial hyper-fission, depolarization, and oxidative stress in macrophages. In the presence of &lt;italic&gt;Lrrk2&lt;sup&gt;G2019S&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt;-dependent mitochondrial perturbations, AIM2 inflammasome activation promotes more cell death but not more pyroptotic IL-1β release. Instead, inflammasome activation in &lt;italic&gt;Lrrk2&lt;sup&gt;G2019S&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; macrophages triggers gasdermin D (GSDMD)-mediated mitochondrial pores, driving up ROS-mediated RIPK1/RIPK3/MLKL dependent necroptosis. Consequently, infection of &lt;italic&gt;Lrrk2&lt;sup&gt;G2019S&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice with &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; elicits hyperinflammation and immunopathology via enhanced neutrophil infiltration. By uncovering that GSDMD promotes non-pyroptotic cell death in &lt;italic&gt;Lrrk2&lt;sup&gt;G2019S&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; macrophages, our findings demonstrate that altered mitochondrial function can reprogram cell death modalities to elicit distinct immune outcomes. This provides mechanistic insights into why mutations in LRRK2 are associated with susceptibility to chronic inflammatory and infectious diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469014" rel="alternate" title="Mitochondrial dysfunction promotes alternative gasdermin D-mediated inflammatory cell death and susceptibility to infection (8 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468433</id><title>Cryptococcus neoformans capsule regrowth experiments reveal dynamics of enlargement and architecture (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.040953+00:00</updated><author><name>Maggie P. Wear</name></author><author><name>Ella Jacobs</name></author><author><name>Siqing Wang</name></author><author><name>Scott McConnell</name></author><author><name>Anthony Bowen</name></author><author><name>Camilla Strother</name></author><author><name>Radames J.B. Cordero</name></author><author><name>Arturo Casadevall</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The polysaccharide capsule of fungal pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Cryptococcus neoformans&lt;/italic&gt; is a critical virulence factor that has historically evaded characterization. Polysaccharides remain attached to the cell as capsular polysaccharide (CPS) or are shed into the surroundings in the form of exopolysaccharide (EPS). While a great deal of study has been done examining the properties of EPS, far less is known about CPS. In this work, we detail the development of new physical and enzymatic methods for the isolation of CPS which can be used to explore the architecture of the capsule and removed capsular material. Sonication and glucanex digestion yield soluble CPS preparations, while French Press and modified glucanex digestion plus vortexing remove the capsule and cell wall producing polysaccharide aggregates that we call ‘capsule ghosts.’ The existence of capsule ghosts implies an inherent organization that allows it to exist independent of the cell wall surface. As sonication and glucanex digestion were noncytotoxic, it was possible to observe the cryptococcal cells rebuilding their capsule, revealing new insights into capsule architecture and synthesis consistent with a model in which the capsule is assembled from smaller polymers, which are then assemble into larger ones.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Characterization of the cryptococcal polysaccharide capsule relies on methods of isolation for its &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; study. This study demonstrates that the capsule is susceptible to physical and enzymatic removal. The application of new methods yields insights into the anatomy, modular nature, and architecture of the capsule with both soluble CPS preparations and ‘capsule ghosts.’ Together these insights inform on a long-standing debate modeling capsular assembly wherein our data shows that the capsule is assembled by smaller polymers added distally rather than by proximal addition or by polymers spanning the entire capsule radius.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468433" rel="alternate" title="Cryptococcus neoformans capsule regrowth experiments reveal dynamics of enlargement and architecture (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469101</id><title>Essential role for an isoform of Escherichia coli translation initiation factor IF2 in repair of two-ended DNA double-strand breaks (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.041246+00:00</updated><author><name>Jillella Mallikarjun</name></author><author><name>J Gowrishankar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt;, three isoforms of the essential translation initiation factor IF2 (IF2-1, IF2-2, and IF2-3) are generated from separate in-frame initiation codons in &lt;italic&gt;infB&lt;/italic&gt;. The isoforms have earlier been suggested to additionally participate in DNA damage repair and replication restart. It is also known that the proteins RecA and RecBCD are needed for repair of DNA double-strand breaks (DSBs) in E. &lt;italic&gt;coli&lt;/italic&gt;. Here we show that strains lacking IF2-1 are profoundly sensitive to two-ended DSBs in DNA generated by radiomimetic agents phleomycin or bleomycin, or by endonuclease I-SceI. However, these strains remained tolerant to other DSB-generating genotoxic agents or perturbations to which &lt;italic&gt;recA&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;recBC&lt;/italic&gt; mutants remained sensitive, such as to mitomycin C, type-2 DNA topoisomerase inhibitors, or DSB caused by palindrome cleavage behind a replication fork. Data from genome-wide copy number analyses following I-SceI cleavage at a single chromosomal locus suggested that, in a strain lacking IF2-1, the magnitude of break induced replication through replication restart mechanisms is largely preserved but the extent of DNA resection around the DSB site is reduced. We propose that in absence of IF2-1 it is the annealing of a RecA nucleoprotein filament to its homologous target that is weakened, which in turn leads to a specific failure in assembly of &lt;italic&gt;Ter-to-oriC&lt;/italic&gt; directed replisomes needed for consummation of two-ended DSB repair.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Double-strand breaks (DSBs) in DNA are major threats to genome integrity. In &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt;, DSBs are repaired by Rec- and RecBCD-mediated homologous recombination (HR). This study demonstrates a critical role for an isoform (IF2-1) of the translation initiation factor IF2 in the repair of two-ended DSBs in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; (that can be generated by ionizing radiation, certain DNA-damaging chemicals, or endonuclease action). It is proposed that IF2-1 acts to facilitate the function of RecA in the annealing between a pair of DNA molecules during HR.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469101" rel="alternate" title="Essential role for an isoform of Escherichia coli translation initiation factor IF2 in repair of two-ended DNA double-strand breaks (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469199</id><title>Three orphan histidine kinases inhibit Clostridioides difficile sporulation (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.041829+00:00</updated><author><name>Adrianne N. Edwards</name></author><author><name>Daniela Wetzel</name></author><author><name>Michael A. DiCandia</name></author><author><name>Shonna M. McBride</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ability of the anaerobic gastrointestinal pathogen, &lt;italic&gt;Clostridioides difficile&lt;/italic&gt;, to survive outside the host relies on the formation of dormant endospores. Spore formation is contingent on the activation of a conserved transcription factor, Spo0A, by phosphorylation. Multiple kinases and phosphatases regulate Spo0A activity in other spore-forming organisms; however, these factors are not well conserved in &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt;. Previously, we discovered that deletion of a conserved phosphotransfer protein, CD1492, increases sporulation, indicating that CD1492 inhibits &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; spore formation. In this study, we investigate the functions of additional conserved orphan phosphotransfer proteins, CD2492, CD1579, and CD1949 which are hypothesized to regulate Spo0A phosphorylation. Disruption of the conserved phosphotransfer protein, CD2492, also increased sporulation frequency, similarly to the &lt;italic&gt;CD1492&lt;/italic&gt; mutant, and in contrast to a previous study. A &lt;italic&gt;CD1492 CD2492&lt;/italic&gt; mutant phenocopied the sporulation and gene expression patterns of the single mutants, suggesting that these proteins function in the same genetic pathway to repress sporulation. Deletion of the conserved CD1579 phosphotransfer protein also variably increased sporulation frequency; however, knockdown of &lt;italic&gt;CD1949&lt;/italic&gt; expression did not influence sporulation. We provide evidence that CD1492, CD2492 and CD1579 function as phosphatases, as mutation of the conserved histidine residue for phosphate transfer abolished CD2492 function, and expression of the &lt;italic&gt;CD1492&lt;/italic&gt; or &lt;italic&gt;CD2492&lt;/italic&gt; histidine site-directed mutants or the wild-type &lt;italic&gt;CD1579&lt;/italic&gt; allele in a parent strain resulted in a dominant negative hypersporulation phenotype. Altogether, at least three phosphotransfer proteins, CD1492, CD2492 and CD1579 (herein, PtpA, PtpB and PtpC) repress &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; sporulation initiation by regulating activity of Spo0A.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The formation of inactive spores is critical for the long-term survival of the gastrointestinal pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Clostridioides difficile&lt;/italic&gt;. The onset of sporulation is controlled by the master regulator of sporulation, Spo0A, which is activated by phosphorylation. Multiple kinases and phosphatases control Spo0A phosphorylation; however, this regulatory pathway is not defined in &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt;. We show that two conserved phosphotransfer proteins, CD1492 (PtpA) and CD2492 (PtpB), function in the same regulatory pathway to repress sporulation by preventing Spo0A phosphorylation. We show that another conserved phosphotransfer protein, CD1579 (PtpC), also represses sporulation, and we eliminate the possibility that a fourth orphan histidine kinase protein, CD1949, impacts &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; sporulation. These results support the idea that &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; inhibits sporulation initiation through multiple phosphatases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469199" rel="alternate" title="Three orphan histidine kinases inhibit Clostridioides difficile sporulation (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468600</id><title>Marmoset Model for Mycobacterium avium Complex Pulmonary Disease (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.042177+00:00</updated><author><name>Jay I Peters</name></author><author><name>Diego Jose Maselli</name></author><author><name>Mandeep Mangat</name></author><author><name>Jacqueline J. Coalson</name></author><author><name>Ceci Hinojosa</name></author><author><name>Luis Giavedoni</name></author><author><name>Barbara A. Brown-Elliott</name></author><author><name>Edward D. Chan</name></author><author><name>David E. Griffith</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Rationale&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium avium&lt;/italic&gt; complex, is the most common nontuberculous mycobacterial respiratory pathogen in humans. Disease mechanisms are poorly understood due to the absence of a reliable animal model for &lt;italic&gt;M. avium&lt;/italic&gt; complex pulmonary disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assess the susceptibility, immunologic and histopathologic responses of the common marmoset (&lt;italic&gt;Callithrix jacchus&lt;/italic&gt;) to &lt;italic&gt;M. avium&lt;/italic&gt; complex pulmonary infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;7 adult female marmosets underwent endobronchial inoculation with 10&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt; colony-forming units &lt;italic&gt;of M. intracellulare&lt;/italic&gt; and were monitored for 30 or 60 days. Prior to infection, chest radiograph and serum cytokines were assessed; serum cytokines were also monitored weekly for 30 days. At sacrifice 30 days (3 animals) or 60 days (4 animals) after infection, chest radiograph, serum and bronchoalveolar lavage cytokines, histopathology, and cultures of the bronchoalveolar lavage, lungs, liver, and kidney were analyzed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Measurements and Main Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Five of seven animals (two at 30 days and three at 60 days of infection) had positive lung cultures for &lt;italic&gt;M. intracellulare&lt;/italic&gt;. Extra-pulmonary cultures were positive in three animals. All animals appeared healthy throughout the study. All five animals with positive lung cultures had radiographic changes consistent with pneumonitis. At 30 days, those with &lt;italic&gt;M. intracellulare&lt;/italic&gt; lung infection showed granulomatous inflammation while at 60 days there was less inflammatory change, but bronchiectasis was noted. The cytokine response in the bronchoalveolar lavage fluid was uniformly greater in the animals with positive &lt;italic&gt;M. intracellulare&lt;/italic&gt; cultures than those without a productive infection with greater levels at 30-days compared to 60-days. Similarly, serum cytokines were more elevated in the animals that had positive &lt;italic&gt;M. intracellulare&lt;/italic&gt; cultures compared to those without a productive infection, peaking 14-21 days after inoculation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Endobronchial instillation of &lt;italic&gt;M. intracellulare&lt;/italic&gt; resulted in pulmonary mycobacterial infection in marmosets with a differential immune response, radiographic and histopathologic abnormalities, and an indolent course consistent with &lt;italic&gt;M. avium&lt;/italic&gt; complex lung infection in humans.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468600" rel="alternate" title="Marmoset Model for Mycobacterium avium Complex Pulmonary Disease (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.469368</id><title>Heat activation and inactivation of bacterial spores. Is there an overlap? (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.043422+00:00</updated><author><name>Juan Wen</name></author><author><name>Jan P.P.M. Smelt</name></author><author><name>Norbert O.E. Vischer</name></author><author><name>Arend D Vos</name></author><author><name>Peter Setlow</name></author><author><name>Stanley Brul</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Heat activation at a sublethal temperature is widely applied to promote Bacillus species spore germination. This treatment also has potential to be employed in food processing to eliminate undesired bacterial spores by enhancing their germination, and then inactivating the less heat resistant germinated spores at a milder temperature. However, incorrect heat treatment could also generate heat damage in spores, and lead to more heterogeneous spore germination. Here, the heat activation and heat damage profile of Bacillus subtilis spores was determined by testing spore germination and outgrowth at both population and single spore levels. The heat treatments used were 40-80 degrees Celcius, and for 0-300 min. The results were as follows. 1) Heat activation at 40-70 degrees Celcius promoted L-valine and L-asparagine-glucose-fructose-potassium (AGFK) induced germination in a time dependent manner. 2) The optimal heat activation temperatures for AGFK and L-valine germination via the GerB plus GerK or GerA germinant receptors were 65 and 50-65 degrees Celcius, respectively. 3) Heat inactivation of dormant spores appeared at 70 degrees Celcius, and the heat damage of molecules essential for germination and growth began at 70 and 65 degrees Celcius, respectively. 4) Heat treatment at 75 degrees Celcius resulted in both activation of germination and damage to the germination apparatus, and 80 degrees Celcius treatment caused more pronounced heat damage. 5) For the spores that should withstand adverse environmental temperatures in nature, heat activation seems functional for a subsequent optimal germination process, while heat damage affected both germination and outgrowth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.469368" rel="alternate" title="Heat activation and inactivation of bacterial spores. Is there an overlap? (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468875</id><title>Birnaviridae virus factories show features of liquid-liquid phase separation, and are distinct from paracrystalline arrays of virions observed by electron microscopy (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.043733+00:00</updated><author><name>Vishwanatha R. A. P. Reddy</name></author><author><name>Elle A. Campbell</name></author><author><name>Joanna Wells</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Simpson</name></author><author><name>Salik Nazki</name></author><author><name>Philippa C. Hawes</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Broadbent</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To gain more information about the nature of &lt;italic&gt;Birnaviridae&lt;/italic&gt; virus factories (VFs), we used a recombinant infectious bursal disease virus (IBDV) expressing split-GFP11 tagged to the polymerase (VP1) that we have previously shown is a marker for VFs in infected cells expressing GFP1-10. We found that VFs co-localized with 5-ethynyl uridine in the presence of actinomycin D, confirming they were the site of &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; RNA synthesis, and VFs were visible in infected cells that were fixed and permeabilized with digitonin, demonstrating that they were not membrane bound. Fluorescence recovery after photobleaching (FRAP) a region of interest within the VFs occurred rapidly, recovering from approximately 25% to 87% the original intensity over 146 seconds, and VFs were dissolved by 1,6-hexanediol treatment, demonstrating they showed properties consistent with liquid-liquid phase separation. There was a lower co-localization of the VF GFP signal with the capsid protein VP2 (Manders’ coefficient (MC) 0.6), compared to VP3 (MC, 0.9), which prompted us to investigate the VF ultrastructure by transmission electron microscopy (TEM). In infected cells, paracrystalline arrays (PAs) of virions were observed in the cytoplasm, as well as discrete electron dense regions. Using correlative light and electron microscopy (CLEM), we observed that the electron dense regions correlated with the GFP signal of the VFs, which were distinct from the PAs. In summary, &lt;italic&gt;Birnaviridae&lt;/italic&gt; VFs are sites of &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; RNA synthesis, are not bound by a membrane, show properties consistent with liquid-liquid phase separation, and are distinct from the PAs observed by TEM.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Members of the &lt;italic&gt;Birnaviridae&lt;/italic&gt; infect birds, fish and insects, and are responsible for diseases of significant economic importance to the poultry industry and aquaculture. Despite their importance, how they replicate in cells remains poorly understood. Here, we show that the &lt;italic&gt;Birnaviridae&lt;/italic&gt; virus factories are not membrane bound, demonstrate properties consistent with liquid-liquid phase separation, and are distinct from the paracrystalline arrays of virions observed by transmission electron microscopy, enhancing our fundamental knowledge of virus replication that could be used to develop strategies to control disease, or optimize their therapeutic application.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468875" rel="alternate" title="Birnaviridae virus factories show features of liquid-liquid phase separation, and are distinct from paracrystalline arrays of virions observed by electron microscopy (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468558</id><title>Bacteriophage cocktails displayed protective effects against soft rot-causing Pectobacterium sp. (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.044004+00:00</updated><author><name>Aeron Jade S. Parena</name></author><author><name>Benji Brayan I. Silva</name></author><author><name>Rae Mark L. Mercado</name></author><author><name>Adelbert Adrian A. Sendon</name></author><author><name>Freddiewebb B. Signabon</name></author><author><name>Johnny F. Balidion</name></author><author><name>Jaymee R. Encabo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Soft rot caused by &lt;italic&gt;Pectobacterium&lt;/italic&gt; spp. is responsible for significant losses in vegetable production worldwide. Methods for the effective control of this disease are limited and are primarily based on good agricultural practices. The use of phages as biocontrol agents appears to be a promising alternative to combat phytopathogens. In this study, we investigated the efficacy of lytic phages against soft rot caused by &lt;italic&gt;Pectobacterium carotovorum&lt;/italic&gt; subsp. &lt;italic&gt;carotovorum&lt;/italic&gt;. Designated as PPc_A3, PPc_D1, and PPc_J3, three bacteriophage isolates, which were recovered from symptomatic tissues and environmental samples, were observed to effectively lyse &lt;italic&gt;P. carotovorum&lt;/italic&gt; subsp. &lt;italic&gt;carotovorum&lt;/italic&gt;. PPc_A3 belongs to the &lt;italic&gt;Podoviridae&lt;/italic&gt; family, while phages PPc_D1 and PPc_J3 belong to the &lt;italic&gt;Myoviridae&lt;/italic&gt; family based on the morphological features of the virions as observed using transmission electron microscopy. The optimal multiplicity of infection (MOI) differed greatly among the three phages. All survived incubations at 30°C, 40°C and 50°C and at pH ranging from 3.0 to 9.0, but were all inactivated at 60°C and at pH 12. Both monophage and cocktail preparations were effective in inhibiting the growth of &lt;italic&gt;P. carotovorum&lt;/italic&gt; subsp. &lt;italic&gt;carotovorum&lt;/italic&gt; in &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; challenge tests. In the semi-&lt;italic&gt;in planta&lt;/italic&gt; assays, monophage treatments resulted in significant reduction of tissue maceration in potato slices, while treatment with cocktail preparations completely inhibited the development of soft rot disease. Overall, these results demonstrate the efficacy of cocktail formulations of phages PPc_A3, PPc_D1, and PPc_J3 for the biocontrol of soft rot disease caused by &lt;italic&gt;P. carotovorum&lt;/italic&gt; subsp. &lt;italic&gt;carotovorum&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468558" rel="alternate" title="Bacteriophage cocktails displayed protective effects against soft rot-causing Pectobacterium sp. (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.469378</id><title>Organization and dynamics of the SpoVAEa protein, and its surrounding inner membrane lipids upon germination of Bacillus subtilis spores (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.044319+00:00</updated><author><name>Juan Wen</name></author><author><name>Norbert O.E. Vischer</name></author><author><name>Arend D Vos</name></author><author><name>Erik M.M. Manders</name></author><author><name>Peter Setlow</name></author><author><name>Stanley Brul</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The SpoVA proteins make up a channel in the inner membrane (IM) of B. subtilis spore. This channel responds to signals from activated germinant receptors (GRs), and allows release of Ca2+-DPA from the spore core during germination. In the current work, we studied the location and dynamics of SpoVAEa in dormant spores. Notably, the SpoVAEa-SGFP2 proteins were present in a single spot in spores, similar to the complex formed by all GRs. However, while the GR's spot remains in one location, the SpoVAEa-SGFP2 spot in the IM moved randomly with high frequency. The dynamics of the SpoVAEa-SGFP2 and its surrounding IM region as stained by fluorescent dyes were also tracked during spore germination, as the dormant spore IM appeared to have an immobile germination related functional microdomain. This microdomain disappeared around the time of appearance of a germinated spore, the loss of fluorescence of the IM by fluorescent dyes, as well as the appearance of SpoVAEa-SGFP2 peak fluorescent intensity occurred in parallel. These observed events were highly related to the rapid phase darkening, which is considered as the Ca2+DPA rapid release. We also tested the response of SpoVAEa and the IM to thermal treatments at 40-80 degrees Celcius. Heat treatment triggered an increase of green autofluorescence, which is speculated to be due to coat protein denaturation, and 80 degrees Celcius treatments induce the appearance of phase-grey-like spores. These spores presumably have a similar intracellular physical state as the phase grey spores detected in the germination but lack the functional proteins for further germination events.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.469378" rel="alternate" title="Organization and dynamics of the SpoVAEa protein, and its surrounding inner membrane lipids upon germination of Bacillus subtilis spores (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468913</id><title>Genome-wide identification of novel sRNAs in Streptococcus mutans (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.044671+00:00</updated><author><name>Madeline C Krieger</name></author><author><name>Justin Merritt</name></author><author><name>Rahul Raghavan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Streptococcus mutans&lt;/italic&gt; is a major pathobiont involved in the development of dental caries. Its ability to utilize numerous sugars and to effectively respond to environmental stress promotes &lt;italic&gt;S. mutans&lt;/italic&gt; proliferation in oral biofilms. Because of their quick action and low energetic cost, non-coding small RNAs (sRNAs) represent an ideal mode of gene regulation in stress response networks, yet their roles in oral pathogens have remained largely unexplored. We identified 15 novel sRNAs in &lt;italic&gt;S. mutans&lt;/italic&gt; and show that they respond to four stress-inducing conditions commonly encountered by the pathogen in human mouth: sugar-phosphate stress, hydrogen peroxide exposure, high temperature, and low pH. To better understand the role of sRNAs in &lt;italic&gt;S. mutans&lt;/italic&gt;, we further explored the function of the novel sRNA, SmsR4. Our data demonstrate that SmsR4 regulates the EIIA component of the sorbitol phosphotransferase system, which transports and phosphorylates the sugar alcohol sorbitol. The fine-tuning of EIIA availability by SmsR4 likely promotes &lt;italic&gt;S. mutans&lt;/italic&gt; growth while using sorbitol as the main carbon source. Our work lays a foundation for understanding the role of sRNAs in regulating gene expression in stress response networks in &lt;italic&gt;S. mutans&lt;/italic&gt; and highlights the importance of the underexplored phenomenon of posttranscriptional gene regulation in oral bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Small RNAs (sRNAs) are important gene regulators in bacteria, but the identities and functions of sRNAs in &lt;italic&gt;Streptococcus mutans&lt;/italic&gt;, the principal bacterium involved in the formation of dental caries, are unknown. In this study, we identified 15 putative sRNAs in &lt;italic&gt;S. mutans&lt;/italic&gt; and show that they respond to four common stress-inducing conditions present in human mouth: sugar-phosphate stress, hydrogen peroxide exposure, high temperature, and low pH. We further show that the novel sRNA SmsR4 likely modulates sorbitol transport into the cell by regulating SMU_313 mRNA, which encodes the EIIA subunit of the sorbitol phosphotransferase system. Gaining a better understanding of sRNA-based gene regulation may provide new opportunities to develop specific inhibitors of &lt;italic&gt;S. mutans&lt;/italic&gt; growth, thereby improving oral health.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468913" rel="alternate" title="Genome-wide identification of novel sRNAs in Streptococcus mutans (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468917</id><title>Resistance profiling of Aspergillus fumigatus to olorofim indicates absence of intrinsic resistance and unveils the molecular mechanisms of acquired olorofim resistance (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.044971+00:00</updated><author><name>Jochem B. Buil</name></author><author><name>Jason D. Oliver</name></author><author><name>Derek Law</name></author><author><name>Tim Baltussen</name></author><author><name>Jan Zoll</name></author><author><name>Margriet W.J. Hokken</name></author><author><name>Marlou Tehupeiory-Kooreman</name></author><author><name>Willem J.G. Melchers</name></author><author><name>Mike Birch</name></author><author><name>Paul E. Verweij</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Olorofim (F901318) is a new antifungal currently under clinical development that shows both in vitro and in vivo activity against a number of filamentous fungi including &lt;italic&gt;Aspergillus fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt;. In this study we screened &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt; isolates for intrinsic olorofim-resistant &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt; and evaluated the ability of &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt; to acquire an olorofim-resistant phenotype. No intrinsic resistance was found in 975 clinical &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt; isolates. However, we found that isolates with increased olorofim MICs (&amp;gt; 8 mg/L) could be selected using a high number of conidia and olorofim exposure under laboratory conditions. Assessment of the frequency of acquired olorofim resistance development of &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt; was shown to be higher than for voriconazole but lower than for itraconazole. Sequencing the &lt;italic&gt;PyrE&lt;/italic&gt; gene of isogenic isolates with olorofim MICs of &amp;gt;8 mg/L identified various amino acid substitutions with a hotspot at locus G119. Olorofim was shown to have reduced affinity to mutated target protein dihydroorotate dehydrogenase (DHODH) and the effect of these mutations were proven by introducing the mutations directly in &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt;. We then investigated whether G119 mutations were associated with a fitness cost in &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus.&lt;/italic&gt; These experiments showed a small but significant reduction in growth rate for strains with a G119V substitution, while strains with a G119C substitution did not exhibit a reduction in growth rate. These in vitro findings were confirmed in an in vivo pathogenicity model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Olorofim represents an important new treatment option for patients with difficult to treat invasive fungal infections, including triazole-resistant &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt; infection. Our study provides insights into one resistance mechanism and the potential dynamics of olorofim resistance, which will help to prevent and manage resistance selection. Such insights are critical to antifungal stewardship and to safeguard its prolonged use in clinical practice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468917" rel="alternate" title="Resistance profiling of Aspergillus fumigatus to olorofim indicates absence of intrinsic resistance and unveils the molecular mechanisms of acquired olorofim resistance (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469458</id><title>Zinc finger protein Zfp335 controls early T cell development and survival through beta-selection-dependent and -independent mechanisms (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.045252+00:00</updated><author><name>Xin Wang</name></author><author><name>Anjun Jiao</name></author><author><name>Yanhong Su</name></author><author><name>Wenhua Li</name></author><author><name>Biao Yang</name></author><author><name>Renyi Ding</name></author><author><name>Cangang Zhang</name></author><author><name>Haiyan Liu</name></author><author><name>Xiaofeng Yang</name></author><author><name>Chenming Sun</name></author><author><name>Lina Sun</name></author><author><name>Baojun Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;T cell development in the thymus undergoes the process of differentiation, selective proliferation and survival from CD4&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;CD8&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; double negative (DN) stage to CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; double positive (DP) stage prior to the formation of CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; helper and CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; cytolytic T cells ready for circulation. Each developmental stage is tightly regulated by sequentially-operating molecular networks, of which only limited numbers of transcription regulators have been deciphered. Here we identified Zfp335 transcription factor as a new player in the regulatory network controlling thymocyte development. We demonstrate that Zfp335 intrinsically controls DN to DP transition, as T cell-specific deficiency in Zfp335 leads to a substantial accumulation of DN3 along with reduction of DP, CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; thymocytes. This developmental blockade at DN stage results from the impaired intracellular TCRβ expression as well as increased susceptibility to apoptosis in thymocytes. Transcriptomic and ChIP-seq analyses revealed a direct regulation of transcription factors Bcl6 and Rorc by Zfp335. Importantly, enhanced expression of TCRβ and Bcl6/RorγT restores the developmental defect during DN3 to DN4 transition and improves thymocytes survival, respectively. These findings identify a critical role of Zfp335 in controlling T cell development by maintaining intracellular TCRβ expression-mediated β-selection and independently activating cell survival signaling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469458" rel="alternate" title="Zinc finger protein Zfp335 controls early T cell development and survival through beta-selection-dependent and -independent mechanisms (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468914</id><title>Identification of shared bacterial strains in the vaginal microbiota of reproductive-age mothers and daughters using genome-resolved metagenomics (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.045498+00:00</updated><author><name>M. France</name></author><author><name>S. Brown</name></author><author><name>A. Rompalo</name></author><author><name>R. M. Brotman</name></author><author><name>J. Ravel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It has been suggested that the human microbiome might be vertically transmitted from mother to offspring and that early colonizers may play a critical role in development of the immune system. Studies have shown limited support for the vertical transmission of the intestinal microbiota but the derivation of the vaginal microbiota remains largely unknown. Although the vaginal microbiota of children and reproductive age cis women differ in composition, the vaginal microbiota could be vertically transmitted. To determine whether there was any support for this hypothesis, we examined the vaginal microbiota of daughter-mother pairs from the Baltimore metropolitan area (ages 14-27, 32-51; n=39). We assessed whether the daughter’s microbiota was similar in composition to their mother’s using metataxonomics. Permutation tests revealed that while some pairs did have similar vaginal microbiota, the degree of similarity did not exceed that expected by chance. Genome-resolved metagenomics was used to identify shared bacterial strains in a subset of the families (n=22). We found a small number of bacterial strains that were shared between mother-daughter pairs but identified more shared strains between individuals from different families, indicating that vaginal bacteria may display biogeographic patterns. Earlier-in-life studies are needed to demonstrate vertical transmission of the vaginal microbiota.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Early colonizers of our microbiota are theorized to play an important role in the development of our immune system, yet we know little about how these communities are established. Vertical transmission from mother to offspring at the time of birth is theorized to be a major source of early colonizers but limited evidence supporting this process has only been shown for the intestinal tract microbiota. The provenance of the vaginal microbiota is largely unknown, although some have posited it is similarly vertically transmitted. We examined the vaginal microbiota of mother-daughter pairs and found limited evidence in support of this hypothesis. However, our analysis also revealed putative biogeographic patterns in the distribution of the strains which comprise the vaginal microbiota. Our results give insight into the role of vertical transmission for the vaginal microbiota and motivate future studies on the biogeography of these bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468914" rel="alternate" title="Identification of shared bacterial strains in the vaginal microbiota of reproductive-age mothers and daughters using genome-resolved metagenomics (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469202</id><title>Replication protein Rep provides selective advantage to viruses in the presence of CRISPR-Cas immunity (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.045677+00:00</updated><author><name>Weijia Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yuvaraj Bhoobalan-Chitty</name></author><author><name>Xichuan Zhai</name></author><author><name>Yan Hui</name></author><author><name>Lars Hestbjerg Hansen</name></author><author><name>Ling Deng</name></author><author><name>Xu Peng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Prokaryotic viruses express anti-CRISPR (Acr) proteins to inhibit the host adaptive immune system, CRISPR-Cas. While the virus infection biology was shown to be strongly dependent on the relative strengths of the host CRISPR-Cas and viral Acrs, little is known about the role of the core processes of viral life cycle (replication, packaging etc) in defence/anti-defence arms race. Here, we demonstrate the selective advantage provided by a replication initiator, Rep, in the context of CRISPR-Acr interactions. First, we developed a two-host based CRISPR-Cas genome editing tool for the deletion of highly conserved and thus potentially important viral genes. Using this strategy, we deleted a highly conserved Rep-coding gene, &lt;italic&gt;gp16&lt;/italic&gt;, from the genome of &lt;italic&gt;Sulfolobus islandicus&lt;/italic&gt; rod-shaped virus 2 (SIRV2). The knockout mutant (Δ&lt;italic&gt;gp16&lt;/italic&gt;) produced around 4 fold less virus in a CRISPR-null host, suggesting that Rep is the major contributor to replication initiation in Rudiviridae. Indeed, DNA sequencing revealed Rep-dependent replication initiation from the viral genome termini, in addition to Rep-independent replication initiation from non-terminal sites. Intriguingly, the lack of Rep showed a profound effect on virus propagation in a host carrying CRISPR-Cas immunity. Accordingly, the co-infecting parental virus (&lt;italic&gt;rep&lt;/italic&gt;-containing) outcompeted the Δ&lt;italic&gt;gp16&lt;/italic&gt; mutant much more quickly in CRISPR-containing host than in CRISPR-null host, demonstrating a selective advantage provided by Rep in the presence of host CRISPR-Cas immunity. Despite the non-essentiality, &lt;italic&gt;rep&lt;/italic&gt; is carried by all known members of Rudiviridae, which is likely an evolutionary outcome driven by the ubiquitous presence of CRISPR-Cas in Sulfolobales.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;CRISPR-Cas and anti-CRISPR proteins are accessary to prokaryotes and their viruses respectively. To date, research has been focused on their diversity, molecular mechanisms and application in genome editing. How CRISPR-Acr arms race influence the evolution of viral core genes involved in the basic virus life cycle remained a gap of knowledge so far. This study provides the first evidence that CRISPR-Acr arms race poses a selection pressure on the efficiency of viral genome replication, forcing viruses to evolve highly productive replication machineries..&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469202" rel="alternate" title="Replication protein Rep provides selective advantage to viruses in the presence of CRISPR-Cas immunity (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469353</id><title>Exploration of the antimicrobial synergy between selected natural substances on Streptococcus mutans to identify candidates for the control of dental caries (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.045819+00:00</updated><author><name>Alisha Evangeline Prince</name></author><author><name>David J McDonald</name></author><author><name>Soumya Roy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Dental caries is caused by dental plaque, a community of micro-organisms embedded in an extracellular polymer matrix as a biofilm on the tooth surface. Natural products that are widely available could be used as an alternative or adjunctive anti-caries therapy. Sometimes, when two products are used together, they yield a more powerful antimicrobial effect than the anticipated additive effect. These synergistic combinations are often better treatment options because individual agents may not have sufficient antimicrobial action to be effective when used alone. Cranberries contain phenolic compounds like proanthocyanidins (PAC) that disrupt biofilm formation. Manuka honey has high concentrations of the agent methylglyoxal, which is cariostatic. Because these agents have varied modes of antimicrobial action, they show potential for possible synergistic effects when paired. Various cranberry extracts were tested pairwise with manuka honey or methylglyoxal by well-diffusion assays and 96-well checkerboard assays in the presence of Streptococcus mutans to test for synergy. Synergy was demonstrated in two of the cranberry extracts paired with manuka honey. The synergistic combinations found in this research thus can be considered as candidates for the formulation of a dentifrice that could be used to inhibit the formation of dental plaque and thereby avoid the development of caries.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469353" rel="alternate" title="Exploration of the antimicrobial synergy between selected natural substances on Streptococcus mutans to identify candidates for the control of dental caries (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468783</id><title>Identification of diverse viruses associated with grasshoppers unveils phylogenetic congruence between hosts and viruses (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.045938+00:00</updated><author><name>Yao Xu</name></author><author><name>Jingyi Jiang</name></author><author><name>Xiaoju Lin</name></author><author><name>Wangpeng Shi</name></author><author><name>Chuan Cao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Locusts and grasshoppers are one of the most dangerous agricultural pests. Environmentally benign microbial pesticides are increasingly desirable for controlling locust outbreaks in fragile ecosystems. Here we use metagenomic sequencing to profile the rich viral communities in 34 grasshopper species and report 322 viruses, including 202 novel species. Most of the identified viruses are related to other insect viruses and some are targeted by antiviral RNAi pathway, indicating they infect grasshoppers. Some plant/fungi/vertebrate associated viruses are also abundant in our samples. Our analysis of relationships between host and virus phylogenies suggests that the composition of viromes is closely allied with host evolution, and there is significant phylogenetic relatedness between grasshoppers and viruses from &lt;italic&gt;Lispiviridae, Partitiviridae, Orthomyxoviridae, Virgaviridae&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Flaviviridae&lt;/italic&gt;. Overall, this study is a thorough exploration of viruses in grasshoppers and provide an essential evolutionary and ecological context for host-virus interaction in Acridoidea.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Locusts are the most destructive migratory pest in the world and continue to cause massive damages that endanger food security and threaten millions of people in 21&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; century. While chemical pesticides are still heavily relied on, biological pesticides developed from natural pathogens offer a reliable, less harmful alternative for controlling locust outbreaks in fragile ecosystems. Unfortunately, little is known about natural pathogens infecting this pest. In this study, we profile the viral communities in 34 grasshopper species include some major swarming species. While we identified as many as 202 novel viral species associated with grasshoppers, some of them are of potential to be developed as biocontrol agents. Our analysis of relatedness of phylogenies of grasshoppers and associated viruses helps to shed light on the eco-evolutionary interactions between insects and viruses. This work provides a valuable dataset of both academic and applied interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468783" rel="alternate" title="Identification of diverse viruses associated with grasshoppers unveils phylogenetic congruence between hosts and viruses (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468784</id><title>The Nerve Growth Factor IB-like Receptor Nurr1 (NR4A2) Recruits CoREST Transcription Repressor Complexes to Silence HIV Following Proviral Reactivation in Microglial Cells (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.046142+00:00</updated><author><name>Fengchun Ye</name></author><author><name>David Alvarez-Carbonell</name></author><author><name>Kien Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Saba Valadkhan</name></author><author><name>Konstantin Leskov</name></author><author><name>Yoelvis Garcia-Mesa</name></author><author><name>Sheetal Sreeram</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Karn</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human immune deficiency virus (HIV) infection of microglial cells in the brain leads to chronic neuroinflammation, which is antecedent to the development of HIV-associated neurocognitive disorders (HAND) in the majority of patients. Productively HIV infected microglia release multiple neurotoxins including proinflammatory cytokines and HIV proteins such as envelope glycoprotein (gp120) and transactivator of transcription (Tat). However, powerful counteracting silencing mechanisms in microglial cells result in the rapid shutdown of HIV expression to limit neuronal damage. Here we investigated whether the Nerve Growth Factor IB-like nuclear receptor Nurr1 (NR4A2), which is a repressor of inflammation in the brain, acts to directly restrict HIV expression. HIV silencing was substantially enhanced by Nurr1 agonists in both immortalized human microglial cells (hµglia) and induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSC)-derived human microglial cells (iMG). Overexpression of Nurr1 led to viral suppression, whereas by contrast, knock down (KD) of endogenous Nurr1 blocked HIV silencing. Chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) assays showed that Nurr1 mediates recruitment of the CoREST/HDAC1/G9a/EZH2 transcription repressor complex to HIV promoter resulting in epigenetic silencing of active HIV. Transcriptomic studies demonstrated that in addition to repressing HIV transcription, Nurr1 also downregulated numerous cellular genes involved in inflammation, cell cycle, and metabolism, thus promoting HIV latency and microglial homoeostasis. Thus, Nurr1 plays a pivotal role in modulating the cycles of proviral reactivation by cytokines and potentiating the proviral transcriptional shutdown. These data highlight the therapeutic potential of Nurr1 agonists for inducing HIV silencing and microglial homeostasis and amelioration of the neuroinflammation associated with HAND.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;AUTHOR SUMMARY&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;HIV enters the brain almost immediately after infection where it infects perivascular macrophages, microglia and, to a less extent, astrocytes. In previous work using an immortalized human microglial cell model, we observed that integrated HIV constantly underwent cycles of reactivation and subsequent silencing. In the present study, we found that the Nurr1 nuclear receptor is a key mediator of HIV silencing. The functional activation of Nurr1 by specific agonists, or the over expression of Nurr1, resulted in rapid silencing of activated HIV in microglial cells. Global gene expression analysis confirmed that Nurr1 not only repressed HIV expression but also regulated numerous genes involved in microglial homeostasis and inflammation. Thus, Nurr1 is pivotal for HIV silencing and repression of inflammation in the brain and is a promising therapeutic target for treatment of HAND.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468784" rel="alternate" title="The Nerve Growth Factor IB-like Receptor Nurr1 (NR4A2) Recruits CoREST Transcription Repressor Complexes to Silence HIV Following Proviral Reactivation in Microglial Cells (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468661</id><title>Investigating Carboxysome Morphology Dynamics with a Rotationally Invariant Variational Autoencoder (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.046339+00:00</updated><author><name>Miguel Fuentes-Cabrera</name></author><author><name>Jonathan K. Sakkos</name></author><author><name>Daniel C. Ducat</name></author><author><name>Maxim Ziatdinov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Carboxysomes are a class of bacterial microcompartments that form proteinaceous organelles within the cytoplasm of cyanobacteria and play a central role in photosynthetic metabolism by defining a cellular microenvironment permissive to &lt;italic&gt;CO&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; fixation. Critical aspects of the assembly of the carboxysomes remain relatively unknown, especially with regard to the dynamics of this microcompartment. We have recently expressed an exogenous protease as a way of gaining control over endogenous protein levels, including carboxysomal components, in the model cyanobacterium &lt;italic&gt;Synechococcous elongatus&lt;/italic&gt; PCC 7942. By utilizing this system, proteins that compose the carboxysome can be tuned in real-time as a method to examine carboxysome dynamics. Yet, analysis of subtle changes in carboxysome morphology with microscopy remains a low-throughput and subjective process. Here we use deep learning techniques, specifically a Rotationally Invariant Variational Autoencoder (rVAE), to analyze the fluorescence microscopy images and quantitatively evaluate how carboxysome shell remodelling impacts trends in the morphology of the microcompartment over time. We find that rVAEs are able to assist in the quantitative evaluation of changes in carboxysome location, shape, and size over time. We propose that rVAEs may be a useful tool to accelerate the analysis of carboxysome assembly and dynamics in response to genetic or environmental perturbation, and may be more generally useful to probe regulatory processes involving a broader array of bacterial microcompartments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468661" rel="alternate" title="Investigating Carboxysome Morphology Dynamics with a Rotationally Invariant Variational Autoencoder (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469109</id><title>Adapting to novel environments together: evolutionary and ecological correlates of the bacterial microbiome of the world’s largest cavefish diversification (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.046464+00:00</updated><author><name>Shipeng Zhou</name></author><author><name>Amrapali Prithvisingh Rajput</name></author><author><name>Yewei Liu</name></author><author><name>Tingru Mao</name></author><author><name>Jian Yang</name></author><author><name>Jayampathi Herath</name></author><author><name>Madhava Meegaskumbura</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The symbiosis between a host and its microbiome is essential for host fitness, and this association is a consequence of the host’s physiology and habitat. &lt;italic&gt;Sinocyclocheilus&lt;/italic&gt;, the largest cavefish diversification of the world, an emerging multi-species model system for evolutionary novelty, provides an excellent opportunity for examining correlates of host evolutionary history, habitat, and gut-microbial community diversity. From the diversification-scale patterns of habitat occupation, major phylogenetic clades (A–D), geographic distribution, and knowledge from captive-maintained &lt;italic&gt;Sinocyclocheilus&lt;/italic&gt; populations, we hypothesize habitat to be the major determinant of microbiome diversity, with phylogeny playing a lesser role. For this, we subject environmental water samples and fecal samples (representative of gut-microbiome) from 24 &lt;italic&gt;Sinocyclocheilus&lt;/italic&gt; species, both from the wild and after being in captivity for six months, to bacterial 16S rRNA gene profiling using Illumina sequencing. We see significant differences in the gut microbiota structure of &lt;italic&gt;Sinocyclocheilus,&lt;/italic&gt; reflective of the three habitat types; gut microbiomes too, were influenced by host-related factors. There is no significant association between the gut microbiomes and host phylogeny. However, there is some microbiome related structure at clade level, with the most geographically distant clades (A and D) being the most distinct, and two geographically overlapping clades (B and C) being similar. Microbes inhabiting water were not a cause for significant differences in fish-gut microbiota, but water quality parameters was. Transferring from wild to captivity, the fish microbiomes changed significantly and became homogenized, signifying adaptability and highlighting the importance of environmental factors (habitat) in microbiome community assembly. The core microbiome of this group closely resembled that of other teleost fishes. Our results suggest that divergent selection giving rise to evolutionary novelties also includes the microbiome of these fishes, which provides a functional advantage for life in the resource-depleted cave environment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SIGNIFICANCE STATEMENT&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The largest diversification of cavefishes of the world, &lt;italic&gt;Sinocyclocheilus&lt;/italic&gt;, not only show that habitat, and phylogenetic clade is important in determining their gut microbiome, but also that they reach a common microbiome in captivity irrespective of their phylogenetic position, region of origin and habitat, indicating that they are adaptable in the context of microbe related changes in their environment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469109" rel="alternate" title="Adapting to novel environments together: evolutionary and ecological correlates of the bacterial microbiome of the world’s largest cavefish diversification (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469075</id><title>Olorofim and the azoles are antagonistic in A. fumigatus and functional genomic screens reveal mechanisms of cross resistance (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.046602+00:00</updated><author><name>Norman van Rhijn</name></author><author><name>Sam Hemmings</name></author><author><name>Clara Valero</name></author><author><name>Jorge Amich</name></author><author><name>Michael J Bromley</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aspergillosis, in its various manifestations, is a major cause of morbidity and mortality. Very few classes of antifungal have been approved for clinical use to treat these diseases and resistance to the first line therapeutics is increasing. A new class of antifungals, the orotomides, are currently in development with the first compound in this class olorofim in late-stage clinical trials. In this study, we characterise a network of genes that govern olorofim response in &lt;italic&gt;A. fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt;. We reveal that the number of transcription factors that regulate olorofim susceptibility are far fewer than we have previously observed for the azoles and the change in sensitivity observed in these isolates is less extreme. Intriguingly, loss of function in two higher order transcriptional regulators, HapB a member of the heterotrimeric HapB/C/E (CBC) complex or the regulator of nitrogen metabolic genes AreA, leads to cross resistance to both the azoles and olorofim. However, a clinical azole resistant isolate with a point mutation in HapE (&lt;italic&gt;hapE&lt;sup&gt;P88L&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt;) retains sensitivity to olorofim. Our transcriptomic analysis suggests that altered sensitivity to olorofim may emerge via modification of genes involved in the production of pyrimidine biosynthetic precursors. Finally, we also show that the action of the azoles are antagonistic to olorofim &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469075" rel="alternate" title="Olorofim and the azoles are antagonistic in A. fumigatus and functional genomic screens reveal mechanisms of cross resistance (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468768</id><title>Pseudomonas synergizes with fluconazole against Candida during treatment of polymicrobial infection (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.046729+00:00</updated><author><name>Siham Hattab</name></author><author><name>Anna-Maria Dagher</name></author><author><name>Robert T. Wheeler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Polymicrobial infections are challenging to treat because we don’t fully understand how pathogens interact during infection and how these interactions affect drug efficacy. &lt;italic&gt;Candida albicans&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; are opportunistic pathogens that can be found in similar sites of infection such as in burn wounds and most importantly in the lungs of CF and mechanically ventilated patients. &lt;italic&gt;C. albicans&lt;/italic&gt; is particularly difficult to treat because of the paucity of antifungal agents, some of which lack fungicidal activity. In this study, we investigated the efficacy of anti-fungal treatment during &lt;italic&gt;C. albicans&lt;/italic&gt;-&lt;italic&gt;P. aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; co-culture &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and co-infection in the mucosal zebrafish infection model analogous to the lung. We find that &lt;italic&gt;P. aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; enhances the activity of fluconazole (FLC), an anti-fungal drug that is fungistatic &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, to promote both clearance of &lt;italic&gt;C. albicans&lt;/italic&gt; during co-infection &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and fungal killing &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. This synergy between FLC treatment andbacterial antagonism is partly due to iron piracy, as it is reduced upon iron supplementation and knockout of bacterial siderophores. Our work demonstrates that FLC has enhanced activity in clinically relevant contexts and highlights the need to understand antimicrobial effectiveness in the complex environment of the host with its associated microbial communities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468768" rel="alternate" title="Pseudomonas synergizes with fluconazole against Candida during treatment of polymicrobial infection (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469321</id><title>The proton motive force determines Escherichia coli's robustness to extracellular pH (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.046851+00:00</updated><author><name>Guillaume Terradot</name></author><author><name>Ekaterina Krasnopeeva</name></author><author><name>Peter S. Swain</name></author><author><name>Teuta Pilizota</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Maintaining intracellular homeostases is a hallmark of life, and key physiological variables, such as cytoplasmic pH, osmotic pressure, and proton motive force (PMF), are typically interdependent. Developing a mathematical model focused on these links, we predict that Escherichia coli uses proton-ion antiporters to generate an out-of-equilibrium plasma membrane potential and so maintain the PMF at the constant levels observed. The strength of the PMF consequently determines the range of extracellular pH over which the cell is able to preserve its near neutral cytoplasmic pH. In support, we concurrently measure the PMF and cytoplasmic pH in single cells and demonstrate both that decreasing the PMF's strength impairs E. coli's ability to maintain its pH and that artificially collapsing the PMF destroys the out-of-equilibrium plasma membrane potential. We further predict the observed ranges of extracellular pH for which three of E. coli's antiporters are expressed, through defining their cost by the rate at which they divert imported protons from generating ATP. Taken together, our results suggest a new perspective on bacterial electrophysiology, where cells regulate the plasma membrane potential by changing the activities of antiporters to maintain both the PMF and cytoplasmic pH.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469321" rel="alternate" title="The proton motive force determines Escherichia coli's robustness to extracellular pH (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.469222</id><title>Epigenetic changes in autoimmune monocytes contribute to disease and can be targeted by JAK inhibition (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.046976+00:00</updated><author><name>Jorg van Loosdregt</name></author><author><name>Janneke Peeters</name></author><author><name>Arjan Boltjes</name></author><author><name>Rianne Scholman</name></author><author><name>Stephin Vervoort</name></author><author><name>Paul Coffer</name></author><author><name>Michal Mokry</name></author><author><name>Bas Vastert</name></author><author><name>Femke van Wijk</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;How the local inflammatory environment regulates epigenetic changes in the context of autoimmune diseases remains unclear. Here we assessed the transcriptional and active enhancer profile of monocytes derived from the inflamed joints of Juvenile Idiopathic Arthritis (JIA) patients, a model well-suited for studying autoimmune diseases. RNA-sequencing analysis demonstrated that synovial-derived monocytes display an activated phenotype, characterized by increased expression of surface activation markers and multiple chemokines and cytokines. This increased expression is regulated on the epigenetic level, as ChIPsequencing indicated increased H3K27 acetylation of genes upregulated in synovial monocytes. IFN signaling-associated genes are increased and epigenetically altered in synovial monocytes, suggesting a role for IFN in establishing the inflammatory phenotype. Treatment of human synovial monocytes with the Janus-associated kinase (JAK) inhibitor Ruxolitinib, which inhibits IFN signaling, transformed the activated enhancer landscape and reduced disease-associated gene expression, thereby inhibiting the inflammatory phenotype. Taken together, these data provide novel insight into epigenetic regulation of autoimmune disease-patient derived monocytes and suggest that altering the epigenetic profile can be a therapeutic approach for the treatment of autoimmune diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.469222" rel="alternate" title="Epigenetic changes in autoimmune monocytes contribute to disease and can be targeted by JAK inhibition (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468817</id><title>Host casein kinase 1-mediated phosphorylation modulates phase separation of a rhabdovirus phosphoprotein and virus infection (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.047131+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiao-Dong Fang</name></author><author><name>Qiang Gao</name></author><author><name>Ying Zang</name></author><author><name>Ji-Hui Qiao</name></author><author><name>Dong-Min Gao</name></author><author><name>Wen-Ya Xu</name></author><author><name>Ying Wang</name></author><author><name>Dawei Li</name></author><author><name>Xian-Bing Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Liquid–liquid phase separation (LLPS) plays important roles in forming cellular membraneless organelles. However, how host factors regulate LLPS of viral proteins during negative-sense RNA (NSR) virus infections is largely unknown. Here, we used &lt;italic&gt;Barley yellow striate mosaic virus&lt;/italic&gt; (BYSMV) as a model to demonstrate regulation of host casein kinase 1 in phase separation and infection of NSR viruses. We first found that the BYSMV phosphoprotein (P) formed spherical granules with liquid properties and recruited viral nucleotide (N) and polymerase (L) proteins &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Moreover, the P-formed granules were tethered to the ER/actin network for trafficking and fusion. BYSMV P alone formed droplets and incorporated the N protein and genomic RNA &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. Interestingly, phase separation of BYSMV P was inhibited by host casein kinase 1 (CK1)-dependent phosphorylation of an intrinsically disordered P protein region. Genetic assays demonstrated that the unphosphorylated mutant of BYSMV P exhibited condensed phase, which promoted virus replication through concentrating the N, L proteins, and genome RNA into viroplasms. Whereas, the phosphorylation-mimic mutant existed in diffuse phase state leading to enhanced virus transcription. Collectively, our results demonstrate that host CK1 modulates phase separation of viral P protein and virus infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468817" rel="alternate" title="Host casein kinase 1-mediated phosphorylation modulates phase separation of a rhabdovirus phosphoprotein and virus infection (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>