<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.673836+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.446380</id><title>An ancient divide in outer membrane tethering systems in Bacteria (58 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.674595+00:00</updated><author><name>Jerzy Witwinowski</name></author><author><name>Anna Sartori-Rupp</name></author><author><name>Najwa Taib</name></author><author><name>Nika Pende</name></author><author><name>To Nam Tham</name></author><author><name>Daniel Poppleton</name></author><author><name>Jean-Marc Ghigo</name></author><author><name>Christophe Beloin</name></author><author><name>Simonetta Gribaldo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent data support the hypothesis that Gram-positive bacteria (monoderms) arose from Gram-negatives (diderms) through loss of the outer membrane (OM). However how this happened remains unknown. Considering that tethering of the OM is essential for cell envelope stability in diderm bacteria we hypothesize that its destabilization may have been involved in OM loss. Here, we present an in-depth analysis of the four main OM tethering systems across all Bacteria. We show that their distribution strikingly follows the bacterial phylogeny with a bimodal distribution matching the deepest phylogenetic cleavage between Terrabacteria (a clade encompassing Cyanobacteria, Deinococcus/Thermus, Firmicutes, etc.) and Gracilicutes (a clade encompassing Proteobacteria, Bacteroidetes, Spirochaetes, etc.). Diderm Terrabacteria display as the main system OmpM, a porin that attaches non-covalently to modified peptidoglycan or to secondary cell wall polymers. In contrast, the lipoprotein Pal is restricted to the Gracilicutes along with a more sporadic occurrence of OmpA. While Braun’s lipoprotein Lpp is largely considered as the textbook example of OM attachment, it is actually present only in a subclade of Gammaproteobacteria. We propose an evolutionary scenario whereby the last common bacterial ancestor used a system based on OmpM, which was later replaced by one based on the lipoprotein Pal concomitantly to the emergence of the Lol machinery to address lipoproteins to the OM, with OmpA as a possible transition state. We speculate that the existence of only one main OM tethering system in the Terrabacteria would have allowed the multiple emergences of the monoderm phenotype specifically observed in this clade through OmpM perturbation. We test this hypothesis by inactivating all four &lt;italic&gt;ompM&lt;/italic&gt; gene copies in the genetically tractable diderm Firmicute &lt;italic&gt;Veillonella parvula&lt;/italic&gt;. The resulting mutant is severely affected in growth and displays high sensitivity to OM stress. High resolution imaging and tomogram reconstructions reveal a dramatic - yet non-lethal - phenotype, in which vast portions of the OM detach, producing large vesicles surrounding multiple monoderm-like cells sharing a common periplasm. Complementation by a single OmpM rescues the phenotype to a normal cell envelope. Together, our results highlight an ancient shift in bacterial evolution involving OM tethering systems. They suggest a possible mechanism for OM loss and a high flexibility of the cell envelope in diderm Firmicutes, making them ideal models to further refine our understanding of the mechanisms involved in bacterial OM stability, and opening the way to recapitulate the monoderm/diderm transition in the laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.446380" rel="alternate" title="An ancient divide in outer membrane tethering systems in Bacteria (58 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.446370</id><title>Breaching the cell-envelope barriers of gram-positive and fungal microbes by a type VI secretion system in Acidovorax citrulli (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.679013+00:00</updated><author><name>Tong-Tong Pei</name></author><author><name>Yumin Kan</name></author><author><name>Zeng-Hang Wang</name></author><author><name>Ming-Xuan Tang</name></author><author><name>Hao Li</name></author><author><name>Shuangquan Yan</name></author><author><name>Yang Cui</name></author><author><name>Hao-Yu Zheng</name></author><author><name>Han Luo</name></author><author><name>Tao G. Dong</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The type VI secretion system (T6SS) is a double-tubular toxin-injection nanomachine widely found in gram-negative human and plant pathogens. The current model depicts that the T6SS spear-like Hcp tube is powered by the contraction of an outer sheath to drill through the envelope of a neighboring cell, achieving cytosol to cytosol delivery. However, gram-positive bacteria seem to be impenetrable to such T6SS action. Here we report that a plant pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Acidovorax citrulli&lt;/italic&gt; (AC) deploys a highly potent T6SS to kill a range of bacteria including &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli, Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium smegmatis&lt;/italic&gt; as well as fungal species including &lt;italic&gt;Candida albicans&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Pichia pastoris&lt;/italic&gt;. Using bioinformatic and biochemical assays, we identified a group of T6SS effectors and characterized one effector RhsB that is critical for interspecies interaction. We report that RhsB contains a conserved YD-repeat domain and a C-terminal nuclease domain. Toxicity of RhsB was neutralized by its downstream immunity proteins through direct interaction. RhsB was cleaved at the C-terminal end and a catalytic mutation within the internal aspartic protease abolished such cleavage. Collectively, the T6SS of AC displays potent activities to penetrate the cell envelope barriers of gram-positive and fungal species, highlighting the greatly expanded capabilities of T6SS in modulating microbiome compositions in complex environments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.446370" rel="alternate" title="Breaching the cell-envelope barriers of gram-positive and fungal microbes by a type VI secretion system in Acidovorax citrulli (18 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.03.446708</id><title>Organic stabilization of extracellular elemental sulfur in a Sulfurovum-rich biofilm: a new role for EPS? (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.679486+00:00</updated><author><name>Brandi Cron</name></author><author><name>Jennifer L. Macalady</name></author><author><name>Julie Cosmidis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This work shines light on the role of extracellular polymeric substances (EPS) in the formation and preservation of elemental sulfur biominerals produced by sulfur-oxidizing bacteria. We characterized elemental sulfur particles produced within a &lt;italic&gt;Sulfurovum&lt;/italic&gt;-rich biofilm in the Frasassi Cave System (Italy). The particles adopt spherical and bipyramidal morphologies, and display both stable (α-S&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt;) and metastable (β-S&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt;) crystal structures. Elemental sulfur is embedded within a dense matrix of EPS and the particles are surrounded by organic envelopes rich in amide and carboxylic groups. Organic encapsulation and the presence of metastable crystal structures are consistent with elemental sulfur organomineralization, i.e. the formation and stabilization of elemental sulfur in the presence of organics, a mechanism that has previously been observed in laboratory studies. This research provides new evidence for the important role of microbial EPS in mineral formation in the environment. We hypothesize that extracellular organics are used by sulfur-oxidizing bacteria for the stabilization of elemental sulfur minerals outside of the cell wall as a store of chemical energy. The stabilization of energy sources (in the form of a solid electron acceptor) in biofilms is a potential new role for microbial EPS that requires further investigation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.03.446708" rel="alternate" title="Organic stabilization of extracellular elemental sulfur in a Sulfurovum-rich biofilm: a new role for EPS? (16 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.01.446617</id><title>Efficacy of epetraborole against Mycobacterium abscessus is increased with norvaline (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.679889+00:00</updated><author><name>Jaryd R. Sullivan</name></author><author><name>Andréanne Lupien</name></author><author><name>Elias Kalthoff</name></author><author><name>Claire Hamela</name></author><author><name>Lorne Taylor</name></author><author><name>Kim A. Munro</name></author><author><name>T. Martin Schmeing</name></author><author><name>Laurent Kremer</name></author><author><name>Marcel A. Behr</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Certain aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases developed a proofreading mechanism to ensure aminoacylation of tRNAs with cognate amino acids. Epetraborole (EPT) was identified as an inhibitor of the leucyl-tRNA synthetase (LeuRS) editing site in &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium abscessus&lt;/italic&gt;. EPT displayed enhanced activity against &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; over &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt;. Crystallographic and equilibrium binding data showed that EPT binds LeuRS&lt;sub&gt;Mabs&lt;/sub&gt; and LeuRS&lt;sub&gt;Mtb&lt;/sub&gt; with similar Kd. Proteomic analysis revealed that when &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; LeuRS mutants were fed the non-proteinogenic amino acid norvaline, leucine residues in proteins were replaced by norvaline, inducing expression of GroEL chaperonins and Clp proteases. &lt;italic&gt;In vitro&lt;/italic&gt; data revealed that supplementation of media with norvaline reduced the emergence of EPT mutants in both &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;M. tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt;. The combination of EPT and norvaline had improved &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; efficacy compared to EPT in a murine model of &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.01.446617" rel="alternate" title="Efficacy of epetraborole against Mycobacterium abscessus is increased with norvaline (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.30.446362</id><title>Identification of Leucinostatins from Ophiocordyceps sp. as Antiparasitic Agents Against Trypanosoma cruzi (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.680480+00:00</updated><author><name>Jean A. Bernatchez</name></author><author><name>Yun-Seo Kil</name></author><author><name>Elany Barbosa da Silva</name></author><author><name>Diane Thomas</name></author><author><name>Laura-Isobel McCall</name></author><author><name>Karen L. Wendt</name></author><author><name>Julia M. Souza</name></author><author><name>Jasmin Ackermann</name></author><author><name>James H. McKerrow</name></author><author><name>Robert H. Cichewicz</name></author><author><name>Jair L. Siqueira-Neto</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Safe and effective treatments for Chagas disease, a potentially fatal parasitic infection associated with cardiac and gastrointestinal pathology and caused by the kinetoplastid parasite &lt;italic&gt;Trypanosoma cruzi&lt;/italic&gt;, have yet to be developed. Benznidazole and nifurtimox, which are currently the only available drugs against &lt;italic&gt;T. cruzi&lt;/italic&gt;, are associated with severe adverse effects and questionable efficacy in the late stage of the disease. Natural products have proven to be a rich source of new chemotypes for other infectious agents. We utilized a microscopy-based high-throughput phenotypic screen to identify inhibitors of &lt;italic&gt;T. cruzi&lt;/italic&gt; from a library of natural product samples obtained from fungi procured through a Citizen Science Soil Collection Program (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://whatsinyourbackyard.org/"&gt;https://whatsinyourbackyard.org/&lt;/ext-link&gt;), and the Great Lakes (USA) benthic environment. We identified five leucinostatins (A, B, F, NPDG C and NPDG D) as potent inhibitors of the intracellular amastigote form of &lt;italic&gt;T. cruzi&lt;/italic&gt;. Leucinostatin B also showed &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; efficacy in a mouse model of Chagas disease. Given prior reports that leucinostatins A and B have antiparasitic activity against the related kinetoplastid &lt;italic&gt;T. brucei&lt;/italic&gt;, our findings suggest a potential cross-trypanocidal compound class and provide a platform for further chemical derivatization of a potent chemical scaffold against &lt;italic&gt;T. cruzi&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.30.446362" rel="alternate" title="Identification of Leucinostatins from Ophiocordyceps sp. as Antiparasitic Agents Against Trypanosoma cruzi (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>