<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.892812+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456173</id><title>Delta spike P681R mutation enhances SARS-CoV-2 fitness over Alpha variant (738 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.893079+00:00</updated><author><name>Yang Liu</name></author><author><name>Jianying Liu</name></author><author><name>Bryan A. Johnson</name></author><author><name>Hongjie Xia</name></author><author><name>Zhiqiang Ku</name></author><author><name>Craig Schindewolf</name></author><author><name>Steven G. Widen</name></author><author><name>Zhiqiang An</name></author><author><name>Scott Weaver</name></author><author><name>Vineet D Menachery</name></author><author><name>Xuping Xie</name></author><author><name>Pei-Yong Shi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 Delta variant has rapidly replaced the Alpha variant around the world. The mechanism that drives this global replacement has not been defined. Here we report that Delta spike mutation P681R plays a key role in the Alpha-to-Delta variant replacement. In a replication competition assay, Delta SARS-CoV-2 efficiently outcompeted the Alpha variant in human lung epithelial cells and primary human airway tissues. Delta SARS-CoV-2 bearing the Alpha-spike glycoprotein replicated less efficiently than the wild-type Delta variant, suggesting the importance of Delta spike in enhancing viral replication. The Delta spike has accumulated mutation P681R located at a furin cleavage site that separates the spike 1 (S1) and S2 subunits. Reverting the P681R mutation to wild-type P681 significantly reduced the replication of Delta variant, to a level lower than the Alpha variant. Mechanistically, the Delta P681R mutation enhanced the cleavage of the full-length spike to S1 and S2, leading to increased infection via cell surface entry. In contrast, the Alpha spike also has a mutation at the same amino acid (P681H), but the spike cleavage from purified Alpha virions was reduced compared to the Delta spike. Collectively, our results indicate P681R as a key mutation in enhancing Delta variant replication via increased S1/S2 cleavage. Spike mutations that potentially affect furin cleavage efficiency must be closely monitored for future variant surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456173" rel="alternate" title="Delta spike P681R mutation enhances SARS-CoV-2 fitness over Alpha variant (738 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455959</id><title>Multiplexed detection of SARS-CoV-2 genomic and subgenomic RNA using in situ hybridization (43 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.893453+00:00</updated><author><name>Kofi K. Acheampong</name></author><author><name>Dylan L. Schaff</name></author><author><name>Benjamin L. Emert</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Lake</name></author><author><name>Sam Reffsin</name></author><author><name>Emily K. Shea</name></author><author><name>Courtney E. Comar</name></author><author><name>Leslie A. Litzky</name></author><author><name>Nigar A. Khurram</name></author><author><name>Rebecca L. Linn</name></author><author><name>Michael Feldman</name></author><author><name>Susan R. Weiss</name></author><author><name>Kathleen T. Montone</name></author><author><name>Sara Cherry</name></author><author><name>Sydney M. Shaffer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The widespread Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) is caused by infection with the novel coronavirus SARS-CoV-2. Currently, we have a limited toolset available for visualizing SARS-CoV-2 in cells and tissues, particularly in tissues from patients who died from COVID-19. Generally, single-molecule RNA FISH techniques have shown mixed results in formalin fixed paraffin embedded tissues such as those preserved from human autopsies. Here, we present a platform for preparing autopsy tissue for visualizing SARS-CoV-2 RNA using RNA FISH with amplification by hybridization chain reaction (HCR). We developed probe sets that target different regions of SARS-CoV-2 (including ORF1a and N) as well as probe sets that specifically target SARS-CoV-2 subgenomic mRNAs. We validated these probe sets in cell culture and tissues (lung, lymph node, and placenta) from infected patients. Using this technology, we observe distinct subcellular localization patterns of the ORF1a and N regions, with the ORF1a concentrated around the nucleus and the N showing a diffuse distribution across the cytoplasm. In human lung tissue, we performed multiplexed RNA FISH HCR for SARS-CoV-2 and cell-type specific marker genes. We found viral RNA in cells containing the alveolar type 2 (AT2) cell marker gene (&lt;italic&gt;SFTPC&lt;/italic&gt;) and the alveolar macrophage marker gene (&lt;italic&gt;MARCO&lt;/italic&gt;), but did not identify viral RNA in cells containing the alveolar type 1 (AT1) cell marker gene (&lt;italic&gt;AGER&lt;/italic&gt;). Moreover, we observed distinct subcellular localization patterns of viral RNA in AT2 cells and alveolar macrophages, consistent with phagocytosis of infected cells. In sum, we demonstrate the use of RNA FISH HCR for visualizing different RNA species from SARS-CoV-2 in cell lines and FFPE autopsy specimens. Furthermore, we multiplex this assay with probes for cellular genes to determine what cell-types are infected within the lung. We anticipate that this platform could be broadly useful for studying SARS-CoV-2 pathology in tissues as well as extended for other applications including investigating the viral life cycle, viral diagnostics, and drug screening.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455959" rel="alternate" title="Multiplexed detection of SARS-CoV-2 genomic and subgenomic RNA using in situ hybridization (43 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456204</id><title>Nrf2 is a central regulator of the metabolic landscape in macrophages and finetunes their inflammatory response (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.893678+00:00</updated><author><name>Dylan Gerard Ryan</name></author><author><name>Elena V Knatko</name></author><author><name>Alva Casey</name></author><author><name>Jens L Hukelmann</name></author><author><name>Alejandro J Brenes</name></author><author><name>Sharadha Dayalan Naidu</name></author><author><name>Maureen Higgins</name></author><author><name>Laura Tronci</name></author><author><name>Efterpi Nikitopoulou</name></author><author><name>Luke AJ O'Neill</name></author><author><name>Angus I Lamond</name></author><author><name>Andrey Y Abramov</name></author><author><name>Doreen A Cantrell</name></author><author><name>Michael P Murphy</name></author><author><name>Albena T Dinkova-Kostova</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To overcome oxidative, inflammatory, and metabolic stress, cells have evolved networks of cytoprotective proteins controlled by nuclear factor erythroid 2 p45-related factor 2 (Nrf2) and its main negative regulator the Kelch-like ECH associated protein 1 (Keap1). Here, we used high-resolution mass-spectrometry to characterize the proteomes of macrophages with genetically altered Nrf2 status. Our analysis revealed significant differences among the genotypes in cellular metabolism and redox homeostasis, which we validated with respirometry and metabolomics, as well as in anti-viral immune pathways and the cell cycle. Nrf2 status significantly affected the proteome following lipopolysaccharide (LPS) stimulation, with alterations in redox, carbohydrate and lipid metabolism, and innate immunity observed. Of note, Nrf2 activation was found to promote mitochondrial fusion in inflammatory macrophages. The Keap1 inhibitor, 4-octyl itaconate (4-OI), a derivative of the mitochondrial immunometabolite itaconate, remodeled the inflammatory macrophage proteome, increasing redox and suppressing anti-viral immune effectors in a Nrf2-dependent manner. These data suggest that Nrf2 activation facilitates metabolic reprogramming and mitochondrial adaptation, and finetunes the innate immune response in macrophages.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456204" rel="alternate" title="Nrf2 is a central regulator of the metabolic landscape in macrophages and finetunes their inflammatory response (27 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456266</id><title>Secreted SARS-CoV-2 ORF8 modulates the cytokine expression profile of human macrophages (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.893889+00:00</updated><author><name>Nisha Kriplani</name></author><author><name>Sara Mary Rose Clohisey</name></author><author><name>Sonia Fonseca</name></author><author><name>Sarah Fletcher</name></author><author><name>Hui-Min Lee</name></author><author><name>Jordan Ashworth</name></author><author><name>Dominic Kurian</name></author><author><name>Samantha J Lycett</name></author><author><name>Christine Tait-Burkard</name></author><author><name>J Kenneth Baillie</name></author><author><name>Mark E J Woolhouse</name></author><author><name>Simon R Carding</name></author><author><name>James P Stewart</name></author><author><name>Paul Digard</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) is still adapting to its new human host. Attention has focussed on the viral spike protein, but substantial variation has been seen in the ORF8 gene. Here, we show that SARS-CoV-2 ORF8 protein undergoes signal peptide-mediated processing through the endoplasmic reticulum and is secreted as a glycosylated, disulphide-linked dimer. The secreted protein from the prototype SARS-CoV-2 virus had no major effect on viability of a variety of cell types, or on IFN or NF-κB; signalling. However, it modulated cytokine expression from primary CSF1-derived human macrophages, most notably by decreasing IL-6 and IL-8 secretion. Furthermore, a sequence polymorphism L84S that appeared early in the pandemic associated with the Clade S lineage of virus, showed a markedly different effect, of increasing IL-6 production. We conclude that ORF8 sequence polymorphisms can potentially affect SARS-CoV-2 virulence and should therefore be monitored in sequencing-based surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456266" rel="alternate" title="Secreted SARS-CoV-2 ORF8 modulates the cytokine expression profile of human macrophages (26 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456007</id><title>Simultaneous infection with porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome and influenza viruses abrogates clinical protection induced by live attenuated porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome vaccination (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.894092+00:00</updated><author><name>Tiphany Chrun</name></author><author><name>Emmanuel A. Maze</name></author><author><name>Eleni Vatzia</name></author><author><name>Veronica Martini</name></author><author><name>Basu Paudyal</name></author><author><name>Matthew Edmans</name></author><author><name>Adam McNee</name></author><author><name>Tanuja Manjegowda</name></author><author><name>Francisco J. Salguero</name></author><author><name>Nanchaya Wanasen</name></author><author><name>Surapong Koonpaew</name></author><author><name>Simon P. Graham</name></author><author><name>Elma Tchilian</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The porcine respiratory disease complex (PRDC) is responsible for significant economic losses in the pig industry worldwide. Porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome virus (PRRSV) and swine influenza virus are major viral contributors to PRDC. Vaccines are cost-effective measures for controlling PRRS, however, their efficacy in the context of co-infections has been poorly investigated. In this study, we aimed to determine the effect of PRRSV-2 and swine influenza H3N2 virus co-infection on the efficacy of PRRSV modified live virus (MLV) vaccination, which is widely used in the field. Following simultaneous challenge with contemporary PRRSV-2 and H3N2 field isolates, we found that the protective effect of PRRS MLV vaccination on clinical disease and pathology was abrogated, although viral load was unaffected and antibody responses were enhanced. In contrast, co-infection in non-immunized animals reduced PRRSV-2 viremia and H3N2 virus load in the upper respiratory tract and potentiated T cell responses against both PRRSV-2 and H3N2 in the lung. Further analysis suggested that an upregulation of inhibitory cytokines gene expression in the lungs of vaccinated pigs may have influenced responses to H3N2 and PRRSV-2. These findings provide important insights into the effect of viral co-infections on PRRS vaccine efficacy that may help identity more effective vaccination strategies against PRDC in the field.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456007" rel="alternate" title="Simultaneous infection with porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome and influenza viruses abrogates clinical protection induced by live attenuated porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome vaccination (18 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456035</id><title>Diversification by CofC and control by CofD govern biosynthesis and evolution of coenzyme F420 and its derivative 3PG-F420 (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.894287+00:00</updated><author><name>Mahmudul Hasan</name></author><author><name>Sabrina Schulze</name></author><author><name>Leona Berndt</name></author><author><name>Gottfried J Palm</name></author><author><name>Daniel Braga</name></author><author><name>Ingrid Richter</name></author><author><name>Daniel Last</name></author><author><name>Michael Lammers</name></author><author><name>Gerald Lackner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Coenzyme F&lt;sub&gt;420&lt;/sub&gt; is a microbial redox cofactor that is increasingly used for biocatalytic applications. Recently, diversified biosynthetic routes to F&lt;sub&gt;420&lt;/sub&gt; and the discovery of a derivative, 3PG-F&lt;sub&gt;420&lt;/sub&gt;, were reported. 3PG-F&lt;sub&gt;420&lt;/sub&gt; is formed via activation of 3-phospho-d-glycerate (3-PG) by CofC, but the structural basis of substrate binding, its evolution, as well as the role of CofD in substrate selection remained elusive. Here, we present a crystal structure of the 3-PG-activating CofC from &lt;italic&gt;Mycetohabitans&lt;/italic&gt; sp. B3 and define amino acids governing substrate specificity. Site-directed mutagenesis enabled bidirectional switching of specificity and thereby revealed the short evolutionary trajectory to 3PG-F&lt;sub&gt;420&lt;/sub&gt; formation. Furthermore, CofC stabilized its product, thus confirming the structure of the unstable molecule, revealing its binding mode and suggesting a substrate channeling mechanism to CofD. The latter enzyme was shown to significantly contribute to the selection of related intermediates to control the specificity of the combined biosynthetic CofC/D step. Taken together, this work closes important knowledge gaps and opens up perspectives for the discovery, enhanced biotechnological production, and engineering of coenzyme F&lt;sub&gt;420&lt;/sub&gt; derivatives in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456035" rel="alternate" title="Diversification by CofC and control by CofD govern biosynthesis and evolution of coenzyme F420 and its derivative 3PG-F420 (17 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456111</id><title>A GGDEF domain serves as a spatial on-switch for a phosphodiesterase by direct interaction with a polar landmark protein (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.894502+00:00</updated><author><name>Tim Rick</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Kreiling</name></author><author><name>Alexander Höing</name></author><author><name>Svenja Fiedler</name></author><author><name>Timo Glatter</name></author><author><name>Wieland Steinchen</name></author><author><name>Georg Hochberg</name></author><author><name>Heike Bähre</name></author><author><name>Roland Seifert</name></author><author><name>Gert Bange</name></author><author><name>Shirley K. Knauer</name></author><author><name>Peter L. Graumann</name></author><author><name>Kai M. Thormann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In bacteria, the monopolar localization of enzymes and protein complexes can result in a bi-modal distribution of enzyme activity between the dividing cells and heterogeneity of cellular behaviors. In &lt;italic&gt;Shewanella putrefaciens&lt;/italic&gt;, the multidomain hybrid diguanylate cyclase/phosphodiesterase PdeB, which degrades the secondary messenger c-di-GMP, is located at the flagellated cell pole. Here we show how PdeB polar recruitment is mediated by direct interaction between the inactive diguanylate cyclase (GGDEF) domain of PdeB and the C-terminal FimV domain of the polar landmark protein HubP. We demonstrate that this interaction is crucial for full function of PdeB as a phosphodiesterase. Thus, the GGDEF domain serves as a spatially controlled on-switch that effectively restricts PdeBs activity to the flagellated cell pole. We further show that PdeB regulates abundance and activity of at least two crucial surface-interaction factors, the BpfA surface adhesion protein and the MSHA type IV pilus. The heterogeneity in c-di-GMP concentrations that is generated by differences in abundance and temporal polar appearance of PdeB as well as by bi-modal distribution after cell fission orchestrates the population behavior with respect to cell-surface interaction and environmental spreading.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Phenotypic heterogeneity benefits the proliferation of microbial populations in changing environments. Such heterogeneity can be created by recruitment of enzymatic activity to specific cellular compartments, e.g., the cell pole. Here we show how a GGDEF domain of a multidomain phosphodiesterase has adopted the function as a spatial on-switch that is specifically activated upon direct interaction with a polar landmark protein.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456111" rel="alternate" title="A GGDEF domain serves as a spatial on-switch for a phosphodiesterase by direct interaction with a polar landmark protein (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455975</id><title>Genome sequencing of the vermicompost strain Stenotrophomonas maltophilia UENF-4GII and population structure analysis of the S. maltophilia Sm3 genogroup (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.894702+00:00</updated><author><name>Francisnei Pedrosa-Silva</name></author><author><name>Filipe P. Matteoli</name></author><author><name>Hemanoel Passarelli-Araujo</name></author><author><name>Fabio L. Olivares</name></author><author><name>Thiago M. Venancio</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;italic&gt;Stenotrophomonas maltophilia&lt;/italic&gt; complex (Smc) is a cosmopolitan bacterial group that has been proposed an emergent multidrug-resistant pathogen. Taxonomic studies support the genomic heterogeneity of Smc, which comprises genogroups exhibiting a range of phenotypically distinct strains from different sources. Here, we report the genome sequencing and in-depth analysis of &lt;italic&gt;S. maltophilia&lt;/italic&gt; UENF-4GII, isolated from vermicompost. This genome harbors a unique region encoding a penicillin-binding protein (&lt;italic&gt;pbp&lt;/italic&gt;X) that was carried by a transposon, as well as horizontally-transferred genomic islands involved in anti-phage defense via DNA modification, and pili glycosylation. We also analyzed all available Smc genomes to investigate genes associated with resistance and virulence, niche occupation, and population structure. &lt;italic&gt;S. maltophilia&lt;/italic&gt; UENF-4GII belongs to genogroup 3 (Sm3), which comprises three phylogenetic clusters (PC). Pan-GWAS analysis uncovered 471 environment-associated and 791 PC-associated genes, including antimicrobial resistance (e.g. &lt;italic&gt;bla&lt;/italic&gt;L1 and &lt;italic&gt;bla&lt;/italic&gt;R1) and virulence determinants (e.g. &lt;italic&gt;tre&lt;/italic&gt;S and &lt;italic&gt;kat&lt;/italic&gt;G) that provide insights on the resistance and virulence potential of Sm3 strains. Together, the results presented here provide the grounds for more detailed clinical and ecological investigations of &lt;italic&gt;S. maltophilia&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455975" rel="alternate" title="Genome sequencing of the vermicompost strain Stenotrophomonas maltophilia UENF-4GII and population structure analysis of the S. maltophilia Sm3 genogroup (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455627</id><title>An ultrapotent neutralizing bispecific antibody with broad spectrum against SARS-CoV-2 variants (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.894856+00:00</updated><author><name>Hui Zhang</name></author><author><name>Haohui Huang</name></author><author><name>Rong Li</name></author><author><name>Lu Zhang</name></author><author><name>Zhiwei Wang</name></author><author><name>Jiaping Li</name></author><author><name>Junyou Chen</name></author><author><name>Huafei Su</name></author><author><name>Dandan Zheng</name></author><author><name>Ziqi Su</name></author><author><name>Li Wang</name></author><author><name>Chunping Deng</name></author><author><name>shujun Pei</name></author><author><name>Shenghua Zhu</name></author><author><name>Chan Li</name></author><author><name>Yaochang Yuan</name></author><author><name>Haitao Yue</name></author><author><name>Yanqun Wang</name></author><author><name>Xiaobo Li</name></author><author><name>Cuihua Liu</name></author><author><name>Jinchen Yu</name></author><author><name>Hui Zhang</name></author><author><name>Shengfeng Li</name></author><author><name>Xianming Huang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In spite of the successful development of effective countermeasures against Covid-19, variants have and will continue to emerge that could compromise the efficacy of currently approved neutralizing antibodies and vaccines. Consequently, novel and more efficacious agents are urgently needed. We have developed a bispecific antibody, 2022, consisting of two antibodies, 2F8 and VHH18. 2F8 was isolated from our proprietary fully synthetic human IDEAL (Intelligently Designed and Engineered Antibody Library)-VH/VL library and VHH18 is a single domain antibody isolated from IDEAL-nanobody library. 2022 was constructed by attaching VHH18 to the C-terminal of Fc of 2F8. 2022 binds two non-overlapping epitopes simultaneously on the RBD of the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein and blocks the binding of RBD to human angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2). 2022 potently neutralizes SARS-CoV-2 and all of the variants tested in both pseudovirus and live virus assays, including variants carrying mutations known to resist neutralizing antibodies approved under EUA and that reduce the protection efficiency of current effective vaccines. The half-maximum inhibitory concentration (IC50) of 2022 is 270 pM, 30 pM, 20 pM, and 1 pM, for wild-type, alpha, beta, and delta pseudovirus, respectively. In the live virus assay, 2022 has an IC50 of 26.4 pM, 13.3 pM, and 88.6 pM, for wild-type, beta, and delta live virus, respectively. In a mouse model of SARS-CoV-2, 2022 showed strong prophylactic and therapeutic effects. A single administration of 2022 intranasal (i.n.) or intraperitoneal (i.p.) 24 hours before virus challenge completely protected all mice from bodyweight loss, as compared with up to 20% loss of bodyweight in placebo treated mice. In addition, the lung viral titers were undetectable (FRNT assay) in all mice treated with 2022 either prophylactically or therapeutically, as compared with around 1×10&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; pfu/g lung tissue in placebo treated mice. In summary, bispecific antibody 2022 showed potent binding and neutralizing activity across a variety of SARS-CoV-2 variants and could be an attractive weapon to combat the ongoing waves of the COVID-19 pandemic propagated mainly by variants, especially, the much more contagious delta variant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455627" rel="alternate" title="An ultrapotent neutralizing bispecific antibody with broad spectrum against SARS-CoV-2 variants (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456012</id><title>In vitro determination of inhibitory effects by humic substances complexing Zn and Se on SARS-CoV-2 virus replication (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.895212+00:00</updated><author><name>Bernadett Pályi</name></author><author><name>Zoltán Kis</name></author><author><name>Polett Hajdrik</name></author><author><name>Noémi Kovács</name></author><author><name>Daniel S. Veres</name></author><author><name>Krisztián Szigeti</name></author><author><name>Imre Hegedűs</name></author><author><name>Tibor Kovács</name></author><author><name>Ralf Bergmann</name></author><author><name>Domokos Máthé</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Humic substances are well known human nutritional supplement materials and play important performance-enhancing roles as animal feed additives, too. For decades, ingredients of humic substances have also been proven to carry potent antiviral effects against different viruses. Here, the antiviral activity of a humic substance containing ascorbic acid, Se&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt; and Zn&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; ions intended as a nutritional supplement material was investigated against SARS-CoV-2 virus B1.1.7 Variant of Concern (“Alpha Variant”) in a VeroE6 cell line. Results show that this combination has a significant &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; antiviral effect at a very low concentration range of its intended active ingredients. Even picomolar concentration ranges of humic substances, vitamin C and Zn/Se ions in the given composition were enough to achieve fifty percent viral replication inhibition in the applied SARS-CoV-2 virus inhibition test.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456012" rel="alternate" title="In vitro determination of inhibitory effects by humic substances complexing Zn and Se on SARS-CoV-2 virus replication (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456184</id><title>Differential regulation and production of secondary metabolites among isolates of the fungal wheat pathogen Zymoseptoria tritici (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.895422+00:00</updated><author><name>M. Amine Hassani</name></author><author><name>Ernest Oppong-Danquah</name></author><author><name>Alice Feurty</name></author><author><name>Deniz Tasdemir</name></author><author><name>Eva H Stukenbrock</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The genome of the wheat pathogenic fungus, &lt;italic&gt;Zymoseptoria tritici&lt;/italic&gt;, represents extensive presence-absence variation in gene content. Here, we addressed variation in biosynthetic gene clusters (BGCs) content and biochemical profiles among three isolates. We analysed secondary metabolite properties based on genome, transcriptome and metabolome data. The isolates represent highly distinct genome architecture, but harbor similar repertoire of BGCs. Expression profiles for most BGCs show comparable patterns of regulation among the isolates, suggesting a conserved 'biochemical infection program'. For all three isolates, we observed a strong up-regulation of an abscisic acid (ABA) gene cluster during biotrophic host colonization, indicating that &lt;italic&gt;Z. tritici&lt;/italic&gt; potentially interfere with host defenses by the biosynthesis of this phytohormone. Further, during &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; growth the isolates show similar metabolomes congruent with the predicted BGC content. We assessed if secondary metabolite production is regulated by histone methylation using a mutant impaired in formation of facultative heterochromatin (H3K27me3). In contrast to other ascomycete fungi, chromatin modifications play a less prominent role in regulation of secondary metabolites. In summary, we show that &lt;italic&gt;Z. tritici&lt;/italic&gt; has a conserved program of secondary metabolite production contrasting the immense variation in effector expression, some of these metabolites might play a key role during host colonization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456184" rel="alternate" title="Differential regulation and production of secondary metabolites among isolates of the fungal wheat pathogen Zymoseptoria tritici (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455925</id><title>Evaluation of the speed, accuracy and precision of the QuickMIC rapid antibiotic susceptibility testing assay in a clinical setting (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.895597+00:00</updated><author><name>Christer Malmberg</name></author><author><name>Jessie Torpner</name></author><author><name>Jenny Fernberg</name></author><author><name>Håkan Öhrn</name></author><author><name>Cecilia Johansson</name></author><author><name>Thomas Tängdén</name></author><author><name>Johan Kreuger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The rapidly changing landscape of antimicrobial resistance poses a challenge for empirical antibiotic therapy in severely ill patients and highlights the need for fast antibiotic susceptibility diagnostics to guide treatment. Traditional methods for antibiotic susceptibility testing (AST) of bacteria such as broth microdilution (BMD) or the disc diffusion method (DDM) are comparatively slow and show high variability. Rapid AST methods under development often trade speed for resolution, sometimes only measuring responses at a single antibiotic concentration. QuickMIC is a recently developed lab-on-a-chip system for rapid AST. Here we evaluate the performance of the QuickMIC method with regard to speed, precision and accuracy in comparison to traditional diagnostic methods. 151 blood cultures of clinical Gram-negative isolates with a high frequency of drug resistance were tested with the QuickMIC system and compared with BMD for 12 antibiotics. To investigate sample turnaround time and functionality in a clinical setting, another 41 clinical blood culture samples were acquired from the Uppsala University Hospital and analyzed on site in the clinical laboratory with the QuickMIC system, and compared with DDM for 8 antibiotics routinely used in the clinical laboratory. The overall essential agreement between MIC values obtained by QuickMIC and BMD was 83.2%, with an average time to result of 3 h 2 min (SD: 24.8 min) for the QuickMIC method. For the clinical dataset, the categorical agreement was 94.9%, and the total turnaround time as compared to routine diagnostics reduced by 40% (33 h vs. 55 h). Interexperiment variability was low (average SD: 44.6% from target MIC) compared to the acceptable standard of ±1 log&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; unit (&lt;italic&gt;i&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;e&lt;/italic&gt;. -50% to +100% deviation from target MIC) in BMD. We conclude that the QuickMIC method can provide rapid and accurate AST, and may be especially valuable in settings with high resistance rates and for antibiotics where wildtype and resistant MIC distributions are close or overlapping.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455925" rel="alternate" title="Evaluation of the speed, accuracy and precision of the QuickMIC rapid antibiotic susceptibility testing assay in a clinical setting (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455858</id><title>Non-mycorrhizal root associated fungi of a tropical montane forest are relatively robust to the long-term addition of moderate rates of nitrogen and phosphorus (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.895762+00:00</updated><author><name>Juan F. Dueñas</name></author><author><name>Stefan Hempel</name></author><author><name>Jürgen Homeier</name></author><author><name>Juan Pablo Suárez</name></author><author><name>Matthias C. Rillig</name></author><author><name>Tessa Camenzind</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Andean forests are biodiversity hotspots and globally important carbon (C) repositories. This status might be at risk due to increasing rates of atmospheric nutrient deposition. As fungal communities are key in the recirculation of soil nutrients, assessing their responses to soil eutrophication can help establish a link between microbial biodiversity and the sustainability of the C sink status of this region. Beyond mycorrhizal fungi, which have been studied more frequently, a wide range of other fungi associate with the fine root fraction of trees. Monitoring these communities can offer insights into how communities composed of both facultative and obligate root associated fungi are responding to soil eutrophication.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we document the response of non-mycorrhizal root associated fungal (RAF) communities to a long-term nutrient manipulation experiment. The stand level fine root fraction of an old growth tropical montane forest was sampled after seven years of nitrogen (N) and phosphorus (P) additions. RAF communities were characterized by a deep sequencing approach. As per the resource imbalance model, we expected that asymmetries in the availability of C, N and P elicited by fertilization will lead to mean richness reductions and alterations of the community structure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We recovered moderately diverse fungal assemblages composed by sequence variants classified within a wide set of trophic guilds. While mean richness remained stable, community composition shifted, particularly among Ascomycota and after the addition of P. Fertilization factors, however, only accounted for a minor proportion of the variance in community composition. These findings suggest that, unlike mycorrhizal fungi, RAF communities are less sensitive to shifts in soil nutrient availability. A plausible explanation is that non-mycorrhizal RAF have fundamentally different nutrient acquisition and life history traits, thus allowing them greater stoichiometric plasticity and an array of functional acclimation responses that collectively express as subtle shifts in community level attributes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455858" rel="alternate" title="Non-mycorrhizal root associated fungi of a tropical montane forest are relatively robust to the long-term addition of moderate rates of nitrogen and phosphorus (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456100</id><title>Tissue-wide metabolomics reveals wide impact of gut microbiota on mice metabolite composition (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.895923+00:00</updated><author><name>Iman Zarei</name></author><author><name>Ville M. Koistinen</name></author><author><name>Marietta Kokla</name></author><author><name>Anton Klåvus</name></author><author><name>Ambrin Farizah Babu</name></author><author><name>Marko Lehtonen</name></author><author><name>Seppo Auriola</name></author><author><name>Kati Hanhineva</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The essential role of gut microbiota in health and disease is well-recognized, but the biochemical details underling beneficial impact remain largely undefined. Dysbiosis of gut bacteria results in the alteration of certain microbial and host metabolites, and identifying these markers could enhance the early detection of certain diseases. We report LC-MS based non-targeted metabolic profiling to demonstrate a large effect of gut microbiota on mammalian tissue metabolites. It was hypothesized that gut microbiota influences the overall biochemistry of the host metabolome and this effect is tissue-specific. Thirteen different tissues from germ-free and conventional mice were selected and their metabolic differences were analyzed. Our study demonstrated a large effect of the microbiome on mammalian biochemistry at different tissue levels and resulted in significant modulation of metabolites from multiple metabolic pathway (p ≤ 0.05). A vast metabolic response of host to metabolites generated by the microbiota was observed, Hundreds of molecular features were detected exclusively in one mouse group, with the majority of these being unique to specific tissue, suggesting direct impact gut microbiota on host metabolism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456100" rel="alternate" title="Tissue-wide metabolomics reveals wide impact of gut microbiota on mice metabolite composition (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456133</id><title>A B cell actomyosin arc network couples integrin co-stimulation to mechanical force-dependent immune synapse formation (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.896092+00:00</updated><author><name>Jia C Wang</name></author><author><name>Yang-In Yim</name></author><author><name>Xufeng Wu</name></author><author><name>Valentin Jaumouillé</name></author><author><name>Clare M Waterman</name></author><author><name>John H Kehrl</name></author><author><name>John A Hammer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;B-cell activation and immune synapse (IS) formation with membrane-bound antigens are actin-dependent processes that scale positively with the strength of antigen-induced signals. Importantly, ligating the B-cell integrin, LFA-1, with ICAM-1 promotes IS formation when antigen is limiting. Whether the actin cytoskeleton plays a specific role in integrin-dependent IS formation is unknown. Here we show using super-resolution imaging of primary B cells that LFA-1: ICAM-1 interactions promote the formation of an actomyosin network that dominates the B-cell IS. This network is created by the formin mDia1, organized into concentric, contractile arcs by myosin 2A, and flows inward at the same rate as B-cell receptor (BCR): antigen clusters. Consistently, individual BCR microclusters are swept inward by individual actomyosin arcs. Under conditions where integrin is required for synapse formation, inhibiting myosin impairs synapse formation, as evidenced by reduced antigen centralization, diminished BCR signaling, and defective signaling protein distribution at the synapse. Together, these results argue that a contractile actomyosin arc network plays a key role in the mechanism by which LFA-1 co-stimulation promotes B-cell activation and IS formation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456133" rel="alternate" title="A B cell actomyosin arc network couples integrin co-stimulation to mechanical force-dependent immune synapse formation (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456290</id><title>Antimicrobial interactions between the phytoextracts of Callistemon citrinus and Eriobotrya japonica against Streptococcus mutans (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.896253+00:00</updated><author><name>ONEN HEALY</name></author><author><name>KAVUO SIFA JUDITH</name></author><author><name>Bukusuba Samuel</name></author><author><name>NAMBOKO KUTOSI JERALD</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Streptococcus mutans  is a gram-positive bacterium in the oral cavity that is most implicated in the dental caries progression. The condition is very expensive to manage and the most commonly used products such as fluoride tooth pastes and alcohol-based mouth washes are associated with many side effects. The current study therefore focused on providing a scientific evidence to guide the use of a combination of  Eriobotrya japonica (EJ) and  Callistemon citrinus  (CC) as actives in development of an effective and cheaper herbal formulation for management of dental caries. The objective of this study was to determine antimicrobial interactions of  Eriobotrya japonica  and  Callistemon citrinus  phytoextracts proportions against  Streptococcus mutans  bacteria. The leaves of both plants (EJ and CC) were shade-dried and pulverized into a coarse powder which were then cold macerated using ethanol (60 %) for 24 h. Phytochemical screening was conducted for the two dry extracts obtained after fan drying before they were mixed in to five different proportions (1:0, 3:1, 1:1, 1:3 and 0:1). Minimum inhibitory concentrations (MIC) and minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC) assays against  Streptococcus mutans  were done for all the proportions above with ciprofloxacin and 2.5 % Dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) as the positive and negative controls respectively. Antimicrobial interactions between the two extracts were also evaluated using Fractional Inhibitory and Bacterial Concentration Indices (FICI/FBCI). Results showed that EJ and CC had percentage yields of 20.05 % and 15.45 % respectively. All the extracts showed similar phytochemical profiles. They also demonstrated an inhibitory effect on  Streptococcus mutans with  MIC and MBC values ranging from 521 to 3333 µg/ml and 1042 to 3667 µg/ml respectively. However, CC: EJ (1:0) had the lowest MIC and MBC comparable to that of the standard drug at P &amp;lt;0.05. The FICI/FBCI were between 1.5 and 3.917. Therefore, CC: EJ (1:0) proportion markedly demonstrated better antimicrobial activity against the test organism and there are no beneficial antimicrobial interactions between the two plant extracts to inform their combination as actives for dental caries product formulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456290" rel="alternate" title="Antimicrobial interactions between the phytoextracts of Callistemon citrinus and Eriobotrya japonica against Streptococcus mutans (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456231</id><title>Across functional boundaries: making non-neutralizing antibodies to neutralize HIV-1 and mediate Fc-mediated effector killing of infected cells (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.896399+00:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Richard</name></author><author><name>Dung Nguyen</name></author><author><name>William D. Tolbert</name></author><author><name>Romain Gasser</name></author><author><name>shilei ding</name></author><author><name>Dani Vezina</name></author><author><name>Shang Yu Gong</name></author><author><name>Jeremie Prevost</name></author><author><name>Gabrielle Gendron-Lepage</name></author><author><name>Halima Medjahed</name></author><author><name>Suneetha Gottumukkala</name></author><author><name>Andres Finzi</name></author><author><name>Marzena Pazgier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In HIV-1 infection, many antibodies (Abs) are elicited to Envelope (Env) epitopes that are conformationally masked in the native trimer and are only available for antibody recognition after the trimer binds host cell CD4. Among these are epitopes within the Co-Receptor Binding Site (CoRBS) and the constant region 1 and 2 (C1-C2 or Cluster A region). In particular, C1-C2 epitopes map to the gp120 face interacting with gp41 in the native, closed Env trimer present on HIV-1 virions or expressed on HIV-1 infected cells. Antibodies targeting this region are therefore non-neutralizing and their potential as mediators of antibody depended cellular cytoxicity (ADCC) of HIV-1 infected cells diminished by a lack of available binding targets.  Here we present the design of Ab-CD4 chimeric proteins that consist of the Ab-IgG1 of a CoRBS or Cluster A specificity to the extracellular domain 1 and 2 of human CD4. Our Ab-CD4 hybrids induce potent ADCC against infected primary CD4+ T cells and neutralize tier 1 and 2 HIV-1 viruses. Furthermore, competition binding experiments reveal that the observed biological activities rely on both the antibody and CD4 moieties confirming their cooperativity in triggering conformational rearrangements of Env. Our data indicate the utility of these Ab-CD4 hybrids as antibody therapeutics effective in eliminating HIV-1 through the combined mechanisms of neutralization and ADCC. This is also the first report of single-chain-Ab-based molecules capable of opening closed Env trimers on HIV-1 particles/infected cells to expose the Cluster A region and activate ADCC and neutralization against these non-neutralizing targets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456231" rel="alternate" title="Across functional boundaries: making non-neutralizing antibodies to neutralize HIV-1 and mediate Fc-mediated effector killing of infected cells (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455891</id><title>Degenerate primed randomly amplified polymorphic DNA (DP-RAPD) fingerprinting of bacteriophages of Vibrio harveyi from shrimp hatcheries in Southern India (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.896595+00:00</updated><author><name>S. Thiyagarajan</name></author><author><name>B. Chrisolite</name></author><author><name>S.V. Alavandi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Vibrio harveyi&lt;/italic&gt; is a significant pathogen of shrimp. Seventy-six bacteriophages infecting luminescent &lt;italic&gt;V. harveyi&lt;/italic&gt; were isolated from a total of 194 water samples drawn from various sources of shrimp hatcheries located in South East coast and Andaman island of India. Degenerate primed randomly amplified polymorphic DNA (DP- RAPD) fingerprinting of these bacteriophages was carried out to determine their genetic relatedness. Similarity matrix based on Dice coefficient followed by construction of dendrogram by unweighted pair group method with arithmetic averages (UPGMA) revealed 12 major clusters. One phage was randomly selected from each of these major clusters for transmission electron microscopic observations. Eleven of them had an icosahedral head (46-115 nm) with a long non-contractile tail (132-329 nm), belonging to the &lt;italic&gt;Siphoviridae&lt;/italic&gt; family and two phages had a short tail (15-27 nm), belonging to the family &lt;italic&gt;Podoviridae&lt;/italic&gt;. The phylogenetic analysis of the phages using DP-RAPD fingerprinting correlated to some extent to the phenotypic nature of the host specifically with regard to sucrose fermentation and source of isolation. However, phages specifically infecting &lt;italic&gt;V. harveyi&lt;/italic&gt; and those belonging to different families did not cluster together in the DP-PCR cluster analysis. Hence, the genetic diversity of phages infecting same host with respect to phenotypic difference was revealed by the DP-RAPD applied in this study.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455891" rel="alternate" title="Degenerate primed randomly amplified polymorphic DNA (DP-RAPD) fingerprinting of bacteriophages of Vibrio harveyi from shrimp hatcheries in Southern India (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455744</id><title>Multiple macroecological laws do characterize various aspects of microbiota dynamics (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.896736+00:00</updated><author><name>Konstantine Tchourine</name></author><author><name>Martin Carballo-Pacheco</name></author><author><name>Dennis Vitkup</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In this letter we address the potential confusion related to our recent demonstration that multiple macroecological laws describe short- and long-term dynamics of microbial communities. Specifically, we clarify that these laws, similarly to many other relationships observed in nature, are characterized not just by the existence of scaling, but also by certain characteristic values of the scaling exponents. By performing proper statistical analysis, we demonstrate that the relationships sensitive to temporal bacterial dynamics are not reproduced in the shuffled data. We also discuss that there is no clear evidence in the data that macroecological relationships in microbiota are primarily driven by external or environmental factors. Proper statistical analyses of the data suggest that the dynamics of gut microbiota, even on a constant diet, contains rich temporal structure. Therefore, it is likely that complex and non-linear internal dynamics may be primarily responsible for the observed macroecological laws in microbiota and other ecological communities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455744" rel="alternate" title="Multiple macroecological laws do characterize various aspects of microbiota dynamics (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456203</id><title>Metabolomics and Transcriptomics unravel the mechanism of browning resistance in Agaricus bisporus (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.896876+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhi-Xin Cai</name></author><author><name>Mei-Yuan Chen</name></author><author><name>Yuan-Ping Lu</name></author><author><name>Zhong-Jie Guo</name></author><author><name>Zhi-Heng Zeng</name></author><author><name>Hui-Qing Zheng</name></author><author><name>Jian-Hua Liao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Agaricus bisporus   is widely used on the world market. The easy browning of mushroom surface is one of the most intuitive factors affecting consumer purchase. A certain cognition on browning mechanism have been made after years of research. At present, people slow down the browning of mushrooms mainly by improving preservation methods. In addition, breeding is also a reliable way. In the production practice, we have identified some browning resistant varieties,and we selected a browning-resistant variety to compare with ordinary variety to reveal the resistance mechanism. Using transcriptomics and metabolomics, the differences in gene expression and metabolite levels were revealed, respectively. The results showed that differentially expressed genes (DEGs) like  AbPPO4  ,  AbPPO3   and  AbPPO2   were differently expressed and these DEGs involved in many pathways that related to browning. The expression of  AbPPO   expression play an important role in the browning of  A. bisporus   and multiple PPO family members are involved in the regulation of browning. However, the resistance to browning cannot be judged only by the expression level of  AbPPOs  . Formetabolomics, most of the different metabolites were organic acids. These organic acids had a higher level in anti-browning (BT) than easy-browning varieties (BS), although the profile was very heterogeneous. On the contrary, the content of trehalose in BS was significantly higher than that in BT. Higher organic acids decreased pH and further inhibited PPO activity. In addition, the BS had a higher content of trehalose, which might play roles in maintain the activity of PPO. The difference of browning resistance between BS and BT is mainly due to the differential regulation mechanism of PPO.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456203" rel="alternate" title="Metabolomics and Transcriptomics unravel the mechanism of browning resistance in Agaricus bisporus (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456183</id><title>Identification of a MarR subfamily that regulates arsenic resistance genes (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.897036+00:00</updated><author><name>Yanshuang Yu</name></author><author><name>Renwei Feng</name></author><author><name>Jichen Chen</name></author><author><name>Yuanping Li</name></author><author><name>Jinxuan Liang</name></author><author><name>Zhenchen Xie</name></author><author><name>Hend A Alwathnani</name></author><author><name>Barry P. Rosen</name></author><author><name>Anne Grove</name></author><author><name>Jian Chen</name></author><author><name>Christopher Rensing</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In this study, comprehensive analyses were performed to determine the function of an atypical MarR homolog. Genomic analyses showed that this &lt;italic&gt;marR&lt;/italic&gt; is located in an arsenic gene island in &lt;italic&gt;Achromobacter&lt;/italic&gt; sp. As-55 adjacent to an &lt;italic&gt;arsV&lt;/italic&gt; gene. ArsV is a flavin-dependent monooxygenase that confers resistance to the antibiotic methylarsenite (MAs(III)), the organoarsenic compound roxarsone(III) (Rox(III)), and the inorganic antimonite (Sb(III)). Similar &lt;italic&gt;marR &lt;/italic&gt;genes are widely distributed in arsenic-resistant bacteria. Phylogenetic analyses showed that these MarRs are found in operons predicted to be involved in resistance to inorganic and organic arsenic species, so the subfamily was named MarR&lt;sub&gt;ars&lt;/sub&gt;. MarR&lt;sub&gt;ars&lt;/sub&gt; orthologs have three conserved cysteine residues, which are Cys36, Cys37 and Cys157 in &lt;italic&gt;Achromobacter &lt;/italic&gt;sp. As-55, mutation of which compromises the response to MAs(III)/Sb(III). GFP-fluorescent biosensor assays show that AdMarR&lt;sub&gt;ars&lt;/sub&gt; (MarR protein of &lt;italic&gt;Achromobacter deleyi&lt;/italic&gt; As-55) responds to trivalent As(III) and Sb(III) but not to pentavalent As(V) or Sb(V). The results of RT-qPCR assays show that &lt;italic&gt;arsV &lt;/italic&gt;is expressed constitutively in a &lt;italic&gt;marR&lt;/italic&gt; deletion mutant, indicating that &lt;italic&gt;marR&lt;/italic&gt; represses transcription of &lt;italic&gt;arsV&lt;/italic&gt;. Moreover, electrophoretic mobility shift assays (EMSA) demonstrate that AdMarR&lt;sub&gt;ars&lt;/sub&gt; binds to the promoters of both &lt;italic&gt;marR&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;arsV&lt;/italic&gt; in the absence of ligands and that DNA binding is relieved upon binding of As(III) and Sb(III). Our results demonstrate that AdMarR&lt;sub&gt;ars&lt;/sub&gt; is a novel As(III)/Sb(III)-responsive transcriptional repressor that controls expression of &lt;italic&gt;arsV,&lt;/italic&gt; which confers resistance to MAs(III), Roxarsone(III) and Sb(III). AdMarR&lt;sub&gt;ars&lt;/sub&gt; and its orthologs form a subfamily of MarR proteins that regulate genes conferring resistance to arsenic-containing antibiotics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456183" rel="alternate" title="Identification of a MarR subfamily that regulates arsenic resistance genes (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>