<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.369879+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476155</id><title>Transatlantic spread of highly pathogenic avian influenza H5N1 by wild birds from Europe to North America in 2021 (64 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.369971+00:00</updated><author><name>V. Caliendo</name></author><author><name>N. S. Lewis</name></author><author><name>A. Pohlmann</name></author><author><name>S.R. Baillie</name></author><author><name>A.C. Banyard</name></author><author><name>M. Beer</name></author><author><name>I.H. Brown</name></author><author><name>R.A.M. Fouchier</name></author><author><name>R.D.E. Hansen</name></author><author><name>T.K. Lameris</name></author><author><name>A.S. Lang</name></author><author><name>S. Laurendeau</name></author><author><name>O. Lung</name></author><author><name>G. Robertson</name></author><author><name>H. van der Jeugd</name></author><author><name>T.N. Alkie</name></author><author><name>K. Thorup</name></author><author><name>M.L. van Toor</name></author><author><name>J. Waldenström</name></author><author><name>C. Yason</name></author><author><name>T. Kuiken</name></author><author><name>Y. Berhane</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Highly pathogenic avian influenza (HPAI) viruses of the A/Goose/Guangdong/1/1996 lineage (GsGd), which threaten the health of poultry, wildlife and humans, are spreading across Asia, Europe and Africa, but are currently absent from Oceania and the Americas. In December 2021, H5N1 HPAI viruses were detected in poultry and a free-living gull in St. John’s, Newfoundland and Labrador, Canada. Phylogenetic analysis showed that these viruses were most closely related to HPAI GsGd viruses circulating in northwestern Europe in spring 2021. Analysis of wild bird migration suggested that these viruses may have been carried across the Atlantic via Iceland, Greenland/Arctic or pelagic routes. The here documented incursion of HPAI GsGd viruses into North America raises concern for further virus spread across the Americas by wild bird migration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Detection of H5N1 highly pathogenic avian influenza in Canada raises concern for spread in the Americas by migratory birds.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476155" rel="alternate" title="Transatlantic spread of highly pathogenic avian influenza H5N1 by wild birds from Europe to North America in 2021 (64 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475790</id><title>The phylogenomic landscape of the genus Serratia (32 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.370104+00:00</updated><author><name>David J. Williams</name></author><author><name>Patrick A. D. Grimont</name></author><author><name>Adrián Cazares</name></author><author><name>Francine Grimont</name></author><author><name>Elisabeth Ageron</name></author><author><name>Kerry A. Pettigrew</name></author><author><name>Daniel Cazares</name></author><author><name>Elisabeth Njamkepo</name></author><author><name>François-Xavier Weill</name></author><author><name>Eva Heinz</name></author><author><name>Matthew T. G. Holden</name></author><author><name>Nicholas R. Thomson</name></author><author><name>Sarah J. Coulthurst</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The genus &lt;italic&gt;Serratia&lt;/italic&gt; has been studied for over a century and includes clinically-important and diverse environmental members. Despite this, there is a paucity of genomic information across the genus and a robust whole genome-based phylogenetic framework is lacking. Here, we have assembled and analysed a representative set of 664 genomes from across the genus, including 215 historic isolates originally used in defining the genus. Phylogenomic analysis of the genus reveals a clearly-defined population structure which displays deep divisions and aligns with ecological niche, as well as striking congruence between historical biochemical phenotyping data and contemporary genomics data. We show that &lt;italic&gt;Serratia&lt;/italic&gt; is a diverse genus which displays striking plasticity and ability to adapt to its environment, including a highly-varied portfolio of plasmids, and provide evidence of different patterns of gene flow across the genus. This work provides an essential platform for understanding the emergence of clinical and other lineages of &lt;italic&gt;Serratia&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475790" rel="alternate" title="The phylogenomic landscape of the genus Serratia (32 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475842</id><title>A new class of protein sensor links spirochete pleomorphism, persistence, and chemotaxis (24 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.370201+00:00</updated><author><name>A.R. Muok</name></author><author><name>K. Kurniyati</name></author><author><name>D.R. Ortega</name></author><author><name>F.A. Olsthoorn</name></author><author><name>A. Sidi Mabrouk</name></author><author><name>C. Li</name></author><author><name>A. Briegel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pathogenic spirochetes can alter their morphologies and behaviors to infect and survive within their hosts. Previous reports demonstrate that the formation of so-called ‘round bodies’ and biofilms, and chemotaxis are involved in spirochete pathogenesis. Here, in the spirochete &lt;italic&gt;Treponema denticola&lt;/italic&gt;, we report a direct link between these cellular states that involves a new class of protein sensor (CheWS) with hitherto unclear function. Using cryo-EM methods, protein modeling, bioinformatics, genetics methods, and behavioral assays we demonstrate that spirochetes regulate these behaviors in response to the small molecule s-adenosylmethionine (SAM) via a SAM sensor that is anchored to chemotaxis arrays. CheWS influences chemotaxis, biofilm and round body formation under nonstressed conditions by a novel sporulation-like mechanism. Taken together, we establish an improved model for round body formation, we discovered a direct link between this SAM sensor and changes in cellular states, as well as characterized a new sensor class involved in chemotaxis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475842" rel="alternate" title="A new class of protein sensor links spirochete pleomorphism, persistence, and chemotaxis (24 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.474735</id><title>Comprehensive assessment of functional effects of commonly used sweeteners on ex vivo human gut microbiome (19 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.370276+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhongzhi Sun</name></author><author><name>Wenju Wang</name></author><author><name>Leyuan Li</name></author><author><name>Xu Zhang</name></author><author><name>Zhibin Ning</name></author><author><name>Janice Mayne</name></author><author><name>Krystal Walker</name></author><author><name>Alain Stintzi</name></author><author><name>Daniel Figeys</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The gut microbiome composition and function are associated with health and diseases. Sweeten-ers are widely used food additives, although many studies using animal models have linked sweetener consumption to gut microbial changes and health issues. Whether sweeteners directly change the human gut microbiome functionality remains largely unknown. In this study, we sys-tematically investigated the responses of five human gut microbiomes to 21 common sweeteners, using an approach combining high-throughput ex vivo microbiome culturing and metaproteomics to quantify functional changes in different taxa. Hierarchical clustering based on metaproteomic responses of individual microbiomes resulted in two clusters. The first cluster was composed of non-caloric artificial sweeteners (NAS) and two sugar alcohols with shorter carbon backbones (4-5 carbon atoms), and the second cluster was composed of sugar alcohols with longer carbon backbones. The metaproteomic functional responses of the second cluster were similar to the prebiotic fructooligosaccharides and kestose, indicating that these sugar alcohol-type sweeteners have potential prebiotic functions. This study provides a comprehensive evaluation of the direct effects of commonly used sweeteners on the functions of the human gut microbiome using a func-tional  metaproteomics approach, improving our understanding of the roles of sweeteners on mi-crobiome-associated human health and disease issues.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.474735" rel="alternate" title="Comprehensive assessment of functional effects of commonly used sweeteners on ex vivo human gut microbiome (19 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476216</id><title>The RNA polymerase gene specificity factor σ54 is required for homogeneous non-planktonic growth of uropathogenic Escherichia coli (18 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.370362+00:00</updated><author><name>Amy Switzer</name></author><author><name>Lynn Burchell</name></author><author><name>Panagiotis Mitsidis</name></author><author><name>Sivaramesh Wigneshweraraj</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The canonical function of a bacterial sigma (σ) factor is to determine the gene specificity of the RNA polymerase (RNAP). In several diverse bacterial species, the σ&lt;sup&gt;54&lt;/sup&gt; factor uniquely confers distinct functional and regulatory properties on the RNAP. A hallmark feature of the σ&lt;sup&gt;54&lt;/sup&gt;-RNAP is the obligatory requirement for an activator ATPase to allow transcription initiation. The genes that rely upon σ&lt;sup&gt;54&lt;/sup&gt; for their transcription have a wide range of different functions suggesting that the repertoire of functions performed by genes, directly or indirectly affected by σ&lt;sup&gt;54&lt;/sup&gt;, is not yet exhaustive. By comparing the non-planktonic growth properties of prototypical enteropathogenic, uropathogenic and non-pathogenic &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; strains devoid of σ&lt;sup&gt;54&lt;/sup&gt;, we uncovered σ&lt;sup&gt;54&lt;/sup&gt; as a determinant of homogenous non-planktonic growth specifically in the uropathogenic strain. Notably, bacteria devoid of individual activator ATPases of the σ&lt;sup&gt;54&lt;/sup&gt;-RNAP do not phenocopy the σ&lt;sup&gt;54&lt;/sup&gt; mutant strain. It seems that σ&lt;sup&gt;54&lt;/sup&gt;’s role as a determinant of homogenous non-planktonic growth represents a putative non-canonical function of σ&lt;sup&gt;54&lt;/sup&gt; in regulating genetic information flow.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476216" rel="alternate" title="The RNA polymerase gene specificity factor σ54 is required for homogeneous non-planktonic growth of uropathogenic Escherichia coli (18 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476242</id><title>Local-scale virome depiction supports significant differences between Aedes aegypti and Aedes albopictus (14 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.370427+00:00</updated><author><name>Arley Calle-Tobón</name></author><author><name>Juliana Pérez-Pérez</name></author><author><name>Nicolás Forero-Pineda</name></author><author><name>Omar Triana Chávez</name></author><author><name>Winston Rojas-Montoya</name></author><author><name>Guillermo Rúa-Uribe</name></author><author><name>Andrés Gómez-Palacio</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; spp. comprise the primary group of mosquitoes that transmit arboviruses such as dengue, Zika, and chikungunya viruses to humans, and thus these insects pose a significant burden on public health worldwide. Advancements in next-generation sequencing and metagenomics have expanded our knowledge on the richness of RNA viruses harbored by arthropods such as &lt;italic&gt;Ae. aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Ae. albopictus&lt;/italic&gt;; increasing evidence suggests that vectorial competence can be modified by the microbiome (comprising both bacteriome and virome) of mosquitoes present in endemic zones. Using an RNA-seq-based metataxonomic approach, this study determined the virome structure of field-caught &lt;italic&gt;Ae. aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Ae. albopictus&lt;/italic&gt; mosquitoes in Medellín, Colombia, a municipality with a high incidence of mosquito-transmitted arboviruses. The two species are sympatric, but their core viromes differed considerably in richness, diversity, and abundance; the viromes were dominated by a few viruses. BLAST searches of assembled contigs suggested that at least 17 virus species (16 of which are insect-specific viruses [ISVs]) infect the &lt;italic&gt;Ae. aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; population. Dengue virus 3 was detected in one sample. In &lt;italic&gt;Ae. albopictus&lt;/italic&gt;, up to 11 ISVs and one plant virus were detected. Therefore, the virome composition was species-specific. The bacterial endosymbiont &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; was identified in all &lt;italic&gt;Ae. albopictus&lt;/italic&gt; samples and in some &lt;italic&gt;Ae. aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; samples collected after 2017. The presence of &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachi&lt;/italic&gt;a sp. in &lt;italic&gt;Ae. aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; was not related to significant changes in the richness, diversity, or abundance of this mosquito’s virome, although it was related to an increase in the abundance of Aedes aegypti To virus 2 (unclassified). The mitochondrial diversity of these mosquitoes suggested that the &lt;italic&gt;Ae. aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; population underwent a change that started in the second half of 2017, which coincides with the release of &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt;-infected mosquitoes in Medellín, indicating that the population of &lt;italic&gt;w&lt;/italic&gt;Mel-infected mosquitoes has expanded. However, additional studies are required on the dispersal speed and intergenerational stability of &lt;italic&gt;w&lt;/italic&gt;Mel in Medellín and nearby areas as well as on the introgression of genetic variants in the native mosquito population.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476242" rel="alternate" title="Local-scale virome depiction supports significant differences between Aedes aegypti and Aedes albopictus (14 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476307</id><title>Metabolic basis for the evolution of a common pathogenic Pseudomonas aeruginosa variant (13 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.370506+00:00</updated><author><name>Dallas L. Mould</name></author><author><name>Mirjana Stevanovic</name></author><author><name>Alix Ashare</name></author><author><name>Daniel Schultz</name></author><author><name>Deborah A Hogan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microbes frequently evolve in reproducible ways. Here, we show that differences in specific metabolic regulation explain the frequent presence of &lt;italic&gt;lasR&lt;/italic&gt; loss-of-function mutations in the bacterial pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa.&lt;/italic&gt; While LasR contributes to virulence, &lt;italic&gt;lasR&lt;/italic&gt; mutants have been associated with more severe disease. A model based on the intrinsic growth kinetics for a wild type strain and its LasR&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; derivative, in combination with an experimental evolution based genetic screen and further genetics analyses, indicated that differences in metabolism were sufficient to explain the rise of these common mutant types. The evolution of LasR&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; lineages in laboratory and clinical isolates depended on activity of the two-component system CbrAB, which modulates substrate prioritization through the catabolite repression control pathway. LasR&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; lineages frequently arise in cystic fibrosis lung infections and their detection correlates with disease severity. Our analysis of bronchoalveolar lavage fluid metabolomes identified compounds that negatively correlate with lung function, and we show that these compounds support enhanced growth of LasR&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; cells in a CbrB-controlled manner. We propose that &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; metabolomes are a major driver of pathogen evolution, which may influence the progression of disease and its treatment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476307" rel="alternate" title="Metabolic basis for the evolution of a common pathogenic Pseudomonas aeruginosa variant (13 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476089</id><title>Systematic analysis of human antibody response to ebolavirus glycoprotein reveals high prevalence of neutralizing public clonotypes (13 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.370576+00:00</updated><author><name>Elaine C. Chen</name></author><author><name>Pavlo Gilchuk</name></author><author><name>Seth J. Zost</name></author><author><name>Philipp A. Ilinykh</name></author><author><name>Elad Binshtein</name></author><author><name>Kai Huang</name></author><author><name>Luke Myers</name></author><author><name>Stefano Bonissone</name></author><author><name>Samuel Day</name></author><author><name>Chandrahaas R. Kona</name></author><author><name>Andrew Trivette</name></author><author><name>Joseph X. Reidy</name></author><author><name>Rachel E. Sutton</name></author><author><name>Christopher Gainza</name></author><author><name>Summer Monroig</name></author><author><name>Edgar Davidson</name></author><author><name>Erica Ollmann Saphire</name></author><author><name>Benjamin J. Doranz</name></author><author><name>Natalie Castellana</name></author><author><name>Alexander Bukreyev</name></author><author><name>Robert H. Carnahan</name></author><author><name>James E. Crowe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the human antibody response to emerging viral pathogens is key to epidemic preparedness. As the size of the B cell response to a pathogenic virus protective antigen is undefined, we performed deep paired heavy and light chain sequencing in EBOV-GP specific memory B cells, allowing analysis of the ebolavirus-specific antibody repertoire both genetically and functionally. This approach facilitated investigation of the molecular and genetic basis for evolution of cross-reactive antibodies by elucidating germline-encoded properties of antibodies to EBOV and identification of the overlap between antibodies in the memory B-cell and serum repertoire. We identified 73 public clonotypes to EBOV, 20% of which encoded antibodies with neutralization activity and capacity to protect &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. This comprehensive analysis of the public and private antibody repertoire provides insight into the molecular basis of the humoral immune response to EBOV-GP, which informs vaccine design of new vaccines and improved therapeutics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476089" rel="alternate" title="Systematic analysis of human antibody response to ebolavirus glycoprotein reveals high prevalence of neutralizing public clonotypes (13 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476238</id><title>Bat Red Blood Cells express Nucleic Acid Sensing Receptors and bind RNA and DNA (12 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.370708+00:00</updated><author><name>LK Metthew Lam</name></author><author><name>Jane Dobkin</name></author><author><name>Kaitlyn A. Eckart</name></author><author><name>Ian Gereg</name></author><author><name>Andrew DiSalvo</name></author><author><name>Amber Nolder</name></author><author><name>Eman Anis</name></author><author><name>Julie C. Ellis</name></author><author><name>Greg Turner</name></author><author><name>Nilam S. Mangalmurti</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Red blood cells (RBCs) demonstrate immunomodulatory capabilities through the expression of nucleic acid sensors. However, little is known about bat RBCs, and no studies have examined the immune function of bat erythrocytes. Here we show that bat RBCs express the nucleic acid-sensing Toll-like receptors TLR7 and TLR9 and bind the nucleic acid ligands, single-stranded RNA, and CpG DNA. Collectively, these data suggest that, like human RBCs, bat erythrocytes possess immune function and may be reservoirs for nucleic acids. These findings provide unique insight into bat immunity and may uncover potential mechanisms by which virulent pathogens in humans are concealed in bats.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476238" rel="alternate" title="Bat Red Blood Cells express Nucleic Acid Sensing Receptors and bind RNA and DNA (12 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.475240</id><title>GR13-type plasmids in Acinetobacter potentiate the accumulation and horizontal transfer of diverse accessory genes (12 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.370793+00:00</updated><author><name>Robert A. Moran</name></author><author><name>Haiyang Liu</name></author><author><name>Emma L. Doughty</name></author><author><name>Xiaoting Hua</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth A. Cummins</name></author><author><name>Tomas Liveikis</name></author><author><name>Alan McNally</name></author><author><name>Zhihui Zhou</name></author><author><name>Willem van Schaik</name></author><author><name>Yunsong Yu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Carbapenem resistance and other antibiotic resistance genes (ARGs) can be found in plasmids in &lt;italic&gt;Acinetobacter&lt;/italic&gt;, but many plasmid types in this genus have not been well-characterised. Here we describe the distribution, diversity and evolutionary capacity of &lt;italic&gt;rep&lt;/italic&gt; group 13 (GR13) plasmids that are found in &lt;italic&gt;Acinetobacter&lt;/italic&gt; species from diverse environments. Our investigation was prompted by the discovery of two GR13 plasmids in &lt;italic&gt;A. baumannii&lt;/italic&gt; isolated in an intensive care unit (ICU). The plasmids harbour distinct accessory genes: pDETAB5 contains &lt;italic&gt;bla&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;NDM-1&lt;/sub&gt; and genes that confer resistance to four further antibiotic classes, while pDETAB13 carries putative alcohol tolerance determinants. Both plasmids contain multiple &lt;italic&gt;dif&lt;/italic&gt; modules, which are flanked by p&lt;italic&gt;dif&lt;/italic&gt; sites recognised by XerC/XerD tyrosine recombinases. The ARG-containing &lt;italic&gt;dif&lt;/italic&gt; modules in pDETAB5 are almost identical to those found in pDETAB2, a GR34 plasmid from an unrelated &lt;italic&gt;A. baumannii&lt;/italic&gt; isolated in the same ICU a month prior. Examination of a further 41 complete, publicly available plasmid sequences revealed that the GR13 pangenome consists of just four core but 1086 accessory genes, 123 in the shell and 1063 in the cloud, reflecting substantial capacity for diversification. The GR13 core genome includes genes for replication and partitioning, and for a putative tyrosine recombinase. Accessory segments encode proteins with diverse putative functions, including for metabolism, antibiotic/heavy metal/alcohol tolerance, restriction-modification, an anti-phage system and multiple toxin-antitoxin systems. The movement of &lt;italic&gt;dif&lt;/italic&gt; modules and actions of insertion sequences play an important role in generating diversity in GR13 plasmids. Discrete GR13 plasmid lineages are internationally disseminated and found in multiple &lt;italic&gt;Acinetobacter&lt;/italic&gt; species, which suggests they are important platforms for the accumulation, horizontal transmission and persistence of accessory genes in this genus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Impact statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Acinetobacter&lt;/italic&gt; species are particularly well-adapted for persistence in hospital environments where they pose a life-threatening infection risk to the most clinically-vulnerable patients. Plasmids with the potential to transfer multiple antibiotic resistance determinants between &lt;italic&gt;Acinetobacter&lt;/italic&gt; species are therefore concerning, but most are not well-characterised. This work sheds further light on the poorly-understood mobile gene pool associated with &lt;italic&gt;Acinetobacter&lt;/italic&gt;. We show here that GR13 plasmids carry a small set of core genes but have access to a highly diverse set of accessory segments that might provide fitness advantages under certain conditions. The complex evolutionary dynamics of GR13 plasmids appear to be driven by the exchange of &lt;italic&gt;dif&lt;/italic&gt; modules and by the actions of a diverse population of insertion sequences. The novel &lt;italic&gt;dif&lt;/italic&gt; modules characterised here emphasise the broader importance of these elements to the dissemination of accessory genes in &lt;italic&gt;Acinetobacter&lt;/italic&gt;. This study has improved our understanding of the diversity and distribution of &lt;italic&gt;dif&lt;/italic&gt; modules, plasmids that carry them, and how both disseminate in the continuum of &lt;italic&gt;Acinetobacter&lt;/italic&gt; populations that link hospitals and the wider environment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.475240" rel="alternate" title="GR13-type plasmids in Acinetobacter potentiate the accumulation and horizontal transfer of diverse accessory genes (12 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475911</id><title>Evolution of a cis-acting SNP that controls Type VI Secretion in Vibrio cholerae (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.370881+00:00</updated><author><name>Siu Lung Ng</name></author><author><name>Sophia Kammann</name></author><author><name>Gabi Steinbach</name></author><author><name>Tobias Hoffmann</name></author><author><name>Peter J Yunker</name></author><author><name>Brian K. Hammer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mutations in regulatory mechanisms that control gene expression contribute to phenotypic diversity and thus facilitate the adaptation of microbes to new niches. Regulatory architecture is often inferred from transcription factor identification and genome analysis using purely computational approaches. However, there are few examples of phenotypic divergence that arise from the rewiring of bacterial regulatory circuity by mutations in intergenic regions, because locating regulatory elements within regions of DNA that do not code for protein requires genomic and experimental data. We identify a single &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-acting single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) dramatically alters control of the type VI secretion system (T6), a common weapon for inter-bacterial competition. Tight T6 regulatory control is necessary for adaptation of the waterborne pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Vibrio cholerae&lt;/italic&gt; to &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; conditions within the human gut, which we show can be altered by this single non-coding SNP that results in constitutive expression &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. Our results support a model of pathogen evolution through &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-regulatory mutation and preexisting, active transcription factors, thus conferring different fitness advantages to tightly regulated strains inside a human host and unfettered strains adapted to environmental niches.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475911" rel="alternate" title="Evolution of a cis-acting SNP that controls Type VI Secretion in Vibrio cholerae (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476237</id><title>RefZ and Noc act synthetically to prevent aberrant divisions during Bacillus subtilis sporulation (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.370950+00:00</updated><author><name>Allyssa K. Miller</name></author><author><name>Jennifer K Herman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During sporulation, Bacillus subtilis undergoes an atypical cell division that requires overriding mechanisms which protect chromosomes from damage and ensure inheritance by daughter cells. Instead of assembling between segregated chromosomes at midcell, the FtsZ-ring (Z-ring) coalesces polarly, directing division over one chromosome. The DNA-binding protein RefZ facilitates the timely assembly of polar Z-rings and partially defines the region of chromosome initially captured in the forespore. RefZ binds to motifs (RBMs) located proximal to the origin of replication (oriC). Although refZ and the RBMs are conserved across the Bacillus genus, a refZ deletion mutant sporulates with wildtype efficiency, so the functional significance of RefZ during sporulation remains unclear. To further investigate RefZ function, we performed a candidate-based screen for synthetic sporulation defects by combining ∆refZ with deletions of genes previously implicated in FtsZ regulation and/or chromosome capture. Combining ∆refZ with deletions of ezrA, sepF, parA, or minD did not detectably affect sporulation. In contrast, a ∆refZ ∆noc mutant exhibited a sporulation defect, revealing a genetic interaction between RefZ and Noc. Using reporters of sporulation progression, we determined the ∆refZ ∆noc mutant exhibited sporulation delays after Spo0A activation but prior to late sporulation, with a subset of cells failing to divide polarly or activate the first forespore-specific sigma factor, SigF. The ∆refZ ∆noc mutant also exhibited extensive dysregulation of cell division, producing cells with extra, misplaced, or otherwise aberrant septa. Our results reveal a previously unknown epistatic relationship that suggests refZ and noc contribute synthetically to regulating cell division and supporting spore development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476237" rel="alternate" title="RefZ and Noc act synthetically to prevent aberrant divisions during Bacillus subtilis sporulation (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475882</id><title>EnteroBase: Hierarchical clustering of 100,000s of bacterial genomes into species/sub-species and populations (9 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.371004+00:00</updated><author><name>Mark Achtman</name></author><author><name>Zhemin Zhou</name></author><author><name>Jane Charlesworth</name></author><author><name>Laura Baxter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The definition of bacterial species is traditionally a taxonomic issue while defining bacterial populations is done with population genetics. These assignments are species specific, and depend on the practitioner. Legacy multilocus sequence typing is commonly used to identify sequence types (STs) and clusters (ST Complexes). However, these approaches are not adequate for the millions of genomic sequences from bacterial pathogens that have been generated since 2012. EnteroBase (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://enterobase.warwick.ac.uk"&gt;http://enterobase.warwick.ac.uk&lt;/ext-link&gt;) automatically clusters core genome MLST alleles into hierarchical clusters (HierCC) after assembling annotated draft genomes from short read sequences. HierCC clusters span core sequence diversity from the species level down to individual transmission chains. Here we evaluate HierCC’s ability to correctly assign 100,000s of genomes to the species/subspecies and population levels for &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella, Clostridoides, Yersinia, Vibrio&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Streptococcus&lt;/italic&gt;. HierCC assignments were more consistent with maximum-likelihood super-trees of core SNPs or presence/absence of accessory genes than classical taxonomic assignments or 95% ANI. However, neither HierCC nor ANI were uniformly consistent with classical taxonomy of &lt;italic&gt;Streptococcus.&lt;/italic&gt; HierCC was also consistent with legacy eBGs/ST Complexes in &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; or &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia&lt;/italic&gt; and revealed differences in vertical inheritance of O serogroups. Thus, EnteroBase HierCC supports the automated identification of and assignment to species/subspecies and populations for multiple genera.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475882" rel="alternate" title="EnteroBase: Hierarchical clustering of 100,000s of bacterial genomes into species/sub-species and populations (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476355</id><title>The C terminus of the mycobacterium ESX-1 secretion system substrate ESAT-6 is required for phagosomal membrane damage and virulence (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.371065+00:00</updated><author><name>Morwan M Osman</name></author><author><name>Jonthan K Shanahan</name></author><author><name>Frances Chu</name></author><author><name>Kevin Takaki</name></author><author><name>Malte Pinckert</name></author><author><name>Antonio J Pagan</name></author><author><name>Roland Brosch</name></author><author><name>William Conrad</name></author><author><name>Lalita Ramakrishnan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis and its close relative Mycobacterium marinum infect macrophages and induce the formation of granulomas, organized macrophage-rich immune aggregates. These mycobacterial pathogens can accelerate and co-opt granuloma formation for their benefit, using the specialized secretion system ESX-1, a key virulence determinant. ESX-1-mediated virulence is attributed to the damage it causes to the membranes of macrophage phagosomal compartments, within which the bacteria reside. This phagosomal damage, in turn, has been attributed to the membranolytic activity of ESAT-6, the major secreted substrate of ESX-1. However, mutations that perturb ESAT-6 membranolytic activity often result in global impairment of ESX-1 secretion. This has precluded an understanding of the causal and mechanistic relationships between ESAT-6 membranolysis and ESX-1-mediated virulence. Here, we identify two conserved residues in the unstructured C-terminal tail of ESAT-6 required for phagosomal damage, granuloma formation and virulence. Importantly, these ESAT-6 mutants have near-normal levels of secretion, far higher than the minimal threshold we establish is needed for ESX-1-mediated virulence early in infection. Unexpectedly, these loss-of-function ESAT-6 mutants retain the ability to lyse acidified liposomes. Thus, ESAT-6 virulence functions in vivo can be uncoupled from this in vitro surrogate assay. These uncoupling mutants highlight an enigmatic functional domain of ESAT-6 and provide key tools to investigate the mechanism of phagosomal damage and virulence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476355" rel="alternate" title="The C terminus of the mycobacterium ESX-1 secretion system substrate ESAT-6 is required for phagosomal membrane damage and virulence (8 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.475903</id><title>The interactome of Cryptococcus neoformans Rmt5 reveals multiple regulatory points in fungal cell biology and pathogenesis (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.371142+00:00</updated><author><name>Murat C. Kalem</name></author><author><name>Harini Subbiah</name></author><author><name>Shichen Shen</name></author><author><name>Runpu Chen</name></author><author><name>Luke Terry</name></author><author><name>Yijun Sun</name></author><author><name>Jun Qu</name></author><author><name>John C. Panepinto</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protein arginine methylation is a key post-translational modification in eukaryotes that modulates core cellular processes, including translation, morphology, transcription, and RNA fate. However, this has not been explored in &lt;italic&gt;Cryptococcus neoformans&lt;/italic&gt;, a human-pathogenic basidiomycetous encapsulated fungus. We characterized the five protein arginine methyltransferases in &lt;italic&gt;C. neoformans&lt;/italic&gt; and highlight Rmt5 as critical regulator of cryptococcal morphology and virulence. An &lt;italic&gt;rmt5&lt;/italic&gt;Δ mutant was defective in thermotolerance, had a remodeled cell wall, and exhibited enhanced growth in an elevated carbon dioxide atmosphere and in chemically induced hypoxia. We revealed that Rmt5 interacts with post-transcriptional gene regulators, such as RNA-binding proteins and translation factors. Further investigation of the &lt;italic&gt;rmt5&lt;/italic&gt;Δ mutant showed that Rmt5 is critical for the homeostasis of eIF2α and its phosphorylation state following 3-amino-1,2,4-triazole-induced ribosome stalling. RNA sequencing of one &lt;italic&gt;rmt5&lt;/italic&gt;Δ clone revealed stable chromosome 9 aneuploidy that was ameliorated by complementation but did not impact the &lt;italic&gt;rmt5&lt;/italic&gt;Δ phenotype. As a result of these diverse interactions and functions, loss of &lt;italic&gt;RMT5&lt;/italic&gt; enhanced phagocytosis by murine macrophages and attenuated disease progression in mice. Taken together, our findings link arginine methylation to critical cryptococcal cellular processes that impact pathogenesis, including post-transcriptional gene regulation by RNA-binding proteins.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fungal pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Cryptococcus neoformans&lt;/italic&gt; is a huge threat for people living with immune deficits, especially HIV/AIDS. Its virulence potential is dependent on virulence factors, stress adaptation, and thermotolerance. Post-transcriptional gene regulation is important for these pathogenic processes, but the mechanisms that govern post-transcriptional regulator function are unexplored. Protein arginine methylation is a major modification of post-transcriptional regulators that has not been investigated in pathogenic fungi. Here we investigated the role of arginine methylation by arginine methyltransferases on the biology and virulence of &lt;italic&gt;C. neoformans&lt;/italic&gt;. Phenotypic characterization of deletion mutants revealed pleiotropic functions for RMTs in this pathogen. Further investigation of the Rmt5 interactome using proximity-dependent biotinylation revealed interactions with RNA binding proteins and translation factors, thereby impacting virulence-associated processes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.475903" rel="alternate" title="The interactome of Cryptococcus neoformans Rmt5 reveals multiple regulatory points in fungal cell biology and pathogenesis (8 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475938</id><title>Generation and characterisation of P. falciparum parasites with a G358S mutation in the PfATP4 Na+ pump and clinically relevant levels of resistance to some PfATP4 inhibitors (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.371217+00:00</updated><author><name>Deyun Qiu</name></author><author><name>Jinxin V. Pei</name></author><author><name>James E. O. Rosling</name></author><author><name>Dongdi Li</name></author><author><name>Yi Xue</name></author><author><name>Jocelyn Sietsma Penington</name></author><author><name>Krittikorn Kümpornsin</name></author><author><name>Yi Tong Vincent Aw</name></author><author><name>Jessica Yi Han Aw</name></author><author><name>Heath Hasemer</name></author><author><name>Adelaide S. M. Dennis</name></author><author><name>Melanie C. Ridgway</name></author><author><name>Anthony T. Papenfuss</name></author><author><name>Marcus C. S. Lee</name></author><author><name>Giel G. van Dooren</name></author><author><name>Kiaran Kirk</name></author><author><name>Adele M. Lehane</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Small-molecule inhibitors of PfATP4, a &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; protein that is believed to pump Na&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; out of the parasite while importing H&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;, are on track to become much-needed new antimalarial drugs. The spiroindolone cipargamin is poised to become the first PfATP4 inhibitor to reach the field, having performed strongly in Phase 1 and 2 clinical trials. Previous attempts to generate cipargamin-resistant parasites in the laboratory have yielded parasites with reduced susceptibility to the drug; however, the highest 50% inhibitory concentration reported to date is 24 nM. Here, we show that &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; parasites can acquire a clinically-significant level of resistance to cipargamin that enables them to withstand micromolar concentrations of the drug. Independent experiments to generate high-level cipargamin resistance using different protocols and strains led to the same change each time – a G358S mutation in PfATP4. Parasites with this mutation showed high-level resistance not only to cipargamin, but also to the dihydroisoquinolone (+)-SJ733. However, for certain other (less clinically advanced) PfATP4-associated compounds the G358S mutation in PfATP4 conferred only moderate resistance or no resistance. The G358S mutation in PfATP4 did not affect parasite susceptibility to antimalarials that do not target PfATP4. The G358S mutation in PfATP4, and the equivalent mutation in the &lt;italic&gt;Toxoplasma gondii&lt;/italic&gt; ATP4 homologue (G419S), decreased the sensitivity of the Na&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;-ATPase activity of ATP4 to inhibition by cipargamin and (+)-SJ733, and decreased the sensitivity of parasites expressing these ATP4 mutations to disruption of parasite Na&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; regulation by cipargamin- and (+)-SJ733. The G358S mutation in PfATP4 reduced the affinity of the protein for Na&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and was associated with an increase in the parasite’s resting cytosolic Na&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; concentration; however, no significant defect in parasite growth rate was observed. Our findings suggest that codon 358 in &lt;italic&gt;pfatp4&lt;/italic&gt; should be monitored closely in the field as a molecular marker for cipargamin resistance, and that PfATP4 inhibitors in clinical development should be tested for their activity against PfATP4&lt;sup&gt;G358S&lt;/sup&gt; parasites.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475938" rel="alternate" title="Generation and characterisation of P. falciparum parasites with a G358S mutation in the PfATP4 Na+ pump and clinically relevant levels of resistance to some PfATP4 inhibitors (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476158</id><title>The erythrocyte membrane properties of beta thalassaemia heterozygotes and their consequences for Plasmodium falciparum invasion (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.371324+00:00</updated><author><name>Viola Introini</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Marin-Menendez</name></author><author><name>Guilherme Nettesheim</name></author><author><name>Yen-Chun Lin</name></author><author><name>Silvia N. Kariuki</name></author><author><name>Adrian L Smith</name></author><author><name>Letitia Jean</name></author><author><name>John N. Brewin</name></author><author><name>David C. Rees</name></author><author><name>Pietro Cicuta</name></author><author><name>Julian C. Rayner</name></author><author><name>Bridget S. Penman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Malaria parasites such as &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; have exerted formidable selective pressures on the human genome. Of the human genetic variants associated with malaria protection, beta thalassaemia (a haemoglobinopathy) was the earliest to be associated with malaria prevalence. However, the malaria protective properties of beta thalassaemic erythrocytes remain unclear. Here we studied the mechanics and surface protein expression of beta thalassaemia heterozygous erythrocytes, measured their susceptibility to &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; invasion, and calculated the energy required for merozoites to invade them. We found invasion-relevant differences in beta thalassaemic cells versus matched controls, specifically: elevated membrane tension, reduced bending modulus, and higher levels of expression of the major invasion receptor basigin. However, these differences acted in opposition to each other with respect to their likely impact on invasion, and overall we did not observe beta thalassaemic cells to have lower &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; invasion efficiency for any of the strains tested.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476158" rel="alternate" title="The erythrocyte membrane properties of beta thalassaemia heterozygotes and their consequences for Plasmodium falciparum invasion (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476239</id><title>Expressing the pro-apoptotic Reaper protein via insertion into the structural open reading frame of Sindbis virus reduces the ability to infect Aedes aegypti mosquitoes (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.371413+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexis Carpenter</name></author><author><name>Rollie J. Clem</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Arboviruses continue to threaten a significant portion of the human population, and a better understanding is needed of the determinants of successful arbovirus infection of arthropod vectors. Avoiding apoptosis has been shown to be one such determinant. Previous work showed that a Sindbis virus (SINV) construct called MRE/rpr that expresses the pro-apoptotic protein Reaper via a duplicated subgenomic promoter had a reduced ability to orally infect &lt;italic&gt;Aedes aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; mosquitoes at 3 days post-blood meal (PBM), but this difference diminished over time as virus variants containing deletions in the inserted &lt;italic&gt;reaper&lt;/italic&gt; gene rapidly predominated. The goal of this study was to generate a SINV construct that more stably expressed Reaper, in order to further clarify the effect of midgut apoptosis on disseminated infection in &lt;italic&gt;Ae. aegypti&lt;/italic&gt;. We did this by inserting &lt;italic&gt;reaper&lt;/italic&gt; as an in-frame fusion into the structural open reading frame (ORF) of SINV. This construct, MRE/rprORF, successfully expressed Reaper, replicated similarly to MRE/rpr in cell lines, and induced apoptosis in cultured cells and in mosquito midgut tissue. Mosquitoes that fed on blood containing MRE/rprORF developed less midgut and disseminated infection when compared to MRE/rpr or a control virus up to at least 7 days PBM, when less than 50% of mosquitoes that ingested MRE/rprORF had detectable disseminated infection, compared with around 80% or more of mosquitoes fed with MRE/rpr or control virus. However, virus titer in mosquitoes infected with MRE/rprORF was not significantly different from control virus, suggesting that induction of apoptosis by expression of Reaper by this method can reduce infection prevalence, but if infection is established then apoptosis induced by this method has limited ability to continue to suppress replication.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476239" rel="alternate" title="Expressing the pro-apoptotic Reaper protein via insertion into the structural open reading frame of Sindbis virus reduces the ability to infect Aedes aegypti mosquitoes (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.476490</id><title>Outer membrane protein A (OmpA) deficient Salmonella Typhimurium displays enhanced susceptibility towards β-lactam antibiotics: third-generation cephalosporins (ceftazidime) and carbapenems (meropenem) (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.371466+00:00</updated><author><name>Atish Roy Chowdhury</name></author><author><name>Debapriya Mukherjee</name></author><author><name>Ashish Kumar Singh</name></author><author><name>Dipshikha Chakravortty</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The invasive non-typhoidal serovar of Salmonella enterica, namely Salmonella Typhimurium ST313, causes bloodstream infection in sub-Saharan Africa. Like other bacterial pathogens, the development of antimicrobial resistance is a severe problem in curing non-typhoidal Salmonella infection. In this work, we have investigated the role of four prominent outer membrane porins of S. Typhimurium, namely OmpA, OmpC, OmpD, and OmpF, in resistance against broad-spectrum β-lactam antibiotics- ceftazidime and meropenem. We found that deleting OmpA from Salmonella makes the bacteria susceptible to β-lactam drugs. The MIC for both the antibiotics reduced significantly for STM ΔompA compared to the wild-type and the ompA complemented strains. Despite the presence of antibiotics, the uninterrupted growth of STM ΔompC, ΔompD, and ΔompF endorsed the dispensability of these three porins in antimicrobial resistance. The β-lactam antibiotics caused massive depolarization in the outer membrane of the bacteria in the absence of OmpA. We have proved that none of the extracellular loops but the complete structure of perfectly folded OmpA is required by the bacteria for developing antimicrobial resistance. Our data revealed that STM ΔompA consumed more antibiotics than the wild-type and the complemented strain, resulting in severe damage of the bacterial outer membrane and subsequent killing of the pathogen by antibiotic-mediated oxidative stress. Upon deleting ompA, the steady decrease in the relative proportion of antibiotic-resistant persisters and the clearance of the STM ΔompA from the liver and spleen of C57BL/6 mice upon treatment with ceftazidime proved the role of OmpA in rendering protection against β-lactam antibiotics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.476490" rel="alternate" title="Outer membrane protein A (OmpA) deficient Salmonella Typhimurium displays enhanced susceptibility towards β-lactam antibiotics: third-generation cephalosporins (ceftazidime) and carbapenems (meropenem) (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476444</id><title>Broad-spectrum mono- and combinational drug therapies for global viral pandemic preparedness (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.371528+00:00</updated><author><name>Aleksandr Ianevski</name></author><author><name>Rouan Yao</name></author><author><name>Ronja Meyer Simonsen</name></author><author><name>Vegard Myhre</name></author><author><name>Erlend Ravlo</name></author><author><name>Gerda Dominyka Kaynova</name></author><author><name>Eva Zusinaite</name></author><author><name>Judith M White</name></author><author><name>Qiuwei Pan</name></author><author><name>Stephen J Polyak</name></author><author><name>Valentyn Oksenych</name></author><author><name>Marc P. Windisch</name></author><author><name>Egle Lastauskiene</name></author><author><name>Astra Vitkauskiene</name></author><author><name>Algimantas Matukevicius</name></author><author><name>Tanel Tenson</name></author><author><name>Magnar Bjoras</name></author><author><name>Denis E Kainov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Broadly effective antiviral therapies must be developed to be ready for clinical trials, which should begin soon after the emergence of new life-threatening viruses. Here, we pave the way towards this goal by analyzing conserved druggable virus-host interactions, mechanisms of action and immunomodulatory properties of broad-spectrum antivirals (BSAs), routes of BSA delivery, and BSA interactions with other antivirals. Based on the analysis we developed scoring systems, which allowed us to predict novel BSAs and BSA-containing drug combinations (BCCs). Thus, we have developed a new strategy to broaden the spectrum of BSA indications and predict novel mono- and combinational therapies that can help better prepare for imminent future viral outbreaks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476444" rel="alternate" title="Broad-spectrum mono- and combinational drug therapies for global viral pandemic preparedness (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.17.476578</id><title>Meta-analysis of the black soldier fly (Hermetia illucens) microbiota based on 16S rRNA gene amplicon sequencing (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.371636+00:00</updated><author><name>Freek Ijdema</name></author><author><name>Jeroen De Smet</name></author><author><name>Sam Crauwels</name></author><author><name>Bart Lievens</name></author><author><name>Leen Van Campenhout</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Black soldier fly larvae (BSFL) belong to the most widely reared insect species as an alternative protein source at industrial scale. Bacteria in the larval gut can provide benefits for the animal, though some bacteria can also be pathogenic for the insect. Accurate characterization of the BSFL microbiota is important for the production of BSFL in terms of yield and microbiological safety. In this study, 16S ribosomal RNA gene sequence data sets from 11 studies were re-analysed to gain better insights in the BSFL gut microbiota, potential factors that influence their composition, and differences between the gut and the whole larvae microbiota. A core gut microbiota was found consisting of members of Enterococcus, Klebsiella, Morganella, Providencia, and Scrofimicrobium. Further, the factors Study, Age and Feed significantly affected the microbiota gut composition. When compared to whole larvae, a significantly lower number of observed zero-radius Operational Taxonomic Units and a lower diversity was found for gut samples, suggesting that the larvae harboured additional microbes on their cuticle or in the insect body. Universal choices in insect sample type, primer selection and bio-informatics can strengthen future meta-analyses and improve our understanding of the BSFL gut microbiota towards the optimization of insect production.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.17.476578" rel="alternate" title="Meta-analysis of the black soldier fly (Hermetia illucens) microbiota based on 16S rRNA gene amplicon sequencing (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476154</id><title>Plasma cell maintenance and antibody secretion are under the control of Sec22b-mediated regulation of organelle dynamics (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.371699+00:00</updated><author><name>Amelie Bonaud</name></author><author><name>Laetitia Gargowitsch</name></author><author><name>Simon Gilbert</name></author><author><name>Elanchezhian Rajan</name></author><author><name>Pablo Canales-Herrerias</name></author><author><name>Daniel Stockholm</name></author><author><name>Nabila Rahman</name></author><author><name>Mark Collins</name></author><author><name>Danika L Hill</name></author><author><name>Andres Alloatti</name></author><author><name>Nagham Alouche</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Balor</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Soldan</name></author><author><name>Daniel Gillet</name></author><author><name>Julien Barbier</name></author><author><name>Francoise Bachelerie</name></author><author><name>Kenneth G. C. Smith</name></author><author><name>Pierre Bruhns</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Amigorena</name></author><author><name>Karl Balabanian</name></author><author><name>Michelle A Linterman</name></author><author><name>Andrew Peden</name></author><author><name>Marion Espeli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite the essential role of plasma cells in health and disease, the cellular mechanisms controlling their survival and secretory capacity are still poorly understood. Here, we identified the SNARE Sec22b as a unique and critical regulator of plasma cell maintenance and function. In absence of Sec22b, plasma cells were barely detectable and serum antibody titres were dramatically reduced. Accordingly, Sec22b deficient mice fail to mount a protective immune response. At the mechanistic level, we demonstrated that Sec22b is indispensable for efficient antibody secretion but also for plasma cell fitness through the regulation of the morphology of the endoplasmic reticulum and mitochondria. Altogether, our results unveil a critical role for Sec22b-mediated regulation of plasma cell biology through the control of organelle dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476154" rel="alternate" title="Plasma cell maintenance and antibody secretion are under the control of Sec22b-mediated regulation of organelle dynamics (6 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476429</id><title>EPSTEIN-BARR VIRUS LMP1 ENHANCES LEVELS OF MICROVESICLE-ASSOCIATED PD-L1 (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.372189+00:00</updated><author><name>Monica Abou Harb</name></author><author><name>Li Sun</name></author><author><name>David G. Meckes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Extracellular vesicles (EVs) circulate throughout the body and carry cargo that can be conferred to proximal or distant cells, making them major delivery vehicles for cellular communication. Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) infected cells release EVs that contain viral proteins such as the major viral oncogene, latent membrane protein 1 (LMP1). LMP1 has been shown to regulate the cellular gene expression of programmed cell death protein 1 ligand (PD-L1). PD-L1, a protein that suppresses the immune system by binding to PD-1, (a receptor found on cytotoxic T cells). PD-L1 has been recently found to be packaged into small EVs contributing to immune evasion of lung cancer cells. Recent studies establish that MVs are shed in very large amounts by tumor cells, and that elevated levels of MVs correlate to disease metastasis and cancers being more aggressive. Here, we demonstrate PD-L1 enrichment in MVs released from nasopharyngeal carcinoma cells and an important function of EBV LMP1 in regulating PD-L1 levels in MVs. These PD-L1+ MVs containing LMP1 likely contribute to the immunosuppressive microenvironment found in EBV-associated cancers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accumulating evidence over the past decade supports that viruses utilize EVs and associated pathways to incorporate viral products to evade eliciting an immune response, while concurrently enabling viral spread or persistence within the host. Considering that viral proteins confer very strong antigenic peptides that will be recognized by T cells, the regulation of the PD-1 pathway by the overexpression of MV-associated PD-L1 may be a strong immune evasion tactic utilized by viruses. The discovery that EBV LMP1 increases PD-L1 microvesicle secretion, identifies a new therapeutic target in immune blockade therapy. We expect that our findings will begin to clarify the mechanism of LMP1-mediated enhanced packaging of PD-L1 into MVs and may produce more specific targets to treat EBV-associated cancers. Consequently, identifying whether a disease is of viral origin through predictive MV biomarkers could further allow for more targeted therapies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476429" rel="alternate" title="EPSTEIN-BARR VIRUS LMP1 ENHANCES LEVELS OF MICROVESICLE-ASSOCIATED PD-L1 (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476453</id><title>Sugar shock: Probing Streptococcus pyogenes metabolism through bioluminescence imaging (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.372304+00:00</updated><author><name>Richard W Davis</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Muse</name></author><author><name>Heather Eggleston</name></author><author><name>Micaila Hill</name></author><author><name>Peter Panizzi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Streptococcus pyogenes (S. pyogenes) can thrive in its host during an infection, and, as a result, it must be able to respond to external stimuli and available carbon sources. The pre-clinical use of engineered pathogens capable of constitutive light production may provide real-time information on microbial-specific metabolic processes. Here we mapped the central metabolism of a luxABCDE-modified S. pyogenes Xen20 (Strep. Xen20) to its de novo synthesis of luciferase substrates as assessed by the rate of light production in response to different environmental triggers. Previous characterization predicted that the lux operon was under the myo-inositol iolE promotor. Here we show that supplementation with myo-inositol generated increased Xen20 luminescence. Surprisingly, when supplemented with infection-relevant carbon sources, such as glucose or glycine, light production was diminished. This was presumably due to the scavenging of pyruvate by L-lactate dehydrogenase (LDH). Inhibition of LDH by its inhibitor, oxamate, partially restored luminescent signal in the presence of glucose, presumably by allowing the resulting pyruvate to proceed to acetyl-coenzyme A (CoA). This phenomenon appeared specific to the lactic acid bacterial metabolism as glucose or glycine did not reduce signal in an analogous luxABCDE-modified Gram-positive pathogen, Staph. Xen29. The Strep. Xen20 cells produced light in a concentration-dependent manner, inversely related to the amount of glucose present. Taken together, our measures of microbial response could provide new information regarding the responsiveness of S. pyogenes metabolism to acute changes in its local environments and cellular health.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476453" rel="alternate" title="Sugar shock: Probing Streptococcus pyogenes metabolism through bioluminescence imaging (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475878</id><title>Hydrogen production in an aerobic environment by Escherichia coli K-12 (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.372385+00:00</updated><author><name>George D. Metcalfe</name></author><author><name>Frank Sargent</name></author><author><name>Michael Hippler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;) is a facultative anaerobe that can grow in a variety of environmental conditions. In the complete absence of O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; can perform a mixed-acid fermentation that contains within it an elaborate metabolism of formic acid. In this study, we use cavity-enhanced Raman spectroscopy (CERS), FTIR, liquid Raman spectroscopy, isotopic labelling, and molecular genetics to make advances in the understanding of bacterial formate and H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; metabolism. It is shown that, under anaerobic conditions, formic acid is generated endogenously, excreted briefly from the cell, and then taken up again to be disproportionated to H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; by formate hydrogenlyase (FHL-1). However, exogenously added D-labelled formate behaves quite differently from the endogenous formate and is taken up immediately, independently, and possibly by a different mechanism, by the cell and converted to H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. Our data support an anion-proton symport model for formic acid transport. In addition, when &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; was grown in a microaerobic environment it was possible to analyse aspects of formate and O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; respiration occurring alongside anaerobic metabolism. While cells growing under microaerobic conditions generated endogenous formic acid, no H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; was produced. However, addition of exogenous formate at the outset of cell growth did induce FHL-1 biosynthesis and resulted in formate-dependent H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; production in the presence of O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475878" rel="alternate" title="Hydrogen production in an aerobic environment by Escherichia coli K-12 (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475941</id><title>Hemagglutinin stability determines influenza A virus susceptibility to a broad-spectrum fusion inhibitor Arbidol (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.372459+00:00</updated><author><name>Li Zhenyu</name></author><author><name>Li Tian</name></author><author><name>Liu Meisui</name></author><author><name>Ivanovic Tijana</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding mechanisms of resistance to antiviral inhibitors can reveal nuanced features of targeted viral mechanisms and, in turn, lead to improved strategies for inhibitor design. Arbidol is a broad-spectrum antiviral which binds to and prevents the fusion-associated conformational changes in the trimeric influenza hemagglutinin (HA). The rate-limiting step during HA-mediated membrane fusion is the release of the hydrophobic fusion peptides from a conserved pocket on HA. Here, we investigated how destabilizing or stabilizing mutations in or near the fusion peptide affect viral sensitivity to Arbidol. The degree of sensitivity was proportional to the extent of fusion peptide stability on the pre-fusion HA: stabilized mutants were more sensitive, and destabilized ones resistant to Arbidol. Single-virion membrane fusion experiments for representative Wild Type and mutant viruses demonstrated that resistance is a direct consequence of fusion-peptide destabilization not dependent on reduced Arbidol binding to HA at neutral pH. Our results support the model whereby the probability of individual HAs extending to engage the target membrane is determined by the composite of two critical forces: a ‘tug’ on the fusion peptide by the extension of the central coiled-coil on HA, and the key interactions stabilizing fusion peptide in the pre-fusion pocket. Arbidol increases the free-energy penalty for coiled-coil extension, but destabilizing mutations decrease the free-energy cost for fusion peptide release, accounting for the observed resistance. Our findings have broad implications for fusion-inhibitor design, viral mechanisms of resistance, and our basic understanding of HA-mediated membrane fusion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475941" rel="alternate" title="Hemagglutinin stability determines influenza A virus susceptibility to a broad-spectrum fusion inhibitor Arbidol (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475671</id><title>Intracellular flow cytometry staining of antibody-secreting cells using phycoerythrin-conjugated antibodies: pitfalls and solutions (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.372539+00:00</updated><author><name>Patrick Renner</name></author><author><name>Michael Crone</name></author><author><name>Matthew Kornas</name></author><author><name>KimAnh T. Pioli</name></author><author><name>Peter D. Pioli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antibody-secreting cells are terminally differentiated B cells that play a critical role in humoral immunity through immunoglobulin secretion along with possessing the potential to be long-lived. It is now appreciated that antibody-secreting cells regulate multiple aspects of biology through the secretion of various cytokines. In this regard, intracellular flow cytometry is a key tool used to assess the presence of intracellular proteins such as cytokines and transcription factors. Here, we showed that the use of phycoerythrin-containing antibody conjugates led to a false interpretation of antibody-secreting cell intracellular protein expression compared to other cell types. This was mainly due to the inappropriate retention of these antibodies specifically within antibody-secreting cells. Furthermore, we demonstrated how to reduce this retention which allowed for a more accurate comparison of intracellular protein expression between antibody-secreting cells and other cell types such as B lymphocytes. Using this methodology, our data revealed that spleen antibody-secreting cells expressed Toll-like receptor 7 as well as the pro-form of the inflammatory cytokine interleukin-1β.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475671" rel="alternate" title="Intracellular flow cytometry staining of antibody-secreting cells using phycoerythrin-conjugated antibodies: pitfalls and solutions (5 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.476537</id><title>Using strain-resolved analysis to identify contamination in metagenomics data (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.372625+00:00</updated><author><name>Yue Clare Lou</name></author><author><name>Jordan Hoff</name></author><author><name>Matthew R. Olm</name></author><author><name>Jacob West-Roberts</name></author><author><name>Spencer Diamond</name></author><author><name>Brian A. Firek</name></author><author><name>Michael J. Morowitz</name></author><author><name>Jillian F. Banfield</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Metagenomics analysis can be negatively impacted by DNA contamination. While external sources of contamination such as DNA extraction kits have been widely reported and investigated, contamination originating within the study itself remains underreported. Here we applied high-resolution strain-resolved analyses to identify contamination in two large-scale clinical metagenomics datasets. By mapping strain sharing to DNA extraction plates, we identified well-to-well contamination in both negative controls and biological samples in one dataset. Such contamination is more likely to occur among samples that are on the same or adjacent columns or rows of the extraction plate than samples that are far apart. Our strain-resolved workflow also reveals the presence of externally derived contamination, primarily in the other dataset. Overall in both datasets, contamination is more significant in samples with lower biomass. Our work demonstrates that genome-resolved strain tracking, with its essentially genome-wide nucleotide-level resolution, can be used to detect contamination in sequencing-based microbiome studies. Our results underscore the value of strain-specific methods to detect contamination and the critical importance of looking for contamination beyond negative and positive controls.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.476537" rel="alternate" title="Using strain-resolved analysis to identify contamination in metagenomics data (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.17.475672</id><title>A deep learning pipeline for segmentation of Proteus mirabilis colony patterns (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.372730+00:00</updated><author><name>Anjali Doshi</name></author><author><name>Marian Shaw</name></author><author><name>Ruxandra Tonea</name></author><author><name>Rosalía Minyety</name></author><author><name>Soonhee Moon</name></author><author><name>Andrew Laine</name></author><author><name>Jia Guo</name></author><author><name>Tal Danino</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The motility mechanisms of microorganisms are critical virulence factors, enabling their spread and survival during infection. Motility is frequently characterized by qualitative analysis of macroscopic colonies, yet the standard quantification method has mainly been limited to manual measurement. Recent studies have applied deep learning for classification and segmentation of specific microbial species in microscopic images, but less work has focused on macroscopic colony analysis. Here, we advance computational tools for analyzing colonies of Proteus mirabilis, a bacterium that produces a macroscopic bullseye-like pattern via periodic swarming, a process implicated in its virulence. We present a dual-task pipeline for segmenting (1) the macroscopic colony including faint outer swarm rings, and (2) internal ring boundaries, unique features of oscillatory swarming. Our convolutional neural network for patch-based colony segmentation and U-Net with a VGG-11 encoder for ring boundary segmentation achieved test Dice scores of 93.28% and 83.24%, respectively. The predicted masks at times improved on the ground truths from our automated annotation algorithms. We demonstrate how application of our pipeline to a typical swarming assay enables ease of colony analysis and precise measurements of more complex pattern features than those which have been historically quantified.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.17.475672" rel="alternate" title="A deep learning pipeline for segmentation of Proteus mirabilis colony patterns (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476327</id><title>CARD9 in Neutrophils Protects from Colitis and Controls Mitochondrial Metabolism and Cell Survival (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.372877+00:00</updated><author><name>Camille Danne</name></author><author><name>Chloe Michaudel</name></author><author><name>Jurate Skerniskyte</name></author><author><name>Julien Planchais</name></author><author><name>Aurelie Magniez</name></author><author><name>Allison Agus</name></author><author><name>Marie-Laure Michel</name></author><author><name>Bruno Lamas</name></author><author><name>Gregory Da-Costa</name></author><author><name>Madeleine Spatz</name></author><author><name>Cyriane Oeuvray</name></author><author><name>Chloe Galbert</name></author><author><name>Maxime Poirier</name></author><author><name>Yazhou Wang</name></author><author><name>Alexia Lapiere</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Rolhion</name></author><author><name>Tatiana Ledent</name></author><author><name>Cedric Pionneau</name></author><author><name>Solenne Chardonnet</name></author><author><name>Floriant Bellvert</name></author><author><name>Edern Cahoreau</name></author><author><name>Amandine Rocher</name></author><author><name>Rafael J Arguello</name></author><author><name>Carole Peyssonnaux</name></author><author><name>Sabine Louis</name></author><author><name>Mathias Lavie-Richard</name></author><author><name>Philippe Langella</name></author><author><name>Jamel El-Benna</name></author><author><name>Benoit Marteyn</name></author><author><name>Harry Sokol</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Objectives: Inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) results from a combination of genetic predisposition, dysbiosis of the gut microbiota and environmental factors, leading to alterations in the gastrointestinal immune response and chronic inflammation. Caspase recruitment domain 9 (Card9), one of the IBD susceptibility genes, has been shown to protect against intestinal inflammation and fungal infection. However, the cell types and mechanisms involved in the CARD9 protective role against inflammation remain unknown. Design: We used dextran sulfate sodium (DSS)-induced and adoptive transfer colitis models in total and conditional CARD9 knock-out mice to uncover which cell types play a role in the CARD9 protective phenotype. The impact of Card9 deletion on neutrophil function was assessed by an in vivo model of fungal infection and various functional assays, including endpoint dilution assay, apoptosis assay by flow cytometry, proteomics and real time bioenergetic profile analysis (Seahorse). Results: Lymphocytes are not intrinsically involved in the CARD9 protective role against colitis. CARD9 expression in neutrophils, but not in epithelial or CD11c+ cells, protects against DSS-induced colitis. In the absence of CARD9, mitochondrial dysfunction in neutrophils leads to their premature death through apoptosis, especially in oxidative environment. The decrease of fonctional neutrophils in tissues could explain the impaired containment of fungi and increased susceptibility to intestinal inflammation. Conclusion: These results provide new insight into the role of CARD9 in neutrophil mitochondrial function and its involvement in intestinal inflammation, paving the way for new therapeutic strategies targeting neutrophils.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476327" rel="alternate" title="CARD9 in Neutrophils Protects from Colitis and Controls Mitochondrial Metabolism and Cell Survival (5 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476151</id><title>Site-specific adaptation mechanisms of an oral pathobiont in the oral and gut mucosae (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.373128+00:00</updated><author><name>Yijie Guo</name></author><author><name>Sho Kitamoto</name></author><author><name>Gustavo Caballero-Flores</name></author><author><name>Daisuke Watanabe</name></author><author><name>Kohei Sugihara</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Núñez</name></author><author><name>Christopher J. Alteri</name></author><author><name>Naohiro Inohara</name></author><author><name>Nobuhiko Kamada</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Periodontal inflammation leads to oral dysbiosis with the expansion of oral pathobionts. Besides the pathogenic role of oral pathobionts during periodontal inflammation, studies have revealed that oral pathobionts contribute to diseases in distant organs beyond the oral mucosa. For example, the oral pathobiont &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella aerogenes&lt;/italic&gt;, which accumulates in the oral mucosa during periodontitis in mice, can exacerbate colitis when it ectopically colonizes the gastrointestinal tract. However, the precise mechanisms by which oral pathobionts establish their colonization in extra-oral mucosal sites remains incompletely understood. We performed high-throughput &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; genetic screening to identify fitness genes required for the adaptation of the oral pathobiont &lt;italic&gt;K. aerogenes&lt;/italic&gt; to different mucosal sites – the oral and gut mucosae – at the steady state and during inflammation. In addition, the global transcriptome of &lt;italic&gt;K. aerogenes&lt;/italic&gt; in different environments was analyzed. We determined that &lt;italic&gt;K. aerogenes&lt;/italic&gt; employs genes related to iron acquisition and chaperone usher pili, which are encoded on a newly identified genomic locus named “locus of colonization in the inflamed gut” (LIG), for adaptation in the gut mucosa, particularly during inflammation. In contrast, the LIG virulence factors are not required for &lt;italic&gt;K. aerogenes&lt;/italic&gt; to adapt to the oral mucosa. Thus, oral pathobionts likely exploit distinct adaptation mechanisms in their ectopically colonized intestinal niche compared to their original niche.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The symbiotic bacterial community evolves uniquely at each body site. However, under certain circumstances, symbionts may disseminate far from their original niche and colonize a site ectopically. It has been reported that oral resident bacteria associated with periodontal disease, namely oral pathobionts, contribute to gastrointestinal diseases, such as inflammatory bowel disease and colorectal cancer, through ectopic colonization of the gut. However, the molecular mechanisms by which oral pathobionts adapt to the gut environment remain largely unexplored. In this study, using a model oral pathobiont &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella aerogenes&lt;/italic&gt;, we screened genes essential for the colonization of the pathobiont at different mucosal sites. We discovered that the oral pathobiont uses distinct virulence mechanisms at two different mucosal sites – the oral and gut mucosae. Understanding the strategies of bacteria localized in ectopic organs may lead to the development of strategies to prevent disease caused by the dissemination of pathogenic oral bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476151" rel="alternate" title="Site-specific adaptation mechanisms of an oral pathobiont in the oral and gut mucosae (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476280</id><title>Bulk and spatially resolved extracellular metabolomics of free-living nitrogen fixation (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.373227+00:00</updated><author><name>Darian Smercina</name></author><author><name>Young-Mo Kim</name></author><author><name>Mary Lipton</name></author><author><name>Dusan Velickovic</name></author><author><name>Kirsten Hofmockel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Soil microorganisms drive ecosystem function, but challenges of scale between microbe and ecosystem hinder our ability to accurately quantify and predictively model the soil microbe-ecosystem function relationship. Quantifying this relationship necessitates studies that systematically characterize multi-omics of soil microorganisms and their activity across sampling scales from spatially resolved to bulk measures, and structural complexity, from liquid pure culture to in situ. To address this need, we cultured two diazotrophic bacteria in liquid and solid media, with and without nitrogen (N) to quantify differences in extracellular metabolites associated with nitrogen fixation under increasing environmental structural complexity. We also quantified extracellular metabolites across sampling scales including bulk sampling via GC-MS analysis and spatially resolved analysis via MALDI mass spectrometry imaging. We found extracellular production of inorganic and organic N during free-living nitrogen fixation activity, highlighting a key mechanism of terrestrial N contributions from this process. Additionally, our results emphasize the need to consider the structural complexity of the environment and spatial scale when quantifying microbial activity. We found differences in metabolite profiles between culture conditions, supporting previous work indicating environmental structure influences microbial function, and across scales, underscoring the need to quantify microbial scale conditions to accurately interpret microbial function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476280" rel="alternate" title="Bulk and spatially resolved extracellular metabolomics of free-living nitrogen fixation (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476098</id><title>Maternally transferred monoclonal antibodies protect neonatal mice from herpes simplex virus-induced mortality and morbidity (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.373294+00:00</updated><author><name>Iara M. Backes</name></author><author><name>Brook K. Byrd</name></author><author><name>Chaya D. Patel</name></author><author><name>Sean A. Taylor</name></author><author><name>Callaghan R. Garland</name></author><author><name>Scott W. MacDonald</name></author><author><name>Alejandro B. Balazs</name></author><author><name>Scott C. Davis</name></author><author><name>Margaret E. Ackerman</name></author><author><name>David A. Leib</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neonatal herpes simplex virus (HSV) infections often result in significant mortality and neurological morbidity despite antiviral drug therapy. Maternally-transferred HSV-specific antibodies reduce the risk of clinically-overt neonatal HSV (nHSV), but this observation has not been translationally applied. Using a neonatal mouse model, we tested the hypothesis that passive transfer of HSV-specific human monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) can prevent mortality and morbidity associated with nHSV. The mAbs were expressed &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; by vectored immunoprophylaxis, or administered &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; following recombinant expression &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. Through these maternally-derived routes or through direct administration to pups, diverse mAbs to HSV glycoprotein D protected against neonatal HSV-1 and HSV-2 infection. Using &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; bioluminescent imaging, both pre- and post-exposure mAb treatment significantly reduced viral load. Administration of mAb also reduced nHSV-induced behavioral morbidity, as measured by anxiety-like behavior. Together these studies support the notion that HSV-specific mAb-based therapies may prevent or improve HSV infection outcomes in neonates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="476098v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Different antibody sources were used to maternally-transfer or directly administer HSV-specific mAbs to mouse pups. Neonatal mice were challenged with wild type or bioluminescent virus before or after mAb acquisition. Following infection, pups were assessed for survival, virus-induced bioluminescence and anxiety-like behavior as a measure of neurological morbidity. Efficacy was time and mAb dependent. Notably, all HSV-specific mAbs prevented nHSV-associated mortality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476098" rel="alternate" title="Maternally transferred monoclonal antibodies protect neonatal mice from herpes simplex virus-induced mortality and morbidity (5 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475769</id><title>Efficient inactivation of African swine fever virus by a highly complexed iodine combined with compound organic acids (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.373378+00:00</updated><author><name>Mengnan Qi</name></author><author><name>Li Pan</name></author><author><name>Ying Gao</name></author><author><name>Miao Li</name></author><author><name>Yanjin Wang</name></author><author><name>Lian-Feng Li</name></author><author><name>Chen Ji</name></author><author><name>Yuan Sun</name></author><author><name>Hua-Ji Qiu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;African swine fever (ASF) is a highly contagious disease with high morbidity and mortality caused by African swine fever virus (ASFV). Cleaning and disinfection remain one of the most effective biosecurity measures to prevent and control the spread of ASFV. In this study, we evaluated the inactivation effects of highly complexed iodine (HPCI) combined with compound organic acids (COAs) against ASFV under different conditions. The results showed that the inactivation rates of the disinfectants on the reporter ASFV increased in dose- and time-dependent manners, the best inactivation effects were obtained when the compatibility ratio of HPCI and COAs was 5:1 at 25°C. Furthermore, there were no significant differences by comparing the efficacy of HPCI combined with COAs (HPCI+COAs) in inactivating wild-type ASFV and the reporter ASFV (&lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt; &amp;gt; 0.05). ASFV of 10&lt;sup&gt;4.0&lt;/sup&gt; TCID&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;/mL was completely inactivated by 0.13% HPCI (0.0065% effective iodine), 0.06% COAs or 0.13% HPCI+COAs (approximately 0.0054% effective iodine), respectively, while 10&lt;sup&gt;6.0&lt;/sup&gt; TCID&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;/mL ASFV was completely inactivated by 1.00% HPCI (0.05% effective iodine), 0.50% COAs or 1.00% HPCI+COAs (0.042% effective iodine), respectively. Therefore, HPCI+COAs had synergistic effects to inactivate ASFV. This study demonstrated that HPCI+COAs could rapidly and efficiently inactivate ASFV and represent an effective compound disinfectant for the control of ASF.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;African swine fever (ASF) is a highly contagious disease with high morbidity and mortality caused by African swine fever virus (ASFV). Due to the lack of commercial vaccines and treatment available for ASF, effective disinfectants and the proper use of them are extremely essential to inactivate ASFV. The significance of this research is in searching for an ideal disinfectant that not only has the advantages of low toxicity and non-pollution but also can inactivate ASFV rapidly and efficiently. In this study, we proved that HPCI+COAs not only exhibited low cytotoxicity, but also could completely inactivate ASFV within 5 min at 4°C, 25°C and 37°C. In addition, HPCI+COAs had synergistic effects on inactivated ASFV. Thus, HPCI +COAs could be used as an effective disinfectant for the control of ASF.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475769" rel="alternate" title="Efficient inactivation of African swine fever virus by a highly complexed iodine combined with compound organic acids (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475751</id><title>Type I IFN promotes pathogenic inflammatory monocyte maturation during H5N1 infection (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.373458+00:00</updated><author><name>Slim Fourati</name></author><author><name>David Jimenez-Morales</name></author><author><name>Judd Hultquist</name></author><author><name>Max W. Chang</name></author><author><name>Christopher Benner</name></author><author><name>Nevan Krogan</name></author><author><name>Lars Pache</name></author><author><name>Sumit Chanda</name></author><author><name>Rafick-Pierre Sekaly</name></author><author><name>Adolfo García-Sastre</name></author><author><name>Melissa B. Uccellini</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ly6C&lt;sup&gt;hi&lt;/sup&gt; inflammatory monocytes show high IFN responses, and contribute to both protective and pathogenic functions following influenza virus infection. In order to understand the significance of IFN responses in this subset, we examined monocytes during infection with a lethal H5N1 virus that induces high levels of IFN and a low-pathogenicity H1N1 virus that induces low levels of IFN. We show that H5N1 infection results in early recruitment of high numbers of Ly6C&lt;sup&gt;hi&lt;/sup&gt; monocytes and induction of chemokines and &lt;italic&gt;Ifnb1&lt;/italic&gt;. Using unbiased transcriptomic and proteomic approaches, we also find that monocytes are significantly enriched during H5N1 infection and are associated with chemokine and IFN signatures in mice, and with severity of symptoms after influenza virus infection in humans. Recruited Ly6C&lt;sup&gt;hi&lt;/sup&gt; monocytes subsequently become infected in the lung, produce IFN-β, and mature into FasL&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; monocyte-derived cells (FasL&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;MCs) expressing dendritic cell markers. Both &lt;italic&gt;Ccr2&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Fasl&lt;sup&gt;gld&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice are protected from lethal infection, indicating that monocytes contribute to pathogenesis. Global loss of type I and type III IFN signaling in &lt;italic&gt;Stat2&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice results in loss of monocyte recruitment, likely reflecting a requirement for IFN-dependent chemokine induction. Here we show that IFN is not directly required for monocyte recruitment on an IFN-sufficient background, but is required for maturation to FasL&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;MCs. Loss of IFN signaling skews to a Ly6C&lt;sup&gt;lo&lt;/sup&gt; phenotype associated with tissue repair, suggesting that IFN signaling in monocytes is a critical determinant of influenza virus pathogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475751" rel="alternate" title="Type I IFN promotes pathogenic inflammatory monocyte maturation during H5N1 infection (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476144</id><title>Bifidobacterium longum attenuates ovariectomy-induced bone loss via modulating the Immunoporotic “Breg-Treg-Th17” cell axis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.373551+00:00</updated><author><name>Leena Sapra</name></author><author><name>Niti Shokeen</name></author><author><name>Konica Gupta</name></author><author><name>Chaman Saini</name></author><author><name>Asha Bhardwaj</name></author><author><name>Mary Mathew</name></author><author><name>Pradyumna K. Mishra</name></author><author><name>Naibedya Chattopadhyay</name></author><author><name>Bhupendra Verma</name></author><author><name>Rupesh K. Srivastava</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Discoveries in the last few years have emphasized the existence of an enormous breadth of communication between osteo-immune system. These discoveries fuel novel approaches for the treatment of several bone-pathologies including osteoporosis, an inflammatory bone anomaly affecting more than 500 million people globally. &lt;italic&gt;Bifidobacterium longum&lt;/italic&gt; (BL) is preferred probiotic of choice due to its varied immunomodulatory potential in alleviating various inflammatory diseases. Here, we evaluate the effect of BL in ovariectomy (ovx)-induced post-menopausal osteoporotic mice model. Our in vitro findings reveal that BL suppresses the differentiation and functional activity of RANKL-induced osteoclastogenesis in both mouse bone marrow cells and human PBMCs. Our in vivo data clearly establish that BL exhibits osteoprotective potential via modulating the “immunoporotic” Breg-Treg-Th17 cell-axis. Furthermore, µCT and bone mechanical strength data support that BL supplementation significantly enhanced bone mass and strength, and improved microarchitecture in ovx mice. Remarkably, alteration in frequencies of CD19&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;CD1d&lt;sup&gt;hi&lt;/sup&gt;CD5&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; Bregs, CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;Foxp3&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;IL-10&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; Tregs, and CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;Rorγt&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;IL-17&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; Th17 immune cells in distinct lymphoid organs along with serum-cytokine data (enhanced anti-osteoclastogenic cytokines IFN-γ and IL-10 and reduced osteoclastogenic-cytokines IL-6, IL-17, and TNF-α) strongly support the immunomodulatory potential of BL. Altogether our findings establish a novel osteo-protective and immunoporotic potential of BL in augmenting bone health under osteoporotic conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476144" rel="alternate" title="Bifidobacterium longum attenuates ovariectomy-induced bone loss via modulating the Immunoporotic “Breg-Treg-Th17” cell axis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476215</id><title>B cells discriminate HIV-1 Envelope protein affinities by sensing antigen binding association rates (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.373636+00:00</updated><author><name>Md. Alamgir Hossain</name></author><author><name>Kara Anasti</name></author><author><name>Brian Watts</name></author><author><name>Kenneth Cronin</name></author><author><name>Advaiti Pai Kane</name></author><author><name>Robert J Edwards</name></author><author><name>David Easterhoff</name></author><author><name>Jinsong Zhang</name></author><author><name>Wes Rountree</name></author><author><name>Yaneth Ortiz</name></author><author><name>Laurent Verkoczy</name></author><author><name>Michael Reth</name></author><author><name>S. Munir Alam</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;HIV-1 Envelope (Env) proteins designed to induce neutralizing antibody responses allow study of the role of affinities (equilibrium dissociation constant, KD) and kinetic rates (association/dissociation rates) on B cell antigen recognition. It is unclear whether affinity discrimination during B cell activation is based solely on Env protein binding KD, and whether B cells discriminate between proteins of similar affinities but that bind with different kinetic rates. Here we used a panel of Env proteins and Ramos B cell lines expressing IgM BCRs with specificity for CD4 binding-site broadly neutralizing (bnAb) or a precursor antibody to study the role of antigen binding kinetic rates on both early (proximal/distal signaling) and late events (BCR/antigen internalization) in B cell activation. Our results support a kinetic model for B cell activation in which Env protein affinity discrimination is based not on overall KD, but on sensing of association rate and a threshold antigen-BCR half-life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476215" rel="alternate" title="B cells discriminate HIV-1 Envelope protein affinities by sensing antigen binding association rates (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476188</id><title>Environmental factors shape the culturable bacterial diversity in deep-sea water and surface sediments from the Mariana Trench (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.373732+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuewei Ma</name></author><author><name>Wenmian Ding</name></author><author><name>Yuepeng Wang</name></author><author><name>Ping Chen</name></author><author><name>Hui Zhou</name></author><author><name>Xuan Li</name></author><author><name>Yanyan Huang</name></author><author><name>Peng Nan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hailed as “The Fourth Pole”, the Mariana Trench is the deepest part of the ocean. The microbial diversity in it is extremely complicated, which might be caused by the unique environmental factors such as high salinity, low temperature, high hydrostatic pressure, and limited nutrition. Based on 4 seawater samples and 4 sediment samples obtained from the Mariana Trench, we isolated and fostered the microorganism clones with kinds of culture mediums and high-throughput culturing. By using the molecular identification methods based on PCR of 16S rDNA and ITS gene, 1266 bacterial strains in total were isolated and identified, which affiliated to 7 classes, 16 orders, 25 families and 36 genera in four phyla : Proteobacteria, Firmicutes, Actinobacteria and Bacteroidetes. Strains in genera &lt;italic&gt;Halomonas, Pseudoaltermonas&lt;/italic&gt; were the dominant bacteria isolated from the samples. With Mantel tests on the sample-environmental parameter matrix, the sample-environmental organic matter diversity matrix and the sample-microbial diversity matrix, we concluded that the environmental parameters and the organic matters in the condition can shape the culturable bacterial diversity in deep-sea water and surface sediments from the Mariana Trench.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476188" rel="alternate" title="Environmental factors shape the culturable bacterial diversity in deep-sea water and surface sediments from the Mariana Trench (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.476546</id><title>Conserved Untranslated Regions of Multipartite Viruses: Natural Markers of Novel Viral Genomic Components and Tags of Viral Evolution (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.373813+00:00</updated><author><name>Song Zhang</name></author><author><name>Caixia Yang</name></author><author><name>Jiaxing Wu</name></author><author><name>Yuanjian Qiu</name></author><author><name>Zhiyou Xuan</name></author><author><name>Liu Yang</name></author><author><name>Ruiling Liao</name></author><author><name>Xiaofei Liang</name></author><author><name>Haodong Yu</name></author><author><name>Fang Ren</name></author><author><name>Yafeng Dong</name></author><author><name>Xiaoying Xie</name></author><author><name>Yanhong Han</name></author><author><name>Di Wu</name></author><author><name>Pedro Luis Ramos-González</name></author><author><name>Juliana Freitas-Astúa</name></author><author><name>Changyong Zhou</name></author><author><name>Mengji Cao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Viruses with split genomes are categorized as being either segmented or multipartite according to whether their genomic segments occur in single or different virions. Some complexity will exist, in that inherited “core” vital segments viruses may renew the others once host and environmental alterations keep driving viral evolution. Despite this uncertainty, empirical observations have been made across the split genomes in the untranslated regions (UTRs) on the short or long stretches of conserved or identical sequences. In this study, we describe a methodology that combines RNA and small RNA sequencing, conventional BLASTx, and iterative BLASTn of UTRs to detect viral genomic components even if they encode orphan genes (ORFans). Within the phylum Kitrinoviricota, novel putative multipartite viruses and viral genomic components were annotated using data obtained from our sampling or publicly available sources. The novel viruses, as extensions or intermediate nodes, enriched the information of the evolutionary networks. Furthermore, the diversity of novel genomic components emphasized the evolutionary roles of reassortment and recombination, as well as genetic deletion, strongly supporting the genomic complexity. These data also suggest insufficient knowledge of these genomic components for categorizing some extant viral taxa. The relative conservation of UTRs at the genome level may explain the relationships between monopartite and multipartite viruses and how the multipartite viruses can have a life strategy involving multiple host cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.476546" rel="alternate" title="Conserved Untranslated Regions of Multipartite Viruses: Natural Markers of Novel Viral Genomic Components and Tags of Viral Evolution (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476417</id><title>Dickeya colocasiae sp. nov. isolated from wetland taro, Colocasia esculentum (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.373923+00:00</updated><author><name>Gamze Boluk</name></author><author><name>Shefali Dobhal</name></author><author><name>Dario Arizala</name></author><author><name>Anne M. Alvarez</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Arif</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial pathogens identified as Dickeya sp. have recently been associated with a corm rot of wetland taro on Oahu, Hawaii, but the species designation of these strains was unclear.  A Gram-negative, pectinolytic bacterial strain PL65T isolated from an infected taro corm was subjected to polyphasic analysis to determine its genomic and phenotypic characteristics. Multi-locus sequence analyses (MLSA) based on five housekeeping genes (dnaA, gapA, gyrB, atpD, and purA) revealed that Dickeya zeae and D. oryzae, were the closest relatives. Phylogenetic analysis based on 463 core gene sequences clearly showed two potentially new species within Dickeya oryzae. In silico DNA-DNA hybridization value of strain PL65T with 12 Type strains of Dickeya species was &amp;lt;68%. Average nucleotide identity (ANI) analysis revealed that PL65T was at the margin of the species delineation cut-off values with a 96% ANI value. The metabolic profile of strain PL65T using BIOLOG differentiated it from the type strains of all other known species of Dickeya. Based on the results of genome-to-genome comparisons and phenotypic data presented in this report, we propose establishment of a new species, Dickeya colocasiae sp. nov.   with strain PL65T as the type strain (ICMP 24361T).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476417" rel="alternate" title="Dickeya colocasiae sp. nov. isolated from wetland taro, Colocasia esculentum (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476391</id><title>Microbiomes of hadal fishes contain similar taxa, obligate symbionts, and known piezophiles across trench habitats (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.373995+00:00</updated><author><name>Jessica M Blanton</name></author><author><name>Logan M Peoples</name></author><author><name>Mackenzie E Gerringer</name></author><author><name>Caroline M Iacuniello</name></author><author><name>Natalya D Gallo</name></author><author><name>Thomas D Linley</name></author><author><name>Alan J Jamieson</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey C Drazen</name></author><author><name>Douglas H Bartlett</name></author><author><name>Eric E Allen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hadal snailfishes are the deepest-living fishes in the ocean, inhabiting trenches from depths of ~6,000 to 8,000 m. While the microbial communities in trench environments have begun to be characterized, the microbes associated with hadal megafauna remain relatively unknown. Here, we describe the gut microbiomes of two hadal snailfishes, &lt;italic&gt;Pseudoliparis swirei&lt;/italic&gt; (Mariana Trench) and &lt;italic&gt;Notoliparis kermadecensis&lt;/italic&gt; (Kermadec Trench) using 16S rRNA gene amplicon sequencing. We contextualize these microbiomes with comparisons to the abyssal macrourid &lt;italic&gt;Coryphaenoides yaquinae&lt;/italic&gt; and the continental shelf-dwelling snailfish &lt;italic&gt;Careproctus melanurus&lt;/italic&gt;. The microbial communities of the hadal snailfishes were distinct from their shallower counterparts and were dominated by the same sequences related to the Mycoplasmataceae and Desulfovibrionaceae. These shared taxa indicate that symbiont lineages may have remained similar to the ancestral symbiont since their geographic separation or that they are dispersed between geographically distant trenches and subsequently colonize specific hosts. The abyssal and hadal fishes contained sequences related to known, cultured piezophiles, microbes that grow optimally under high hydrostatic pressure, including &lt;italic&gt;Psychromonas&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;Moritella&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;Shewanella&lt;/italic&gt;. These taxa are adept at colonizing nutrient-rich environments present in the deep ocean, such as on particles and in the guts of hosts, and we hypothesize they could make a dietary contribution to deep-sea fishes by degrading chitin and producing fatty acids. We characterize the gut microbiota within some of the deepest fishes to provide new insight into the diversity and distribution of host-associated microbial taxa and the potential of these animals, and the microbes they harbor, for understanding adaptation to deep-sea habitats.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476391" rel="alternate" title="Microbiomes of hadal fishes contain similar taxa, obligate symbionts, and known piezophiles across trench habitats (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476281</id><title>The bladder microbiome, metabolome, cytokines, and phenotypes in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.374080+00:00</updated><author><name>Fengping Liu</name></author><author><name>Jingjie Du</name></author><author><name>Qixiao Zhai</name></author><author><name>Jialin Hu</name></author><author><name>Aaron W. Miller</name></author><author><name>Tianli Ren</name></author><author><name>Yangkun Feng</name></author><author><name>Peng Jiang</name></author><author><name>Lei Hu</name></author><author><name>Jiayi Sheng</name></author><author><name>Chaoqun Gu</name></author><author><name>Ren Yan</name></author><author><name>Longxian Lv</name></author><author><name>Alan J. Wolfe</name></author><author><name>Ninghan Feng</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background and aims&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Emerging studies reveal a unique bacterial community in the human bladder, with alteration of composition associated to disease states. Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) is a complex autoimmune disease that is characterized by frequent impairment of the kidney. Here, we explored the bladder microbiome, metabolome, and cytokine profiles in SLE patients, as well as correlations between microbiome and metabolome, cytokines, and disease profiles.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods and materials&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We recruited a cohort of 50 SLE patients and 50 individually matched asymptomatic controls. We used transurethral catheterization to collect urine samples, 16S rRNA gene sequencing to profile bladder microbiomes, and LC-MS/MS to perform untargeted metabolomic profiling.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compared to controls, SLE patients possessed a unique bladder microbial community and increased alpha diversity. These differences were accompanied by differences in urinary metabolomes, cytokines, and patients’ disease profiles. The SLE-enriched genera, including &lt;italic&gt;Bacteroides&lt;/italic&gt;, were positively correlated with several SLE-enriched metabolites, including olopatadine. The SLE-depleted genera, such as &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/italic&gt;, were negatively correlated to SLE-depleted cytokines, including IL-8. Alteration of the bladder microbiome was associated with disease profile. For example, the genera &lt;italic&gt;Megamonas&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Phocaeicola&lt;/italic&gt; were negatively correlated with serum complement C3, and &lt;italic&gt;Streptococcus&lt;/italic&gt; was positively correlated with IgG.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our present study reveals associations between the bladder microbiome and the urinary metabolome, cytokines, and disease phenotypes. Our results could help identify biomarkers for SLE.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476281" rel="alternate" title="The bladder microbiome, metabolome, cytokines, and phenotypes in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.475644</id><title>The C-terminal domain of SEC-10 is fundamental for exocyst function, Spitzenkörper organization and cell morphogenesis in Neurospora crassa (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.374177+00:00</updated><author><name>Alfredo Figueroa-Meléndez</name></author><author><name>Leonora Martínez-Núñez</name></author><author><name>Adriana M. Rico-Ramírez</name></author><author><name>Juan M. Martínez-Andrade</name></author><author><name>Mary Munson</name></author><author><name>Meritxell Riquelme</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The exocyst is a conserved multimeric complex that participates in the final steps of the secretion of vesicles. In the filamentous fungus &lt;italic&gt;Neurospora crassa,&lt;/italic&gt; the exocyst is crucial for polar growth, morphology, and the organization of the Spitzenkörper (Spk), the apical body where secretory vesicles accumulate before being delivered to the plasma membrane. In the highly polarized cells of &lt;italic&gt;N. crassa,&lt;/italic&gt; the exocyst subunits SEC-3, SEC-5, SEC-6, SEC-8, and SEC-15 were previously found localized at the plasma membrane of the cells’ apices, while EXO-70 and EXO-84 occupied the frontal outer layer of the Spk, occupied by vesicles. The localization of SEC-10 had remained so far elusive. In this work, SEC-10 was tagged with the green fluorescent protein (GFP) either at its N- or C-terminus and found localized at the plasma membrane of growing hyphal tips, similar to what was previously observed for some exocyst subunits. While expression of an N-terminally tagged version of SEC-10 at its native locus was fully viable, expression of a C-terminally tagged version at its native locus resulted in severe hyphal growth and polarity defects. Additionally, a &lt;italic&gt;sec-10&lt;/italic&gt; knockout mutant in a heterokaryotic state (with genetically different nuclei) was viable but showed a strongly aberrant phenotype, confirming that this subunit is essential to maintain hyphal morphogenesis. Transmission electron microscopy analysis revealed the lack of a Spk in the SEC-10-GFP strain, suggesting a critical role of the exocyst in the vesicular organization at the Spk. Mass spectrometry analysis revealed fewer peptides of exocyst subunits interacting with SEC-10-GFP than with GFP-SEC-10, suggesting an essential role of the C-terminus of SEC-10 in exocyst assembly and/or stability. Altogether, our data suggest that an unobstructed C-terminus of SEC-10 is indispensable for the exocyst complex function and that a GFP tag could be blocking important subunit-subunit interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.475644" rel="alternate" title="The C-terminal domain of SEC-10 is fundamental for exocyst function, Spitzenkörper organization and cell morphogenesis in Neurospora crassa (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475845</id><title>Differentiation of a CD4+/CD8αβ+ Double Positive T Cell Population From The CD8 Pool Is Sufficient To Mediate Graft-vs-Host Disease but not Graft-vs-Leukemia Effects (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.374248+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas J. Hess</name></author><author><name>David P. Turicek</name></author><author><name>Kalyan Nadiminti</name></author><author><name>Amy Hudson</name></author><author><name>Peiman Hematti</name></author><author><name>Jenny E. Gumperz</name></author><author><name>Christian M. Capitini</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Acute graft-vs-host disease (aGVHD) and tumor relapse remain the primary complications following allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (allo-HSCT) for malignant blood disorders. While post-transplant cyclophosphamide has reduced the overall prevalence and severity of aGVHD, relapse rates remain a concern. Thus, there remains a need to identify the specific human T cell subsets mediating GVHD pathology versus graft-versus-leukemia (GVL) effects. In xenogeneic transplantation studies using primary human cells from a variety of donors and tissue sources, we observed the development of a mature CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;/CD8αβ&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; double positive T cell (DPT) population in mice succumbing to lethal aGVHD but not in mice that failed to develop aGVHD. The presence of DPT, irrespective of graft source, was predictive of lethal GVHD as early as one week after xenogeneic transplantation. DPT co-express the master transcription factors of the CD8 and CD4 lineages, RUNX3 and THPOK respectively, and produce both cytotoxic and modulatory cytokines. To identify the origin of DPT, we transplanted isolated human CD4 or CD8 T cells, which in turn revealed that DPT only arise from the CD8 pool. Interestingly, re-transplantation of sorted CD8 T cells from GVHD mice did not reveal a second wave of DPT differentiation. Re-transplantation of flow-sorted DPT, CD8 or CD4 T cells from GVHD mice revealed that DPT are sufficient to mediate GVHD pathology but not GVL effects versus B-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Lastly, we confirmed the presence and correlation of DPT with aGVHD pathology in a small cohort of allo-HSCT patients that developed grade 2-4 aGVHD in our clinic. Further understanding of DPT differentiation and pathology may lead to targeted prophylaxis and/or treatment regimens for aGVHD and potentially other human chronic inflammatory diseases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key Points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Human DPT cell differentiation is a predictive metric of xenogeneic GVHD lethality&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The origin of DPT are CD8 T cells that gain THPOK expression and CD4 lineage effector functions&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;DPT cells are sufficient to mediate GVHD pathology but not GVL effects&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Visual Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="475845v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475845" rel="alternate" title="Differentiation of a CD4+/CD8αβ+ Double Positive T Cell Population From The CD8 Pool Is Sufficient To Mediate Graft-vs-Host Disease but not Graft-vs-Leukemia Effects (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476461</id><title>Culture and genomic analysis of Symbiopectobacterium purcellii, gen.nov. sp. nov., isolated from the leafhopper Empoasca decipiens (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.374319+00:00</updated><author><name>Pol Nadal-Jimenez</name></author><author><name>Stefanos Siozios</name></author><author><name>Nigel Halliday</name></author><author><name>Miguel Camara</name></author><author><name>Greg D.D. Hurst</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial endosymbionts are found in multiple arthropod species, where they play crucial roles as nutritional symbionts, defensive symbionts or reproductive parasites. Recent work has highlighted a new clade of heritable microbes within the gammaproteobacteria that enter into both obligate and facultative symbioses, with an obligately required unculturable symbiont recently given the name Cand. Symbiopectobacterium. In this study, we describe a culturable rod shaped non-flagellated bacterial symbiont from this clade isolated from the leafhopper Empoasca decipiens. The symbiont is related to the transovarially-transmitted 'BEV' bacterium that was first isolated from the leafhopper Euscelidius variegatus by Alexander Purcell, and we therefore name the symbiont Symbiopectobacterium purcellii sp. nov. gen. nov. We further report the closed genome sequence for S. purcellii. The genome is atypical for a heritable microbe, being large in size, without profound AT bias and with little evidence of pseudogenization. The genome is predicted to encode Type II, III and VI secretion systems and associated effectors and a non-ribosomal peptide synthase array likely to produce bioactive small molecules. Predicted metabolism is more complete than for other symbionts in the Symbiopectobacterium clade, and the microbe is predicted to synthesize a range of B vitamins. However, Biolog plate analysis indicate metabolism is depauperate compared to the sister clade, represented by Pectobacterium carotovorum. A quorum-sensing pathway related to that of Pectobacterium spp. (containing an overlapping expI-expR1 pair in opposite directions and a "solo" expR2) is evidenced, and LC-MS/MS analysis reveals the presence of 3-hydroxy-C10-HSL as the sole N-acylhomoserine lactone (AHL) in our strain. This AHL profile is profoundly divergent from that of other Erwinia and Pectobacterium spp., which produce mostly 3-oxo-C6- and 3-oxo-C8-HSL and could aid group identification. Thus, this microbe denotes one that has lost certain pathways associated with a saprophytic lifestyle but represents an important baseline against which to compare other members of the genus Symbiopectobacterium that show more profound integration into host biology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476461" rel="alternate" title="Culture and genomic analysis of Symbiopectobacterium purcellii, gen.nov. sp. nov., isolated from the leafhopper Empoasca decipiens (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475974</id><title>A Longitudinal Study of Dominant E. coli Lineages and Antimicrobial Resistance in the Gut of Children Living in an Upper Middle-income Country (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.374383+00:00</updated><author><name>Diana Calderón</name></author><author><name>Paúl A. Cárdenas</name></author><author><name>Belen Prado</name></author><author><name>Jay P. Graham</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Trueba</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The gastrointestinal tract constitutes a complex and diverse ecosystem. &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; is one of the most frequently studied and characterized species in the gut ecosystem, nevertheless, there has been little research to determine their diversity and population dynamics in the intestines of children over time. In this prospective study, a fresh fecal sample was obtained from children longitudinally over one year (30 fecal samples at sampling period 1 and 22 fecal samples at sampling periods 2 and 3). From each stool sample, five &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; colonies were randomly selected (n = 405 &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; isolates total) in order to characterize the genotype and phenotypic antimicrobial resistance patterns. We found that all numerically dominant &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; lineages in children’s intestines were transient colonizers, and antimicrobial resistance phenotypes of these strains varied significantly over time without any apparent selective force. Whole-genome sequencing of 3 isolates belonging to ST131 found in one child during the sampling period I and II indicated that isolates were three different ST 131 clones that carried extended-spectrum β-lactamase (ESBL) genes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The length of residency and numeric dominance of antimicrobial-resistant &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; may affect the extent to which an isolate contributes to the dissemination of antimicrobial resistance in a community. We studied the persistence of numerically dominant and antimicrobial-resistant lineages of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; in the human intestine. We found that &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; lineages in the children's gut change considerably and rapidly over time. This study suggests that some phenotypic resistance patterns may result from the random distribution of genes in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; populations over time and may not be associated with differential exposure to antimicrobials.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475974" rel="alternate" title="A Longitudinal Study of Dominant E. coli Lineages and Antimicrobial Resistance in the Gut of Children Living in an Upper Middle-income Country (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>