<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.633275+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453184</id><title>The dual nature of bacteriophage: growth-dependent predation and generalised transduction of antimicrobial resistance (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.634153+00:00</updated><author><name>Quentin J Leclerc</name></author><author><name>Jacob Wildfire</name></author><author><name>Arya Gupta</name></author><author><name>Jodi A Lindsay</name></author><author><name>Gwenan M Knight</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacteriophage ("phage") are both predators and evolutionary drivers for bacteria, notably contributing to the spread of antimicrobial resistance (AMR) genes by generalised transduction. Our current understanding of the dual nature of this relationship is limited. We used an interdisciplinary approach to quantify how these interacting dynamics can lead to the evolution of multi-drug resistant bacteria. We co-cultured two strains of Methicillin-resistant &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/italic&gt;, each harbouring a different antibiotic resistance gene, with 80α generalized transducing phage. After a growth phase of 8h, bacteria and phage surprisingly coexisted at a stable equilibrium in our culture, the level of which was dependent on the starting concentration of phage. We detected double-resistant bacteria as early as 7h, indicating that transduction of AMR genes had occurred. We developed multiple mathematical models of the bacteria and phage relationship, and found that phage-bacteria dynamics were best captured by a model in which the phage burst size decreases as the bacteria population reaches stationary phase, and where phage predation is frequency-dependent. We estimated that one in every 10&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt; new phage generated was a transducing phage carrying an AMR gene, and that double-resistant bacteria were always predominantly generated by transduction rather than by growth. Our results suggest a fundamental shift in how we understand and model phage-bacteria dynamics. Although rates of generalised transduction may seem insignificant, they are sufficient to consistently lead to the evolution of multi-drug resistant bacteria. Currently, the potential of phage to contribute to the growing burden of AMR is likely underestimated.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453184" rel="alternate" title="The dual nature of bacteriophage: growth-dependent predation and generalised transduction of antimicrobial resistance (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453610</id><title>Adapted protocol for Saccharibacteria co-cultivation: two new members join the club of Candidate Phyla radiation (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.635167+00:00</updated><author><name>Ahmad Ibrahim</name></author><author><name>Mohamad Maatouk</name></author><author><name>Andreamiharimamy Rajaonison</name></author><author><name>Rita Zgheib</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Haddad</name></author><author><name>Jacques Yaacoub Bou Khalil</name></author><author><name>Didier Raoult</name></author><author><name>Fadi Bittar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The growing application of metagenomics to different ecological and microbiome niches in recent years has enhanced our knowledge of global microbial biodiversity. Among these abundant and widespread microbes, Candidate Phyla Radiation or CPR have been recognised as representing a large proportion of the microbial kingdom (&amp;gt; 26%). CPR are characterised by their obligate symbiotic or exo-parasitic activity with other microbial hosts, mainly bacteria. Currently, isolating CPR is still considered challenging for microbiologists. The idea of this study was to develop an adapted protocol for the co-culture of CPR with a suitable bacterial host. Based on various sputa, we tried to purify CPR (Saccharibacteria members) and to cultivate them with pure hosts. This protocol was monitored by real-time PCR quantification using a specific system for Saccharibacteria designed in this study, as well as by electron microscopy and sequencing. We succeeded in co-culturing and sequencing a complete genome of two new Saccharibacteria species: Candidatus Minimicrobia naudis and Candidatus Minimicrobia vallesae. In addition, we noticed a decrease in the Ct number of Saccharibacteria, and a significant multiplication through their physical association with Schaalia odontolytica strains in the enriched medium that we developed. This work may help bridge gaps in the genomic database by providing new CPR members and, in the future, their currently unknown characteristics may be revealed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453610" rel="alternate" title="Adapted protocol for Saccharibacteria co-cultivation: two new members join the club of Candidate Phyla radiation (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>