<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.148431+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.459620</id><title>Variant surface glycoprotein expression in human African trypanosomiasis patients (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.148751+00:00</updated><author><name>Jaime So</name></author><author><name>Sarah Sudlow</name></author><author><name>Abeer Sayeed</name></author><author><name>Tanner Grudda</name></author><author><name>Stijn Deborggraeve</name></author><author><name>Dieudonné Mumba Ngoyi</name></author><author><name>Didier Kashiama Desamber</name></author><author><name>Bill Wickstead</name></author><author><name>Veerle Lejon</name></author><author><name>Monica R. Mugnier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Trypanosoma brucei gambiense&lt;/italic&gt;, an extracellular protozoan parasite, is the primary causative agent of human African Trypanosomiasis. &lt;italic&gt;T. b. gambiense&lt;/italic&gt; is endemic to West and Central Africa where it is transmitted by the bite of infected tsetse flies. In the bloodstream of an infected host, the parasite evades antibody recognition by altering the Variant Surface Glycoprotein (VSG) that forms a dense coat on its cell surface through a process known as antigenic variation. Each VSG has a variable N-terminal domain that is exposed to the host and a less variable C-terminal domain that is at least partially hidden from host antibodies. Our lab developed VSG-seq, a targeted RNA-seq method, to study &lt;italic&gt;VSG&lt;/italic&gt; expression in &lt;italic&gt;T. brucei&lt;/italic&gt;. Studies using VSG-seq to characterize antigenic variation in a mouse model have revealed marked diversity in &lt;italic&gt;VSG&lt;/italic&gt; expression within parasite populations, but this finding has not yet been validated in a natural human infection. Here, we used VSG-seq to analyze &lt;italic&gt;VSGs&lt;/italic&gt; expressed in the blood of twelve patients infected with &lt;italic&gt;T. b. gambiense&lt;/italic&gt;. The number of &lt;italic&gt;VSGs&lt;/italic&gt; identified per patient ranged from one to fourteen and, notably, two &lt;italic&gt;VSGs&lt;/italic&gt; were shared by more than one patient. Analysis of expressed &lt;italic&gt;VSG&lt;/italic&gt; N-terminal domain types revealed that 82% of expressed &lt;italic&gt;VSGs&lt;/italic&gt; encoded a type B N-terminus, a bias not seen in datasets from other &lt;italic&gt;T. brucei&lt;/italic&gt; subspecies. C-terminal types in &lt;italic&gt;T. b. gambiense&lt;/italic&gt; infection were also restricted. These results demonstrate a bias either in the underlying &lt;italic&gt;VSG&lt;/italic&gt; repertoire of &lt;italic&gt;T. b. gambiense&lt;/italic&gt; or in the selection of &lt;italic&gt;VSGs&lt;/italic&gt; from the repertoire during infection. This work demonstrates the feasibility of using VSG-seq to study antigenic variation in human infections and highlights the importance of understanding &lt;italic&gt;VSG&lt;/italic&gt; repertoires in the field.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Human African Trypanosomiasis is a neglected tropical disease largely caused by the extracellular parasite known as &lt;italic&gt;Trypanosoma brucei gambiense&lt;/italic&gt;. To avoid elimination by the host, these parasites repeatedly replace their dense surface coat of Variant Surface Glycoprotein (VSG). Despite the important role of VSGs in prolonging infection, &lt;italic&gt;VSG&lt;/italic&gt; expression during natural human infections is poorly understood. A better understanding of natural &lt;italic&gt;VSG&lt;/italic&gt; expression dynamics can clarify the mechanisms which &lt;italic&gt;T. brucei&lt;/italic&gt; uses to alter its VSG coat and improve how trypanosomiasis is diagnosed in humans. We analyzed the expressed &lt;italic&gt;VSGs&lt;/italic&gt; detected in the blood of patients with trypanosomiasis. Our findings indicate that a diverse range of &lt;italic&gt;VSGs&lt;/italic&gt; are expressed in both natural and experimental infections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.459620" rel="alternate" title="Variant surface glycoprotein expression in human African trypanosomiasis patients (23 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.459708</id><title>HypVW is an HOCl-Sensing Two Component System in Escherichia coli (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.149031+00:00</updated><author><name>Sara El Hajj</name></author><author><name>Camille Henry</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Vergnes</name></author><author><name>Laurent Loiseau</name></author><author><name>Brasseur Gael</name></author><author><name>Romain Barré</name></author><author><name>Laurent Aussel</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Ezraty</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Two component systems (TCS) are signalling pathways that allow bacterial cells to sense, respond and adapt to fluctuating environments. Among the classical TCS of Escherichia coli, YedVW has been recently showed to be involved in the regulation of msrPQ, encoding for the periplasmic methionine sulfoxide reductase system. In this study, we demonstrate that hypochlorous acid (HOCl) induces the expression of msrPQ in a YedVW dependant manner, whereas H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, NO and paraquat (a superoxide generator) do not. Therefore, YedV appears to be an HOCl-sensing histidine kinase. Based on this finding, we proposed to rename this system HypVW.  Moreover, using a directed mutagenesis approach, we show that Met residues located in the periplasmic loop of HypV (formerly YedV) are important for its activity. Given that HOCl oxidizes preferentially Met residues, we bring evidences that HypV could be activated via the reversible oxidation of its methionine residues, thus conferring to MsrPQ a role in switching HypVW off. Based on these results, we propose that the activation of HypV by HOCl could occur through a Met redox switch. HypVW appears to be the first characterized TCS able to detect HOCl in E. coli. This study represents an important step in understanding the mechanisms of reactive chlorine species resistance in prokaryotes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.459708" rel="alternate" title="HypVW is an HOCl-Sensing Two Component System in Escherichia coli (8 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.08.459470</id><title>Classification of antimicrobial mechanism of action using bacterial time-lapse imaging (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.149312+00:00</updated><author><name>Xudong Ouyang</name></author><author><name>Jelmer Hoeksma</name></author><author><name>Tjalling K. Siersma</name></author><author><name>Leendert W. Hamoen</name></author><author><name>Jeroen den Hertog</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antimicrobial resistance is a major threat to human health. Basic knowledge of antimicrobial mechanism of action (MoA) is imperative for patient care and for identification of novel antimicrobials. However, the process of antimicrobial MoA identification is relatively laborious. Here, we developed a simple, quantitative time-lapse fluorescence imaging method, Dynamic Bacterial Morphology Imaging (DBMI), to facilitate this process. It uses a membrane dye and a nucleoid dye to track the morphological changes of single &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; cells in response to antimicrobials for up to 60 min. DBMI of bacterial cells facilitated assignment of the MoAs of 14 distinct, known antimicrobial compounds to the five main classes. Using this method, we found that the poorly studied antimicrobial, harzianic acid, a secondary metabolite that we purified from the fungal culture of &lt;italic&gt;Oidiodendron flavum&lt;/italic&gt;, targets the cell envelope. We conclude that DBMI is a simple method, which facilitates rapid classification of the MoA of antimicrobials in functionally distinct classes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.08.459470" rel="alternate" title="Classification of antimicrobial mechanism of action using bacterial time-lapse imaging (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>