<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.087401+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462010</id><title>Drivers and Determinants of Strain Dynamics Following Faecal Microbiota Transplantation (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.087790+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas SB Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Simone S Li</name></author><author><name>Oleksandr M Maistrenko</name></author><author><name>Wasiu Akanni</name></author><author><name>Luis Pedro Coelho</name></author><author><name>Sibasish Dolai</name></author><author><name>Anthony Fullam</name></author><author><name>Anna M Glazek</name></author><author><name>Rajna Hercog</name></author><author><name>Hilde Herrema</name></author><author><name>Ferris Jung</name></author><author><name>Stefanie Kandels</name></author><author><name>Askarbek Orakov</name></author><author><name>Thea Van Rossum</name></author><author><name>Vladimir Benes</name></author><author><name>Thomas J Borody</name></author><author><name>Willem M de Vos</name></author><author><name>Cyriel Y Ponsioen</name></author><author><name>Max Nieuwdorp</name></author><author><name>Peer Bork</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Faecal microbiota transplantation (FMT) is an efficacious therapeutic intervention, but its clinical mode of action and underlying microbiome dynamics remain poorly understood. Here, we analysed the metagenomes associated with 142 FMTs, in a time series-based meta-study across five disease indications. We quantified strain-level dynamics of 1,089 microbial species based on their pangenome, complemented with 47,548 newly constructed metagenome-assembled genomes. Using subsets of procedural-, host- and microbiome-based variables, LASSO-regularised regression models accurately predicted the colonisation and resilience of donor and recipient microbes, as well as turnover of individual species. Linking this to putative ecological mechanisms, we found these sets of variables to be informative of the underlying processes that shape the post-FMT gut microbiome. Recipient factors and complementarity of donor and recipient microbiomes, encompassing entire communities to individual strains, were the main determinants of individual strain population dynamics, and mostly independent of clinical outcomes. Recipient community state and the degree of residual strain depletion provided a neutral baseline for donor strain colonisation success, in addition to inhibitive priority effects between species and conspecific strains, as well as putatively adaptive processes. Our results suggest promising tunable parameters to enhance donor flora colonisation or recipient flora displacement in clinical practice, towards the development of more targeted and personalised therapies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462010" rel="alternate" title="Drivers and Determinants of Strain Dynamics Following Faecal Microbiota Transplantation (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462132</id><title>An anti-inflammatory activation sequence governs macrophage transcriptional dynamics during tissue injury (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.088258+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicolas Denans</name></author><author><name>Nhung T. T. Tran</name></author><author><name>Madeleine E. Swall</name></author><author><name>Daniel C. Diaz</name></author><author><name>Jillian Blanck</name></author><author><name>Tatjana Piotrowski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Macrophages are essential for tissue repair and regeneration. Yet, the molecular programs, as well as the timing of their activation during and after tissue injury are poorly defined. Using a high spatio-temporal resolution single cell analysis of macrophages coupled with live imaging after sensory hair cell death in zebrafish, we find that the same population of macrophages transitions through a sequence of three major anti-inflammatory activation states. Macrophages first show a signature of glucocorticoid activation, then IL10 signaling and finally the induction of oxidative phosphorylation by IL4/Polyamine signaling. Importantly, loss-of-function of glucocorticoid and IL10 signaling shows that each step of the sequence is independently activated. Our results provide the first evidence that macrophages, in addition to a switch from M1 to M2, sequentially and independently transition though three anti-inflammatory pathways &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; during tissue injury in a regenerating organ.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We show that macrophages are sequentially activated by three different anti-inflammatory pathways during tissue injury.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462132" rel="alternate" title="An anti-inflammatory activation sequence governs macrophage transcriptional dynamics during tissue injury (8 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462663</id><title>A gut commensal niche regulates stable association of a multispecies microbiota (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.088628+00:00</updated><author><name>Ren Dodge</name></author><author><name>Eric W. Jones</name></author><author><name>Haolong Zhu</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Obadia</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Martinez</name></author><author><name>Chenhui Wang</name></author><author><name>Andrés Aranda-Díaz</name></author><author><name>Kevin Aumiller</name></author><author><name>Zhexian Liu</name></author><author><name>Marco Voltolini</name></author><author><name>Eoin L. Brodie</name></author><author><name>Kerwyn Casey Huang</name></author><author><name>Jean M. Carlson</name></author><author><name>David A. Sivak</name></author><author><name>Allan C. Spradling</name></author><author><name>William B. Ludington</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The intestines of animals are typically colonized by a complex, relatively stable microbiota that influences health and fitness, but the underlying mechanisms of colonization remain poorly understood. As a typical animal, the fruit fly, &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; melanogaster, is associated with a consistent set of commensal bacterial species, yet the reason for this consistency is unknown. Here, we use gnotobiotic flies, microscopy, and microbial pulse-chase protocols to show that a commensal niche exists within the proventriculus region of the &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; foregut that selectively binds bacteria with exquisite strain-level specificity. Primary colonizers saturate the niche and exclude secondary colonizers of the same strain, but initial colonization by &lt;italic&gt;Lactobacillus&lt;/italic&gt; physically remodels the niche to favor secondary colonization by &lt;italic&gt;Acetobacter&lt;/italic&gt;. Our results provide a mechanistic framework for understanding the establishment and stability of an intestinal microbiome.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A strain-specific set of bacteria inhabits a defined spatial region of the &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; gut that forms a commensal niche.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462663" rel="alternate" title="A gut commensal niche regulates stable association of a multispecies microbiota (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462733</id><title>A novel locally c-di-GMP-controlled exopolysaccharide synthase required for N4 phage infection of E. coli (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.089032+00:00</updated><author><name>Eike H. Junkermeier</name></author><author><name>Regine Hengge</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A major target of c-di-GMP signaling is the production of biofilm-associated extracellular polymeric substances (EPS), which in &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; K-12 include amyloid curli fibres, phosphoethanolamine-modified (pEtN-)cellulose and poly-N-acetyl-glucosamine (PGA). However, the characterized c-di-GMP-binding effector systems are largely outnumbered by the 12 diguanylate cyclases (DGCs) and 13 phosphodiesterases (PDEs), which synthetize and degrade c-di-GMP, respectively. &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; possesses a single protein with a potentially c-di-GMP-binding MshEN domain, NfrB, which – together with the outer membrane protein NfrA – is known to serve as a receptor system for phage N4. Here, we show that NfrB not only binds c-di-GMP with high affinity, but as a novel c-di-GMP-controlled glycosyltransferase synthesizes a secreted EPS, which can impede motility and is required as an initial receptor for phage N4 infection. In addition, a systematic screening of the 12 DGCs of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; K-12 revealed that specifically DgcJ is required for the infection with phage N4 and interacts directly with NfrB. This is in line with local signaling models, where specific DGCs and/or PDEs form protein complexes with particular c-di-GMP effector/target systems. Our findings thus provide further evidence that intracellular signaling pathways, which all use the same diffusible second messenger, can act in parallel in a highly specific manner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Key findings in model organisms led to the concept of ‘local’ signaling, challenging the dogma of a gradually increasing global intracellular c-di-GMP concentration driving the motile-sessile transition in bacteria. In our current model, bacteria dynamically combine global as well as local signaling modes, in which specific DGCs and/or PDEs team up with effector/target systems in multiprotein complexes. Our present study highlights a novel example of how specificity in c-di-GMP signaling can be achieved by showing NfrB as a novel c-di-GMP binding effector in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;, which is controlled in a local manner specifically by DgcJ. We further show that NfrB (which was initially found as a part of a receptor system for phage N4) is involved in the production of a novel exopolysaccharide. Finally, our data shine new light on host interaction of phage N4, which uses this exopolysaccharide as an initial receptor for adsorption.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462733" rel="alternate" title="A novel locally c-di-GMP-controlled exopolysaccharide synthase required for N4 phage infection of E. coli (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462712</id><title>Mycobacterial resistance to zinc poisoning requires assembly of P-ATPase-containing membrane metal efflux platforms (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.089274+00:00</updated><author><name>Yves-Marie Boudehen</name></author><author><name>Marion Faucher</name></author><author><name>Xavier Maréchal</name></author><author><name>Roger Miras</name></author><author><name>Jérôme Rech</name></author><author><name>Olivier Sénèque</name></author><author><name>Maximilian Wallat</name></author><author><name>Pascal Demange</name></author><author><name>Jean-Yves Bouet</name></author><author><name>Olivier Saurel</name></author><author><name>Patrice Catty</name></author><author><name>Claude Gutierrez</name></author><author><name>Olivier Neyrolles</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Transition metals are toxic at high concentrations. The P&lt;sub&gt;1B&lt;/sub&gt;-ATPase metal exporter CtpC/Rv3270 is required for resistance to zinc poisoning in the human pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt;. Here, we discovered that zinc resistance also depends on the chaperone-like protein PacL1/Rv3269. PacL1 bound Zn&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;, but unlike PacL1 and CtpC, the PacL1 metal-binding motif (MBM) was required only at high zinc concentrations. PacL1 co-localized with CtpC in dynamic microdomains within the mycobacterial plasma membrane. Microdomain formation did not require flotillins nor the PacL1 MBM. Instead, loss of the PacL1 Glutamine/Alanine repeats led to loss of CtpC and sensitivity to zinc. PacL1 and CtpC are within the same operon, and homologous PacL1-P&lt;sub&gt;1B&lt;/sub&gt;-ATPase pairs are widely distributed within and across prokaryotes. PacL1 colocalized and functioned redundantly with PacL orthologs in &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt;. Overall, our study suggests that PacL proteins are scaffolds that assemble P-ATPase-containing metal efflux platforms, a novel type of functional membrane microdomain that underlies bacterial resistance to metal poisoning.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462712" rel="alternate" title="Mycobacterial resistance to zinc poisoning requires assembly of P-ATPase-containing membrane metal efflux platforms (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>