<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.029242+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474984</id><title>Mapping functional regions of essential bacterial proteins with dominant-negative protein fragments (28 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.029640+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew Savinov</name></author><author><name>Andres Fernandez</name></author><author><name>Stanley Fields</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Massively-parallel measurements of dominant negative inhibition by protein fragments have been used to map protein interaction sites and discover peptide inhibitors. However, the underlying principles governing fragment-based inhibition have thus far remained unclear. Here, we adapt a high-throughput inhibitory fragment assay for use in &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt;, applying it to a set of ten essential proteins. This approach yielded single amino acid-resolution maps of inhibitory activity, with peaks localized to functionally important interaction sites, including oligomerization interfaces and folding contacts. Leveraging these data, we perform a systematic analysis to uncover principles of fragment-based inhibition. We determine a robust negative correlation between susceptibility to inhibition and cellular protein concentration, demonstrating that inhibitory fragments likely act primarily by titrating native protein interactions. We also characterize a series of trade-offs related to fragment length, showing that shorter peptides allow higher-resolution mapping but suffer from lower inhibitory activity. We employ an unsupervised statistical analysis to show that the inhibitory activities of protein fragments are largely driven not by generic properties such as charge, hydrophobicity, and secondary structure, but by the more specific characteristics of their bespoke macromolecular interactions. AlphaFold computational modeling of peptide complexes with one protein shows that the inhibitory activity of peptides is associated with their predicted ability to form native-like interactions. Overall, this work demonstrates fundamental characteristics of inhibitory protein fragment function and provides a foundation for understanding and controlling protein interactions &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Peptide fragments derived from protein sequences can inhibit interactions of their parental proteins, providing a promising avenue for drug development. Here we employ a massively-parallel assay to measure &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; inhibition by fragments that tile the full sequences of ten essential bacterial proteins. We leverage these data to decipher principles of fragment-based inhibition, showing how parental protein concentration drives activity and how protein fragment length interplays with activity and specificity. We employ statistical analysis to parse the roles of biophysical properties in fragment-to-fragment variation, and AlphaFold modeling to determine the relationship between measured inhibitory activity and predicted native-like binding. These results provide a path towards rational design of peptide inhibitors and broader principles of protein-protein interactions in living cells.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474984" rel="alternate" title="Mapping functional regions of essential bacterial proteins with dominant-negative protein fragments (28 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475072</id><title>Recurrent emergence of carbapenem resistance in Klebsiella pneumoniae mediated by an inhibitory ompK36 mRNA secondary structure (24 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.029882+00:00</updated><author><name>Joshua L. C. Wong</name></author><author><name>Sophia David</name></author><author><name>Julia Sanchez-Garrido</name></author><author><name>Jia Z. Woo</name></author><author><name>Wen Wen Low</name></author><author><name>Fabio Morecchiato</name></author><author><name>Tommaso Giani</name></author><author><name>Gian Maria Rossolini</name></author><author><name>Stephen J. Brett</name></author><author><name>Abigail Clements</name></author><author><name>David M Aanensen</name></author><author><name>Silvi Rouskin</name></author><author><name>Gad Frankel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Outer membrane porins in Gram-negative bacteria facilitate antibiotic influx. In &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; (KP), modifications in the porin OmpK36 are implicated in increasing resistance to carbapenems. Analysis of large KP genome collections, encompassing major healthcare-associated clones, revealed the recurrent emergence of a synonymous cytosine to thymine transition at position 25 (25c&amp;gt;t) in &lt;italic&gt;ompK36.&lt;/italic&gt; We show that the 25c&amp;gt;t transition increases carbapenem resistance through depletion of OmpK36 from the outer membrane. The mutation attenuates KP in a murine pneumonia model, which accounts for its limited clonal expansion observed by phylogenetic analysis. However, in the context of carbapenem treatment, the 25c&amp;gt;t transition tips the balance towards treatment failure, thus accounting for its recurrent emergence. Mechanistically, the 25c&amp;gt;t transition mediates an intramolecular mRNA interaction between a uracil encoded by 25t and the first adenine within the Shine-Dalgarno sequence. This specific interaction leads to the formation of an RNA stem structure, which obscures the ribosomal binding site thus disrupting translation. While mutations reducing OmpK36 expression via transcriptional silencing are known, we uniquely demonstrate the repeated selection of a synonymous &lt;italic&gt;ompK36&lt;/italic&gt; mutation mediating translational suppression in response to antibiotic pressure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475072" rel="alternate" title="Recurrent emergence of carbapenem resistance in Klebsiella pneumoniae mediated by an inhibitory ompK36 mRNA secondary structure (24 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474948</id><title>Siglec-5 is an inhibitory immune checkpoint molecule for human T cells (21 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.030157+00:00</updated><author><name>Aleksandra Vuchkovska</name></author><author><name>David G. Glanville</name></author><author><name>Gina M. Scurti</name></author><author><name>Paula White</name></author><author><name>Michael I. Nishimura</name></author><author><name>Andrew T. Ulijasz</name></author><author><name>Makio Iwashima</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sialic acid-binding immunoglobulin-type lectins (Siglecs) are a family of immunoglobulin-type lectins that mediate protein-carbohydrate interactions via sialic acids attached to glycoproteins or glycolipids. Most of the CD33-related Siglecs (CD33rSiglecs), a major subfamily of rapidly evolving Siglecs, contain a cytoplasmic signaling domain consisting of the immunoreceptor tyrosine-based inhibitory motif (ITIM) and immunoreceptor tyrosine-based switch motif (ITSM) and mediate suppressive signals for lymphoid and myeloid cells. While most CD33rSiglecs are expressed by innate immune cells, such as monocytes and neutrophils, to date, the expression of Siglecs in human T cells has not been well appreciated. In this study, we found that Siglec-5, a member of the CD33rSiglecs, is expressed by most activated T cells upon antigen receptor stimulation. Functionally, Siglec-5 suppresses T cell activation. In support of these findings, we found that Siglec-5 overexpression abrogates antigen receptor induced activation of Nuclear factor of activated T cells (NFAT) and Activator protein 1 (AP-1). Furthermore, we show that GBS β-protein, a known bacterial ligand of Siglec-5, reduces the production of cytokines and cytolytic molecules by activated primary T cells in a Siglec-5 dependent manner. Our data also show that some cancer cell lines express a putative Siglec-5 ligand(s), and that the presence of soluble Siglec-5 enhances tumor-cell specific T cell activation, suggesting that some tumor cells inhibit T cell activation via Siglec-5. Together, our data demonstrate that Siglec-5 is a previously unrecognized inhibitory T cell immune checkpoint molecule and suggests that blockade of Siglec-5 could serve as a new strategy to enhance anti-tumor T cell functions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One Sentence Summary:&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Siglec-5 is a novel checkpoint receptor expressed by activated human T cells that antagonizes TCR mediated activation and suppresses T cell effector functions such as cytokine production.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474948" rel="alternate" title="Siglec-5 is an inhibitory immune checkpoint molecule for human T cells (21 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474787</id><title>The AMA1-RON complex drives Plasmodium sporozoite invasion in the mosquito and mammalian hosts (17 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.030372+00:00</updated><author><name>Priyanka Fernandes</name></author><author><name>Manon Loubens</name></author><author><name>Rémi Le Borgne</name></author><author><name>Carine Marinach</name></author><author><name>Beatrice Ardin</name></author><author><name>Sylvie Briquet</name></author><author><name>Laetitia Vincensini</name></author><author><name>Soumia Hamada</name></author><author><name>Bénédicte Hoareau-Coudert</name></author><author><name>Jean-Marc Verbavatz</name></author><author><name>Allon Weiner</name></author><author><name>Olivier Silvie</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium&lt;/italic&gt; sporozoites that are transmitted by blood-feeding female &lt;italic&gt;Anopheles&lt;/italic&gt; mosquitoes invade hepatocytes for an initial round of intracellular replication, leading to the release of merozoites that invade and multiply within red blood cells. Sporozoites and merozoites share a number of proteins that are expressed by both stages, including the Apical Membrane Antigen 1 (AMA1) and the Rhoptry Neck Proteins (RONs). Although AMA1 and RONs are essential for merozoite invasion of erythrocytes during asexual blood stage replication of the parasite, their function in sporozoites is still unclear. Here we show that AMA1 interacts with RONs in mature sporozoites. By using DiCre-mediated conditional gene deletion in &lt;italic&gt;P. berghei&lt;/italic&gt;, we demonstrate that loss of AMA1, RON2 or RON4 in sporozoites impairs colonization of the mosquito salivary glands and invasion of mammalian hepatocytes, without affecting transcellular parasite migration. Our data establish that AMA1 and RONs facilitate host cell invasion across &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium&lt;/italic&gt; invasive stages, and suggest that sporozoites use the AMA1-RON complex to safely enter the mosquito salivary glands without causing cell damage, to ensure successful parasite transmission. These results open up the possibility of targeting the AMA1-RON complex for transmission-blocking antimalarial strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474787" rel="alternate" title="The AMA1-RON complex drives Plasmodium sporozoite invasion in the mosquito and mammalian hosts (17 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475016</id><title>Genomic dissection of the microevolution of Australian epidemic Bordetella pertussis (13 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.030640+00:00</updated><author><name>Zheng XU</name></author><author><name>Dalong Hu</name></author><author><name>Laurence Don Wai Luu</name></author><author><name>Sophie Octavia</name></author><author><name>Anthony D Keil</name></author><author><name>Vitali Sintchenko</name></author><author><name>Mark M. Tanaka</name></author><author><name>Frits R. Mooi</name></author><author><name>Jenny Robson</name></author><author><name>Ruiting Lan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Whooping cough (pertussis) is a highly contagious respiratory disease caused by the bacterium Bordetella pertussis. Despite high vaccine coverage, pertussis has re-emerged in many countries and caused two large epidemics in Australia since 2007. Here, we undertook a genomic and phylogeographic study of 385 Australian B. pertussis isolates collected from 2008 to 2017. The Australian B. pertussis population was found to be composed of mostly ptxP3 strains carrying different fim3 alleles, with ptxP3-fim3A genotype expanded far more than ptxP3-fim3B. Within the former, there were six co-circulating epidemic lineages (EL1 to EL6). The multiple ELs emerged, expanded, and then declined at different time points over the two epidemics, likely driven by immune selection from pertussis vaccination and natural infection in addition to local and global transmission events. Both hard and soft selective sweeps through vaccine selection pressures determined the current B. pertussis population dynamics. Relative risk analysis found that once a new B. pertussis lineage emerged, it was more likely to spread locally within the first 1.5 years. However, after 1.5 years, any new lineage was likely to expand to a wider region and became no longer spatially structured across the country. Phylogenetic analysis revealed the expansion of ptxP3 strains was also associated with replacement of the type III secretion system allele bscI1 with bscI3. This study advanced our understanding of the epidemic population structure and spatial and temporal dynamics of B. pertussis in a highly immunised population.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475016" rel="alternate" title="Genomic dissection of the microevolution of Australian epidemic Bordetella pertussis (13 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474942</id><title>Exploring the onset of B12-based mutualisms using a recently evolved Chlamydomonas auxotroph and B12-producing bacteria (13 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.030867+00:00</updated><author><name>Freddy Bunbury</name></author><author><name>Evelyne Deery</name></author><author><name>Andrew Sayer</name></author><author><name>Vaibhav Bhardwaj</name></author><author><name>Ellen Harrison</name></author><author><name>Martin J. Warren</name></author><author><name>Alison G. Smith</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cobalamin (vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;), is a cofactor for crucial metabolic reactions in multiple eukaryotic taxa, including major primary producers such as algae, and yet only prokaryotes can produce it. Many bacteria can colonise the algal phycosphere, forming stable communities that gain preferential access to exudates and in return provide compounds, such as B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;. Extended coexistence can then drive gene loss, leading to greater algal-bacterial interdependence. In this study, we investigate how a recently evolved B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;-dependent strain of &lt;italic&gt;Chlamydomonas reinhardtii&lt;/italic&gt;, metE7, forms a mutualism with certain bacteria, including the rhizobium &lt;italic&gt;Mesorhizobium loti&lt;/italic&gt; and even a strain of the gut bacterium &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; engineered to produce cobalamin. Although metE7 was supported by B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; producers, its growth in co-culture was slower than the B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;-independent wild-type, suggesting that high bacterial B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; provision may be necessary to favour B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; auxotrophs and their evolution. Moreover, we found that an &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; strain that releases more B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; makes a better mutualistic partner, and although this trait may be more costly in isolation, greater B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; release provided an advantage in co-cultures. We hypothesise that, given the right conditions, bacteria that release more B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; may be selected for, particularly if they form close interactions with B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;-dependent algae.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Originality-Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Microalgae are fundamental to the global carbon cycle, and yet despite being photosynthetic they often rely on other organisms for micronutrients. One of these micronutrients is vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; (cobalamin), which they receive from bacteria. Many environmental studies support the widespread role of B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; in algal-bacterial mutualisms, so here we wished to investigate how these mutualisms may arise evolutionarily by using an experimentally evolved B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;-dependent alga and various B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;-producers. A B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;-producing rhizobium, &lt;italic&gt;Mesorhizobium loti&lt;/italic&gt;, could stably support the B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;-dependent &lt;italic&gt;Chlamydomonas reinhardtii&lt;/italic&gt; metE7 strain, and vice versa, but nutrient supplementation increased growth of both species further. metE7 could also be supported by &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; strains engineered to produce B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;, and engineering a strain to release a higher proportion of B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; led to better algal growth, which increased bacterial growth in turn. We suggest that as B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;-based mutualisms develop, increased B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; release may be selected for and therefore lead to more productive symbioses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474942" rel="alternate" title="Exploring the onset of B12-based mutualisms using a recently evolved Chlamydomonas auxotroph and B12-producing bacteria (13 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474781</id><title>In planta transcriptomics reveals conflicts between pattern-triggered immunity and the AlgU sigma factor regulon (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.031068+00:00</updated><author><name>Haibi Wang</name></author><author><name>Amelia Lovelace</name></author><author><name>Amy Smith</name></author><author><name>Brian H. Kvitko</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In previous work, we determined the transcriptomic impacts of flg22 pre-induced Pattern Triggered Immunity (PTI) in &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; on the pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas syringae&lt;/italic&gt; pv. &lt;italic&gt;tomato&lt;/italic&gt; DC3000 (&lt;italic&gt;Pto&lt;/italic&gt;). During PTI exposure we observed expression patterns in &lt;italic&gt;Pto&lt;/italic&gt; reminiscent of those previously observed in a &lt;italic&gt;Pto algU&lt;/italic&gt; mutant. AlgU is a conserved extracytoplasmic function sigma factor which has been observed to regulate over 950 genes in &lt;italic&gt;Pto in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. We sought to identify the AlgU regulon &lt;italic&gt;in planta&lt;/italic&gt;.and which PTI-regulated genes overlapped with AlgU-regulated genes. In this study, we analyzed transcriptomic data from RNA-sequencing to identify the AlgU &lt;italic&gt;in planta&lt;/italic&gt; regulon and its relationship with PTI. Our results showed that approximately 224 genes are induced by AlgU, while another 154 genes are downregulated by AlgU in &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/italic&gt; during early infection. Both stress response and virulence-associated genes were induced by AlgU, while the flagellar motility genes are downregulated by AlgU. Under the pre-induced PTI condition, more than half of these AlgU-regulated genes have lost induction/suppression in contrast to naïve plants, and almost all function groups regulated by AlgU were affected by PTI.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474781" rel="alternate" title="In planta transcriptomics reveals conflicts between pattern-triggered immunity and the AlgU sigma factor regulon (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474981</id><title>A unique class of Zn2+-binding PBPs underlies cephalosporin resistance and sporogenesis of Clostridioides difficile (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.031243+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael D. Sacco</name></author><author><name>Shaohui Wang</name></author><author><name>Swamy R. Adapa</name></author><author><name>Xiujun Zhang</name></author><author><name>Maura V. Gongora</name></author><author><name>Jean R. Gatdula</name></author><author><name>Eric M. Lewandowski</name></author><author><name>Lauren R. Hammond</name></author><author><name>Julia A. Townsend</name></author><author><name>Michael T. Marty</name></author><author><name>Jun Wang</name></author><author><name>Prahathees J. Eswara</name></author><author><name>Rays H.Y. Jiang</name></author><author><name>Xingmin Sun</name></author><author><name>Yu Chen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;β-Lactam antibiotics, particularly cephalosporins, are major risk factors for &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; infection (CDI), the most common hospital acquired infection. These broad-spectrum antibiotics irreversibly inhibit penicillin-binding proteins (PBPs), essential enzymes that assemble the bacterial cell wall. Little is known about the &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; PBPs, yet they play central roles in the growth, infection, and transmission of this pathogen. In this study we discover that PBP2, essential for vegetative growth, is the primary bactericidal target for β-lactams in &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt;. We further demonstrate PBP2 is insensitive to cephalosporin inhibition, revealing a key cause of the well-documented, but poorly understood, cephalosporin resistance in &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt;. For the first time, we determine the crystal structures of &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; PBP2, which bears several highly unique features, including significant ligand-induced conformational changes and an active site Zn&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;-binding motif that influences β-lactam binding and protein stability. Remarkably, this motif is shared in two other &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; PBPs essential for sporulation, PBP3 and SpoVD. While these PBPs are present in a wide range of bacterial taxa, including species in extreme environments and the human gut, they are mostly found in anaerobes, typically Firmicutes. The widespread presence of this convergently evolved thiol-containing motif and its cognate Zn&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; suggests it may function as a redox-sensor to regulate cell wall synthesis for survival in adverse environments. Collectively, our findings address important etiological questions surrounding &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt;, characterize new elements of PBP structure and function, and lay the groundwork for antibiotic development targeting both &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; growth and sporulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474981" rel="alternate" title="A unique class of Zn2+-binding PBPs underlies cephalosporin resistance and sporogenesis of Clostridioides difficile (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.475019</id><title>Interferon lambda signals in maternal tissues to exert protective and pathologic effects in a gestational-stage dependent manner (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.031509+00:00</updated><author><name>Rebecca L. Casazza</name></author><author><name>Drake T. Philip</name></author><author><name>Helen M. Lazear</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Interferon lambda (IFN-λ, type III IFN) is constitutively secreted from human placental cells in culture and reduces Zika virus (ZIKV) transplacental transmission in mice. However, the roles of IFN-λ during healthy pregnancy and in restricting congenital infection remain unclear. Here we used mice lacking the IFN-λ receptor (&lt;italic&gt;Ifnlr1&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;) to generate pregnancies lacking either maternal or fetal IFN-λ responsiveness and found that the antiviral effect of IFN-λ resulted from signaling exclusively in maternal tissues. This protective effect depended on gestational stage, as infection earlier in pregnancy (E7 rather than E9) resulted in enhanced transplacental transmission of ZIKV. In &lt;italic&gt;Ifnar1&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; dams, which sustain robust ZIKV infection, maternal IFN-λ signaling caused fetal resorption and intrauterine growth restriction. Pregnancy pathology elicited by poly(I:C) treatment also was mediated by maternal IFN-λ signaling, specifically in maternal leukocytes, and also occurred in a gestational stage-dependent manner. These findings identify an unexpected effect of IFN-λ signaling specifically in maternal (rather than placental or fetal) tissues, which is distinct from the pathogenic effects of IFN-αβ (type I IFN) during pregnancy. These results highlight the complexity of immune signaling at the maternal-fetal interface, where disparate outcomes can result from signaling at different gestational stages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pregnancy is an immunologically complex situation, which must balance protecting the fetus from maternal pathogens with preventing maternal immune rejection of non-self fetal and placental tissue. Cytokines, such as interferon lambda (IFN-λ), contribute to antiviral immunity at the maternal-fetal interface. We found in a mouse model of congenital Zika virus infection that IFN-λ can have either a protective antiviral effect or cause immune-mediated pathology, depending on the stage of gestation when IFN-λ signaling occurs. Remarkably, both the protective and pathologic effects of IFN-λ occurred through signaling exclusively in maternal immune cells, rather than in fetal or placental tissues, or in other maternal cell types, identifying a new role for IFN-λ at the maternal-fetal interface.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.475019" rel="alternate" title="Interferon lambda signals in maternal tissues to exert protective and pathologic effects in a gestational-stage dependent manner (6 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475125</id><title>Intestinal Bacteroides Modulates Systemic Inflammation and the Microbial Ecology in a Mouse Model of CF: Evidence for Propionate and other Short Chain Fatty Acids Reducing Systemic Inflammatory Cytokines (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.031681+00:00</updated><author><name>Courtney E. Price</name></author><author><name>Rebecca A. Valls</name></author><author><name>Alexis R. Ramsey</name></author><author><name>Nicole A. Loeven</name></author><author><name>Jane T. Jones</name></author><author><name>Kaitlyn E. Barrack</name></author><author><name>Joseph D Schwartzman</name></author><author><name>Darlene B. Royce</name></author><author><name>Robert A. Cramer</name></author><author><name>Juliette C. Madan</name></author><author><name>Benjamin D. Ross</name></author><author><name>James Bliska</name></author><author><name>George A. O’Toole</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Persons with cystic fibrosis, starting in early life, have intestinal microbiome dysbiosis characterized in part by a decreased relative abundance of the genus &lt;italic&gt;Bacteroides&lt;/italic&gt;. &lt;italic&gt;Bacteroides&lt;/italic&gt; is a major producer of the intestinal short chain fatty acid (SCFA) propionate. We demonstrate here that CFTR-/- Caco-2 intestinal epithelial cells are responsive to the anti-inflammatory effects of propionate. Furthermore, &lt;italic&gt;Bacteroides&lt;/italic&gt; isolates inhibit the IL-1β-induced inflammatory response of CFTR-/- Caco-2 intestinal epithelial cells and do so in a propionate-dependent manner. &lt;italic&gt;Bacteroides&lt;/italic&gt; isolates also produce low levels of butyrate; this SCFA is positively correlated with inhibition of the inflammatory response. Finally, the introduction of &lt;italic&gt;Bacteroides-&lt;/italic&gt;supplemented stool from infants with CF into the gut of &lt;italic&gt;Cftr&lt;sup&gt;F508del&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice results in an increase in propionate in the stool as well as the reduction in several systemic pro-inflammatory cytokines. &lt;italic&gt;Bacteroides&lt;/italic&gt; supplementation also reduced the fecal relative abundance of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;, indicating a potential interaction between these two microbes, consistent with previous clinical studies. Together, our data indicate the important role of &lt;italic&gt;Bacteroides&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Bacteroides&lt;/italic&gt;-derived propionate in the context of the developing microbiome in infants and children with CF, which could help explain the observed gut-lung axis in CF.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475125" rel="alternate" title="Intestinal Bacteroides Modulates Systemic Inflammation and the Microbial Ecology in a Mouse Model of CF: Evidence for Propionate and other Short Chain Fatty Acids Reducing Systemic Inflammatory Cytokines (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474930</id><title>A Comparison Of Fecal Glucocorticoid Metabolite Concentration And Gut Microbiota Diversity In Bonobos (Pan paniscus) (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.031951+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexana J Hickmott</name></author><author><name>Klaree J Boose</name></author><author><name>Monica L Wakefield</name></author><author><name>Colin M Brand</name></author><author><name>J. Josh Snodgrass</name></author><author><name>Nelson Ting</name></author><author><name>Frances J White</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Host sex, age, diet, stress, and social environment have all been found to influence the gut microbiota. In non-human primates (NHP), recent evidence from gorillas found fecal glucocorticoid metabolite concentration (FGMC) had no significant role in structuring their gut microbiota, but there was a significant differential abundance between family Anaerolineaceae and gorilla FGMC. This pattern has yet to be examined in other NHP, like bonobos (Pan paniscus). We compared FGMC to 16S rRNA amplicons for 201 bonobo fecal samples collected in the wild across five months to evaluate the impact of stress, measured with FGMC, on the gut microbiota. Simpsons index was the only alpha diversity index to have a significant linear relationship with FGMC [R2 = 0.9643, F(4, 210) = 28.56, p = 0.0023]. FGMC level explained 1.63% of the variation in beta diversity for Jensen-Shannon Distance, 2.49% for Weighted UniFrac, and 3.53% for Unweighted UniFrac using PERMANOVAs. Differential abundance models showed seventeen taxa that were significantly correlated with FGMC. We found that genus SHD-231 in the family Anaerolinaceae was significant in our differential abundance model results, similar to western lowland gorilla abundance model results. These results suggest bonobos exhibit different patterns than gorillas in alpha and beta diversity measures and that members of the family Anaerolinaceae may be differentially affected by host stress across great apes. Incorporating FGMC into gut microbiota research can provide a more robust understanding of how stress impacts the gut microbiota of primates and humans and has important ties to overall host health.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474930" rel="alternate" title="A Comparison Of Fecal Glucocorticoid Metabolite Concentration And Gut Microbiota Diversity In Bonobos (Pan paniscus) (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474906</id><title>Wnt5A supports antigen cross-presentation and CD8 T cell activation (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.032198+00:00</updated><author><name>Tresa Rani Sarraf</name></author><author><name>Malini Sen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antigen processing, cross-presentation, and antigen-specific CD8 T cell response form part and parcel of T cell-mediated immunity. Yet, lacunae remain in our understanding of antigen processing/presentation and CD8 T cell response. Given the association of Wnt5A signaling with immune homeostasis, we evaluated the utility of Wnt5A in antigen processing, cross-presentation, and CD8 T cell activation. Using mouse bone marrow-derived dendritic cells as antigen-presenting cells and ovalbumin as a model antigen we found that Wnt5A mediated regulation of actin and proteasome dynamics is inherently associated with antigen processing. A Wnt5A-Actin-Protasome axis also contributes to antigen cross-presentation and antigen responsive CD8 T cell expansion. In concurrence with these observations, we demonstrated impaired activation of ovalbumin-specific CD8 T cells in ovalbumin immunized Wnt5A heterozygous mice as illustrated by their poor CD8 T cell recall response to ovalbumin when compared to similarly immunized wild type cohorts. Our results suggest that Wnt5A signaling-directed antigen processing/presentation could be vital for generating CD8 T cell recall response to antigen, thus shedding light on a critical parameter of immunity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474906" rel="alternate" title="Wnt5A supports antigen cross-presentation and CD8 T cell activation (6 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474954</id><title>GWAS and functional studies implicate a role for altered DNA repair in the evolution of drug resistance in Mycobacterium tuberculosis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.032388+00:00</updated><author><name>Saba Naz</name></author><author><name>Kumar Paritosh</name></author><author><name>Priyadarshini Sanyal</name></author><author><name>Sidra Khan</name></author><author><name>Yogendra Singh</name></author><author><name>Umesh Varshney</name></author><author><name>Vinay Kumar Nandicoori</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The emergence of drug resistance in &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Mtb&lt;/italic&gt;) is alarming and demands in-depth knowledge for timely diagnosis. We performed genome-wide association analysis (GWAS) using 2237 clinical strains of &lt;italic&gt;Mtb&lt;/italic&gt; to identify novel genetic factors that evoke drug resistance. In addition to the known direct targets, for the first time, we identified a strong association between the mutations in the DNA repair genes and the multidrug-resistant phenotype. To evaluate the impact of variants identified in the clinical samples in the evolution of drug resistance, we utilized knockouts and complemented strains in &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium smegmatis (Msm)&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Mtb&lt;/italic&gt;. Results show that variant mutations abrogated the function of MutY and UvrB. MutY variant showed enhanced survival compared with wild-type (&lt;italic&gt;Rv&lt;/italic&gt;) when the &lt;italic&gt;Mtb&lt;/italic&gt; strains were subjected to multiple rounds of &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; antibiotic stress. Notably, in an &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; Guinea pig infection model, the MutY variant outcompeted the wild-type strain. Collectively, we show that novel variant mutations in the DNA repair genes abrogate their function and contribute to better survival under antibiotic/host stress conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474954" rel="alternate" title="GWAS and functional studies implicate a role for altered DNA repair in the evolution of drug resistance in Mycobacterium tuberculosis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.474053</id><title>Genomic insights into the phylogeny and biomass-degrading enzymes of rumen ciliates (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.032597+00:00</updated><author><name>Zongjun Li</name></author><author><name>Xiangnan Wang</name></author><author><name>Yu Zhang</name></author><author><name>Zhongtang Yu</name></author><author><name>Tingting Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xuelei Dai</name></author><author><name>Xiangyu Pan</name></author><author><name>Ruoxi Jing</name></author><author><name>Yueyang Yan</name></author><author><name>Yangfan Liu</name></author><author><name>Shan Gao</name></author><author><name>Fei Li</name></author><author><name>Youqin Huang</name></author><author><name>Jian Tian</name></author><author><name>Junhu Yao</name></author><author><name>XvPeng Xing</name></author><author><name>Tao Shi</name></author><author><name>Jifeng Ning</name></author><author><name>Bin Yao</name></author><author><name>Huoqing Huang</name></author><author><name>Yu Jiang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the biodiversity and genetics of the gut microbiome has important implications for host physiology. One underexplored and elusive group is ciliated protozoa, which play crucial roles in regulating gut microbial interactions. Integrating single-cell sequencing and an assembly-and-identification pipeline, we acquired 52 high-quality ciliate genomes of 22 rumen morphospecies for all major abundant clades. With these genomes, we firstly resolved the taxonomic and phylogenetic framework that reclassified them into 19 species spanning 13 genera and reassigned the genus Dasytricha from Isotrichidae to a new family Dasytrichidae. Via extensive horizontal gene transfer and gene family expansion, rumen ciliates possess a broad array of enzymes to synergistically degrade plant and microbial carbohydrates. In particular, ∼80% of the degrading enzymes in Diplodiniinae and Ophryoscolecinae act on plant cell wall, and the high activities of their cellulase, xylanase and lysozyme reflect the potential of ciliate enzymes for biomass-conversion. Additionally, the new ciliate dataset greatly facilitated the rumen metagenomic analyses by allowing ∼12% of reads to be classified.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.474053" rel="alternate" title="Genomic insights into the phylogeny and biomass-degrading enzymes of rumen ciliates (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475030</id><title>Identification and molecular characterization of novel viruses in Ugandan cattle (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.033012+00:00</updated><author><name>Stephen Balinandi</name></author><author><name>Juliette Hayer</name></author><author><name>Harindranath Cholleti</name></author><author><name>Michelle Wille</name></author><author><name>Julius J. Lutwama</name></author><author><name>Maja Malmberg</name></author><author><name>Lawrence Mugisha</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The risk for the emergence of novel viral zoonotic diseases in animals and humans in Uganda is high given its geographical location with high biodiversity. We aimed to identify and characterize viruses in 175 blood samples from cattle selected in Uganda using molecular approaches. We identified 8 viral species belonging to 4 families (&lt;italic&gt;Flaviviridae, Peribunyaviridae, Reoviridae&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Rhabdoviridae&lt;/italic&gt;) and 6 genera (&lt;italic&gt;Hepacivirus, Pestivirus, Orthobunyavirus, Coltivirus, Dinovernavirus&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Ephemerovirus&lt;/italic&gt;). Four viruses were novel and tetantively named as Zikole virus (Family: &lt;italic&gt;Flaviviridae&lt;/italic&gt;), Zeboroti virus (Family: &lt;italic&gt;Reoviridae&lt;/italic&gt;), Zebtine virus (Family: &lt;italic&gt;Rhabdoviridae&lt;/italic&gt;) and Kokolu virus (Family: &lt;italic&gt;Rhabdoviridae&lt;/italic&gt;). In addition, Bovine hepacivirus, Obodhiang virus, &lt;italic&gt;Aedes pseudoscutellaris reovirus&lt;/italic&gt; and Schmallenberg virus were identified for the first time in Ugandan cattle. We report a broad range of viruses including novel ones in the blood of cattle likely as reservoir hosts for emergence of novel viruses with serious public health implications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pan PCR and High Throughput Sequencing Approaches reveal novel viruses in the blood of cattle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Identified 8 viral species belonging to 4 families: &lt;italic&gt;Flaviviridae, Peribunyaviridae, Reoviridae&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Rhabdoviridae&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;60% of the identified viruses were found in the Ankole cattle breed&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475030" rel="alternate" title="Identification and molecular characterization of novel viruses in Ugandan cattle (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475170</id><title>Age-Related Impairment of Innate and Adaptive Immune Responses Following Intranasal Herpes Simplex Infection (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.033346+00:00</updated><author><name>Ruchi Srivastava</name></author><author><name>Anshu Agrawal</name></author><author><name>Hawa Vahed</name></author><author><name>Lbachir BenMohamed</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Immune function declines with age, leading to an increased vulnerability to respiratory viral infections. The mechanisms by which aging negatively impacts the innate and adaptive immune system leading to enhanced susceptibility to infections remain to be fully elucidated. In the present study, we used a mouse model of intranasal infection with herpes simplex virus type 1 (HSV-1), a virus that can enter the lungs through the nasal route causing pneumonia, a serious health concern in the elderly. Following intranasal inoculation of young (6 weeks), adult (36 weeks), and aged (68 weeks) with HSV-1 (KOS strain) we: (i) compared the local and systemic innate and adaptive immune response to infection; and (ii) correlated the level and type of immune response to protection against HSV-1 infection. Compared to young and adult mice, aged mice displayed: (i) increased basal level activation of epithelial cells with a decreased expression of TLR3; (ii) increased activation of dendritic cells with increased expression of MHC-1, MHC-II and CD80/86; and (iii) decreased production of type-I interferons upon stimulation; (iv) a delay in cytokines and chemokines production in the lungs; and (v) an impairment in function (CD107 and IFN-g production) of HSV-specific CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells. These impairment in innate and adaptive immune responses in aged mice following intranasal HSV-1 inoculation was associated with symptomatic herpes infection. The findings suggest an age-related impairment of both innate and adaptive immune responses which may exacerbate herpes infection and disease in the elderly.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475170" rel="alternate" title="Age-Related Impairment of Innate and Adaptive Immune Responses Following Intranasal Herpes Simplex Infection (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474968</id><title>Multivalent interactions drive the Toxoplasma AC9:AC10:ERK7 complex to concentrate ERK7 in the apical cap (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.033530+00:00</updated><author><name>Peter S. Back</name></author><author><name>William J. O’Shaughnessy</name></author><author><name>Andy S. Moon</name></author><author><name>Pravin S. Dewangan</name></author><author><name>Michael L. Reese</name></author><author><name>Peter J. Bradley</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;italic&gt;Toxoplasma&lt;/italic&gt; inner membrane complex (IMC) is a specialized organelle that is crucial for the parasite to establish an intracellular lifestyle and ultimately cause disease. The IMC is composed of both membrane and cytoskeletal components, further delineated into the apical cap, body, and basal subcompartments. The apical cap cytoskeleton was recently demonstrated to govern the stability of the apical complex, which controls parasite motility, invasion, and egress. While this role was determined by individually assessing the apical cap proteins AC9, AC10, and the MAP kinase ERK7, how the three proteins collaborate to stabilize the apical complex is unknown. In this study, we use a combination of deletion analyses and yeast-2-hybrid experiments to establish that these proteins form an essential complex in the apical cap. We show that AC10 is a foundational component of the AC10:AC9:ERK7 complex and demonstrate that the interactions among them are critical to maintain the apical complex. Importantly, we identify multiple independent regions of pairwise interaction between each of the three proteins, suggesting that the AC9:AC10:ERK7 complex is organized by multivalent interactions. Together, these data support a model in which multiple interacting domains enable the oligomerization of the AC9:AC10:ERK7 complex and its assembly into the cytoskeletal IMC, which serves as a structural scaffold that concentrates ERK7 kinase activity in the apical cap.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The phylum Apicomplexa consists of obligate, intracellular parasites including the causative agents of toxoplasmosis, malaria, and cryptosporidiosis. Hallmarks of these parasites are the IMC and the apical complex, both of which are unique structures that are conserved throughout the phylum and required for parasite survival. The apical cap portion of the IMC has previously been shown to stabilize the apical complex. Here, we expand on those studies to determine the precise protein-protein interactions of the apical cap complex that confer this essential function. We describe the multivalent nature of these interactions and show that the resulting protein oligomers likely tether ERK7 in the apical cap. This study represents the first description of the architecture of the apical cap at a molecular level, expanding our understanding of the unique cell biology that drives &lt;italic&gt;Toxoplasma&lt;/italic&gt; infections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474968" rel="alternate" title="Multivalent interactions drive the Toxoplasma AC9:AC10:ERK7 complex to concentrate ERK7 in the apical cap (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.475014</id><title>Herpes simplex virus 1 expressing GFP-tagged virion host shutoff (vhs) protein uncouples the activities of degradation and nuclear retention of the infected cell transcriptome (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.033727+00:00</updated><author><name>Emma L Wise</name></author><author><name>Jerzy Samolej</name></author><author><name>Gillian Elliott</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Virion host shutoff (vhs) protein is an endoribonuclease encoded by herpes simplex virus 1 (HSV1). Vhs causes a number of changes to the infected cell environment that favour translation of late (L) virus proteins: cellular mRNAs are degraded, immediate-early (IE) and early (E) viral transcripts are sequestered in the nucleus with polyA binding protein (PABPC1), and dsRNA is degraded to help dampen the PKR-dependent stress response. To further our understanding of the cell biology of vhs, we constructed a virus expressing vhs tagged at its C-terminus with GFP. When first expressed, vhs-GFP localised to juxtanuclear clusters, and later it colocalised and interacted with its binding partner VP16, and was packaged into virions. Despite vhs-GFP maintaining activity when expressed in isolation, it failed to degrade mRNA or relocalise PABPC1 during infection, while viral transcript levels were similar to those seen for a vhs knockout virus. PKR phosphorylation was also enhanced in vhs-GFP infected cells, in line with a failure to degrade dsRNA. Nonetheless, mRNA FISH revealed that as in Wt but not Δvhs infection, IE and E, but not L transcripts were retained in the nucleus of vhs-GFP infected cells at late times. Moreover, a representative cellular transcript which is ordinarily highly susceptible to vhs degradation, was also retained in the nucleus. These results reveal that the vhs-induced nuclear retention of the infected cell transcriptome is dependent on vhs expression but not on its endoribonuclease activity, uncoupling these two functions of vhs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like many viruses, herpes simplex virus 1 (HSV1) expresses an endoribonuclease, the virion host shutoff (vhs) protein, which regulates the RNA environment of the infected cell and facilitates the classical cascade of virus protein translation. It does this by causing the degradation of some mRNA molecules and the nuclear retention of others. Here we describe a virus expressing vhs tagged at its C-terminus with green fluorescent protein (GFP) and show that the vhs-GFP fusion protein retains the physical properties of native vhs, but does not induce the degradation of mRNA. Nonetheless, vhs-GFP maintains the ability to trap the infected cell transcriptome in the nucleus, proving for the first time that mRNA degradation is not a prerequisite for vhs effects on the nuclear transcriptome. This virus has therefore uncoupled the nuclear retention and degradation activities of vhs, providing new understanding of vhs during infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.475014" rel="alternate" title="Herpes simplex virus 1 expressing GFP-tagged virion host shutoff (vhs) protein uncouples the activities of degradation and nuclear retention of the infected cell transcriptome (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474879</id><title>Core Microbiota Drive the Prevalence of Extracellular Antibiotic Resistome in the Water Compartments (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.033898+00:00</updated><author><name>Kai-Feng Yu</name></author><author><name>Peng Li</name></author><author><name>Yuansheng Huang</name></author><author><name>Jun Yang</name></author><author><name>Han Li</name></author><author><name>Yu Xie</name></author><author><name>Rui Li</name></author><author><name>Bo Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yiliang He</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Unlike intracellular chromosome, extracellular DNA (eDNA) may accelerate the spreading of antibiotic resistance genes (ARGs) through natural transformation, but one of the core issues regarding to the taxonomic characterization of eDNA in the complex water environments is largely unknown. Hence, Illumina Miseq sequencing was used to identify the genotype of eDNA from wastewater (WW), river water (RW) and stormwater (SW) runoff. High-throughput qPCR targeting 384 genes was implemented to detect extracellular ARGs (eARGs) and mobile genetic elements (eMGEs). We obtained 2,708,291 high quality sequences from 66 eDNA samples. The SW exhibited the significant higher Shannon Index. Subsequently, we identified 34 core bacteria sources of eDNA widely distributed in the three water compartments. Among which, Pseudomonas, Flavobacterium, Limnohabitans, Burkholderiaceae_unclassified, Methylotenera and Acinetobacter were the most prevalent. A total of 302 eARGs and eMGEs were detected, suggesting that eDNA is an important antibiotic resistance reservoir. Among the 127 shared genes of the three groups, 15 core resistance genes were filtered, including IS6100, sul1 NEW, intI1, ISPps1-pseud, aac3-Via, qacH_351 and ISSm2-Xanthob. The Procrustes analysis and Variance Partitioning Analysis (VPA) demonstrated that core bacteria and MGEs were significantly correlated with eARGs. These results suggested that the occurrence and changes of eARGs in the water compartments may be largely attributed to the core microbiota and eMGEs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474879" rel="alternate" title="Core Microbiota Drive the Prevalence of Extracellular Antibiotic Resistome in the Water Compartments (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.475000</id><title>Combination therapy of metformin with sodium selenite reverses effects of monotherapy on nitric oxide production, IL-1β and TNF-α release, and upregulates relative expression of Bcl-2 by LPS-activated human primary monocytes in T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.034141+00:00</updated><author><name>Fella Rostane</name></author><author><name>Nidel Sari</name></author><author><name>Ilyes Bali</name></author><author><name>Rabia Messali</name></author><author><name>Zeyneb Hadjidj</name></author><author><name>Maroua Miliani</name></author><author><name>Imène Belhassena</name></author><author><name>Charazed El Mezouar</name></author><author><name>Mourad Aribi</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We examined the influence of the &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; combination therapy of metformin (Met, 1,1-dimethylbiguanide hydrochloride) with sodium selenite (Ss, Na&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;SeO&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;) on the changes in the production of nitric oxide (NO) and selected cytokines by circulating monocytes (MOs) during T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia (T-ALL).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assays were performed on MO cell samples isolated from children with T-ALL.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Met+Ss combination therapy reversed the Ss effect on the upregulation of NO production. Both Met+Ss and Ss treatment alone induced a significant downregulation of extracellular calcium ions consumption (&lt;sub&gt;ec&lt;/sub&gt;Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;) levels. Additionally, Met treatment induced a significant upregulation of IL-1β and TNF-α production; such effects were significantly reversed after combination with Ss treatment. Moreover, Met+Ss induced no significant effect on the production of IL-10, IL-6 and TNF-α, but a slight increase in IFN-γ levels. Furthermore, treatment with Ss alone induced a slight increase of IFN-γ. Finally, Met+Ss induced a marked upregulation of relative Bcl-2 expression in MOs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Met+Ss combination therapy results in downregulation of NO production, IL-1β and TNF-α release as well as in upregulation of the relative expression levels of Bcl-2-associated survival of primary MOs in human T-ALL.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.475000" rel="alternate" title="Combination therapy of metformin with sodium selenite reverses effects of monotherapy on nitric oxide production, IL-1β and TNF-α release, and upregulates relative expression of Bcl-2 by LPS-activated human primary monocytes in T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474767</id><title>Understanding drivers of phylogenetic clustering and terminal branch lengths distribution in epidemics of Mycobacterium tuberculosis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.034377+00:00</updated><author><name>Fabrizio Menardo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Detecting factors associated with transmission is important to understand disease epidemics, and to design effective public health measures. Clustering and terminal branch lengths (TBL) analyses are commonly applied to genomic data sets of &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; (MTB) to identify sub-populations with increased transmission. Here, I used a simulation-based approach to investigate what epidemiological processes influence the results of clustering and TBL analyses, and whether difference in transmission can be detected with these methods. I simulated MTB epidemics with different dynamics (latency, infectious period, transmission rate, basic reproductive number R&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;, sampling proportion, and molecular clock), and found that all these factors, except the length of the infectious period and R&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;, affect the results of clustering and TBL distributions. I show that standard interpretations of this type of analyses ignore two main caveats: 1) clustering results and TBL depend on many factors that have nothing to do with transmission, 2) clustering results and TBL do not tell anything about whether the epidemic is stable, growing, or shrinking. An important consequence is that the optimal SNP threshold for clustering depends on the epidemiological conditions, and that sub-populations with different epidemiological characteristics should not be analyzed with the same threshold. Finally, these results suggest that different clustering rates and TBL distributions, that are found consistently between different MTB lineages, are probably due to intrinsic bacterial factors, and do not indicate necessarily differences in transmission or evolutionary success.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474767" rel="alternate" title="Understanding drivers of phylogenetic clustering and terminal branch lengths distribution in epidemics of Mycobacterium tuberculosis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475262</id><title>Release of acidic store calcium is required for effective priming of the NLRP3 inflammasome (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.034536+00:00</updated><author><name>Nick Platt</name></author><author><name>Dawn Shepherd</name></author><author><name>Yuzhe Weng</name></author><author><name>Grant Charles Churchill</name></author><author><name>Antony Galione</name></author><author><name>Frances M. Platt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The lysosome is a dynamic signaling organelle that is critical for cell functioning. It is a regulated calcium store that can contribute to Ca2+-regulated processes via both local calcium release and more globally by influencing ER Ca2+release. Here, we provide evidence from studies of an authentic mouse model of the lysosomal storage disease Niemann-Pick Type C (NPC) that has reduced lysosomal Ca2+ levels, and genetically modified mice in which the two-pore lysosomal Ca2+ release channel family are deleted that lysosomal Ca2+ signaling is required for normal pro-inflammatory responses. We demonstrate that production of the pro-inflammatory cytokine IL-1beta via the NLRP3 inflammasome is significantly reduced in murine Niemann-Pick Type C, the inhibition is selective because secretion of TNF alpha is not diminished, and it is a consequence of inefficient inflammasome priming.  Synthesis of precursor ProIL-1 beta is significantly reduced in macrophages genetically deficient in the lysosomal protein Npc1, which is mutated in most clinical cases of NPC, and in wild type cells in which Npc1 activity is pharmacologically inhibited. Comparable reductions in ProIL-1 beta generation were measured in vitro and in vivo by macrophages genetically altered to lack expression of the two-pore lysosomal Ca2+ release channels Tpcn1 or Tpcn2. These data demonstrate a requirement for lysosome-dependent Ca2+ signaling in the generation of specific pro-inflammatory responses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475262" rel="alternate" title="Release of acidic store calcium is required for effective priming of the NLRP3 inflammasome (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474996</id><title>Human land-use impacts viral diversity and abundance in a New Zealand river (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.034927+00:00</updated><author><name>Rebecca French</name></author><author><name>Justine Charon</name></author><author><name>Callum Le Lay</name></author><author><name>Chris Muller</name></author><author><name>Edward C. Holmes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Although water-borne viruses have important implications for the health of humans and other animals, little is known about the impact of human land-use on viral diversity and evolution in water systems such as rivers. We used metagenomic next-generation sequencing to compare the diversity and abundance of viruses at sampling sites along a single river in New Zealand that differed in human land use impact, ranging from pristine to urban. From this we identified 504 putative virus species, of which 97% were novel. Many of the novel viruses were highly divergent, and likely included a new subfamily within the &lt;italic&gt;Parvoviridae&lt;/italic&gt;. We identified at least 63 virus species that may infect vertebrates – most likely fish and water birds – from the &lt;italic&gt;Astroviridae, Birnaviridae, Parvoviridae&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Picornaviridae&lt;/italic&gt;. No putative human viruses were detected. Importantly, we observed differences in the composition of viral communities at sites impacted by human land-use (farming and urban) compared to native forest sites (pristine). At the viral species level, the urban sites had higher diversity (327 virus species) than the farming (n=150) and pristine sites (n=119), and more viruses were shared between the urban and farming sites (n=76) than between the pristine and farming or urban sites (n=24). The two farming sites had a lower viral abundance across all host types, while the pristine sites had a higher abundance of viruses associated with animals, plants and fungi. We also identified viruses linked to agriculture and human impact at the river sampling sites in farming and urban areas that were not present at the native forest sites. Overall, our study shows that human land-use can impact viral communities in rivers, such that further work is needed to reduce the impact of intensive farming and urbanization on water systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474996" rel="alternate" title="Human land-use impacts viral diversity and abundance in a New Zealand river (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474823</id><title>Cell type specific IL-27p28 (IL-30) deletion uncovers an unexpected pro-inflammatory property of IL-30 in autoimmune inflammation (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.035283+00:00</updated><author><name>Dongkyun Kim</name></author><author><name>Sohee Kim</name></author><author><name>Zhinan Yin</name></author><author><name>Booki Min</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;IL-27 is an IL-12 family cytokine with potent immunoregulatory properties, capable of modulating inflammatory responses, including autoimmunity. While extensive studies have been performed to investigate the major target cells of IL-27 mediating its functions, the source of IL-27 especially during tissue specific autoimmune inflammation has not formally been tested. IL-27p28 subunit, also known as IL-30, was initially discovered as an IL-27-specific subunit, and its expression has thus been used as a surrogate for IL-27. However, there is emerging evidence that IL-27p28 can be secreted without Ebi3, a subunit that forms IL-27 with IL-27p28. Furthermore, IL-27p28 was also reported to act as a negative regulator antagonizing IL-27. In this study, we utilized various cell type specific IL-27p28-deficient mouse models and examined the major source of IL-27p28 in T cell mediated autoimmune neuroinflammation. We found that dendritic cell-derived IL-27p28 is dispensable for the disease development but that IL-27p28 expressed by infiltrating and CNS resident APC subsets, namely, infiltrating monocytes, microglia, and astrocytes, play an essential role in limiting inflammation. Unexpectedly, we observed that cell type specific IL-27p28 deficiency expressing severe disease phenotype is associated with dysregulated IL-27p28 expression in otherwise unaffected APC subsets, suggesting that disproportionate IL-27p28 expressed may increase disease susceptibility. Indeed, systemic recombinant IL-30 administration also induced severe disease. Taken together, our results uncover a pro-inflammatory property of IL-30 that supports encephalitogenic immunity in vivo.&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474823" rel="alternate" title="Cell type specific IL-27p28 (IL-30) deletion uncovers an unexpected pro-inflammatory property of IL-30 in autoimmune inflammation (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475013</id><title>Presence of sodium taurocholate co-transporting polypeptide and Hepatitis B replication marker on placenta: Another home for the virus (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.035493+00:00</updated><author><name>Garima Garg</name></author><author><name>Meenu MN</name></author><author><name>Kajal Patel</name></author><author><name>Shashank Purwar</name></author><author><name>Sramana Mukhopadhyay</name></author><author><name>Nitu Mishra</name></author><author><name>Sudheer Gupta</name></author><author><name>Sumit Kumar Rawat</name></author><author><name>Ritu Khosla</name></author><author><name>Jitendra Singh</name></author><author><name>Shashwati Nema</name></author><author><name>Debasis Biswas</name></author><author><name>Anirudh K Singh</name></author><author><name>Ashish Kumar Vyas</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The role of sodium taurocholate co-transporting polypeptide (NTCP), in facilitating the binding of Hepatitis B virus (HBV) on surface of hepatocytes is well documented. Expression of NTCP in extra hepatic cells may make these cells susceptible to HBV infection and support cellular proliferation akin to hepatocytes. &lt;italic&gt;Placental replication of HBV is not well explored&lt;/italic&gt;. In this study we have assessed the expression of NTCP and HBV replication markers (HBeAg, HBcAg, and HBV DNA) in placental cells, to investigate if these cells act as host for HBV.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fourty one HBsAg+ve pregnant women along with 10 healthy controls were enrolled after obtaining informed consent. The HBV DNA in placenta was detected by qPCR using primers for X and core ORF. Expression of NTCP in placenta was analyzed by qRT-PCR and further investigated by immunohistochemistry (IHC) along with HBV replication biomarkers, HBeAg, and HBcAg.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;HBsAg positive subjects were divided in two groups on the basis of viral load [High Viral Load (HVL) Group; viral load ≥ 2000IU/ml, Low Viral Load (LVL) Group; viral load &amp;lt;2000IU/ml] according to INASL guidelines 2018. HBV infected females showed increased expression of NTCP in trophoblasts of placenta compared to control group (HVL 3.69±0.13 Vs Control 1.74±0.15, p=0.0117). Furthermore, significant difference in NTCP expression was also observed between HVL and LVL group (HVL 3.69±0.13 Vs LVL 1.98±0.17, p=0.022) and positively correlated with the maternal HBV DNA load. Membranous and/or cytoplasmic immunostaining of NTCP, and cytoplasmic staining of HBeAg and HBcAg in trophoblasts along with presence of HBV DNA indicated that trophoblasts are not only susceptible to HBV infection but may also be a site for viral replication.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the pioneer study, which demonstrates expression of NTCP on placenta which may facilitate the entry of HBV. Furthermore, the study establishes the presence of HBeAg in placenta of patients without circulating HBeAg, indicating these cells may act as replication host/reservoir. This pioneering finding hints at the possibility of exploring the potential of NTCP blocking strategies in preventing vertical transmission of HBV.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475013" rel="alternate" title="Presence of sodium taurocholate co-transporting polypeptide and Hepatitis B replication marker on placenta: Another home for the virus (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>