<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.250254+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472703</id><title>Linear plasmids in Klebsiella and other Enterobacteriaceae (86 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.250590+00:00</updated><author><name>Jane Hawkey</name></author><author><name>Hugh Cottingham</name></author><author><name>Alex Tokolyi</name></author><author><name>Ryan R. Wick</name></author><author><name>Louise M. Judd</name></author><author><name>Louise Cerdeira</name></author><author><name>Doroti de Oliveira Garcia</name></author><author><name>Kelly L. Wyres</name></author><author><name>Kathryn E. Holt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Linear plasmids are extrachromosomal DNA that have been found in a small number of bacterial species. To date, the only linear plasmids described in the Enterobacteriaceae family belong to &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella,&lt;/italic&gt; first found in &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; Typhi. Here, we describe a collection of 12 isolates of the &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; species complex in which we identified linear plasmids. We used this collection to search public sequence databases and discovered an additional 74 linear plasmid sequences in a variety of Enterobacteriaceae species. Gene content analysis divided these plasmids into five distinct phylogroups, with very few genes shared across more than two phylogroups. The majority of linear plasmid-encoded genes are of unknown function, however each phylogroup carried its own unique toxin-antitoxin system and genes with homology to those encoding the ParAB plasmid stability system. Passage &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; of the 12 linear plasmid-carrying &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella&lt;/italic&gt; isolates in our collection (which include representatives of all five phylogroups) indicated that these linear plasmids can be stably maintained, and our data suggest they can transmit between &lt;italic&gt;K. pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; strains (including members of globally disseminated multidrug resistant clones) and also between diverse Enterobacteriaceae species. The linear plasmid sequences, and representative isolates harbouring them, are made available as a resource to facilitate future studies on the evolution and function of these novel plasmids.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance as a BioResource to the community&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study provides the first report of linear plasmids identified within the &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; species complex and the first report in Enterobacteriaceae besides &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella.&lt;/italic&gt;We present the first comparative analysis of linear plasmid sequences in Enterobacteriaceae, however whilst this family is highly clinically significant, the functional and/or evolutionary importance of these plasmids is not yet clear. To facilitate future studies to address these questions, we have publicly deposited (i) the collection of linear plasmid sequence data; (ii) isolates representative of each of the distinct linear plasmid phylogroups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;The authors confirm all supporting data, code and protocols have been provided within the article or through supplementary information&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whole genome sequence reads from &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; isolates sequenced in this study have been deposited in NCBI SRA under the accession numbers listed in &lt;bold&gt;Table S1&lt;/bold&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative annotated sequences of one linear plasmid per phylogroup have been deposited in FigShare, &lt;bold&gt;doi 10.26180/16729126&lt;/bold&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;A copy of all linear plasmid sequences that we assembled from publicly available genome sequence reads are available in FigShare, &lt;bold&gt;doi 10.26180/16531365&lt;/bold&gt;. Read accessions for these are given in &lt;bold&gt;Table S1&lt;/bold&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eleven representative &lt;italic&gt;K. pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; isolates harbouring linear plasmids described in this study have been deposited with the National Collection of Type Cultures (NCTC) and are available for purchase under the NCTC accession numbers listed in &lt;bold&gt;Table S1.&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;K. pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; 1194/11 (representative of phylogroup B) has been deposited in the Microorganisms Collection Center, Adolfo Lutz Institute, São Paulo, Brazil. To request strain 1194/11 (IAL 3063, SISGEN ABBF09B), contact:
&lt;list list-type="simple"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Microorganisms Collection Center&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Culture Collection Laboratory&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instituto Adolfo Lutz, Sao Paulo State Department of Health&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Address: Av Dr Arnaldo, 351, 10 floor, room 1020&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Phone number: +55 11 3068-2884&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zip code 01246-000, São Paulo, Brazil&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;E-mail: &lt;email&gt;colecaoial@ial.sp.gov.br&lt;/email&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alignments of terminal inverted repeat sequences for each phylogroup can be found in &lt;bold&gt;Data S1&lt;/bold&gt;, available on FigShare, &lt;bold&gt;doi 10.26180/16531371&lt;/bold&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472703" rel="alternate" title="Linear plasmids in Klebsiella and other Enterobacteriaceae (86 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473116</id><title>Intra-colony channel morphology in Escherichia coli biofilms is governed by nutrient availability and substrate stiffness (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.250944+00:00</updated><author><name>Beatrice Bottura</name></author><author><name>Liam M Rooney</name></author><author><name>Paul A Hoskisson</name></author><author><name>Gail McConnell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nutrient-transporting channels are found throughout mature Escherichia coli biofilms, however the influence of environmental conditions on intra-colony channel formation is poorly understood. We report the effect of different substrate nutrient concentrations and agar stiffness on the structure and distribution of intra-colony channels in mature E. coli colony biofilms using fluorescence mesoscopy and quantitative image analysis. Intra-colony channel width was observed to increase non-linearly with radial distance from the centre of the biofilm and channels were, on average, 50% wider at the centre of carbon-limited biofilms compared to nitrogen-limited biofilms. Channel density also differed in colonies grown on rich and minimal medium substrates, with the former creating a network of tightly packed channels and the latter leading to well-separated, wider channels with easily identifiable edges. We conclude that intra-colony channel morphology in E. coli biofilms is influenced by both substrate composition and nutrient availability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473116" rel="alternate" title="Intra-colony channel morphology in Escherichia coli biofilms is governed by nutrient availability and substrate stiffness (20 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472321</id><title>Insights into the role of lipoteichoic acids in Bacillus subtilis- a new function for MprF (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.251085+00:00</updated><author><name>Aurélie Guyet</name></author><author><name>Amirah Alofi</name></author><author><name>Richard A. Daniel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus subtilis,&lt;/italic&gt; the cell is protected from the environment by a cell envelope, which comprises of layers of peptidoglycan that maintain the cell shape and anionic teichoic acids polymers whose biological function remains unclear. In &lt;italic&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/italic&gt;, loss of all Class A Penicillin-Binding Proteins (aPBPs) which function in peptidoglycan synthesis is conditionally lethal. Here we show that this lethality is associated with an alteration of the lipoteichoic acids (LTA) and the accumulation of the major autolysin LytE in the cell wall. We provide the first evidence that the length and abundance of LTA acts to regulate the cellular level of LytE. Importantly, we identify a novel function for the aminoacyl-phosphatidylglycerol synthase MprF which acts to modulate LTA biosynthesis in &lt;italic&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; and in the pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/italic&gt;. This finding has implications for our understanding of antimicrobial peptide resistance (particularly daptomycin) in clinically relevant bacteria and MprF-associated virulence in pathogens, such as methicillin resistant &lt;italic&gt;S. aureus&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472321" rel="alternate" title="Insights into the role of lipoteichoic acids in Bacillus subtilis- a new function for MprF (18 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472606</id><title>A world of viruses nested within parasites: Unraveling viral diversity within parasitic flatworms (Platyhelminthes) (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.251211+00:00</updated><author><name>Nolwenn M Dheilly</name></author><author><name>Pierrick Lucas</name></author><author><name>Yannick Blanchard</name></author><author><name>Karyna Rosario</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Because parasites have an inextricable relationship with their host, they have the potential to serve as viral reservoirs or facilitate virus host-shifts. Yet, little is known about viruses infecting parasitic hosts except for blood-feeding arthropods that are well-known vectors of zoonotic viruses. Herein we uncover viruses of flatworms (Phylum Platyhelminthes, group Neodermata) that specialize in parasitizing vertebrates and their ancestral free-living relatives. We discovered 115 novel viral sequences, including 1 in Macrostomorpha, 5 in Polycladida, 44 in Tricladida, 1 in Monogenea, 15 in Cestoda and 49 in Trematoda, through data mining. The majority of newly identified viruses constitute novel families or genera. Phylogenetic analyses show that the virome of flatworms changed dramatically during the transition of Neodermatans to a parasitic lifestyle. Most Neodermatan viruses seem to co-diversify with their host, with the exception of rhabdoviruses which may switch host more often, based on phylogenetic relationships. Neodermatan rhabodviruses also have an ancestral position to vertebrate-associated viruses, including Lyssaviruses, suggesting that vertebrate rhabdoviruses emerged from a flatworm rhabdovirus in a parasitized host. This study reveals an extensive diversity of viruses in Platyhelminthes and highlights the need to evaluate the role of viral infection in flatworm-associated diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472606" rel="alternate" title="A world of viruses nested within parasites: Unraveling viral diversity within parasitic flatworms (Platyhelminthes) (16 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472530</id><title>The ColR/S two-component system is a conserved determinant of host association across Pseudomonas species (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.251337+00:00</updated><author><name>Christina L. Wiesmann</name></author><author><name>Yue Zhang</name></author><author><name>Morgan Alford</name></author><author><name>David Thoms</name></author><author><name>Melanie Dostert</name></author><author><name>Andrew Wilson</name></author><author><name>Daniel Pletzer</name></author><author><name>Robert E. W. Hancock</name></author><author><name>Cara H. Haney</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Members of the bacterial genus &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/italic&gt; form mutualistic, commensal and pathogenic associations with diverse hosts. The prevalence of host association across the genus suggests that symbiosis may be a conserved ancestral trait and that distinct symbiotic lifestyles may be more recently evolved. Here we show that the ColR/S two-component system, part of the &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/italic&gt; core genome, is functionally conserved between &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas fluorescens&lt;/italic&gt;. Using plant rhizosphere colonization and virulence in a murine abscess model, we show that &lt;italic&gt;colR&lt;/italic&gt; is required for commensalism with plants and virulence in animals. Comparative transcriptomics revealed that the ColR regulon has diverged between &lt;italic&gt;P. aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;P. fluorescens&lt;/italic&gt; and deleting components of the ColR regulon revealed strain-specific, but not hostspecific, requirements for ColR-dependent genes. Collectively, our results suggest that ColR/S allows &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/italic&gt; to sense and respond to a host, but that the ColR-regulon has diverged between &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/italic&gt; strains with distinct lifestyles.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472530" rel="alternate" title="The ColR/S two-component system is a conserved determinant of host association across Pseudomonas species (15 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472285</id><title>Adaptive discrimination of antigen risk by predictive coding in immune system (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.251648+00:00</updated><author><name>Kana Yoshido</name></author><author><name>Honda Naoki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The immune system discriminates between harmful and harmless antigens based on past experiences; however, the underlying mechanism is largely unknown. From the viewpoint of machine learning, the learning system predicts the observation and updates the prediction based on prediction error, a process known as ‘predictive coding’. Here, we modeled the population dynamics of T cells by adopting the concept of predictive coding; helper and regulatory T cells predict the antigen amount and excessive immune response, respectively. Their prediction error signals, possibly via cytokines, induce their differentiation to memory T cells. Through numerical simulations, we found that the immune system identifies antigen risks depending on the concentration and input rapidness of the antigen. Further, our model reproduced history-dependent discrimination, as in allergy onset and subsequent therapy. Together, this study provided a novel framework to improve our understanding of how the immune system adaptively learns the risks of diverse antigens.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472285" rel="alternate" title="Adaptive discrimination of antigen risk by predictive coding in immune system (15 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473053</id><title>Prediction of prophages and their host ranges in pathogenic and commensal Neisseria species (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.251784+00:00</updated><author><name>Giulia Orazi</name></author><author><name>Alan J Collins</name></author><author><name>Rachel J Whitaker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The genus &lt;italic&gt;Neisseria&lt;/italic&gt; includes two pathogenic species, &lt;italic&gt;N. gonorrhoeae&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;N. meningitidis&lt;/italic&gt;, and numerous commensal species. &lt;italic&gt;Neisseria&lt;/italic&gt; species frequently exchange DNA with one other, primarily via transformation and homologous recombination, and via multiple types of mobile genetic elements (MGEs). Few &lt;italic&gt;Neisseria&lt;/italic&gt; bacteriophages (phages) have been identified and their impact on bacterial physiology is poorly understood. Furthermore, little is known about the range of species that &lt;italic&gt;Neisseria&lt;/italic&gt; phages can infect. In this study, we used three virus prediction tools to scan 248 genomes of 21 different &lt;italic&gt;Neisseria&lt;/italic&gt; species and identified 1302 unique predicted prophages. Using comparative genomics, we found that many predictions are dissimilar from other prophages and MGEs previously described to infect &lt;italic&gt;Neisseria&lt;/italic&gt; species. We also identified similar predicted prophages in genomes of different &lt;italic&gt;Neisseria&lt;/italic&gt; species. Additionally, we examined CRISPR-Cas targeting of each &lt;italic&gt;Neisseria&lt;/italic&gt; genome and predicted prophage. While CRISPR targeting of chromosomal DNA appears to be common among several &lt;italic&gt;Neisseria&lt;/italic&gt; species, we found that 20% of the prophages we predicted are targeted significantly more than the rest of the bacterial genome in which they were identified (i.e., backbone). Furthermore, many predicted prophages are targeted by CRISPR spacers encoded by other species. We then used these results to infer additional host species of known &lt;italic&gt;Neisseria&lt;/italic&gt; prophages and predictions that are highly targeted relative to the backbone. Together, our results suggest that we have identified novel &lt;italic&gt;Neisseria&lt;/italic&gt; prophages, several of which may infect multiple &lt;italic&gt;Neisseria&lt;/italic&gt; species. These findings have important implications for understanding horizontal gene transfer between members of this genus. IMPORTANCE: Drug-resistant &lt;italic&gt;N. gonorrhoeae&lt;/italic&gt; is a major threat to human health. Commensal &lt;italic&gt;Neisseria&lt;/italic&gt; species are thought to serve as reservoirs of antibiotic resistance and virulence genes for the pathogenic species &lt;italic&gt;N. gonorrhoeae&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;N. meningitidis&lt;/italic&gt;. Therefore, it is important to understand both the diversity of mobile genetic elements (MGEs) that can mediate horizontal gene transfer within this genus, and the breadth of species these MGEs can infect. In particular, few bacteriophages (phages) have been identified and characterized in &lt;italic&gt;Neisseria&lt;/italic&gt; species. In this study, we identified a large number of candidate phages integrated within the genomes of commensal and pathogenic &lt;italic&gt;Neisseria&lt;/italic&gt; species, many of which appear to be novel phages. Importantly, we discovered extensive interspecies targeting of predicted phages by &lt;italic&gt;Neisseria&lt;/italic&gt; CRISPR-Cas systems, which may reflect their movement between different species. Uncovering the diversity and host range of phages is essential for understanding how they influence the evolution of their microbial hosts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473053" rel="alternate" title="Prediction of prophages and their host ranges in pathogenic and commensal Neisseria species (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473081</id><title>Biology and engineering of integrative and conjugative elements: Construction and analyses of hybrid ICEs reveal element functions that affect species-specific efficiencies (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.251975+00:00</updated><author><name>Emily L Bean</name></author><author><name>Calvin Herman</name></author><author><name>Alan D. Grossman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Integrative and conjugative elements (ICEs) are mobile genetic elements that reside in a bacterial host chromosome and are prominent drivers of bacterial evolution. They are also powerful tools for genetic analyses and engineering. Transfer of an ICE to a new host involves many steps, including excision from the chromosome, DNA processing and replication, transfer across the envelope of the donor and recipient, processing of the DNA, and eventual integration into the chromosome of the new host (now a stable transconjugant). Interactions between an ICE and its hosts throughout the life cycle likely influence the efficiencies of acquisition by new hosts. Here, we investigated how different functional modules of two ICEs, Tn&lt;italic&gt;916&lt;/italic&gt; and ICE&lt;italic&gt;Bs1&lt;/italic&gt;, affect the transfer efficiencies into different host bacteria. We constructed hybrid elements that utilize the high-efficiency regulatory and excision modules of ICE&lt;italic&gt;Bs1&lt;/italic&gt; and the conjugation genes of Tn&lt;italic&gt;916&lt;/italic&gt;. These elements produced more transconjugants than Tn&lt;italic&gt;916&lt;/italic&gt;, likely due to increased excision frequencies. We also found that several Tn&lt;italic&gt;916&lt;/italic&gt; and ICE&lt;italic&gt;Bs1&lt;/italic&gt; components can substitute for one other. Using &lt;italic&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; donors and three &lt;italic&gt;Enterococcus&lt;/italic&gt; species as recipients, we found that different hybrid elements were more readily acquired by some species than others, demonstrating species-specific interactions in steps of the ICE life cycle. This work demonstrates that hybrid elements utilizing the efficient regulatory functions of ICE&lt;italic&gt;Bs1&lt;/italic&gt; can be built to enable efficient transfer into and engineering of a variety of other species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473081" rel="alternate" title="Biology and engineering of integrative and conjugative elements: Construction and analyses of hybrid ICEs reveal element functions that affect species-specific efficiencies (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472764</id><title>Bacterial origin of thymidylate and folate metabolism in Asgard Archaea (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.252116+00:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Filée</name></author><author><name>Hubert F. Becker</name></author><author><name>Lucille Mellottee</name></author><author><name>Zhihui Li</name></author><author><name>Jean-Christophe Lambry</name></author><author><name>Ursula Liebl</name></author><author><name>Hannu Myllykallio</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Little is known about the evolution and biosynthetic function of DNA precursor and the folate metabolism in the Asgard group of archaea. As Asgard occupy a key position in the archaeal and eukaryotic phylogenetic trees, we have exploited very recently emerged genome and metagenome sequence information to investigate these central metabolic pathways. Our genome-wide analyses revealed that the recently cultured Asgard archaeon &lt;italic&gt;Candidatus&lt;/italic&gt; Prometheoarchaeum syntrophicum strain MK-D1 (&lt;italic&gt;Psyn&lt;/italic&gt;) contains a complete folate-dependent network for the biosynthesis of DNA/RNA precursors, amino acids and syntrophic amino acid utilization. Altogether our experimental and computational data suggest that phylogenetic incongruences of functional folate-dependent enzymes from Asgard archaea reflect their persistent horizontal transmission from various bacterial groups, which has rewired the key metabolic reactions in an important and recently identified archaeal phylogenetic group. We also experimentally validated the functionality of the lateral gene transfer of &lt;italic&gt;Psyn&lt;/italic&gt; thymidylate synthase ThyX. This enzyme uses bacterial-like folates efficiently and is inhibited by mycobacterial ThyX inhibitors. Our data raise the possibility that the thymidylate metabolism, required for &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; DNA synthesis, originated in bacteria and has been independently transferred to archaea and eukaryotes. In conclusion, our study has revealed that recent prevalent lateral gene transfer has markedly shaped the evolution of Asgard archaea by allowing them to adapt to specific ecological niches.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472764" rel="alternate" title="Bacterial origin of thymidylate and folate metabolism in Asgard Archaea (8 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472618</id><title>Generating Electricity from Water Evaporation Through Microbial Biofilms (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.252272+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaomeng Liu</name></author><author><name>Toshiyuki Ueki</name></author><author><name>Hongyan Gao</name></author><author><name>Trevor L. Woodard</name></author><author><name>Kelly P. Nevin</name></author><author><name>Tianda Fu</name></author><author><name>Shuai Fu</name></author><author><name>Lu Sun</name></author><author><name>Derek R. Lovley</name></author><author><name>Jun Yao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sustainable strategies for energy production are required to reduce reliance on fossil fuels and to power electronics without generating toxic waste.&lt;sup&gt;1-7&lt;/sup&gt; Generating electricity from water evaporation through engineered materials is a promising approach,&lt;sup&gt;8,9&lt;/sup&gt; but power outputs have been low and the materials employed were not sustainably produced. Microorganisms can be mass produced with renewable feedstocks. Here, we demonstrate that it is possible to engineer microbial biofilms as a cohesive, flexible material for long-term continuous electricity production from evaporating water. The biofilm sheets were the functional component in devices that continuously produced power densities (∼1 μW/cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;) higher than that achieved with non-biological materials. Current production scaled directly with biofilm-sheet size and skin-patch devices harvested sufficient electricity from the moisture on skin to continuously power wearable devices. The results demonstrate that appropriately engineered biofilms can perform as robust functional materials without the need for further processing or maintaining cell viability. Biofilm-based hydroelectric current production was comparable to that achieved with similar sized biofilms catalyzing current production in microbial fuel cells,&lt;sup&gt;10,11&lt;/sup&gt; without the need for an organic feedstock or maintaining cell viability. The ubiquity of biofilms in nature suggests the possibility of additional sources of biomaterial for evaporation-based electricity generation and the possibility of harvesting electricity from diverse aqueous environments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472618" rel="alternate" title="Generating Electricity from Water Evaporation Through Microbial Biofilms (8 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472303</id><title>Dehalobium species implicated in 2,3,7,8-tetrachloro-p-dioxin dechlorination in the contaminated sediments of Sydney Harbour Estuary (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.252438+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Lee</name></author><author><name>Gan Liang</name></author><author><name>Sophie I. Holland</name></author><author><name>Casey O’Farrell</name></author><author><name>Keith Osbourne</name></author><author><name>Michael J. Manefield</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Polychlorinated dibenzo-&lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt;-dioxins and furans (PCDD/F) are some of the most environmentally recalcitrant and toxic compounds. They are naturally occurring and by-products of anthropogenic activity. Sydney Harbour Estuary (Sydney, Australia), is heavily contaminated with PCDD/F. Analysis of sediment cores revealed that the contamination source in Homebush Bay continues to have one of the highest levels of PCDD/F contamination in the world (5207 pg WHO-TEQ g&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) with &amp;gt;50% of the toxicity attributed to 2,3,7,8-tetrachlorodibenzo-&lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt;-dioxin (2,3,7,8-TCDD) the most toxic and concerning of the PCDD/F congeners. Comparison of congener profiles at the contamination source with surrounding bays and historical data provided evidence for the attenuation of 2,3,7,8-TCDD and other congeners at the source. This finding was supported by the detection of di-, mono- and unchlorinated dibenzo-&lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt;-dioxin. Microbial community analysis of sediments by 16S amplicon sequencing revealed an abundance of lineages from the class Dehalococcoidia (up to 15% of the community), including the genus &lt;italic&gt;Dehalobium&lt;/italic&gt; (up to 0.5%). Anaerobic seawater enrichment cultures using perchloroethene as a more amenable growth substrate enriched only the &lt;italic&gt;Dehalobium&lt;/italic&gt; population by more than six-fold. The enrichment culture then proved capable of reductively dechlorinating 2,3,7,8-TCDD to 2,3,7-TCDD and octachlorodibenzo-&lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt;-dibenzodioxin to hepta and hexa congeners. This work is the first to show microbial reductive dehalogenation of 2,3,7,8-TCDD with a bacterium from outside the &lt;italic&gt;Dehalococcoides&lt;/italic&gt; genus, and one of only a few that demonstrates PCDD/F degradation in a marine environment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472303" rel="alternate" title="Dehalobium species implicated in 2,3,7,8-tetrachloro-p-dioxin dechlorination in the contaminated sediments of Sydney Harbour Estuary (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472350</id><title>An amphipathic and cationic antimicrobial peptide kills colistin resistant Gram-negative pathogens in vivo (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.252577+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas T. Thomsen</name></author><author><name>Mette Kolpen</name></author><author><name>Vinoth Wigneswaran</name></author><author><name>Ulrik Kromann</name></author><author><name>Anna E. Ebbensgaard</name></author><author><name>Anette M. Hammerum</name></author><author><name>Henrik Hasman</name></author><author><name>Stine Radmer</name></author><author><name>Kasper N. Kragh</name></author><author><name>Rasmus Hartmann-Petersen</name></author><author><name>Paul Robert Hansen</name></author><author><name>Anders Folkesson</name></author><author><name>Niels Frimodt-Møller</name></author><author><name>Anders Løbner-Olesen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;New antibiotics are needed against multidrug resistant Gram-negative pathogens that have compromised global health systems. Antimicrobial peptides are generally considered promising lead candidates for the next generation of antibiotics but have not fulfilled this expectation. Here we demonstrate activity of a cationic amphipathic undecapeptide (ChIP; &lt;underline&gt;Ch&lt;/underline&gt;arge change &lt;underline&gt;I&lt;/underline&gt;ndependent &lt;underline&gt;P&lt;/underline&gt;eptide) against a wide panel of multidrug resistant Gram-negative pathogens. Importantly, the antimicrobial activity of ChIP is independent of the surface charge changes that confer colistin resistance through modification of Lipid A, while decreased activity of ChIP correlates with GlcN1 tri-acylation of Lipid A. In an &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; peritonitis mouse model ChIP displays excellent activity against both colistin sensitive and resistant &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Acinetobacter baumannii&lt;/italic&gt; strains.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Antimicrobial peptides hold promise as novel treatment options for diseases caused by multidrug resistant bacteria. Here we present evidence that the ChIP peptide, comprised of 11 D-amino acids, is active against a variety of Gram-negative bacteria that ranks high on the WHO list of critically important pathogens. ChIP initially interacts with the Gram-negative outer membrane, independent of its surface charge, followed by entry into the periplasm and permeabilization of the inner membrane, leading to bacterial cell death. Detailed analyses of the outer membrane indicate that the acylation pattern of lipopolysaccharides plays an important role for ChIP activity. In a mouse infection model, ChIP display excellent activity in reducing bacterial numbers for both &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Acinetobacter baumannii&lt;/italic&gt;. Importantly, ChIP is highly efficient against bacteria resistant to colistin, an antibiotic normally considered as a last resort treatment of infections caused by multidrug resistant Gram-negative bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472350" rel="alternate" title="An amphipathic and cationic antimicrobial peptide kills colistin resistant Gram-negative pathogens in vivo (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472971</id><title>A high-throughput neutralization assay for yellow fever serodiagnostics (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.252765+00:00</updated><author><name>Madina Rasulova</name></author><author><name>Thomas Vercruysse</name></author><author><name>Jasmine Paulissen</name></author><author><name>Catherina Coun</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Suin</name></author><author><name>Leo Heyndrickx</name></author><author><name>Ji Ma</name></author><author><name>Katrien Geerts</name></author><author><name>Jolien Timmermans</name></author><author><name>Niraj Mishra</name></author><author><name>Li-Hsin Li</name></author><author><name>Dieudonné Buh Kum</name></author><author><name>Lotte Coelmont</name></author><author><name>Steven Van Gucht</name></author><author><name>Hadi Karimzadeh</name></author><author><name>Julia Thorn-Seshold</name></author><author><name>Simon Rothenfußer</name></author><author><name>Kevin K. Ariën</name></author><author><name>Johan Neyts</name></author><author><name>Kai Dallmeier</name></author><author><name>Hendrik Jan Thibaut</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Quick and accurate detection of neutralizing antibodies (nAbs) against yellow fever is essential in  serodiagnosis during outbreaks, for surveillance and to evaluate vaccine efficacy in population-wide studies. All this requires serological assays that can process a large number of samples in a highly standardized format. Albeit being laborious, time-consuming and limited in throughput, classical plaque reduction neutralization test (PRNT) is still considered gold standard for the detection and quantification of nAbs due to its sensitivity and specificity. Here we report the development of an alternative fluorescence-based serological assay (SNTFLUO) with an equally high sensitivity and specificity that is fit for high-throughput testing with the potential for automation. Finally, our novel SNTFLUO was cross-validated in several reference laboratories and against international WHO standards showing its potential to be implemented in clinical use. SNTFLUO assays with similar performance are available for the Japanese encephalitis, Zika and dengue viruses amenable for differential diagnostics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472971" rel="alternate" title="A high-throughput neutralization assay for yellow fever serodiagnostics (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472732</id><title>Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of Vancomycin derivative LYSC98 in a Murine Thigh Infection Model against Staphylococcus aureus (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.253222+00:00</updated><author><name>Peng He</name></author><author><name>Xin Li</name></author><author><name>Xiaohan Guo</name></author><author><name>Xingchen Bian</name></author><author><name>Meiqing Feng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;LYSC98&lt;/bold&gt; is a vancomycin derivative used for gram-positive bacterial infections therapy. We reported the pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic (PK/PD) targets of LYSC98 against &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/italic&gt; using a murine thigh infection model. Three &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/italic&gt; strains were utilized. Single-dose plasma pharmacokinetics of LYSC98 were determined in infected mice after the tail vein injection of 2, 4, and 8mg/kg. The results showed maximum plasma concentration (C&lt;sub&gt;max&lt;/sub&gt;) 11466.67 - 48866.67 ng/mL, area under the concentration-time curve from 0 to 24 h(AUC&lt;sub&gt;0-24&lt;/sub&gt;) 14788.42 -91885.93 ng/mL·h, and elimination half-life(T&lt;sub&gt;1/2&lt;/sub&gt;) 1.70-2.64 h, respectively. The C&lt;sub&gt;max&lt;/sub&gt; (R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 0.9994) and AUC&lt;sub&gt;0-24&lt;/sub&gt; (R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 0.981) were positively correlated with the dose of LYSC98 in the range of 2-8 mg/kg.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dose fractionation studies using total doses of 2 to 8 mg/kg administered with q6h, q8h, q12h, and q24h were performed to evaluate the correlation of different PK/PD indices with efficacy. Sigmoid model analysis showed C&lt;sub&gt;max&lt;/sub&gt;/MIC (R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 0.8941) was the best PK/PD index to predict the efficacy of LYSC98. In the dose ranging studies, two Methicillin-resistant &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/italic&gt; (MRSA) clinical strains were used to infect the mice and 2-fold-increasing doses (1 to 16 mg/kg) of LYSC98 were administered. The magnitude of LYSC98 C&lt;sub&gt;max&lt;/sub&gt;/MIC associated with net stasis, 1, 2, 3 and 4 - log10 kill were 5.78, 8.17, 11.14, 15.85 and 30.58, respectively. The results of this study showed LYSC98 a promising antibiotic with in vivo potency against MRSA, and will help in the dose design of phase one study for LYSC98.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472732" rel="alternate" title="Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of Vancomycin derivative LYSC98 in a Murine Thigh Infection Model against Staphylococcus aureus (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473079</id><title>Assessment and Comparative Study of Biofilm Formation with frequency of Multi Drug Resistance in strains of Staphylococcus aureus (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.253370+00:00</updated><author><name>Kiran Fatima</name></author><author><name>Kashif Ali</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: The study was conducted to identify the role of biofilms in the antibiotic susceptibility in the strains of Staphylococcus aureus. A total of 19 non repeated pus/wound swab samples from different anatomic locations and 17 samples that were previously identified as S. aureus and preserved in the labs were included in the study. The Staphylococcus aureus was identified on the basis of colony morphology, Gram's stain, biochemical tests (catalase and coagulase tests) and molecular identification through PCR amplification. Methodology: A total of 26 samples were recovered out of the 31 samples. Kirby-Bauer disk diffusion susceptibility test was used to determine the sensitivity or resistance of S. aureus to methicillin. Out of the 26 strains, 4 were highly resistant, 10 were moderately resistant and 12 strains were sensitive. Three different protocols (Tube Method, Congo Red Agar Method and Tissue Culture plate method) were used for the detection of biofilm formation for both resistant and sensitive strains. Result: Comparative analysis of the antibiotic susceptibility and biofilm formation by different protocols showed that 70% strains that are resistant to antibiotic methicillin produced moderate-strong biofilms. 50% have produced the moderate-strong biofilms in all 3 protocols. In case of sensitive, 50% strains had produced none-weak biofilms in all 3 protocols. Decisions: The strains that had zone of inhibition of close to resistance produced weak-strong biofilms but they all produced weak biofilms in CRA method. It can be concluded that the strains of S. aureus that have the ability to produce biofilms become methicillin resistant. Keywords: Biofilm, antibiotic susceptibility, Congo Red Agar, Tube Method, Tissue culture plats.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473079" rel="alternate" title="Assessment and Comparative Study of Biofilm Formation with frequency of Multi Drug Resistance in strains of Staphylococcus aureus (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.471511</id><title>A core salivary microbiome shows the high prevalence of bacterial members yet variability across human populations (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.253490+00:00</updated><author><name>Xinwei Ruan</name></author><author><name>Jiaqiang Luo</name></author><author><name>Pangzhen Zhang</name></author><author><name>Kate Howell</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Human saliva contains diverse bacterial communities, reflecting human health status, dietary patterns and contributing to variability in the sensory perception of food. Many descriptions of salivary microbiome diversity compare commonalities and differences with reference to a diseased state, but the composition of healthy saliva has not been described.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we use a meta-analysis approach to define and explore the core membership of the human salivary microbial community by collecting and re-analysing raw 16S rRNA amplicon sequencing data from 47 studies with 2206 saliva samples. We found 68 core bacterial taxa that were consistently detected. Differences induced by various host intrinsic and behaviour factors, including gender, age, geographic location, tobacco usage, and alcohol consumption, were evident. The core of the salivary microbiome was verified by collecting and analysing saliva in an independent study.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;These results suggest that the methods used can effectively define a core microbial community in human saliva with high prevalence. The core salivary microbiome demonstrated both stability and variability among populations. Geographic location was identified as the host factor with the largest effect in shaping salivary microbiota. The independent analysis underlined that the impact of geographic variation is likely due to diet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.471511" rel="alternate" title="A core salivary microbiome shows the high prevalence of bacterial members yet variability across human populations (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472299</id><title>Age dependent changes in circulating Tfh cells influence the development of functional antibodies to malaria in children (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.253616+00:00</updated><author><name>Jo-Anne Chan</name></author><author><name>Jessica R Loughland</name></author><author><name>Lauren de la Parte</name></author><author><name>Satomi Okano</name></author><author><name>Isaac Ssewanyana</name></author><author><name>Mayimuna Nalubega</name></author><author><name>Felistas Nankya</name></author><author><name>Kenneth Musinguzi</name></author><author><name>John Rek</name></author><author><name>Emmanuel Arinaitwe</name></author><author><name>Peta Tipping</name></author><author><name>Peter Bourke</name></author><author><name>Dean Andrew</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Dooley</name></author><author><name>Arya SheelaNair</name></author><author><name>Bruce D Wines</name></author><author><name>Mark Hogarth</name></author><author><name>James Beeson</name></author><author><name>Bryan Greenhouse</name></author><author><name>Grant Dorsey</name></author><author><name>Moses Kamya</name></author><author><name>Gunter Hartel</name></author><author><name>Gabriela Minigo</name></author><author><name>Margaret Feeney</name></author><author><name>Prasanna Jagannathan</name></author><author><name>Michelle J Boyle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;T-follicular helper (Tfh) cells are key drivers of antibodies that protect from malaria. However, little is known regarding the host and parasite factors that influence Tfh and functional antibody development. Here, we use samples from a large cross-sectional study of children residing in an area of high malaria transmission in Uganda to characterize Tfh cells and functional antibodies to multiple parasites stages. We identify a dramatic re-distribution of the Tfh cell compartment with age that is independent of malaria exposure, with Th2-Tfh cells predominating in early childhood, while Th1-Tfh cell gradually increase to adult levels over the first decade of life. Functional antibody acquisition is age-dependent and hierarchical acquired based on parasite stage, with merozoite responses followed by sporozoite and gametocyte antibodies. Antibodies were boosted in children with current infection, and were higher in females. The children with the very highest antibody levels had increased Tfh cell activation and proliferation, consistent with a key role of Tfh cells in antibody development. Together, these data reveal a complex relationship between the circulating Tfh compartment, antibody development and protection from malaria.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472299" rel="alternate" title="Age dependent changes in circulating Tfh cells influence the development of functional antibodies to malaria in children (5 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472564</id><title>A salvaging strategy enables stable metabolite provisioning among free-living bacteria (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.253963+00:00</updated><author><name>Sebastian Gude</name></author><author><name>Gordon J. Pherribo</name></author><author><name>Michiko E. Taga</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;All organisms rely on complex metabolites such as amino acids, nucleotides, and cofactors for essential metabolic processes. Some microbes synthesize these fundamental ingredients of life &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt;, while others rely on uptake to fulfill their metabolic needs. Although certain metabolic processes are inherently ’leaky’, the mechanisms enabling stable metabolite provisioning among microbes in the absence of a host remain largely unclear. In particular, how can metabolite provisioning among free-living bacteria be maintained under the evolutionary pressure to economize resources? Salvaging, the process of ‘recycling and reusing’, can be a metabolically efficient route to obtain access to required resources. Here, we show experimentally how precursor salvaging in engineered &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; populations can lead to stable, long-term metabolite provisioning. We find that salvaged cobamides (vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; and related enzyme cofactors) are readily made available to non-productive population members, yet salvagers are strongly protected from overexploitation due to partial metabolite privatization. We also describe a previously unnoted benefit of precursor salvaging, namely the removal of the non-functional, proliferation-inhibiting precursor. As long as compatible precursors are present, any microbe possessing the terminal steps of a biosynthetic process can, in principle, forgo &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; biosynthesis in favor of salvaging. Consequently, precursor salvaging likely represents a potent, yet overlooked, alternative to &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; biosynthesis for the acquisition and provisioning of metabolites in free-living bacterial populations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472564" rel="alternate" title="A salvaging strategy enables stable metabolite provisioning among free-living bacteria (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472778</id><title>The African Swine Fever Isolate ASFV-Kenya-1033-IX is highly virulent and stable after growth in the wild boar cell line WSL (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.254116+00:00</updated><author><name>Johanneke D. Hemmink</name></author><author><name>Hussein M. Abkallo</name></author><author><name>Sonal P. Henson</name></author><author><name>Emmanuel M. Khazalwa</name></author><author><name>Bernard Oduor</name></author><author><name>Anna Lacasta</name></author><author><name>Edward Okoth</name></author><author><name>Walter Fuchs</name></author><author><name>Richard P. Bishop</name></author><author><name>Lucilla Steinaa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In this study, we describe an African swine fever genotype IX virus (ASFV-Kenya-1033-IX), which was isolated from a domestic pig in Western Kenya during a reported outbreak, including efficiency of virus replication, &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; virulence, and genome stability in pulmonary alveolar macrophages (PAM) and in a wild boar cell line (WSL). The ASFV-Kenya-1033-IX stock, which underwent multiple passages in WSL (more than 20), retained its ability to replicate in primary macrophages and it also retained the virulence &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. At the genomic level, only a few single nucleotide differences were observed between the macrophage and WSL-grown virus. Thus, we propose that the WSL cell line is suitable to produce live attenuated ASFV vaccine candidates based on this isolate and probably of similar viruses. The genome sequences for ASFV-Kenya-1033-IX grown in macrophages and in WSL cells was submitted to GenBank and a challenge model based on this isolate was set up, which will aid the development of vaccines against genotype IX ASFV circulating in Eastern and Central Africa.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472778" rel="alternate" title="The African Swine Fever Isolate ASFV-Kenya-1033-IX is highly virulent and stable after growth in the wild boar cell line WSL (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472884</id><title>Emergence of compensatory mutations reveal the importance of electrostatic interactions between HIV-1 integrase and genomic RNA (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.254287+00:00</updated><author><name>Christian Shema Mugisha</name></author><author><name>Tung Dinh</name></author><author><name>Kasyap Tenneti</name></author><author><name>Jenna Eve Eschbach</name></author><author><name>Keanu Davis</name></author><author><name>Robert Gifford</name></author><author><name>Mamuka Kvaratskhelia</name></author><author><name>Sebla Kutluay</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Independent of its catalytic activity, HIV-1 integrase (IN) enzyme regulates proper particle maturation by binding to and packaging the viral RNA genome (gRNA) inside the mature capsid lattice. Allosteric integrase inhibitors (ALLINIs) and class II IN substitutions inhibit the binding of IN to the gRNA and cause the formation of non-infectious virions characterized by mislocalization of the viral ribonucleoprotein complexes between the translucent conical capsid lattice and the viral lipid envelope. To gain insight into the molecular nature of IN-gRNA interactions, we have isolated compensatory substitutions in the background of a class II IN (R269A/K273A) variant that directly inhibits IN binding to the gRNA. We found that additional D256N and D270N substitutions in the C-terminal domain (CTD) of IN restored its ability to bind gRNA and led to the formation of infectious particles with correctly matured morphology. Furthermore, reinstating the overall positive electrostatic potential of the CTD through individual D256R or D256K substitutions was sufficient to restore IN-RNA binding and infectivity for the R269A/K273A as well as the R262A/R263A class II IN mutants. The compensatory mutations did not impact functional IN oligomerization, suggesting that they directly contributed to IN binding to the gRNA. Interestingly, HIV-1 IN R269A/K273A, but not IN R262A/R263A, bearing compensatory mutations was more sensitive to ALLINIs providing key genetic evidence that specific IN residues required for RNA binding also influence ALLINI activity. Structural modeling provided further insight into the molecular nature of IN-gRNA interactions and ALLINI mechanism of action. Taken together, our findings highlight an essential role of IN-gRNA interactions for proper virion maturation and reveal the importance of electrostatic interactions between the IN CTD and the gRNA.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472884" rel="alternate" title="Emergence of compensatory mutations reveal the importance of electrostatic interactions between HIV-1 integrase and genomic RNA (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472993</id><title>SMAD4 and TGFβ are architects of inverse genetic programs during fate-determination of antiviral memory CD8 T cells (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.254485+00:00</updated><author><name>Karthik Chandiran</name></author><author><name>Jenny Suarez-Ramirez</name></author><author><name>Yinghong Hu</name></author><author><name>Zeynep Ugur</name></author><author><name>Evan R Jellison</name></author><author><name>Jun-Siong low</name></author><author><name>Bryan McDonald</name></author><author><name>Susan M Kaech</name></author><author><name>Linda S Cauley</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Transforming growth factor β (TGFβ) is a morphogenic protein that augments antiviral immunity by altering the functional properties of pathogen-specific memory CD8 T cells. During infection, TGFβ inhibits formation of effector (TEFF) and circulating memory CD8 T cells, while encouraging tissue resident memory CD8 T cells (TRM) to settle in peripheral tissues. SMAD proteins are signaling intermediates that are used by members of the TGF cytokine family to modify gene expression. Using RNA-sequencing we determined that SMAD4 altered the transcriptional profile of antiviral CTLs during respiratory infection. Our data show that SMAD4 and TGFβ use alternate signaling pathways to cooperatively regulate a collection of genes that determine whether pathogen-specific memory CD8 T cells localize in peripheral or lymphoid tissues. During infection, SMAD4 acts independently of TGFβ to inhibit TRM development, while inducing genes that support formation of circulating memory CD8 T cells. The genes that are modulated by SMAD4 include several homing receptors (CD103, KLRG1 and CD62L) and transcription factors (Hobit and EOMES) that support memory formation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472993" rel="alternate" title="SMAD4 and TGFβ are architects of inverse genetic programs during fate-determination of antiviral memory CD8 T cells (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472734</id><title>Manganese modulates metabolic activity and redox homeostasis in translationally-blocked Lactococcus cremoris, impacting metabolic persistence, cell-culturability, and flavor formation (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.254718+00:00</updated><author><name>Avis Dwi Wahyu Nugroho</name></author><author><name>Berdien van Olst</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Agnes Bachtiar</name></author><author><name>Sjef Boeren</name></author><author><name>Michiel Kleerebezem</name></author><author><name>Herwig Bachmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Manganese (Mn) is an essential trace element that is supplemented in microbial media with varying benefits across species and growth conditions. We found that growth of &lt;italic&gt;Lactococcus cremoris&lt;/italic&gt; was unaffected by manganese omission from the growth medium. The main proteome adaptation to manganese omission involved increased manganese transporter production (up to 2000-fold), while the remaining 10 significant proteome changes were between 1.4 and 4 fold. Further investigation in translationally-blocked (TB), non-growing cells showed that Mn supplementation (20 μM) led to approximately 1.5X faster acidification compared to Mn-free conditions. However, this faster acidification stagnated within 24 hours, likely due to draining of intracellular NADH that coincides with substantial loss of culturability. Conversely, without manganese, non-growing cells persisted to acidify for weeks, albeit at a reduced rate, but maintaining redox balance and culturability. Strikingly, despite being unculturable, α-keto acid-derived aldehydes continued to accumulate in cells incubated in the presence of manganese, whereas without manganese cells predominantly formed the corresponding alcohols. This is most likely reflecting NADH availability for the alcohol dehydrogenase-catalyzed conversion. Overall, manganese influences the lactococcal acidification rate, and flavor formation capacity in a redox dependent manner. These are important industrial traits especially during cheese ripening, where cells are in a non-growing, often unculturable state.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472734" rel="alternate" title="Manganese modulates metabolic activity and redox homeostasis in translationally-blocked Lactococcus cremoris, impacting metabolic persistence, cell-culturability, and flavor formation (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472716</id><title>Potential and action mechanism of favipiravir as an antiviral against Junin virus (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.254881+00:00</updated><author><name>Vahid Rajabali Zadeh</name></author><author><name>Shuzo Urata</name></author><author><name>Tosin Oladipo Afowowe</name></author><author><name>Jiro Yasuda</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Favipiravir is a nucleoside analogue that inhibits the replication and transcription of a broad spectrum of RNA viruses, including pathogenic arenaviruses. In this study, we isolated a favipiravir-resistant mutant of Junin virus (JUNV), which is the causative agent of Argentine hemorrhagic fever, and analyzed the antiviral mechanism of favipiravir against JUNV. Two amino acid substitutions, N462D in the RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp) and A168T in the glycoprotein precursor GPC, were identified in the mutant. GPC-A168T substitution enhanced the efficiency of JUNV internalization, which explains the robust replication kinetics of the mutant in the virus growth analysis. Although RdRp-N462D substitution did not affect polymerase activity levels in a minigenome system, comparisons of RdRp error frequencies showed that the virus with RdRp-D462 possessed a significantly higher fidelity. We also provided experimental evidence for the first time that favipiravir inhibited JUNV through the accumulation of transition mutations, confirming its role as a purine analogue against arenaviruses. Moreover, we showed that treatment with a combination of favipiravir and either ribavirin or remdesivir inhibited JUNV replication in a synergistic manner, blocking the generation of the drug-resistant mutant. Our findings provide new insights for the clinical management and treatment of Argentine hemorrhagic fever.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472716" rel="alternate" title="Potential and action mechanism of favipiravir as an antiviral against Junin virus (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472581</id><title>Adaptive strategies under prolonged starvation and role of slow growth in bacterial fitness (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.255041+00:00</updated><author><name>Pabitra Nandy</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1.&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adaptive evolution has the power to illuminate genetic mechanisms under a pre-defined set of selection factors in a controlled environment. Laboratory evolution of bacteria under long-term starvation has gained importance in recent years because of its ability to uncover adaptive strategies to overcome prolonged nutrient limitation- a condition thought to be encountered often by natural microbial isolates. In this evolutionary paradigm, bacteria are maintained in an energy-restricted environment in the growth phase called as long-term stationary phase or LTSP. This phase is characterized by a stable viable population size and highly dynamic genetic changes. Multiple independent iterations of LTSP evolution experiments have given rise to mutants that are slow-growing compared to the ancestor. Although the antagonistic regulation between rapid growth and stress response is fairly well-known in bacteria (especially &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt;), the reason behind the growth deficit of many LTSP-adapted mutants has not been explored in detail. In this review, I revisit the trade-off between growth and stress response and delve into the regulatory mechanisms currently known to control growth under nutrient deficiency. Focusing on the theme of “sigma-factor competition” I try to search for the evolutionary reasoning of slow growth amongst mutants adapted to prolonged starvation. Additionally, I present novel experimental data indicating the dynamics of four such slow-growing variants that evolved during a 30-day long LTSP evolution experiment with &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472581" rel="alternate" title="Adaptive strategies under prolonged starvation and role of slow growth in bacterial fitness (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472329</id><title>Disruption of c-di-GMP signaling networks unlocks cryptic expression of secondary metabolites during biofilm growth in Burkholderia pseudomallei (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.255149+00:00</updated><author><name>Grace I. Borlee</name></author><author><name>Mihnea R. Mangalea</name></author><author><name>Kevin H. Martin</name></author><author><name>Brooke A. Plumley</name></author><author><name>Samuel J. Golon</name></author><author><name>Bradley R. Borlee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The regulation and production of secondary metabolites during biofilm growth of &lt;italic&gt;Burkholderia&lt;/italic&gt; spp. is not well understood. To learn more about the crucial role and regulatory control of cryptic molecules produced during biofilm growth, we disrupted c-di-GMP signaling in &lt;italic&gt;Burkholderia pseudomallei,&lt;/italic&gt; a soil-borne bacterial saprophyte and the etiologic agent of melioidosis. Our approach to these studies combined transcriptional profiling with genetic deletions that targeted key c-di-GMP regulatory components to characterize responses to changes in temperature. Mutational analyses and conditional expression studies of c-di-GMP genes demonstrates their contribution to phenotypes such as biofilm formation, colony morphology, motility, and expression of secondary metabolite biosynthesis when grown as a biofilm at different temperatures. RNA-seq analysis was performed at varying temperatures in a ΔII2523 mutant background that is responsive to temperature alterations resulting in hypo- and hyper-biofilm forming phenotypes. Differential regulation of genes was observed for polysaccharide biosynthesis, secretion systems, and nonribosomal peptide and polyketide synthase (NRPS/PKS) clusters in response to temperature changes. Deletion mutations of biosynthetic gene clusters (BGCs) clusters 2, 11, 14 (syrbactin), and 15 (malleipeptin) in wild-type and ΔII2523 backgrounds also reveals the contribution of these BGCs to biofilm formation and colony morphology in addition to inhibition of &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Rhizoctonia solani&lt;/italic&gt;. Our findings suggest that II2523 impacts the regulation of genes that contribute to biofilm formation and competition.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Characterization of cryptic BGCs under differing environmental conditions will allow for a better understanding of the role of secondary metabolites in the context of biofilm formation and microbe-microbe interactions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Burkholderia pseudomallei&lt;/italic&gt; is a saprophytic bacterium residing in the environment that switches to a pathogenic lifestyle during infection of a wide range of hosts. The environmental cues that serve as the stimulus to trigger this change are largely unknown. However, it is well established that the cellular level of c-di-GMP, a secondary signal messenger, controls the switch from growth as planktonic cells to growth as a biofilm. Disrupting the signaling mediated by c-di-GMP allows for a better understanding of the regulation and the contribution of the surface associated and secreted molecules that contribute to the various lifestyles of this organism. The genome of &lt;italic&gt;B. pseudomallei&lt;/italic&gt; also encodes cryptic biosynthetic gene clusters predicted to encode small molecules that potentially contribute to growth as a biofilm, adaptation, and interactions with other organisms. A better understanding of the regulation of these molecules is crucial to understanding how this versatile pathogen alters its lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472329" rel="alternate" title="Disruption of c-di-GMP signaling networks unlocks cryptic expression of secondary metabolites during biofilm growth in Burkholderia pseudomallei (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472427</id><title>The influence of Janthinobacterium sp. strain SLB01 on the cell culture of primmorphs of the sponge Lubomirskia baicalensis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.255285+00:00</updated><author><name>Lubov I. Chernogor</name></author><author><name>Marina G. Eliseikina</name></author><author><name>Ivan S. Petrushin</name></author><author><name>Ekaterina A. Chernogor</name></author><author><name>Igor V. Khanaev</name></author><author><name>Sergei I. Belikov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sponges (phylum Porifera) are ancient, filtering, multicellular metazoans. Freshwater sponges (Demosponges, Lubomirskiidae) dominate the fauna of the littoral zone of Lake Baikal. Over the last years, there have been mass diseases and death of endemic sponges. Previously, the strain &lt;italic&gt;Janthinobacterium&lt;/italic&gt; sp. SLB01 was isolated from the diseased sponge &lt;italic&gt;Lubomirskia baicalensis&lt;/italic&gt;. The studies of the pathogenicity of the strain &lt;italic&gt;Janthinobacterium&lt;/italic&gt; sp. SLB01 for Baikal sponges has not been carried out. Therefore we infected experimentally &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; to determine its pathogenicity by the cell culture of the primmorphs with subsequent isolation, sequencing, and analysis of the genomes. The purpose of the study is to show that the strain &lt;italic&gt;Janthinobacterium&lt;/italic&gt; sp. SLB01 isolated from the diseased sponge &lt;italic&gt;L. baicalensis&lt;/italic&gt; is a pathogen for the cell culture of primmorphs. The bacteria from the infected samples of the primmorphs were isolated and identified as strain &lt;italic&gt;Janthinobacterium&lt;/italic&gt; sp. PLB02. A comparative analysis of the genomes of the strains &lt;italic&gt;Janthinobacterium&lt;/italic&gt; sp. SLB01 and &lt;italic&gt;Janthinobacterium&lt;/italic&gt; sp. PLB02 showed that they are practically identical. The genomes of both strains contain genes vioABCDE violacein, flok formation, and strong biofilm, and the type VI secretion system (T6SS), as the primary virulence factor. The bacterial strains &lt;italic&gt;Janthinobacterium&lt;/italic&gt; sp. based on a comparison of complete genomes showed similarity with strain &lt;italic&gt;Janthinobacterium lividum&lt;/italic&gt; MTR. Isolated our strains of &lt;italic&gt;Janthinobacterium&lt;/italic&gt; sp. are pathogens for cell cultures of primmorphs and &lt;italic&gt;L. baicalensis&lt;/italic&gt; sponges. The results of the study will help to expand the understanding of microbial relationships in the development of disease and the death of Baikal sponges.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472427" rel="alternate" title="The influence of Janthinobacterium sp. strain SLB01 on the cell culture of primmorphs of the sponge Lubomirskia baicalensis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472660</id><title>Differential Impact of rhamnolipids and TWEEN80 on composition and functionality of the gut microbiota in the SHIME system (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.255420+00:00</updated><author><name>Lisa Miclotte</name></author><author><name>Ellen De Paepe</name></author><author><name>Qiqiong Li</name></author><author><name>John Van Camp</name></author><author><name>Andreja Raikovic</name></author><author><name>Tom Van de Wiele</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Dietary emulsifiers have been shown to affect the composition and function of the gut microbial community, both &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. Yet, several knowledge gaps remain to be addressed: the impact from a longer timeframe exposure on the gut microbiota, interindividual variability in microbiome response and the putative impact from novel clean label alternatives for current food emulsifiers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the present study, the impact of one conventional dietary emulsifier, TWEEN80, and one potential novel alternative, rhamnolipids, on the human gut microbiota was investigated using the Mucosal Simulator of the Human Intestinal Microbial Ecosystem (M-SHIME). The faecal microbiota from two human donors, with high and low responsiveness to the emulsifiers, were exposed to 0,05 m% and 0,5 m% of the emulsifiers for 7 days.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The results confirmed previous observations that the effects on the composition and functionality are both emulsifier- and donor dependent. The effects reached an equilibrium after about 3 days of exposure. Overall, TWEEN80 and rhamnolipids displayed opposite effects: TWEEN80 increased cell counts, reduced propionate concentration, increased butyrate levels, increased a.o. &lt;italic&gt;Faecalibacterium, Blautia&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Hungatella&lt;/italic&gt; abundance, while rhamnolipids did the opposite. Rhamnolipids also sharply increased the abundance of unclassified Lachnospiraceae. On the other hand, both emulsifiers increased the relative abundance of unclassified Enterobacteriaceae. Both emulsifiers also altered the microbial metabolome in different ways and a pathway enrichment analysis tool revealed that the metabolome alterations could be reminiscent of gut issues and obesity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overall, the impact from the rhamnolipids was larger than that of TWEEN80 at similar concentrations, indicating that the former may not necessarily be a safer alternative for the latter. The microbiota’s response also depended on its original composition and the sensitivity status for which the faecal donors were selected, was preserved. Whether the same donor-diversity and longitudinal impact can be expected in the human colon as well and what impact this has on the host will have to be further investigated.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472660" rel="alternate" title="Differential Impact of rhamnolipids and TWEEN80 on composition and functionality of the gut microbiota in the SHIME system (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472339</id><title>Stratified microbial communities are highly sensitive towards multiple combined global change factors, revealing antagonistic and synergistic effects (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.255557+00:00</updated><author><name>Marcel Suleiman</name></author><author><name>Yves Choffat</name></author><author><name>Xue Zheng</name></author><author><name>Owen L Petchey</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microbial communities in many ecosystems are facing a broad range of global change scenarios, resulting in microbial changes and possibly regime shifts with unknown ecological consequences. While the influence of single stressors is already described in numerous studies, the effects of multiple stressors working simultaneously are still poorly understood. In this study, we used 240 highly replicable oxic/anoxic aquatic lab micro-ecosystems to understand the influence of four stressors (fertilizer, glyphosate, metal pollution, antibiotics) in all possible combinations at three different temperatures (20 °C, 24 °C, and 28 °C) to shed light into consequences of multiple stressors on different levels of organization, ranging from species abundance to community and ecosystem parameters. Our data reveal that (i) combination of specific stressors can change the biological consequence and direction compared to single stressors in all levels of organisation (ii), effects of stressor combinations are modified by temperature, and (iii) that the number of stressors applied also lead to significant changes. In sum, our study confirmed the need of investigating multiple stressors working simultaneously across different ecological levels of organisation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472339" rel="alternate" title="Stratified microbial communities are highly sensitive towards multiple combined global change factors, revealing antagonistic and synergistic effects (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472348</id><title>Integrative Interactome and Ubiquitinome Analyses Reveal Multiple Regulatory Pathways Targeted by ICP0 in HSV-1 Infected Neuronal Cells (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.255680+00:00</updated><author><name>Fujun Hou</name></author><author><name>Zeyu Sun</name></author><author><name>Yue Deng</name></author><author><name>Siyu Chen</name></author><author><name>Xiyuan Yang</name></author><author><name>Feiyang Ji</name></author><author><name>Menghao Zhou</name></author><author><name>Keyi Ren</name></author><author><name>Dongli Pan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Herpes simplex virus 1 (HSV-1) is a neurotropic virus that can undergo both productive and latent infection in neurons. ICP0 is an HSV-1 E3 ubiquitin ligase crucial for productive infection and reactivation from latency. However, its targets have not been systematically investigated in neuronal cells. After confirming the importance of ICP0 in HSV-1 neuronal replication using an ICP0-null virus, we identified many ICP0-interacting proteins in infected neuronal and non-neuronal cells by mass-spectrometry-based interactome analysis. Co-immunoprecipitation assays validated ICP0 interactions with ACOT8, C1QBP, OTUD4, SNX9 and VIM in both Neuro-2a and 293T cells. Overexpression and knockdown experiments showed that SNX9 restricted replication of the ICP0-null but not wild-type virus in Neuro-2a cells. Ubiquitinome analysis by immunoprecipitating the trypsin digested ubiquitin reminant followed by mass spectrometry identified numerous candidate ubiquitination substrates of ICP0 in infected Neuro-2a cells, among which OTUD4 and VIM were novel substrates confirmed to be ubiquitinated by transfected ICP0 in Neuro-2a cells despite no evidence of their degradation by ICP0. Expression of OTUD4 was induced independently of ICP0 during HSV-1 infection. Overexpressed OTUD4 enhanced type I interferon expression during infection with the ICP0-null but not wild-type virus. In summary, by combining two proteomic approaches followed by confirmatory and functional experiments, we identified and validated multiple novel targets of ICP0 in neuronal cells, and revealed potential restrictive activities of SNX9 and OTUD4 as well as ICP0-dependent antagonism of these activities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Herpes simplex virus 1 (HSV-1) establishes latent infection in neurons. ICP0 is known for its critical role in antagonizing cellular restrictive functions thereby initiating productive infection. It has been demonstrated to be important for both acute infection and reactivation from latency in neurons. However, little is known about its targets in neuronal cells. Here we combined two proteomic approaches, interactome and ubiquitinome analyses, to integratively identify interaction partners and substrates of ICP0 in HSV-1 infected neuronal cells. The results identified many novel targets as well as confirming previously reported ones. We also further validated some of the binding interactions and ubiquitin modifications. Functional studies revealed that the ICP0-interacting protein SNX9 restricted HSV-1 replication and the ICP0 substrate OTUD4 was induced to enhance type I interferon expression during HSV-1 neuronal infection. Moreover, the activities of these proteins appeared to be antagonized by ICP0-dependent mechanisms. This study provided comprehensive insight into ICP0 targets in neuronal cells and might prompt further investigation into the newly identified targets of ICP0.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472348" rel="alternate" title="Integrative Interactome and Ubiquitinome Analyses Reveal Multiple Regulatory Pathways Targeted by ICP0 in HSV-1 Infected Neuronal Cells (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472529</id><title>Simulated colonic fluid replicates the in vivo growth capabilities of Citrobacter rodentium mutants and highlights a critical role for the Cpx envelope stress response in mediating stressors encountered in the gastrointestinal tract (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.255954+00:00</updated><author><name>Ashley Gilliland</name></author><author><name>Christina Gavino</name></author><author><name>Samantha Gruenheid</name></author><author><name>Tracy Raivio</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Citrobacter rodentium&lt;/italic&gt; is an attaching and effacing (A/E) pathogen used as a model for enteropathogenic and enterohemorrhagic &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; infections in mice. While in the host, &lt;italic&gt;C. rodentium&lt;/italic&gt; must adapt to stresses in the gastrointestinal tract such as antimicrobial peptides, pH changes, and bile salts. The Cpx envelope stress response (ESR) is a two-component system used by some bacteria to remediate stress by modulating gene expression and is necessary for &lt;italic&gt;C. rodentium&lt;/italic&gt; pathogenesis in mice. To investigate genes in the Cpx regulon that may contribute to &lt;italic&gt;C. rodentium&lt;/italic&gt; pathogenesis, RNA-Seq, SILAC, and microarray data from previous research was mined and the genes &lt;italic&gt;yebE, ygiB, bssR,&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;htpX&lt;/italic&gt; were confirmed to be strongly upregulated by the presence of CpxRA using &lt;italic&gt;lux&lt;/italic&gt; reporter constructs. To determine the function of these genes &lt;italic&gt;in vivo,&lt;/italic&gt; knockout mutants were tested in C57Bl/6J and C3H/HeJ mice. Although none of the mutants exhibited marked virulence phenotypes, the Δ&lt;italic&gt;cpxRA&lt;/italic&gt; mutant had reduced colonization and attenuated virulence, as previously determined. We also found that the absence of the Cpx ESR resulted in higher expression of the LEE master regulator, &lt;italic&gt;ler.&lt;/italic&gt; In addition, we determined that the Δ&lt;italic&gt;cpxRA&lt;/italic&gt; mutant had a growth defect in medium simulating the colon, as did several of the mutants bearing deletions in Cpx-upregulated genes. Overall, these results indicate that the Δ&lt;italic&gt;cpxRA&lt;/italic&gt; virulence defect is not due to any single Cpx regulon gene examined. Instead, attenuation may be the result of defective growth in the colonic environment resulting from the collective impact of multiple Cpx-regulated genes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472529" rel="alternate" title="Simulated colonic fluid replicates the in vivo growth capabilities of Citrobacter rodentium mutants and highlights a critical role for the Cpx envelope stress response in mediating stressors encountered in the gastrointestinal tract (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472834</id><title>Novel mechanism of plasmid-DNA transfer mediated by heterologous cell fusion in syntrophic coculture of Clostridium organisms (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.256099+00:00</updated><author><name>Kamil Charubin</name></author><author><name>Gwendolyn J Gregory</name></author><author><name>ELEFTHERIOS TERRY PAPOUTSAKIS</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The evolution of bacteria is driven by random genetic mutations and horizontal gene transfer (HGT) of genetic material from other bacteria. HGT can occur via transformation, transduction, and conjugation. Here, we present a potential new mechanism of HGT which occurs in a syntrophic Clostridium coculture. We have previously shown that in syntrophic cocultures of Clostridium acetobutylicum and Clostridium ljungdahlii, the two organisms undergo heterologous cell fusion, which includes fusion of the peptidoglycan cell walls and membranes. Heterologous cell fusion facilitated a large-scale exchange of cytoplasmic protein and RNA between the two organisms, leading to the formation of hybrid bacterial cells containing cytoplasmic material of the two parent organisms. Here we present new evidence that cell fusion events also facilitate the exchange of plasmid DNA between the two organisms of the syntrophic coculture. Through the use of a selective subculturing process, we successfully isolated wild-type C. acetobutylicum clones which have acquired a portion of the plasmid DNA, containing the antibiotic resistance marker, from a recombinant strain of C. ljungdahlii. Fusion events led to formation of persistent aberrant hybrid cells with distinct morphogenetic characteristics. Furthermore, our data support the concept of a novel, interspecies, mechanism of acquiring antibiotic resistance. Since neither organism contains any known conjugation machinery or mechanism, these findings expand our understanding of multi-species microbiomes, their survival strategies, and evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472834" rel="alternate" title="Novel mechanism of plasmid-DNA transfer mediated by heterologous cell fusion in syntrophic coculture of Clostridium organisms (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472789</id><title>Soluble MAC is primarily released from MAC-resistant bacteria that potently convert complement component C5 (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.256224+00:00</updated><author><name>Dennis J. Doorduijn</name></author><author><name>Marie V. Lukassen</name></author><author><name>Marije F.L. van ’t Wout</name></author><author><name>Vojtech Franc</name></author><author><name>Maartje Ruyken</name></author><author><name>Bart W. Bardoel</name></author><author><name>Albert J.R. Heck</name></author><author><name>Suzan H. M. Rooijakkers</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Membrane Attack Complex (MAC or C5b-9) is an important effector of the immune system to kill invading microbes. MAC is formed when complement enzymes on the bacterial surface convert complement component C5 into C5b. Although the MAC is a membrane-inserted complex, soluble forms of MAC (sMAC, or terminal complement complex (TCC)) are often detected in sera of patients suffering from infections. Consequently, sMAC has been proposed as a biomarker, but it remains unclear when and how it is formed during infections. Here, we studied mechanisms of MAC formation on bacteria and found that sMAC is primarily formed in human serum by bacteria resistant to MAC-dependent killing. Surprisingly, C5 was converted into C5b more potently by MAC-resistant compared to MAC-sensitive &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; strains. Both the increase in C5 conversion and sMAC generation were linked to the expression of lipopolysaccharide (LPS) O-Antigen in the bacterial outer membrane. In addition, we found that MAC precursors are released from the surface of MAC-resistant bacteria during MAC assembly. Release of MAC precursors from bacteria induced lysis of bystander human erythrocytes in the absence of other serum components. However, serum regulators vitronectin (Vn) and clusterin (Clu) can prevent this bystander lysis. Combining size exclusion chromatography with mass spectrometry profiling, we show that sMAC released from bacteria in serum is a heterogeneous mixture of complexes composed of C5b-8, up to 3 copies of C9 and multiple copies of Vn and Clu. Altogether, our data provide molecular insight into how sMAC is generated during bacterial infections. This fundamental knowledge could form the basis for exploring the use of sMAC as biomarker.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472789" rel="alternate" title="Soluble MAC is primarily released from MAC-resistant bacteria that potently convert complement component C5 (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472991</id><title>Tryptophol acetate and tyrosol acetate, metabolites secreted by a probiotic yeast, halt cytokine storm (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.256376+00:00</updated><author><name>orit malka</name></author><author><name>ravit malishev</name></author><author><name>marina bersudsky</name></author><author><name>manikand rajendran</name></author><author><name>mathumathi krishnamohan</name></author><author><name>jakeer shaik</name></author><author><name>evgeni tikhonov</name></author><author><name>eliya sultan</name></author><author><name>omry koren</name></author><author><name>ron apte</name></author><author><name>benyamin rosental</name></author><author><name>elena voronov</name></author><author><name>raz jelinek</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Probiotic fermented foods are perceived as contributing to human health and capable of protecting against inflammation, however solid mechanistic evidence for the presumptive therapeutic benefits is lacking. Here we report that tryptophol acetate and tyrosol acetate, small molecule metabolites secreted by the probiotic milk-fermented yeast Kluyveromyces marxianus exhibit remarkable anti-inflammatory properties. Comprehensive in vivo, ex vivo and in vitro experiments, employing LPS-induced 'cytokine storm' models, reveal dramatic effects of the two molecules, added in tandem, on mice morbidity, laboratory parameters and mortality. In parallel, significant attenuation of pro-inflammatory cytokines including IL-6, IL-1α, IL-1β and TNF-κB, and reduction of reactive oxygen species were recorded. Importantly, tryptophol acetate and tyrosol acetate did not completely suppress cytokine generation, but rather brought their concentrations back to baseline levels, further maintaining core immune functions, including phagocytosis. The anti-inflammatory effects of tryptophol acetate and tyrosol acetate were mediated through downregulation of TLR4, IL-1R, and TNFR signaling pathways and increased A20 expression, attenuating NF-kB level. In addition, the two molecules had a significant impact on mice microbiome, increasing the abundance of the genus Bactericides, known to exhibit anti-inflammatory properties. Overall, this work illuminates pronounced and broad-based immune modulation properties of probiotic yeast-secreted metabolites, uncovering their mechanism of action and underscoring potential new therapeutic avenues for severe inflammation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472991" rel="alternate" title="Tryptophol acetate and tyrosol acetate, metabolites secreted by a probiotic yeast, halt cytokine storm (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472798</id><title>Long term exposure of human gut microbiota with high and low emulsifier sensitivity to soy lecithin in M-SHIME model. (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.256567+00:00</updated><author><name>Lisa Miclotte</name></author><author><name>Ellen De Paepe</name></author><author><name>Qiqiong Li</name></author><author><name>Andreja Rajkovic</name></author><author><name>John Van Camp</name></author><author><name>Tom Van de Wiele</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the context of the potential health hazards related to food processing, dietary emulsifiers have been shown to alter the structure and function of the gut microbial community, both in vivo and in vitro. In mouse models, these emulsifier exposed gut microbiota were shown to contribute to gut inflammation. Several knowledge gaps remain to be addressed though. As such, the impact from a longer timeframe of exposure on the gut microbiota is not known and interindividual variability in microbiome response needs to be measured. To answer these research questions, in this study the faecal microbiota from two individuals, previously selected for high and low emulsifier sensitivity, were exposed to two concentrations of soy lecithin during a 7 day treatment phase in the dynamic mucosal simulator of the human intestinal microbial ecosystem (M-SHIME). The results showed mild effects from soy lecithin on the composition and functionality of these microbial communities, which depended on the original microbial composition. The effects also mostly levelled off after 3 days of exposure. The emulsifier sensitivity for which the microbiota were selected, was preserved. Some potentially concerning effects were also registered: butyrate levels, positively correlating with Faecalibacterium abundance, were lowered by soy lecithin. Also the abundance of the beneficial Bifidobacterium genus was lowered, while the abundance of the notorious unclassified Enterobacteriaceae was increased. Within the family of the unclassified Lachnospiraceae, several genera were either suppressed or stimulated. The effects that these microbial alterations would have on a living host is not yet certain, especially given the fact that large fractions of soy lecithins constituents can be absorbed. Nevertheless, choline and phosphatidylcholine, both primary and absorbable constituents of soy lecithin, have recently been linked to cardiovascular disease via the generation of TMA by the gut microbiota. Further studies that validate our findings and link them to potential health outcomes are thus justified.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472798" rel="alternate" title="Long term exposure of human gut microbiota with high and low emulsifier sensitivity to soy lecithin in M-SHIME model. (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472542</id><title>Multi-virulence and phenotypic spread of Campylobacter jejuni carried by chicken meat in Brazil (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.256772+00:00</updated><author><name>Phelipe Augusto Borba Martins Peres</name></author><author><name>Roberta Torres de Melo</name></author><author><name>Paulo Marcel Armendaris</name></author><author><name>Fabiano Barreto</name></author><author><name>Tiago Follmann Perin</name></author><author><name>Ana Laura Grazziotin</name></author><author><name>Guilherme Paz Monteiro</name></author><author><name>Eliane Pereira Mendonça</name></author><author><name>Eduarda Cristina Alves Lourenzatto</name></author><author><name>Arthur Slompo Muniz Bicalho</name></author><author><name>Marcelo de Vito Filho</name></author><author><name>Ana Beatriz Garcez Buiatte</name></author><author><name>Daise Aparecida Rossi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Campylobacter jejuni&lt;/italic&gt; is the most incriminated pathogen in bacterial gastroenteritis, and therefore, characteristics of its epidemiology must be continuously investigated to support possible mitigating measures. This is particularly important when evaluating representative strains of the world’s leading chicken meat exporter, Brazil. We evaluated a panel of 14 virulence genes in 359 strains of &lt;italic&gt;C. jejuni&lt;/italic&gt; isolated from chilled broiler carcasses of Brazil. The genes were classified into five virulence categories (B: biofilm/motility; SS: secretion/cytotoxicity system; CI: invasion/colonization; GB: Guillain-Barré and AE: adaptation to stress). The percentage of strains with stress adaptation genes (86.07%) indicates the potential to adapt to unfavorable environmental conditions and &lt;italic&gt;hcp&lt;/italic&gt; gene in 97.77%, indicates the ability to cause serious infections in humans. Genes related to GBS in 77.44% of strains are an additional concern, which must be monitored. The gene panel showed the presence of 124 virulence profiles. Individual analyzes by carcass, slaughter establishment, and municipalities where they were located showed high I.Var., of 0.82, 0.87 and 0.78, respectively. Georeferencing indicated state A as a hotspot for virulent strains. Higher levels of isolation and multi-virulence were identified in the summer, which in Brazil is hot and humid. Proteomics was able to discriminate the strains, but due to the high heterogeneity between them, it did not allow to explain their dissemination. Together, our results showed that the studied strains are a potential danger to public health and that there is an urgent need for their surveillance and the adoption of control measures, especially in state A.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;AUTHOR SUMMARY&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Campylobacter jejuni&lt;/italic&gt; is a bacterium considered one of the main causes of foodborne illnesses and the consumption of undercooked chicken meat is one of the main sources of human infection. In Brazil, epidemiological studies of this pathogen are still scarce, when compared to countries with structured surveillance, as well as, its analysis is not required by public health agencies in any group of foods intended for human consumption. Here we investigate the epidemiology of C. jejuni strains isolated from chilled chicken carcasses in Brazil, determining virulent and multivirulent strains, by the origin of the sample and its phenotypic patterns. The strains showed a high potential for adaptation to the environment, being classified as virulent and multivirulent, with a seasonal pattern in the hottest and humid periods of the year. In state A, the strains with the highest evolutionary level were isolated, when compared to the other states in the region. We hope that this study will help to better understand the potential risks that C. jejuni poses to the population and support surveillance agencies in tracking and adopting measures to minimize the dangers that this pathogen poses to public health.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472542" rel="alternate" title="Multi-virulence and phenotypic spread of Campylobacter jejuni carried by chicken meat in Brazil (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.471281</id><title>Link between aging and atheroprotection in Mif-deficient atherosclerotic mice (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.256997+00:00</updated><author><name>Christine Krammer</name></author><author><name>Bishan Yang</name></author><author><name>Sabrina Reichl</name></author><author><name>Verena Bolini</name></author><author><name>Corinna Schulte</name></author><author><name>Heidi Noels</name></author><author><name>Omar El Bounkari</name></author><author><name>Aphrodite Kapurniotu</name></author><author><name>Christian Weber</name></author><author><name>Sarajo Mohanta</name></author><author><name>Jürgen Bernhagen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Atherosclerosis is a lipid-triggered chronic inflammatory condition of our arteries and the main underlying pathology of myocardial infarction and stroke. Pathogenesis is age-dependent, but the mechanistic links between disease progression, age, and atherogenic cytokines and chemokines are incompletely understood. Here, we studied the chemokine-like inflammatory cytokine macrophage migration inhibitory factor (MIF) in atherogenic &lt;italic&gt;Apoe&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;italic&gt;/&lt;/italic&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt; mice across different stages of aging and cholesterol-rich high-fat diet (HFD). MIF promotes atherosclerosis by mediating atherogenic monocyte and T-cell recruitment, amplifying lesional inflammation, and suppressing atheroprotective B-cell responses. However, age-related links between atherogenesis and MIF and its role in advanced atherosclerosis in aged mice have not been systematically explored. We compared effects of global &lt;italic&gt;Mif&lt;/italic&gt;-gene deficiency in 30-, 42-, and 48-week-old &lt;italic&gt;Apoe&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;italic&gt;/&lt;/italic&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt; mice on HFD for 24, 36, or 42 weeks, respectively, and in 52-week-old mice on a 6-week HFD. While a regio-specific atheroprotective phenotype of &lt;italic&gt;Mif-&lt;/italic&gt;deficiency was observed in the 30/24-week-old group, atheroprotection was not detected in the 48/42- and 52/6-week-old groups, suggesting that atheroprotection afforded by global &lt;italic&gt;Mif&lt;/italic&gt;-gene deletion differs across aging stages and atherogenic diet duration. We identify a combination of mechanisms that could explain this phenotype: i) &lt;italic&gt;Mif&lt;/italic&gt;-deficiency promotes lesional Trem2&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; macrophage numbers in younger but not aged mice; ii) &lt;italic&gt;Mif&lt;/italic&gt;-deficiency favors formation of lymphocyte-rich stage-I/II ATLOs in younger mice but ATLO numbers equalize with those in &lt;italic&gt;Apoe&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;italic&gt;/&lt;/italic&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt; controls in the older mice; and iii) plasma anti-oxLDL-IgM antibody levels are decreased in aged &lt;italic&gt;Mif&lt;/italic&gt;-deficient mice. Of note, these three markers (Trem2&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; macrophages, ATLOs, anti-oxLDL-IgM antibodies) have been previously linked to atheroprotection. Together, our study thus suggests that regio-specific atheroprotection due to global &lt;italic&gt;Mif&lt;/italic&gt;-gene deficiency in atherogenic &lt;italic&gt;Apoe&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;italic&gt;/&lt;/italic&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt; mice is lost upon advanced aging and identifies mechanisms that could explain this phenotype shift. These observations may have implications for translational MIF- directed strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.471281" rel="alternate" title="Link between aging and atheroprotection in Mif-deficient atherosclerotic mice (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472014</id><title>Dynamic structural cell responses in the thymus to acute injury, regeneration, and age (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.257169+00:00</updated><author><name>Lorenz L Jahn</name></author><author><name>Anastasia I Kousa</name></author><author><name>Lisa Sikkema</name></author><author><name>Angel E Flores</name></author><author><name>Kimon V Argyropoulos</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Tsai</name></author><author><name>Amina Lazrak</name></author><author><name>Katherine Nichols</name></author><author><name>Nicole Lee</name></author><author><name>Florent Malard</name></author><author><name>Hana Andrlova</name></author><author><name>Antonio LC Gomes</name></author><author><name>Enrico Velardi</name></author><author><name>Salma Youssef</name></author><author><name>Marina B da Silva</name></author><author><name>Melissa Docampo</name></author><author><name>Roshan Sharma</name></author><author><name>Linus Mazoutis</name></author><author><name>Manu Setty</name></author><author><name>Dana Pe'er</name></author><author><name>Nancy R Manley</name></author><author><name>Jarrod A Dudakov</name></author><author><name>Marcel RM van den Brink</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The thymus, the primary site of T cell development, is extremely sensitive to insult but also harbors tremendous capacity for repair. Using single cell sequencing of thymic structural cells, as well as functional and structural analyses, we revealed distinct regenerative programs by endothelial and mesenchymal subsets after injury that stimulated epithelial repair; the compartment primarily supporting T cell development. Thymic function not only declined over lifespan, contributing to immune aging, but the capacity of the thymus to regenerate after damage also declined in old mice. This could be attributed to an inability of the old microenvironment to induce reparative programs; leading to reduced ability to restore tissue structure and function. These findings provide a detailed framework for the response of structural cells to aging and acute damage, which could have considerable implications for our understanding of aging immunity and recovery from treatments such as chemotherapy and bone marrow transplant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472014" rel="alternate" title="Dynamic structural cell responses in the thymus to acute injury, regeneration, and age (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472347</id><title>Molecular Epidemiology and Microbiological Characteristics of Cryptococcus gattii VGII isolates from China (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.257446+00:00</updated><author><name>Xuelei Zang</name></author><author><name>weixin ke</name></author><author><name>Lifeng Wang</name></author><author><name>Hua Wu</name></author><author><name>Yemei Huang</name></author><author><name>Hengyu Deng</name></author><author><name>Meng Zhou</name></author><author><name>Ningxin Wu</name></author><author><name>Dingxia Shen</name></author><author><name>Xinying Xue</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Cryptococcus gattii&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;C. gattii&lt;/italic&gt;) is a fungal pathogen that once caused an outbreak of cryptococcosis on Vancouver Island, and had spread worldwide, while few data were available in China. In this study, seven clinical isolates of &lt;italic&gt;C. gattii&lt;/italic&gt; VGII were collected from 19 hospitals, Multi-locus Sequence Typing (MLST) analysis and whole-genome sequencing (WGS) was performed, and combined with published data for phylogenetic analysis. In addition, in vitro antifungal susceptibility testing, phenotypic analysis, and in vivo virulence studies were performed, subsequently, histopathological analysis of lung tissue was performed. &lt;italic&gt;C.gattii&lt;/italic&gt; VGII infected patients were mainly immunocompetent male, and most of them had symptoms of central nervous system (CNS) involvement. MLST results showed that isolates from china exhibited high genetic diversity, and sequence type (ST) 7 was the major ST among the isolates. Some clinical isolates showed a close phylogenetic relationship with strains from Australia and South America. All clinical isolates did not show resistance to antifungal drugs. In addition, there was no correlation between virulence factors (temperature, melanin production, and capsule size) and virulence while in vivo experiments showed significant differences in virulence among strains. Lung fungal burden and damage to lung tissue correlated with virulence, and degree of damage to lung tissue in mice may highlight differences in virulence. Our work seeks to provide useful data for molecular epidemiology, antifungal susceptibility, and virulence differences of &lt;italic&gt;C. gattii&lt;/italic&gt; VGII in China.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Cryptococcus gattii&lt;/italic&gt; is one of the life-threatening fungal pathogens that can infect immunocompetent individuals. &lt;italic&gt;C.gattii&lt;/italic&gt; can be invaded through the respiratory tract and can be spread to the brain, causing meningoencephalitis and even death. In 1999, an outbreak of &lt;italic&gt;C. gattii&lt;/italic&gt; VGII occurred on Vancouver Island in Canada and spread in the Pacific Northwest region, which attracted more attention. Compared with other nations, the data of &lt;italic&gt;C gattii&lt;/italic&gt; VGII in China was limited. To better understand the molecular epidemiology and microbiological characteristics of &lt;italic&gt;C.gattii&lt;/italic&gt; VGII isolates from China, Bioinformatics analysis and in vivo and in vitro experiments were performed for clinical strains. Multi-locus Sequence Typing and whole-genome sequencing reveal the genetic diversity of the isolates and genetic relationships with isolates from other countries. We also investigated the antifungal drug susceptibility and virulence differences of the isolates. The authors expect that our work can provide useful data for the prevention and control of &lt;italic&gt;C. gattii&lt;/italic&gt; VGII in China and to draw attention to &lt;italic&gt;C. gattii&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472347" rel="alternate" title="Molecular Epidemiology and Microbiological Characteristics of Cryptococcus gattii VGII isolates from China (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472399</id><title>The mating type transcription factor MAT1-1-1 from the fungal human pathogen Aspergillus fumigatus: synthesis, purification, and crystallization of the DNA binding domain (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.257755+00:00</updated><author><name>Barbara Ramšak</name></author><author><name>Ulrich Kück</name></author><author><name>Eckhard Hofmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mating type (&lt;italic&gt;MAT&lt;/italic&gt;) loci are the most important and significant regulators of sexual reproduction and development in ascomycetous fungi. Usually, they encode two transcription factors (TFs), named MAT1-1-1 or MAT1-2-1. Mating-type strains carry only one of the two TF genes, which control expression of pheromone and pheromone receptor genes, involved in the cell-cell recognition process. The present work presents the crystallization for the alpha1 (α1) domain of MAT1-1-1 from the human pathogenic fungus &lt;italic&gt;Aspergillus fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt; (AfMAT1-1-1). Crystals were obtained for the complex between a polypeptide containing the α1 domain and DNA carrying the AfMAT1-1-1 recognition sequence. A streak seeding technique was applied to improve native crystal quality, resulting in diffraction data to 3.2 Å resolution. Further, highly redundant data sets were collected from the crystals of selenomethionine-substituted AfMAT1-1-1 with a maximum resolution of 3.2 Å. This is the first report of structural studies on the α1 domain MAT regulator involved in the mating of ascomycetes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Synopsis&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;An optimized purification and crystallization protocol together with initial X-ray datasets are described for this mating type transcription factor from human pathogenic fungus &lt;italic&gt;Aspergillus fumigatus&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472399" rel="alternate" title="The mating type transcription factor MAT1-1-1 from the fungal human pathogen Aspergillus fumigatus: synthesis, purification, and crystallization of the DNA binding domain (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>