<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.459333+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471643</id><title>Live imaging of the Cryptosporidium parvum lifecycle reveals direct development of male and female gametes from type one meronts (36 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.459826+00:00</updated><author><name>Elizabeth D. English</name></author><author><name>Amandine Guérin</name></author><author><name>Jayesh Tandel</name></author><author><name>Boris Striepen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Cryptosporidium&lt;/italic&gt; is a leading infectious cause of diarrhea around the world associated with waterborne outbreaks, community spread, or zoonotic transmission. The parasite has significant impact on early childhood mortality, and infection is both consequence and cause of malnutrition and stunting. There is currently no vaccine, and treatment options are very limited. &lt;italic&gt;Cryptosporidium&lt;/italic&gt; is a member of the Apicomplexa, and as typical for this protist phylum relies on asexual and sexual reproduction. In contrast to other Apicomplexa, like malaria parasite &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium, Cryptosporidium’s&lt;/italic&gt; entire lifecycle unfolds in a single host in less than three days. Here we establish a model to image lifecycle progression in living cells, and observe, track, and compare nuclear division of asexual and sexual stage parasites. We establish the length and sequence of the cell cycles of all stages and map the developmental fate of parasites across multiple rounds of invasion and egress. We determine that the parasite executes an intrinsic program of three generations of asexual replication, followed by a single generation of sexual stages that is independent of environmental stimuli. We find no evidence for a morphologically distinct intermediate stage (the tetraploid type II meront) but demonstrate direct development of gametes from 8N type I meronts. The progeny of each meront is collectively committed to either asexual or sexual fate, but importantly, meronts committed to sexual fate give rise to both males and females. We define a &lt;italic&gt;Cryptosporidium&lt;/italic&gt; lifecycle matching Tyzzer’s original description and inconsistent with the coccidian lifecycle now shown in many textbooks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471643" rel="alternate" title="Live imaging of the Cryptosporidium parvum lifecycle reveals direct development of male and female gametes from type one meronts (36 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471943</id><title>Single-cell profiling of healthy human kidney reveals features of sex-based transcriptional programs and tissue-specific immunity (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.460008+00:00</updated><author><name>Caitriona M McEvoy</name></author><author><name>Julia M Murphy</name></author><author><name>Lin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Sergi Clotet-Freixas</name></author><author><name>Jessica A Mathews</name></author><author><name>James An</name></author><author><name>Mehran Karimzadeh</name></author><author><name>Delaram Pouyabahar</name></author><author><name>Shenghui Su</name></author><author><name>Olga Zaslaver</name></author><author><name>Hannes Rost</name></author><author><name>Madhurangi Arambewela</name></author><author><name>Lewis Y Liu</name></author><author><name>Sally Zhang</name></author><author><name>Keith A Lawson</name></author><author><name>Antonio Finelli</name></author><author><name>Bo Wang</name></author><author><name>Sonya A MacParland</name></author><author><name>Gary D Bader</name></author><author><name>Ana Konvalinka</name></author><author><name>Sarah Q Crome</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Maintaining organ homeostasis requires complex functional synergy between distinct cell types, a snapshot of which is glimpsed through the simultaneously broad and granular analysis provided by single-cell atlases. Knowledge of the transcriptional programs underpinning the complex and specialized functions of human kidney cell populations at homeostasis is limited by difficulty accessing healthy, fresh tissue. Here, we present a single-cell perspective of healthy human kidney from 19 living donors, with equal contribution from males and females, profiling the transcriptome of 27677 high-quality cells to map healthy kidney at high resolution. Our sex-balanced dataset revealed sex-based differences in gene expression within proximal tubular cells, specifically, increased anti-oxidant metallothionein genes in females and the predominance of aerobic metabolism-related genes in males. Functional differences in metabolism were confirmed between male and female proximal tubular cells, with male cells exhibiting higher oxidative phosphorylation and higher levels of energy precursor metabolites. Within the immune niche, we identified kidney-specific lymphocyte populations with unique transcriptional profiles indicative of kidney-adapted functions and validated findings by flow cytometry. We observed significant heterogeneity in resident myeloid populations and identified an MRC1+ LYVE1+ FOLR2+ C1QC+ population as the predominant myeloid population in healthy kidney. This study provides a detailed cellular map of healthy human kidney, revealing novel insights into the complexity of renal parenchymal cells and kidney-resident immune populations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471943" rel="alternate" title="Single-cell profiling of healthy human kidney reveals features of sex-based transcriptional programs and tissue-specific immunity (21 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471248</id><title>Design principles to assemble drug combinations for effective tuberculosis therapy using interpretable pairwise drug response measurements (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.460383+00:00</updated><author><name>Jonah Larkins-Ford</name></author><author><name>Yonatan N. Degefu</name></author><author><name>Nhi Van</name></author><author><name>Artem Sokolov</name></author><author><name>Bree B. Aldridge</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A challenge in designing treatment regimens for tuberculosis is the necessity to use three or more antibiotics in combination. The combination space is too large to be comprehensively assayed; therefore, only a small number of possible combinations are tested. We narrowed the prohibitively large search space of combination drug responses by breaking down high-order combinations into units of drug pairs. Using pairwise drug potency and drug interaction metrics from in vitro experiments across multiple growth environments, we trained machine learning models to predict outcomes associated with higher-order combinations in the BALB/c relapsing mouse model, an important preclinical model for drug development. We systematically predicted treatment outcomes of &amp;gt;500 combinations among twelve antibiotics. Our classifiers performed well on test data and predicted many novel combinations to be improved over bedaquiline + pretomanid + linezolid, an effective regimen for multidrug-resistant tuberculosis that also shortens treatment in BALB/c mice compared to the standard of care. To understand the design features of effective drug combinations, we reformulated classifiers as simple rulesets to reveal guiding principles of constructing combination therapies for both preclinical and clinical outcomes. One example ruleset is to include a drug pair that is synergistic in dormancy and another pair that is potent in a cholesterol-rich growth environment. These rulesets are predictive, intuitive, and practical, thus enabling rational construction of effective drug combinations based on in vitro pairwise drug synergies and potencies. As more preclinical and clinical drug combination data become available, we expect to improve predictions and combination design rules.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471248" rel="alternate" title="Design principles to assemble drug combinations for effective tuberculosis therapy using interpretable pairwise drug response measurements (16 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.470702</id><title>Relationships between pond water and tilapia skin microbiomes in aquaculture ponds in Malawi (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.460677+00:00</updated><author><name>Jamie McMurtrie</name></author><author><name>Shayma Alathari</name></author><author><name>Dominique L. Chaput</name></author><author><name>David Bass</name></author><author><name>Camerson Ghambi</name></author><author><name>Joseph Nagoli</name></author><author><name>Jérôme Delamare-Deboutteville</name></author><author><name>Chadag Vishnumurthy Mohan</name></author><author><name>Joanne Cable</name></author><author><name>Ben Temperton</name></author><author><name>Charles R. Tyler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Intensification of fish farming practices is being driven by the demand for increased food production to support a rapidly growing global human population, particularly in lower-middle income countries. Intensification of production, however, increases the risk of disease outbreaks and thus likelihood for crop losses. The microbial communities that colonise the skin mucosal surface of fish are poorly understood, but are important in maintaining fish health and resistance against disease. This skin microbial community is susceptible to disruption through stressors associated with transport, handling and the environment of intensive practices, and this risks the propagation of disease-causing pathogens. In this study, we characterised the microbial assemblages found on tilapia skin — the most widely farmed finfish globally — and in the surrounding water of seven earthen aquaculture ponds from two pond systems in distinct geographic regions in Malawi. Metabarcoding approaches were used to sequence the prokaryotic and microeukaryotic communities. We found 92% of prokaryotic amplicon sequence variants were common to both skin and water samples. Differentially enriched and core taxa, however, differed between the skin and water samples. In tilapia skin, &lt;italic&gt;Cetobacterium, Paucibacter, Pseudomonas&lt;/italic&gt; and Comamonadaceae were enriched, whereas, the cyanobacteria &lt;italic&gt;Cyanobium, Microcystis&lt;/italic&gt; and/or &lt;italic&gt;Synechocystis&lt;/italic&gt;, and the diatom &lt;italic&gt;Cyclotella&lt;/italic&gt;, were most prevalent in pond water. Ponds that clustered together according to their water prokaryotic communities also had similar microeukaryotic communities indicating strong environmental influences on prokaryotic and microeukaryotic community structures. While strong site-specific clustering was observed in pond water, the grouping of tilapia skin prokaryotes by pond site was less distinct, suggesting fish microbiota have a greater buffering capacity against environmental influences. The characterised diversity, structure and variance of microbial communities associated with tilapia culture in Malawi provides the baseline for studies on how future intensification practices may lead to microbial dysbiosis and disease onset.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tilapia skin communities vary in different ponds but share some common taxa&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pond sites have a stronger influence on water microbiome community structure than in fish skin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Selected skin-associated taxa could be used to monitor dysbiotic events&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fish skin microeukaryotic community is complex and poorly characterised&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.470702" rel="alternate" title="Relationships between pond water and tilapia skin microbiomes in aquaculture ponds in Malawi (15 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471835</id><title>Chlorine redox chemistry is not rare in biology (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.461283+00:00</updated><author><name>Tyler P. Barnum</name></author><author><name>John D. Coates</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chlorine is abundant in cells and biomolecules, yet the biology of chlorine oxidation and reduction is poorly understood. Some bacteria encode the enzyme chlorite dismutase (Cld), which detoxifies chlorite (CIO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;) by converting it to chloride (Cl&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;) and molecular oxygen (O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;). Cld is highly specific for chlorite and aside from low hydrogen peroxide activity has no known alternative substrate. Here, we reasoned that because chlorite is an intermediate oxidation state of chlorine, Cld can be used as a biomarker for oxidized chlorine species in microorganisms and microbial habitats. Cld was abundant in metagenomes from soils and freshwater to water treatment systems. About 5% of bacterial and archaeal genera contain an organism encoding Cld in its genome, and within some genera Cld is nearly conserved. Cld has been subjected to extensive horizontal gene transfer, suggesting selection by chlorite is episodic yet strong. Cld was also used as a biomarker to predict genes related to chlorine redox chemistry. Genes found to have a genetic association with Cld include known genes for responding to reactive chlorine species and uncharacterized genes for transporters, regulatory elements, and putative oxidoreductases that present targets for future research. Cld was repeatedly co-located in genomes with genes for enzymes that can inadvertently reduce perchlorate (CIO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;) or chlorate (CIO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;), confirming that in nature (per)chlorate reduction does not only occur in specialized anaerobic respiratory metabolisms. The presence of Cld in genomes of obligate aerobes without such enzymes suggested that chlorite, like hypochlorous acid (HOCl), might be formed by oxidative processes within natural habitats. In summary, the comparative genomics of Cld has provided an atlas for a deeper understanding of chlorine oxidation and reduction reactions that are an underrecognized feature of biology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471835" rel="alternate" title="Chlorine redox chemistry is not rare in biology (15 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471424</id><title>Transactive response DNA-binding Protein (TDP-43) regulates early HIV-1 entry and infection (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.461530+00:00</updated><author><name>Romina Cabrera-Rodríguez</name></author><author><name>Silvia Pérez-Yanes</name></author><author><name>Rafaela González-Montelongo</name></author><author><name>José M. Lorenzo-Salazar</name></author><author><name>Judith Estévez-Herrera</name></author><author><name>Jonay García-Luis</name></author><author><name>Antonio Íñigo-Campos</name></author><author><name>Luis A. Rubio-Rodríguez</name></author><author><name>Adrián Muñoz-Barrera</name></author><author><name>Rodrigo Trujillo-González</name></author><author><name>Roberto Dorta-Guerra</name></author><author><name>Concha Casado</name></author><author><name>María Pernas</name></author><author><name>Julià Blanco</name></author><author><name>Carlos Flores</name></author><author><name>Agustín Valenzuela-Fernández</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The transactive response DNA-binding protein (TDP-43) is an important regulator of mRNA, being reported to stabilize the anti-HIV factor, histone deacetylase 6 (HDAC6). However, little is known about the role of TDP-43 in HIV infection. In this work, we seek for the TDP-43 function on regulating CD4+ T cell permissibility to HIV infection. We observed that over-expression of wt-TDP-43 in CD4+ T cells stabilized HDAC6, increasing mRNA and the protein levels of this antiviral enzyme. Under this experimental condition, HIV-1 infection was impaired, independently of the viral envelope glycoprotein (Env) complex tropism. The results obtained by using an HIV-1 Env-mediated cell-to-cell fusion model, under the same experimental conditions, suggest that the increase in TDP-43 levels negatively affects the viral Env fusion capacity. Moreover, the specific siRNA silencing of endogenous TDP-43 in target cells lead to a significant decrease in the levels of HDAC6 which consistently induces an increase in the fusogenic and infection activities of the HIV-1 Env. These observations were confirmed by using primary viral Envs from HIV+ individuals with different clinical phenotypes. An increase in the level of expression of wt-TDP-43 strongly reduced the Envs infection activity of viremic non-progressors (VNP) and rapid progressors (RP) HIV+ individuals down to the levels of the inefficient HIV-1 Envs from long-term non-progressor elite controllers (LTNP-EC) individuals. On the contrary, low levels of endogenous TDP-43, obtained after specific siRNA-TDP-43 knocking-down, significantly favors the infection activity of primary HIV-1 Envs of VNP and RP individuals, leading to an increase in the infection ability of the primary HIV-1/LTNP-EC Envs. Based on this evidence, we interpret that TDP-43 conditions cell permissibility to HIV infection by affecting viral Env fusion and infection capacities, at least by altering the cellular levels of the antiviral enzyme HDAC6.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471424" rel="alternate" title="Transactive response DNA-binding Protein (TDP-43) regulates early HIV-1 entry and infection (10 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.472016</id><title>Nitrogen metabolism in Pseudomonas putida: functional analysis using random barcode transposon sequencing (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.461889+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthias Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Allison N. Pearson</name></author><author><name>Matthew R. Incha</name></author><author><name>Mitchell G. Thompson</name></author><author><name>Edward E. K. Baidoo</name></author><author><name>Ramu Kakumanu</name></author><author><name>Aindrilla Mukhopadhyay</name></author><author><name>Patrick M. Shih</name></author><author><name>Adam M. Deutschbauer</name></author><author><name>Lars M. Blank</name></author><author><name>Jay D. Keasling</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pseudomonas putida KT2440 has long been studied for its diverse and robust metabolisms, yet many genes and proteins imparting these growth capacities remain uncharacterized. Using pooled mutant fitness assays, we identified genes and proteins involved in the assimilation of 52 different nitrogen containing compounds. To assay amino acid biosynthesis, 19 amino acid drop-out conditions were also tested. From these 71 conditions, significant fitness phenotypes were elicited in 672 different genes including 100 transcriptional regulators and 112 transport-related proteins. We divide these conditions into 6 classes, and propose assimilatory pathways for the compounds based on this wealth of genetic data. To complement these data, we characterize the substrate range of three promiscuous aminotransferases relevant to metabolic engineering efforts in vitro. Furthermore, we examine the specificity of five transcriptional regulators, explaining some fitness data results and exploring their potential to be developed into useful synthetic biology tools. In addition, we use manifold learning to create an interactive visualization tool for interpreting our BarSeq data, which will improve the accessibility and utility of this work to other researchers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.472016" rel="alternate" title="Nitrogen metabolism in Pseudomonas putida: functional analysis using random barcode transposon sequencing (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.470720</id><title>N-acetyl-cysteinylated streptophenazines from Streptomyces (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.462219+00:00</updated><author><name>Kristiina Vind</name></author><author><name>Sonia Maffioli</name></author><author><name>Blanca Fernandez Ciruelos</name></author><author><name>Valentin Waschulin</name></author><author><name>Cristina Brunati</name></author><author><name>Matteo Simone</name></author><author><name>Margherita Sosio</name></author><author><name>Stefano Donadio</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Here, we describe two &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;-acetyl-cysteinylated streptophenazines (&lt;bold&gt;1&lt;/bold&gt; and &lt;bold&gt;2&lt;/bold&gt;) produced by soil-derived &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt; sp. ID63040 and identified through a metabolomic approach. These metabolites attracted our interest due to their low occurrence frequency in a large library of fermentation broth extracts and their consistent presence in biological replicates of the producer strain. The compounds were found to possess broad-spectrum antibacterial activity while exhibiting low cytotoxicity. The biosynthetic gene cluster from &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt; sp. ID63040 was found to be highly similar to the streptophenazine reference cluster in the MIBiG database, which originates from the marine &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt; sp. CNB-091. Compounds &lt;bold&gt;1&lt;/bold&gt; and &lt;bold&gt;2&lt;/bold&gt; were the main streptophenazine products from &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt; sp. ID63040 at all cultivation times, but were not detected in &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt; sp. CNB-091. The lack of obvious candidates for cysteinylation in the &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt; sp. ID63040 biosynthetic gene cluster suggests that the &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;-acetyl-cysteine moiety derives from cellular functions, most likely from mycothiol. Overall, our data represent an interesting example on how to leverage metabolomics for the discovery of new natural products and point out to the often-neglected contribution of house-keeping cellular functions to natural product diversification.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="470720v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.470720" rel="alternate" title="N-acetyl-cysteinylated streptophenazines from Streptomyces (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471363</id><title>Transcriptome-wide identification of coding and noncoding RNA-binding proteins defines the comprehensive RNA interactome of Leishmania mexicana (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.462400+00:00</updated><author><name>Karunakaran Kalesh</name></author><author><name>Wenbin Wei</name></author><author><name>Brian S. Mantilla</name></author><author><name>Theodoros I. Roumeliotis</name></author><author><name>Jyoti Choudhary</name></author><author><name>Paul W. Denny</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Proteomic profiling of RNA-binding proteins in &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; is currently limited to polyadenylated mRNA-binding proteins, leaving proteins that interact with nonadenylated RNAs, including noncoding RNAs and pre-mRNAs, unidentified. Using a combination of unbiased orthogonal organic phase separation methodology and tandem mass tag-labelling-based high resolution quantitative proteomic mass spectrometry, we robustly identified 2,417 RNA-binding proteins, including 1289 putative novel non-poly(A)-RNA-binding proteins across the two main &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; life cycle stages. Eight out of twenty &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; deubiquitinases including the recently characterised &lt;italic&gt;L. mexicana&lt;/italic&gt; DUB2 with an elaborate RNA-binding protein interactome were exclusively identified in the non-poly(A)-RNA-interactome. Additionally, an increased representation of WD40 repeat domains were observed in the &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; non-poly(A)-RNA-interactome, thus uncovering potential involvement of this protein domain in RNA-protein interactions in &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt;. We also characterise the protein-bound RNAs using RNA-sequencing and show that in addition to protein coding transcripts ncRNAs are also enriched in the protein-RNA interactome. Differential gene expression analysis revealed enrichment of 145 out of 195 total &lt;italic&gt;L. mexicana&lt;/italic&gt; protein kinase genes in the protein-RNA-interactome, suggesting important role of protein-RNA interactions in the regulation of the &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; protein kinome. Additionally, we characterise the quantitative changes in RNA-protein interactions in hundreds of &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; proteins following inhibition of heat shock protein 90 (Hsp90). Our results show that the Hsp90 inhibition in &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; causes widespread disruption of RNA-protein interactions in ribosomal proteins, proteasomal proteins and translation factors in both life cycle stages, suggesting downstream effect of the inhibition on protein synthesis and degradation pathways in &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt;. This study defines the comprehensive RNA interactome of &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; and provides in-depth insight into the widespread involvement of RNA-protein interactions in &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; biology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471363" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptome-wide identification of coding and noncoding RNA-binding proteins defines the comprehensive RNA interactome of Leishmania mexicana (8 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471530</id><title>Distinct within-host bacterial populations ensure function, colonization and transmission in leaf symbiosis (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.462676+00:00</updated><author><name>Tessa Acar</name></author><author><name>Sandra Moreau</name></author><author><name>Olivier Coen</name></author><author><name>Frédéric De Meyer</name></author><author><name>Olivier Leroux</name></author><author><name>Marine Beaumel</name></author><author><name>Paul Wilkin</name></author><author><name>Aurélien Carlier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hereditary symbioses have the potential to drive transgenerational effects, yet the mechanisms responsible for transmission of heritable plant symbionts are still poorly understood. The leaf symbiosis between &lt;italic&gt;Dioscorea sansibarensis&lt;/italic&gt; and the bacterium &lt;italic&gt;Orrella dioscoreae&lt;/italic&gt; offers an appealing model system to study how heritable bacteria are transmitted to the next generation. Here, we demonstrate that inoculation of apical buds with a bacterial suspension is sufficient to colonize newly-formed leaves and propagules, and to ensure transmission to the next plant generation. Flagellar motility is not required for movement inside the plant, but is important for the colonization of new hosts. Further, stringent tissue-specific regulation of putative symbiotic functions highlight the presence of two distinct subpopulations of bacteria in the leaf gland and at the shoot meristem. We propose that bacteria in the leaf gland dedicate resources to symbiotic functions, while dividing bacteria in the shoot tip ensure successful colonization of meristematic tissue, glands and propagules. Compartmentalization of intra-host populations, together with tissue-specific regulation may serve as a robust mechanism for the maintenance of mutualism in leaf symbiosis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Several plant species form associations with bacteria in their leaves, called leaf symbiosis. These associations are highly specific, but the mechanisms responsible for symbiont transmission are poorly understood. Using the association between the yam species &lt;italic&gt;Dioscorea sansibarensis&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Orrella dioscoreae&lt;/italic&gt; as a model leaf symbiosis, we provide experimental evidence that bacteria are transmitted vertically and distributed to specific leaf structures via association with shoot meristems. Flagellar motility is required for initial infection, but does not contribute to spread within host tissue. We also provide evidence that bacterial subpopulations at the meristem or in the symbiotic leaf gland differentially express key symbiotic genes. We argue that this separation of functional symbiont populations, coupled to tight control over bacterial infection and transmission, explain the evolutionary robustness of leaf symbiosis. These findings may provide insights into how plants may recruit and maintain beneficial symbionts at the leaf surface.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471530" rel="alternate" title="Distinct within-host bacterial populations ensure function, colonization and transmission in leaf symbiosis (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471712</id><title>Amphotericin B resistance in Leishmania mexicana: Alterations to sterol metabolism, lipid transport and oxidative stress response (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.467110+00:00</updated><author><name>Edubiel A. Alpizar-Sosa</name></author><author><name>Nur Raihana Binti Ithnin</name></author><author><name>Wenbin Wei</name></author><author><name>Andrew W. Pountain</name></author><author><name>Stefan K. Weidt</name></author><author><name>Anne M. Donachie</name></author><author><name>Ryan Ritchie</name></author><author><name>Emily A. Dickie</name></author><author><name>Richard J. S. Burchmore</name></author><author><name>Paul W. Denny</name></author><author><name>Michael P. Barrett</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Amphotericin B is increasingly used in treatment of leishmaniasis. Here, fourteen independent lines of &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania mexicana&lt;/italic&gt; and one &lt;italic&gt;L. infantum&lt;/italic&gt; line were selected for resistance to either amphotericin B or the related polyene antimicrobial, nystatin. Sterol profiling revealed that, in each line, the predominant ergostane-type sterol of wild-type cells was replaced by other sterol species. Broadly, two different profiles emerged among the resistant lines. Whole genome sequencing then showed that these distinct profiles were due either to mutations in the sterol methyl transferase (C24SMT) gene locus or the sterol C5 desaturase (C5DS) gene. In three lines an additional deletion of the miltefosine transporter was found. Differences in sensitivity to amphotericin B were apparent, depending on whether cells were grown in HOMEM, supplemented with foetal bovine serum, or a serum free defined medium (DM). These differences appeared to relate to the presence of lipids in the former. Metabolomic analysis after exposure to AmB showed that a large increase in glucose flux via the pentose phosphate pathway preceded cell death in cells sustained in HOMEM but not DM, indicating the oxidative stress was more significantly induced under HOMEM conditions. Several of the lines were tested for ability to infect macrophages and replicate as amastigote forms, alongside their ability to establish infections in mice. While several lines showed reduced virulence, at least one AmB resistant line displayed heightened virulence in mice whilst retaining its resistance phenotype, emphasising the risks of resistance emerging to this critical drug.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471712" rel="alternate" title="Amphotericin B resistance in Leishmania mexicana: Alterations to sterol metabolism, lipid transport and oxidative stress response (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471457</id><title>IHF regulates host colonization factors in the bee gut symbiont Frischella perrara (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.467491+00:00</updated><author><name>K. Schmidt</name></author><author><name>S. Leopold-Messer</name></author><author><name>O. Emery</name></author><author><name>Y. El-Chazli</name></author><author><name>T. Steiner</name></author><author><name>J. Piel</name></author><author><name>P. Engel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacteria colonize specific niches in the animal gut. However, the genetic basis of these associations is often unclear. The protobacterium &lt;italic&gt;Frischella perrara&lt;/italic&gt; colonizes the hindgut of honey bees, where it causes a characteristic immune response leading to the formation of the scab phenotype. Genetic determinants required for the establishment of this specific association are unknown. Here, we isolated three point mutations in the genes encoding the DNA-binding protein integration host factor (IHF). All three mutants formed larger colonies than the wild type &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and did not produce an aryl polyene metabolite, which confers a yellow color to &lt;italic&gt;F. perrara&lt;/italic&gt; colonies. Inoculation of microbiota-free bees with one of the mutants drastically decreased gut colonization of &lt;italic&gt;F. perrara&lt;/italic&gt; and abolished scab development. Using RNAseq we find that IHF affects the expression of potential colonization factors, including a colibactin biosynthetic gene cluster, two Type 6 secretion systems, pili genes, and the aryl polyene biosynthesis pathway. Gene deletions of these components revealed different colonization defects. While some mutants were abolished in their capacity to colonize the gut, others colonized but did not trigger the scab phenotype. IHF is conserved across many bacteria and may thus regulate host colonization also in other animal symbionts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471457" rel="alternate" title="IHF regulates host colonization factors in the bee gut symbiont Frischella perrara (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471581</id><title>In-depth characterization of the serum antibody epitope repertoire in inflammatory bowel disease using phage-displayed immunoprecipitation sequencing (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.467854+00:00</updated><author><name>Arno R. Bourgonje</name></author><author><name>Sergio Andreu-Sánchez</name></author><author><name>Thomas Vogl</name></author><author><name>Shixian Hu</name></author><author><name>Arnau Vich Vila</name></author><author><name>Ranko Gacesa</name></author><author><name>Sigal Leviatan</name></author><author><name>Alexander Kurilshikov</name></author><author><name>Shelley Klompus</name></author><author><name>Iris N. Kalka</name></author><author><name>Hendrik M. van Dullemen</name></author><author><name>Adina Weinberger</name></author><author><name>Marijn C. Visschedijk</name></author><author><name>Eleonora A. M. Festen</name></author><author><name>Klaas Nico Faber</name></author><author><name>Cisca Wijmenga</name></author><author><name>Gerard Dijkstra</name></author><author><name>Eran Segal</name></author><author><name>Jingyuan Fu</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Zhernakova</name></author><author><name>Rinse K. Weersma</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Inflammatory bowel diseases (IBD), e.g. Crohn’s disease (CD) and ulcerative colitis (UC), are chronic immune-mediated inflammatory diseases. A comprehensive overview of an IBD-specific antibody epitope repertoire is, however, lacking. We leveraged a high-throughput phage-displayed immunoprecipitation sequencing (PhIP-seq) workflow to identify antibodies against 344,000 antimicrobial, immune and food antigens in 497 IBD patients as compared to 1,326 controls. IBD was characterized by 373 differentially abundant antibodies (202 overrepresented and 171 underrepresented), with 17% shared by both IBDs, 55% unique to CD and 28% unique to UC. Antibodies against bacterial flagellins dominated in CD and were associated with ileal involvement, fibrostenotic disease and anti-&lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; antibody positivity, but not with fecal microbiome composition. Antibody epitope repertoires accurately discriminated CD from controls (AUC=0.89), and similar discrimination was achieved when using only ten antibodies (AUC=0.87). IBD patients thus show a distinct antibody repertoire against selected peptides, allowing patient stratification and discovery of immunological targets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471581" rel="alternate" title="In-depth characterization of the serum antibody epitope repertoire in inflammatory bowel disease using phage-displayed immunoprecipitation sequencing (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471103</id><title>Impaired LAIR-1-mediated immune control due to collagen degradation in fibrosis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.468270+00:00</updated><author><name>Tiago Carvalheiro</name></author><author><name>Wioleta Marut</name></author><author><name>M. Inês Pascoal Ramos</name></author><author><name>Samuel García</name></author><author><name>Devan Fleury</name></author><author><name>Alsya J. Affandi</name></author><author><name>Aniek S. Meijers</name></author><author><name>Barbara Giovannone</name></author><author><name>Ralph G. Tieland</name></author><author><name>Eline Elshof</name></author><author><name>Andrea Ottria</name></author><author><name>Marta Cossu</name></author><author><name>Matthew L. Meizlish</name></author><author><name>Tineke Veenendaal</name></author><author><name>Meera Ramanujam</name></author><author><name>Miguel E. Moreno-García</name></author><author><name>Judith Klumperman</name></author><author><name>Nalan Liv</name></author><author><name>Timothy R.D.J. Radstake</name></author><author><name>Linde Meyaard</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tissue repair is disturbed in fibrotic diseases like systemic sclerosis (SSc), where the deposition of large amounts of extracellular matrix components such as collagen interferes with organ function. LAIR-1 is an inhibitory collagen receptor highly expressed on tissue immune cells. We questioned whether in SSc, impaired LAIR-1-collagen interaction is contributing to the ongoing inflammation and fibrosis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found that SSc patients do not have an intrinsic defect in LAIR-1 expression or function. Instead, fibroblasts from SSc patients deposit disorganized collagen products &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, which are dysfunctional LAIR-1 ligands. This can be mimicked in healthy fibroblast stimulated by soluble factors that drive inflammation and fibrosis in SSc and is dependent of matrix metalloproteinases and platelet-derived growth factor receptor signaling.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In support of a non-redundant role of LAIR-1 in the control of fibrosis, we found that LAIR-1-deficient mice have increased skin fibrosis in the bleomycin mouse model for SSc. Thus, LAIR-1 represents an essential control mechanism for tissue repair. In fibrotic disease, excessive collagen degradation may lead to a disturbed feedback loop. The presence of functional LAIR-1 in patients provides a therapeutic opportunity to reactivate this intrinsic negative feedback mechanism in fibrotic diseases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract Figure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="471103v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471103" rel="alternate" title="Impaired LAIR-1-mediated immune control due to collagen degradation in fibrosis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471526</id><title>Meet me in the middle: median temperatures impact cyanobacteria and photoautotrophy in eruptive Yellowstone hot springs (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.468662+00:00</updated><author><name>Trinity L. Hamilton</name></author><author><name>Jeff Havig</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Geographic isolation can be a main driver of microbial evolution in hot springs while temperature plays a role on local scales. For example, cyanobacteria, particularly high temperature &lt;italic&gt;Synechococcus&lt;/italic&gt; spp., have undergone ecological diversification along temperature gradients in hot spring outflow channels. While water flow, and thus temperature, is largely stable in many hot springs, flow can vary in geysing/eruptive hot springs resulting in large temperature fluctuations (sometimes more than 40°C). However, the role of large temperature fluctuations in driving diversification of cyanobacteria in eruptive hot springs has not been explored. Here, we examined phototroph community composition and potential photoautotrophic activity in two alkaline eruptive hot springs with similar geochemistry in the Lower Geyser Basin in Yellowstone National Park, WY. We observed distinct cyanobacterial amplicon sequencing variants (ASVs) consistent with allopatry and levels of light-dependent inorganic carbon uptake rates similar to other hot springs, despite large temperature fluctuations. Our data suggests median temperatures may drive phototroph fitness in eruptive hot springs while future studies are necessary to determine the evolutionary consequences of thriving under continuously fluctuating temperatures. We propose that large temperature swings in eruptive hot springs offer unique environments to examine the role of allopatry vs. physical and chemical characteristics of ecosystems in driving cyanobacteria evolution and add to the debate regarding the ecology of thermal adaptation and the potential for narrowing niche breadth with increasing temperature.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec id="s1"&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hot spring cyanobacteria have long been model systems for examining ecological diversification as well as characterizing microbial adaptation and evolution to extreme environments. These studies have reported cyanobacterial diversification in hot spring outflow channels that can be defined by distinct temperature ranges. Our study builds on these previous studies by examining cyanobacteria in geysing hot springs. Geysing hot springs result in outflow channel that experience regular and large temperature fluctuations. While community composition is similar between geysing and nongeysing hot spring outflow channels, our data suggests median, rather than high temperature, drive the fitness of cyanobacteria in geysing hot springs. We propose that large temperature swings may result in patterns of ecological diversification that are distinct from more stable outflows.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471526" rel="alternate" title="Meet me in the middle: median temperatures impact cyanobacteria and photoautotrophy in eruptive Yellowstone hot springs (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471948</id><title>Discovery of a new species of trichomonasvirus in the human parasite Trichomonas vaginalis using transcriptome mining (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.468883+00:00</updated><author><name>Austin Reid Manny</name></author><author><name>Carrie Ann Hetzel</name></author><author><name>Arshan Mizani</name></author><author><name>Max Lee Nibert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Trichomonas vaginalis is the most common nonviral cause of sexually transmitted infections globally, with an estimated quarter of a billion people infected around the world. Infection by the protozoan parasite results in the clinical syndrome trichomoniasis, which manifests as an inflammatory syndrome with acute and chronic consequences. Half or more of these parasites are themselves infected with one or more dsRNA viruses which can exacerbate the inflammatory disease. Four distinct viruses have been found in T. vaginalis to date, Trichomonas vaginalis virus 1 through 4 (or TVVs). Despite the global prevalence of these viruses, few coding-complete genome sequences have been determined. We conducted viral sequence mining in publicly available transcriptomes across 60 RNA-seq datasets representing 13 distinct T. vaginalis isolates. We assembled sequences for 27 new trichomonasvirus strains across all known TVV species, with 17 of these assemblies representing coding-complete genomes. Using a strategy of de novo sequence assembly followed by taxonomic classification, we discovered a fifth species of TVV that we term Trichomonas vaginalis virus 5 (TVV5). Six strains of TVV5 were assembled, including two coding-complete genomes. These TVV5 sequences exhibit high sequence identity to each other, but low identity to any strains of TVV1-4. Phylogenetic analysis corroborates the species-level designation. These results substantially increase the number of coding-complete TVV genome sequences and demonstrate the utility of mining publicly available transcriptomes for the discovery of RNA viruses in a critical human pathogen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471948" rel="alternate" title="Discovery of a new species of trichomonasvirus in the human parasite Trichomonas vaginalis using transcriptome mining (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471358</id><title>Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium chitinases modulate the intestinal glycome and promote small intestinal invasion (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.469084+00:00</updated><author><name>Jason R Devlin</name></author><author><name>William Santus</name></author><author><name>Jorge Mendez</name></author><author><name>Wenjing Peng</name></author><author><name>Aiying Yu</name></author><author><name>Junyao Wang</name></author><author><name>Xiomarie Alejandro-Navarreto</name></author><author><name>Kaitlyn Kiernan</name></author><author><name>Manmeet Singh</name></author><author><name>Peilin Jiang</name></author><author><name>Yehia Mechref</name></author><author><name>Judith Behnsen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Salmonella enterica&lt;/italic&gt; serovar Typhimurium (&lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt;) is one of the leading causes of food-borne illnesses worldwide. To colonize the gastrointestinal tract, &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; produces multiple virulence factors that facilitate cellular invasion. Chitinases have been recently emerging as virulence factors for various pathogenic bacterial species and the &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; genome contains two annotated chitinases: &lt;italic&gt;STM0018&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;chiA&lt;/italic&gt;) and &lt;italic&gt;STM0233&lt;/italic&gt;. However, the role of these chitinases during &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; pathogenesis is unknown. The putative chitinase STM0233 has not been studied previously and only limited data exists on ChiA. Chitinases typically hydrolyze chitin polymers, which are absent in vertebrates. However, &lt;italic&gt;chiA&lt;/italic&gt; expression was detected in infection models and purified ChiA cleaved carbohydrate subunits present on mammalian surface glycoproteins, indicating a role during pathogenesis. Here, we demonstrate that expression of &lt;italic&gt;chiA&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;STM0233&lt;/italic&gt; is upregulated in the mouse gut and that both chitinases facilitate epithelial cell adhesion and invasion. &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; lacking both chitinases showed a 70% reduction in invasion of small intestinal epithelial cells &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. In a gastroenteritis mouse model, chitinase-deficient &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; strains were also significantly attenuated in the invasion of small intestinal tissue. This reduced invasion resulted in significantly delayed &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; dissemination to the spleen and the liver, but chitinases were not required for systemic survival. The invasion defect of the chitinase-deficient strain was rescued by the presence of wild-type &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt;, suggesting that chitinases are secreted. By analyzing &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;-linked glycans of small intestinal cells, we identified specific &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;-acetylglucosamine-containing glycans as potential extracellular targets of &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; chitinases. This analysis also revealed differential abundance of Lewis X-containing glycans that is likely a result of host cell modulation due to the detection of &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; chitinases. Similar glycomic changes elicited by chitinase deficient strains indicate functional redundancy of the chitinases. Overall, our results demonstrate that &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; chitinases contribute to intestinal adhesion and invasion through modulation of the host glycome.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; Typhimurium infection is one of the leading causes of food-borne illnesses worldwide. In order for &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; to effectively cause disease, it has to invade the epithelial cells lining the intestinal tract. This invasion step allows &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; to replicate efficiently, causing further tissue damage and inflammation. In susceptible patients, &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; can spread past the intestines and infect peripheral organs. It is essential to fully understand the invasion mechanism used by &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; to design better treatments for infection. Here, we demonstrate that the two chitinases produced by &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; are involved in this invasion process. We show that &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; chitinases interact with surface glycans of intestinal epithelial cells and promote adhesion and invasion. Using a mouse infection model, we show that &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; chitinases are required for the invasion of the small intestine and enhance the dissemination of &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; to other organs. This study reveals an additional mechanism by which &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; invades and causes infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471358" rel="alternate" title="Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium chitinases modulate the intestinal glycome and promote small intestinal invasion (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.472010</id><title>Quantitative Structural Analysis of Influenza Virus by Cryo-electron Tomography and Convolutional Neural Networks (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.469501+00:00</updated><author><name>Qiu Yu Huang</name></author><author><name>Kangkang Song</name></author><author><name>Chen Xu</name></author><author><name>Daniel N.A. Bolon</name></author><author><name>Jennifer P. Wang</name></author><author><name>Robert W. Finberg</name></author><author><name>Celia A. Schiffer</name></author><author><name>Mohan Somasundaran</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Influenza viruses pose severe public health threats; they cause millions of infections and tens of thousands of deaths annually in the US. Influenza viruses are extensively pleomorphic, in both shape and size as well as organization of viral structural proteins. Analysis of influenza morphology and ultrastructure can help elucidate viral structure-function relationships as well as aid in therapeutics and vaccine development. While cryo-electron tomography (cryoET) can depict the 3D organization of pleomorphic influenza, the low signal-to-noise ratio inherent to cryoET and extensive viral heterogeneity have precluded detailed characterization of influenza viruses. In this report, we developed a cryoET processing pipeline leveraging convolutional neural networks (CNNs) to characterize the morphological architecture of the A/Puerto Rico/8/34 (H1N1) influenza strain. Our pipeline improved the throughput of cryoET analysis and accurately identified viral components within tomograms. Using this approach, we successfully characterized influenza viral morphology, glycoprotein density, and conduct subtomogram averaging of HA glycoproteins. Application of this processing pipeline can aid in the structural characterization of not only influenza viruses, but other pleomorphic viruses and infected cells.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="472010v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.472010" rel="alternate" title="Quantitative Structural Analysis of Influenza Virus by Cryo-electron Tomography and Convolutional Neural Networks (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471678</id><title>Bacterial and fungal communities experience rapid succession during the first year following a wildfire in a California chaparral (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.469809+00:00</updated><author><name>M. Fabiola Pulido-Chavez</name></author><author><name>James W. J. Randolph</name></author><author><name>Cassandra Zalman</name></author><author><name>Loralee Larios</name></author><author><name>Peter M. Homyak</name></author><author><name>Sydney I. Glassman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The rise in wildfire frequency in the western United States has increased interest in secondary succession. However, despite the role of soil microbial communities in plant regeneration and establishment, microbial secondary succession is poorly understood owing to a lack of measurements immediately post-fire and at high temporal resolution. To fill this knowledge gap, we collected soils at 2 and 3 weeks and 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 9, and 12 months after a chaparral wildfire in Southern California. We assessed bacterial and fungal biomass with qPCR of 16S and 18S and richness and composition with Illumina MiSeq sequencing of the 16S and ITS2 amplicons. We found that fire severely reduced bacterial biomass by 47% and richness by 46%, but the impacts were stronger for fungi, with biomass decreasing by 86% and richness by 68%. These declines persisted for the entire post-fire year, but bacterial biomass and richness oscillated in response to precipitation, whereas fungal biomass and richness did not. Fungi and bacteria experienced rapid succession, with 5-6 compositional turnover periods. As with plants, fast-growing surviving microbes drove successional dynamics. For bacteria, succession was driven by the phyla Firmicutes and Proteobacteria, with the Proteobacteria &lt;italic&gt;Massilia&lt;/italic&gt; dominating all successional time points, and the Firmicutes (&lt;italic&gt;Domibacillus&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Paenibacillus&lt;/italic&gt;) dominating early-to mid-successional stages (1-4.5 months), while the Proteobacteria &lt;italic&gt;Noviherbaspirillum&lt;/italic&gt; dominated late successional stages (4.5-1 year). For fungi, succession was driven by the phyla Ascomycota, but ectomycorrhizal basidiomycetes, and the heat-resistant yeast, &lt;italic&gt;Geminibasidium&lt;/italic&gt; were present in the early successional stages (1 month). However, pyrophilous filamentous Ascomycetes &lt;italic&gt;Pyronema&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;Penicillium&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;Aspergillus&lt;/italic&gt;, dominated all post-fire time points. While wildfires vastly decrease bacterial and fungal biomass and richness, similar to plants, pyrophilous bacteria and fungi increase in abundance and experience rapid succession and compositional turnover in the first post-fire year, with potential implications for post-fire chaparral regeneration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471678" rel="alternate" title="Bacterial and fungal communities experience rapid succession during the first year following a wildfire in a California chaparral (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471825</id><title>Mapping of the autophagosomal degradome identifies IL-7Rα as key cargo in proliferating CD4+ T-cells (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.470098+00:00</updated><author><name>Dingxi Zhou</name></author><author><name>Mariana Borsa</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Puleston</name></author><author><name>Susanne Zellner</name></author><author><name>Jesusa Capera</name></author><author><name>Sharon Sanderson</name></author><author><name>Luke Jostins</name></author><author><name>Christian Behrends</name></author><author><name>Ghada Alsaleh</name></author><author><name>Anna Katharina Simon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;CD4+ T cells orchestrate both humoral and cytotoxic immune responses. While it is known that CD4+ T cell proliferation relies on autophagy, direct identification of the autophagosomal cargo involved is still missing. Here, we created a transgenic mouse model, which, for the first time, enables us to directly map the proteinaceous content of autophagosomes in any primary cell by LC3 proximity labelling. IL-7Rα, a cytokine receptor mostly found in naive and memory T cells, was reproducibly detected in autophagosomes of activated CD4+ T cells. Consistently, CD4+ T cells lacking autophagy showed increased IL-7Rα surface expression, while no defect in internalisation was observed. Mechanistically, excessive surface IL-7Rα sequestrates the common gamma chain, impairing the IL-2R assembly and downstream signalling crucial for T cell proliferation. This study provides proof-of-principle that key autophagy substrates can be reliably identified with this model to help mechanistically unravel autophagy's contribution to healthy physiology and disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471825" rel="alternate" title="Mapping of the autophagosomal degradome identifies IL-7Rα as key cargo in proliferating CD4+ T-cells (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471880</id><title>Strain variation in Clostridioides difficile toxin activity associated with genomic variation at both PaLoc and non-PaLoc loci (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.470369+00:00</updated><author><name>Katie Saund</name></author><author><name>Ali Pirani</name></author><author><name>Borden Lacy</name></author><author><name>Philip C Hanna</name></author><author><name>Evan S Snitkin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Clinical disease from&lt;italic&gt; Clostridioides difficile&lt;/italic&gt; infection can be mediated by two toxins and their neighboring regulatory genes encoded within the five-gene pathogenicity locus (PaLoc). We provide several lines of evidence that the toxin activity of&lt;italic&gt; C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; may be modulated by genomic variants outside of the PaLoc. We used a phylogenetic tree-based approach to demonstrate discordance between toxin activity and PaLoc evolutionary history, an elastic net method to show the insufficiency of PaLoc variants alone to model toxin activity, and a convergence-based bacterial genome-wide association study (GWAS) to identify correlations between non-PaLoc loci with changes in toxin activity. Combined, these data support a model of &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; disease wherein toxin activity may be strongly affected by many non-PaLoc loci. Additionally, we characterize multiple other in vitro phenotypes relevant to human infections including germination and sporulation. These phenotypes vary greatly in their clonality, variability, convergence, and concordance with genomic variation. Lastly, we highlight the intersection of loci identified by GWAS for different phenotypes and clinical severity. This strategy to identify the overlapping loci can facilitate the identification of genetic variation linking phenotypic variation to clinical outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471880" rel="alternate" title="Strain variation in Clostridioides difficile toxin activity associated with genomic variation at both PaLoc and non-PaLoc loci (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471453</id><title>Escherichia coli antimicrobial resistance; Phenotypic and genotypic characterization (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.471074+00:00</updated><author><name>Nagwa Thabet Elsharawy</name></author><author><name>Hind A. A. Al-Zahrani</name></author><author><name>Amr A. El-Waseif</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Improper use of the antimicrobials as &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; giving the microorganism multi-resistance against many antimicrobials by gene mutation on integrons, transposons and plasmids. Therefore, our aim in this study is to 1)examine antibiotics resistance phenotype and genotype in &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt;, 2) identifying the structure of bacterial resistance genes on whole-genome sequencing against multi-drug resistant of &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; in marketed poultry meat. Samples collected, prepared and Bacteriological examination, Antimicrobial sensitivity test performed, Serological identification of &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; isolates. Results declared that; the prevalence of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; from tested chicken meat samples of 100 chicken meat samples surveyed against &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; the result declared that about 40%. Antimicrobial susceptibility was; antibiotics of choice against &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; Sulfonamides, Cephalosporins,Tetracyclines, Quinolones. Serologically, STEC (O157:H7) 30%, ETEC (O142) 10%, EHEC (O26:H11). The subunit B of shiga-like toxin (SLT) gene appeared as a homogenous band. Heat-labile toxin (LT) gene was screened in both genomic DNA and plasmid preps in tested strains. Control STEC as it represents a danger to the poultry consumers. We recommended to increase the hygienic measures during slaughtering, processing and/or handling of chicken carcasses and avoidance unnecessary usage of any antimicrobials to avoid appearance of new antimicrobials resistant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471453" rel="alternate" title="Escherichia coli antimicrobial resistance; Phenotypic and genotypic characterization (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.472040</id><title>Salmonella Typhimurium induces NAIP/NLRC4- and NLRP3/ASC-independent, caspase-1/4-dependent inflammasome activation in human intestinal epithelial cells (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.471295+00:00</updated><author><name>Nawar Naseer</name></author><author><name>Renate Bauer</name></author><author><name>Jenna Zhang</name></author><author><name>Igor E. Brodsky</name></author><author><name>Isabella Rauch</name></author><author><name>Sunny Shin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Salmonella enterica&lt;/italic&gt; serovar Typhimurium is a gram-negative pathogen that causes diseases ranging from gastroenteritis to systemic infection and sepsis. &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella &lt;/italic&gt;uses type III secretion systems (T3SSs) to inject effectors into host cells. While these effectors are necessary for bacterial invasion and intracellular survival, intracellular delivery of T3SS products also enables detection of &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella &lt;/italic&gt;by cytosolic immune sensors. Upon detecting translocated &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella &lt;/italic&gt;ligands, these sensors form multimeric complexes called inflammasomes, which activate caspases that lead to proinflammatory cytokine release and pyroptosis. In particular, the &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella &lt;/italic&gt;T3SS needle, inner rod, and flagellin proteins activate the NAIP/NLRC4 inflammasome in murine intestinal epithelial cells (IECs), which leads to restriction of bacterial replication and extrusion of infected IECs into the intestinal lumen, thereby preventing systemic dissemination of &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella &lt;/italic&gt;. While these processes are studied quite well in mice, the role of the NAIP/NLRC4 inflammasome in human IECs remains unknown. Unexpectedly, we found the NAIP/NLRC4 inflammasome is dispensable for early inflammasome responses to &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella &lt;/italic&gt;in both human intestinal epithelial cell lines and organoids. Additionally, the NLRP3 inflammasome and the adaptor protein ASC are not required for inflammasome activation in Caco-2 cells. Instead, we observed a partial requirement for caspase-1, and a necessity for caspase-4 and GSDMD pore-forming activity in mediating inflammasome responses to &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella &lt;/italic&gt; in Caco-2 cells. These findings suggest that unlike murine IECs, human IECs do not rely on NAIP/NLRC4, and also do not use NLRP3/ASC. Instead, they primarily use caspases-1 and -4 to mediate early inflammasome responses to SPI-1-expressing &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella &lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.472040" rel="alternate" title="Salmonella Typhimurium induces NAIP/NLRC4- and NLRP3/ASC-independent, caspase-1/4-dependent inflammasome activation in human intestinal epithelial cells (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471573</id><title>Seroprevalence of brucellosis and molecular characterization of Brucella spp. from slaughtered cattle in Rwanda (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.471538+00:00</updated><author><name>Jean Bosco Ntivuguruzwa</name></author><author><name>Francis Babaman Kolo</name></author><author><name>Emil Ivan Mwikarago</name></author><author><name>Henriette vanHeerden</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bovine brucellosis is endemic in Rwanda, although, there is paucity of documented evidence about the disease in slaughtered cattle. A cross-sectional study was conducted in slaughtered cattle (n=300) to determine the seroprevalence of anti-&lt;italic&gt;Brucella&lt;/italic&gt; antibodies using the Rose Bengal Test (RBT), and indirect enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (i-ELISA). Corresponding tissues were cultured onto a modified Centro de Investigación y Tecnología Agroalimentaria (CITA) selective medium and analysed for &lt;italic&gt;Brucella&lt;/italic&gt; spp. using the 16S-23S ribosomal interspacer region (ITS), AMOS, and Bruce-ladder PCR assays. The RBT seroprevalence was 20.7% (62/300), and 2.9% (8/300) with i-ELISA and 2.9% (8/300) using both tests in parallel. &lt;italic&gt;Brucella&lt;/italic&gt; specific 16S-23S ribosomal DNA interspace region (ITS) PCR detected &lt;italic&gt;Brucella&lt;/italic&gt; DNA in 5.6% (17/300; &lt;italic&gt;Brucella&lt;/italic&gt; culture prevalence). AMOS-PCR assay identified mixed &lt;italic&gt;B. abortus&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;B. melitensis&lt;/italic&gt; (n=3), &lt;italic&gt;B. abortus&lt;/italic&gt; (n=3) and &lt;italic&gt;B. melitensis&lt;/italic&gt; (n=5) while Bruce-ladder PCR also identified &lt;italic&gt;B. abortus&lt;/italic&gt; (n=5) and &lt;italic&gt;B. melitensis&lt;/italic&gt; (n=6). The gold standard culture method combined with PCR confirmation identified 5.6% &lt;italic&gt;Brucella&lt;/italic&gt; cultures which is higher than the more sensitive seroprevalence of 2.9%. This emphasizes the need to validate the serological tests in Rwanda. The mixed infection caused by &lt;italic&gt;B. abortus&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;B. melitensis&lt;/italic&gt; in slaughtered cattle indicates cross-infection and poses a risk of exposure potential to abattoir workers. It is essential to urgently strengthen the national bovine brucellosis control program through vaccination as well as test- and-slaughter.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471573" rel="alternate" title="Seroprevalence of brucellosis and molecular characterization of Brucella spp. from slaughtered cattle in Rwanda (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>