<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.766228+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460331</id><title>Defective endosome-TGN retrograde transport promotes NLRP3 inflammasome activation (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.766635+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhirong Zhang</name></author><author><name>Li Ran</name></author><author><name>Rossella Venditti</name></author><author><name>Zengzhen Liu</name></author><author><name>Annette Schürmann</name></author><author><name>Juan S. Bonifacino</name></author><author><name>Maria Antonietta De Matteis</name></author><author><name>Romeo Ricci</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Inflammasome complexes are pivotal in the innate immune response to pathogens and other danger signals&lt;sup&gt;1–4&lt;/sup&gt;. The NLRP3 inflammasome is activated in response to a broad variety of cellular stressors. Most of the stimuli act in a potassium efflux-dependent manner but a primary and converging sensing mechanism by the NLRP3 receptor initiating inflammasome assembly remains ill-defined. Here we show that NLRP3 activators disrupt endosome-TGN retrograde transport (ETRT) and lead to localization of NLRP3 to endosomal vesicles. Genetic and pharmacologic perturbation of ETRT leads to accumulation of phosphoinositol-4-phosphate (PI4P) in endosomes to which NLRP3 is recruited. Disruption of ETRT potentiates NLRP3 inflammasome activation in murine and human macrophages &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. Mice with defects in ETRT in the myeloid compartment are more susceptible to LPS-induced sepsis showing enhanced mortality and IL-1β serum levels as compared to control animals. Our study thus uncovers that changes in endocytic trafficking mediate NLRP3-dependent inflammatory responses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460331" rel="alternate" title="Defective endosome-TGN retrograde transport promotes NLRP3 inflammasome activation (16 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.18.460647</id><title>Diet-derived metabolites and mucus link the gut microbiome to fever after cytotoxic cancer treatment (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.766946+00:00</updated><author><name>Zaker Schwabkey</name></author><author><name>Diana Wiesnoski</name></author><author><name>Chia-Chi Chang</name></author><author><name>Wen-Bin Tsai</name></author><author><name>Dung Pham</name></author><author><name>Saira S Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Tomo Hayase</name></author><author><name>Miriam R Ortega Turrubiates</name></author><author><name>Rawan K El-Himri</name></author><author><name>Christopher A Sanchez</name></author><author><name>Eiko Hayase</name></author><author><name>Annette C Frenk Oquendo</name></author><author><name>Takahiko Miyama</name></author><author><name>Taylor M Halsey</name></author><author><name>Brooke E Heckel</name></author><author><name>Alexandria N Brown</name></author><author><name>Yimei Jin</name></author><author><name>Philip L Lorenzi</name></author><author><name>Marc O Warmoes</name></author><author><name>Lin Tan</name></author><author><name>Alton Swennes</name></author><author><name>Vanessa B Jensen</name></author><author><name>Christine B Peterson</name></author><author><name>Kim-Anh Do</name></author><author><name>Liangliang Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yushu Shi</name></author><author><name>Yinghong Wang</name></author><author><name>Jessica R Galloway-Pena</name></author><author><name>Pablo C Okhuysen</name></author><author><name>Carrie Daniel-MacDougall</name></author><author><name>Yusuke Shono</name></author><author><name>Marina Burgos da Silva</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Peled</name></author><author><name>Marcel RM van den Brink</name></author><author><name>Nadim J Ajami</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Wargo</name></author><author><name>Gabriela Rondon</name></author><author><name>Samer A Srour</name></author><author><name>Rohtesh S Mehta</name></author><author><name>Amin M Alousi</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth J Shpall</name></author><author><name>Richard E Champlin</name></author><author><name>Samuel A Shelburne</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey J Molldrem</name></author><author><name>Mohamed A Jamal</name></author><author><name>Jennifer L Karmouch</name></author><author><name>Robert R Jenq</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fever in the setting of low white blood cell counts, also known as neutropenic fever, is considered an oncologic emergency. Only some 30% of patients with neutropenic fever have an identifiable source of infection, such as a bloodstream bacterial infection of intestinal origin. Whether other nonpathogenic intestinal bacteria can contribute to neutropenic fever is not known. In a cohort of 119 patients undergoing hematopoietic cell transplantation, a treatment with a high risk for neutropenic fever, the fecal microbiome was examined at onset of neutropenia. Over the next 4 days, 63 patients (53%) developed a fever, which was associated with increased Akkermansia muciniphila, a species of intestinal commensal bacteria with mucus-degrading capabilities (p=0.006, corrected for multiple comparisons). In mouse models, two cytotoxic therapies, irradiation and melphalan, each also produced an expansion of fecal A. muciniphila as well as thinning of the colonic mucus layer. Direct irradiation of fecal bacteria, however, did not lead to expansion of A. muciniphila, suggesting an indirect effect via the host. Irradiated mice displayed reduced oral food intake, and dietary restriction of unirradiated mice was sufficient to produce an expansion of A. muciniphila and thinning of the colonic mucus layer. Treatment of diet-restricted mice with several narrow-spectrum antibiotics demonstrated that azithromycin, which depleted intestinal A. muciniphila, led to preservation of the colonic mucus layer. Diet-restricted mice developed an increase in colonic luminal pH and reductions in acetate, propionate, and butyrate. Treatment of A. muciniphila in vitro with lower pH and increased propionate led to delayed growth and prevented utilization of mucin. Dietary restriction and low propionate also produced large changes in A. muciniphila gene expression, including upregulation of L-fucose isomerase, a member of glycosyl hydrolase family 109, and a member of the Idh/MocA family of oxidoreductases, which may play roles in mucin glycan utilization. Supplementing the drinking water of diet-restricted mice with propionate led to preservation of the colonic mucus layer. In the setting of irradiation, we found that by 6 days following treatment mice developed signs of systemic infection manifesting as hypothermia. Upon examination of colon tissues, we found that irradiated mice had elevated levels of inflammatory cytokines including IL-1b, CCL2, CCL7, IL-22, CXCL1, and CXCL10. Treatment with azithromycin or propionate lessened the severity of hypothermia, preserved the mucus layer, and mitigated elevations in inflammatory cytokines in the colon. In summary, we have found that clinical neutropenic fever is associated with increased intestinal abundance of mucolytic bacteria, and further experiments in mice have identified a pathway linking impaired diet and loss of bacterial metabolites as important mediators of this process.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.18.460647" rel="alternate" title="Diet-derived metabolites and mucus link the gut microbiome to fever after cytotoxic cancer treatment (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.16.460530</id><title>Genome-wide identification of genes important for growth of Dickeya dadantii and D. dianthicola in potato (Solanum tuberosum) tubers (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.767393+00:00</updated><author><name>Tyler C. Helmann</name></author><author><name>Melanie J. Filiatrault</name></author><author><name>Paul V. Stodghill</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Dickeya&lt;/italic&gt; species are causal agents of soft rot diseases in many economically important crops, including soft rot disease of potato (&lt;italic&gt;Solanum tuberosum&lt;/italic&gt;). Using random barcode transposon-site sequencing (RB-TnSeq), we generated genome-wide mutant fitness profiles of &lt;italic&gt;Dickeya dadantii&lt;/italic&gt; 3937, &lt;italic&gt;Dickeya dianthicola&lt;/italic&gt; ME23, and &lt;italic&gt;Dickeya dianthicola&lt;/italic&gt; 67-19 isolates collected after passage through several &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; conditions. Tubers from the potato cultivars “Atlantic”, “Dark Red Norland”, and “Upstate Abundance” provided highly similar conditions for bacterial growth. Using the homolog detection software PyParanoid, we matched fitness values for orthologous genes in the three bacterial strains. Direct comparison of fitness among the strains highlighted shared and variable traits important for growth. Bacterial growth in minimal medium required many metabolic traits that were also essential for competitive growth &lt;italic&gt;in planta&lt;/italic&gt;, such as amino acid, carbohydrate, and nucleotide biosynthesis. Growth in tubers specifically required the pectin degradation gene &lt;italic&gt;kduD&lt;/italic&gt;. Disruption in three putative DNA-binding proteins had strain-specific effects on competitive fitness in tubers. Though the Soft Rot &lt;italic&gt;Pectobacteriaceae&lt;/italic&gt; can cause disease with little host specificity, it remains to be seen the extent to which strain-level variation impacts virulence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.16.460530" rel="alternate" title="Genome-wide identification of genes important for growth of Dickeya dadantii and D. dianthicola in potato (Solanum tuberosum) tubers (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460193</id><title>Genomic and physiological characterization of Novosphingobium terrae sp. nov., an alphaproteobacterium isolated from Cerrado soil containing a megasized chromid (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.767768+00:00</updated><author><name>Aline Belmok</name></author><author><name>Felipe Marques de Almeida</name></author><author><name>Rodrigo Theodoro Rocha</name></author><author><name>Carla Simone Vizzotto</name></author><author><name>Marcos Rogério Tótola</name></author><author><name>Marcelo Henrique Soller Ramada</name></author><author><name>Ricardo Henrique Krüger</name></author><author><name>Cynthia Maria Kyaw</name></author><author><name>Georgios J. Pappas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A novel bacterial strain, designated GeG2&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt;, was isolated from soils of native Cerrado, a highly biodiverse savanna-like Brazilian biome. 16S rRNA gene sequence analysis of strain GeG2&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; revealed high sequence identity (100%) to the alphaproteobacterium &lt;italic&gt;Novosphingobium rosa&lt;/italic&gt;, however, comparisons with &lt;italic&gt;N. rosa&lt;/italic&gt; DSM7285&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; showed several distinctive features, prompting a full characterization of the new strain in terms of growth, morphology, biochemistry and, ultimately, its genome. GeG2&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; cells were Gram-stain negative bacilli, facultatively anaerobic, motile, positive for catalase and oxidase activities and for starch hydrolysis. Strain GeG2&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; presented planktonic-sessile dimorphism and cell aggregates surrounded by extracellular matrix and nanometric spherical structures were observed in liquid cultures, suggesting the production of exopolysaccharides (EPS) and outer membrane vesicles (OMVs). Whole genome assembly revealed four circular replicons: a 4.1 Mb chromosome, a 2.7 Mb extrachromosomal megareplicon and two plasmids (212.7 and 68.6 kb). The megareplicon contains few core genes and plasmid-type replication/maintenance systems, consistent with its classification as a chromid. Genome annotation shows a vast repertoire of carbohydrate active enzymes and genes involved in the degradation of aromatic compounds, highlighting the biotechnological potential of the new isolate obtained from Cerrado soils, especially regarding EPS production and biodegradation of recalcitrant compounds. Chemotaxonomic features, including polar lipid and fatty acid profiles, as well as physiological, molecular and whole genome comparisons showed significant differences between strain GeG2&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; and a &lt;italic&gt;N. rosa&lt;/italic&gt;, clearly indicating that it represents a novel species, for which the name &lt;italic&gt;Novosphingobium terrae&lt;/italic&gt; is proposed. The type strain is GeG2&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; (=CBMAI 2313T =CBAS 753T).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Novosphingobium&lt;/italic&gt; is an alphaproteobacterial genus presenting diverse physiological profiles and broad biotechnological applications. However, many aspects regarding the biology of this important bacterial group remain elusive. A novel &lt;italic&gt;Novosphingobium&lt;/italic&gt; strain was isolated from soils of Cerrado, an important Brazilian biome. Despite 100% 16S rRNA gene identity with &lt;italic&gt;Novosphingobium rosa&lt;/italic&gt;, polyphasic characterizations, including physiological, chemotaxonomic, and whole genome- based analyses revealed significant differences between GeG2&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; and N. rosa DSM7285&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt;, reinforcing resolution limitations in phylogenetic analysis based solely on 16S RNA and highlighting the importance of employing different approaches for the description of bacterial species. Using short and long read sequencing approaches, a high-quality fully resolved genome assembly was generated and one of the largest chromids reported to date was identified. A comprehensive characterization of environmental isolates allows us to better elucidate the diversity and biology of members of this bacterial group with potential biotechnological importance, guiding future bioprospecting efforts and genomic studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460193" rel="alternate" title="Genomic and physiological characterization of Novosphingobium terrae sp. nov., an alphaproteobacterium isolated from Cerrado soil containing a megasized chromid (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460204</id><title>Controls on the isotopic composition of microbial methane (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.767980+00:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Gropp</name></author><author><name>Qusheng Jin</name></author><author><name>Itay Halevy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microbial methane production (methanogenesis) is responsible for more than half of the annual emission of this major greenhouse gas to the atmosphere. Though the stable isotopic composition of methane is often used to characterize its sources and sinks, empirical descriptions of the isotopic signature of methanogenesis currently limit such attempts. We developed a biochemical-isotopic model of methanogenesis by CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; reduction, which predicts carbon and hydrogen isotopic fractionations, and clumped isotopologue distributions, as functions of the cell’s environment. We mechanistically explain multiple-isotopic patterns in laboratory and natural settings and show that such patterns constrain the in-situ energetics of methanogenesis. Combining our model with environmental data, we infer that in almost all marine environments and gas deposits, energy-limited methanogenesis operates close to chemical and isotopic equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460204" rel="alternate" title="Controls on the isotopic composition of microbial methane (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-09-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>