<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.275823+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.27.469863</id><title>A chemical-genetic map of the pathways controlling drug potency in Mycobacterium tuberculosis (51 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.276205+00:00</updated><author><name>Shuqi Li</name></author><author><name>Nicholas C Poulton</name></author><author><name>Jesseon S Chang</name></author><author><name>Zachary A Azadian</name></author><author><name>Michael A Dejusus</name></author><author><name>Nadine Ruecker</name></author><author><name>Matthew D Zimmerman</name></author><author><name>Kathryn Eckartt</name></author><author><name>Barbara Bosch</name></author><author><name>Curtis A. Engelhart</name></author><author><name>Daniel Sullivan</name></author><author><name>Martin Gengenbacher</name></author><author><name>Véronique A Dartois</name></author><author><name>Dirk Schnappinger</name></author><author><name>Jeremy M Rock</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; infection is notoriously difficult to treat. To define the bacterial determinants that limit treatment efficacy, we developed a CRISPRi chemical genetics platform to titrate the expression of nearly all Mtb genes and quantify bacterial fitness in the presence of different drugs. Mining this dataset, we discovered diverse mechanisms of intrinsic drug resistance, unveiling hundreds of potential targets for synergistic drug combinations. Combining our data with comparative genomics of Mtb clinical isolates, we further identified new mechanisms of acquired drug resistance, one of which is associated with the emergence of a multidrug-resistant tuberculosis (TB) outbreak in South America. Lastly, we make the unexpected discovery of loss-of-function mutations in the intrinsic resistance factor &lt;italic&gt;whiB7&lt;/italic&gt; in an entire Mtb sublineage endemic to Southeast Asia, presenting an opportunity to repurpose macrolides to treat TB. This chemical-genetic map provides a rich resource to understand drug efficacy and guide future TB drug development and treatment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.27.469863" rel="alternate" title="A chemical-genetic map of the pathways controlling drug potency in Mycobacterium tuberculosis (51 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469859</id><title>High prevalence of Klebsiella pneumoniae in European food products: a multicentric study comparing culture and molecular detection methods (38 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.277004+00:00</updated><author><name>Carla Rodrigues</name></author><author><name>Kathrin Hauser</name></author><author><name>Niamh Cahill</name></author><author><name>Małgorzata Ligowska-Marzęta</name></author><author><name>Gabriella Centorotola</name></author><author><name>Alessandra Cornacchia</name></author><author><name>Raquel Garcia Fierro</name></author><author><name>Marisa Haenni</name></author><author><name>Eva Møller Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Pascal Piveteau</name></author><author><name>Elodie Barbier</name></author><author><name>Dearbháile Morris</name></author><author><name>Francesco Pomilio</name></author><author><name>Sylvain Brisse</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; species complex (KpSC) is a leading cause of multidrug-resistant human infections. To better understand the potential contribution of food as a vehicle of KpSC, we conducted a multicentric study to define an optimal culture method for its recovery from food matrices, and to characterize food isolates phenotypically and genotypically. Chicken meat (n=160) and salad (n=145) samples were collected in five European countries and screened for KpSC presence using culture-based and ZKIR qPCR methods. Enrichment using buffered peptone water followed by streaking on Simmons citrate agar with inositol (44°C/48h) was defined as the most suitable selective culture method for KpSC recovery. High prevalence of KpSC was found in chicken meat (60% and 52% by ZKIR qPCR and culture approach, respectively) and salad (30% and 21%, respectively) samples. Genomic analyses revealed high genetic diversity with the dominance of phylogroups Kp1 (91%) and Kp3 (6%). 82% of isolates presented a natural antimicrobial susceptibility phenotype and genotype, with only four CTX-M-15-producing isolates detected. Notably, identical genotypes were found across samples: same food type and same country (15 cases); different food types and same country (1); same food type and two countries (1), suggesting high rates of transmission of KpSC within the food sector. Our study provides a novel isolation strategy for KpSC from food matrices and reinforces the view of food as a potential source of KpSC colonization in humans.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bacteria of the &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; species complex (KpSC) are ubiquitous and &lt;italic&gt;K. pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; (Kp) is a leading cause of antibiotic-resistant infections in humans and animals. Despite the urgent public health threat represented by Kp, there is a lack of knowledge on the contribution of food sources to colonization and subsequent infection in humans. This is partly due to the absence of standardized methods for characterizing KpSC presence in food matrices. Our multicentric study provides and implements a novel isolation strategy for KpSC from food matrices and shows that KpSC members are highly prevalent in salads and chicken meat, reinforcing the view of food as a potential source of KpSC colonization in humans. Despite the large genetic diversity and the low-levels of resistance detected, the occurrence of identical genotypes across samples suggests high rates of transmission of KpSC within the food sector, which need to be further explored to define possible control strategies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469859" rel="alternate" title="High prevalence of Klebsiella pneumoniae in European food products: a multicentric study comparing culture and molecular detection methods (38 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469969</id><title>Transcriptional profiles of a foliar fungal endophyte (Pestalotiopsis, Ascomycota) and its endohyphal bacterium (Luteibacter, Gammaproteobacteria) in co-culture support sulfur exchange and growth regulation (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.277443+00:00</updated><author><name>Justin P. Shaffer</name></author><author><name>Morgan E. Carter</name></author><author><name>Joseph E. Spraker</name></author><author><name>Meara Clark</name></author><author><name>Brian A. Smith</name></author><author><name>Kevin L. Hockett</name></author><author><name>David A. Baltrus</name></author><author><name>A. Elizabeth Arnold</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Symbiosis with bacteria is widespread among eukaryotes, including fungi. Bacteria that live within fungal mycelia (endohyphal bacteria) occur in many plant-associated fungi, including diverse Mucoromycota and Dikarya. &lt;italic&gt;Pestalotiopsis&lt;/italic&gt; sp. 9143 is a filamentous ascomycete isolated originally as a foliar endophyte of &lt;italic&gt;Platycladus orientalis&lt;/italic&gt; (Cupressaceae). It is infected naturally with the endohyphal bacterium &lt;italic&gt;Luteibacter&lt;/italic&gt; sp. 9143, which influences auxin and enzyme production by its fungal host. Previous studies have used transcriptomics to examine similar symbioses between endohyphal bacteria and root-associated fungi such as arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi and plant pathogens. However, currently there are no gene expression studies of endohyphal bacteria of Ascomycota, the most species-rich fungal phylum. We developed methods for assessing gene expression by &lt;italic&gt;Pestalotiopsis&lt;/italic&gt; sp. and &lt;italic&gt;Luteibacter&lt;/italic&gt; sp. when grown in co-culture and when each was grown axenically. Our assays showed that the density of &lt;italic&gt;Luteibacter&lt;/italic&gt; sp. in co-culture was greater than in axenic culture, but the opposite was true for the &lt;italic&gt;Pestalotiopsis&lt;/italic&gt; sp. Dual RNA-seq data demonstrate that growing in co-culture modulates developmental and metabolic processes in both the fungus and bacterium, potentially through changes in the balance of organic sulfur via methionine acquisition. Our analyses also suggest an unexpected, potential role of the bacterial type VI secretion system in symbiosis establishment, expanding current understanding of the scope and dynamics of fungal-bacterial symbioses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;TWEET&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;When in co-culture, &lt;italic&gt;Luteibacter&lt;/italic&gt; downregulates motility and upregulates a T6SS. Gene expression changes in its host, &lt;italic&gt;Pestalotiopsis&lt;/italic&gt;, suggest the bacterium impacts fungal cell structure and methionine availability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interactions between microbes and their hosts have important outcomes for host- and environmental health. Foliar fungal endophytes that infect healthy plants can harbor facultative endosymbionts called endohyphal bacteria, which can influence the outcome of plant-fungus interactions. These bacterial-fungal interactions can be influential but are poorly understood, particularly from a transcriptome perspective. Here, we report on a comparative, dual RNA-seq study examining the gene expression patterns of a foliar fungal endophyte and a facultative endohyphal bacterium when cultured together vs. separately. Our findings support a role for the fungus in providing organic sulfur to the bacterium, potentially through methionine acquisition, and potential involvement of a bacterial type VI secretion system in symbiosis establishment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This work adds to the growing body of literature characterizing endohyphal bacterial-fungal interactions, with a focus on a model facultative bacterial-fungal symbiosis in two species-rich lineages, the Ascomycota and Proteobacteria.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469969" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptional profiles of a foliar fungal endophyte (Pestalotiopsis, Ascomycota) and its endohyphal bacterium (Luteibacter, Gammaproteobacteria) in co-culture support sulfur exchange and growth regulation (26 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469587</id><title>The energy requirements of ion homeostasis determine the lifespan of starving bacteria (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.277781+00:00</updated><author><name>Severin Schink</name></author><author><name>Mark Polk</name></author><author><name>Edward Athaide</name></author><author><name>Avik Mukherjee</name></author><author><name>Constantin Ammar</name></author><author><name>Xili Liu</name></author><author><name>Seungeun Oh</name></author><author><name>Yu-Fang Chang</name></author><author><name>Markus Basan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The majority of microbes on earth, whether they live in the ocean, the soil or in animals, are not growing, but instead struggling to survive starvation&lt;sup&gt;1–6&lt;/sup&gt;. Some genes and environmental conditions affecting starvation survival have been identified&lt;sup&gt;7–13&lt;/sup&gt;, but despite almost a century of study&lt;sup&gt;14–16&lt;/sup&gt;, we do not know which processes lead to irreversible loss of viability, which maintenance processes counteract them and how lifespan is determined from the balance of these opposing processes. Here, we used time-lapse microscopy to capture and characterize the cell death process of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; during carbon starvation for the first time. We found that a lack of nutrients results in the collapse of ion homeostasis, triggering a positive-feedback cascade of osmotic swelling and membrane permeabilization that ultimately results in lysis. Based on these findings, we hypothesized that ion transport is the major energetic requirement for starving cells and the primary determinant of the timing of lysis. We therefore developed a mathematical model that integrates ion homeostasis and ‘cannibalistic’ nutrient recycling from perished cells&lt;sup&gt;16,17&lt;/sup&gt; to predict lifespan changes under diverse conditions, such as changes of cell size, medium composition, and prior growth conditions. Guided by model predictions, we found that cell death during starvation could be dramatically slowed by replacing inorganic ions from the medium with a non-permeating osmoprotectant, removing the cost of ion homeostasis and preventing lysis. Our quantitative and predictive model explains how survival kinetics are determined in starvation and elucidates the mechanistic underpinnings of starvation survival.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469587" rel="alternate" title="The energy requirements of ion homeostasis determine the lifespan of starving bacteria (21 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469601</id><title>Genome context influences evolutionary flexibility of nearly identical type III effectors in two phytopathogenic Pseudomonads (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.278094+00:00</updated><author><name>David A. Baltrus</name></author><author><name>Qian Feng</name></author><author><name>Brian H Kvitko</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Integrative Conjugative Elements (ICEs) are replicons that can insert and excise from chromosomal locations in a site specific manner, can conjugate across strains, and which often carry a variety of genes useful for bacterial growth and survival under specific conditions. Although ICEs have been identified and vetted within certain clades of the agricultural pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas syringae&lt;/italic&gt;, the impact of ICE carriage and transfer across the entire &lt;italic&gt;P. syringae&lt;/italic&gt; species complex remains underexplored. Here we identify and vet an ICE (PmaICE-DQ) from &lt;italic&gt;P. syringae&lt;/italic&gt; pv. maculicola ES4326, a strain commonly used for laboratory virulence experiments, demonstrate that this element can excise and conjugate across strains, and contains loci encoding multiple type III effector proteins. Moreover, genome context suggests that another ICE (PmaICE-AOAB) is highly similar in comparison with and found immediately adjacent to PmaICE-DQ within the chromosome of strain ES4326, and also contains multiple type III effectors. Lastly, we present passage data from &lt;italic&gt;in planta&lt;/italic&gt; experiments that suggests that genomic plasticity associated with ICEs may enable strains to more rapidly lose type III effectors that trigger R-gene mediated resistance in comparison to strains where nearly isogenic effectors are not present in ICEs. Taken together, our study sheds light on a set of ICE elements from &lt;italic&gt;P. syringae&lt;/italic&gt; pv. maculicola ES4326 and highlights how genomic context may lead to different evolutionary dynamics for shared virulence genes between strains.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469601" rel="alternate" title="Genome context influences evolutionary flexibility of nearly identical type III effectors in two phytopathogenic Pseudomonads (19 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469614</id><title>Peptidoglycan recycling contributes to outer membrane integrity and carbapenem tolerance in Acinetobacter baumannii (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.278281+00:00</updated><author><name>Nowrosh Islam</name></author><author><name>Misha I. Kazi</name></author><author><name>Katie N. Kang</name></author><author><name>Jacob Biboy</name></author><author><name>Joe Gray</name></author><author><name>Feroz Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Richard D. Schargel</name></author><author><name>Cara C. Boutte</name></author><author><name>Tobias Dörr</name></author><author><name>Waldemar Vollmer</name></author><author><name>Joseph M. Boll</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Gram-negative cell envelope is an essential structure that not only protects the cell against lysis from the internal turgor, but also forms a barrier to limit entry of antibiotics. Some of our most potent bactericidal antibiotics, the β-lactams, exploit the essentiality of the cell envelope by inhibiting its biosynthesis, typically inducing lysis and rapid death. However, many Gram-negative bacteria exhibit “antibiotic tolerance”, the ability to sustain viability in the presence of β-lactams for extended time periods. Despite several studies showing that antibiotic tolerance contributes directly to treatment failure, and is a steppingstone in acquisition of true resistance, the molecular factors that promote intrinsic tolerance are not well-understood. &lt;italic&gt;Acinetobacter baumannii&lt;/italic&gt; is a critical-threat nosocomial pathogen notorious for its ability to rapidly develop multidrug resistance. While typically reserved to combat multidrug resistant infections, carbapenem β-lactam antibiotics (i.e., meropenem) are first-line prescriptions to treat &lt;italic&gt;A. baumannii&lt;/italic&gt; infections. Meropenem tolerance in Gram-negative pathogens is characterized by morphologically distinct populations of spheroplasts, but the impact of spheroplast formation is not fully understood. Here, we show that susceptible &lt;italic&gt;A. baumannii&lt;/italic&gt; clinical isolates demonstrate high intrinsic tolerance to meropenem, form spheroplasts with the antibiotic and revert to normal growth after antibiotic removal. Using transcriptomics and genetics screens, we characterized novel tolerance factors and found that outer membrane integrity maintenance, drug efflux and peptidoglycan homeostasis collectively contribute to meropenem tolerance in &lt;italic&gt;A. baumannii&lt;/italic&gt;. Furthermore, outer membrane integrity and peptidoglycan recycling are tightly linked in their contribution to meropenem tolerance in &lt;italic&gt;A. baumannii&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carbapenem treatment failure associated with “superbug” infections has rapidly increased in prevalence, highlighting an urgent need to develop new therapeutic strategies. Antibiotic tolerance can directly lead to treatment failure but has also been shown to promote acquisition of true resistance within a population. While some studies have addressed mechanisms that promote tolerance, factors that underlie Gram-negative bacterial survival during carbapenem treatment are not well-understood. Here, we characterized a role for peptidoglycan recycling in outer membrane integrity maintenance and carbapenem tolerance in &lt;italic&gt;A. baumannii&lt;/italic&gt;. These studies suggest that the pathogen limits antibiotic concentrations in the periplasm and highlights physiological processes that could be targeted to improve antimicrobial treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469614" rel="alternate" title="Peptidoglycan recycling contributes to outer membrane integrity and carbapenem tolerance in Acinetobacter baumannii (17 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.470047</id><title>Development of a novel glycoengineering platform for the rapid production of conjugate vaccines (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.278459+00:00</updated><author><name>Sherif Abouelhadid</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Atkins</name></author><author><name>Emily Kay</name></author><author><name>Ian Passmore</name></author><author><name>Simon J North</name></author><author><name>Burhan Lehri</name></author><author><name>Paul Hitchen</name></author><author><name>Eirik Bakke</name></author><author><name>Mohammed Rahman</name></author><author><name>Janine Bosse</name></author><author><name>Yanwen Li</name></author><author><name>Vanessa S. Terra</name></author><author><name>Paul Langford</name></author><author><name>Anne Dell</name></author><author><name>Brendan W Wren</name></author><author><name>Jon Cuccui</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antimicrobial resistance (AMR) is threatening the lives of millions worldwide. Antibiotics which once saved countless lives, are now failing, ushering in vaccines development as a current global imperative. Conjugate vaccines produced either by chemical synthesis or biologically in &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; cells, have been demonstrated to be safe and efficacious in protection against several deadly bacterial diseases. However, conjugate vaccines assembly and production have several shortcomings which hinders their wider availability. Here, we developed a tool, Mobile-element Assisted Glycoconjugation by Insertion on Chromosome, MAGIC, a novel method that overcomes the limitations of the current conjugate vaccine design method(s). We demonstrate at least 2-fold increase in glycoconjugate yield via MAGIC when compared to conventional bioconjugate method(s). Furthermore, the modularity of the MAGIC platform also allowed us to perform glycoengineering in genetically intractable bacterial species other than &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;. The MAGIC system promises a rapid, robust and versatile method to develop vaccines against bacteria, especially AMR pathogens, and could be applied for biopreparedness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.470047" rel="alternate" title="Development of a novel glycoengineering platform for the rapid production of conjugate vaccines (14 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469549</id><title>“Comparative genomics and pangenomics of vancomycin resistant and susceptible Enterococcus faecium from Irish hospitals across 20 years” (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.278655+00:00</updated><author><name>R.J. Leigh</name></author><author><name>C. McKenna</name></author><author><name>R. McWade</name></author><author><name>B. Lynch</name></author><author><name>F. Walsh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Enterococcus faecium&lt;/italic&gt; has emerged as an important nosocomial pathogen, which is increasingly difficult to treat due to the genetic acquisition of vancomycin resistance. Ireland exhibits a recalcitrant vancomycin resistant bloodstream infection rate compared to other developed countries. A set of 28 vancomycin resistant isolates was sequenced to construct a dataset alongside 61 other publicly available Irish genomes. This dataset was extensively analysed using &lt;italic&gt;in-silico&lt;/italic&gt; methodologies and uncovered distinct evolutionary, coevolutionary, and clinically relevant population trends. These results suggest that a stable (in terms of genome size, GC%, and number of genes), yet genetically diverse population (in terms of gene content) of &lt;italic&gt;Enterococcus faecium&lt;/italic&gt; persist in Ireland with acquired resistance arising &lt;italic&gt;via&lt;/italic&gt; plasmid acquisition (&lt;italic&gt;vanA&lt;/italic&gt;) or to a lesser extent, chromosomal recombination (&lt;italic&gt;vanB&lt;/italic&gt;). Population analysis described five clusters with one cluster partitioned into four clades which transcend isolation dates. Pangenomic and recombination analyses revealed an open (whole genome and chromosomal specific) pangenome illustrating a rampant evolutionary pattern. Comparative resistomics and virulomics uncovered distinct chromosomal and mobilomal propensity for multidrug resistance, widespread chromosomal point-mutation mediated resistance, and chromosomal harboured arsenals of virulence factors. Comparative phagomics revealed a core prophagome of three prophages throughout the dataset. Interestingly, a potential difference in biofilm formation strategies was highlighted by coevolutionary analysis, suggesting differential biofilm genotypes between &lt;italic&gt;vanA&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;vanB&lt;/italic&gt; isolates. These results highlight the evolutionary history of Irish &lt;italic&gt;Enterococcus faecium&lt;/italic&gt; isolates and may provide an insight into underlying infection dynamics in a clinical setting.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469549" rel="alternate" title="“Comparative genomics and pangenomics of vancomycin resistant and susceptible Enterococcus faecium from Irish hospitals across 20 years” (13 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469855</id><title>Fibroblastic reticular cells provide a supportive niche for lymph node-resident macrophages (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.278789+00:00</updated><author><name>Joshua D’Rozario</name></author><author><name>Konstantin Knoblich</name></author><author><name>Mechthild Lütge</name></author><author><name>Christian Pérez Shibayama</name></author><author><name>Hung-Wei Cheng</name></author><author><name>Yannick O. Alexandre</name></author><author><name>David Roberts</name></author><author><name>Joana Campos</name></author><author><name>Jillian Astarita</name></author><author><name>Emma Dutton</name></author><author><name>Muath Suliman</name></author><author><name>Alice E. Denton</name></author><author><name>Shannon J. Turley</name></author><author><name>Richard L. Boyd</name></author><author><name>Scott Mueller</name></author><author><name>Burkhard Ludewig</name></author><author><name>Tracy Heng</name></author><author><name>Anne L Fletcher</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The lymph node (LN) is home to resident macrophage populations that are essential for immune function and homeostasis. The T cell paracortical zone is a major site of macrophage efferocytosis of apoptotic cells, but key factors controlling this niche are undefined. Here we show that fibroblastic reticular cells (FRCs) are an essential component of the LN macrophage niche. Macrophages co-localised with FRCs in human LNs, and murine single-cell RNA-sequencing revealed that most reticular cells expressed master macrophage regulator CSF1. Functional assays showed that CSF1R signalling was sufficient to support macrophage development. In the presence of LPS, FRCs underwent a mechanistic switch and maintained support through CSF1R-independent mechanisms. These effects were conserved between mouse and human systems. Rapid loss of macrophages and monocytes from LNs was observed upon genetic ablation of FRCs. These data reveal a critically important role for FRCs in the creation of the parenchymal macrophage niche within LNs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469855" rel="alternate" title="Fibroblastic reticular cells provide a supportive niche for lymph node-resident macrophages (13 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469816</id><title>Genome sequences of Arthrobacter spp. that use a modified sulfoglycolytic Embden-Meyerhof-Parnas pathway (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.278996+00:00</updated><author><name>Arashdeep Kaur</name></author><author><name>Phillip L. van der Peet</name></author><author><name>Janice W.-Y. Mui</name></author><author><name>Marion Herisse</name></author><author><name>Sacha Pidot</name></author><author><name>Spencer J. Williams</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sulfoglycolysis pathways enable the breakdown of the sulfosugar sulfoquinovose and environmental recycling of its carbon and sulfur content. Several pathways exist for the breakdown of sulfoquinovose that usually lead to production of C3-sulfonates (sulfolactate and 2,3-dihydroxypropanesulfonate) that are excreted and sustain secondary bacterial communities. The prototypical sulfoglycolytic pathway is a variant of the classical Embden-Meyerhof-Parnas pathway that has been described in gram-negative &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; and results in production of 2,3-dihydroxypropanesulfonate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used enrichment cultures to discover new sulfoglycolytic bacteria from Australian soil samples. Two gram-positive &lt;italic&gt;Arthrobacter&lt;/italic&gt; spp. were isolated that produced sulfolactate as the metabolic end-product. Genome sequences identified a modified sulfoglycolytic Embden-Meyerhof-Parnas (sulfo-EMP) gene cluster that retained the core sulfoglycolysis genes encoding metabolic enzymes, but featuring the replacement of the gene encoding sulfolactaldehyde (SLA) reductase with SLA dehydrogenase, and the absence of sulfoquinovosidase and sulfoquinovose mutarotase genes. The gene clusters were broadly conserved across a range of other sequenced Actinobacteria.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We report the first gram-positive soil bacteria that utilize sulfo-EMP pathways to metabolize SQ. Excretion of sulfolactate is consistent with an aerobic saprophytic lifestyle. This work broadens our knowledge of the sulfo-EMP pathway to include soil bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469816" rel="alternate" title="Genome sequences of Arthrobacter spp. that use a modified sulfoglycolytic Embden-Meyerhof-Parnas pathway (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469476</id><title>Novel RNA viruses associated with avian haemosporidian parasites (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.279133+00:00</updated><author><name>Jose Roberto Rodrigues</name></author><author><name>Scott William Roy</name></author><author><name>Ravinder Sehgal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Avian haemosporidian parasites can cause malaria-like symptoms in their hosts and have been implicated in the demise of some bird species. The newly described Matryoshka RNA viruses (MaRNAV1 and MaRNAV2) infect parasites that in turn infect their vertebrate hosts. MaRNAV2 was the first RNA virus discovered associated with parasites of the genus &lt;italic&gt;Leucocytozoon&lt;/italic&gt;. By analyzing metatranscriptomes from the NCBI SRA database with local sequence alignment tools, we detected two novel RNA viruses; we describe them as MaRNAV3 associated with &lt;italic&gt;Leucocytozoon&lt;/italic&gt; and MaRNAV4 associated with &lt;italic&gt;Parahaemoproteus&lt;/italic&gt;. These had ~40-60% amino acid identity to the RNA-dependent RNA-polymerase (RdRp) of MaRNAV1 and 2, respectively. These findings lead us to hypothesize that MaRNAV_like viruses are widespread and tightly associated with the order Haemosporida since they have been described in human &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium vivax&lt;/italic&gt;, and now two genera of avian haemosporidians.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469476" rel="alternate" title="Novel RNA viruses associated with avian haemosporidian parasites (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470137</id><title>Staphylococcus aureus β-toxin exerts anti-angiogenic effects by inhibiting re-endothelialization and neovessel formation (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.279249+00:00</updated><author><name>Phuong M Tran</name></author><author><name>Sharon S Tang</name></author><author><name>Wilmara Salgado-Pabón</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/italic&gt; is the causative agent of numerous severe human infections associated with significant morbidity and mortality worldwide. &lt;italic&gt;S. aureus&lt;/italic&gt; often targets the vascular endothelium to interfere with proper host responses during invasive infections. In this study, we provide evidence that &lt;italic&gt;S. aureus&lt;/italic&gt; β-toxin inhibits wound repair mechanisms in human endothelial cells by preventing cell proliferation and migration. These findings were confirmed in a rabbit aortic explant model where β-toxin impedes sprout formation. Decreased cell proliferation was accompanied by decreased production of the angiogenic proteins endothelin-1, IGFBP-3, thrombospondin-1, TIMP-1, and TIMP-4. Meanwhile, inhibited wound repair was marked by increased HGF secretion from endothelial cells, likely a marker of endothelial cell damage. Together, these findings establish a mechanistic role for β-toxin where it inhibits proper tissue repair processes that likely promote &lt;italic&gt;S. aureus&lt;/italic&gt; infective niche.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470137" rel="alternate" title="Staphylococcus aureus β-toxin exerts anti-angiogenic effects by inhibiting re-endothelialization and neovessel formation (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469651</id><title>SmdA is a novel cell morphology determinant in Staphylococcus aureus (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.279367+00:00</updated><author><name>Ine S. Myrbråten</name></author><author><name>Gro A. Stamsås</name></author><author><name>Helena Chan</name></author><author><name>Danae Morales Angeles</name></author><author><name>Tiril Mathiesen Knutsen</name></author><author><name>Zhian Salehian</name></author><author><name>Volha Shapaval</name></author><author><name>Daniel Straume</name></author><author><name>Morten Kjos</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cell division and cell wall synthesis in staphylococci need to be precisely coordinated and controlled to allow the cell to multiply while maintaining their nearly spherical shape. The mechanisms ensuring correct placement of the division plane and synthesis of new cell wall have been studied intensively, however, hitherto unknown factors and proteins are likely to play key roles in this complex interplay. We here identified and investigated a protein with major influence on cell morphology in &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/italic&gt;. The protein, named SmdA (for staphylococcal morphology determinant A), is a membrane-protein with septum-enriched localization. By CRISPRi knockdown and overexpression combined with different microscopy techniques, we demonstrate that proper levels of SmdA is necessary for cell division, including septum formation and cell splitting. We also identified conserved residues in SmdA that are critical for its functionality. Pulldown- and bacterial two-hybrid interaction experiments showed that SmdA interacts with several known cell division- and cell wall synthesis proteins, including penicillin binding proteins (PBPs) and EzrA. Notably, SmdA also affects susceptibility to cell wall targeting antibiotics, particularly in methicillin-resistant &lt;italic&gt;S. aureus&lt;/italic&gt; (MRSA). Together, our results show that &lt;italic&gt;S. aureus&lt;/italic&gt; is dependent on balanced amounts of membrane-attached SmdA in order to carry out proper cell division.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469651" rel="alternate" title="SmdA is a novel cell morphology determinant in Staphylococcus aureus (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470090</id><title>Heterocomplexes between the Atypical Chemokine MIF and the CXC-Motif Chemokine CXCL4L1 Regulate Inflammation and Thrombus Formation (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.279627+00:00</updated><author><name>Markus Brandhofer</name></author><author><name>Adrian Hoffmann</name></author><author><name>Xavier Blanchet</name></author><author><name>Elena Siminkovitch</name></author><author><name>Anne-Katrin Rohlfing</name></author><author><name>Omar El Bounkari</name></author><author><name>Jeremy A. Nestele</name></author><author><name>Alexander Bild</name></author><author><name>Christos Kontos</name></author><author><name>Katleen Hille</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Rohde</name></author><author><name>Adrian Froehlich</name></author><author><name>Jona Golemi</name></author><author><name>Oezguen Goekce</name></author><author><name>Patrick Scheiermann</name></author><author><name>Nikolaos Tsilimparis</name></author><author><name>Wolfgang E. Kempf</name></author><author><name>Lars Maegdefessel</name></author><author><name>Remco T.A. Megens</name></author><author><name>Hans Ippel</name></author><author><name>Rory R. Koenen</name></author><author><name>Kevin Mayo</name></author><author><name>Meinrad Gawaz</name></author><author><name>Aphrodite Kapurniotu</name></author><author><name>Christian Weber</name></author><author><name>Philipp von Hundelshausen</name></author><author><name>Juergen Bernhagen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To fulfil their orchestrating function in immune cell trafficking in homeostasis and disease, a network of 49 chemokines and 23 receptors capitalizes on features of specificity, redundancy, and functional selectivity such as biased agonism. The discovery of the chemokine interactome, i.e. heteromeric chemokine-chemokine interactions, even across CC- and CXC-class borders, has further expanded the complexity within the network. Moreover, some inflammatory mediators, which are not structurally linked to classical CC-, CXC-, CX3C-, or C-chemokines, can bind to chemokine receptors and behave as atypical chemokines (ACKs). We identified the cytokine macrophage migration inhibitory factor (MIF) as an ACK that binds to the chemokine receptors CXCR2 and CXCR4 to promote atherogenic leukocyte recruitment. Here, we hypothesized that chemokine-chemokine interactions extend to ACKs and that MIF may form heterocomplexes with classical chemokines. We tested this hypothesis, applying an unbiased chemokine protein binding array. The platelet chemokine CXCL4L1, but not its variant CXCL4 or the CXCR2/CXCR4 ligands CXCL8 or CXCL12, was identified as a candidate interactor. MIF/CXCL4L1 complexation was verified by co-immunoprecipitation, surface plasmon-resonance analysis, and microscale thermophoresis, which also established high-affinity binding (KD=100-150 nM). The binding interface was predicted by peptide array-based mapping and molecular docking. We next determined whether heterocomplex formation modulates inflammatory and atherogenic activities of MIF. MIF-elicited T-cell chemotaxis as assessed in a 3D-matrix-based live cell-imaging set-up was abrogated, when cells were co-incubated with MIF and CXCL4L1. Heterocomplexation also blocked MIF-triggered migration of Egfp+ microglia in cortical cultures in situ. Of note, CXCL4L1 blocked the binding of Alexa-MIF to a soluble ectodomain mimic of CXCR4 and co-incubation with CXCL4L1 attenuated MIF-triggered dynamic mass redistribution in HEK293-CXCR4 transfectants, indicating that complex formation interferes with MIF/CXCR4 pathways. As MIF and CXCL4L1 are abundant platelet products, we finally tested their role in platelet activation. Multi-photon microscopy, FLIM-FRET, and proximity ligation assay visualized heterocomplexes in platelet aggregates and clinical human thrombus sections. Moreover, heterocomplex formation inhibited MIF-stimulated thrombus formation under flow and skewed the morphology of adhering platelets from a large to a small lamellipodia phenotype. Together, our study establishes a novel molecular interaction, adding to the complexity of the chemokine interactome and chemokine/receptor network. MIF/CXCL4L1, or more generally, ACK/CXC-motif chemokine heterocomplexes may be promising target structures to modulate inflammation and thrombosis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470090" rel="alternate" title="Heterocomplexes between the Atypical Chemokine MIF and the CXC-Motif Chemokine CXCL4L1 Regulate Inflammation and Thrombus Formation (6 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.468873</id><title>Microbial community analysis of biofilters reveals a dominance of either comammox Nitrospira or archaea as ammonia oxidizers in freshwater aquaria (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.280446+00:00</updated><author><name>Michelle M. McKnight</name></author><author><name>Josh D. Neufeld</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nitrification by aquarium biofilters transforms toxic ammonia waste (NH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;/NH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;) to less toxic nitrate (NO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;) via nitrite (NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;). Ammonia oxidation is mediated by ammonia-oxidizing bacteria (AOB), ammonia-oxidizing archaea (AOA), and the recently discovered complete ammonia oxidizing (comammox) &lt;italic&gt;Nitrospira&lt;/italic&gt;. Prior to the discovery of comammox &lt;italic&gt;Nitrospira&lt;/italic&gt;, previous research revealed that AOA dominate among ammonia oxidizers in freshwater biofilters. Here, we characterized the composition of aquarium filter microbial communities and quantified the abundance of all three known groups of ammonia oxidizers. Aquarium biofilter and water samples were collected from representative freshwater and saltwater systems in Southwestern Ontario, Canada. Using extracted DNA, we performed 16S rRNA gene sequencing and quantitative PCR (qPCR) to assess community composition and quantify the abundance of &lt;italic&gt;amoA&lt;/italic&gt; genes, respectively. Our results show that aquarium biofilter microbial communities were consistently represented by putative heterotrophs of the &lt;italic&gt;Proteobacteria&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Bacteroides&lt;/italic&gt; phyla, with distinct profiles associated with fresh versus saltwater biofilters. Among nitrifiers, comammox &lt;italic&gt;Nitrospira amoA&lt;/italic&gt; genes were detected in all 38 freshwater aquarium biofilter samples and were the most abundant ammonia oxidizer in 30 of these samples, with the remaining biofilters dominated by AOA, based on &lt;italic&gt;amoA&lt;/italic&gt; gene abundances. In saltwater biofilters, AOA or AOB were differentially abundant, with no comammox &lt;italic&gt;Nitrospira&lt;/italic&gt; detected. These results demonstrate that comammox &lt;italic&gt;Nitrospira&lt;/italic&gt; play an important role in biofilter nitrification that has been previously overlooked and such microcosms are useful for exploring the ecology of nitrification for future research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.468873" rel="alternate" title="Microbial community analysis of biofilters reveals a dominance of either comammox Nitrospira or archaea as ammonia oxidizers in freshwater aquaria (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469631</id><title>Genetic and chemical validation of Plasmodium falciparum aminopeptidase PfA-M17 as a drug target in the hemoglobin digestion pathway (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.280666+00:00</updated><author><name>Rebecca C.S. Edgar</name></author><author><name>Ghizal Siddiqui</name></author><author><name>Kathryn Hjerrild</name></author><author><name>Tess R. Malcolm</name></author><author><name>Natalie B. Vinh</name></author><author><name>Chaille T. Webb</name></author><author><name>Christopher A. MacRaild</name></author><author><name>Natalie A. Counihan</name></author><author><name>Darren J. Creek</name></author><author><name>Peter J Scammells</name></author><author><name>Sheena McGowan</name></author><author><name>Tania F. de Koning-Ward</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium falciparum,&lt;/italic&gt; a causative agent of malaria, continues to remain a global health threat since these parasites have developed increasing resistance to all anti-malaria drugs used throughout the world. Accordingly, drugs with novel modes of action are desperately required to combat malaria. &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; parasites infect human red blood cells where they digest the hosts main protein constituent, hemoglobin. Leucine aminopeptidase &lt;italic&gt;Pf&lt;/italic&gt;A-M17 is one of several aminopeptidases that have been implicated in the last step of this digestive pathway. Here we utilize both reverse genetics and a compound specifically designed to inhibit the activity of &lt;italic&gt;Pf&lt;/italic&gt;A-M17 to show that &lt;italic&gt;Pf&lt;/italic&gt;A-M17 is essential for &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; survival as it provides parasites with free amino acids for growth, many of which are highly likely to originate from hemoglobin. We further show that our inhibitor is on-target for &lt;italic&gt;Pf&lt;/italic&gt;A-M17 and has the ability to kill parasites at nanomolar concentrations. Thus, in contrast to other hemoglobin-degrading proteases that have overlapping redundant functions, we validate &lt;italic&gt;Pf&lt;/italic&gt;A-M17 as a potential novel drug target.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469631" rel="alternate" title="Genetic and chemical validation of Plasmodium falciparum aminopeptidase PfA-M17 as a drug target in the hemoglobin digestion pathway (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470254</id><title>Metabolic analysis of a bacterial synthetic community from maize roots provides new mechanistic insights into microbiome stability (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.281053+00:00</updated><author><name>Jenna Krumbach</name></author><author><name>Patrizia Kroll</name></author><author><name>Vera Wewer</name></author><author><name>Sabine Metzger</name></author><author><name>Till Ischebeck</name></author><author><name>Richard P Jacoby</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Stability is a desirable property for agricultural microbiomes, but there is a poor understanding of the mechanisms that mediate microbial community stability. Recently, a representative bacterial synthetic community from maize roots has been proposed as a model system to study microbiome stability (Niu 2017, PNAS, 114:E2450). This SynCom assembles stably when all seven members are present, but community diversity collapses without the keystone E. cloacae strain. The aim of this study was to assess the role of metabolites for the stability of this SynCom, by defining the metabolic niches occupied by each strain, as well as their cross-feeding phenotypes and B-vitamin dependencies. We show that the individual member strains occupy complementary metabolic niches, measured by the depletion of distinct metabolites in exometabolomic experiments, as well as contrasting growth phenotypes on diverse carbon substrates. Minimal medium experiments show that the established seven-member community comprises a mixture of prototrophic and auxotrophic strains. Correspondingly, experimental cross-feeding phenotypes showed that spent media harvested from the prototrophic strains can sustain growth of two auxotrophs. We suggest that the metabolic mechanisms exhibited by this SynCom could serve as design principles to inform the rational assembly of stable plant-associated microbial communities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470254" rel="alternate" title="Metabolic analysis of a bacterial synthetic community from maize roots provides new mechanistic insights into microbiome stability (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469798</id><title>Microbial consortiums of putative degraders of low-density polyethylene-associated compounds in the ocean (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.281431+00:00</updated><author><name>Maria Pinto</name></author><author><name>Zihao Zhao</name></author><author><name>Katja Klun</name></author><author><name>Eugen Libowitzky</name></author><author><name>Gerhard J Herndl</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Polyethylene (PE) is one of the most abundant plastics in the ocean. The development of a biofilm on PE in the ocean has been reported, yet whether some of the biofilm-forming organisms can biodegrade this plastic in the environment remains unknown. Via metagenomics analysis, we taxonomically and functionally analysed three biofilm communities using low-density polyethylene (LDPE) as their sole carbon source for two years. Several of the taxa that increased in relative abundance over time were closely related to known degraders of alkane and other hydrocarbons. Alkane degradation has been proposed to be involved in PE degradation, and most of the organisms increasing in relative abundance over time harboured genes encoding proteins essential in alkane degradation, such as the genes alkB and CYP153, encoding an alkane monooxygenase and a cytochrome P450 alkane hydroxylase. Weight loss of PE sheets when incubated with these communities and chemical and electron microscopic analyses provided evidence for alteration of the PE surface over time. Taken together, these results provide evidence for the utilization of LDPE-associated compounds by the prokaryotic communities. This study identifies a group of genes potentially involved in the degradation of the LDPE polymeric structure and/or associated plastic additives in the ocean and describes a phylogenetically diverse community of plastic biofilm-dwelling microbes with the potential of utilizing LDPE-associated compounds as carbon and energy source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Low-density polyethylene (LDPE) is one of the most used plastics worldwide and a large portion of it ends up in the ocean. Very little is known about its fate in the ocean and whether it can be biodegraded by microorganisms. By combining 2-year incubations with metagenomics, respiration measurements and LDPE surface analysis, we identified bacteria and associated genes and metabolic pathways potentially involved in LDPE biodegradation. After two years of incubation, two of the microbial communities exhibited a very similar taxonomic composition mediating changes to the LDPE pieces they were incubated with. We provide evidence that there are plastic-biofilm dwelling bacteria in the ocean, that might have the potential to degrade LDPE-associated compounds, and that alkane degradation pathways might be involved.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469798" rel="alternate" title="Microbial consortiums of putative degraders of low-density polyethylene-associated compounds in the ocean (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469750</id><title>Treatment of infection-induced vascular pathologies is protective against persistent rough morphotype Mycobacterium abscessus infection in zebrafish (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.281689+00:00</updated><author><name>Julia Y Kam</name></author><author><name>Kathryn Wright</name></author><author><name>Warwick J Britton</name></author><author><name>Stefan H Oehlers</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; infections are of increasing global prevalence and are often difficult to treat due to complex antibiotic resistance profiles. While there are similarities between the pathogenesis of &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; and tuberculous mycobacteria, including granuloma formation and stromal remodeling, there are distinct molecular differences at the host-pathogen interface. Here we have used a zebrafish-&lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; model and host-directed therapies that were previously identified in the zebrafish-&lt;italic&gt;M. marinum&lt;/italic&gt; model to identify potential host-directed therapies against &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; infection. We find efficacy of anti-angiogenic and vascular normalizing therapies against rough &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; infection, but no effect of anti-platelet drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469750" rel="alternate" title="Treatment of infection-induced vascular pathologies is protective against persistent rough morphotype Mycobacterium abscessus infection in zebrafish (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469858</id><title>High diversity in the regulatory region of Stx-converting bacteriophage genomes (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.281836+00:00</updated><author><name>Annette Fagerlund</name></author><author><name>Marina Aspholm</name></author><author><name>Grzegorz Węgrzyn</name></author><author><name>Toril Lindbäck</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Shiga toxin (Stx) is the major virulence factor of enterohemorrhagic &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; (EHEC), and the &lt;italic&gt;stx&lt;/italic&gt; genes are carried by temperate bacteriophages (Stx phages). The switch between lysogenic and lytic life cycle of the phage, which is crucial for Stx production and for severity of the disease, is regulated by the CI repressor. CI maintain latency by preventing transcription of the replication proteins. Three &lt;underline&gt;E&lt;/underline&gt;HEC phage &lt;underline&gt;r&lt;/underline&gt;eplication &lt;underline&gt;u&lt;/underline&gt;nits (Eru1-3) in addition to the classical lambdoid replication region have been described previously, and Stx phages carrying the Eru1 replication region were associated with highly virulent EHEC strains. In this study, we have classified the Eru replication region of 419 Stx phages. In addition to the lambdoid replication region and the three already described Erus, ten novel Erus (named Eru4 to Eru13) were detected. The lambdoid type, Eru1, Eru4 and Eru7 seem to be widely distributed in Western Europe. Notably, EHEC strains involved in severe outbreaks in England and Norway carry Stx phages with Eru1, Eru2, Eru5 and Eru7 replication regions. Phylogenetic analysis of CI repressors from Stx phages revealed eight major clades that largely separate according to Eru type. The classification of replication regions and CI proteins of Stx phages provides an important platform for further studies aimed to assess how characteristics of the replication region influence the regulation of phage life cycle and, consequently, the virulence potential of the host EHEC strain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;EHEC is an emerging health challenge worldwide and outbreaks caused by this pathogen tend to be more frequent and severe. Increased knowledge on how characteristics of the replication region influence the virulence of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; may be used for more precise identification of high-risk EHEC strains.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469858" rel="alternate" title="High diversity in the regulatory region of Stx-converting bacteriophage genomes (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470138</id><title>Noise in a metabolic pathway leads to persister formation in Mycobacterium tuberculosis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.281974+00:00</updated><author><name>Jeffrey Quigley</name></author><author><name>Kim Lewis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tuberculosis is difficult to treat due to dormant cells in hypoxic granulomas, and stochastically-formed persisters tolerant of antibiotics. Bactericidal antibiotics kill by corrupting their energy-dependent targets. We reasoned that noise in the expression of an energy-generating component will produce rare persister cells. In sorted low ATP &lt;italic&gt;M. tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; grown on acetate there is considerable cell-to-cell variation in the level of mRNA coding for AckA, the acetate kinase. Quenching the noise by overexpressing ackA sharply decreases persisters, showing that it acts as the main persister gene under these conditions. This demonstrates that a low energy mechanism is responsible for the formation of &lt;italic&gt;M. tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; persisters and suggests that the mechanism of their antibiotic tolerance is similar to that of dormant cells in a granuloma. Entrance into a low energy state driven by stochastic variation in expression of energy-producing enzymes is likely a general mechanism by which bacteria produce persisters.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470138" rel="alternate" title="Noise in a metabolic pathway leads to persister formation in Mycobacterium tuberculosis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469156</id><title>Simultaneous assessment of eight phosphorylated STAT residues in T-cells by flow cytometry. (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.282097+00:00</updated><author><name>Emily Monk</name></author><author><name>Melinda Vassallo</name></author><author><name>Paulo Burke</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey Weber</name></author><author><name>Pratip Chattopadhyay</name></author><author><name>David Woods</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Signal transducer and activator of transcription (STAT) proteins are a family of transcription factors controlling functions in immune responses and other cell types. Given their importance, we developed a flow cytometry panel to assess eight phosphorylated STAT residues in human T-cells, including six tyrosine residues across six STAT proteins (STAT1, STAT2, STAT3, STAT4, STAT5a, STAT6) and additional serine residues on STAT1 and STAT3. We applied this protocol to test the in vitro induction of pSTATs in response to CD3/CD28 activation and a panel of recombinant cytokines. We also assessed the pSTAT expression profiles of naive CD4+ T-cells polarized to Th1, Th2, Th17 or iTregs.  pSTAT1(S727), pSTAT2(Y689) and pSTAT3(S727) were constitutively expressed in most T-cells, even in the absence of stimulation. For pSTAT1(S727) and pSTAT3(S727), we observed two positive states, high and low. Conversely, expression of pSTAT1(Y701), pSTAT3(Y705), pSTAT4(Y693) and pSTAT6(Y641) were absent in resting T-cells and only expressed with CD3/CD28 activation or with specific cytokines. Variable frequencies of pSTAT5a(Y694) expression were observed in resting T-cells, which increased with activation or specific cytokine stimulation (e.g. IL-2). IFN-beta stimulation enhanced frequencies of expressing cells for all pSTATs. Correlations among several pSTATs, particularly pSTAT1(S727)high and pSTAT3(S727)high were observed. While polarization resulted in increases in canonically associated pSTATs, other non-canonical pSTAT changes were also observed. Collectively, we developed, optimized, and tested a sensitive and rapid approach for simultaneously assessing phosphorylation of six STAT proteins. Using this approach, we made several novel observations of T-cell pSTAT induction in response to stimuli.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469156" rel="alternate" title="Simultaneous assessment of eight phosphorylated STAT residues in T-cells by flow cytometry. (5 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469532</id><title>Evaluation of new polymer-iodine complexes for the fabrication of medical devices (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.282608+00:00</updated><author><name>Marina López-Álvarez</name></author><author><name>Herb Ulmer</name></author><author><name>Nico Klay</name></author><author><name>Jan Maarten van Dijl</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Povidone-iodine has been a true success story in the fight against infections by harnessing the antimicrobial and antiviral properties of elemental iodine for water-based applications. However, to date there has been little success in implementing iodine attributes in water-insoluble engineering plastics. Here, we describe the first development of biocidal active polyamide- and polyurethane-iodine complexes at laboratory and commercially relevant scales. These polymer-iodine materials are active against a broad range of microorganisms, including bacteria, yeast and fungi, and can be used as base materials for medical devices. The use of new polymer-iodine complexes for infection prevention in medical devices, such as sutures, catheters and drains, or wound care is expected to have significant positive effects at reducing healthcare-acquired infections. In addition, the materials are expected to find significant applications in other fields, such as air handling with the production of biocidal face masks and air filters to control spread of pathogens.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469532" rel="alternate" title="Evaluation of new polymer-iodine complexes for the fabrication of medical devices (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469799</id><title>Prevalence and correlates of phenazine resistance in culturable bacteria from a dryland wheat field (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.282917+00:00</updated><author><name>Elena K. Perry</name></author><author><name>Dianne K. Newman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Phenazines are a class of bacterially-produced redox-active natural antibiotics that have demonstrated potential as a sustainable alternative to traditional pesticides for the biocontrol of fungal crop diseases. However, the prevalence of bacterial resistance to agriculturally-relevant phenazines is poorly understood, limiting both the understanding of how these molecules might shape rhizosphere bacterial communities and the ability to perform risk assessment for off-target effects. Here, we describe profiles of susceptibility to the antifungal agent phenazine-1-carboxylic acid (PCA) across more than 100 bacterial strains isolated from a wheat field where PCA producers are indigenous and abundant. We find that Gram-positive bacteria are typically more sensitive to PCA than Gram-negative bacteria, but that there is also significant variability in susceptibility both within and across phyla. Phenazine-resistant strains are more likely to be isolated from the wheat rhizosphere, where PCA producers are also more abundant, compared to bulk soil. Furthermore, PCA toxicity is pH-dependent for most susceptible strains and broadly correlates with PCA reduction rates, suggesting that uptake and redox-cycling are important determinants of phenazine toxicity. Our results shed light on which classes of bacteria are most likely to be susceptible to phenazine toxicity in acidic or neutral soils. In addition, the taxonomic and phenotypic diversity of our strain collection represents a valuable resource for future studies on the role of natural antibiotics in shaping wheat rhizosphere communities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Microbial communities contribute to crop health in important ways. For example, phenazine metabolites are a class of redox-active molecules made by diverse soil bacteria that underpin the biocontrol of wheat and other crops. Their physiological functions are nuanced: in some contexts they are toxic, in others, beneficial. While much is known about phenazine production and the effect of phenazines on producing strains, our ability to predict how phenazines might shape the composition of environmental microbial communities is poorly constrained; that phenazine prevalence in the rhizosphere is predicted to increase in arid soils as the climate changes provides an impetus for further study. As a step towards gaining a predictive understanding of phenazine-linked microbial ecology, we document the effects of phenazines on diverse bacteria that were co-isolated from a wheat rhizosphere and identify conditions and phenotypes that correlate with how a strain will respond to phenazines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469799" rel="alternate" title="Prevalence and correlates of phenazine resistance in culturable bacteria from a dryland wheat field (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470168</id><title>More than meets the Kappa for Antibody Superantigen Protein L (PpL) (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.283147+00:00</updated><author><name>Wei Li Ling</name></author><author><name>Joshua Yi Yeo</name></author><author><name>Yuen Ling Ng</name></author><author><name>Anil Wipat</name></author><author><name>Samuel KE Gan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Immunoglobulin superantigens play an important role in the affinity purification of antibodies and underlie the microbiota-immune axis at mucosal areas Focussing on the Staphylococcal Protein A (SpA), Streptococcal Protein G (SpG), and the Finegoldia Protein L (PpL) that were previously thought to bind to only specific regions of human antibodies, a systematic and holistic analysis of the antibody regions using 63 antibody permutations involving six Vκ and seven VH region IgG1 revealed showed novel PpL-antibody interactions. While SpA and SpG showed relatively consistent interactions with the antibodies, our findings showed PpL binding to certain VH-Vκ2, 5 and 6 interactions had contribution by other antibody regions. The findings of this have implications on PpL-based affinity antibody purifications and antibody design as well as provides novel insights to PpL-based microbiota-immune axis effects.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470168" rel="alternate" title="More than meets the Kappa for Antibody Superantigen Protein L (PpL) (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470074</id><title>Comparative analysis of Mycobacterium abscessus clinical isolate virulence using an invertebrate infection model (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.283295+00:00</updated><author><name>Yasuhiko Matsumoto</name></author><author><name>Hanako Fukano</name></author><author><name>Naoki Hasegawa</name></author><author><name>Yoshihiko Hoshino</name></author><author><name>Takashi Sugita</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aims: &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; causes chronic skin infections, lung diseases, and systemic or disseminated infections. We investigated the quantitative evaluation of the virulence of &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; clinical isolates by calculating the LD50 using a silkworm infection model. Methods and Results: &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; subsp. &lt;italic&gt;abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; cells were injected into the hemolymph of silkworms. Silkworms died within two days post-infection with &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; subsp. &lt;italic&gt;abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; when reared at 37˚C. Viable cell numbers of &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; subsp. &lt;italic&gt;abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; increased in the hemolymph of the silkworms injected with &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; subsp. &lt;italic&gt;abscessus&lt;/italic&gt;. Silkworms were not killed following injections with heat-killed &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; subsp. &lt;italic&gt;abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; cells. The administration of clarithromycin, an antibacterial drug used for the treatment of the infection, prolonged the survival time of silkworms injected with &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; subsp. &lt;italic&gt;abscessus&lt;/italic&gt;. The LD50 values of seven clinical isolates were determined using the silkworm infection model and differed by up to nine-fold.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470074" rel="alternate" title="Comparative analysis of Mycobacterium abscessus clinical isolate virulence using an invertebrate infection model (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470275</id><title>DUAL FUNCTION OF ZIKA VIRUS NS2B-NS3 PROTEASE (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.283429+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexey Terskikh</name></author><author><name>Sergey Shiryaev</name></author><author><name>Anton Cheltsov</name></author><author><name>Robert C Liddington</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Zika virus (ZIKV) serine protease, indispensable for viral polyprotein processing and replication, is composed of an NS2B polypeptide that associates with a proteolytic N terminal fragment of NS3 polypeptide (NS3pro) to form NS2B-NS3pro. The larger C-terminal fragment of NS3 polypeptide contains helicase activity. In the present study, we discovered that ZIKV NS2BNS3pro efficiently binds single-stranded (ss) RNA (Kd ~0.3 uM), suggesting that the protease may have a novel function. We tested an array of NS2B-NS3pro modifications and found that NS2B NS3pro constructs that adopt the recently discovered super-open conformation could not bind ssRNA. Likewise, stabilization of NS2B-NS3pro in the closed (proteolytically active) conformation by substrate-like inhibitors abolished ssRNA binding. Therefore, we suggest that ssRNA binding occurs when ZIKV protease adopts the open conformation, which could be modeled using dengue NS2B-NS3pro in the open conformation. ssRNA binding competes with ZIKV NS2B-NS3pro protease activity, likely by shifting the complex into the open conformation. Modeling of ZIKV NS3 helicase activity based on homologous crystal structures suggests that the open conformation of NS3pro domains provides a positively charged surface contiguous with the NS3 helicase domain. Such a positively charged surface is well poised to bind ssRNA, providing an explanation for the previously observed requirement of NS3pro for RNA processivity by viral helicase. Our structure-function analyses suggest that binding of ssRNA by the protease domain of NS3 is likely to be a universal feature of Flaviviridae, given the high level of homology between NS3 protease-helicase proteins in this family.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470275" rel="alternate" title="DUAL FUNCTION OF ZIKA VIRUS NS2B-NS3 PROTEASE (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470012</id><title>Patients with recurrent PVL+-Staphylococcus aureus infections show enhanced sensitivity to PVL-mediated formation of atypical NETs (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.283558+00:00</updated><author><name>Hina Jhelum</name></author><author><name>Dora Čerina</name></author><author><name>Christopher J Harbort</name></author><author><name>Andreas Lindner</name></author><author><name>Leif Gunnar Hanitsch</name></author><author><name>Rasmus Leistner</name></author><author><name>Jennyver-Tabea Schröder</name></author><author><name>Horst von Bernuth</name></author><author><name>Miriam Songa Stegemann</name></author><author><name>Mariana Schürmann</name></author><author><name>Arturo Zychlinsky</name></author><author><name>Renate Krüger</name></author><author><name>Gerben Marsman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Panton-Valentine leukocidin (PVL) is a Staphylococcus aureus (S. aureus) toxin that binds to and kills human neutrophils, resulting in the formation of neutrophil extracellular traps (NETs). Some individuals colonized with PVL-positive S. aureus (PVL-SA) suffer from recurring infections whereas others are asymptomatically colonized. We found that neutrophils from affected patients express higher levels of CD45, one of the PVL receptors, and are more susceptible to killing at a low concentration of recombinant PVL than control neutrophils. We verified that PVL induces the formation of NETs and provide genetic and pharmacological evidence that PVL-induced NET formation is independent of NADPH-oxidase and reactive oxygen species (ROS) production. Through NET proteome analysis we identified that the protein content of PVL-induced NETs is different from NETs induced by mitogen or the microbial toxin nigericin. The abundance of the proteins cathelicidin (CAMP), elastase (NE), and proteinase 3 (PRTN3) was lower on PVL-induced NETs, which were inefficient in killing S. aureus. Neutrophils from patients that suffer from recurring PVL-positive infections may be more sensitive to PVL-induced NET formation, which may impair their ability to combat the infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470012" rel="alternate" title="Patients with recurrent PVL+-Staphylococcus aureus infections show enhanced sensitivity to PVL-mediated formation of atypical NETs (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.470057</id><title>Experimental Investigation Of Pulse Sterilization Of Pathogens (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.283862+00:00</updated><author><name>Volodymyr I Chumakov</name></author><author><name>Mykhailo Ostryzhnyi</name></author><author><name>Oksana Kharchenko</name></author><author><name>Nataliya Rybalchenko</name></author><author><name>Vasiliy Muraveinyk</name></author><author><name>Aleksandr Tarasevich</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The results of experimental investigations of the effect of high-intensity pulsed UV radiation on reference strains of opportunistic pathogens S, aureus and E. coli are presented. The modified pulse UV sterilizer МПК-300-3 based on an end-face plasma accelerator was used as a radiation source, which provides a power pulsed discharge in an open atmosphere. The high efficiency of inactivation of the pathogens was provided within a short period of time. The possibility of providing urgent 100% sterilization of a pathogens has been shown. The prospects for the application of pulse sterilization technology to combat pathogens are considered.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.470057" rel="alternate" title="Experimental Investigation Of Pulse Sterilization Of Pathogens (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469700</id><title>Zika virus-specific IgM elicited during pregnancy exhibits ultrapotent neutralization (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.284014+00:00</updated><author><name>Tulika Singh</name></author><author><name>Kwan-Ki Hwang</name></author><author><name>Andrew S. Miller</name></author><author><name>Rebecca L. Jones</name></author><author><name>Cesar A. Lopez</name></author><author><name>Camila Giuberti</name></author><author><name>Morgan A. Gladden</name></author><author><name>Itzayana Miller</name></author><author><name>Helen S. Webster</name></author><author><name>Joshua A. Eudailey</name></author><author><name>Kan Luo</name></author><author><name>Tarra Von Holle</name></author><author><name>Robert J. Edwards</name></author><author><name>Sarah Valencia</name></author><author><name>Katherine E. Burgomaster</name></author><author><name>Summer Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jesse F. Mangold</name></author><author><name>Joshua J. Tu</name></author><author><name>Maria Dennis</name></author><author><name>S. Munir Alam</name></author><author><name>Lakshmanane Premkumar</name></author><author><name>Reynaldo Dietze</name></author><author><name>Theodore C. Pierson</name></author><author><name>Eng Eong Ooi</name></author><author><name>Helen M. Lazear</name></author><author><name>Richard J. Kuhn</name></author><author><name>Sallie R. Permar</name></author><author><name>Mattia Bonsignori</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Congenital Zika virus (ZIKV) infection results in neurodevelopmental deficits in up to 14% of infants born to ZIKV-infected mothers. Neutralizing antibodies are a critical component of protective immunity. Here, we demonstrate that plasma IgM responses contribute to ZIKV immunity in pregnancy, mediating neutralization up to three months post symptoms. From a ZIKV-infected pregnant woman, we established a B cell line secreting a pentameric ZIKV-specific IgM (DH1017.IgM) that exhibited ultrapotent ZIKV neutralization dependent on the IgM isotype. DH1017.IgM targets a novel envelope dimer epitope within Domain II. The arrangement of this epitope on the virion is compatible with concurrent engagement of all ten antigen-binding sites of DH1017.IgM, a solution not achievable by IgG antibodies. DH1017.IgM protected against lethal ZIKV challenge in mice. Our findings identify a unique role of antibodies of the IgM isotype in protection against ZIKV and posit DH1017.IgM as a safe and effective candidate immunoprophylactic, particularly during pregnancy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plasma IgM contributes to early ZIKV neutralization during pregnancy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ultrapotent neutralization by pentameric DH1017.IgM mAb depends on isotype&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;DH1017.IgM can engage all binding sites concurrently through different angles of approach&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;DH1017.IgM protects mice against lethal ZIKV challenge&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469700" rel="alternate" title="Zika virus-specific IgM elicited during pregnancy exhibits ultrapotent neutralization (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469644</id><title>Comparative analysis of Bacillus cereus group isolates’ resistance using disk diffusion and broth microdilution and the correlation between resistance phenotypes and genotypes (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.284278+00:00</updated><author><name>Emma Mills</name></author><author><name>Erin Sullivan</name></author><author><name>Jasna Kovac</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A collection of 85 &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus cereus&lt;/italic&gt; group isolates were screened for phenotypic resistance to nine antibiotics using disk diffusion and broth microdilution. The broth microdilution antimicrobial results were interpreted using the CLSI M45 breakpoints for &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus&lt;/italic&gt; spp. Due to the lack of &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus&lt;/italic&gt; spp. disk diffusion breakpoints, the results obtained with the disk diffusion assay were interpreted using the CLSI M100 breakpoints for &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus&lt;/italic&gt; spp. We identified significant (p &amp;lt; 0.05) discrepancies in resistance interpretation between the two methods for ampicillin, gentamicin, rifampicin, tetracycline, and trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole. Antimicrobial resistance genes were detected using unassembled and assembled whole-genome sequences with Ariba and Abricate, respectively, to assess the sensitivity and specificity for predicting phenotypic resistance based on the presence of antimicrobial resistance genes. We found antimicrobial resistance gene presence to be a poor indicator for phenotypic resistance, calling for further investigation of mechanisms underlying antimicrobial resistance in the &lt;italic&gt;B. cereus&lt;/italic&gt; group. Genes with poor sensitivity and/or specificity, as determined based on broth microdilution results included &lt;italic&gt;rph&lt;/italic&gt; (rifampicin, 0%, 95%), &lt;italic&gt;mph&lt;/italic&gt; genes (erythromycin, 0%, 96%), and all &lt;italic&gt;van&lt;/italic&gt; genes (vancomycin, 100%, 35%). However, &lt;italic&gt;Bc&lt;/italic&gt; (ampicillin, 64%, 100%) and &lt;italic&gt;tet&lt;/italic&gt; genes (tetracycline, 67%, 100%) were highly specific, albeit moderately sensitive indicators of phenotypic resistance based on broth microdilution results. Only beta-lactam resistance genes (&lt;italic&gt;Bc, BcII&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;blaTEM&lt;/italic&gt;) were highly sensitive (94%) and specific (100%) markers of resistance to ceftriaxone based on the disk diffusion results, providing further evidence of these beta-lactams’ role in nonsusceptibility of &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus cereus&lt;/italic&gt; group isolates to ceftriaxone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Bacillus cereus&lt;/italic&gt; group includes human pathogens that can cause severe infections requiring antibiotic treatment. Screening of environmental and food isolates for antimicrobial resistance can provide insight into what antibiotics may be more effective therapeutic options based on the lower prevalence of resistance. Currently, interpretation of antimicrobial susceptibility testing results using the disk diffusion method is complicated by the fact that there are no standard disk diffusion resistance breakpoints defined for &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus&lt;/italic&gt; spp. Hence, the breakpoints for &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus&lt;/italic&gt; are often used in research studies. By comparing the results of disk diffusion interpreted using the &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus&lt;/italic&gt; spp. breakpoints against broth microdilution interpreted using &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus&lt;/italic&gt; spp. breakpoints, this study demonstrated that disk diffusion results interpretation with &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus&lt;/italic&gt; spp. breakpoints are inconsistent. This study also provides new insight into the poor associations between antimicrobial resistance genotypes and phenotypes for the &lt;italic&gt;B. cereus&lt;/italic&gt; group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469644" rel="alternate" title="Comparative analysis of Bacillus cereus group isolates’ resistance using disk diffusion and broth microdilution and the correlation between resistance phenotypes and genotypes (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469643</id><title>Spatial metabolomics reveals localized impact of influenza virus infection on the lung tissue metabolome (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.284404+00:00</updated><author><name>Danya A. Dean</name></author><author><name>London Klechka</name></author><author><name>Ekram Hossain</name></author><author><name>Adwaita R. Parab</name></author><author><name>Krystin Eaton</name></author><author><name>Myron Hinsdale</name></author><author><name>Laura-Isobel McCall</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The influenza virus (IAV) is a major cause of respiratory disease, with significant infection increases in pandemic years. Vaccines are a mainstay of IAV prevention, but are complicated by consideration of IAV’s vast strain diversity, manufacturing and vaccine uptake limitations. While antivirals may be used for treatment of IAV, they are most effective in early stages of the infection and several virus strains have become drug resistant. Therefore, there is a need for advances in IAV treatment, especially host-directed, personalized therapeutics.Given the spatial dynamics of IAV infection and the relationship between viral spatial distribution and disease severity, a spatial approach is necessary to expand our understanding of IAV pathogenesis. We used spatial metabolomics to address this issue. Spatial metabolomics combines liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry of metabolites extracted from systematic organ sections, 3D models and computational techniques, to develop spatial models of metabolite location and their role in organ function and disease pathogenesis. In this project, we analyzed plasma and systematically sectioned lung tissue samples from uninfected or infected mice. Spatial mapping of sites of metabolic perturbations revealed significantly lower metabolic perturbation in the trachea compared to other lung tissue sites. Using random forest machine learning, we identified metabolites that responded differently in each lung position based on infection, including specific amino acids, lipids and lipid-like molecules, and nucleosides. These results support the implementation of spatial metabolomics to understand metabolic changes upon IAV infection and to identify candidate pathways to be targeted for IAV therapeutics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The influenza virus is a major health concern. Over 1 billion people become infected annually despite the wide distribution of vaccines, and antiviral agents are insufficient to address current clinical needs. In this study, we used spatial metabolomics to understand changes in the lung and plasma metabolome of mice infected with influenza A virus, compared to uninfected controls. We determined metabolites altered by infection in specific lung tissue sites and distinguished metabolites perturbed by infection between lung tissue and plasma samples. Our findings highlight the importance of a spatial approach to understanding the intersection between lung metabolome, viral infection and disease severity. Ultimately, this approach will expand our understanding of respiratory disease pathogenesis and guide the development of novel host-directed therapeutics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469643" rel="alternate" title="Spatial metabolomics reveals localized impact of influenza virus infection on the lung tissue metabolome (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469634</id><title>Discovering Novel Antimicrobial Peptides in Generative Adversarial Network (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.284544+00:00</updated><author><name>Tzu-Tang Lin</name></author><author><name>Li-Yen Yang</name></author><author><name>Ching-Tien Wang</name></author><author><name>Ga-Wen Lai</name></author><author><name>Chi-Fong Ko</name></author><author><name>Yang-Hsin Shih</name></author><author><name>Shu-Hwa Chen</name></author><author><name>Chung-Yen Lin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Due to the growing number of clinical antibiotic resistance cases in recent years, novel antimicrobial peptides (AMPs) can become ideal for next-generation antibiotics. This study trained a deep convolutional generative adversarial network (GAN) with known AMPs to generate novel AMP candidates. The quality of the GAN-designed peptides was evaluated &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt;, and eight of them named GAN-pep 1∼8 were chosen to be synthesized for further experiments. Disk diffusion testing and minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) determination were used to determine the antibacterial effects of the synthesized GAN-designed peptides. Seven out of the eight synthesized GAN-designed peptides showed antibacterial activities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, GAN-pep 3 and GAN-pep 8 had a broad spectrum of antibacterial effects. Both of them were also effective against antibiotic-resistant bacteria strains such as methicillin-resistant &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;S. aureus&lt;/italic&gt;) and carbapenem-resistant &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;P. aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt;). GAN-pep 3, the most promising GAN-designed peptide candidate, had low MICs against all the tested bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469634" rel="alternate" title="Discovering Novel Antimicrobial Peptides in Generative Adversarial Network (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469479</id><title>Early age-related atrophy of cutaneous lymph nodes precipitates an early functional decline in skin immunity in mice with aging (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.284738+00:00</updated><author><name>Sandip Ashok Sonar</name></author><author><name>Jennifer L. Uhrlaub</name></author><author><name>Christopher P. Coplen</name></author><author><name>Gregory D. Sempowski</name></author><author><name>Jarrod A. Dudakov</name></author><author><name>Marcel R.M. van den Brink</name></author><author><name>Bonnie J. LaFleur</name></author><author><name>Mladen Jergovic</name></author><author><name>Janko Nikolich-Žugich</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Secondary lymphoid organs (SLO; including the spleen and lymph nodes) are critical both for the maintenance of naïve T (T&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;) lymphocytes and for the initiation and coordination of immune responses. How they age, including the exact timing, extent, physiological relevance, and the nature of age-related changes, remains incompletely understood. We used time-stamping to indelibly mark cohorts of newly generated naïve T cells (a.k.a. recent thymic emigrants - RTE) in mice, and followed their presence, phenotype and retention in SLO. We found that SLO involute asynchronously. Skin-draining lymph nodes (LN) atrophied early (6-9 months) in life and deeper tissue-draining LN and the spleen late (18-20 months), as measured by the loss of both T&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt; numbers and the fibroblastic reticular cell (FRC) network. Time-stamped RTE cohorts of all ages entered SLO and successfully completed post-thymic differentiation. However, in older mice, these cells were poorly retained, and those found in SLO exhibited an emigration phenotype (CCR7&lt;sup&gt;lo&lt;/sup&gt;S1P1&lt;sup&gt;hi&lt;/sup&gt;). Transfers of adult RTE into recipients of different ages formally demonstrated that the defect segregates with the age of the SLO microenvironment and not with the age of T cells. Finally, upon intradermal immunization, RTE generated in mice as early as 6-7 months of age barely participated in &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; immune responses and failed to produce well-armed effector cells. These results highlight changes in structure and function of superficial secondary lymphoid organs in laboratory mice that are earlier than expected and are consistent with the long-appreciated and pronounced reduction of cutaneous immunity with aging.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469479" rel="alternate" title="Early age-related atrophy of cutaneous lymph nodes precipitates an early functional decline in skin immunity in mice with aging (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469664</id><title>Matrix-assisted laser desorption ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometry identification of methanogens of clinical interest (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.284965+00:00</updated><author><name>Cheick Oumar Guindo</name></author><author><name>Lynda Amir</name></author><author><name>Carine Couderc</name></author><author><name>Michel Drancourt</name></author><author><name>Ghiles Grine</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Methanogens, the archaea uniquely detoxifying fermentative hydrogen into methane in the digestive tract, are increasingly detected in pathology situations, rendering their rapid identification mandatory. We improved the experimental protocol to identify broth-cultured methanogens by matrix-assisted laser desorption time-of-flight mass spectrometry (MALDI- TOF-MS). A database incorporating 34 reference spectra derived from 16 methanogen reference strains representative of eight species, supported further identification of 21 &lt;italic&gt;Methanobrevibacter smithii&lt;/italic&gt; and 14 &lt;italic&gt;Methanobrevibacter oralis&lt;/italic&gt; isolates broth-cultured from human stool and oral fluid, respectively, with scores &amp;gt; 2. In addition, MALDI-TOF-MS differentiated five &lt;italic&gt;Methanobrevibacter smithii&lt;/italic&gt; genotypes incorporated in the study. Data here reported found MALDI-TOF-MS as a first line identification method for methanogens recovered from microbiota and clinical samples.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469664" rel="alternate" title="Matrix-assisted laser desorption ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometry identification of methanogens of clinical interest (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469781</id><title>Inhibition of infection-induced vascular permeability modulates host leukocyte recruitment to Mycobacterium marinum granulomas in zebrafish (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.285402+00:00</updated><author><name>Julia Y Kam</name></author><author><name>Tina Cheng</name></author><author><name>Danielle C Garland</name></author><author><name>Warwick J Britton</name></author><author><name>David M Tobin</name></author><author><name>Stefan H Oehlers</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mycobacterial granuloma formation involves significant stromal remodeling and the growth of leaky, granuloma-associated vasculature. These permeable blood vessels aid mycobacterial growth, as anti-angiogenic or vascular normalizing therapies are beneficial host-directed therapies in pre-clinical models of tuberculosis. Here we demonstrate that vascular normalization through vascular endothelial-protein tyrosine phosphatase inhibition decreases granuloma hypoxia, the opposite effect of hypoxia-inducing anti-angiogenic therapy. Vascular normalization leads to increased T cell and decreased neutrophil recruitment to granulomas, correlates of a protective immune response against mycobacterial infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469781" rel="alternate" title="Inhibition of infection-induced vascular permeability modulates host leukocyte recruitment to Mycobacterium marinum granulomas in zebrafish (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>