<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.596917+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.12.448192</id><title>Harnessing methylotrophs as a bacterial platform to reduce adverse effects of the use of the heavy lanthanide gadolinium in magnetic resonance imaging (40 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.597400+00:00</updated><author><name>Nathan Michael Good</name></author><author><name>Harvey Lee</name></author><author><name>Emily R Hawker</name></author><author><name>Assaf Gilad</name></author><author><name>Norma Cecilia Martinez-Gomez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gadolinium is a key component of magnetic resonance imaging contrast agents that are critical tools for enhanced detection and diagnosis of tissue and vascular abnormalities. Untargeted post-injection deposition of gadolinium &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, and association with diseases like nephrogenic systemic fibrosis, has alerted regulatory agencies to re-evaluate their widespread use and generated calls for safer gadolinium-based contrast agents (GBCAs). Increasing anthropogenic gadolinium in surface water has also raised concerns of potential bioaccumulation in plants and animals. Methylotrophic bacteria can acquire, transport, store and use light lanthanides as part of a cofactor complex with pyrroloquinoline quinone (PQQ), an essential component of XoxF-type methanol dehydrogenases (MDHs), a critical enzyme for methylotrophic growth with methanol. We report robust gadolinium-dependent methanol growth of a genetic variant of &lt;italic&gt;Methylorubrum extorquens&lt;/italic&gt; AM1, named &lt;italic&gt;evo&lt;/italic&gt;-HLn, for evolved for heavy lanthanides. Genetic adaptation of &lt;italic&gt;evo&lt;/italic&gt;-HLn resulted in increased &lt;italic&gt;xox1&lt;/italic&gt; promoter and XoxF MDH activities, transport and storage of Gd&lt;sup&gt;3+&lt;/sup&gt;, and augmented biosynthesis of PQQ. Gadolinium-grown cells exhibited a shorter T1 relaxation time compared to cells with lanthanum or no lanthanide when analyzed by MRI. In addition, &lt;italic&gt;evo&lt;/italic&gt;-HLn was able to grow on methanol using the GBCA Gd-DTPA as the sole gadolinium source, showing the potential of this strain for the development of novel GBCAs and gadolinium recovery from medical waste and/or wastewater.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.12.448192" rel="alternate" title="Harnessing methylotrophs as a bacterial platform to reduce adverse effects of the use of the heavy lanthanide gadolinium in magnetic resonance imaging (40 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.11.448153</id><title>A panel of KSHV mutants in the polycistronic kaposin locus for precise analysis of individual protein products (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.597777+00:00</updated><author><name>Mariel Kleer</name></author><author><name>Grant MacNeil</name></author><author><name>Eric S. Pringle</name></author><author><name>Jennifer A. Corcoran</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus (KSHV) is the infectious cause of several human cancers including the endothelial cell (EC) malignancy, Kaposi's sarcoma. Unique KSHV genes absent from other human herpesvirus genomes, known as K-genes, are typically important for KSHV replication and pathogenesis. Among the K-genes, the kaposin mRNA is highly expressed in both latent and lytic phases of infection, but its polycistronic nature has hindered methodical analysis of the role of kaposin translation products in viral replication. At least three proteins are produced from the kaposin transcript, Kaposin A (KapA), B (KapB), and C (KapC). We have previously shown that KapB overexpression is sufficient to recapitulate two KS phenotypes, EC spindling and elevated proinflammatory cytokine transcripts, the latter which proceeds via the disassembly of RNA decay granules called processing bodies (PBs). To pinpoint the relative contributions of kaposin proteins at different stages of KSHV infection, we constructed four recombinant viruses by deleting or recoding the kaposin locus. Latent infection of iSLK cells with kaposin-deficient viruses resulted in reduced viral genome copy number and small LANA nuclear bodies; despite this, all iSLK cells were capable of progeny virion production. De novo infection of ECs revealed that KapB was dispensable for EC spindling but required for PB disassembly during KSHV latency, suggesting other viral proteins contribute to spindling. These findings demonstrate that our panel of viruses enables precise analysis of respective contributions of individual kaposin proteins to KSHV replication. This approach serves as a guide for the functional analysis of complex multicistronic viral loci.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.11.448153" rel="alternate" title="A panel of KSHV mutants in the polycistronic kaposin locus for precise analysis of individual protein products (13 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.08.447584</id><title>Leveraging host-genetics and gut microbiota to determine immunocompetence in pigs (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.598778+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuliaxis Ramayo-Caldas</name></author><author><name>Laura M. Zingaretti</name></author><author><name>David Pérez-Pascual</name></author><author><name>Pamela A. Alexandre</name></author><author><name>Antonio Reverter</name></author><author><name>Toni Dalmau</name></author><author><name>Raquel Quintanilla</name></author><author><name>Maria Ballester</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The aim of the present work was to identify microbial biomarkers linked to immunity traits and to characterize the contribution of host-genome and gut microbiota to the immunocompetence in healthy pigs. To achieve this goal, we undertook a combination of network, mixed model and microbial-wide association studies (MWAS) for 21 immunity traits and the relative abundance of gut bacterial communities in 389 pigs genotyped for 70K SNPs. The heritability (h&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;; proportion of phenotypic variance explained by the host genetics) and microbiability (m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;; proportion of variance explained by the microbial composition) showed similar values for most of the analyzed immunity traits, except for both IgM and IgG in plasma that were dominated by the host genetics, and the haptoglobin in serum which was the trait with larger m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; (0.275) compared to h&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; (0.138). Results from the MWAS suggested a polymicrobial nature of the immunocompetence in pigs and revealed associations between pigs gut microbiota composition and 15 of the analyzed traits. The lymphocytes phagocytic capacity (quantified as mean fluorescence) and the total number of monocytes in blood were the traits associated with the largest number of taxa (6 taxa). Among the associations identified by MWAS, 30% were confirmed by an information theory network approach. The strongest confirmed associations were between &lt;italic&gt;Fibrobacter&lt;/italic&gt; and phagocytic capacity of lymphocytes (r=0.37), followed by correlations between &lt;italic&gt;Streptococcus&lt;/italic&gt; and the percentage of phagocytic lymphocytes (r=-0.34) and between &lt;italic&gt;Megasphaera&lt;/italic&gt; and serum concentration of haptoglobin (r=0.26). In the interaction network, &lt;italic&gt;Streptococcus&lt;/italic&gt; and percentage of phagocytic lymphocytes were the keystone bacterial and immune-trait, respectively. Overall, our findings reveal an important connection between immunity traits and gut microbiota in pigs and highlight the need to consider both sources of information, host genome and microbial levels, to accurately characterize immunocompetence in pigs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.08.447584" rel="alternate" title="Leveraging host-genetics and gut microbiota to determine immunocompetence in pigs (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>