<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>BioRxiv preprints in microbiology posted in the last week with at least 5 tweets</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.428317+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.02.442311</id><title>Vibrio cholerae biofilm dispersal regulator causes cell release from matrix through type IV pilus retraction (53 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.430464+00:00</updated><author><name>Praveen K. Singh</name></author><author><name>Daniel K.H. Rode</name></author><author><name>Pauline Buffard</name></author><author><name>Kazuki Nosho</name></author><author><name>Miriam Bayer</name></author><author><name>Hannah Jeckel</name></author><author><name>Eric Jelli</name></author><author><name>Konstantin Neuhaus</name></author><author><name>Eva Jiménez-Siebert</name></author><author><name>Nikolai Peschek</name></author><author><name>Timo Glatter</name></author><author><name>Kai Papenfort</name></author><author><name>Knut Drescher</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The extracellular matrix is a defining feature of bacterial biofilms and provides structural stability to the community by binding cells to the surface and to each other. Transitions between bacterial biofilm initiation, growth, and dispersion require different regulatory programs, all of which result in modifications to the extracellular matrix composition, abundance, or functionality. However, the mechanisms by which individual cells in biofilms disengage from the matrix to enable their departure during biofilm dispersal are unclear. Here, we investigated active biofilm dispersal of &lt;italic&gt;Vibrio cholerae&lt;/italic&gt; during nutrient starvation, resulting in the discovery of the conserved &lt;italic&gt;Vibrio&lt;/italic&gt; biofilm dispersal regulator VbdR. We show that VbdR triggers biofilm dispersal by controlling cellular release from the biofilm matrix, which is achieved by inducing the retraction of the mannose-sensitive hemagglutinin (MSHA) type IV pili and the expression of a matrix protease IvaP. We further show that MSHA pili have numerous binding partners in the matrix and that the joint effect of MSHA pilus retraction and IvaP activity is necessary and sufficient for causing biofilm dispersal. These results highlight the crucial role of type IV pilus dynamics during biofilm dispersal and provide a new target for controlling &lt;italic&gt;V. cholerae&lt;/italic&gt; biofilm abundance through the induction and manipulation of biofilm dispersal.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.02.442312</id><title>Aminoglycoside antibiotics inhibit phage infection by blocking an early step of the phage infection cycle (133 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.429642+00:00</updated><author><name>Larissa Kever</name></author><author><name>Aël Hardy</name></author><author><name>Tom Luthe</name></author><author><name>Max Hünnefeld</name></author><author><name>Cornelia Gätgens</name></author><author><name>Lars Milke</name></author><author><name>Johanna Wiechert</name></author><author><name>Johannes Wittmann</name></author><author><name>Cristina Moraru</name></author><author><name>Jan Marienhagen</name></author><author><name>Julia Frunzke</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In response to viral predation, bacteria have evolved a wide range of defense mechanisms, which rely mostly on proteins acting at the cellular level. Here, we show that aminoglycosides, a well-known class of antibiotics produced by &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt;, are potent inhibitors of phage infection in widely divergent bacterial hosts. We demonstrate that aminoglycosides block an early step of the viral life cycle, prior to genome replication. Phage inhibition was also achieved using supernatants from natural aminoglycoside producers, hinting at a broad physiological significance of the antiviral properties of aminoglycosides. Strikingly, we show that acetylation of the aminoglycoside antibiotic apramycin abolishes its antibacterial effect, but retains its antiviral properties. Altogether, this study expands the knowledge of potential aminoglycoside functions in bacterial communities suggesting that aminoglycosides are not only used by their producers as toxic molecules against their bacterial competitors, but could also provide protection against the threat of phage predation at the community level.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>