<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.839157+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464035</id><title>Brain endothelial antigen presentation detains CD8+ T cells at the blood-brain barrier leading to its breakdown (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.839634+00:00</updated><author><name>Sidar Aydin</name></author><author><name>Javier Pareja</name></author><author><name>Vivianne M. Schallenberg</name></author><author><name>Armelle Klopstein</name></author><author><name>Thomas Gruber</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Page</name></author><author><name>Elisa Kaba</name></author><author><name>Urban Deutsch</name></author><author><name>Aaron J. Johnson</name></author><author><name>Mirjam Schenk</name></author><author><name>Doron Merkler</name></author><author><name>Britta Engelhardt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Blood-brain barrier (BBB) breakdown and immune cell infiltration into the central nervous system (CNS) are early hallmarks of multiple sclerosis (MS). High numbers of CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells are found in MS lesions and antigen (Ag)-presentation at the BBB was proposed to promote CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T-cell entry into the CNS. Employing live cell imaging and primary mouse brain microvascular endothelial cells (pMBMECs) as &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; model of the BBB and a mouse model of CNS autoimmunity, we here show that pMBMECs process and present antigens leading to effector CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T-cell differentiation. Under physiological flow, endothelial Ag-presentation prohibited CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T-cell crawling and diapedesis leading to pMBMEC apoptosis. Reduced motility of Ag-specific CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells was also observed in CNS microvessels in neuroinflammation &lt;italic&gt;in vivo.&lt;/italic&gt; Luminal MHC class I Ag-presentation at the BBB thus prohibits CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T-cell entry into the CNS and rather triggers CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cell mediated focal BBB breakdown.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464035" rel="alternate" title="Brain endothelial antigen presentation detains CD8+ T cells at the blood-brain barrier leading to its breakdown (26 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.11.463953</id><title>Coping with oxidative stress in extreme environments: the distinctive roles played by Acinetobacter sp. Ver3 superoxide dismutases (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.839928+00:00</updated><author><name>Bruno Alejandro Steimbrüch</name></author><author><name>Mariana G. Sartorio</name></author><author><name>Néstor Cortez</name></author><author><name>Daniela Albanesi</name></author><author><name>María-Natalia Lisa</name></author><author><name>Guillermo Daniel Repizo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Acinetobacter sp&lt;/italic&gt;. Ver3 is a polyextremophilic strain characterized by a high tolerance to radiation and pro-oxidants. The Ver3 genome comprises the &lt;italic&gt;sodB&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;sodC&lt;/italic&gt; genes encoding an iron (&lt;sup&gt;AV3&lt;/sup&gt;SodB) and a copper/zinc superoxide dismutase (&lt;sup&gt;AV3&lt;/sup&gt;SodC), respectively; however, the specific role(s) of these genes has remained elusive. We show that the expression of &lt;italic&gt;sodB&lt;/italic&gt; remained unaltered in different oxidative stress conditions whereas &lt;italic&gt;sodC&lt;/italic&gt; was up-regulated in the presence of blue light. Besides, we studied the changes in the in vitro activity of each SOD enzyme in response to diverse agents and solved the crystal structure of &lt;sup&gt;AV3&lt;/sup&gt;SodB at 1.34 Å, one of the highest resolutions achieved for a SOD. Cell fractionation studies interestingly revealed that &lt;sup&gt;AV3&lt;/sup&gt;SodB is located in the cytosol whereas &lt;sup&gt;AV3&lt;/sup&gt;SodC is also found in the periplasm. Consistently, a bioinformatic analysis of the genomes of 53 &lt;italic&gt;Acinetobacter&lt;/italic&gt; species pointed out the presence of at least one SOD type in each compartment, suggesting that these enzymes are separately required to cope with oxidative stress. Surprisingly, &lt;sup&gt;AV3&lt;/sup&gt;SodC was found in an active state also in outer membrane vesicles, probably exerting a protective role. Overall, our multidisciplinary approach highlights the relevance of SOD enzymes when &lt;italic&gt;Acinetobacter&lt;/italic&gt; spp. are confronted with oxidizing agents.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.11.463953" rel="alternate" title="Coping with oxidative stress in extreme environments: the distinctive roles played by Acinetobacter sp. Ver3 superoxide dismutases (22 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.10.463858</id><title>A curated collection of Klebsiella metabolic models reveals variable substrate usage and gene essentiality (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.840254+00:00</updated><author><name>Jane Hawkey</name></author><author><name>Ben Vezina</name></author><author><name>Jonathan M. Monk</name></author><author><name>Louise M. Judd</name></author><author><name>Taylor Harshegyi</name></author><author><name>Sebastián López-Fernández</name></author><author><name>Carla Rodrigues</name></author><author><name>Sylvain Brisse</name></author><author><name>Kathryn E. Holt</name></author><author><name>Kelly L. Wyres</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; species complex (KpSC) is a set of seven &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella&lt;/italic&gt; taxa which are found in a variety of niches, and are an important cause of opportunistic healthcare-associated infections in humans. Due to increasing rates of multi-drug resistance within the KpSC, there is a growing interest in better understanding the biology and metabolism of these organisms to inform novel control strategies. We collated 37 sequenced KpSC isolates isolated from a variety of niches, representing all seven taxa. We generated strain-specific genome scale metabolic models (GEMs) for all 37 isolates and simulated growth phenotypes on 511 distinct carbon, nitrogen, sulphur and phosphorus substrates. Models were curated and their accuracy assessed using matched phenotypic growth data for 94 substrates (median accuracy of 96%). We explored species-specific growth capabilities and examined the impact of all possible single gene deletions on growth in 145 core carbon substrates. These analyses revealed multiple strain-specific differences, within and between species and highlight the importance of selecting a diverse range of strains when exploring KpSC metabolism. This diverse set of highly accurate GEMs could be used to inform novel drug design, enhance genomic analyses, and identify novel virulence and resistance determinants. We envisage that these 37 curated strain-specific GEMs, covering all seven taxa of the KpSC, provide a valuable resource to the &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella&lt;/italic&gt; research community.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.10.463858" rel="alternate" title="A curated collection of Klebsiella metabolic models reveals variable substrate usage and gene essentiality (19 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464064</id><title>New from old: discovery of the novel antibiotic actinomycin L in Streptomyces sp. MBT27 (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.840730+00:00</updated><author><name>Nataliia Machushynets</name></author><author><name>Somayah S. Elsayed</name></author><author><name>Chao Du</name></author><author><name>Maxime A. Siegler</name></author><author><name>Mercedes de la Cruz</name></author><author><name>Olga Genilloud</name></author><author><name>Thomas Hankemeier</name></author><author><name>Gilles P. van Wezel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Streptomycetes are major producers of bioactive natural products, including the majority of the antibiotics. While much if the low-hanging fruit has been discovered, it is predited that less than 5% of the chemical space has been mined. Here, we describe the novel actinomycins L&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; and L&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, which are produced by &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt; sp. MBT27. The molecules were discovered via metabolic analysis combined with molecular networking of cultures grown with different combinations of carbon sources. Actinomycins L&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; and L&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; are diastereoisomers, and the structure of actinomycin L&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; was resolved using NMR and single crystal X-ray crystallography. Actinomycin L is formed via a unique spirolinkage of anthranilamide to the 4-oxoproline moiety of actinomycin X&lt;sub&gt;2,&lt;/sub&gt; prior to the condensation of the actinomycin halves. Feeding anthranilamide to cultures of &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces antibioticus&lt;/italic&gt;, which has the same biosynthetic gene cluster as &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt; sp. MBT27 but only produces actinomycin X&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, resulted in the production of actinomycin L. This shows that actinomycin L results from joining two distinct metabolic pathways, namely those for actinomycin X&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and for anthranilamide. Actinomycins L&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; and L&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; showed significant antimicrobial activity against Gram- positive bacteria. Our work shows how new molecules can still be identified even in the oldest of natural product families.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Actinomycin was the first antibiotic discovered in an actinobacterium by Selman Waksman and colleagues, as early as 1940. This period essentially marks the start of the ‘golden era’ of antibiotic discovery. Over time, emerging antimicrobial resistance (AMR) and the declining success rate of antibiotic discovery resulted in the current antibiotic crisis. We surprisingly discovered that under some growth conditions, &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt; sp. MBT27 can produce actinomycins that are significantly different from those that have been published so far. The impact of this work is not only that we have discovered a novel molecule with very interesting chemical modifications in one of the oldest antibiotics ever described, but also that this requires the combined action of primary and secondary metabolic pathways, namely the biosynthesis of anthranilamide and of actinomycin X&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, respectively. The implication of the discovery is that even the most well-studied families of natural products may still have surprises in store for us.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464064" rel="alternate" title="New from old: discovery of the novel antibiotic actinomycin L in Streptomyces sp. MBT27 (14 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.464073</id><title>Rates of primary production in groundwater rival those in oligotrophic marine systems (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.841706+00:00</updated><author><name>Will A. Overholt</name></author><author><name>Susan Trumbore</name></author><author><name>Xiaomei Xu</name></author><author><name>Till L.V. Bornemann</name></author><author><name>Alexander J. Probst</name></author><author><name>Markus Krüger</name></author><author><name>Martina Herrmann</name></author><author><name>Bo Thamdrup</name></author><author><name>Laura Bristow</name></author><author><name>Martin Taubert</name></author><author><name>Valérie F. Schwab</name></author><author><name>Martin Hölzer</name></author><author><name>Manja Marz</name></author><author><name>Kirsten Küsel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The terrestrial subsurface contains nearly all of Earth’s freshwater reserves&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; and harbors upwards of 60% of our planet’s total prokaryotic biomass&lt;sup&gt;2,3&lt;/sup&gt;. While genetic surveys suggest these organisms rely on &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; carbon fixation, rather than the translocation of photosynthetically derived organic carbon&lt;sup&gt;4–6&lt;/sup&gt;, corroborating measurements of carbon fixation in the subsurface are absent. Using a novel ultra-low level &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;C-labeling technique, we show that &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; carbon fixation rates in a carbonate aquifer reached 10% of the median rates measured in oligotrophic marine surface waters, and were up to six-fold greater than those observed in lower euphotic zone waters where deep chlorophyll levels peak. Empirical carbon fixation rates were substantiated by both nitrification and anammox rate data. Metagenomic analyses revealed a remarkable abundance of putative chemolithoautotrophic members of an uncharacterized order of Nitrospiria – the first representatives of this class expected to fix carbon via the Wood-Ljungdahl pathway. Based on these fixation rates, we extrapolate global primary production in carbonate groundwaters to be 0.11 Pg of carbon per year.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.464073" rel="alternate" title="Rates of primary production in groundwater rival those in oligotrophic marine systems (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.16.464638</id><title>Ionizing radiation improves RIG-I mediated immunotherapy through enhanced p53 activation in malignant melanoma (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.842753+00:00</updated><author><name>Silke Lambing</name></author><author><name>Stefan Holdenrieder</name></author><author><name>Patrick Müller</name></author><author><name>Christian Hagen</name></author><author><name>Stephan Garbe</name></author><author><name>Martin Schlee</name></author><author><name>Jasper G. van den Boorn</name></author><author><name>Eva Bartok</name></author><author><name>Gunther Hartmann</name></author><author><name>Marcel Renn</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The activation of the innate immune receptor RIG-I is a promising approach in immunooncology and currently under investigation in clinical trials. RIG-I agonists elicit a strong immune activation in both tumor and immune cells and induce both direct and indirect immune cell-mediated tumor cell death which involves tumor-specific cytotoxic T-cell response and type I interferon-driven innate cytotoxic immunity. Besides RIG-I, irradiation is known to induce cytotoxic DNA damage resulting in tumor debulking followed by the induction of tumor-specific immunity. To date, it is unclear whether the molecular antitumor effects of RIG-I and irradiation are additive or even synergize. Here, we investigated the combination of RIG-I activation with radiotherapy in melanoma. We found that low dose x-ray irradiation enhanced the extent and immunogenicity of RIG-I mediated tumor cell death in human and murine melanoma cell lines and in the murine B16 melanoma model in vivo. Pathway analysis of transcriptomic data revealed a central role for p53 downstream of the combined treatment, which was corroborated using p53-/- B16 cells. In vivo, the additional effect of irradiation on immune cell activation and inhibition of tumor growth was lost in mice carrying p53-knockout B16 tumors, while the response to RIG-I stimulation in those mice was maintained. Thus, our results identify p53 as pivotal for the synergy of RIG-I with irradiation, resulting in potent induction of immunogenic tumor cell death. Consequently, low dose radiotherapy holds great promise to further improve the efficacy or RIG-I ligands especially in patients with malignant melanoma or other tumors exhibiting a functional p53 pathway.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.16.464638" rel="alternate" title="Ionizing radiation improves RIG-I mediated immunotherapy through enhanced p53 activation in malignant melanoma (5 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>