<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.162619+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.469893</id><title>Cellular selectivity of STING stimulation determines priming of tumor-specific T cell responses (32 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.163355+00:00</updated><author><name>Bakhos Jneid</name></author><author><name>Aurore Bochnakian</name></author><author><name>Fabien Delisle</name></author><author><name>Emeline Djacoto</name></author><author><name>Jordan Denizeau</name></author><author><name>Christine Sedlik</name></author><author><name>Frederic Fiore</name></author><author><name>Robert Kramer</name></author><author><name>Ian Walters</name></author><author><name>Sylvain Carlioz</name></author><author><name>Bernard Malissen</name></author><author><name>Eliane Piaggio</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Manel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;T cells that recognize tumor antigens are crucial for anti-tumor immune responses. Induction of anti-tumor T cells in immunogenic tumors depends on STING, the intracellular innate immune receptor for cyclic guanosine monophosphate-adenosine monophosphate (cGAMP) and related cyclic dinucleotides (CDNs). However, the optimal way to leverage STING activation in non-immunogenic tumors is still unclear. Here, we show that cGAMP delivery by intra-tumoral injection of virus-like particles (cGAMP-VLP) leads to differentiation of tumor-specific T cells, decrease in tumor regulatory T cells (Tregs) and anti-tumoral responses that synergize with PD1 blockade. By contrast, intra-tumoral injection of synthetic CDN leads to tumor necrosis and systemic T cell activation but no differentiation of tumor-specific T cells, and a demise of immune cells in injected tumors. Analyses of cytokine responses and genetic models revealed that cGAMP-VLP preferentially targets STING in dendritic cells at a 1000-fold less dose than synthetic CDN. Sub-cutaneous administration of cGAMP-VLP showed synergy when combined with a tumor Treg-depleting antibody to elicit systemic tumor-specific T cells, leading to complete and lasting tumor eradication. These finding show that cell targeting of STING stimulation shapes the anti-tumor T cell response and reveal a therapeutic strategy with T cell modulators.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.469893" rel="alternate" title="Cellular selectivity of STING stimulation determines priming of tumor-specific T cell responses (32 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470747</id><title>An ecological perspective on microbial genes of unknown function in soil (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.163756+00:00</updated><author><name>Hannah Holland-Moritz</name></author><author><name>Chiara Vanni</name></author><author><name>Antonio Fernandez-Guerra</name></author><author><name>Andrew Bissett</name></author><author><name>Noah Fierer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genes that remain hypothetical, uncharacterized, and unannotated comprise a substantial portion of metagenomic datasets and are likely to be particularly prevalent in soils where poorly characterized taxa predominate. Documenting the prevalence, distribution, and potential roles of these genes of unknown function is an important first step to understanding their functional contributions in soil communities. We identified genes of unknown function from 50 soil metagenomes and analyzed their environmental distributions and ecological associations. We found that genes of unknown function are prevalent in soils, particularly fine-textured, higher pH soils that harbor greater abundances of &lt;italic&gt;Crenarchaeota, Gemmatimonadota, Nitrospirota&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;Methylomirabilota&lt;/italic&gt;. We identified 43 dominant (abundant and ubiquitous) gene clusters of unknown function and determined their associations with soil microbial phyla and other “known” genes. We found that these dominant unknown genes were commonly associated with microbial phyla that are relatively uncharacterized, with the majority of these dominant unknown genes associated with mobile genetic elements. This work demonstrates a strategy for investigating genes of unknown function in soils, emphasizes the biological insights that can be learned by adopting this strategy, and highlights specific hypotheses that warrant further investigation regarding the functional roles of abundant and ubiquitous genes of unknown function in soil metagenomes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470747" rel="alternate" title="An ecological perspective on microbial genes of unknown function in soil (14 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470848</id><title>Redox-active secondary metabolites act as interspecies modulators of antibiotic resilience (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.164042+00:00</updated><author><name>Lucas A. Meirelles</name></author><author><name>Dianne K. Newman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial opportunistic pathogens make a wide range of secondary metabolites both in the natural environment and when causing infections, yet how these molecules mediate microbial interactions and their consequences for antibiotic treatment are still poorly understood. Here, we explore the role of two redox-active secondary metabolites, pyocyanin and toxoflavin, as interspecies modulators of antibiotic resilience. We find that these molecules dramatically change susceptibility levels of diverse bacteria to clinical antibiotics. Pyocyanin is made by &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt;, while toxoflavin is made by &lt;italic&gt;Burkholderia gladioli&lt;/italic&gt;, organisms that infect cystic fibrosis and other immunocompromised patients. Both molecules alter the susceptibility profile of pathogenic species within the “&lt;italic&gt;Burkholderia cepacia&lt;/italic&gt; complex” to different antibiotics, either antagonizing or potentiating their effects, depending on the drug’s class. Defense responses regulated by the redox-sensitive transcription factor SoxR potentiate the antagonistic effects these metabolites have against fluoroquinolones, and the presence of genes encoding SoxR and the efflux systems it regulates can be used to predict how these metabolites will affect antibiotic susceptibility of different bacteria. Finally, we demonstrate that inclusion of secondary metabolites in standard protocols used to assess antibiotic resistance can dramatically alter the results, motivating the development of new tests for more accurate clinical assessment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470848" rel="alternate" title="Redox-active secondary metabolites act as interspecies modulators of antibiotic resilience (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470380</id><title>Communication determines population-level fitness under cation stress by modulating the ratio of motile to sessile B. subtilis cells (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.164251+00:00</updated><author><name>Benedikt K. Steinfeld</name></author><author><name>Qinna Cui</name></author><author><name>Tamara Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Ilka B. Bischofs</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial populations frequently encounter potentially lethal environmental stress factors. Growing &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; populations are comprised of a mixture of “motile” and “sessile” cells but how this affects population-level fitness under stress is poorly understood. Here, we show that, unlike sessile cells, motile cells are readily killed by monovalent cations under conditions of nutrient deprivation – owing to elevated expression of the &lt;italic&gt;lytABC&lt;/italic&gt; operon, which codes for a cell-wall lytic complex. Forced induction of the operon in sessile cells also causes lysis. We demonstrate that population composition is regulated by the quorum sensing regulator ComA, which can favor either the motile or the sessile state. Specifically social interactions by ComX-pheromone signaling enhance population-level fitness under stress. Our study highlights the importance of characterizing population composition and cellular properties for studies of bacterial physiology and functional genomics. Our findings open new perspectives for understanding the functions of autolysins and collective behaviors that are coordinated by chemical and electrical signals, with implications for multicellular development and biotechnology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470380" rel="alternate" title="Communication determines population-level fitness under cation stress by modulating the ratio of motile to sessile B. subtilis cells (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470317</id><title>A positive feedback loop mediates crosstalk between calcium, cyclic nucleotide and lipid signalling in Toxoplasma gondii (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.164476+00:00</updated><author><name>Caia Dominicus</name></author><author><name>Stephanie D. Nofal</name></author><author><name>Malgorzata Broncel</name></author><author><name>Nicholas J. Katris</name></author><author><name>Helen R. Flynn</name></author><author><name>Gustavo Arrizabalaga</name></author><author><name>Cyrille Y. Botté</name></author><author><name>Brandon M. Invergo</name></author><author><name>Moritz Treeck</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fundamental processes of obligate intracellular parasites, such as &lt;italic&gt;Toxoplasma gondii&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium falciparum&lt;/italic&gt;, are controlled by a set of plant-like calcium dependent kinases (CDPKs), the conserved cAMP- and cGMP-dependent protein kinases (PKA and PKG), secondary messengers and lipid signalling. While some major components of the signalling networks have been identified, how these are connected remains largely unknown. Here, we compare the phospho-signalling networks during &lt;italic&gt;Toxoplasma&lt;/italic&gt; egress from its host cell by artificially raising cGMP or calcium levels to activate PKG or CDPKs, respectively. We show that both these inducers trigger near identical signalling pathways and provide evidence for a positive feedback loop involving CDPK3. We measure phospho- and lipid signalling in parasites treated with the Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; ionophore A23187 in a sub-minute timecourse and show CDPK3-dependent regulation of diacylglycerol levels and increased phosphorylation of four phosphodiesterases (PDEs), suggesting their function in the feedback loop. Disruption of CDPK3 leads to elevated cAMP levels and inhibition of PKA signalling rescues the egress defect of ΔCDPK3 parasites treated with A23187. Biochemical analysis of the four PDEs identifies PDE2 as the only cAMP-specific PDE among these candidates, while the other PDEs are cGMP specific, two of which are inhibited by the predicted PDE inhibitor BIPPO. Conditional deletion of the four PDEs supports an important, but non-essential role for PDE1 and PDE2 in growth, with PDE2 controlling A23187-mediated egress. In summary we uncover a positive feedback loop that enhances signalling during egress and links several signalling pathways together.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470317" rel="alternate" title="A positive feedback loop mediates crosstalk between calcium, cyclic nucleotide and lipid signalling in Toxoplasma gondii (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.469274</id><title>Plasmodiophora brassicae in Mexico, from anecdote to fact (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.164788+00:00</updated><author><name>Legnara Padrón-Rodríguez</name></author><author><name>Carlos Roberto Cerdán Cabrera</name></author><author><name>Nadia Guadalupe Sánchez Coello</name></author><author><name>Mauricio Luna-Rodríguez</name></author><author><name>Edel Pérez-López</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;For years, the presence of clubroot disease and its causal agent, &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodiophora brassicae&lt;/italic&gt;, in Mexico has been given by granted. However, after a long search in the scientific literature in English and Spanish, as well as grey literature including thesis and government reports, we were not able to find any information regarding the actual detection of the pathogen, hosts affected, areas with the disease, or any real information about clubroot (‘hernia de la col’, in Mexico). To confirm if &lt;italic&gt;P. brassicae&lt;/italic&gt; was indeed in Mexico, we started a true detective adventure. First, we identified agricultural communities in south-east Mexico known to grow cruciferous crops. Second, we asked to the growers if they have ever seen clubroot symptoms, showing them during the inquires pictures of the characteristic galls that might have been present in their crops. Third, we collected soil from two of the communities with positive response and grew an array of cruciferous in the soil as baits to “fish” the clubroot pathogen. We detected the presence of galls in the roots of 32 plants and observed the presence of resting spores. Through a &lt;italic&gt;P. brassicae&lt;/italic&gt; specific PCR assay, we were able to confirm the presence of the clubroot pathogen in the samples and in Mexico for the very first time. This study is the first report and identification of &lt;italic&gt;P. brassicae&lt;/italic&gt; in Mexico, opening the doors to understand the genetic diversity of this elusive and devastating plant pathogen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.469274" rel="alternate" title="Plasmodiophora brassicae in Mexico, from anecdote to fact (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470831</id><title>The AdcACB/AdcAII system is Essential for Zinc Homeostasis and an Important Contributor of Enterococcus faecalis Virulence (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.165103+00:00</updated><author><name>Ling Ning Lam</name></author><author><name>Debra N. Brunson</name></author><author><name>Jonathan J. Molina</name></author><author><name>Ana L. Flores-Mireles</name></author><author><name>José A. Lemos</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial pathogens require a variety of micronutrients for growth, including trace metals such as iron, manganese, and zinc (Zn). Despite their relative abundance in host environments, access to these metals is severely restricted during infection due to host-mediated defense mechanisms collectively known as nutritional immunity. Despite a growing appreciation of the importance of Zn in host-pathogen interactions, the mechanisms of Zn homeostasis and the significance of Zn to the pathophysiology of &lt;italic&gt;E. faecalis&lt;/italic&gt;, a major pathogen of nosocomial and community-associated infections, have not been investigated. Here, we show that &lt;italic&gt;E. faecalis&lt;/italic&gt; encoded an ABC-type transporter AdcACB and an orphan substrate-binding lipoprotein AdcAII that work cooperatively to maintain Zn homeostasis. Simultaneous inactivation of &lt;italic&gt;adcA&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;adcAII&lt;/italic&gt; or the entire &lt;italic&gt;adcACB&lt;/italic&gt; operon led to significant reduction in intracellular Zn under Zn-restricted conditions, heightened sensitivity to Zn-chelating agents including human calprotectin, aberrant cell morphology, and impaired fitness in serum &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Additionally, inactivation of &lt;italic&gt;adcACB&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;adcAII&lt;/italic&gt; significantly reduced bacterial tolerance towards cell envelope-targeting antibiotics, which may be associated to altered fatty acid abundance and species. Lastly, we show that the AdcACB/AdcAII system contributes to &lt;italic&gt;E. faecalis&lt;/italic&gt; virulence in an invertebrate (&lt;italic&gt;Galleria mellonella&lt;/italic&gt;) infection model and in two catheter-associated mouse infection models that recapitulate many of the host conditions associated with enterococcal human infections. Collectively, this report reveals that high-affinity Zn import is essential for the pathogenesis of &lt;italic&gt;E. faecalis&lt;/italic&gt; indicating that the surface-associated AdcA and AdcAII lipoproteins are potential therapeutic targets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470831" rel="alternate" title="The AdcACB/AdcAII system is Essential for Zinc Homeostasis and an Important Contributor of Enterococcus faecalis Virulence (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470493</id><title>Tertiary lymphoid structures induced by CXCL13-producing CD4+ T cells increase tumor infiltrating CD8+ T cells and B cells in ovarian cancer (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.166450+00:00</updated><author><name>Masayo Ukita</name></author><author><name>Junzo Hamanishi</name></author><author><name>Hiroyuki Yoshitomi</name></author><author><name>Koji Yamanoi</name></author><author><name>Shiro Takamatsu</name></author><author><name>Akihiko Ueda</name></author><author><name>Haruka Suzuki</name></author><author><name>Yuko Hosoe</name></author><author><name>Yoko Furutake</name></author><author><name>Mana Taki</name></author><author><name>Kaoru Abiko</name></author><author><name>Ken Yamaguchi</name></author><author><name>Hidekatsu Nakai</name></author><author><name>Tsukasa Baba</name></author><author><name>Noriomi Matsumura</name></author><author><name>Akihiko Yoshizawa</name></author><author><name>Hideki Ueno</name></author><author><name>Masaki Mandai</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tertiary lymphoid structures (TLSs) are transient ectopic lymphoid aggregates whose formation might be caused by chronic inflammation states, such as cancer. The presence of TLS is associated with a favorable prognosis in most solid malignancies. The recognition of the relevance of TLS to cancer has led to a growing interest in TLS as an immunomodulatory target to enhance tumor immunity, although how TLSs are induced in the tumor microenvironment (TME) and how they affect patient survival are not well understood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;TLS distribution in relation to tumor infiltrating lymphocytes (TILs) and related gene expression were investigated in high grade serous ovarian cancer (HGSC) specimens. CXCL13 expression, which is strongly associated with TLS, and its localization in immune cells, were examined. We explored the tumor microenvironment for CXCL13 secretion by adding various inflammatory cytokines &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. The induction of TLS by CXCL13 was examined in a mouse model of ovarian cancer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;CXCL13 gene expression correlated with TLS formation and the infiltration of T cells and B cells, and was a favorable prognostic factor for HGSC patients. The coexistence of CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells and B-cell lineages in the TME was associated with a better prognosis of HGSC and was closely related to the presence of TLSs. CXCL13 expression was predominantly coincident with CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells in TLSs and CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells in TILs, and shifted from CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells to CD21&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; follicular dendritic cells as the TLS matured. Although TGF-β was reported to stimulate CXCL13 production, our &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; results revealed that CXCL13 secretion was promoted in CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells under TGF-β + IL-2-restricted conditions and in CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells under TGF-β + IL-12-rich conditions. In a mouse model of ovarian cancer, recombinant CXCL13 induced TLSs and enhanced survival by the infiltration of CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;TLS formation was promoted by CXCL13-producing CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells and TLSs facilitated the coordinated antitumor responses of cellular and humoral immunity in ovarian cancer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470493" rel="alternate" title="Tertiary lymphoid structures induced by CXCL13-producing CD4+ T cells increase tumor infiltrating CD8+ T cells and B cells in ovarian cancer (6 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470877</id><title>Dynamic utilization of low-molecular-weight organic substrates across a microbial growth rate gradient (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.167137+00:00</updated><author><name>K. Taylor Cyle</name></author><author><name>Annaleise R. Klein</name></author><author><name>Ludmilla Aristilde</name></author><author><name>Carmen Enid Martínez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Constantly in flux, low-molecular-weight organic substances (LMWOSs) are at the nexus between microorganisms, plant roots, detritus, and the soil mineral matrix. Nominal oxidation state of carbon (NOSC) has been put forward as one way to parameterize microbial uptake rates of LMWOSs and efficiency of carbon incorporation into new biomass. In this study, we employed an ecophysiological approach to test these proposed relationships using targeted exometabolomics (&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;H-NMR, HR-LCMS) coupled with stable isotope (&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C) probing. We assessed the role of compound class and oxidation state on uptake kinetics and substrate-specific carbon use efficiency (SUE) during the growth of three model soil microorganisms (&lt;italic&gt;Penicillium spinulosum&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;Paraburkholderia solitsugae,&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Ralstonia pickettii&lt;/italic&gt;) in media containing 34 common LMWOSs. Microbial isolates were chosen to span a gradient in growth rate (0.046-0.316 hr&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt;) and differ phylogenetically (a fungal isolate and two bacterial isolates). Clustered, co-utilization of LMWOSs occured for all three organisms, but temporal cluster separation was most apparent for &lt;italic&gt;P. solitsugae&lt;/italic&gt;. Potential trends (p &amp;lt;0.05) for early utilization of more oxidized substrates were present for the two bacterial isolates (&lt;italic&gt;P. solitsugae&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;R. pickettii&lt;/italic&gt;), but high variability (R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; &amp;gt; 0.15) and a small effect of NOSC indicate these are not useful relationships for prediction. The SUEs ranged from 0.16-0.99 and the hypothesized inverse relationship between NOSC and SUE was not observed. Thus, our results do not provide compelling support for NOSC as a predictive tool, implying that metabolic strategies of organisms may be more important than chemical identity in determining LMWOS cycling in soils.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Community-level observations from soils indicate that low-molecular-weight compounds of higher oxidation state tend to be depleted from soil solution faster and incorporated less efficiently into microbial biomass under oxic conditions. Here, we tested hypothetical relationships between substrate chemical characteristics and the order of substrate utilization by aerobic heterotrophs at the population-level in culture, using two bacterial isolates (&lt;italic&gt;Ralstonia pickettii&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Paraburkholderia solitsugae&lt;/italic&gt;) and one fungal isolate from soil (&lt;italic&gt;Penicillium spinulosum&lt;/italic&gt;). We found weak relationships indicating earlier uptake of more oxidized substrates by the two bacterial isolates but no relationship for the fungal isolate. We found no relationship between substrate identity and substrate use efficiency. Our findings indicate that substrate chemical characteristics have limited utility for modeling the depletion of low-molecular-weight organics from soil solution and incorporation into biomass over broader phylogenetic gradients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470877" rel="alternate" title="Dynamic utilization of low-molecular-weight organic substrates across a microbial growth rate gradient (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471163</id><title>Modelling of filamentous phage-induced antibiotic tolerance of P.aeruginosa (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.167751+00:00</updated><author><name>Maria Tessel van Rossem</name></author><author><name>Sandra Wilks</name></author><author><name>Malgosia Kaczmarek</name></author><author><name>Patrick R. Secor</name></author><author><name>Giampaolo D’Alessandro</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Filamentous molecules tend to spontaneously assemble into liquid crystalline droplets with a tactoid morphology in the environments with the high concentration on non-adsorbing molecules. Tactoids of filamentous Pf bacteriophage, such as those produced by &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt;, have been linked with increased antibiotic tolerance. We modelled this system and show that tactoids, composed of filamentous Pf virions, can lead to antibiotic tolerance by acting as an adsorptive diffusion barrier. The continuum model, reminiscent of descriptions of reactive diffusion in porous media, has been solved numerically and good agreement was found with the analytical results, obtained using a homogenisation approach. We find that the formation of tactoids significantly increases antibiotic diffusion times leading to stronger antibiotic resistance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471163" rel="alternate" title="Modelling of filamentous phage-induced antibiotic tolerance of P.aeruginosa (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470536</id><title>A bistable orthogonal prokaryotic differentiation system underlying development of conjugative transfer competence (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.168187+00:00</updated><author><name>Sandra Sulser</name></author><author><name>Andrea Vucicevic</name></author><author><name>Veronica Bellini</name></author><author><name>Roxane Moritz</name></author><author><name>François Delavat</name></author><author><name>Vladimir Sentchilo</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Carraro</name></author><author><name>Jan Roelof van der Meer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mechanisms and impact of horizontal gene transfer processes to distribute gene functions with potential adaptive benefit among prokaryotes have been well documented. In contrast, little is known about the life-style of mobile elements mediating horizontal gene transfer, whereas this is the ultimate determinant for their transfer fitness. Here, we investigate the life-style of an integrative and conjugative element (ICE) within the genus &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/italic&gt; that stands model for a widespread family transmitting genes for xenobiotic compound metabolism and antibiotic resistances. The ICE only transfers from a small fraction of cells in a population, which we uncover here, results from a dedicated transfer competence program imposed by the ICE. Transfer competence is orthogonally maintained in individual cells in which it is activated, making them the centerpiece of ICE conjugation. The components mediating transfer competence are widely conserved, underscoring their selected fitness for efficient transfer of this class of mobile elements.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470536" rel="alternate" title="A bistable orthogonal prokaryotic differentiation system underlying development of conjugative transfer competence (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470646</id><title>The processing of staphylococcal biofilm images from Fluorescence and Confocal Microscopy to assess in vitro efficacy of antiseptic molecules (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.168601+00:00</updated><author><name>Grzegorz Krasowski</name></author><author><name>Paweł Migdał</name></author><author><name>Marta Woroszyło</name></author><author><name>Karol Fijałkowski</name></author><author><name>Grzegorz Chodaczek</name></author><author><name>Joanna Czajkowska</name></author><author><name>Bartłomiej Dudek</name></author><author><name>Joanna Nowicka</name></author><author><name>Monika Oleksy-Wawrzyniak</name></author><author><name>Bartłomiej Kwiek</name></author><author><name>Justyna Paleczny</name></author><author><name>Malwina Brożyna</name></author><author><name>Adam Junka</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; efficacy of locally applied antiseptic molecules against staphylococcal biofilm is frequently assessed by a set of standard quantitative and semi-quantitative methods. The development of software for parametric image processing allowed to obtain parametric data also from microscopic images of biofilm dyed with a variety of dyes, especially with propidium iodine and SYTO-9, differentiating dead from live cells. In this work, using confocal/epifluorescent microscopy, we analyzed such major properties of staphylococcal biofilm &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; as its thickness, cellular density and share of Live/Dead cells within its individual parts. We also scrutinized the impact of sample preparation and antiseptic introduction on the outcome obtained. As a result of our analyses we developed a revelatory method of assessment of the impact of antiseptic agents on staphylococcal biofilm &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, in which the microscopic images are processed with the use of ABE formula (Antiseptic’s Biofilm Eradication) which implements all the data and phenomena detected and revealed within the course of this study. We tested ABE with regard to polyhexanide, pov idone-iodine and hypochlorous antiseptics and found a high correlation between this parameter and the results obtained by means of traditional techniques. Taking into account the fact that i&lt;italic&gt;n vitro&lt;/italic&gt; results of the efficacy of antiseptic agents against staphylococcal biofilm are frequently applied to back up their use in hospitals and ambulatory units, our work should be considered an important tool providing reliable, parametric data with this regard.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470646" rel="alternate" title="The processing of staphylococcal biofilm images from Fluorescence and Confocal Microscopy to assess in vitro efficacy of antiseptic molecules (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470634</id><title>Clinical implementation of single-cell RNA sequencing using liver fine needle aspirate tissue sampling and centralized processing captures compartment specific immuno-diversity (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.169076+00:00</updated><author><name>Alex S. Genshaft</name></author><author><name>Sonu Subudhi</name></author><author><name>Arlin Keo</name></author><author><name>Juan D. Sanchez Vasquez</name></author><author><name>Nádia Conceição-Neto</name></author><author><name>Deeqa Mahamed</name></author><author><name>Lauke L. Boeijen</name></author><author><name>Nadia Alatrakchi</name></author><author><name>Chris Oetheimer</name></author><author><name>Mike Vilme</name></author><author><name>Riley Drake</name></author><author><name>Ira Fleming</name></author><author><name>Nancy Tran</name></author><author><name>Constantine Tzouanas</name></author><author><name>Jasmin Joseph-Chazan</name></author><author><name>Martin Arreola Villanueva</name></author><author><name>Harmen J. G. van de Werken</name></author><author><name>Gertine W. van Oord</name></author><author><name>Zwier M.A. Groothuismink</name></author><author><name>Boris J. Beudeker</name></author><author><name>Zgjim Osmani</name></author><author><name>Shirin Nkongolo</name></author><author><name>Aman Mehrotra</name></author><author><name>Jordan Feld</name></author><author><name>Raymond T. Chung</name></author><author><name>Robert J. de Knegt</name></author><author><name>Harry L. A. Janssen</name></author><author><name>Jeroen Aerssens</name></author><author><name>Jacques Bollekens</name></author><author><name>Nir Hacohen</name></author><author><name>Georg M. Lauer</name></author><author><name>Andre Boonstra</name></author><author><name>Alex K. Shalek</name></author><author><name>Adam Gehring</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Blood samples are frequently collected in human studies of the immune system but poorly represent tissue-resident immunity. Understanding the immunopathogenesis of tissue-restricted diseases, such as chronic hepatitis B, necessitates direct investigation of local immune responses. We developed a workflow that enables frequent, minimally invasive collection of liver fine-needle aspirates in multi-site international studies and centralized single-cell RNA sequencing data generation using the Seq-Well S&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; picowell-based technology. All immunological cell types were captured, including liver macrophages, and showed distinct compartmentalization and transcriptional profiles, providing a systematic assessment of the capabilities and limitations of peripheral blood samples when investigating tissue-restricted diseases. The ability to electively sample the liver of chronic viral hepatitis patients and generate high-resolution data will enable multi-site clinical studies to power fundamental and therapeutic discovery.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470634" rel="alternate" title="Clinical implementation of single-cell RNA sequencing using liver fine needle aspirate tissue sampling and centralized processing captures compartment specific immuno-diversity (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.471000</id><title>Phage resistance accompanies reduced fitness of uropathogenic E. coli in the urinary environment (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.170180+00:00</updated><author><name>Jacob J Zulk</name></author><author><name>Justin R Clark</name></author><author><name>Samantha Ottinger</name></author><author><name>Mallory B Ballard</name></author><author><name>Marlyd E Mejia</name></author><author><name>Vicki Mercado</name></author><author><name>Emmaline R Heckmann</name></author><author><name>Belkys C Sanchez</name></author><author><name>Barbara W Trautner</name></author><author><name>Anthony W Maresso</name></author><author><name>Katy A Patras</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Urinary tract infections (UTIs) are among the most common infections treated worldwide each year and are primarily caused by uropathogenic E. coli (UPEC). Rising rates of antibiotic resistance among uropathogens have spurred consideration of alternative strategies such as bacteriophage (phage) therapy; however, phage-bacterial interactions within the urinary environment are poorly defined. Here, we assess the activity of two phages, HP3 and ES17, against clinical UPEC isolates using in vitro and in vivo models of UTI. In both bacteriologic medium and pooled human urine, we identified phage resistance arising within the first 6-8 hours of coincubation. Whole genome sequencing revealed that UPEC resistant to HP3 and ES17 harbored mutations in genes involved in lipopolysaccharide (LPS) biosynthesis. These mutations coincided with several in vitro phenotypes, including alterations to adherence to and invasion of human bladder epithelial HTB-9 cells, and increased biofilm formation. Interestingly, these phage-resistant UPEC demonstrated reduced growth in pooled human urine, which could be partially rescued by nutrient supplementation, and were more sensitive to several outer membrane targeting antibiotics than parental strains. Additionally, these phage-resistant UPEC were attenuated in a murine UTI model. In total, our findings suggest that while resistance to phages, such as LPS-targeted HP3 and ES17, may readily arise in the urinary environment, phage resistance is accompanied by fitness costs rendering UPEC more susceptible to host immunity or antibiotics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.471000" rel="alternate" title="Phage resistance accompanies reduced fitness of uropathogenic E. coli in the urinary environment (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470772</id><title>Regulation of dctA and DctA by cAMP-CRP and EIIAGlc at the transcriptional and post-translational levels in E. coli: Consequences for aerobic uptake and metabolism of C4-dicarboxylates (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.170513+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher Schubert</name></author><author><name>Gottfried Unden</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The expression of &lt;italic&gt;dctA&lt;/italic&gt;, encoding the aerobic C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-dicarboxylate (C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-DC) transporter DctA of &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt;, and its use in the presence of alternative carbon sources was characterized. &lt;italic&gt;dctA&lt;/italic&gt; is regulated by cAMP-CRP and substrates that control cAMP levels, either through the phosphotransferase system (PTS), or through their metabolic link to PEP synthesis. The data indicates that phosphorylation of the regulator EIIA&lt;sup&gt;Glc&lt;/sup&gt; of the glucose-specific PTS represents the mediator for regulation. The &lt;italic&gt;dctA&lt;/italic&gt; promotor region contains a class I CRP-binding site (position -81.5) and a DcuR-binding site (position -105.5). The response regulator DcuR of the C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-DC-activated DcuS-DcuR two-component system is known to stimulate expression of &lt;italic&gt;dctA&lt;/italic&gt;, and cAMP-CRP is known to stimulate expression of &lt;italic&gt;dcuS-dcuR&lt;/italic&gt;. Thus, activation of &lt;italic&gt;dctA&lt;/italic&gt; expression by cAMP-CRP and DcuR is organized in a coherent feed-forward loop (FFL) where cAMP-CRP positively regulates the expression of &lt;italic&gt;dctA&lt;/italic&gt; by direct stimulation and by stimulating the expression of &lt;italic&gt;dcuR&lt;/italic&gt;. Stimulation by DcuR is presumed to require DNA bending by cAMP-CRP. In this way, CRP-FFL integrates carbon catabolite control and C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-DC-specific regulation. Moreover, EIIA&lt;sup&gt;Glc&lt;/sup&gt; of the glucose-specific PTS strongly interacts with DctA, which could lead to substrate exclusion of C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-DCs when preferred carbon substrates such as sugars are present. Since C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-DCs are perceived in the periplasmic space by the sensor DcuS, the substrate exclusion is not linked to inducer exclusion, contrasting classical inducer exclusion known for the lactose permease LacY. Thus, aerobic C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-DC metabolism is tightly regulated at the transcriptional and post-translational levels, whereas uptake of L-aspartate by DcuA is essentially unaffected. Overall, transcriptional and post-translational regulation of &lt;italic&gt;dctA&lt;/italic&gt; expression and DctA function efficiently fine-tunes C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-DC catabolism in response to other preferred carbon sources.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470772" rel="alternate" title="Regulation of dctA and DctA by cAMP-CRP and EIIAGlc at the transcriptional and post-translational levels in E. coli: Consequences for aerobic uptake and metabolism of C4-dicarboxylates (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471060</id><title>Loquacious Modulates Flaviviral RNA Replication in Mosquito Cells (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.170780+00:00</updated><author><name>Shwetha Shivaprasad</name></author><author><name>Kuo-Feng Weng</name></author><author><name>Yan Shin Ooi</name></author><author><name>Julia Belk</name></author><author><name>Jan E Carette</name></author><author><name>Ryan Flynn</name></author><author><name>Peter Sarnow</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Arthropod-borne viruses infect both mosquito and mammalian hosts. While much is known about virus-host interactions that modulate viral gene expression in their mammalian host, much less is known about the interactions that involve inhibition, subversion or avoidance strategies in the mosquito host. A novel RNA-Protein interaction detection assay was used to detect proteins that directly or indirectly bind to dengue viral genomes in infected mosquito cells. Membrane-associated mosquito proteins SEC61A1 and Loquacious (Loqs) were found to be in complex with the viral RNA. Depletion analysis demonstrated that both SEC61A1 and Loqs have pro-viral functions in the dengue viral infectious cycle. Co-localization and pull-down assays showed that Loqs interacts with viral protein NS3 and both full-length and subgenomic viral RNAs. While Loqs coats the entire positive-stranded viral RNA, it binds selectively to the 3’ end of the negative-strand of the viral genome. In-depth analyses showed that the absence of Loqs did not affect translation or turnover of the viral RNA but modulated viral replication. Loqs also displayed pro-viral functions for several flaviviruses in infected mosquito cells, suggesting a conserved role for Loqs in flavivirus-infected mosquito cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471060" rel="alternate" title="Loquacious Modulates Flaviviral RNA Replication in Mosquito Cells (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470292</id><title>Developing an Antiviral Peptides Predictor with Generative Adversarial Network Data Augmentation (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.171562+00:00</updated><author><name>Tzu-Tang Lin</name></author><author><name>Yi-Yun Sun</name></author><author><name>Wei-Chih Cheng</name></author><author><name>I-Hsuan Lu</name></author><author><name>Shu-Hwa Chen</name></author><author><name>Chung-Yen Lin</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Motivation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;New antiviral drugs are urgently needed because of emerging viral pathogens’ increasing severity and drug resistance. Antiviral peptides (AVPs) have multiple antiviral properties and are appealing candidates for antiviral drug development. We developed a sequence-based binary classifier to identify whether an unknown short peptide has AVP activity. We collected AVP sequence data from six existing databases. We used a generative adversarial network to augment the number of AVPs in the positive training dataset and allow our deep convolutional neural network model to train on more data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our classifier achieved outstanding performance on the testing dataset compared with other state-of-the-art classifiers. We deployed our trained classifier on a user-friendly web server.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability and implementation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;AI4AVP is freely accessible at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://axp.iis.sinica.edu.tw/AI4AVP/"&gt;http://axp.iis.sinica.edu.tw/AI4AVP/&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contact&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;email&gt;cylin@iis.sinica.edu.tw&lt;/email&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Supplementary information&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supplementary data is also available.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470292" rel="alternate" title="Developing an Antiviral Peptides Predictor with Generative Adversarial Network Data Augmentation (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470408</id><title>Carbon-based Fluorescent Antibody Nanoprobes as Brain Tumour Glioblastoma Diagnostics (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.172002+00:00</updated><author><name>Mattia Ghirardello</name></author><author><name>Radhe Shyam</name></author><author><name>Xia Liu</name></author><author><name>Teodoro Garcia-Millan</name></author><author><name>Imke Sittel</name></author><author><name>F. Javier Ramos-Soriano</name></author><author><name>Kathreena Kurian</name></author><author><name>M. Carmen Galan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The development of efficient and sensitive tools for the detection of brain cancer in patients is of the utmost importance particularly because many of these tumours go undiagnosed until the disease has advanced and when treatment is less effective. Current strategies employ antibodies (Abs) to detect Glial Fibrillary Acid Protein (GFAP) in tissue samples, since GFAP is unique to the brain and not present in normal peripheral blood and rely on fluorescent reporters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Herein we describe a low cost, practical and general method for the labelling of proteins and antibodies with fluorescent carbon dots (CD) to generate diagnostic probes that are robust, photostable and applicable to the clinical setting. The two-step protocol relies on the conjugation of a dibenzocyclooctyne (DBCO)-functionalised CD with azide functionalised proteins by combining amide conjugation and strain promoted alkyne-azide cycloaddition (SPAAC) ligation chemistry. The new class of Abs-CD conjugates developed using this strategy were used for the immunohistochemical staining of human brain tissues of patients with glioblastoma (GBM) to validate the approach. Overall, these novel fluorescent probes offer a promising and versatile strategy in terms of costs, photostability and applicability which can be extended to other Abs and protein systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470408" rel="alternate" title="Carbon-based Fluorescent Antibody Nanoprobes as Brain Tumour Glioblastoma Diagnostics (3 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470506</id><title>The decrotonylase FoSir5 facilitates mitochondrial metabolic state switching in conidial germination of Fusarium oxysporum (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.172432+00:00</updated><author><name>Ning Zhang</name></author><author><name>Limin Song</name></author><author><name>Yang Xu</name></author><author><name>Xueyuan Pei</name></author><author><name>Ben F. Luisi</name></author><author><name>Wenxing Liang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Fusarium oxysporum&lt;/italic&gt; is one of the most important pathogenic fungi with a broad range of plant and animal hosts. The first key step of its infection cycle is conidial germination, but there is limited information available on the molecular events supporting this process. We show here that germination is accompanied by a sharp decrease in expression of FoSir5, an ortholog of the human lysine deacetylase SIRT5. We observe that FoSir5 decrotonylates a subunit of the fungal pyruvate dehydrogenase complex (FoDLAT) at K148, resulting in inhibition of the activity of the complex in mitochondria. Moreover, FoSir5 decrotonylates histone H3K18, leading to a downregulation of transcripts encoding enzymes of aerobic respiration pathways. Thus, the activity of FoSir5 coordinates regulation in different organelles to steer metabolic flux through respiration. As ATP content is positively related to fungal germination, we propose that FoSir5 negatively modulates conidial germination in &lt;italic&gt;F. oxysporum&lt;/italic&gt; through its metabolic impact. These findings provide insights into the multifaceted roles of decrotonylation, catalysed by FoSir5, that support conidial germination in &lt;italic&gt;F. oxysporum&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470506" rel="alternate" title="The decrotonylase FoSir5 facilitates mitochondrial metabolic state switching in conidial germination of Fusarium oxysporum (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470820</id><title>A Co-abundant Gene Analysis for Identification of Gut Microbial Strains Associated with Immune Responses to Oral Cholera Vaccine (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.172782+00:00</updated><author><name>Fred J. Heller</name></author><author><name>Hasan Al Banna</name></author><author><name>M. Hasanul Kaisar</name></author><author><name>Denise Chac</name></author><author><name>Fahima Chowdhury</name></author><author><name>Taufiqur R. Bhuiyan</name></author><author><name>Afroza Akter</name></author><author><name>Ashraful I. Khan</name></author><author><name>Polash Chandra Karmakar</name></author><author><name>Pinki Dash</name></author><author><name>Regina C. LaRocque</name></author><author><name>Edward T. Ryan</name></author><author><name>Samuel S. Minot</name></author><author><name>Jason B. Harris</name></author><author><name>Firdausi Qadri</name></author><author><name>Ana A. Weil</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oral cholera vaccines (OCVs) are an important tool for reduction of the worldwide cholera burden, but some individuals who receive an OCV do not develop protective immune responses. The gut microbiota is a potential explanation for these differences. Components of the gut microbiota associated with differences in OCV response have not been identified.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used metagenomic sequencing to identify predicted protein-coding genes in the gut microbiota at the time of OCV administration, and then measured immune responses to vaccination. Vaccine recipients were classified as OCV “responders” if they developed a post­vaccination increase in memory B cell populations that produce IgA or IgG specific for cholera toxin and the &lt;italic&gt;V. cholerae&lt;/italic&gt; O-specific polysaccharide. We next analyzed microbial genes seen at similar abundances across individual samples and classified these into co-abundant gene groupings (CAGs), and correlated CAGs with OCV responses. Next, to identify specific bacterial strains associated with OCV responses, we mapped CAGs to bacterial genomes and generated a “priority score” for each strain detected in the study population. This score reflects both the number of CAGs aligning to a specific bacterial genome and the strength of the association between the CAGs and the vaccine response. This strain-level analysis revealed relationships between the gut microbiota and immune response to OCV that were not detected at the genus or species level. Bacterial strains which produce short-chain fatty acids and those with sphingolipid-containing cell membranes were correlated with more robust immune responses to vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our study demonstrates a method for translating metagenomic sequencing data into strain-specific results associated with a biological outcome. Using this approach, we identified strains for the study of bacterial-derived molecules or metabolites associated with immune responses; such agents might have potential utility as vaccine adjuvants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470820" rel="alternate" title="A Co-abundant Gene Analysis for Identification of Gut Microbial Strains Associated with Immune Responses to Oral Cholera Vaccine (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470879</id><title>MgrB dependent colistin resistance in Klebsiella pneumoniae is associated with an increase in host-to-host transmission (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.173144+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew S. Bray</name></author><author><name>Richard D. Smith</name></author><author><name>Andrew W. Hudson</name></author><author><name>Giovanna E. Hernandez</name></author><author><name>Taylor M. Young</name></author><author><name>Robert K. Ernst</name></author><author><name>M. Ammar Zafar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Due to its high transmissibility, &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Kpn&lt;/italic&gt;) is one of the leading causes of nosocomial infections. Here, we studied the biological cost of colistin resistance, an antibiotic of last resort, of this opportunistic pathogen using a murine model of gut colonization and transmission. Colistin resistance in &lt;italic&gt;Kpn&lt;/italic&gt; is commonly the result of inactivation of the small regulatory protein MgrB. Without a functional MgrB, the two-component system PhoPQ is constitutively active, leading to increased lipid A modifications and subsequent colistin resistance. Using an engineered MgrB mutant, we observed that MgrB-dependent colistin resistance is not associated with a fitness defect during &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; growth conditions. However, colistin-resistant &lt;italic&gt;Kpn&lt;/italic&gt; colonizes the murine gut poorly, which may be due to the decreased production of capsular polysaccharide by the mutant. The colistin-resistant mutant of &lt;italic&gt;Kpn&lt;/italic&gt; had increased survival outside the host when compared to the parental colistin-sensitive strain. We attribute this enhanced survivability to dysregulation of the PhoPQ two-component system and accumulation of the master stress regulator RpoS. The enhanced survival of the colistin resistant strain may be a key factor in the observed rapid host-to-host transmission in our model. Together, our data demonstrate that colistin-resistant &lt;italic&gt;Kpn&lt;/italic&gt; experiences a biological cost in gastrointestinal colonization. However, this cost is mitigated by enhanced survival outside the host, increasing the risk of transmission. Additionally, it underscores the importance of considering the entire life cycle of a pathogen to truly determine the biological cost associated with antibiotic resistance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The biological cost associated with colistin resistance in &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Kpn&lt;/italic&gt;) was examined using a murine model of &lt;italic&gt;Kpn&lt;/italic&gt; gut colonization and fecal-oral transmission. A common mutation resulting in colistin resistance in &lt;italic&gt;Kpn&lt;/italic&gt; is a loss-of-function mutation of the small regulatory protein MgrB that regulates the two-component system PhoPQ. Even though colistin resistance in &lt;italic&gt;Kpn&lt;/italic&gt; comes with a fitness defect in gut colonization, it increases bacterial survival outside the host enabling it to more effectively transmit to a new host. The enhanced survival is dependent upon the accumulation of RpoS and dysregulation of the PhoPQ. Hence, our study expands our understanding of the underlying molecular mechanism contributing to the transmission of colistin-resistant &lt;italic&gt;Kpn&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470879" rel="alternate" title="MgrB dependent colistin resistance in Klebsiella pneumoniae is associated with an increase in host-to-host transmission (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470874</id><title>Microbial ecology of sulfur biogeochemical cycling at a mesothermic hot spring atop Northern Himalayas, India (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.173390+00:00</updated><author><name>Shekhar Nagar</name></author><author><name>Chandni Talwar</name></author><author><name>Mikael Motelica-Heino</name></author><author><name>Hans-Hermann Richnow</name></author><author><name>Mallikarjun Shakarad</name></author><author><name>Rup Lal</name></author><author><name>Ram Krishan Negi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;caption&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;/caption&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="470874v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sulfur Related Prokaryotes (SRP) residing in hot spring present good opportunity for exploring the limitless possibilities of integral ecosystem processes. Metagenomic analysis further expand the phylogenetic breadth of these extraordinary sulfur metabolizing microorganisms, as well a their complex metabolic networks and syntrophic interactions in environmental biosystems. Through this study, we explored and expanded the microbial genetic repertoire with focus on sulfur cycling genes through metagenomic analysis of sulfur (S) contaminated hot spring, located at the Northern Himalayas. The analysis revealed rich diversity of microbial consortia with established roles in S cycling such as &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;Thioalkalivibrio&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;Desulfovibrio&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Desulfobulbaceae&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Proteobacteria&lt;/italic&gt;). The major gene families inferred to be abundant across microbial mat, sediment and water were assigned to &lt;italic&gt;Proteobacteria&lt;/italic&gt; as reflected from the RPKs (reads per kilobase) categorized into translation and ribosomal structure and biogenesis. Analysis of sequence similarity showed conserved pattern of both &lt;italic&gt;dsrAB&lt;/italic&gt; genes (n=178) retrieved from all metagenomes while other sulfur disproportionation proteins were diverged due to different structural and chemical substrates. The diversity of sulfur oxidizing bacteria (SOB) and sulfate reducing bacteria (SRB) with conserved (r)&lt;italic&gt;dsrAB&lt;/italic&gt; suggests for it to be an important adaptation for microbial fitness at this site. Here, we confirm that (i) SRBs belongs to &lt;italic&gt;δ-Proteobacteria&lt;/italic&gt; occurring independent LGT of &lt;italic&gt;dsr&lt;/italic&gt; genes to different and few novel lineages (ii) also, the oxidative and reductive &lt;italic&gt;dsr&lt;/italic&gt; evolutionary time scale phylogeny, proved that the earliest (not first) &lt;italic&gt;dsrAB&lt;/italic&gt; proteins belong to anaerobic &lt;italic&gt;Thiobacillus&lt;/italic&gt; with other (&lt;italic&gt;rdsr&lt;/italic&gt;) oxidizers. Further, the structural prediction of unassigned DsrAB proteins confirmed their relatedness with species of &lt;italic&gt;Desulfovibrio&lt;/italic&gt; (TM score= 0.86; 0.98; 0.96) and &lt;italic&gt;Archaeoglobus fulgidus&lt;/italic&gt; (TM score= 0.97; 0.98). We proposed that the genetic repertoire might provide the basis of studying time scale evolution and horizontal gene transfer of these genes in biogeochemical S cycling and the complementary genes could be implemented in biotechnology and bioremediation applications.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470874" rel="alternate" title="Microbial ecology of sulfur biogeochemical cycling at a mesothermic hot spring atop Northern Himalayas, India (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>