<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.725953+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.05.451122</id><title>Disturbance-based management of ecosystem services and disservices in partial nitritation anammox biofilms (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.726844+00:00</updated><author><name>Carolina Suarez</name></author><author><name>Christopher J. Sedlacek</name></author><author><name>David J. I. Gustavsson</name></author><author><name>Alexander Eiler</name></author><author><name>Oskar Modin</name></author><author><name>Malte Hermansson</name></author><author><name>Frank Persson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The resistance and resilience provided by functional redundancy, a common feature of microbial communities, is not always advantageous. An example is nitrite oxidation in partial nitritation-anammox (PNA) reactors during wastewater treatment, where suppression of nitrite oxidizers like &lt;italic&gt;Nitrospira&lt;/italic&gt; is sought. In these ecosystems, biofilms provide microhabitats with oxygen gradients, allowing the coexistence aerobic and anaerobic bacteria. We designed a disturbance experiment where PNA biofilms treating water from a high rate activated sludge process removing organic matter (mainstream wastewater), were constantly or intermittently exposed to the effluent of anaerobic sewage sludge digestion dewatering (sidestream wastewater), which has been proposed to inhibit nitrite oxidizers. With increasing sidestream exposure we observed decreased abundance, alpha-diversity, functional versatility, and hence functional redundancy, among &lt;italic&gt;Nitrospira&lt;/italic&gt; in the PNA biofilms, while the opposite patterns were observed for anammox bacteria within &lt;italic&gt;Brocadia&lt;/italic&gt;. At the same time, species turnover was observed for the aerobic ammonia-oxidizing &lt;italic&gt;Nitrosomonas&lt;/italic&gt; populations. The different exposure regimens were associated with metagenomic assembled genomes of &lt;italic&gt;Nitrosomonas, Nitrospira&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;Brocadia&lt;/italic&gt;, encoding genes related to N-cycling, substrate usage, and osmotic stress response, possibly explaining the three different patterns by niche differentiation. These findings imply that disturbances can be used to manage the functional redundancy of biofilm microbiomes in a desirable direction, which should be considered when designing operational strategies for wastewater treatment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.05.451122" rel="alternate" title="Disturbance-based management of ecosystem services and disservices in partial nitritation anammox biofilms (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.04.451084</id><title>Global evolutionary dynamics and resistome analysis of Clostridioides difficile ribotype 017 (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.728684+00:00</updated><author><name>Korakrit Imwattana</name></author><author><name>Papanin Putsathit</name></author><author><name>Deirdre A Collins</name></author><author><name>Teera Leepattarakit</name></author><author><name>Pattarachai Kiratisin</name></author><author><name>Thomas V Riley</name></author><author><name>Daniel R Knight</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Clostridioides difficile&lt;/italic&gt; PCR ribotype (RT) 017 ranks among the most successful strains of &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; in the world. In the past three decades, it has caused outbreaks on four continents, more than other “epidemic” strains, however, our understanding of the genomic epidemiology underpinning the spread of &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; RT 017 is limited. Here, we performed high-resolution phylogenomic and Bayesian evolutionary analyses on an updated and more representative dataset of 282 non-clonal &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; RT 017 isolates collected worldwide between 1981 and 2019. These analyses place an estimated time of global dissemination between 1953 and 1983 and identified the acquisition of the &lt;italic&gt;ermB&lt;/italic&gt;-positive transposon &lt;italic&gt;Tn6194&lt;/italic&gt; as a key factor behind global emergence. This coincided with the introduction of clindamycin, a key inciter of &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; infection, into clinical practice in the 1960s. Based on the genomic data alone, the origin of &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; RT 017 could not be determined, however, geographical data and records of population movement suggest that &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; RT 017 had been moving between Asia and Europe since the Middle Ages and was later transported to North America around 1860 (95% CI: 1622 – 1954). A focused epidemiological study of 45 clinical &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; RT 017 genomes from a cluster in a tertiary hospital in Thailand revealed that the population consisted of two groups of multidrug-resistant (MDR) &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; RT 017 and a group of early, non-MDR &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; RT 017. The significant genomic diversity within each MDR group suggests that although they were all isolated from hospitalised patients, there was likely a reservoir of &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; RT 017 in the community that contributed to the spread of this pathogen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Impact statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study utilises genomic sequence data from 282 non-clonal &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; ribotype (RT) 017 isolates collected from around the world to delineate the origin and spread of this epidemic lineage, as well as explore possible factors that have driven its success. It also reports a focused epidemiological investigation of a cluster of &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; RT 017 in a tertiary hospital in Thailand to identify possible sources of transmission in this specific setting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;All new WGS data generated in this study has been submitted to the European Nucleotide Archive under the BioProject PRJEB44406 (sample accession ERS6268756 – ERS6268798). The complete genome of &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; MAR286 was submitted to GenBank under BioProject PRJNA679085 (accession &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="CP072118"&gt;CP072118&lt;/ext-link&gt;). Details of all genomes included in the final analyses are available in the &lt;bold&gt;Supplementary Document&lt;/bold&gt;, available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14544792"&gt;10.6084/m9.figshare.14544792&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.04.451084" rel="alternate" title="Global evolutionary dynamics and resistome analysis of Clostridioides difficile ribotype 017 (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.05.451090</id><title>A bacterial derived plant- mimicking cytokinin hormone regulates social behaviour in a rice pathogen (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.729929+00:00</updated><author><name>Sohini Deb</name></author><author><name>Chandan Kumar</name></author><author><name>Rahul Kumar</name></author><author><name>Amandeep Kaur</name></author><author><name>Palash Ghosh</name></author><author><name>Gopaljee Jha</name></author><author><name>Prabhu B. Patil</name></author><author><name>Subhadeep Chatterjee</name></author><author><name>Hitendra K. Patel</name></author><author><name>Ramesh V. Sonti</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many plant-associated bacteria produce plant- mimicking hormones which are involved in modulating host physiology. However, their function in modulating bacterial physiology has not been reported. Here we show that the XopQ protein, a type-III effector of the rice pathogen, &lt;italic&gt;Xanthomonas oryzae&lt;/italic&gt; pv. &lt;italic&gt;oryzae&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Xoo&lt;/italic&gt;), is involved in cytokinin biosynthesis. &lt;italic&gt;Xoo&lt;/italic&gt; produces and secretes an active form of cytokinin which enables the bacterium to maintain a planktonic lifestyle and promotes virulence. RNA-seq analysis indicates that the cytokinin produced by &lt;italic&gt;Xoo&lt;/italic&gt; is required for the regulation of several genes which are involved in biofilm formation. We have also identified the &lt;italic&gt;Xoo&lt;/italic&gt; isopentenyl transferase gene, which is involved in the cytokinin biosynthesis pathway and is required for maintaining planktonic behaviour and virulence. Furthermore, mutations in the predicted cytokinin receptor kinase (PcrK) and the downstream response regulator (PcrR) of &lt;italic&gt;Xoo&lt;/italic&gt; phenocopy the cytokinin biosynthetic mutants, but are not complemented by supplementation with exogenous cytokinin. Cytokinin biosynthetic functions are encoded in a number of diverse bacterial genomes suggesting that cytokinin may be a widespread signalling molecule in the bacterial kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.05.451090" rel="alternate" title="A bacterial derived plant- mimicking cytokinin hormone regulates social behaviour in a rice pathogen (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>