<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.755207+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453748</id><title>Identification of a new family of “megaphages” that are abundant in the marine environment (74 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.755751+00:00</updated><author><name>Slawomir Michniewski</name></author><author><name>Branko Rihtman</name></author><author><name>Ryan Cook</name></author><author><name>Michael A. Jones</name></author><author><name>William H Wilson</name></author><author><name>David J Scanlan</name></author><author><name>Andrew Millard</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Megaphages – bacteriophages harbouring extremely large genomes – have recently been found to be ubiquitous, being described from a variety of microbiomes ranging from the animal gut to soil and freshwater systems. However, no complete marine megaphage has been identified to date. Here, using both short and long read sequencing, we assembled &amp;gt;900 high-quality draft viral genomes from water in the English Channel. One of these genomes included a novel megaphage, Mar_Mega_1 at &amp;gt;650 Kb, making it one of the largest phage genomes assembled to date. Utilising phylogenetic and network approaches, we found this phage represents a new family of bacteriophages. Genomic analysis showed Mar_Mega_1 shares relatively few homologues with its closest relatives, but, as with other mega-phages Mar_Mega_1 contained a variety of auxiliary metabolic genes responsible for carbon metabolism and nucleotide biosynthesis, including isocitrate dehydrogenase [NADP] and nicotinamide-nucleotide amidohydrolase [PncC] which have not previously been identified in megaphages. The results of this study indicate that phages containing extremely large genomes can be found in abundance in the marine environment and augment host metabolism by mechanisms not previously described.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453748" rel="alternate" title="Identification of a new family of “megaphages” that are abundant in the marine environment (74 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453760</id><title>A bacterial dynamin-like protein confers a novel phage resistance strategy on the population level in Bacillus subtilis (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.756269+00:00</updated><author><name>Lijun Guo</name></author><author><name>Laura Sattler</name></author><author><name>Peter Graumann</name></author><author><name>Marc Bramkamp</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; DynA is a member of the dynamin superfamily, involved in membrane remodeling processes. DynA was shown to catalyze full membrane fusion and it plays a role in membrane surveillance against antibiotics. We show here that DynA also provides a novel resistance mechanism against phage infection. Cells lacking DynA are efficiently lysed after phage infection and virus replication. DynA does not prevent phage infection and replication in individual cells, but significantly delays host cell lysis, thereby slowing down the release of phage progeny from the host cells. During the process, DynA forms large, almost immobile clusters on the cell membrane that seem to support membrane integrity. Single molecule tracking revealed a shift of freely diffusive molecules within the cytosol towards extended, confined motion at the cell membrane following phage induction. Thus, the bacterial dynamins are the first anti-phage system reported to delay host cell lysis and the last line of defense of a multilayered antiviral defense. DynA is therefore providing protective effects on the population, but not on single cell level.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453760" rel="alternate" title="A bacterial dynamin-like protein confers a novel phage resistance strategy on the population level in Bacillus subtilis (37 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453184</id><title>The dual nature of bacteriophage: growth-dependent predation and generalised transduction of antimicrobial resistance (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.756474+00:00</updated><author><name>Quentin J Leclerc</name></author><author><name>Jacob Wildfire</name></author><author><name>Arya Gupta</name></author><author><name>Jodi A Lindsay</name></author><author><name>Gwenan M Knight</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacteriophage (“phage”) are both predators and evolutionary drivers for bacteria, notably contributing to the spread of antimicrobial resistance (AMR) genes by generalised transduction. Our current understanding of the dual nature of this relationship is limited. We used an interdisciplinary approach to quantify how these interacting dynamics can lead to the evolution of multi-drug resistant bacteria. We co-cultured two strains of Methicillin-resistant &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/italic&gt;, each harbouring a different antibiotic resistance gene, with 80α generalized transducing phage. After a growth phase of 8h, bacteria and phage surprisingly coexisted at a stable equilibrium in our culture, the level of which was dependent on the starting concentration of phage. We detected double-resistant bacteria as early as 7h, indicating that transduction of AMR genes had occurred. We developed multiple mathematical models of the bacteria and phage relationship, and found that phage-bacteria dynamics were best captured by a model in which the phage burst size decreases as the bacteria population reaches stationary phase, and where phage predation is frequency-dependent. We estimated that one in every 10&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt; new phage generated was a transducing phage carrying an AMR gene, and that double-resistant bacteria were always predominantly generated by transduction rather than by growth. Our results suggest a fundamental shift in how we understand and model phage-bacteria dynamics. Although rates of generalised transduction may seem insignificant, they are sufficient to consistently lead to the evolution of multi-drug resistant bacteria. Currently, the potential of phage to contribute to the growing burden of AMR is likely underestimated.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453184" rel="alternate" title="The dual nature of bacteriophage: growth-dependent predation and generalised transduction of antimicrobial resistance (20 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453610</id><title>Adapted protocol for Saccharibacteria co-cultivation: two new members join the club of Candidate Phyla radiation (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.756647+00:00</updated><author><name>Ahmad Ibrahim</name></author><author><name>Mohamad Maatouk</name></author><author><name>Andriamiharimamy Rajaonison</name></author><author><name>Rita Zgheib</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Haddad</name></author><author><name>Jacques Bou-Khalil</name></author><author><name>Didier Raoult</name></author><author><name>Fadi Bittar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The growing application of metagenomics to different ecological and microbiome niches in recent years has enhanced our knowledge of global microbial biodiversity. Among these abundant and widespread microbes, Candidate Phyla Radiation or CPR have been recognised as representing a large proportion of the microbial kingdom (&amp;gt; 26%). CPR are characterised by their obligate symbiotic or exo-parasitic activity with other microbial hosts, mainly bacteria. Currently, isolating CPR is still considered challenging for microbiologists. The idea of this study was to develop an adapted protocol for the co-culture of CPR with a suitable bacterial host. Based on various sputa, we tried to purify CPR (&lt;italic&gt;Saccharibacteria&lt;/italic&gt; members) and to cultivate them with pure hosts. This protocol was monitored by real-time PCR quantification using a specific system for &lt;italic&gt;Saccharibacteria&lt;/italic&gt; designed in this study, as well as by electron microscopy and sequencing. We succeeded in co-culturing and sequencing a complete genome of two new &lt;italic&gt;Saccharibacteria&lt;/italic&gt; species: &lt;italic&gt;Candidatus&lt;/italic&gt; Minimicrobia naudis and &lt;italic&gt;Candidatus&lt;/italic&gt; Minimicrobia vallesae. In addition, we noticed a decrease in the Ct number of &lt;italic&gt;Saccharibacteria&lt;/italic&gt;, and a significant multiplication through their physical association with &lt;italic&gt;Schaalia odontolytica&lt;/italic&gt; strains in the enriched medium that we developed. This work may help bridge gaps in the genomic database by providing new CPR members and, in the future, their currently unknown characteristics may be revealed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this study, the first real-time PCR system has been developed. This technique is able to quantify specifically &lt;italic&gt;Saccharibacteria&lt;/italic&gt; members in any sample of interest in order to investigate their prevalence. In addition, another easy, specific and sensitive protocol has been developed to maintain the viability of &lt;italic&gt;Saccharibacteria&lt;/italic&gt; cells in an enriched medium with their bacterial host. The use of this protocol subsequently facilitates studying the phenotypic characteristics of CPR and their physical interactions with bacterial species, as well as the sequencing of new genomes to improve the current database.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453610" rel="alternate" title="Adapted protocol for Saccharibacteria co-cultivation: two new members join the club of Candidate Phyla radiation (12 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453744</id><title>Global protein responses of multi-drug resistant plasmid containing Escherichia coli to ampicillin, cefotaxime, imipenem and ciprofloxacin (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.756831+00:00</updated><author><name>Anatte Margalit</name></author><author><name>James C. Carolan</name></author><author><name>Fiona Walsh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antimicrobial resistance (AMR) and multi-drug resistance (MDR) in pathogenic bacteria are frequently mediated by plasmids. However, plasmids do not exist in isolation but rather require the bacterial host interaction in order to produce the AMR phenotype. This study aimed to utilise mass spectrometry-based proteomics to reveal the plasmid and chromosomally derived protein profile of &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; under antimicrobial stress. This was achieved by comparing the proteomes of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; containing the MDR pEK499 plasmid, under ampicillin, cefotaxime, imipenem or ciprofloxacin stress with the proteomes of these bacteria grown in the absence of antimicrobial. Our analysis identified statistically significant differentially abundant proteins common to groups exposed to the β-lactam antimicrobials but not ciprofloxacin, indicating a β-lactam stress response to exposure from this class of drugs, irrespective of β-lactam resistance or susceptibility. These include ecotin and free methionine-R-sulfoxide reductase. These data also identified distinct differences in the cellular response to each β-lactam. Data arising from comparisons of the proteomes of ciprofloxacin-treated &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; and controls detected an increase in the relative abundance of proteins associated with ribosomes, translation, the TCA-cycle and several proteins associated with detoxification and a decrease in the relative abundances of proteins associated with stress response, including oxidative stress. We identified changes in proteins associated with persister formation in the presence of ciprofloxacin but not the β-lactams. The plasmid proteome differed across each treatment and did not follow the pattern of antimicrobial – AMR protein associations. For example, a relative increase in the amount of blaCTX-M-15 in the presence of cefotaxime and ciprofloxacin but not the other β-lactams, suggesting regulation of the blaCTX-M-15 protein production. The proteomic data from the this study provided novel insights into the proteins produced from the chromosome and plasmid under different antimicrobial stresses. These data also identified novel proteins not previously associated with AMR or antimicrobials responses in pathogens, which may well represent potential targets of AMR inhibition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453744" rel="alternate" title="Global protein responses of multi-drug resistant plasmid containing Escherichia coli to ampicillin, cefotaxime, imipenem and ciprofloxacin (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453710</id><title>A comprehensive collection of transcriptome data to support life cycle analysis of the poplar rust fungus Melampsora larici-populina (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.756983+00:00</updated><author><name>Pamela Guerillot</name></author><author><name>Emmanuelle Morin</name></author><author><name>Annegret Kohler</name></author><author><name>Clémentine Louet</name></author><author><name>Sébastien Duplessis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Melampsora larici-populina&lt;/italic&gt; is an obligate biotrophic plant pathogen responsible for the poplar rust disease. This fungus belongs to the taxonomical order Pucciniales and exhibits a complex heteroecious and macrocyclic life cycle, i.e. it has the capacity to infect two unrelated host plants, larch and poplar, and to form five distinct spore types through the year. The &lt;italic&gt;M. larici-populina&lt;/italic&gt; genome has been sequenced and annotated in 2011 and since, different transcriptomic analyses were conducted at different stages with oligoarrays and later on with RNA-Seq covering most of its life cycle. Here, we collected published transcriptome data for the poplar rust fungus, transposed them for the version 2 of the genome now available at the Joint Genome Institute Mycocosm website and performed normalization of different oligoarray datasets on one hand, and of RNA-Seq on the other hand. We report a comprehensive normalized dataset for this fungus, made available for the community, which allows life cycle transcriptomics analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453710" rel="alternate" title="A comprehensive collection of transcriptome data to support life cycle analysis of the poplar rust fungus Melampsora larici-populina (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>