<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.815971+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453748</id><title>Identification of a new family of “megaphages” that are abundant in the marine environment (75 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.816427+00:00</updated><author><name>Slawomir Michniewski</name></author><author><name>Branko Rihtman</name></author><author><name>Ryan Cook</name></author><author><name>Michael A. Jones</name></author><author><name>William H Wilson</name></author><author><name>David J Scanlan</name></author><author><name>Andrew Millard</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Megaphages – bacteriophages harbouring extremely large genomes – have recently been found to be ubiquitous, being described from a variety of microbiomes ranging from the animal gut to soil and freshwater systems. However, no complete marine megaphage has been identified to date. Here, using both short and long read sequencing, we assembled &amp;gt;900 high-quality draft viral genomes from water in the English Channel. One of these genomes included a novel megaphage, Mar_Mega_1 at &amp;gt;650 Kb, making it one of the largest phage genomes assembled to date. Utilising phylogenetic and network approaches, we found this phage represents a new family of bacteriophages. Genomic analysis showed Mar_Mega_1 shares relatively few homologues with its closest relatives, but, as with other mega-phages Mar_Mega_1 contained a variety of auxiliary metabolic genes responsible for carbon metabolism and nucleotide biosynthesis, including isocitrate dehydrogenase [NADP] and nicotinamide-nucleotide amidohydrolase [PncC] which have not previously been identified in megaphages. The results of this study indicate that phages containing extremely large genomes can be found in abundance in the marine environment and augment host metabolism by mechanisms not previously described.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453748" rel="alternate" title="Identification of a new family of “megaphages” that are abundant in the marine environment (75 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453760</id><title>A bacterial dynamin-like protein confers a novel phage resistance strategy on the population level in Bacillus subtilis (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.816698+00:00</updated><author><name>Lijun Guo</name></author><author><name>Laura Sattler</name></author><author><name>Peter Graumann</name></author><author><name>Marc Bramkamp</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; DynA is a member of the dynamin superfamily, involved in membrane remodeling processes. DynA was shown to catalyze full membrane fusion and it plays a role in membrane surveillance against antibiotics. We show here that DynA also provides a novel resistance mechanism against phage infection. Cells lacking DynA are efficiently lysed after phage infection and virus replication. DynA does not prevent phage infection and replication in individual cells, but significantly delays host cell lysis, thereby slowing down the release of phage progeny from the host cells. During the process, DynA forms large, almost immobile clusters on the cell membrane that seem to support membrane integrity. Single molecule tracking revealed a shift of freely diffusive molecules within the cytosol towards extended, confined motion at the cell membrane following phage induction. Thus, the bacterial dynamins are the first anti-phage system reported to delay host cell lysis and the last line of defense of a multilayered antiviral defense. DynA is therefore providing protective effects on the population, but not on single cell level.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453760" rel="alternate" title="A bacterial dynamin-like protein confers a novel phage resistance strategy on the population level in Bacillus subtilis (37 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453744</id><title>Global protein responses of multi-drug resistant plasmid containing Escherichia coli to ampicillin, cefotaxime, imipenem and ciprofloxacin (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.817189+00:00</updated><author><name>Anatte Margalit</name></author><author><name>James C. Carolan</name></author><author><name>Fiona Walsh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antimicrobial resistance (AMR) and multi-drug resistance (MDR) in pathogenic bacteria are frequently mediated by plasmids. However, plasmids do not exist in isolation but rather require the bacterial host interaction in order to produce the AMR phenotype. This study aimed to utilise mass spectrometry-based proteomics to reveal the plasmid and chromosomally derived protein profile of &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; under antimicrobial stress. This was achieved by comparing the proteomes of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; containing the MDR pEK499 plasmid, under ampicillin, cefotaxime, imipenem or ciprofloxacin stress with the proteomes of these bacteria grown in the absence of antimicrobial. Our analysis identified statistically significant differentially abundant proteins common to groups exposed to the β-lactam antimicrobials but not ciprofloxacin, indicating a β-lactam stress response to exposure from this class of drugs, irrespective of β-lactam resistance or susceptibility. These include ecotin and free methionine-R-sulfoxide reductase. These data also identified distinct differences in the cellular response to each β-lactam. Data arising from comparisons of the proteomes of ciprofloxacin-treated &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; and controls detected an increase in the relative abundance of proteins associated with ribosomes, translation, the TCA-cycle and several proteins associated with detoxification and a decrease in the relative abundances of proteins associated with stress response, including oxidative stress. We identified changes in proteins associated with persister formation in the presence of ciprofloxacin but not the β-lactams. The plasmid proteome differed across each treatment and did not follow the pattern of antimicrobial – AMR protein associations. For example, a relative increase in the amount of blaCTX-M-15 in the presence of cefotaxime and ciprofloxacin but not the other β-lactams, suggesting regulation of the blaCTX-M-15 protein production. The proteomic data from the this study provided novel insights into the proteins produced from the chromosome and plasmid under different antimicrobial stresses. These data also identified novel proteins not previously associated with AMR or antimicrobials responses in pathogens, which may well represent potential targets of AMR inhibition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453744" rel="alternate" title="Global protein responses of multi-drug resistant plasmid containing Escherichia coli to ampicillin, cefotaxime, imipenem and ciprofloxacin (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.27.453653</id><title>Spores and extracellular matrix components impart molecular order in Bacillus subtilis biofilms (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.817391+00:00</updated><author><name>David N Azulay</name></author><author><name>Oliver Späker</name></author><author><name>Mnar Ghrayeb</name></author><author><name>Michaela Wilsch-Bräuninger</name></author><author><name>Ernesto Scoppola</name></author><author><name>Manfred Burghammer</name></author><author><name>Ivo Zizak</name></author><author><name>Luca Bertinetti</name></author><author><name>Yael Politi</name></author><author><name>Liraz Chai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Biofilms are surface-associated soft microbial communities, which may be either detrimental or beneficial to their hosting environment. They develop from single cells into mature colonies, that are composed of cells and sometimes (in &lt;italic&gt;Firmicutes&lt;/italic&gt; phylum) spores, held together by an extracellular matrix (ECM) of secreted biomolecular components. Biofilm development is a dynamic process, during which cells organize into subgroups, creating functionally distinct regions in space. Specific examples of functional-spatial division in &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; biofilms include matrix and spore formation as well as water channels that form beneath wrinkles. An interesting question arising is whether the division of labor in biofilms is also reflected in the molecular-level order across whole biofilms. Using combined X-ray diffraction (XRD)/X-ray fluorescence (XRF), we studied the molecular order in intact biofilms across multiple length scales. We discovered that biofilms display a distinct spatio-temporal XRD signature that depends on highly ordered structures in spores and on cross β sheet structures in matrix components. Spore signal is found especially enhanced with water molecules and metal-ions signals along macroscopic wrinkles, known to act as water channels. Demonstrating &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; the link between molecular structures, metal ions distribution and division of labor across whole biofilms in time and space, this study provides new pivotal insight to the understanding biofilm development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.27.453653" rel="alternate" title="Spores and extracellular matrix components impart molecular order in Bacillus subtilis biofilms (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.30.454490</id><title>Roscovitine exacerbates Mycobacterium abscessus infection by reducing NADPH oxidase-dependent neutrophil trafficking (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.817691+00:00</updated><author><name>Vincent Le Moigne</name></author><author><name>Daniela Rodriguez Rincon</name></author><author><name>Simon Glatigny</name></author><author><name>Christian Dupont</name></author><author><name>Christelle Langevin</name></author><author><name>Amel Ait Ali Said</name></author><author><name>Stephen A Renshaw</name></author><author><name>Andres R Floto</name></author><author><name>Jean-Louis Herrmann</name></author><author><name>Audrey Bernut</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Persistent neutrophilic inflammation associated with chronic pulmonary infection causes progressive lung injury and eventually death in individuals with cystic fibrosis (CF), a genetic disease caused by bi-allelic mutations in the cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator (CFTR) gene. We therefore examined whether Roscovitine, a cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor that (in other conditions) reduces inflammation while promoting host defence, might provide a beneficial effect in the context of CF. Herein, using CFTR-depleted zebrafish larvae as an innovative vertebrate model of CF immuno-pathophysiology, combined with murine and human approaches, we sought to determine the effects of Roscovitine on innate immune responses to tissue injury and pathogens in CF condition. We show that Roscovitine exerts anti-inflammatory and pro-resolution effects in neutrophilic inflammation induced by infection or tail amputation in zebrafish. Roscovitine reduces overactive epithelial ROS-mediated neutrophil trafficking, by reducing DUOX2/NADPH-oxidase activity, and accelerates inflammation resolution by inducing neutrophil apoptosis and reverse migration. Importantly, while Roscovitine efficiently enhances intracellular bacterial killing of Mycobacterium abscessus in human CF macrophages ex vivo, we found that treatment with Roscovitine results in worse infection in mouse and zebrafish models. By interfering with DUOX2/NADPH oxidase-dependent ROS production, Roscovitine reduces the number of neutrophils at infection sites, and consequently compromises granuloma formation and maintenance, favouring extracellular multiplication of M. abscessus and more severe infection. Our findings bring important new understanding of the immune-targeted action of Roscovitine and have significant therapeutic implications for safety targeting inflammation in CF.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.30.454490" rel="alternate" title="Roscovitine exacerbates Mycobacterium abscessus infection by reducing NADPH oxidase-dependent neutrophil trafficking (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453710</id><title>A comprehensive collection of transcriptome data to support life cycle analysis of the poplar rust fungus Melampsora larici-populina (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.817978+00:00</updated><author><name>Pamela Guerillot</name></author><author><name>Emmanuelle Morin</name></author><author><name>Annegret Kohler</name></author><author><name>Clémentine Louet</name></author><author><name>Sébastien Duplessis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Melampsora larici-populina&lt;/italic&gt; is an obligate biotrophic plant pathogen responsible for the poplar rust disease. This fungus belongs to the taxonomical order Pucciniales and exhibits a complex heteroecious and macrocyclic life cycle, i.e. it has the capacity to infect two unrelated host plants, larch and poplar, and to form five distinct spore types through the year. The &lt;italic&gt;M. larici-populina&lt;/italic&gt; genome has been sequenced and annotated in 2011 and since, different transcriptomic analyses were conducted at different stages with oligoarrays and later on with RNA-Seq covering most of its life cycle. Here, we collected published transcriptome data for the poplar rust fungus, transposed them for the version 2 of the genome now available at the Joint Genome Institute Mycocosm website and performed normalization of different oligoarray datasets on one hand, and of RNA-Seq on the other hand. We report a comprehensive normalized dataset for this fungus, made available for the community, which allows life cycle transcriptomics analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453710" rel="alternate" title="A comprehensive collection of transcriptome data to support life cycle analysis of the poplar rust fungus Melampsora larici-populina (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453918</id><title>Anaerobic biodegradation of chloroform and dichloromethane with a Dehalobacter enrichment culture (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.818185+00:00</updated><author><name>Hao Wang</name></author><author><name>Rong Yu</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Webb</name></author><author><name>Peter Dollar</name></author><author><name>David L Freedman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chloroform (CF) and dichloromethane (DCM) are among the more commonly identified chlorinated aliphatic compounds found in contaminated soil and groundwater. Complete dechlorination of CF has been reported under anaerobic conditions by microbes that respire CF to DCM and others that biodegrade DCM. The objectives of this study were to ascertain if a commercially available bioaugmentation enrichment culture (KB-1&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; Plus) uses an oxidative or fermentative pathway for biodegradation of DCM; and to determine if the products from DCM biodegradation can support organohalide respiration of CF to DCM in the absence of an exogenous electron donor. In various treatments with the KB-1&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; Plus culture to which &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;C-CF was added, the predominant product was &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, indicating that oxidation is the predominant &lt;sub&gt; &lt;/sub&gt;pathway for DCM. Recovery of &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;C-DCM when biodegradation was still in progress confirmed that CF first undergoes reductive dechlorination to DCM. &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;C-labeled organic acids, including acetate and propionate, were also recovered, suggesting that synthesis of organic acids provides a sink for the electron equivalents from oxidation of DCM. When the culture was washed to remove organic acids from prior additions of exogenous electron donor and only CF and DCM were added, the culture completely dechlorinated CF. The total amount of DCM added was not sufficient to provide the electron equivalents needed to reduce CF to DCM. Thus, the additional reducing power came via the DCM generated from CF reduction. Nevertheless, the rate of CF consumption was considerably slower in comparison to treatments that received an exogenous electron donor.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453918" rel="alternate" title="Anaerobic biodegradation of chloroform and dichloromethane with a Dehalobacter enrichment culture (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453679</id><title>Plasmid supercoiling decreases during the dark phase in cyanobacteria: a clarification of the interpretation of chloroquine-agarose gels. (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.818360+00:00</updated><author><name>Salima Rüdiger</name></author><author><name>Anne Rediger</name></author><author><name>Adrian Kölsch</name></author><author><name>Dennis Dienst</name></author><author><name>Ilka Maria Axmann</name></author><author><name>Rainer Machné</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In cyanobacteria DNA supercoiling varies over the diurnal light/dark cycle and is integrated with the circadian transcription program and (Woelfle et al. [2007], Vijayan et al. [2009], PNAS). Specifically, Woelfle et al. have reported that DNA supercoiling of an endogenous plasmid became progressively higher during prolonged dark phases in Synechococcus elongatus PCC 7942. This is counterintuitive, since higher levels of negative DNA supercoiling are commonly associated with exponential growth and high metabolic flux. Vijayan et al. then have reverted the interpretation of plasmid mobility on agarose gels supplemented with chloroquine diphosphate (CQ), but not further discussed the differences. Here, we set out to clarify this open issue in cyanobacterial DNA supercoiling dynamics. We first re-capitulate Keller's band counting method (1975, PNAS) using CQ instead of ethidium bromide as the intercalating agent. A 500x-1000x higher CQ concentration is required in the DNA relaxation reaction (topoisomerase I) than in the agarose gel buffer to quench all negative supercoiling of pUC19 extracted from Escherichia coli. This is likely due to the dependence of both, the DNA binding affinity of CQ and the induced DNA unwinding angle, on the ionic strength of the buffer. Lower levels of CQ were required to fully relax in vivo pUC19 supercoiling than were used by Woelfle et al. Next, we analyzed the in vivo supercoiling of endogenous plasmids of Synechocystis sp. PCC 6803, at two different CQ concentrations. This clearly indicates that negative supercoiling of plasmids does not increase but decreases in the dark phase, and progressively decreases further in prolonged darkness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453679" rel="alternate" title="Plasmid supercoiling decreases during the dark phase in cyanobacteria: a clarification of the interpretation of chloroquine-agarose gels. (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>