<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.253007+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.26.457786</id><title>Pseudomonas aeruginosa differentiates substrate rigidity using retraction of type IV pili (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.253700+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthias D. Koch</name></author><author><name>Endao Han</name></author><author><name>Joshua W. Shaevitz</name></author><author><name>Zemer Gitai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ability of eukaryotic cells to differentiate substrate stiffness is fundamental for many processes such as the development of stem cells into mature tissue. Here, we establish that bacteria feel their microenvironment in a similar manner. We show that &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; actively probes and measures substrate stiffness using type IV pili (TFP). The activity of the major virulence factor regulator Vfr is peaked with stiffness in a physiologically important range between 0.1 kPa (mucus) and 1000 kPa (cartilage). The local concentration of PilA at the base of dynamic TFP changes during extension and retraction in a surface dependent manner due to slow PilA diffusion in the cell membrane. Traction force measurements reveal that TFP retraction deforms even stiff substrates. Modeling of the measured substrate deformation and optical tweezers experiments suggest that TFP adhere at the tip only. Informed by these experimental results, we developed a model that describes substrate stiffness dependent dynamics of the polar PilA concentration which are quantitatively consistent with the transcriptional response to stiffness. Manipulating the ATPase activity of the TFP motors changes the TFP extension and retraction velocities and consequently the PilA concentration dynamics in a manner that is predictive of the experimental stiffness response. This work points to the use of a competition between PilA diffusion and TFP extension-retraction as a molecular shear rheometer. Our results highlight that stiffness sensing is a conserved property between the kingdoms of life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.26.457786" rel="alternate" title="Pseudomonas aeruginosa differentiates substrate rigidity using retraction of type IV pili (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>