<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.808408+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463556</id><title>Large-scale discovery of candidate type VI secretion effectors with antibacterial activity (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.808827+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Martin Geller</name></author><author><name>David Zlotkin</name></author><author><name>Asaf Levy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Type VI secretion systems (T6SS) are common bacterial contractile injection systems that inject toxic effector proteins into neighboring cells. Effector discovery is generally done manually, and computational approaches used for effector discovery depend on genetic linkage to T6SS genes and/or sequence similarity to known effectors. We bioinformatically investigated T6SS in more than 11,832 genomes of Gram negative bacteria. We found that T6SS encoding bacteria are host-associated and pathogenic, enriched in specific human and plant tissues, while depleted in marine, soil, and engineered environments. Analysis of T6SS cores with C-terminal domains ("evolved" cores) showed "evolved" HCP are rare, overwhelmingly encoded in orphan operons, and are largely restricted to Escherichia. Using the wealth of data generated from our bioinformatic analysis, we developed two algorithms for large-scale discovery of T6SS effector proteins (T6Es). We experimentally validated ten putative antibacterial T6SS effector proteins and one cognate immunity gene from a diverse species. This study provides a systematic genomic perspective of the role of the T6SS in nature, a thorough analysis of T6E evolution and genomic properties, and discovery of a large number of candidate T6Es using new approaches.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463556" rel="alternate" title="Large-scale discovery of candidate type VI secretion effectors with antibacterial activity (14 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.06.463453</id><title>Multiple regulatory mechanisms control the production of CmrRST, an atypical signal transduction system in Clostridioides difficile (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.809152+00:00</updated><author><name>Elizabeth M. Garrett</name></author><author><name>Anchal Mehra</name></author><author><name>Ognjen Sekulovic</name></author><author><name>Rita Tamayo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Clostridioides difficile&lt;/italic&gt;, an intestinal pathogen and leading cause of nosocomial infection, exhibits extensive phenotypic heterogeneity through phase variation by site-specific recombination. The signal transduction system CmrRST, which encodes two response regulators (CmrR and CmrT) and a sensor kinase (CmrS), impacts &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt; cell and colony morphology, surface and swimming motility, biofilm formation, and virulence in an animal model. CmrRST is subject to phase variation through site-specific recombination and reversible inversion of the ‘&lt;italic&gt;cmr&lt;/italic&gt; switch’, and expression of &lt;italic&gt;cmrRST&lt;/italic&gt; is also regulated by c-di-GMP through a riboswitch. The goal of this study was to determine how the &lt;italic&gt;cmr&lt;/italic&gt; switch and c-di-GMP work together to regulate &lt;italic&gt;cmrRST&lt;/italic&gt; expression. We generated “phase locked” strains by mutating key residues in the right inverted repeat flanking the &lt;italic&gt;cmr&lt;/italic&gt; switch. Phenotypic characterization of these phase locked &lt;italic&gt;cmr&lt;/italic&gt;-ON and -OFF strains demonstrates that they cannot switch between rough and smooth colony morphologies, respectively, or other CmrRST-associated phenotypes. Manipulation of c-di-GMP levels in these mutants showed that c-di-GMP promotes &lt;italic&gt;cmrRST&lt;/italic&gt; expression and associated phenotypes independent of &lt;italic&gt;cmr&lt;/italic&gt; switch orientation. We identified multiple promoters controlling &lt;italic&gt;cmrRST&lt;/italic&gt; transcription, including one within the ON orientation of &lt;italic&gt;cmr&lt;/italic&gt; switch and another that is positively autoregulated by CmrR. Overall, this work reveals a complex regulatory network that governs &lt;italic&gt;cmrRST&lt;/italic&gt; expression and a unique intersection of phase variation and c-di-GMP signaling. These findings suggest that multiple environmental signals impact the production of this signaling transduction system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Clostridioides difficile&lt;/italic&gt; is a leading cause of hospital-acquired intestinal infections in the U.S. The CmrRST signal transduction system controls numerous physiological traits and processes in &lt;italic&gt;C. difficile&lt;/italic&gt;, including cell and colony morphology, motility, biofilm formation, and virulence. Here we define the complex, multi-level regulation of &lt;italic&gt;cmrRST&lt;/italic&gt; expression, including stochastic control through phase variation, modulation by the second messenger c-di-GMP, and positive autoregulation by CmrR. The results of this study suggest that multiple, distinct environmental stimuli and selective pressures must be integrated to appropriately control &lt;italic&gt;cmrRST&lt;/italic&gt; expression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.06.463453" rel="alternate" title="Multiple regulatory mechanisms control the production of CmrRST, an atypical signal transduction system in Clostridioides difficile (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463515</id><title>Genomic and antigenic diversity of carried Klebsiella pneumoniae isolates mirrors that of invasive isolates in Blantyre, Malawi (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.809360+00:00</updated><author><name>Joseph M Lewis</name></author><author><name>Madalitso Mphasa</name></author><author><name>Rachel Banda</name></author><author><name>Mathew A Beale</name></author><author><name>Jane Mallewa</name></author><author><name>Eva Heinz</name></author><author><name>Nicholas R Thomson</name></author><author><name>Nicholas A Feasey</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Klebsiella pneumoniae is an antimicrobial resistance (AMR) associated pathogen of global importance, and polyvalent vaccines targeting K. pneumoniae O-antigens are in development. Genomes from sub-Saharan Africa (sSA) are underrepresented in global sequencing efforts. We therefore carried out a genomic analysis of extended-spectrum beta-lactamase (ESBL)-producing K. pneumoniae complex isolates colonising adults in Blantyre, Malawi, placed these isolates in a global genomic context, and compared colonising to invasive isolates from the main public hospital in Blantyre. 

203 isolates from stool and rectal swabs from adults were whole-genome sequenced and compared to a publicly available multicountry collection of 484 K. pneumoniae genomes sampled to cover maximum diversity of the species, 150 previously sequenced Malawian and 66 Kenyan isolates from blood or sterile sites. We inferred phylogenetic relationships and analysed the diversity of genetic loci linked to AMR, virulence, capsule (K-) and LPS O-antigen (O-types). 

We find that the diversity of Malawian Klebsiella isolates is representative of the species population structure, but with local success and expansion of sequence types (STs) ST14, ST15, ST340 and ST307. Siderophore and hypermucoidy genes were more frequent in invasive versus carriage isolates (present in 13% vs 1%, p &amp;lt; 0.001) but still generally lacking in most invasive isolates. The population structure and distribution of O-antigen types was similar in Malawian invasive and carriage isolates, with O4 being more common in Malawian isolates (14%) than in previously published studies (2-5%). We conclude that host factors, pathogen opportunity or alternate virulence loci not linked to invasive disease elsewhere are likely to be the major determinants of invasive disease in Malawi. Distinct ST and O-type distributions in Malawi highlights the need for geographically aware sampling to robustly define secular trends in Klebsiella diversity. Colonising and invasive isolates in Blantyre are similar and hence O-typing of colonising Klebsiella isolates may be a rapid and cost-effective approach to describe global diversity and guide vaccine development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463515" rel="alternate" title="Genomic and antigenic diversity of carried Klebsiella pneumoniae isolates mirrors that of invasive isolates in Blantyre, Malawi (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.06.463450</id><title>High throughput identification of genes conferring resistance or sensitivity to toxic effectors delivered by the type VI secretion system (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.809575+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven J. Hersch</name></author><author><name>Rehnuma Tabassum Sejuty</name></author><author><name>Kevin Manera</name></author><author><name>Tao G. Dong</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The type six secretion system (T6SS) is a prevalent bacterial weapon delivering toxic effector proteins into nearby competitors. In addition to immunity genes that protect against a particular effector, alternate yet crucial nonspecific defences have also recently been identified. To systematically identify genes influencing T6SS susceptibility in numerous species, we designed a Tn-Seq-based competition assay. Combined with follow-up analyses using &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;V. cholerae&lt;/italic&gt; gene knockout collections, we demonstrate that our Tn-Seq competition technique can be used to identify both immunity and non-immunity defences against the T6SS. We also identify &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; proteins that facilitate T6SS-mediated cell death, including metabolic genes such as &lt;italic&gt;cyaA&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;gltA,&lt;/italic&gt; where mutant strains were resistant to attack. Our findings act as a proof-of-concept for the technique while also illuminating novel genes of interest. Since Tn-Seq can be applied in numerous species, our method has broad potential for identifying diverse T6SS defence genes across genomes in a high-throughput manner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The type six secretion system (T6SS) is a molecular poison-tipped spear that bacteria use to kill nearby competitors. To prevent self killing, they use antitoxins called immunity genes that specifically neutralize the poisons. Beyond immunity genes, multiple additional defences have recently been discovered but there are likely many more across the genomes of diverse species. To help discover these novel mechanisms, we designed a high-throughput method that can be used in numerous different species to rapidly identify genes involved in sensitivity to T6SS attacks. Using T6SS ‘killers’ delivering individual poisons and two commonly studied ‘prey’ bacteria, we show proof-of-principle that the technique can discover proteins that make the prey cells more resistant or sensitive to particular poisons. This will greatly improve the speed at which genes influencing the T6SS can be identified and selected for further study in follow-up analyses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.06.463450" rel="alternate" title="High throughput identification of genes conferring resistance or sensitivity to toxic effectors delivered by the type VI secretion system (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.06.463447</id><title>Genomic and phenotypic characterization of Pseudomonas hygromyciniae, a novel bacterial species discovered from a commercially purchased antibiotic (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.809814+00:00</updated><author><name>Timothy L. Turner</name></author><author><name>Sumitra D. Mitra</name></author><author><name>Travis J. Kochan</name></author><author><name>Nathan B. Pincus</name></author><author><name>Marine Lebrun-Corbin</name></author><author><name>Bettina Cheung</name></author><author><name>Samuel W. Gatesy</name></author><author><name>Tania Afzal</name></author><author><name>Egon A. Ozer</name></author><author><name>Alan R. Hauser</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A purchased lot of the antibiotic hygromycin B was found to be contaminated with a novel bacterial species, which we designate &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas hygromyciniae&lt;/italic&gt;. Characteristics of &lt;italic&gt;P. hygromyciniae&lt;/italic&gt; include its ability to use a variety of compounds as carbon sources, its pathogenicity towards lettuce and &lt;italic&gt;Galleria mellonella&lt;/italic&gt;, and its ability to inhibit the growth of an &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; strain. &lt;italic&gt;P. hygromyciniae&lt;/italic&gt; is unlikely to be a human pathogen, as it did not survive at 37 °C and was not cytotoxic towards a mammalian cell line. The &lt;italic&gt;P. hygromyciniae&lt;/italic&gt; strain harbors a novel 250 kb megaplasmid which confers resistance to hygromycin B and contains numerous other genes predicted to encode replication and conjugation machinery. These findings indicate that commercially manufactured antibiotics represent another extreme environment that may support the growth of novel bacterial species.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Microbial ecologists have surveyed numerous natural and manmade environments in search of new microbial species. In some instances, these microbes are discovered in harsh conditions, such as deep-sea vents, and their discovery leads to better understanding of how microbes adapt to their environment. Here, we have discovered a new species of bacteria from an extreme manmade environment: a lyophilized, commercially available bottle of the antibiotic hygromycin B.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.06.463447" rel="alternate" title="Genomic and phenotypic characterization of Pseudomonas hygromyciniae, a novel bacterial species discovered from a commercially purchased antibiotic (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463504</id><title>PBP1 of Staphylococcus aureus has multiple essential functions in cell division (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.810100+00:00</updated><author><name>Katarzyna Wacnik</name></author><author><name>Vincenzo A Rao</name></author><author><name>Xinyue Chen</name></author><author><name>Lucia Lafage</name></author><author><name>Manuel Pazos</name></author><author><name>Simon Booth</name></author><author><name>Waldemar Vollmer</name></author><author><name>Jamie K Hobbs</name></author><author><name>Richard J Lewis</name></author><author><name>Simon J Foster</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial cell division is a complex process requiring the coordination of multiple components, to allow the appropriate spatial and temporal control of septum formation and cell scission. Peptidoglycan (PG) is the major structural component of the septum, and our recent studies in the human pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/italic&gt; have revealed a complex, multi–stage PG architecture that develops during septation. Penicillin binding proteins (PBPs) are essential for the final steps of PG biosynthesis — their transpeptidase activity links together the peptide sidechain of nascent glycan strands together. PBP1 is required for cell division in &lt;italic&gt;S. aureus&lt;/italic&gt; and here we demonstrate that it has multiple essential functions associated with its enzymatic activity and as a regulator of division. Loss of PBP1, or just its C–terminal PASTA domains, results in cessation of division at the point of septal plate formation. The PASTA domains can bind PG and thus coordinate the cell division process. The transpeptidase activity of PBP1 is also essential but its loss leads to a strikingly different phenotype of thickened and aberrant septa, which is phenocopied by the morphological effects of adding the PBP1–specific β–lactam, meropenem. Together these results lead to a model for septal PG synthesis where PBP1 enzyme activity is responsible for the characteristic architecture of the septum and PBP1 protein molecules coordinate cell division allowing septal plate formation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463504" rel="alternate" title="PBP1 of Staphylococcus aureus has multiple essential functions in cell division (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463499</id><title>Genomic and metabolic adaptations of biofilms to ecological windows of opportunities in glacier-fed streams (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.810438+00:00</updated><author><name>Susheel Bhanu Busi</name></author><author><name>Massimo Bourquin</name></author><author><name>Stilianos Fodelianakis</name></author><author><name>Gregoire Michoud</name></author><author><name>Tyler J Kohler</name></author><author><name>Hannes Peter</name></author><author><name>Paraskevi Pramateftaki</name></author><author><name>Michail Styllas</name></author><author><name>Matteo Tolosano</name></author><author><name>Vincent De Staercke</name></author><author><name>Martina Schon</name></author><author><name>Laura de Nies</name></author><author><name>Ramona Marasco</name></author><author><name>Daniele Daffonchio</name></author><author><name>Leila Ezzat</name></author><author><name>Paul Wilmes</name></author><author><name>Tom J Battin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microorganisms dominate life in cryospheric ecosystems. In glacier-fed streams (GFSs), ecological windows of opportunities allow complex microbial biofilms to develop and transiently form the basis of the food web, thereby controlling key ecosystem processes. Here, using high-resolution metagenomics, we unravel strategies that allow biofilms to seize this opportunity in an ecosystem otherwise characterized by harsh environmental conditions. We found a diverse microbiome spanning the entire tree of life and including a rich virome. Various and co-existing energy acquisition pathways point to diverse niches and the simultaneous exploitation of available resources, likely fostering the establishment of complex biofilms in GFSs during windows of opportunity. The wide occurrence of rhodopsins across metagenome-assembled genomes (MAGs), besides chlorophyll, highlights the role of solar energy capture in these biofilms. Concomitantly, internal carbon and nutrient cycling between photoautotrophs and heterotrophs may help overcome constraints imposed by the high oligotrophy in GFSs. MAGs also revealed mechanisms potentially protecting bacteria against low temperatures and high UV-radiation. The selective pressure of the GFS environment is further highlighted by the phylogenomic analysis, differentiating the representatives of the genus Polaromonas, an important component of the GFS microbiome, from those found in other ecosystems. Our findings reveal key genomic underpinnings of adaptive traits that contribute to the success of complex biofilms to exploit environmental opportunities in GFSs, now rapidly changing owing to global warming.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463499" rel="alternate" title="Genomic and metabolic adaptations of biofilms to ecological windows of opportunities in glacier-fed streams (4 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463549</id><title>Evolutionary sweeps of subviral parasites and their phage host bring unique parasite variants and disappearance of a phage CRISPR-Cas system (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.810833+00:00</updated><author><name>Angus Angermeyer</name></author><author><name>Stephanie G. Hays</name></author><author><name>Maria H.T. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Fatema-tuz Johura</name></author><author><name>Marzia Sultana</name></author><author><name>Munirul Alam</name></author><author><name>Kimberley D. Seed</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Vibrio cholerae&lt;/italic&gt; is a significant threat to global public health in part due to its propensity for large-scale evolutionary sweeps where lineages emerge and are replaced. These sweeps may originate from the Bay of Bengal where bacteriophage predation and the evolution of anti-phage counter defenses is a recurring theme. The bacteriophage ICP1 is a key predator of epidemic &lt;italic&gt;V. cholerae&lt;/italic&gt; and is notable for acquiring a CRISPR-Cas system to combat PLE, a defensive subviral parasite encoded by its &lt;italic&gt;V. cholerae&lt;/italic&gt; host. Here we describe the discovery of five previously unknown PLE variants, including one found during recent surveillance of patient samples in Bangladesh. We also observed a lineage sweep of PLE negative &lt;italic&gt;V. cholerae&lt;/italic&gt; occurring within a patient population in under a year which coincided with a loss of ICP1’s CRISPR-Cas system. These findings reinforce the importance of surveillance to better understand the selective pressures that drive pandemic cholera.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463549" rel="alternate" title="Evolutionary sweeps of subviral parasites and their phage host bring unique parasite variants and disappearance of a phage CRISPR-Cas system (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463523</id><title>Genomic analysis of extended-spectrum beta-lactamase (ESBL) producing Escherichia coli colonising adults in Blantyre, Malawi reveals previously undescribed diversity (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.811151+00:00</updated><author><name>Joseph M. Lewis</name></author><author><name>Madalitso Mphasa</name></author><author><name>Rachel Banda</name></author><author><name>Mathew A. Beale</name></author><author><name>Jane Mallewa</name></author><author><name>Adam P. Roberts</name></author><author><name>Eva Heinz</name></author><author><name>Nicholas R. Thomson</name></author><author><name>Nicholas A Feasey</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; is a ubiquitous bacterial species, associated with drug resistant infections; hundreds of thousands of genomes are now available, but are biased towards high-income countries and clinical isolates. Data from sub-Saharan Africa (sSA) are underrepresented in global sequencing efforts and may represent a major source of genetic diversity with respect to transmissible antimicrobial resistance (AMR). We carried out a genomic investigation of extended-spectrum beta-lactamase (ESBL)-producing &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; colonising adults in Blantyre, Malawi to assess the diversity and AMR determinants and to place these isolates in the context of globally available genomes. We carried out short-read whole-genome sequencing of 473 colonising ESBL &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; isolated from stool and placed them in the context of a previous curated species wide collection of 10,146 isolates using the popPUNK clustering algorithm and by constructing a core gene phylogeny. The most frequently identified STs in Malawian isolates were the globally successful ST131 and ST410, and &lt;italic&gt;bla&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;CTX-M&lt;/sub&gt; were the dominant ESBL genes, mirroring global trends. However, 37% of Malawian isolates did not cluster with any isolates in the global collection, and the core gene phylogeny was consistent with local subclades including in ST410 and several phylogroup A lineages. Apparent undescribed diversity in Malawian &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; could be due to local selection pressures or sampling biases in global &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; collections. Taking a one health approach to further sampling of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; from Malawi and sSA, and principled incorporation into unbiased global collections is necessary to understand local, regional and global transmission of both &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; and priority AMR genes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;All data and code to replicate this analysis is available as the &lt;italic&gt;blantyreESBL&lt;/italic&gt; v1.0.0 R package (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5554082"&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5554082&lt;/ext-link&gt;) available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/joelewis101/blantyreESBL"&gt;https://github.com/joelewis101/blantyreESBL&lt;/ext-link&gt;. Reads from all isolates sequenced as part of this study have been deposited in the European Nucleotide Archive, and accession numbers (as well as accession numbers of publicly available genomes used in this analysis) are provided in the R package.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463523" rel="alternate" title="Genomic analysis of extended-spectrum beta-lactamase (ESBL) producing Escherichia coli colonising adults in Blantyre, Malawi reveals previously undescribed diversity (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>