<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.464461+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444942</id><title>Mosquito-bacteria interactions during larval development trigger metabolic changes with carry-over effects on adult fitness (25 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.465122+00:00</updated><author><name>Émilie Giraud</name></author><author><name>Hugo Varet</name></author><author><name>Rachel Legendre</name></author><author><name>Odile Sismeiro</name></author><author><name>Fabien Aubry</name></author><author><name>Stéphanie Dabo</name></author><author><name>Laura B. Dickson</name></author><author><name>Claire Valiente Moro</name></author><author><name>Louis Lambrechts</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In animals with distinct life stages such as holometabolous insects, adult phenotypic variation is often shaped by the environment of immature stages, including their interactions with microbes colonizing larval habitats. Such carry-over effects were previously observed for several adult traits of the mosquito &lt;italic&gt;Aedes aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; after larval exposure to different bacteria, but the mechanistic underpinnings are unknown. Here, we investigated the molecular changes triggered by gnotobiotic larval exposure to different bacteria in &lt;italic&gt;Ae. aegypti&lt;/italic&gt;. We initially screened a panel of 16 bacterial isolates from natural mosquito breeding sites to determine their ability to influence adult life-history traits. We subsequently focused on four bacterial isolates (belonging to &lt;italic&gt;Flavobacterium, Lysobacter, Paenibacillus&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;Enterobacteriaceae&lt;/italic&gt;) with significant carry-over effects on adult survival and found that they were associated with distinct transcriptomic profiles throughout mosquito development. Moreover, we detected carry-over effects at the level of gene expression for the &lt;italic&gt;Flavobacterium&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Paenibacillus&lt;/italic&gt; isolates. The most prominent transcriptomic changes in gnotobiotic larvae reflected a profound remodeling of lipid metabolism, which translated into phenotypic differences in lipid storage and starvation resistance at the adult stage. Together, our findings indicate that larval exposure to environmental bacteria trigger substantial physiological changes that impact adult fitness, uncovering a mechanism underlying carry-over effects of mosquito-bacteria interactions during larval development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444942" rel="alternate" title="Mosquito-bacteria interactions during larval development trigger metabolic changes with carry-over effects on adult fitness (25 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.16.444350</id><title>OmpF Downregulation Mediated by Sigma E or OmpR Activation Confers Cefalexin Resistance in Escherichia coli in the Absence of Acquired β-Lactamases (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.465569+00:00</updated><author><name>Maryam Alzayn</name></author><author><name>Punyawee Dulyayangkul</name></author><author><name>Naphat Satapoomin</name></author><author><name>Kate J. Heesom</name></author><author><name>Matthew B. Avison</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cefalexin is a widely used 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; generation cephalosporin, and resistance in &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; is caused by Extended-Spectrum (e.g. CTX-M) and AmpC β-lactamase production and therefore frequently coincides with 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; generation cephalosporin resistance. However, we have recently identified large numbers of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; isolates from human infections, and from cattle, where cefalexin resistance is not β-lactamase mediated. Here we show, by studying laboratory selected mutants, clinical isolates, and isolates from cattle, that OmpF porin disruption or downregulation is a major cause of cefalexin resistance in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;. Importantly, we identify multiple regulatory mutations that cause OmpF downregulation. In addition to mutation of &lt;italic&gt;ompR&lt;/italic&gt;, already known to downregulate OmpF and OmpC porin production, we find that &lt;italic&gt;rseA&lt;/italic&gt; mutation, which strongly activates the Sigma E regulon, greatly increasing DegP production, which degrades OmpF, OmpC and OmpA porins. Furthermore, we reveal that mutations affecting lipopolysaccharide structure, exemplified by the loss of GmhB, essential for lipopolysaccharide heptosylation, also modestly activate DegP production, resulting in OmpF degradation. Remarkably, given the critical importance attached to such systems for normal &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; physiology, we find evidence for DegP-mediated OmpF downregulation, &lt;italic&gt;gmhB&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;rseA&lt;/italic&gt; loss of function mutation in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; isolates derived from human infections. Finally, we show that these regulatory mutations enhance the ability of group 1 CTX-M β-lactamase to confer reduced carbapenem susceptibility, particularly those mutations that cause OmpC in addition to OmpF downregulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.16.444350" rel="alternate" title="OmpF Downregulation Mediated by Sigma E or OmpR Activation Confers Cefalexin Resistance in Escherichia coli in the Absence of Acquired β-Lactamases (16 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444929</id><title>The gatekeeper of Yersinia type III secretion is under RNA thermometer control (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.467081+00:00</updated><author><name>Stephan Pienkoß</name></author><author><name>Soheila Javadi</name></author><author><name>Paweena Chaoprasid</name></author><author><name>Thomas Nolte</name></author><author><name>Christian Twittenhoff</name></author><author><name>Petra Dersch</name></author><author><name>Franz Narberhaus</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many bacterial pathogens use a type III secretion system (T3SS) as molecular syringe to inject effector proteins into the host cell. In the foodborne pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Yersinia pseudotuberculosis,&lt;/italic&gt; delivery of the secreted effector protein cocktail through the T3SS depends on YopN, a molecular gatekeeper that controls access to the secretion channel from the bacterial cytoplasm. Here, we show that several checkpoints adjust &lt;italic&gt;yopN&lt;/italic&gt; expression to virulence conditions. A dominant cue is the host body temperature. A temperature of 37 °C is known to induce the RNA thermometer (RNAT)-dependent synthesis of LcrF, a transcription factor that activates expression of the entire T3SS regulon. Here, we uncovered a second layer of temperature control. We show that another RNAT silences translation of the &lt;italic&gt;yopN&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA at low environmental temperatures. The long and short 5’-untranslated region of both cellular &lt;italic&gt;yopN&lt;/italic&gt; isoforms fold into a similar secondary structure that blocks ribosome binding. The hairpin structure with an internal loop melts at 37 °C and thereby permits formation of the translation initiation complex as shown by mutational analysis, &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; structure probing and toeprinting methods. Importantly, we demonstrate the physiological relevance of the RNAT in the faithful control of type III secretion by using a point-mutated thermostable RNAT variant with a trapped SD sequence. Abrogated YopN production in this strain led to unrestricted effector protein secretion into the medium, bacterial growth arrest and delayed translocation into eukaryotic host cells. Cumulatively, our results show that substrate delivery by the &lt;italic&gt;Yersinia&lt;/italic&gt; T3SS is under hierarchical surveillance of two RNATs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Temperature serves as reliable external cue for pathogenic bacteria to recognize the entry into or exit from a warm-blooded host. At the molecular level, a temperature of 37 °C induces various virulence-related processes that manipulate host cell physiology. Here, we demonstrate the temperature-dependent synthesis of the secretion regulator YopN in the foodborne pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Yersinia pseudotuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt;, a close relative of &lt;italic&gt;Yersinia pestis&lt;/italic&gt;. YopN blocks secretion of effector proteins through the type III secretion system unless host cell contact is established. Temperature-specific regulation relies on an RNA structure in the 5’-untranslated region of the &lt;italic&gt;yopN&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA, referred to as RNA thermometer, which allows ribosome binding and thus translation initiation only at an infection-relevant temperature of 37 °C. A mutated variant of the thermosensor resulting in a closed conformation prevented synthesis of the molecular gatekeeper YopN and led to permanent secretion and defective translocation of virulence factors into host cells. We suggest that the RNA thermometer plays a critical role in adjusting the optimal cellular concentration of a surveillance factor that maintains the controlled translocation of virulence factors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444929" rel="alternate" title="The gatekeeper of Yersinia type III secretion is under RNA thermometer control (14 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444594</id><title>Prophylactic inhibition of colonization by Streptococcus pneumoniae with the secondary bile acid metabolite deoxycholic acid (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.467322+00:00</updated><author><name>Jorge E. Vidal</name></author><author><name>Meagan N. Wier</name></author><author><name>Uriel Angulo-Zamudio</name></author><author><name>Erin McDevitt</name></author><author><name>Ana G. Jop Vidal</name></author><author><name>Babek Alibayov</name></author><author><name>Anna Scasny</name></author><author><name>Sandy M. Wong</name></author><author><name>Brian J. Akerley</name></author><author><name>Larry S. McDaniel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Streptococcus &lt;italic&gt;pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; (Spn) colonizes the nasopharynx of children and the elderly but also kills millions worldwide yearly. The secondary bile acid metabolite, deoxycholic acid (DoC), affects the viability of human pathogens but also plays multiple roles in host physiology. We assessed &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; the antimicrobial activity of DoC and investigated its potential to eradicate Spn colonization using an &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; model of human nasopharyngeal colonization and an &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; mouse model of colonization. At a physiological concentration DoC (0.5 mg/ml; 1.27 mM) killed all tested Spn strains (N=48) two h post-inoculation. The &lt;italic&gt;ex-vivo&lt;/italic&gt; model of nasopharyngeal colonization showed that DoC eradicated colonization by Spn strains as soon as 10 min post-exposure. The mechanism of action did not involve activation of autolysis since the autolysis-defective double mutants Δ&lt;italic&gt;lytA&lt;/italic&gt;Δ&lt;italic&gt;lytC&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;ΔspxBΔlctO&lt;/italic&gt; were as susceptible to DoC as was the wild-type (WT). Oral streptococcal species (N=20), however, were not susceptible to DoC (0.5 mg/ml). Unlike trimethoprim, whose spontaneous resistance frequency (srF) for TIGR4 or EF3030 was ≥1×10&lt;sup&gt;−9&lt;/sup&gt;, no spontaneous resistance was observed with DoC (srF≥1×10&lt;sup&gt;−12&lt;/sup&gt;). Finally, the efficacy of DoC to eradicate Spn colonization was assessed &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; using a topical route via intranasal (i.n.) administration and as a prophylactic treatment. Mice challenged with Spn EF3030 carried a median of 4.05×10&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; cfu/ml four days post-inoculation compared to 6.67×10&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; cfu/ml for mice treated with DoC. Mice in the prophylactic group had a ∼99% reduction of the pneumococcal density (median, 2.61 ×10&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; cfu/ml). Thus, DoC, an endogenous human bile salt, has therapeutic potential against Spn.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444594" rel="alternate" title="Prophylactic inhibition of colonization by Streptococcus pneumoniae with the secondary bile acid metabolite deoxycholic acid (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.444901</id><title>Proteome, bioinformatic and functional analyses reveal a distinct and conserved metabolic pathway for bile salt degradation in the Sphingomonadaceae (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.467759+00:00</updated><author><name>Franziska Maria Feller</name></author><author><name>Lars Wöhlbrand</name></author><author><name>Johannes Holert</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Schnaars</name></author><author><name>Lea Elsner</name></author><author><name>William W. Mohn</name></author><author><name>Ralf Rabus</name></author><author><name>Bodo Philipp</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bile salts are amphiphilic steroids with a C&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt; carboxylic side chain with digestive functions in vertebrates. Upon excretion, they are degraded by environmental bacteria. Degradation of the bile-salt steroid skeleton resembles the well-studied pathway for other steroids like testosterone, while specific differences occur during side-chain degradation and the initiating transformations of the steroid skeleton. Of the latter, two variants via either Δ&lt;sup&gt;1,4&lt;/sup&gt;- or Δ&lt;sup&gt;4,6&lt;/sup&gt;-3-ketostructures of the steroid skeleton exist for 7-hydroxy bile salts. While the Δ&lt;sup&gt;1,4&lt;/sup&gt;- variant is well-known from many model organisms, the Δ&lt;sup&gt;4,6&lt;/sup&gt;-variant involving a 7-hydroxysteroid dehydratase as key enzyme has not been systematically studied. Here, combined proteomic, bioinformatic and functional analyses of the Δ&lt;sup&gt;4,6&lt;/sup&gt;-variant in &lt;italic&gt;Sphingobium&lt;/italic&gt; sp. strain Chol11 were performed. They revealed a degradation of the steroid rings similar to the Δ&lt;sup&gt;1,4&lt;/sup&gt;-variant except for the elimination of the 7-OH as key difference. In contrast, differential production of the respective proteins revealed a putative gene cluster for side-chain degradation encoding a CoA-ligase, an acyl-CoA dehydrogenase, a Rieske monooxygenase, and an amidase, but lacking most canonical genes known from other steroid-degrading bacteria. Bioinformatic analyses predicted the Δ&lt;sup&gt;4,6&lt;/sup&gt;-variant to be widespread among the &lt;italic&gt;Sphingomonadaceae&lt;/italic&gt;, which was verified for three type strains which also have the predicted side-chain degradation cluster. A second amidase in the side-chain degradation gene cluster of strain Chol11 was shown to cleave conjugated bile salts while having low similarity to known bile-salt hydrolases. This study signifies members of the &lt;italic&gt;Sphingomonadaceae&lt;/italic&gt; remarkably well-adapted to the utilization of bile salts via a partially distinct metabolic pathway.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.444901" rel="alternate" title="Proteome, bioinformatic and functional analyses reveal a distinct and conserved metabolic pathway for bile salt degradation in the Sphingomonadaceae (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444596</id><title>Biochemical Barriers on the Path to Ocean Anoxia? (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.468608+00:00</updated><author><name>Stephen Giovannoni</name></author><author><name>Francis Chan</name></author><author><name>Edward Davis</name></author><author><name>Curtis Deutsch</name></author><author><name>Sarah Wolf</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The kinetics of microbial respiration suggest that, if excess organic matter is present, oxygen should fall to nanomolar levels, in the range of the Michaelis-Menten constants (K&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt;). Yet even in many biologically productive coastal regions, lowest observed O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; concentrations often remain several orders of magnitude higher than respiratory K&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt; values. We propose the &lt;italic&gt;Hypoxic Barrier Hypothesis&lt;/italic&gt; (HBH) to explain this apparent discrepancy. The HBH postulates that oxidative enzymes involved in organic matter catabolism are kinetically limited by O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; at concentrations far higher than the thresholds for respiration. We found support for the HBH in a meta-analysis of 1137 O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; K&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt; values reported in the literature: the median value for terminal respiratory oxidases was 350 nM, but for other oxidase types the median value was 67 μM. The HBH directs our attention to the kinetic properties of an important class of oxygen-dependent reactions that could help explain the trajectories of ocean ecosystems experiencing O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; stress.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Declining ocean oxygen associated with global warming and climate change is impacting marine ecosystems across scales from microscopic planktonic communities to global fisheries. We report a fundamental dichotomy in the affinity of enzymes for oxygen. The importance of this observation has yet to be fully assessed, but it is predicted to impact the rate at which organic matter is oxidized in hypoxic ecosystems, and the types of organic matter that accumulate. Competition between intracellular enzymes for oxygen may also have impacted microbial strategies of adaptation to suboxia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444596" rel="alternate" title="Biochemical Barriers on the Path to Ocean Anoxia? (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.445078</id><title>Repurposing of the tamoxifen metabolites to treat methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus epidermidis and vancomycin-resistant Enterococcus faecalis infections (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.469132+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrea Miró Canturri</name></author><author><name>Andrea Vila-Domínguez</name></author><author><name>Rafael Ayerbe Algaba</name></author><author><name>Jerónimo Pachón</name></author><author><name>Manuel Enrique Jiménez-Mejías</name></author><author><name>Younes Smani</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Repurposing drugs provides a new approach to the fight against multidrug-resistant (MDR) bacteria. We have reported that three major tamoxifen metabolites, N-desmethyltamoxifen (DTAM), 4-hydroxytamoxifen (HTAM) and endoxifen (ENDX), presented bactericidal activity against &lt;italic&gt;Acinetobacter baumannii&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt;. Here, we aimed to analyse the activity of a mixture of the three tamoxifen metabolites against methicillin-resistant &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus epidermidis&lt;/italic&gt; (MRSE) and &lt;italic&gt;Enterococcus&lt;/italic&gt; spp. MRSE (n=17) and &lt;italic&gt;Enterococcus&lt;/italic&gt; spp. (&lt;italic&gt;E. faecalis&lt;/italic&gt; n=8, and &lt;italic&gt;E. faecium&lt;/italic&gt; n=10) strains were used. MIC of the mixture of DTAM, HTAM and ENDX, and vancomycin were determined by microdilution assay. The bactericidal activity of the three metabolites together and vancomycin against MRSE (SE385 and SE742) and vancomycin-resistant&lt;italic&gt; E. faecalis&lt;/italic&gt; (EVR1 and EVR2) strains was determined by time-kill curve assays. Finally, changes in membrane permeability of SE742 and EVR1 strains were analyzed using fluorescence assays. MIC&lt;sub&gt;50 &lt;/sub&gt;and MIC&lt;sub&gt;90&lt;/sub&gt; of tamoxifen metabolites were 1 mg/L for MRSE strains and 2 mg/L for &lt;italic&gt;Enterococcus&lt;/italic&gt; spp. strains. In the time-killing assays, tamoxifen metabolites mixture showed bactericidal activity at 2x and 4xMIC for MRSE (SE385 and SE742) and &lt;italic&gt;E. faecalis&lt;/italic&gt; (EVR1 and EVR2) strains. This antimicrobial activity of tamoxifen metabolites paralleled an increased membrane permeability of SE385 and EVR2 strains. Altogether, these results showed that tamoxifen metabolites presented antibacterial activity against MRSE and vancomycin-resistant &lt;italic&gt;E. faecalis&lt;/italic&gt;, suggesting that tamoxifen metabolites might increase the arsenal of drugs treatment against these bacterial pathogens.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.445078" rel="alternate" title="Repurposing of the tamoxifen metabolites to treat methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus epidermidis and vancomycin-resistant Enterococcus faecalis infections (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>