<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.278567+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.443778</id><title>STING mediates immune responses in a unicellular choanoflagellate (99 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.279702+00:00</updated><author><name>Arielle Woznica</name></author><author><name>Ashwani Kumar</name></author><author><name>Carolyn R. Sturge</name></author><author><name>Chao Xing</name></author><author><name>Nicole King</name></author><author><name>Julie K. Pfeiffer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Animals have evolved unique repertoires of innate immune genes and pathways that provide their first line of defense against pathogens. To reconstruct the ancestry of animal innate immunity, we have developed the choanoflagellate &lt;italic&gt;Monosiga brevicollis&lt;/italic&gt;, one of the closest living relatives of animals, as a model for studying mechanisms underlying pathogen recognition and immune response. We found that &lt;italic&gt;M. brevicollis&lt;/italic&gt; is killed by exposure to &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; bacteria and selectively avoids ingesting them. Moreover, &lt;italic&gt;M. brevicollis&lt;/italic&gt; expresses STING, which, in animals, activates innate immune pathways in response to cyclic dinucleotides during pathogen sensing. &lt;italic&gt;M. brevicollis&lt;/italic&gt; STING increases the susceptibility of &lt;italic&gt;M. brevicollis&lt;/italic&gt; to &lt;italic&gt;P. aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt;-induced cell death and is required for responding to the cyclic dinucleotide 2’3’ cGAMP. Furthermore, similar to animals, autophagic signaling in &lt;italic&gt;M. brevicollis&lt;/italic&gt; is induced by 2’3’ cGAMP in a STING-dependent manner. This study provides evidence for a pre-animal role for STING in antibacterial immunity and establishes &lt;italic&gt;M. brevicollis&lt;/italic&gt; as a model system for the study of immune responses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.443778" rel="alternate" title="STING mediates immune responses in a unicellular choanoflagellate (99 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443681</id><title>Bacteriophage adaptation to a mammalian mucosa reveals a trans-domain evolutionary axis (68 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.280129+00:00</updated><author><name>Wai Hoe Chin</name></author><author><name>Ciaren Kett</name></author><author><name>Oren Cooper</name></author><author><name>Deike Müseler</name></author><author><name>Yaqi Zhang</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Bamert</name></author><author><name>Ruzeen Patwa</name></author><author><name>Laura C. Woods</name></author><author><name>Citsabehsan Devendran</name></author><author><name>Joe Tiralongo</name></author><author><name>Trevor Lithgow</name></author><author><name>Mike J. McDonald</name></author><author><name>Adrian Neild</name></author><author><name>Jeremy J. Barr</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The majority of viruses within the human gut are obligate bacterial viruses known as bacteriophages (phages)&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. Their bacteriotropism underscores the study of phage ecology in the gut, where they sustain top-down control&lt;sup&gt;2–4&lt;/sup&gt; and co-evolve&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; with gut bacterial communities. Traditionally, these were investigated empirically via &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; experimental evolution&lt;sup&gt;6–8&lt;/sup&gt; and more recently, &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; models were adopted to account for gut niche effects&lt;sup&gt;4,9&lt;/sup&gt;. Here, we probed beyond conventional phage-bacteria co-evolution to investigate the potential evolutionary interactions between phages and the mammalian “host”. To capture the role of the mammalian host, we recapitulated a life-like mammalian gut mucosa using &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; lab-on-a-chip devices (to wit, the gut-on-a-chip) and showed that the mucosal environment supports stable phage-bacteria co-existence. Next, we experimentally evolved phage populations within the gut-on-a-chip devices and discovered that phages adapt by &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; mutations and genetic recombination. We found that a single mutation in the phage capsid protein Hoc – known to facilitate phage adherence to mucus&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt; – caused altered phage binding to fucosylated mucin glycans. We demonstrated that the altered glycan-binding phenotype provided the evolved mutant phage a competitive fitness advantage over their ancestral wildtype phage in the gut-on-a-chip mucosal environment. Collectively, our findings revealed that phages – in addition to their evolutionary relationship with bacteria – are also able to engage in evolution with the mammalian host.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443681" rel="alternate" title="Bacteriophage adaptation to a mammalian mucosa reveals a trans-domain evolutionary axis (68 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.441322</id><title>Linking carbohydrate structure with function in the human gut microbiome using hybrid metagenome assemblies (36 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.280573+00:00</updated><author><name>Anuradha Ravi</name></author><author><name>Perla Troncoso-Rey</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Ahn-Jarvis</name></author><author><name>Kendall R. Corbin</name></author><author><name>Suzanne Harris</name></author><author><name>Hannah Harris</name></author><author><name>Alp Aydin</name></author><author><name>Gemma L. Kay</name></author><author><name>Thanh Le Viet</name></author><author><name>Rachel Gilroy</name></author><author><name>Mark J. Pallen</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Page</name></author><author><name>Justin O’Grady</name></author><author><name>Frederick J. Warren</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Complex carbohydrates that escape digestion in the small intestine, are broken down in the large intestine by enzymes encoded by the gut microbiome. This is a symbiotic relationship between particular microbes and the host, resulting in metabolic products that influence host gut health and are exploited by other microbes. However, the role of carbohydrate structure in directing microbiota community composition and the succession of carbohydrate-degrading microbes, is not fully understood. In this study we evaluate species-level compositional variation within a single microbiome in response to six structurally distinct carbohydrates in a controlled model gut using hybrid metagenome assemblies. We identified 509 high-quality metagenome-assembled genomes (MAGs) belonging to ten bacterial classes and 28 bacterial families. We found dynamic variations in the microbiome amongst carbohydrate treatments, and over time. Using these data, the MAGs were characterised as primary (0h to 6h) and secondary degraders (12h to 24h). Recent advances in sequencing technology allowed us to identify significant unexplored diversity amongst starch degrading species in the human gut microbiota including CAZyme profiles for novel MAGs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.441322" rel="alternate" title="Linking carbohydrate structure with function in the human gut microbiome using hybrid metagenome assemblies (36 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443560</id><title>Efflux only impacts drug accumulation in actively growing cells (34 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.281674+00:00</updated><author><name>Emily E Whittle</name></author><author><name>Helen E McNeil</name></author><author><name>Eleftheria Trampari</name></author><author><name>Mark Webber</name></author><author><name>Tim W Overton</name></author><author><name>Jessica M A Blair</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;For antibiotics with intracellular targets, effective treatment of bacterial infections requires the drug to accumulate to a high concentration inside cells. Bacteria produce a complex cell envelope and possess drug-export efflux pumps to limit drug accumulation inside cells. Decreasing cell envelope permeability and increasing efflux pump activity can reduce intracellular accumulation of antibiotics, and are commonly seen in antibiotic resistant strains. Here, we show that the balance between influx and efflux differs depending on bacterial growth phase in Gramnegative bacteria. Accumulation of the model fluorescent drug, ethidium bromide (EtBr) was measured in &lt;italic&gt;S&lt;/italic&gt;. Typhimurium SL1344 (wild-type) and efflux deficient (Δ&lt;italic&gt;acrB&lt;/italic&gt;) strains during growth. In SL1344, EtBr accumulation remained low, regardless of growth phase and did not correlate with &lt;italic&gt;acrAB&lt;/italic&gt; transcription. EtBr accumulation in Δ&lt;italic&gt;acrB&lt;/italic&gt; was high in exponential phase but dropped sharply later in growth, with no significant difference to SL1344 in stationary phase. Low EtBr accumulation in stationary phase was not due to the upregulation of other efflux pumps, but instead, due to decreased permeability of the envelope in stationary phase. RNAseq identified changes in expression of several pathways that remodel the envelope in stationary phase, leading to lower permeability. This study shows that efflux is only important for maintaining low drug accumulation in actively growing cells, and that envelope permeability is the predominant factor dictating the rate of drug entry in stationary phase cells. This conclusion means that (i) antibiotics with intracellular targets may be less effective in complex non-growing or slow-growing bacterial infections where intracellular accumulation may be low, (ii) efflux inhibitors may be successful in potentiating the activity of existing antibiotics, but potentially only for bacterial infections where cells are actively growing and (iii) the remodelling of the cell envelope prior to stationary phase could provide novel drug targets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443560" rel="alternate" title="Efflux only impacts drug accumulation in actively growing cells (34 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.443986</id><title>Vector-borne Trypanosoma brucei parasites develop in artificial human skin and persist as skin tissue forms (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.282186+00:00</updated><author><name>Christian Reuter</name></author><author><name>Fabian Imdahl</name></author><author><name>Laura Hauf</name></author><author><name>Ehsan Vafadarnejad</name></author><author><name>Philipp Fey</name></author><author><name>Tamara Finger</name></author><author><name>Heike Walles</name></author><author><name>Antoine-Emmanuel Saliba</name></author><author><name>Florian Groeber-Becker</name></author><author><name>Markus Engstler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Transmission of &lt;italic&gt;Trypanosoma brucei&lt;/italic&gt; by tsetse flies involves the deposition of the cell cycle-arrested metacyclic life cycle stage into mammalian skin at the site of the fly’s bite. In the skin, the metacyclic parasites reactivate and differentiate into proliferative trypanosomes before colonizing the host’s blood and tissues. We generated an advanced human skin equivalent and used tsetse flies to naturally infect the artificial skin with trypanosomes. We detailed the chronological order of the parasites’ development in the skin, and found a rapid activation of metacyclic trypanosomes and differentiation to proliferative parasites. Single-cell parasite transcriptomics were used to document the biological events during differentiation and host invasion at five different timepoints. After the establishment of a proliferative trypanosome population in the skin, the parasites entered a reversible quiescent state characterized by slow replication and a strongly reduced metabolism. We termed these quiescent trypanosomes skin tissue forms (STF), a parasite population that may play an important role in maintaining the infection over long time periods and in asymptomatic infected individuals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.443986" rel="alternate" title="Vector-borne Trypanosoma brucei parasites develop in artificial human skin and persist as skin tissue forms (29 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443473</id><title>A widely distributed genus of soil Acidobacteria genomically enriched in biosynthetic gene clusters (25 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.282905+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Crits-Christoph</name></author><author><name>Spencer Diamond</name></author><author><name>Basem Al-Shayeb</name></author><author><name>Luis Valentin-Alvarado</name></author><author><name>Jillian F. Banfield</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacteria of the phylum Acidobacteria are one of the most abundant bacterial across soil ecosystems, yet they are represented by comparatively few sequenced genomes, leaving gaps in our understanding of their metabolic diversity. Recently, genomes of Acidobacteria species with unusually large repertoires of biosynthetic gene clusters (BGCs) were reconstructed from grassland soil metagenomes, but the degree to which these species are widespread is still unknown. To investigate this, we augmented a dataset of publicly available Acidobacteria genomes with 46 metagenome-assembled genomes recovered from permanently saturated organic-rich soils of a vernal (spring) pool ecosystem in Northern California. We recovered high quality genomes for three novel species from &lt;italic&gt;Candidatus&lt;/italic&gt; Angelobacter (a proposed subdivision 1 Acidobacterial genus), a genus that is genomically enriched in genes for specialized metabolite biosynthesis. Acidobacteria were particularly abundant in the vernal pool sediments, and a &lt;italic&gt;Ca&lt;/italic&gt;. Angelobacter species was the most abundant bacterial species detected in some samples. We identified numerous diverse biosynthetic gene clusters in these genomes, and also in additional genomes from other publicly available soil metagenomes for other related &lt;italic&gt;Ca&lt;/italic&gt;. Angelobacter species. Metabolic analysis indicates that &lt;italic&gt;Ca&lt;/italic&gt;. Angelobacter likely are aerobes that ferment organic carbon, with potential to contribute to carbon compound turnover in soils. Using metatranscriptomics, we identified in situ expression of specialized metabolic traits for two species from this genus. In conclusion, we expand genomic sampling of the uncultivated &lt;italic&gt;Ca&lt;/italic&gt;. Angelobacter, and show that they represent common and sometimes highly abundant members of dry and saturated soil communities, with a high degree of capacity for synthesis of diverse specialized metabolites.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443473" rel="alternate" title="A widely distributed genus of soil Acidobacteria genomically enriched in biosynthetic gene clusters (25 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443510</id><title>Phyllosphere-inhabiting endophytic bacteria feature a stationary phase-like lifestyle (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.283346+00:00</updated><author><name>André C. Velásquez</name></author><author><name>José C. Huguet-Tapia</name></author><author><name>Sheng Yang He</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Plants are in constant association with a variety of microbes, and although much is known about how symbiotic and pathogenic microbes interact with plants, less is known about the population dynamics, adaptive traits, and transcriptional features of endophytic commensal microbes that live inside leaves. In this study, we evaluated the long-term population and transcriptional dynamics of two bacterial microbiota endophytes and compared them to those of a commensal-simulating non-pathogenic mutant of the bacterial pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas syringae&lt;/italic&gt;. We found that population densities of all three endophytic phyllosphere bacteria remained static over a long period of time, which was caused by a continual equilibrium between bacterial multiplication and death, as evidenced by treatment of plants with antibiotics that only targeted dividing bacteria or by &lt;italic&gt;in planta&lt;/italic&gt; visualization of bacteria carrying a fluorescent division reporter. Population stasis could not be explained by a lack of resources, as Arabidopsis leaves could support population densities up to 100 times higher than the normal microbiota populations, nor was population stasis reversed by significantly quenching PAMP-triggered immunity. Long-term temporal &lt;italic&gt;in planta&lt;/italic&gt; transcriptomic analysis of these three bacterial endophytes revealed up-regulation of protein translation, the generation of energy, and the response to stress, and interestingly, for the microbiota strains, the longer the bacteria remained inside plants, the greater the up-regulation of some of these processes. Further transcriptomic analysis of &lt;italic&gt;in planta&lt;/italic&gt; populations of commensal-simulating &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas syringae&lt;/italic&gt; revealed a remarkable resemblance to those of &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; bacteria in stationary phase, a metabolically active physiological state in which the production of secondary metabolites and stress responses are induced. This study provides novel insight into how endophytic bacteria survive and thrive inside plant leaves, and reshapes our current understanding of what it means to be part of the endophytic microbiota in the phyllosphere.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443510" rel="alternate" title="Phyllosphere-inhabiting endophytic bacteria feature a stationary phase-like lifestyle (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443588</id><title>CdrS is a global transcriptional regulator influencing cell division in Haloferax volcanii (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.283678+00:00</updated><author><name>Yan Liao</name></author><author><name>Verena Vogel</name></author><author><name>Sabine Hauber</name></author><author><name>Jürgen Bartel</name></author><author><name>Omer S. Alkhnbashi</name></author><author><name>Sandra Maaß</name></author><author><name>Thandi S. Schwarz</name></author><author><name>Rolf Backofen</name></author><author><name>Dörte Becher</name></author><author><name>Iain G. Duggin</name></author><author><name>Anita Marchfelder</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Transcriptional regulators that integrate cellular and environmental signals to control cell division are well known in bacteria and eukaryotes, but their existence is poorly understood in archaea. We identified a conserved gene (&lt;italic&gt;cdrS)&lt;/italic&gt; that encodes a small protein and is highly transcribed in the model archaeon &lt;italic&gt;Haloferax volcanii&lt;/italic&gt;. The &lt;italic&gt;cdrS&lt;/italic&gt; gene could not be deleted, but CRISPRi-mediated repression of the &lt;italic&gt;cdrS&lt;/italic&gt; gene caused slow growth, cell division defects, and changed the expression of multiple genes and their products associated with cell division, protein degradation and metabolism. Consistent with this complex regulatory network, overexpression of &lt;italic&gt;cdrS&lt;/italic&gt; inhibited cell division, whereas overexpression of the operon encoding both CdrS and a tubulin-like cell division protein (FtsZ2) stimulated division. ChIP-Seq identified 18 DNA-binding sites of the CdrS protein including one upstream of the promoter for diadenylate cyclase, which is an essential gene involved in c-di-AMP signalling implicated in the regulation of cell division. These findings suggest that CdrS is a transcription factor that plays a central role in a regulatory network coordinating metabolism and cell division.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cell division is a central mechanism of life, and is essential for growth and development. Bacteria and Eukarya have different mechanisms for cell division, which have been studied in detail. In contrast, cell division in Archaea is still understudied, and its regulation is poorly understood. Interestingly, different cell division machineries appear in the Archaea, with the Euryarchaeota using a cell division apparatus based on the tubulin-like cytoskeletal protein FtsZ, as in bacteria. Here we identify the small protein CdrS as essential for survival and a central regulator of cell division in the Euryarchaeon &lt;italic&gt;Haloferax volcanii&lt;/italic&gt;. CdrS also appears to coordinate other cellular pathways including synthesis of signalling molecules and protein degradation. Our results show that CdrS plays a sophisticated role in cell division, including regulation of numerous associated genes. These findings are expected to initiate investigations into conditional regulation of division in archaea.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443588" rel="alternate" title="CdrS is a global transcriptional regulator influencing cell division in Haloferax volcanii (11 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443333</id><title>RNA virome diversity and Wolbachia infection in individual Drosophila simulans flies (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.284084+00:00</updated><author><name>Ayda Susana Ortiz-Baez</name></author><author><name>Mang Shi</name></author><author><name>Ary A. Hoffmann</name></author><author><name>Edward C. Holmes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The endosymbiont bacterium &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; is associated with multiple mutualistic effects on insect biology, including nutritional and antiviral properties. &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; naturally occurs in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; fly species, providing an operational model host to study how virome composition may be impacted by its presence. &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila simulans&lt;/italic&gt; populations can carry a variety of &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; strains. In particular, the &lt;italic&gt;w&lt;/italic&gt;Au strain of &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; has been associated with strong antiviral protection under experimental conditions. We used &lt;italic&gt;D. simulans&lt;/italic&gt; sampled from the Perth Hills, Western Australia, to investigate the potential virus protective effect of the &lt;italic&gt;w&lt;/italic&gt;Au strain on individual wild-caught flies. Our data revealed no appreciable variation in virus composition and abundance between &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; infected/uninfected individuals associated with the presence/absence of &lt;italic&gt;w&lt;/italic&gt;Au. However, it remains unclear whether &lt;italic&gt;w&lt;/italic&gt;Au might impact viral infection and host survival by increasing tolerance rather than inducing complete resistance. These data also provide new insights into the natural virome diversity of &lt;italic&gt;D. simulans&lt;/italic&gt;. Despite the small number of individuals sampled, we identified a repertoire of RNA viruses, including Nora virus, Galbut virus, Chaq virus, Thika virus and La Jolla virus, that have been identified in other &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; species. In addition, we identified five novel viruses from the families &lt;italic&gt;Reoviridae&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;Tombusviridae&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;Mitoviridae&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Bunyaviridae.&lt;/italic&gt; Overall, this study highlights the complex interaction between &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; and RNA virus infections and provides a baseline description of the natural virome of &lt;italic&gt;D. simulans&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443333" rel="alternate" title="RNA virome diversity and Wolbachia infection in individual Drosophila simulans flies (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443545</id><title>Unraveling protein interactions between the temperate virus Bam35 and its Bacillus host using an integrative Yeast two hybrid-High throughput sequencing approach (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.284391+00:00</updated><author><name>Ana Lechuga</name></author><author><name>Cédric Lood</name></author><author><name>Mónica Berjón-Otero</name></author><author><name>Alicia del Prado</name></author><author><name>Jeroen Wagemans</name></author><author><name>Vera van Noort</name></author><author><name>Rob Lavigne</name></author><author><name>Margarita Salas</name></author><author><name>Modesto Redrejo-Rodríguez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Bacillus&lt;/italic&gt; virus Bam35 is the model &lt;italic&gt;Betatectivirus&lt;/italic&gt; and member of the &lt;italic&gt;Tectiviridae&lt;/italic&gt; family, which is composed of tailless, icosahedral, and membrane-containing bacteriophages. The interest in these viruses has greatly increased in recent years as they are thought to be an evolutionary link between diverse groups of prokaryotic and eukaryotic viruses. Additionally, betatectiviruses infect bacteria of the &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus cereus&lt;/italic&gt; group, known for their applications in industry and notorious since it contains many pathogens. Here, we present the first protein-protein interactions network for a tectivirus-host system by studying the Bam35-&lt;italic&gt;Bacillus thuringiensis&lt;/italic&gt; model using a novel approach that integrates the traditional yeast two-hybrid system and Illumina high-throughput sequencing. We generated and thoroughly analyzed a genomic library of Bam35’s host &lt;italic&gt;B. thuringiensis&lt;/italic&gt; HER1410 and screened interactions with all the viral proteins using different combinations of bait-prey couples. In total, this screen resulted in the detection of over 4,000 potential interactions, of which 183 high-confidence interactions were defined as part of the core virus-host interactome. Overall, host metabolism proteins and peptidases are particularly enriched within the detected interactions, distinguishing this host-phage system from the other reported host-phage protein-protein interaction networks (PPIs). Our approach also suggests biological roles for several Bam35 proteins of unknown function, resulting in a better understanding of the Bam35-&lt;italic&gt;B. thuringiensis&lt;/italic&gt; interaction at the molecular level.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;A&lt;sc&gt;uthor summary&lt;/sc&gt;&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Members of the family &lt;italic&gt;Tectiviridae&lt;/italic&gt;, composed of non-tailed icosahedral, membrane-containing bacteriophages, have been increasingly scrutinized in recent years for their possible role in the origin of dsDNA viruses. In particular, the genus &lt;italic&gt;Betatectivirus&lt;/italic&gt; receives increased attention as these phages can infect clinical strains as well as industrially relevant members of the &lt;italic&gt;B. cereus&lt;/italic&gt; group. However, little is known about the interactions between these temperate viruses and their hosts. Here, we present the first high-throughput study of tectivirus-host protein-protein interactions focusing on Bam35, model virus of betatectiviruses, and its host &lt;italic&gt;B. thuringiensis&lt;/italic&gt;, an important entomopathogenic bacterium. We adapted the well-known technique yeast-two-hybrid and integrated high-throughput sequencing and bioinformatics for the downstream analysis of the results which enables large-scale analysis of protein-protein interactions. In total, 182 detected interactions show an enrichment in host metabolic proteins and peptidases, in contrast with the current knowledge on host-phage PPIs. Specific host-viral protein-protein interactions were also detected enabling us to propose functions for uncharacterized proteins.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443545" rel="alternate" title="Unraveling protein interactions between the temperate virus Bam35 and its Bacillus host using an integrative Yeast two hybrid-High throughput sequencing approach (10 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443950</id><title>Analysis of nucleic acids extracted from rapid diagnostic tests reveals a significant proportion of false positive test results associated with recent malaria treatment (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.284871+00:00</updated><author><name>Salome Hosch</name></author><author><name>Charlene Aya Yoboue</name></author><author><name>Olivier Tresor Donfack</name></author><author><name>Etienne A Guirou</name></author><author><name>Jean-Pierre Dangy</name></author><author><name>Maximillian Mpina</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Nyakurungu</name></author><author><name>Koranan Blöchliger</name></author><author><name>Carlos A Guerra</name></author><author><name>Wonder P Phiri</name></author><author><name>Mitoha Ondo'o Ayekaba</name></author><author><name>Guillermo García</name></author><author><name>Marcel Tanner</name></author><author><name>Claudia Daubenberger</name></author><author><name>Tobias Schindler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Surveillance programs often use malaria rapid diagnostic tests (RDTs) to determine the proportion of the population carrying parasites in their peripheral blood to assess the malaria transmission intensity. Despite an increasing number of reports on false-negative and false-positive RDT results, there is a lack of systematic quality control activities for RDTs deployed in malaria surveillance programs. Our study provides a larger scale comparative evaluation of RDTs used in the 2018 Malaria Indicator Survey (MIS) conducted on Bioko Island, Equatorial Guinea. We conducted a molecular analysis by extraction of nucleic acids from 1,800 negative and 1,065 positive RDTs followed by qPCR analysis. These results were combined with a dataset collected in a comprehensive questionnaire from each MIS participant. Of the 2,865 RDTs that were collected in 2018 on Bioko Island and analysed in our study, 4.7% had a false-negative result. These false-negative RDT results were associated with low parasite density infections. In a substantial proportion of samples, we identified masked &lt;italic&gt;pfhrp2&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;pfhrp3&lt;/italic&gt; gene deletions in which at least one &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; strain carried a gene deletion. Among all positive RDTs analysed, 28.4% were tested negative by qPCR and therefore considered to be false-positive. Analysing the questionnaire data collected from the participants, this high proportion of false-positive RDT results could be explained by PfHRP2 antigen persistence after recent malaria treatment. We conclude that malaria surveillance depending solely on RDTs needs well-integrated quality control procedures assessing the extend and impact of reduced sensitivity and specificity of RDTs on malaria control programs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443950" rel="alternate" title="Analysis of nucleic acids extracted from rapid diagnostic tests reveals a significant proportion of false positive test results associated with recent malaria treatment (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443335</id><title>Revealing RNA virus diversity and evolution in unicellular algae transcriptomes (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.285291+00:00</updated><author><name>Justine Charon</name></author><author><name>Shauna Murray</name></author><author><name>Edward C. Holmes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Remarkably little is known about the diversity and evolution of RNA viruses in unicellular eukaryotes. We screened a total of 570 transcriptomes from the Marine Microbial Eukaryote Transcriptome Sequencing Project (MMETSP) project that encompasses a wide diversity of microbial eukaryotes, including most major photosynthetic lineages (i.e. the microalgae). From this, we identified 30 new and divergent RNA virus species, occupying a range of phylogenetic positions within the overall diversity of RNA viruses. Approximately one-third of the newly described viruses comprised single-stranded positive-sense RNA viruses from the order &lt;italic&gt;Lenarviricota&lt;/italic&gt; associated with fungi, plants and protists, while another third were related to the order &lt;italic&gt;Ghabrivirales&lt;/italic&gt;, including members of the protist and fungi-associated &lt;italic&gt;Totiviridae&lt;/italic&gt;. Other viral species showed sequence similarity to positive-sense RNA viruses from the algae-associated &lt;italic&gt;Marnaviridae&lt;/italic&gt;, the double-stranded RNA &lt;italic&gt;Partitiviridae&lt;/italic&gt;, as well as a single negative-sense RNA virus related to the &lt;italic&gt;Qinviridae.&lt;/italic&gt; Importantly, we were able to identify divergent RNA viruses from distant host taxa, revealing the ancestry of these viral families and greatly extending our knowledge of the RNA viromes of microalgal cultures. Both the limited number of viruses detected per sample and the low sequence identity to known RNA viruses imply that additional microalgal viruses exist that could not be detected at the current sequencing depth or were too divergent to be identified using sequence similarity. Together, these results highlight the need for further investigation of algal-associated RNA viruses as well as the development of new tools to identify RNA viruses that exhibit very high levels of sequence divergence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443335" rel="alternate" title="Revealing RNA virus diversity and evolution in unicellular algae transcriptomes (8 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443593</id><title>A novel dual enrichment strategy provides soil- and digestate-competent N2O-respiring bacteria for mitigating climate forcing in agriculture (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.285569+00:00</updated><author><name>Kjell Rune Jonassen</name></author><author><name>Ida Ormaasen</name></author><author><name>Clara Duffner</name></author><author><name>Torgeir R Hvidsten</name></author><author><name>Åsa Frostegård</name></author><author><name>Lars R Bakken</name></author><author><name>Silas HW Vick</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Manipulating soil metabolism by heavy inoculation with microbes is deemed realistic if waste from anaerobic digestion (digestate) is utilized as substrate and vector, but requires organisms that can grow both in digestate and soil (=generalist). We designed a strategy to enrich and isolate such generalist N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O-respiring bacteria (NRB) in soil and digestate, to provide inoculum for reducing N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O-emissions from agricultural soil. Sequential anaerobic enrichment cultures were provided with a small dose of O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and unlimited N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O, alternating between sterilized digestate and soil as substrates. The cultures were monitored for gas kinetics and community composition (16SrDNA), and cluster-analysis identified generalist-OTUs which became dominant, digestate/soil-specialists which did not, and a majority that were diluted out. Several NRBs circumscribed by generalist-OTU’s were isolated, genome sequenced to screen for catabolic capacity, and phenotyped, to assess their capacity as N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O-sinks in soil. The two isolates &lt;italic&gt;Cloacibacterium&lt;/italic&gt; sp., carrying only N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O-reductase (Clade-II) and &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas sp&lt;/italic&gt;., with full-fledged denitrification-pathway, were both very effective N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O-sinks in soil, with &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/italic&gt; sp., showing a long-lasting sink effect, suggesting better survival in soil. This avenue for utilizing waste to bioengineer the soil microbiota holds promise to effectively combat N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O-emissions but could also be utilized for enhancing other metabolic functions in soil.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="443593v2_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443593" rel="alternate" title="A novel dual enrichment strategy provides soil- and digestate-competent N2O-respiring bacteria for mitigating climate forcing in agriculture (8 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.06.443049</id><title>Reduced virulence and enhanced host adaption during antibiotics therapy: A story of a within-host carbapenem-resistant Klebsiella pneumoniae sequence type 11 evolution in a fatal scrotal abscess patient (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.285900+00:00</updated><author><name>Meiping Ye</name></author><author><name>Chunjie Liao</name></author><author><name>Mengya Shang</name></author><author><name>Danyang Zou</name></author><author><name>Jingmin Yan</name></author><author><name>Zhixiang Hu</name></author><author><name>Xiaogang Xu</name></author><author><name>Jianping Jiang</name></author><author><name>Pingyu Zhou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Carbapenem-resistant &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; (CRKP) has disseminated globally and become a major threat to human life. The sequence type (ST) 11 CRKP is a dominant clone in Asia, especially China, but how this clone evolves &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, then adapts to host and facilitates dissemination remain largely unknown. We analyzed the genomic dynamics of 4 ST11-CRKP isolates sequencially isolated from the urine of a patient with initial fatal scrotal abscess and finally recovered without effective medication. Genomic differences were identified and their implications for pathogenesis and host adaptation were investigated. The related transcriptional pathways were further explored by RNA-Seq. Genomic analysis identified 4-24 mutations and 94%-100% were synonymous or intergenic. The mutation rate of ST11-CRKP was 2.1×10&lt;sup&gt;−6&lt;/sup&gt;-1.7×10&lt;sup&gt;−5&lt;/sup&gt; substitutions/site/year over 47 days of antibiotics therapy. During this period, CRKP underwent several adaptive changes including tigecycline resistance and virulence attenuation. Tigecycline resistance was caused by &lt;italic&gt;ramR&lt;/italic&gt; ribosomal binding site (RBS) deletion, which has been described by us previously. In this study, we demonstrated that mutations associated with acyltransferase (&lt;italic&gt;act&lt;/italic&gt;) and &lt;italic&gt;ompK26&lt;/italic&gt; caused the virulence attenuation of ST11-CRKP&lt;italic&gt;. act&lt;/italic&gt; deletion reduced the production of capsular polysaccharide and enhanced biofilm formation. RNA-Seq analysis revealed that &lt;italic&gt;act&lt;/italic&gt; influenced the expression of &lt;italic&gt;ldhA&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;bglX&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;mtnK&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;metE&lt;/italic&gt; which likely participate in capsular synthesis and biofilm formation. &lt;italic&gt;ompK26&lt;/italic&gt; affected the virulence by its overexpression caused by the deletion of upstream repressor binding site. Our finding suggested that the broad genomic diversity, high evolutionary capacity and rapid within-host adaptability of ST11-CRKP might contribute to the worldwide dissemination of this clone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carbapenem-resistant &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; (CRKP) has disseminated worldwide and can cause life threatening infections, including pneumonia, bloodstream infections, urinary tract infections, intra-abdominal infection, liver abscess and meningitis. CRKP infection is the leading cause of high mortality in clinical. The sequence type (ST) 11 CRKP is a dominant clone and accounts for 60% of CRKP infections in China. Recently, the ST11-CRKP with high transmissibility are increasingly identified. Understanding how this clone evolved is crucial in controlling its further dissemination. The significance of our research is identifying the &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; genomic dynamics of ST11-CRKP and the genetic basis for ST11-CRKP to facilitate persistence and dissemination, which will has broader biomedical impacts on understanding of ST11-CRKP dissemination. Furthermore, our study also highlights the importance of monitoring the development of variation in antibiotics susceptibility and virulence of bacteria in clinical practice, considering that pathogens can rapidly adapt to host during the treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.06.443049" rel="alternate" title="Reduced virulence and enhanced host adaption during antibiotics therapy: A story of a within-host carbapenem-resistant Klebsiella pneumoniae sequence type 11 evolution in a fatal scrotal abscess patient (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.444006</id><title>Composition and Biophysical Properties of the Sorting Platform Pods in the Shigella Type III Secretion System (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.286253+00:00</updated><author><name>Shoichi Tachiyama</name></author><author><name>Ryan Skaar</name></author><author><name>Yunjie Chang</name></author><author><name>Brittany Carroll</name></author><author><name>Meenakumari Muthuramalingam</name></author><author><name>Sean K. Whittier</name></author><author><name>Michael L. Barta</name></author><author><name>Wendy L. Picking</name></author><author><name>Jun Liu</name></author><author><name>William D. Picking</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Shigella flexneri&lt;/italic&gt;, causative agent of bacillary dysentery (shigellosis), uses a type III secretion system (T3SS) as its primary virulence factor. The T3SS injectisome delivers effector proteins into host cells to promote entry and create an important intracellular niche. The injectisome’s cytoplasmic sorting platform (SP) is a critical assembly that contributes to substrate selection and energizing secretion. The SP consists of oligomeric Spa33 “pods” that associate with the basal body via MxiK and connect to the Spa47 ATPase via MxiN. The pods contain heterotrimers of Spa33 with one full-length copy associated with two copies of a C-terminal domain (Spa33&lt;sup&gt;C&lt;/sup&gt;). The structure of Spa33&lt;sup&gt;C&lt;/sup&gt; is known, but the precise makeup and structure of the pods &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; remains elusive. We show here that recombinant wild-type Spa33 can be prepared as a heterotrimer that forms distinct stable complexes with MxiK and MxiN. In two-hybrid analyses, association of the Spa33 complex with these proteins occurs via the full-length Spa33 component. Furthermore, these complexes each have distinct biophysical properties. Based on these properties, new high-resolution cryo-electron tomography data and architectural similarities between the Spa33 and flagellar FliM-FliN complexes, we provide a preliminary model of the Spa33 heterotrimers within the SP pods. From these findings and evolving models of SP interfaces and dynamics in the &lt;italic&gt;Yersinia&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; T3SS, we suggest a model for SP function in which two distinct complexes come together within the context of the SP to contribute to form the complete pod structures during the recruitment of T3SS secretion substrates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.444006" rel="alternate" title="Composition and Biophysical Properties of the Sorting Platform Pods in the Shigella Type III Secretion System (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443947</id><title>Metagenomic sequencing for rapid identification of Xylella fastidiosa from leaf samples (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.286615+00:00</updated><author><name>Veronica Roman-reyna</name></author><author><name>Enora Dupas</name></author><author><name>Sophie Cesbron</name></author><author><name>Guido Marchi</name></author><author><name>Sara Campigli</name></author><author><name>Mary Ann Hansen</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Bush</name></author><author><name>Melanie Prarat</name></author><author><name>Katherine Shiplett</name></author><author><name>Melanie L. Lewis Ivey</name></author><author><name>Joy Pierzynski</name></author><author><name>Sally A. Miller</name></author><author><name>Francesca Peduto Hand</name></author><author><name>Marie-Agnès Jacques</name></author><author><name>Jonathan M Jacobs</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Xylella fastidiosa (Xf) is a globally distributed plant pathogenic bacterium. The primary control strategy for Xf diseases is eradicating infected plants; therefore, timely and accurate detection is necessary to prevent crop losses and further pathogen dispersal. Conventional Xf diagnostics primarily relies on quantitative PCR (qPCR) assays. However, these methods do not consider new or emerging variants due to pathogen genetic recombination and sensitivity limitations. We developed and tested a metagenomics pipeline using in-house short-read sequencing as a complementary approach for affordable, fast, and highly accurate Xf detection. We used metagenomics to identify Xf to strain level in single and mixed infected plant samples at concentrations as low as one picogram of bacterial DNA per gram of tissue. We also tested naturally infected samples from various plant species originating from Europe and the United States. We identified Xf subspecies in samples previously considered inconclusive with real-time PCR (Cq &amp;gt; 35). Overall, we showed the versatility of the pipeline by using different plant hosts and DNA extraction methods. Our pipeline provides taxonomic and functional information for Xf diagnostics without extensive knowledge of the disease. We hope this pipeline can be used for early detection of Xf and incorporated as a tool to inform disease management strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443947" rel="alternate" title="Metagenomic sequencing for rapid identification of Xylella fastidiosa from leaf samples (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443476</id><title>Mycobacterium abscessus HelR interacts with RNA Polymerase to confer intrinsic rifamycin resistance (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.287044+00:00</updated><author><name>Kelley R. Hurst-Hess</name></author><author><name>Aavrati Saxena</name></author><author><name>Pallavi Ghosh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Rifampicin (RIF) constitutes the frontline therapy against &lt;italic&gt;M. tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; as well as most slow-growing non-tuberculous mycobacteria (NTM). However, RIF is completely ineffective against &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; despite the absence of mutations in the rifampicin resistance determining region of &lt;italic&gt;Mab_rpoB&lt;/italic&gt;. This has been attributed to the presence of an ADP-ribosyltransferase (Arr) activity that inactivates RIF. Rifabutin (RBT), a close analogue of RIF, has recently been shown to be effective against &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and in a mouse model and comprises a promising therapeutic against &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; infections. Using RNA sequencing we show that exposure of &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; to sublethal doses of RIF and RBT results in ∼25-fold upregulation of &lt;italic&gt;Mab_helR&lt;/italic&gt; in laboratory and clinical isolates; an isogenic deletion of &lt;italic&gt;Mab_helR&lt;/italic&gt; is hypersensitive to RIF and RBT, and over-expression of &lt;italic&gt;Mab_helR&lt;/italic&gt; confers RIF tolerance in &lt;italic&gt;M. tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; implying that &lt;italic&gt;helR&lt;/italic&gt; constitutes a significant determinant of inducible RIF and RBT resistance. We demonstrate a preferential association of MabHelR with RNA polymerase &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; in bacteria exposed to RIF and showed that purified MabHelR can rescue transcription inhibition in the presence of RIF in &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; transcription assays. Furthermore, MabHelR can dissociate RNAP from RIF-stalled initiation complexes &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, a species we envisage accumulates upon RIF exposure. Lastly, we show that the tip of the PCh-loop of &lt;italic&gt;Mab_helR&lt;/italic&gt;, in particular residues E496 and D497 that are in proximity to RIF, is critical for conferring RIF resistance without being required for RNAP dissociation from stalled complexes. This suggests that HelR may be additionally involved in displacing RIF bound to RNAP and function as an RNAP protection protein.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bacterial RNA polymerase is a target for the potent and broad-spectrum rifamycin group of antibiotics. Mutations within rpoB and inactivation by a diverse group of enzymes constitute the most widespread mechanisms of resistance. Herein we report an unprecedented mechanism of rifamycin resistance in &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; mediated by MabHelR, a putative SF1 like helicase, that involves disassembly of RIF-stalled initiation complexes, likely followed by displacement of the antibiotic, leading to RNAP recycling. The mechanism is reminiscent of the role of HflX and ribosome protection proteins in resistance to ribosome targeting antibiotics and suggests that removal of stalled macromolecular complexes and their recycling comprises a widespread but underappreciated mechanism of antibiotic resistance. Rifampicin (RIF) is pivotal in the control of &lt;italic&gt;M. tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; infections but ineffective against &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt;. Identification of inducible rifamycin resistance determinants in &lt;italic&gt;M. abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; is therefore particularly crucial for informing treatment strategies and development of novel therapeutic approaches.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443476" rel="alternate" title="Mycobacterium abscessus HelR interacts with RNA Polymerase to confer intrinsic rifamycin resistance (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443543</id><title>Mixing crop residues induces a synergistic effect on microbial biomass and an additive effect on soil organic matter priming (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.287328+00:00</updated><author><name>Xin Shu</name></author><author><name>Yiran Zou</name></author><author><name>Liz J. Shaw</name></author><author><name>Lindsay Todman</name></author><author><name>Mark Tibbett</name></author><author><name>Tom Sizmur</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Applying crop residues is a widely used strategy to increase soil organic matter (SOM) in arable soils because of its recorded effects on increasing microbial biomass and consequently necromass. However, fresh residue inputs could also “prime” the decomposition of native SOM, resulting in accelerated SOM depletion and greenhouse gas (GHG) emission. Increasing the botanical diversity of the crops grown in arable systems has been promoted to increase the delivery of multiple ecological functions, including increasing soil microbial biomass and SOM. Whether mixtures of fresh residues from different crops grown in polyculture contribute to soil carbon (C) pools to a greater extent than would be expected from applying individual residues (i.e., the mixture produces a non-additive synergistic effect) has not been systematically tested and is currently unknown. In this study, we used &lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C isotope labelled cover crop residues (i.e., buckwheat, clover, radish, and sunflower) to track the fate of plant residue-derived C and C derived from the priming of SOM in treatments comprising a quaternary mixture of the residues and the average effect of the four individual residues one day after residue incorporation in a laboratory microcosm experiment. Our results indicate that, despite all treatments receiving the same amount of plant residue-derived C (1 mg&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; C g soil), the total microbial biomass in the treatment receiving the residue mixture was significantly greater, by 26% (3.69 µg&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; C g), than the average microbial biomass observed in treatments receiving the four individual components of the mixture one day after applying crop residues. The greater microbial biomass C in the quaternary mixture, compared to average of the individual residue treatments, that can be attributed directly to the plant residue applied was also significantly greater, by 132% (3.61 µg&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; C g). However, there was no evidence that the mixture resulted in any more priming of native SOM than average priming observed in the individual residue treatments. The soil microbial community structure, assessed using phospholipid fatty acid (PLFA) analysis, was significantly (&lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt; &amp;lt; 0.001) different in the soil receiving the residue mixture, compared to the average structures of the communities in soil receiving four individual residues. Differences in the biomass of fungi, general bacteria, and Gram-positive bacteria were responsible for the observed synergistic effect of crop residue mixtures on total microbial biomass and residue-derived microbial biomass, especially biomarkers 16:0, 18:2ω6 and 18:3ω3. Our study demonstrates that applying a mixture of crop residues increases soil microbial biomass to a greater extent than would be expected from applying individual residues and that this occurs either due to faster decomposition of the crop residues or greater carbon use efficiency (CUE), rather than priming the decomposition of native SOM. Therefore, growing crop polycultures (e.g., cover crop mixtures) and incorporating mixtures of the resulting crop residues into the soil could be an effective method to increase microbial biomass and ultimately C stocks in arable soils.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443543" rel="alternate" title="Mixing crop residues induces a synergistic effect on microbial biomass and an additive effect on soil organic matter priming (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443367</id><title>Diagnosis and analysis of unexplained cases of childhood encephalitis in Australia using metagenomic next-generation sequencing (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.287635+00:00</updated><author><name>Ci-Xiu Li</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Burrell</name></author><author><name>Russell C Dale</name></author><author><name>Alison Kesson</name></author><author><name>Christopher C Blyth</name></author><author><name>Julia E Clark</name></author><author><name>Nigel Crawford</name></author><author><name>Cheryl A. Jones</name></author><author><name>Philip N. Britton</name></author><author><name>Edward C. Holmes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Encephalitis is most often caused by a variety of infectious agents, the identity of which is commonly determined through diagnostic tests utilising cerebrospinal fluid (CSF). Immune-mediated disorders are also a differential in encephalitis cases. We investigated the clinical characteristics and potential aetiological agents of unexplained encephalitis through metagenomic next-generation sequencing of residual clinical samples of multiple tissue types and independent clinical review. A total of 43 specimens, from both sterile and non-sterile sites, were collected from 18 encephalitis cases with no cause identified by the Australian Childhood Encephalitis study. Samples were subjected to total RNA sequencing to determine the presence and abundance of potential pathogens, to reveal mixed infections, pathogen genotypes, and epidemiological origins, and to describe the possible aetiologies of unexplained encephalitis. From this, we identified five RNA and two DNA viruses associated with human infection from both non-sterile (nasopharyngeal aspirates, nose/throat swabs, urine, stool rectal swab) and sterile (cerebrospinal fluid, blood) sites. These comprised two human rhinoviruses, two human seasonal coronaviruses, two polyomaviruses and one picobirnavirus. With the exception of picobirnavirus all have been previously associated with respiratory disease. Human rhinovirus and seasonal coronaviruses may be responsible for five of the encephalitis cases reported here. Immune-mediated encephalitis was considered clinically likely in six cases and RNA sequencing did not identify a possible pathogen in these cases. The aetiology remained unknown in nine cases. Our study emphasises the importance of respiratory viruses in the aetiology of unexplained child encephalitis and suggests that the routine inclusion of non-CNS sampling in encephalitis clinical guidelines/protocols could improve the diagnostic yield.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Encephalitis is caused by both infectious agents and auto-immune disorders. However, the aetiological agents, including viruses, remain unknown in around half the cases of encephalitis in many cohorts. Importantly, diagnostic tests are usually based on the analysis of cerebrospinal fluid which may limit their utility. We used a combination of meta-transcriptomic sequencing and independent clinical review to identify the potential causative pathogens in cases of unexplained childhood encephalitis. Accordingly, we identified seven viruses associated with both sterile and non-sterile sampling sites. Human rhinovirus and seasonal coronaviruses were considered as most likely responsible for five of the 18 encephalitis cases studied, while immune-mediated encephalitis was considered the cause in six cases, and we were unable to determine the aetiology in nine cases. Overall, we demonstrate the role of respiratory viruses as a cause of unexplained encephalitis and that sampling sites other than cerebrospinal fluid is of diagnostic value.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443367" rel="alternate" title="Diagnosis and analysis of unexplained cases of childhood encephalitis in Australia using metagenomic next-generation sequencing (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443673</id><title>Colicin-mediated transport of DNA through the iron transporter FepA (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.288000+00:00</updated><author><name>Ruth Cohen-Khait</name></author><author><name>Ameya Harmalkar</name></author><author><name>Phuong Pham</name></author><author><name>Melissa N. Webby</name></author><author><name>Nicholas G. Housden</name></author><author><name>Emma Elliston</name></author><author><name>Jonathan TS. Hopper</name></author><author><name>Shabaz Mohammed</name></author><author><name>Carol V. Robinson</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey J. Gray</name></author><author><name>Colin Kleanthous</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Colicins are protein antibiotics used by bacteria to eliminate competing Escherichia coli. A key event in the selective colicin function is a highly specific initial recognition step of an outer membrane (OM) receptor, which consequently allows the active transport of the colicin across the otherwise impervious OM. Though the colicin-receptor interaction is exclusive, the translocation process is likely to be universal as many receptors and colicins have surprisingly similar 3D folds. Here, using a combination of photo-activated crosslinking, mass spectrometry, and structural modeling, we reveal how colicin B (ColB) associates with its OM receptor FepA. We demonstrate that complex formation is coincident with a large-scale conformational change in the colicin. In vivo crosslinking experiments and further simulations of the translocation process indicate that part of the colicin engages active transport by disguising itself to part of the cellular receptor. Applying live-cell fluorescence imaging we were able to follow ColB into E. coli and localize it within the periplasm. Finally, we demonstrate that single-stranded DNA coupled to ColB is transported into the bacterial periplasm, emphasizing that the import routes of colicins can be exploited to carry large cargo molecules into Gram-negative bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443673" rel="alternate" title="Colicin-mediated transport of DNA through the iron transporter FepA (5 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>