<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.711114+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450542</id><title>The development of ovine gastric and intestinal organoids for studying ruminant host-pathogen interactions (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.712858+00:00</updated><author><name>David Smith</name></author><author><name>Daniel R. G. Price</name></author><author><name>Alison Burrells</name></author><author><name>Marc N. Faber</name></author><author><name>Katie A. Hildersley</name></author><author><name>Cosmin Chintoan-Uta</name></author><author><name>Ambre F. Chapuis</name></author><author><name>Mark Stevens</name></author><author><name>Karen Stevenson</name></author><author><name>Stewart T. G. Burgess</name></author><author><name>Elisabeth A. Innes</name></author><author><name>Alasdair J. Nisbet</name></author><author><name>Tom N. McNeilly</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gastrointestinal (GI) infections in sheep have significant implications for animal health, welfare and productivity, as well as being a source of zoonotic pathogens. Interactions between pathogens and epithelial cells at the mucosal surface play a key role in determining the outcome of GI infections; however, the inaccessibility of the GI tract &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; significantly limits the ability to study such interactions in detail. We therefore developed ovine epithelial organoids representing physiologically important gastric and intestinal sites of infection, specifically the abomasum (analogous to the stomach in monogastrics) and ileum. We show that both abomasal and ileal organoids form self-organising three-dimensional structures with a single epithelial layer and a central lumen that are stable in culture over serial passage. We performed RNA-seq analysis on abomasal and ileal tissue from multiple animals and on organoids across multiple passages and show the transcript profile of both abomasal and ileal organoids cultured under identical conditions are reflective of the tissue from which they were derived and that the transcript profile in organoids is stable over at least five serial passages. In addition, we demonstrate that the organoids can be successfully cryopreserved and resuscitated, allowing long-term storage of organoid lines, thereby reducing the number of animals required as a source of tissue. We also report the first published observations of a helminth infecting gastric and intestinal organoids by challenge with the sheep parasitic nematode &lt;italic&gt;Teladorsagia circumcincta&lt;/italic&gt;, demonstrating the utility of these organoids for pathogen co-culture experiments. Finally, the polarity in the abomasal and ileal organoids can be inverted to make the apical surface directly accessible to pathogens or their products, here shown by infection of apical-out organoids with the zoonotic enteric bacterial pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella enterica&lt;/italic&gt; serovar Typhimurium. In summary, we report a simple and reliable &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; culture system for generation and maintenance of small ruminant intestinal and gastric organoids. In line with 3Rs principals, use of such organoids will reduce and replace animals in host-pathogen research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450542" rel="alternate" title="The development of ovine gastric and intestinal organoids for studying ruminant host-pathogen interactions (19 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450457</id><title>A simplified method for CRISPR-Cas9 engineering of Bacillus subtilis (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.713363+00:00</updated><author><name>Ankita Jagdish Sachla</name></author><author><name>Alexander Jesus Alfonso</name></author><author><name>John D Helmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeat (CRISPR)-Cas9 system from &lt;italic&gt;Streptococcus pyogenes&lt;/italic&gt; has been widely deployed as a tool for bacterial strain construction. Conventional CRISPR-Cas9 editing strategies require design and molecular cloning of an appropriate guide RNA (gRNA) to target genome cleavage and a repair template for introduction of the desired site-specific genome modification. Here, we present a streamlined method that leverages the existing collection of nearly 4000 &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; strains (the BKE collection) with individual genes replaced by an integrated erythromycin (&lt;italic&gt;erm&lt;/italic&gt;) resistance cassette. A single plasmid (pAJS23) with a gRNA targeted to &lt;italic&gt;erm&lt;/italic&gt; allows cleavage of the genome at any non-essential gene, and at sites nearby to many essential genes. This plasmid can be engineered to include a repair template, or the repair template can be co-transformed with the plasmid as either a PCR product or genomic DNA. We demonstrate the utility of this system for generating gene replacements, site-specific mutations, modification of intergenic regions, and introduction of gene-reporter fusions. In sum, this strategy bypasses the need for gRNA design and allows the facile transfer of mutations and genetic constructions with no requirement for intermediate cloning steps.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450457" rel="alternate" title="A simplified method for CRISPR-Cas9 engineering of Bacillus subtilis (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450566</id><title>Short homology-directed repair using optimized Cas9 in the pathogen Cryptococcus neoformans  enables rapid gene deletion and tagging (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.713631+00:00</updated><author><name>Manning Y. Huang</name></author><author><name>Meenakshi B. Joshi</name></author><author><name>Michael J Boucher</name></author><author><name>Sujin Lee</name></author><author><name>Liza C. Loza</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth A. Gaylord</name></author><author><name>Tamara L Doering</name></author><author><name>Hiten D. Madhani</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Cryptococcus neoformans&lt;/italic&gt;, the most common cause of fungal meningitis, is a basidiomycete haploid budding yeast with a complete sexual cycle. Genome modification by homologous recombination is feasible using biolistic transformation and long homology arms, but the method is arduous and unreliable. Recently, multiple groups have reported the use of CRISPR-Cas9 as an alternative to biolistics, but long homology arms are still necessary, limiting the utility of this method. Since the &lt;italic&gt;S. pyogenes&lt;/italic&gt; Cas9 derivatives used in prior studies were not optimized for expression in &lt;italic&gt;C. neoformans&lt;/italic&gt;, we designed, synthesized, and tested a fully &lt;italic&gt;C. neoformans&lt;/italic&gt;-optimized Cas9. We found that a Cas9 harboring only common &lt;italic&gt;C. neoformans&lt;/italic&gt; codons and a consensus &lt;italic&gt;C. neoformans&lt;/italic&gt; intron together with a &lt;italic&gt;TEF1&lt;/italic&gt; promoter and terminator and a nuclear localization signal (&lt;italic&gt;C. neoformans&lt;/italic&gt;-optimized &lt;italic&gt;CAS9&lt;/italic&gt; or '&lt;italic&gt;CnoCAS9&lt;/italic&gt;') reliably enabled genome editing in the widely-used KN99α &lt;italic&gt;C. neoformans&lt;/italic&gt; strain. Furthermore, editing was accomplished using donors harboring short (50 bp) homology arms attached to marker DNAs produced with synthetic oligonucleotides and PCR amplification. We also demonstrated that prior stable integration of &lt;italic&gt;CnoCAS9&lt;/italic&gt; further enhances both transformation and homologous recombination efficiency; importantly, this manipulation does not impact virulence in animals. We also implemented a universal tagging module harboring a codon-optimized fluorescent protein (mNeonGreen) and a tandem Calmodulin Binding Peptide-2X FLAG Tag that allows for both localization and purification studies of proteins for which the corresponding genes are modified by short homology-directed recombination. These tools enable short-homology genome engineering in &lt;italic&gt;C. neoformans&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450566" rel="alternate" title="Short homology-directed repair using optimized Cas9 in the pathogen Cryptococcus neoformans  enables rapid gene deletion and tagging (9 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450544</id><title>The MpsB protein contributes to both the toxicity and immune evasion capacity of Staphylococcus aureus (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.714157+00:00</updated><author><name>Edward J.A. Douglas</name></author><author><name>Seána Duggan</name></author><author><name>Tarcisio Brignoli</name></author><author><name>Ruth C. Massey</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the role specific bacterial factors play in the development of severe disease in humans is critical if new approaches to tackle such infections are to be developed. In this study we focus on genes we have found to be associated with patient outcome following bacteraemia caused by the major human pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/italic&gt;. By examining the contribution these genes make to the ability of the bacteria to survive exposure to the antibacterial factors found in serum, we identify three novel serum resistance associated genes, &lt;italic&gt;mdeA, mpsB&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;yycH&lt;/italic&gt;. Detailed analysis of an MpsB mutant supports its previous association with the slow growing SCV phenotype of &lt;italic&gt;S. aureus&lt;/italic&gt;, and we demonstrate that the effect this mutation has on membrane potential prevents the activation of the Agr quorum sensing system, and as a consequence the mutant bacteria do not produce cytolytic toxins. Given the importance of both toxin production and immune evasion to the ability of &lt;italic&gt;S. aureus&lt;/italic&gt; to cause disease, we believe these findings explain the role of the &lt;italic&gt;mpsB&lt;/italic&gt; gene as a mortality-associate locus during human disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450544" rel="alternate" title="The MpsB protein contributes to both the toxicity and immune evasion capacity of Staphylococcus aureus (8 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450460</id><title>Antimicrobial activity of a repurposed harmine-derived compound on extensively drug-resistant Acinetobacter baumannii clinical isolates (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.714385+00:00</updated><author><name>Anke Breine</name></author><author><name>Mégane Van Gysel</name></author><author><name>Mathias Elsocht</name></author><author><name>Clémence Whiteway</name></author><author><name>Chantal Philippe</name></author><author><name>Théo Quinet</name></author><author><name>Adam Valcek</name></author><author><name>Johan Wouters</name></author><author><name>Steven Ballet</name></author><author><name>Charles Van der Henst</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objectives&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The spread of antibiotic resistant bacteria is an important threat for human healthcare. &lt;italic&gt;Acinetobacter baumannii&lt;/italic&gt; bacteria impose one of the major issues, as multidrug- to pandrug-resistant strains have been found, rendering some infections untreatable. In addition, &lt;italic&gt;A. baumannii&lt;/italic&gt; is a champion in surviving in harsh environments, being capable of resisting to disinfectants and to persist prolonged periods of desiccation. Due to the high degree of variability found in &lt;italic&gt;A. baumannii&lt;/italic&gt; isolates, the search for new antibacterials is challenging. Here, we screened a compound library to identify compounds active against recent isolates of &lt;italic&gt;A. baumannii&lt;/italic&gt; bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A repurposing drug screen was undertaken to identify &lt;italic&gt;A. baumannii&lt;/italic&gt; growth inhibitors. One hit was further characterized by determining its IC&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; and testing its activity on 43 recent clinical &lt;italic&gt;A. baumannii&lt;/italic&gt; isolates, amongst which 40 are extensively drug- and carbapenem-resistant strains.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The repurposing screen led to the identification of a harmine-derived compound, called HDC1, which proved to have bactericidal activity on the multidrug-resistant AB5075-VUB reference strain with an IC&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; of 48.23 µM. In addition, HDC1 impairs growth of all 43 recent clinical &lt;italic&gt;A. baumannii&lt;/italic&gt; isolates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We identified a compound with inhibitory activity on all tested, extensively drug-resistant clinical &lt;italic&gt;A. baumannii&lt;/italic&gt; isolates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450460" rel="alternate" title="Antimicrobial activity of a repurposed harmine-derived compound on extensively drug-resistant Acinetobacter baumannii clinical isolates (6 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>