<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular microbiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.670306+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/microbiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.473670</id><title>Reconstitution of the S. aureus agr quorum sensing pathway reveals a direct role for the integral membrane protease MroQ in pheromone biosynthesis (17 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.670829+00:00</updated><author><name>Aishan Zhao</name></author><author><name>Steven Parker Bodine</name></author><author><name>Qian Xie</name></author><author><name>Boyuan Wang</name></author><author><name>Geeta Ram</name></author><author><name>Richard P Novick</name></author><author><name>Tom W Muir</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In Staphylococcus aureus, virulence is under the control of a quorum sensing (QS) circuit encoded in the accessory gene regulator (agr) genomic locus. Key to this pathogenic behavior is the production and signaling activity of a secreted pheromone, the autoinducing peptide (AIP), generated following the ribosomal synthesis and post-translational modification of a precursor polypeptide, AgrD, through two discrete cleavage steps. The integral membrane protease AgrB is known to catalyze the first processing event, generating the AIP biosynthetic intermediate, AgrD (1-32) thiolactone. However, the identity of the second protease in this biosynthetic pathway, which removes an N-terminal leader sequence, has remained ambiguous. Here, we show that MroQ, an integral membrane protease recently implicated in the agr response, is directly involved in AIP production. Genetic complementation and biochemical experiments reveal that MroQ proteolytic activity is required for AIP biosynthesis in agr specifiy groups -I and -II, but not group-III. Notably, as part of this effort, the biosynthesis and AIP-sensing arms of the QS circuit were reconstituted together in vitro. Our experiments also reveal the molecular features guiding MroQ cleavage activity, a critical factor in defining agr specificity group identity. Collectively, our study adds to the molecular understanding of the agr response and Staphylococcus aureus virulence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.473670" rel="alternate" title="Reconstitution of the S. aureus agr quorum sensing pathway reveals a direct role for the integral membrane protease MroQ in pheromone biosynthesis (17 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474454</id><title>Longitudinal analysis of invariant natural killer T cell activation reveals a cMAF-associated transcriptional state of NKT10 cells (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.671124+00:00</updated><author><name>Lydia Lynch</name></author><author><name>Harry Kane</name></author><author><name>Nelson M LaMarche</name></author><author><name>Áine Ní Scannail</name></author><author><name>Michael P. Brenner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Innate T cells, including CD1d-restricted invariant natural killer T (iNKT) cells, are characterized by their rapid activation in response to nonpeptide antigens, such as lipids. While the transcriptional profiles of naive, effector and memory adaptive T cells have been well studied, less is known about transcriptional regulation of different iNKT cell activation states. Here, using single cell RNA-sequencing, we performed longitudinal profiling of activated iNKT cells, generating a transcriptomic atlas of iNKT cell activation states. We found that transcriptional signatures of activation are highly conserved among heterogeneous iNKT cell populations, including NKT1, NKT2 and NKT17 subsets, and human iNKT cells. Strikingly, we found that regulatory iNKT cells, such as adipose iNKT cells, undergo blunted activation, and display constitutive enrichment of memory-like cMAF&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and KLRG1&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; populations. Moreover, we identify a conserved cMAF-associated transcriptional network among NKT10 cells, providing novel insights into the biology of regulatory and antigen experienced iNKT cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474454" rel="alternate" title="Longitudinal analysis of invariant natural killer T cell activation reveals a cMAF-associated transcriptional state of NKT10 cells (7 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.27.473672</id><title>Effector-mediated subversion of proteasome activator (PA)28αβ enhances lysosomal targeting of Legionella pneumophila within cytokine-activated macrophages (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.671336+00:00</updated><author><name>Tshegofatso Ngwaga</name></author><author><name>Deepika Chauhan</name></author><author><name>Abigail G Salberg</name></author><author><name>Stephanie R Shames</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Legionella pneumophila causes Legionnaires' Disease via replication within host macrophages using an arsenal of hundreds of translocated virulence factors termed effector proteins. Effectors are critical for intracellular replication but can also enhance pathogen clearance in mammalian hosts via effector-triggered immunity. The effector LegC4 confers a fitness disadvantage on L. pneumophila within mouse models of Legionnaires' Disease and uniquely potentiates the antimicrobial activity of macrophages activated with either tumor necrosis factor (TNF) or interferon (IFN)-γ. Here, we investigated the mechanism of LegC4 function. We found that LegC4 binds proteasome activator (PA)28α, a subunit of the PA28αβ (11S) proteasome regulator, and that the LegC4 restriction phenotype is abolished within PA28αβ-deficient macrophages. PA28αβ facilitates ubiquitin-independent proteasomal degradation of oxidant-damaged proteins. Impaired proteasome activity results in compensatory upregulation of lysosomal degradation pathways to relieve oxidative proteotoxic stress. We found that LegC4 impairs the resolution of oxidative proteotoxic stress and enhances phagolysosomal fusion with the Legionella-containing vacuole. PA28αβ has been traditionally associated with antigen presentation and adaptive immunity; however, our data support a model whereby suppression of PA28αβ by LegC4 impairs resolution of oxidative proteotoxic stress, which culminates in the lysosomal killing of L. pneumophila within activated macrophages. This work provides a solid foundation on which to evaluate induced proteasome regulators as mediators of cell-autonomous immunity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.27.473672" rel="alternate" title="Effector-mediated subversion of proteasome activator (PA)28αβ enhances lysosomal targeting of Legionella pneumophila within cytokine-activated macrophages (7 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474514</id><title>Kinetics Of Interferon-λ And Receptor Expression In Response To In Vitro Respiratory Viral Infection (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.671850+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexey Lozhkov</name></author><author><name>Nikita Yolshin</name></author><author><name>Irina Baranovskaya</name></author><author><name>Marina Plotnikova</name></author><author><name>Mariia Sergeeva</name></author><author><name>Natalia Gyulikhandanova</name></author><author><name>Sergey Klotchenko</name></author><author><name>Andrey Vasin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The major protective immune response against viruses is production of type I and III interferons (IFNs). IFNs induce the expression of hundreds of IFN-stimulated genes (ISGs) that block viral replication and further viral spread. The ability of respiratory viruses to suppress induction of IFN-mediated antiviral defenses in infected epithelial cells may be a factor contributing to the particular pathogenicity of several strains. In this report, we analyzed expression of IFNs and some ISGs in an alveolar epithelial cell subtype (A549) in response to infection with: influenza A viruses (A/California/07/09pdm (H1N1), A/Texas/50/12 (H3N2)); influenza B virus (B/Phuket/3073/13); adenovirus type 5 and 6; or respiratory syncytial virus (strain A2). IFNL and ISGs expression significantly increased in response to infection with all RNA viruses 24 hpi. Nevertheless, only IBV led to early increase in IFNL and ISGs mRNA level. IBV and H1N1 infection led to elevated proinflammatory cytokine production. We speculate that augmented IFN-α, IFN-β, IL-6 levels negatively correlate to SOCS1 expression. Importantly, we showed a decrease in IFNLR1 mRNA in case of IBV infection that implies the existence of negative ISGs expression regulation at IFNλR level. It could be either a specific feature of IBV or a consequence of early IFNL expression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474514" rel="alternate" title="Kinetics Of Interferon-λ And Receptor Expression In Response To In Vitro Respiratory Viral Infection (4 tweets)"/><category term="Immunology"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474260</id><title>Simple and cost-effective SNP genotyping method for discriminating subpopulations of the fish pathogen, Nocardia seriolae (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.672325+00:00</updated><author><name>Cuong T. Le</name></author><author><name>Erin P. Price</name></author><author><name>Derek S. Sarovich</name></author><author><name>Thu T.A. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Hung Vu-Khac</name></author><author><name>Ipek Kurtböke</name></author><author><name>Wayne Knibb</name></author><author><name>Shih-Chu Chen</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Katouli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nocardia seriolae has caused significant fish losses in Asia and the Americas in recent decades, including in Vietnam, which has witnessed devastating economic and social impacts due to this bacterial pathogen. Surveillance strategies are urgently needed to mitigate N. seriolae dissemination in Vietnamese aquaculture and mariculture industries. Whole-genome sequencing (WGS) offers the highest level of resolution to discriminate closely related strains and to determine their putative origin and transmission routes. However, WGS is impractical for epidemiological investigations and pathogen surveillance due to its time-consuming and costly nature, putting this technology out-of-reach for many industry end-users. To overcome this issue, we targeted two previously characterised, phylogenetically informative single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in N. seriolae that accurately distinguish: i) Vietnamese from non-Vietnamese strains, and ii) the two Vietnamese subclades. Using the mismatch amplification mutation assay (MAMA) format, we developed assays that genotype strains based on differences in amplicon melting temperature (melt-MAMA) and size (agarose-MAMA). Our MAMA assays accurately genotyped strains both from culture and fish tissues at low cost, using either real-time (~AUD$1/per sample) or conventional (~AUD$0.50/per sample) PCR instrumentation. Our novel assays provide a rapid, reproducible, and cost-effective tool for routine genotyping of this pathogen, allowing faster identification and treatment of nocardiosis-effected permit fish within Vietnamese aquaculture/mariculture facilities, an essential step in mitigating N. seriolae-associated losses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474260" rel="alternate" title="Simple and cost-effective SNP genotyping method for discriminating subpopulations of the fish pathogen, Nocardia seriolae (3 tweets)"/><category term="Microbiology"/><published>2021-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>