<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.451929+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471006</id><title>Chromatin accessibility differences between alpha, beta, and delta cells identifies common and cell type-specific enhancers (293 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.452153+00:00</updated><author><name>Alex M. Mawla</name></author><author><name>Talitha van der Meulen</name></author><author><name>Mark O. Huising</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;High throughput sequencing has enabled the interrogation of the transcriptomic landscape of glucagon-secreting alpha cells, insulin-secreting beta cells, and somatostatin-secreting delta cells. These approaches have furthered our understanding of expression patterns that define healthy or diseased islet cell types and helped explicate some of the intricacies between major islet cell crosstalk and glucose regulation. All three endocrine cell types derive from a common pancreatic progenitor, yet alpha and beta cells have partially opposing functions, and delta cells modulate and control insulin and glucagon release. While gene signatures that define and maintain cellular identity have been widely explored, the underlying epigenetic components are incompletely characterized and understood. Chromatin accessibility and remodeling is a dynamic attribute that plays a critical role to determine and maintain cellular identity. Here, we compare and contrast the chromatin landscape between mouse alpha, beta, and delta cells using ATAC-Seq to evaluate the significant differences in chromatin accessibility. The similarities and differences in chromatin accessibility between these related islet endocrine cells help define their fate in support of their distinct functional roles. We identify patterns that suggest that both alpha and delta cells are poised, but repressed, from becoming beta-like. We also identify patterns in differentially enriched chromatin that have transcription factor motifs preferentially associated with different regions of the genome. Finally, we identify and visualize both novel and previously discovered common endocrine- and cell specific- enhancer regions across differentially enriched chromatin.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471006" rel="alternate" title="Chromatin accessibility differences between alpha, beta, and delta cells identifies common and cell type-specific enhancers (293 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471431</id><title>A convolutional neural network highlights mutations relevant to antimicrobial resistance in Mycobacterium tuberculosis (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.452316+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna G. Green</name></author><author><name>Chang H. Yoon</name></author><author><name>Michael L. Chen</name></author><author><name>Luca Freschi</name></author><author><name>Matthias I. Gröschel</name></author><author><name>Isaac Kohane</name></author><author><name>Andrew Beam</name></author><author><name>Maha Farhat</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Long diagnostic wait times hinder international efforts to address multi-drug resistance in &lt;italic&gt;M. tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt;. Pathogen whole genome sequencing, coupled with statistical and machine learning models, offers a promising solution. However, generalizability and clinical adoption have been limited in part by a lack of interpretability and verifiability, especially in deep learning methods. Here, we present a deep convolutional neural network (CNN) that predicts the antibiotic resistance phenotypes of &lt;italic&gt;M. tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; isolates. The CNN performs with state-of-the-art levels of predictive accuracy. Evaluation of salient sequence features permits biologically meaningful interpretation and validation of the CNN’s predictions, with promising repercussions for functional variant discovery, clinical applicability, and translation to phenotype prediction in other organisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471431" rel="alternate" title="A convolutional neural network highlights mutations relevant to antimicrobial resistance in Mycobacterium tuberculosis (29 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471659</id><title>Spatiotemporal transcriptomics reveals pathogenesis of viral myocarditis (28 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.452485+00:00</updated><author><name>Madhav Mantri</name></author><author><name>Meleana M. Hinchman</name></author><author><name>David W. McKellar</name></author><author><name>Michael F. Z. Wang</name></author><author><name>Shaun T. Cross</name></author><author><name>John S. L. Parker</name></author><author><name>Iwijn De Vlaminck</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A significant fraction of sudden death in children and young adults is due to myocarditis, an inflammatory disease of the heart, most often caused by viral infection. Here we used integrated single-cell and spatial transcriptomics to create a high-resolution, spatially resolved map of reovirus-induced myocarditis in neonatal murine hearts. We assayed hearts collected at three timepoints after reovirus infection and studied the temporal, spatial, and cellular heterogeneity of host-virus interactions. We further assayed the intestine, the primary site of reovirus infection to establish a full chronology of molecular events that ultimately lead to myocarditis. We implemented targeted enrichment of viral transcripts to establish the cellular targets of the virus in the intestine and the heart. Our data give insight into the cell-type specificity of innate immune responses, and into the transcriptional states of inflamed cardiac cells that recruit circulating immune cells, including cytotoxic T cells which induce pyroptosis in the myocarditic tissue. Analyses of spatially restricted gene expression in myocarditic regions and the border zone around those regions identified immune-mediated cell-type specific injury and stress responses. Overall, we observe a dynamic and complex network of cellular phenotypes and cell-cell interactions associated with viral myocarditis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471659" rel="alternate" title="Spatiotemporal transcriptomics reveals pathogenesis of viral myocarditis (28 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.470997</id><title>MitoVisualize: A resource for analysis of variants in human mitochondrial RNAs and DNA (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.452640+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicole J. Lake</name></author><author><name>Lily Zhou</name></author><author><name>Jenny Xu</name></author><author><name>Monkol Lek</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We present MitoVisualize, a new tool for analysis of the human mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA). MitoVisualize enables visualization of: (1) the position and effect of variants in mitochondrial transfer RNA (tRNA) and ribosomal RNA (rRNA) secondary structures alongside curated variant annotations, (2) data across RNA structures, such as to show all positions with disease-associated variants or with post-transcriptional modifications, and (3) the position of a base, gene or region in the circular mtDNA map, such as to show the location of a large deletion. All visualizations can be easily downloaded as figures for reuse. MitoVisualize can be useful for anyone interested in exploring mtDNA variation, though is designed to facilitate mtDNA variant interpretation in particular. MitoVisualize can be accessed via &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.mitovisualize.org/"&gt;https://www.mitovisualize.org/&lt;/ext-link&gt;. The source code is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/leklab/mito_visualize/"&gt;https://github.com/leklab/mito_visualize/&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.470997" rel="alternate" title="MitoVisualize: A resource for analysis of variants in human mitochondrial RNAs and DNA (18 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471745</id><title>Genomic ancestry, diet and microbiomes of Upper Palaeolithic hunter-gatherers from San Teodoro cave (Sicily, Italy) (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.452776+00:00</updated><author><name>Gabriele Scorrano</name></author><author><name>Sofie Holtsmark Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Domenico Lo Vetro</name></author><author><name>Meaghan Mackie</name></author><author><name>Ashot Margaryan</name></author><author><name>Anna K. Fotakis</name></author><author><name>Cristina Martínez-Labarga</name></author><author><name>Pier Francesco Fabbri</name></author><author><name>Morten E. Allentoft</name></author><author><name>Marialetizia Carra</name></author><author><name>Fabio Martini</name></author><author><name>Olga Rickards</name></author><author><name>Jesper V. Olsen</name></author><author><name>Enrico Cappellini</name></author><author><name>Martin Sikora</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent improvements in the analysis of ancient biomolecules from human remains and associated dental calculus have provided new insights into the prehistoric diet and past genetic diversity of our species. Here we present a “multi-omics” study, integrating genomic and proteomic analyses of two post-Last Glacial Maximum (LGM) individuals from San Teodoro cave (Italy), to reconstruct their lifestyle and the post-LGM resettlement of Europe. Our analyses show genetic homogeneity in Sicily during the Palaeolithic, representing a hitherto unknown Italian genetic lineage within the previously identified “Villabruna cluster”. We argue that this lineage took refuge in Italy during the LGM, followed by a subsequent spread to central-western Europe. Multi-omics analysis of dental calculus showed a diet rich of animal proteins which is also reflected on the oral microbiome composition. Our results demonstrate the power of using a multi-omics approach in the study of prehistoric human populations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471745" rel="alternate" title="Genomic ancestry, diet and microbiomes of Upper Palaeolithic hunter-gatherers from San Teodoro cave (Sicily, Italy) (15 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471819</id><title>Ongoing transposition in cell culture reveals the phylogeny of diverse Drosophila S2 sub-lines. (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.452995+00:00</updated><author><name>Shunhua Han</name></author><author><name>Guilherme B. Dias</name></author><author><name>Preston J. Basting</name></author><author><name>Michael G. Nelson</name></author><author><name>Sanjai Patel</name></author><author><name>Mar Marzo</name></author><author><name>Casey M. Bergman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cultured cells are widely used in molecular biology despite poor understanding of how cell line genomes change in vitro over time. Previous work has shown that Drosophila cultured cells have a higher transposable element (TE) content than whole flies, but whether this increase in TE content resulted from an initial burst of transposition during cell line establishment or ongoing transposition in cell culture remains unclear. Here we sequence the genomes of 25 sub-lines of Drosophila S2 cells and show that TE insertions provide abundant markers for the phylogenetic reconstruction of diverse sub-lines in a model animal cell culture system. Analysis of DNA copy number evolution across S2 sub-lines revealed dramatically different patterns of genome organization that support the overall evolutionary history reconstructed using TE insertions. Analysis of TE insertion site occupancy and ancestral states support a model of ongoing transposition dominated by episodic activity of a small number of retrotransposon families. Our work demonstrates that substantial genome evolution occurs during long-term Drosophila cell culture, which may impact the reproducibility of experiments that do not control for sub-line identity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471819" rel="alternate" title="Ongoing transposition in cell culture reveals the phylogeny of diverse Drosophila S2 sub-lines. (9 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471816</id><title>Temporal response characterization across individual multiomics profiles of prediabetic and diabetic subjects (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.453132+00:00</updated><author><name>Minzhang Zheng</name></author><author><name>Carlo Piermarocchi</name></author><author><name>George I. Mias</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Longitudinal deep multi-omics profiling, which combines biomolecular, physiological, environmental and clinical measures data, shows great promise for precision health. However, integrating and understanding the complexity of such data remains a big challenge. Here we propose a bottom-up framework starting from assessing single individuals' multi-omics time series, and using individual responses to assess multi-individual grouping based directly on similarity of their longitudinal deep multi-omics profiles. We applied our method to individual profiles from a study profiling longitudinal responses in type 2 diabetes mellitus. After generating periodograms for individual subject omics signals, we constructed within-person omics networks and analyzed personal-level immune changes. The results showed that our method identified both individual-level responses to immune perturbation, and the clusters of individuals that have similar behaviors in immune response and which was associated to measures of their diabetic status.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471816" rel="alternate" title="Temporal response characterization across individual multiomics profiles of prediabetic and diabetic subjects (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471568</id><title>From STRs to SNPs via ddRAD-seq: geographic assignment of confiscated tortoises at reduced costs (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.453246+00:00</updated><author><name>Roberto Biello</name></author><author><name>Mauro Zampiglia</name></author><author><name>Silvia Fuselli</name></author><author><name>Giulia Fabbri</name></author><author><name>Roberta Bisconti</name></author><author><name>Andrea Chiocchio</name></author><author><name>Emiliano Trucchi</name></author><author><name>Daniele Canestrelli</name></author><author><name>Giorgio Bertorelle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Assigning individuals to their source populations is crucial for conservation research, especially for endangered species threatened by illegal trade and translocations. Genetic assignment can be achieved with different types of molecular markers, but technical advantages and cost saving are recently promoting the shift from short tandem repeats (STRs) to single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs). Here, we designed, developed, and tested a small panel of SNPs for cost-effective geographic assignment of individuals with unknown origin of the endangered Mediterranean tortoise &lt;italic&gt;Testudo hermanni&lt;/italic&gt;. We started by performing a ddRAD-seq experiment on 70 wild individuals of &lt;italic&gt;T. hermanni&lt;/italic&gt; from 38 locations. Results obtained using 3,182 SNPs are comparable to those previously obtained using STR markers in terms of genetic structure and power to identify the macro-area of origin. However, our SNPs revealed further insights into the substructure in Western populations, especially in Southern Italy. A small panel of highly informative SNPs was then selected and tested by genotyping 190 individuals using the KASP genotyping chemistry. All the samples from wild populations of known geographic origin were genetically re-assigned with high accuracy to the original population. This reduced SNPs panel represents an efficient molecular tool that enables individuals to be genotyped at low cost (less than €15 per sample) for geographical assignment and identification of hybrids. This information is crucial for the management in-situ of confiscated animals and their possible re-allocation in the wild. Our methodological pipeline can easily be extended to other species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471568" rel="alternate" title="From STRs to SNPs via ddRAD-seq: geographic assignment of confiscated tortoises at reduced costs (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471508</id><title>The genetic origin and architecture of sex determination (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.453390+00:00</updated><author><name>Tisham De</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Here, I demonstrate that sex determination and sexual dimorphism across tree of life are deeply related to polyamine biochemistry in cells, especially to the synteny of genes: [SAT1-NR0B1], [SAT2-SHBG] and DMRT1. This synteny was found to be most distinct in mammals. Further, the common protein domain of SAT1 and SAT2 - PF00583 was shown to be present in the genome of the last universal common ancestor (LUCA). Protein domain-domain interaction analysis of LUCA’s genes suggests the possibility that LUCA had developed an immune defence against viruses. This domain-domain interaction analysis is the first scientific evidence indicating that viruses existed at least 3.5 billions years ago and probably co-existed with LUCA on early Hadean Earth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471508" rel="alternate" title="The genetic origin and architecture of sex determination (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471710</id><title>Transcriptomic modulation in response to an intoxication with deltamethrin in Triatoma infestans, vector of Chagas disease (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.453493+00:00</updated><author><name>Lucila Traverso</name></author><author><name>Jose Manuel Latorre Estivalis</name></author><author><name>Gabriel da Rocha Fernandes</name></author><author><name>Georgina Fronza</name></author><author><name>Patricia Lobbia</name></author><author><name>Gastón Mougabure Cueto</name></author><author><name>Sheila Ons</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Triatoma infestans&lt;/italic&gt; is the main vector of Chagas disease in the Southern Cone. The resistance to pyrethroid insecticides developed by populations of this species impairs the effectiveness of vector control campaigns in wide regions of Argentina. The study of the global transcriptomic response to pyrethroid insecticides is important to deepen the knowledge about detoxification in triatomines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methodology and findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used RNA-Seq to explore the early transcriptomic response of &lt;italic&gt;T. infestans&lt;/italic&gt; after intoxication with deltamethrin. We were able to assemble a complete transcriptome of this vector and found evidence of differentially expressed genes belonging to diverse families such as chemosensory and odorant-binding proteins, ABC transporters and heat-shock proteins. Moreover, genes related to transcription and translation, energetic metabolism and cuticle rearrangements were also modulated. Finally, we characterized the repertoire of previously uncharacterized detoxification-related gene families in &lt;italic&gt;T. infestans&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Rhodnius prolixus&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions and significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our work contributes to the understanding of the detoxification response in vectors of Chagas disease. Given the absence of genomic information from &lt;italic&gt;T. infestans&lt;/italic&gt;, the analysis presented here constitutes a resource for molecular and physiological studies in this species. The results increase the knowledge on detoxification processes in vectors of Chagas disease, and provide relevant information to explore new potential insecticide resistance mechanisms in these insects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chagas disease affects millions of people worldwide. In the Southern Cone, the development of pyrethroid resistant populations from &lt;italic&gt;T. infestans&lt;/italic&gt; is related to vector persistence and affects the efficiency of vector control campaigns. Several studies have explored the causes of insecticide resistance in &lt;italic&gt;T. infestans&lt;/italic&gt; populations. However, the global transcriptomic response after insecticide treatment has not been analyzed in this species so far. In this study, we obtained transcriptomic information which allowed us to characterize important gene families despite the absence of genomic information. Furthermore, we performed a quantitative analysis of gene expression after deltamethrin intoxication. The results provided here increase the knowledge on detoxification processes in vectors of Chagas disease, which is essential for the design of new vector control strategies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471710" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptomic modulation in response to an intoxication with deltamethrin in Triatoma infestans, vector of Chagas disease (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471776</id><title>Aneuploidy influences the gene expression profiles in Saccharomyces pastorianus group I and II strains during fermentation. (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.453628+00:00</updated><author><name>Roberto de la Cerda</name></author><author><name>Karsten Hookamp</name></author><author><name>Fiona Roche</name></author><author><name>Georgia Thompson</name></author><author><name>Soukaina Timouma</name></author><author><name>Daniela Delneri</name></author><author><name>Ursula M Bond</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The lager yeasts, &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces pastorianus&lt;/italic&gt;, are hybrids of &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces eubayanus&lt;/italic&gt; and are divided into two broad groups, Group I and II. The two groups evolved from at least one common hybridisation event but have subsequently diverged with Group I strains losing many &lt;italic&gt;S. cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; chromosomes while the Group II strains retain both sub-genomes. The complex genomes, containing orthologous alleles from the parental chromosomes, pose interesting questions regarding gene regulation and its impact on the fermentation properties of the strains. Superimposed on the presence of orthologous alleles are complexities of gene dosage due to the aneuploid nature of the genomes. We examined the contribution of the &lt;italic&gt;S. cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;S. eubayanus&lt;/italic&gt; alleles to the gene expression patterns of Group I and II strains during fermentation. We show that the relative expression of &lt;italic&gt;S. cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;S. eubayanus&lt;/italic&gt; orthologues is positively correlated with gene copy number. Despite the reduced &lt;italic&gt;S. cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; content in the Group I strain, &lt;italic&gt;S. cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; orthologues contribute to biochemical pathways upregulated during fermentation which may explain the retention of specific chromosomes in the strain. Conversely, &lt;italic&gt;S. eubayanus&lt;/italic&gt; genes are significantly overrepresented in the upregulated gene pool in the Group II strain. Comparison of the transcription profiles of Group I and II strains during fermentation identified both common and unique gene expression patterns, with gene copy number being a dominant contributory factor. Thus, the aneuploid genomes create complex patterns of gene expression during fermentation with gene dosage playing a crucial role both within and between strains.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471776" rel="alternate" title="Aneuploidy influences the gene expression profiles in Saccharomyces pastorianus group I and II strains during fermentation. (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.472038</id><title>A single-cell genomic strategy for alternative transcript start sites identification (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.453761+00:00</updated><author><name>Yanling Peng</name></author><author><name>Qitong Huang</name></author><author><name>Rui Kamada</name></author><author><name>Keiko Ozato</name></author><author><name>Yubo Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jun Zhu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Alternative transcription start sites (TSSs) usage plays a critical role in gene transcription regulation in mammals. However, precisely identifying alternative TSSs remains challenging at the genome-wide level. Here, we report a single-cell genomic technology for alternative TSSs annotation and cell heterogeneity detection. In the method, we utilize Fluidigm C1 system to capture individual cells of interest, SMARTer cDNA synthesis kit to recover full-length cDNAs, then dual priming oligonucleotide system to specifically enrich TSSs for genomic analysis. We apply this method to a genome-wide study of alternative TSSs identification in two different IFN-β stimulated mouse embryonic fibroblasts (MEFs). We quantify the performance of our method and find it as accurate as other single cell methods for the detection of TSSs. Our data are also clearly discriminate two IFN-β stimulated MEFs. Moreover, our results indicate 82% expressed genes in these two cell types containing multiple TSSs, which is much higher than previous predictions based on CAGE (58%) or empirical determination (54%) in various cell types. This indicates that alternative TSSs are more pervasive than expected and implies our strategy could position them at an unprecedented sensitivity. It would be helpful for elucidating their biological insights in future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.472038" rel="alternate" title="A single-cell genomic strategy for alternative transcript start sites identification (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471225</id><title>Inter-species geographic signatures for tracing horizontal gene transfer and long-term persistence of carbapenem resistance (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.454039+00:00</updated><author><name>Rauf Salamzade</name></author><author><name>Abigail L. Manson</name></author><author><name>Bruce J. Walker</name></author><author><name>Thea Brennan-Krohn</name></author><author><name>Colin J. Worby</name></author><author><name>Peijun Ma</name></author><author><name>Lorrie L. He</name></author><author><name>Terrance P. Shea</name></author><author><name>James Qu</name></author><author><name>Sinéad B. Chapman</name></author><author><name>Whitney Howe</name></author><author><name>Sarah K. Young</name></author><author><name>Jenna I. Wurster</name></author><author><name>Mary L. Delaney</name></author><author><name>Sanjat Kanjilal</name></author><author><name>Andrew B. Onderdonk</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Pironti</name></author><author><name>Cassiana E. Bittencourt</name></author><author><name>Gabrielle M. Gussin</name></author><author><name>Diane Kim</name></author><author><name>Ellena M. Peterson</name></author><author><name>Mary Jane Ferraro</name></author><author><name>David C. Hooper</name></author><author><name>Erica S. Shenoy</name></author><author><name>Christina A. Cuomo</name></author><author><name>Deborah T. Hung</name></author><author><name>Lisa A. Cosimi</name></author><author><name>Susan S. Huang</name></author><author><name>James E. Kirby</name></author><author><name>Virginia M. Pierce</name></author><author><name>Roby P. Bhattacharyya</name></author><author><name>Ashlee M. Earl</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carbapenem-resistant &lt;italic&gt;Enterobacterales&lt;/italic&gt; (CRE) are an urgent global health threat. Inferring the dynamics of local CRE dissemination is currently limited by our inability to confidently trace the spread of resistance determinants to unrelated bacterial hosts. Whole genome sequence comparison is useful for identifying CRE clonal transmission and outbreaks, but high-frequency horizontal gene transfer (HGT) of carbapenem resistance genes and subsequent genome rearrangement complicate tracing the local persistence and mobilization of these genes across organisms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To overcome this limitation, we developed a new approach to identify recent HGT of large, near-identical plasmid segments across species boundaries, which also allowed us to overcome technical challenges with genome assembly. We applied this to complete and near-complete genome assemblies to examine the local spread of CRE in a systematic, prospective collection of all CRE, as well as time- and species-matched carbapenem susceptible &lt;italic&gt;Enterobacterales&lt;/italic&gt;, isolated from patients from four U.S. hospitals over nearly five years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our CRE collection comprised a diverse range of species, lineages and carbapenem resistance mechanisms, many of which were encoded on a variety of promiscuous plasmid types. We found and quantified rearrangement, persistence, and repeated transfer of plasmid segments, including those harboring carbapenemases, between organisms over multiple years. Some plasmid segments were found to be strongly associated with specific locales, thus representing &lt;italic&gt;geographic signatures&lt;/italic&gt; that make it possible to trace recent and localized HGT events.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Functional analysis of these signatures revealed genes commonly found in plasmids of nosocomial pathogens, such as functions required for plasmid retention and spread, as well survival against a variety of antibiotic and antiseptics common to the hospital environment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Collectively, the framework we developed provides a clearer, high resolution picture of the epidemiology of antibiotic resistance importation, spread, and persistence in patients and healthcare networks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471225" rel="alternate" title="Inter-species geographic signatures for tracing horizontal gene transfer and long-term persistence of carbapenem resistance (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.472007</id><title>Modulation of the Drosophila Transcriptome by Developmental Exposure to Alcohol (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.454603+00:00</updated><author><name>Tatiana V Morozova</name></author><author><name>Vijay Shankar</name></author><author><name>Rebecca A MacPherson</name></author><author><name>Trudy F C Mackay</name></author><author><name>Robert R H Anholt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Prenatal exposure to ethanol can cause fetal alcohol spectrum disorder (FASD), a prevalent, preventable pediatric disorder. Identifying genetic risk alleles for FASD is challenging since time, dose, and frequency of exposure are often unknown, and manifestations of FASD are diverse and evident long after exposure. &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; is an excellent model to study the genetic basis of the effects of developmental alcohol exposure since many individuals of the same genotype can be reared under controlled environmental conditions. We used 96 sequenced, wild-derived inbred lines from the &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; Genetic Reference Panel (DGRP) to profile genome-wide transcript abundances in young adult flies that developed on ethanol-supplemented medium or standard culture medium. We found substantial genetic variation in gene expression in response to ethanol with extensive sexual dimorphism.  We constructed sex-specific genetic networks associated with alcohol-dependent modulation of gene expression that include protein-coding genes, Novel Transcribed Regions (NTRs, postulated to encode long non-coding RNAs) and female-specific coordinated regulation of snoRNAs that regulate pseudouridylation of ribosomal RNA. We reared DGRP lines which showed extreme upregulation or downregulation of snoRNA expression during developmental alcohol exposure on standard or ethanol supplemented medium and demonstrated that developmental exposure to ethanol has genotype-specific effects on adult locomotor activity and sleep. There is significant and sex-specific natural genetic variation in the transcriptional response to developmental exposure to ethanol in Drosophila that comprises networks of genes affecting nervous system development and ethanol metabolism as well as networks of regulatory non-coding RNAs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.472007" rel="alternate" title="Modulation of the Drosophila Transcriptome by Developmental Exposure to Alcohol (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471676</id><title>Host immune responses to enzootic and invasive pathogen lineages vary in magnitude, timing, and efficacy (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.454839+00:00</updated><author><name>Coby A McDonald</name></author><author><name>C. Guilherme Becker</name></author><author><name>Carolina Lambertini</name></author><author><name>Luis Felipe Toledo</name></author><author><name>Celio FB Haddad</name></author><author><name>Kelly R Zamudio</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Infectious diseases of wildlife continue to pose a threat to biodiversity worldwide, yet pathogens are far from monolithic in virulence. Within the same pathogen species, virulence can vary considerably depending on strain or lineage, in turn eliciting variable host responses. One pathogen that has caused extensive biodiversity loss is the amphibian-killing fungus, Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis (Bd), which is comprised of a globally widespread hypervirulent lineage (Bd-GPL), and multiple geographically restricted lineages. Whereas host immunogenomic responses to Bd-GPL have been characterized in a number of amphibian species, immunogenomic responses to geographically-restricted, enzootic Bd lineages are unknown. To examine lineage-specific host immune responses to Bd, we exposed a species of pumpkin toadlet, Brachycephalus pitanga, which is endemic to Brazil's Southern Atlantic Forest, to either the Bd-GPL or the enzootic Bd-Asia-2/Brazil (hereafter Bd-Brazil) lineage. We quantified functional immunogenomic responses over the course of infection using differential gene expression tests and coexpression network analyses. Host immune responses varied significantly with Bd lineage. Toadlet responses to Bd-Brazil were weak at early infection (26 genes differentially expressed), peaked by mid-stage infection (435 genes) and were nearly fully resolved by late-stage disease (9 genes). In contrast, responses to Bd-GPL were magnified and delayed; toadlets differentially expressed 97 genes early, 86 genes at mid-stage infection, and 728 genes by late-stage infection. Given that infection intensity did not vary between mid- and late-stage disease, this suggests that pumpkin toadlets may be at least partially tolerant to the geographically-restricted Bd-Brazil lineage. In contrast, mortality was higher in Bd-GPL-infected toadlets, suggesting that late-stage immune activation against Bd-GPL was not protective and was consistent with immune dysregulation previously observed in other species. Our results demonstrate that both the timing of immune response and the particular immune pathways activated are specific to Bd lineage. Within regions where multiple Bd lineages co-occur, and given continued global Bd movement, these differential host responses may influence not only individual disease outcome, but transmission dynamics at the population and community levels.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471676" rel="alternate" title="Host immune responses to enzootic and invasive pathogen lineages vary in magnitude, timing, and efficacy (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471551</id><title>A target capture approach for phylogenomic analyses at multiple evolutionary timescales in rosewoods (Dalbergia spp.) and the legume family (Fabaceae) (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.455002+00:00</updated><author><name>Simon Crameri</name></author><author><name>Simone Fior</name></author><author><name>Stefan Zoller</name></author><author><name>Alex Widmer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the genetic changes associated with the evolution of biological diversity is of fundamental interest to molecular ecologists. The assessment of genetic variation at hundreds or thousands of unlinked genetic loci forms a sound basis to address questions ranging from micro-to macro-evolutionary timescales, and is now possible thanks to advances in sequencing technology. Major difficulties are associated with i) the lack of genomic resources for many taxa, especially from tropical biodiversity hotspots, ii) scaling the numbers of individuals analyzed and loci sequenced, and iii) building tools for reproducible bioinformatic analyses of such datasets. To address these challenges, we developed a set of target capture probes for phylogenomic studies of the highly diverse, pantropically distributed and economically significant rosewoods (&lt;italic&gt;Dalbergia&lt;/italic&gt; spp.), explored the performance of an overlapping probe set for target capture across the legume family (Fabaceae), and built a general-purpose bioinformatics pipeline. Phylogenomic analyses of &lt;italic&gt;Dalbergia&lt;/italic&gt; species from Madagascar yielded highly resolved and well supported hypotheses of evolutionary relationships. Population genomic analyses identified differences between closely related species and revealed the existence of a potentially new species, suggesting that the diversity of Malagasy &lt;italic&gt;Dalbergia&lt;/italic&gt; species has been underestimated. Analyses at the family level corroborated previous findings by the recovery of monophyletic subfamilies and many well-known clades, as well as high levels of gene tree discordance, especially near the root of the family. The new genomic and bioinformatics resources will hopefully advance systematics and ecological genetics research in legumes, and promote conservation of the highly diverse and endangered &lt;italic&gt;Dalbergia&lt;/italic&gt; rosewoods.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471551" rel="alternate" title="A target capture approach for phylogenomic analyses at multiple evolutionary timescales in rosewoods (Dalbergia spp.) and the legume family (Fabaceae) (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>