<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.269997+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469176</id><title>Single-cell RNA sequencing of Plasmodium vivax sporozoites reveals stage- and species-specific transcriptomic signatures (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.270344+00:00</updated><author><name>Anthony A. Ruberto</name></author><author><name>Caitlin Bourke</name></author><author><name>Amélie Vantaux</name></author><author><name>Steven P. Maher</name></author><author><name>Aaron Jex</name></author><author><name>Benoit Witkowski</name></author><author><name>Georges Snounou</name></author><author><name>Ivo Mueller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium vivax&lt;/italic&gt; sporozoites reside in the salivary glands of a mosquito before infecting a human host. Previous transcriptome-wide studies in populations of these forms were limited in their ability to elucidate cell-to-cell variation, thereby masking cellular states potentially important in understanding transmission outcomes. In this study, we performed transcription profiling on 9,947 &lt;italic&gt;P. vivax&lt;/italic&gt; sporozoites to assess the extent to which they differ at single-cell resolution. We show that sporozoites residing in the mosquito’s salivary glands exist in distinct developmental states, as defined by their transcriptomic signatures. Additionally, relative to &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum, P. vivax&lt;/italic&gt; displays overlapping and unique gene usage patterns, highlighting conserved and species-specific gene programs. Notably, distinguishing &lt;italic&gt;P. vivax&lt;/italic&gt; from &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; were a subset of &lt;italic&gt;P. vivax&lt;/italic&gt; sporozoites expressing genes associated with translational regulation and repression. Finally, our comparison of single-cell transcriptomic data from &lt;italic&gt;P. vivax&lt;/italic&gt; sporozoite and erythrocytic forms reveals gene usage patterns unique to sporozoites. In defining the transcriptomic signatures of individual &lt;italic&gt;P. vivax&lt;/italic&gt; sporozoites, our work provides new insights into the factors driving their developmental trajectory and lays the groundwork for a more comprehensive &lt;italic&gt;P. vivax&lt;/italic&gt; cell atlas.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469176" rel="alternate" title="Single-cell RNA sequencing of Plasmodium vivax sporozoites reveals stage- and species-specific transcriptomic signatures (14 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469656</id><title>Parent-offspring inference in inbred populations (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.270580+00:00</updated><author><name>Jan-Niklas Runge</name></author><author><name>Barbara König</name></author><author><name>Anna K. Lindholm</name></author><author><name>Andres Bendesky</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genealogical relationships are fundamental components of genetic studies. However, it is often challenging to infer correct and complete pedigrees even when genome-wide information is available. For example, inbreeding can obfuscate genetic differences between individuals, making it difficult to even distinguish first-degree relatives such as parent-offspring from full siblings. Similarly, genotyping errors can interfere with the detection of genetic similarity between parents and their offspring. Inbreeding is common in natural, domesticated, and experimental populations and genotyping of these populations often has more errors than in human datasets, so efficient methods for building pedigrees under these conditions are necessary. Here, we present a new method for parent-offspring inference in inbred pedigrees called &lt;italic&gt;SPORE&lt;/italic&gt; (Specific Parent-Offspring Relationship Estimation). &lt;italic&gt;SPORE&lt;/italic&gt; is vastly superior to existing pedigree-inference methods at detecting parent-offspring relationships, in particular when inbreeding is high or in the presence of genotyping errors, or both. &lt;italic&gt;SPORE&lt;/italic&gt; therefore fills an important void in the arsenal of pedigree inference tools.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Knowing the genealogical relationships among individuals is critical for genetic analyses, such as for identifying the mutations that cause diseases or that contribute to valuable agricultural traits such as milk production. Although many tools exist for establishing pedigrees using genetic information, these tools fail when individuals are highly inbred, such as in domesticated animals, or in groups of people in which consanguineous matings are common. Furthermore, existing tools do not work well when genetic information has errors at levels observed in modern datasets. Here, we present a novel approach to solve these problems. Our method is significantly more accurate than existing tools and more tolerant of errors in the genetic data. We expect that our method, which is simple to use and computationally efficient, will be a useful tool in a diversity of settings, from the studies of human and natural populations, to agricultural and experimental settings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469656" rel="alternate" title="Parent-offspring inference in inbred populations (9 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469911</id><title>The ADAR1 editome reveals drivers of editing-specificity for ADAR1-isoforms (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.270737+00:00</updated><author><name>Renata Kleinova</name></author><author><name>Alina F. Leuchtenberger</name></author><author><name>Claudio Lo Giudice</name></author><author><name>Andrea Tanzer</name></author><author><name>Sophia Derdak</name></author><author><name>Ernesto Picardi</name></author><author><name>Michael F. Jantsch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Adenosine deaminase acting on RNA (ADAR) (also known as ADAR1) promotes A-to-I conversion in double-stranded and highly structured RNAs. ADAR1 has two isoforms transcribed from different promoters: ADAR1p150, which is mainly cytoplasmic and interferon-inducible, and constitutively expressed ADAR1p110 that is primarily localized in the nucleus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mutations in ADAR1 cause Aicardi – Goutières syndrome (AGS), a severe autoinflammatory disease in humans associated with aberrant IFN production. In mice, deletion of ADAR1 or selective knockout of the p150 isoform alone leads to embryonic lethality driven by overexpression of interferon-stimulated genes. This phenotype can be rescued by concurrent deletion of cytoplasmic dsRNA-sensor MDA5. These findings indicate that the interferon- inducible p150 isoform is indispensable and cannot be rescued by the ADAR1p110 isoform. Nevertheless, editing sites uniquely targeted by ADAR1p150 but also mechanisms of isoform- specificity remain elusive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we combine RIP-seq on human cells expressing ADAR1 isoforms and combine this with analysis of isoform-specific editing patterns in genetically modified mouse cells to extensively investigate ADAR1-isoform binding- and editing characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moreover, using mutated ADAR variants, we examine the effect of two unique features of ADAR1p150 on its target specificity: 1) cytoplasmic localization and 2) Z-DNA binding domain &lt;italic&gt;α&lt;/italic&gt;. Our findings indicate that ZBD&lt;italic&gt;α&lt;/italic&gt; contributes only minimally to p150 editing-specificity and that isoform-specific editing is directed mainly by the cytoplasmic localization of the editase.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469911" rel="alternate" title="The ADAR1 editome reveals drivers of editing-specificity for ADAR1-isoforms (9 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469473</id><title>Genomic regions associated with chocolate spot (Botrytis fabae Sard.) resistance in faba bean (Vicia faba L.) (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.270914+00:00</updated><author><name>Tadesse S. Gela</name></author><author><name>Margaret Bruce</name></author><author><name>Wei Chang</name></author><author><name>Frederick L. Stoddard</name></author><author><name>Alan H. Schulman</name></author><author><name>Albert Vandenberg</name></author><author><name>Hamid Khazaei</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chocolate spot (CS), caused by &lt;italic&gt;Botrytis fabae&lt;/italic&gt; Sard., is an important threat to global faba bean production. Growing resistant faba bean cultivars is, therefore, paramount to preventing yield loss. To date, there have been no reported quantitative trait loci (QTLs) associated with CS resistance in faba bean. The objective of this study was to identify genomic regions associated with CS resistance using a recombinant inbred line (RIL) population derived from resistant accession ILB 938. A total of 165 RILs from the cross Mélodie/2 × ILB 938/2 were genotyped and evaluated for CS reactions under replicated controlled climate conditions. QTL analysis identified five loci contributing to CS resistance on faba bean chromosomes 1 and 6, accounting for 5.0–23.4% of the total phenotypic variance. The sequences of SNP markers linked to resistance QTLs on chromosome 1 that have the largest effects encode multiple classes of putative disease and/or defense-related genes. The results of this study not only provide insight into disease-resistance QTLs, but also can be used as potential targets for marker-assisted breeding in faba bean genetic improvement for CS resistance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key message&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;QTL mapping identified key genomic regions associated with chocolate spot resistance on faba bean chromosomes 1 and 6, which may serve as novel genetic tools to develop disease-resistant faba bean cultivars.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469473" rel="alternate" title="Genomic regions associated with chocolate spot (Botrytis fabae Sard.) resistance in faba bean (Vicia faba L.) (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.468991</id><title>An allelic series of spontaneous mutations in Rorb cause a gait phenotype, retinal abnormalities, and transcriptomic changes relevant to human neurodevelopmental conditions (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.271085+00:00</updated><author><name>George C Murray</name></author><author><name>Jason Bubier</name></author><author><name>Oraya J Zinder</name></author><author><name>Belinda Harris</name></author><author><name>James Clark</name></author><author><name>Mia-Cara Christopher</name></author><author><name>Courtany Hanley</name></author><author><name>Harianto Tjong</name></author><author><name>Meihong Li</name></author><author><name>Chew Yee Ngan</name></author><author><name>Laura Reinholdt</name></author><author><name>Robert W Burgess</name></author><author><name>Abby LD Tadenev</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Rorb encodes the Retinoic Acid Receptor-related orphan receptor beta. Mutations in either of the two transcripts of Rorb cause defects in multiple systems, including abnormal photoreceptor abundance and morphology in the retina and a characteristic high-stepper or duck-like gait arising from dysfunction of interneurons in the spinal cord. Rorb is also important for cortical development and cell fate specification in mice. Rorb variants segregate with epilepsy and comorbidities such as intellectual disability in numerous clinical cases. Here we describe five mouse strains with spontaneous mutations in Rorb identified by their gait phenotype. These mutations affect different domains and isoforms of Rorb, which correspond to the spectrum of anatomical and physiological phenotypes exhibited by these mice. Gene set analysis in Rorb mutants implicates pathways associated with development and nervous system function, and differential gene expression analysis indicates changes in numerous genes related to epilepsy, bipolar disorder, and autism spectrum disorder (ASD). Many of these genes and their protein products are known to interact during synapse formation and neuronal activity. These findings further illuminate the role of Rorb in nervous system development, provide further evidence for an association between Rorb and several neurological conditions, and describe an allelic series of Rorb mutant mice that will be useful for dissecting thalamocortical afferent(TCA) development, neural cell fate determination, and as animal models exhibiting transcriptomic shifts in neurological conditions such as epilepsy, bipolar disorder, and ASD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.468991" rel="alternate" title="An allelic series of spontaneous mutations in Rorb cause a gait phenotype, retinal abnormalities, and transcriptomic changes relevant to human neurodevelopmental conditions (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469702</id><title>High-quality reference genome for an arid-adapted mammal, the banner-tailed kangaroo rat (Dipodomys spectabilis) (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.271287+00:00</updated><author><name>Avril M. Harder</name></author><author><name>Kimberly K.O. Walden</name></author><author><name>Nicholas J. Marra</name></author><author><name>Janna R. Willoughby</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Kangaroo rats in the genus &lt;italic&gt;Dipodomys&lt;/italic&gt; are found in a variety of habitat types in western North America, including deserts, arid and semi-arid grasslands, and scrublands. Many &lt;italic&gt;Dipodomys&lt;/italic&gt; species are experiencing strong population declines due to increasing habitat fragmentation, with two species listed as federally endangered. The precarious state of many &lt;italic&gt;Dipodomys&lt;/italic&gt; populations, including those occupying extreme environments, make species of this genus valuable subjects for studying the impacts of habitat degradation and fragmentation on population genomic patterns and for characterizing the genomic bases of adaptation to harsh conditions. To facilitate exploration of such questions, we assembled and annotated a reference genome for the banner-tailed kangaroo rat (&lt;italic&gt;D. spectabilis&lt;/italic&gt;) using PacBio HiFi sequencing reads, providing a more contiguous genomic resource than two previously assembled &lt;italic&gt;Dipodomys&lt;/italic&gt; genomes. Using the HiFi data for &lt;italic&gt;D. spectabilis&lt;/italic&gt; and publicly available sequencing data for two other &lt;italic&gt;Dipodomys&lt;/italic&gt; species (&lt;italic&gt;D. ordii&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;D. stephensi&lt;/italic&gt;), we demonstrate the utility of this new assembly for studies of congeners by conducting inference of historic effective population sizes (&lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;e&lt;/sub&gt;) and linking these patterns to the species’ current extinction risk statuses. The genome assembly presented here will serve as a valuable resource for population and conservation genomic studies of &lt;italic&gt;Dipodomys&lt;/italic&gt; species, comparative genomic research within mammals and rodents, and investigations into genomic adaptation to extreme environments and changing landscapes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kangaroo rats in the genus &lt;italic&gt;Dipodomys&lt;/italic&gt; occur in a wide variety of habitat types, ranging from scrublands to arid deserts, and are increasingly impacted by habitat fragmentation with populations of many species in strong decline. To facilitate population and conservation genomic studies of &lt;italic&gt;Dipodomys&lt;/italic&gt; species, we generated the first reference genome assembly for the extensively studied banner-tailed kangaroo rat (&lt;italic&gt;D. spectabilis&lt;/italic&gt;) from long read PacBio sequencing data. The genome assembly presented here will serve as a valuable resource for studies of &lt;italic&gt;Dipodomys&lt;/italic&gt; species—which have long served as ecological and physiological models for the study of osmoregulation—comparative genomic surveys of mammals and rodents, and investigations into genomic adaptation to extreme environments and changing landscapes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469702" rel="alternate" title="High-quality reference genome for an arid-adapted mammal, the banner-tailed kangaroo rat (Dipodomys spectabilis) (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.469203</id><title>High Resolution Single Cell Maps Reveals Distinct Cell Organization and Function Across Different Regions of the Human Intestine (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.271438+00:00</updated><author><name>John W. Hickey</name></author><author><name>Winston R. Becker</name></author><author><name>Stephanie A. Nevins</name></author><author><name>Aaron Horning</name></author><author><name>Almudena Espin Perez</name></author><author><name>Roxanne Chiu</name></author><author><name>Derek C. Chen</name></author><author><name>Daniel Cotter</name></author><author><name>Edward D. Esplin</name></author><author><name>Annika K. Weimer</name></author><author><name>Chiara Caraccio</name></author><author><name>Vishal Venkataraaman</name></author><author><name>Christian M. Schürch</name></author><author><name>Sarah Black</name></author><author><name>Maria Brbić</name></author><author><name>Kaidi Cao</name></author><author><name>Jure Leskovec</name></author><author><name>Zhengyan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Shin Lin</name></author><author><name>Teri Longacre</name></author><author><name>Sylvia K. Plevitis</name></author><author><name>Yiing Lin</name></author><author><name>Garry P. Nolan</name></author><author><name>William J. Greenleaf</name></author><author><name>Michael Snyder</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The colon is a complex organ that promotes digestion, extracts nutrients, participates in immune surveillance, maintains critical symbiotic relationships with microbiota, and affects overall health. To better understand its organization, functions, and its regulation at a single cell level, we performed CODEX multiplexed imaging, as well as single nuclear RNA and open chromatin assays across eight different intestinal sites of four donors. Through systematic analyses we find cell compositions differ dramatically across regions of the intestine, demonstrate the complexity of epithelial subtypes, and find that the same cell types are organized into distinct neighborhoods and communities highlighting distinct immunological niches present in the intestine. We also map gene regulatory differences in these cells suggestive of a regulatory differentiation cascade, and associate intestinal disease heritability with specific cell types. These results describe the complexity of the cell composition, regulation, and organization for this organ, and serve as an important reference map for understanding human biology and disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.469203" rel="alternate" title="High Resolution Single Cell Maps Reveals Distinct Cell Organization and Function Across Different Regions of the Human Intestine (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469878</id><title>Optimizing bulk segregant analysis of drug resistance using Plasmodium falciparum genetic crosses conducted in humanized mice (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.271719+00:00</updated><author><name>Katelyn Vendrely Brenneman</name></author><author><name>Xue Li</name></author><author><name>Sudhir Kumar</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Delgado</name></author><author><name>Lisa A. Checkley</name></author><author><name>Douglas A. Shoue</name></author><author><name>Ann Reyes</name></author><author><name>Biley Abatiyow</name></author><author><name>Meseret Haile</name></author><author><name>Rupam Tripura</name></author><author><name>Tom Peto</name></author><author><name>Dysoley Lek</name></author><author><name>Katrina A. Button-Simons</name></author><author><name>Stefan H.I. Kappe</name></author><author><name>Mehul Dhorda</name></author><author><name>Francois Nosten</name></author><author><name>Standwell C. Nkhoma</name></author><author><name>Ian H Cheeseman</name></author><author><name>Ashley M Vaughan</name></author><author><name>Michael T Ferdig</name></author><author><name>Tim JC Anderson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Classical genetic crosses in malaria parasites involve isolation, genotyping, and phenotyping of multiple progeny parasites, which is time consuming and laborious. Bulk segregant analysis (BSA) offers a powerful and efficient alternative to identify loci underlying complex traits in the human malaria parasite, Plasmodium falciparum. 
Methods: We have used BSA, which combines genetic crosses using humanized mice with pooled sequencing of progeny populations to measure changes in allele frequency following selection with antimalarial drugs. We used dihydroartemisinin (DHA) drug selection in two genetic crosses (Mal31xKH004 and NF54xNHP1337). We specifically investigated how synchronization, cryopreservation, and the drug selection regimen of progeny pools impacted the success of BSA experiments.
Findings: We detected a strong and repeatable quantitative trait locus (QTL) at chr13 kelch13 locus in both crosses, but did not detect QTLs at ferredoxin (fd), the apicoplast ribosomal protein S10 (arps10), multidrug resistance protein 2 (mdr2). QTLs were detected using synchronized, but not unsynchronized pools, consistent with the stage-specific action of DHA. We also successfully applied BSA to cryopreserved progeny pools.
Interpretation: Our results provide proof-of-principal of the utility of BSA for rapid, robust genetic mapping of drug resistance loci. Use of cryopreserved progeny pools expands the utility of BSA because we can conduct experiments using archived progeny pools from previous genetic crosses. BSA provides a powerful approach that complements traditional QTL methods for investigating the genetic architecture of resistance to antimalarials, and to reveal new or accessory loci contributing to artemisinin resistance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469878" rel="alternate" title="Optimizing bulk segregant analysis of drug resistance using Plasmodium falciparum genetic crosses conducted in humanized mice (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469627</id><title>The Mutational Dynamics of Short Tandem Repeats in Large, Multigenerational Families (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.271974+00:00</updated><author><name>Cody J. Steely</name></author><author><name>W. Scott Watkins</name></author><author><name>Lisa Baird</name></author><author><name>Lynn B. Jorde</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Short tandem repeats (STRs) are tandemly repeated sequences of 1-6 bp motifs. STRs compose approximately 3% of the genome, and mutations at STR loci have been linked to dozens of human diseases including amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, Friedreich ataxia, Huntington disease, and fragile X syndrome. Improving our understanding of these mutations would increase our knowledge of the mutational dynamics of the genome and may uncover additional loci that contribute to disease. Here, to estimate the genome-wide pattern of mutations at STR loci, we analyzed blood-derived whole-genome sequencing data for 544 individuals from 29 three-generation CEPH pedigrees. These pedigrees contain both sets of grandparents, the parents, and an average of 9 grandchildren per family. Using HipSTR we identified &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; STR mutations in the 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; generation of these pedigrees. Analyzing ~1.6 million STR loci, we estimate the empircal &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; STR mutation rate to be 5.24*10&lt;sup&gt;−5&lt;/sup&gt; mutations per locus per generation. We find that perfect repeats mutate ~2x more often than imperfect repeats. &lt;italic&gt;De novo&lt;/italic&gt; STRs are significantly enriched in &lt;italic&gt;Alu&lt;/italic&gt; elements (p &amp;lt; 2.2e-16). Approximately 30% of STR mutations occur within &lt;italic&gt;Alu&lt;/italic&gt; elements, which compose only ~11% of the genome, and ~10% are found in LINE-1 insertions, which compose ~17% of the genome. Phasing these &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; mutations to the parent of origin shows that parental transmission biases vary among families. We estimate the average number of &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; genome-wide STR mutations per individual to be ~85, which is similar to the average number of observed &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; single nucleotide variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469627" rel="alternate" title="The Mutational Dynamics of Short Tandem Repeats in Large, Multigenerational Families (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469527</id><title>Genome Assembly and Population Resequencing Reveal the Geographical Divergence of ‘Shanmei’ (Rubus corchorifolius) (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.272138+00:00</updated><author><name>Yinqing Yang</name></author><author><name>Kang Zhang</name></author><author><name>Ya Xiao</name></author><author><name>Lingkui Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yile Huang</name></author><author><name>Xing Li</name></author><author><name>Shumin Chen</name></author><author><name>Yansong Peng</name></author><author><name>Shuhua Yang</name></author><author><name>Yongbo Liu</name></author><author><name>Feng Cheng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Rubus corchorifolius&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt; (‘&lt;bold&gt;Shanmei&lt;/bold&gt;’ or mountain berry, 2n =14) is widely distributed in China, and its fruit has high nutritional and medicinal values. Here, we report a high-quality chromosome-scale &lt;bold&gt;genome assembly&lt;/bold&gt; of Shanmei, with a size of 215.69 Mb and encompassing 26,696 genes. Genome comparisons among Rosaceae species show that Shanmei and Fupenzi (&lt;italic&gt;Rubus chingii&lt;/italic&gt; Hu) are most closely related, and then is blackberry (&lt;italic&gt;Rubus occidentalis&lt;/italic&gt;). Further &lt;bold&gt;resequencing&lt;/bold&gt; of 101 samples of Shanmei collected from four regions in provinces of Yunnan, Hunan, Jiangxi, and Sichuan in South China reveals that the Hunan population of Shanmei possesses the highest diversity and may represent the relatively more ancestral population. Moreover, the Yunnan population undergoes strong selection based on nucleotide diversity, linkage disequilibrium, and the historical effective population size analyses. Furthermore, genes from candidate genomic regions that show strong &lt;bold&gt;divergence&lt;/bold&gt; are significantly enriched in flavonoid biosynthesis and plant hormone signal transduction, indicating the genetic basis of adaptation of Shanmei to the local environments. The high-quality genome sequences and the variome dataset of Shanmei provide valuable resources for breeding applications and for elucidating the &lt;bold&gt;genome evolution&lt;/bold&gt; and ecological adaptation of &lt;italic&gt;Rubus&lt;/italic&gt; species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469527" rel="alternate" title="Genome Assembly and Population Resequencing Reveal the Geographical Divergence of ‘Shanmei’ (Rubus corchorifolius) (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469779</id><title>Loss of CEP162 function at the primary cilium delays ciliogenesis and causes retinal ciliopathy in humans (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.272446+00:00</updated><author><name>Nafisa Nuzhat</name></author><author><name>Kristof Van Schil</name></author><author><name>Sandra Liakopoulos</name></author><author><name>Miriam Bauwens</name></author><author><name>Alfredo Duenas Rey</name></author><author><name>Stephan Käseberg</name></author><author><name>Melanie Jäger</name></author><author><name>Jason R. Willer</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Winter</name></author><author><name>Hanh Truong</name></author><author><name>Nuria Gruartmoner</name></author><author><name>Mattias Van Heetvelde</name></author><author><name>Joachim Wolf</name></author><author><name>Robert Merget</name></author><author><name>Sabine Grasshoff-Derr</name></author><author><name>Jo Van Dorpe</name></author><author><name>Anne Hoorens</name></author><author><name>Heidi Stöhr</name></author><author><name>Luke Mansard</name></author><author><name>Anne-Françoise Roux</name></author><author><name>Thomas Langmann</name></author><author><name>Katharina Dannhausen</name></author><author><name>David Rosenkranz</name></author><author><name>Karl Martin Wissing</name></author><author><name>Michel Van Lint</name></author><author><name>Heidi Rossmann</name></author><author><name>Friederike Häuser</name></author><author><name>Peter Nürnberg</name></author><author><name>Holger Thiele</name></author><author><name>Ulrich Zechner</name></author><author><name>Jillian N. Pearring</name></author><author><name>Elfride De Baere</name></author><author><name>Hanno J. Bolz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ciliopathies often comprise retinal degeneration since the photoreceptor’s outer segment is an adapted primary cilium. CEP162 is a distal end centriolar protein required for proper transition zone assembly during ciliogenesis and whose loss causes ciliopathy in zebrafish. CEP162 has so far not been implicated in human disease. Here, we identified a homozygous &lt;italic&gt;CEP162&lt;/italic&gt; frameshift variant, c.1935dupA (p.(E646R*5)), in retinitis pigmentosa patients from two unrelated Moroccan families, likely representing a founder allele. We found that even though mRNA levels were reduced, the truncated CEP162-E646R*5 protein was expressed and localized to the mitotic spindle during mitosis, but not at the basal body of the cilium. In &lt;italic&gt;CEP162&lt;/italic&gt; knockdown cells, expression of the truncated CEP162-E646R*5 protein is unable to restore ciliation indicating its loss of function at the cilium. In patient fibroblasts, cilia overcome the absence of CEP162 from the primary cilium by delaying ciliogenesis through the persistence of CP110 at the mother centriole. The patient fibroblasts are ultimately able to extend some abnormally long cilia that are missing key transition zone components. Defective transition zone formation likely disproportionately affects the long-living ciliary outer segment of photoreceptors resulting in retinal dystrophy. CEP162 is expressed in human retina, and we show that wild-type CEP162, but not truncated CEP162-E646R*5, specifically localizes to the distal end of centrioles of mouse photoreceptor cilia. Together, our genetic, cell-based, and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; modeling establish that CEP162 deficiency causes retinal ciliopathy in humans.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SIGNIFICANCE STATEMENT&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ciliopathies often comprise retinal degeneration since the photoreceptor’s outer segment is an adapted primary cilium. CEP162 is a basal body protein required for proper transition zone assembly during ciliogenesis and has so far not been implicated in human disease. Using genetic, cell-based, and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; studies, we show that a biallelic mutation of &lt;italic&gt;CEP162&lt;/italic&gt; causes late-onset human retinal degeneration. This mutation specifically hinders CEP162 function at the cilia, leading to impaired transition zone assembly and delayed formation of dysmorphic cilia. Studies in mouse photoreceptors support that absence of CEP162 could lead to defective outer segments. The discovery of novel ciliopathy genes, such as &lt;italic&gt;CEP162,&lt;/italic&gt; advances our insight into cell-specific functions of the primary cilium.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469779" rel="alternate" title="Loss of CEP162 function at the primary cilium delays ciliogenesis and causes retinal ciliopathy in humans (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469505</id><title>Genome-wide association studies and genomic selection assays made in a large sample of cacao (Theobroma cacao L.) germplasm reveal significant marker-trait associations and good predictive value for improving yield potential (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.272903+00:00</updated><author><name>Frances L. Bekele</name></author><author><name>Gillian G. Bidaisee</name></author><author><name>Mathilde Allegre</name></author><author><name>Xavier Argout</name></author><author><name>Olivier Fouet</name></author><author><name>Michel Boccara</name></author><author><name>Duraisamy Saravanakumar</name></author><author><name>Isaac Bekele</name></author><author><name>Claire Lanaud</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A genome-wide association study was undertaken to unravel marker-trait associations (MTAs) between SNP markers and yield-related traits. It involved a subset of 421 cacao accessions from the large and diverse collection conserved &lt;italic&gt;ex situ&lt;/italic&gt; at the International Cocoa Genebank Trinidad. An average linkage disequilibrium (r&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;) of 0.10 at 5.2 Mb was found across several chromosomes. Seventeen significant (&lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt; ≤ 8.17 × 10&lt;sup&gt;-5&lt;/sup&gt; (–log10 (p) = 4.088)) MTAs of interest, which accounted for 5 to 17% of the explained phenotypic variation, were identified using a Mixed Linear Model in TASSEL version 5.2.50. The most significant MTAs identified were related to seed number and seed length on chromosome 7 and seed number on chromosome 1. Other significant MTAs involved seed length to width ratio on chromosomes 3 and 5 and seed length on chromosomes 4 and 9. It was noteworthy that several yield-related traits, &lt;italic&gt;viz&lt;/italic&gt;., seed length, seed length to width ratio and seed number were associated with markers on different chromosomes, indicating their polygenic nature. Approximately 40 candidate genes that encode embryo and seed development, protein synthesis, carbohydrate transport and lipid biosynthesis and transport were identified in this study. A significant association of fruit surface anthocyanin intensity co-localised with MYB-related protein 308 on chromosome 4. Testing of a genomic selection approach revealed good predictive value (GEBV) for economic traits such as seed number (GEBV = 0.611), seed length (0.6199), seed width (0.5435), seed length to width ratio (0.5503), seed/cotyledon mass (0.6014) and ovule number (0.6325). The findings of this study could facilitate genomic selection and marker-assisted breeding of cacao thereby expediting improvement in the yield potential of cacao planting material.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469505" rel="alternate" title="Genome-wide association studies and genomic selection assays made in a large sample of cacao (Theobroma cacao L.) germplasm reveal significant marker-trait associations and good predictive value for improving yield potential (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469645</id><title>Genomic variation across a clinical Cryptococcus population linked to disease outcome (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.273102+00:00</updated><author><name>Poppy Sephton-Clark</name></author><author><name>Jennifer L. Tenor</name></author><author><name>Dena L. Toffaletti</name></author><author><name>Nancy Meyers</name></author><author><name>Charles Giamberardino</name></author><author><name>Síle F. Molloy</name></author><author><name>Adrienne Chan</name></author><author><name>Tarsizio Chikaonda</name></author><author><name>Robert Heyderman</name></author><author><name>Mina Hosseinipour</name></author><author><name>Newton Kalata</name></author><author><name>Cecilia Kanyama</name></author><author><name>Christopher Kukacha</name></author><author><name>Duncan Lupiya</name></author><author><name>Henry C. Mwandumba</name></author><author><name>Thomas Harrison</name></author><author><name>Tihana Bicanic</name></author><author><name>John R. Perfect</name></author><author><name>Christina A. Cuomo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Cryptococcus neoformans&lt;/italic&gt; is the causative agent of cryptococcosis, a disease with poor patient outcomes, accounting for approximately 180,000 deaths each year. Patient outcomes may be impacted by the underlying genetics of the infecting isolate, however, our current understanding of how genetic diversity contributes to clinical outcomes is limited. Here, we leverage clinical, in vitro growth and genomic data for 284 &lt;italic&gt;C. neoformans&lt;/italic&gt; isolates to identify clinically relevant pathogen variants within a population of clinical isolates from patients with HIV-associated cryptococcosis in Malawi. Through a genome-wide association study (GWAS) approach, we identify variants associated with fungal burden and growth rate. We also find both small and large-scale variation, including aneuploidy, associated with alternate growth phenotypes, which may impact the course of infection. Genes impacted by these variants are involved in transcriptional regulation, signal transduction, glycolysis, sugar transport, and glycosylation. When combined with clinical data, we show that growth within the CNS is reliant upon glycolysis in an animal model, and likely impacts patient mortality, as CNS burden modulates patient outcome. Additionally, we find genes with roles in sugar transport are under selection in the majority of these clinical isolates. Further, we demonstrate that two hypothetical proteins identified by GWAS impact virulence in animal models. Our approach illustrates links between genetic variation and clinically relevant phenotypes, shedding light on survival mechanisms within the CNS and pathways involved in this persistence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Infection outcomes for cryptococcosis, most commonly caused by &lt;italic&gt;C. neoformans&lt;/italic&gt;, are influenced by host immune responses, as well as host and pathogen genetics. Infecting yeast isolates are genetically diverse, however, we lack a deep understanding of how this diversity impacts patient outcomes. To better understand both clinical isolate diversity and how diversity contributes to infection outcome, we utilize a large collection of clinical &lt;italic&gt;C. neoformans&lt;/italic&gt; samples, isolated from patients enrolled in a clinical trial across 3 hospitals in Malawi. By combining whole-genome sequence data, clinical data, and in vitro growth data, we utilize genome-wide association approaches to examine the genetic basis of virulence. Genes with significant associations show virulence phenotypes in both murine and rabbit models, demonstrating that our approach successfully identifies links between genetic variation and biologically significant phenotypes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469645" rel="alternate" title="Genomic variation across a clinical Cryptococcus population linked to disease outcome (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469778</id><title>Genome assembly of the JD17 soybean provides a new reference genome for Comparative genomics (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.273489+00:00</updated><author><name>Xinxin Yi</name></author><author><name>Jing Liu</name></author><author><name>Shengcai Chen</name></author><author><name>Hao Wu</name></author><author><name>Min Liu</name></author><author><name>Qing Xu</name></author><author><name>Lingshan Lei</name></author><author><name>Seunghee Lee</name></author><author><name>Bao Zhang</name></author><author><name>Dave Kudrna</name></author><author><name>Wei Fan</name></author><author><name>Rod A. Wing</name></author><author><name>Chunyan Yang</name></author><author><name>Mengchen Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jianwei Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xuelu Wang</name></author><author><name>Nansheng Chen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cultivated soybean (&lt;italic&gt;Glycine max&lt;/italic&gt;) is an important source for protein and oil. Many elite cultivars with different traits have been developed for different conditions. Each soybean strain has its own genetic diversity, and the availability of more high-quality soybean genomes can enhance comparative genomic analysis for identifying genetic underpinnings for its unique traits. In this study, we constructed a high-quality &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; assembly of an elite soybean cultivar Jidou 17 (JD17) with chromsome contiguity and high accuracy. We annotated 52,840 gene models and reconstructed 74,054 high-quality full-length transcripts. We performed a genome-wide comparative analysis based on the reference genome of JD17 with three published soybeans (WM82, ZH13 and W05), which identified five large inversions and two large translocations specific to JD17, 20,984 - 46,912 PAVs spanning 13.1 - 46.9 Mb in size, and 5 - 53 large PAV clusters larger than 500kb. 1,695,741 - 3,664,629 SNPs and 446,689 - 800,489 Indels were identified and annotated between JD17 and them. Symbiotic nitrogen fixation (SNF) genes were identified and the effects from these variants were further evaluated. It was found that the coding sequences of 9 nitrogen fixation-related genes were greatly affected. The high-quality genome assembly of JD17 can serve as a valuable reference for soybean functional genomics research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469778" rel="alternate" title="Genome assembly of the JD17 soybean provides a new reference genome for Comparative genomics (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>