<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.609706+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.06.447246</id><title>A single amino acid in RTEL1 determines telomere length in mice (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.609958+00:00</updated><author><name>Riham Smoom</name></author><author><name>Catherine Lee May</name></author><author><name>Hannah Kolev</name></author><author><name>Yitzhak Reizel</name></author><author><name>Ashleigh Morgan</name></author><author><name>Klaus H. Kaestner</name></author><author><name>Yehuda Tzfati</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Maintaining optimal telomere length throughout life limits cancer and enables healthy aging. Yet, it is unclear how the telomere length set point is determined. Telomeres in the house mouse, &lt;italic&gt;Mus musculus,&lt;/italic&gt; are 2-4 times longer than human telomeres, limiting the use of the mouse as a model for telomere research. By introducing a single amino acid variation found in &lt;italic&gt;M. spretus&lt;/italic&gt; into the helicase RTEL1 of &lt;italic&gt;M. musculus,&lt;/italic&gt; we shortened its telomere length set point 2-3 times, implicating this variation in the dramatic difference in telomere length between the two mouse species. While the engineered mice are fertile and healthy, hepatocytes with short telomeres displayed reduced proliferation capacity. This ‘telomouse’ is a unique model for studying the implications of short telomeres in aging and cancer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.06.447246" rel="alternate" title="A single amino acid in RTEL1 determines telomere length in mice (37 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.11.447996</id><title>Development of the myzozoan aquatic parasite Perkinsus marinus as a versatile experimental genetic model organism (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.610180+00:00</updated><author><name>Elin Einarsson</name></author><author><name>Imen Lassadi</name></author><author><name>Jana Zielinski</name></author><author><name>Qingtian Guan</name></author><author><name>Tobias Wyler</name></author><author><name>Arnab Pain</name></author><author><name>Sebastian G Gornik</name></author><author><name>Ross F Waller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The phylum Perkinsozoa is an aquatic parasite lineage that has devastating effects on commercial and natural mollusc populations, and also comprises parasites of algae, fish and amphibians. They are related to, and share much of their biology with, dinoflagellates and apicomplexans and thus offer excellent genetic models for both parasitological and evolutionary studies. Genetic transformation has been previously achieved for select &lt;italic&gt;Perkinsus&lt;/italic&gt; spp. but with few tools for transgene expression and only limited selection efficacy. We thus sought to expand the power of experimental genetic tools for &lt;italic&gt;Perkinsus marinus&lt;/italic&gt; — the principal perkinsozoan model to date. We constructed a modular plasmid assembly system that enables expression of multiple genes simultaneously. We developed an efficient selection system for three drugs, puromycin, bleomycin and blasticidin, that achieves transformed cell populations in as little as three weeks. We developed and quantified eleven new promoters of variable expression strength. Furthermore, we identified that genomic integration of transgenes is predominantly via non-homologous recombination and often involves transgene fragmentation including deletion of some introduced elements. To counter these dynamic processes, we show that bi-cistronic transcripts using the viral 2A peptides can couple selection systems to the maintenance of the expression of a transgene of interest. Collectively, these new tools and insights provide new capacity to efficiently genetically modify and study &lt;italic&gt;Perkinsus&lt;/italic&gt; as an aquatic parasite and evolutionary model.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.11.447996" rel="alternate" title="Development of the myzozoan aquatic parasite Perkinsus marinus as a versatile experimental genetic model organism (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-06-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.12.448202</id><title>Comparative therapeutic strategies for preventing aortic rupture in a mouse model of vascular Ehlers Danlos syndrome (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.610376+00:00</updated><author><name>Anne Legrand</name></author><author><name>Charline Guery</name></author><author><name>Julie Faugeroux</name></author><author><name>Erika Fontaine</name></author><author><name>Amelie Gianfermi</name></author><author><name>Irmine Ferreira</name></author><author><name>Marie-christine Verpont</name></author><author><name>Salma Adham</name></author><author><name>Tristan Mirault</name></author><author><name>Juliette Hadchouel</name></author><author><name>Xavier Jeunemaitre</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We created a knock-in Col3a1+/G182R mouse model with spontaneous mortality caused by thoracic aortic rupture that recapitulates a rare vascular genetic disease of type III collagen, the vascular Ehlers-Danlos syndrome (vEDS). Investigation of this model showed lower survival rate in males caused by aortic rupture, thin non-inflammatory arteries and altered arterial collagen. Transcriptomic analysis of aortas showed upregulation of genes related to inflammation and cell stress response. Compared to water, survival rate of Col3a1+/G182R mice was not affected by beta-blockers (propranolol or celiprolol). Two other vasodilating anti-hypertensive agents (hydralazine, amlodipine) gave opposite results on aortic rupture and mortality rate. There was a spectacular beneficial effect of losartan, reversed by the cessation of its administration, and a marked deleterious effect of exogenous angiotensin II. These results suggest that blockade of the renin angiotensin system should be tested as a first-line medical therapy in patients with vEDS.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.12.448202" rel="alternate" title="Comparative therapeutic strategies for preventing aortic rupture in a mouse model of vascular Ehlers Danlos syndrome (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>