<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.024983+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475049</id><title>The genomic basis of host and vector specificity in non-pathogenic trypanosomatids (18 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.025386+00:00</updated><author><name>Guy Oldrieve</name></author><author><name>Beatrice Malacart</name></author><author><name>Javier López-Vidal</name></author><author><name>Keith Matthews</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ability of trypanosome parasites to survive and sustain infections is dependent on diverse and intricate immune evasion mechanisms. Pathogenic trypanosomes often have broad host niches that preclude identification of host specific adaptations. In contrast, some non-pathogenic species of the genus Trypanosoma have highly specific hosts and vectors. Trypanosoma theileri, a non-pathogenic parasite of bovines, has a predicted surface protein architecture that likely aids survival in its mammalian host, distinct from the dominant variant surface glycoprotein coat of pathogenic African trypanosomes. In both species, their surface proteins are encoded by genes which account for ~10% of their genome. A non-pathogenic parasite of sheep, Trypanosoma melophagium, is transmitted by the sheep ked and is closely related to T. theileri. To explore host and vector specificity between these closely related species, we sequenced the T. melophagium genome and transcriptome and an annotated draft genome was assembled. T. melophagium was compared to 43 kinetoplastid genomes, including T. theileri. T. melophagium and T. theileri have an AT biased genome, the greatest bias of publicly available trypanosomatids. This trend may result from selection acting to decrease the genome nucleotide cost. The T. melophagium genome is 6.3Mb smaller than T. theileri and large families of proteins, characteristic of the predicted surface of T. theileri, were found to be absent or greatly reduced in T. melophagium. Instead, T. melophagium has modestly expanded protein families associated with the avoidance of complement-mediated lysis. The genome of T. melophagium contains core genes required for development, glycolysis, RNA interference, and meiotic exchange, each being shared with T. theileri. Comparisons between T. melophagium and T. theileri provide insight into the specific adaptations of these related trypanosomatids to their distinct mammalian hosts and arthropod vectors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475049" rel="alternate" title="The genomic basis of host and vector specificity in non-pathogenic trypanosomatids (18 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474854</id><title>High-throughput analysis of ANRIL circRNA isoforms in human pancreatic islets (16 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.025645+00:00</updated><author><name>Hannah J. MacMillan</name></author><author><name>Yahui Kong</name></author><author><name>Ezequiel Calvo-Roitberg</name></author><author><name>Laura C. Alonso</name></author><author><name>Athma A. Pai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;underline&gt;a&lt;/underline&gt;ntisense &lt;underline&gt;n&lt;/underline&gt;on-coding &lt;underline&gt;R&lt;/underline&gt;NA in the &lt;underline&gt;I&lt;/underline&gt;NK &lt;underline&gt;l&lt;/underline&gt;ocus (ANRIL) is a hotspot for genetic variants associated with cardiometabolic disease. We recently found increased ANRIL abundance in human pancreatic islets from donors with certain Type II Diabetes (T2D) risk-SNPs, including a T2D risk-SNP located within ANRIL exon 2 associated with beta cell proliferation. Recent studies have found that expression of circular species of ANRIL is linked to the regulation of cardiovascular phenotypes. Less is known about how the abundance of circular ANRIL may influence T2D phenotypes. Herein, we sequence circular RNA in pancreatic islets to characterize circular isoforms of ANRIL. We identify highly expressed circular ANRIL isoforms whose expression is correlated across dozens of individuals and characterize ANRIL splice sites that are commonly involved in back-splicing. We find that samples with the T2D risk allele in ANRIL exon 2 had higher ratios of circular to linear ANRIL compared to protective-allele carriers, and that higher circular:linear ANRIL was associated with decreased beta cell proliferation. Our study points to a combined involvement of both linear and circular ANRIL species in T2D phenotypes and opens the door for future studies of the molecular mechanisms by which ANRIL impacts cellular function in pancreatic islets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474854" rel="alternate" title="High-throughput analysis of ANRIL circRNA isoforms in human pancreatic islets (16 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474770</id><title>Missense variants causing Wiedemann-Steiner syndrome preferentially occur in the KMT2A-CXXC domain and are accurately classified using AlphaFold2 (16 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.025843+00:00</updated><author><name>Tinna Reynisdottir</name></author><author><name>Kimberley Anderson</name></author><author><name>Leandros Boukas</name></author><author><name>Hans Tomas Bjornsson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Wiedemann-Steiner syndrome (WSS) is a neurodevelopmental disorder caused by &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; variants in &lt;italic&gt;KMT2A&lt;/italic&gt;, which encodes a multi-domain histone methyltransferase. To gain insight into the currently unknown pathogenesis of WSS, we examined the spatial distribution of likely WSS-causing variants across the 15 different domains of KMT2A. Compared to variants in healthy controls, WSS variants exhibit a 64.1-fold overrepresentation within the CXXC domain – which mediates binding to unmethylated CpGs – suggesting a major role for this domain in mediating the phenotype. In contrast, we find no significant overrepresentation within the catalytic SET domain. Corroborating these results, we find that hippocampal neurons from &lt;italic&gt;Kmt2a&lt;/italic&gt;-deficient mice demonstrate disrupted H3K4me1 preferentially at CpG-rich regions, but this has no systematic impact on gene expression. Motivated by these results, we combine accurate prediction of the CXXC domain structure by AlphaFold2 with prior biological knowledge to develop a classification scheme for missense variants in the CXXC domain. Our classifier achieved 96.0% positive and 92.3% negative predictive value on a hold-out test set. This classification performance enabled us to subsequently perform an &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; saturation mutagenesis and classify a total of 445 variants according to their functional effects. Our results yield a novel insight into the mechanistic basis of WSS and provide an example of how AlphaFold2 can contribute to the &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; characterization of variant effects with very high accuracy, establishing a paradigm potentially applicable to many other Mendelian disorders.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474770" rel="alternate" title="Missense variants causing Wiedemann-Steiner syndrome preferentially occur in the KMT2A-CXXC domain and are accurately classified using AlphaFold2 (16 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474578</id><title>Splicing QTL analysis focusing on coding sequences reveals pathogenicity of disease susceptibility loci (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.026029+00:00</updated><author><name>Kensuke Yamaguchi</name></author><author><name>Kazuyoshi Ishigaki</name></author><author><name>Akari Suzuki</name></author><author><name>Yumi Tsuchida</name></author><author><name>Haruka Tsuchiya</name></author><author><name>Shuji Sumitomo</name></author><author><name>Yasuo Nagafuchi</name></author><author><name>Fuyuki Miya</name></author><author><name>Tatsuhiko Tsunoda</name></author><author><name>Shoda Hirofumi</name></author><author><name>Keishi Fujio</name></author><author><name>Kazuhiko Yamamoto</name></author><author><name>Yuta Kochi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Splicing QTL (sQTL) are one of the major causal mechanisms in GWAS loci, but their role in disease pathogenesis is poorly understood. One reason is the huge complexity of alternative splicing events producing many unknown isoforms. Here, we proposed two novel approaches, namely integration and selection, for this complexity by focusing on protein-structure of isoforms. First, we integrated isoforms with the same coding sequence (CDS) and identified 369-601 integrated-isoform ratio QTLs (i&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;-rQTLs), which altered protein-structure, in six immune subsets. Second, we selected CDS incomplete isoforms annotated in GENCODE and identified 175-337 isoform-ratio QTL (i-rQTL). By comprehensive long-read capture RNA-seq among these incomplete isoforms, we revealed 29 full-length isoforms with novel CDSs associated with GWAS traits. Furthermore, we have shown that disease-causal sQTL genes can be identified by evaluating their trans-eQTL effects. Our approaches highlight the understudied role of protein-altering sQTLs and are broadly applicable to other tissues and diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474578" rel="alternate" title="Splicing QTL analysis focusing on coding sequences reveals pathogenicity of disease susceptibility loci (10 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474990</id><title>Understanding host response to infectious salmon anaemia virus in an Atlantic salmon cell line using single-cell RNA sequencing (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.026291+00:00</updated><author><name>Ophélie Gervais</name></author><author><name>Remi Gratacap</name></author><author><name>Athina Papadopoulou</name></author><author><name>Ross D. Houston</name></author><author><name>Musa A. Hassan</name></author><author><name>Diego Robledo</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Infectious Salmon Anaemia Virus (ISAV) is an Orthomixovirus that currently represents a large problem for salmonid aquaculture worldwide. Prevention and treatment methods are only partially effective. Genetic selection and genome engineering strategies have potential to develop ISAV resistant salmon stocks. However, this requires a detailed understanding of the genomic regulation of ISAV pathogenesis. Here, we used single cell RNA sequencing on a salmonid cell line to provide a high dimensional insight into the transcriptional landscape that underpin host-virus interactions during ISAV infection at the single cell level.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Salmon head kidney 1 (SHK-1) cells were single-cell RNA sequenced before challenge, and at 24h, 48h, and 96h post-ISAV challenge. The results revealed marked changes in the host transcriptome at 48h and 96h post-infection, even in uninfected cells, potentially suggesting paracrine signalling. This paracrine activation of uninfected cells seemed to be unspecific, involving pathways such as mRNA sensing, ubiquitination or proteasome, and also the up-regulation of the mitochondrial ribosome genes. At 24h post infection, cells showed expression signatures consistent with viral entry, with up-regulation of genes such as PI3K, FAK or JNK. At 48h and 96h, infected cells showed a clear anti-viral response, characterised by the expression of IFNA2 or IRF2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study has increased our understanding of the cellular response of Atlantic salmon during ISAV infection, and revealed potential host-virus interactions at the cellular level. The results highlight the value of single-cell sequencing to characterise cell culture models of viral infection, and the results can be exploited in future functional studies to increase the resistance of Atlantic salmon to ISAV.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474990" rel="alternate" title="Understanding host response to infectious salmon anaemia virus in an Atlantic salmon cell line using single-cell RNA sequencing (10 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474805</id><title>Revealing genomic changes responsible for cannabinoid receptor loss in parrots: mechanism and functional effects (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.026486+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Divín</name></author><author><name>Mercedes Goméz Samblas</name></author><author><name>Nithya Kuttiyarthu Veetil</name></author><author><name>Eleni Voukali</name></author><author><name>Zuzana Świderska</name></author><author><name>Tereza Krajzingrová</name></author><author><name>Martin Tĕšický</name></author><author><name>Vladimír Beneš</name></author><author><name>Daniel Elleder</name></author><author><name>Oldřich Bartoš</name></author><author><name>Michal Vinkler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In vertebrates, an ancient duplication in the genes for cannabinoid receptors (CNRs) allowed the evolution of specialised endocannabinoid receptors expressed in the brain (CNR1) and the periphery (CNR2). While dominantly conserved throughout vertebrate phylogeny, our comparative genomic analysis suggests that certain taxa may have lost either the CNR1 regulator of neural processes or, more frequently, the CNR2 involved in immune regulation. Focussing on conspicuous &lt;italic&gt;CNR2&lt;/italic&gt; pseudogenization in parrots (Psittaciformes), a diversified crown lineage of cognitively-advanced birds, we highlight possible functional effects of such a loss. Parrots appear to have lost the &lt;italic&gt;CNR2&lt;/italic&gt; gene at at least two separate occasions due to chromosomal rearrangement. Using gene expression data from the brain and periphery of birds with experimentally-induced sterile inflammation, we compare &lt;italic&gt;CNR&lt;/italic&gt; and inflammatory marker (interleukin 1 beta, &lt;italic&gt;IL1B&lt;/italic&gt;) expression patterns in &lt;italic&gt;CNR2&lt;/italic&gt;-deficient parrots (represented by the budgerigar, &lt;italic&gt;Melopsittacus undulatus&lt;/italic&gt; and five other parrot species) with &lt;italic&gt;CNR2&lt;/italic&gt;-intact passerines (represented by the zebra finch, &lt;italic&gt;Taeniopygia guttata&lt;/italic&gt;). Though no significant changes in &lt;italic&gt;CNR&lt;/italic&gt; expression were observed in either parrots or passerines during inflammation of the brain or periphery, we detected a significant up-regulation of &lt;italic&gt;IL1B&lt;/italic&gt; expression in the brain after stimulation with lipopolysaccharide (LPS) only in parrots. As our analysis failed to show evidence for selection on altered &lt;italic&gt;CNR1&lt;/italic&gt; functionality in parrots, compared to other birds, &lt;italic&gt;CNR1&lt;/italic&gt; is unlikely to be involved in compensation for &lt;italic&gt;CNR2&lt;/italic&gt; loss in modulation of the neuroimmune interaction. Thus, our results provide evidence for the functional importance of &lt;italic&gt;CNR2&lt;/italic&gt; pseudogenization for regulation of neuroinflammation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474805" rel="alternate" title="Revealing genomic changes responsible for cannabinoid receptor loss in parrots: mechanism and functional effects (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475143</id><title>Chromosome-scale assembly of the highly heterozygous genome of red clover (Trifolium pratense L.), an allogamous forage crop species (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.026722+00:00</updated><author><name>Derek M Bickhart</name></author><author><name>Lisa M Koch</name></author><author><name>Timothy P.L. Smith</name></author><author><name>Heathcliffe Riday</name></author><author><name>Michael L Sullivan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Red clover (Trifolium pratense L.) is used as a forage crop due to a variety of favorable traits relative to other crops. Improved varieties have been developed through conventional breeding approaches, but progress could be accelerated and gene discovery facilitated using modern genomic methods. Existing short-read based genome assemblies of the ~420 Megabase (Mb) genome are fragmented into &amp;gt;135,000 contigs with numerous errors in order and orientation within scaffolds, likely due to the biology of the plant which displays gametophytic self-incompatibility resulting in inherent high heterozygosity. A high-quality long-read based assembly of red clover is presented that reduces the number of contigs by more than 500-fold, improves the per-base quality, and increases the contig N50 statistic by three orders of magnitude. The 413.5 Mb assembly is nearly 20% longer than the 350 Mb short read assembly, closer to the predicted genome size. Quality measures are presented and full-length isoform sequence of RNA transcripts reported for use in assessing accuracy and for future annotation of the genome. The assembly accurately represents the seven main linkage groups present in the genome of an allogamous (outcrossing), highly heterozygous plant species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475143" rel="alternate" title="Chromosome-scale assembly of the highly heterozygous genome of red clover (Trifolium pratense L.), an allogamous forage crop species (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474757</id><title>New genomic signals underlying the emergence of human proto-genes (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.026906+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna Grandchamp</name></author><author><name>Katrin Berk</name></author><author><name>Elias Dohmen</name></author><author><name>Erich Bornberg-Bauer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;De novo&lt;/italic&gt; genes are novel genes which emerge from non-coding DNA. Until now, little is known about &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; genes properties, correlated to their age and mechanisms of emergence. In this study, we investigate four properties: introns, upstream regulatory motifs, 5’ UTRs and protein domains, in 23135 human proto-genes. We found that proto-genes contain introns, whose number and position correlates with the genomic position of proto-gene emergence. The origin of these introns is debated, as our result suggest that 41% proto-genes might have captured existing introns, as well as the fact that 13.7% of them do not splice the ORF. We show that proto-genes which emerged via overprinting tend to be more enriched in core promotor motifs, while intergenic and intronic ones are more enriched in enhancers, even if the motif TATA is most expressed upstream these genes. Intergenic and intronic 5’ UTRs of protogenes have a lower potential to stabilise mRNA structures than exonic proto-genes and established human genes. Finally, we confirm that proto-genes gain new putative domains with age. Overall, we find that regulatory motifs inducing transcription and translation of previously non-coding sequences may facilitate proto-gene emergence. Our paper demonstrates that introns, 5’UTRs, and domains have specific properties in proto-genes. We also show the importance of studying proto-genes in relation to their genomic position, as it strongly impacts these properties.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474757" rel="alternate" title="New genomic signals underlying the emergence of human proto-genes (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475144</id><title>CRISPR-LRS for mapping transgenes in the mouse genome (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.027083+00:00</updated><author><name>W. Bart Bryant</name></author><author><name>Allison Yang</name></author><author><name>Susan Griffin</name></author><author><name>Wei Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xiaochun Long</name></author><author><name>Joseph M Miano</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microinjected transgenes, including bacterial artificial chromosomes (BACs), insert randomly in the mouse genome. Traditional methods of mapping a transgene are challenging, thus complicating breeding strategies and the accurate interpretation of phenotypes, particularly when a transgene disrupts critical coding or noncoding sequences. Here, we introduce CRISPR-Cas9 long-read sequencing (CRISPR-LRS) to ascertain transgene integration locus and estimated copy number. This method revealed integration loci for both a BAC and Cre-driver line, and estimated the copy numbers for two other BAC mouse lines. CRISPR-LRS offers an easy approach to establish robust breeding practices and accurate phenotyping of most any transgenic mouse line.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475144" rel="alternate" title="CRISPR-LRS for mapping transgenes in the mouse genome (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475139</id><title>Simultaneous inference of parental admixture proportions and admixture times from unphased local ancestry calls (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.027272+00:00</updated><author><name>Siddharth Avadhanam</name></author><author><name>Amy L Williams</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Population genetic analyses of local ancestry tracts routinely assume that the ancestral admixture process is identical for both parents of an individual, an assumption that may be invalid when considering recent admixture. Here we present Parental Admixture Proportion Inference (PAPI), a Bayesian tool for inferring the admixture proportions and admixture times for each parent of a single admixed individual. PAPI analyzes unphased local ancestry tracts and has two components models: a binomial model that exploits the informativeness of homozygous ancestry regions to infer parental admixture proportions, and a hidden Markov model (HMM) that infers admixture times from tract lengths. Crucially, the HMM employs an approximation to the pedigree crossover dynamics that accounts for unobserved within-ancestry recombination, enabling inference of parental admixture times. We compared the accuracy of PAPI's admixture proportion estimates with those of ANCESTOR in simulated admixed individuals and found that PAPI outperforms ANCESTOR by an average of 46% in a representative set of simulation scenarios, with PAPI's estimates deviating from the ground truth by 0.047 on average. Moreover, PAPI's admixture time estimates were strongly correlated with the ground truth in these simulations (&lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt; = 0.76), but have an average downward bias of 1.01 generations that is partly attributable to inaccuracies in local ancestry inference. As an illustration of its utility, we ran PAPI on real African Americans from the PAGE study (&lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt; = 5,786) and found strong evidence of assortative mating by ancestry proportion: couples' ancestry proportions are closer to each other than expected by chance (&lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt;&amp;lt;10&lt;sup&gt;-6&lt;/sup&gt;), and are highly correlated (&lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt; = 0.87). We anticipate that PAPI will be useful in studying the population dynamics of admixture and will also be of interest to individuals seeking to learn about their personal genealogies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475139" rel="alternate" title="Simultaneous inference of parental admixture proportions and admixture times from unphased local ancestry calls (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475069</id><title>Postnatal developmental trajectory of sex-biased gene expression in the mouse pituitary gland (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.027431+00:00</updated><author><name>Huayun Hou</name></author><author><name>Cadia Chan</name></author><author><name>Kyoko E Yuki</name></author><author><name>Dustin Sokolowski</name></author><author><name>Anna Roy</name></author><author><name>Rihao Qu</name></author><author><name>Liis Uuskula-Reimand</name></author><author><name>Mariela Faykoo-Martinez</name></author><author><name>Matt Hudson</name></author><author><name>Christina Corre</name></author><author><name>Anna Goldenberg</name></author><author><name>Zhaolei Zhang</name></author><author><name>Mark R Palmert</name></author><author><name>Michael D Wilson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The pituitary gland controls sexually dimorphic processes such as growth, pubertal onset, and lactation. However, the mechanisms underlying sex biases in pituitary gene regulation are not fully understood. To capture pituitary gene regulation dynamics during postnatal development, we ascertained gene and miRNA expression across five postnatal days that span the pubertal transition in mice. Using three prime untranslated region and small RNA sequencing, we observed over 900 instances of sex-biased gene expression, including 18 genes that were putative targets of 5 sex-biased miRNAs. In addition, by combining bulk RNA-seq with scRNA-seq pituitary data, we obtained evidence that cell-type proportion sex differences exist prior to puberty and contribute substantially to the observed sex-biased gene expression post-puberty. This work provides a resource for postnatal mouse pituitary gene regulation and highlights the importance of sex-biases in both cell-type composition and gene regulation when understanding the sexually dimorphic processes regulated by the pituitary gland.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475069" rel="alternate" title="Postnatal developmental trajectory of sex-biased gene expression in the mouse pituitary gland (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475202</id><title>Sperm exposure to accessory gland secretions alters the transcriptomic response of the endometrium in cattle (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.027691+00:00</updated><author><name>Jose Maria Sanchez</name></author><author><name>Maria Belen Rabaglino</name></author><author><name>Sandra Bages-Arnal</name></author><author><name>Michael McDonald</name></author><author><name>Susanta K Behura</name></author><author><name>Thomas E Spencer</name></author><author><name>Pat Lonergan</name></author><author><name>Beatriz Fernandez-Fuertes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In a recent study from our group, mating to intact, but not vasectomised, bulls modified the endometrial transcriptome, suggesting an important role of sperm in the modulation of the uterine environment in this species. However, it is not clear whether these changes are driven by intrinsic sperm factors, or by factors of accessory gland (AG) origin that bind to sperm at ejaculation. Thus, the aim of the present study was to determine whether ejaculated sperm, which are suspended in the secretions of the AGs, elicit a different  endometrial transcriptomic response than epididymal sperm, which have never been exposed to AG factors. To this end, bovine endometrial explants collected from heifers in oestrus were incubated alone (control), or with epididymal or ejaculated sperm. RNA-sequencing revealed 1912 differentially expressed genes (DEGs) between in endometrial explants exposed to epididymal sperm compared with control explants, whereas 115 DEGs genes detected between endometrial explants exposed to ejaculated sperm in comparison to control explants. In both cases, the top pathways associated with these genes included T cell regulation and NF-KB and IL17 signalling. To confirm whether AG factors were directly responsible for the dampening of the endometrial response elicited by ejaculated sperm, endometrial explants were incubated with epididymal sperm previously exposed, or not, to seminal plasma (SP). Exposure to SP abrogated the downregulation of SQSTM1 by epididymal sperm, and partially inhibited the upregulation of MYL4 and CHRM3 and downregulation of SCRIB. These data indicate that factors of AG origin modulate the interaction between sperm and the endometrium in cattle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475202" rel="alternate" title="Sperm exposure to accessory gland secretions alters the transcriptomic response of the endometrium in cattle (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474885</id><title>Gene expression profiles of some prognostic markers in a human breast cell line (MCF7) exposed to Curcumin nanoparticles and nanocapsules (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.027897+00:00</updated><author><name>Emad S. Shaker</name></author><author><name>Ghada M. Nasr</name></author><author><name>Mahmoud Moawad</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1.&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Worldwide, cancer is a significant public health problem. Curcumin exhibits anti-inflammatory, antiproliferative, and anticancer properties when used in medicine. Investigated study for Curcumin’s chemopreventive mechanism against human malignancies, this research examined the cellular and molecular alterations generated by curcumin modified compound in breast cancer (MCF-7) cell lines. Oncogenic EGFR and VEGFR2 mutations lead to the formation, invasion, and maintenance of malignant phenotypes in humans, including breast cancer. Studied prognostic markers such as C-myc and Ki67 in breast cancer, and the apoptotic gene as Caspase-3 have been done.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aim of the work&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study is to determine the therapeutic efficacy of curcumin nanoparticles and nanocapsules in breast cancer cell lines (MCF7).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Materials and methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used real-time PCR to assess the expression of the C-myc, Ki67, EGFR, VEGFR2, and Caspase-3 genes in MCF7 cells treated with Curcumin nanoparticles and nanocapsules.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Curcumin nanoparticles and nanocapsules boosted apoptotic cell populations considerably regardless of the nanotechnology used. Additionally, the mRNA expression analysis results indicated that the mechanism activated by curcumin nanocapsules involved the upregulation of the oncogenes EGFR and VEGFR2. In comparison to curcumin nanoparticles, curcumin nanocapsules significantly reduced the expression of Ki67 and c-myc mRNAs in breast cancer cells. The mRNA expression study revealed that curcumin nanocapsules produce an increase in the apoptotic Caspase-3 gene production compared to cells treated with curcumin nanoparticles.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This work demonstrates that curcumin nanoparticles created using a novel mechanical process can be employed successfully as an anticancer agent. These findings add to our understanding of the molecular mechanisms behind curcumin nanocapsules’ anticancer activity in breast cancer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474885" rel="alternate" title="Gene expression profiles of some prognostic markers in a human breast cell line (MCF7) exposed to Curcumin nanoparticles and nanocapsules (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>