<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.430349+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445471</id><title>Multiple Causal Variants Underlie Genetic Associations in Humans (90 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.432013+00:00</updated><author><name>Nathan S. Abell</name></author><author><name>Marianne K. DeGorter</name></author><author><name>Michael Gloudemans</name></author><author><name>Emily Greenwald</name></author><author><name>Kevin S. Smith</name></author><author><name>Zihuai He</name></author><author><name>Stephen B. Montgomery</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The majority of associations between genetic variation and human traits and diseases are non-coding and in strong linkage disequilibrium (LD) with surrounding genetic variation. In these cases, a single causal variant is often assumed to underlie the association, however no systematic assessment of the number of causal variants has been performed. In this study, we applied a massively parallel reporter assay (MPRA) in lymphoblastoid cells to functionally evaluate 49,256 allelic pairs, representing 30,893 genetic variants in high, local linkage disequilibrium for 744 independent cis-expression quantitative trait loci (eQTL) and assessed each for colocalization across 114 traits. We identified 3,536 allele-independent regulatory regions containing 907 allele-specific regulatory variants, and found that 17.3% of eQTL contained more than one significant allelic effect. We show that detected regulatory variants are highly and specifically enriched for activating chromatin structures and allelic transcription factor binding, for which ETS-domain family members are a large driver. Integration of MPRA profiles with eQTL/complex trait colocalizations identified causal variant sets for associations with blood cell measurements, Multiple Sclerosis, Irritable Bowel Disease, and Crohn’s Disease. These results demonstrate that a sizable number of association signals are manifest through multiple, tightly-linked causal variants requiring high-throughput functional assays for fine-mapping.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445471" rel="alternate" title="Multiple Causal Variants Underlie Genetic Associations in Humans (90 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445457</id><title>Island-specific evolution of a sex-primed autosome in the planarian Schmidtea mediterranea (62 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.432704+00:00</updated><author><name>Longhua Guo</name></author><author><name>Joshua Bloom</name></author><author><name>Daniel Dols Serrate</name></author><author><name>Eyal Ben David</name></author><author><name>Olga T. Schubert</name></author><author><name>Kaiya Kazuma</name></author><author><name>Katarina Ho</name></author><author><name>Yubao Wei</name></author><author><name>Daniel Leighton</name></author><author><name>James Boocock</name></author><author><name>Tzitziki Lemus Vergara</name></author><author><name>Marta Riutort</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Sánchez Alvarado</name></author><author><name>Leonid Kruglyak</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The sexual biotype of the planarian &lt;italic&gt;Schmidtea mediterranea&lt;/italic&gt; is a hermaphrodite indigenous to Tunisia and several Mediterranean islands. Here, we isolated individual chromosomes and used sequencing, Hi-C and linkage mapping to assemble a chromosome-scale genome reference. The linkage map revealed an extremely low rate of recombination on chromosome 1. We confirmed suppression of recombination on chromosome 1 by quantifying recombination events in individual sperm and oocytes. We showed that the extensive heterozygous regions, previously designated as J and V haplotypes, comprise essentially all of chromosome 1. Genome sequencing of individuals isolated in the wild indicated that this heterozygosity has evolved specifically in populations from Sardinia and Corsica. We found that chromosome 1 acquired many genes that determine the development of female and male reproductive systems, along with haplotype-specific expression of such sex specific genes. These molecular signatures and restricted recombination in a hermaphrodite led us to propose that chromosome 1 is a sex-primed autosome, providing direct molecular evidence for the traditional model of how sex chromosomes may have evolved from autosomes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445457" rel="alternate" title="Island-specific evolution of a sex-primed autosome in the planarian Schmidtea mediterranea (62 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.445246</id><title>An improved hidden Markov model for the characterization of homozygous-by-descent segments in individual genomes (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.433210+00:00</updated><author><name>Tom Druet</name></author><author><name>Mathieu Gautier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Inbreeding results from the mating of related individuals and has negative consequences because it brings together deleterious variants in one individual. Genomic estimates of the inbreeding coefficients are preferred to pedigree-based estimators as they measure the realized inbreeding levels and they are more robust to pedigree errors. Several methods identifying homozygous-by-descent (HBD) segments with hidden Markov models (HMM) have been recently developed and are particularly valuable when the information is degraded or heterogeneous (e.g., low-fold sequencing, low marker density, heterogeneous genotype quality or variable marker spacing). We previously developed a multiple HBD class HMM where HBD segments are classified in different groups based on their length (e.g., recent versus old HBD segments) but we recently observed that for high inbreeding levels with many HBD segments, the estimated contributions might be biased towards more recent classes (i.e., associated with large HBD segments) although the overall estimated level of inbreeding remained unbiased. We herein propose an updated multiple HBD classes model in which the HBD classification is modeled in successive nested levels. In each level, the rate specifying the expected length of HBD segments, and that is directly related to the number of generations to the ancestors, is distinct. The non-HBD classes are now modeled as a mixture of HBD segments from later generations and shorter non-HBD segments (i.e., both with higher rates). The updated model had better statistical properties and performed better on simulated data compared to our previous version. We also show that the parameters of the model are easier to interpret and that the model is more robust to the choice of the number of classes. Overall, the new model results in an improved partitioning of inbreeding in different HBD classes and should be preferred in applications relying on the length of estimated HBD segments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.445246" rel="alternate" title="An improved hidden Markov model for the characterization of homozygous-by-descent segments in individual genomes (9 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445445</id><title>Dissection of multiple sclerosis genetics identifies B and CD4+ T cells as driver cell subsets (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.433532+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael H. Guo</name></author><author><name>Prashanth Sama</name></author><author><name>Brenna A. LaBarre</name></author><author><name>Hrishikesh Lokhande</name></author><author><name>John Balibalos</name></author><author><name>Ci Chu</name></author><author><name>Xiaomi Du</name></author><author><name>Pouya Kheradpour</name></author><author><name>Charles C Kim</name></author><author><name>Taylor Oniskey</name></author><author><name>Thomas Snyder</name></author><author><name>Damien Z Soghoian</name></author><author><name>Howard L. Weiner</name></author><author><name>Tanuja Chitnis</name></author><author><name>Nikolaos A. Patsopoulos</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Multiple sclerosis (MS) is an autoimmune condition of the central nervous system with a well-characterized genetic background. Prior analyses of MS genetics have identified broad enrichments across peripheral immune cells, yet the driver immune subsets are unclear. We utilized chromatin accessibility data across hematopoietic cells to identify cell type-specific enrichments of MS genetic signals. We found that CD4 T and B cells were independently enriched for MS genetics and further refined the driver subsets to T&lt;sub&gt;h&lt;/sub&gt;17 and memory B cells, respectively. We replicated our findings in data from untreated and treated MS patients and found that immunomodulatory treatments suppress chromatin accessibility at driver cell types. Integration of statistical fine-mapping and chromatin interactions nominated numerous putative causal genes, illustrating complex interplay between shared and cell-specific genes. Our study highlights how careful integration of genetics and epigenetics can provide fine-scale insights into causal cell types and nominate new genes and pathways for disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445445" rel="alternate" title="Dissection of multiple sclerosis genetics identifies B and CD4+ T cells as driver cell subsets (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>