<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.436993+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465778</id><title>Cost-effective epigenetic age profiling in shallow methylation sequencing data (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.437366+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexandre Trapp</name></author><author><name>Vadim N Gladyshev</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;There is a critical need for robust, high-throughput assays of biological aging trajectories. Among various approaches, epigenetic aging clocks emerged as reliable molecular trackers of the aging process. However, current methods for epigenetic age profiling are inherently costly and lack throughput. Here, we leverage the scAge framework for accurate prediction of biological age from very few bisulfite sequencing reads in bulk samples, thereby enabling drastic (100-1,000-fold) reduction in sequencing costs per sample. Our approach permits age assessment based on distinct assortments of CpG sites in different samples, without the need for targeted site enrichment or specialized reagents. We demonstrate the efficacy of this method to quantify the age of mouse blood samples across independent cohorts, identify the effect of calorie restriction as an attenuator of the aging process, and discern rejuvenation upon cellular reprogramming. We propose that this framework may be used for epigenetic age prediction in extremely high-throughput applications, enabling robust, large-scale and inexpensive interventions testing and age profiling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465778" rel="alternate" title="Cost-effective epigenetic age profiling in shallow methylation sequencing data (21 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465878</id><title>Chromosome-scale assemblies of Acanthamoeba castellanii genomes provide insights into Legionella pneumophila infection-related chromatin re-organization (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.437668+00:00</updated><author><name>Cyril Matthey-Doret</name></author><author><name>Morgan J. Colp</name></author><author><name>Pedro Escoll</name></author><author><name>Agnès Thierry</name></author><author><name>Bruce Curtis</name></author><author><name>Matt Sarrasin</name></author><author><name>Michael W. Gray</name></author><author><name>B. Franz Lang</name></author><author><name>John M. Archibald</name></author><author><name>Carmen Buchrieser</name></author><author><name>Romain Koszul</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The unicellular amoeba &lt;italic&gt;Acanthamoeba castellanii&lt;/italic&gt; is ubiquitous in aquatic environments, where it preys on bacteria. The organism also hosts bacterial endosymbionts, some of which are parasitic, including human pathogens such as &lt;italic&gt;Chlamydia&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Legionella&lt;/italic&gt; spp. Here we report complete, high quality genome sequences for two extensively studied &lt;italic&gt;A. castellanii&lt;/italic&gt; strains, Neff and C3. Combining long- and short-read data with Hi-C, we generated near chromosome-level assemblies for both strains with 90% of the genome contained in 29 scaffolds for the Neff strain and 31 for the C3 strain. Comparative genomics revealed strain-specific functional enrichment, most notably genes related to signal transduction in the C3 strain, and to viral replication in Neff. Furthermore, we characterized the spatial organization of the &lt;italic&gt;A. castellanii&lt;/italic&gt; genome and showed that it is reorganized during infection by &lt;italic&gt;Legionella pneumophila.&lt;/italic&gt; Infection-dependent chromatin loops were found to be enriched in genes for signal transduction and phosphorylation processes. In genomic regions where chromatin organization changed during &lt;italic&gt;Legionella&lt;/italic&gt; infection, we found functional enrichment for genes associated with metabolism, organelle assembly, and cytoskeleton organization, suggesting that changes in chromosomal folding are associated with host cell biology during infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465878" rel="alternate" title="Chromosome-scale assemblies of Acanthamoeba castellanii genomes provide insights into Legionella pneumophila infection-related chromatin re-organization (20 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465975</id><title>Integration of GWAS and TWAS to elucidate the genetic architecture of natural variation for leaf cuticular conductance in maize (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.437884+00:00</updated><author><name>Meng Lin</name></author><author><name>Pengfei Qiao</name></author><author><name>Susanne Matschi</name></author><author><name>Miguel Vasquez</name></author><author><name>Guillaume P. Ramstein</name></author><author><name>Richard Bourgault</name></author><author><name>Marc Mohammadi</name></author><author><name>Michael J Scanlon</name></author><author><name>Isabel Molina</name></author><author><name>Laurie G. Smith</name></author><author><name>Michael A Gore</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The cuticle, a hydrophobic layer of cutin and waxes synthesized by plant epidermal cells, is the major barrier to water loss when stomata are closed. Dissecting the genetic architecture of natural variation for maize leaf cuticular conductance (gc) is important for identifying genes relevant to improving crop productivity in drought-prone environments. To this end, we performed an integrated genome- and transcriptome-wide association study (GWAS/TWAS) to identify candidate genes putatively regulating variation in leaf gc. Of the 22 plausible candidate genes identified, five were predicted to be involved in cuticle precursor biosynthesis and export, two in cell wall modification, nine in intracellular membrane trafficking, and seven in the regulation of cuticle development. A gene encoding an INCREASED SALT TOLERANCE1-LIKE1 (ISTL1) protein putatively involved in intracellular protein and membrane trafficking was identified in GWAS and TWAS as the strongest candidate causal gene. A set of maize nested near-isogenic lines that harbor the ISTL1 genomic region from eight donor parents were evaluated for gc, confirming the association between gc and ISTL1 in a haplotype-based association analysis. The findings of this study provide novel insights into the role of regulatory variants in the development of the maize leaf cuticle, and will ultimately assist breeders to develop drought-tolerant maize for target environments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465975" rel="alternate" title="Integration of GWAS and TWAS to elucidate the genetic architecture of natural variation for leaf cuticular conductance in maize (11 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465742</id><title>Genomic adaptation in the CAZyome and specialised metabolism of the plant-associated Streptomyces violaceusniger clade (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.438100+00:00</updated><author><name>D. Gayrard</name></author><author><name>M. Veyssière</name></author><author><name>K. Adam</name></author><author><name>Y. Martinez</name></author><author><name>C. Vandecasteele</name></author><author><name>M. Vidal</name></author><author><name>B. Dumas</name></author><author><name>T. Rey</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Streptomycetes are Gram-positive actinobacteria largely represented in the plant root microbiota. The genetic determinants involved in the presence of &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt; in the rhizosphere are largely unknown and can rely on the ability to degrade plant-derived compounds such as cell-wall polysaccharides and on the production of specialised metabolites. To address whether &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt; strains recruited into root microbiota share genomic specificities related to these two functions, we engaged a comparative genomic analysis using a newly sequenced rhizospheric strain, &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt; sp. AgN23 and strains from the phylogenetically related &lt;italic&gt;S. violaceusniger&lt;/italic&gt; clade. This analysis enlightens a shared prominent CAZyome potentially involved in plant polysaccharides degradation and a strong conservation of antimicrobials biosynthetic clusters (rustmicin, mediomycin, niphimycin, nigericin) as well as plant bioactive compounds (nigericin, echosides, elaiophylin). Taken together, our work supports the hypothesis that specific hydrolytic enzymes and specialised metabolites repertoires may play important roles in the development of &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt; strains in the rhizosphere.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465742" rel="alternate" title="Genomic adaptation in the CAZyome and specialised metabolism of the plant-associated Streptomyces violaceusniger clade (9 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465726</id><title>Population structure in the MHC region (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.438300+00:00</updated><author><name>André Silva Maróstica</name></author><author><name>Kelly Nunes</name></author><author><name>Erick C. Castelli</name></author><author><name>Nayane S. B. Silva</name></author><author><name>Bruce S. Weir</name></author><author><name>Jérôme Goudet</name></author><author><name>Diogo Meyer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In his 1972 “The apportionment of human diversity”, Lewontin showed that, when averaged over loci, genetic diversity is predominantly attributable to differences among individuals within populations. However, selection on specific genes and genomic regions can alter the apportionment of diversity. We examine genetic diversity at the HLA loci, located within the MHC region. HLA genes code for proteins that are critical to adaptive immunity and are well-documented targets of balancing selection. The SNPs within HLA genes show strong signatures of balancing selection on large timescales and are broadly shared among populations, with low F&lt;sub&gt;ST&lt;/sub&gt; values. However, when we analyze haplotypes defined by these SNPs (i.e., which define “HLA alleles”), we find marked differences in frequencies between geographic regions. These differences are not reflected in the F&lt;sub&gt;ST&lt;/sub&gt; values because of the extreme polymorphism at HLA loci, illustrating challenges in interpreting F&lt;sub&gt;ST&lt;/sub&gt;. Differences in the frequency of HLA alleles among geographic regions are relevant to bone-marrow transplantation, which requires genetic identity at HLA loci between patient and donor. We explore the case of Brazil’s bone-marrow registry, where a deficit of enrolled volunteers with African ancestry reduces the chance of finding donors for individuals with an MHC region of African ancestry.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465726" rel="alternate" title="Population structure in the MHC region (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466423</id><title>Modeling the efficacy of CRISPR gene drive for schistosomiasis control (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.438852+00:00</updated><author><name>Richard E Grewelle</name></author><author><name>Javier Perez-Saez</name></author><author><name>Josh Tycko</name></author><author><name>Erica KO Namigai</name></author><author><name>Chloe G Rickards</name></author><author><name>Giulio A De Leo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;CRISPR gene drives could revolutionize the control of infectious diseases by accelerating the spread of engineered traits that limit parasite transmission in wild populations.  While much effort has been spent developing gene drives in mosquitoes, gene drive technology in molluscs has received little attention despite the role of freshwater snails as obligate, intermediate hosts of parasitic flukes causing schistosomiasis -- a disease of poverty affecting more than 200 million people worldwide.  A successful drive in snails must overcome self-fertilization, which prevents a drive's spread. Simultaneous hermaphroditism is a feature of snails -- distinct from gene drive model organisms -- and is not yet incorporated in gene drive models of disease control.  Here we developed a novel population genetic model accounting for snails' sexual and asexual reproduction, susceptibility to parasite infection regulated by multiple alleles, fitness differences between genotypes, and a range of drive characteristics.  We then integrated this model with an epidemiological model of schistosomiasis transmission and snail population dynamics.  Simulations showed that gene drive establishment can be hindered by a variety of biological and ecological factors, including selfing.  However, our model suggests that, under a range of conditions, gene drive mediated immunity in snails could maintain rapid disease reduction achieved by annual chemotherapy treatment of the human population, leading to long-term elimination.  These results indicate that gene drives, in coordination with existing public health measures, may become a useful tool to reduce schistosomiasis burden in selected transmission settings with effective CRISPR construct design and close evaluation of the genetic and ecological landscape.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466423" rel="alternate" title="Modeling the efficacy of CRISPR gene drive for schistosomiasis control (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466232</id><title>Mandrake: visualising microbial population structure by embedding millions of genomes into a low-dimensional representation (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.439117+00:00</updated><author><name>John A Lees</name></author><author><name>Gerry Tonkin-Hill</name></author><author><name>Zhirong Yang</name></author><author><name>Jukka Corander</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In less than a decade, population genomics of microbes has progressed from the effort of sequencing dozens of strains to thousands, or even tens of thousands of strains in a single study. There are now hundreds of thousands of genomes available even for a single bacterial species and the number of genomes is expected to continue to increase at an accelerated pace given the advances in sequencing technology and widespread genomic surveillance initiatives. This explosion of data calls for innovative methods to enable rapid exploration of the structure of a population based on different data modalities, such as multiple sequence alignments, assemblies and estimates of gene content across different genomes. Here we present Mandrake, an efficient implementation of a dimensional reduction method tailored for the needs of large-scale population genomics. Mandrake is capable of visualising population structure from millions of whole genomes and we illustrate its usefulness with several data sets representing major pathogens. Our method is freely available both as an analysis pipeline (https://github.com/johnlees/mandrake) and as a browser-based interactive application (https://gtonkinhill.github.io/mandrake-web/).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466232" rel="alternate" title="Mandrake: visualising microbial population structure by embedding millions of genomes into a low-dimensional representation (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466094</id><title>Formation and recycling of an active epigenetic mark mediated by cell cycle-specific RNAs (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.439687+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander K. Ebralidze</name></author><author><name>Simone Ummarino</name></author><author><name>Mahmoud A. Bassal</name></author><author><name>Haoran Zhang</name></author><author><name>Bogdan Budnik</name></author><author><name>Emanuele Monteleone</name></author><author><name>Dennis Kappei</name></author><author><name>Yanjing V. Liu</name></author><author><name>Danielle E. Tenen</name></author><author><name>Rory Coffey</name></author><author><name>Mee Rie Sheen</name></author><author><name>Yanzhou Zhang</name></author><author><name>Anaïs Wanet</name></author><author><name>Bon Q. Trinh</name></author><author><name>Valeria Poli</name></author><author><name>Vladimir Espinosa Angarica</name></author><author><name>Roberto Tirado Magallanes</name></author><author><name>Touati Benoukraf</name></author><author><name>Colyn Crane-Robinson</name></author><author><name>Annalisa Di Ruscio</name></author><author><name>Daniel G. Tenen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mechanisms by which epigenetic modifications are established in gene regulatory regions of active genes remain poorly understood. The data presented show that the establishment and recycling of a major epigenetic mark, the acetylated form of the replacement histone H2A.Z, is regulated by cell cycle-specific long noncoding RNAs encoded in regions adjacent to the promoters of active genes. These transcripts, termed &lt;italic&gt;SPEARs&lt;/italic&gt; (S Phase EArly RNAs), are induced in early S phase: their expression precedes that of the downstream genes on which they exert their regulatory action. &lt;italic&gt;SPEARs&lt;/italic&gt; drive the modification and deposition of the acetylated form of histone H2A.Z by bringing together the replacement histone and the histone acetyl transferase TIP60. This widespread bimodal pathway constitutes a novel RNA-mediated mechanism for the establishment of epigenetic marks and cell-specific epigenetic profiles, thereby providing a unifying explanation for the accuracy and persistence of epigenetic marks on chromatin.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466094" rel="alternate" title="Formation and recycling of an active epigenetic mark mediated by cell cycle-specific RNAs (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466311</id><title>Sequencing Micronuclei Reveals the Landscape of Chromosomal Instability (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.440081+00:00</updated><author><name>Catalina Pereira</name></author><author><name>Ana Rita Rebelo</name></author><author><name>Dashiell Massey</name></author><author><name>John C. Schimenti</name></author><author><name>Robert S Weiss</name></author><author><name>Amnon Koren</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genome instability (GIN) is a main contributing factor to congenital and somatic diseases, but its sporadic occurrence in individual cell cycles makes it difficult to study mechanistically. One profound manifestation of GIN is the formation of micronuclei (MN), the engulfment of chromosomes or chromosome fragments in their own nuclear structures separate from the main nucleus. Here, we developed MN-seq, an approach for sequencing the DNA contained within micronuclei. We applied MN-seq to mice with mutations in Mcm4 and Rad9a, which disrupt DNA replication, repair, and damage responses. Data analysis and simulations show that centromere presence, fragment length, and a heterogenous landscape of chromosomal fragility all contribute to the patterns of DNA present within MN. In particular, we show that long genes, but also gene-poor regions, are associated with chromosome breaks that lead to the enrichment of particular genomic sequences in MN, in a genetic background-specific manner. Finally, we introduce single-cell micronucleus sequencing (scMN-seq), an approach to sequence the DNA present in MN of individual cells. Together, sequencing micronuclei provides a systematic approach for studying GIN and reveals novel molecular associations with chromosome breakage and segregation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466311" rel="alternate" title="Sequencing Micronuclei Reveals the Landscape of Chromosomal Instability (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>