<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.211709+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.465323</id><title>Defining cellular complexity in human autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease by multimodal single cell analysis (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.212330+00:00</updated><author><name>Yoshiharu Muto</name></author><author><name>Eryn E. Dixon</name></author><author><name>Yasuhiro Yoshimura</name></author><author><name>Haojia Wu</name></author><author><name>Kohei Omachi</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. King</name></author><author><name>Eric N. Olson</name></author><author><name>Marvin G. Gunawan</name></author><author><name>Jay J. Kuo</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Cox</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey H. Miner</name></author><author><name>Stephen L. Seliger</name></author><author><name>Owen M. Woodward</name></author><author><name>Paul A. Welling</name></author><author><name>Terry J. Watnick</name></author><author><name>Benjamin D. Humphreys</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease (ADPKD) is the leading genetic cause of end stage renal disease and is characterized by the formation and progressive expansion of kidney cysts. Most ADPKD cases arise from mutations in either the &lt;italic&gt;PKD1&lt;/italic&gt; or &lt;italic&gt;PKD2&lt;/italic&gt; gene but the precise downstream signaling pathways driving cyst growth are not well understood, and relatively few studies investigate human cystic kidney due to sample scarcity. In order to better understand the cell types and states driving human ADPKD progression, we analyzed eight ADPKD and five healthy human kidney samples, generating a single cell multiomic atlas consisting of ~100,000 single nucleus transcriptomes and ~50,000 single nucleus epigenomes. The integrated datasets identified 11 primary cell clusters including most epithelial cell types as well as large endothelial and fibroblast cell clusters. Proximal tubular cells from ADPKD kidneys expressed a failed repair transcriptomic signature characterized by profibrotic and proinflammatory transcripts. We identified the G protein-coupled receptor GPRC5A as specifically upregulated in cyst lining cells derived from collecting duct. The principal cell subpopulation enriched for GPRC5A expression also exhibited increased transcription factor binding motif availability for NF-κB, TEAD, CREB and retinoic acid receptor families and we identified and validated a distal enhancer regulating GPRC5A expression containing these transcription factor binding motifs. This study establishes the single cell transcriptomic and epigenomic landscape of ADPKD, revealing previously unrecognized cellular heterogeneity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.465323" rel="alternate" title="Defining cellular complexity in human autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease by multimodal single cell analysis (26 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-10-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.20.465093</id><title>Inherited MUTYH mutations cause elevated somatic mutation rates and distinctive mutational signatures in normal human cells (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.212750+00:00</updated><author><name>Philip S. Robinson</name></author><author><name>Laura E. Thomas</name></author><author><name>Federico Abascal</name></author><author><name>Hyunchul Jung</name></author><author><name>Luke M.R. Harvey</name></author><author><name>Hannah D. West</name></author><author><name>Sigurgeir Olafsson</name></author><author><name>Bernard C. H. Lee</name></author><author><name>Tim H.H. Coorens</name></author><author><name>Henry Lee-Six</name></author><author><name>Laura Butlin</name></author><author><name>Nicola Lander</name></author><author><name>Mathijs A. Sanders</name></author><author><name>Stefanie V. Lensing</name></author><author><name>Simon J.A. Buczacki</name></author><author><name>Rogier ten Hoppen</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Coleman</name></author><author><name>Roxanne Brunton-Sim</name></author><author><name>Simon Rushbrook</name></author><author><name>Kourosh Saeb-Parsy</name></author><author><name>Fiona Lalloo</name></author><author><name>Peter J. Campbell</name></author><author><name>Iñigo Martincorena</name></author><author><name>Julian R. Sampson</name></author><author><name>Michael R. Stratton</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cellular DNA damage caused by reactive oxygen species is repaired by the base excision repair (BER) pathway which includes the DNA glycosylase MUTYH. Inherited biallelic &lt;italic&gt;MUTYH&lt;/italic&gt; mutations cause predisposition to colorectal adenomas and carcinoma. However, the mechanistic progression from germline &lt;italic&gt;MUTYH&lt;/italic&gt; mutations to &lt;bold&gt;M&lt;/bold&gt;UTYH-&lt;bold&gt;A&lt;/bold&gt;ssociated &lt;bold&gt;P&lt;/bold&gt;olyposis (MAP) is incompletely understood. Here, we sequenced normal tissue DNAs from 10 individuals with MAP. Somatic base substitution mutation rates in intestinal epithelial cells were elevated 2 to 5-fold in all individuals, except for one showing a 33-fold increase, and were also increased in other tissues. The increased mutation burdens were of multiple mutational signatures characterised by C&amp;gt;A changes. Different mutation rates and signatures between individuals were likely due to different &lt;italic&gt;MUTYH&lt;/italic&gt; mutations or additional inherited mutations in other BER pathway genes. The elevated base substitution rate in normal cells likely accounts for the predisposition to neoplasia in MAP. Despite ubiquitously elevated mutation rates, individuals with MAP do not display overt evidence of premature ageing. Thus, accumulation of somatic mutations may not be sufficient to cause the global organismal functional decline of ageing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;Summary&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.20.465093" rel="alternate" title="Inherited MUTYH mutations cause elevated somatic mutation rates and distinctive mutational signatures in normal human cells (26 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.20.465206</id><title>Regulatory variants active in iPSC-derived pancreatic progenitor cells are associated with Type 2 Diabetes in adults (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.213278+00:00</updated><author><name>Jennifer P. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Agnieszka D'Antonio-Chronowska</name></author><author><name>Kyohei Fujita</name></author><author><name>Bianca M. Salgado</name></author><author><name>Hiroko Matsui</name></author><author><name>Timothy D. Arthur</name></author><author><name>Margaret KR Donovan</name></author><author><name>Matteo D'Antonio</name></author><author><name>Kelly A Frazer</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pancreatic progenitor cells (PPC) are an early developmental multipotent cell type that give rise to mature endocrine, exocrine, and ductal cells. To investigate the extent to which regulatory variants active in PPC contribute to pancreatic complex traits and disease in the adult, we derived PPC from induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs) of nine unrelated individuals and generated single cell profiles of chromatin accessibility (snATAC-seq) and transcriptome (scRNA-seq). While iPSC-PPC differentiation was asynchronous and included cell types from early to late developmental stages, we found that the predominant cell type consisted of NKX6-1+ progenitors. Genetic characterization using snATAC-seq identified 86,261 regulatory variants that either displayed chromatin allelic bias and/or were predicted to affect active transcription factor (TF) binding sites. Integration of these regulatory variants with 380 fine-mapped type 2 diabetes (T2D) risk loci identified regulatory variants in 209 of these loci that are functional in iPSC-PPC, either by affecting transcription factor binding or through association with allelic effects on chromatin accessibility. The PPC active regulatory variants in 65 of these loci showed strong evidence of causally underlying the association with T2D. Our study shows that studying the functional associations of regulatory variation in iPSC-PPC enables the identification and characterization of causal SNPs for adult Type 2 Diabetes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.20.465206" rel="alternate" title="Regulatory variants active in iPSC-derived pancreatic progenitor cells are associated with Type 2 Diabetes in adults (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.465269</id><title>Systematic analysis of intrinsic enhancer-promoter compatibility in the mouse genome (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.213571+00:00</updated><author><name>Miguel Martinez-Ara</name></author><author><name>Federico Comoglio</name></author><author><name>Joris van Arensbergen</name></author><author><name>Bas van Steensel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gene expression is in part controlled by cis-regulatory elements (CREs) such as enhancers and repressive elements. Anecdotal evidence has indicated that a CRE and a promoter need to be biochemically compatible for promoter regulation to occur, but this compatibility has remained poorly characterised in mammalian cells. We used high-throughput combinatorial reporter assays to test thousands of CRE – promoter pairs from three Mb-sized genomic regions in mouse cells. This revealed that CREs vary substantially in their promoter compatibility, ranging from striking specificity for a single promoter to quantitative differences in activation across a broad set of promoters. More than half of the tested CREs exhibit significant promoter selectivity. Housekeeping promoters tend to have similar CRE preferences, but other promoters exhibit a wide diversity of compatibilities. Higher-order TF motif combinations may account for compatibility. CRE–promoter selectivity does not correlate with looping interactions in the native genomic context, suggesting that chromatin folding and compatibility are two orthogonal mechanisms that confer specificity to gene regulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.465269" rel="alternate" title="Systematic analysis of intrinsic enhancer-promoter compatibility in the mouse genome (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-10-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>