<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.934569+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467743</id><title>Large-scale identification of RBP-RNA interactions by RAPseq refines essentials of post-transcriptional gene regulation (86 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.934897+00:00</updated><author><name>Ionut Atanasoai</name></author><author><name>Sofia Papavasileiou</name></author><author><name>Natalie Preiß</name></author><author><name>Claudia Kutter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Over the past decade, thousands of putative human RNA binding proteins (RBPs) have been identified and increased the demand for specifying RNA binding capacities. Here, we developed RNA affinity purification followed by sequencing (RAPseq) that enables &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; large-scale profiling of RBP binding to native RNAs. First, by employing RAPseq, we found that vertebrate HURs recognize a conserved RNA binding motif and bind predominantly to introns in zebrafish compared to 3’UTRs in human RNAs. Second, our dual RBP assays (co-RAPseq) uncovered cooperative RNA binding of HUR and PTBP1 within an optimal distance of 27 nucleotides. Third, we developed T7-RAPseq to discern m&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;A-dependent and - independent RNA binding sites of YTHDF1. Fourth, RAPseq of 26 novel non-canonical RBPs revealed specialized moonlighting interactions. Last, five pathological IGF2BP family variants exhibited different RNA binding patterns. Overall, our simple, scalable and versatile method enables to fast-forward RBP-related questions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="467743v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;HIGHLIGHTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;RAPseq reveals &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;-derived RBP-RNA interactomes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;the vertebrate-conserved HUR binding motif adapted to species-unique RNA features&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;co-RAPseq and T7-RAPseq uncover binding cooperativity and modification dependencies&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;non-canonical RBPs have specialized RNA interactomes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467743" rel="alternate" title="Large-scale identification of RBP-RNA interactions by RAPseq refines essentials of post-transcriptional gene regulation (86 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467731</id><title>Lipid nanoparticles incorporating a GalNAc ligand enable in vivo liver ANGPTL3 editing in wild-type and somatic LDLR knockout non-human primates (42 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.935222+00:00</updated><author><name>Lisa N. Kasiewicz</name></author><author><name>Souvik Biswas</name></author><author><name>Aaron Beach</name></author><author><name>Huilan Ren</name></author><author><name>Chaitali Dutta</name></author><author><name>Anne Marie Mazzola</name></author><author><name>Ellen Rohde</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Chadwick</name></author><author><name>Christopher Cheng</name></author><author><name>Kiran Musunuru</name></author><author><name>Sekar Kathiresan</name></author><author><name>Padma Malyala</name></author><author><name>Kallanthottathil G. Rajeev</name></author><author><name>Andrew M. Bellinger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Standard lipid nanoparticles (LNPs) deliver gene editing cargoes to hepatocytes through receptor-mediated uptake via the low-density lipoprotein receptor (LDLR). Homozygous familial hypercholesterolemia (HoFH) is a morbid genetic disease characterized by complete or near-complete LDLR deficiency, markedly elevated blood low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-C) levels, and premature atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease. In order to enable in vivo liver gene editing in HoFH patients, we developed a novel LNP delivery technology that incorporates a targeting ligand—&lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;-acetylgalactosamine (GalNAc)—which binds to the asialoglycoprotein receptor (ASGPR). In a cynomolgus monkey (Macaca fascicularis) non-human primate (NHP) model of HoFH created by somatic knockout of the &lt;italic&gt;LDLR&lt;/italic&gt; gene via CRISPR-Cas9, treatment with GalNAc-LNPs formulated with an adenine base editor mRNA and a guide RNA (gRNA) targeting the &lt;italic&gt;ANGPTL3&lt;/italic&gt; gene yielded ~60% whole-liver editing and ~94% reduction of blood ANGPTL3 protein levels, whereas standard LNPs yielded minimal editing. Moreover, in wild-type NHPs, the editing achieved by GalNAc-LNPs compared favorably to that achieved by standard LNPs, suggesting that GalNAc-LNP delivery technology may prove useful across a range of in vivo therapeutic applications targeting the liver.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467731" rel="alternate" title="Lipid nanoparticles incorporating a GalNAc ligand enable in vivo liver ANGPTL3 editing in wild-type and somatic LDLR knockout non-human primates (42 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467815</id><title>Natural variation in gene expression and Zika virus susceptibility revealed by villages of neural progenitor cells (35 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.935533+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael F. Wells</name></author><author><name>James Nemesh</name></author><author><name>Sulagna Ghosh</name></author><author><name>Jana M. Mitchell</name></author><author><name>Curtis J. Mello</name></author><author><name>Daniel Meyer</name></author><author><name>Kavya Raghunathan</name></author><author><name>Matthew Tegtmeyer</name></author><author><name>Derek Hawes</name></author><author><name>Anna Neumann</name></author><author><name>Kathleen A. Worringer</name></author><author><name>Joseph J. Raymond</name></author><author><name>Sravya Kommineni</name></author><author><name>Karrie Chan</name></author><author><name>Daniel Ho</name></author><author><name>Brant K. Peterson</name></author><author><name>Federica Piccioni</name></author><author><name>Ralda Nehme</name></author><author><name>Kevin Eggan</name></author><author><name>Steven A. McCarroll</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Variation in the human genome contributes to abundant diversity in human traits and vulnerabilities, but the underlying molecular and cellular mechanisms are not yet known, and will need scalable approaches to accelerate their recognition. Here, we advanced and applied an experimental platform that analyzes genetic, molecular, and phenotypic heterogeneity across cells from very many human donors cultured in a single, shared &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; environment, with algorithms (Dropulation and Census-seq) for assigning phenotypes to individual donors. We used natural genetic variation and synthetic (CRISPR-Cas9) genetic perturbations to analyze the vulnerability of neural progenitor cells to infection with Zika virus. These analyses identified a common variant in the antiviral &lt;italic&gt;IFITM3&lt;/italic&gt; gene that regulated &lt;italic&gt;IFITM3&lt;/italic&gt; expression and explained most inter-individual variation in NPCs’ susceptibility to Zika virus infectivity. These and other approaches could provide scalable ways to recognize the impact of genes and genetic variation on cellular phenotypes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;HIGHLIGHTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Measuring cellular phenotypes in iPSCs and hPSC-derived NPCs from many donors&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Effects of donor sex, cell source, genetic and other variables on hPSC RNA expression&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Natural genetic variation and synthetic perturbation screens both identify &lt;italic&gt;IFITM3&lt;/italic&gt; in NPC susceptibility to Zika virus&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;A common genetic variant in &lt;italic&gt;IFITM3&lt;/italic&gt; explains most inter-individual variation in NPC susceptibility to Zika virus&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467815" rel="alternate" title="Natural variation in gene expression and Zika virus susceptibility revealed by villages of neural progenitor cells (35 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.466891</id><title>Genetic Continuity of Indo-Iranian Speakers Since the Iron Age in Southern Central Asia (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.935857+00:00</updated><author><name>Perle Guarino-Vignon</name></author><author><name>Nina Marchi</name></author><author><name>Julio Bendezu-Sarmiento</name></author><author><name>Evelyne Heyer</name></author><author><name>Céline Bon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Since prehistoric times, South Central Asia has been at the crossroads of the movement of people, culture, and goods. Today, the Central Asia’s populations are divided into two cultural and linguistic groups: the Indo-Iranian and the Turko-Mongolian groups. Previous genetic studies unveiled that migrations from East Asia contributed to the spread of Turko-Mongolian populations in Central Asia and the partial replacement of the Indo-Iranian population. However, little is known about the origin of the latter. To shed light on this, we compare the genetic data on two current-day populations– Yaghnobis and Tajiks – with genome-wide data from published ancient individuals. The present Indo-Iranian populations from Central Asia display a strong genetic continuity with Iron Age samples from Turkmenistan and Tajikistan. We model Yaghnobis as a mixture of 93% Iron Age individual from Turkmenistan and 7% from Baikal. For the Tajiks, we observe a higher Baikal ancestry and an additional admixture event with a South Asian population. Our results, therefore, suggest that in addition to a complex history, Central Asia shows a remarkable genetic continuity since the Iron Age, with only limited gene flow.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.466891" rel="alternate" title="Genetic Continuity of Indo-Iranian Speakers Since the Iron Age in Southern Central Asia (29 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468308</id><title>A single-cell massively parallel reporter assay detects cell type specific cis-regulatory activity (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.936050+00:00</updated><author><name>Siqi Zhao</name></author><author><name>Clarice Hong</name></author><author><name>David M Granas</name></author><author><name>Barak A. Cohen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We developed a single-cell massively parallel reporter assay (scMPRA) to measure the activity of libraries of cis-regulatory sequences (CRSs) across multiple cell-types simultaneously. As a proof of concept, we assayed a library of core promoters in a mixture of HEK293 and K562 cells and showed that scMPRA is a reproducible, highly parallel, single-cell reporter gene assay. Our results show that housekeeping promoters and CpG island promoters have lower activity in K562 cells relative to HEK293, which likely reflects developmental differences between the cell lines. Within K562 cells, scMPRA identified a subset of developmental promoters that are upregulated in the CD34+ /CD38 - sub-state, confirming this state as more "stem-like." Finally, we deconvolved the intrinsic and extrinsic components of promoter cell-to-cell variability and found that developmental promoters have a higher proportion of extrinsic noise compared to housekeeping promoters, which may reflect the responsiveness of developmental promoters to the cellular environment. We anticipate scMPRA will be widely applicable for studying the role of CRSs across diverse cell types.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468308" rel="alternate" title="A single-cell massively parallel reporter assay detects cell type specific cis-regulatory activity (24 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468057</id><title>SARS-CoV-2 ORF8 encoded protein contains a histone mimic, disrupts chromatin regulation, and enhances replication (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.936252+00:00</updated><author><name>John Kee</name></author><author><name>Samuel Thudium</name></author><author><name>David Renner</name></author><author><name>Karl Glastad</name></author><author><name>Katherine Palozola</name></author><author><name>Zhen Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yize Li</name></author><author><name>Joseph Cesare</name></author><author><name>Yemin Lan</name></author><author><name>Rachel Truitt</name></author><author><name>Fabian L. Cardenas-Diaz</name></author><author><name>Darrell N. Kotton</name></author><author><name>Konstantinos D. Alysandratos</name></author><author><name>Xianwen Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xuping Xie</name></author><author><name>Pei-Yong Shi</name></author><author><name>Wenli Yang</name></author><author><name>Edward Morrisey</name></author><author><name>Benjamin A. Garcia</name></author><author><name>Shelley L. Berger</name></author><author><name>Susan R. Weiss</name></author><author><name>Erica Korb</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 emerged in China at the end of 2019 and caused the global pandemic of COVID-19, a disease with high morbidity and mortality. While our understanding of this new virus is rapidly increasing, gaps remain in our understanding of how SARS-CoV-2 can effectively suppress host cell antiviral responses. Recent work on other viruses has demonstrated a novel mechanism through which viral proteins can mimic critical regions of human histone proteins. Histone proteins are responsible for governing genome accessibility and their precise regulation is critical for a cell’s ability to control transcription and respond to viral threats. Here, we show that the protein encoded by ORF8 (Orf8) in SARS-CoV-2 functions as a histone mimic of the ARKS motif in histone 3. Orf8 is associated with chromatin, binds to numerous histone-associated proteins, and is itself acetylated within the histone mimic site. Orf8 expression in cells disrupts multiple critical histone post-translational modifications (PTMs) including H3K9ac, H3K9me3, and H3K27me3 and promotes chromatin compaction while Orf8 lacking the histone mimic motif does not. Further, SARS-CoV-2 infection in human cell lines and postmortem patient lung tissue cause these same disruptions to chromatin. However, deletion of the Orf8 gene from SARS-CoV-2 largely blocks its ability to disrupt host-cell chromatin indicating that Orf8 is responsible for these effects. Finally, deletion of the ORF8 gene affects the host-cell transcriptional response to SARS-CoV-2 infection in multiple cell types and decreases the replication of SARS-CoV-2 in human induced pluripotent stem cell-derived lung alveolar type 2 (iAT2) pulmonary cells. These findings demonstrate a novel function for the poorly understood ORF8-encoded protein and a mechanism through which SARS-CoV-2 disrupts host cell epigenetic regulation. Finally, this work provides a molecular basis for the finding that SARS-CoV-2 lacking ORF8 is associated with decreased severity of COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468057" rel="alternate" title="SARS-CoV-2 ORF8 encoded protein contains a histone mimic, disrupts chromatin regulation, and enhances replication (23 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.06.467573</id><title>Cohort Profile: Genetic data in the German Socio-Economic Panel Innovation Sample (Gene-SOEP) (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.936651+00:00</updated><author><name>Philipp D. Koellinger</name></author><author><name>Aysu Okbay</name></author><author><name>Hyeokmoon Kweon</name></author><author><name>Annemarie Schweinert</name></author><author><name>Richard Karlsson Linnér</name></author><author><name>Jan Goebel</name></author><author><name>David Richter</name></author><author><name>Lisa Reiber</name></author><author><name>Bettina Maria Zweck</name></author><author><name>Daniel W. Belsky</name></author><author><name>Pietro Biroli</name></author><author><name>Rui Mata</name></author><author><name>Elliot M. Tucker-Drob</name></author><author><name>K. Paige Harden</name></author><author><name>Gert Wagner</name></author><author><name>Ralph Hertwig</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The German Socio-Economic Panel (SOEP) serves a global research community by providing representative annual longitudinal data of private households in Germany. The sample provides a detailed life course perspective based on a rich collection of information about living conditions, socio-economic status, family relationships, personality, values, preferences, and health. We collected genetic data from 2,598 individuals in the SOEP Innovation Sample, yielding the first genotyped sample that is representative of the entire German population (Gene-SOEP). The Gene-SOEP sample is a longitudinal study that includes 107 full-sibling pairs, 501 parent-offspring pairs, and 152 parent-offspring trios that are overlapping with the parent-offspring pairs. We constructed a repository of 66 polygenic indices in the Gene-SOEP sample based on results from well-powered genome-wide association studies. The Gene-SOEP data provides a valuable resource to study individual differences, inequalities, life-course development, health, and interactions between genetic predispositions and environment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.06.467573" rel="alternate" title="Cohort Profile: Genetic data in the German Socio-Economic Panel Innovation Sample (Gene-SOEP) (20 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468279</id><title>Nanopore adaptive sampling for mitogenome sequencing and bloodmeal identification in hematophagous insects (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.937538+00:00</updated><author><name>Evan J. Kipp</name></author><author><name>Laramie L. Lindsey</name></author><author><name>Cristina M. Blanco</name></author><author><name>Julia Baker</name></author><author><name>Marissa S. Milstein</name></author><author><name>Christopher Faulk</name></author><author><name>Jonathan D. Oliver</name></author><author><name>Peter A Larsen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Blood-feeding insects are important vectors for an array of zoonotic pathogens. Despite significant research focused on well-documented insect vectors of One Health importance, resources for molecular species identification of a large number of hematophagous arthropods are limited. Advancements in next-generation sequencing technologies provide opportunities for targeting mitochondrial genomes of blood-feeding insects, as well as their bloodmeal hosts. This dual approach holds great promise for elucidating complex disease transmission pathways and enhancing the molecular resources for the identification of cryptic insect species. To this end, we leveraged the newly developed Oxford Nanopore Adaptive Sampling (NAS) pipeline to dually sequence the mitogenomes of hematophagous insects and their bloodmeals. Using NAS, we sequenced the entire mitogenomes of Aedes vexans, Culex restuans, Culex territans, and Chrysops niger and successfully identified bloodmeal hosts of Chrysops niger, Culex restuans, and Aedes trivittatus. We show that NAS has the utility to simultaneously molecularly identify blood-feeding insects and characterize disease transmission pathways through bloodmeal host identification. Moreover, our data indicate NAS can facilitate a wide array of molecular systematic studies through novel 'phylogenetic capture' methods. We conclude the NAS approach has great potential for informing global One Health initiatives centered on the mitigation of vector-borne disease through dual vector and bloodmeal identification.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468279" rel="alternate" title="Nanopore adaptive sampling for mitogenome sequencing and bloodmeal identification in hematophagous insects (15 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.465712</id><title>Genomic landscape of drug response reveals novel mediators of anthelmintic resistance (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.938129+00:00</updated><author><name>Stephen R Doyle</name></author><author><name>Roz Laing</name></author><author><name>David Bartley</name></author><author><name>Alison Morrison</name></author><author><name>Nancy Holroyd</name></author><author><name>Kirsty Maitland</name></author><author><name>Alistair Antonopoulos</name></author><author><name>Umer Chaudhry</name></author><author><name>Ilona Flis</name></author><author><name>Sue Howell</name></author><author><name>Jennifer McIntyre</name></author><author><name>John Stuart Gilleard</name></author><author><name>Andy Tait</name></author><author><name>Barbara K Mable</name></author><author><name>Ray Kaplan</name></author><author><name>Neil Sargison</name></author><author><name>Collette Britton</name></author><author><name>Matthew Berriman</name></author><author><name>Eileen Devaney</name></author><author><name>James Cotton</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the genetic basis of anthelmintic drug resistance in parasitic nematodes is key to tracking and combatting their spread. Here, we use a genetic cross in a natural host-parasite system to simultaneously map resistance loci for the three major classes of anthelmintics. This approach identifies novel alleles for resistance to benzimidazoles and levamisole and implicates the transcription factor, cky-1, in ivermectin resistance. This gene is within a locus under selection in ivermectin resistant populations worldwide; functional validation using knockout and gene expression experiments supports a role for cky-1 overexpression in ivermectin resistance. Our work demonstrates the feasibility of high-resolution forward genetics in a parasitic nematode, and identifies variants for the development of molecular diagnostics to combat drug resistance in the field.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.465712" rel="alternate" title="Genomic landscape of drug response reveals novel mediators of anthelmintic resistance (12 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468372</id><title>Transcriptomic analyses implicate neuronal plasticity and chloride homeostasis in ivermectin resistance and recovery in a parasitic nematode (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.938606+00:00</updated><author><name>Roz Laing</name></author><author><name>Stephen R Doyle</name></author><author><name>Jennifer McIntyre</name></author><author><name>Kirsty Maitland</name></author><author><name>Alison Morrison</name></author><author><name>David J Bartley</name></author><author><name>Ray Kaplan</name></author><author><name>Umer Chaudhry</name></author><author><name>Neil Sargison</name></author><author><name>Andy Tait</name></author><author><name>James A Cotton</name></author><author><name>Collette Britton</name></author><author><name>Eileen Devaney</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The antiparasitic drug ivermectin plays an essential role in human and animal health globally. However, ivermectin resistance is widespread in veterinary helminths and there are growing concerns of sub-optimal responses to treatment in related helminths of humans. Despite decades of research, the genetic mechanisms underlying ivermectin resistance are poorly understood in parasitic helminths. This reflects significant uncertainty regarding the mode of action of ivermectin in parasitic helminths, and the genetic complexity of these organisms; parasitic helminths have large, rapidly evolving genomes and differences in evolutionary history and genetic background can confound comparisons between resistant and susceptible populations. We undertook a controlled genetic cross of a multi-drug resistant and a susceptible reference isolate of &lt;italic&gt;Haemonchus contortus&lt;/italic&gt;, an economically important gastrointestinal nematode of sheep, and ivermectin-selected the F2 population for comparison with an untreated F2 control. RNA-seq analyses of male and female adults of all populations identified high transcriptomic differentiation between parental isolates, which was significantly reduced in the F2, allowing differences associated specifically with ivermectin resistance to be identified. In all resistant populations, there was constitutive upregulation of a single gene, &lt;italic&gt;HCON_00155390:cky-1&lt;/italic&gt;, a putative pharyngeal-expressed transcription factor, in a narrow locus on chromosome V previously shown to be under ivermectin selection. In addition, we detected sex-specific differences in gene expression between resistant and susceptible populations, including constitutive upregulation of a P-glycoprotein, &lt;italic&gt;HCON_00162780:pgp-11&lt;/italic&gt;, in resistant males only. After ivermectin selection, we identified differential expression of genes with roles in neuronal function and chloride homeostasis, which is consistent with an adaptive response to ivermectin-induced hyperpolarisation of neuromuscular cells. Overall, we show the utility of a genetic cross to identify differences in gene expression that are specific to ivermectin selection and provide a framework to better understand ivermectin resistance and recovery in parasitic helminths.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468372" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptomic analyses implicate neuronal plasticity and chloride homeostasis in ivermectin resistance and recovery in a parasitic nematode (11 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468086</id><title>Improvement of eukaryotic proteins prediction from soil metagenomes (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.939056+00:00</updated><author><name>Carole Belliardo</name></author><author><name>Georgios Koutsovoulos</name></author><author><name>Corinne Rancurel</name></author><author><name>Mathilde Clément</name></author><author><name>Justine Lipuma</name></author><author><name>Marc Bailly-Bechet</name></author><author><name>Etienne G.J. Danchin</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the last decades, shotgun metagenomics and metabarcoding have highlighted the diversity of microorganisms from environmental or host-associated samples. Most assembled metagenome public repositories use annotation pipelines tailored for prokaryotes regardless of the taxonomic origin of contigs and metagenome-assembled genomes (MAGs). Consequently, eukaryotic contigs and MAGs, with intrinsically different gene features, are not optimally annotated, resulting in an incorrect representation of the eukaryotic component of biodiversity, despite their biological relevance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using an automated analysis pipeline, we have filtered eukaryotic contigs from 6,873 soil metagenomes from the IMG/M database of the Joint Genome Institute. We have re-annotated genes using eukaryote-tailored methods, yielding 5,6 million eukaryotic proteins. Our pipeline improves eukaryotic proteins completeness, contiguity and quality. Moreover, the better quality of eukaryotic proteins combined with a more comprehensive assignment method improves the taxonomic annotation as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using public soil metagenomic data, we provide a dataset of eukaryotic soil proteins with improved completeness and quality as well as a more reliable taxonomic annotation. This unique resource is of interest for any scientist aiming at studying the composition, biological functions and gene flux in soil communities involving eukaryotes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key Points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eukaryotic micro-organisms have key roles in soil microbial communities and ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eukaryotes are underrepresented in metagenomic libraries due to using methods dedicated to prokaryotes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have improved the quality and completeness of the &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; proteins prediction and taxonomic annotation of eukaryotic organisms from soil or plant-associated microbiome.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468086" rel="alternate" title="Improvement of eukaryotic proteins prediction from soil metagenomes (11 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467620</id><title>The evolutionary dynamics of genetic mutational load throughout tomato domestication history (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.939337+00:00</updated><author><name>Hamid Razifard</name></author><author><name>Sofia Visa</name></author><author><name>Denise Tieman</name></author><author><name>Esther van der Knaap</name></author><author><name>Ana L. Caicedo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the evolution of deleterious mutations through domestication has fascinated evolutionary biologists and breeders alike. Some domesticated organisms have been reported to accumulate deleterious mutations, i.e. radical amino acid changes, through their domestication history (“cost of domestication”). However, more recent evidence paints a more complex picture of this phenomenon in different domesticated organisms. In this study, we used genomic sequences of 253 tomato accessions to investigate the evolution of deleterious mutations and genomic structural variants (SVs) through tomato domestication history. Specifically, we used phylogeny-based methods to identify deleterious mutations in the cultivated tomato as well as its closely related semi-wild and wild populations. We also explored a potential correlation between deleterious mutations and SVs. To create a functional link between deleterious alleles and phenotypes of interest for tomato breeding, we also conducted Genome-wide Association Studies (GWAS) on several fruit volatiles.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our results implicate a downward trend, throughout tomato domestication history, in diversity of most alleles, regardless of their functional impact. This suggests that demographic factors, such as bottleneck events and inbreeding, have reduced overall genetic diversity, leading to lower deleterious load and SVs as well as loss of some beneficial alleles during tomato domestication. We also detected an increase in proportions of nonsynonymous and deleterious alleles (relative to synonymous and neutral nonsynonymous alleles, respectively) during the initial stage of tomato domestication in Ecuador, although the final stage of tomato domestication in Mexico did not seem to involve such an increase. However, deleterious alleles in cultivated tomato seem to be more frequent than expected by neutral theory of molecular evolution. Additionally, for all tomato populations, we found a higher proportion of deleterious mutations in genomic regions impacted by SVs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our analyses also revealed frequent deleterious alleles in several well-studied tomato genes, probably involved in response to biotic and abiotic stress as well as fruit development and flavor regulation. Also, through genome-wide association studies (GWAS), we discovered deleterious alleles associated with two volatiles: isobutyl acetate, which is important for tomato fruit flavor, and methyl salicylate, involved in disease resistance and regulating flowering time. To provide a practical guide for breeding experiments, we created TomDel, a public searchable database of 21,162 deleterious alleles identified in this study (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/hrazif/TomDel-0.1"&gt;https://github.com/hrazif/TomDel-0.1&lt;/ext-link&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467620" rel="alternate" title="The evolutionary dynamics of genetic mutational load throughout tomato domestication history (10 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468142</id><title>MusMorph, a database of standardized mouse morphology data for morphometric meta-analyses (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.939518+00:00</updated><author><name>Jay Devine</name></author><author><name>Marta Vidal-García</name></author><author><name>Wei Liu</name></author><author><name>Amanda Neves</name></author><author><name>Lucas Daniel Lo Vercio</name></author><author><name>Rebecca M Green</name></author><author><name>Heather A Richbourg</name></author><author><name>Marta Marchini</name></author><author><name>Colton M Unger</name></author><author><name>Audrey C Nickle</name></author><author><name>Bethany Radford</name></author><author><name>Nathan M Young</name></author><author><name>Paula N Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Robert E Schuler</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Bugacov</name></author><author><name>Campbell Rolian</name></author><author><name>Christopher J Percival</name></author><author><name>Trevor Williams</name></author><author><name>Lee Niswander</name></author><author><name>Anne L Calof</name></author><author><name>Arthur D Lander</name></author><author><name>Axel Visel</name></author><author><name>Frank R Jirik</name></author><author><name>James M Cheverud</name></author><author><name>Ophir D Klein</name></author><author><name>Ramon Y Birnbaum</name></author><author><name>Amy E Merrill</name></author><author><name>Rebecca R Ackermann</name></author><author><name>Daniel Graf</name></author><author><name>Myriam Hemberger</name></author><author><name>Wendy Dean</name></author><author><name>Nils D Forkert</name></author><author><name>Stephen A Murray</name></author><author><name>Henrik Westerberg</name></author><author><name>Ralph S Marcucio</name></author><author><name>Benedikt Hallgrimsson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Complex morphological traits are the product of many genes with transient or lasting developmental effects that interact in anatomical context. Mouse models are a key resource for disentangling such effects, because they offer myriad tools for manipulating the genome in a controlled environment. Unfortunately, phenotypic data are often obtained using laboratory-specific protocols, resulting in self-contained datasets that are difficult to relate to one another for larger scale analyses. To enable meta-analyses of morphological variation, particularly in the craniofacial complex and brain, we created MusMorph, a database of standardized mouse morphology data spanning numerous genotypes and developmental stages, including E10.5, E11.5, E14.5, E15.5, E18.5, and adulthood. To standardize data collection, we implemented an atlas-based phenotyping pipeline that combines techniques from image registration, deep learning, and morphometrics. Alongside stage-specific atlases, we provide aligned micro-computed tomography images, dense anatomical landmarks, and segmentations (if available) for each specimen (N=10,056). Our workflow is open-source to encourage transparency and reproducible data collection. The MusMorph data and scripts are available on FaceBase (www.facebase.org, doi.org/10.25550/3-HXMC) and GitHub (https://github.com/jaydevine/MusMorph).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468142" rel="alternate" title="MusMorph, a database of standardized mouse morphology data for morphometric meta-analyses (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468425</id><title>Persistent parental RNAi in the beetle Tribolium castaneum involves maternal transmission of long double-stranded RNA (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.940141+00:00</updated><author><name>Thorsten Horn</name></author><author><name>Kalin D. Narov</name></author><author><name>Kristen A. Panfilio</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Parental RNA interference (pRNAi) is a powerful and widely used method for gene-specific knockdown.  Yet in insects its efficacy varies between species, and how the systemic RNAi response is transmitted from mother to offspring remains elusive.  Using the flour beetle &lt;italic&gt;Tribolium castaneum&lt;/italic&gt;, we report an RT-qPCR strategy to unmask the presence of double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) distinct from endogenous mRNA.  We find that the injected dsRNA is directly transmitted into the egg and persists throughout embryogenesis.  Despite this depletion of dsRNA from the mother, we show that strong pRNAi can persist for months before waning at strain-specific rates.  In seeking the receptor proteins for cellular uptake of long dsRNA into the egg, we lastly present a phylogenomics profiling approach to ascertain macroevolutionary distributions of candidate proteins.  We demonstrate a visualization strategy based on taxonomically hierarchical assessment of orthology clustering data to rapidly assess gene age and copy number changes, refined by several lines of sequence-based evidence.  We use this approach to document repeated losses of SID-1-like channel proteins in the arthropods, including wholesale loss in the Heteroptera (true bugs), which are nonetheless highly sensitive to pRNAi.  Overall, we elucidate practical considerations for insect pRNAi against a backdrop of outstanding questions on the molecular mechanism of dsRNA transmission to achieve long-term, systemic knockdown.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468425" rel="alternate" title="Persistent parental RNAi in the beetle Tribolium castaneum involves maternal transmission of long double-stranded RNA (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467248</id><title>Transcriptome analysis of Plasmodium falciparum isolates from Benin reveals specific gene expression associated with cerebral malaria (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.940368+00:00</updated><author><name>E. Guillochon</name></author><author><name>J. Fraering</name></author><author><name>V. Joste</name></author><author><name>C. Kamaliddin</name></author><author><name>B. Vianou</name></author><author><name>L. Houzé</name></author><author><name>L.G Baudrin</name></author><author><name>J.F. Faucher</name></author><author><name>A. Aubouy</name></author><author><name>S. Houzé</name></author><author><name>M. Cot</name></author><author><name>N. Argy</name></author><author><name>O. Taboureau</name></author><author><name>G.I. Bertin</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The host and parasitic factors leading to cerebral malaria (CM) are not yet fully elucidated and CM &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; isolates transcriptome profile remains largely unknown. Based on RNA-seq data from 15 CM and 15 uncomplicated malaria (UM) children from Benin, we identified an increased ring stage signature in CM parasites. Reduced circulating time may result from a higher adherence ability of CM isolates and consistent with this hypothesis, we measured an overexpression of &lt;italic&gt;var&lt;/italic&gt; genes in CM. &lt;italic&gt;var&lt;/italic&gt; genes domains expression was more restricted in CM isolates compared to UM, reflecting the specific binding to receptors in host brain endothelium capillaries. However, ICAM-1 binding motif was found expressed in both CM and UM, questioning its role in &lt;italic&gt;Pf&lt;/italic&gt;EMP1 adhesion to ICAM-1 receptor. UM isolates increased circulation time may also be modulated by a more efficient immune response against infected erythrocytes surface proteins, which we could not demonstrate on our cohort. Identification of deregulated genes involved in adhesion, excluding variant surface antigens, also supports the hypothesis of an increased CM adhesion capacity. Finally, numerous upregulated genes involved in entry into host pathway were found, reflecting a greater erythrocytes invasion capacity of CM parasites.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467248" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptome analysis of Plasmodium falciparum isolates from Benin reveals specific gene expression associated with cerebral malaria (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468259</id><title>Genome assembly of the Australian black tiger shrimp (Penaeus monodon) reveals a fragmented IHHNV EVE sequence (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.940759+00:00</updated><author><name>Roger Huerlimann</name></author><author><name>Jeff A Cowley</name></author><author><name>Nicholas M Wade</name></author><author><name>Yinan Wang</name></author><author><name>Naga Kasinadhuni</name></author><author><name>Chon-Kit Kenneth Chan</name></author><author><name>Jaffar Jabbari</name></author><author><name>Kirby Siemering</name></author><author><name>Lavinia Gordon</name></author><author><name>Matthew Tinning</name></author><author><name>Juan D Montenegro</name></author><author><name>Gregory E Maes</name></author><author><name>Melony J Sellars</name></author><author><name>Greg J Coman</name></author><author><name>Sean McWilliam</name></author><author><name>Kyall R Zenger</name></author><author><name>Mehar S. Khatkar</name></author><author><name>Herman W Raadsma</name></author><author><name>Dalllas Donovan</name></author><author><name>Gopala Krishna</name></author><author><name>Dean Jerry</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Shrimp are a valuable aquaculture species globally; however, disease remains a major hindrance to shrimp aquaculture sustainability and growth. Mechanisms mediated by endogenous viral elements (EVEs) have been proposed as a means by which shrimp that encounter a new virus start to accommodate rather than succumb to infection over time. However, evidence on the nature of such EVEs and how they mediate viral accommodation is limited. More extensive genomic data on Penaeid shrimp from different geographical locations should assist in exposing the diversity of EVEs. In this context, reported here is a PacBio Sequel-based draft genome assembly of an Australian black tiger shrimp (&lt;italic&gt;Penaeus monodon&lt;/italic&gt;) inbred for one generation. The 1.89 Gbp draft genome is comprised of 31,922 scaffolds (N50: 496,398 bp) covering 85.9% of the projected genome size. The genome repeat content (61.8% with 30% representing simple sequence repeats) is almost the highest identified for any species. The functional annotation identified 35,517 gene models, of which 25,809 were protein-coding and 17,158 were annotated using interproscan. Scaffold scanning for specific EVEs identified an element comprised of a 9,045 bp stretch of repeated, inverted and jumbled genome fragments of Infectious hypodermal and hematopoietic necrosis virus (IHHNV) bounded by a repeated 591/590 bp host sequence. As only near complete linear ~4 kb IHHNV genomes have been found integrated in the genome of &lt;italic&gt;P. monodon&lt;/italic&gt; previously, its discovery has implications regarding the validity of PCR tests designed to specifically detect such linear EVE types. The existence of conjoined inverted IHHNV genome fragments also provides a means by which hairpin dsRNAs could be expressed and processed by the shrimp RNA interference (RNAi) machinery.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468259" rel="alternate" title="Genome assembly of the Australian black tiger shrimp (Penaeus monodon) reveals a fragmented IHHNV EVE sequence (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.468508</id><title>The impact of rare germline variants on human somatic mutation processes (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.941268+00:00</updated><author><name>Mischan Vali-Pour</name></author><author><name>Ben Lehner</name></author><author><name>Fran Supek</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Somatic mutations are an inevitable component of ageing and the most important cause of cancer.  The rates and types of somatic mutation vary across individuals, but relatively few inherited influences on mutation processes are known. We performed a comprehensive gene-based rare variant association study with diverse mutational processes, using human cancer genomes from over 11,000 individuals of European ancestry. By combining burden and variance tests, we identify 207 associations involving 15 somatic mutational phenotypes and 42 genes that replicated in an independent data set at a FDR of 1%. We associated rare inherited deleterious variants in novel genes such as MSH3, EXO1, SETD2, and MTOR with two different forms of DNA mismatch repair deficiency, and variants in genes such as EXO1, PAXIP1, and WRN with deficiency in homologous recombination repair. In addition, we identified associations with other mutational processes, such as APEX1 with APOBEC-signature mutagenesis. Many of the novel genes interact with each other and with known mutator genes within cellular sub-networks. Considered collectively, damaging variants in the newly-identified genes are prevalent in the population. We suggest that rare germline variation in diverse genes commonly impacts mutational processes in somatic cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.468508" rel="alternate" title="The impact of rare germline variants on human somatic mutation processes (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468418</id><title>Formal meta-analysis of hypoxic gene expression profiles reveals a universal gene signature and cell type-specific effects (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.941433+00:00</updated><author><name>Laura Puente-Santamaria</name></author><author><name>Lucia Sanchez-Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Barbara Pilar Gonzalez-Serrano</name></author><author><name>Nuria Pescador</name></author><author><name>Oscar Hernan Martinez-Costa</name></author><author><name>Ricardo Ramos-Ruiz</name></author><author><name>Luis del Peso</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Integrating transcriptional profiles results in the identification of gene expression signatures that are more robust than those obtained for individual datasets. However, direct comparison of datasets derived from heterogeneous experimental conditions is not possible and their integration requires the application of specific meta-analysis techniques. The transcriptional response to hypoxia has been the focus of intense research due to its central role in tissue homeostasis and in prevalent diseases. Accordingly, a large number of studies have determined the gene expression profile of hypoxic cells. Yet, in spite of this wealth of information, little effort have been done to integrate these dataset to produce a robust hypoxic signature. Results: We applied a formal meta-analysis procedure to a dataset comprising 425 RNAseq samples derived from 42 individual studies including 33 different cell types, to derive a pooled estimate of the effect of hypoxia on gene expression. This approach revealed that a large proportion of the transcriptome (8556 genes out of 20888) is significantly regulated by hypoxia. However, only a small fraction of the differentially expressed genes (1265 genes, 15%) show an effect size that, according to comparisons to gene pathways known to be regulated by hypoxia, is likely to be biologically relevant. By focusing on genes ubiquitously expressed we identified a signature of 291 genes robustly and consistently regulated by hypoxia. Finally, by a applying a moderator analysis we found that endothelial cells show a characteristic gene expression pattern that is significantly different from other cell types. Conclusion: By the application of a formal meta-analysis to hypoxic gene profiles, we have developed a robust gene signature that characterizes the transcriptomic response to low oxygen. In addition to identifying a universal set of hypoxia-responsive genes, we found a set of genes whose regulation is cell-type specific and suggest a unique metabolic response of endothelial cells to reduced oxygen tension.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468418" rel="alternate" title="Formal meta-analysis of hypoxic gene expression profiles reveals a universal gene signature and cell type-specific effects (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468413</id><title>Pathways to polar adaptation in fishes revealed by long-read sequencing (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.941750+00:00</updated><author><name>Scott Hotaling</name></author><author><name>Thomas Desvignes</name></author><author><name>John S. Sproul</name></author><author><name>Luana S.F. Lins</name></author><author><name>Joanna L Kelley</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Long-read sequencing is driving a new reality for genome science where highly contiguous assemblies can be produced efficiently with modest resources. Genome assemblies from long-read sequencing are particularly exciting for understanding the evolution of complex genomic regions that are often difficult to assemble. In this study, we leveraged long-read sequencing to generate a high-quality genome assembly for an Antarctic eelpout, Opthalmolycus amberensis, the first for the globally distributed family Zoarcidae. We used this assembly to understand how O. amberensis has adapted to the harsh Southern Ocean and compared it to another group of Antarctic fishes: the notothenioids. We showed that from a genome-wide perspective, selection has largely acted on different targets in eelpouts relative to notothenioids. However, we did find some overlap; in both groups, selection has acted on genes involved in membrane structure and DNA repair. We found evidence for historical shifts of transposable element activity in O. amberensis and other polar fishes, perhaps reflecting a response to environmental change. We were specifically interested in the evolution of two complex genomic regions known to underlie key adaptations to polar seas: hemoglobin and antifreeze proteins (AFPs). We observed unique evolution of the hemoglobin MN cluster in eelpouts and related fishes in the suborder Zoarcoidei relative to other teleosts. For AFPs, we identified the first species in the suborder with no evidence of afpIII sequences (Cebidichthys violaceus), potentially reflecting a lineage-specific loss of this gene cluster. Beyond polar fishes, our results highlight the power of long-read sequencing to understand genome evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468413" rel="alternate" title="Pathways to polar adaptation in fishes revealed by long-read sequencing (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468099</id><title>The genetic diversity of Ethiopian barley genotypes in relation to their geographical origin (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.941985+00:00</updated><author><name>Surafel Shibru Teklemariam</name></author><author><name>Kefyalew Negisho Bayissa</name></author><author><name>Andrea Matros</name></author><author><name>Klaus Pillen</name></author><author><name>Frank Ordon</name></author><author><name>Gwendolin Wehner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ethiopia is recognized as a center of diversity for barley, and its landraces are known for the distinct genetic features compared to other barley collections. The genetic diversity of Ethiopian barley likely results from the highly diverse topography, altitude, climate conditions, soil types, and farming systems. To get detailed information on the genetic diversity a panel of 260 accessions, comprising 239 landraces and 21 barley breeding lines, obtained from the Ethiopian biodiversity institute (EBI) and the national barley improvement program, respectively were studied for their genetic diversity using the 50k iSelect single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) array. A total of 983 highly informative SNP markers were used for structure and diversity analysis. Three genetically distinct clusters were obtained from the structure analysis comprising 80, 71, and 109 accessions, respectively. Analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA) revealed the presence of higher genetic variation (89%) within the clusters than between the clusters (11%), with moderate genetic differentiation (PhiPT=0.11) and adequate gene flow (Nm=2.02). The Mantel test revealed that the genetic distance between accessions is poorly associated with their geographical distance. Despite the observed weak correlation between geographic distance and genetic differentiation, for some regions like Gonder, Jimma, Gamo-Gofa, Shewa, and Welo, more than 50% of the landraces derived from these regions are assigned to one of the three clusters.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468099" rel="alternate" title="The genetic diversity of Ethiopian barley genotypes in relation to their geographical origin (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467797</id><title>The Escherichia coli serS gene promoter region overlaps with the rarA gene (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.942233+00:00</updated><author><name>Kanika Jain</name></author><author><name>Tyler H. Stanage</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth A. Wood</name></author><author><name>Michael M. Cox</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Deletion of the entire gene encoding the RarA protein of &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; results in a growth defect and additional deficiencies that were initially ascribed to a lack of RarA function. Further work revealed that most of the effects reflected the presence of sequences in the &lt;italic&gt;rarA&lt;/italic&gt; gene that affect expression of the downstream gene, &lt;italic&gt;serS.&lt;/italic&gt; The &lt;italic&gt;serS&lt;/italic&gt; gene encodes the seryl aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase. Decreases in the expression of &lt;italic&gt;serS&lt;/italic&gt; can trigger the stringent response. The sequences that affect &lt;italic&gt;serS&lt;/italic&gt; expression are located in the last 15 nucleotides of the &lt;italic&gt;rarA&lt;/italic&gt; gene.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467797" rel="alternate" title="The Escherichia coli serS gene promoter region overlaps with the rarA gene (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467777</id><title>Prevalent mouse phenotypes in the unexplored druggable genome (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.942464+00:00</updated><author><name>Olga Gulyaeva</name></author><author><name>Zicheng Hu</name></author><author><name>Tudor Oprea</name></author><author><name>K. C. Kent Lloyd</name></author><author><name>Shawn Gomez</name></author><author><name>Bryan L Roth</name></author><author><name>Michael T McManus</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Among the estimated ~23,000 protein encoding human genes, the class of ‘druggable genes’– defined by their ability to bind drug-like compounds– represents an enticing collection of targets for clinical intervention. Yet many if not most of these genes remain poorly understood and understudied. Here we evaluate three major classes of druggable genes (GPCRs, ion channels, and kinases) and found that a third of these remain largely ignored yet display significant mouse phenotypes upon genetic ablation. We show that both well-studied and understudied druggable genes share a similar number and spectrum of phenotypes. Moreover, many of the mouse phenotypes arising from the ablation of both well-studied and understudied druggable genes show similarities with symptoms in rare human diseases. Collectively these data diminish the notion that most poorly studied genes may not be especially ‘important’ and highlight therapeutic opportunities and potential disease models among poorly characterized druggable genes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467777" rel="alternate" title="Prevalent mouse phenotypes in the unexplored druggable genome (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>