<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.243176+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472469</id><title>Giant Starship elements mobilize accessory genes in fungal genomes (171 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.243535+00:00</updated><author><name>Emile Gluck-Thaler</name></author><author><name>Timothy Ralston</name></author><author><name>Zachary Konkel</name></author><author><name>Cristhian Grabowski Ocampos</name></author><author><name>Veena Devi Ganeshan</name></author><author><name>Anne E. Dorrance</name></author><author><name>Terry L. Niblack</name></author><author><name>Corlett W. Wood</name></author><author><name>Jason C. Slot</name></author><author><name>Horacio D. Lopez-Nicora</name></author><author><name>Aaron A. Vogan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Accessory genes are variably present among members of a species and are a reservoir of adaptive functions. In bacteria, differences in gene distributions among individuals largely result from mobile elements that acquire and disperse accessory genes as cargo. In contrast, the impact of cargo-carrying elements on eukaryotic evolution remains largely unknown. Here, we show that variation in genome content within multiple fungal species is facilitated by &lt;italic&gt;Starships,&lt;/italic&gt; a novel group of massive mobile elements that are 110 kb long on average, share conserved components, and carry diverse arrays of accessory genes. We identified hundreds of &lt;italic&gt;Starship-&lt;/italic&gt;like regions across every major class of filamentous Ascomycetes, including 28 distinct &lt;italic&gt;Starships&lt;/italic&gt; that range from 27-393 kb and last shared a common ancestor ca. 400 mya. Using new long-read assemblies of the plant pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Macrophomina phaseolina&lt;/italic&gt;, we characterize 4 additional &lt;italic&gt;Starships&lt;/italic&gt; whose past and ongoing activities contribute to standing variation in genome structure and content. One of these elements, &lt;italic&gt;Voyager&lt;/italic&gt;, inserts into 5S rDNA and contains a candidate virulence factor whose increasing copy number has contrasting associations with pathogenic and saprophytic growth, suggesting &lt;italic&gt;Voyager&lt;/italic&gt;’s activity underlies an ecological trade-off. We propose that &lt;italic&gt;Starships&lt;/italic&gt; are eukaryotic analogs of bacterial integrative and conjugative elements based on parallels between their conserved components and may therefore represent the first known agents of active gene transfer in eukaryotes. Our results suggest that &lt;italic&gt;Starships&lt;/italic&gt; have shaped the content and structure of fungal genomes for millions of years and reveal a new concerted route for evolution throughout an entire eukaryotic phylum.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472469" rel="alternate" title="Giant Starship elements mobilize accessory genes in fungal genomes (171 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472426</id><title>Absolute Scaling of Single-Cell Transcriptomes Reveals Pervasive Hypertranscription in Adult Stem and Progenitor Cells (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.243802+00:00</updated><author><name>Yun-Kyo Kim</name></author><author><name>Miguel Ramalho-Santos</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hypertranscription facilitates biosynthetically demanding cellular state transitions through global upregulation of the nascent transcriptome. Despite its potential widespread relevance, documented examples of hypertranscription remain few and limited predominantly to early development. This limitation is in large part due to the fact that modern sequencing approaches, including single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq), generally assume similar levels of transcriptional output per cell. Here, we use molecule counting and spike-in normalization to develop absolute scaling of single-cell RNA sequencing data. Absolute scaling enables an estimation of total transcript abundances per cell, which we validate in embryonic stem cell (ESC) and germline data and apply to adult mouse organs at steady-state or during regeneration. The results reveal a remarkable dynamic range in transcriptional output among adult cell types. We find that many different multipotent stem and progenitor cell populations are in a state of hypertranscription, including in the hematopoietic system, intestine and skin. Hypertranscription marks cells with multilineage potential in adult organs, is redeployed in conditions of tissue injury, and can precede by 1-2 days bursts of proliferation during regeneration. In addition to the association between hypertranscription and the stem/progenitor cell state, we dissect the relationship between transcriptional output and cell cycle, ploidy and secretory behavior. Our analyses reveal a common set of molecular pathways associated with hypertranscription across adult organs, including chromatin remodeling, DNA repair, ribosome biogenesis and translation. Our findings introduce an approach towards maximizing single-cell RNA-seq profiling. By applying this methodology across a diverse collection of cell states and contexts, we put forth hypertranscription as a general and dynamic cellular program that is pervasively employed during development, organ maintenance and regeneration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SUMMARY STATEMENT&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Absolute scaling of single-cell transcriptomic data reveals highly dynamic global levels of transcription across adult cell lineages&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472426" rel="alternate" title="Absolute Scaling of Single-Cell Transcriptomes Reveals Pervasive Hypertranscription in Adult Stem and Progenitor Cells (30 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472358</id><title>Lessons from the meiotic recombination landscape of the ZMM deficient budding yeast Lachancea waltii (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.243946+00:00</updated><author><name>Fabien Dutreux</name></author><author><name>Abhishek Dutta</name></author><author><name>Emilien Peltier</name></author><author><name>Sabrina Bibi-Triki</name></author><author><name>Anne Friedrich</name></author><author><name>Bertrand Llorente</name></author><author><name>Joseph Schacherer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Meiotic recombination has been deeply characterized in a few model species only, notably in the budding yeast &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt;. Interestingly, most members of the ZMM pathway that implements meiotic crossover interference in &lt;italic&gt;S. cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; have been lost in &lt;italic&gt;Lachancea&lt;/italic&gt; yeast species after the divergence of &lt;italic&gt;Lachancea kluyveri&lt;/italic&gt; from the rest of the clade. This suggests major differences in the control of crossover distribution. After investigating meiosis in &lt;italic&gt;L. kluyveri&lt;/italic&gt;, we determined the meiotic recombination landscape of &lt;italic&gt;Lachancea waltii&lt;/italic&gt; and identified several characteristics that should help understand better the underlying mechanisms. Such characteristics include systematic regions of loss of heterozygosity (LOH) in &lt;italic&gt;L. waltii&lt;/italic&gt; hybrids, compatible with dysregulated Spo11-mediated DNA double strand breaks (DSB) independently of meiosis. They include a higher recombination rate in &lt;italic&gt;L. waltii&lt;/italic&gt; than in &lt;italic&gt;L. kluyveri&lt;/italic&gt; despite the lack of multiple ZMM pro-crossover factors. &lt;italic&gt;L. waltii&lt;/italic&gt; exhibits an elevated frequency of zero-crossover bivalents as &lt;italic&gt;L. kluyveri&lt;/italic&gt; but opposite to &lt;italic&gt;S. cerevisiae. L. waltii&lt;/italic&gt; gene conversion tracts lengths are comparable to those observed in &lt;italic&gt;S. cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; and shorter than in &lt;italic&gt;L. kluyveri&lt;/italic&gt; despite the lack of Mlh2, a factor limiting conversion tracts size in &lt;italic&gt;S. cerevisiae. L. waltii&lt;/italic&gt; recombination hotspots are not shared with either &lt;italic&gt;S. cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; or &lt;italic&gt;L. kluyveri&lt;/italic&gt;, showing that meiotic recombination hotspots can evolve at a rather limited evolutionary scale within budding yeasts. Finally, in line with the loss of several ZMM genes, we found only residual crossover interference in &lt;italic&gt;L. waltii&lt;/italic&gt; likely coming from the modest interference existing between recombination precursors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Studying non-model species is relevant to understand better biological processes by shedding light on their evolutionary variations. Here we chose the non-model budding yeast &lt;italic&gt;Lachancea waltii&lt;/italic&gt; to study meiotic recombination. In sexually reproducing organisms, meiotic recombination shuffles parental genetic combinations notably by crossovers that cluster in hotspots at the population level. We found remarkable variations compared to both the canonical &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; model and another close relative &lt;italic&gt;Lachancea kluyveri&lt;/italic&gt;. Such variations notably include the loss in &lt;italic&gt;L. waltii&lt;/italic&gt; of a layer of regulation of crossover distribution that is otherwise conserved in budding yeasts and mammals. They also include the lack of conservation of crossover hotspots across the &lt;italic&gt;Lachancea&lt;/italic&gt; species while crossover hotspots are remarkably stable across the &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces&lt;/italic&gt; species.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="simple"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;-&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Extensive LOH events in &lt;italic&gt;L. waltii&lt;/italic&gt; intraspecific hybrids&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;-&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;No conservation of the recombination hotspots across the &lt;italic&gt;Lachancea&lt;/italic&gt; genus&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;-&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reduced but not suppressed crossover interference in the absence of the ZMM pathway&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;-&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Similar gene conversion tract lengths in &lt;italic&gt;L. waltii, S. cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;L. kluyveri&lt;/italic&gt; despite the lack of &lt;italic&gt;MLH2&lt;/italic&gt; in &lt;italic&gt;L. waltii&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472358" rel="alternate" title="Lessons from the meiotic recombination landscape of the ZMM deficient budding yeast Lachancea waltii (24 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472942</id><title>Controlling homology-directed repair outcomes in human stem cells with dCas9 (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.244123+00:00</updated><author><name>William C Skarnes</name></author><author><name>Gang Ning</name></author><author><name>Sofia Giansiracusa</name></author><author><name>Alexander S Cruz</name></author><author><name>Cornelis Blauwendraat</name></author><author><name>Brandon Saavedra</name></author><author><name>Kevin Holden</name></author><author><name>Mark R Cookson</name></author><author><name>Michael E Ward</name></author><author><name>Justin A McDonough</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Modeling human disease in human stem cells requires precise, scarless editing of single nucleotide variants (SNV) on one or both chromosomes.  Here we describe improved conditions for Cas9 RNP editing of SNVs that yield high rates of biallelic homology-directed repair.  To recover both heterozygous and homozygous SNV clones, catalytically inactive dCas9 was added to moderate high activity Cas9 RNPs. dCas9 can also block re-cutting and damage to SNV alleles engineered with non-overlapping guide RNAs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472942" rel="alternate" title="Controlling homology-directed repair outcomes in human stem cells with dCas9 (16 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472830</id><title>An unexpected role for the conserved ADAM-family metalloprotease ADM-2 in Caenorhabditis elegans molting (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.244317+00:00</updated><author><name>Braveen B Joseph</name></author><author><name>Sarina Meadows</name></author><author><name>Phillip T Edeen</name></author><author><name>Shaonil Binti</name></author><author><name>David S Fay</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Molting is a widespread developmental process in which the external extracellular matrix (ECM), the cuticle, is remodeled to allow for organismal growth and environmental adaptation. Studies in the nematode Caenorhabditis elegans have identified a diverse set of molting-associated factors including signaling molecules, intracellular trafficking regulators, ECM components, and ECM-modifying enzymes such as matrix metalloproteases. C. elegans NEKL-2 and NEKL-3, two conserved members of the NEK family of protein kinases, are essential for molting and promote the endocytosis of environmental steroid-hormone precursors by the epidermis. Steroids in turn drive the cyclic induction of many genes required for molting. Here we report a novel role for the sole C. elegans ADAM-meltrin metalloprotease family member, ADM-2, as a negative regulator of molting. Whereas loss of adm-2 led to strong suppression of molting defects in partial loss-of-function nekl mutants, overexpression of ADM-2 induced molting defects in wild-type animals. CRISPR genome editing implicated the Zn-binding motif within the metalloprotease domain as critical for mediating the effects of ADM-2 on molting. ADM-2 is expressed in the epidermis, and its trafficking through the endo-lysosomal network was disrupted after NEKL depletion. We also identified the epidermally expressed low-density lipoprotein receptor-related protein, LRP-1, as a candidate target of ADM-2 regulation. Whereas loss of ADM-2 activity led to the upregulation of LRP-1, ADM-2 overexpression caused a reduction in LRP-1 abundance, suggesting that ADM-2 may function as a sheddase for LRP-1. We propose that loss of adm-2 suppresses molting defects in nekl mutants by eliminating a negative regulator of LRP-1, thereby compensating for defects in the efficiency of LRP-1 and sterol uptake. Our findings emphasize the importance of endocytic trafficking for both the internalization of factors that promote molting and the removal of proteins that would otherwise be deleterious to the molting process.
 &lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472830" rel="alternate" title="An unexpected role for the conserved ADAM-family metalloprotease ADM-2 in Caenorhabditis elegans molting (15 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471935</id><title>No evidence of paralogous loci or new bona fide microRNAs in telomere to telomere (T2T) genomic data (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.244588+00:00</updated><author><name>Arun H. Patil</name></author><author><name>Marc K. Halushka</name></author><author><name>Bastian Fromm</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The telomere to telomere (T2T) genome project discovered and mapped ∼240 million additional base pairs of primarily telomeric and centromeric reads. Much of this sequence was comprised of satellite sequences and large segmental duplications. We evaluated the extent to which human &lt;italic&gt;bona fide&lt;/italic&gt; microRNAs (miRNAs) may be found in additional paralogous genomic loci or if previously undescribed microRNAs are present in these newly sequenced regions of the human genome. New genomic regions of the T2T project spanning ∼240 million bp of sequence were obtained and evaluated by blastn for the human miRNAs contained in MirGeneDB2.0 (N=556) and miRBase (N = 1917) along with all species of MirGeneDB2.0 miRNAs (N=10,899). Additionally, bowtie was used to compare unmapped reads from &amp;gt;4,000 primary cell samples to the new T2T sequence. Based on sequence and structure, no &lt;italic&gt;bona fide&lt;/italic&gt; miRNAs were identified. Ninety-seven miRNAs of questionable authenticity (frequently known repeat elements) were identified from the miRBase dataset across the newly described regions of the human genome. These 97 represent only 51 miRNA families due to paralogy of highly similar miRNAs such as 24 members of the hsa-mir-548 family. Altogether, this data strongly supports our having identified widely expressed &lt;italic&gt;bona fide&lt;/italic&gt; miRNAs in the human genome and move us further toward the completion of human miRNA discovery.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471935" rel="alternate" title="No evidence of paralogous loci or new bona fide microRNAs in telomere to telomere (T2T) genomic data (13 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472681</id><title>pop-1/TCF, ref-2/ZIC and T-box factors regulate the development of anterior cells in the C. elegans embryo (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.244739+00:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan D. Rumley</name></author><author><name>Elicia A. Preston</name></author><author><name>Dylan Cook</name></author><author><name>Felicia L. Peng</name></author><author><name>Amanda L. Zacharias</name></author><author><name>Lucy Wu</name></author><author><name>Ilona Jileaeva</name></author><author><name>John Isaac Murray</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Patterning of the anterior-posterior axis is fundamental to animal development. The Wnt pathway plays a major role in this process by activating the expression of posterior genes in animals from worms to humans. This observation raises the question of whether the Wnt pathway or other regulators control the expression of the many anterior-expressed genes. We found that the expression of five anterior-specific genes in &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/italic&gt; embryos depends on the Wnt pathway effectors &lt;italic&gt;pop-1/TCF&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;sys-1/&lt;/italic&gt;β-catenin. We focused further on one of these anterior genes, &lt;italic&gt;ref-2/ZIC,&lt;/italic&gt; a conserved transcription factor expressed in multiple anterior lineages. Live imaging of &lt;italic&gt;ref-2&lt;/italic&gt; mutant embryos identified defects in cell division timing and position in anterior lineages. &lt;italic&gt;Cis-&lt;/italic&gt;regulatory dissection identified three &lt;italic&gt;ref-2&lt;/italic&gt; transcriptional enhancers, one of which is necessary and sufficient for anterior-specific expression. This enhancer is activated by the T-box transcription factors TBX-37 and TBX-38, and surprisingly, concatemerized TBX-37/38 binding sites are sufficient to drive anterior-biased expression alone, despite the broad expression of TBX-37 and TBX-38. Taken together, our results highlight the diverse mechanisms used to regulate anterior expression patterns in the embryo.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472681" rel="alternate" title="pop-1/TCF, ref-2/ZIC and T-box factors regulate the development of anterior cells in the C. elegans embryo (10 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472185</id><title>learnMET: an R package to apply machine learning methods for genomic prediction using multi-environment trial data (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.244917+00:00</updated><author><name>Cathy C. Westhues</name></author><author><name>Henner Simianer</name></author><author><name>Timothy M. Beissinger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We introduce the R-package &lt;italic&gt;learnMET&lt;/italic&gt;, developed as a flexible framework to enable a collection of analyses on multi-environment trial (MET) breeding data with machine learning-based models. &lt;italic&gt;learnMET&lt;/italic&gt; allows the combination of genomic information with environmental data such as climate and/or soil characteristics. Notably, the package offers the possibility of incorporating weather data from field weather stations, or can retrieve global meteorological datasets from a NASA database. Daily weather data can be aggregated over specific periods of time based on naive (for instance, non-overlapping 10-day windows) or phenological approaches. Different machine learning methods for genomic prediction are implemented, including gradient boosted trees, random forests, stacked ensemble models, and multi-layer perceptrons. These prediction models can be evaluated via a collection of cross-validation schemes that mimic typical scenarios encountered by plant breeders working with MET experimental data in a user-friendly way. The package is fully open source and accessible on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472185" rel="alternate" title="learnMET: an R package to apply machine learning methods for genomic prediction using multi-environment trial data (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473000</id><title>Characterizing the variation in chromosome structure ensembles in the context of the nuclear microenvironment (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.245063+00:00</updated><author><name>Priyojit Das</name></author><author><name>Tongye Shen</name></author><author><name>Rachel Patton McCord</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Inside the nucleus, chromosomes are subjected to direct physical interaction between different components, active forces, and thermal noise, leading to the formation of an ensemble of three-dimensional structures. However, it is still not well understood to what extent and how the structural ensemble varies from one chromosome region or cell-type to another. We designed a statistical analysis technique and applied it to single-cell chromosome imaging data to reveal the fluctuation of individual chromosome structures. By analyzing the resulting structural landscape, we find that the largest dynamic variation is the overall radius of gyration of the chromatin region, followed by domain reorganization within the region. By comparing different human cell-lines and experimental perturbations data using this statistical analysis technique and a network entropy approach, we identify both cell-type and condition-specific features of the structural landscapes. We identify a relationship between epigenetic state and the properties of chromosome structure fluctuation and validate this relationship through polymer simulations. Overall, our study suggests that the types of variation in a chromosome structure ensemble are cell-type as well as region-specific and can be attributed to constraints placed on the structure by factors such as variation in epigenetic state.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473000" rel="alternate" title="Characterizing the variation in chromosome structure ensembles in the context of the nuclear microenvironment (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472744</id><title>Autophagy-related protein Atg11 preserves asymmetric inheritance of spindle microtubule-organizing centers (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.245203+00:00</updated><author><name>Md. Hashim Reza</name></author><author><name>Jigyasa Verma</name></author><author><name>Ratul Chowdhury</name></author><author><name>Ravi Manjithaya</name></author><author><name>Kaustuv Sanyal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Asymmetric spindle pole body (SPB) inheritance requires a cascade of events that involve kinases, phosphatases and structural scaffold proteins including molecular motors and microtubule-associated proteins present in the nucleus and/or the cytoplasm. Higher levels of an SPB component Spc72 and the spindle positioning factor Kar9 at the old SPB, which migrates to the daughter cell, ensure asymmetric SPB inheritance. Timely SPB duplication followed by its asymmetric inheritance is a key to correct spindle alignment leading to high-fidelity chromosome segregation. By combining &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; analysis of known protein-protein interactions of autophagy (Atg)-related proteins with those that constitute the chromosome segregation machinery, and growth dynamics of 35 &lt;italic&gt;atg&lt;/italic&gt; mutants in the presence of a microtubule poison, we identified Atg11 as a potential regulator of chromosome transmission. Cells lacking Atg11 did not show any kinetochore defects but displayed a high rate of chromosome loss and delayed anaphase onset. Atg11 positively interacted with Kar9 and Kip2 and negatively with Dyn1 and Kar3 in mediating proper chromosome segregation suggesting a role of Atg11 in spindle positioning. Indeed, &lt;italic&gt;atg11&lt;/italic&gt;∆ cells displayed an inverted SPB inheritance. We further show that Atg11 promotes asymmetric localization of Spc72 and Kar9 on the old SPB. Atg11 physically interacted with Spc72 and transiently localized close to the old SPB during metaphase-to-anaphase progression. Taken together, our study uncovers an autophagy-independent role of Atg11 in spindle alignment and emphasizes the importance of unbiased screens to identify factors mediating the complex and intricate crosstalk between processes fundamental to genomic integrity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dysregulation in spindle alignment during cell division causes decreased lifespan and contributes to diseased states related to aneuploidy such as cancer. The alignment of the mitotic spindle along the mother-bud axis in the budding yeast relies on the differential distribution of proteins between existing old and freshly formed new spindle pole bodies (SPBs). Non-random distribution of Spc72 and Kar9 facilitates the asymmetric inheritance of SPBs, vital for proper spindle elongation and alignment. Here, we identified a non-canonical role of an autophagy-related protein Atg11 in the Kar9-mediated spindle positioning and faithful chromosome segregation. Loss of Atg11 leads to randomized Spc72 distribution. Atg11, like other autophagy proteins, is evolutionarily conserved. Thus, this study reiterates the importance of crosstalk among major biological processes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472744" rel="alternate" title="Autophagy-related protein Atg11 preserves asymmetric inheritance of spindle microtubule-organizing centers (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472759</id><title>GiPS: Genomics-informed parent selection uncovers the breeding value of wheat genetic resources (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.245357+00:00</updated><author><name>Albert W. Schulthess</name></author><author><name>Sandip M. Kale</name></author><author><name>Fang Liu</name></author><author><name>Yusheng Zhao</name></author><author><name>Norman Philipp</name></author><author><name>Maximilian Rembe</name></author><author><name>Yong Jiang</name></author><author><name>Ulrike Beukert</name></author><author><name>Albrecht Serfling</name></author><author><name>Axel Himmelbach</name></author><author><name>Jörg Fuchs</name></author><author><name>Markus Oppermann</name></author><author><name>Stephan Weise</name></author><author><name>Philipp H. G. Boeven</name></author><author><name>Johannes Schacht</name></author><author><name>C. Friedrich H. Longin</name></author><author><name>Sonja Kollers</name></author><author><name>Nina Pfeiffer</name></author><author><name>Viktor Korzun</name></author><author><name>Matthias Lange</name></author><author><name>Uwe Scholz</name></author><author><name>Nils Stein</name></author><author><name>Martin Mascher</name></author><author><name>Jochen C. Reif</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The great efforts spent in the maintenance of past diversity in genebanks are rationalized by the potential role of plant genetic resources in future crop improvement – a concept whose practical implementation has fallen short of expectations. Here, we implement genomics-informed parent selection to expedite pre-breeding without discriminating against non-adapted germplasm. We collect dense genetic profiles for a large winter wheat collection and evaluate grain yield and resistance to yellow rust in representative coresets. Genomic prediction within and across genebanks identified the best parents for PGR x elite derived crosses that outyielded current elite cultivars in multiple field trials.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472759" rel="alternate" title="GiPS: Genomics-informed parent selection uncovers the breeding value of wheat genetic resources (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472627</id><title>Clustering and visualization of single-cell RNA-seq data using path metrics (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.245631+00:00</updated><author><name>Andriana Manousidaki</name></author><author><name>Anna Little</name></author><author><name>Yuying Xie</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent advances in single-cell technologies have enabled high-resolution characterization of tissue and cancer compositions. Although numerous tools for dimension reduction and clustering are available for single-cell data analyses, these methods often fail to simultaneously preserve local cluster structure and global data geometry. This article explores the application of power-weighted path metrics for the analysis of single cell RNA data.
Extensive experiments on single cell RNA sequencing data sets confirm the usefulness of path metrics for dimension reduction and clustering. Distances between cells are measured in a data- driven way which is both density sensitive (decreasing distances across high density regions) and respects the underlying data geometry. By combining path metrics with multidimensional scaling, a low dimensional embedding of the data is obtained which respects both the global geometry of the data and preserves cluster structure. We evaluate the method both for clustering quality and geometric fidelity, and it outperforms other algorithms on a wide range of bench marking data sets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472627" rel="alternate" title="Clustering and visualization of single-cell RNA-seq data using path metrics (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472952</id><title>The zinc-finger transcription factor LSL-1 is a major regulator of the germline transcriptional program in C. elegans (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.246227+00:00</updated><author><name>David Rodriguez-Crespo</name></author><author><name>Magali Nanchen</name></author><author><name>Shweta Rajopadhye</name></author><author><name>Chantal Wicky</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Specific gene transcriptional programs are required to ensure proper proliferation and differentiation processes underlying the production of specialized cells during development. Gene activity is mainly regulated by the concerted action of transcription factors and chromatin proteins. In the nematode &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt;, mechanisms that silence improper transcriptional programs in germline and somatic cells have been well studied, however, how are tissue specific sets of genes turned on is less known. LSL-1 is herein defined as a novel crucial transcriptional regulator of germline genes in &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt;. LSL-1 is first detected in the P4 blastomere and remains present at all stages of germline development, from primordial germ cell proliferation to the end of meiotic prophase. &lt;italic&gt;lsl-1&lt;/italic&gt; loss-of-function mutants exhibit many defects including meiotic prophase progression delay, a high level of germline apoptosis, and production of almost no functional gametes. Transcriptomic analysis and ChIP-seq data show that LSL-1 binds to promoters and acts as a transcriptional activator of germline genes involved in various processes, including homologous chromosome pairing, recombination, and genome stability. Furthermore, we show that LSL-1 functions by antagonizing the action of the heterochromatin proteins HPL-2/HP1 and LET-418/Mi2 known to be involved in the repression of germline genes in somatic cells. Based on our results, we propose LSL-1 to be a major regulator of the germline transcriptional program during development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472952" rel="alternate" title="The zinc-finger transcription factor LSL-1 is a major regulator of the germline transcriptional program in C. elegans (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473094</id><title>Genomic characteristics of recently recognized Vibrio cholerae El Tor lineages associated with cholera in Bangladesh, 1991-2017 (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.246474+00:00</updated><author><name>Md Mamun Monir</name></author><author><name>Talal Hossain</name></author><author><name>Masatomo Morita</name></author><author><name>Makoto Ohnishi</name></author><author><name>Fatema-tuj Johura</name></author><author><name>Marzia Sultana</name></author><author><name>Shirajum Monira</name></author><author><name>Tahmeed Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Thomson</name></author><author><name>Haruo Watanabe</name></author><author><name>Anwar Huq</name></author><author><name>Rita R. Colwell</name></author><author><name>Kimberley D Seed</name></author><author><name>Munirul Alam</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Comparative genomic analysis of Vibrio cholerae El Tor associated with endemic cholera in Asia revealed two distinct lineages, one dominant in Bangladesh and the other in India. An in depth whole genome study of V. cholerae El Tor clinical strains isolated during endemic cholera in Bangladesh (1991 – 2017) included reference genome sequence data obtained online. Core genome phylogeny established using single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) showed V. choleraeEl Tor strains comprised two lineages, BD-1 and BD-2, which, according to Bayesian phylodynamic analysis, originated from paraphyletic group BD-0 around 1981. BD-1 and BD-2 lineages overlapped temporally but were negatively associated as causative agents of cholera 2004-2017. Genome wide association study (GWAS) revealed 140 SNPs and 31 indels, resulting in gene alleles unique to BD-1 and BD-2. Regression analysis of root to tip distance and year of isolation indicated early BD-0 strains at the base, whereas BD-1 and BD-2 subsequently emerged and progressed by accumulating SNPs. Pangenome analysis provided evidence of gene acquisition by both BD-1 and BD-2, of which six crucial proteins of known function were predominant in BD-2. BD-1 and BD-2 diverged and have distinctively different genomic traits, namely heterogeneity in VSP-2, VPI-1, mobile elements, toxin encoding elements, and total gene abundance. In addition, the observed phage-inducible chromosomal island-like element (PLE1), and SXT ICE elements (ICE&lt;sup&gt;TET&lt;/sup&gt;) in BD-2 presumably provided a fitness advantage for the lineage to outcompete BD-1 as the etiological agent of the endemic cholera in Bangladesh, with implications for global cholera epidemiology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473094" rel="alternate" title="Genomic characteristics of recently recognized Vibrio cholerae El Tor lineages associated with cholera in Bangladesh, 1991-2017 (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472741</id><title>Age determination through DNA methylation patterns of fingernails and toenails (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.247045+00:00</updated><author><name>Kristina Fokias</name></author><author><name>Lotte Dierckx</name></author><author><name>Wim Van de Voorde</name></author><author><name>Bram Bekaert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Over the past decade, age prediction based on DNA methylation has become a vastly investigated topic; many age prediction models have been developed based on different DNAm markers and using various tissues. However, the potential of using nails to this end has not yet been explored. Their inherent resistance to decay and ease of sampling would offer an advantage in cases where post-mortem degradation poses challenges concerning sample collection and DNA-extraction. In the current study, clippings from both fingernails and toenails were collected from 108 living test subjects (age range: 0 – 96 years). The methylation status of 15 CpGs located in 4 previously established age-related markers (ASPA, EDARADD, PDE4C, ELOVL2) was investigated through pyrosequencing of bisulphite converted DNA. Significant dissimilarities in methylation levels were observed between all four limbs, hence limb-specific age prediction models were developed using ordinary least squares, weighted least squares and quantile regression analysis. When applied to their respective test sets, these models yielded a mean absolute deviation between predicted and chronological age ranging from 6.71 to 8.48 years. In addition, the assay was tested on methylation data derived from 5 nail samples collected from deceased individuals, demonstrating its feasibility for application in post-mortem cases. In conclusion, this study provides the first proof that chronological age can be assessed through DNA methylation patterns in nails.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472741" rel="alternate" title="Age determination through DNA methylation patterns of fingernails and toenails (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472569</id><title>The blackgrass genome reveals patterns of divergent evolution of non-target site resistance to herbicides (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.247459+00:00</updated><author><name>Lichun Cai</name></author><author><name>David Comont</name></author><author><name>Dana MacGregor</name></author><author><name>Claudia Lowe</name></author><author><name>Roland Beffa</name></author><author><name>Christopher Saski</name></author><author><name>Paul Neve</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Globally, weedy plants result in more crop yield loss than plant pathogens and insect pests combined. Much of the success of weeds rests with their ability to rapidly adapt in the face of human-mediated environmental management and change. The evolution of resistance to herbicides is an emblematic example of this rapid adaptation. Here, we focus on &lt;italic&gt;Alopecurus myosuroides&lt;/italic&gt; (blackgrass), the most impactful agricultural weed in Europe. To gain insights into the evolutionary history and genomic mechanisms underlying adaptation in blackgrass, we assembled and annotated its large, complex genome. We show that non-target site herbicide resistance is oligogenic and likely evolves from standing genetic variation. We present evidence for divergent selection of resistance at the level of the genome in wild, evolved populations, though at the transcriptional level, resistance mechanisms are underpinned by similar patterns of up-regulation of stress- and defence-responsive gene families. These gene families are expanded in the blackgrass genome, suggesting that the large, duplicated, and dynamic genome plays a role in enabling rapid adaptation in blackgrass. These observations have wide significance for understanding rapid plant adaptation in novel stressful environments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472569" rel="alternate" title="The blackgrass genome reveals patterns of divergent evolution of non-target site resistance to herbicides (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472291</id><title>genomicSimulation: fast R functions for stochastic simulation of breeding programs (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.247610+00:00</updated><author><name>Kira Villiers</name></author><author><name>Eric Dinglasan</name></author><author><name>Ben J. Hayes</name></author><author><name>Kai P. Voss-Fels</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Simulation tools are key to designing and optimising breeding programs that are many-year, high-effort endeavours. Tools that operate on real genotypes and integrate easily with other analysis software are needed for users to integrate simulated data into their analysis and decision-making processes. This paper presents genomicSimulation, a fast and flexible tool for the stochastic simulation of crossing and selection on real genotypes. It is fully written in C for high execution speeds, has minimal dependencies, and is available as an R package for integration with R’s broad range of analysis and visualisation tools. Comparisons of a simulated recreation of a breeding program to the real data shows that the tool’s simulated offspring correctly show key population features. Both versions of genomicSimulation are freely available on GitHub: The R package version at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/vllrs/genomicSimulation/"&gt;https://github.com/vllrs/genomicSimulation/&lt;/ext-link&gt; and the C library version at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/vllrs/genomicSimulationC"&gt;https://github.com/vllrs/genomicSimulationC&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472291" rel="alternate" title="genomicSimulation: fast R functions for stochastic simulation of breeding programs (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472295</id><title>Protective effect of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-α in regulating the early inflammation response to extended hepatectomy from a comparative transcriptomic analysis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.247863+00:00</updated><author><name>Cheng-Cheng Shi</name></author><author><name>Yang Bai</name></author><author><name>Xin Yan</name></author><author><name>Nuo Cheng</name></author><author><name>Wen-Zhi Guo</name></author><author><name>Shui-Jun Zhang</name></author><author><name>Ji-Hua Shi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The regulation mechanism of small-for-size syndrome remains unclear. Thus, we aimed to analyze the molecular profiles following extended hepatectomy and identify the therapeutic target. Major hepatectomy and extended hepatectomy were performed in the rat model, and the remnant livers were obtained dynamically for the high-throughput transcriptome analysis to identify the differentially expressed genes (DEGs). The general framework for weighted gene co-expression network analysis (WGCNA) was employed to explore the expression patterns of DEGs. As result, WGCNA identified 10 distinct gene co-expression modules according to the correlation between module eigengene and different postoperative time-points. The magenta module (gene count: 289) and the lightcyan module (gene count: 484) were found positively correlated with major hepatectomy instead of extended hepatectomy. In the lightcyan module, peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-α (PPARα) was selected and found the down-regulation in the remnant liver following extended (marginal) hepatectomy in rats and humans. Besides, administration of PPARα agonist attenuated hepatic inflammation injury while PPARα antagonist increased liver inflammation injury after extended hepatectomy in rats, marked by the significantly changed aminotransferases, tumor necrosis factor-α and interleukin&lt;italic&gt;-&lt;/italic&gt;6 levels in the plasm, and histological Suzuki criteria. Consequently, DEGs and their molecular profiles after extended hepatectomy were identified, and PPARα might be a potential therapy target for small-for-size syndrome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472295" rel="alternate" title="Protective effect of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-α in regulating the early inflammation response to extended hepatectomy from a comparative transcriptomic analysis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.471847</id><title>Dynamic interplay between structural variations and 3D chromosome organization in pancreatic cancer (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.248013+00:00</updated><author><name>Yongxing Du</name></author><author><name>Zongting Gu</name></author><author><name>Zongze Li</name></author><author><name>Zan Yuan</name></author><author><name>Yue Zhao</name></author><author><name>Xiaohao Zheng</name></author><author><name>Xiaochen Bo</name></author><author><name>Hebing Chen</name></author><author><name>Chengfeng Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Structural variations (SVs) are the greatest source of variation in the genome and can lead to oncogenesis. However, the identification and interpretation of SVs in human pancreatic cancer remain largely undefined due to technological limitations. Here, we investigate the spectrum of SVs and three-dimensional (3D) chromatin architecture in human pancreatic ductal epithelial cell carcinogenesis by using state-of-the-art long-read single-molecule real-time (SMRT) and high-throughput chromosome conformation capture (Hi-C) sequencing techniques. We find that the 3D genome organization is remodeled and correlated with gene expressional change. The bulk remodeling effect of cross-boundary SVs in the 3D genome partly depends on intercellular genomic heterogeneity. Meanwhile, contact domains tend to minimize these disrupting effects of SVs within local adjacent genomic regions to maintain overall stability of 3D genome organization. Moreover, our data also demonstrates complex genomic rearrangements involving two key driver genes CDKN2A and SMAD4, and elucidates their influence on cancer-related gene expression from both linear view and 3D perspective. Overall, this study provides a valuable resource and highlights the impact, complexity and dynamicity of the interplay between SVs and 3D genome organization, which further expands our understanding of pathogenesis of SVs in human pancreatic cancer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.471847" rel="alternate" title="Dynamic interplay between structural variations and 3D chromosome organization in pancreatic cancer (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472985</id><title>Classification and Regression Models for Genomic Selection of Skewed Phenotypes: A Case for Disease Resistance in Winter Wheat (Triticum aestivum L.) (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.248168+00:00</updated><author><name>Lance F Merrick</name></author><author><name>Dennis N Lozada</name></author><author><name>Xianming Chen</name></author><author><name>Arron H Carter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Most genomic prediction models are linear regression models that assume continuous and normally distributed phenotypes, but responses to diseases such as stripe rust (caused by Puccinia striiformis f. sp. tritici) are commonly recorded in ordinal scales and percentages. Disease severity (SEV) and infection type (IT) data in germplasm screening nurseries generally do not follow these assumptions. On this regard, researchers may ignore the lack of normality, transform the phenotypes, use generalized linear models, or use supervised learning algorithms and classification models with no restriction on the distribution of response variables, which are less sensitive when modeling ordinal scores. The goal of this research was to compare classification and regression genomic selection models for skewed phenotypes using stripe rust SEV and IT in winter wheat. We extensively compared both regression and classification prediction models using two training populations composed of breeding lines phenotyped in four years (2016-2018, and 2020) and a diversity panel phenotyped in four years (2013-2016). The prediction models used 19,861 genotyping-by-sequencing single-nucleotide polymorphism markers. Overall, square root transformed phenotypes using rrBLUP and support vector machine regression models displayed the highest combination of accuracy and relative efficiency across the regression and classification models. Further, a classification system based on support vector machine and ordinal Bayesian models with a 2-Class scale for SEV reached the highest class accuracy of 0.99. This study showed that breeders can use linear and non-parametric regression models within their own breeding lines over combined years to accurately predict skewed phenotypes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472985" rel="alternate" title="Classification and Regression Models for Genomic Selection of Skewed Phenotypes: A Case for Disease Resistance in Winter Wheat (Triticum aestivum L.) (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472883</id><title>Specific vulnerability of long telomeres to undergo end fusions revealed by mutational analysis of Rap1 (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.248294+00:00</updated><author><name>Peter Baumann</name></author><author><name>Lili Pan</name></author><author><name>Duncan Tormey</name></author><author><name>Nadine Bobon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The conserved Rap1 protein is part of the shelterin complex that plays critical roles in chromosome end protection and telomere length homeostasis. Previous studies addressed how fission yeast Rap1 contributes to telomere length maintenance, but the mechanism by which the protein inhibits end fusions has remained elusive. Here, we use a genetic screen in combination with high throughput sequencing to identify several amino acid positions in Rap1 that have a key role in end protection.  Interestingly, mutations at these sites render cells susceptible to genome instability in a conditional manner with longer telomeres being prone to undergoing end fusions, while short telomeres are sufficiently protected.  The protection of long telomeres requires their nuclear envelope attachment mediated by the Rap1-Bqt4 interaction. Our data demonstrates that longer telomeres pose an additional challenge for the maintenance of genome integrity and provides an explanation for a species-specific upper limit in telomere length.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472883" rel="alternate" title="Specific vulnerability of long telomeres to undergo end fusions revealed by mutational analysis of Rap1 (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>