<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.367429+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476251</id><title>Mixing genome annotation methods in a comparative analysis inflates the apparent number of lineage-specific genes (84 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.367515+00:00</updated><author><name>Caroline M. Weisman</name></author><author><name>Andrew M. Murray</name></author><author><name>Sean R Eddy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Comparisons of genomes of different species are used to identify lineage-specific genes, those genes that appear unique to one species or clade. Lineage-specific genes are often thought to represent genetic novelty that underlies unique adaptations. Identification of these genes depends not only on genome sequences, but also on inferred gene annotations. Comparative analyses typically use available genomes that have been annotated using different methods, increasing the risk that orthologous DNA sequences may be erroneously annotated as a gene in one species but not another, appearing lineage-specific as a result. To evaluate the impact of such 'annotation heterogeneity', we identified four clades of species with sequenced genomes with more than one publicly available gene annotation, allowing us to compare the number of lineage-specific genes inferred when differing annotation methods are used to those resulting when annotation method is uniform across the clade. In these case studies, annotation heterogeneity increases the apparent number of lineage-specific genes by up to 15-fold, suggesting that annotation heterogeneity is a substantial source of potential artifact.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476251" rel="alternate" title="Mixing genome annotation methods in a comparative analysis inflates the apparent number of lineage-specific genes (84 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476171</id><title>A high-resolution comparative atlas across 74 fish genomes illuminates teleost evolution after whole-genome duplication (65 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.367585+00:00</updated><author><name>Elise Parey</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Louis</name></author><author><name>Jérôme Monfort</name></author><author><name>Yann Guiguen</name></author><author><name>Hugues Roest Crollius</name></author><author><name>Camille Berthelot</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Teleost fish are one of the most species-rich and diverse clades amongst vertebrates, which makes them an outstanding model group for evolutionary, ecological and functional genomics. Yet, despite a growing number of sequence reference genomes, large-scale comparative analysis remains challenging in teleosts due to the specifics of their genomic organization. As legacy of a whole genome duplication dated 320 million years ago, a large fraction of teleost genomes remain in duplicate paralogous copies. This ancestral polyploidy confounds the detailed identification of orthologous genomic regions across teleost species. Here, we combine tailored gene phylogeny methodology together with the state-of-the art ancestral karyotype reconstruction to establish the first high resolution comparative atlas of paleopolyploid regions across 74 teleost fish genomes. We show that this atlas represents a unique, robust and reliable resource for fish genomics. We then use the comparative atlas to study the tetraploidization and rediploidization mechanisms that affected the ancestor of teleosts. Although the polyploid history of teleost genomes appears complex, we uncover that meiotic recombination persisted between duplicated chromosomes for over 60 million years after polyploidization, suggesting that the teleost ancestor was an autotetraploid.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476171" rel="alternate" title="A high-resolution comparative atlas across 74 fish genomes illuminates teleost evolution after whole-genome duplication (65 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476419</id><title>Population genomic evidence of selection on structural variants in a natural hybrid zone (56 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.367659+00:00</updated><author><name>Linyi Zhang</name></author><author><name>Samridhi Chaturvedi</name></author><author><name>Chris Nice</name></author><author><name>Lauren Lucas</name></author><author><name>Zachariah Gompert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Structural variants (SVs) can promote speciation by directly causing reproductive isolation or by suppressing recombination across large genomic regions. Whereas examples of each mechanism have been documented, systematic tests of the role of SVs in speciation are lacking. Here, we take advantage of long-read (Oxford nanopore) whole-genome sequencing and a hybrid zone between two Lycaeides butterfly taxa (L. melissa and Jackson Hole Lycaeides) to comprehensively evaluate genome-wide patterns of introgression for SVs and relate these patterns to hypotheses about speciation. We found &amp;gt;100,000 SVs segregating within or between the two hybridizing species. SVs and SNPs exhibited similar levels of genetic differentiation between species, with the exception of inversions, which were more differentiated. We detected credible variation in patterns of introgression among SV loci in the hybrid zone, with 562 of 1419 ancestry-informative SVs exhibiting genomic clines that deviating from null expectations based on genome-average ancestry. Overall, hybrids exhibited a directional shift towards Jackson Hole Lycaeides ancestry at SV loci, consistent with the hypothesis that these loci experienced more selection on average then SNP loci. Surprisingly, we found that deletions, rather than inversions, showed the highest skew towards excess introgression from Jackson Hole Lycaeides. Excess Jackson Hole Lycaeides ancestry in hybrids was also especially pronounced for Z-linked SVs and inversions containing many genes. In conclusion, our results show that SVs are ubiquitous and suggest that SVs in general, but especially deletions, might contribute disproportionately to hybrid fitness and thus (partial) reproductive isolation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476419" rel="alternate" title="Population genomic evidence of selection on structural variants in a natural hybrid zone (56 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476329</id><title>Meiosis in the human pathogen Aspergillus fumigatus has the highest known number of crossovers (53 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.367726+00:00</updated><author><name>Ben Auxier</name></author><author><name>Frank Becker</name></author><author><name>Reindert Nijland</name></author><author><name>Alfons J.M. Debets</name></author><author><name>Joost van den Heuvel</name></author><author><name>Eveline Snelders</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Evidence from both population genetics and a laboratory sexual cycle indicate that sex is common in the fungus Aspergillus fumigatus. However, the impact of sexual reproduction has remained unclear. Here, we show that meiosis in A. fumigatus involves the highest known recombination rate, producing ~29 crossovers per chromosome. This represents the highest known crossover rate for any Eukaryotic species. We validate this recombination rate by mapping resistance to acriflavine, a common genetic marker. We further show that this recombination rate can produce the commonly encountered TR34/L98H azole-resistant cyp51A haplotype in each sexual event, facilitating its rapid and global spread. Understanding the consequences of this unparalleled crossover rate will not only enrich our genetic understanding of this emergent human pathogen, but of meiosis in general.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476329" rel="alternate" title="Meiosis in the human pathogen Aspergillus fumigatus has the highest known number of crossovers (53 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.475871</id><title>An ancient truncated duplication of the anti-Mullerian hormone receptor type 2 gene is a potential conserved master sex determinant in the Pangasiidae catfish family (36 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.367801+00:00</updated><author><name>Ming Wen</name></author><author><name>Qiaowei Pan</name></author><author><name>Elodie Jouanno</name></author><author><name>Jerome Montfort</name></author><author><name>Margot Zahm</name></author><author><name>Cedric Cabau</name></author><author><name>Christophe Klopp</name></author><author><name>Carole Iampietro</name></author><author><name>Celine Roques</name></author><author><name>Olivier Bouchez</name></author><author><name>Adrien Castinel</name></author><author><name>Cecile Donnadieu</name></author><author><name>Hugues Parrinello</name></author><author><name>Charles Poncet</name></author><author><name>Elodie Belmonte</name></author><author><name>Veronique Gautier</name></author><author><name>Jean-Christophe Avarre</name></author><author><name>Remi Dugue</name></author><author><name>Rudhy Gustiano</name></author><author><name>Tran Thi thuy Ha</name></author><author><name>Marc Campet</name></author><author><name>Kednapat Sriphairoj</name></author><author><name>Josiane Ribolli</name></author><author><name>Fernanda L. deAlmeida</name></author><author><name>Thomas Desvignes</name></author><author><name>John H. Postlethwait</name></author><author><name>Christabel FloiBucao</name></author><author><name>Marc Robinson-Rechavi</name></author><author><name>Julien Bobe</name></author><author><name>Amaury Herpin</name></author><author><name>Yann Guiguen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The evolution of sex determination (SD) mechanisms in teleost fishes is amazingly dynamic, as reflected by the variety of different master sex-determining genes identified, even sometimes among closely related species. Pangasiids are a group of economically important catfishes in many South-Asian countries, but little is known about their sex determination system. Here, we generated novel genomic resources for 12 Pangasiid species and provided a first characterization of their SD system. Based on an Oxford Nanopore long-read chromosome-scale high quality genome assembly of the striped catfish Pangasianodon hypophthalmus, we identified a duplication of the anti-Mullerian hormone receptor type II gene (amhr2), which was further characterized as being sex-linked in males and expressed only in testicular samples. These first results point to a male-specific duplication on the Y chromosome (amhr2by) of the autosomal amhr2a. Sequence annotation revealed that the P. hypophthalmus Amhr2by is truncated in its N-terminal domain, lacking the cysteine-rich extracellular part of the receptor that is crucial for ligand binding, suggesting a potential route for its neofunctionalization. Short-read genome sequencing and reference-guided assembly of 11 additional Pangasiid species, along with sex-linkage studies, revealed that this truncated amhr2by duplication is also conserved as a male-specific gene in many Pangasiids. Reconstructions of the amhr2 phylogeny suggested that amhr2by arose from an ancient duplication / insertion event at the root of the Siluroidei radiation that is dated around 100 million years ago. Altogether these results bring multiple lines of evidence supporting that amhr2by is an ancient and conserved master sex-determining gene in Pangasiid catfishes, a finding that highlights the recurrent usage of the transforming growth factor β pathway in teleost sex determination and brings another empirical case towards the understanding of the dynamics or stability of sex determination systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.475871" rel="alternate" title="An ancient truncated duplication of the anti-Mullerian hormone receptor type 2 gene is a potential conserved master sex determinant in the Pangasiidae catfish family (36 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.474936</id><title>The megabase-scale crossover landscape is independent of sequence divergence (32 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.367966+00:00</updated><author><name>Qichao Lian</name></author><author><name>Victor Solier</name></author><author><name>Birgit Walkemeier</name></author><author><name>Bruno Huettel</name></author><author><name>Korbinian Schneeberger</name></author><author><name>Raphael Mercier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Meiotic recombination frequency varies along chromosomes and strongly correlates with sequence divergence. However, the causality underlying this correlation is unclear. To untangle the relationship between recombination landscapes and polymorphisms, we characterized the genome-wide recombination landscape in the absence of polymorphisms, using &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; homozygous inbred lines in which a few hundred genetic markers were introduced through mutagenesis. We found that megabase-scale recombination landscapes in inbred lines are strikingly similar to the recombination landscapes in hybrids, with the sole exception of heterozygous large rearrangements where recombination is prevented locally. In addition, we found that the megabase-scale recombination landscape can be accurately predicted by chromatin features. Our results show that polymorphisms are not causal for the shape of the megabase-scale recombination landscape, rather, favor alternative models in which recombination and chromatin shape sequence divergence across the genome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.474936" rel="alternate" title="The megabase-scale crossover landscape is independent of sequence divergence (32 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476002</id><title>In vivo single-cell profiling of lncRNAs during Ebola virus infection (29 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.368036+00:00</updated><author><name>Luisa Santus</name></author><author><name>Raquel García-Pérez</name></author><author><name>Maria Sopena-Rios</name></author><author><name>Aaron E Lin</name></author><author><name>Gordon C Adams</name></author><author><name>Kayla G Barnes</name></author><author><name>Katherine J Siddle</name></author><author><name>Shirlee Wohl</name></author><author><name>Ferran Reverter</name></author><author><name>John L Rinn</name></author><author><name>Richard S Bennett</name></author><author><name>Lisa E Hensley</name></author><author><name>Pardis C Sabeti</name></author><author><name>Marta Melé</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Long non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs) are pivotal mediators of systemic immune response to viral infection, yet most studies concerning their expression and functions upon immune stimulation are limited to &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; bulk cell populations. This strongly constrains our understanding of how lncRNA expression varies at single-cell resolution, and how their cell-type specific immune regulatory roles may differ compared to protein-coding genes. Here, we perform the first in-depth characterization of lncRNA expression variation at single-cell resolution during Ebola virus (EBOV) infection &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Using bulk RNA-sequencing from 119 samples and 12 tissue types, we significantly expand the current macaque lncRNA annotation. We then profile lncRNA expression variation in immune circulating single-cells during EBOV infection and find that lncRNAs’ expression in fewer cells is a major differentiating factor from their protein-coding gene counterparts. Upon EBOV infection, lncRNAs present dynamic and mostly cell-type specific changes in their expression profiles especially in monocytes, the main cell type targeted by EBOV. Such changes are associated with gene regulatory modules related to important innate immune responses such as interferon response and purine metabolism. Within infected cells, several lncRNAs have positively and negatively correlated expression with viral load, suggesting that expression of some of these lncRNAs might be directly hijacked by EBOV to attack host cells. This study provides novel insights into the roles that lncRNAs play in the host response to acute viral infection and paves the way for future lncRNA studies at single-cell resolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476002" rel="alternate" title="In vivo single-cell profiling of lncRNAs during Ebola virus infection (29 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476326</id><title>Transposable elements contribute to the spatiotemporal microRNA landscape in human brain development (15 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.368133+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher J. Playfoot</name></author><author><name>Shaoline Sheppard</name></author><author><name>Evarist Planet</name></author><author><name>Didier Trono</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Transposable elements (TEs) contribute to the evolution of gene regulatory networks and are dynamically expressed throughout human brain development and disease. One gene regulatory mechanism influenced by TEs is the miRNA system of post-transcriptional control. miRNA sequences frequently overlap TE loci and this miRNA expression landscape is crucial for control of gene expression in adult brain and different cellular contexts. Despite this, a thorough investigation of the spatiotemporal expression of TE-embedded miRNAs in human brain development is lacking. Here, we identify a spatiotemporally dynamic TE-embedded miRNA expression landscape between childhood and adolescent stages of human brain development. These miRNAs sometimes arise from two apposed TEs of the same subfamily, such as for L2 or MIR elements, but in the majority of cases stem from solo TEs. They give rise to &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; predicted high-confidence pre-miRNA hairpin structures, likely represent functional miRNAs and have predicted genic targets associated with neurogenesis. TE-embedded miRNA expression is distinct in the cerebellum when compared to other brain regions, as has previously been described for gene and TE expression. Furthermore, we detect expression of previously non-annotated TE-embedded miRNAs throughout human brain development, suggestive of a previously undetected miRNA control network. Together, as with non-TE-embedded miRNAs, TE-embedded sequences give rise to spatiotemporally dynamic miRNA expression networks, the implications of which for human brain development constitute extensive avenues of future experimental research. To facilitate interactive exploration of these spatiotemporal miRNA expression dynamics, we provide the “Brain miRTExplorer” web application freely accessible for the community.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476326" rel="alternate" title="Transposable elements contribute to the spatiotemporal microRNA landscape in human brain development (15 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475153</id><title>Evaluation of methods incorporating biological function and GWAS summary statistics to accelerate discovery (12 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.368197+00:00</updated><author><name>Amy Moore</name></author><author><name>Jesse Marks</name></author><author><name>Bryan C. Quach</name></author><author><name>Yuelong Guo</name></author><author><name>Laura J. Bierut</name></author><author><name>Nathan C. Gaddis</name></author><author><name>Dana B. Hancock</name></author><author><name>Grier P. Page</name></author><author><name>Eric O. Johnson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Where sufficiently large genome-wide association study (GWAS) samples are not currently available or feasible, methods that leverage increasing knowledge of the biological function of variants may illuminate discoveries without increasing sample size. We comprehensively evaluated 18 functional weighting methods for identifying novel associations. We assessed the performance of these methods using published results from multiple GWAS waves across each of five complex traits. Although no method achieved both high sensitivity and positive predictive value (PPV) for any trait, a subset of methods utilizing pleiotropy and expression quantitative trait loci nominated variants with high PPV (&amp;gt;75%) for multiple traits. Application of functionally weighting methods to enhance GWAS power for locus discovery is unlikely to circumvent the need for larger sample sizes in truly underpowered GWAS, but these results suggest that applying functional weighting to GWAS can accurately nominate additional novel loci from available samples for follow-up studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475153" rel="alternate" title="Evaluation of methods incorporating biological function and GWAS summary statistics to accelerate discovery (12 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476072</id><title>Integrative in situ mapping of single-cell transcriptional states and tissue histopathology in an Alzheimer's disease model (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.368285+00:00</updated><author><name>Hu Zeng</name></author><author><name>Jiahao Huang</name></author><author><name>Haowen Zhou</name></author><author><name>William J. Meilandt</name></author><author><name>Borislav Dejanovic</name></author><author><name>Yiming Zhou</name></author><author><name>Christopher J. Bohlen</name></author><author><name>Seung-Hye Lee</name></author><author><name>Jingyi Ren</name></author><author><name>Albert Liu</name></author><author><name>Hao Sheng</name></author><author><name>Jia Liu</name></author><author><name>Morgan Sheng</name></author><author><name>Xiao Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Amyloid-β plaques and neurofibrillary tau tangles are the neuropathologic hallmarks of Alzheimer's disease (AD), but the spatiotemporal cellular responses and molecular mechanisms underlying AD pathophysiology remain poorly understood. Here we introduce STARmap PLUS to simultaneously map single-cell transcriptional states and disease marker proteins in brain tissues of AD mouse models at subcellular resolution (200 nm). This high-resolution spatial transcriptomics map revealed a core-shell structure where disease-associated microglia (DAM) closely contact amyloid-β plaques, whereas disease-associated astrocytes (DAA) and oligodendrocyte precursor cells (OPC) are enriched in the outer shells surrounding the plaque-DAM complex. Hyperphosphorylated tau emerged mainly in excitatory neurons in the CA1 region accompanied by the infiltration of oligodendrocyte subtypes into the axon bundles of hippocampal alveus. The integrative STARmap PLUS method bridges single-cell gene expression profiles with tissue histopathology at subcellular resolution, providing an unprecedented roadmap to pinpoint the molecular and cellular mechanisms of AD pathology and neurodegeneration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476072" rel="alternate" title="Integrative in situ mapping of single-cell transcriptional states and tissue histopathology in an Alzheimer's disease model (10 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476375</id><title>Identification of a transcriptional signature found in multiple models of ASD and related disorders (9 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.368381+00:00</updated><author><name>Samuel Thudium</name></author><author><name>Katherine C Palozola</name></author><author><name>Eloise L'Her</name></author><author><name>Erica Korb</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Epigenetic regulation plays a critical role in many neurodevelopmental disorders, including Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD). In particular, many such disorders are the result of mutations in genes that encode chromatin modifying proteins. However, while these disorders share many features, it is unclear whether they also share gene expression disruptions resulting from the aberrant regulation of chromatin. We examined 5 chromatin modifiers that are all linked to ASD despite their different roles in regulating chromatin. Specifically, we depleted Ash1L, Chd8, Crebbp, Ehmt1, and Nsd1 in parallel in a highly controlled neuronal culture system. We then identified sets of shared genes, or transcriptional signatures, that are differentially expressed following loss of multiple ASD-linked chromatin modifiers. We examined the functions of genes within the transcriptional signatures and found an enrichment in many neurotransmitter transport genes and activity-dependent genes. In addition, these genes are enriched for specific chromatin features such as bivalent domains that allow for highly dynamic regulation of gene expression. The downregulated transcriptional signature is also observed within multiple mouse models of neurodevelopmental disorders that result in ASD, but not those only associated with intellectual disability. Finally, the downregulated transcriptional signature can distinguish between neurons generated from iPSCs derived from healthy donors and idiopathic ASD patients through RNA-deconvolution, demonstrating that this gene set is relevant to the human disorder. This work identifies a transcriptional signature that is found within many neurodevelopmental syndromes, helping to elucidate the link between epigenetic regulation and the underlying cellular mechanisms that result in ASD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476375" rel="alternate" title="Identification of a transcriptional signature found in multiple models of ASD and related disorders (9 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476259</id><title>Three Reagents for in-Solution Enrichment of Ancient Human DNA at More than a Million SNPs (9 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.368442+00:00</updated><author><name>Nadin Rohland</name></author><author><name>Swapan Mallick</name></author><author><name>Matthew Mah</name></author><author><name>Robert M Maier</name></author><author><name>Nick J Patterson</name></author><author><name>David Reich</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In-solution enrichment for hundreds of thousands of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) has been the source of &amp;gt;70% of all genome-scale ancient human DNA data published to date. This approach has made it possible to generate data for one to two orders of magnitude lower cost than random shotgun sequencing, making it economical to study ancient samples with low proportions of human DNA, and increasing the rate of conversion of sampled remains into working data thereby facilitating ethical stewardship of human remains. So far, nearly all ancient DNA data obtained using in-solution enrichment has been generated using a set of bait sequences targeting about 1.24 million SNPs (the 1240k reagent). These sequences were published in 2015, but synthesis of the reagent has been cost-effective for only a few laboratories. In 2021, two companies made available reagents that target the same core set of SNPs along with supplementary content. Here, we test the properties of the three reagents on a common set of 27 ancient DNA libraries across a range of richness of DNA content and percentages of human molecules. All three reagents are highly effective at enriching many hundreds of thousands of SNPs. For all three reagents and a wide range of conditions, one round of enrichment produces data that is as useful as two rounds when tens of millions of sequences are read out as is typical for such experiments. In our testing, the Twist Ancient DNA reagent produces the highest coverages, greatest uniformity on targeted positions, and almost no bias toward enriching one allele more than another relative to shotgun sequencing. Allelic bias in 1240k enrichment has made it challenging to carry out joint analysis of these data with shotgun data, creating a situation where the ancient DNA community has been publishing two important bodes of data that cannot easily be co-analyzed by population genetic methods. To address this challenge, we introduce a subset of hundreds of thousands of SNPs for which 1240k data can be effectively co-analyzed with all other major data types.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476259" rel="alternate" title="Three Reagents for in-Solution Enrichment of Ancient Human DNA at More than a Million SNPs (9 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.476524</id><title>A chromosome-scale genome assembly of the false clownfish, Amphiprion ocellaris (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.368510+00:00</updated><author><name>Taewoo Ryu</name></author><author><name>Marcela Herrera</name></author><author><name>Billy Moore</name></author><author><name>Michael Izumiyama</name></author><author><name>Erina Kawai</name></author><author><name>Vincent Laudet</name></author><author><name>Timothy Ravasi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: The false clownfish Amphiprion ocellaris is a popular fish species and an emerging model organism for studying the ecology, evolution, adaptation, and developmental biology of reef fishes. Despite this, high-quality genomic resources for this species are scarce, hindering advanced genomic analyses. Leveraging the power of PacBio long-read sequencing and Hi-C chromosome conformation capture techniques, we constructed a high-quality chromosome-scale genome assembly for the clownfish A. ocellaris. Results: The initial genome assembly comprised of 1,551 contigs of 861.42 Mb, with an N50 of 863.85 kb. Hi-C scaffolding of the genome resulted in 24 chromosomes containing 856.61 Mb. The genome was annotated with 26,797 protein-coding genes and had 96.62 % completeness of conserved actinopterygian genes, making this genome the most complete and high quality among published anemonefish genomes. Transcriptomic analysis identified tissue-specific gene expression patterns, with the brain and optic lobe having the largest number of expressed genes. Further, comparative genomic analysis revealed 91 genome elements conserved only in A. ocellaris and its sister species Amphiprion percula, and not in other anemonefish species. These elements are close to genes that are involved in various nervous system functions and exhibited distinct expression patterns in brain tissue, potentially highlighting the genetic toolkits involved in lineage-specific divergence and behaviors of the clownfish branch. Conclusions: Overall, our study provides the highest quality A. ocellaris genome assembly and annotation to date, whilst also providing a valuable resource for understanding the ecology and evolution of reef fishes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.476524" rel="alternate" title="A chromosome-scale genome assembly of the false clownfish, Amphiprion ocellaris (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.476488</id><title>ISSAAC-seq enables sensitive and flexible multimodal profiling of chromatin accessibility and gene expression in single cells (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.368581+00:00</updated><author><name>Wei Xu</name></author><author><name>Weilong Yang</name></author><author><name>Yunlong Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yawen Chen</name></author><author><name>Qian Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xuefei Wang</name></author><author><name>Kun Song</name></author><author><name>Wenfei Jin</name></author><author><name>Xi Chen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Joint profiling of chromatin accessibility and gene expression from the same single cell/nucleus provides critical information about cell types in a tissue and cell states during a dynamic process. These emerging multi-omics techniques help the investigation of cell-type resolved gene regulatory mechanisms. However, many methods are currently limited by low sensitivity, low throughput or complex workflow. Here, we developed in situ SHERRY after ATAC-seq (ISSAAC-seq), a highly sensitive and flexible single cell multi-omics method to interrogate chromatin accessibility and gene expression from the same single nucleus. We demonstrated that ISSAAC-seq is sensitive and provides high quality data with orders of magnitude more features than existing methods. Using the joint profiles from over 10,000 nuclei from the mouse cerebral cortex, we uncovered major and rare cell types and cell-type specific regulatory elements and identified heterogeneity at the chromatin level within established cell types defined by gene expression. Finally, we revealed distinct dynamics and relationships of gene expression and chromatin accessibility during an oligodendrocyte maturation trajectory.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.476488" rel="alternate" title="ISSAAC-seq enables sensitive and flexible multimodal profiling of chromatin accessibility and gene expression in single cells (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475685</id><title>Multi-GBS: A massively multiplexed GBS-based protocol optimized for large, repetitive conifer genomes (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.368663+00:00</updated><author><name>Miguel Vallebueno-Estrada</name></author><author><name>Sonja Steindl</name></author><author><name>Vasilina Akulova</name></author><author><name>Julia Riefler</name></author><author><name>Lucyna Slusarz</name></author><author><name>Alexis Arizpe</name></author><author><name>Kelly Swarts</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Reduced representation library approaches are still a valuable tool for breeding and population and ecological genomics, even with impressive increases in sequencing capacity in recent years. Unfortunately, current approaches only allow for multiplexing up to 384 samples. To take advantage of increased sequencing capacity, we present Multi-GBS, a massively multiplexable extension to Genotyping-by-Sequencing that is also optimized for large conifer genomes. In Norway Spruce, a highly repetitive 20Gbp diploid genome with high population genetic variation, we call over a million variants in 32 genotypes from three populations, two natural forest in the Alps and Bohemian Alps, and a managed population from southeastern Austria using the existing TASSEL GBSv2 pipeline. Metric MDS analysis of replicated genotypes shows that technical bias in resulting genotype calling is minimal and that populations cluster in biologically meaningful ways.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475685" rel="alternate" title="Multi-GBS: A massively multiplexed GBS-based protocol optimized for large, repetitive conifer genomes (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476241</id><title>Enumeration of Citrus endophytic bacterial communities based on illumine metagenomics technique (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.368740+00:00</updated><author><name>Sehrish Mushtaq</name></author><author><name>Muhammad Shafiq</name></author><author><name>Tehseen Ashraf</name></author><author><name>Muhammad Saleem Haider</name></author><author><name>Sagheer Atta</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Citrus is a valuable crop in Pakistan because it is rich in vitamin C and antioxidants. Huanglongbing (HLB) has an influence on citrus production around the world caused by a bacterium &lt;italic&gt;“Candidatus liberibacter asmticus”&lt;/italic&gt; (CLas), africanus and americanus. The structure and diversity of bacterial species in various ecosystems can be quickly examined using NGS. This approach is considerably quicker and more precise than outdated methods. Healthy or citrus greening infected leaf samples of Grapefruit, &lt;italic&gt;Citrus aurantifolia&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;Citrus reticulata&lt;/italic&gt; Blanco was used for diversity analysis. In this study high throughput, NGS technique was used to access the population of both cultivable and non-cultivable bacterial endophytes from citrus leaves, by using PCR amplicons of 16S rDNA sequences (V5–V7 regions) with Illumina Hi seq. As a result, a total number of 68,722 sequences were produced from the test samples. According to the NGS-based diversity classification, the most common genera of exploited bacterial endophytes were Proteobacteria, Firmicutes, Bacteroides, Cyanobacteria, and Actinobacteria. &lt;italic&gt;Citrus aurantifolia&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Citrus paradisi&lt;/italic&gt; showed almost equal diversity, whereas &lt;italic&gt;Citrus reticulata&lt;/italic&gt; Blanco had a higher proportion of Proteobacteria and Cyanobacteria in their leaves. To determine alpha diversity (AD), additional data was analyzed using statistical indices such as Shannon, Chao1, and Simpson. According to the inverse Simpson diversity index, the abundance of the microbial population in six different citrus samples was 0.48, 0.567, and 0.163, respectively. The metagenomics of microbiota in plant tissues was successfully recorded by NGS technology, which can help us learn more about the interactions between plants and microbes. This research is the first step toward a better understanding of 16SrRNA-based metagenomics from citrus in Pakistan using Illumina (Hi seq) Technology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476241" rel="alternate" title="Enumeration of Citrus endophytic bacterial communities based on illumine metagenomics technique (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.17.476647</id><title>Genome sequence data reveal at least two distinct incursions of the tropical race 4 (TR4) variant of Fusarium wilt into South America (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.368866+00:00</updated><author><name>Paula H. Reyes-Herrera</name></author><author><name>Eliana Torres-Bedoya</name></author><author><name>Diana Lopez-Alvarez</name></author><author><name>Diana Burbano-David</name></author><author><name>Sandra L. Carmona</name></author><author><name>Daniel Patrick Bebber</name></author><author><name>David John Studholme</name></author><author><name>Monica Betancourt</name></author><author><name>Mauricio Soto-Suarez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The global banana industry is threatened by one of the most devastating diseases: Fusarium wilt (FWB). FWB is caused by the soil-borne fungus Fusarium oxysporum f. sp. cubense (Foc), which almost annihilated the banana production in the late 1950s. A new strain of Foc, known as tropical race 4 (TR4), attacks a wide range of banana varieties including Cavendish clones which are the source of 99% of banana exports. In 2019, Foc TR4 was reported in Colombia, and more recently (2021) in Peru. In this study, we sequenced three fungal isolates identified as Foc TR4 from La Guajira (Colombia) and compared them against 19 whole-genome sequences of Foc TR4 publicly available, including four genome sequences recently released from Peru. To understand the genetic relatedness of the Colombian Foc TR4 isolates and those from Peru, we conducted a phylogenetic analysis based on a genome-wide set of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs). Additionally, we compared the genomes of the 22 available Foc TR4 isolates looking for the presence-absence of gene polymorphisms and genomic regions. Our results reveal that (i) the Colombian and Peruvian isolates are genetically distant, which could be better explained by independent incursions of the pathogen to the continent, and (ii) there is a high correspondence between the genetic relatedness and geographic origin of Foc TR4. The profile of present/absent genes and the distribution of missing genomic regions showed a high correspondence to the clades recovered in the phylogenetic analysis, supporting the results obtained by SNP-based phylogeny.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.17.476647" rel="alternate" title="Genome sequence data reveal at least two distinct incursions of the tropical race 4 (TR4) variant of Fusarium wilt into South America (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475628</id><title>Optimal experimental designs for estimating genetic and non-genetic effects underlying infectious disease transmission (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.368952+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher Pooley</name></author><author><name>Glenn Marion</name></author><author><name>Stephen Bishop</name></author><author><name>Andrea Doeschl-Wilson</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Infectious disease spread in populations is controlled by individuals’ susceptibility (propensity to acquire infection), infectivity (propensity to pass on infection to others) and recoverability (propensity to recover/die). Estimating the effects of genetic risk factors on these host epidemiological traits can help reduce disease spread through genetic control strategies. However, the effects of previously identified ‘disease resistance SNPs’ on these epidemiological traits are usually unknown. Recent advances in computational statistics make it now possible to estimate the effects of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) on these traits from longitudinal epidemic data (&lt;italic&gt;e&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;g&lt;/italic&gt;. infection and/or recovery times of individuals or diagnostic test results). However, little is known how to optimally design disease transmission experiments or field studies to maximise the precision at which pleiotropic SNP effects estimates for susceptibility, infectivity and recoverability can be estimated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We develop and validate analytical expressions for the precision of SNP effects estimates on the three host traits assuming a disease transmission experiment with one or more non-interacting contact groups. Maximising these leads to three distinct ‘experimental’ designs, each specifying a different set of ideal SNP genotype compositions across groups: a) appropriate for a single contact-group, b) a multi-group design termed “pure”, and c) a multi-group design termed “mixed”, where ‘pure’ and ‘mixed’ refer to contact groups consisting of individuals with the same or different SNP genotypes, respectively. Precision estimates for susceptibility and recoverability were found to be less sensitive to the experimental design than infectivity. Data from multiple groups were found more informative about infectivity effects than from a single group containing the same number of individuals. Whilst the analytical expressions suggest that the multi-group pure and mixed designs estimate SNP effects with similar precision, the mixed design is preferable because it uses information from naturally occurring infections rather than those artificially induced. The same optimal design principles apply to estimating other categorical fixed effects, such as vaccinations status, helping to more effectively quantify their epidemiological impact.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An online &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://theiteam.github.io/SIRE-PC.html"&gt;software tool&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;italic&gt;SIRE-PC&lt;/italic&gt; has been developed which calculates the precision of estimated substitution and dominance effects of a single SNP (or vaccine status) associated with all three traits depending on experimental design parameters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The developed methodology and software tool can be used to aid the design of disease transmission experiments for estimating the effect of individual SNPs and other categorical variables underlying host susceptibility, infectivity and recoverability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475628" rel="alternate" title="Optimal experimental designs for estimating genetic and non-genetic effects underlying infectious disease transmission (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476457</id><title>User-guided local and global copy-number segmentation for tumor sequencing data (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.369018+00:00</updated><author><name>Zubair Lalani</name></author><author><name>Gillian Chu</name></author><author><name>Silas Hsu</name></author><author><name>Simone Zaccaria</name></author><author><name>Mohammed El-Kebir</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Motivation: Copy-number aberrations (CNA) are genetic alterations that amplify or delete the number of copies of large genomic segments. Although they are ubiquitous in cancer and subsequently a critical area of current cancer research, CNA identification from DNA sequencing data is challenging because it requires partitioning of the genome into complex segments that may not be contiguous. Existing segmentation algorithms address these challenges either by leveraging the local information among neighboring genomic regions, or by globally grouping genomic regions that are affected by similar CNAs across the entire genome. However, both approaches have limitations: overclustering in the case of local segmentation, or the omission of clusters corresponding to focal CNAs in the case of global segmentation. Importantly, inaccurate segmentation will lead to inaccurate identification of important CNAs. Results: We introduce CNAViz, a web-based tool that enables the user to simultaneously perform local and global segmentation, thus overcoming the limitations of each approach. Using simulated data, we demonstrate that by several metrics, CNAViz yields more accurate segmentations relative to existing local and global segmentation methods. Moreover, we analyze six bulk DNA sequencing samples from three breast cancer patients. By validating with parallel single-cell DNA sequencing data from the same samples, we show that with CNAViz we produce more accurate segmentation which improves accuracy in downstream copy-number calling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476457" rel="alternate" title="User-guided local and global copy-number segmentation for tumor sequencing data (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476061</id><title>A survey on antimicrobial resistance genes of frequently used bacteria in kefir and yoghurt (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.369088+00:00</updated><author><name>Maura Fiona Judge</name></author><author><name>Adrienn Gréta Tóth</name></author><author><name>Sára Ágnes Nagy</name></author><author><name>Márton Papp</name></author><author><name>Norbert Solymosi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antimicrobial resistance (AMR) is one of the foremost threats facing the treatment of infectious diseases worldwide. Recent studies have highlighted the potential for antimicrobial resistance genes (ARGs) in fermented foods to contribute to AMR via horizontal gene transfer (HGT). The focus of our study was investigating the ARG content (resistome) and mobility potential of the ARGs (mobilome) of bacterial strains commonly used in probiotic products, namely yoghurt and kefir. We performed metagenomic analyses on freely available data sets (n=584) originating from various kefir and yoghurt strains using next generation sequencing (NGS) in order to gain an insight into the ARG diversity, frequency and mobility. Our study shows that kefir and yoghurt products carry diverse and significant amounts of ARGs and that these genes may often be associated with iMGEs or plasmids, conferring mobility. Certain bacteria species such as &lt;italic&gt;Bifidobacterium animalis&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Streptococcus thermophilus&lt;/italic&gt; were found to have higher ARG content. Overall, our results support the hypothesis that ARGs are present in fermented foods, namely yoghurt and kefir, and have the potential to contribute to AMR.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476061" rel="alternate" title="A survey on antimicrobial resistance genes of frequently used bacteria in kefir and yoghurt (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>