<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.009063+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.05.463267</id><title>Intercellular transport of RNA can limit heritable epigenetic changes (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.009434+00:00</updated><author><name>Nathan Shugarts</name></author><author><name>Andrew L. Yi</name></author><author><name>Winnie M. Chan</name></author><author><name>Julia A. Marré</name></author><author><name>Aishwarya Sathya</name></author><author><name>Antony M. Jose</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;RNAs in circulation carry sequence-specific regulatory information between cells in animal, plant, and host-pathogen systems. Double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) delivered into the extracellular space of the nematode &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; accumulates within the germline and reaches progeny. Here we provide evidence for spatial, temporal, and substrate specificity in the transport of dsRNA from parental circulation to progeny. Temporary loss of dsRNA transport resulted in the persistent accumulation of mRNA from a germline gene. The expression of this gene varied among siblings and even between gonad arms within one animal. Perturbing RNA regulation of the gene created new epigenetic states that lasted for many generations. Thus, one role for the transport of dsRNA into the germline in every generation is to limit heritable changes in gene expression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;RNA from parental circulation reduces heritable changes in gene expression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.05.463267" rel="alternate" title="Intercellular transport of RNA can limit heritable epigenetic changes (26 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>