<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-13T12:54:26.681177+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.02.454472</id><title>Microbial community of recently discovered Auka vent field sheds light on vent biogeography and evolutionary history of thermophily (57 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-13T12:54:26.681644+00:00</updated><author><name>Daan R Speth</name></author><author><name>Feiqiao B Yu</name></author><author><name>Stephanie A Connon</name></author><author><name>Sujung Lim</name></author><author><name>John S Magyar</name></author><author><name>Manet E Peña</name></author><author><name>Stephen R Quake</name></author><author><name>Victoria J Orphan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hydrothermal vents have been key to our understanding of the limits of life, and the metabolic and phylogenetic diversity of thermophilic organisms. Here we used environmental metagenomics combined with analysis of physico-chemical data and 16S rRNA amplicons to characterize the diversity, temperature optima, and biogeographic distribution of sediment-hosted microorganisms at the recently discovered Auka vents in the Gulf of California, the deepest known hydrothermal vent field in the Pacific Ocean. We recovered 325 metagenome assembled genomes (MAGs) representing 54 phyla, over 1/3 of the currently known phylum diversity, showing the microbial community in Auka hydrothermal sediments is highly diverse. Large scale 16S rRNA amplicon screening of 227 sediment samples across the vent field indicates that the MAGs are largely representative of the microbial community. Metabolic reconstruction of a vent-specific, deeply branching clade within the Desulfobacterota (Tharpobacteria) suggests these organisms metabolize sulfur using novel octaheme cytochrome-c proteins related to hydroxylamine oxidoreductase. Community-wide comparison of the average nucleotide identity of the Auka MAGs with MAGs from the Guaymas Basin vent field, found 400 km to the Northwest, revealed a remarkable 20% species-level overlap between vent sites, suggestive of long-distance species transfer and sediment colonization. An adapted version of a recently developed model for predicting optimal growth temperature to the Auka and Guaymas MAGs indicates several of these uncultured microorganisms could grow at temperatures exceeding the currently known upper limit of life. Extending this analysis to reference data shows that thermophily is a trait that has evolved frequently among Bacteria and Archaea. Combined, our results show that Auka vent field offers new perspectives on our understanding of hydrothermal vent microbiology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.02.454472" rel="alternate" title="Microbial community of recently discovered Auka vent field sheds light on vent biogeography and evolutionary history of thermophily (57 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.04.455085</id><title>GEPSi: A Python Library to Simulate GWAS Phenotype Data (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-13T12:54:26.682147+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel A Reidenbach</name></author><author><name>Avantika Lal</name></author><author><name>Lotfi Slim</name></author><author><name>Ohad Mosafi</name></author><author><name>Johnny Israeli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many computational methods aim to identify genetic variants associated with diseases and complex traits. Due to the absence of ground truth data, simulated genotype and phenotype data is needed to benchmark these methods. However, phenotypes are frequently simulated as an additive function of randomly selected variants, neglecting biological complexity such as non-random occurrence of causal SNPs, epistatic effects, heritability and dominance. Including such features would improve benchmarking studies and accelerate the development of methods for genetic analysis. Here, we describe GEPSi (GWAS Epistatic Phenotype Simulator), a user-friendly python package to simulate phenotype data based on user-supplied genotype data for a population. GEPSi incorporates diverse biological parameters such as heritability, dominance, population stratification and epistatic interactions between SNPs. We demonstrate the use of this package to compare machine learning methods for GWAS analysis.
GEPSi is freely available under an Apache 2.0 license, and can be downloaded from https://github.com/clara-parabricks/GEPSi.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.04.455085" rel="alternate" title="GEPSi: A Python Library to Simulate GWAS Phenotype Data (11 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>