<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.762830+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450637</id><title>daf-16/FOXO blocks adult cell fate in Caenorhabditis elegans dauer larvae via lin-41/TRIM71 (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.763307+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew J. Wirick</name></author><author><name>Allison R. Cale</name></author><author><name>Isaac T. Smith</name></author><author><name>Amelia F. Alessi</name></author><author><name>Margaret R. Starostik</name></author><author><name>Liberta Cuko</name></author><author><name>Kyal Lalk</name></author><author><name>Mikayla N. Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Benjamin S. Olson</name></author><author><name>Payton M. Salomon</name></author><author><name>Alexis Santos</name></author><author><name>Axel Schmitter-Sánchez</name></author><author><name>Himani Galagali</name></author><author><name>Kevin J. Ranke</name></author><author><name>Payton A. Wolbert</name></author><author><name>Macy L. Knoblock</name></author><author><name>John K. Kim</name></author><author><name>Xantha Karp</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many tissue-specific stem cells maintain the ability to produce multiple cell types during long periods of non-division, or quiescence. FOXO transcription factors promote quiescence and stem cell maintenance, but the mechanisms by which FOXO proteins promote multipotency during quiescence are still emerging. The single FOXO ortholog in &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans, daf-16&lt;/italic&gt;, promotes entry into a quiescent and stress-resistant larval stage called dauer in response to adverse environmental cues. During dauer, stem and progenitor cells maintain or re-establish multipotency to allow normal development to resume after dauer. We find that during dauer, &lt;italic&gt;daf-16&lt;/italic&gt;/FOXO prevents epidermal stem cells (seam cells) from prematurely adopting differentiated, adult characteristics. In particular, dauer larvae that lack &lt;italic&gt;daf-16&lt;/italic&gt; misexpress collagens that are normally adult-enriched. Using &lt;italic&gt;col-19p::gfp&lt;/italic&gt; as an adult cell fate marker, we find that all major &lt;italic&gt;daf-16&lt;/italic&gt; isoforms contribute to opposing &lt;italic&gt;col-19p::gfp&lt;/italic&gt; expression during dauer. By contrast, &lt;italic&gt;daf-16(0)&lt;/italic&gt; larvae that undergo non-dauer development do not misexpress &lt;italic&gt;col-19p::gfp&lt;/italic&gt;. Adult cell fate and the timing of &lt;italic&gt;col-19p::gfp&lt;/italic&gt; expression are regulated by the heterochronic gene network, including &lt;italic&gt;lin-41&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;lin-29. lin-41&lt;/italic&gt; encodes an RNA-binding protein orthologous to LIN41/TRIM71 in mammals, and &lt;italic&gt;lin-29&lt;/italic&gt; encodes a conserved zinc finger transcription factor. In non-dauer development &lt;italic&gt;lin-41&lt;/italic&gt; opposes adult cell fate by inhibiting the translation of &lt;italic&gt;lin-29&lt;/italic&gt;, which directly activates &lt;italic&gt;col-19&lt;/italic&gt; transcription and promotes adult cell fate. We find that during dauer, &lt;italic&gt;lin-41&lt;/italic&gt; blocks &lt;italic&gt;col-19p::gfp&lt;/italic&gt; expression, but surprisingly, &lt;italic&gt;lin-29&lt;/italic&gt; is not required in this context. Additionally, &lt;italic&gt;daf-16&lt;/italic&gt; promotes the expression of &lt;italic&gt;lin-41&lt;/italic&gt; in dauer larvae. The &lt;italic&gt;col-19p::gfp&lt;/italic&gt; misexpression phenotype observed in dauer larvae with reduced &lt;italic&gt;daf-16&lt;/italic&gt; requires the downregulation of &lt;italic&gt;lin-41&lt;/italic&gt;, but does not require &lt;italic&gt;lin-29&lt;/italic&gt;. Taken together, this work demonstrates a novel role for &lt;italic&gt;daf-16&lt;/italic&gt;/FOXO as a heterochronic gene that promotes expression of &lt;italic&gt;lin-41/&lt;/italic&gt;TRIM71 to contribute to multipotent cell fate in a quiescent stem cell model.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450637" rel="alternate" title="daf-16/FOXO blocks adult cell fate in Caenorhabditis elegans dauer larvae via lin-41/TRIM71 (13 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450337</id><title>A quantitative trait variant in Gabra2 underlies increased methamphetamine stimulant sensitivity (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.763694+00:00</updated><author><name>Lisa R. Goldberg</name></author><author><name>Emily J. Yao</name></author><author><name>Julia C. Kelliher</name></author><author><name>Eric R. Reed</name></author><author><name>Jiayi Wu Cox</name></author><author><name>Cory Parks</name></author><author><name>Stacey L. Kirkpatrick</name></author><author><name>Jacob A. Beierle</name></author><author><name>Melanie M. Chen</name></author><author><name>William E. Johnson</name></author><author><name>Gregg E. Homanics</name></author><author><name>Robert W. Williams</name></author><author><name>Camron D. Bryant</name></author><author><name>Megan K. Mulligan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Psychostimulant (methamphetamine, cocaine) use disorders have a genetic component that remains mostly unknown. Here, we conducted genome-wide quantitative trait locus (QTL) analysis of methamphetamine stimulant sensitivity. To facilitate gene identification, we employed a Reduced Complexity Cross between closely related C57BL/6 mouse substrains and examined maximum speed and distance traveled over 30 min following methamphetamine (2 mg/kg, i.p.). For maximum methamphetamine-induced speed following the second and third administration, we identified a single genome-wide significant QTL on chromosome 11 that peaked near the &lt;italic&gt;Cyfip2&lt;/italic&gt; locus [LOD = 3.5, 4.2; peak = 21 cM (36 Mb)]. For methamphetamine-induced distance traveled, we identified a single genome-wide significant QTL on chromosome 5 that peaked near a functional intronic indel in &lt;italic&gt;Gabra2&lt;/italic&gt; that codes for the alpha-2 subunit of the GABA-A receptor [LOD = 5.2; peak = 35 cM (67 Mb)]. Striatal &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-expression QTL mapping corroborated &lt;italic&gt;Gabra2&lt;/italic&gt; as a functional candidate gene underlying methamphetamine-induced distance traveled. CRISPR/Cas9-mediated correction of the mutant intronic deletion on the C57BL/6J background to the wild-type C57BL/6NJ allele was sufficient to reduce methamphetamine-induced locomotor activity toward the wild-type C57BL/6NJ-like level, thus validating the quantitative trait variant (QTV). These studies demonstrate the power and efficiency of Reduced Complexity Crosses in identifying causal genes and variants underlying complex traits. Functionally restoring &lt;italic&gt;Gabra2&lt;/italic&gt; expression decreased methamphetamine stimulant sensitivity and supports preclinical and human genetic studies implicating the GABA-A receptor in psychostimulant addiction-relevant traits. Importantly, our findings have major implications for investigators studying psychostimulants in the C57BL/6J strain - the gold standard strain in biomedical research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450337" rel="alternate" title="A quantitative trait variant in Gabra2 underlies increased methamphetamine stimulant sensitivity (9 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.03.451005</id><title>Gene drive that results in addiction to a temperature sensitive version of an essential gene triggers population collapse in Drosophila (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.764266+00:00</updated><author><name>Georg Oberhofer</name></author><author><name>Bruce Hay</name></author><author><name>Tobin Ivy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;One strategy for population suppression seeks to use gene drive to spread genes that confer conditional lethality or sterility, providing a way of combining population modification with suppression. Stimuli of potential interest could be introduced by humans, such as an otherwise benign virus or chemical, or occur naturally on a seasonal basis, such as a change in temperature. Cleave and Rescue (&lt;italic&gt;ClvR&lt;/italic&gt;) selfish genetic elements use Cas9 and gRNAs to disrupt endogenous versions of an essential gene, while also including a Rescue version of the essential gene resistant to disruption. &lt;italic&gt;ClvR&lt;/italic&gt; spreads by creating loss-of-function alleles of the essential gene that select against those lacking it, resulting in populations in which the Rescue provides the only source of essential gene function. In consequence, if function of the Rescue, a kind of Trojan horse now omnipresent in a population, is condition-dependent, so too will be the survival of that population. To test this idea we created a &lt;italic&gt;ClvR&lt;/italic&gt; in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; in which Rescue activity of an essential gene, &lt;italic&gt;dribble&lt;/italic&gt;, requires splicing of a temperature-sensitive intein (TS-&lt;italic&gt;ClvR&lt;sup&gt;dbe&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt;). This element spreads to transgene fixation at 23° C, but when populations now dependent on TS-&lt;italic&gt;ClvR&lt;sup&gt;dbe&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; are shifted to 29° C death and sterility result in a rapid population crash. These results show that conditional population elimination can be achieved. A similar logic, in which Rescue activity is conditional, could also be used in HEG-based drive, and to bring about suppression and/or killing of specific individuals in response to other stimuli.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.03.451005" rel="alternate" title="Gene drive that results in addiction to a temperature sensitive version of an essential gene triggers population collapse in Drosophila (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-07-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>