<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.653103+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.19.452969</id><title>A Bayesian model selection approach to mediation analysis (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.654185+00:00</updated><author><name>Wesley L Crouse</name></author><author><name>Gregory R Keele</name></author><author><name>Madeleine S Gastonguay</name></author><author><name>Gary A Churchill</name></author><author><name>William Valdar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mediation analysis is a powerful tool for discovery of causal relationships. We describe a Bayesian model selection approach to mediation analysis that is implemented in our bmediatR software. Using simulations, we show that bmediatR performs as well or better than established methods including the Sobel test, while allowing greater flexibility in both model specification and in the types of inference that are possible. We applied bmediatR to genetic data from mice and human cell lines to demonstrate its ability to derive biologically meaningful findings. The Bayesian model selection framework is extensible to support a wide variety of mediation models.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.19.452969" rel="alternate" title="A Bayesian model selection approach to mediation analysis (20 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-07-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453515</id><title>Low dose/dose rate γ irradiation protects Drosophila melanogaster chromosomes from double strand breaks and telomere fusions by modulating the expression of Loquacious. (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.654864+00:00</updated><author><name>Antonella Porrazzo</name></author><author><name>Francesca Cipressa</name></author><author><name>Alex De Gregorio</name></author><author><name>Cristiano De Pitta</name></author><author><name>Gabriele Sales</name></author><author><name>Patrizia Morciano</name></author><author><name>Giuseppe Esposito</name></author><author><name>Antonella Tabocchini</name></author><author><name>Giovanni Cenci</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It is still continuously debated whether the low-dose/dose-rate (LDDR) of ionizing radiation represents a hazard for humans. Model organisms, such as fruit flies, are considered valuable systems to reveal insights into this issue. We found that, in wild-type Drosophila melanogaster larval neuroblasts, the frequency of Chromosome Breaks (CBs), induced by acute γ-radiation, is significantly reduced when flies are previously exposed to a protracted dose of 0.4 Gy delivered at a dose rate of 2.5 mGy/h. This indicates that this exposure, which is associated with an increased expression of DNA damage response proteins, induces a radioadaptive response (RAR) that protects Drosophila from extensive DNA damage. Interestingly, the same exposure reduces the frequency of telomere fusions (TFs) from Drosophila telomere capping mutants suggesting that the LDDR can generally promote a protective response on chromatin sites that are recognized as DNA breaks. Deep RNA sequencing revealed that RAR is associated with a modulation of genes involved in RNA processing and the reduction of expression of Loquacious D (Loqs-RD) gene that encodes a well-conserved dsRNA binding protein required for esiRNAs biogenesis. Remarkably, loss of Loqs mimics the LDDR-mediated chromosome protection as it decreases the IR-induced CBs and TF frequency. Thus, our work identifies Loqs as a key factor in mediating the cellular response to LDDR and reveals that the study of the molecular bases underlying RAR is instrumental for unraveling novel and conserved epigenetic routes that have evolved to preserve genome integrity following robust insults to DNA.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453515" rel="alternate" title="Low dose/dose rate γ irradiation protects Drosophila melanogaster chromosomes from double strand breaks and telomere fusions by modulating the expression of Loquacious. (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>