<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.146034+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459279</id><title>eQTLs are key players in the integration of genomic and transcriptomic data for phenotype prediction (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.146583+00:00</updated><author><name>Abdou Rahmane Wade</name></author><author><name>Harold Duruflé</name></author><author><name>Leopoldo Sanchez</name></author><author><name>Vincent Segura</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Multi-omics represent a promising link between phenotypes and genome variation. Few studies yet address their integration to understand genetic architecture and improve predictability. Our study used 241 poplar genotypes, phenotyped in two common gardens, with their xylem and cambium RNA sequenced at one site, yielding large phenotypic, genomic and transcriptomic datasets. For each trait, prediction models were built with genotypic or transcriptomic data and compared to concatenation integrating both omics. The advantage of integration varied across traits and, to understand such differences, we made an eQTL analysis to characterize the interplay between the genome and the transcriptome and classify the predicting features into CIS or TRANS relationships. A strong and significant negative correlation was found between the change in predictability and the change in predictor importance for eQTLs (both TRANS and CIS effects) and CIS regulated transcripts, and mostly for traits showing beneficial integration and evaluated in the site of transcriptomic sampling. Consequently, beneficial integration happens when redundancy of predictors is decreased, leaving the stage to other less prominent but complementary predictors. An additional GO enrichment analysis appeared to corroborate such statistical output. To our knowledge, this is a novel finding delineating a promising way to explore data integration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Successful multi-omics integration when predicting phenotypes makes redundant the predictors that are linked to ubiquitous connections between the omics, according to biological and statistical approaches&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459279" rel="alternate" title="eQTLs are key players in the integration of genomic and transcriptomic data for phenotype prediction (19 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459322</id><title>Illuminating links between cis-regulators and trans-acting variants in the human prefrontal cortex (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.146979+00:00</updated><author><name>Shuang Liu</name></author><author><name>Hyejung Won</name></author><author><name>Declan Clarke</name></author><author><name>Nana Matoba</name></author><author><name>Saniya Khullar</name></author><author><name>Yudi Mu</name></author><author><name>Daifeng Wang</name></author><author><name>Mark Gerstein</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Psychiatric disorders exact immense human and economic tolls in societies globally. Underlying many of these disorders is a complex repertoire of genomic variants that influence the expression of genes involved in pathways and processes in the brain. Identifying such variants and their associated brain functions is thus essential for understanding the molecular underpinnings of psychiatric disorders. Genome-wide association studies (GWASes) have provided many variants associated with these disorders; however, our knowledge of the precise biological mechanisms by which these contribute to disease remains limited. In connection with this, expression quantitative trait loci (eQTLs) have provided useful information linking variants to genes and functions. However, most eQTL studies on human brain have focused exclusively on cis-eQTLs. A complete understanding of disease etiology should also include trans-regulatory mechanisms. Thus, we conduct one of the first genome-wide surveys of trans-eQTLs in the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC) by leveraging the large datasets from the PsychENCODE consortium. We identified ∼80,000 trans-eQTLs. We found that a significant number of these overlap with cis-eQTLs, thereby implicating cis-mediators as key players in trans-acting regulation. We show, furthermore, that trans-regulatory mechanisms provide novel insights into psychiatric disease. Particularly, colocalization analysis between trans-eQTLs and schizophrenia (SCZ) GWAS loci identified 90 novel SCZ risk genes and 23 GWAS loci previously uncharacterized by cis-eQTLs. Moreover, these 90 genes tend to be more central in transcriptome-wide co-expression networks and more susceptible to rare variants than SCZ-risk genes associated by cis-variation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459322" rel="alternate" title="Illuminating links between cis-regulators and trans-acting variants in the human prefrontal cortex (11 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.459722</id><title>CAMOIP: A Web Server for Comprehensive Analysis on Multi-Omics of Immunotherapy in Pan-cancer (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.147298+00:00</updated><author><name>Anqi LIN</name></author><author><name>Ting WEI</name></author><author><name>Junyi LIANG</name></author><author><name>Chang QI</name></author><author><name>Mengyao LI</name></author><author><name>Peng LUO</name></author><author><name>Jian Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Immune checkpoint inhibitors (ICIs) have completely changed the therapeutic approach for tumor patients. Immunotherapy has also produced much needed data about mutation, expression, and prognosis, providing an unprecedented opportunity for discovering candidate drug targets and screening for immunotherapy-relevant biomarkers. Although existing web tools enable biologists to analyze the expression, mutation, and prognosis data on tumors, they are currently not able to carry out data mining and mechanism analyses related to immune checkpoint therapy. Thus, we developed our own web-based tool called Comprehensive Analysis on Multi-Omics of Immunotherapy in Pan-cancer(CAMOIP), in which we can screen prognostic markers and analyze the mechanisms involved with markers and immunotherapy (more than 4000 patients). The analyses include survival analysis, expression analysis, drug sensitivity analysis, mutational landscape, immune checkpoint analysis, immune related signature analysis, immune cell analysis, immune gene analysis, immunogenicity analysis and gene sets enrichment analysis(GSEA). This comprehensive analysis of biomarkers for immunotherapy can be carried out by a click of CAMOIP, and the software should greatly encourage the further development of immunotherapy. CAMOIP fills the gap between the big data of cancer genomics based on immunotherapy and providing comprehensive information to users, helping to release the value of current ICI-treated data resources. CAMOIP can be found in https://www.camoip.net.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.459722" rel="alternate" title="CAMOIP: A Web Server for Comprehensive Analysis on Multi-Omics of Immunotherapy in Pan-cancer (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>