<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv preprints in genetics posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.646643+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443595</id><title>Epigenetic Inheritance is Gated by Naïve Pluripotency and Dppa2 (80 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.667647+00:00</updated><author><name>Valentina Carlini</name></author><author><name>Cristina Policarpi</name></author><author><name>Jamie A. Hackett</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Environmental factors can trigger cellular responses that propagate across mitosis or even generations. Perturbations to the epigenome could underpin such acquired changes, however, the extent and contexts in which modified chromatin states confer heritable memory in mammals is unclear. Here we exploit a modular epigenetic editing strategy to establish &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; heterochromatin domains (epialleles) at endogenous loci and track their inheritance in a developmental model. We find that naïve pluripotent phases systematically erase ectopic domains of heterochromatin via active mechanisms, which acts as an intergenerational safeguard against transmission of epialleles. Upon lineage specification however, acquired chromatin states can be probabilistically inherited under selectively favourable conditions, including propagation of &lt;italic&gt;p53&lt;/italic&gt; silencing through &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; development. Using genome-wide CRISPR screening, we identify the mechanisms that block heritable silencing memory in pluripotent cells, and demonstrate removal of &lt;italic&gt;Dppa2&lt;/italic&gt; unlocks the potential for epigenetic inheritance uncoupled from DNA sequence. Our study outlines a mechanistic basis for how epigenetic inheritance is restricted in mammals, and reveals genomic- and developmental-contexts in which heritable memory is feasible.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443220</id><title>SCON - A Short Conditional intrON for conditional knockout with one-step zygote injection (50 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.668475+00:00</updated><author><name>Szu-Hsien Sam Wu</name></author><author><name>Réka Szép-Bakonyi</name></author><author><name>Heetak Lee</name></author><author><name>Gabriele Colozza</name></author><author><name>Ayse Boese</name></author><author><name>Krista Rene Gert</name></author><author><name>Natalia Hallay</name></author><author><name>Jihoon Kim</name></author><author><name>Yi Zhu</name></author><author><name>Sandra Pilat-Carotta</name></author><author><name>Hans-Christian Theussl</name></author><author><name>Andrea Pauli</name></author><author><name>Bon-Kyoung Koo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The generation of conditional alleles using CRISPR technology is still challenging. Here, we introduce a Short Conditional intrON (SCON, 189 bp) that enables rapid generation of conditional alleles via one-step zygote injection. SCON has conditional intronic function in various vertebrate species and its target insertion is as simple as CRISPR/Cas9-mediated gene tagging.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443466</id><title>Genetic determinants of chromatin reveal prostate cancer risk mediated by context-dependent gene regulation (32 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.673723+00:00</updated><author><name>Sylvan C. Baca</name></author><author><name>Cassandra Singler</name></author><author><name>Soumya Zacharia</name></author><author><name>Ji-Heui Seo</name></author><author><name>Tunc Morova</name></author><author><name>Faraz Hach</name></author><author><name>Yi Ding</name></author><author><name>Tommer Schwarz</name></author><author><name>Chia-Chi Flora Huang</name></author><author><name>Cynthia Kalita</name></author><author><name>Stefan Groha</name></author><author><name>Mark M. Pomerantz</name></author><author><name>Victoria Wang</name></author><author><name>Simon Linder</name></author><author><name>Christopher J. Sweeney</name></author><author><name>Wilbert Zwart</name></author><author><name>Nathan A. Lack</name></author><author><name>Bogdan Pasaniuc</name></author><author><name>David Y. Takeda</name></author><author><name>Alexander Gusev</name></author><author><name>Matthew L. Freedman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Methods that link genetic variation to steady-state gene expression levels, such as expression quantitative trait loci (eQTLs), are widely used to functionally annotate trait-associated variants, but they are limited in identifying context-dependent effects on transcription. To address this challenge, we developed the cistrome-wide association study (CWAS), a framework for nominating variants that impact traits through their effects on chromatin state. CWAS associates the genetic determinants of cistromes (&lt;italic&gt;e.g.&lt;/italic&gt;, the genome-wide profiles of transcription factor binding sites or histone modifications) with traits using summary statistics from genome-wide association studies (GWAS). We performed CWASs of prostate cancer and androgen-related traits, using a reference panel of 307 prostate cistromes from 165 individuals. CWAS nominated susceptibility regulatory elements or androgen receptor (AR) binding sites at 52 out of 98 known prostate cancer GWAS loci and implicated an additional 17 novel loci. We functionally validated a subset of our results using CRISPRi and &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; reporter assays. At 28 of the 52 risk loci, CWAS identified regulatory mechanisms that are not observable via eQTLs, implicating genes with complex or context-specific regulation that are overlooked by current approaches that relying on steady-state transcript measurements. CWAS genes include transcription factors that govern prostate development such as &lt;italic&gt;NKX3-1&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;HOXB13&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;GATA2&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;KLF5&lt;/italic&gt;. Moreover, CWAS boosts discovery power in modestly sized GWAS, identifying novel genetic associations mediated through AR binding for androgen-related phenotypes, including resistance to prostate cancer therapy. CWAS is a powerful and biologically interpretable paradigm for studying variants that influence traits by affecting context-dependent transcriptional regulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443352</id><title>The genetic architecture of phenotypic diversity in the betta fish (Betta splendens) (25 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.674186+00:00</updated><author><name>Wanchang Zhang</name></author><author><name>Hongru Wang</name></author><author><name>Débora Y. C. Brandt</name></author><author><name>Beijuan Hu</name></author><author><name>Junqing Sheng</name></author><author><name>Mengnan Wang</name></author><author><name>Haijiang Luo</name></author><author><name>Shujie Guo</name></author><author><name>Bin Sheng</name></author><author><name>Qi Zeng</name></author><author><name>Kou Peng</name></author><author><name>Daxian Zhao</name></author><author><name>Shaoqing Jian</name></author><author><name>Di Wu</name></author><author><name>Junhua Wang</name></author><author><name>Joep H. M. van Esch</name></author><author><name>Wentian Shi</name></author><author><name>Jun Ren</name></author><author><name>Rasmus Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Yijiang Hong</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Betta fish displays a remarkable variety of phenotypes selected during domestication. However, the genetic basis underlying these traits remain largely unexplored. Here, we report a high-quality genome assembly and re-sequencing of 727 individuals representing diverse morphologies of the betta fish. We show that current breeds have a complex domestication history with extensive introgression with wild species. Using GWAS, we identify the genetic basis of multiple traits, including several coloration phenotypes, sex-determination which we map to &lt;italic&gt;DMRT1&lt;/italic&gt;, and the long-fin phenotype which maps to &lt;italic&gt;KCNJ15&lt;/italic&gt;. We identify a polygenic signal related to aggression with many similarities to human psychiatric traits, involving genes such as &lt;italic&gt;CACNB2&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;DISC1&lt;/italic&gt;. Our study provides a resource for developing the Betta fish as a genetic model for morphology and behavior in vertebrates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443797</id><title>Robust detection of natural selection using a probabilistic model of tree imbalance (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.674849+00:00</updated><author><name>Enes Dilber</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Terhorst</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neutrality tests such as Tajima’s &lt;italic&gt;D&lt;/italic&gt; (Tajima, 1989) and Fay and Wu’s &lt;italic&gt;H&lt;/italic&gt; (Fay and Wu, 2000) are standard implements in the population genetics toolbox. One of their most common uses is to scan the genome for signals of natural selection. However, it is well understood that deviance measures like &lt;italic&gt;D&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;H&lt;/italic&gt; are confounded by other evolutionary forces—in particular, population expansion—that may be unrelated to selection. Because they are not model-based, it is not clear how to deconfound these statistics in a principled way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this paper we derive new likelihood-based methods for detecting natural selection which are robust to confounding by fluctuations in effective population size. At the core of our method is a novel probabilistic model of tree imbalance, which generalizes Kingman’s coalescent to allow certain aberrant tree topologies to arise more frequently than is expected under neutrality. We derive a frequency spectrumbased estimator which can be used in place of &lt;italic&gt;D&lt;/italic&gt;, and also extend to the case where genealogies are first estimated. We benchmark our methods on real and simulated data, and provide an open source software implementation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443088</id><title>Natural Killer cells demonstrate distinct eQTL and transcriptome-wide disease associations, highlighting their role in autoimmunity (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.675224+00:00</updated><author><name>James J Gilchrist</name></author><author><name>Seiko Makino</name></author><author><name>Vivek Naranbhai</name></author><author><name>Evelyn Lau</name></author><author><name>Sara Danielli</name></author><author><name>Dan Hameiri-Bowen</name></author><author><name>Wanseon Lee</name></author><author><name>Esther Ng</name></author><author><name>Justin Whalley</name></author><author><name>Julian C Knight</name></author><author><name>Benjamin P Fairfax</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Natural Killer (NK) cells are innate lymphocytes with central roles in immunosurveillance and are implicated in autoimmune pathogenesis. The degree to which regulatory variants affect NK gene expression is poorly understood. We performed expression quantitative trait locus (eQTL) mapping of negatively selected NK cells from a population of healthy Europeans (n=245). We find a significant subset of genes demonstrate eQTL specific to NK cells and these are highly informative of human disease, in particular autoimmunity. An NK cell transcriptome-wide association study (TWAS) across five common autoimmune diseases identified further novel associations at 27 genes. In addition to these &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt; observations, we find novel master-regulatory regions impacting expression of &lt;italic&gt;trans&lt;/italic&gt; gene networks at regions including 19q13.4, the Killer cell Immunoglobulin-like Receptor (KIR) Region, &lt;italic&gt;GNLY&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;MC1R&lt;/italic&gt;. Our findings provide new insights into the unique biology of NK cells, demonstrating markedly different eQTL from other immune cells, with implications for disease mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.444000</id><title>Transcriptional landscape of human microglia reveals robust gene expression signatures that implicates age, sex and APOE-related immunometabolic pathway perturbations (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.684308+00:00</updated><author><name>Tulsi Patel</name></author><author><name>Troy P Carnwath</name></author><author><name>Xue Wang</name></author><author><name>Mariet Allen</name></author><author><name>Sarah J Lincoln</name></author><author><name>Laura J Lewis-Tuffin</name></author><author><name>Zachary S Quicksall</name></author><author><name>Shu Lin</name></author><author><name>Frederick Q Tutor-New</name></author><author><name>Charlotte CG Ho</name></author><author><name>Yuhao Min</name></author><author><name>Kimberly G Malphrus</name></author><author><name>Thuy T Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Martin</name></author><author><name>Cesar A Garcia</name></author><author><name>Rawan M Alkharboosh</name></author><author><name>Sanjeet Grewal</name></author><author><name>Kaisorn Chaichana</name></author><author><name>Robert Wharen</name></author><author><name>Hugo Guerrero-Cazares</name></author><author><name>Alfredo Quinones-Hinojosa</name></author><author><name>Nilufer Ertekin-Taner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microglia have fundamental roles in health and disease, however effects of age, sex and genetic factors on human microglia have not been fully explored. We applied bulk and single cell approaches to comprehensively characterize human microglia transcriptomes and their associations with age, sex and APOE. We identified a novel microglial signature, characterized its expression in bulk data from 1,306 brain samples across 6 regions and in single cell microglia transcriptome. We discovered microglial co-expression network modules associated with age, sex and APOE-ε4 that are enriched for lipid and carbohydrate metabolism genes. Integrated analyses of modules with single cell transcriptomes revealed significant overlap between age-associated module genes and both pro-inflammatory and disease-associated microglial clusters. These modules and clusters harbor known neurodegenerative disease genes including APOE, PLCG2 and BIN1. These data represent a well-characterized human microglial transcriptome resource; and highlight age, sex and APOE-related microglial immunometabolism perturbations with potential relevance in neurodegeneration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443361</id><title>Comprehensive analysis of meiosis-derived cDNA libraries reveals gene isoforms and mitochondrial proteins important for competitive fitness (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.685036+00:00</updated><author><name>Tina L. Sing</name></author><author><name>Katie Conlon</name></author><author><name>Stephanie H. Lu</name></author><author><name>Nicole Madrazo</name></author><author><name>Juliet C. Barker</name></author><author><name>Ina Hollerer</name></author><author><name>Gloria A. Brar</name></author><author><name>Peter H. Sudmant</name></author><author><name>Elçin Ünal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gametogenesis is a highly regulated and dynamic developmental program where a diploid progenitor cell differentiates into haploid gametes, the precursors for sexual reproduction. During meiosis, several pathways converge to initiate ploidy reduction and organelle remodelling to render gametes competent for zygote formation and subsequent organismal development. Additionally, meiosis inherently rejuvenates the newly formed gametes resulting in lifespan resetting. Here, we construct five stage-specific, inducible meiotic cDNA libraries that represent over 84% of the yeast genome. We employ computational strategies to detect stage-specific meiotic transcript isoforms in each library and develop a robust screening pipeline to test the effect of each cDNA on competitive fitness. Our multi-day proof-of-principle time course reveals gene isoforms that are important for competitive fitness as well as mitochondrial proteins that cause dose-dependent disruption of respiration. Together, these novel meiotic cDNA libraries provide an important resource for systematically studying meiotic genes and gene isoforms in future studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;HIGHLIGHTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Construction of five stage-specific, inducible meiotic cDNA libraries in budding yeast that collectively represent 5563 genes, which is over 84% of the genome&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Analysis of the cDNA libraries reveal the presence of meiosis-specific transcript isoforms that are largely uncharacterized&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Development of a robust gain-of-function screening pipeline identifies previously characterized genes and novel gene isoforms important for competitive fitness&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Multi-day proof-of-principle screen reveals mitochondrial proteins that cause dosage-specific respiration defects&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443284</id><title>Population Structure of Nation-wide Rice in Thailand (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.688073+00:00</updated><author><name>Phanchita Vejchasarn</name></author><author><name>Jeremy R. Shearman</name></author><author><name>Usawadee Chaiprom</name></author><author><name>Yotwarit Phansenee</name></author><author><name>Tatpong Tulyananda</name></author><author><name>Jirapong Jairin</name></author><author><name>Chainarong Amornbunchornvej</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thailand is a country with large diversity in rice varieties due to its rich and diverse ecology. In this paper, 300 rice varieties from all across Thailand were sequenced to identify SNP variants allowing for the population-structure to be explored.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The result of inferred population structure from admixture and clustering analysis illustrated strong evidence of substructure in each geographical region. The results of phylogenetic tree, PCA analysis, and machine learning on SNPs selected by QTL analysis also supported the inferred population structure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The population structure, which was inferred in this study, contains five populations s.t. each population has a unique ecological system, genetic pattern, as well as agronomic traits. This study can serve as a reference point of the nation-wide population structure for supporting breeders and researchers who are interested in Thai rice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>