<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.829264+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467079</id><title>Parent-of-origin effects in the UK Biobank (53 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.830023+00:00</updated><author><name>Robin J Hofmeister</name></author><author><name>Simone Rubinacci</name></author><author><name>Diogo M Ribeiro</name></author><author><name>Zoltan Kutalik</name></author><author><name>Alfonso Buil</name></author><author><name>Olivier Delaneau</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Identical genetic variations can have different phenotypic effects depending on their parent of origin (PofO). Yet, studies focussing on PofO effects have been largely limited in terms of sample size due to the need of parental genomes or known genealogies. Here, we used a novel probabilistic approach to infer PofO of individual alleles in the UK Biobank that does not require parental genomes nor prior knowledge of genealogy. Our model uses Identity-By-Descent (IBD) sharing with second- and third-degree relatives to assign alleles to parental groups and leverages chromosome X data in males to distinguish maternal from paternal groups. When combined with robust haplotype inference and haploid imputation, this allowed us to infer the PofO at 5.4 million variants genome-wide for 26,393 UK Biobank individuals. We used this large dataset to systematically screen 59 biomarkers and 38 anthropomorphic phenotypes for PofO effects and discovered 101 significant associations, demonstrating that this type of effects contributes to the genetics of complex traits. Notably, we retrieved well known PofO effects, such as the MEG3/DLK1 locus on platelet count, and we discovered many new ones at loci often unsuspected of being imprinted and, in some cases, previously thought to harbour additive associations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467079" rel="alternate" title="Parent-of-origin effects in the UK Biobank (53 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467435</id><title>Ancient genomes from the last three millennia support multiple human dispersals into Wallacea (43 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.830394+00:00</updated><author><name>Sandra Oliveira</name></author><author><name>Kathrin Nägele</name></author><author><name>Selina Carlhoff</name></author><author><name>Irina Pugach</name></author><author><name>Toetik Koesbardiati</name></author><author><name>Alexander Hübner</name></author><author><name>Matthias Meyer</name></author><author><name>Adhi Agus Oktaviana</name></author><author><name>Masami Takenaka</name></author><author><name>Chiaki Katagiri</name></author><author><name>Delta Bayu Murti</name></author><author><name>Rizky Sugianto Putri</name></author><author><name> Mahirta</name></author><author><name>Thomas Higham</name></author><author><name>Charles F W Higham</name></author><author><name>Sue O'Connor</name></author><author><name>Stuart Hawkins</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Kinaston</name></author><author><name>Peter Bellwood</name></author><author><name>Rintaro Ono</name></author><author><name>Adam Powell</name></author><author><name>Johannes Krause</name></author><author><name>Cosimo Posth</name></author><author><name>Mark Stoneking</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Previous research indicates that the human genetic diversity found in Wallacea - islands in present-day Eastern Indonesia and Timor-Leste that were never part of the Sunda or Sahul continental shelves - has been shaped by complex interactions between migrating Austronesian farmers and indigenous hunter-gatherer communities. Here, we provide new insights into this region's demographic history based on genome-wide data from 16 ancient individuals (2600-250 yrs BP) from islands of the North Moluccas, Sulawesi, and East Nusa Tenggara. While the ancestry of individuals from the northern islands fit earlier views of contact between groups related to the Austronesian expansion and the first colonization of Sahul, the ancestry of individuals from the southern islands revealed additional contributions from Mainland Southeast Asia, which seems to predate the Austronesian admixture in the region. Admixture time estimates for the oldest individuals of Wallacea are closer to archaeological estimates for the Austronesian arrival into the region than are admixture time estimates for present-day groups. The decreasing trend in admixture times exhibited by younger individuals supports a scenario of multiple or continuous admixture involving Papuan- and Asian-related groups. Our results clarify previously debated times of admixture and suggest that the Neolithic dispersals into Island Southeast Asia are associated with the spread of multiple genetic ancestries.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467435" rel="alternate" title="Ancient genomes from the last three millennia support multiple human dispersals into Wallacea (43 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.466897</id><title>Genome-wide association analyses of individual differences in quantitatively assessed reading- and language-related skills in up to 34,000 people (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.830887+00:00</updated><author><name>Else Eising</name></author><author><name>Nazanin Mirza-Schreiber</name></author><author><name>Eveline L de Zeeuw</name></author><author><name>Carol A Wang</name></author><author><name>Dongnhu T Truong</name></author><author><name>Andrea G Allegrini</name></author><author><name>Chin Yang Shapland</name></author><author><name>Gu Zhu</name></author><author><name>Karen G Wigg</name></author><author><name>Margot Gerritse</name></author><author><name>Barbara Molz</name></author><author><name>Gokberk Alagoz</name></author><author><name>Alessandro Gialluisi</name></author><author><name>Filippo Abbondanza</name></author><author><name>Kaili Rimfeld</name></author><author><name>Marjolein MJ Van Donkelaar</name></author><author><name>Zhijie Liao</name></author><author><name>Philip R Jansen</name></author><author><name>Till F M Andlauer</name></author><author><name>Timothy C Bates</name></author><author><name>Manon Bernard</name></author><author><name>Kirsten Blokland</name></author><author><name>Anders D Borglum</name></author><author><name>Thomas Bourgeron</name></author><author><name>Daniel Brandeis</name></author><author><name>Fabiola Ceroni</name></author><author><name>Philip S Dale</name></author><author><name>Peter F. de Jong</name></author><author><name>John C DeFries</name></author><author><name>Ditte Demontis</name></author><author><name>Yu Feng</name></author><author><name>Scott D. Gordon</name></author><author><name>Sharon L Guger</name></author><author><name>Marianna E Hayiou-Thomas</name></author><author><name>Juan A. Hernandez-Cabrera</name></author><author><name>Jouke- Jan Hottenga</name></author><author><name>Charles Hulme</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth N Kerr</name></author><author><name>Tanner Koomar</name></author><author><name>Karin Landerl</name></author><author><name>Maureen W Lovett</name></author><author><name>Heikki Lyytinen</name></author><author><name>Nicholas G. Martin</name></author><author><name>Angela Martinelli</name></author><author><name>Urs Maurer</name></author><author><name>Jacob J Michaelson</name></author><author><name>Kristina Moll</name></author><author><name>Antony P. Monaco</name></author><author><name>Angela T. Morgan</name></author><author><name>Markus M. Noethen</name></author><author><name>Zdenka Pausova</name></author><author><name>Craig E Pennell</name></author><author><name>Bruce Pennington</name></author><author><name>Kaitlyn M Price</name></author><author><name>Veera M. Rajagopal</name></author><author><name>Franck Ramus</name></author><author><name>Louis Richer</name></author><author><name>Nuala H Simpson</name></author><author><name>Shelley Smith</name></author><author><name>Margaret J. Snowling</name></author><author><name>John Stein</name></author><author><name>Lisa J Strug</name></author><author><name>Joel B Talcott</name></author><author><name>Henning Tiemeier</name></author><author><name>Marc MP van der Schroeff</name></author><author><name>Ellen Verhoef</name></author><author><name>Kate E Watkins</name></author><author><name>Margaret Wilkinson</name></author><author><name>Margaret J. Wright</name></author><author><name>Cathy L Barr</name></author><author><name>Dorret I Boomsma</name></author><author><name>Manuel Carreiras</name></author><author><name>Marie-Christine J Franken</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey R Gruen</name></author><author><name>Michelle Luciano</name></author><author><name>Bertram Mueller-Myhsok</name></author><author><name>Dianne F Newbury</name></author><author><name>Richard K Olson</name></author><author><name>Silvia Paracchini</name></author><author><name>Tomas Paus</name></author><author><name>Robert Plomin</name></author><author><name>Sheena Reilly</name></author><author><name>Gerd Schulte-Koerne</name></author><author><name>James B Tomblin</name></author><author><name>Elsje van Bergen</name></author><author><name>Andrew JO Whitehouse</name></author><author><name>Erik G. Willcutt</name></author><author><name>Beate St Pourcain</name></author><author><name>Clyde Francks</name></author><author><name>Simon E. Fisher</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The use of spoken and written language is a capacity that is unique to humans. Individual differences in reading- and language-related skills are influenced by genetic variation, with twin-based heritability estimates of 30-80%, depending on the trait. The relevant genetic architecture is complex, heterogeneous, and multifactorial, and yet to be investigated with well-powered studies. Here, we present a multicohort genome-wide association study (GWAS) of five traits assessed individually using psychometric measures: word reading, nonword reading, spelling, phoneme awareness, and nonword repetition, with total sample sizes ranging from 13,633 to 33,959 participants aged 5-26 years (12,411 to 27,180 for those with European ancestry, defined by principal component analyses). We identified a genome-wide significant association with word reading (rs11208009, p=1.098 x 10-8) independent of known loci associated with intelligence or educational attainment. All five reading-/language-related traits had robust SNP-heritability estimates (0.13-0.26), and genetic correlations between them were modest to high. Using genomic structural equation modelling, we found evidence for a shared genetic factor explaining the majority of variation in word and nonword reading, spelling, and phoneme awareness, which only partially overlapped with genetic variation contributing to nonword repetition, intelligence and educational attainment. A multivariate GWAS was performed to jointly analyse word and nonword reading, spelling, and phoneme awareness, maximizing power for follow-up investigation. Genetic correlation analysis of multivariate GWAS results with neuroimaging traits identified association with cortical surface area of the banks of the left superior temporal sulcus, a brain region with known links to processing of spoken and written language. Analysis of evolutionary annotations on the lineage that led to modern humans showed enriched heritability in regions depleted of Neanderthal variants. Together, these results provide new avenues for deciphering the biological underpinnings of these uniquely human traits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.466897" rel="alternate" title="Genome-wide association analyses of individual differences in quantitatively assessed reading- and language-related skills in up to 34,000 people (30 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467534</id><title>Kaptive 2.0: updated capsule and LPS locus typing for the Klebsiella pneumoniae species complex (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.832181+00:00</updated><author><name>Margaret M.C. Lam</name></author><author><name>Ryan R. Wick</name></author><author><name>Kathryn E. Holt</name></author><author><name>Kelly L Wyres</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The outer polysaccharide capsule and lipopolysaccharide antigens are key targets for novel control strategies targeting Klebsiella pneumoniae and related taxa from the K. pneumoniae species complex (KpSC), including vaccines, phage and monoclonal antibody therapies. Given the importance and growing interest in these highly diverse surface antigens, we had previously developed Kaptive, a tool for rapidly identifying and typing capsule (K) and outer lipopolysaccharide (O) loci from whole genome sequence data. Here, we report two significant updates, now freely available in Kaptive 2.0 (github.com/katholt/kaptive); i) the addition of 16 novel K locus sequences to the K locus reference database following an extensive search of &amp;gt;17,000 KpSC genomes; and ii) enhanced O locus typing to enable prediction of the clinically relevant O2 antigen (sub)types, for which the genetic determinants have been recently described. We applied Kaptive 2.0 to a curated dataset of &amp;gt;12,000 public KpSC genomes to explore for the first time the distribution of predicted O (sub)types across species, sampling niches and clones, which highlighted key differences in the distributions that warrant further investigation. As the uptake of genomic surveillance approaches continues to expand globally, the application of Kaptive 2.0 will generate novel insights essential for the design of effective KpSC control strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467534" rel="alternate" title="Kaptive 2.0: updated capsule and LPS locus typing for the Klebsiella pneumoniae species complex (29 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467388</id><title>A temporally resolved, multiplex molecular recorder based on sequential genome editing (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.832667+00:00</updated><author><name>Junhong Choi</name></author><author><name>Wei Chen</name></author><author><name>Anna Minkina</name></author><author><name>Florence M Chardon</name></author><author><name>Chase C Suiter</name></author><author><name>Samuel G Regalado</name></author><author><name>Silvia Domcke</name></author><author><name>Nobuhiko Hamazaki</name></author><author><name>Choli Lee</name></author><author><name>Beth Martin</name></author><author><name>Riza M Daza</name></author><author><name>Jay Shendure</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;DNA is naturally well-suited to serve as a digital medium for in vivo molecular recording. However, DNA-based memory devices described to date are constrained in terms of the number of distinct signals that can be concurrently recorded and/or by a failure to capture the precise order of recorded events. Here we describe DNA Ticker Tape, a general system for in vivo molecular recording that largely overcomes these limitations. Blank DNA Ticker Tape consists of a tandem array of partial CRISPR-Cas9 target sites, with all but the first site truncated at their 5' ends, and therefore inactive. Signals of interest are coupled to the expression of specific prime editing guide RNAs. Editing events are insertional, and record the identity of the guide RNA mediating the insertion while also shifting the position of the "write head" by one unit along the tandem array, i.e. sequential genome editing. In this proof-of-concept of DNA Ticker Tape, we demonstrate the recording and decoding of complex event histories or short text messages; evaluate the performance of dozens of orthogonal tapes; and construct "long tape" potentially capable of recording the order of as many as 20 serial events. Finally, we demonstrate how DNA Ticker Tape simplifies the decoding of cell lineage histories.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467388" rel="alternate" title="A temporally resolved, multiplex molecular recorder based on sequential genome editing (27 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466790</id><title>Programmable large DNA deletion, replacement, integration, and inversion with twin prime editing and site-specific recombinases (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.833018+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew V. Anzalone</name></author><author><name>Xin D. Gao</name></author><author><name>Christopher J. Podracky</name></author><author><name>Andrew T. Nelson</name></author><author><name>Luke W. Koblan</name></author><author><name>Aditya Raguram</name></author><author><name>Jonathan M. Levy</name></author><author><name>Jaron A. M. Mercer</name></author><author><name>David R. Liu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The targeted deletion, replacement, integration, or inversion of DNA sequences at specified locations in the genome could be used to study or treat many human genetic diseases. Here, we describe twin prime editing (twinPE), a method for the programmable replacement or excision of DNA sequence at endogenous human genomic sites without requiring double-strand DNA breaks. TwinPE uses a prime editor (PE) protein and two prime editing guide RNAs (pegRNAs) that template the synthesis of complementary DNA flaps on opposing strands of genomic DNA, resulting in the replacement of endogenous DNA sequence between the PE-induced nick sites with pegRNA-encoded sequences. We show that twinPE in human cells can perform precise deletions of at least 780 bp and precise replacements of genomic DNA sequence with new sequences of at least 108 bp. By combining single or multiplexed twinPE with site-specific serine recombinases either in separate steps or in a single step, we demonstrate targeted integration of gene-sized DNA plasmids (&amp;gt;5,000 bp) into safe-harbor loci including &lt;italic&gt;AAVS1&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;CCR5,&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;ALB&lt;/italic&gt; in human cells. To our knowledge, these results represent the first RNA-programmable insertion of gene-sized DNA sequences into targeted genomic sites of unmodified human cells without requiring double-strand breaks or homology-directed repair. Twin PE combined with recombinases also mediated a 40,167-bp inversion at &lt;italic&gt;IDS&lt;/italic&gt; that corrects a common Hunter syndrome allele. TwinPE expands the capabilities of precision gene editing without requiring double-strand DNA breaks and synergizes with other tools to enable the correction or complementation of large or complex pathogenic alleles in human cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466790" rel="alternate" title="Programmable large DNA deletion, replacement, integration, and inversion with twin prime editing and site-specific recombinases (26 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467434</id><title>Multiplex genomic recording of enhancer and signal transduction activity in mammalian cells (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.833490+00:00</updated><author><name>Wei Chen</name></author><author><name>Junhong Choi</name></author><author><name>Jenny F. Nathans</name></author><author><name>Vikram Agarwal</name></author><author><name>Beth Martin</name></author><author><name>Eva Nichols</name></author><author><name>Anh Leith</name></author><author><name>Choli Lee</name></author><author><name>Jay Shendure</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Measurements of gene expression and signal transduction activity are conventionally performed with methods that require either the destruction or live imaging of a biological sample within the timeframe of interest. Here we demonstrate an alternative paradigm, termed ENGRAM (ENhancer-driven Genomic Recording of transcriptional Activity in Multiplex), in which the activity and dynamics of multiple transcriptional reporters are stably recorded to DNA. ENGRAM is based on the prime editing-mediated insertion of signal- or enhancer-specific barcodes to a genomically encoded recording unit. We show how this strategy can be used to concurrently genomically record the relative activity of at least hundreds of enhancers with high fidelity, sensitivity and reproducibility. Leveraging synthetic enhancers that are responsive to specific signal transduction pathways, we further demonstrate time- and concentration-dependent genomic recording of Wnt, NF-κB, and Tet-On activity. Finally, by coupling ENGRAM to sequential genome editing, we show how serially occurring molecular events can potentially be ordered. Looking forward, we envision that multiplex, ENGRAM-based recording of the strength, duration and order of enhancer and signal transduction activities has broad potential for application in functional genomics, developmental biology and neuroscience.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467434" rel="alternate" title="Multiplex genomic recording of enhancer and signal transduction activity in mammalian cells (12 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467340</id><title>A comparative analysis of current phasing and imputation software (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.834083+00:00</updated><author><name>Puya G Yazdi</name></author><author><name>Adriano De Marino</name></author><author><name>Abdallah Amr Mahmoud</name></author><author><name>Madhuchanda Bose</name></author><author><name>Karatuğ Ozan Bircan</name></author><author><name>Andrew Terpolovsky</name></author><author><name>Varuna Bamunusinghe</name></author><author><name>Umar Khan</name></author><author><name>Biljana Novković</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Whole-genome data has become significantly more accessible over the last two decades. This can largely be attributed to both reduced sequencing costs and imputation models which make it possible to obtain nearly whole-genome data from less expensive genotyping methods, such as microarray chips. Although there are many different approaches to imputation, the Hidden Markov Model remains the most widely used. In this study, we compared the latest versions of the most popular Hidden Markov Model based tools for phasing and imputation: Beagle 5.2, Eagle 2.4.1, Shapeit 4, Impute 5 and Minimac 4. We benchmarked them on three input datasets with three levels of chip density. We assessed each imputation software on the basis of accuracy, speed and memory usage, and showed how the choice of imputation accuracy metric can result in different interpretations. The highest average concordance rate was achieved by Beagle 5.2, followed by Impute 5 and Minimac 4, using a reference-based approach during phasing and the highest density chip. IQS and R  2  metrics revealed that IMPUTE5 obtained better results for low frequency markers, while Beagle 5.2 remained more accurate for common markers (MAF&amp;gt;5%). Computational load as measured by run time was lower for Beagle 5.2 than Impute 5 and Minimac 4, while Minimac utilized the least memory of the imputation tools we compared. ShapeIT 4, used the least memory of the phasing tools examined, even with the highest density chip. Finally, we determined the combination of phasing software, imputation software, and reference panel, best suited for different situations and analysis needs and created an automated pipeline that provides a way for users to create customized chips designed to optimize their imputation results.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467340" rel="alternate" title="A comparative analysis of current phasing and imputation software (11 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467060</id><title>De novo assembly of 20 chickens reveals the undetectable phenomenon for thousands of core genes on sub-telomeric regions (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.834785+00:00</updated><author><name>Ming Li</name></author><author><name>Congjiao Sun</name></author><author><name>Naiyi Xu</name></author><author><name>Peipei Bian</name></author><author><name>Xiaomeng Tian</name></author><author><name>Xihong Wang</name></author><author><name>Yuzhe Wang</name></author><author><name>Xinzheng Jia</name></author><author><name>Rasmus Heller</name></author><author><name>Mingshan Wang</name></author><author><name>Fei Wang</name></author><author><name>Xuelei Dai</name></author><author><name>Rongsong Luo</name></author><author><name>Yingwei Guo</name></author><author><name>Xiangnan Wang</name></author><author><name>Peng Yang</name></author><author><name>Shunjin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xiaochang Li</name></author><author><name>Chaoliang Wen</name></author><author><name>Fangren Lan</name></author><author><name>AMAM Z SIDDIKI</name></author><author><name>Chatmongkon Suwannapoom</name></author><author><name>Xin Zhao</name></author><author><name>Qinghua Nie</name></author><author><name>Xiaoxiang Hu</name></author><author><name>Yu Jiang</name></author><author><name>Ning Yang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The gene numbers and evolutionary rates of birds were assumed to be much lower than that of mammals, which in sharp contrast to the huge species number and morphological diversity of birds. It is very necessary to construct a complete avian genome and analyze its evolution.We constructed a chicken pan-genome from 20 de novo genome assemblies with high sequencing depth, newly identified 1,335 protein-coding genes and 3,011 long noncoding RNAs. The majority of these novel genes were detected across most individuals of the examined transcriptomes but were accidentally measured in each of the DNA sequencing data regardless of Illumina or PacBio technology. Furthermore, different from previous pan-genome models, most of these novel genes were overrepresented on chromosomal sub-telomeric regions, surrounded with extremely high proportions of tandem repeats, and strongly blocked DNA sequencing. These hidden genes were proved to be shared by all chicken genomes, included many housekeeping genes, and enriched in immune pathways. Comparative genomics revealed the novel genes had three-fold elevated substitution rates than known ones, updating the evolutionary rates of birds. Our study provides a framework for constructing a better chicken genome, which will contribute towards the understanding of avian evolution and improvement of poultry breeding.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467060" rel="alternate" title="De novo assembly of 20 chickens reveals the undetectable phenomenon for thousands of core genes on sub-telomeric regions (10 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467250</id><title>Genome-wide association study of cerebellar volume (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.835458+00:00</updated><author><name>Elleke Tissink</name></author><author><name>Siemon C de Lange</name></author><author><name>Jeanne E Savage</name></author><author><name>Douglas P Wightman</name></author><author><name>Kristen Kelly</name></author><author><name>Mats Nagel</name></author><author><name>Martijn P van den Heuvel</name></author><author><name>Danielle Posthuma</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cerebellar volume is highly heritable and associated with neurodevelopmental and neurodegenerative disorders. Understanding the genetic architecture of cerebellar volume may improve our insight into these disorders. This study aims to investigate the convergence of cerebellar volume genetic associations in close detail. A genome-wide associations study for cerebellar volume was performed in a sample of 27,486 individuals from UK Biobank, resulting in 29 genome-wide significant loci and a SNP heritability of 39.82%. We pinpoint variants that have effects on amino acid sequence or cerebellar gene-expression. Additionally, 85 genome-wide significant genes were detected and tested for convergence onto biological pathways, cerebellar cell types or developmental stages. Local genetic correlations between cerebellar volume and neurodevelopmental and neurodegenerative disorders reveal shared loci with Parkinson's disease, Alzheimer's disease and schizophrenia. These results provide insights into the heritable mechanisms that contribute to developing a brain structure important for cognitive functioning and mental health.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467250" rel="alternate" title="Genome-wide association study of cerebellar volume (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466900</id><title>Bovine pangenome reveals trait-associated structural variation from diverse assembly inputs (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.836040+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander S. Leonard</name></author><author><name>Danang Crysnanto</name></author><author><name>Zih-Hua Fang</name></author><author><name>Michael P Heaton</name></author><author><name>Brian L. Vander Ley</name></author><author><name>Carolina Herrera</name></author><author><name>Heinrich Bollwein</name></author><author><name>Derek M. Bickhart</name></author><author><name>Kristen L. Kuhn</name></author><author><name>Timothy PL. Smith</name></author><author><name>Benjamin D. Rosen</name></author><author><name>Hubert Pausch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Advantages of pangenomes over linear reference assemblies for genome research have recently been established. However, potential effects of sequence platform and assembly approach, or of combining assemblies created by different approaches, on pangenome construction have not been investigated. Ten haplotype-resolved assemblies of three bovine trios representing increasing levels of heterozygosity were generated that each demonstrate a substantial improvement in contiguity and accuracy over the current &lt;italic&gt;Bos taurus&lt;/italic&gt; reference genome, with more telomere and centromere content and an average 2.5x increase in NG50 and 11x decrease in base errors. Downsampling analysis demonstrated that diploid coverage as low as 20x for HiFi or 60x for ONT was sufficient to produce two haplotype-resolved assemblies meeting the standards set by the Vertebrate Genome Project. The assemblies were integrated into structural variant-based pangenomes that demonstrated significant consensus regardless of sequence platform, assembler algorithm, or coverage. Inspecting pangenome topologies identified approximately 900 structural variants overlapping with coding sequences; this approach revealed variants affecting &lt;italic&gt;QRICH2&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;PRDM9&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;HSPA1A&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;TAS2R46&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;GC&lt;/italic&gt; that have potential to affect phenotype.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466900" rel="alternate" title="Bovine pangenome reveals trait-associated structural variation from diverse assembly inputs (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466856</id><title>Population replacement gene drive characteristics for malaria elimination in a range of seasonal transmission settings: a modeling study (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.836528+00:00</updated><author><name>Shirley Leung</name></author><author><name>Nikolai Windblicher</name></author><author><name>Edward Wenger</name></author><author><name>Caitlin Bever</name></author><author><name>Prashanth Selvaraj</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genetically engineering mosquitoes is a promising new vector control strategy to reinvigorate the fight against malaria in Sub-Saharan Africa. Using an agent-based model of malaria transmission with vector genetics, we examine the impacts of releasing population-replacement gene drive mosquitoes on malaria transmission and quantify the gene drive system parameters required to achieve local elimination within a spatially-resolved, seasonal Sahelian setting. We evaluate the performance of two different gene drive systems: “classic” and “integral.” Various transmission regimes (low, moderate, and high - corresponding to annual entomological inoculation rates of 10, 30, and 80 infectious bites per person) and other simultaneous interventions, including deployment of insecticide-treated nets (ITNs) and passive healthcare seeking, are also simulated. Local elimination probabilities decreased with pre-existing population target site resistance frequency, increased with transmission-blocking effectiveness of the introduced antiparasitic gene and drive efficiency, and were context dependent with respect to fitness costs associated with the introduced gene. Of the four parameters, transmission-blocking effectiveness may be the most important to focus on for improvements to future gene drive strains because a single release of classic gene drive mosquitoes is likely to locally eliminate malaria in low to moderate transmission settings only when transmission-blocking effectiveness is very high (above &lt;sup&gt;~&lt;/sup&gt;80-90%). However, simultaneously deploying ITNs and releasing integral rather than classic gene drive mosquitoes significantly boosts elimination probabilities, such that elimination remains highly likely in low to moderate transmission regimes down to transmission-blocking effectiveness values as low as &lt;sup&gt;~&lt;/sup&gt;50% and in high transmission regimes with transmission-blocking effectiveness values above &lt;sup&gt;~&lt;/sup&gt;80-90%. Thus, a single release of currently achievable population replacement gene drive mosquitoes, in combination with traditional forms of vector control, can likely locally eliminate malaria in low to moderate transmission regimes within the Sahel. In a high transmission regime, higher levels of transmission-blocking effectiveness than are currently available may be required.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Malaria remains a significant health burden in Sub-Saharan Africa. The mass deployment of insecticide-treated nets and antimalarial drugs have drastically reduced malaria incidence, but insecticide and drug resistance threaten to stall these efforts. The genetic engineering of mosquito populations is a promising new vector control strategy to reinvigorate the fight against malaria. Releases of engineered gene drive mosquitoes that can spread introduced antimalarial genes quickly throughout the mosquito population may be a particularly effective new method for reducing malaria transmission. Important questions arise, however, about how well these gene drive systems must work in order to deliver substantial reductions in transmission. Here we use a spatial model of individual humans and vectors to simulate the effects of releasing gene drive mosquitoes with antimalarial properties on malaria transmission in a Sahelian setting. We quantify the gene drive system parameters required to achieve local elimination and find that when deployed in combination with traditional forms of vector control, a single release of gene drive mosquitoes with realistically achievable characteristics is highly likely to locally eliminate malaria in low to moderate transmission regimes. In a high transmission regime, improved strains of gene drive mosquitoes may be required. In all settings, releasing gene drive mosquitoes with antimalarial properties helps create a window of opportunity during which malaria prevalence is suppressed and other interventions can be ramped up to achieve elimination, even when a single gene drive mosquito release by itself cannot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466856" rel="alternate" title="Population replacement gene drive characteristics for malaria elimination in a range of seasonal transmission settings: a modeling study (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466756</id><title>Comparative genomics among three cyst nematode species reveals distinct evolutionary histories among effector families and an irregular distribution of effector-associated promoter motifs (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.837160+00:00</updated><author><name>Joris J.M. van Steenbrugge</name></author><author><name>Sven van den Elsen</name></author><author><name>Martijn Holterman</name></author><author><name>Jose L. Lozano-Torres</name></author><author><name>Vera Putker</name></author><author><name>Peter Thorpe</name></author><author><name>Aska Goverse</name></author><author><name>Mark G. Sterken</name></author><author><name>Geert Smant</name></author><author><name>Johannes Helder</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Potato cyst nematodes (PCNs), an umbrella term used for two species, &lt;italic&gt;Globodera pallida&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;G. rostochiensis&lt;/italic&gt;, belong worldwide to the most harmful pathogens of potato. Pathotype-specific host plant resistances are an essential handle for PCN control. However, the poor delineation of &lt;italic&gt;G. pallida&lt;/italic&gt; pathotypes hampers the efficient use of available host plant resistances. Long-read sequencing technology allowed us to generate a new reference genome of &lt;italic&gt;G. pallida&lt;/italic&gt; population D383 and, as compared to the current reference, the new genome assembly is 42 times less fragmented. For comparison of diversification patterns of six effector families between &lt;italic&gt;G. pallida&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;G. rostochiensis&lt;/italic&gt;, an additional reference genome was generated for an outgroup, the beet cyst nematode &lt;italic&gt;Heterodera schachtii&lt;/italic&gt; (IRS population). Large evolutionary contrasts in effector family topologies were observed. While VAPs diversified before the split between the three cyst nematode species, the families GLAND5 and GLAND13 only expanded in PCN after their separation from the genus &lt;italic&gt;Heterodera&lt;/italic&gt;. Although DNA motifs in the promoter regions thought to be involved in the orchestration of effector expression (‘DOG boxes’) were present in all three cyst nematode species, their presence is not a necessity for dorsal gland-produced effectors. Notably, DOG box dosage was only loosely correlated with expression level of individual effector variants. Comparison of the &lt;italic&gt;G. pallida&lt;/italic&gt; genome with those of two other cyst nematodes underlined the fundamental differences in evolutionary history between effector families. Re-sequencing of PCN populations with deviant virulence characteristics will allow for the linking of these characteristics with the composition of the effector repertoire as well as for the mapping of PCN diversification patterns resulting from extreme anthropogenic range expansion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466756" rel="alternate" title="Comparative genomics among three cyst nematode species reveals distinct evolutionary histories among effector families and an irregular distribution of effector-associated promoter motifs (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467059</id><title>The Biosynthetic Costs of Amino Acids at the Base of the Food Chain Determine Their Use in Higher-order Consumer Genomes (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.837731+00:00</updated><author><name>Javier Gómez Ortega</name></author><author><name>Sonika Tyagi</name></author><author><name>Christen Mirth</name></author><author><name>Matthew Piper</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Dietary nutrient composition is essential for shaping important fitness traits and behaviours. Many organisms are protein limited and for Drosophila melanogaster, this limitation manifests at the level of the single most limiting essential Amino Acid (AA) in the diet. The identity of this AA and its effects on female fecundity is readily predictable by a procedure called exome matching in which the sum of AAs encoded by a consumer's exome is used to predict the relative proportion of AAs required in its diet. However, the exome matching calculation does not weight AA contributions to the overall profile by protein size or expression. Here we update the exome matching calculation to include these weightings. Surprisingly, although nearly half of the transcriptome is differentially expressed when comparing male and female flies, we found that creating transcriptome-weighted exome matched diets for each sex did not enhance their fecundity over that supported by exome matching alone. These data indicate that while organisms may require different amounts of dietary protein across conditions, the relative proportion of the constituent AAs remains constant. Interestingly, we also found remarkable conservation of exome matched AA profiles across taxa and that the composition of these profiles could be explained by the metabolic costs of microbial AA synthesis. Thus, it appears that bioenergetic constraints amongst autotrophs shape the relative proportion of AAs that are available across trophic levels and that that this constrains biomass composition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467059" rel="alternate" title="The Biosynthetic Costs of Amino Acids at the Base of the Food Chain Determine Their Use in Higher-order Consumer Genomes (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466849</id><title>Sex significantly impacts the function of major depression-linked variants in vivo (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.838208+00:00</updated><author><name>Bernard Mulvey</name></author><author><name>Din Selmanovic</name></author><author><name>Joseph D. Dougherty</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genome-wide association studies have discovered blocks of common variants—likely transcriptional-regulatory—associated with major depressive disorder (MDD), though the functional subset and their biological impacts remain unknown. Likewise, why depression occurs in females more frequently than males is unclear. We therefore tested the hypothesis that risk-associated functional variants interact with sex and produce greater impact in female brains. We developed methods to directly measure regulatory variant activity and sex interactions using massively parallel reporter assays (MPRAs) in the mouse brain &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, in a cell type-specific manner. We measured activity of &amp;gt;1,000 variants from &amp;gt;30 MDD loci, identifying extensive sex-by-allele effects in mature hippocampal neurons and suggesting sex-differentiated impacts of genetic risk may underlie sex bias in disease. Unbiased informatics approaches indicated that functional MDD variants recurrently disrupt sex hormone receptor binding sequences. We confirmed this with MPRAs in neonatal brains, comparing brains undergoing the masculinizing hormone surge to hormonally-quiescent juveniles. Our study provides novel insights into the influence of age, biological sex, and cell type on regulatory-variant function, and provides a framework for &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; parallel assays to functionally define interactions between organismal variables like sex and regulatory variation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Massively parallel assays &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; identified extensive functional and sex-interacting common variants in depression risk loci.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466849" rel="alternate" title="Sex significantly impacts the function of major depression-linked variants in vivo (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467506</id><title>Structure and Function of the Retina of Low-density Lipoprotein Receptor-related Protein 5 (Lrp5)-deficient Rats (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.838663+00:00</updated><author><name>John L. Ubels</name></author><author><name>Cheng-Mao Lin</name></author><author><name>David A. Antonetti</name></author><author><name>Monica Diaz-Coranguez</name></author><author><name>Cassandra R. Diegel</name></author><author><name>Bart O. Williams</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Loss-of-function mutations in the Wnt co-receptor, low-density lipoprotein receptor-related protein 5 (LRP5), result in familial exudative vitreoretinopathy (FEVR), osteoporosis-pseudoglioma syndrome (OPPG), and Norrie disease. CRISPR/Cas9 gene editing was used to produce rat strains deficient in Lrp5. The purpose of this study was to validate this rat model for studies of hypovascular, exudative retinopathies. The retinal vasculature of wildtype and Lrp5 knockout rats was stained with Giffonia simplifolia isolectin B4 and imaged by fluorescence microscopy. Effects on retinal structure were investigated by histology. The integrity of the blood-retina barrier was analyzed by staining for claudin-5 and measurement of permeability to Evans blue dye. Retinas were imaged by fundus photography and SD-OCT, and electroretinograms were recorded. Lrp5 gene deletion led to sparse superficial retinal capillaries and loss of the deep and intermediate plexuses. Autofluorescent exudates were observed, correlated with absence of claudin-5 expression in superficial vessels and increased Evans blue permeability. OCT images show pathology similar to OCT of humans with FEVR, and retinal thickness is reduced by 50% compared to wild-type rats. Histology and OCT reveal that photoreceptor and outer plexiform layers are absent. The retina failed to demonstrate an ERG response. CRISPR/Cas9 gene-editing produced a predictable rat Lrp5 knockout model with extensive defects in the retinal vascular and neural structure and function. This rat model should be useful for studies of exudative retinal vascular diseases involving the Wnt and norrin pathways.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467506" rel="alternate" title="Structure and Function of the Retina of Low-density Lipoprotein Receptor-related Protein 5 (Lrp5)-deficient Rats (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467485</id><title>Probabilistic Genotyping of Single Cell Replicates from Complex DNA Mixtures Recovers Higher Contributor LRs than Standard Analysis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.839135+00:00</updated><author><name>Kaitlin Huffman</name></author><author><name>Erin Hanson</name></author><author><name>Jack Ballantyne</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;DNA mixtures are a common source of crime scene evidence and are often one of the more difficult sources of biological evidence to interpret. With the implementation of probabilistic genotyping (PG), mixture analysis has been revolutionized allowing previously unresolvable mixed profiles to be analyzed and probative genotype information from contributors to be recovered. However, due to allele overlap, artifacts, or low-level minor contributors, genotype information loss inevitably occurs. In order to reduce the potential loss of significant DNA information from donors in complex mixtures, an alternative approach is to physically separate individual cells from mixtures prior to performing DNA typing thus obtaining single source profiles from contributors. In the present work, a simplified micro-manipulation technique combined with enhanced single-cell DNA typing was used to collect one or few cells, referred to as direct single-cell subsampling (DSCS). Using this approach, single and 2-cell subsamples were collected from 2-6 person mixtures. Single-cell subsamples resulted in single source DNA profiles while the 2-cell subsamples returned either single source DNA profiles or new mini-mixtures that are less complex than the original mixture due to the presence of fewer contributors.  PG (STRmixTM) was implemented, after appropriate validation, to analyze the original bulk mixtures, single source cell subsamples, and the 2-cell mini mixture subsamples from the original 2-6-person mixtures. PG further allowed replicate analysis to be employed which, in many instances, resulted in a significant gain of genotype information such that the returned donor likelihood ratios (LRs) were comparable to that seen in their single source reference profiles (i.e., the reciprocal of their random match probabilities). In every mixture, the DSCS approach gave improved results for each donor compared to standard bulk mixture analysis. With the 5- and 6- person complex mixtures, DSCS recovered highly probative LRs (&amp;gt; 1020) from donors that had returned non-probative LRs (&amp;lt;103) by standard methods.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467485" rel="alternate" title="Probabilistic Genotyping of Single Cell Replicates from Complex DNA Mixtures Recovers Higher Contributor LRs than Standard Analysis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.06.467539</id><title>Whole-genome sequencing of Chinese native goat offers biological insights into cashmere fiber formation (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.839404+00:00</updated><author><name>Hu Han</name></author><author><name>Man-Man Yang</name></author><author><name>Dan Jiang</name></author><author><name>Xing-Ju Zhang</name></author><author><name>Qiang Wei</name></author><author><name>Tao Chen</name></author><author><name>Qi-Ju Wang</name></author><author><name>Cheng-Ye Yang</name></author><author><name>Bater Wulan</name></author><author><name>Ting-Ting Zhang</name></author><author><name>Geng Gang</name></author><author><name>Dala Mengke</name></author><author><name>Bin LI</name></author><author><name>Wei-Dong Deng</name></author><author><name>Ze-Pu Miao</name></author><author><name>Ran Wang</name></author><author><name>Qing-Feng Zhang</name></author><author><name>Lin Li</name></author><author><name>Sheng-Yu CHao</name></author><author><name>Ming Fang</name></author><author><name>Yong Li</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cashmere evolved naturally in the goat, and almost all breeds of goat can produce more or less cashmere fibers. However, the genetic alterations underlying cashmere trait selection are still unclear.We sequenced 120 Chinese native goat including two cashmere goat breeds (Ujumain, Chaidamu) and six ordinary goat breeds (Jining Gray, Matou, Guizhou Black, Jintang Black, Yunnan Black Bone, Chengdu Brown). The genome-wide selective sweep of cashmere goat and ordinary goat revealed a novel set of candidate genes as well as pathways, such as Nuclear factor kappa-B and Wnt Signaling pathways. Of them, the LHX2 gene regulating hair follicle development, was evident from the strongest selection signal when comparing the Uhumqin cashmere goat and ordinary goat. Interestingly, we identified a 582bp deletion at 367 kb upstream of LHX2 with higher frequency in cashmere goats and their ancient relatives. This mutation probably rises along the breeding procedures, and is putatively responsible for cashmere production and diameter, as revealed by association studies. Luciferase assay shows that the deletion, which acts as an insulator, restrains the expression of LHX2 by interfering its upstream enhancers.Our study discovers a novel insulator of the LHX2 involved in regulating cashmere production and diameter, which would be beneficial to understanding hair follicle development and regeneration. Our findings also provide new insights into the genetic formation of cashmere, and facilitate subsequent molecular breeding for cashmere goat improvement.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.06.467539" rel="alternate" title="Whole-genome sequencing of Chinese native goat offers biological insights into cashmere fiber formation (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467115</id><title>Blueprint for Phasing and Assembling the Genomes of Heterozygous Polyploids: Application to the Octoploid Genome of Strawberry (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.840022+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael A Hardigan</name></author><author><name>Mitchell J Feldmann</name></author><author><name>Dominique DA Pincot</name></author><author><name>Randi A Famula</name></author><author><name>Michaela V Vachev</name></author><author><name>Mary A Madera</name></author><author><name>Philipp J Zerbe</name></author><author><name>Kristin Mars</name></author><author><name>Paul Peluso</name></author><author><name>David Rank</name></author><author><name>Shujun Ou</name></author><author><name>Christopher A Saski</name></author><author><name>Charlotte B Acharya</name></author><author><name>Glenn S Cole</name></author><author><name>Alan E Yocca</name></author><author><name>Adrian E Platts</name></author><author><name>Patrick P Edger</name></author><author><name>Steven J Knapp</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The challenge of allelic diversity for assembling haplotypes is exemplified in polyploid genomes containing homoeologous chromosomes of identical ancestry, and significant homologous variation within their ancestral subgenomes. Cultivated strawberry (Fragaria x ananassa) and its wild progenitors are outbred octoploids (2n = 8x = 56) in which up to eight homologous and homoeologous alleles are preserved. This introduces significant risk of haplotype collapse, switching, and chimeric fusions during assembly. Using third generation HiFi sequences from PacBio, we assembled the genome of the day-neutral octoploid F. x ananassa hybrid 'Royal Royce' from the University of California. Our goal was to produce subgenome- and haplotype-resolved assemblies of all 56 chromosomes, accurately reconstructing the parental haploid chromosome complements.  Previous work has demonstrated that partitioning sequences by parental phase supports direct assembly of haplotypes in heterozygous diploid species. We leveraged the accuracy of HiFi sequence data with pedigree-informed sequencing to partition long read sequences by phase, and reduce the downstream risk of subgenomic chimeras during assembly. We were able to utilize an octoploid strawberry recombination breakpoint map containing 3.6 M variants to identify and break chimeric junctions, and perform scaffolding of the phase-1 and phase-2 octoploid assemblies. The N50 contiguity of the phase-1 and phase-2 assemblies prior to scaffolding and gap-filling was 11 Mb. The final haploid assembly represented seven of 28 chromosomes in a single contiguous sequence, and averaged fewer than three gaps per pseudomolecule. Additionally, we re-annotated the octoploid genome to produce a custom F. x ananassa repeat library and improved set of gene models based on IsoSeq transcript data and an expansive RNA-seq expression atlas. Here we present 'FaRR1', a gold-standard reference genome of F. x ananassa cultivar 'Royal Royce' to assist future genomic research and molecular breeding of allo-octoploid strawberry.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467115" rel="alternate" title="Blueprint for Phasing and Assembling the Genomes of Heterozygous Polyploids: Application to the Octoploid Genome of Strawberry (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467126</id><title>Towards routine employment of computational tools for antimicrobial resistance determination via high-throughput sequencing (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.840765+00:00</updated><author><name>Simone Marini</name></author><author><name>Rodrigo A. Mora</name></author><author><name>Christina Boucher</name></author><author><name>Noelle Noyes</name></author><author><name>Mattia Prosperi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antimicrobial resistance (AMR) is a growing threat to public health and farming at large. Without appropriate interventions, it can lead to millions of deaths per year and substantial economic loss worldwide. In clinical and veterinary practice, a timely characterization of the antibiotic susceptibility profile of bacterial infections is a crucial step in optimizing treatment. Fast turnaround of AMR testing is also needed in food safety and infection control surveillance (e.g., contamination of healthcare or long-term nursing facilities). High-throughput sequencing is a promising option for clinical point-of-care and ecological surveillance, opening the opportunity to develop genotyping-based AMR determination as a possibly faster alternative to phenotypic testing. In the present work, we compare the performance of state-of-the-art methods for detection of AMR from high-throughput sequencing data in healthcare settings. We consider five complementary computational approaches –alignment (AMRPlusPlus), deep learning (DeepARG), &lt;italic&gt;k&lt;/italic&gt;-mer genomic signatures (KARGA, Res-Finder), and hidden Markov models (Meta-MARC). We use an extensive collection of clinical studies never employed for model training. To do so, we assemble data from multiple, independent AMR high-throughput sequencing experiments collected in a variety of hospital settings, comprising of 585 isolates with a available AMR resistance profiles determined by phenotypic tests across nine antibiotic classes. We show how the pre-diction landscape of AMR classifiers is highly heterogeneous, with balanced accuracy varying from 0.4 to 0.92. Although some algorithms—ResFinder, KARGA, and AMRPlusPlus– exhibit overall better balanced accuracy than others, the high per-AMR-class variance and related findings suggest that: (1) all algorithms might be subject to sampling bias present both in data repositories used for training and experimental/clinical settings; and (2) a portion of clinical samples might contain uncharacterized AMR genes that the algorithms—mostly trained on known AMR genes—fail to generalize upon. These results lead us to formulate practical advice for software configuration and application, as well as give suggestions for future study design to further develop AMR prediction tools from proof-of-concept to bedside.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467126" rel="alternate" title="Towards routine employment of computational tools for antimicrobial resistance determination via high-throughput sequencing (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467051</id><title>Restricting a single amino acid cross-protects D. melanogaster from nicotine poisoning through mTORC1 and GCN2 signalling (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.841126+00:00</updated><author><name>Tahlia L. Fulton</name></author><author><name>Christen K. Mirth</name></author><author><name>Matthew D. W. Piper</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Dietary interventions that restrict protein intake have repeatedly been shown to offer beneficial health outcomes to the consumer. Benefits such as increased stress tolerance can be observed in response to restricting individual amino acids, thus mimicking dietary protein restriction. Here, we sought to further understand the relationship between dietary amino acids and stress tolerance using &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt;. Utilising a chemically defined medium for &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt;, we found that transiently restricting adult flies of a single essential amino acid generally protects against a lethal dose of the naturally occurring insecticide, nicotine. This protection was conferred during the pre-treatment window, was specific for individual amino acids and depended on the identity of the focal amino acid, as well as the duration and intensity of its restriction. For instance, complete isoleucine deprivation for 7 days maximised its protective effect - increasing survival during nicotine exposure by 100%. However, a dose of 25% threonine was required to maximise its protective effect (53% enhanced survival). To understand the molecular basis of these effects, we modified the signalling of two cellular sensors of amino acids, GCN2 (General control non-derepressible) and mTORC1 (mechanistic Target of Rapamycin Complex 1) in combination with amino acid restriction. We found that GCN2 was necessary for diets to protect against nicotine, whereas suppression of mTORC1 was sufficient to induce nicotine resistance. This finding implies that amino acid restriction acts via amino acid signalling to cross-protect against seemingly unrelated stressors. Altogether, our study offers new insights into the physiological responses to restriction of individual amino acids that confer stress tolerance. This has broad potential for application in animal and human health.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467051" rel="alternate" title="Restricting a single amino acid cross-protects D. melanogaster from nicotine poisoning through mTORC1 and GCN2 signalling (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466885</id><title>Operon formation by insertion sequence IS3 in Escherichia coli (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.841453+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuki Kanai</name></author><author><name>Saburo Tsuru</name></author><author><name>Chikara Furusawa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Operons are a hallmark of the genomic and regulatory architecture of prokaryotes. However, the mechanism by which two genes placed far apart gradually come close and form operons remains to be elucidated. Here, we propose a new model of the origin of operons: Mobile genetic elements called insertion sequences can facilitate the formation of operons by consecutive insertion-deletion-excision reactions. This mechanism barely leaves traces of insertion sequences and is difficult to detect in evolution in nature. We performed, to the best of our knowledge, the first experimental demonstration of operon formation, as a proof of concept. The insertion sequence IS&lt;italic&gt;3&lt;/italic&gt; and the insertion sequence excision enhancer are genes found in a broad range of bacterial species. We introduced these genes into insertion sequence-less &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; and found that, supporting our hypothesis, the activity of the two genes altered the expression of genes surrounding IS&lt;italic&gt;3&lt;/italic&gt;, closed a 2.7 kilobase pair gap between a pair of genes, and formed new operons. This study shows how insertion sequences can facilitate the rapid formation of operons through locally increasing the structural mutation rates and highlights how coevolution with mobile elements may shape the organization of prokaryotic genomes and gene regulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466885" rel="alternate" title="Operon formation by insertion sequence IS3 in Escherichia coli (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467445</id><title>Mitochondrial DNA variants segregate during human preimplantation development into genetically different cell lineages that are maintained postnatally (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.841764+00:00</updated><author><name>Joke Mertens</name></author><author><name>Marius Regin</name></author><author><name>Neelke De Munck</name></author><author><name>Edouard Couvreu de Deckersberg</name></author><author><name>Florence Belva</name></author><author><name>Karen D Sermon</name></author><author><name>Herman Tournaye</name></author><author><name>Christophe Blockeel</name></author><author><name>Hilde Van de Velde</name></author><author><name>Claudia Spits</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Humans present remarkable mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) variant mosaicism, not only across tissues but even across individual cells within one person. The timing of the first appearance of this mosaicism has not yet been established. In this study, we hypothesized it occurs during preimplantation development. To investigate this, we deep-sequenced the mtDNA of 254 oocytes from 85 donors, 158 single blastomeres of 25 day-3 embryos, 17 inner cell mass and trophectoderm samples of 7 day-5 blastocysts, 142 bulk DNA and 68 single cells of different adult tissues. We found that day-3 preimplantation embryos already present blastomeres that carry variants unique to that cell, showing that the first events of mtDNA mosaicism happen very early in human development. We classified the mtDNA variants based on their recurrence or uniqueness across sibling oocytes and embryos, and between single cells and samples from the same embryos or adult individuals. Variants that recurred across samples had higher heteroplasmic loads and more frequently resulted in synonymous changes or were located in non-coding regions than variants that were unique to one oocyte or single embryonic cell. These differences were maintained through developmental stages, suggesting that the mtDNA mosaicism arising in preimplantation development is maintained into adulthood. Further, the results support a model in which close clustering of mitochondria carrying specific mtDNA variants in the ooplasm leads to asymmetric distribution of these mitochondria throughout the cell divisions of the preimplantation embryo, resulting in the appearance of the first form of mtDNA mosaicism in human development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467445" rel="alternate" title="Mitochondrial DNA variants segregate during human preimplantation development into genetically different cell lineages that are maintained postnatally (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467166</id><title>Two-speed genome expansion drives the evolution of pathogenicity in animal fungal pathogens (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.844317+00:00</updated><author><name>Theresa Wacker</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Helmstetter</name></author><author><name>Duncan Wilson</name></author><author><name>Matthew C. Fisher</name></author><author><name>David J. Studholme</name></author><author><name>Rhys A. Farrer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The origins of virulence in amphibian-infecting chytrids &lt;italic&gt;Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Bd&lt;/italic&gt;) and &lt;italic&gt;Batrachochytrium salamandrivorans&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Bsal)&lt;/italic&gt; are largely unknown. Here, we use deep nanopore sequencing of &lt;italic&gt;Bsal&lt;/italic&gt; and comparative genomics against 21 high-quality genome assemblies that span the fungal Chytridiomycota. &lt;italic&gt;Bsal&lt;/italic&gt; has the most repeat-rich genome, comprising 40.9% repetitive elements, which has expanded to more than 3X the length of its conspecific &lt;italic&gt;Bd&lt;/italic&gt;. M36 metalloprotease virulence factors are highly expanded in &lt;italic&gt;Bsal&lt;/italic&gt; and 53% of the 177 unique genes are flanked by transposable elements, suggesting repeat-driven expansion. The largest M36 sub-family are mostly (84%) flanked upstream by a novel LINE element, a repeat superfamily implicated with gene copy number variations. We find that &lt;italic&gt;Bsal&lt;/italic&gt; has a highly compartmentalized genome architecture, with virulence factors enriched in gene-sparse/repeat-rich compartments, while core conserved genes occur in gene-rich/repeat-poor compartments. This is a hallmark of two-speed genome evolution. Furthermore, genes with signatures of positive selection in &lt;italic&gt;Bd&lt;/italic&gt; are enriched in repeat-rich regions, suggesting they are a cradle for chytrid pathogenicity evolution, and &lt;italic&gt;Bd&lt;/italic&gt; also has a two-speed genome. This is the first evidence of two-speed genomes in any animal pathogen, and sheds new light on the evolution of fungal pathogens of vertebrates driving global declines and extinctions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467166" rel="alternate" title="Two-speed genome expansion drives the evolution of pathogenicity in animal fungal pathogens (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.467006</id><title>SVJAM: Joint Analysis of Structural Variants Using Linked Read Sequencing Data (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.847252+00:00</updated><author><name>Mustafa Hakan Gunturkun</name></author><author><name>Flavia Villani</name></author><author><name>Vincenza Colonna</name></author><author><name>David Ashbrook</name></author><author><name>Robert W Williams</name></author><author><name>Hao Chen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Linked-read whole genome sequencing methods, such as the 10x Chromium, attach a unique molecular barcode to each high molecular weight DNA molecule. The samples are then sequenced using short-read technology. During analysis, sequence reads sharing the same barcode are aligned to adjacent genomic locations. The pattern of barcode sharing between genomic regions allows the discovery of large structural variants (SVs) in the range of 1 Kb to a few Mb. Most SV calling methods for these data, such as LongRanger, analyze one sample at a time and often produces inconsistent results for the same genomic location across multiple samples. We developed a method, SVJAM, for joint calling of SVs, using data from 152 members of the BXD family of recombinant inbred strains of mice. Our method first collects candidate SV regions from single sample analysis, such as those produced by LongRanger. We then retrieve barcode overlapping data from all samples for each region. These data are organized as a high dimensional matrix. The dimension of this matrix is then reduced using principal component analysis. Samples projected onto a two dimensional space formed by the first two principal components forms two or three clusters based on their genotype, representing the reference, alternative, or heterozygotic alleles. We developed a novel distance measure for hierarchical clustering and rotating the axes to find the optimal clustering results. We also developed an algorithm to decide whether the pattern of sample distribution is best fitted with one, two, or three genotypes. For each sample, we calculate its membership score for each genotype. We compared results produced by SVJAM with LongRanger and few methods that rely on PacBio or Oxford Nanopore data. In a comparison of SVJAM with SV detected using long-read sequencing data for the DBA/2J strain, we found that our results recovered many SVs missed by LongRanger. We also found many SVs called by LongRanger were assigned with an incorrect SV type. Our algorithm also consistently identified heterozygotic regions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.467006" rel="alternate" title="SVJAM: Joint Analysis of Structural Variants Using Linked Read Sequencing Data (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466789</id><title>Prioritising Autoimmunity Risk Variants for Functional Analyses by Fine-Mapping Mutations Under Natural Selection (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.847883+00:00</updated><author><name>Vasili Pankratov</name></author><author><name>Milyausha Yunusbaeva</name></author><author><name>Sergei Ryakhovsky</name></author><author><name>Maksym Zarodniuk</name></author><author><name>Bayazit Yunusbayev</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pathogens imposed selective pressure on humans and shaped genetic variation in immunity genes. This can also be true for a fraction of causal variants implicated in chronic inflammatory disorders. Hence, locating adaptive mutations among candidate variants for these disorders can be a promising way to prioritize and decipher their functional response to microbial stimuli and contribution to pathogenesis. This idea has been discussed for decades, but challenges in locating adaptive SNPs hindered its application in practice. Our study addresses this issue and shows that a fraction of candidate variants for inflammatory conditions evolved under moderate and weak selection regimes (sweeps), and such variants are mappable. Using a novel powerful local-tree-based methodology, we show that 204 out of 593 risk loci for 21 autoimmune disorders contain at least one candidate SNP with strong evidence of selection. More importantly, in 28% of cases, these candidates for causal variants colocalize with SNPs under natural selection that we fine-mapped in this study. Causal SNPs under selection represent promising targets for functional experiments. Such experiments will help decipher molecular events triggered by infectious agents, a likely early event in autoimmunity. Finally, we show that a large fraction (60%) of candidate variants are either hitchhikers or linked with the selected mutation. Our findings, thus, support both hitchhiking and natural selection models, with the latter having important practical implications in medicine.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466789" rel="alternate" title="Prioritising Autoimmunity Risk Variants for Functional Analyses by Fine-Mapping Mutations Under Natural Selection (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466675</id><title>Initial approach to the Conservation Genetics of the Guatemalan Beaded Lizard (Heloderma charlesbogerti): A route to genetic rescue (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.848317+00:00</updated><author><name>Sergio González</name></author><author><name>Thomas Schrei</name></author><author><name>Brad Lock</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In this study, samples from 33 Guatemalan Beaded Lizard (&lt;italic&gt;Heloderma charlesbogerti&lt;/italic&gt;) were analyzed for genetic diversity. Twenty-three samples were obtained from wild individuals from two separate population areas, and 10 samples were obtained from captive individuals. Because the seasonally dry tropical forest habitat sampled for this study, is degraded and fragmented, it was hypothesized that beaded lizard populations were small and isolated and would be subject to genetic erosion and an elevated extinction risk. To test this hypothesis, eight microsatellite markers were employed to analyze 22 individual samples from the population of Cabañas, Zacapa, a single individual from the eastern-most population and 10 captive individuals of unknown origin. An average of three alleles per maker was reported for the Cabañas population, evidencing a low genetic diversity. In addition, a recent bottleneck event was detected and an effective population size of 19.6 was estimated. Demographic reconstruction using a Bayesian approach was inconclusive possibly due to a small dataset and shallow coalescence trees obtained with the generated data. No clear structuring pattern was detected for the Cabañas population and most samples from individuals in captivity were found to have similar alleles to the ones from Cabañas. Population designation is challenging without the genotyping of every wild population, but unique alleles were found in captive individuals of unknown origin that could suggest that different genotypes might exist within other, less studied, wild populations. Low genetic diversity, and a small effective population size represent a risk for the Cabañas population facing the threats of isolation, habitat loss and climate change. These findings suggest that genetic management of the Cabañas population might be utilized to avoid high rates of inbreeding and subsequent inbreeding depression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466675" rel="alternate" title="Initial approach to the Conservation Genetics of the Guatemalan Beaded Lizard (Heloderma charlesbogerti): A route to genetic rescue (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>