<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>BioRxiv preprints in genetics posted in the last week with at least 5 tweets</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.458621+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.07.443118</id><title>Intergenerational adaptations to stress are evolutionarily conserved, stress-specific, and have deleterious trade-offs (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.459815+00:00</updated><author><name>Nick Burton</name></author><author><name>Alexandra R Willis</name></author><author><name>Kinsey Fisher</name></author><author><name>Fabian Braukmann</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Price</name></author><author><name>Lewis Stevens</name></author><author><name>Ryan Baugh</name></author><author><name>Aaron W Reinke</name></author><author><name>Eric Alexander Miska</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite reports of parental exposure to stress promoting physiological adaptations in progeny in diverse organisms, there remains considerable debate over the significance and evolutionary conservation of such multigenerational effects. Here, we investigate four independent models of intergenerational adaptations to stress in C. elegans (bacterial infection, eukaryotic infection, osmotic stress and nutrient stress) across multiple species. We found that all four intergenerational physiological adaptations are conserved in at least one other species, that they are stress-specific, and that they have deleterious trade-offs in mismatched environments. By profiling the effects of parental bacterial infection and osmotic stress exposure on progeny gene expression across species we established a core set of 279 highly conserved genes that exhibited intergenerational changes in expression in response to stress in all species tested and provide evidence suggesting that presumed adaptive and deleterious intergenerational effects are molecularly related at the gene expression level. By contrast, we found that these same stresses did not elicit any similarly conserved transgenerational changes in progeny gene expression three generations after stress exposure. We conclude that intergenerational responses to stress play a substantial and evolutionarily conserved role in regulating animal physiology and that the vast majority of the effects of parental stress on progeny gene expression are reversible and not maintained transgenerationally.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.06.442996</id><title>Genome-wide admixture mapping of eGFR and CKD identify European and African ancestry-of-origin loci in U.S. Hispanics/Latinos (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.459111+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrea R.V.R. Horimoto</name></author><author><name>Jianwen Cai</name></author><author><name>James P. Lash</name></author><author><name>Martha L. Daviglus</name></author><author><name>Nora Franceschini</name></author><author><name>Timothy A. Thornton</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Admixture mapping is a powerful approach for gene mapping of complex traits that leverages the diverse genetic ancestry in populations with recent admixture such as U.S. Hispanics/Latinos (HL), who have increased risk of chronic kidney disease (CKD).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Genome-wide admixture mapping was performed for CKD and estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) in a sample of 12,601 participants from the Hispanic Community Health Study/Study of Latinos, with validation in a sample of 8191 African Americans from the Women’s Health Initiative (WHI).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Three novel ancestry-of-origin loci were identified on chromosomes 2, 14 and 15 for CKD and eGFR. The chromosome 2 locus (2p16.3) consisted of two European ancestry regions encompassing the &lt;italic&gt;FSHR&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;NRXN1&lt;/italic&gt; genes, with European ancestry at this locus associated with increased risk for CKD. The chromosome 14 locus (14q32.2) located within the &lt;italic&gt;DLK1-DIO3&lt;/italic&gt; imprinted domain was driven by European ancestry, and was associated with lower eGFR. The chromosome 15 locus (15q13.3-14) included intronic variants of &lt;italic&gt;RYR3&lt;/italic&gt; and was within an African-specific genomic region that was associated with higher eGFR. These findings were compared to the conventional genome-wide association study that failed to identify significant associations in these regions. We validated the chromosome 14 and 15 loci for eGFR in the WHI African Americans.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study provides evidence of shared ancestry-specific genomic regions influencing eGFR in HL and African Americans, and illustrates the potential for leveraging genetic ancestry in recently admixed populations for novel discovery of kidney trait loci.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>