<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.147768+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470722</id><title>Barcode aware adaptive sampling for Oxford Nanopore sequencers. (62 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.148134+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Payne</name></author><author><name>Rory Munro</name></author><author><name>Nadine Holmes</name></author><author><name>Christopher Moore</name></author><author><name>Matthew Carlile</name></author><author><name>Matthew W Loose</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Adaptive sampling enables selection of individual molecules from sequencing libraries, a unique property of nanopore sequencing. Here we develop our adaptive sampling tool readfish to become "barcode-aware" enabling selection of different targets within barcoded samples or filtering out individual barcodes. We show that multiple human genomes can be assessed for copy number and structural variation on a single sequencing flow cell using sample specific customised target panels.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470722" rel="alternate" title="Barcode aware adaptive sampling for Oxford Nanopore sequencers. (62 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470653</id><title>The three-dimensional chromatin structure of the major human pancreatic cell types reveals lineage-specific regulatory architecture of T2D risk (25 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.148414+00:00</updated><author><name>Su Chun</name></author><author><name>Long Gao</name></author><author><name>Catherine L. May</name></author><author><name>James A. Pippin</name></author><author><name>Keith Boehm</name></author><author><name>Michelle Lee</name></author><author><name>Chengyang Liu</name></author><author><name>Matthew C. Pahl</name></author><author><name>Maria L. Golson</name></author><author><name>Ali Naji</name></author><author><name>Struan F.A. Grant</name></author><author><name>Andrew D. Wells</name></author><author><name>Klaus H. Kaestner</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Three-dimensional (3D) chromatin organization maps help to dissect cell type-specific gene regulatory programs. Furthermore, 3D chromatin maps have contributed to elucidating the pathogenesis of complex genetic diseases by connecting distal regulatory regions and genetic risk variants to their respective target genes. To understand the cell type-specific regulatory architecture of diabetes risk, we generated transcriptomic and 3D epigenomic profiles of human pancreatic acinar, alpha, and beta cells using single-cell RNA-seq, single-cell ATAC-seq, and high-resolution Hi-C of sorted cells. Comparisons of these profiles revealed differential A/B (open/closed) chromatin compartmentalization, chromatin looping, and control of cell type-specific gene regulatory programs. We identified a total of 1,094 putative causal-variant-target-gene pairs at 129 type 2 diabetes GWAS signals using pancreatic 3D chromatin maps. We found that the connections between candidate causal variants and their putative target effector genes are cell-type stratified and emphasize previously underappreciated roles for alpha and acinar cells in diabetes pathogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470653" rel="alternate" title="The three-dimensional chromatin structure of the major human pancreatic cell types reveals lineage-specific regulatory architecture of T2D risk (25 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470663</id><title>Epiphany: predicting Hi-C contact maps from 1D epigenomic signals (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.148746+00:00</updated><author><name>Rui Yang</name></author><author><name>Arnav Das</name></author><author><name>Vianne R. Gao</name></author><author><name>Alireza Karbalayghareh</name></author><author><name>William S. Noble</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey A. Bilmes</name></author><author><name>Christina S. Leslie</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent deep learning models that predict the Hi-C contact map from DNA sequence achieve promising accuracy but cannot generalize to new cell types and indeed do not capture cell-type-specific differences among training cell types. We propose Epiphany, a neural network to predict cell-type-specific Hi-C contact maps from five epigenomic tracks that are already available in hundreds of cell types and tissues: DNase I hypersensitive sites and ChIP-seq for CTCF, H3K27ac, H3K27me3, and H3K4me3. Epiphany uses 1D convolutional layers to learn local representations from the input tracks, a bidirectional long short-term memory (Bi-LSTM) layers to capture long term dependencies along the epigenome, as well as a generative adversarial network (GAN) architecture to encourage contact map realism. To improve the usability of predicted contact matrices, we trained and evaluated models using multiple normalization and matrix balancing techniques including KR, ICE, and HiC-DC+ Z-score and observed-over-expected count ratio. Epiphany is trained with a combination of MSE and adversarial (i.a., a GAN) loss to enhance its ability to produce realistic Hi-C contact maps for downstream analysis. Epiphany shows robust performance and generalization to held-out chromosomes within and across cell types and species, and its predicted contact matrices yield accurate TAD and significant interaction calls. At inference time, Epiphany can be used to study the contribution of specific epigenomic peaks to 3D architecture and to predict the structural changes caused by perturbations of epigenomic signals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470663" rel="alternate" title="Epiphany: predicting Hi-C contact maps from 1D epigenomic signals (10 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470807</id><title>Chromosome-level reference genomes for two strains of Caenorhabditis briggsae: an improved platform for comparative genomics (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.150142+00:00</updated><author><name>Lewis Stevens</name></author><author><name>Nicolas D. Moya</name></author><author><name>Robyn E. Tanny</name></author><author><name>Sophia B. Gibson</name></author><author><name>Alan Tracey</name></author><author><name>Huimin Na</name></author><author><name>Ye Zhan</name></author><author><name>Rojin Chitrakar</name></author><author><name>Job Dekker</name></author><author><name>Albertha J.M. Walhout</name></author><author><name>L. Ryan Baugh</name></author><author><name>Erik C. Andersen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The publication of the &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis briggsae&lt;/italic&gt; reference genome in 2003 enabled the first comparative genomics studies between &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;C. briggsae&lt;/italic&gt;, shedding light on the evolution of genome content and structure in the &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis&lt;/italic&gt; genus. However, despite being widely used, the currently available &lt;italic&gt;C. briggsae&lt;/italic&gt; reference genome is substantially less complete and structurally accurate than the &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; reference genome. Here, we used high-coverage Oxford Nanopore long-read and chromosome conformation capture data to generate chromosomally resolved reference genomes for two &lt;italic&gt;C. briggsae&lt;/italic&gt; strains: QX1410, a new reference strain closely related to the laboratory AF16 strain, and VX34, a highly divergent strain isolated in China. We also sequenced 99 recombinant inbred lines (RILs) generated from reciprocal crosses between QX1410 and VX34 to create a recombination map and identify chromosomal domains. Additionally, we used both short- and long-read RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) data to generate high-quality gene annotations. By comparing these new reference genomes to the current reference, we reveal that hyper-divergent haplotypes cover large portions of the &lt;italic&gt;C. briggsae&lt;/italic&gt; genome, similar to recent reports in &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;C. tropicalis&lt;/italic&gt;. We also show that the genomes of selfing &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis&lt;/italic&gt; species have undergone more rearrangement than their outcrossing relatives, which has biased previous estimates of rearrangement rate in &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis&lt;/italic&gt;. These new genomes provide a substantially improved platform for comparative genomics in &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis&lt;/italic&gt; and narrow the gap between the quality of genomic resources available for &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;C. briggsae&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470807" rel="alternate" title="Chromosome-level reference genomes for two strains of Caenorhabditis briggsae: an improved platform for comparative genomics (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470897</id><title>A 3’-end capture sequencing method for high-throughput targeted gene expression profiling (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.151928+00:00</updated><author><name>Eric de Bony</name></author><author><name>Fien Gysens</name></author><author><name>Nurten Yigit</name></author><author><name>Jasper Anckaert</name></author><author><name>Celine Everaert</name></author><author><name>Eveline Vanden Eynde</name></author><author><name>Kimberly Verniers</name></author><author><name>Willem Van Snippenberg</name></author><author><name>Wim Trypsteen</name></author><author><name>Pieter Mestdagh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Molecular phenotyping through shallow 3’-end RNA-sequencing workflows is increasingly applied in the context of large-scale chemical or genetic perturbation screens to study disease biology or support drug discovery. While these workflows enable accurate quantification of the most abundant genes, they are less effective for applications that require expression profiling of low abundant transcripts, like long non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs), or selected gene panels. To tackle these issues, we describe a workflow combining 3’-end library preparation with 3’-end hybrid capture probes and shallow RNA-sequencing for cost-effective, targeted quantification of subsets of (low abundant) genes across hundreds to thousands of samples. To assess the performance of the method, we designed a capture probe set for more than 100 mRNA and lncRNA target genes and applied the workflow to a cohort of 360 samples. When compared to standard 3’-end RNA-sequencing, 3’-end capture sequencing resulted in a more than 100-fold enrichment of target gene abundance while conserving relative inter-gene and inter-sample abundances. 3’-end RNA capture sequencing enables accurate targeted gene expression profiling at extremely shallow sequencing depth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470897" rel="alternate" title="A 3’-end capture sequencing method for high-throughput targeted gene expression profiling (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471111</id><title>A spatiotemporally resolved single cell atlas of the Plasmodium liver stage (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.152874+00:00</updated><author><name>Amichay Afriat</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Zuzarte-Luís</name></author><author><name>Keren Bahar Halpern</name></author><author><name>Lisa Buchauer</name></author><author><name>Sofia Marques</name></author><author><name>Aparajita Lahree</name></author><author><name>Ido Amit</name></author><author><name>Maria Manuel Mota</name></author><author><name>Shalev Itzkovitz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Malaria infection involves an obligatory, yet clinically silent liver stage. Hepatocytes operate in repeating units termed lobules, exhibiting heterogeneous gene expression patterns along the lobule axis, but the effects of hepatocyte zonation on parasite development have not been molecularly explored. Here, we combine single-cell RNA sequencing and single-molecule transcript imaging to characterize the host's and parasite's temporal expression programs in a zonally-controlled manner for the rodent malaria parasite &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium berghei&lt;/italic&gt; ANKA. We identify differences in parasite gene expression in distinct zones, and a sub-population of periportally-biased hepatocytes that harbor abortive infections associated with parasitophorous vacuole breakdown. These 'abortive hepatocytes' up-regulate immune recruitment and key signaling programs. They exhibit reduced levels of &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium&lt;/italic&gt; transcripts, perturbed parasite mRNA localization, and may give rise to progressively lower abundance of periportal infections. Our study provides a resource for understanding the liver stage of &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium&lt;/italic&gt; infection at high spatial resolution and highlights heterogeneous behavior of both the parasite and the host hepatocyte.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471111" rel="alternate" title="A spatiotemporally resolved single cell atlas of the Plasmodium liver stage (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470861</id><title>Detection of allele-specific expression in spatial transcriptomics with spASE (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.153271+00:00</updated><author><name>Luli S. Zou</name></author><author><name>Tongtong Zhao</name></author><author><name>Dylan M. Cable</name></author><author><name>Evan Murray</name></author><author><name>Martin J. Aryee</name></author><author><name>Fei Chen</name></author><author><name>Rafael A. Irizarry</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Allele-specific expression (ASE), or the preferential expression of one allele, can be observed in transcriptomics data from early development throughout the lifespan. However, the prevalence of spatial and cell type-specific ASE variation remains unclear. Spatial transcriptomics technologies permit the study of spatial ASE patterns genome-wide at near-single-cell resolution. However, the data are highly sparse, and confounding between cell type and spatial location present further statistical challenges. Here, we introduce spASE (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/lulizou/spase"&gt;https://github.com/lulizou/spase&lt;/ext-link&gt;), a computational framework for detecting spatial patterns in ASE within and across cell types from spatial transcriptomics data. To tackle the challenge presented by the low signal to noise ratio due to the sparsity of the data, we implement a spatial smoothing approach that greatly improves statistical power. We generated Slide-seqV2 data from the mouse hippocampus and detected ASE in X-chromosome genes, both within and across cell type, validating our ability to recover known ASE patterns. We demonstrate that our method can also identify cell type-specific effects, which we find can explain the majority of the spatial signal for autosomal genes. The findings facilitated by our method provide new insight into the uncharacterized landscape of spatial and cell type-specific ASE in the mouse hippocampus.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470861" rel="alternate" title="Detection of allele-specific expression in spatial transcriptomics with spASE (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470445</id><title>MaveDB v2: a curated community database with over three million variant effects from multiplexed functional assays (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.155255+00:00</updated><author><name>Alan F Rubin</name></author><author><name>Joseph K Min</name></author><author><name>Nathan J Rollins</name></author><author><name>Estelle Y Da</name></author><author><name>Daniel Esposito</name></author><author><name>Matthew Harrington</name></author><author><name>Jeremy Stone</name></author><author><name>Aisha Haley Bianchi</name></author><author><name>Yunfan Fu</name></author><author><name>Molly Gallaher</name></author><author><name>Iris Li</name></author><author><name>Olivia Moscatelli</name></author><author><name>Jesslyn YL Ong</name></author><author><name>Joshua E Rollins</name></author><author><name>Matthew J Wakefield</name></author><author><name>Shenyi “Sunny” Ye</name></author><author><name>Amy Tam</name></author><author><name>Abbye E McEwen</name></author><author><name>Lea M Starita</name></author><author><name>Vanessa L Bryant</name></author><author><name>Debora S Marks</name></author><author><name>Douglas M Fowler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A central problem in genomics is understanding the effect of individual DNA variants. Multiplexed Assays of Variant Effect (MAVEs) can help address this challenge by measuring all possible single nucleotide variant effects in a gene or regulatory sequence simultaneously. Here we describe MaveDB v2, which has become the database of record for MAVEs. MaveDB now contains a large fraction of published studies, comprising over two hundred datasets and three million variant effect measurements. We created tools and APIs to streamline data submission and access, transforming MaveDB into a hub for the analysis and dissemination of these impactful datasets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470445" rel="alternate" title="MaveDB v2: a curated community database with over three million variant effects from multiplexed functional assays (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470420</id><title>Gut transcriptome reveals differential gene expression and enriched pathways linked to immune activation in response to weaning in pigs (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.155996+00:00</updated><author><name>M. Le Bon</name></author><author><name>S. Tötemeyer</name></author><author><name>R. D. Emes</name></author><author><name>K. H. Mellits</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Weaning represents one of the most critical periods in pig production associated with increase in disease risk, reduction in performance and economic loss. Physiological changes faced by piglets during the weaning period have been well characterised, however little is currently known about the underlying molecular pathways involved in these processes. As pig meat remains one of the most consumed sources of protein worldwide, understanding how these changes are mediated is critical to improve pig production and consequently sustainable food production globally. In this study, we evaluated the effect of weaning on transcriptomic changes in the colon of healthy piglets over time using an RNA-sequencing approach.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The findings revealed a complex and coordinated response to weaning with the majority of genes found to be rapidly differentially expressed within one day post weaning. Multiple genes and pathways affected by weaning in the colon were associated with immune regulation, cell signalling and bacterial defence. NOD-like receptors, Toll-like receptor and JAK-STAT signalling pathways were amongst the pathways significantly enriched. Immune activation was evidenced by the enrichment of pathways involved in interferon response, cytokines interactions, oxidoreductase activities and response to microbial invasion. Biosynthesis of amino acids, in particular arginine, was also amongst the most enriched KEGG pathways in weaned pigs, reinforcing the critical role of arginine in gut homeostasis under stress conditions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overall, transcriptomic and physiological results suggest that pigs going through the weaning transition undergo a transient period of inflammatory state with a temporary breakdown of barrier functions in the gut. These findings could provide valuable tools to monitor host response post weaning, and may be of particular relevance for the investigation and development of intervention strategies aimed to reduce antibiotic use and improve pig health and performance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470420" rel="alternate" title="Gut transcriptome reveals differential gene expression and enriched pathways linked to immune activation in response to weaning in pigs (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>