<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.517282+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.30.458233</id><title>Temporal inhibition of chromatin looping and enhancer accessibility during neuronal remodeling (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.517800+00:00</updated><author><name>Dahong Chen</name></author><author><name>Catherine E. McManus</name></author><author><name>Behram Radmanesh</name></author><author><name>Leah H. Matzat</name></author><author><name>Elissa P. Lei</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During development, looping of an enhancer to a promoter is frequently observed in conjunction with temporal and tissue-specific transcriptional activation. The chromatin insulator-associated protein Shep promotes &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; post-mitotic neuronal remodeling by repressing transcription of master developmental regulators, such as &lt;italic&gt;brain tumor&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;brat&lt;/italic&gt;), specifically in maturing neurons. Since insulator proteins can promote looping, we hypothesized that Shep antagonizes &lt;italic&gt;brat&lt;/italic&gt; promoter interaction with an as yet unidentified enhancer. Using chromatin conformation capture and reporter assays, we identified two novel enhancer regions that increase in looping frequency with the &lt;italic&gt;brat&lt;/italic&gt; promoter specifically in pupal brains after Shep depletion. The &lt;italic&gt;brat&lt;/italic&gt; promoters and enhancers function independently of Shep, ruling out direct repression of these elements. Moreover, ATAC-seq in isolated neurons demonstrated that Shep restricts chromatin accessibility of a key &lt;italic&gt;brat&lt;/italic&gt; enhancer as well as other enhancers genome-wide in remodeling pupal but not larval neurons. These enhancers are enriched for chromatin targets of Shep and are located at Shep-inhibited genes, suggesting direct Shep inhibition of enhancer accessibility and gene expression during neuronal remodeling. Our results provide evidence for temporal regulation of chromatin looping and enhancer accessibility during neuronal maturation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.30.458233" rel="alternate" title="Temporal inhibition of chromatin looping and enhancer accessibility during neuronal remodeling (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.30.458145</id><title>Dicer-to-Argonaute switch controls biogenesis of oncogenic miRNA (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.518224+00:00</updated><author><name>L. Winchester</name></author><author><name>L. van Bijsterveldt</name></author><author><name>A. Dhawan</name></author><author><name>S. Wigfield</name></author><author><name>C. Triantafyllidis</name></author><author><name>S. Haider</name></author><author><name>A. McIntyre</name></author><author><name>T.C. Humphrey</name></author><author><name>A.L. Harris</name></author><author><name>F.M. Buffa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;miRNAs are post-transcriptional regulators of gene expression, controlling biological processes from development to pathogenesis. We asked whether the reshaped functional miRNA landscape in cancers is driven by altered transcription of its precursors, or altered biogenesis and maturation of miRNAs. Integrated analysis of genomic and transcriptomic data in 9,111 samples across 10 cancer types and healthy tissues revealed a recurrent genomic switch from DICER-dependent to non-canonical Argonaute-mediated, DICER-independent, miRNA biogenesis. Experimental validation in AGO2-amplified clinical samples and cancer cell lines confirmed that canonical miRNAs can undergo maturation in a DICER-independent manner, and that elevated Argonaute levels promote selective maturation of the oncogenic miR-106b/25 cluster as shown by the altered ratio of mature miRNA to immature pri-miRNA levels. The preferential maturation of these oncogenic miRNAs, whose processing bypasses DICER1, promotes cancer progression and predicts poor prognosis. This highlights the evolution of non-canonical AGO2-dependent oncomiR processing as a novel driver pathway in cancer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.30.458145" rel="alternate" title="Dicer-to-Argonaute switch controls biogenesis of oncogenic miRNA (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>