<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.837132+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.16.463767</id><title>Genomic insights into the population history and biological adaptation of Southwestern Chinese Hmong-Mien people (25 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.837475+00:00</updated><author><name>Yan Yan Liu</name></author><author><name>Mengge Wang</name></author><author><name>Changhui Liu</name></author><author><name>Jingrong Zhu</name></author><author><name>Xing Zou</name></author><author><name>Wenshan Li</name></author><author><name>Lin Lin Wang</name></author><author><name>Cuo Leng</name></author><author><name>Quyi Xu</name></author><author><name>Hui-Yuan Yeh</name></author><author><name>Chuan-Chao Wang</name></author><author><name>Xiaohong Wen</name></author><author><name>Chao Liu</name></author><author><name>Guanglin He</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hmong-Mien-speaking (HM) populations, widely distributed in South China, North of Thailand, Laos and Vietnam, have experienced different settlement environments, dietary habits and pathogen exposure. However, their specific biological adaptation also remained largely uncharacterized, which is important in the population evolutionary genetics and Trans-Omics for regional Precision Medicine. Besides, the origin and genetic diversity of HM people and their phylogenetic relationship with surrounding modern and ancient populations are unknown. Here, we reported genome-wide SNPs in 52 representative Miao people and combined them with 144 HM people from 13 geographically representative populations to characterize the full genetic admixture and adaptive landscape of HM speakers. We found that obvious genetic substructures existed in geographically different HM populations and also identified one new ancestral lineage specifically exited in HM people, which spatially distributed from Sichuan and Guizhou in the North to Thailand in the South and temporally dated to at least 500 years. The sharing patterns of the newly-identified homogeneous ancestry component combined the estimated admixture times via the decay of Linkage Disequilibrium and haplotype sharing in GLOBETROTTER suggested that the modern HM-speaking populations originated from Southwest China and migrated southward recently, which is consistent with the reconstructed phenomena of linguistic and archeological documents. Additionally, we identified specific adaptive signatures associated with several important human nervous system biological functions. Our pilot work emphasized the importance of anthropologically-informed sampling and deeply genetic structure reconstruction via whole-genome sequencing in the next step in the deep Chinese population genomic diversity project (CPGDP), especially in the ethnolinguistic regions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.16.463767" rel="alternate" title="Genomic insights into the population history and biological adaptation of Southwestern Chinese Hmong-Mien people (25 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464112</id><title>In vivo versus in silico assessment of potentially pathogenic missense variants in human reproductive genes (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.837760+00:00</updated><author><name>Xinbao Ding</name></author><author><name>Priti Singh</name></author><author><name>Tina N. Tran</name></author><author><name>Robert Fragoza</name></author><author><name>Haiyuan Yu</name></author><author><name>John C. Schimenti</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Infertility is a highly heterogeneous condition, with genetic causes estimated to be involved in approximately half of the cases. High-throughput sequencing (HTS) approaches are becoming an increasingly important tool for genetic diagnosis of diseases, including idiopathic infertility. Nevertheless, most rare or minor alleles revealed by HTS are classified as variants of uncertain significance (VUS). Interpreting the functional impacts of VUS is challenging but profoundly important for clinical management and genetic counseling. To determine the consequences of segregating polymorphisms in key fertility genes, we functionally evaluated 8 missense variants in the genes &lt;italic&gt;ANKRD31&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;BRDT&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;DMC1&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;EXOI&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;FKBP6&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;MSH4&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;SEPT12&lt;/italic&gt; by generating genome-edited mouse models. Six variants were classified as deleterious by most functional prediction algorithms, and two disrupted a protein-protein interaction in the yeast 2 hybrid assay. Even though these genes are known to be essential for normal meiosis or spermiogenesis in mice, none of the tested human variants compromised fertility or gametogenesis in the mouse models. These results should be useful for genetic diagnoses of infertile patients, but they also underscore the need for more effective VUS categorization. To this end, we evaluated the performance of 10 widely used pathogenicity prediction algorithms in classifying missense variants within fertility-related genes from two sources: 1) the ClinVar database, and 2) those functionally tested in mice. We found that all the algorithms performed poorly in terms of predicting phenotypes of mouse-modeled variants. These studies highlight the importance of functional validation of potential infertility-causing genetic variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464112" rel="alternate" title="In vivo versus in silico assessment of potentially pathogenic missense variants in human reproductive genes (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.463977</id><title>The Nup2 meiotic-autonomous region relieves autoinhibition of Nup60 to promote progression of meiosis and sporulation in Saccharomyces cerevisiae (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.837948+00:00</updated><author><name>Kelly Komachi</name></author><author><name>Sean M. Burgess</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During meiosis, chromosomes undergo dramatic changes in structural organization, nuclear positioning, and motion. Although the nuclear pore complex has been shown to affect genome organization and function in vegetative cells, its role in meiotic chromosome dynamics has remained largely unexplored. Recent work in the budding yeast &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; demonstrated that the mobile nucleoporin Nup2 is required for normal progression through meiosis I prophase and sporulation in strains where telomere-led chromosome movement has been compromised. The meiotic autonomous region (MAR), a short fragment of Nup2 responsible for its role in meiosis, was shown to localize to the nuclear envelope via Nup60 and to bind to meiotic chromosomes. To understand the relative contribution these two activities have on MAR function, we first carried out a screen for MAR mutants defective in sporulation and found that all the mutations disrupt interaction with both Nup60 and meiotic chromosomes. Moreover, &lt;italic&gt;nup60&lt;/italic&gt; mutants phenocopy &lt;italic&gt;nup2&lt;/italic&gt; mutants, exhibiting similar nuclear division kinetics, sporulation efficiencies, and genetic interactions with mutations that affect the telomere bouquet. Although full-length Nup60 requires Nup2 for function, removal of Nup60’s C-terminus allows Nup60 to bind meiotic chromosomes and promote sporulation without Nup2. In contrast, binding of the MAR to meiotic chromosomes is completely dependent on Nup60. Our findings uncover an inhibitory function for the Nup60 C-terminus and suggest that Nup60 mediates recruitment of meiotic chromosomes to the nuclear envelope, while Nup2 plays a secondary role counteracting Nup60’s autoinhibition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.463977" rel="alternate" title="The Nup2 meiotic-autonomous region relieves autoinhibition of Nup60 to promote progression of meiosis and sporulation in Saccharomyces cerevisiae (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.11.463689</id><title>Mutating novel interaction sites in NRP1 reduces SARS-CoV-2 spike protein internalization (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.838103+00:00</updated><author><name>Debjani Pal</name></author><author><name>Kuntal De</name></author><author><name>Timothy B. Yates</name></author><author><name>Wellington Muchero</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The global pandemic of Coronavirus disease 2019 caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 has become a severe global health problem because of its rapid spread(&lt;italic&gt;1&lt;/italic&gt;). Both angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 and neuropilin 1 provide initial viral binding sites for SARS-CoV-2 (&lt;italic&gt;2, 3&lt;/italic&gt;). Here, we show that three cysteine residues located in a1/a2 and b1 domains of neuropilin 1 are necessary for SARS-CoV-2 spike protein internalization in human cells. Mutating cysteines C82, C104 and C147 altered neuropilin 1 stability and binding ability as well as cellular internalization and lysosomal translocation of the spike protein. This resulted in up to 4 times reduction in spike protein load in cells for the original, alpha and delta SARS-CoV-2 variants even in the presence of the endogenous angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 receptor. Transcriptome analysis of cells transfected with mutated NRP1 revealed significantly reduced expression of genes involved in viral infection and replication, including eight members of the ribosomal protein L, ten members of ribosomal protein S and five members of the proteasome β subunit family proteins. We also observed higher expression of genes involved in suppression of inflammation and endoplasmic reticulum associated degradation. These observations suggest that these cysteines offer viable targets for therapies against COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.11.463689" rel="alternate" title="Mutating novel interaction sites in NRP1 reduces SARS-CoV-2 spike protein internalization (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464059</id><title>New cycle, same old mistakes? Overlapping vs. discrete generations in long-term recurrent selection (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.838280+00:00</updated><author><name>Marlee R. Labroo</name></author><author><name>Jessica E. Rutkoski</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recurrent selection is a foundational breeding method for quantitative trait improvement. It typically features rapid breeding cycles that can lead to high rates of genetic gain. In recurrent phenotypic selection, generations do not overlap, which means that breeding candidates are evaluated and considered for selection for only one cycle. With recurrent genomic selection, candidates can be evaluated based on genomic estimated breeding values indefinitely, therefore facilitating overlapping generations. Candidates with true high breeding values that were discarded in one cycle due to underestimation of breeding value could be identified and selected in subsequent cycles. The consequences of allowing generations to overlap in recurrent selection are unknown. We assessed whether maintaining overlapping and discrete generations led to differences in genetic gain for phenotypic, genomic truncation, and genomic optimum contribution recurrent selection by simulation of traits with various heritabilities and genetic architectures across fifty breeding cycles. We also assessed differences of overlapping and discrete generations in a conventional breeding scheme with multiple stages and cohorts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;With phenotypic selection, overlapping generations led to decreased genetic gain compared to discrete generations due to increased selection error bias. Selected individuals, which were in the upper tail of the distribution of phenotypic values, tended to also have high absolute error relative to their true breeding value compared to the overall population. Without repeated phenotyping, these individuals erroneously believed to have high value were repeatedly selected across cycles, leading to decreased genetic gain. With genomic truncation selection, overlapping and discrete generations performed similarly as updating breeding values precluded repeatedly selecting individuals with inaccurately high estimates of breeding values in subsequent cycles. Overlapping generations did not outperform discrete generations in the presence of a positive genetic trend with genomic truncation selection, as past generations had lower mean genetic values than the current generation of selection candidates. With genomic optimum contribution selection, overlapping and discrete generations performed similarly, but overlapping generations slightly outperformed discrete generations in the long term if the targeted inbreeding rate was extremely low.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Maintaining discrete generations in recurrent phenotypic selection leads to increased genetic gain, especially at low heritabilities, by preventing selection error bias. With genomic truncation selection and genomic optimum contribution selection, genetic gain does not differ between discrete and overlapping generations assuming non-genetic effects are not present. Overlapping generations may increase genetic gain in the long term with very low targeted rates of inbreeding in genomic optimum contribution selection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464059" rel="alternate" title="New cycle, same old mistakes? Overlapping vs. discrete generations in long-term recurrent selection (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>