<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.251745+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457153</id><title>Loops, TADs, Compartments, and Territories are Elastic and Robust to Dramatic Nuclear Volume Swelling (56 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.252213+00:00</updated><author><name>Jacob T. Sanders</name></author><author><name>Rosela Golloshi</name></author><author><name>Peyton H. Terry</name></author><author><name>Darrian G. Nash</name></author><author><name>Yang Xu</name></author><author><name>Job Dekker</name></author><author><name>Rachel Patton McCord</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Layers of genome organization are becoming increasingly better characterized, but less is known about how these structures respond to perturbation or shape changes. Low-salt swelling of isolated chromatin fibers or nuclei has been used for decades to investigate the structural properties of chromatin. But, visible changes in chromatin appearance have not been linked to known building blocks of genome structure or features along the genome sequence. We combine low-salt swelling of isolated nuclei with genome-wide chromosome conformation capture (Hi-C) and imaging approaches to probe the effects of chromatin extension genome-wide. Photoconverted patterns on nuclei during expansion and contraction indicate that global genome structure is preserved after dramatic nuclear volume swelling, suggesting a highly elastic chromosome topology. Hi-C experiments before, during, and after nuclear swelling show changes in average contact probabilities at short length scales, reflecting the extension of the local chromatin fiber. But, surprisingly, during this large increase in nuclear volume, there is a striking maintenance of loops, TADs, active and inactive compartments, and chromosome territories. Subtle differences after expansion are observed, suggesting that the local chromatin state, protein interactions, and location in the nucleus can affect how strongly a given structure is maintained under stress. From these observations, we propose that genome topology is robust to extension of the chromatin fiber and isotropic shape change, and that this elasticity may be beneficial in physiological circumstances of changes in nuclear size and volume.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457153" rel="alternate" title="Loops, TADs, Compartments, and Territories are Elastic and Robust to Dramatic Nuclear Volume Swelling (56 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>