<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.419885+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.472354</id><title>Haplotype-resolved inversion landscape reveals hotspots of mutational recurrence associated with genomic disorders (56 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.420327+00:00</updated><author><name>David Porubsky</name></author><author><name>Wolfram Höps</name></author><author><name>Hufsah Ashraf</name></author><author><name>PingHsun Hsieh</name></author><author><name>Bernardo Rodriguez-Martin</name></author><author><name>Feyza Yilmaz</name></author><author><name>Jana Ebler</name></author><author><name>Pille Hallast</name></author><author><name>Flavia Angela Maria Maggiolini</name></author><author><name>William T. Harvey</name></author><author><name>Barbara Henning</name></author><author><name>Peter A. Audano</name></author><author><name>David S. Gordon</name></author><author><name>Peter Ebert</name></author><author><name>Patrick Hasenfeld</name></author><author><name>Eva Benito</name></author><author><name>Qihui Zhu</name></author><author><name>Charles Lee</name></author><author><name>Francesca Antonacci</name></author><author><name>Matthias Steinrücken</name></author><author><name>Christine R. Beck</name></author><author><name>Ashley D. Sanders</name></author><author><name>Tobias Marschall</name></author><author><name>Evan E. Eichler</name></author><author><name>Jan O. Korbel</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Unlike copy number variants (CNVs), inversions remain an underexplored genetic variation class. By integrating multiple genomic technologies, we discover 729 inversions in 41 human genomes. Approximately 85% of inversions &amp;lt;2 kbp form by twin-priming during L1-retrotransposition; 80% of the larger inversions are balanced and affect twice as many base pairs as CNVs. Balanced inversions show an excess of common variants, and 72% are flanked by segmental duplications (SDs) or mobile elements. Since this suggests recurrence due to non-allelic homologous recombination, we developed complementary approaches to identify recurrent inversion formation. We describe 40 recurrent inversions encompassing 0.6% of the genome, showing inversion rates up to 2.7×10&lt;sup&gt;-4&lt;/sup&gt; per locus and generation. Recurrent inversions exhibit a sex- chromosomal bias, and significantly co-localize to the critical regions of genomic disorders. We propose that inversion recurrence results in an elevated number of heterozygous carriers and structural SD diversity, which increases mutability in the population and predisposes to disease- causing CNVs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.472354" rel="alternate" title="Haplotype-resolved inversion landscape reveals hotspots of mutational recurrence associated with genomic disorders (56 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473377</id><title>Simultaneous CUT&amp;Tag profiling of the accessible and silenced regulome in single cells (35 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.420780+00:00</updated><author><name>Derek H. Janssens</name></author><author><name>Dominik J. Otto</name></author><author><name>Michael P. Meers</name></author><author><name>Manu Setty</name></author><author><name>Kami Ahmad</name></author><author><name>Steven Henikoff</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cleavage Under Targets &amp;amp; Tagmentation (CUT&amp;amp;Tag) is an antibody-directed transposase tethering strategy for &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; chromatin profiling in small samples and single cells. We describe a modified CUT&amp;amp;Tag protocol using a mixture of an antibody to the initiation form of RNA Polymerase II (Pol2 Serine-5 phosphate) and an antibody to repressive Polycomb domains (H3K27me3) followed by computational signal deconvolution to produce high-resolution maps of both the active and repressive regulomes in single cells. The ability to seamlessly map active promoters, enhancers and repressive regulatory elements using a single workflow provides a complete regulome profiling strategy suitable for high-throughput single-cell platforms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473377" rel="alternate" title="Simultaneous CUT&amp;Tag profiling of the accessible and silenced regulome in single cells (35 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473345</id><title>Estimating human mobility in Holocene Western Eurasia with large-scale ancient genomic data (33 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.420998+00:00</updated><author><name>Clemens Schmid</name></author><author><name>Stephan Schiffels</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The recent increase in openly available ancient human DNA samples allows for new, large-scale meta analysis applications. Trans-generational past human mobility is one of the key aspects that ancient genomics can contribute to, since changes in ancestry – unlike cultural changes seen in the archaeological record – necessarily reflect movements of people. Here we present a new algorithm to quantify past human mobility from large ancient genomic datasets. The key idea of the method is for each individual to compare a hypothetical genetic “origin” point with its actual burial point in space. This is achieved by first creating an interpolated ancestry field through space and time based on Multidimensional scaling and Gaussian process regression, and then using this field to map the ancient individuals into space according to their genetic profile. We apply this new algorithm to a dataset of 3191 aDNA samples with genome-wide data from Western Eurasia in the last 10,000 years and derive a diachronic measure of mobility for subregions in Western, Central, Southern and Eastern Europe. For regions and periods with sufficient data coverage, our mobility estimates show general concordance with previous results, but also reveal new signals of movements beyond the well-known key events.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ancient human DNA (aDNA) extracted from archaeological contexts (e.g. burials) allows to reconstruct past population movements. Relevant methods work by calculating proportions of shared ancestry among individuals or groups in order to answer specific, regional research questions. Here, we propose a largescale algorithm to quantify human mobility through time and space using bulk aDNA data. The algorithm has two core components: i) Interpolation of the spatio-temporal distribution of genetic ancestry to obtain a continuous ancestry information field and ii) estimation of the spatial origin of each input sample by projecting its ancestry into this field. We apply this to thousands of published genomic samples in the last 10,000 years to trace diachronic mobility patterns across Western Eurasia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473345" rel="alternate" title="Estimating human mobility in Holocene Western Eurasia with large-scale ancient genomic data (33 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473199</id><title>The origins and functional effects of postzygotic mutations throughout the human lifespan (32 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.421165+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicole B. Rockweiler</name></author><author><name>Avinash Ramu</name></author><author><name>Liina Nagirnaja</name></author><author><name>Wing H. Wong</name></author><author><name>Michiel J. Noordam</name></author><author><name>Casey W. Drubin</name></author><author><name>Ni Huang</name></author><author><name>Brian Miller</name></author><author><name>Ellen Z. Todres</name></author><author><name>Katinka A. Vigh-Conrad</name></author><author><name>Antonino Zito</name></author><author><name>Kerrin S. Small</name></author><author><name>Kristin G. Ardlie</name></author><author><name>Barak A. Cohen</name></author><author><name>Donald F. Conrad</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Postzygotic mutations (PZMs) begin to accrue in the human genome immediately after fertilization, but how and when PZMs affect development and lifetime health remains unclear. To study the origins and functional consequences of PZMs, we generated a multi-tissue atlas of PZMs from 948 donors using the final major release of the Genotype-Tissue Expression (GTEx) project. Nearly half the variation in mutation burden among tissue samples can be explained by measured technical and biological effects, while 9% can be attributed to donor-specific effects. Through phylogenetic reconstruction of PZMs, we find that their type and predicted functional impact varies during prenatal development, across tissues, and the germ cell lifecycle. Remarkably, a class of prenatal mutations was predicted to be more deleterious than any other category of genetic variation investigated and under positive selection as strong as somatic mutations in cancers. In total, the data indicate that PZMs can contribute to phenotypic variation throughout the human lifespan, and, to better understand the relationship between genotype and phenotype, we must broaden the long-held assumption of one genome per individual to multiple, dynamic genomes per individual.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The predicted rates, functional effects and selection pressure of postzygotic mutations vary through the human lifecycle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473199" rel="alternate" title="The origins and functional effects of postzygotic mutations throughout the human lifespan (32 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473906</id><title>Heterogeneity and genomic loci of ubiquitous Cre reporter transgenes in zebrafish (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.421689+00:00</updated><author><name>Robert L. Lalonde</name></author><author><name>Cassie L. Kemmler</name></author><author><name>Frederike W. Riemslagh</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Aman</name></author><author><name>Jelena Kresoja-Rakic</name></author><author><name>Hannah R. Moran</name></author><author><name>Susan Nieuwenhuize</name></author><author><name>David M. Parichy</name></author><author><name>Alexa Burger</name></author><author><name>Christian Mosimann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The most-common strategy for zebrafish Cre/lox-mediated lineage labeling experiments combines ubiquitously expressed, lox-based Switch reporter transgenes with tissue-specific Cre or 4-OH-Tamoxifen-inducible CreERT2 driver lines. Although numerous Cre driver lines have been produced, only a few broadly expressed Switch reporters exist in zebrafish and their generation by random transgene integration has been challenging due to position-effect sensitivity of the lox-flanked recombination cassettes. Here, we compare commonly used Switch reporter lines for their recombination efficiency and reporter expression pattern during zebrafish development. Using different experimental setups, we show that ubi:Switch and hsp70l:Switch outperform current generations of two additional Switch reporters due to favorable transgene integration sites. Our comparisons also document preferential Cre-dependent recombination of ubi:Switch and hsp70l:Switch in distinct zebrafish tissues at early developmental stages. To investigate what genomic features may influence Cre accessibility and lox recombination efficiency in highly functional Switch lines, we mapped these transgenes and charted chromatin dynamics at their integration sites. Our data documents the heterogeneity among lox-based Switch transgenes towards informing suitable transgene selection for lineage labeling experiments. Our work further proposes that ubi:Switch and hsp70l:Switch define genomic integration sites suitable for universal transgene or switch reporter knock-in in zebrafish.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473906" rel="alternate" title="Heterogeneity and genomic loci of ubiquitous Cre reporter transgenes in zebrafish (30 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473890</id><title>A Single-copy Knock In Translating Ribosome ImmunoPrecipitation (SKI TRIP) tool kit for tissue specific profiling of actively translated mRNAs in C. elegans (25 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.422075+00:00</updated><author><name>Laura E. Wester</name></author><author><name>Anne Lanjuin</name></author><author><name>Emanuel H. W. Bruckisch</name></author><author><name>Maria C. Perez Matos</name></author><author><name>Caroline Heintz</name></author><author><name>Martin S. Denzel</name></author><author><name>William B. Mair</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Translating Ribosome Affinity Purification (TRAP) methods have emerged as a powerful approach to profile actively translated transcripts in specific cell and tissue types. Epitope tagged ribosomal subunits are expressed in defined cell populations and used to pull down ribosomes and their associated mRNAs, providing a snapshot of cell type-specific translation occurring in that space and time. Current TRAP toolkits available to the &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; community have been built using multi-copy arrays, randomly integrated in the genome. Here we introduce a &lt;underline&gt;S&lt;/underline&gt;ingle-copy &lt;underline&gt;K&lt;/underline&gt;nock In &lt;underline&gt;T&lt;/underline&gt;ranslating &lt;underline&gt;R&lt;/underline&gt;ibosome Immuno&lt;underline&gt;P&lt;/underline&gt;recipitation (SKI TRIP) tool kit, a collection of &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; strains engineered by CRISPR in which tissue specific expression of FLAG tagged ribosomal subunit protein RPL-22 is driven by cassettes present in single copy from defined sites in the genome. In depth characterization of the SKI TRIP strains and methodology shows that 3xFLAG tagged RPL-22 expressed from its endogenous locus or within defined cell types incorporates into actively translating ribosomes and can be used to efficiently and cleanly pull-down cell type specific transcripts without impacting overall mRNA translation or fitness of the animal. We propose SKI TRIP use for the study of processes that are acutely sensitive to changes in translation, such as aging.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473890" rel="alternate" title="A Single-copy Knock In Translating Ribosome ImmunoPrecipitation (SKI TRIP) tool kit for tissue specific profiling of actively translated mRNAs in C. elegans (25 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473632</id><title>Expanded FLP toolbox for spatiotemporal protein degradation and transcriptomic profiling in C. elegans (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.422290+00:00</updated><author><name>Adrián Fragoso-Luna</name></author><author><name>Cristina Ayuso</name></author><author><name>Michael Eibl</name></author><author><name>Celia Muñoz-Jiménez</name></author><author><name>Vladimir Benes</name></author><author><name>Ildefonso Cases</name></author><author><name>Peter Askjaer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Control of gene expression in specific tissues and/or at certain stages of development allows the study and manipulation of gene function with high precision. Site-specific genome recombination by the Flippase (FLP) and Cre enzymes has proven particularly relevant. Joint efforts of many research groups have led to the creation of efficient FLP and Cre drivers to regulate gene expression in a variety of tissues in &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans.&lt;/italic&gt; Here, we extend this toolkit by the addition of FLP lines that drive recombination specifically in distal tip cells, the somatic gonad, coelomocytes and the epithelial P lineage. In some cases, recombination-mediated gene knockouts do not completely deplete protein levels due to persistence of long-lived proteins. To overcome this, we developed a spatiotemporally regulated degradation system for GFP fusion proteins (GFPdeg) based on FLP-mediated recombination. Using two stable nuclear pore proteins, MEL-28/ELYS and NPP-2/NUP85 as examples, we report the benefit of combining tissue-specific gene knockout and protein degradation to achieve complete protein depletion. We also demonstrate that FLP-mediated recombination can be utilized to identify nascent transcripts in a tissue of interest. We have adapted thiol(SH)-linked alkylation for the metabolic sequencing of RNA in tissue (SLAM-ITseq) for &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans.&lt;/italic&gt; By focusing on a well-characterized tissue, the hypodermis, we show that the vast majority of genes identified by SLAM-ITseq are known to be expressed in this tissue, but with the added value of temporal resolution. These tools allow combining FLP activity for simultaneous gene inactivation and transcriptomic profiling, thus enabling the inquiry of gene function in various complex biological processes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473632" rel="alternate" title="Expanded FLP toolbox for spatiotemporal protein degradation and transcriptomic profiling in C. elegans (24 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.472248</id><title>Variant-to-gene-mapping followed by cross-species genetic screening identifies GPI-anchor biosynthesis as novel regulator of sleep (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.422603+00:00</updated><author><name>Justin Palermo</name></author><author><name>Alessandra Chesi</name></author><author><name>Amber Zimmerman</name></author><author><name>Shilpa Sonti</name></author><author><name>Chiara Lasconi</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth B. Brown</name></author><author><name>James A. Pippin</name></author><author><name>Andrew D. Wells</name></author><author><name>Fusun Doldur-Balli</name></author><author><name>Diego R. Mazzotti</name></author><author><name>Allan I. Pack</name></author><author><name>Phillip R. Gehrman</name></author><author><name>Struan F.A. Grant</name></author><author><name>Alex C. Keene</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sleep is nearly ubiquitous throughout the animal kingdom, with deficiencies in sleep having been linked to a wide range of human disorders and diseases. While genome wide association studies (GWAS) in humans have identified loci robustly associated with several heritable diseases or traits, little is known about the functional roles of the underlying causal variants in regulating sleep duration or quality. We applied an ATAC-seq/promoter focused Capture C strategy in human iPSC-derived neural progenitors to carry out a ‘variant-to-gene’ mapping campaign that identified 88 candidate sleep effector genes connected to relevant GWAS signals. To functionally validate the role of the implicated effector genes in sleep regulation, we performed a neuron-specific RNAi screen in the fruit fly, &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt;. This approach identified a number of genes that regulated sleep, including phosphatidylinositol N-acetylglucosaminyltransferase subunit Q (&lt;italic&gt;PIG-Q&lt;/italic&gt;), a gene that encodes an enzyme involved in the first step of glycosylphosphatidylinositol (GPI)- anchor biosynthesis. We show that flies deficient for &lt;italic&gt;PIG-Q&lt;/italic&gt; have longer sleep during both day and night due to an increase in the total number of sleep bouts. Subsequent systematic investigation of other PIG-family genes identified increased sleep in flies for multiple different genes within the PIG pathway. We then mutated the &lt;italic&gt;PIG-Q&lt;/italic&gt; locus in zebrafish and identified similar increases in sleep to those observed in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt;, confirming deep homology of &lt;italic&gt;PIG-Q&lt;/italic&gt; mediated sleep regulation. These results provide the first physical variant-to-gene mapping of human sleep genes followed by a model organism-based prioritization, revealing a novel and conserved role for GPI-anchor biosynthesis in sleep regulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.472248" rel="alternate" title="Variant-to-gene-mapping followed by cross-species genetic screening identifies GPI-anchor biosynthesis as novel regulator of sleep (20 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473429</id><title>hapCon: Estimating contamination of ancient genomes by copying from reference haplotypes (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.422861+00:00</updated><author><name>Yilei Huang</name></author><author><name>Harald Ringbauer</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Motivation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Human ancient DNA (aDNA) studies have surged in recent years, revolutionizing the study of the human past. Typically, aDNA is preserved poorly, making such data prone to contamination from other human DNA. Therefore, it is important to rule out substantial contamination before proceeding to downstream analysis. As most aDNA samples can only be sequenced to low coverages (&amp;lt;1x average depth), computational methods that can robustly estimate contamination in the low coverage regime are needed. However, the ultra low-coverage regime (0.1x and below) remains a challenging task for existing approaches.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present a new method to estimate contamination in aDNA for male individuals. It utilizes a Li&amp;amp;Stephen’s haplotype copying model for haploid X chromosomes, with mismatches modelled as genotyping error or contamination. We assessed an implementation of this new approach, hapCon, on simulated and down-sampled empirical aDNA data. Our results demonstrate that hapCon outperforms a commonly used tool for estimating male X contamination (ANGSD), with substantially lower variance and narrower confidence intervals, especially in the low coverage regime. We found that hapCon provides useful contamination estimates for coverages as low as 0.1x for SNP capture data (1240k) and 0.02x for whole genome sequencing data (WGS), substantially extending the coverage limit of previous male X chromosome based contamination estimation methods.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability and Implementation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A implementation of our software (hapCON) using Python and C has been deposited at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/hyl317/hapROH"&gt;https://github.com/hyl317/hapROH&lt;/ext-link&gt;. We make hapCon available as part of a python package (hapROH), which is available at the Python Package Index (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pypi.org/project/hapROH"&gt;https://pypi.org/project/hapROH&lt;/ext-link&gt;) and can be installed via pip. The documentation provides example use cases as blueprints for custom applications (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://haproh.readthedocs.io"&gt;https://haproh.readthedocs.io&lt;/ext-link&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473429" rel="alternate" title="hapCon: Estimating contamination of ancient genomes by copying from reference haplotypes (16 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473932</id><title>Transcriptome-wide analysis of microRNA-mRNA correlations in unperturbed tissue transcriptomes identifies microRNA targeting determinants. (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.423020+00:00</updated><author><name>Juan Manuel Trinidad</name></author><author><name>Rafael Sebastian Fort</name></author><author><name>Guillermo Trinidad</name></author><author><name>Beatriz Garat</name></author><author><name>Maria A Duhagon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;MicroRNAs are small RNAs that regulate gene expression through complementary base pairing with their target mRNAs. Given the small size of the pairing region and the large number of mRNAs that each microRNA can control, the identification of biologically relevant targets is difficult. Since current knowledge of target recognition and repression has mainly relied on in vitro studies, we sought to determine if the interrogation of gene expression data of unperturbed tissues could yield new insight into these processes. The transcriptome-wide repression at the microRNA-mRNA canonical interaction sites (seed and 3'-supplementary region, identified by sole base complementarity) was calculated as a normalized Spearman correlation (Z-score) between the abundance of the transcripts in the PRAD-TCGA tissues (RNA-seq and small RNA-seq data of 546 samples). Using the repression values obtained we confirmed established properties or microRNA targeting efficacy, such as the preference for gene regions (3'UTR&amp;gt;CDS&amp;gt;5'UTR), the proportionality between repression and seed length (6mer&amp;lt;7mer&amp;lt;8mer) and the contribution to the repression exerted by the supplementary pairing at 13-16nt of the microRNA. Our results suggest that the 7mer-m8 seed could be more repressive than the 7mer-A1, while they have similar efficacy when they interact using the 3'-supplementary pairing. Strikingly, the 6mer+suppl sites yielded normalized Z-score of repression similar to the sole 7mer-m8 or 7mer-A1 seeds, which raise awareness of its potential biological relevance. We then used the approach to further characterize the 3'-supplementary pairing, using 39 microRNAs that hold repressive 3'-supplementary interactions. The analysis of the bridge between seed and 3'-supplementary pairing site confirmed the optimum +1 offset previously evidenced, but higher offsets appear to hold similar repressive strength. In addition, they show a low GC content at position 13-16, and base preferences that allow the selection of a candidate sequence motif. Overall, our study demonstrates that transcriptome-wide analysis of microRNA-mRNA correlations in large, matched RNA-seq and small-RNA-seq data has the power to uncover hints of microRNA targeting determinants operating in the in vivo unperturbed set. Finally, we made available a bioinformatic tool to analyze microRNA-target mRNA interactions using our approach.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473932" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptome-wide analysis of microRNA-mRNA correlations in unperturbed tissue transcriptomes identifies microRNA targeting determinants. (12 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473552</id><title>Identification of novel genetic regions associated with resistance to European canker in apple (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.423202+00:00</updated><author><name>Amanda Karlström</name></author><author><name>Antonio Gómez-Cortecero</name></author><author><name>Charlotte F Nellist</name></author><author><name>Matthew Ordidge</name></author><author><name>Jim M. Dunwell</name></author><author><name>Richard J Harrison</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Resistance to &lt;italic&gt;Neonectria ditissima&lt;/italic&gt;, the fungus causing European canker in apple, was studied in a multiparental population of apple scions using several phenotyping methods. The studied population consists of individuals from multiple families connected through a common pedigree. The degree of disease of each individual in the population was assessed in three experiments: artificial inoculations of detached dormant shoots, potted trees in a glasshouse and in a replicated field experiment. The genetic basis of the differences in disease was studied using a pedigree-based analysis (PBA). Three quantitative trait loci (QTL), on linkage groups (LG) 6, 8 and 10 were identified in more than one of the phenotyping strategies. An additional four QTL, on LG 2, 5, 15 and 16 were only identified in the field experiment. The QTL on LG2 and 16 were further validated in a biparental population. QTL effect sizes were small to moderate with 4.3 to 19 % of variance explained by a single QTL. A subsequent analysis of QTL haplotypes revealed a dynamic response to this disease, in which the estimated effect of a haplotype varied over the field time-points. Two groups of QTL-haplotypes could be distinguished, one that displayed increased effect and one with a constant effect across time-points. These results suggest that there are different modes of control of &lt;italic&gt;N. ditissima&lt;/italic&gt; in the early stages of infection compared to later time-points of disease development. It also shows that multiple QTL will need to be considered to improve resistance to European canker in apple breeding germplasm.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473552" rel="alternate" title="Identification of novel genetic regions associated with resistance to European canker in apple (10 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.25.474161</id><title>SHERRY2: A method for rapid and sensitive single cell RNA-seq (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.423490+00:00</updated><author><name>Lin Di</name></author><author><name>Bo Liu</name></author><author><name>Yuzhu Lyu</name></author><author><name>Shihui Zhao</name></author><author><name>Yuhong Pang</name></author><author><name>Chen Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jianbin Wang</name></author><author><name>Hai Qi</name></author><author><name>Jie Shen</name></author><author><name>Yanyi Huang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many single cell RNA-seq applications aim to probe a wide dynamic range of gene expression, but most of them are still challenging to accurately quantify low-aboundance transcripts. Based on our previous finding that Tn5 transposase can directly cut-and-tag DNA/RNA hetero-duplexes, we present SHERRY2, an optimized protocol for sequencing transcriptomes of single cells or single nuclei. SHERRY2 is robust and scalable, and it has higher sensitivity and more uniform coverage in comparison with prevalent scRNA-seq methods. With throughput of a few thousand cells per batch, SHERRY2 can reveal the subtle transcriptomic differences between cells and facilitate important biological discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.25.474161" rel="alternate" title="SHERRY2: A method for rapid and sensitive single cell RNA-seq (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473467</id><title>Genomes of keystone Mortierella species lead to better in silico prediction of soil mycobiome functions from Taiwan’s offshore islands (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.423856+00:00</updated><author><name>Yu-fei Lin</name></author><author><name>Wei-An Liu</name></author><author><name>Yu-Ching Liu</name></author><author><name>Hsin-Han Lee</name></author><author><name>Yen-Ju Lin</name></author><author><name>Ed-Haun Chang</name></author><author><name>Meiyeh J Lu</name></author><author><name>Chih-Yu Chiu</name></author><author><name>Isheng Jason Tsai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ability to correlate the functional relationship between microbial communities and their environment is critical to understanding microbial ecology. There is emerging knowledge on island biogeography of microbes but how island characteristics influence functions of microbial community remain elusive. Here, we explored soil mycobiomes from nine islands adjacent to Taiwan using ITS2 amplicon sequencing. Geographical distances and island size were positively correlated to dissimilarity in mycobiomes, and we identified 56 zero-radius operational taxonomic units (zOTUs) that were ubiquitously present across all islands, and as few as five &lt;italic&gt;Mortierella&lt;/italic&gt; zOTUs dominate more than half of mycobiomes. Correlation network analyses revealed that seven of the 45 hub species were part of the ubiquitous zOTUs belonging to &lt;italic&gt;Mortierella, Trichoderma, Aspergillus, Clonostachys&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Staphylotrichum&lt;/italic&gt;. We sequenced and annotated the genomes of seven &lt;italic&gt;Mortierella&lt;/italic&gt; isolates, and comparative predictions of KEGG orthologues using PICRUSt2 database updated with new genomes increased sequence reads coverage by 62.9% at the genus level. In addition, genes associated with carbohydrate and lipid metabolisms were differentially abundant between islands which remained undetected in the original database. Predicted functional pathways were similar across islands despite their geographical separation, difference in differentially abundant genes and composition. Our approach demonstrated the incorporation of the key taxa genomic data can improve functional gene prediction results and can be readily applied to investigate other niches of interests.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473467" rel="alternate" title="Genomes of keystone Mortierella species lead to better in silico prediction of soil mycobiome functions from Taiwan’s offshore islands (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473702</id><title>Tutorial: Investigating SARS-CoV-2 evolution and phylogeny using MNHN-Tree-Tools (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.424115+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas Haschka</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Covid-19 pandemic has caused at more than 3 million deaths by Mai this year. It had a significant impact on the daily life and the global economy. The virus has since its first recorded outbreak in China mutated into new strains. The Nextstrain project has so far been monitoring the evolution of the virus. At the same time we were developing in our lab the MNHN-Tree-Tools toolkit, primarily for the investigation of DNA repeat sequences. We have further extended MNHN-Tree-Tools to guide phylogenetics. As such the toolkit has evolved into a high performance code, allowing for a fast investigation of millions of sequences. Given the context of the pandemic it became evident that we will use our versatile tool to investigate the evolution of SARS-CoV-2 sequences. Our efforts have cumulated in this tutorial that we share with the scientific community.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473702" rel="alternate" title="Tutorial: Investigating SARS-CoV-2 evolution and phylogeny using MNHN-Tree-Tools (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473375</id><title>A Cartography of Differential Gene Methylation in Myalgic Encephalomyelitis/Chronic Fatigue Syndrome: Different Network Roles in the Protein-Protein Interactions Network Play Different, Biologically Relevant, Roles (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.424352+00:00</updated><author><name>Aurelia Wilberforce</name></author><author><name>Giulio Valentino Dalla Riva</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Myalgic Encephalomyelitis, also known as Chronic Fatigue Syndrome (ME/CFS), is a debilitating illness characterised by severe fatigue and associated with immune dysfunction. Previous studies of DNA methylation (epigenetic changes that can affect the gene transcription) have found evidence of changes in immune cells for ME/CFS. However these studies have been limited by their small sample size, precluding the ability to detect changes to methylation of smaller magnitude. Therefore, to achieve a larger sample size and detect small changes to DNA methylation, we aggregate three comparable datasets and analyse them in unison. We find 10,824 differentially methylated genes, with a very small average change. We then turn our attention to the network structure of the Protein-Protein interaction, which we built from the currently known interactions of relevant proteins, and localising the network cartography framework, we identify 184 hub genes. A distinct structuring emerges, with different hub types playing differing, meaningful, biological roles. Supporting previous theories about ME/CFS, Gene ontology enrichment analysis of these hubs reveal that they are involved in immune system processes, including response to TGF-&lt;italic&gt;β&lt;/italic&gt; and LPS, as well as mitochondrial functioning. We also show that dopaminergic signalling may potentially contribute to immune pathology in ME/CFS. Our results demonstrate the potentiality of network cartographic approaches in shedding light on the epigenetic contribution to the immune dysregulation of ME/CFS.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473375" rel="alternate" title="A Cartography of Differential Gene Methylation in Myalgic Encephalomyelitis/Chronic Fatigue Syndrome: Different Network Roles in the Protein-Protein Interactions Network Play Different, Biologically Relevant, Roles (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473912</id><title>Adjustment for SNPs instead of demographic and clinical covariates in GWAS (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.424768+00:00</updated><author><name>Fuzhong Xue</name></author><author><name>Xiaoru Sun</name></author><author><name>Hongkai Li</name></author><author><name>Yuanyuan Yu</name></author><author><name>Zhongshang Yuan</name></author><author><name>Chuandi Jin</name></author><author><name>Lei Hou</name></author><author><name>Xinhui Liu</name></author><author><name>Qing Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genome-wide association study (GWAS) is fundamentally designed to detect disease-causing genes. To reduce spurious associations or improve statistical power, about 80% of GWASs arbitrarily adjusted for demographic and clinical covariates. However, adjustment strategies in GWASs have not achieved consistent conclusions. Given the initial aim of GWAS that is to identify the causal association between a specific causal single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) and disease trait, we summarized all complex relationships of the target SNP, covariate and disease trait into 15 causal diagrams according to various roles of the covariate. Following each causal diagram, we conducted a series of theoretical justifications and statistical simulations. Our results demonstrate that it is unadvisable to adjust for any demographic or clinical covariates. We illustrate our point by applying GWASs for body mass index (BMI) and breast cancer, including adjusting and non-adjusting for age and smoking status. Genetic effects and P values might vary across different strategies. Instead, adjustments for SNPs (G') should be strongly recommended when G' are in linkage disequilibrium with the target SNP, and correlated with disease trait conditional on the target SNP. Specifically, adjustment for such G' can block all the confounding paths between the target SNP and disease trait, and avoid over-adjusting for colliders or intermediaries.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473912" rel="alternate" title="Adjustment for SNPs instead of demographic and clinical covariates in GWAS (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.26.474183</id><title>Cell type-specific differential expression for spatial transcriptomics (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.425264+00:00</updated><author><name>Dylan M Cable</name></author><author><name>Evan Murray</name></author><author><name>Vignesh Shanmugam</name></author><author><name>Simon Zhang</name></author><author><name>Michael Z Diao</name></author><author><name>Haiqi Chen</name></author><author><name>Evan Macosko</name></author><author><name>Rafael A Irizarry</name></author><author><name>Fei Chen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spatial transcriptomics enables spatially resolved gene expression measurements at near single-cell resolution. There is a pressing need for computational tools to enable the detection of genes that are differentially expressed across tissue context for cell types of interest. However, changes in cell type composition across space and the fact that measurement units often detect transcripts from more than one cell type introduce complex statistical challenges. Here, we introduce a statistical method, Robust Cell Type Differential Expression (RCTDE), that estimates cell type-specific patterns of differential gene expression while accounting for localization of other cell types. By using general log-linear models, we provide a unified framework for defining and identifying gene expression changes for a wide-range of relevant contexts: changes due to pathology, anatomical regions, physical proximity to specific cell types, and cellular microenvironment. Furthermore, our approach enables statistical inference across multiple samples and replicates when such data is available. We demonstrate, through simulations and validation experiments on Slide-seq and MERFISH datasets, that our approach accurately identifies cell type-specific differential gene expression and provides valid uncertainty quantification. Lastly, we apply our method to characterize spatially-localized tissue changes in the context of disease. In an Alzheimer's mouse model Slide-seq dataset, we identify plaque-dependent patterns of cellular immune activity. We also find a putative interaction between tumor cells and myeloid immune cells in a Slide-seq tumor dataset. We make our RCTDE method publicly available as part of the open source R package https://github.com/dmcable/spacexr.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.26.474183" rel="alternate" title="Cell type-specific differential expression for spatial transcriptomics (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473394</id><title>Soil organic carbon fractionation and metagenomics pipeline to link carbon content and stability with microbial composition – First results investigating fungal endophytes (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.425858+00:00</updated><author><name>Wolfram Buss</name></author><author><name>Raghvendra Sharma</name></author><author><name>Scott Ferguson</name></author><author><name>Justin Borevitz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Society needs to capture gigatons of carbon dioxide from the atmosphere annually and then store it long-term to limit and ultimately reverse the effects of climate change. Bringing lost carbon back into agricultural soils should be a priority as it brings the added benefit of improving soil properties. Linking soil organic carbon (SOC) fractions of different stability with soil microbial composition can help understand and subsequently manage SOC storage. Here we develop a pipeline for evaluating the effects of microbial management on SOC content using rapid and low-cost SOC fractionation and metagenomics approaches. We tested the methods in a wheat pot trial inoculated with 17 individual endophytic fungal isolates. Two fungi increased total SOC in the area under the plant stem by ~15%. The fractionation assay showed that the medium stability soil aggregate carbon fraction (AggC) was increased by one of these fungi (+21%) and the chemically recalcitrant proportion (bleach oxidation) of AggC by the other (+35%). Both fungi increased mineral-associated organic carbon (MAOC), the long-term SOC storage, by ~10%. We used rapid, portable, low-cost, whole metagenome long read sequencing to detect a shift in the microbial composition for one of the fungi-inoculated treatments. This treatment showed a more diverse microbial community and a higher quantity of DNA in soil. The results emphasise the link between composition and abundance of soil microorganisms with soil carbon formation. Our dual carbon fractional and metagenomic analysis pipeline can be used to further test the effects of microbial management and ultimately to model the soil factors that influence SOC storage, such as nutrient and water availability, starting SOC content, soil texture and aggregation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473394" rel="alternate" title="Soil organic carbon fractionation and metagenomics pipeline to link carbon content and stability with microbial composition – First results investigating fungal endophytes (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.18.473290</id><title>GRaNIE and GRaNPA: Inference and evaluation of enhancer-mediated gene regulatory networks applied to study macrophages (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.426078+00:00</updated><author><name>Aryan Kamal</name></author><author><name>Christian Arnold</name></author><author><name>Annique Claringbould</name></author><author><name>Rim Moussa</name></author><author><name>Neha Daga</name></author><author><name>Daria Nogina</name></author><author><name>Maksim Kholmatov</name></author><author><name>Nila Servaas</name></author><author><name>Sophia Mueller-Dott</name></author><author><name>Armando Reyes-Palomares</name></author><author><name>Giovanni Palla</name></author><author><name>Olga Sigalova</name></author><author><name>Daria Bunina</name></author><author><name>Caroline Pabst</name></author><author><name>Judith B. Zaugg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Among the biggest challenges in the post-GWAS (genome-wide association studies) era is the interpretation of disease-associated genetic variants in non-coding genomic regions. Enhancers have emerged as key players in mediating the effect of genetic variants on complex traits and diseases. Their activity is regulated by a combination of transcription factors (TFs), epigenetic changes and genetic variants. Several approaches exist to link enhancers to their target genes, and others that infer TF-gene connections. However, we currently lack a framework that systematically integrates enhancers into TF-gene regulatory networks. Furthermore, we lack an unbiased way of assessing whether inferred regulatory interactions are biologically meaningful. Here we present two methods, implemented as user-friendly R-packages, for building and evaluating enhancer-mediated gene regulatory networks (eGRNs) called GRaNIE (Gene Regulatory Network Inference including Enhancers - &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://git.embl.de/grp-zaugg/GRaNIE"&gt;https://git.embl.de/grp-zaugg/GRaNIE&lt;/ext-link&gt;) and GRaNPA (Gene Regulatory Network Performance Analysis - &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://git.embl.de/grp-zaugg/GRaNPA"&gt;https://git.embl.de/grp-zaugg/GRaNPA&lt;/ext-link&gt;), respectively. GRaNIE jointly infers TF-enhancer, enhancer-gene and TF-gene interactions by integrating open chromatin data such as ATAC-Seq or H3K27ac with RNA-seq across a set of samples (e.g. individuals), and optionally also Hi-C data. GRaNPA is a general framework for evaluating the biological relevance of TF-gene GRNs by assessing their performance for predicting cell-type specific differential expression. We demonstrate the power of our tool-suite by investigating gene regulatory mechanisms in macrophages that underlie their response to infection, and their involvement in common genetic diseases including autoimmune diseases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="473290v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.18.473290" rel="alternate" title="GRaNIE and GRaNPA: Inference and evaluation of enhancer-mediated gene regulatory networks applied to study macrophages (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473323</id><title>Deeply hidden genome organization directly mediated by SATB1 (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.426486+00:00</updated><author><name>Yoshinori Kohwi</name></author><author><name>Mari Grange</name></author><author><name>Hunter W. Richards</name></author><author><name>Ya-Chen Liang</name></author><author><name>Cheng-Ming Chuong</name></author><author><name>Yohko Kitagawa</name></author><author><name>Shimon Sakaguchi</name></author><author><name>Vladimir A. Botchkarev</name></author><author><name>Ichiro Taniguchi</name></author><author><name>Terumi Kohwi-Shigematsu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mammalian genomes are organized by multi-layered chromatin folding. Whether and how three-dimensional genome organization contributes to cell-type specific transcription remains unclear. Here we uncover genome architecture formed by specialized sequences, base-unpairing regions (BURs), bound to a nuclear architectural protein, SATB1. SATB1 regulates cell-type specific transcription that underlies changes in cellular phenotypes. We developed a modified ChIP-seq protocol that stringently purifies genomic DNA only with its directly-associated proteins and unmasked previously-hidden BURs as direct SATB1 targets genome-wide. These SATB1-bound BURs are mutually exclusive from CTCF binding sites, and SATB1 is dispensable for CTCF/cohesion-mediated topologically associated domains (TADs). Instead, BURs largely overlap with lamina associated domains (LADs), and the fraction of BURs tethered to the SATB1 protein network in the nuclear interior is cell type-dependent. Our results reveal TAD-independent chromatin folding mediated by BUR sequences which serve as genome architecture landmarks for direct targeting by cell type-specific gene regulator, SATB1.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Genome-wide chromatin folding by direct tethering of base-unpairing regions to SATB1 nuclear architecture is unveiled.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473323" rel="alternate" title="Deeply hidden genome organization directly mediated by SATB1 (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.18.473306</id><title>An exploration of linkage fine-mapping on sequences from case-control studies (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.426923+00:00</updated><author><name>Payman Nickchi</name></author><author><name>Charith Karunarathna</name></author><author><name>Jinko Graham</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Linkage analysis maps genetic loci for a heritable trait by identifying genomic regions with excess relatedness among individuals with similar trait values. Analysis may be conducted on related individuals from families, or on samples of unrelated individuals from a population. For allelically heterogeneous traits, population-based linkage analysis can be more powerful than genotypic-association analysis. Here, we focus on linkage analysis in a population sample, but use sequences rather than individuals as our unit of observation. Earlier investigations of sequence-based linkage mapping relied on known sequence relatedness, whereas we infer relatedness from the sequence data. We propose two ways to associate similarity in relatedness of sequences with similarity in their trait values and compare the resulting linkage methods to two genotypic-association methods. We also introduce a procedure to label case sequences as potential carriers or non-carriers of causal variants after an association has been found. This &lt;italic&gt;post-hoc&lt;/italic&gt; labeling of case sequences is based on inferred relatedness to other case sequences. Our simulation results indicate that methods based on sequence-relatedness improve localization and perform as well as genotypic-association methods for detecting rare causal variants. Sequence-based linkage analysis therefore has potential to fine-map allelically heterogeneous disease traits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.18.473306" rel="alternate" title="An exploration of linkage fine-mapping on sequences from case-control studies (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473918</id><title>A novel zebrafish model of SPEG-related centronuclear myopathy (CNM): characterization and comparison with other CNM model zebrafish (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.427161+00:00</updated><author><name>Karla G Espinosa</name></author><author><name>Salma Geissah</name></author><author><name>Linda Groom</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Volpatti</name></author><author><name>Ian C Scott</name></author><author><name>Robert T Dirksen</name></author><author><name>Mo Zhao</name></author><author><name>James J Dowling</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Centronuclear myopathy (CNM) is a congenital neuromuscular disorder caused by pathogenic variation in genes associated with membrane trafficking and excitation-contraction coupling (ECC). Bi-allelic autosomal recessive mutations in striated muscle enriched protein kinase (&lt;italic&gt;SPEG&lt;/italic&gt;) account for a subset of CNM patients. Previous research has been limited by the perinatal lethality of &lt;italic&gt;Speg&lt;/italic&gt; knockout mice. Thus, the precise biological role of SPEG in skeletal muscle remains unknown. To address this issue, we generated zebrafish &lt;italic&gt;spega&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;spegb&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;spega/spegb&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;speg&lt;/italic&gt;-DKO) mutant lines. We demonstrate that &lt;italic&gt;speg&lt;/italic&gt;-DKO zebrafish faithfully recapitulate multiple phenotypes associated with human CNM, including disruption of the ECC protein machinery, dysregulation of calcium homeostasis during ECC, and impairment of muscle performance. Taking advantage of the availability of zebrafish models of multiple CNM genetic subtypes, we compared novel and known disease markers in &lt;italic&gt;speg&lt;/italic&gt;-DKO with &lt;italic&gt;mtm1&lt;/italic&gt;-KO and &lt;italic&gt;DNM2&lt;/italic&gt;-S619L transgenic zebrafish. We observed desmin (DES) accumulation common to all CNM subtypes, and Dnm2 upregulation in muscle of both &lt;italic&gt;speg&lt;/italic&gt;-DKO and &lt;italic&gt;mtm1&lt;/italic&gt;-KO zebrafish. In all, we establish a new model of &lt;italic&gt;SPEG&lt;/italic&gt;-related CNM, and identify abnormalities in this model suitable for defining disease pathomechanisms and evaluating potential therapies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473918" rel="alternate" title="A novel zebrafish model of SPEG-related centronuclear myopathy (CNM): characterization and comparison with other CNM model zebrafish (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473149</id><title>The antique genetic plight of the Mediterranean monk seal (Monachus monachus) (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.427414+00:00</updated><author><name>Jordi Salmona</name></author><author><name>Julia Dayon</name></author><author><name>Emilie Lecompte</name></author><author><name>Alexandros A Karamanlidis</name></author><author><name>Alex Aguilar</name></author><author><name>Pablo Fernandez de Larrinoa</name></author><author><name>Rosa Pires</name></author><author><name>Giulia Mo</name></author><author><name>Abrina Agnesi</name></author><author><name>Asunción Borrell</name></author><author><name>Erdem Danyer</name></author><author><name>Bayam Öztürk</name></author><author><name>Arda M Tonay</name></author><author><name>Luis M González</name></author><author><name>Panagiotis Dendrinos</name></author><author><name>Philippe Gaubert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Disentangling the impact of Late Quaternary climate change from human activities can have crucial implications on the conservation of endangered species. We investigated the population genetics and demography of the Mediterranean monk seal (&lt;italic&gt;Monachus monachus&lt;/italic&gt;), one of the world's most endangered marine mammals, through an unprecedented dataset encompassing historical (extinct) and extant populations from the eastern North Atlantic to the entire Mediterranean Basin. We show that Western-Sahara/Mauritania (Cabo Blanco), Madeira, Western Mediterranean (historical range) and Eastern Mediterranean regions segregate in four populations. This structure is likely the consequence of recent drift, combined with long-term isolation by distance (R2 = 0.7), resulting from prevailing short-distance (&amp;lt; 500 km) and infrequent long-distance dispersal (&amp;lt; 1,500 km). All populations (Madeira especially), show high levels of inbreeding and low levels of genetic diversity, seemingly declining since historical time, but surprisingly not being impacted by the 1997 massive die-off in Cabo Blanco. Approximate Bayesian Computation analyses support a scenario combining local extinctions and a major effective population size decline in all populations during Antiquity. Our results suggest that the early densification of human populations around the Mediterranean Basin coupled to the development of seafaring techniques were the main drivers of the decline of Mediterranean monk seals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473149" rel="alternate" title="The antique genetic plight of the Mediterranean monk seal (Monachus monachus) (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473474</id><title>Epi-MEIF, a flexible and efficient method for detection of high order epistatic interactions from complex phenotypic traits (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.427747+00:00</updated><author><name>Saswati Saha</name></author><author><name>Laurent Perrin</name></author><author><name>Laurence Röder</name></author><author><name>Christine Brun</name></author><author><name>Lionel Spinelli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the relationship between genetic variations and variations in complex and quantitative phenotypes remains an ongoing challenge. While Genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have become a vital tool for identifying single-locus associations, we lack methods for identifying epistatic interactions. In this article, we propose a novel method for high-order epistasis detection using mixed effect conditional inference forest (&lt;italic&gt;epiMEIF&lt;/italic&gt;). The &lt;italic&gt;epiMEIF&lt;/italic&gt; model is fitted on a group of potential causal SNPs and the tree structure in the forest facilitates the identification of n-way interactions between the SNPs. Additional testing strategies further improve the robustness of the method. We demonstrate its ability to detect true n-way interactions via extensive simulations in both cross-sectional and longitudinal synthetic datasets. This is further illustrated in an application to reveal epistatic interactions from natural variations of cardiac traits in flies (Drosophila). Overall, the method provides a generalized way to identify high order interactions from any GWAS data, thereby greatly improving the detection of the genetic architecture of complex phenotypes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473474" rel="alternate" title="Epi-MEIF, a flexible and efficient method for detection of high order epistatic interactions from complex phenotypic traits (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473777</id><title>Therapeutic advantages of combined gene/cell therapy strategies in a murine model of GM2 gangliosidosis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.427967+00:00</updated><author><name>Davide Sala</name></author><author><name>Francesca Ornaghi</name></author><author><name>Francesco Morena</name></author><author><name>Chiara Argentati</name></author><author><name>Manuela Valsecchi</name></author><author><name>Valeria Alberizzi</name></author><author><name>Roberta Di Guardo</name></author><author><name>Alessandra Bolino</name></author><author><name>Massimo Aureli</name></author><author><name>Sabata Martino</name></author><author><name>Angela Gritti</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The GM2 gangliosidoses Tay-Sachs disease and Sandhoff disease (SD) are respectively caused by mutations in the HEXA and HEXB genes encoding the α and β subunits of β-N-acetylhexosaminidase (Hex). The consequential accumulation of ganglioside in the brain leads to severe and progressive neurological impairment. There are currently no approved therapies to counteract or reverse the effects of GM2 gangliosidosis. Adeno-associated vector (AAV)-based investigational gene therapy (GT) products have raised expectations but come with safety and efficacy issues that need to be addressed. Thus, there is an urgent need to develop novel therapies targeting the CNS and other affected tissues that are appropriately timed to ensure pervasive metabolic correction and counteract disease progression. In this report, we show that the sequential administration of lentiviral vector (LV)-mediated intracerebral (IC) GT and bone marrow transplantation (BMT) in pre-symptomatic SD mice provide a timely and long-lasting source of the Hex enzyme in the central and peripheral nervous systems and peripheral tissues, leading to global rescue of the disease phenotype. Combined therapy showed a clear therapeutic advantage compared to individual treatments in terms of lifespan extension and normalization of the neuroinflammatory and neurodegenerative phenotypes of the SD mice. These benefits correlated with a time-dependent increase in Hex activity and a remarkable reduction in GM2 storage in the brain tissues that single treatments failed to achieve. Our results highlight the complementary and synergic mode of action of LV-mediated IC GT and BMT, clarify the relative contribution of treatments to the therapeutic outcome, and inform on the realistic threshold of enzymatic activity that is required to achieve a significant therapeutic benefit, with important implications for the monitoring and interpretation of ongoing experimental therapies, and for the design of more effective treatment strategies for GM2 gangliosidosis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473777" rel="alternate" title="Therapeutic advantages of combined gene/cell therapy strategies in a murine model of GM2 gangliosidosis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473872</id><title>Profiling subcellular localization of nuclear-encoded mitochondrial gene products in zebrafish (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.428234+00:00</updated><author><name>Barbara Uszczynska-Ratajczak</name></author><author><name>Sreedevi Sugunan</name></author><author><name>Monika Kwiatkowska</name></author><author><name>Maciej Migdal</name></author><author><name>Silvia Carbonell-Sala</name></author><author><name>Anna M. Sokol</name></author><author><name>Cecilia L. Winata</name></author><author><name>Agnieszka Chacinska</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Most mitochondrial proteins are encoded by nuclear genes, synthetized in the cytosol and targeted into the organelle. The import of some, but not all, nuclear-encoded mitochondrial proteins begins with translation of messenger RNAs (mRNAs) on the surface of mitochondria. To characterize the spatial organization of mitochondrial gene products in zebrafish (Danio rerio), we sequenced RNA from different cellular fractions. Our results confirmed the presence of nuclear-encoded mRNAs in the mitochondrial fraction, which in unperturbed conditions, are mainly transcripts encoding large proteins with specific properties, like transmembrane domains. To further explore the principles of mitochondrial protein compartmentalization in zebrafish, we quantified the transcriptomic changes for each subcellular fraction triggered by the chchd4a-/- mutation, causing the disorders in the mitochondrial protein import. Our results indicate that the proteostatic stress further restricts the population of transcripts on the mitochondrial surface, allowing only the largest and the most evolutionary conserved proteins to be synthetized there. We also show that many nuclear-encoded mitochondrial transcripts translated by the cytosolic ribosomes stay resistant to the global translation shutdown. Thus, vertebrates, in contrast to yeast, are not likely to employ localized translation to facilitate synthesis of mitochondrial proteins under proteostatic stress conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473872" rel="alternate" title="Profiling subcellular localization of nuclear-encoded mitochondrial gene products in zebrafish (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473573</id><title>Fine mapping of goat polledness variant in six Chinese native breeds (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.428644+00:00</updated><author><name>Yong Li</name></author><author><name>Tao Chen</name></author><author><name>Man-Man Yang</name></author><author><name>Hu Han</name></author><author><name>Dan jiang</name></author><author><name>Qiang Wei</name></author><author><name>Xing-Ju Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yan Ao</name></author><author><name>Qingfeng Zhang</name></author><author><name>Ze-Pu Miao</name></author><author><name>Ran Wang</name></author><author><name>Yuan-Lun Li</name></author><author><name>Sheng-Yu Chao</name></author><author><name>Lin Li</name></author><author><name>Ting-Ting Zhang</name></author><author><name>Ming Fang</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The genetic mechanism of goat polledness has been studied for decades, but identifying causative variants and functional genes remains challenging.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using a genome-wide association study (GWAS), we identified a significant striking locus for polledness in two different goat breeds. To reduce the linkage disequilibrium among variants for localizing causative variants in the finer region, we sequenced 79 goats from six Chinese native breeds (Jining Gray, Matou, Guizhou black, Yunnan black bone, Chaidamu, and Ujumqin) and identified 483.5 kb CNV (150,334,567-150,818,099) translocated into the previously identified 11.7 kb polled intersex syndrome region, which was consistent with previous research using intersex goat populations. Within the 483.5 kb CNV, a ~322 bp horn-specific element, similar to the superfamily of tRNA-derived families of SINEs, located at the first intron of the &lt;italic&gt;ERG&lt;/italic&gt; gene was identified. The results of the GO enrichment analysis showed that the Horn-SINE element-associated genes were involved in both nervous system and head development. Finally, we used RNA sequencing to investigate gene expression profiles in the horn bud and skin tissues of horned and polled goats. We identified 1077 and 1222 differentially expressed genes between the horn bud and skin tissue in polled and horned goats, respectively. We also identified 367 differentially expressed genes in horn buds between polled and horned animals, and found that the two CNV-related genes, &lt;italic&gt;ERG&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;FOXL2&lt;/italic&gt;, were upregulated in the horn bud of polled goats. Gene functional enrichment analysis demonstrated that the downregulated genes in the horn bud of polled goats were enriched in skeletal system development, whereas the upregulated genes were significantly overexpressed in muscle tissue development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Broadly, this study describes a novel structural variant responsible for polledness/intersex traits and contributes to the discovery of molecular mechanisms underlying the development and regulation of the polledness trait.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473573" rel="alternate" title="Fine mapping of goat polledness variant in six Chinese native breeds (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>