<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.195447+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461965</id><title>Intergenerational hormesis is regulated by heritable 18S rRNA methylation (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.195977+00:00</updated><author><name>Noa Liberman</name></author><author><name>Maxim V. Gerashchenko</name></author><author><name>Konstantinos Boulias</name></author><author><name>Fiona G MacWhinnie</name></author><author><name>Albert Kejun Ying</name></author><author><name>Anya Flood Taylor</name></author><author><name>Joseph Al Haddad</name></author><author><name>Hiroki Shibuya</name></author><author><name>Lara Roach</name></author><author><name>Anna Dong</name></author><author><name>Vadim N. Gladyshev</name></author><author><name>Eric Lieberman Greer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Heritable non-genetic information can regulate a variety of complex phenotypes. However, what specific non-genetic cues are transmitted from parents to their descendants are poorly understood. Here, we perform metabolic methyl-labelling experiments to track the heritable transmission of methylation from ancestors to their descendants in the nematode &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/italic&gt;. We find that methylation is transmitted to descendants in proteins, RNA, DNA and lipids. We further find that in response to parental starvation, fed naïve progeny display reduced fertility, increased heat stress resistance, and extended longevity. This intergenerational hormesis is accompanied by a heritable increase in N6’-dimethyl adenosine (m&lt;sup&gt;6,2&lt;/sup&gt;A) on the 18S ribosomal RNA at adenosines 1735 and 1736. We identified the conserved DIMT-1 as the m&lt;sup&gt;6,2&lt;/sup&gt;A methyltransferase in &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; and find that &lt;italic&gt;dimt-1&lt;/italic&gt; is required for the intergenerational hormesis phenotypes. This study provides the first labeling and tracking of heritable non-genetic material across generations and demonstrates the importance of rRNA methylation for regulating the heritable response to starvation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461965" rel="alternate" title="Intergenerational hormesis is regulated by heritable 18S rRNA methylation (31 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.459575</id><title>Prime-seq, efficient and powerful bulk RNA-sequencing (28 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.196276+00:00</updated><author><name>Aleksandar Janjic</name></author><author><name>Lucas E. Wange</name></author><author><name>Johannes W. Bagnoli</name></author><author><name>Johanna Geuder</name></author><author><name>Phong Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Daniel Richter</name></author><author><name>Beate Vieth</name></author><author><name>Binje Vick</name></author><author><name>Irmela Jeremias</name></author><author><name>Christoph Ziegenhain</name></author><author><name>Ines Hellmann</name></author><author><name>Wolfgang Enard</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;With the advent of Next Generation Sequencing, RNA-sequencing (RNA-seq) has become the major method for quantitative gene expression analysis. Reducing library costs by early barcoding has propelled single-cell RNA-seq, but has not yet caught on for bulk RNA-seq. Here, we optimized and validated a bulk RNA-seq method we call prime-seq. We show that with respect to library complexity, measurement accuracy, and statistical power it performs equivalent to TruSeq, a standard bulk RNA-seq method, but is four-fold more cost-efficient due to almost 50-fold cheaper library costs. We also validate a direct RNA isolation step that further improves cost and time-efficiency, show that intronic reads are derived from RNA, validate that prime-seq performs optimal with only 1,000 cells as input, and calculate that prime-seq is the most cost-efficient bulk RNA-seq method currently available. We discuss why many labs would profit from a cost-efficient early barcoding RNA-seq protocol and argue that prime-seq is well suited for setting up such a protocol as it is well validated, well documented, and requires no specialized equipment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.459575" rel="alternate" title="Prime-seq, efficient and powerful bulk RNA-sequencing (28 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461259</id><title>Polygenic score accuracy in ancient samples: quantifying the effects of allelic turnover (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.196498+00:00</updated><author><name>Maryn O. Carlson</name></author><author><name>Daniel P. Rice</name></author><author><name>Jeremy J. Berg</name></author><author><name>Matthias Steinrücken</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Polygenic scores link the genotypes of ancient individuals to their phenotypes, which are often unobservable, offering a tantalizing opportunity to reconstruct complex trait evolution. In practice, however, interpretation of ancient polygenic scores is subject to numerous assumptions. For one, the genome-wide association (GWA) studies from which polygenic scores are derived, can only estimate effect sizes for loci segregating in contemporary populations. Therefore, a GWA study may not correctly identify all loci relevant to trait variation in the ancient population. In addition, the frequencies of trait-associated loci may have changed in the intervening years. Here, we devise a theoretical framework to quantify the effect of this allelic turnover on the statistical properties of polygenic scores as functions of population genetic dynamics, trait architecture, power to detect significant loci, and the age of the ancient sample. We model the allele frequencies of loci underlying trait variation using the Wright-Fisher diffusion, and employ the spectral representation of its transition density to find analytical expressions for several error metrics, including the correlation between an ancient individual’s polygenic score and true phenotype, referred to as polygenic score accuracy. Our theory also applies to a two-population scenario and demonstrates that allelic turnover alone &lt;italic&gt;may&lt;/italic&gt; explain a substantial percentage of the reduced accuracy observed in cross-population predictions, akin to those performed in human genetics. Finally, we use simulations to explore the effects of recent directional selection, a bias-inducing process, on the statistics of interest. We find that even in the presence of bias, weak selection induces minimal deviations from our neutral expectations for the decay of polygenic score accuracy. By quantifying the limitations of polygenic scores in an explicit evolutionary context, our work lays the foundation for the development of more sophisticated statistical procedures to analyze both temporally and geographically resolved polygenic scores.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461259" rel="alternate" title="Polygenic score accuracy in ancient samples: quantifying the effects of allelic turnover (23 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462505</id><title>S. pombe wtf genes use dual transcriptional regulation and selective protein exclusion from spores to cause meiotic drive (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.196706+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicole L. Nuckolls</name></author><author><name>Ananya Nidamangala Srinivasa</name></author><author><name>Anthony C. Mok</name></author><author><name>María Angélica Bravo Núñez</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey J. Lange</name></author><author><name>Todd J. Gallagher</name></author><author><name>Chris W. Seidel</name></author><author><name>Sarah E. Zanders</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Meiotic drivers bias gametogenesis to ensure their transmission into more than half the offspring of a heterozygote. In &lt;italic&gt;Schizosaccharomyces pombe&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;wtf&lt;/italic&gt; meiotic drivers destroy the meiotic products (spores) that do not inherit the driver from a heterozygote, thereby reducing fertility. &lt;italic&gt;wtf&lt;/italic&gt; drivers encode both a Wtf&lt;sup&gt;poison&lt;/sup&gt; protein and a Wtf&lt;sup&gt;antidote&lt;/sup&gt; protein using alternative transcriptional start sites. Here, we analyze how the expression and localization of the Wtf proteins are regulated to achieve drive. We show that transcriptional timing and selective protein exclusion from developing spores ensure that all spores are exposed to Wtf4&lt;sup&gt;poison&lt;/sup&gt;, but only the spores that inherit &lt;italic&gt;wtf4&lt;/italic&gt; receive a dose of Wtf4&lt;sup&gt;antidote&lt;/sup&gt; sufficient for survival. In addition, we show that the Mei4 transcription factor, a master regulator of meiosis, controls the expression of the &lt;italic&gt;wtf4&lt;sup&gt;poison&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; transcript. This dual transcriptional regulation, which includes the use of a critical meiotic transcription factor, likely complicates the universal suppression of &lt;italic&gt;wtf&lt;/italic&gt; genes without concomitantly disrupting spore viability. We propose that these features contribute to the evolutionary success of the &lt;italic&gt;wtf&lt;/italic&gt; drivers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Killer meiotic drivers are one type of selfish DNA sequence. When only one copy of a killer meiotic driver is found in a genome, the driver is expected to be transmitted to only half of the gametes (e.g. eggs or sperm). Killer meiotic drivers, however, kill developing gametes that do not inherit them, giving the driver a transmission advantage into the next generation. The molecular mechanisms used by these killers are not well understood. In this work, we analyzed how one killer meiotic driver, &lt;italic&gt;wtf4&lt;/italic&gt; from fission yeast, ensures targeted gamete (spore) killing. Previous work showed that &lt;italic&gt;wtf&lt;/italic&gt; meiotic drivers encode a poison protein that is transmitted to all spores and an antidote protein that rescues only spores that inherit the locus. Here, we show that different timing of the expression of the two proteins, combined with differential inclusion of the proteins in developing spores, both contribute to targeted spore killing. We also demonstrate that &lt;italic&gt;wtf4&lt;/italic&gt; exploits an essential gene expression pathway, making it difficult for the genome to prevent this locus from being expressed and killing. This extends our knowledge both of how these genetic parasites act and how they are equipped to evade host suppression mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462505" rel="alternate" title="S. pombe wtf genes use dual transcriptional regulation and selective protein exclusion from spores to cause meiotic drive (21 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461443</id><title>Zebrafish Information Network, the knowledgebase for Danio rerio research (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.196998+00:00</updated><author><name>Yvonne M. Bradford</name></author><author><name>Ceri E. Van Slyke</name></author><author><name>Amy Singer</name></author><author><name>Holly Paddock</name></author><author><name>Anne Eagle</name></author><author><name>David Fashena</name></author><author><name>Douglas G. Howe</name></author><author><name>Ken Frazer</name></author><author><name>Ryan Martin</name></author><author><name>Christian Pich</name></author><author><name>Sridhar Ramachandran</name></author><author><name>Leyla Ruzicka</name></author><author><name>Monte Westerfield</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Zebrafish Information Network (ZFIN, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://zfin.org"&gt;zfin.org&lt;/ext-link&gt;) is the central repository for zebrafish genetic and genomic data. ZFIN expertly curates, integrates, and displays zebrafish data including genes, alleles, human disease models, gene expression, phenotype, gene function, orthology, morpholino, CRISPR, TALEN, and antibodies. ZFIN makes zebrafish research data Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and Reusable (FAIR) through nomenclature, curatorial and annotation activities, web interfaces, and data downloads. ZFIN is a founding member of the Alliance of Genome Resources, providing zebrafish data for integration into the cross species platform as well as contributing to model organism data harmonization efforts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461443" rel="alternate" title="Zebrafish Information Network, the knowledgebase for Danio rerio research (17 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461757</id><title>Leafy and Weedy Seadragon Genomes Connect Genic and Repetitive DNA Features to the Extravagant Biology of Syngnathid Fishes (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.197348+00:00</updated><author><name>Clayton M. Small</name></author><author><name>Hope M. Healey</name></author><author><name>Mark C. Currey</name></author><author><name>Emily A. Beck</name></author><author><name>Julian Catchen</name></author><author><name>Angela S. P. Lin</name></author><author><name>William A. Cresko</name></author><author><name>Susan Bassham</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Seadragons are a remarkable lineage of teleost fishes, and they are members of the family Syngnathidae renowned for having evolved male pregnancy. Comprising three known species, seadragons are widely recognized and admired for their fantastical body forms and coloration, and their specific habitat requirements have made them flagship representatives for marine conservation and natural history interests. Until recently, a gap has been the lack of significant genomic resources for seadragons. We have produced gene-annotated, chromosome-scale genome models for the leafy and weedy seadragon to advance investigations into evolutionary innovation and elaboration of morphological traits in seadragons as well as their pipefish and seahorse relatives. We identified several interesting features specific to seadragon genomes, including divergent non-coding regions near a developmental gene important for integumentary outgrowth, a high genome-wide density of repetitive DNA, and recent expansions of transposable elements and a vesicular trafficking gene family. Surprisingly, comparative analyses leveraging the seadragon genomes and additional syngnathid and outgroup genomes revealed striking, syngnathid-specific losses in the family of fibroblast growth factors (FGFs), which likely involve re-organization of highly conserved gene regulatory networks in ways that have not previously been documented in natural populations. The resources presented here serve as important tools for future evolutionary studies of developmental processes in syngnathids and will be a key resource for conservation studies of the extravagant seadragons and their relatives.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461757" rel="alternate" title="Leafy and Weedy Seadragon Genomes Connect Genic and Repetitive DNA Features to the Extravagant Biology of Syngnathid Fishes (14 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461579</id><title>Multi-context genetic modeling of transcriptional regulation resolves novel disease loci (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.197662+00:00</updated><author><name>Mike Thompson</name></author><author><name>Mary Grace Gordon</name></author><author><name>Andrew Lu</name></author><author><name>Anchit Tandon</name></author><author><name>Eran Halperin</name></author><author><name>Alexander Gusev</name></author><author><name>Chun Jimmie Ye</name></author><author><name>Brunilda Balliu</name></author><author><name>Noah Zaitlen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A majority of the variants identified in genome-wide association studies fall in non-coding regions of the genome, indicating their mechanism of impact is mediated via gene expression. Leveraging this hypothesis, transcriptome-wide association studies (TWAS) have assisted in both the interpretation and discovery of additional genes associated with complex traits. However, existing methods for conducting TWAS do not take full advantage of the intra-individual correlation inherently present in multi-context expression studies and do not properly adjust for multiple testing across contexts. We developed CONTENT— a computationally efficient method with proper cross-context false discovery correction that leverages correlation structure across contexts to improve power and generate context-specific and context-shared components of expression. We applied CONTENT to bulk multi-tissue and single-cell RNA-seq data sets and show that CONTENT leads to a 42% (bulk) and 110% (single cell) increase in the number of genetically predicted genes relative to previous approaches. Interestingly, we find the context-specific component of expression comprises 30% of heritability in tissue-level bulk data and 75% in single-cell data, consistent with cell type heterogeneity in bulk tissue. In the context of TWAS, CONTENT increased the number of gene-phenotype associations discovered by over 47% relative to previous methods across 22 complex traits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461579" rel="alternate" title="Multi-context genetic modeling of transcriptional regulation resolves novel disease loci (12 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.17.460835</id><title>Identification and Functional Annotation of Long Intergenic Non-coding RNAs in the Brassicaceae (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.197892+00:00</updated><author><name>Kyle Palos</name></author><author><name>Anna C. Nelson Dittrich</name></author><author><name>Li’ang Yu</name></author><author><name>Jordan R. Brock</name></author><author><name>Larry Wu</name></author><author><name>Ewelina Sokolowska</name></author><author><name>Aleksandra Skirycz</name></author><author><name>Polly Hsu</name></author><author><name>Eric Lyons</name></author><author><name>Mark A. Beilstein</name></author><author><name>Andrew D. L. Nelson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Long intergenic noncoding RNAs (lincRNAs) are a large yet enigmatic class of eukaryotic transcripts with critical biological functions. Despite the wealth of RNA-seq data available, lincRNA identification lags in the plant lineage. In addition, there is a need for a harmonized identification and annotation effort to enable cross-species functional and genomic comparisons. In this study we processed &amp;gt;24 Tbp of RNA-seq data from &amp;gt;16,000 experiments to identify ~130,000 lincRNAs in four Brassicaceae: &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;Camelina sativa, Brassica rapa&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;Eutrema salsugineum&lt;/italic&gt;. We used Nanopore RNA-seq, transcriptome-wide structural information, peptide data, and epigenomic data to characterize these lincRNAs and identify functional motifs. We then used comparative genomic and transcriptomic approaches to highlight lincRNAs in our dataset with sequence or transcriptional evolutionary conservation, including lincRNAs transcribed adjacent to orthologous genes that display little sequence similarity and likely function as transcriptional regulators. Finally, we used guilt-by-association techniques to further classify these lincRNAs according to putative function. LincRNAs with Brassicaceae-conserved putative miRNA binding motifs, short ORFs, and whose expression is modulated by abiotic stress are a few of the annotations that will prioritize and guide future functional analyses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.17.460835" rel="alternate" title="Identification and Functional Annotation of Long Intergenic Non-coding RNAs in the Brassicaceae (9 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462135</id><title>Bursts of recent transposable element activity and signatures of element removal in the monarch genome, Danaus plexippus (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.198183+00:00</updated><author><name>Tobias Baril</name></author><author><name>Alexander Hayward</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lepidoptera (butterflies and moths) are an important model system in ecology and evolution. A high-quality chromosomal genome assembly of the monarch butterfly (&lt;italic&gt;Danaus plexippus&lt;/italic&gt;), famous for its North American migration, is available but lacks an in-depth transposable element (TE) annotation. This provides an opportunity to explore host-TE interactions, and the impact TEs have in shaping the monarch genome.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;6.47% of the monarch genome is comprised of TEs, a reduction of 6.59% compared to the original TE annotation performed on the draft genome assembly. TE content is low compared to two closely related species, &lt;italic&gt;Danaus chrysippus&lt;/italic&gt; (26.70%) and &lt;italic&gt;Danaus melanippus&lt;/italic&gt; (11.87%). The biggest contributors to genome size in the monarch are LINEs and &lt;italic&gt;Penelope&lt;/italic&gt;-like elements, and 37.7% of TE content is contributed by five newly identified TE families (two LINE, two &lt;italic&gt;Penelope&lt;/italic&gt;-like, and one SINE). Some young DNA TE families show similar activity profiles to these LINEs, with their success putatively due to horizontal transposon transfer from species sharing the same environment. There are several recent peaks of TE activity in the monarch, with little evidence for peaks of activity more anciently. LINE fragments demonstrate signatures of genomic deletions as reported by studies on &lt;italic&gt;Heliconius&lt;/italic&gt; butterflies, indicating a high rate of TE turnover. Given previous associations in other species, we investigated the association of TEs with wing colouration and immune genes. We find a single unclassified element 7kb upstream of the myosin gene locus, associated with wing colouration, and 49 immune genes with TEs within 5kb upstream of the transcription start site, presenting the potential for the involvement of TEs in regulatory functions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We provide an in-depth TE annotation and analysis of TE diversity and evolution for the monarch genome. We identify highly successful novel DNA TE families, mirroring the activity profile of the most successful LINEs. We also find evidence of ongoing TE expansion and removal in the monarch, highlighting the dynamic nature of repeat content in genomes over time. Further in-depth comparative studies across closely related species will be beneficial to our understanding of the evolutionary dynamics of TEs and the processes leading to their contrasting distributions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462135" rel="alternate" title="Bursts of recent transposable element activity and signatures of element removal in the monarch genome, Danaus plexippus (9 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461369</id><title>Genetic effect modification of cis-acting C-reactive protein variants in cardiometabolic disease status (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.198448+00:00</updated><author><name>Jie Zheng</name></author><author><name>Haotian Tang</name></author><author><name>Matthew Lyon</name></author><author><name>Neil M. Davies</name></author><author><name>Venexia Walker</name></author><author><name>James S. Floyd</name></author><author><name>Thomas R. Austin</name></author><author><name>Ali Shojaie</name></author><author><name>Bruce M. Psaty</name></author><author><name>Tom R. Gaunt</name></author><author><name>George Davey Smith</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mendelian randomization (MR) studies carried out among patients with a particular health condition should establish the genetic instrument influences the exposure in that subgroup, however this is normally investigated in the general population. Here, we investigated whether the genetic associations of four cis-acting C-reactive protein (CRP) variants differed between participants with and without three cardiometabolic conditions: obesity, type 2 diabetes, and cardiovascular disease. Associations of cis-genetic variants with CRP differed between obese and non-obese individuals. A multivariable analysis suggested strong independent associations of the gene-by-body mass index (BMI) interaction on CRP (P&amp;lt;1.18×10&lt;sup&gt;−8&lt;/sup&gt; for the CRP variants). Applying MR, we observed strong causal effect of BMI on CRP (P=2.14×10&lt;sup&gt;−65&lt;/sup&gt;). In summary, our study indicates that genetic associations with CRP differ across disease sub-groups, with evidence to suggest that BMI is an effect modifier. MR studies of disease progression should report on the genetic instrument-exposure association in the disease subgroup under investigation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461369" rel="alternate" title="Genetic effect modification of cis-acting C-reactive protein variants in cardiometabolic disease status (9 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462396</id><title>Quantifying mediation between omics layers and complex traits (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.198786+00:00</updated><author><name>Marie C. Sadler</name></author><author><name>Chiara Auwerx</name></author><author><name>Eleonora Porcu</name></author><author><name>Zoltán Kutalik</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;High-dimensional omics datasets provide valuable resources to determine the causal role of molecular traits in mediating the path from genotype to phenotype. Making use of quantitative trait loci (QTL) and genome-wide association studies (GWASs) summary statistics, we developed a multivariable Mendelian randomization (MVMR) framework to quantify the connectivity between three omics layers (DNA methylome (DNAm), transcriptome and proteome) and their cascading causal impact on complex traits and diseases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Evaluating 50 complex traits, we found that on average 37.8% (95% CI: [36.0%-39.5%]) of DNAm-to-trait effects were mediated through transcripts in the &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-region, while only 15.8% (95% CI: [11.9%-19.6%]) are mediated through proteins in &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;. DNAm sites typically regulate multiple transcripts, and while found to predominantly decrease gene expression, this was only the case for 53.4% across ≈ 47,000 significant DNAm-transcript pairs. The average mediation proportion for transcript-to-trait effects through proteins (encoded for by the assessed transcript or located in &lt;italic&gt;trans&lt;/italic&gt;) was estimated to be 5.27% (95%CI: [4.11%-6.43%]). Notable differences in the transcript and protein QTL architectures were detected with only 22% of protein levels being causally driven by their corresponding transcript levels. Several regulatory mechanisms were hypothesized including an example where cg10385390 (chr1:8’022’505) increases the risk of irritable bowel disease by reducing &lt;italic&gt;PARK7&lt;/italic&gt; transcript and protein expression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The proposed integrative framework identified putative causal chains through omics layers providing a powerful tool to map GWAS signals. Quantification of causal effects between successive layers indicated that molecular mechanisms can be more complex than what the central dogma of biology would suggest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462396" rel="alternate" title="Quantifying mediation between omics layers and complex traits (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462044</id><title>TT-Mars: Structural Variants Assessment Based on Haplotype-resolved Assemblies (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.199025+00:00</updated><author><name>Jianzhi Yang</name></author><author><name>Mark Chaisson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Variant benchmarking is a critical component of method development and evaluating the accuracy of studies of genetic variation. Currently, the best approach to evaluate the accuracy of a callset is the comparison against a well curated gold standard. In repetitive regions of the genome it may be difficult to establish what is the truth for a call, for example when different alignment scoring metrics provide equally supported but different variant calls in on the same data. Here we provide an alternative approach, TT-Mars, that takes advantage of the recent production of high-quality haplotype-resolved genome assemblies by evaluating variant calls based on how well their call reflects the content of the assembly, rather than comparing calls themselves. We used TT-Mars to assess callsets from different SV discovery methods on multiple human genome samples and demonstrated that it is capable at accurately classifying true positive and false positive SVs. On the HG002 personal genome, TT-Mars recapitulates 96.0%-99.6% of the validations made using the Genome in a Bottle gold standard callset evaluated by truvari, and evaluates an additional 121-10,966 variants across different callsets. Furthermore, with a group of high-quality assemblies, TT-Mars can evaluate performance of SV calling algorithms as a distribution rather than a point estimate. We also compare TT-Mars against the long-read based validation tool, VaPoR, and when assembly-based variant calls produced by dipcall are used as a gold standard. Compared with VaPoR, TT-Mars analyzes more calls on a long read callset by assessing more short variant calls (&amp;lt; 100 bases), while requiring smaller input. Compared with validation using dipcall variants, TT-Mars analyzes 1,497-2,229 more calls on long read callsets and has favorable results when candidate calls are fragmented into multiple calls in alignments. TT-Mars is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/ChaissonLab/TT-Mars.git"&gt;https://github.com/ChaissonLab/TT-Mars.git&lt;/ext-link&gt; with accompanying assembly data and corresponding liftover files.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462044" rel="alternate" title="TT-Mars: Structural Variants Assessment Based on Haplotype-resolved Assemblies (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461398</id><title>Dominant negative effects of SCN5A missense variants (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.199270+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew J. O’Neill</name></author><author><name>Ayesha Muhammad</name></author><author><name>Bian Li</name></author><author><name>Yuko Wada</name></author><author><name>Lynn Hall</name></author><author><name>Joseph F. Solus</name></author><author><name>Laura Short</name></author><author><name>Dan M. Roden</name></author><author><name>Andrew M. Glazer</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Up to 30% of patients with Brugada Syndrome (BrS) carry loss-of-function (LoF) variants in the cardiac sodium channel gene &lt;italic&gt;SCN5A&lt;/italic&gt;. Recent studies have suggested that the &lt;italic&gt;SCN5A&lt;/italic&gt; protein product Na&lt;sub&gt;V&lt;/sub&gt;1.5 can form dimers and exert dominant negative effects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We identified 35 LoF variants (&amp;lt;10% peak current compared to wild type (WT)) and 15 partial LoF variants (10-50% peak current compared to WT) that we assessed for dominant negative behavior. &lt;italic&gt;SCN5A&lt;/italic&gt; variants were studied in HEK293T cells alone or in heterozygous co-expression with WT &lt;italic&gt;SCN5A&lt;/italic&gt; using automated patch clamp. To assess clinical risk, we compared the prevalence of dominant negative vs. putative haploinsufficient (frameshift/splice site) variants in a BrS case consortium and the gnomAD population database.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In heterozygous expression with WT, 32/35 LoF variants and 6/15 partial LoF showed reduction to &amp;lt;75% of WT-alone peak I&lt;sub&gt;Na&lt;/sub&gt;, demonstrating a dominant negative effect. Carriers of dominant negative LoF missense variants had an enriched disease burden compared to putative haploinsufficient variant carriers (2.7-fold enrichment in BrS cases, p=0.019).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most &lt;italic&gt;SCN5A&lt;/italic&gt; missense LoF variants exert a dominant negative effect. Cohort analyses reveal that this class of variant confers an especially high burden of BrS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461398" rel="alternate" title="Dominant negative effects of SCN5A missense variants (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461848</id><title>Broadscale evolutionary analysis of eukaryotic DDE transposons (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.201113+00:00</updated><author><name>Mathilde Dupeyron</name></author><author><name>Tobias Baril</name></author><author><name>Alexander Hayward</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;DDE transposons are widespread selfish genetic elements, often comprising a large proportion of eukaryotic genomic content. DDE transposons have also made important contributions to varied host functions during eukaryotic evolution, and their transposases may be the most abundant and ubiquitous genes in nature. Yet much remains unknown about their basic biology. We employ a broadscale screen of DDE transposase diversity to characterise major evolutionary patterns for all 19 DDE transposon superfamilies. We identify considerable variation in DDE transposon superfamily size, and find a dominant association with animal hosts. While few DDE transposon superfamilies specialise in plants or fungi, the four largest superfamilies contain major plant-associated clades, at least partially underlying their relative success. We recover a pattern of host conservation among DDE transposon lineages, punctuated by occasional horizontal transfer to distantly related hosts. Host range and horizontal transfer are strongly positively correlated with DDE transposon superfamily size, arguing against variation in the capacity for generalism. We find that rates of horizontal transfer decrease sharply with increasing levels of host taxonomy, supporting the existence of host-associated barriers to DDE transposon spread. Overall, despite their relatively simple genetic structure, our results imply that trade-offs in host adaptation are important in defining DDE transposon-host relationships and evolution. In addition, our study provides a phylogenetic framework to facilitate the identification and further analysis of DDE transposons.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461848" rel="alternate" title="Broadscale evolutionary analysis of eukaryotic DDE transposons (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461747</id><title>Single cell Iso-Sequencing enables rapid genome annotation for scRNAseq analysis (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.201427+00:00</updated><author><name>Hope M. Healey</name></author><author><name>Susan Bassham</name></author><author><name>William A. Cresko</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single cell RNA sequencing (scRNAseq) is a powerful technique that continues to expand across various biological applications. However, incomplete 3′ UTR annotations in less developed or non-model systems can impede single cell analysis resulting in genes that are partially or completely uncounted. Performing scRNAseq with incomplete 3′ UTR annotations can impede the identification of cell identities and gene expression patterns and lead to erroneous biological inferences. We demonstrate that performing single cell isoform sequencing (ScISOr-Seq) in tandem with scRNAseq can rapidly improve 3′ UTR annotations. Using threespine stickleback fish (&lt;italic&gt;Gasterosteus aculeatus&lt;/italic&gt;), we show that gene models resulting from a minimal embryonic ScISOr-Seq dataset retained 26.1% greater scRNAseq reads than gene models from Ensembl alone. Furthermore, pooling our ScISOr-Seq isoforms with a previously published adult bulk Iso-Seq dataset from stickleback, and merging the annotation with the Ensembl gene models, resulted in a marginal improvement (+0.8%) over the ScISOr-Seq only dataset. In addition, isoforms identified by ScISOr-Seq included thousands of new splicing variants. The improved gene models obtained using ScISOr-Seq lead to successful identification of cell types and increased the reads identified of many genes in our scRNAseq stickleback dataset. Our work illuminates ScISOr-Seq as a cost-effective and efficient mechanism to rapidly annotate genomes for scRNAseq.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461747" rel="alternate" title="Single cell Iso-Sequencing enables rapid genome annotation for scRNAseq analysis (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461556</id><title>Meta-analysis of immune induced gene expression changes in diverse Drosophila melanogaster innate immune responses (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.201729+00:00</updated><author><name>Ashley L. Waring</name></author><author><name>Joshua Hill</name></author><author><name>Brooke M. Allen</name></author><author><name>Nicholas M. Bretz</name></author><author><name>Nguyen Le</name></author><author><name>Pooja Kr</name></author><author><name>Dakota Fuss</name></author><author><name>Nathan T. Mortimer</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Organisms are commonly infected by a diverse array of pathogen types including bacteria, fungi, viruses, and parasites, and mount functionally distinct responses to each of these varied immune challenges. Host immune responses are characterized by the induction of gene expression in response to infection. However, the extent to which expression changes are shared among responses to distinct pathogens is largely unknown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We performed meta-analysis of gene expression data collected from &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; following infection with a wide array of pathogens. We identified 62 genes that are significantly induced by infection. While many of these infection-induced genes encode known immune response factors, we also identified 21 genes that have not been previously associated with host immunity. Examination of the upstream flanking sequences of the infection-induced genes lead to the identification of two conserved enhancer sites. These sites correspond to conserved binding sites for GATA and nuclear factor κB (NFκB) family transcription factors and are associated with higher levels of transcript induction. We further identified 31 genes with predicted functions in metabolism and organismal development that are significantly downregulated following infection by diverse pathogens.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our study identifies conserved gene expression changes in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; following infection with varied pathogens, and transcription factor families that may regulate this immune induction. These findings provide new insight into transcriptional changes that accompany &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; immunity. They may suggest possible roles for the differentially regulated genes in innate immune responses to diverse classes of pathogens, and serve to identify candidate genes for further empirical study of these processes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461556" rel="alternate" title="Meta-analysis of immune induced gene expression changes in diverse Drosophila melanogaster innate immune responses (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462680</id><title>Evolutionary insights into primate skeletal gene regulation using a comparative cell culture model (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.201939+00:00</updated><author><name>Genevieve Housman</name></author><author><name>Emilie Briscoe</name></author><author><name>Yoav Gilad</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The evolution of complex skeletal traits in primates was likely influenced by both genetic and environmental factors. Because skeletal tissues are notoriously challenging to study using functional genomic approaches, they remain poorly characterized even in humans, let alone across multiple species. The challenges involved in obtaining functional genomic data from the skeleton, combined with the difficulty of obtaining such tissues from nonhuman apes, motivated us to consider an alternative &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; system with which to comparatively study gene regulation in skeletal cell types. Specifically, we differentiated six human and six chimpanzee induced pluripotent stem cell lines (&lt;bold&gt;iPSCs&lt;/bold&gt;) into mesenchymal stem cells (&lt;bold&gt;MSCs&lt;/bold&gt;) and subsequently into osteogenic cells (bone cells). We validated differentiation using standard methods and collected single-cell RNA sequencing data from over 100,000 cells across multiple samples and replicates at each stage of differentiation. While most genes that we examined display conserved patterns of expression across species, hundreds of genes are differentially expressed (&lt;bold&gt;DE&lt;/bold&gt;) between humans and chimpanzees within and across stages of osteogenic differentiation. Some of these interspecific DE genes show functional enrichments relevant in skeletal tissue trait development. Moreover, topic modeling indicates that interspecific gene programs become more pronounced as cells mature. Overall, we propose that this &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; model can be used to identify interspecific regulatory differences that may have contributed to skeletal trait differences between species.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Primates display a range of skeletal morphologies and susceptibilities to skeletal diseases, but the molecular basis of these phenotypic differences is unclear. Studies of gene expression variation in primate skeletal tissues are extremely restricted due to the ethical and practical challenges associated with collecting samples. Nevertheless, the ability to study gene regulation in primate skeletal tissues is crucial for understanding how the primate skeleton has evolved. We therefore developed a comparative primate skeletal cell culture model that allows us to access a spectrum of human and chimpanzee cell types as they differentiate from stem cells into bone cells. While most gene expression patterns are conserved across species, we also identified hundreds of differentially expressed genes between humans and chimpanzees within and across stages of differentiation. We also classified cells by osteogenic stage and identified additional interspecific differentially expressed genes which may contribute to skeletal trait differences. We anticipate that this model will be extremely useful for exploring questions related to gene regulation variation in primate bone biology and development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462680" rel="alternate" title="Evolutionary insights into primate skeletal gene regulation using a comparative cell culture model (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461294</id><title>miRNAs Copy Number Variations repertoire as hallmark indicator of cancer species predisposition (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.202173+00:00</updated><author><name>Chiara Vischioni</name></author><author><name>Fabio Bove</name></author><author><name>Federica Mandreoli</name></author><author><name>Riccardo Martoglia</name></author><author><name>Valentino Pisi</name></author><author><name>Cristian Taccioli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aging is one of the hallmarks of multiple human diseases, including cancer. However, the molecular mechanisms associated with high longevity and low cancer incidence percentages characterizing long-living organisms have not been fully understood yet. In this context, we hypothesized that variations in the number of copies (CNVs) of specific genes may protect some species from cancer onset. Based on the statistical comparison of gene copy numbers within the genomes of cancer -prone and -resistant organisms, we identified novel gene targets linked to the tumor predisposition of a species, such as CD52, SAT1 and SUMO protein family members. Furthermore, for the first time, we were able to discover that, considering the entire genome copy number landscape of a species, microRNAs (miRNAs) are among the most significant gene families enriched for cancer progression and predisposition. However, their roles in ageing and cancer resistance from a comparative perspective remains largely unknown. To this end, we identified through bioinformatics analysis, several alterations in miRNAs copy number patterns, represented by duplication of miR-221, miR-222, miR-21, miR-372, miR-30b, miR-30d and miR-31 among others. Therefore, our analysis provides the first evidence that an altered copy number miRNAs signature is able to statistically discriminate species more susceptible to cancer than those that are tumor resistant, helping researchers to discover new possible therapeutic targets involved in tumor predisposition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461294" rel="alternate" title="miRNAs Copy Number Variations repertoire as hallmark indicator of cancer species predisposition (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462095</id><title>High-resolution genetic mapping of the mucosa-associated gut microbiome in hybrid mice provides novel insight on the impact of host genetics (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.202636+00:00</updated><author><name>Shauni Doms</name></author><author><name>Hanna Fokt</name></author><author><name>Malte Christoph Rühlemann</name></author><author><name>Cecilia J. Chung</name></author><author><name>Axel Künstner</name></author><author><name>Saleh Ibrahim</name></author><author><name>Andre Franke</name></author><author><name>Leslie M. Turner</name></author><author><name>John F. Baines</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Determining the forces that shape diversity in host-associated bacterial communities is critical to understanding the evolution and maintenance of meta-organisms. To gain novel insight on the genetics of gut microbial traits, we employed a powerful approach using inbred lines derived from the hybrid zone of two incipient house mouse species. We identify a high number of mucosa-associated bacterial taxa with significant heritability estimates, particularly for 16S rRNA transcript-based traits. Interestingly, heritability estimates also positively correlate with cospeciation rate estimates. Association mapping identifies 443 loci influencing 123 taxa, whose narrow genomic intervals enable promising individual candidate genes and pathways to be pinpointed. These results indicate a unique genetic architecture for cospeciating taxa, a clear enrichment for several classes of human disease, and identify important functional categories including innate immunity and G-protein-coupled receptors, whose role in host-microbe interactions diverge as new species form.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462095" rel="alternate" title="High-resolution genetic mapping of the mucosa-associated gut microbiome in hybrid mice provides novel insight on the impact of host genetics (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461754</id><title>The germline-specific region of the sea lamprey genome plays a key role in spermatogenesis (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.202927+00:00</updated><author><name>Tamanna Yasmin</name></author><author><name>Phil Grayson</name></author><author><name>Margaret F. Docker</name></author><author><name>Sara V. Good</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The sea lamprey genome undergoes programmed genome rearrangement (PGR) in which ∼20% is jettisoned from somatic cells soon after fertilization. Although the role of PGR in embryonic development has been studied, the role of the germline-specific region (GSR) in gonad development is unknown. We analysed RNA-sequence data from 28 sea lamprey gonads sampled across life-history stages, generated a genome-guided &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; superTransciptome with annotations, and identified genes in the GSR. We found that the 638 genes in the GSR are enriched for reproductive processes, exhibit 36x greater odds of being expressed in testes than ovaries, show little evidence of conserved synteny with other chordates, and most have putative paralogues in the GSR and/or somatic genomes. Further, several of these genes play known roles in sex determination and differentiation in other vertebrates. We conclude that the GSR of sea lamprey plays an important role in testicular differentiation and potentially sex determination.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461754" rel="alternate" title="The germline-specific region of the sea lamprey genome plays a key role in spermatogenesis (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.19.460999</id><title>Genomic Heritability: A Ragged Diagonal Between Bias and Variance (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.203105+00:00</updated><author><name>Mitchell J. Feldmann</name></author><author><name>Hans-Peter Piepho</name></author><author><name>Steven J. Knapp</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many important traits in plants, animals, and microbes are polygenic and are therefore difficult to improve through traditional marker-assisted selection. Genomic prediction addresses this by enabling the inclusion of all genetic data in a mixed model framework. The main method for predicting breeding values is genomic best linear unbiased prediction (GBLUP), which uses the realized genomic relationship or kinship matrix (&lt;bold&gt;K&lt;/bold&gt;) to connect genotype to phenotype. The use of relationship matrices allows information to be shared for estimating the genetic values for observed entries and predicting genetic values for unobserved entries. One of the key parameters of such models is genomic heritability &lt;inline-formula&gt;&lt;alternatives&gt;&lt;inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="460999v1_inline1.gif" /&gt;&lt;/alternatives&gt;&lt;/inline-formula&gt;, or the variance of a trait associated with a genome-wide sample of DNA polymorphisms. Here we discuss the relationship between several common methods for calculating the genomic relationship matrix and propose a new matrix based on the average semivariance that yields accurate estimates of genomic variance in the observed population regardless of the focal population quality as well as accurate breeding value predictions in unobserved samples. Notably, our proposed method is highly similar to the approach presented by Legarra (2016) despite different mathematical derivations and statistical perspectives and only deviates from the classic approach presented in VanRaden (2008) by a scaling factor. With current approaches, we found that the genomic heritability tends to be either over- or underestimated depending on the scaling and centering applied to the marker matrix (&lt;bold&gt;Z&lt;/bold&gt;), the value of the average diagonal element of &lt;bold&gt;K&lt;/bold&gt;, and the assortment of alleles and heterozygosity (&lt;italic&gt;H&lt;/italic&gt;) in the observed population and that, unlike its predecessors, our newly proposed kinship matrix &lt;bold&gt;K&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;italic&gt;ASV&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; yields accurate estimates of &lt;inline-formula&gt;&lt;alternatives&gt;&lt;inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="460999v1_inline2.gif" /&gt;&lt;/alternatives&gt;&lt;/inline-formula&gt; in the observed population, generalizes to larger populations, and produces BLUPs equivalent to common methods in plants and animals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.19.460999" rel="alternate" title="Genomic Heritability: A Ragged Diagonal Between Bias and Variance (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461734</id><title>Transcriptome-wide association and prediction for carotenoids and tocochromanols in fresh sweet corn kernels (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.203282+00:00</updated><author><name>Jenna Hershberger</name></author><author><name>Ryokei Tanaka</name></author><author><name>Joshua C. Wood</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Kaczmar</name></author><author><name>Di Wu</name></author><author><name>John P. Hamilton</name></author><author><name>Dean DellaPenna</name></author><author><name>C. Robin Buell</name></author><author><name>Michael A. Gore</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sweet corn is consistently one of the most highly consumed vegetables in the U.S., providing a valuable opportunity to increase nutrient intake through biofortification. Significant variation for carotenoid (provitamin A, lutein, zeaxanthin) and tocochromanol (vitamin E, antioxidants) levels is present in temperate sweet corn germplasm, yet previous genome-wide association studies (GWAS) of these traits have been limited by low statistical power and mapping resolution. Here, we employed a high-quality transcriptomic dataset collected from fresh sweet corn kernels to conduct transcriptome-wide association studies (TWAS) and transcriptome prediction studies for 39 carotenoid and tocochromanol traits. In agreement with previous GWAS findings, TWAS detected significant associations for four causal genes, &lt;italic&gt;β-carotene hydroxylase (crtRB1)&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;lycopene epsilon cyclase&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;lcyE&lt;/italic&gt;), &lt;italic&gt;γ-tocopherol methyltransferase&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;vte4&lt;/italic&gt;), and &lt;italic&gt;homogentisate geranylgeranyltransferase&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;hggt1&lt;/italic&gt;) on a transcriptome-wide level. Pathway-level analysis revealed additional associations for &lt;italic&gt;deoxy-xylulose synthase2&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;dxs2&lt;/italic&gt;), &lt;italic&gt;diphosphocytidyl methyl erythritol synthase2&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;dmes2&lt;/italic&gt;), &lt;italic&gt;cytidine methyl kinase1&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;cmk1&lt;/italic&gt;), and &lt;italic&gt;geranylgeranyl hydrogenase1&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;ggh1&lt;/italic&gt;), of which, &lt;italic&gt;dmes2, cmk1&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;ggh1&lt;/italic&gt; have not previously been identified through maize association studies. Evaluation of prediction models incorporating genome-wide markers and transcriptome-wide abundances revealed a trait-dependent benefit to the inclusion of both genomic and transcriptomic data over solely genomic data, but both transcriptome- and genome-wide datasets outperformed &lt;italic&gt;a priori&lt;/italic&gt; candidate gene-targeted prediction models for most traits. Altogether, this study represents an important step towards understanding the role of regulatory variation in the accumulation of vitamins in fresh sweet corn kernels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Core Ideas&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transcriptomic data aid the study of vitamin levels in fresh sweet corn kernels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;crtRB1, lcyE, dxs2, dmes2&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;cmk1&lt;/italic&gt; were associated with carotenoid traits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;vte4, hggt1&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;ggh1&lt;/italic&gt; were associated with tocochromanol traits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transcriptomic data boosted predictive ability over genomic data alone for some traits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Joint transcriptome- and genome-wide models achieved the highest predictive abilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461734" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptome-wide association and prediction for carotenoids and tocochromanols in fresh sweet corn kernels (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461665</id><title>RNA nucleotide repeats induce mitochondrial dysfunction and the ribosome-associated quality control (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.203489+00:00</updated><author><name>Joana Teixeira</name></author><author><name>Anu-Mari Harju</name></author><author><name>Alaa Othman</name></author><author><name>Ove Eriksson</name></author><author><name>Ana Brandão</name></author><author><name>Brendan J. Battersby</name></author><author><name>Susana M. D. A. Garcia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nucleotide repeat sequences are prevalent in the genome and expansion of these sequences is associated with more than 40 neuromuscular disorders. To understand the pathogenic mechanisms underlying RNA-repeat toxicity, we performed a genetic screen in a &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/italic&gt; model expressing an expanded CUG repeat specifically in the muscle. Here, we show that expression of this RNA repeat impairs motility by mitochondrial dysfunction, disrupting mitochondrial morphology and respiration. The phenotype is dependent on the RNA-binding factor MBL-1 and requires factors from the ribosome-associated protein quality control complex. Furthermore, Coenzyme Q supplementation rescued the motility impairment and all of the mitochondrial phenotypes. Together, our data reveal the importance of mitochondrial dysfunction in the molecular pathogenesis of RNA repeat expansion disorders.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461665" rel="alternate" title="RNA nucleotide repeats induce mitochondrial dysfunction and the ribosome-associated quality control (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461648</id><title>Intraspecific de novo gene birth revealed by presence–absence variant genes in Caenorhabditis elegans (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.203675+00:00</updated><author><name>Bo Yun Lee</name></author><author><name>Jun Kim</name></author><author><name>Junho Lee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genes embed their evolutionary history in the form of various alleles. Presence–absence variants (PAVs) are extreme cases of such alleles, where a gene present in one haplotype does not exist in another. Since PAVs may result from either birth or death of a gene, PAV genes and their alternative alleles, if available, can represent a basis for rapid intraspecific gene evolution. Here, we traced a possible evolution of PAV genes in the PD1074 and CB4856 &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; strains as well as their alternative alleles found in other 14 wild strains, using long-read sequencing technologies. We updated the CB4856 genome by filling 18 gaps and identified 50 novel genes and 7,460 novel isoforms from both strains. We verified 328 PAV genes, out of which 48 were &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt;-specific. Among these possible newly-born genes, 13 had alternative alleles in other wild strains and, in particular, alternative alleles of three genes showed signatures active transposons. Alternative alleles of four other genes showed another type of signature reflected in accumulation of small insertions or deletions. Our results exemplify that research on gene evolution using both species-specific PAV genes and their alternative alleles is expected to provide new perspectives for how genes evolve.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461648" rel="alternate" title="Intraspecific de novo gene birth revealed by presence–absence variant genes in Caenorhabditis elegans (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461537</id><title>A Drosophila Su(H) Model of Adams-Oliver Syndrome Reveals Notch Cofactor Titration as a Mechanism Underlying Developmental Defects (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.203861+00:00</updated><author><name>Ellen K. Gagliani</name></author><author><name>Lisa M. Gutzwiller</name></author><author><name>Yi Kuang</name></author><author><name>Yoshinobu Odaka</name></author><author><name>Phillipp Hoffmeister</name></author><author><name>Stefanie Hauff</name></author><author><name>Aleksandra Turkiewicz</name></author><author><name>Emily Harding-Theobald</name></author><author><name>Patrick J. Dolph</name></author><author><name>Tilman Borggrefe</name></author><author><name>Franz Oswald</name></author><author><name>Brian Gebelein</name></author><author><name>Rhett A. Kovall</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Notch signaling is a conserved pathway that converts extracellular receptor-ligand interactions into changes in gene expression via a single transcription factor (CBF1/RBPJ in mammals; Su(H) in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt;). In humans, RBPJ variants have been linked to Adams-Oliver syndrome (AOS), a rare autosomal dominant disorder characterized by scalp, cranium, and limb defects. Here, we found that a previously described &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila Su(H)&lt;/italic&gt; allele encodes a missense mutation that alters an analogous residue found in an AOS-associated RBPJ variant. Importantly, genetic studies support a model that &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; with a single copy of the AOS-like &lt;italic&gt;Su(H)&lt;/italic&gt; allele behave in an opposing manner as flies with a &lt;italic&gt;Su(H)&lt;/italic&gt; null allele due to a dominant activity of sequestering either the Notch co-activator or the antagonistic Hairless co-repressor. Consistent with this model, AOS-like Su(H) and Rbpj variants decrease DNA binding activity compared to wild type proteins, but these variants do not significantly alter protein binding to the Notch co-activator or the fly and mammalian co-repressors, respectively. Taken together, these data suggest a cofactor sequestration mechanism underlies AOS phenotypes associated with RBPJ variants, whereby a single &lt;italic&gt;RBPJ&lt;/italic&gt; allele encodes a protein with compromised DNA binding activity that retains cofactor binding, resulting in Notch target gene dysregulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461537" rel="alternate" title="A Drosophila Su(H) Model of Adams-Oliver Syndrome Reveals Notch Cofactor Titration as a Mechanism Underlying Developmental Defects (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461289</id><title>Internal oligo(dT) priming in bulk and single cell RNA sequencing (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.204092+00:00</updated><author><name>Marek Svoboda</name></author><author><name>H. Robert Frost</name></author><author><name>Giovanni Bosco</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Significant advances in RNA sequencing have been recently made possible by the use of oligo(dT) primers for simultaneous mRNA enrichment and reverse transcription priming. The associated increase in efficiency has enabled more economical bulk RNA sequencing methods as well as the advent of high throughput single cell RNA sequencing, now already one of the most widely adopted new methods in the study of transcriptomics. However, the effects of off-target oligo(dT) priming on gene expression quantification have not been fully appreciated. In the present study, we describe the extent, the possible causes, and the consequences of internal oligo(dT) priming across multiple publicly available datasets obtained from a variety of bulk and single cell RNA sequencing platforms. In order to explore and address this issue, we developed a computational algorithm for identification of sequencing read alignments that likely resulted from internal oligo(dT) priming and their subsequent removal from the data. Directly comparing filtered datasets to those obtained by an alternative method reveals significant improvements in gene expression measurement. Finally, we infer a list of genes whose expression quantification is most likely to be affected by internal oligo(dT) priming.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461289" rel="alternate" title="Internal oligo(dT) priming in bulk and single cell RNA sequencing (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461946</id><title>The Clock:cycle complex is a major transcriptional regulator of Drosophila photoreceptors that protects the eye from retinal degeneration and oxidative stress (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.204469+00:00</updated><author><name>Juan Jauregui-Lozano</name></author><author><name>Hana Hall</name></author><author><name>Sarah C. Stanhope</name></author><author><name>Kimaya Bakhle</name></author><author><name>Makayla M. Marlin</name></author><author><name>Vikki M. Weake</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The aging eye experiences physiological changes that include decreased visual function and increased risk of retinal degeneration. Although there are transcriptomic signatures in the aging retina that correlate with these physiological changes, the gene regulatory mechanisms that contribute to cellular homeostasis during aging remain to be determined. Here, we integrated ATAC-seq and RNA-seq data to identify 61 transcription factors that showed differential activity in aging &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; photoreceptors. These 61 age-regulated transcription factors include two circadian regulators, Clock and cycle, that showed sustained increases in activity during aging. When we disrupted Clock activity in adult photoreceptors, we observed changes in expression of 15 – 20% of genes including key components of the phototransduction machinery and many eye-specific transcription factors. Using ATAC-seq, we showed that loss of Clock activity leads to changes in activity of 31 transcription factors and causes a progressive decrease in global levels of chromatin accessibility in photoreceptors. Supporting a key role for Clock-dependent transcription in the eye, disruption of Clock activity in photoreceptors also induced light-dependent retinal degeneration and increased oxidative stress, independent of light exposure. Together, our data suggests that the circadian regulators Clock and cycle act as neuroprotective factors in the aging eye by directing gene regulatory networks that maintain expression of the phototransduction machinery and counteract oxidative stress.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461946" rel="alternate" title="The Clock:cycle complex is a major transcriptional regulator of Drosophila photoreceptors that protects the eye from retinal degeneration and oxidative stress (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.458228</id><title>A framework for evaluating edited cell libraries created by massively parallel genome engineering (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.204750+00:00</updated><author><name>Simon Cawley</name></author><author><name>Eric Abbate</name></author><author><name>Christopher G. Abraham</name></author><author><name>Steven Alvarez</name></author><author><name>Mathew Barber</name></author><author><name>Scott Bolte</name></author><author><name>Jocelyne Bruand</name></author><author><name>Deanna M. Church</name></author><author><name>Clint Davis</name></author><author><name>Matt Estes</name></author><author><name>Stephen Federowicz</name></author><author><name>Richard Fox</name></author><author><name>Miles W. Gander</name></author><author><name>Andrew D. Garst</name></author><author><name>Gozde Gencer</name></author><author><name>Paul Hardenbol</name></author><author><name>Thomas Hraha</name></author><author><name>Surbhi Jain</name></author><author><name>Charlie Johnson</name></author><author><name>Kara Juneau</name></author><author><name>Nandini Krishnamurthy</name></author><author><name>Shea Lambert</name></author><author><name>Bryan Leland</name></author><author><name>Francesca Pearson</name></author><author><name>J. Christian J. Ray</name></author><author><name>Chad D. Sanada</name></author><author><name>Timothy M. Shaver</name></author><author><name>Tyson R. Shepherd</name></author><author><name>Eileen C. Spindler</name></author><author><name>Craig A. Struble</name></author><author><name>Maciej H. Swat</name></author><author><name>Stephen Tanner</name></author><author><name>Tian Tian</name></author><author><name>Ken Wishart</name></author><author><name>Michael S. Graige</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genome engineering methodologies are transforming biological research and discovery. Approaches based on CRISPR technology have been broadly adopted and there is growing interest in the generation of massively parallel edited cell libraries. Comparing the libraries generated by these varying approaches is challenging and researchers lack a common framework for defining and assessing the characteristics of these libraries. Here we describe a framework for evaluating massively parallel libraries of edited genomes based on established methods for sampling complex populations. We define specific attributes and metrics that are informative for describing a complex cell library and provide examples for estimating these values. We also connect this analysis to generic phenotyping approaches, using either pooled (typically via a selection assay) or isolate (often referred to as screening) phenotyping approaches. We approach this from the context of creating massively parallel, precisely edited libraries with one edit per cell, though the approach holds for other types of modifications, including libraries containing multiple edits per cell (combinatorial editing). This framework is a critical component for evaluating and comparing new technologies as well as understanding how a massively parallel edited cell library will perform in a given phenotyping approach.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.458228" rel="alternate" title="A framework for evaluating edited cell libraries created by massively parallel genome engineering (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461091</id><title>Gene regulation by DNA methylation is contingent on chromatin accessibility during transgenerational plasticity in the purple sea urchin (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.205248+00:00</updated><author><name>Samuel N Bogan</name></author><author><name>Marie E Strader</name></author><author><name>Gretchen E Hofmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Epigenetic processes are proposed to contribute to phenotypic plasticity. In invertebrates, DNA methylation commonly varies across environments and can correlate or causally associate with phenotype, but its role in transcriptional responses to the environment remains unclear. Maternal environments experienced by the sea urchin &lt;italic&gt;Strongylocentrotus purpuratus&lt;/italic&gt; induce 3 – 6x greater differential CpG methylation in offspring larvae relative to larval developmental environments, suggesting a role for DNA methylation in transgenerational plasticity (TGP). However, a negligible association has been observed between differentially methylated and differentially expressed genes. What gene regulatory roles does invertebrate DNA methylation possess under environmental change, if any? We quantified DNA methylation and gene expression in &lt;italic&gt;S. purpuratus&lt;/italic&gt; larvae exposed to different ecologically relevant conditions during gametogenesis (maternal conditioning) or embryogenesis (developmental conditioning). We modeled differential gene expression and differential splicing under maternal conditioning as functions of DNA methylation, incorporating variables for genomic feature and chromatin accessibility. We detected significant interactions between differential methylation, chromatin accessibility, and genic architecture associated with differential expression and splicing. Observed transcriptional responses to maternal conditioning were also 4 – 13x more likely when accounting for interactions between methylation and chromatin accessibility. Our results provide evidence that DNA methylation possesses multiple functional roles during TGP in &lt;italic&gt;S. purpuratus,&lt;/italic&gt; but its effects are contingent upon other genomic and epigenomic states. Singularly unpredictive of transcription, DNA methylation is likely one cog in the epigenomic machinery contributing to environmental responses and phenotypic plasticity in &lt;italic&gt;S. purpuratus&lt;/italic&gt; and other invertebrates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461091" rel="alternate" title="Gene regulation by DNA methylation is contingent on chromatin accessibility during transgenerational plasticity in the purple sea urchin (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461552</id><title>Neural network modeling of differential binding between wild-type and mutant CTCF reveals putative binding preferences for zinc fingers 1-2 (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.205477+00:00</updated><author><name>Irene M. Kaplow</name></author><author><name>Abhimanyu Banerjee</name></author><author><name>Chuan Sheng Foo</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many transcription factors (TFs), such as multi zinc-finger (ZF) TFs, have multiple DNA binding domains (DBDs) with multiple components, and deciphering the DNA binding motifs of individual components is a major challenge. One example of such a TF is &lt;italic&gt;CCCTC-binding factor&lt;/italic&gt; (CTCF), a TF with eleven ZFs that plays a variety of roles in transcriptional regulation, most notably anchoring DNA loops. Previous studies found that CTCF zinc fingers (ZFs) 3-7 bind CTCF’s core motif and ZFs 9-11 bind a specific upstream motif, but the motifs of ZFs 1-2 have yet to be identified.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We developed a new approach to identifying the binding motifs of individual DBDs of a TF through analyzing chromatin immunoprecipitation sequencing (ChIP-seq) experiments in which a single DBD is mutated: we train a deep convolutional neural network to predict whether wild-type TF binding sites are preserved in the mutant TF dataset and interpret the model. We applied this approach to mouse CTCF ChIP-seq data and, in addition to identifying the known binding preferences of CTCF ZFs 3-11, we identified a GAG binding motif for ZF1 and a weak ATT binding motif for ZF2. We analyzed other CTCF datasets to provide additional evidence that ZFs 1-2 interact with the motifs we identified, and we found that the presence of the motif for ZF1 is associated with Ctcf peak strength.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our approach can be applied to any TF for which &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; binding data from both the wild-type and mutated versions of the TF are available, and our findings provide an unprecedently comprehensive understanding of the binding preferences of CTCF’s DBDs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461552" rel="alternate" title="Neural network modeling of differential binding between wild-type and mutant CTCF reveals putative binding preferences for zinc fingers 1-2 (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.460630</id><title>Mutational signature profiling classifies subtypes of clinically different mismatch repair deficient tumors with a differential immunogenic response potential (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.205755+00:00</updated><author><name>Mar Giner-Calabuig</name></author><author><name>Seila De Leon</name></author><author><name>Julian Wang</name></author><author><name>Tara D Fehlmann</name></author><author><name>Chinedu Ukaegbu</name></author><author><name>Joanna Gibson</name></author><author><name>Miren Alustiza Fernandez</name></author><author><name>Maria-Dolores Pico</name></author><author><name>Cristina Alenda</name></author><author><name>Maite Herraiz</name></author><author><name>Marta Carrillo-Palau</name></author><author><name>Inmaculada Salces</name></author><author><name>Josep Reyes</name></author><author><name>Silvia P Ortega</name></author><author><name>Antònia Obrador</name></author><author><name>Michael Cecchini</name></author><author><name>Sapna Syngal</name></author><author><name>Elena Stoffel</name></author><author><name>Nathan A Ellis</name></author><author><name>Joann Sweasy</name></author><author><name>Rodrigo Jover</name></author><author><name>Xavier Llor</name></author><author><name>Rosa M Xicola</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mismatch repair (MMR) deficiency is the hallmark of tumors from Lynch syndrome (LS), sporadic &lt;italic&gt;MLH1&lt;/italic&gt; hypermethylated, and Lynch-like syndrome (LLS), but there is a lack of understanding of the variability in their mutational profiles based on clinical phenotypes. The aim of this study was to perform a molecular characterization to identify novel features that can impact tumor behavior and clinical management.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We tested 105 MMR-deficient colorectal cancer tumors (25 LS, 35 LLS, and 45 sporadic) for global exome microsatellite instability, cancer mutational signatures, mutational spectrum and neoepitope load.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;78% of tumors showed high contribution of MMR-deficient mutational signatures, high level of global exome microsatellite instability, loss of MLH1/PMS2 protein expression and included sporadic tumors. 22% of tumors showed weaker features of MMR deficiency, 73% lost MSH2/MSH6 expression and included half of LS and LLS tumors. Remarkably, 9% of all tumors lacked global exome microsatellite instability. Lastly, HLA-B07:02 could be triggering the neoantigen presentation in tumors that show the strongest contribution of MMR-deficient tumors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next-generation sequencing approaches allow for a granular molecular characterization of MMR-deficient tumors, which can be essential to properly diagnose and treat patients with these tumors in the setting of personalized medicine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.460630" rel="alternate" title="Mutational signature profiling classifies subtypes of clinically different mismatch repair deficient tumors with a differential immunogenic response potential (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462061</id><title>MARS: a tool for haplotype-resolved population-based structural variation detection (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.206074+00:00</updated><author><name>Lu Zhang</name></author><author><name>Arend Sidow</name></author><author><name>Xin Zhou</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Motivation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Linked-reads enables genome-wide phased diploid assemblies. These haplotype-resolved assemblies allow us to genotype structural variants (SVs) with a high sensitivity and be able to further phase them. Yet, existing SV callers are designed for haploid genome assemblies only, and there is no tool to call SV from a large population of diploid assemblies which can define and refine SVs from a global view.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We introduce MARS (Multiple Alignment-based Refinement of Svs) in linked-reads for the detection of the most common SV types - indels from diploid genome assemblies of a large population. We evaluated SVs from MARS based on Mendelian law of inheritance and PacBio HiFi reads and it achieved a high validation rate around 73%-87% for indels that we have selected from 34 assembled samples.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Source code and documentation are available on &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/maiziex/MARS"&gt;https://github.com/maiziex/MARS&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contact&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;email&gt;maizie.zhou@vanderbilt.edu&lt;/email&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Supplementary information&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supplementary data are available at &lt;italic&gt;Bioinformatics&lt;/italic&gt; online.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462061" rel="alternate" title="MARS: a tool for haplotype-resolved population-based structural variation detection (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462436</id><title>Single-cell and nucleus RNA-seq in a mouse model of AD reveal activation of distinct glial subpopulations in the presence of plaques and tangles (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.206633+00:00</updated><author><name>Gabriela Balderrama-Gutierrez</name></author><author><name>Heidi Liang</name></author><author><name>Narges Rezaie</name></author><author><name>Klebea Carvalho</name></author><author><name>Stefania Forner</name></author><author><name>Dina Matheos</name></author><author><name>Elisabeth Rebboah</name></author><author><name>Kim N. Green</name></author><author><name>Andrea J. Tenner</name></author><author><name>Frank LaFerla</name></author><author><name>Ali Mortazavi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Multiple mouse models have been generated that strive to recapitulate human Alzheimer’s disease (AD) pathological features to investigate disease mechanisms and potential treatments. The 3xTg-AD mouse presents the two major hallmarks of AD, which are plaques and tangles that increase during aging. While behavioral changes and the accumulation of plaques and tangles have been well described in the 3xTg-AD mice, the subpopulations of neurons and glial cells present throughout disease progression have not been characterized. Here, we used single-cell RNA-seq to investigate changes in subpopulations of microglia, and single-nucleus RNA-seq to explore subpopulations of neurons, astrocytes, and oligodendrocytes in the hippocampus and cortex of aging 3xTg-AD as well as 5xFAD mice for comparison. We recovered a common path of age-associated astrocyte activation between the 3xTg-AD and the 5xFAD models and found that 3xTg-AD-derived astrocytes seem to be less activated. We identified multiple subtypes of microglia, including a subpopulation with a distinct transcription factor expression profile that showed an early increase in &lt;italic&gt;Csf1&lt;/italic&gt; expression before the switch to disease associated microglia (DAM). We used bulk RNA-seq in the hippocampus of 3xTg-AD mice across their lifespan to identify distinct modules of genes whose expression increases with aging and worsening pathology. Finally, scATAC-seq revealed multiple subpopulations of cells with accessible chromatin in regions around genes associated with glial activation. Overall, differences between the main glial groups point to a slower activation process in the 3xTg-AD model when compared to the 5xFAD. Our study contributes to the identification of progressive transcriptional changes of glial cells in a mouse model that has plaques and tangles, thus providing information to aid in targeted AD therapeutics that could translate into positive clinical outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462436" rel="alternate" title="Single-cell and nucleus RNA-seq in a mouse model of AD reveal activation of distinct glial subpopulations in the presence of plaques and tangles (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461596</id><title>Prioritizing candidate peptides for cancer vaccines by PEPPRMINT: a statistical model to predict peptide presentation by HLA-I proteins (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.208088+00:00</updated><author><name>Laura Y. Zhou</name></author><author><name>Fei Zou</name></author><author><name>Wei Sun</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent development of cancer immunotherapy has opened unprecedented avenues to eliminate tumor cells using the human immune system. Cancer vaccines composed of neoantigens, or peptides unique to tumor cells due to somatic mutations, have emerged as a promising approach to activate or strengthen the immune response against cancer. A key step to identifying neoantigens is computationally predicting which somatically mutated peptides are presented on the cell surface by a human leukocyte antigen (HLA). Computational prediction relies on large amounts of high-quality training data, such as mass spectrometry data of peptides presented by one of several HLAs in living cells. We developed a complete pipeline to prioritize neoantigens for cancer vaccines. A key step of our pipeline is PEPPRMINT (PEPtide PResentation using a MIxture model and Neural neTwork), a model designed to exploit mass spectrometry data to predict peptide presentation by HLAs. We applied our pipeline to DNA sequencing data of 60 melanoma patients and identified a group of neoantigens that were more immunogenic in tumor cells than in normal cells. Additionally, the neoantigen burden estimated by PEPPRMINT was significantly associated with activity of the immune system, suggesting these neoantigens could induce an immune response.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461596" rel="alternate" title="Prioritizing candidate peptides for cancer vaccines by PEPPRMINT: a statistical model to predict peptide presentation by HLA-I proteins (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461410</id><title>Tyr is Responsible for the Cctq1a QTL and Links Developmental Environment to Central Corneal Thickness Determination (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.210045+00:00</updated><author><name>Kacie J. Meyer</name></author><author><name>Demelza R. Larson</name></author><author><name>S. Scott Whitmore</name></author><author><name>Carly J. van der Heide</name></author><author><name>Adam Hedberg-Buenz</name></author><author><name>Laura M. Dutca</name></author><author><name>Swanand Koli</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Pomernackas</name></author><author><name>Hannah E. Mercer</name></author><author><name>Maurisa N. Mansaray</name></author><author><name>William J. Paradee</name></author><author><name>Kai Wang</name></author><author><name>K. Saidas Nair</name></author><author><name>Todd E. Scheetz</name></author><author><name>Michael G. Anderson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Central corneal thickness is a quantitative trait with important associations to human health. In a phenotype-driven approach studying corneal thickness of congenic derivatives of C57BLKS/J and SJL/J mice, the critical region for a quantitative trait locus influencing corneal thickness, &lt;italic&gt;Cctq1a,&lt;/italic&gt; was delimited to a 10-gene interval. Exome sequencing, RNAseq, and studying independent mutations eliminated multiple candidate genes and confirmed one. Though the causative gene, &lt;italic&gt;Tyr,&lt;/italic&gt; has no obvious direct function in the transparent cornea, studies with multiple alleles on matched genetic backgrounds, both in isolation and genetic complementation crosses, confirmed allelism of &lt;italic&gt;Tyr-Cctq1a;&lt;/italic&gt; albino mice lacking &lt;italic&gt;Tyr&lt;/italic&gt; function had thin corneas. Albino mice also had increased axial length. Because albinism exposes eyes to increased light, the effect of dark-rearing was tested and found to rescue central corneal thickness. In sum, the results point to an epiphenomenon; developmental light exposure interacts with genotype as an important determinate of adult corneal thickness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461410" rel="alternate" title="Tyr is Responsible for the Cctq1a QTL and Links Developmental Environment to Central Corneal Thickness Determination (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461700</id><title>High-resolution mapping of DNA alkylation damage and base excision repair at yeast transcription factor binding sites (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.277764+00:00</updated><author><name>Mingrui Duan</name></author><author><name>Smitha Sivapragasam</name></author><author><name>Jacob S. Antony</name></author><author><name>Jenna Ulibarri</name></author><author><name>John M. Hinz</name></author><author><name>Gregory M.K. Poon</name></author><author><name>John J. Wyrick</name></author><author><name>Peng Mao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;DNA base damage arises frequently in living cells and needs to be removed by base excision repair (BER) to prevent mutagenesis and genome instability. Both the formation and repair of base damage occur in chromatin and are conceivably affected by DNA-binding proteins such as transcription factors (TFs). However, to what extent TF binding affects base damage distribution and BER in cells is unclear. Here, we used a genome-wide damage mapping method, &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;-methylpurine-sequencing (NMP-seq), to characterize alkylation damage distribution and BER at TF binding sites in yeast cells treated with the alkylating agent methyl methanesulfonate (MMS). Our data shows that alkylation damage formation was mainly suppressed at the binding sites of yeast TFs Abf1 and Reb1, but individual hotspots with elevated damage levels were also found. Additionally, Abf1 and Reb1 binding strongly inhibits BER &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, causing slow repair both within the core motif and its adjacent DNA. The observed effects are caused by the TF-DNA interaction, because damage formation and BER can be restored by depletion of Abf1 or Reb1 protein from the nucleus. Thus, our data reveal that TF binding significantly modulates alkylation base damage formation and inhibits repair by the BER pathway. The interplay between base damage formation and BER may play an important role in affecting mutation frequency in gene regulatory regions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461700" rel="alternate" title="High-resolution mapping of DNA alkylation damage and base excision repair at yeast transcription factor binding sites (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462004</id><title>Deficiency of Irx5 protects mice from diet-induced obesity and associated metabolic abnormalities (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.284539+00:00</updated><author><name>Joe Eun Son</name></author><author><name>Kyoung-Han Kim</name></author><author><name>Chi-chung Hui</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Obesity, a leading cause of several metabolic abnormalities, is mainly due to an imbalance of energy homeostasis. &lt;italic&gt;IRX3&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;IRX5&lt;/italic&gt; have been suggested as determinants of obesity in connection with the intronic variants of &lt;italic&gt;FTO&lt;/italic&gt;, the strongest genetic risk factor of polygenic obesity in humans. Although the causal effects of &lt;italic&gt;Irx3&lt;/italic&gt; on obesity and its related metabolic consequences have been demonstrated &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, the metabolic function of &lt;italic&gt;Irx5&lt;/italic&gt; remains unclear. In this study, using mice homozygous for an &lt;italic&gt;Irx5&lt;/italic&gt;-knockout (&lt;italic&gt;Irx5&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;KO&lt;/sup&gt;) allele, we show a direct link between &lt;italic&gt;Irx5&lt;/italic&gt; expression and regulation of body mass/composition and energy homeostasis. &lt;italic&gt;Irx5&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;KO&lt;/sup&gt; mice are leaner and resistant to diet-induced obesity and associated metabolic abnormalities, primarily through the loss of adiposity with an increase in basal metabolic rate with adipose thermogenesis and lower food intake. Furthermore, our long-term feeding analysis found that &lt;italic&gt;Irx3&lt;/italic&gt; mutant mouse lines also have less food intake, indicating that lower caloric intake also contributes to their lean phenotype. Together, these results demonstrate that &lt;italic&gt;Irx5&lt;/italic&gt; is critical for energy homeostasis and regulation of body mass/composition and suggest that it likely acts in other tissues beyond adipocytes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462004" rel="alternate" title="Deficiency of Irx5 protects mice from diet-induced obesity and associated metabolic abnormalities (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461553</id><title>Identification of microRNAs in the West Nile virus vector Culex tarsalis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.284924+00:00</updated><author><name>Sultan Asad</name></author><author><name>Ahmed M. Mehdi</name></author><author><name>Sujit Pujari</name></author><author><name>Claudia Rüeckert</name></author><author><name>Gregory D. Ebel</name></author><author><name>Jason L. Rasgon</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;microRNAs (miRNAs) represent a group of small non-coding RNAs that are crucial gene regulators of important biological functions including development and pathogen defense in most living organisms. Presently, there is a lack of availability of information regarding the miRNAs in the mosquito &lt;italic&gt;Culex tarsalis&lt;/italic&gt;, which is one of the most important vectors of West Nile virus (WNV) in the United States. We used small RNA sequencing data and &lt;italic&gt;in vitr&lt;/italic&gt;o and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; experiments to identify and validate the presence of a repertoire of miRNAs in &lt;italic&gt;Cx. tarsalis&lt;/italic&gt; mosquitoes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using bioinformatic approaches we analyzed small RNA sequencing data from the &lt;italic&gt;Cx. tarsalis&lt;/italic&gt; CT embryonic cell line to discover 86 miRNAs. Consistent with other mosquitoes such as &lt;italic&gt;Aedes albopictus&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Cx. quinquefasciatus&lt;/italic&gt;, mi-184 was found to be the most abundant miRNA in &lt;italic&gt;Cx tarsalis&lt;/italic&gt;. We also identified an additional 20 novel miRNAs from the recently sequenced &lt;italic&gt;Cx. tarsalis&lt;/italic&gt; genome, for a total of 106 miRNAs identified in this study. The presence of selected miRNAs was biologically validated in both cell line and adult &lt;italic&gt;Cx. tarsalis&lt;/italic&gt; mosquitoes using RT-qPCR and sequencing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Cx. tarsalis&lt;/italic&gt; is an important vector of many medically important pathogens including WNV and Western Equine encephalitis. Here we report a detailed insight into the miRNA population in &lt;italic&gt;Cx. tarsalis&lt;/italic&gt; mosquitoes. These results will open new avenues of research deciphering the role of miRNAs in different &lt;italic&gt;Cx. tarsalis&lt;/italic&gt; biological events such as development, metabolism, immunity and pathogen infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461553" rel="alternate" title="Identification of microRNAs in the West Nile virus vector Culex tarsalis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461433</id><title>AMPK regulates germline stem cell integrity and quiescence through a mir-1/tbc-7/rab-7 pathway in C. elegans (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.285302+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher Wong</name></author><author><name>Pratik Kadekar</name></author><author><name>Elena Jurczak</name></author><author><name>Richard Roy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During periods of energetic stress, &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/italic&gt; can undergo a global quiescent stage known as “dauer”. During this stage, all germline stem cells undergo G2 cell cycle arrest through an AMPK-dependent mechanism. In animals that lack AMPK signalling, the germ cells fail to arrest, undergo uncontrolled proliferation and lose their reproductive capacity. These germline defects are accompanied by an altered chromatin landscape and gene expression program. We identified an allele of &lt;italic&gt;tbc-7&lt;/italic&gt;, a RabGAP protein that functions in the neurons, which when compromised, suppresses the germline hyperplasia in the dauer larvae, as well as the post-dauer sterility and somatic defects characteristic of AMPK mutants. This mutation also corrects the abundance and aberrant distribution of transcriptionally activating and repressive chromatin marks in animals that otherwise lack all AMPK signalling. We identified RAB-7 as one of the potential RAB proteins that is regulated by &lt;italic&gt;tbc-7&lt;/italic&gt; and show that the activity of RAB-7 is critical for the maintenance of germ cell integrity during the dauer stage. A singular small RNA, &lt;italic&gt;mir-1&lt;/italic&gt;, was identified as a direct negative regulator of &lt;italic&gt;tbc-7&lt;/italic&gt; expression through the analysis of seed sequences on the 3’UTR of &lt;italic&gt;tbc-7&lt;/italic&gt;. Animals lacking &lt;italic&gt;mir-1&lt;/italic&gt; are post-dauer sterile, displaying a similar phenotype to AMPK mutants. Altogether, our findings describe a novel &lt;italic&gt;mir-1/tbc-7/rab-7&lt;/italic&gt; pathway occurring in the neurons that regulates the germ line in a cell non-autonomous manner.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461433" rel="alternate" title="AMPK regulates germline stem cell integrity and quiescence through a mir-1/tbc-7/rab-7 pathway in C. elegans (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462440</id><title>Loss of the cleaved-protamine 2 domain leads to incomplete histone-to-protamine exchange and infertility in mice (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.285616+00:00</updated><author><name>Lena Arévalo</name></author><author><name>Gina Esther Merges</name></author><author><name>Simon Schneider</name></author><author><name>Franka Enow Oben</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Neumann</name></author><author><name>Hubert Schorle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protamines are unique sperm-specific proteins that package and protect paternal chromatin until fertilization. A subset of mammalian species expresses two protamines (PRM1 and PRM2), while in others PRM1 is sufficient for sperm chromatin packaging. Alterations of the species-specific ratio between PRM1 and PRM2 are associated with infertility. Unlike PRM1, PRM2 is generated as a precursor protein consisting of a highly conserved N-terminal domain, termed cleaved PRM2 (cP2), which is consecutively trimmed off during chromatin condensation. The carboxyterminal part, called mature PRM2 (mP2), interacts with DNA and mediates chromatin-hypercondensation, together with PRM1. The removal of the cP2 domain is believed to be imperative for proper chromatin condensation and the prevention of DNA damage. Yet, the role of cP2 is not yet understood. Using CRISPR-Cas9 mediated gene editing, we generated mice lacking the cP2 domain while the mP2 is still expressed. We show that deletion of one allele of the cP2 domain is sufficient to render male mice infertile. cP2 deficient sperm show incomplete PRM2 incorporation, retention of transition proteins and a severely altered protamine ratio. During epididymal transit, cP2 deficient sperm seem to undergo ROS mediated degradation leading to complete DNA fragmentation, inviability and immotility of mature sperm. The cP2 domain therefore seems to be necessary for the complex crosstalk leading to the successive and complete removal of transition proteins and complete protamination of sperm chromatin. Overall, we present the first step towards understanding the role of the cP2 domain in paternal chromatin packaging and open up avenues for further research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462440" rel="alternate" title="Loss of the cleaved-protamine 2 domain leads to incomplete histone-to-protamine exchange and infertility in mice (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461500</id><title>A population based expression atlas provides insights into disease resistance and other physiological traits in cassava (Manihot esculenta Crantz) (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.286040+00:00</updated><author><name>Alex C. Ogbonna</name></author><author><name>Punna Ramu</name></author><author><name>Esuma Williams</name></author><author><name>Leah Nandudu</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Morales</name></author><author><name>Adrian Powell</name></author><author><name>Robert Kawuki</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Bauchet</name></author><author><name>Jean-Luc Jannink</name></author><author><name>Lukas A. Mueller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cassava, a food security crop in Africa, is grown throughout the tropics and subtropics. Although cassava can provide high productivity in suboptimal conditions, the yield in Africa is substantially lower than in other geographies. The yield gap is attributable to many challenges faced by cassava in Africa, including susceptibility to diseases and poor soil conditions. In this study, we carried out 3’RNA sequencing on 150 accessions from the National Crops Resources Research Institute, Ugandan for 5 tissue types, providing population-based transcriptomics resources to the research community in a web-based queryable cassava expression atlas. Differential expression and weighted gene co-expression network analysis were performed to detect 8,820 significantly differentially expressed genes (DEGs), revealing similarity in expression patterns between tissue types and the clustering of detected DEGs into 18 gene modules. As a confirmation of data quality, differential expression and pathway analysis targeting cassava mosaic disease (CMD) identified 27 genes observed in the plant-pathogen interaction pathway, several previously identified CMD resistance genes and two peroxidase family proteins different from the &lt;italic&gt;CMD2&lt;/italic&gt; gene. Present research work represents a novel resource towards understanding complex traits at expression and molecular levels for the development of resistant and high-yielding cassava varieties, as exemplified with CMD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461500" rel="alternate" title="A population based expression atlas provides insights into disease resistance and other physiological traits in cassava (Manihot esculenta Crantz) (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461904</id><title>Avian haemosporidians (Plasmodium and Haemoproteus) in selected bird groups (Old world Flycatchers, Warblers, Babblers, and Thrushes) of India and their phylogenetic relationships with other lineages of the world (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.286464+00:00</updated><author><name> Vipin</name></author><author><name>Ashutosh Singh</name></author><author><name>Rajnikant Dixit</name></author><author><name>Narinder Kumar Tripathi</name></author><author><name>Bhim Singh</name></author><author><name>Vinita Sharma</name></author><author><name>Chandra Prakash Sharma</name></author><author><name>Dhananjai Mohan</name></author><author><name>Sandeep Kumar Gupta</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We examined the Avian haemosporidians (&lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Haemoproteus&lt;/italic&gt;) status in selected bird groups (Old world Flycatchers, Warblers, Babblers, and Thrushes) of India and their phylogenetic relationships with other known lineages of the world. The use of common genetic markers with information on the geographic distribution of parasite and host samples makes the data of avian haemosporidians genetic studies more comparable and infection source surveillance ready. The prevalence of Avian haemosporidians, in above bird groups from northern, eastern, and southern parts of India and the phylogenetic genetic analysis of genetic lineages was carried out at world level to know the possible source of infection. The MCC tree revealed six Haemosporidian lineages in which one was common (H_MSP01) and five were unique (H_CYOPOL01, H_CHD01, H_CYORUB01, H_EUMTHA01, and P_GEOCIT01). The avian host richness Index was 2.0852. 9.9%, prevalence of &lt;italic&gt;Haemosporidian&lt;/italic&gt; infection was found in 111 DNA samples belonging to 6 host species. The &lt;italic&gt;Haemoproteus&lt;/italic&gt; prevalence was found to be 9.0% across five host species (&lt;italic&gt;Phylloscopus trochiloides, Cyornis poliogenys, C. hainanus dialilaemus, C. rubeculoides, Eumiyas thalassinus&lt;/italic&gt;) and &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium&lt;/italic&gt; prevalence was 0.9% in &lt;italic&gt;Geokichla citrina&lt;/italic&gt;. The spatial phylogeny map showed possible source populations of hosts having &lt;italic&gt;H. pallidus&lt;/italic&gt; lineages COLL2 and PFC1 infections in parts of Africa, Europe, North America, Malaysia, and Philippines. The &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium&lt;/italic&gt; lineage (P_GEOCIT01) showed a weak (93.89%) similarity with PADOM16 in Egypt. The statistical analysis suggested that the haemosporidian’s host species’ distribution range was directly and significantly associated with the altitude, minimum temperature, and relative humidity. H_MSP01 distribution was in accordance with &lt;italic&gt;H. pallidus&lt;/italic&gt; having a wide geographic and host range.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461904" rel="alternate" title="Avian haemosporidians (Plasmodium and Haemoproteus) in selected bird groups (Old world Flycatchers, Warblers, Babblers, and Thrushes) of India and their phylogenetic relationships with other lineages of the world (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>