<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.489510+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444514</id><title>A Cre-dependent massively parallel reporter assay allows for cell-type specific assessment of the functional effects of genetic variants in vivo (38 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.489969+00:00</updated><author><name>Tomas Lagunas</name></author><author><name>Stephen P. Plassmeyer</name></author><author><name>Ryan Z. Friedman</name></author><author><name>Michael A. Rieger</name></author><author><name>Anthony D. Fischer</name></author><author><name>Alessandra F. Aguilar Lucero</name></author><author><name>Joon-Yong An</name></author><author><name>Stephan J. Sanders</name></author><author><name>Barak A. Cohen</name></author><author><name>Joseph D. Dougherty</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human genetic studies have identified a large number of disease-associated &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; variants in presumptive regulatory regions of the genome that pose a challenge for interpretation of their effects: the impact of regulatory variants is highly dependent on the cellular context, and thus for psychiatric diseases these would ideally be studied in neurons in a living brain. Furthermore, for both common and rare variants, it is expected that only a subset fraction will affect gene expression. Massively Parallel Reporter Assays (MPRAs) are molecular genetic tools that enable functional screening of hundreds of predefined sequences in a single experiment. These assays have been used for functional screening of several different types of regulatory sequences &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. However, they have not yet been adapted to query specific cell types &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; in a complex tissue like the mouse brain. Here, using a test-case 3′UTR MPRA library with variants from ASD patients, we sought to develop a method to achieve reproducible measurements of variant effects &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; in a cell type-specific manner. We implemented a Cre-dependent design to control expression of our library and first validated our system &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. Next, we measured the effect of &amp;gt;500 3′UTR variants in excitatory neurons in the mouse brain. Finally, we report &amp;gt;40 variants with significant effects on transcript abundance in the context of the brain. This new technique should enable robust, functional annotation of genetic variants in the cellular contexts most relevant to psychiatric disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.17.444514" rel="alternate" title="A Cre-dependent massively parallel reporter assay allows for cell-type specific assessment of the functional effects of genetic variants in vivo (38 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.445039</id><title>A novel gene-by-environment quantitative trait locus on mouse chromosome 15 underlies susceptibility to acute ozone-induced lung injury (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.490340+00:00</updated><author><name>Adelaide Tovar</name></author><author><name>Gregory J. Smith</name></author><author><name>Joseph M. Thomas</name></author><author><name>Kathryn M. McFadden</name></author><author><name>Samir N. P. Kelada</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Respiratory toxicity caused by the common urban air pollutant ozone (O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;) varies considerably within the human population and across inbred mouse strains, suggestive of gene-environment interactions (GxE). Though previous studies genetic mapping studies using classical inbred strains have identified several and quantitative trait locus (QTL) and candidate genes underlying responses to O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; exposure, precise mechanisms of susceptibility remain incompletely described. We sought to expand our understanding of the genetic architecture of O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; responsiveness using the Collaborative Cross (CC) recombinant inbred mouse panel, which contains more genetic diversity than previous inbred strain panels. We evaluated hallmark O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-induced respiratory phenotypes in 56 CC strains after exposure to filtered air or 2 ppm O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;, and performed focused genetic analysis of variation in lung injury as measured by the total bronchoalveolar lavage protein concentration. Because animals were exposed in sex- and batch-matched pairs, we defined a protein response phenotype as the difference in lavage protein between the O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;- and FA-exposed animal within a pair. The protein response phenotype was heritable, and QTL mapping revealed two novel loci on Chromosomes 10 (peak: 26.2 Mb; 80% CI: 24.6-43.6 Mb) and 15 (peak: 47.1 Mb; 80% CI: 40.2-54.9 Mb), the latter surpassing the 95% significance threshold. At the Chr. 15 locus, C57BL/6J and CAST/EiJ founder haplotypes were associated with higher protein responses compared to all other CC founder strain haplotypes. Using additional statistical analysis and high-density SNP data, we delimited the Chr. 15 QTL to a ∼2 Mb region containing 21 genes (10 protein coding). Using a weight of evidence approach that incorporated candidate variant analysis, functional annotations, and publicly available lung gene expression data, we nominated three candidate genes (&lt;italic&gt;Oxr1, Rspo2&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;Angpt1&lt;/italic&gt;). In summary, we have shown that O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-induced lung injury is modulated by genetic variation and demonstrated the value of the CC for uncovering and dissecting gene-environment interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.445039" rel="alternate" title="A novel gene-by-environment quantitative trait locus on mouse chromosome 15 underlies susceptibility to acute ozone-induced lung injury (10 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.21.445208</id><title>Leveraging a founder population to identify novel rare-population genetic determinants of lipidome (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.490601+00:00</updated><author><name>May E Montasser</name></author><author><name>Stella Aslibekyan</name></author><author><name>Vinodh Srinivasasainagendra</name></author><author><name>Hemant K Tiwari</name></author><author><name>Amit Patki</name></author><author><name>Minoo Bagheri</name></author><author><name>James A Perry</name></author><author><name>Kathleen A Ryan</name></author><author><name>Donna K Arnett</name></author><author><name>Amber L Beitelshees</name></author><author><name>Marguerite R Irvin</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey R O'Connell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Identifying the genetic determinants of inter-individual variation in lipid species (lipidome) may provide deeper understanding and new insight into the mechanistic effect of complex lipidomic pathways in CVD risk and progression beyond simple traditional lipids. Previous studies have been largely population based and thus only powered to discover associations with common genetic variants. Founder populations represent a powerful resource to accelerate discovery of novel biology associated with rare population alleles that have risen to higher frequency due to genetic drift. We performed a GWAS of 355 lipid species in 650 individuals from the Old Order Amish founder population including 127 lipid species not previously tested. We report for the first time the lipid species associated with two rare-population but Amish-enriched lipid variants: APOB_rs5742904 and APOC3_rs76353203. We also identified novel associations for 3 rare-population Amish-enriched loci with several sphingolipids and with proposed potential functional/causal variant in each locus including GLPTD2_rs536055318, CERS5_rs771033566, and AKNA_rs531892793. We replicated 7 previously known common loci including novel associations with two sterols: androstenediol with UGT locus on chromosome 2 and estriol with SLC22A8/A24 locus on chromosome 11. Our results show the power of founder populations to discover novel biology due to genetic drift that can increase an allele found in only a few subjects in even large samples such as UKBiobank to dozens in even samples as small as 650.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.21.445208" rel="alternate" title="Leveraging a founder population to identify novel rare-population genetic determinants of lipidome (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.18.444691</id><title>A protein-trap allele reveals roles for Drosophila ATF4 in photoreceptor degeneration, oocyte maturation and wing development (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.490942+00:00</updated><author><name>Deepika Vasudevan</name></author><author><name>Hidetaka Katow</name></author><author><name>Grace Tang</name></author><author><name>Hyung Don Ryoo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Metazoans have evolved various stress response mechanisms to cope with cellular stress inflicted by external and physiological conditions. The Integrated Stress Response (ISR) is an evolutionarily conserved pathway that mediates adaptation to cellular stress via the transcription factor, ATF4. Loss of function of &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; ATF4, encoded by the gene &lt;italic&gt;cryptocephal&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;crc&lt;/italic&gt;), results in lethality during pupal development. The roles of &lt;italic&gt;crc&lt;/italic&gt; in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; disease models and adult tissue homeostasis thus remain poorly understood. Here, we report that a protein-trap MiMIC insertion in the &lt;italic&gt;crc&lt;/italic&gt; locus generates a crc-GFP fusion protein that allows visualization of crc activity in vivo, and acts as a hypomorphic mutant that uncovers previously unknown roles for &lt;italic&gt;crc&lt;/italic&gt;. Specifically, the &lt;italic&gt;crc&lt;/italic&gt; protein-trap line shows crc-GFP induction in a &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; model for Retinitis Pigmentosa (RP). This &lt;italic&gt;crc&lt;/italic&gt; allele renders photoreceptors more vulnerable to age-dependent retinal degeneration. &lt;italic&gt;crc&lt;/italic&gt; mutant adult animals also show greater susceptibility to amino acid deprivation and reduced levels of known crc transcriptional targets. Furthermore, this mutant allele shows defects in wing veins and oocyte maturation, uncovering previously unknown roles for &lt;italic&gt;crc&lt;/italic&gt; in the development of these tissues. Together, our data establish physiological and pathological functions of &lt;italic&gt;crc-&lt;/italic&gt;mediated ISR in adult &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; tissues.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.18.444691" rel="alternate" title="A protein-trap allele reveals roles for Drosophila ATF4 in photoreceptor degeneration, oocyte maturation and wing development (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>