<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.016508+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469228</id><title>Pre-metazoan origin of neuropeptide signalling (107 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.029187+00:00</updated><author><name>Luis Alfonso Yanez-Guerra</name></author><author><name>Daniel Thiel</name></author><author><name>Gaspar Jekely</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neuropeptides are a diverse class of signalling molecules in metazoans. They occur in all animals with a nervous system and also in neuron-less placozoans. However, their origin has remained unclear because no neuropeptide shows deep homology across lineages and none have been found in sponges. Here, we identify two neuropeptide precursors, phoenixin and nesfatin, with broad evolutionary conservation. By database searches, sequence alignments and gene-structure comparisons we show that both precursors are present in bilaterians, cnidarians, ctenophores and sponges. We also found phoenixin and a secreted nesfatin precursor homolog in the choanoflagellate Salpingoeca rosetta. Phoenixin in particular, is highly conserved, including its cleavage sites, suggesting that prohormone processing occurs also in choanoflagellates. In addition, based on phyletic patterns and negative pharmacological assays we question the originally proposed GPR-173 (SREB3) as a phoenixin receptor. Our findings indicate that signalling by secreted neuropeptide homologs has pre-metazoan origins and thus evolved before neurons.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469228" rel="alternate" title="Pre-metazoan origin of neuropeptide signalling (107 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468686</id><title>Evaluation of methods for the inference of ancestral recombination graphs (71 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.029448+00:00</updated><author><name>Débora Y. C. Brandt</name></author><author><name>Xinzhu Wei</name></author><author><name>Yun Deng</name></author><author><name>Andrew H. Vaughn</name></author><author><name>Rasmus Nielsen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ancestral recombination graph (ARG) is a structure that describes the joint genealogies of sampled DNA sequences along the genome. Recent computational methods have made impressive progress towards scalably estimating whole-genome genealogies. In addition to inferring the ARG, some of these methods can also provide ARGs sampled from a defined posterior distribution. Obtaining good samples of ARGs is crucial for quantifying statistical uncertainty and for estimating population genetic parameters such as effective population size, mutation rate, and allele age. Here, we use simulations to benchmark three popular ARG inference programs: ARGweaver, Relate, and tsdate. We use neutral coalescent simulations to 1) compare the true coalescence times to the inferred times at each locus; 2) compare the distribution of coalescence times across all loci to the expected exponential distribution; 3) evaluate whether the sampled coalescence times have the properties expected of a valid posterior distribution. We find that inferred coalescence times at each locus are more accurate in ARGweaver and Relate than in tsdate. However, all three methods tend to overestimate small coalescence times and underestimate large ones. Lastly, the posterior distribution of ARGweaver is closer to the expected posterior distribution than Relate’s, but this higher accuracy comes at a substantial trade-off in scalability. The best choice of method will depend on the number and length of input sequences and on the goal of downstream analyses, and we provide guidelines for the best practices.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468686" rel="alternate" title="Evaluation of methods for the inference of ancestral recombination graphs (71 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469106</id><title>Transgenic tools for targeted chromosome rearrangements allow construction of balancer chromosomes in non-melanogaster Drosophila species (71 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.029597+00:00</updated><author><name>David L. Stern</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most valuable single set of resources for genetic studies of &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; is the collection of multiply-inverted chromosomes commonly known as balancer chromosomes. Balancers prevent the recovery of recombination exchange products within genomic regions included in inversions and allow perpetual maintenance of deleterious alleles in living stocks and the execution of complex genetic crosses. Balancer chromosomes have been generated traditionally by exposing animals to ionizing radiation and screening for altered chromosome structure or for unusual marker segregation patterns. These approaches are tedious and unpredictable, and have failed to produce the desired products in some species. Here I describe transgenic tools that allow targeted chromosome rearrangements in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; species. The key new resources are engineered reporter genes containing introns with yeast recombination sites and enhancers that drive fluorescent reporter genes in multiple body regions. These tools were used to generate a doubly-inverted chromosome 3R in &lt;italic&gt;D. simulans&lt;/italic&gt; that serves as an effective balancer chromosome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469106" rel="alternate" title="Transgenic tools for targeted chromosome rearrangements allow construction of balancer chromosomes in non-melanogaster Drosophila species (71 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468725</id><title>Trait Association and Prediction Through Integrative K-mer Analysis (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.030117+00:00</updated><author><name>Cheng He</name></author><author><name>Jacob D Washburn</name></author><author><name>Yangfan Hao</name></author><author><name>Zhiwu Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jinliang Yang</name></author><author><name>Sanzhen Liu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genome-wide association study (GWAS) with single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) has been widely used to explore genetic controls of phenotypic traits. Here we employed an GWAS approach using k-mers, short substrings from sequencing reads. Using maize cob and kernel color traits, we demonstrated that k-mer GWAS can effectively identify associated k-mers. Co-expression analysis of kernel color k-mers and pathway genes directly found k-mers from causal genes. Analyzing complex traits of kernel oil and leaf angle resulted in k-mers from both known and candidate genes. Evolution analysis revealed most k-mers positively correlated with kernel oil were strongly selected against in maize populations, while most k-mers for upright leaf angle were positively selected. In addition, phenotypic prediction of kernel oil, leaf angle, and flowering time using k-mer data showed at least a similarly high prediction accuracy to the standard SNP-based method. Collectively, our results demonstrated the bridging role of k-mers for data integration and functional gene discovery.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468725" rel="alternate" title="Trait Association and Prediction Through Integrative K-mer Analysis (14 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469233</id><title>A 1-bp deletion in bovine QRICH2 causes low sperm count and immotile sperm with multiple morphological abnormalities (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.030266+00:00</updated><author><name>Maya Hiltpold</name></author><author><name>Fredi Janett</name></author><author><name>Xena Marie Mapel</name></author><author><name>Naveen Kumar Kadri</name></author><author><name>Zih-Hua Fang</name></author><author><name>Hermann Schwarzenbacher</name></author><author><name>Franz Seefried</name></author><author><name>Mirjam Spengeler</name></author><author><name>Ulrich Witschi</name></author><author><name>Hubert Pausch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Semen quality and male fertility are monitored in artificial insemination bulls to ensure high insemination success rates. Only ejaculates that fulfill minimum quality requirements are processed and eventually used for artificial inseminations. We examined 70,990 ejaculates from 1343 Brown Swiss bulls to identify bulls from which all ejaculates were rejected due to low semen quality. This procedure identified a bull that produced twelve ejaculates with an aberrantly low number of sperm (0.2±0.2 x 10&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt; sperm per ml) which were mostly immotile due to multiple morphological abnormalities.
Results: The genome of the bull was sequenced at 12-fold coverage to investigate a suspected genetic cause. Comparing the sequence variant genotypes of the bull with those from 397 fertile bulls revealed a 1-bp deletion in the coding sequence of &lt;italic&gt;QRICH2&lt;/italic&gt; encoding glutamine rich 2 as a compelling candidate causal variant. The 1-bp deletion causes a frameshift in translation and induces a premature termination codon (ENSBTAP00000018337.1:p.Cys1644AlafsTer52). The analysis of testis transcriptomes from 76 bulls showed that the transcript with the premature termination codon is subjected to nonsense-mediated mRNA decay. The 1-bp deletion resides on a 675 kb haplotype spanning 181 SNPs from the Illumina BovineHD Bead chip. The haplotype segregates at a frequency of 5% in the Brown Swiss cattle population. This analysis also identified another bull that carried the 1-bp deletion in the homozygous state. Semen analyses from the second bull confirmed low sperm concentration and immotile sperm with multiple morphological abnormalities primarily affecting the sperm flagellum and, to a lesser extent, the sperm head.
Conclusions: A recessive loss-of-function allele of bovine &lt;italic&gt;QRICH2&lt;/italic&gt; likely causes low sperm concentration and immotile sperm with multiple morphological abnormalities. Routine sperm analyses unambiguously identify homozygous bulls. A direct gene test can be implemented to monitor the frequency of the undesired allele in cattle populations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469233" rel="alternate" title="A 1-bp deletion in bovine QRICH2 causes low sperm count and immotile sperm with multiple morphological abnormalities (11 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468780</id><title>Getting close to nature – Plasmodium knowlesi reference genome sequences from contemporary clinical isolates (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.030434+00:00</updated><author><name>Damilola R. Oresegun</name></author><author><name>Peter Thorpe</name></author><author><name>Ernest Diez Benavente</name></author><author><name>Susana Campino</name></author><author><name>Fauzi Muh</name></author><author><name>Robert Moon</name></author><author><name>Taane G. Clark</name></author><author><name>Janet Cox-Singh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium knowlesi,&lt;/italic&gt; a malaria parasite of old-world macaque monkeys, is used extensively to model &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium&lt;/italic&gt; biology. Recently &lt;italic&gt;P. knowlesi&lt;/italic&gt; was found in the human population of Southeast Asia, particularly Malaysia. &lt;italic&gt;P. knowlesi&lt;/italic&gt; causes un-complicated to severe and fatal malaria in the human host with features in common with the more prevalent and virulent malaria caused by &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium falciparum&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As such &lt;italic&gt;P. knowlesi&lt;/italic&gt; presents a unique opportunity to inform an experimental model for malaria with clinical data from same-species human infections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Experimental lines of &lt;italic&gt;P. knowlesi&lt;/italic&gt; represent well characterised genetically static parasites and to maximise their utility as a backdrop for understanding malaria pathophysiology, genetically diverse contemporary clinical isolates, essentially wild-type, require comparable characterization.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Oxford Nanopore PCR-free long-read sequencing platform was used to sequence &lt;italic&gt;P. knowlesi&lt;/italic&gt; parasites from archived clinical samples. The sequencing platform and assembly pipeline was designed to facilitate capturing data on important multiple gene families, including the &lt;italic&gt;P. knowlesi schizont-infected cell agglutination&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;SICA&lt;/italic&gt;) &lt;italic&gt;var&lt;/italic&gt; genes and the &lt;italic&gt;Knowlesi-Interspersed Repeats&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;KIR&lt;/italic&gt;) genes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;italic&gt;SICAvar&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;KIR&lt;/italic&gt; gene families code for antigenically variant proteins that have been difficult to resolve and characterise. Analyses presented here suggest that the family members have arisen through a process of gene duplication, selection pressure and variation. Highly evolving genes tend to be located proximal to genetic elements that drive change rather than regions that support core gene conservation. For example, the virulence-associated &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; erythrocyte membrane protein (&lt;italic&gt;PfEMP1&lt;/italic&gt;) gene family members are restricted to relatively unstable sub-telomeric regions. In contrast the &lt;italic&gt;SICAvar&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;KIR&lt;/italic&gt; genes are located throughout the genome but as the study presented here shows, they occupy otherwise gene-sparse chromosomal locations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The novel methods presented here offer the malaria research community new tools to generate comprehensive genome sequence data from small clinical samples and renewed insight into these complex real-world parasites.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Malaria is a potentially severe disease caused by parasite species within genus Plasmodium. Even though the number of cases is in decline there were over 200 million reported cases of malaria in 2019 that resulted in &amp;gt;400,000 deaths. Despite huge research efforts we still do not understand precisely how malaria makes some individuals very ill and by extension how to successfully augment and manage severe disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we developed a novel method to generate comprehensive robust genome sequences from the malaria parasite &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium knowlesi&lt;/italic&gt; collected from clinical samples.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We propose to use the method and initial data generated here to begin to build a resource to identify disease associated genetic traits of &lt;italic&gt;P. knowlesi&lt;/italic&gt; taken from patient’s samples. In addition to the methodology, what further sets this work apart is the unique opportunity to utilize same-species experimental &lt;italic&gt;P. knowlesi&lt;/italic&gt; parasites to discover a potential role for particular parasite traits in the differential disease progression we observe in patients with &lt;italic&gt;P. knowlesi&lt;/italic&gt; malaria.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While we developed the methods to study severe malaria, they are affordable and accessible, and offer the wider malaria research community the means to add context and insight into real-world malaria parasites.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468780" rel="alternate" title="Getting close to nature – Plasmodium knowlesi reference genome sequences from contemporary clinical isolates (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469022</id><title>The natural adaptation and human selection history of African sheep genomes (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.030584+00:00</updated><author><name>Abulgasim M Ahbara</name></author><author><name>Christelle Robert</name></author><author><name>Adebabay Kebede</name></author><author><name>Ayele Abebe</name></author><author><name>Suliman Latairish</name></author><author><name>Mukhtar Omar Agoub</name></author><author><name>Hassan H. Musa</name></author><author><name>Pam Wiener</name></author><author><name>Emily Clark</name></author><author><name>Olivier Hanotte</name></author><author><name>Joram M. Mwacharo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;African sheep manifest diverse but distinct physio-anatomical traits which are the outcomes of natural- and human-driven selection. Here, we generated 34.8 million variants from 150 indigenous African sheep genomes sequenced at an average depth of ∼54x for 130 samples (Ethiopia, Libya) and ∼10x for 20 samples (Sudan), representing sheep from diverse environments, tail morphology and post-Neolithic introductions to Africa. Phylogenetic and model-based admixture analysis provided evidence of four genetic groups that correspond to altitudinal geographic origins and tail morphotypes. Comparative genomic analysis identified targets of selection spanning conserved haplotype structures overlapping genes and gene families relating to hypoxia responses, caudal vertebrae and tail skeleton length, ear morphology, and tail fat-depot structure. Our findings provide novel insights underpinning variation and response to human selection and environmental adaptation, and possible pleiotropic gene interactions in indigenous African sheep genomes, which guaranteed the successful establishment of the species on the continent.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469022" rel="alternate" title="The natural adaptation and human selection history of African sheep genomes (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469050</id><title>Guide-directed DNA cleavage by a prokaryotic Argonaute protein induces chromosome recombination in Escherichia coli (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.030753+00:00</updated><author><name>Shan Huang</name></author><author><name>Kaihang Wang</name></author><author><name>Stephen L. Mayo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Emerging evidence supports the argument that some prokaryotic argonautes (pAgos) serve as a defensive system against invasion of viruses and plasmids through guide DNAs (gDNAs) directed DNA cleavage. This DNA-guided DNA interference motivates research to induce genomic mutations via pAgo mediated cleavage. Here we demonstrate that CbAgo, a pAgo from &lt;italic&gt;Clostridium butyricum&lt;/italic&gt;, is able to induce chromosomal recombination between direct repeat sequences via its gDNA-directed cleavage in &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; chromosome. We also show that CbAgo targeting can assist Lambda-Red recombineering in RecA-deficient strain. Our study reveals that cleavage by CbAgo in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; chromosome can be mutagenic and suggests its broader application in genetic manipulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469050" rel="alternate" title="Guide-directed DNA cleavage by a prokaryotic Argonaute protein induces chromosome recombination in Escherichia coli (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469068</id><title>Epigenetic machinery is functionally conserved in cephalopods (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.030873+00:00</updated><author><name>Filippo Macchi</name></author><author><name>Eric Edsinger</name></author><author><name>Kirsten C. Sadler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Epigenetic regulatory mechanisms are divergent across the animal kingdom, yet little is known about the epigenome in non-model organisms. Unique features of cephalopods make them attractive for investigating behavioral, sensory, developmental and regenerative processes, but using molecular approaches in such studies is hindered by the lack of knowledge about genome organization and gene regulation in these animals. We combined bioinformatic and molecular analysis of &lt;italic&gt;Octopus bimaculoides&lt;/italic&gt; to identify gene expression signatures for 12 adult tissues and a hatchling, and investigate the presence and pattern of DNA methylation and histone methylation marks across tissues. This revealed a dynamic gene expression profile encoding several epigenetic regulators, including DNA methylation maintenance factors that were highly conserved and functional in cephalopods, as shown by detection of 5-methyl-cytosine in multiple tissues of octopus, squid and bobtail squid. WGBS of octopus brain and RRBS from a hatchling revealed that less than 10% of CpGs are methylated, highlighting a non-random distribution in the genome of all tissues, with enrichment in the bodies of a subset of 14,000 genes and absence from transposons. Each DNA methylation pattern encompassed genes with distinct functions and, strikingly, many of these genes showed similar expression levels across tissues. In contrast to the static pattern of DNA methylation, the histone marks H3K27me3, H3K9me3 and H3K4me3 were detected at different levels in diverse cephalopod tissues. This suggests the methylome and histone code cooperate to regulate tissue specific gene expression in a way that may be unique to cephalopods.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469068" rel="alternate" title="Epigenetic machinery is functionally conserved in cephalopods (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469076</id><title>Genome and transcriptome architecture of allopolyploid okra (Abelmoschus esculentus) (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.030991+00:00</updated><author><name>Ronald Nieuwenhuis</name></author><author><name>Thamara Hesselink</name></author><author><name>Hetty C. van den Broeck</name></author><author><name>Jan Cordewener</name></author><author><name>Elio Schijlen</name></author><author><name>Linda Bakker</name></author><author><name>Sara Diaz Trivino</name></author><author><name>Darush Struss</name></author><author><name>Simon-Jan de Hoop</name></author><author><name>Hans de Jong</name></author><author><name>Sander A. Peters</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We present the first annotated genome assembly of the allopolyploid okra (&lt;italic&gt;Abelmoschus esculentus&lt;/italic&gt;). Analysis of telomeric repeats and gene rich regions suggested we obtained whole chromosome and chromosomal arm scaffolds. Besides long distal blocks we also detected short interstitial TTTAGGG telomeric repeats, possibly representing hallmarks of chromosomal speciation upon polyploidization of okra. Ribosomal RNA genes are organized in 5S clusters separated from the 18S-5.8S-28S units, clearly indicating an S-type rRNA gene arrangement. The assembly is consistent with cytogenetic and cytometry observations, identifying 65 chromosomes and 1.45Gb of expected genome size in a haploid sibling. Approximately 57% of the genome consists of repetitive sequence. BUSCO scores and A50 plot statistics indicated a nearly complete genome. Kmer distribution analysis suggests that approximately 75% has a diploid nature, and at least 15% of the genome is heterozygous. We did not observe aberrant meiotic configurations, suggesting there is no recombination among the sub-genomes. BUSCO configurations pointed to the presence of at least 3 sub-genomes. These observations are indicative for an allopolyploid nature of the okra genome. Structural annotation using gene models derived from mapped transcriptome data, generated over 130,000 putative genes. The discovered genes appeared to be located predominantly at the distal ends of scaffolds, gradually decreasing in abundance toward more centrally positioned scaffold domains. In contrast, LTR retrotransposons were more abundant in centrally located scaffold domains, while less frequently represented in the distal ends. This gene and LTR-retrotransposon distribution is consistent with the observed heterochromatin organization of pericentromeric heterochromatin and distal euchromatin. The derived amino acid queries of putative genes were subsequently used for phenol biosynthesis pathway annotation in okra. Comparison against manually curated reference KEGG pathways from related &lt;italic&gt;Malvaceae&lt;/italic&gt; species revealed the genetic basis for putative enzyme coding genes that likely enable metabolic reactions involved in the biosynthesis of dietary and therapeutic compounds in okra.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469076" rel="alternate" title="Genome and transcriptome architecture of allopolyploid okra (Abelmoschus esculentus) (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468624</id><title>Genetic coordination of sperm morphology and seminal fluid proteins promotes male reproductive success in Drosophila melanogaster (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.031156+00:00</updated><author><name>Jake Galvin</name></author><author><name>Erica L. Larson</name></author><author><name>Sevan Yedigarian</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Rahman</name></author><author><name>Kirill Borziak</name></author><author><name>Michael DeNieu</name></author><author><name>Mollie K. Manier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spermatozoal morphology is highly variable both among and within species and in ways that can significantly impact fertilization success. In &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt;, paternity success depends on sperm length of both competing males and length of the female’s primary sperm storage organ. We found that genes upregulated in long sperm testes are enriched for lncRNAs and seminal fluid proteins (Sfps). Transferred in seminal fluid to the female during mating, Sfps are secreted by the male accessory glands (AG) and affect female remating rate, physiology, and behavior with concomitant advantages for male reproductive success. Despite being upregulated in long sperm testes, they have no known function in testis tissue. We found that Sex Peptide and ovulin (Acp26Aa) knockouts resulted in shorter sperm, suggesting that Sfps may regulate sperm length during spermatogenesis. However, knockout of AG function did not affect sperm length, suggesting that AG expression has no influence on spermatogenic processes. We also found that long sperm males are better able to delay female remating, suggesting higher Sfp expression in AG. These results might suggest that long sperm males have a double advantage in sperm competition by both delaying female remating, likely through transfer of more Sfps, and by resisting sperm displacement. However, we also found that this extra advantage does not necessarily translate to more progeny or higher paternity success. Thus, we found that multiple components of the ejaculate coordinate to promote male reproductive success at different stages of reproduction, but the realized fitness advantages in sperm competition are uncertain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ejaculate is comprised of sperm produced in the testis and seminal fluid primarily produced in the male accessory glands (AG). These complementary components are both critical for male reproductive success, but they are largely considered to be functionally, genetically, and developmentally independent. In a quest to understand genetic mechanisms of sperm length variation, we found that genes upregulated in long sperm testes are enriched for lncRNAs and seminal fluid proteins (Sfps). Knockout of two Sfps, Sex Peptide and ovulin, results in shorter sperm, though knockout of AG function has no effect. Moreover, long sperm males delay female remating longer. These results suggest sophisticated testis-AG coordination that amplifies male reproductive success, with implications for evolutionary integration of sexually selected traits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468624" rel="alternate" title="Genetic coordination of sperm morphology and seminal fluid proteins promotes male reproductive success in Drosophila melanogaster (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>