<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.886403+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456011</id><title>Long reads and Hi-C sequencing illuminate the two-compartment genome of the model arbuscular mycorrhizal symbiont Rhizophagus irregularis (89 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.886735+00:00</updated><author><name>Gokalp Yildirir</name></author><author><name>Jana Sperschneider</name></author><author><name>Mathu C Malar</name></author><author><name>Eric CH Chen</name></author><author><name>Wataru Iwasaki</name></author><author><name>Calvin Cornell</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Corradi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chromosome folding links genome structure with gene function by generating distinct nuclear compartments and topologically associating domains (TADs). In mammals, these domains undergo preferential interactions and regulate gene expression, however in fungi the role of chromosome folding in genome biology is unclear. Here, we combine Nanopore (ONT) sequencing with chromatin conformation capture sequencing (Hi-C) to reveal chromosome diversity in a group of obligate plant symbionts with a multinucleate mycelium; the arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF). We find that phylogenetically distinct strains of the model AMF Rhizophagus irregularis all carry 33 chromosomes. Homologous chromosomes show within species variability in size, as well as in gene and repeat content. Strain-specific Hi-C sequencing reveals that all strains have a 3D genome organization that resembles a checkerboard structure with two distinct (A/B) chromatin compartments. Each compartment differs in the level of gene transcription, regulation of candidate effectors and methylation rate. The A-compartment is more gene-dense and contains most core genes, while the B-compartment is more repeat-rich and has higher rates of chromosomal rearrangement. While the B-compartment is transcriptionally repressed, it has significantly more secreted proteins and in planta up-regulated candidate effectors suggesting a possible host-induced change in chromosome conformation. Overall, this study provides a fine-scale view into the genome biology and evolution of prominent plant symbionts, and opens avenues to study the mechanisms that generate and modify chromosome folding during host-microbe interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456011" rel="alternate" title="Long reads and Hi-C sequencing illuminate the two-compartment genome of the model arbuscular mycorrhizal symbiont Rhizophagus irregularis (89 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455920</id><title>A global survey of specialized metabolic diversity encoded in bacterial genomes (51 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.886956+00:00</updated><author><name>Athina Gavriilidou</name></author><author><name>Satria A. Kautsar</name></author><author><name>Nestor Zaburannyi</name></author><author><name>Daniel Krug</name></author><author><name>Rolf Müller</name></author><author><name>Marnix H. Medema</name></author><author><name>Nadine Ziemert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial secondary metabolites have been studied for decades for their usefulness as drugs, such as antibiotics. However, the identification of new structures has been decelerating, in part due to rediscovery of known compounds. Meanwhile, multi-resistant pathogens continue to emerge, urging the need for new antibiotics. It is unclear how much chemical diversity exists in Nature and whether discovery efforts should be focused on established antibiotic producers or rather on understudied taxa. Here, we surveyed around 170,000 bacterial genomes as well as several thousands of Metagenome Assembled Genomes (MAGs) for their diversity in Biosynthetic Gene Clusters (BGCs) known to encode the biosynthetic machinery for producing secondary metabolites. We used two distinct algorithms to provide a global overview of the biosynthetic diversity present in the sequenced part of the bacterial kingdom. Our results indicate that only 3% of genomic potential for natural products has been experimentally discovered. We connect the emergence of most biosynthetic diversity in evolutionary history close to the taxonomic rank of genus. Despite enormous differences in potential among taxa, we identify &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt; as by far the most biosynthetically diverse based on currently available data. Simultaneously, our analysis highlights multiple promising high-producing taxas that have thus far escaped investigation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455920" rel="alternate" title="A global survey of specialized metabolic diversity encoded in bacterial genomes (51 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456148</id><title>Neuronal mTORC1 inhibition promotes longevity without suppressing anabolic growth and reproduction in C. elegans (45 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.887126+00:00</updated><author><name>Hannah J. Smith</name></author><author><name>Anne Lanjuin</name></author><author><name>Arpit Sharma</name></author><author><name>Aditi Prabhakar</name></author><author><name>Emina Tabakovic</name></author><author><name>Rohan Sehgal</name></author><author><name>William B. Mair</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;One of the most robust and reproducible methods to prolong lifespan in a variety of organisms is inhibition of the mTORC1 (mechanistic target of rapamycin complex 1) pathway. mTORC1 is a metabolic sensor that promotes anabolic growth when nutrients are abundant. Inhibition of mTORC1 extends lifespan, but also frequently has other effects such as stunted growth, slowed development, reduced fertility, and disrupted metabolism. It has long been assumed that suppression of anabolism and resulting phenotypes such as impaired growth and reproduction may be causal to mTORC1 longevity, but this hypothesis has not been directly tested. RAGA-1 is an upstream activator of TORC1. Previous work from our lab using a &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; model of mTORC1 longevity, the long-lived &lt;italic&gt;raga-1&lt;/italic&gt; null mutant, found that the presence of &lt;italic&gt;raga-1&lt;/italic&gt; only in the neurons suppresses longevity of the null mutant. Here, we use the auxin-inducible degradation (AID) system to test whether neuronal mTORC1 inhibition is sufficient for longevity, and whether any changes in lifespan are also linked to stunted growth or fertility. We find that life-long AID of RAGA-1 either in all somatic tissue or only in the neurons of &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; is sufficient to extend lifespan. We also find that AID of RAGA-1 or LET-363/mTOR beginning at day 1 of adulthood extends lifespan to a similar extent. Unlike somatic degradation of RAGA-1, neuronal degradation of RAGA-1 doesn’t impair growth, slow development, or decrease the reproductive capacity of the worms. Lastly, while AID of LET-363/mTOR in all somatic cells shortens lifespan, neuronal AID of LET-363/mTOR slows aging. This work demonstrates that targeting mTORC1 specifically in the neurons uncouples longevity from growth and reproductive impairments, challenging previously held ideas about the mechanisms of mTORC1 longevity and elucidating the promise of tissue-specific aging therapeutics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456148" rel="alternate" title="Neuronal mTORC1 inhibition promotes longevity without suppressing anabolic growth and reproduction in C. elegans (45 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456138</id><title>The impact of evolutionary processes in shaping the genetics of complex traits in East Asia and Europe: a specific contribution from Denisovan and Neanderthal introgression (34 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.887291+00:00</updated><author><name>Dora Koller</name></author><author><name>Frank R Wendt</name></author><author><name>Gita Pathak</name></author><author><name>Antonella De Lillo</name></author><author><name>Flavio De Angelis</name></author><author><name>Brenda Cabrera Mendoza</name></author><author><name>Serena Tucci</name></author><author><name>Renato Polimanti</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Evidence of how human evolution shaped the polygenicity of human traits and diseases has been extensively studied in populations of European descent. However, limited information is currently available about its impact on other ancestry groups. Here, we investigated how different evolutionary processes affected the common variant heritability of traits and diseases in East Asians. Leveraging genome-wide association statistics from the Biobank Japan (up to 158,284 participants), we assessed natural selection (negative and positive), archaic introgression from Neanderthal and Denisova, and several genomic functional categories with respect to the heritability of physiological and pathological conditions. Similar to reports in European descent populations, the heritability estimates for East Asian traits were ubiquitously enriched for negative selection annotations (false discovery rate, FDR q&amp;lt;0.05). Enrichment of Denisovan introgression was identified in coronary artery disease (1.69-fold enrichment, p=0.003). We followed up these enrichments by conducting a phenome-wide association study (PheWAS) of Denisovan and Neanderthal alleles in participants of six ancestral backgrounds from the UK Biobank. In East Asians, Denisovan-inherited alleles were associated with 22 phenotypes, including metabolic, immunological, cardiovascular, endocrine, and dermatological traits. The strongest association was observed for the Denisovan-inherited locus rs59185462 with rheumatoid arthritis (beta=0.82, p=1.91x10-105). In summary, our study provides the first evidence regarding the impact of evolutionary processes on the genetics of complex traits in worldwide populations, highlighting the specific contribution of Denisovan introgression in East Asian populations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456138" rel="alternate" title="The impact of evolutionary processes in shaping the genetics of complex traits in East Asia and Europe: a specific contribution from Denisovan and Neanderthal introgression (34 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455687</id><title>The epigenetic evolution of gliomas is determined by their IDH1 mutation status and treatment regimen (33 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.887460+00:00</updated><author><name>Tathiane M Malta</name></author><author><name>Thais S Sabedot</name></author><author><name>Indrani Datta</name></author><author><name>Luciano Garofano</name></author><author><name>Wies Vallentgoed</name></author><author><name>Frederick S Varn</name></author><author><name>Kenneth Aldape</name></author><author><name>Fulvio D’Angelo</name></author><author><name>Spyridon Bakas</name></author><author><name>Jill S Barnholtz-Sloan</name></author><author><name>Hui K Gan</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Hasanain</name></author><author><name>Ann-Christin Hau</name></author><author><name>Kevin C Johnson</name></author><author><name>Mustafa Khasraw</name></author><author><name>Emre Kocakavuk</name></author><author><name>Mathilde CM Kouwenhoven</name></author><author><name>Simona Migliozzi</name></author><author><name>Simone P Niclou</name></author><author><name>Johanna M Niers</name></author><author><name>D. Ryan Ormond</name></author><author><name>Sun Ha Paek</name></author><author><name>Guido Reifenberger</name></author><author><name>Peter A Sillevis Smitt</name></author><author><name>Marion Smits</name></author><author><name>Lucy F Stead</name></author><author><name>Martin J van den Bent</name></author><author><name>Erwin G Van Meir</name></author><author><name>Annemiek Walenkamp</name></author><author><name>Tobias Weiss</name></author><author><name>Michael Weller</name></author><author><name>Bart A Westerman</name></author><author><name>Bauke Ylstra</name></author><author><name>Pieter Wesseling</name></author><author><name>Anna Lasorella</name></author><author><name>Pim J French</name></author><author><name>Laila M Poisson</name></author><author><name>Roel GW Verhaak</name></author><author><name>Antonio Iavarone</name></author><author><name>Houtan Noushmehr</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tumor adaptation or selection is thought to underlie therapy resistance of gliomas. To investigate the longitudinal epigenetic evolution of gliomas in response to therapeutic pressure, we performed an epigenomic analysis of 143 matched initial and recurrent patients with IDH-wildtype (IDHwt) and IDH-mutant (IDHmut) gliomas. IDHwt gliomas showed a longitudinally stable epigenome with relatively low levels of global methylation, whereas the epigenome of IDHmut gliomas showed initial high levels genome-wide of DNA methylation that was progressively reduced to levels similar to those of IDHwt tumors. By integrating DNA methylation and gene expression data, adaptive changes of putative master regulators of the cell cycle and of differentiation were seen in IDHmut recurrent tumors. Furthermore, relapses of IDHmut tumors were accompanied by histological progression which in turn influenced survival, as validated in an independent cohort. Finally, the initial cell composition of the tumor microenvironment differed between IDHwt and IDHmut tumors and changed differentially following treatment, suggesting increased neo-angiogenesis and T-cell infiltration upon treatment for IDHmut gliomas. Our study provides one of the largest cohorts of paired glioma samples profiled with epigenomics, transcriptomics and genomics; and our results demonstrate that the treatment of IDHmut gliomas reshapes the epigenome towards an IDHwt-like phenotype. Accordingly, the prevalent practice of early genotoxic treatment in this patient population may need to be revisited.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455687" rel="alternate" title="The epigenetic evolution of gliomas is determined by their IDH1 mutation status and treatment regimen (33 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456314</id><title>Assembled chromosomes of the blood fluke Schistosoma mansoni provide insight into the evolution of its ZW sex-determination system (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.887809+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah K Buddenborg</name></author><author><name>Alan Tracey</name></author><author><name>Duncan J Berger</name></author><author><name>Zhigang Lu</name></author><author><name>Stephen Doyle</name></author><author><name>Beiyuan Fu</name></author><author><name>Fengtang Yang</name></author><author><name>Adam James Reid</name></author><author><name>Faye H Rodgers</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Rinaldi</name></author><author><name>Geetha Sankaranarayanan</name></author><author><name>Ulrike Bohme</name></author><author><name>Nancy Holroyd</name></author><author><name>Matthew Berriman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Schistosoma mansoni is a flatworm that causes a neglected tropical disease affecting millions worldwide. Most flatworms are hermaphrodites but schistosomes have genotypically determined male (ZZ) and female (ZW) sexes. Sex is essential for pathology and transmission, however, the molecular determinants of sex remain unknown and is limited by poorly resolved sex chromosomes in previous genome assemblies. Results: We assembled the 391.4 Mb S. mansoni genome into individual, single-scaffold chromosomes, including Z and W. Manual curation resulted in a vastly improved gene annotation, resolved gene and repeat arrays, trans-splicing, and almost all UTRs. The sex chromosomes each comprise pseudoautosomal regions and single sex-specific regions. The Z-specific region contains 932 genes, but on W all but 29 of these genes have been lost and the presence of five pseudogenes indicates that degeneration of W is ongoing. Synteny analysis reveals an ancient chromosomal fusion corresponding to the oldest part of Z, where only a single gene-encoding the large subunit of pre-mRNA splicing factor U2AF has retained an intact copy on W. The sex-specific copies of U2AF have divergent N-termini and show sex-biased gene expression. Conclusion: Our assembly with fully resolved chromosomes provides evidence of an evolutionary path taken to create the Z and W sex chromosomes of schistosomes. Sex-linked divergence of the single U2AF gene, which has been present in the sex-specific regions longer than any other extant gene with distinct male and female specific copies and expression, may have been a pivotal step in the evolution of gonorchorism and genotypic sex determination of schistosomes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456314" rel="alternate" title="Assembled chromosomes of the blood fluke Schistosoma mansoni provide insight into the evolution of its ZW sex-determination system (18 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456029</id><title>Towards the extended barcode concept: Generating DNA reference data through genome skimming of danish plants (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.888036+00:00</updated><author><name>Physilia Y. S. Chua</name></author><author><name>Frederik Leerhøi</name></author><author><name>Emilia M. R. Langkjær</name></author><author><name>Ashot Margaryan</name></author><author><name>Christina L. Noer</name></author><author><name>Stine R. Richter</name></author><author><name>Marlene E. Restrup</name></author><author><name>Hans Henrik Bruun</name></author><author><name>Ida Hartvig</name></author><author><name>Eric Coissac</name></author><author><name>Sanne Boessenkool</name></author><author><name>Inger G. Alsos</name></author><author><name>Kristine Bohmann</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently, there has been a push towards the extended barcode concept of utilising chloroplast genomes (cpGenome) and nuclear ribosomal DNA (nrDNA) sequences for molecular identification of plants instead of the standard barcode regions. These extended barcodes has a wide range of applications, including biodiversity monitoring and assessment, primer design, and evolutionary studies. However, these extended barcodes are not well represented in global reference databases. To fill this gap, we generated cpGenomes and nrDNA reference data from genome skims of 184 plant species collected in Denmark. We further explored the application of our generated reference data for molecular identifications of plants in an environmental DNA metagenomics study.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We assembled partial cpGenomes for 82.1% of sequenced species and full or partial nrDNA sequences for 83.7% of species. We added all assemblies to GenBank, of which chloroplast reference data from 101 species and nuclear reference data from 6 species were not previously represented. On average, we recovered 45 genes per species. The rate of recovery of standard barcodes was higher for nuclear barcodes (&amp;gt;89%) than chloroplast barcodes (&amp;lt; 60%). Extracted DNA yield did not affect assembly outcome, whereas high GC content did so negatively. For the &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; simulation of metagenomic reads, taxonomic assignments using the reference data generated had better species resolution (94.9%) as compared to GenBank (18.1%) without any identification errors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Genome skimming generates reference data of both standard barcodes and other loci, contributing to the global DNA reference database for plants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456029" rel="alternate" title="Towards the extended barcode concept: Generating DNA reference data through genome skimming of danish plants (16 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456072</id><title>SUMOylation of Jun fine-tunes the Drosophila gut immune response (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.888259+00:00</updated><author><name>Amarendranath Soory</name></author><author><name>Girish Ratnaparkhi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Post-translational modification by the small ubiquitin-like modifier, SUMO can modulate the activity of its conjugated proteins. The transcriptional regulator Jun, a member of the AP-1, complex is one such SUMO target. We find that Jra, the &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; Jun ortholog, is a regulator of the &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas entomophila&lt;/italic&gt; induced gut immune gene regulatory network, modulating the expression of a few thousand genes, as measured by quantitative RNA sequencing. Decrease in &lt;italic&gt;Jra&lt;/italic&gt; in gut enterocytes is protective, suggesting that reduction of Jra signaling favors the host over the pathogen. In Jra, lysines 29 and 190 are SUMO conjugation targets, with the Jra&lt;sup&gt;K29R+K190R&lt;/sup&gt; double mutant being SUMO conjugation resistant (SCR). Interestingly, a &lt;italic&gt;Jra&lt;sup&gt;SCR&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; fly line, generated by CRISPR/Cas9 based genome editing, is more sensitive to infection, with adults showing a weakened host response and increased proliferation of &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas.&lt;/italic&gt; Transcriptome analysis of the guts of &lt;italic&gt;Jra&lt;sup&gt;SCR&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Jra&lt;sup&gt;WT&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; flies suggests that lack of SUMOylation of Jra significantly changes core elements of the immune gene regulatory network, that include antimicrobial agents, secreted ligands, feedback regulators, and transcription factors. SUMOylation attenuates Jra activity, with the master immune regulator Relish being an important transcriptional target. Our study implicates Jra as a major immune regulator, with dynamic SUMO conjugation/deconjugation modulating the kinetics of the gut transcriptional immune response.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456072" rel="alternate" title="SUMOylation of Jun fine-tunes the Drosophila gut immune response (14 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.08.455466</id><title>Powerful eQTL mapping through low coverage RNA sequencing (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.888396+00:00</updated><author><name>Tommer Schwarz</name></author><author><name>Toni Boltz</name></author><author><name>Kangcheng Hou</name></author><author><name>Merel Bot</name></author><author><name>Chenda Duan</name></author><author><name>Loes Olde Loohuis</name></author><author><name>Marco P. Boks</name></author><author><name>René S. Kahn</name></author><author><name>Roel A. Ophoff</name></author><author><name>Bogdan Pasaniuc</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mapping genetic variants that regulate gene expression (eQTL mapping) in large-scale RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) studies is often employed to understand functional consequences of regulatory variants. However, the high cost of RNA-Seq limits sample size, sequencing depth, and therefore, discovery power. In this work, we demonstrate that, given a fixed budget, eQTL discovery power can be increased by lowering the sequencing depth per sample and increasing the number of individuals sequenced in the assay. We perform RNA-Seq of whole blood tissue across 1490 individuals at low-coverage (5.9 million reads/sample) and show that the effective power is higher than that of an RNA-Seq study of 570 individuals at high-coverage (13.9 million reads/sample). Next, we leverage synthetic datasets derived from real RNA-Seq data to explore the interplay of coverage and number individuals in eQTL studies, and show that a 10-fold reduction in coverage leads to only a 2.5-fold reduction in statistical power. Our study suggests that lowering coverage while increasing the number of individuals is an effective approach to increase discovery power in RNA-Seq studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.08.455466" rel="alternate" title="Powerful eQTL mapping through low coverage RNA sequencing (13 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456025</id><title>A reference genome sequence resource for the sugar beet root rot pathogen Aphanomyces cochlioides (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.888633+00:00</updated><author><name>Jacob Botkin</name></author><author><name>Ashok K. Chanda</name></author><author><name>Frank N. Martin</name></author><author><name>Cory D. Hirsch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Aphanomyces cochlioides,&lt;/italic&gt; the causal agent of damping-off and root rot of sugar beet (&lt;italic&gt;Beta vulgaris&lt;/italic&gt; L.), is a soil-dwelling oomycete responsible for yield losses in all major sugar beet growing regions. Currently, genomic resources for &lt;italic&gt;A. cochlioides&lt;/italic&gt; are limited. Here we report a &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; genome assembly using a combination of long-read MinION (Oxford Nanopore Technologies) and short-read Illumina sequence data for &lt;italic&gt;A. cochlioides&lt;/italic&gt; isolate 103-1, from Breckenridge, MN. The assembled genome was 76.3 Mb, with a contig N50 of 2.6 Mb. The reference assembly was annotated and was composed of 32.1% repetitive elements and 20,274 gene models. This high-quality genome assembly of &lt;italic&gt;A. cochlioides&lt;/italic&gt; will be a valuable resource for understanding genetic variation, virulence factors, and comparative genomics of this important sugar beet pathogen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456025" rel="alternate" title="A reference genome sequence resource for the sugar beet root rot pathogen Aphanomyces cochlioides (12 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456172</id><title>Single-nucleus RNA-sequencing in pre-cellularization Drosophila melanogaster embryos (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.888783+00:00</updated><author><name>Ashley R Albright</name></author><author><name>Michael R Stadler</name></author><author><name>Michael Eisen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Our current understanding of the regulation of gene expression in the early Drosophila melanogaster embryo comes from observations of a few genes at a time, as with in situ hybridizations, or observation of gene expression levels without regards to patterning, as with RNA-sequencing. Single-nucleus RNA-sequencing however, has the potential to provide new insights into the regulation of gene expression for many genes at once while simultaneously retaining information regarding the position of each nucleus prior to dissociation based on patterned gene expression. In order to establish the practicality of single-nucleus RNA sequencing in the context of a real biological question, here we look at the difference in gene expression between control and an insulator protein, dCTCF, maternal null embryos during zygotic genome activation at nuclear cycle 14. We find that early embryonic nuclei can be grouped into distinct clusters according to gene expression. From both virtual and published in situ hybridizations, we also find that these clusters correspond to spatial regions of the embryo. Lastly, we present multiple examples of differential gene expression between control and maternal CTCF null nuclei in one or more clusters, but not in bulk when grouping expression across all nuclei. These results highlight the potential for single-nucleus RNA-sequencing to reveal new insights into the regulation of gene expression in the early Drosophila melanogaster embryo.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456172" rel="alternate" title="Single-nucleus RNA-sequencing in pre-cellularization Drosophila melanogaster embryos (10 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456098</id><title>A Meta-Analytic Single-Cell Atlas of Mouse Bone Marrow Hematopoietic Development (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.888926+00:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin D. Harris</name></author><author><name>John Lee</name></author><author><name>Jesse Gillis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The clinical importance of the hematopoietic system makes it one of the most heavily studied lineages in all of biology. A clear understanding of the cell types and functional programs during hematopoietic development is central to research in aging, cancer, and infectious diseases. Known cell types are traditionally identified by the expression of proteins on the surface of the cells. Stem and progenitor cells defined based on these markers are assigned functions based on their lineage potential. The rapid growth of single cell RNA sequencing technologies (scRNAseq) provides a new modality for evaluating the cellular and functional landscape of hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells. The popularity of this technology among hematopoiesis researchers enables us to conduct a robust meta-analysis of mouse bone marrow scRNAseq data. Using over 300,000 cells across 12 datasets, we evaluate the classification and function of cell types based on discrete clustering, &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; FACS sorting, and a continuous trajectory. We identify replicable signatures that define cell types based on genes and known cellular functions. Additionally, we evaluate the conservation of signatures associated with erythroid and monocyte lineage development across species using co-expression networks. The co-expression networks predict the effectiveness of the signature at identifying erythroid and monocyte cells in zebrafish and human scRNAseq data. Together, this analysis provides a robust reference, particularly marker genes and functional annotations, for future experiments in hematopoietic development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key Points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meta-analysis of 9 mouse bone marrow scRNAseq identifies markers for cell types and hematopoietic development&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Characterize a replicable functional landscape of cell types by exploiting co-expression&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456098" rel="alternate" title="A Meta-Analytic Single-Cell Atlas of Mouse Bone Marrow Hematopoietic Development (10 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456112</id><title>A low-cost greenhouse-based high-throughput phenotyping platform for genetic studies: a case study in maize under inoculation with plant growth-promoting bacteria (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.889064+00:00</updated><author><name>Rafael Massahiro Yassue</name></author><author><name>Giovanni Galli</name></author><author><name>Ronaldo Borsato Junior</name></author><author><name>Hao Cheng</name></author><author><name>Gota Morota</name></author><author><name>Roberto Fritsche-Neto</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Greenhouse-based high-throughput phenotyping (HTP) presents a useful approach for studying novel plant growth-promoting bacteria (PGPB). Despite the potential of this approach to leverage genetic variability for breeding new maize cultivars exhibiting highly stable symbiosis with PGPB, greenhouse-based HTP platforms are not yet widely used because they are highly expensive; hence, it is challenging to perform HTP studies under a limited budget. In this study, we built a low-cost greenhouse-based HTP platform to collect growth-related image-derived phenotypes. We assessed 360 inbred maize lines with or without PGPB inoculation under nitrogen-limited conditions. Plant height, canopy coverage, and canopy volume obtained from photogrammetry were evaluated five times during early maize development. A plant biomass index was constructed as a function of plant height and canopy coverage. Inoculation with PGPB promoted plant growth. Phenotypic correlations between the image-derived phenotypes and manual measurements were at least 0.6. The genomic heritability estimates of the image-derived phenotypes ranged from 0.23 to 0.54. Moderate-to-strong genomic correlations between the plant biomass index and shoot dry mass (0.24-0.47) and between HTP-based plant height and manually measured plant height (0.55-0.68) across the developmental stages showed the utility of our HTP platform. Collectively, our results demonstrate the usefulness of the low-cost HTP platform for large-scale genetic and management studies to capture plant growth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456112" rel="alternate" title="A low-cost greenhouse-based high-throughput phenotyping platform for genetic studies: a case study in maize under inoculation with plant growth-promoting bacteria (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456099</id><title>Maximizing GWAS discovery and genomic prediction accuracy in Biobank data (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.889220+00:00</updated><author><name>Etienne J. Orliac</name></author><author><name>Daniel Trejo Banos</name></author><author><name>Sven E. Ojavee</name></author><author><name>Kristi Läll</name></author><author><name>Reedik Mägi</name></author><author><name>Peter M. Visscher</name></author><author><name>Matthew R. Robinson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Across 21 heritable traits in the UK and Estonian Biobank data, a Bayesian grouped mixture of regressions model (GMRM) obtains the highest genomic prediction accuracy reported to date, 15% (SD 10%) greater than a baseline model without MAF-LD-annotation groups, and 106% (SD 50%) greater than mixed-linear model association (MLMA) estimate polygenic scores. Prediction accuracy was up to 13% (mean 4%, SD 3%) higher than theoretical expectations, at 76% of the &lt;inline-formula&gt;&lt;alternatives&gt;&lt;inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="456099v1_inline1.gif" /&gt;&lt;/alternatives&gt;&lt;/inline-formula&gt; for height (&lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; of 47%) and over 50% of the &lt;inline-formula&gt;&lt;alternatives&gt;&lt;inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="456099v1_inline2.gif" /&gt;&lt;/alternatives&gt;&lt;/inline-formula&gt; for 12 traits. Using these predictors in MLMA, increased the independent GWAS loci detected from 16,899 using standard approaches to 18,837 using GMRM, an 11.5% increase. Modelling genetic associations accounting for MAF and LD differences among SNP markers, and incorporating prior knowledge of genomic function, is important for large-scale individual-level biobank-scale analyses and is facilitated by our scalable highly parallel open source GMRM software.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456099" rel="alternate" title="Maximizing GWAS discovery and genomic prediction accuracy in Biobank data (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455263</id><title>An efficient method to identify, date and describe admixture events using haplotype information (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.889379+00:00</updated><author><name>Pongsakorn Wangkumhang</name></author><author><name>Matthew Greenfield</name></author><author><name>Garrett Hellenthal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We present fastGLOBETROTTER, an efficient new haplotype-based technique to identify, date and describe admixture events using genome-wide autosomal data. With simulations, we demonstrate how fastGLOBETROTTER reduces computation time by 4-20 fold relative to the haplotype-based technique GLOBETROTTER without suffering loss of accuracy. We apply fastGLOBETROTTER to a cohort of &amp;gt;6000 Europeans from ten countries, revealing previously unreported admixture signals. In particular we infer multiple periods of admixture related to East Asian or Siberian-like sources, starting &amp;gt;2000 years ago, in people living in countries north of the Baltic Sea. In contrast, we infer admixture related to West Asian, North African and/or Southern European sources in populations south of the Baltic Sea, including admixture dated to ≈300-700CE, overlapping the fall of the Roman Empire, in people from Belgium, France and parts of Germany. Our new approach scales to analysing hundreds to thousands of individuals from a putatively admixed populations and hence is applicable to emerging large-scale cohorts of genetically homogeneous populations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455263" rel="alternate" title="An efficient method to identify, date and describe admixture events using haplotype information (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456132</id><title>De novo chromosome level assembly of the mule deer (Odocoileus hemionus) genome (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.889518+00:00</updated><author><name>Sydney Lamb</name></author><author><name>Adam M. Taylor</name></author><author><name>Tabitha A. Hughes</name></author><author><name>Brock R. McMillan</name></author><author><name>Randy T. Larsen</name></author><author><name>Ruqayya Khan</name></author><author><name>David Weisz</name></author><author><name>Olga Dudchenko</name></author><author><name>Erez Lieberman Aiden</name></author><author><name>Paul B. Frandsen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mule deer (&lt;italic&gt;Odocoileus hemionus&lt;/italic&gt;) is an ungulate species that ranges from western Canada to central Mexico. Mule deer are an essential source of food for many predators, are relatively abundant, and commonly make broad migration movements. A clearer understanding of the mule deer genome can help facilitate knowledge of its population genetics, movements, and demographic history, aiding in conservation efforts. While mule deer are excellent candidates for population genomic studies because of their large population size, continuous distribution, and diversity of habitat, few genomic resources are currently available for this species. Here, we sequence and assemble the mule deer genome into a highly contiguous chromosome-length assembly for use in future research using long-read sequencing and Hi-C. We also provide a genome annotation and compare demographic histories of the mule deer and white-tail deer using PSMC. We expect this assembly to be a valuable resource in the continued study and conservation of mule deer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456132" rel="alternate" title="De novo chromosome level assembly of the mule deer (Odocoileus hemionus) genome (6 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456174</id><title>The effect of weak clonal interference on average fitness trajectories in the presence of macroscopic epistasis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.889695+00:00</updated><author><name>Yipei Guo</name></author><author><name>Ariel Amir</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Adaptation dynamics on fitness landscapes is often studied theoretically in the strong-selection, weak-mutation (SSWM) regime. However, in a large population, multiple beneficial mutants can emerge before any of them fixes in the population. Competition between mutants is known as clonal interference, and how it affects the form of long-term fitness trajectories in the presence of epistasis is an open question. Here, by considering how changes in fixation probabilities arising from weak clonal interference affect the dynamics of adaptation on fitness-parameterized landscapes, we find that the change in the form of fitness trajectory arises only through changes in the supply of beneficial mutations (or equivalently, the beneficial mutation rate). Furthermore, a depletion of beneficial mutations as a population climbs up the fitness landscape can speed up the functional form of the fitness trajectory, while an enhancement of the beneficial mutation rate does the opposite of slowing down the form of the dynamics. Our findings suggest that by carrying out evolution experiments in both regimes (with and without clonal interference), one could potentially distinguish the different sources of macroscopic epistasis (fitness effect of mutations vs. change in fraction of beneficial mutations).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456174" rel="alternate" title="The effect of weak clonal interference on average fitness trajectories in the presence of macroscopic epistasis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455267</id><title>Large-scale integration of DNA methylation and gene expression array platforms (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.889830+00:00</updated><author><name>Eva E. Lancaster</name></author><author><name>Vladimir I. Vladimirov</name></author><author><name>Brien P. Riley</name></author><author><name>Joseph W. Landry</name></author><author><name>Roxann Roberson-Nay</name></author><author><name>Timothy P. York</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Epigenome-wide association studies (EWAS) aim to provide evidence that marks of DNA methylation (DNAm) have downstream consequences that can result in the development of human diseases. Although these methods have been successful in identifying DNAm patterns associated with disease states, any further characterization of etiologic mechanisms underlying disease remains elusive. This knowledge gap does not originate from a lack of DNAm-trait associations, but rather stems from study design issues that affect the interpretability of EWAS results. Despite known limitations in predicting the function of a particular CpG site, most EWAS maintain the broad assumption that altered DNAm results in a concomitant change of transcription at the most proximal gene. This study integrated DNAm and gene expression (GE) measurements in two cohorts, the Adolescent and Young Adult Twin Study (AYATS) and the Pregnancy, Race, Environment, Genes (PREG) study, to improve the understanding of epigenomic regulatory mechanisms. CpG sites associated with GE in &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt; were enriched in areas of transcription factor binding and areas of intermediate-to-low CpG density. CpG sites associated with &lt;italic&gt;trans&lt;/italic&gt; GE were also enriched in areas of known regulatory significance, including enhancer regions. These results highlight issues with restricting DNAm-transcript annotations to small genomic intervals and question the validity of assuming a canonical &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt; DNAm-GE pathway. Based on these findings, the interpretation of EWAS results is limited in studies without multi-omic support and further research should identify genomic regions in which GE-associated DNAm is overrepresented.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455267" rel="alternate" title="Large-scale integration of DNA methylation and gene expression array platforms (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455946</id><title>Grandparent inference from genetic data: The potential for parentage-based tagging programs to identify offspring of hatchery strays (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.889983+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas A. Delomas</name></author><author><name>Matthew Campbell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fisheries managers routinely use hatcheries to increase angling opportunity. Many hatcheries operate as segregated programs where hatchery-origin fish are not intended to spawn with natural-origin conspecifics in order to prevent potential negative effects on the natural-origin population. Currently available techniques to monitor the frequency with which hatchery-origin strays successfully spawn in the wild rely on either genetic differentiation between the hatchery- and natural-origin fish or extensive sampling of fish on the spawning grounds. We present a method to infer grandparent-grandchild trios using only genotypes from two putative grandparents and one putative grandchild. We developed estimators of false positive and false negative error rates and showed that genetic panels containing 500 - 700 single nucleotide polymorphisms or 200 - 300 microhaplotypes are expected to allow application of this technique for monitoring segregated hatchery programs. We discuss the ease with which this technique can be implemented by pre-existing parentage-based tagging programs and provide an R package that applies the method.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455946" rel="alternate" title="Grandparent inference from genetic data: The potential for parentage-based tagging programs to identify offspring of hatchery strays (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456090</id><title>Heterochromatin rewiring and domain disruption-mediated chromatin compaction during erythropoiesis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.890114+00:00</updated><author><name>Dong Li</name></author><author><name>Fan Wu</name></author><author><name>Shuo Zhou</name></author><author><name>Xiao-Jun Huang</name></author><author><name>Hsiang-Ying Lee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Development of mammalian red blood cells involves progressive chromatin compaction and subsequent enucleation in terminal stages of differentiation, but the molecular mechanisms underlying the three-dimensional chromatin reorganization and compaction remains obscure. Here, we systematically analyze the distinct features of higher-order chromatin in purified populations of primary human erythroblasts. Our results reveal that while heterochromatin regions undergo substantial compression, select transcription competent regions with active transcription signature are preferentially maintained to achieve a highly-compacted yet functional chromatin state in terminal erythropoiesis, which is about 20-30% of the nuclear volume compared to that of erythroid progenitors. While the partition of euchromatic and heterochromatic regions (compartment A and B) remain mostly unchanged, H3K9me3 marks relocalize to the nuclear periphery and a significant number of H3K9me3 long-range interactions are formed in the three-dimensional rewiring during terminal erythroid chromatin condensation. Moreover, ∼63% of the topologically associating domain (TAD) boundaries are disrupted, while certain TADs with active chromatin modification are selectively maintained during terminal erythropoiesis. The most well-maintained TADs are enriched for chromatin structural factors CTCF and SMC3, as well as factors and marks of the active transcription state. Finally, we demonstrate that the erythroid master regulator GATA1 involves in safeguarding select essential chromatin domains during terminal erythropoiesis. Our study therefore delineate the molecular characteristics of a development-driven chromatin compaction process, which reveals transcription competence as a key determinant of the select domain maintenance to ensure appropriate gene expression during immense chromatin compaction.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456090" rel="alternate" title="Heterochromatin rewiring and domain disruption-mediated chromatin compaction during erythropoiesis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456120</id><title>Wnt16 exerts pleiotropic effects on bone and lean mass in zebrafish (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.890263+00:00</updated><author><name>Claire J. Watson</name></author><author><name>Ernesto Morfin Montes de Oca</name></author><author><name>Imke A. K. Fiedler</name></author><author><name>Andrea R. Cronrath</name></author><author><name>Lulu K. Callies</name></author><author><name>Avery Angell Swearer</name></author><author><name>Visali Sethuraman</name></author><author><name>Ali Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Adrian T. Monstad-Rios</name></author><author><name>Maria F. Rojas</name></author><author><name>W. Joyce Tang</name></author><author><name>Edith M. Gardiner</name></author><author><name>Bjorn Busse</name></author><author><name>Yi-Hsiang Hsu</name></author><author><name>Ronald Y. Kwon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Identifying the mechanisms by which genetic variants exert pleiotropic effects on muscle and bone is a promising strategy to reveal molecular pathways that stimulate coupled bone and muscle growth, and which can be targeted to treat osteoporosis and sarcopenia simultaneously. Previously, it has been shown that genetic variants at the &lt;italic&gt;CPED1-WNT16&lt;/italic&gt; locus have pleiotropic effects on bone mineral density (BMD) and lean tissue mass in humans. While it is known that &lt;italic&gt;WNT16&lt;/italic&gt; is required for normal bone mass, our current functional understanding of WNT16 cannot account for dual effects on bone and lean mass at this locus. Using single cell analysis, microCT imaging, and genetic approaches, we reveal that &lt;italic&gt;wnt16&lt;/italic&gt; exerts pleiotropic effects on bone and lean tissue in zebrafish. We show an early influence of &lt;italic&gt;wnt16&lt;/italic&gt; on axial bone and lean tissue during skeletogenesis, and provide evidence that &lt;italic&gt;wnt16&lt;/italic&gt;+ cells are myogenic precursors during embryonic development. We also show that &lt;italic&gt;wnt16&lt;/italic&gt; is a gene of major effect at the &lt;italic&gt;CPED1-WNT16&lt;/italic&gt; locus. Our findings indicate a critical function for &lt;italic&gt;wnt16&lt;/italic&gt; in muscle and lean tissue development and support &lt;italic&gt;WNT16&lt;/italic&gt; as the principal gene driving pleiotropic effects on bone and lean mass at this locus.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456120" rel="alternate" title="Wnt16 exerts pleiotropic effects on bone and lean mass in zebrafish (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455732</id><title>Genetic diversity of local and introduced cassava germplasm in Burundi using DArTseq molecular analyses (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.890546+00:00</updated><author><name>niyonzima pierre</name></author><author><name>Lydia Nanjala Wamalwa</name></author><author><name>William Maina Muiru</name></author><author><name>Bigirimana Simon</name></author><author><name>Edward Kanju</name></author><author><name>Morag Elizabeth Ferguson</name></author><author><name>Malu Muia Ndavi</name></author><author><name>Silver Tumwegamire</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In Burundi, most of small-scale farmers still grow traditional cassava landraces that are adapted to local conditions and have been selected for consumer preferred attributes. They tend to be susceptible, in varying degrees, to devastating cassava viral diseases such as Cassava Brown Steak Disease (CBSD) and Cassava Mosaic Disease (CMD) with production annual losses of US$1 billion annually. For long term resistance to the disease, several breeding strategies have been proposed. A sound basis for a breeding program is to understand the genetic diversity of both landraces and elite introduced breeding cultivars. This will also assist in efforts to conserve landraces ahead of the broad distribution of improved varieties which have the possibility of replacing landraces. Our study aimed at determining the genetic diversity and relationships of local landraces and introduced elite germplasm using morphological and simple nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) markers as well as identifying a core set of germplasm from the local varieties to be used in the cassava breeding program. A total of 118 cultivars were characterized for morphological trait variation based on leaf, stem and root traits, and genetic variation using SNP markers. Results of morphological characterization based on Ward’s Method revealed three main clusters and five accessions sharing similar characteristics. Molecular characterization identified over 18,000 SNPs and six main clusters and three pairs of duplicates which should be pooled together as one cultivar to avoid redundancy. Results of population genetic analysis showed low genetic distance between populations and between local landraces and elite germplasm. Accessions that shared similar morphological traits were divergent at the molecular level indicating that clustering using morphological traits was inconsistent. Despite the variabilities found within the collection, it was observed that cassava germplasm in Burundi have a narrow genetic base.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455732" rel="alternate" title="Genetic diversity of local and introduced cassava germplasm in Burundi using DArTseq molecular analyses (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-08-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455876</id><title>Whole genome analysis for 163 guide RNAs in Cas9 edited mice reveals minimal off-target activity (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.890715+00:00</updated><author><name>Kevin A. Peterson</name></author><author><name>Sam Khalouei</name></author><author><name>Joshua A. Wood</name></author><author><name>Denise G. Lanza</name></author><author><name>Lauri G. Lintott</name></author><author><name>Brandon J. Willis</name></author><author><name>John R. Seavitt</name></author><author><name>Nour Hanafi</name></author><author><name>Robert E. Braun</name></author><author><name>Mary E. Dickinson</name></author><author><name>Jacqueline K. White</name></author><author><name>K.C. Kent Lloyd</name></author><author><name>Jason D. Heaney</name></author><author><name>Stephen A. Murray</name></author><author><name>Arun Ramani</name></author><author><name>Lauryl M.J. Nutter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Knockout Mouse Phenotyping Program (KOMP&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;) uses CRISRPR/Cas9 for high-throughput mouse line production to generate null alleles in the inbred C57BL/6N strain for broad-based &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; phenotyping. In order to assess the risk of spurious &lt;italic&gt;S. pyogenes&lt;/italic&gt; Cas9-induced off-target mutagenesis, we applied whole genome sequencing to compare the genomes of 50 Cas9-derived founder mice representing 163 different gRNAs to 28 untreated inbred control mice. Our analysis pipeline detected 28 off-target sequence variants associated with 21 guides. These potential off-targets were identified in 18/50 (36%) founders with 9/28 (32%) independently validated corresponding to 8 founder animals. In total, only 4.9% (8/163) of all guides exhibited off-target activity resulting in a rate of 0.16 Cas9 off-target mutations per founder analyzed. In comparison, we observed ~1225 unique variants in each mouse regardless of whether or not it was exposed to Cas9. These findings indicate that Cas9-mediated off-target mutagenesis is rare in founder knockout mice generated using guide RNAs designed to minimize off-target risk. Overall, bona fide off-target variants comprise a small fraction of the genetic heterogeneity found in carefully maintained colonies of inbred strains.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455876" rel="alternate" title="Whole genome analysis for 163 guide RNAs in Cas9 edited mice reveals minimal off-target activity (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>