<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.753783+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.453442</id><title>Leveraging gene co-regulation to identify gene sets enriched for disease heritability (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.754247+00:00</updated><author><name>Katherine M. Siewert-Rocks</name></author><author><name>Samuel S. Kim</name></author><author><name>Douglas W. Yao</name></author><author><name>Huwenbo Shi</name></author><author><name>Alkes L. Price</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Identifying gene sets that are associated to disease can provide valuable biological knowledge, but a fundamental challenge of gene set analyses of GWAS data is linking disease-associated SNPs to genes. Transcriptome-wide association studies (TWAS) can be used to detect associations between the genetically predicted expression of a gene and disease risk, thus implicating candidate disease genes. However, causal disease genes at TWAS-associated loci generally remain unknown due to gene co-regulation, which leads to correlations across genes in predicted expression. We developed a new method, gene co-regulation score (GCSC) regression, to identify gene sets that are enriched for disease heritability explained by the predicted expression of causal disease genes in the gene set. GCSC regresses TWAS chi-square statistics on gene co-regulation scores reflecting correlations in predicted gene expression; GCSC determines that a gene set is enriched for disease heritability if genes with high co-regulation to the gene set have higher TWAS chi-square statistics than genes with low co-regulation to the gene set, beyond what is expected based on co-regulation to all genes. We verified via simulations that GCSC is well-calibrated, and well-powered to identify gene sets that are enriched for disease heritability explained by predicted expression. We applied GCSC to gene expression data from GTEx (48 tissues) and GWAS summary statistics for 43 independent diseases and complex traits (average &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt; =344K), analyzing a broad set of biological pathways and specifically expressed gene sets. We identified many enriched gene sets, recapitulating known biology. For Alzheimer’s disease, we detected evidence of an immune basis, and specifically a role for antigen presentation, in analyses of both biological pathways and specifically expressed gene sets. Our results highlight the advantages of leveraging gene co-regulation within the TWAS framework to identify gene sets associated to disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.453442" rel="alternate" title="Leveraging gene co-regulation to identify gene sets enriched for disease heritability (14 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453515</id><title>Low dose/dose rate γ irradiation protects Drosophila melanogaster chromosomes from double strand breaks and telomere fusions by modulating the expression of Loquacious (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.754515+00:00</updated><author><name>A. Porrazzo</name></author><author><name>F. Cipressa</name></author><author><name>A. De Gregorio</name></author><author><name>C De Pittà</name></author><author><name>G. Sales</name></author><author><name>P. Morciano</name></author><author><name>G Esposito</name></author><author><name>M.A Tabocchini</name></author><author><name>G. Cenci</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It is still continuously debated whether the low-dose/dose-rate (LDDR) of ionizing radiation represents a hazard for humans. Model organisms, such as fruit flies, are considered valuable systems to reveal insights into this issue. We found that, in wild-type &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; larval neuroblasts, the frequency of Chromosome Breaks (CBs), induced by acute γ-radiation, is significantly reduced when flies are previously exposed to a protracted dose of 0.4 Gy delivered at a dose rate of 2.5 mGy/h. This indicates that this exposure, which is associated with an increased expression of DNA damage response proteins, induces a radioadaptive response (RAR) that protects Drosophila from extensive DNA damage. Interestingly, the same exposure reduces the frequency of telomere fusions (TFs) from Drosophila telomere capping mutants suggesting that the LDDR can generally promote a protective response on chromatin sites that are recognized as DNA breaks. Deep RNA sequencing revealed that RAR is associated with a modulation of genes involved in RNA processing and the reduction of expression of &lt;italic&gt;Loquacious D (Loqs-RD)&lt;/italic&gt; gene that encodes a well-conserved dsRNA binding protein required for esiRNAs biogenesis. Remarkably, loss of &lt;italic&gt;Loqs&lt;/italic&gt; mimics the LDDR-mediated chromosome protection as it decreases the IR-induced CBs and TF frequency. Thus, our work identifies Loqs as a key factor in mediating the cellular response to LDDR and reveals that the study of the molecular bases underlying RAR is instrumental for unraveling novel and conserved epigenetic routes that have evolved to preserve genome integrity following robust insults to DNA.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453515" rel="alternate" title="Low dose/dose rate γ irradiation protects Drosophila melanogaster chromosomes from double strand breaks and telomere fusions by modulating the expression of Loquacious (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>