<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.595344+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443595</id><title>Epigenetic Inheritance is Gated by Naïve Pluripotency and Dppa2 (80 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.595617+00:00</updated><author><name>Valentina Carlini</name></author><author><name>Cristina Policarpi</name></author><author><name>Jamie A. Hackett</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Environmental factors can trigger cellular responses that propagate across mitosis or even generations. Perturbations to the epigenome could underpin such acquired changes, however, the extent and contexts in which modified chromatin states confer heritable memory in mammals is unclear. Here we exploit a modular epigenetic editing strategy to establish &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; heterochromatin domains (epialleles) at endogenous loci and track their inheritance in a developmental model. We find that naïve pluripotent phases systematically erase ectopic domains of heterochromatin via active mechanisms, which acts as an intergenerational safeguard against transmission of epialleles. Upon lineage specification however, acquired chromatin states can be probabilistically inherited under selectively favourable conditions, including propagation of &lt;italic&gt;p53&lt;/italic&gt; silencing through &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; development. Using genome-wide CRISPR screening, we identify the mechanisms that block heritable silencing memory in pluripotent cells, and demonstrate removal of &lt;italic&gt;Dppa2&lt;/italic&gt; unlocks the potential for epigenetic inheritance uncoupled from DNA sequence. Our study outlines a mechanistic basis for how epigenetic inheritance is restricted in mammals, and reveals genomic- and developmental-contexts in which heritable memory is feasible.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443595" rel="alternate" title="Epigenetic Inheritance is Gated by Naïve Pluripotency and Dppa2 (80 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443466</id><title>Genetic determinants of chromatin reveal prostate cancer risk mediated by context-dependent gene regulation (32 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.595888+00:00</updated><author><name>Sylvan C. Baca</name></author><author><name>Cassandra Singler</name></author><author><name>Soumya Zacharia</name></author><author><name>Ji-Heui Seo</name></author><author><name>Tunc Morova</name></author><author><name>Faraz Hach</name></author><author><name>Yi Ding</name></author><author><name>Tommer Schwarz</name></author><author><name>Chia-Chi Flora Huang</name></author><author><name>Cynthia Kalita</name></author><author><name>Stefan Groha</name></author><author><name>Mark M. Pomerantz</name></author><author><name>Victoria Wang</name></author><author><name>Simon Linder</name></author><author><name>Christopher J. Sweeney</name></author><author><name>Wilbert Zwart</name></author><author><name>Nathan A. Lack</name></author><author><name>Bogdan Pasaniuc</name></author><author><name>David Y. Takeda</name></author><author><name>Alexander Gusev</name></author><author><name>Matthew L. Freedman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Methods that link genetic variation to steady-state gene expression levels, such as expression quantitative trait loci (eQTLs), are widely used to functionally annotate trait-associated variants, but they are limited in identifying context-dependent effects on transcription. To address this challenge, we developed the cistrome-wide association study (CWAS), a framework for nominating variants that impact traits through their effects on chromatin state. CWAS associates the genetic determinants of cistromes (&lt;italic&gt;e.g.&lt;/italic&gt;, the genome-wide profiles of transcription factor binding sites or histone modifications) with traits using summary statistics from genome-wide association studies (GWAS). We performed CWASs of prostate cancer and androgen-related traits, using a reference panel of 307 prostate cistromes from 165 individuals. CWAS nominated susceptibility regulatory elements or androgen receptor (AR) binding sites at 52 out of 98 known prostate cancer GWAS loci and implicated an additional 17 novel loci. We functionally validated a subset of our results using CRISPRi and &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; reporter assays. At 28 of the 52 risk loci, CWAS identified regulatory mechanisms that are not observable via eQTLs, implicating genes with complex or context-specific regulation that are overlooked by current approaches that relying on steady-state transcript measurements. CWAS genes include transcription factors that govern prostate development such as &lt;italic&gt;NKX3-1&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;HOXB13&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;GATA2&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;KLF5&lt;/italic&gt;. Moreover, CWAS boosts discovery power in modestly sized GWAS, identifying novel genetic associations mediated through AR binding for androgen-related phenotypes, including resistance to prostate cancer therapy. CWAS is a powerful and biologically interpretable paradigm for studying variants that influence traits by affecting context-dependent transcriptional regulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443466" rel="alternate" title="Genetic determinants of chromatin reveal prostate cancer risk mediated by context-dependent gene regulation (32 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443797</id><title>Robust detection of natural selection using a probabilistic model of tree imbalance (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.596150+00:00</updated><author><name>Enes Dilber</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Terhorst</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neutrality tests such as Tajima’s &lt;italic&gt;D&lt;/italic&gt; (Tajima, 1989) and Fay and Wu’s &lt;italic&gt;H&lt;/italic&gt; (Fay and Wu, 2000) are standard implements in the population genetics toolbox. One of their most common uses is to scan the genome for signals of natural selection. However, it is well understood that deviance measures like &lt;italic&gt;D&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;H&lt;/italic&gt; are confounded by other evolutionary forces—in particular, population expansion—that may be unrelated to selection. Because they are not model-based, it is not clear how to deconfound these statistics in a principled way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this paper we derive new likelihood-based methods for detecting natural selection which are robust to confounding by fluctuations in effective population size. At the core of our method is a novel proba-bilistic model of tree imbalance, which generalizes Kingman’s coales-cent to allow certain aberrant tree topologies to arise more frequently than is expected under neutrality. We derive a frequency spectrum-based estimator which can be used in place of &lt;italic&gt;D&lt;/italic&gt;, and also extend to the case where genealogies are first estimated. We benchmark our meth-ods on real and simulated data, and provide an open source software implementation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443797" rel="alternate" title="Robust detection of natural selection using a probabilistic model of tree imbalance (18 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.444000</id><title>Transcriptional landscape of human microglia reveals robust gene expression signatures that implicates age, sex and APOE-related immunometabolic pathway perturbations (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.596296+00:00</updated><author><name>Tulsi Patel</name></author><author><name>Troy P. Carnwath</name></author><author><name>Xue Wang</name></author><author><name>Mariet Allen</name></author><author><name>Sarah J. Lincoln</name></author><author><name>Laura J. Lewis-Tuffin</name></author><author><name>Zachary S. Quicksall</name></author><author><name>Shu Lin</name></author><author><name>Frederick Q. Tutor-New</name></author><author><name>Charlotte C.G. Ho</name></author><author><name>Yuhao Min</name></author><author><name>Kimberly G. Malphrus</name></author><author><name>Thuy T. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Martin</name></author><author><name>Cesar A. Garcia</name></author><author><name>Rawan M. Alkharboosh</name></author><author><name>Sanjeet Grewal</name></author><author><name>Kaisorn Chaichana</name></author><author><name>Robert Wharen</name></author><author><name>Hugo Guerrero-Cazares</name></author><author><name>Alfredo Quinones-Hinojosa</name></author><author><name>Nilüfer Ertekin-Taner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microglia have fundamental roles in health and disease, however effects of age, sex and genetic factors on human microglia have not been fully explored. We applied bulk and single cell approaches to comprehensively characterize human microglia transcriptomes and their associations with age, sex and &lt;italic&gt;APOE&lt;/italic&gt;. We identified a novel microglial signature, characterized its expression in bulk data from 1,306 brain samples across 6 regions and in single cell microglia transcriptome. We discovered microglial co-expression network modules associated with age, sex and &lt;italic&gt;APOE&lt;/italic&gt;-ε4 that are enriched for lipid and carbohydrate metabolism genes. Integrated analyses of modules with single cell transcriptomes revealed significant overlap between age-associated module genes and both pro-inflammatory and disease-associated microglial clusters. These modules and clusters harbor known neurodegenerative disease genes including &lt;italic&gt;APOE, PLCG2&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;BIN1&lt;/italic&gt;. These data represent a well-characterized human microglial transcriptome resource; and highlight age, sex and &lt;italic&gt;APOE&lt;/italic&gt;-related microglial immunometabolism perturbations with potential relevance in neurodegeneration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.444000" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptional landscape of human microglia reveals robust gene expression signatures that implicates age, sex and APOE-related immunometabolic pathway perturbations (12 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443088</id><title>Natural Killer cells demonstrate distinct eQTL and transcriptome-wide disease associations, highlighting their role in autoimmunity (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.596546+00:00</updated><author><name>James J Gilchrist</name></author><author><name>Seiko Makino</name></author><author><name>Vivek Naranbhai</name></author><author><name>Evelyn Lau</name></author><author><name>Sara Danielli</name></author><author><name>Dan Hameiri-Bowen</name></author><author><name>Wanseon Lee</name></author><author><name>Esther Ng</name></author><author><name>Justin Whalley</name></author><author><name>Julian C Knight</name></author><author><name>Benjamin P Fairfax</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Natural Killer (NK) cells are innate lymphocytes with central roles in immunosurveillance and are implicated in autoimmune pathogenesis. The degree to which regulatory variants affect NK gene expression is poorly understood. We performed expression quantitative trait locus (eQTL) mapping of negatively selected NK cells from a population of healthy Europeans (n=245). We find a significant subset of genes demonstrate eQTL specific to NK cells and these are highly informative of human disease, in particular autoimmunity. An NK cell transcriptome-wide association study (TWAS) across five common autoimmune diseases identified further novel associations at 27 genes. In addition to these &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt; observations, we find novel master-regulatory regions impacting expression of &lt;italic&gt;trans&lt;/italic&gt; gene networks at regions including 19q13.4, the Killer cell Immunoglobulin-like Receptor (KIR) Region, &lt;italic&gt;GNLY&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;MC1R&lt;/italic&gt;. Our findings provide new insights into the unique biology of NK cells, demonstrating markedly different eQTL from other immune cells, with implications for disease mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443088" rel="alternate" title="Natural Killer cells demonstrate distinct eQTL and transcriptome-wide disease associations, highlighting their role in autoimmunity (10 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>