<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.496649+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.456982</id><title>Somatic mutation rates scale with lifespan across mammals (812 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.496992+00:00</updated><author><name>Alex Cagan</name></author><author><name>Adrian Baez-Ortega</name></author><author><name>Natalia Brzozowska</name></author><author><name>Federico Abascal</name></author><author><name>Tim H. H. Coorens</name></author><author><name>Mathijs A. Sanders</name></author><author><name>Andrew R. J. Lawson</name></author><author><name>Luke M. R. Harvey</name></author><author><name>Shriram G. Bhosle</name></author><author><name>David Jones</name></author><author><name>Raul E. Alcantara</name></author><author><name>Timothy M. Butler</name></author><author><name>Yvette Hooks</name></author><author><name>Kirsty Roberts</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Anderson</name></author><author><name>Edmund Flach</name></author><author><name>Simon Spiro</name></author><author><name>Inez Januszczak</name></author><author><name>Ethan Wrigglesworth</name></author><author><name>Matthew W. Perkins</name></author><author><name>Robert Deaville</name></author><author><name>Megan Druce</name></author><author><name>Ruzhica Bogeska</name></author><author><name>Michael D. Milsom</name></author><author><name>Björn Neumann</name></author><author><name>Frank Gorman</name></author><author><name>Fernando Constantino-Casas</name></author><author><name>Laura Peachey</name></author><author><name>Diana Bochynska</name></author><author><name>Ewan St. John Smith</name></author><author><name>Moritz Gerstung</name></author><author><name>Peter J. Campbell</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth P. Murchison</name></author><author><name>Michael R. Stratton</name></author><author><name>Iñigo Martincorena</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The rates and patterns of somatic mutation in normal tissues are largely unknown outside of humans. Comparative analyses can shed light on the diversity of mutagenesis across species and on long-standing hypotheses regarding the evolution of somatic mutation rates and their role in cancer and ageing. Here, we used whole-genome sequencing of 208 intestinal crypts from 56 individuals to study the landscape of somatic mutation across 16 mammalian species. We found somatic mutagenesis to be dominated by seemingly endogenous mutational processes in all species, including 5-methylcytosine deamination and oxidative damage. With some differences, mutational signatures in other species resembled those described in humans, although the relative contribution of each signature varied across species. Remarkably, the somatic mutation rate per year varied greatly across species and exhibited a strong inverse relationship with species lifespan, with no other life-history trait studied displaying a comparable association. Despite widely different life histories among the species surveyed, including ~30-fold variation in lifespan and ~40,000-fold variation in body mass, the somatic mutation burden at the end of lifespan varied only by a factor of ~3. These data unveil common mutational processes across mammals and suggest that somatic mutation rates are evolutionarily constrained and may be a determinant of lifespan.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.456982" rel="alternate" title="Somatic mutation rates scale with lifespan across mammals (812 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.17.456740</id><title>Accuracy of multiple sequence alignment methods in the reconstruction of transposable element families (33 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.497493+00:00</updated><author><name>Robert Hubley</name></author><author><name>Travis J. Wheeler</name></author><author><name>Arian F.A. Smit</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The construction of a high-quality multiple sequence alignment (MSA) from copies of a transposable element (TE) is a critical step in the characterization of a new TE family. Most studies of MSA accuracy have been conducted on protein or RNA sequence families where structural features and strong signals of selection may assist with alignment. Less attention has been given to the quality of sequence alignments involving neutrally evolving DNA sequences such as those resulting from TE replication. Such alignments play an important role in understanding and representing TE family history. Transposable element sequences are challenging to align due to their wide divergence ranges, fragmentation, and predominantly-neutral mutation patterns. To gain insight into the effects of these properties on MSA accuracy, we developed a simulator of TE sequence evolution, and used it to generate a benchmark with which we evaluated the MSA predictions produced by several popular aligners, along with Refiner, a method we developed in the context of our RepeatModeler software. We find that MAFFT and Refiner generally outperform other aligners for low to medium divergence simulated sequences, while Refiner is uniquely effective when tasked with aligning high-divergent and fragmented instances of a family. As a result, consensus sequences derived from Refiner-based MSAs are more similar to the true consensus.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.17.456740" rel="alternate" title="Accuracy of multiple sequence alignment methods in the reconstruction of transposable element families (33 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.456368</id><title>Signatures of adaptive evolution in platyrrhine primate genomes (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.497769+00:00</updated><author><name>Hazel Byrne</name></author><author><name>Timothy H Webster</name></author><author><name>Sarah F Brosnan</name></author><author><name>Patricia Izar</name></author><author><name>Jessica W Lynch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The family Cebidae (capuchin and squirrel monkeys) form a remarkable platyrrhine clade exhibiting among the largest primate encephalisation quotients. Each cebid lineage is characterised by notable lineage-specific traits, with capuchins showing striking similarities to Hominidae including high sensorimotor intelligence with tool use, advanced cognitive abilities, and behavioural flexibility. Here, we take a comparative genomics approach, analysing five cebid branches including successive lineages, to infer a stepwise timeline for cebid adaptive evolution. We uncover candidate targets of selection across various periods of cebid evolution that may underlie the emergence of lineage-specific traits. Our analyses highlight shifting and sustained selective pressures on genes related to brain development, longevity, reproduction, and morphology, including evidence for cumulative and diversifying neurobiological adaptations over cebid evolutionary history. In addition to generating a new, high-quality reference genome assembly for robust capuchins, our results lend to a better understanding of the adaptive diversification of this distinctive primate clade.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.456368" rel="alternate" title="Signatures of adaptive evolution in platyrrhine primate genomes (22 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456438</id><title>Genetic analysis of early phenology in lentil identifies distinct loci controlling component traits (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.498260+00:00</updated><author><name>Vinodan Rajandran</name></author><author><name>Raul Ortega</name></author><author><name>Jacqueline K. Vander Schoor</name></author><author><name>Jakob B. Butler</name></author><author><name>Jules S. Freeman</name></author><author><name>Valerie F.G. Hecht</name></author><author><name>Willie Erskine</name></author><author><name>Ian C. Murfet</name></author><author><name>Kirstin E. Bett</name></author><author><name>James L. Weller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Reproductive phenology is well known to be a key feature of crop adaptation to diverse ecogeographic variation and management practices. Lentil is one of the founder pulse crops of middle-eastern Neolithic agriculture, and the modern-day domesticated lentil germplasm is generally considered to form three broad adaptation groups: Mediterranean, South Asian and northern temperate, which correspond approximately to the major global production environments. Understanding the molecular basis of these adaptations is crucial to maximise efficiency of breeding programs. Here, we use a QTL approach to dissect the earliness that is characteristic of the South Asian &lt;italic&gt;pilosae&lt;/italic&gt; ecotype, and that suits it to the typically short winter cropping season. We identified two loci, &lt;italic&gt;DTF6a&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;DTF6b&lt;/italic&gt;, at which dominant alleles confer early flowering. We show that, although these loci can interact in an additive manner, &lt;italic&gt;DTF6a&lt;/italic&gt; alone is sufficient to confer early flowering even in extremely short photoperiods. Comparisons with closely related legume species confirmed the presence of a conserved cluster of three &lt;italic&gt;FT&lt;/italic&gt; orthologs among potential candidate genes in the region, and expression analysis in near-isogenic material showed that the early &lt;italic&gt;dtf6a&lt;/italic&gt; allele is associated with a strong derepression of the &lt;italic&gt;FTa1&lt;/italic&gt; gene in particular. Analysis of sequence variation revealed the presence of a 7.4 kb deletion in the &lt;italic&gt;FTa1&lt;/italic&gt;-&lt;italic&gt;FTa2&lt;/italic&gt; intergenic region in the &lt;italic&gt;pilosae&lt;/italic&gt; parent, and a wide survey of over 400 accessions with diverse origin showed that the &lt;italic&gt;dtf6a&lt;/italic&gt; allele is dominant in South Asia material. Collectively, these results contribute to understanding the molecular basis of global adaptation in lentil, and further emphasize the importance of this conserved genomic region for adaptation in temperate legumes generally.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456438" rel="alternate" title="Genetic analysis of early phenology in lentil identifies distinct loci controlling component traits (13 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.18.456372</id><title>Identification and comparative analysis of long non-coding RNAs in the brain of fire ant queens in two different reproductive states (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.498644+00:00</updated><author><name>Cheng-Hung Tsai</name></author><author><name>Tzu-Chieh Lin</name></author><author><name>Yi-Hsien Chang</name></author><author><name>Huai-Kuang Tsai</name></author><author><name>Jia-Hsin Huang</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many long non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs) have been extensively identified in many higher eukaryotic species. The function of lncRNAs has been reported to play important roles in diverse biological processes, including developmental regulation and behavioral plasticity. However, there are no reports of systematic characterization of long non-coding RNAs in the fire ant &lt;italic&gt;Solenopsis invicta&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this study, we performed a genome-wide analysis of lncRNAs in the brains of &lt;italic&gt;S. invicta&lt;/italic&gt; from RNA-seq. In total, 1,393 novel lncRNA transcripts were identified in the fire ant. In contrast to the annotated lncRNA transcripts having at least two exons, novel lncRNAs are monoexonic transcripts with a shorter length. Besides, the transcriptome from virgin alate and dealate mated queens were analyzed and compared. The results showed 295 differentially expressed mRNA genes (DEGs) and 65 differentially expressed lncRNA genes (DELs) between virgin and mated queens, of which 17 lncRNAs were highly expressed in the virgin alates and 47 lncRNAs were highly expressed in the mated dealates. By identifying the DEL:DEG pairs with high association in their expression (Spearman’s |&lt;italic&gt;rho&lt;/italic&gt;| &amp;gt; 0.8 and &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt;-value &amp;lt; 0.01), many DELs were co-regulated with DEGs after mating. Furthermore, several remarkable lncRNAs (&lt;italic&gt;MSTRG&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;6523, MSTRG&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;588&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;nc909&lt;/italic&gt;) that were found to associate with particular coding genes may play important roles in the regulation of brain gene expression in reproductive transition in fire ants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study provides the first genome-wide identification of &lt;italic&gt;S. invicta&lt;/italic&gt; lncRNAs in the brains in different reproductive states and will contribute to a fuller understanding of the transcriptional regulation underpinning reproductive changes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.18.456372" rel="alternate" title="Identification and comparative analysis of long non-coding RNAs in the brain of fire ant queens in two different reproductive states (8 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>