<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.082873+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462505</id><title>S. pombe wtf genes use dual transcriptional regulation and selective protein exclusion from spores to cause meiotic drive (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.083291+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicole L. Nuckolls</name></author><author><name>Ananya Nidamangala Srinivasa</name></author><author><name>Anthony C. Mok</name></author><author><name>María Angélica Bravo Núñez</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey J. Lange</name></author><author><name>Todd J. Gallagher</name></author><author><name>Chris W. Seidel</name></author><author><name>Sarah E. Zanders</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Meiotic drivers bias gametogenesis to ensure their transmission into more than half the offspring of a heterozygote. In &lt;italic&gt;Schizosaccharomyces pombe&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;wtf&lt;/italic&gt; meiotic drivers destroy the meiotic products (spores) that do not inherit the driver from a heterozygote, thereby reducing fertility. &lt;italic&gt;wtf&lt;/italic&gt; drivers encode both a Wtf&lt;sup&gt;poison&lt;/sup&gt; protein and a Wtf&lt;sup&gt;antidote&lt;/sup&gt; protein using alternative transcriptional start sites. Here, we analyze how the expression and localization of the Wtf proteins are regulated to achieve drive. We show that transcriptional timing and selective protein exclusion from developing spores ensure that all spores are exposed to Wtf4&lt;sup&gt;poison&lt;/sup&gt;, but only the spores that inherit &lt;italic&gt;wtf4&lt;/italic&gt; receive a dose of Wtf4&lt;sup&gt;antidote&lt;/sup&gt; sufficient for survival. In addition, we show that the Mei4 transcription factor, a master regulator of meiosis, controls the expression of the &lt;italic&gt;wtf4&lt;sup&gt;poison&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; transcript. This dual transcriptional regulation, which includes the use of a critical meiotic transcription factor, likely complicates the universal suppression of &lt;italic&gt;wtf&lt;/italic&gt; genes without concomitantly disrupting spore viability. We propose that these features contribute to the evolutionary success of the &lt;italic&gt;wtf&lt;/italic&gt; drivers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Killer meiotic drivers are one type of selfish DNA sequence. When only one copy of a killer meiotic driver is found in a genome, the driver is expected to be transmitted to only half of the gametes (e.g. eggs or sperm). Killer meiotic drivers, however, kill developing gametes that do not inherit them, giving the driver a transmission advantage into the next generation. The molecular mechanisms used by these killers are not well understood. In this work, we analyzed how one killer meiotic driver, &lt;italic&gt;wtf4&lt;/italic&gt; from fission yeast, ensures targeted gamete (spore) killing. Previous work showed that &lt;italic&gt;wtf&lt;/italic&gt; meiotic drivers encode a poison protein that is transmitted to all spores and an antidote protein that rescues only spores that inherit the locus. Here, we show that different timing of the expression of the two proteins, combined with differential inclusion of the proteins in developing spores, both contribute to targeted spore killing. We also demonstrate that &lt;italic&gt;wtf4&lt;/italic&gt; exploits an essential gene expression pathway, making it difficult for the genome to prevent this locus from being expressed and killing. This extends our knowledge both of how these genetic parasites act and how they are equipped to evade host suppression mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462505" rel="alternate" title="S. pombe wtf genes use dual transcriptional regulation and selective protein exclusion from spores to cause meiotic drive (21 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462680</id><title>Evolutionary insights into primate skeletal gene regulation using a comparative cell culture model (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.084667+00:00</updated><author><name>Genevieve Housman</name></author><author><name>Emilie Briscoe</name></author><author><name>Yoav Gilad</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The evolution of complex skeletal traits in primates was likely influenced by both genetic and environmental factors. Because skeletal tissues are notoriously challenging to study using functional genomic approaches, they remain poorly characterized even in humans, let alone across multiple species. The challenges involved in obtaining functional genomic data from the skeleton, combined with the difficulty of obtaining such tissues from nonhuman apes, motivated us to consider an alternative &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; system with which to comparatively study gene regulation in skeletal cell types. Specifically, we differentiated six human and six chimpanzee induced pluripotent stem cell lines (&lt;bold&gt;iPSCs&lt;/bold&gt;) into mesenchymal stem cells (&lt;bold&gt;MSCs&lt;/bold&gt;) and subsequently into osteogenic cells (bone cells). We validated differentiation using standard methods and collected single-cell RNA sequencing data from over 100,000 cells across multiple samples and replicates at each stage of differentiation. While most genes that we examined display conserved patterns of expression across species, hundreds of genes are differentially expressed (&lt;bold&gt;DE&lt;/bold&gt;) between humans and chimpanzees within and across stages of osteogenic differentiation. Some of these interspecific DE genes show functional enrichments relevant in skeletal tissue trait development. Moreover, topic modeling indicates that interspecific gene programs become more pronounced as cells mature. Overall, we propose that this &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; model can be used to identify interspecific regulatory differences that may have contributed to skeletal trait differences between species.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Primates display a range of skeletal morphologies and susceptibilities to skeletal diseases, but the molecular basis of these phenotypic differences is unclear. Studies of gene expression variation in primate skeletal tissues are extremely restricted due to the ethical and practical challenges associated with collecting samples. Nevertheless, the ability to study gene regulation in primate skeletal tissues is crucial for understanding how the primate skeleton has evolved. We therefore developed a comparative primate skeletal cell culture model that allows us to access a spectrum of human and chimpanzee cell types as they differentiate from stem cells into bone cells. While most gene expression patterns are conserved across species, we also identified hundreds of differentially expressed genes between humans and chimpanzees within and across stages of differentiation. We also classified cells by osteogenic stage and identified additional interspecific differentially expressed genes which may contribute to skeletal trait differences. We anticipate that this model will be extremely useful for exploring questions related to gene regulation variation in primate bone biology and development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462680" rel="alternate" title="Evolutionary insights into primate skeletal gene regulation using a comparative cell culture model (7 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462396</id><title>Quantifying mediation between omics layers and complex traits (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.085497+00:00</updated><author><name>Marie C. Sadler</name></author><author><name>Chiara Auwerx</name></author><author><name>Eleonora Porcu</name></author><author><name>Zoltán Kutalik</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;High-dimensional omics datasets provide valuable resources to determine the causal role of molecular traits in mediating the path from genotype to phenotype. Making use of quantitative trait loci (QTL) and genome-wide association studies (GWASs) summary statistics, we developed a multivariable Mendelian randomization (MVMR) framework to quantify the connectivity between three omics layers (DNA methylome (DNAm), transcriptome and proteome) and their cascading causal impact on complex traits and diseases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Evaluating 50 complex traits, we found that on average 37.8% (95% CI: [36.0%-39.5%]) of DNAm-to-trait effects were mediated through transcripts in the &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-region, while only 15.8% (95% CI: [11.9%-19.6%]) are mediated through proteins in &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;. DNAm sites typically regulate multiple transcripts, and while found to predominantly decrease gene expression, this was only the case for 53.4% across ≈ 47,000 significant DNAm-transcript pairs. The average mediation proportion for transcript-to-trait effects through proteins (encoded for by the assessed transcript or located in &lt;italic&gt;trans&lt;/italic&gt;) was estimated to be 5.27% (95%CI: [4.11%-6.43%]). Notable differences in the transcript and protein QTL architectures were detected with only 22% of protein levels being causally driven by their corresponding transcript levels. Several regulatory mechanisms were hypothesized including an example where cg10385390 (chr1:8’022’505) increases the risk of irritable bowel disease by reducing &lt;italic&gt;PARK7&lt;/italic&gt; transcript and protein expression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The proposed integrative framework identified putative causal chains through omics layers providing a powerful tool to map GWAS signals. Quantification of causal effects between successive layers indicated that molecular mechanisms can be more complex than what the central dogma of biology would suggest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462396" rel="alternate" title="Quantifying mediation between omics layers and complex traits (5 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462436</id><title>Single-cell and nucleus RNA-seq in a mouse model of AD reveal activation of distinct glial subpopulations in the presence of plaques and tangles (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.085872+00:00</updated><author><name>Gabriela Balderrama-Gutierrez</name></author><author><name>Heidi Liang</name></author><author><name>Narges Rezaie</name></author><author><name>Klebea Carvalho</name></author><author><name>Stefania Forner</name></author><author><name>Dina Matheos</name></author><author><name>Elisabeth Rebboah</name></author><author><name>Kim N. Green</name></author><author><name>Andrea J. Tenner</name></author><author><name>Frank LaFerla</name></author><author><name>Ali Mortazavi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Multiple mouse models have been generated that strive to recapitulate human Alzheimer’s disease (AD) pathological features to investigate disease mechanisms and potential treatments. The 3xTg-AD mouse presents the two major hallmarks of AD, which are plaques and tangles that increase during aging. While behavioral changes and the accumulation of plaques and tangles have been well described in the 3xTg-AD mice, the subpopulations of neurons and glial cells present throughout disease progression have not been characterized. Here, we used single-cell RNA-seq to investigate changes in subpopulations of microglia, and single-nucleus RNA-seq to explore subpopulations of neurons, astrocytes, and oligodendrocytes in the hippocampus and cortex of aging 3xTg-AD as well as 5xFAD mice for comparison. We recovered a common path of age-associated astrocyte activation between the 3xTg-AD and the 5xFAD models and found that 3xTg-AD-derived astrocytes seem to be less activated. We identified multiple subtypes of microglia, including a subpopulation with a distinct transcription factor expression profile that showed an early increase in &lt;italic&gt;Csf1&lt;/italic&gt; expression before the switch to disease associated microglia (DAM). We used bulk RNA-seq in the hippocampus of 3xTg-AD mice across their lifespan to identify distinct modules of genes whose expression increases with aging and worsening pathology. Finally, scATAC-seq revealed multiple subpopulations of cells with accessible chromatin in regions around genes associated with glial activation. Overall, differences between the main glial groups point to a slower activation process in the 3xTg-AD model when compared to the 5xFAD. Our study contributes to the identification of progressive transcriptional changes of glial cells in a mouse model that has plaques and tangles, thus providing information to aid in targeted AD therapeutics that could translate into positive clinical outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462436" rel="alternate" title="Single-cell and nucleus RNA-seq in a mouse model of AD reveal activation of distinct glial subpopulations in the presence of plaques and tangles (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462440</id><title>Loss of the cleaved-protamine 2 domain leads to incomplete histone-to-protamine exchange and infertility in mice (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.086247+00:00</updated><author><name>Lena Arévalo</name></author><author><name>Gina Esther Merges</name></author><author><name>Simon Schneider</name></author><author><name>Franka Enow Oben</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Neumann</name></author><author><name>Hubert Schorle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protamines are unique sperm-specific proteins that package and protect paternal chromatin until fertilization. A subset of mammalian species expresses two protamines (PRM1 and PRM2), while in others PRM1 is sufficient for sperm chromatin packaging. Alterations of the species-specific ratio between PRM1 and PRM2 are associated with infertility. Unlike PRM1, PRM2 is generated as a precursor protein consisting of a highly conserved N-terminal domain, termed cleaved PRM2 (cP2), which is consecutively trimmed off during chromatin condensation. The carboxyterminal part, called mature PRM2 (mP2), interacts with DNA and mediates chromatin-hypercondensation, together with PRM1. The removal of the cP2 domain is believed to be imperative for proper chromatin condensation and the prevention of DNA damage. Yet, the role of cP2 is not yet understood. Using CRISPR-Cas9 mediated gene editing, we generated mice lacking the cP2 domain while the mP2 is still expressed. We show that deletion of one allele of the cP2 domain is sufficient to render male mice infertile. cP2 deficient sperm show incomplete PRM2 incorporation, retention of transition proteins and a severely altered protamine ratio. During epididymal transit, cP2 deficient sperm seem to undergo ROS mediated degradation leading to complete DNA fragmentation, inviability and immotility of mature sperm. The cP2 domain therefore seems to be necessary for the complex crosstalk leading to the successive and complete removal of transition proteins and complete protamination of sperm chromatin. Overall, we present the first step towards understanding the role of the cP2 domain in paternal chromatin packaging and open up avenues for further research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462440" rel="alternate" title="Loss of the cleaved-protamine 2 domain leads to incomplete histone-to-protamine exchange and infertility in mice (3 tweets)"/><category term="Genetics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>