<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular genetics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.668483+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/genetics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474385</id><title>Single-nuclei isoform RNA sequencing reveals combination patterns of transcript elements across human brain cell types (37 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.668977+00:00</updated><author><name>Simon A Hardwick</name></author><author><name>Wen Hu</name></author><author><name>Anoushka Joglekar</name></author><author><name>Li Fan</name></author><author><name>Paul G Collier</name></author><author><name>Careen Foord</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Balacco</name></author><author><name>Natan Belchikov</name></author><author><name>Julien Jarroux</name></author><author><name>Andrey D Prjibelski</name></author><author><name>Alla Mikheenko</name></author><author><name>Wenjie Luo</name></author><author><name>Teresa A Milner</name></author><author><name>Lishomwa Ndhlovu</name></author><author><name>John Q Trojanowski</name></author><author><name>Virginia MY Lee</name></author><author><name>Olivier Fedrigo</name></author><author><name>Dora Tombacz</name></author><author><name>Margaret Elizabeth Ross</name></author><author><name>Erich Jarvis</name></author><author><name>Zsolt Boldogkoi</name></author><author><name>Li Gan</name></author><author><name>Hagen U Tilgner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single-nuclei RNA-Seq is being widely employed to investigate cell types, especially of human brain and other frozen samples. In contrast to single-cell approaches, however, the majority of single-nuclei RNA counts originate from partially processed RNA leading to intronic cDNAs, thus hindering the investigation of complete isoforms. Here, using microfluidics, PCR-based artifact removal, target enrichment, and long-read sequencing, we developed single-nuclei isoform RNA-sequencing ('SnISOr-Seq'), and applied it to the analysis of human adult frontal cortex samples. We found that exons associated with autism exhibit coordinated and more cell-type specific inclusion than exons associated with schizophrenia or ALS. We discovered two distinct modes of combination patterns: first, those distinguishing cell types in the human brain. These are enriched in combinations of TSS-exon, exon-polyA site, and distant (non-adjacent) exon pairs. Second, those with all isoform combinations found within one neural cell type, which are enriched in adjacent exon pairs. Furthermore, adjacent exon pairs are predominantly mutually associated, while distant pairs are frequently mutually exclusive. Finally, we observed that human-specific exons are as tightly coordinated as conserved exons, pointing to an efficient evolutionary mechanism underpinning coordination. SnISOr-Seq opens the door to single-nuclei long-read isoform analysis in the human brain, and in any frozen, archived or hard-to-dissociate sample.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474385" rel="alternate" title="Single-nuclei isoform RNA sequencing reveals combination patterns of transcript elements across human brain cell types (37 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474478</id><title>First high-quality genome assembly data of sago palm (Metroxylon sagu Rottboll) (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.669506+00:00</updated><author><name>LEONARD WHYE KIT LIM</name></author><author><name>Melinda Mei Lin Lau</name></author><author><name>Hung-Hui Chung</name></author><author><name>Hasnain Hussain</name></author><author><name>HAN MING GAN</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The sago palm (Metroxylon sagu Rottboll) is a all-rounder palm, it is both a tropical halophytic starch-producing palm as well as an ornamental plant. Recently, a genome survey was conducted on this palm using Illumina sequencing platform but the BUSCO genome completeness is very low (21.5%) and most of them (~78%) are either fragmented or missing. Thus, in this study, the sago palm genome completeness was further improved with the utilization of the Nanopore sequencing platform that produced longer reads. A hybrid genome assembly was conducted and the outcome was a much complete sago palm genome with BUSCO completeness achieved at as high as 97.9% with only ~2% of them either fragmented or missing. The estimated genome size of the sago palm is 509,812,790 bp in this study. A sum of 33,242 protein-coding genes were revealed from the sago palm genome and around 96.39% of them had been functionally annotated. An investigation on the carbohydrate metabolism KEGG pathways also unearthed that starch synthesis was one of the major sago palm activities. These data are indispensable for future molecular evolutionary and genome-wide association studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474478" rel="alternate" title="First high-quality genome assembly data of sago palm (Metroxylon sagu Rottboll) (4 tweets)"/><category term="Genomics"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>