<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv preprints in developmental_biology posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.691113+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/developmental_biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443895</id><title>Inferring kinetic parameters of oscillatory gene regulation from single cell time series data (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.691907+00:00</updated><author><name>Joshua Burton</name></author><author><name>Cerys S. Manning</name></author><author><name>Magnus Rattray</name></author><author><name>Nancy Papalopulu</name></author><author><name>Jochen Kursawe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gene expression dynamics, such as stochastic oscillations and aperiodic fluctuations, have been associated with cell fate changes in multiple contexts, including development and cancer. Single cell live imaging of protein expression with endogenous reporters is widely used to observe such gene expression dynamics. However, the experimental investigation of regulatory mechanisms underlying the observed dynamics is challenging, since these mechanisms include complex interactions of multiple processes, including transcription, translation, and protein degradation. Here, we present a Bayesian method to infer kinetic parameters of oscillatory gene expression regulation using an auto-negative feedback motif with delay. Specifically, we use a delay-adapted nonlinear Kalman filter within a Metropolis-adjusted Langevin algorithm to identify posterior probability distributions. Our method can be applied to time series data on gene expression from single cells and is able to infer multiple parameters simultaneously. We apply it to published data on murine neural progenitor cells and show that it outperforms alternative methods. We further analyse how parameter uncertainty depends on the duration and time resolution of an imaging experiment, to make experimental design recommendations. This work demonstrates the utility of parameter inference on time course data from single cells and enables new studies on cell fate changes and population heterogeneity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.441399</id><title>Establishment of CRISPR/Cas9-based knock-in in a hemimetabolous insect: targeted gene tagging in the cricket Gryllus bimaculatus (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.692403+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuji Matsuoka</name></author><author><name>Taro Nakamura</name></author><author><name>Takahito Watanabe</name></author><author><name>Austen A. Barnett</name></author><author><name>Sumihare Noji</name></author><author><name>Taro Mito</name></author><author><name>Cassandra G. Extavour</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Studies of traditional model organisms like the fruit fly &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; have contributed immensely to our understanding of the genetic basis of developmental processes. However, the generalizability of these findings cannot be confirmed without functional genetic analyses in additional organisms. Direct genome editing using targeted nucleases has the potential to transform hitherto poorly-understood organisms into viable laboratory organisms for functional genetic study. To this end, here we present a method to induce targeted genome knock-out and knock-in of desired sequences in an insect that serves as an informative contrast to &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt;, the cricket &lt;italic&gt;Gryllus bimaculatus&lt;/italic&gt;. The efficiency of germ line transmission of induced mutations is comparable to that reported for other well-studied laboratory organisms, and knock-ins targeting introns yields viable, fertile animals in which knock-in events are directly detectable by visualization of a fluorescent marker in the expression pattern of the targeted gene. Combined with the recently assembled and annotated genome of this cricket, this knock-in/knock-out method increases the viability of &lt;italic&gt;G. bimaculatus&lt;/italic&gt; as a tractable system for functional genetics in a basally branching insect.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443326</id><title>Morphogenesis of a complex glial niche requires an interplay between cellular growth and fusion (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.693664+00:00</updated><author><name>Maria Alexandra Rujano</name></author><author><name>David Briand</name></author><author><name>Bojana Ðelić</name></author><author><name>Pauline Spéder</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neural stem cells (NSCs) are found in a tailored, intricate cellular microenvironment, the niche, which supports and regulates their activity. Whilst niche architecture is indissociable from its function, the morphogenetic aspects of niche development have been poorly explored. Here, we use the formation of the cortex glia (CG) network in Drosophila as a paradigm of acquisition of architectural complexity of a NSC niche. CG are essential for normal neurogenesis and build a reticular network spanning the entire central nervous system while encasing each NSC linage. We first show that individual CG cells grow tremendously to enwrap several NSC linages, ultimately covering and tiling the entire tissue. Several proliferative mechanisms, including endoreplication and mitosis, in part acytokinetic, support such growth and result in the formation of multinucleated, syncytial CG cells, that we call units. We then reveal that CG units are able to fuse to each other, resulting in the exchange of several subcellular compartments, such as membrane, cytoplasm and organelles. This process relies on well-known molecular players of cell fusion, involving cell surface communication molecules and actin regulators, while being atypical by its extent, dynamics and partial nature. Ultimately, the coordination in time and space of growth, proliferation and fusion mechanisms is required for the remarkable, multi-level architecture of the Drosophila NSC niche.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443782</id><title>Transcriptomic profiling of tissue environments critical for post-embryonic patterning and morphogenesis of zebrafish skin (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.694824+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew J. Aman</name></author><author><name>Lauren M. Saunders</name></author><author><name>Sanjay R. Srivatsan</name></author><author><name>Cole Trapnell</name></author><author><name>David M. Parichy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Regulation of neural crest derived pigment cells and dermal cells that form skin appendages is broadly similar across vertebrate taxa. In zebrafish, organized pigment stripes and an array of calcified scales form simultaneously in the skin during post-embryonic development. Understanding mechanisms that regulate stripe patterning and dermal morphogenesis may lead to discovery of fundamental mechanisms that govern development of animal form. To learn about cell types and potential signaling interactions that govern skin patterning and morphogenesis we generated and analyzed single cell transcriptomes of skin with genetic or induced defects in pigmentation and squamation. These data reveal a previously undescribed population of ameloblast-like epidermal cells, suggest hormonal control of epithelial-mesenchymal signaling, clarify the signaling network that governs scale papillae development, and identify the hypodermis as a crucial pigment cell support environment. These analyses provide new insights into the development of skin and pigmentation and highlight the utility of zebrafish for uncovering essential features of post-embryonic development in vertebrates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.444178</id><title>Dynamic Runx1 chromatin boundaries affect gene expression in hematopoietic development (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.697173+00:00</updated><author><name>Dominic D.G. Owens</name></author><author><name>Giorgio Anselmi</name></author><author><name>A. Marieke Oudelaar</name></author><author><name>Damien J Downes</name></author><author><name>Alessandro Cavallo</name></author><author><name>Joe R Harman</name></author><author><name>Ron Schwessinger</name></author><author><name>Akin Bucakci</name></author><author><name>Lucas Greder</name></author><author><name>Sara De Ornellas</name></author><author><name>Danuta Jeziorska</name></author><author><name>Jelena Telenius</name></author><author><name>Jim R Hughes</name></author><author><name>Marella F.T.R. de Bruijn</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The transcription factor RUNX1 is a critical regulator of developmental hematopoiesis and is frequently disrupted in leukemia. Runx1 is a large, complex gene that is expressed from two alternative promoters under the spatiotemporal control of multiple hematopoietic enhancers. To dissect the dynamic regulation of Runx1 in hematopoietic development, we analyzed its three-dimensional chromatin conformation in mouse embryonic stem cell (ESC) differentiation cultures. Runx1 resides in a 1.1 Mb topologically associating domain (TAD) demarcated by convergent CTCF motifs. As ESCs differentiate to mesoderm, chromatin accessibility, Runx1 enhancer-promoter (E-P) interactions, and CTCF-CTCF interactions increased in the TAD, along with initiation of Runx1 expression from the P2 promoter. Differentiation to hematopoietic progenitor cells was associated with the formation of tissue-specific sub-TADs over Runx1, a shift in E-P interactions, P1 promoter demethylation, and robust expression from both Runx1 promoters. Deletions of promoter-proximal CTCF sites at the sub-TAD boundaries had no obvious effects on E-P interactions but led to partial loss of domain structure, mildly affected gene expression, and delayed hematopoietic development. Together, our analyses of gene regulation at a large multi-promoter developmental gene revealed that dynamic sub-TAD chromatin boundaries play a role in establishing TAD structure and coordinated gene expression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443569</id><title>Development and genetics of red coloration in the zebrafish relative Danio albolineatus (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.697637+00:00</updated><author><name>Delai Huang</name></author><author><name>Victor M. Lewis</name></author><author><name>Matthew B. Toomey</name></author><author><name>Joseph C. Corbo</name></author><author><name>David M. Parichy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Animal pigment patterns play important roles in behavior and, in many species, red coloration serves as an honest signal of individual quality in mate choice. Among &lt;italic&gt;Danio&lt;/italic&gt; fishes, some species develop erythrophores, pigment cells that contain red ketocarotenoids, whereas other species, like zebrafish (&lt;italic&gt;D. rerio&lt;/italic&gt;) only have yellow xanthophores. Here, we use pearl danio (&lt;italic&gt;D. albolineatus&lt;/italic&gt;) to assess the developmental origin of erythrophores and their mechanisms of differentiation. We show that erythrophores in the fin of &lt;italic&gt;D. albolineatus&lt;/italic&gt; share a common progenitor with xanthophores and maintain plasticity in cell fate even after differentiation. We further identify the predominant ketocarotenoids that confer red coloration to erythrophores and use reverse genetics to pinpoint genes required for the differentiation and maintenance of these cells. Our analyses are a first step towards defining the mechanisms underlying the development of erythrophore-mediated red coloration in &lt;italic&gt;Danio&lt;/italic&gt; and reveal striking parallels with the mechanism of red coloration in birds.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443456</id><title>Pigment pattern morphospace of Danio fishes: evolutionary diversification and mutational effects (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.697900+00:00</updated><author><name>Braedan M. McCluskey</name></author><author><name>Yipeng Liang</name></author><author><name>Victor M. Lewis</name></author><author><name>Larissa B. Patterson</name></author><author><name>David M. Parichy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Molecular and cellular mechanisms underlying differences in adult form remain largely unknown. Adult pigment patterns of fishes in the genus &lt;italic&gt;Danio&lt;/italic&gt;, which includes zebrafish, &lt;italic&gt;D. rerio&lt;/italic&gt;, include horizontal stripes, vertical bars, spots and uniform patterns, and provide an outstanding opportunity to identify causes of species level variation in a neural crest derived trait. Yet understanding such variation requires quantitative approaches to assess phenotypes, and such methods have been mostly lacking for pigment patterns. We introduce metrics derived from information theory that describe patterns and pattern variation in &lt;italic&gt;Danio&lt;/italic&gt; fishes. We find that such metrics used singly and in multivariate combinations are suitable for distinguishing general pattern types, and can reveal even subtle phenotypic differences attributable to mutations. Our study provides new tools for analyzing pigment pattern in &lt;italic&gt;Danio&lt;/italic&gt; and potentially other groups, and sets the stage for future analyses of pattern morphospace and its mechanistic underpinnings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We provide quantitative metrics for studying pigment patterns of zebrafish and other species. These metrics are applicable to changes between species as well as impacts of laboratory induced mutations&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.443974</id><title>Origami: Single-cell oriented 3D shape dynamics of folding epithelia from fluorescence microscopy images (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T11:12:27.698205+00:00</updated><author><name>Tania Mendonca</name></author><author><name>Ana A. Jones</name></author><author><name>Jose M. Pozo</name></author><author><name>Sarah Baxendale</name></author><author><name>Tanya T. Whitfield</name></author><author><name>Alejandro F. Frangi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A common feature of morphogenesis is the formation of three-dimensional structures from the folding of two-dimensional epithelial sheets aided by spatio-temporal cell shape changes at the cellular-level. Studying cell shape dynamics and polarised processes that underpin them, requires orienting cells within the epithelial sheet. In epithelia with highly curved surfaces, assigning cell orientation can be difficult to automate &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt;. We present ‘Origami’, a MATLAB-based image analysis pipeline to compute oriented cell shape-features. Our automated method accurately computed cell orientation in regions with opposing curvature in synthetic epithelia and fluorescence images of zebrafish embryos. As proof of concept, we identified different cell shape signatures in the developing zebrafish inner ear, where the epithelium deforms in opposite orientations to form different structures. Origami is designed to be user-friendly and is generally applicable to fluorescence images of curved epithelia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>