<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>BioRxiv preprints in developmental_biology posted in the last week with at least 5 tweets</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.462347+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/developmental_biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.02.442348</id><title>The sperm protein SPACA4 is required for efficient fertilization in mice (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.463318+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah Herberg</name></author><author><name>Yoshitaka Fujihara</name></author><author><name>Andreas Blaha</name></author><author><name>Karin Panser</name></author><author><name>Kiyonori Kobayashi</name></author><author><name>Tamara Larasati</name></author><author><name>Maria Novatchkova</name></author><author><name>H. Christian Theußl</name></author><author><name>Olga Olszanska</name></author><author><name>Masahito Ikawa</name></author><author><name>Andrea Pauli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fertilization is the fundamental process that initiates the development of a new individual in all sexually reproducing species. Despite its importance, our understanding of the molecular players that govern mammalian sperm-egg interaction is incomplete, partly because many of the essential factors found in non-mammalian species do not have obvious mammalian homologs. We have recently identified the Ly6/uPAR protein Bouncer as a new, essential fertilization factor in zebrafish (Herberg et al., 2018). Here, we show that Bouncer’s homolog in mammals, SPACA4, is also required for efficient fertilization in mice. In contrast to fish, where Bouncer is expressed specifically in the egg, SPACA4 is expressed exclusively in the sperm. Male knockout mice are severely sub-fertile, and sperm lacking SPACA4 fail to fertilize wild-type eggs &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. Interestingly, removal of the zona pellucida rescues the fertilization defect of &lt;italic&gt;Spaca4&lt;/italic&gt;-deficient sperm &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, indicating that SPACA4 is not required for the interaction of sperm and the oolemma but rather of sperm and zona pellucida. Our work identifies SPACA4 as an important sperm protein necessary for zona pellucida penetration during mammalian fertilization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.02.442359</id><title>Definitive Hematopoietic Stem Cells Minimally Contribute to Embryonic Hematopoiesis (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.462726+00:00</updated><author><name>Bianca A Ulloa</name></author><author><name>Samima S Habbsa</name></author><author><name>Kathryn S. Potts</name></author><author><name>Alana Lewis</name></author><author><name>Mia McKinstry</name></author><author><name>Sara G. Payne</name></author><author><name>Julio Flores</name></author><author><name>Anastasia Nizhnik</name></author><author><name>Maria Feliz Norberto</name></author><author><name>Christian Mosimann</name></author><author><name>Teresa V Bowman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hematopoietic stem cells (HSCs) are rare cells that arise in the embryo and sustain adult hematopoiesis. Although the functional potential of nascent HSCs is detectable by transplantation, their native contribution during development is unknown, in part due to the overlapping genesis and marker gene expression with other embryonic blood progenitors. Using single cell transcriptomics, we defined gene signatures that distinguish nascent HSCs from embryonic blood progenitors. Applying a new lineage tracing approach, we selectively tracked HSC output &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; and discovered significantly delayed lymphomyeloid contribution. Using a novel inducible HSC injury model, we demonstrated a negligible impact on larval lymphomyelopoiesis following HSC depletion. HSCs are not merely dormant at this developmental stage as they showed robust regeneration after injury. Combined, our findings illuminate that nascent HSCs self-renew but display differentiation latency, while HSC-independent embryonic progenitors sustain developmental hematopoiesis. Understanding the differences among embryonic HSC and progenitor populations will guide improved &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; generation and expansion of functional HSCs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>