<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular ecology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.263670+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/ecology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469913</id><title>Synchrony and idiosyncrasy in the gut microbiome of wild primates (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.263951+00:00</updated><author><name>Johannes R. Björk</name></author><author><name>Mauna R. Dasari</name></author><author><name>Kim Roche</name></author><author><name>Laura Grieneisen</name></author><author><name>Trevor J. Gould</name></author><author><name>Jean-Christophe Grenier</name></author><author><name>Vania Yotova</name></author><author><name>Neil Gottel</name></author><author><name>David Jansen</name></author><author><name>Laurence R. Gesquiere</name></author><author><name>Jacob B. Gordon</name></author><author><name>Niki H. Learn</name></author><author><name>Tim L. Wango</name></author><author><name>Raphael S. Mututua</name></author><author><name>J. Kinyua Warutere</name></author><author><name>Long’ida Siodi</name></author><author><name>Sayan Mukherjee</name></author><author><name>Luis B. Barreiro</name></author><author><name>Susan C. Alberts</name></author><author><name>Jack A. Gilbert</name></author><author><name>Jenny Tung</name></author><author><name>Ran Blekhman</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth A. Archie</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human gut microbial dynamics are highly individualized, making it challenging to link microbiota to health and to design universal microbiome therapies. This individuality is typically attributed to variation in diets, environments, and medications, but it could also emerge from fundamental ecological forces that shape primate microbiota more generally. Here we leverage extensive gut microbiome time series from wild baboons—hosts who experience little interindividual dietary and environmental heterogeneity—to test whether gut microbial dynamics are synchronized across hosts or largely idiosyncratic. Despite their shared lifestyles, we find strong evidence for idiosyncrasy. Over time, samples from the same baboon were much more similar than samples from different baboons, and host-specific factors collectively explained 30% of the deviance in microbiome dynamics, compared to just 3% for factors shared across hosts. Hence, individualization may be common to mammalian gut microbiota, and designing universal microbiome interventions may face challenges beyond heterogeneity in human lifestyles.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469913" rel="alternate" title="Synchrony and idiosyncrasy in the gut microbiome of wild primates (22 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469854</id><title>Long-term culture system for deep-sea mussels Gigantidas childressi (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.264243+00:00</updated><author><name>Claas Hiebenthal</name></author><author><name>Finn-Ole Gehlert</name></author><author><name>Mark Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Thorsten B. H. Reusch</name></author><author><name>Frank Melzner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The simulation of deep-sea conditions in laboratories is technically challenging but necessary for experiments that aim at a deeper understanding of physiological mechanisms or host-symbiont interactions of deep-sea organisms. In a proof-of-concept study, we designed a recirculating system for long-term culture (&amp;gt;2 years) of deep-sea mussels &lt;italic&gt;Gigantidas childressi&lt;/italic&gt; (previously &lt;italic&gt;Bathymodiolus childressi&lt;/italic&gt;). Mussels were automatically (and safely) supplied with a maximum stable level of ~60 µM methane in seawater using a novel methane-air mixing system. Experimental animals also received daily doses of live microalgae. Condition indices of cultured &lt;italic&gt;G. childressi&lt;/italic&gt; remained high over years, and low shell thickness growth could be detected, which is indicative of positive energy budgets. Using stable isotope data, we demonstrate that &lt;italic&gt;G. childressi&lt;/italic&gt; in our culture system gained energy, both, from digestion of methane oxidizing endosymbionts and from digesting particulate food (microalgae). Limitations of the system, as well as opportunities for future experimental approaches involving deep-sea mussels are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469854" rel="alternate" title="Long-term culture system for deep-sea mussels Gigantidas childressi (8 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469737</id><title>Plants species’ influence on rhizosphere microbial communities depends on N availability (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.264383+00:00</updated><author><name>Teal S. Potter</name></author><author><name>Brian L. Anacker</name></author><author><name>Amber C. Churchill</name></author><author><name>William D. Bowman</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Purpose&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plants and soil microbes both influence how ecosystems respond to environmental change. Yet, we lack the ability to generalize how plants and soil microbes influence each other in the same or varying soil conditions. This limitation thwarts ecologists’ ability to understand and predict effects of environmental changes such and elevated anthropogenic nitrogen (N) deposition. Accordingly, we examined the specificity of plant species’ influence on soil microbial community composition.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We tested (1) whether congeneric grass species have unique effects on soil microbial communities, (2) how relative abundances of microbial taxa can be explained by &lt;italic&gt;Poa&lt;/italic&gt; phylogeny, plant traits, and range-wide traits (annual temperature and soil pH), and (3) whether N addition alters associations between &lt;italic&gt;Poa&lt;/italic&gt; species and soil microbes, and (4) whether the magnitude of microbial community change in response to elevated N can be explained by plant growth responses to N. We conducted a greenhouse experiment with seven &lt;italic&gt;Poa&lt;/italic&gt; species and native soils.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found that individual &lt;italic&gt;Poa&lt;/italic&gt; species were associated with different soil fungi but similar soil bacteria. Differences in microbial composition were not attributable to &lt;italic&gt;Poa&lt;/italic&gt; phylogeny, plant traits, or range-wide traits. Nitrogen addition enhanced the unique effects of &lt;italic&gt;Poa&lt;/italic&gt; species on fungal and bacterial community compositions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;These results demonstrate how ecological interactions of related plant species vary depending on resource supply, revealing important context dependency for accurately predicting microbially-mediated nutrient cycling and ecosystem responses to changes in nutrient availability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469737" rel="alternate" title="Plants species’ influence on rhizosphere microbial communities depends on N availability (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469426</id><title>Towards environmental DNA-based bioassessment of freshwater reservoirs with small volumes of water: robust molecular protocols (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.264510+00:00</updated><author><name>Rebecca K. Loh</name></author><author><name>Sujatha N. Kutty</name></author><author><name>Darren C. J. Yeo</name></author><author><name>Rudolf Meier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bioassessment of freshwater quality via eDNA is rapidly developing into a powerful alternative to traditional methods involving collecting, sorting, and identifying macroinvertebrates based on morphology. Particularly attractive would be methods that can use remote-controlled boats for sampling because it would allow for cost-effective, and frequent monitoring at multiple sites. The latter will be particularly important for tropical reservoirs that require year-around surveillance. We here optimize molecular protocols for capturing reservoir-specific differences in metazoan communities based on small water volumes (15 mL). The optimization is based on samples from two freshwater reservoirs with very different water qualities (“reservoir signal”). Each reservoir was sampled at three sites (“biological replicates”). For each water sample, the DNA was extracted twice (“technical replicates”). We then tested how much DNA template (0.1 ng to 15 ng) and how many PCR cycles (25 or 35) minimized variance between technical replicates. We find that 15 mL is sufficient for capturing the reservoir signal regardless of sampling time, template amounts, or PCR cycle numbers. Indeed, extrapolation from our results suggests that &amp;lt;1 mL would be sufficient because only 17 of 59 metazoan mOTUs (mainly planktonic crustaceans and rotifers) detected with a 313bp COI minibarcode were shared. We find that the use of 35 PCR cycles significantly lowered the number of detected species and that template amounts &amp;lt;0.5 ng yielded somewhat higher variance between technical replicates. Despite extensive trials, the variance between technical replicates remained high (Bray-Curtis: 5–20%; Jaccard: 10–40%) and we predict that it will be difficult to reduce this variance further. However, the overall reservoir differences are so strong that all biological and technical replicates can be correctly assigned.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469426" rel="alternate" title="Towards environmental DNA-based bioassessment of freshwater reservoirs with small volumes of water: robust molecular protocols (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>