<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular ecology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.405073+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/ecology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473511</id><title>Applying computer vision to digitised natural history collections for climate change research: temperature-size responses in British butterflies (36 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.405624+00:00</updated><author><name>Rebecca J Wilson</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Fioravante de Siqueira</name></author><author><name>Stephen J Brooks</name></author><author><name>Benjamin W Price</name></author><author><name>Lea M Simon</name></author><author><name>Stéfan J van der Walt</name></author><author><name>Phillip B Fenberg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Natural history collections (NHCs) are invaluable resources for understanding biotic response to global change. Museums around the world are currently imaging specimens, capturing specimen data, and making them freely available online. In parallel to the digitisation effort, there have been great advancements in computer vision (CV): the computer trained automated recognition/detection, and measurement of features in digital images. Applying CV to digitised NHCs has the potential to greatly accelerate the use of NHCs for biotic response to global change research. In this paper, we apply CV to a very large, digitised collection to test hypotheses in an established area of biotic response to climate change research: temperature-size responses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We develop a CV pipeline (Mothra) and apply it to the NHM iCollections of British butterflies (&amp;gt;180,000 specimens). Mothra automatically detects the specimen in the image, sets the scale, measures wing features (e.g., forewing length), determines the orientation of the specimen (pinned ventrally or dorsally), and identifies the sex. We pair these measurements and meta-data with temperature records to test how adult size varies with temperature during the immature stages of species and to assess patterns of sexual-size dimorphism across species and families.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mothra accurately measures the forewing lengths of butterfly specimens and compared to manual baseline measurements, Mothra accurately determines sex and forewing lengths of butterfly specimens. Females are the larger sex in most species and an increase in adult body size with warm monthly temperatures during the late larval stages is the most common temperature size response. These results confirm suspected patterns and support hypotheses based on recent studies using a smaller dataset of manually measured specimens.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We show that CV can be a powerful tool to efficiently and accurately extract phenotypic data from a very large collection of digital NHCs. In the future, CV will become widely applied to digital NHC collections to advance ecological and evolutionary research and to accelerate the use of NHCs for biotic response to global change research.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473511" rel="alternate" title="Applying computer vision to digitised natural history collections for climate change research: temperature-size responses in British butterflies (36 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473628</id><title>dynamAedes: a unified modelling framework for invasive Aedes mosquitoes (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.406041+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniele Da Re</name></author><author><name>Wim Van Bortel</name></author><author><name>Friederike Reuss</name></author><author><name>Ruth Müller</name></author><author><name>Sebastien Boyer</name></author><author><name>Fabrizio Montarsi</name></author><author><name>Silvia Ciocchetta</name></author><author><name>Daniele Arnoldi</name></author><author><name>Giovanni Marini</name></author><author><name>Annapaola Rizzoli</name></author><author><name>Gregory L’Ambert</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Lacour</name></author><author><name>Constantianus J.M. Koenraadt</name></author><author><name>Sophie O. Vanwambeke</name></author><author><name>Matteo Marcantonio</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mosquito species belonging to the genus &lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; have attracted the interest of scientists and public health officers for their invasive species traits and efficient capacity of transmitting viruses affecting humans. Some of these species were brought outside their native range by human activities such as trade and tourism, and colonised new regions thanks to a unique combination of eco-physiological traits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Considering mosquito physiological and behavioural traits to understand and predict the spatial and temporal population dynamics is thus a crucial step to develop strategies to mitigate the local densities of invasive &lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; populations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we synthesised the life cycle of four invasive &lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; species (&lt;italic&gt;Ae. aegypti&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;Ae. albopictus&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;Ae. japonicus&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Ae. koreicus&lt;/italic&gt;) in a single multi-scale stochastic modelling framework which we coded in the R package &lt;monospace&gt;dynamAedes&lt;/monospace&gt;. We designed a stage-based and time-discrete stochastic model driven by temperature, photo-period and inter-specific larval competition that can be applied to three different spatial scales: punctual, local and regional. These spatial scales consider different degrees of spatial complexity and data availability, by accounting for both active and passive dispersal of mosquito species as well as for the heterogeneity of the input temperature data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our overarching aim was to provide a flexible, open-source and user-friendly tool rooted in the most updated knowledge on species biology which could be applied to the management of invasive &lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; populations as well as for more theoretical ecological inquiries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473628" rel="alternate" title="dynamAedes: a unified modelling framework for invasive Aedes mosquitoes (24 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473457</id><title>The catscape: spatial manifestation of a pet cat population with outdoor access (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.406426+00:00</updated><author><name>Richard Bischof</name></author><author><name>Nina Rosita Hansen</name></author><author><name>Øyvind Skarsgard Nyheim</name></author><author><name>Astrid Kisen</name></author><author><name>Lillian Prestmoen</name></author><author><name>Torbjørn Haugaasen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The domestic cat (&lt;italic&gt;Felis catus&lt;/italic&gt;) is the most popular companion animal and the most abundant carnivore globally. It is also a pet with an immense ecological footprint, because even non-feral and food-subsidized cats are prolific predators. Whereas knowledge about the spatial behavior of individual domestic cats is growing, we still know little about how a local population of free-ranging pet cats occupies the landscape. Using a citizen science approach, we GPS-tagged 92 pet cats with outdoor access living in a residential area in southern Norway. The resulting position data allowed us to construct both individual home range kernels and a population-level utilization distribution. Our results reveal a dense predatory blanket that outdoor cats drape over and beyond the urban landscape. It is this population-level intensity surface - the “catscape” - that potential prey have to navigate. There were almost no gaps in the catscape within our residential study area and therefore few terrestrial refuges from potential cat predation. However, cats spent on average 79% of their outdoor time within 50 meters to their owner’s home, which suggests that the primary impact is local and most acute for wildlife in the vicinity to homes with cats. We discuss the catscape as a conceptual and quantitative tool for better understanding and mitigating the environmental impact of domestic cats.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473457" rel="alternate" title="The catscape: spatial manifestation of a pet cat population with outdoor access (8 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.472855</id><title>Assessing the impact of fire on spider abundance through a global comparative analysis (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.406670+00:00</updated><author><name>Claire A. McLean</name></author><author><name>Jane Melville</name></author><author><name>Joseph Schubert</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Rose</name></author><author><name>Iliana Medina</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fire is an important ecological disturbance; however, in many regions fire regimes are changing due to anthropogenic factors. Understanding the responses of species and ecosystem to fire can help to develop predictive models and inform fire management decisions. Despite their massive diversity and abundance, relatively little is known about the impacts of fire on invertebrates. Spiders are a diverse and ubiquitous group, with variation in ecological, behavioural and life history traits, and can offer important insights into the impacts of fire on invertebrates and whether these depend on environmental factors, phylogenetic history, or species traits. We conducted phylogenetic comparative analyses of published data from studies investigating the impacts of fire on spiders. We investigated whether fire affects family level abundance and whether this effect depends on ecologically relevant traits or site-specific factors (vegetation, latitude, fire type, time since fire). We found that time since fire had a significant effect on the abundance of some spider families (Lycosidae, Linyphiidae, Agelenidae), and within forest vegetation types. There was no relationship between family level traits and response to fire, suggesting that a trait-based approach does not increase predictive power in this group at this taxonomic level. Overall, it is difficult to make broad generalisations about the impacts of fire on spider abundance due to variation in site- and fire-specific factors. We did, however, find evidence that short fire intervals may be a threat to some spider families, and in forest ecosystems, where abundance initially decreased after fire, which may have important implications for fire management strategies. Finally, we show that analyses of published data can be used to detect broad scale ecological patterns and provide an alternative to traditional meta-analytical approaches.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.472855" rel="alternate" title="Assessing the impact of fire on spider abundance through a global comparative analysis (6 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473630</id><title>The marine gastropod Conomurex luhuanus (Strombidae) has high-resolution spatial vision and eyes with complex retinas (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.406928+00:00</updated><author><name>Alison R Irwin</name></author><author><name>Suzanne T Williams</name></author><author><name>Daniel I Speiser</name></author><author><name>Nicholas W Roberts</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;All species within the conch snail family Strombidae possess large camera-type eyes that are surprisingly well-developed compared to those found in most other gastropods. Although these eyes are known to be structurally complex, very little research on their visual function has been conducted. Here, we use isoluminant expanding visual stimuli to measure the spatial resolution and contrast sensitivity of a strombid, Conomurex luhuanus. Using these stimuli, we show that this species responds to objects as small as 1.06° in its visual field. We also show that C. luhuanus responds to Michelson contrasts of 0.07, a low contrast sensitivity between object and background. The defensive withdrawal response elicited by visual stimuli of such small angular size and low contrast suggests that conch snails may use spatial vision for the early detection of potential predators. We support these findings with morphological estimations of spatial resolution of 1.04 ± 0.14°. These anatomical data therefore agree with the behavioural measures and highlight the benefits of integrating morphological and behavioural approaches in animal vision studies. Furthermore, using contemporary imaging techniques including serial block-face scanning electron microscopy (SBF-SEM), in conjunction with transmission electron microscopy (TEM), we found that C. luhuanus have more complex retinas, in terms of cell type diversity, than previous studies of the group have discovered using TEM alone. We found the C. luhuanus retina is comprised of six cell types, including a newly identified ganglion cell and accessory photoreceptor, rather than the previously described four cell types.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473630" rel="alternate" title="The marine gastropod Conomurex luhuanus (Strombidae) has high-resolution spatial vision and eyes with complex retinas (5 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473527</id><title>Assessment of the Finnish wolf population combines DNA captures, citizen observations and mortality data using a Bayesian state-space model (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.407463+00:00</updated><author><name>Samu Mäntyniemi</name></author><author><name>Inari Helle</name></author><author><name>Ilpo Kojola</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Assessment of the Finnish wolf population relies on multiple sources of information. This paper describes how Bayesian inference is used to pool the information contained in different kind of data sets (point observations, non-invasive genetics, known mortalities) for the estimation of the number of territories occupied by family packs and pairs. The output of the assessment model is a joint probability distribution, which describes current knowledge about the number of wolves within each territory. The joint distribution can be used to derive probability distributions for the total number of wolves in all territories and for the pack status within each territory. Most of the data set comprises of both voluntary-provided point observations and DNA samples provided by volunteers and research personnel. The new method reduces the role of expert judgement in the assessment process, providing increased transparency and repeatability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473527" rel="alternate" title="Assessment of the Finnish wolf population combines DNA captures, citizen observations and mortality data using a Bayesian state-space model (5 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473824</id><title>Treated like dirt: Robust forensic and ecological inferences from soil eDNA after challenging sample storage (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.407986+00:00</updated><author><name>Tobias Guldberg Frøslev</name></author><author><name>Rasmus Ejrnæs</name></author><author><name>Anders Johannes Hansen</name></author><author><name>Hans Henrik Bruun</name></author><author><name>Ida Broman Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Flemming Ekelund</name></author><author><name>Mette Vestergård</name></author><author><name>Rasmus Kjøller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Biodiversity of soil microbiota is routinely assessed with environmental DNA-based methods, among which amplification and massive parallel sequencing of marker genes (eDNA metabarcoding) is the most common. Soil microbiota may for example be investigated in relation to biodiversity research or as a tool in forensic investigations.

After sampling, the taxonomic composition of soil biotic communities may change. In order to minimize community changes after sampling, it is desirable to reduce biological activity, e.g. by freezing immediately after sampling. However, this may be impossible due to remoteness of study sites or, in forensic cases, where soil has been attached to a questioned item for protracted periods of time.

Here we investigated the effect of storage duration and conditions on the assessment of the soil biota with eDNA metabarcoding. We extracted eDNA from freshly collected soil samples and again from the same samples after storage under contrasting temperature conditions. We used five different primer sets targeting bacteria, fungi, protists (cercozoans), general eukaryotes, and plants. For these groups, we quantified differences in richness, evenness and community composition. Subsequently, we tested whether we could correctly infer habitat type and original sample identity after storage using a large reference dataset.

We found increased community composition differences with extended storage time and with higher storage temperature. However, for samples stored less than 28 days at a maximum of 20 C, changes were generally insignificant. Classification models could successfully assign most stored samples to their exact location of origin and correct habitat type even after weeks of storage. Even samples showing larger compositional changes generally retained the original sample as the best match (relative similarity).

Our results show that for most biodiversity and forensic applications, storage of samples for days and even several weeks may not be a problem, if storage temperature does not exceed 20 C. Even after suboptimal storage conditions, significant patterns can be reproduced.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473824" rel="alternate" title="Treated like dirt: Robust forensic and ecological inferences from soil eDNA after challenging sample storage (5 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473993</id><title>Megaherbivores modify forest structure and increase carbon stocks through multiple pathways (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.408636+00:00</updated><author><name>Fabio Berzaghi</name></author><author><name>Francois Bretagnolle</name></author><author><name>Clementine Durand-Bessart</name></author><author><name>Stephen Blake</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Megaherbivores have pervasive ecological effects. In African rainforests, elephants can increase aboveground carbon, though the mechanisms are unclear. Here we combine a large unpublished dataset of forest elephant feeding with published browsing preferences totaling &amp;gt; 120,000 records covering 700 plant species, including nutritional data for 102 species. Elephants increase carbon stocks by: 1) promoting high wood density tree species via preferential browsing on leaves from low wood density species, which are more digestible; 2) dispersing seeds of trees that are relatively large and have the highest average wood density among tree guilds based on dispersal mode. Loss of forest elephants could cause a 5-12% decline in carbon stocks due to regeneration failure of elephant-dispersed trees and an increase in abundance of low wood density trees. These results show the major importance of megaherbivores in maintaining diverse, high-carbon tropical forests. Successful elephant conservation will contribute to climate mitigation at a scale of global relevance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473993" rel="alternate" title="Megaherbivores modify forest structure and increase carbon stocks through multiple pathways (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473860</id><title>Primary productivity in subsidized green-brown food webs (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.409230+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuval R. Zelnik</name></author><author><name>Stefano Manzoni</name></author><author><name>Riccardo Bommarco</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ecosystems worldwide receive large amounts of nutrients from both natural processes and human activities. While direct subsidy effects on primary productivity are relatively well known (the green food web), the indirect effects of subsidies on producers as mediated by the brown food web and predators have been neglected. With a dynamical green-brown food web model, parameterized using empirical estimates from the literature, we illustrate the effect of nutrient subsidies on net primary productivity (i.e., after removing loss to herbivory) in two generic ecosystems, terrestrial and aquatic. We find that nutrient subsidies increase net primary productivity because more nutrients are available, but this effect saturates with higher subsidies. Changing the quality of subsidies from inorganic to organic tends to increase net primary productivity in terrestrial ecosystems, but less often so in aquatic ecosystems. This occurs when organic nutrient inputs promote detritivores in the brown food web, and hence predators that in turn control herbivores, thus promoting primary productivity. This previously largely overlooked effect is further enhanced by ecosystem properties such as fast decomposition and low rates of nutrient additions, and demonstrates the importance of nutrient subsidy quality on ecosystem functioning.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473860" rel="alternate" title="Primary productivity in subsidized green-brown food webs (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>