<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular ecology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.880644+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/ecology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455764</id><title>Opportunistic gut sampling indicates differential diet and plastic ingestion risk in Indian dugongs (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.880986+00:00</updated><author><name>Sumit Prajapati</name></author><author><name>Chinmaya Ghanekar</name></author><author><name>Sameeha Pathan</name></author><author><name>Rukmini Shekar</name></author><author><name>K. Madhu Magesh</name></author><author><name>Swapnali Gole</name></author><author><name>Srabani Bose</name></author><author><name>Sweta Iyer</name></author><author><name>Anant Pande</name></author><author><name>Jeyaraj Antony Johnson</name></author><author><name>Kuppusamy Sivakumar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Dugongs, exclusively seagrass foragers, are globally threatened marine mammals. Knowledge on their feeding biology has been derived from few direct observations and mostly by analysis of stomach contents. Given limitations in data from Indian populations, dugong strandings serve as an opportunity to understand their dietary composition through gut sampling. In this paper, we utilize the gut contents collected from stranded dugongs to detect differences in the seagrass foraging between two isolated pockets of dugong distribution (Tamil Nadu and Gujarat) and supplement existing knowledge on dugong feeding biology in Indian waters. We extracted, enumerated and identified seagrass species from dugong gut contents. The proportion of seagrass leaf fragments were found higher (&amp;gt;40%) than other fragments in all the gut samples analysed. We recorded two seagrass genera (&lt;italic&gt;Halophila&lt;/italic&gt; spp. and &lt;italic&gt;Halodule&lt;/italic&gt; spp.) from Gujarat and five seagrass genera (&lt;italic&gt;Halophila&lt;/italic&gt; spp., &lt;italic&gt;Halodule&lt;/italic&gt; spp., &lt;italic&gt;Cymodocea&lt;/italic&gt; spp., &lt;italic&gt;Enhalus&lt;/italic&gt; spp., &lt;italic&gt;Syringodium&lt;/italic&gt; spp.) from Tamil Nadu dugong individuals. We also obtained anthropogenic debris such as plastic, fishing net and wood fragments from the gut samples. We suggest enhanced monitoring of seagrass habitats and fine spatial scale threat mapping in entire dugong distribution range in India.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455764" rel="alternate" title="Opportunistic gut sampling indicates differential diet and plastic ingestion risk in Indian dugongs (10 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456177</id><title>Quantifying microbial associations of dissolved organic matter under global change (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.881226+00:00</updated><author><name>Ang Hu</name></author><author><name>Mira Choi</name></author><author><name>Andrew J Tanentzap</name></author><author><name>Jingfu Liu</name></author><author><name>Kyoung-Soon Jang</name></author><author><name>Jay T Lennon</name></author><author><name>Yongqin Liu</name></author><author><name>Janne Soininen</name></author><author><name>Xiancai Lu</name></author><author><name>Yunlin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Ji Shen</name></author><author><name>jianjun wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microbes play a critical role in regulating the size, composition, and turnover of dissolved organic matter (DOM), which is one of the largest pools of carbon in aquatic ecosystems. Global change may alter DOM-microbe associations with implications for biogeochemical cycles, although disentangling these complex interactions remains a major challenge. Here we develop a framework called Energy-Diversity-Trait integrative Analysis (EDTiA) to examine the associations between DOM and bacteria along temperature and nutrient gradients in a manipulative field experiment on mountainsides in contrasting subarctic and subtropical climates. In both study regions, the chemical composition of DOM correlated with bacterial communities, and was primarily controlled by nutrients and to a lesser degree by temperature. At a molecular-level, DOM-bacteria associations depended strongly on the molecular traits of DOM, with negative associations indicative of decomposition as molecules are more biolabile. Using bipartite networks, we further demonstrated that negative associations were more specialized than positive associations indicative of DOM production. Nutrient enrichment promoted specialization of positive associations, but decreased specialization of negative associations particularly at warmer temperatures in subtropical climate. These global change drivers influenced specialization of negative associations most strongly via molecular traits, while both molecular traits and bacterial diversity similarly affected positive associations. Together, our framework provides a quantitative approach to understand DOM-microbe associations and wider carbon cycling across scales under global change.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456177" rel="alternate" title="Quantifying microbial associations of dissolved organic matter under global change (6 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456018</id><title>Next generation restoration metrics: Using soil eDNA bacterial community data to measure trajectories towards rehabilitation targets (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.882018+00:00</updated><author><name>Craig Liddicoat</name></author><author><name>Siegy L. Krauss</name></author><author><name>Andrew Bissett</name></author><author><name>Ryan J. Borrett</name></author><author><name>Luisa C. Ducki</name></author><author><name>Shawn D. Peddle</name></author><author><name>Paul Bullock</name></author><author><name>Mark Dobrowolski</name></author><author><name>Andrew Grigg</name></author><author><name>Mark Tibbett</name></author><author><name>Martin Breed</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Soil microbiota are fundamentally linked to the restoration of degraded ecosystems, as they are central to important ecological functions including the support of plant communities. High throughput sequencing of environmental DNA used to characterise soil microbiota offers promise to monitor ecological progress towards reference states. In post-mining rehabilitation, successful mine closure planning requires specific, measurable, achievable, relevant and time-bound (SMART) completion criteria, such as returning ecological communities to match a target level of similarity to reference sites. We analysed patterns of surface soil bacterial community similarity to reference ('rehabilitation trajectory') data from three long-term (&amp;gt; 25 year) post-mining rehabilitation chronosequence case studies from south-west Western Australia. We examined the influence of different ecological distance measures, sequence grouping approaches, and eliminating rare taxa on rehabilitation trajectories and predicted recovery times. We also explored the issue of spatial autocorrelation in our rehabilitation trajectory assessments and trialled a first-pass approach for correcting its undue influence. We found considerable variation in bacterial communities among reference sites within each case study minesite, providing valuable context for setting targets and evaluating recovery. Median Bray-Curtis similarities among references within each minesite ranged from 30-36%, based on amplicon sequence variant-level data. Median predicted times for rehabilitated sites to recover to these levels ranged from around 40 to over 100 years. We discuss strengths and limitations of the different approaches and offer recommendations to improve the robustness of this assessment method. Synthesis and applications. We demonstrate a proof-of-concept, complexity-reducing application of soil eDNA sequence-based surveys of bacterial communities in restoration chronosequence studies to quantitatively assess progress towards reference communities and corresponding rehabilitation targets. Our method provides a step towards developing microbiota-based SMART metrics for measuring rehabilitation success in post-mining, and potentially other, restoration contexts. Our approach enables prediction of recovery time, explicitly including uncertainty in assessments, and assists examination of potential barriers to ecological recovery, including biologically-associated variation in soil properties.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456018" rel="alternate" title="Next generation restoration metrics: Using soil eDNA bacterial community data to measure trajectories towards rehabilitation targets (5 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455943</id><title>Deep Learning Classification of Lake Zooplankton (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.882221+00:00</updated><author><name>Sreenath Pruthviraj Kyathanahally</name></author><author><name>Tommy Hardeman</name></author><author><name>Ewa Merz</name></author><author><name>Thea Kozakiewicz</name></author><author><name>Marta reyes</name></author><author><name>Peter Isles</name></author><author><name>Francesco Pomati</name></author><author><name>Marco Baity-Jesi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Plankton are eﬀective indicators of environmental change and ecosystem health in freshwater habitats, but collection of plankton data using manual microscopic methods is extremely labor- intensive and expensive. Automated plankton imaging oﬀers a promising way forward to monitor plankton communities with high frequency and accuracy in real-time. Yet, manual annotation of millions of images proposes a serious challenge to taxonomists. Deep learning classiﬁers have been successfully applied in various ﬁelds and provided encouraging results when used to categorize marine plankton images. Here, we present a set of deep learning models developed for the identiﬁcation of lake plankton, and study several strategies to obtain optimal performances, which lead to operational prescriptions for users. To this aim, we annotated into 35 classes over 17900 images of zooplankton and large phytoplankton colonies, detected in Lake Greifensee (Switzerland) with the Dual Scripps Plankton Camera. Our best models were based on transfer learning and ensembling, which classiﬁed plankton images with 98% accuracy and 93% F1 score. When tested on freely available plankton datasets produced by other automated imaging tools (ZooScan, FlowCytobot and ISIIS), our models performed better than previously used models. Our annotated data, code and classiﬁcation models are freely available online.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455943" rel="alternate" title="Deep Learning Classification of Lake Zooplankton (5 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456157</id><title>Effects of land-use and landscape drivers in the species richness and distribution of carnivores in Faragosa-Fura Landscape of Southern Rift Valley, Ethiopia (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.882395+00:00</updated><author><name>Berhanu Gebo</name></author><author><name>Serekebirhan Takele</name></author><author><name>Simon Shibru</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the species richness and distribution of carnivores across anthropogenic land-use types in an area is an essential first step for biodiversity conservation and human-carnivore coexistence. However, quantitative data on carnivore species coexisting with humans in different land-use types remain largely missing. Thus, this paper investigated the effect of anthropogenic land-use and landscape drivers on carnivore species richness and distribution in the Faragosa-Fura Landscape, Gamo Zone, southern Ethiopia. To collect data, we employed the line transect method using three complementary field surveys techniques: sign survey, camera-trapping, and opportunistic sighting survey during wet and dry seasons in 2020 and 2021. We stratified the study landscape into five land-use types-forest, wetland, grassland, agricultural land, and settlement. The result proved the occurrence of 12 carnivore species belonging to six families, including vulnerable Felidae species - &lt;italic&gt;Panthera pardus&lt;/italic&gt;. Family Felidae and Herpestidae were composed of a greater number of species, while Hyaenidae and Mustelidae were each represented by single species. Out of identified species, only two species (&lt;italic&gt;Panthera pardus&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Crocuta crocuta&lt;/italic&gt;) were large-sized, while the rest were medium and small-sized carnivores. Overall, the mean richness of the study area was 5.73±0.284(SE). The species richness was highest in the wetland (n = 12, mean = 7.67±0.494(SE)) and lowest in the settlement (n = 5, mean = 4.25±0.479(SE)). The regression analysis showed that most of the carnivores displayed a strong negative relationship with agriculture, roads, and settlement while displayed a strong positive relationship with wetland and forest. In general, out of 32 species recorded in Ethiopia, this study quantified 12 carnivore species that signify the area is an important area for wildlife conservation in Ethiopia. Further, the study concluded that the wetland is the most important habitat, particularly for larger-sized and habitat specialists while anthropogenic land-uses types adversely affecting species richness. Thus, a generic paradigm to reconcile land management and biodiversity conservation is highly important.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456157" rel="alternate" title="Effects of land-use and landscape drivers in the species richness and distribution of carnivores in Faragosa-Fura Landscape of Southern Rift Valley, Ethiopia (4 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456102</id><title>Temperature and nutrients drive complex eco-phenotypic dynamics in a microbial food web (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.882538+00:00</updated><author><name>Ze-Yi Han</name></author><author><name>Daniel J Wieczynski</name></author><author><name>Andrea Yammine</name></author><author><name>Jean Philippe Gibert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Anthropogenic increases in temperature and nutrient loads will likely impact food web structure and stability. Though their independent effects have been well studied, their joint effects-particularly on coupled ecological and phenotypic dynamics-remain poorly understood. Here we experimentally manipulated temperature and nutrient levels in microbial food webs and used time-series analysis to quantify the strength and causality of reciprocal effects between ecological and phenotypic dynamics across species. We found that i) temperature and nutrients have more complex effects on ecological dynamics at higher trophic levels, ii) temperature and nutrients interact antagonistically to shift the relative strength of top-down vs. bottom-up control, iii) phenotypic dynamics have stronger impacts on ecological dynamics than vice versa (especially at higher temperature), and iv) rapid phenotypic change mediates observed ecological responses to changes in temperature and nutrients. Our results expose how feedbacks between ecological and phenotypic dynamics mediate food web responses to environmental change.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456102" rel="alternate" title="Temperature and nutrients drive complex eco-phenotypic dynamics in a microbial food web (4 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456155</id><title>Predicting the distributions of Pouteria adolfi-friederici and Prunus africana iconic tree species under current and future climate change scenarios in Ethiopia (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.882684+00:00</updated><author><name>Zerihun Tadesse</name></author><author><name>Sileshi Nemomissa</name></author><author><name>Debissa Lemessa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The distributions of the potential adaptive ranges of iconic plant species are not yet fully known especially in regions such as Ethiopia where high climatic variability and vegetation types are found. This study was undertaken to predict the distributions of the potential suitable habitats of &lt;italic&gt;Pouteria adolfi-friederici&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Prunus africana&lt;/italic&gt; tree species under the current and two future climate scenarios (i.e., RCP 4.5 and RCP 8.5 in 2050 and 2070) using MaxEnt software (version: 3.4.4.). Eleven less correlated environmental variables (r&amp;lt;0.7) were identified and used to make the prediction models. Elevational shifts of the highly suitable habitats, effects of elevation, solar radiation and topographic position in relation to the current and future climatic scenarios on the habitats were statistically analyzed using independent t-test and linear model. Under all climate scenarios, we found a decrease in the proportion of areas of highly suitable habitats for both study species. High potentials of suitable habitats for &lt;italic&gt;Pouteria adolfi-friederici&lt;/italic&gt; are predicted to be confined to southwest, west central and south parts of Ethiopia in fragmented moist afromontane forest patches, while it is in the southwest and west central parts of Ethiopia for &lt;italic&gt;Prunus africana&lt;/italic&gt;. On basis of vegetation types of the country, potential suitable habitats for &lt;italic&gt;Pouteria adolfi-friederici&lt;/italic&gt; are predicted to occur in moist evergreen forest, dry evergreen forest and grassland complex and &lt;italic&gt;Combretum-Terminalia&lt;/italic&gt; woodland vegetation types. Whereas, moist evergreen forest, dry evergreen forest and grassland complex and riverine vegetation types are predicted to comprise potential suitable habitats for &lt;italic&gt;Prunus africana,&lt;/italic&gt; showing considerable spatial dynamics. Overall, our results suggest that the strategies deem to design biodiversity conservation should take into account the dynamics of the suitable niches of different species under different future climate scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456155" rel="alternate" title="Predicting the distributions of Pouteria adolfi-friederici and Prunus africana iconic tree species under current and future climate change scenarios in Ethiopia (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>