<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv ecology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.748374+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/ecology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453574</id><title>Bats host the most virulent—but not the most dangerous—zoonotic viruses (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.748934+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah Guth</name></author><author><name>Nardus Mollentze</name></author><author><name>Katia Renault</name></author><author><name>Daniel G. Streicker</name></author><author><name>Elisa Visher</name></author><author><name>Mike Boots</name></author><author><name>Cara E. Brook</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Identifying virus characteristics associated with the largest public health impacts on human populations is critical to informing zoonotic risk assessments and surveillance strategies. Efforts to assess “zoonotic risk” often use trait-based analyses to identify which viral and reservoir host groups are most likely to source zoonoses but have not fully addressed how and why the impacts of zoonotic viruses vary in terms of disease severity (‘virulence’), capacity to spread within human populations (‘transmissibility’), or total human mortality (‘death burden’). We analyzed trends in human case fatality rates, transmission capacities, and total death burdens across a comprehensive dataset of mammalian and avian zoonotic viruses. Bats harbor the most virulent zoonotic viruses even when compared to birds, which alongside bats, have been hypothesized to be “special” zoonotic reservoirs due to molecular adaptations that support the physiology of flight. Reservoir host groups more closely related to humans—in particular, Primates—harbor less virulent, but more highly transmissible viruses. Importantly, disproportionately high human death burden, arguably the most important metric of zoonotic risk, is not associated with any animal reservoir, including bats. Our data demonstrate that mechanisms driving death burdens are diverse and often contradict trait-based predictions. Ultimately, total human mortality is dependent on context-specific epidemiological dynamics, which are shaped by a combination of viral traits and conditions in the animal host population and across and beyond the human-animal interface. Understanding the conditions that predict high zoonotic burden in humans will require longitudinal studies of epidemiological dynamics in wildlife and human populations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The clear need to mitigate zoonotic risk has fueled increased viral discovery in specific reservoir host taxa. We show that a combination of viral and reservoir traits can predict zoonotic virus virulence and transmissibility in humans, supporting the hypothesis that bats harbor exceptionally virulent zoonoses. However, pandemic prevention requires thinking beyond zoonotic capacity, virulence, and transmissibility to consider collective ‘burden’ on human health. For this, viral discovery targeting specific reservoirs may be inefficient as death burden correlates with viral, not reservoir, traits, and depends on context-specific epidemiological dynamics across and beyond the human-animal interface. These findings suggest that longitudinal studies of viral dynamics in reservoir and spillover host populations may offer the most effective strategy for mitigating zoonotic risk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453574" rel="alternate" title="Bats host the most virulent—but not the most dangerous—zoonotic viruses (12 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453807</id><title>The benefits of merging two tracking approaches: passive acoustic telemetry combined with active acoustic tracking by transects provide new insights into riverine migration by salmonid smolts (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.749385+00:00</updated><author><name>Louise Chavarie</name></author><author><name>Hannele M. Honkanen</name></author><author><name>Matthew Newton</name></author><author><name>Jessie M. Lilly</name></author><author><name>Hannah R. Greetham</name></author><author><name>Colin E. Adams</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The process of smolting is a critical phase in the life-cycle of anadromous salmonids and it has been associated with substantial rates of mortality. Survival during freshwater and marine migration is known to have population level effects, thus an understanding of the patterns of mortality has the potential to yield important insights into population bottlenecks. Despite important advancements in tracking techniques, the specifics of mortality events in anadromous salmonids during their initial migration to sea remains somewhat elusive. Here, we develop a framework combining spatial and temporal detections of smolt riverine migration from two tracking techniques, which enable inferences to be made about mortality locations, causes, and rates. We embed this framework into a fine-scale behaviour study of migration and social structure. In this study, we demonstrate that during their initial riverine transitional phase, smolts were particularly vulnerable to predators. Specifically, avian predation appeared to be the main cause of mortality (42%), although piscine predation events were not trivial (14%). Our results suggested some direct and indirect tagging-induced mortality (e.g., through increased predation vulnerability), which highlights the importance of determining tagging mortality in a telemetry study to ensure adequate interpretation of migration success. There is evidence that predation induced selection on smolt morphology. Unsuccessful river salmon migrants with a phenotype comprising a shorter head and jaw and smaller eye had a higher probability of mortality in the later parts of riverine migration where avian and aquatic predation mortality dominated. In contrast, mortality earlier in river migration was independent of phenotype, most likely a result of tagging effects. Successfully river migrants were found to be interacting with each other, often in a pair or as a trio, indicating that a few individuals of Atlantic salmon and sea trout formed notable intra- and interspecific social associations. However, the heterogeneity of the social associations of successful migrants did not support the assumption that social network features attributed any clear specific benefits of reduced predation risk. Overall, by estimating migration loss and its variability, our study framework should help to guide management actions to mitigate the widespread population declines these species are currently facing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453807" rel="alternate" title="The benefits of merging two tracking approaches: passive acoustic telemetry combined with active acoustic tracking by transects provide new insights into riverine migration by salmonid smolts (9 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453341</id><title>Trait-trait relationships and functional tradeoffs vary with genome size in prokaryotes (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.749693+00:00</updated><author><name>Sara Beier</name></author><author><name>Johannes Werner</name></author><author><name>Thierry Bouvier</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Mouquet</name></author><author><name>Cyrille Violle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We report genomic traits that have been associated with the life history of prokaryotes and highlight conflicting findings concerning earlier observed trait correlations and tradeoffs. In order to address possible explanations for these contradictions we examined trait-trait variations of 11 genomic traits from ∼ 17,000 sequenced genomes. The studied trait-trait variations suggested: (i) the predominance of two resistance and resilience-related orthogonal axes, (ii) an overlap between a resilience axis and an axis of resource usage efficiency. These findings imply that resistance associated traits of prokaryotes are globally decoupled from resilience and resource use efficiencies associated traits. However, further inspection of pairwise scatterplots showed that resistance and resilience traits tended to be positively related for genomes up to roughly five million base pairs and negatively for larger genomes. This in turn precludes a globally consistent assignment of prokaryote genomic traits to the competitor - stress-tolerator -ruderal (CSR) schema that sorts species depending on their location along disturbance and productivity gradients into three ecological strategies and may serve as an explanation for conflicting findings from earlier studies. All reviewed genomic traits featured significant phylogenetic signals and we propose that our trait table can be applied to extrapolate genomic traits from taxonomic marker genes. This will enable to empirically evaluate the assembly of these genomic traits in prokaryotic communities from different habitats and under different productivity and disturbance scenarios as predicted via the resistance-resilience framework formulated here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453341" rel="alternate" title="Trait-trait relationships and functional tradeoffs vary with genome size in prokaryotes (9 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453553</id><title>Community health and human-animal contacts on the edges of Bwindi Impenetrable National Park, Uganda (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.749976+00:00</updated><author><name>Renata L. Muylaert</name></author><author><name>Ben Davidson</name></author><author><name>Alex Ngabirano</name></author><author><name>Gladys Kalema-Zikusoka</name></author><author><name>Hayley MacGregor</name></author><author><name>James O. Lloyd-Smith</name></author><author><name>Ahmed Fayaz</name></author><author><name>Matthew A. Knox</name></author><author><name>David T. S. Hayman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cross-species transmission of pathogens is intimately linked to human and environmental health. With limited healthcare and challenging living conditions, people living in poverty may be particularly susceptible to endemic and emerging diseases. Similarly, wildlife is impacted by human influences, including pathogen sharing, especially for species in close contact with people and domesticated animals. Here we investigate human and animal contacts and human health in a community living around the Bwindi Impenetrable National Park (BINP), Uganda. We used contact and health survey data to identify opportunities for cross-species pathogen transmission, focusing mostly on people and the endangered mountain gorilla. We conducted a survey with background questions and self-reported diaries to investigate 100 participants’ health, such as symptoms and behaviours, and contact patterns, including direct contacts and sightings over a week. Contacts were revealed through networks, including humans, domestic, peri-domestic, and wild animals for 1) network of contacts seen in the week of background questionnaire completion, 2) network of contacts seen during the diary week. Participants frequently felt unwell during the study, reporting from one to 10 disease symptoms at different intensity levels (maximum of seven symptoms in one day), with severe symptoms comprising 6.4% of the diary records and tiredness and headaches the most common symptoms. Besides human-human contacts, direct contacts with livestock and peri-domestic animals were the most common. Wildlife contacts were the rarest, including one direct contact with gorilla with a concerning timeline of reported symptoms. The contact networks were moderately connected and revealing a preference in contacts within the same species or taxon and within their groups. Despite sightings of wildlife being much more common than touching, one participant declared direct contact with a mountain gorilla during the week. Gorillas were seen very close to six animal taxa (including themselves) considering all interaction types, mostly seen closer to other gorillas, but also people and domestic animals. Our findings reveal a local human population with recurrent symptoms of illness in a location with intense exposure to factors that can increase pathogen transmission, such as direct contact with domestic and wild animals and proximity among animal species. Despite significant biases and study limitations, the information generated here can guide future studies, such as models for disease spread and One Health interventions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453553" rel="alternate" title="Community health and human-animal contacts on the edges of Bwindi Impenetrable National Park, Uganda (8 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453227</id><title>Disentangling key species interactions in diverse and heterogeneous communities: A Bayesian sparse modeling approach (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.750314+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher P. Weiss-Lehman</name></author><author><name>Chhaya M. Werner</name></author><author><name>Catherine H. Bowler</name></author><author><name>Lauren M. Hallett</name></author><author><name>Margaret M. Mayfield</name></author><author><name>Oscar Godoy</name></author><author><name>Lina Aoyama</name></author><author><name>György Barabás</name></author><author><name>Chengjin Chu</name></author><author><name>Emma Ladouceur</name></author><author><name>Loralee Larios</name></author><author><name>Lauren G. Shoemaker</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Modeling species interactions in diverse communities traditionally requires a prohibitively large number of species-interaction coefficients, especially when considering environmental dependence of parameters. We implemented Bayesian variable selection via sparsity-inducing priors on non-linear species abundance models to determine which species-interactions should be retained and which can be represented as an average heterospecific interaction term, reducing the number of model parameters. We evaluated model performance using simulated communities, computing out-of-sample predictive accuracy and parameter recovery across different input sample sizes. We applied our method to a diverse empirical community, allowing us to disentangle the direct role of environmental gradients on species’ intrinsic growth rates from indirect effects via competitive interactions. We also identified a few neighboring species from the diverse community that had non-generic interactions with our focal species. This sparse modeling approach facilitates exploration of species-interactions in diverse communities while maintaining a manageable number of parameters.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453227" rel="alternate" title="Disentangling key species interactions in diverse and heterogeneous communities: A Bayesian sparse modeling approach (5 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>