<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular ecology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.003461+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/ecology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469341</id><title>Scoping the Line Up: A Comparison of Biomonitoring Methodologies for Surf Zone Fish Communities (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.003931+00:00</updated><author><name>Zachary Gold</name></author><author><name>McKenzie Q. Koch</name></author><author><name>Nicholas K. Schooler</name></author><author><name>Kyle A. Emery</name></author><author><name>Jennifer E. Dugan</name></author><author><name>Robert J. Miller</name></author><author><name>Henry M. Page</name></author><author><name>Donna M. Schroeder</name></author><author><name>David M. Hubbard</name></author><author><name>Jessica R. Madden</name></author><author><name>Stephen G. Whitaker</name></author><author><name>Paul H. Barber</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Surf zones are highly dynamic marine ecosystems that are subject to increasing anthropogenic and climatic pressures, posing multiple challenges for biomonitoring. Traditional methods such as seines and hook and line surveys are often labor intensive, taxonomically biased, and can be physically hazardous. Emerging techniques, such as baited remote underwater video (BRUV) and environmental DNA (eDNA) are promising nondestructive tools for assessing marine biodiversity in surf zones of sandy beaches. Here we compare the relative performance of beach seines, BRUV, and eDNA in characterizing community composition of bony (teleost) and cartilaginous (elasmobranch) fishes of surf zones at 18 open coast sandy beaches in southern California. Seine and BRUV surveys captured overlapping, but distinct fish communities with 50% (18/36) of detected species shared. BRUV surveys more frequently detected larger species (e.g. sharks and rays) while seines more frequently detected one of the most abundant species, barred surfperch (  Amphistichus argenteus  ). In contrast, eDNA metabarcoding captured 83.3% (30/36) of all fishes observed in seine and BRUV surveys plus 59 additional species, including 13 that frequent surf zone habitats. eDNA approaches showed significantly higher sensitivity than seine and BRUV methods and more consistently detected 29 of the 30 (96.7%) jointly observed species across beaches. The six species detected by BRUV/seines, but not eDNA either lacked reference sequences, were only resolved at higher taxonomic ranks (e.g.  Embiotocidae  surfperches), or were detected below occupancy thresholds. Low site-species overlap between methods limited comparisons of richness and abundance estimates, highlighting the challenge of comparing biomonitoring approaches. Despite potential for improvement, results overall demonstrate that eDNA can provide a cost-effective tool for long-term surf zone monitoring that complements data from seine and BRUV surveys, allowing more comprehensive surveys of vertebrate diversity in surf zone habitats.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469341" rel="alternate" title="Scoping the Line Up: A Comparison of Biomonitoring Methodologies for Surf Zone Fish Communities (14 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469079</id><title>Multitrophic higher-order interactions modulate species persistence (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.004381+00:00</updated><author><name>Lisa Buche</name></author><author><name>Ignasi Bartomeus</name></author><author><name>Oscar Godoy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;There is growing recognition that interactions between species pairs are modified in a multispecies context by the density of a third species. However, how these higher-order interactions (HOIs) affect species persistence remains poorly understood. To explore the effect of HOIs steaming from multiple trophic layers on plant persistence, we experimentally built a mutualistic system containing three plants and three pollinators species with two contrasting network structures. For both structures, we first estimated the statistically supported HOIs on plant species, in addition to the pairwise interactions among plants and  plant-pollinators. Following a structuralist approach, we then assessed the effects of the supported HOIs on the persistence probability of each of the three competing plant species and their combinations. HOIs produced substantial effects on the strength and sign of per capita interactions between plant species to such an extent that predictions of species persistence differ from a non-HOIs scenario. Changes in network structure due to removing a plant-pollinator link further modulated the species persistence probabilities by reorganizing per capita interaction strengths of both pairwise interactions and HOIs. Our study provides empirical evidence of the joint importance of HOIs and network structure for determining the probability of species to persist within diverse communities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469079" rel="alternate" title="Multitrophic higher-order interactions modulate species persistence (13 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468603</id><title>Estimating the Mosquito Density in Guangzhou City, China (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.004947+00:00</updated><author><name>Meili Li</name></author><author><name>Xian Zhang</name></author><author><name>Junling Ma</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mosquito is a vector of many diseases. Predicting the trend of mosquito density is important for early warning and control of mosquito diseases. In this paper, we fit a discrete time mosquito model developed by Gong et al. in 2011, which considers the immature and adult stages, and weather dependent model parameters, to the Breteau Index and Bite Index data for Aedes aegypti in Guangzhou city, China in 2014, as well as the weather data for average temperature, precipitation, evaporation and daylight for the same period. We estimated the model parameters using the Markov Chain Monte-Carlo (MCMC) method. We find that many parameters are not identifiable. We revise and simplify the model so that the parameters of our new model are identifiable. Our results indicate that the model predicted mosquito prevalence agrees well with data. We then use the fitted parameter values against the Breteau Index and Bite Index data for Guangzhou city in 2017 and 2018, and show that the estimated parameter values are applicable for other seasons.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468603" rel="alternate" title="Estimating the Mosquito Density in Guangzhou City, China (12 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468867</id><title>Evaluating the contribution of aestivation to the persistence of malaria mosquitoes through the Sahelian dry season using stable isotopes (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.005118+00:00</updated><author><name>Roy Faiman</name></author><author><name>Alpha SEYDOU YARO</name></author><author><name>Adama Dao</name></author><author><name>Zana L Sanogo</name></author><author><name>Moussa Diallo</name></author><author><name>Djibril Samake</name></author><author><name>Ousmane Yossi</name></author><author><name>Laura R Veru</name></author><author><name>Leland C Graber</name></author><author><name>Abigail R Conte</name></author><author><name>Cedric Kouam</name></author><author><name>Benjamin J Krajacich</name></author><author><name>Tovi Lehmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Data suggests the malaria vector Anopheles coluzzii persists in the Sahel by dry-season aestivation though evidence is scant. We have marked Anopheles mosquitoes using deuterium (2H) to assess the contribution of aestivation to persistence of mosquitoes through the seven-month dry season.  If local aestivation is the only way A. coluzzii persists, the frequency of marked mosquitoes should remain stable throughout, whereas finding no marked mosquitoes would be evidence against aestivation. Larval sites were spiked with 2H at the end of the 2017 wet season in two Sahelian villages in Mali. We monitored 2H-enriched populations until the onset of rains.  By the end of the enrichment period, 33% of A. coluzzii mosquitoes were clearly marked. Expectedly, 2H levels in marked mosquitoes degraded over time, resulting in a partial overlap of the marked and non-marked 2H distributions. We utilized three methods to estimate the fraction of marked mosquitoes in the population. Seven months after enrichment, 7% of the population had 2H values above the highest pre-enrichment value. An excess of 21% exceeded the 3rd quartile of the pre-enrichment population. A finite mixed population model showed 2.5% represented a subpopulation of marked mosquitoes with elevated 2H, compatible with our predictions. We provide evidence that aestivation is a major persistence mechanism of A. coluzzii in the Sahel, contributing at least 20% of the adults at the onset of rains, suggesting A. coluzzii utilizes multiple persistence strategies enabling its populations rapid buildup, facilitating subsequent malaria resurgence. These may complicate vector control and malaria elimination campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468867" rel="alternate" title="Evaluating the contribution of aestivation to the persistence of malaria mosquitoes through the Sahelian dry season using stable isotopes (8 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468820</id><title>The relationship between land cover and microbial community composition in European lakes (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.005580+00:00</updated><author><name>Theodor Sperlea</name></author><author><name>Jan Philip Schenk</name></author><author><name>Hagen Dreßler</name></author><author><name>Daniela Beisser</name></author><author><name>Georges Hattab</name></author><author><name>Jens Boenigk</name></author><author><name>Dominik Heider</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microbes such as bacteria, archaea, and protists are essential for element cycling and ecosystem functioning, but many questions central to the understanding of the role of microbes in ecology are still open. Here, we analyze the relationship between lake microbiomes and the land cover surrounding the lakes. By applying machine learning methods, we quantify the covariance between land cover categories and the microbial community composition recorded in the largest amplicon sequencing dataset of European lakes available to date. We identify microbial bioindicators for these land cover categories. Combining land cover and physico-chemical bioindicators identified from the same amplicon sequencing dataset, we develop two novel similarity metrics that facilitate insights into the ecology of the lake microbiome. We show that the bioindicator network, i.e., the graph linking OTUs indicative of the same environmental parameters, corresponds to microbial co-occurrence patterns. Taken together, we demonstrate the strength of machine learning approaches to identify correlations between microbial diversity and environmental factors, potentially opening new approaches to integrate environmental molecular diversity into monitoring and water quality assessments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468820" rel="alternate" title="The relationship between land cover and microbial community composition in European lakes (5 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>