<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular ecology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.135874+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/ecology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461426</id><title>Prescribed versus wildfire impacts on exotic plants and soil microbes in California grasslands (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.136403+00:00</updated><author><name>Sydney I Glassman</name></author><author><name>James WJ Randolph</name></author><author><name>Sameer S Saroa</name></author><author><name>Joia K Capocchi</name></author><author><name>Kendra E Walters</name></author><author><name>M. Fabiola Pulido-Chavez</name></author><author><name>Loralee Larios</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prescribed fire is often used as a management tool to decrease exotic plant cover and increase native plant cover in grasslands. These changes may also be mediated by fire impacts on soil microbial communities, which drive plant productivity and function. Yet, the ecological effects of prescribed burns compared to wildfires on either plant or soil microbial composition remain unclear.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we investigated the impacts of a spring prescribed fire versus a fall wildfire on plant cover and community composition and bacterial and fungal richness, abundance, and composition in a California grassland. We used qPCR of 16S and 18S to assess impacts on bacterial and fungal abundance and Illumina MiSeq of 16S and ITS2 to assess impacts on bacterial and fungal richness and composition.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wildfire had stronger impacts than prescribed fire on microbial communities and both fires had similar impacts on plants with both prescribed and wildfire reducing exotic plant cover but neither reducing exotic plant richness. Fungal richness declined after the wildfire but not prescribed fire, but bacterial richness was unaffected by either. Yet increasing char levels in both fire types resulted in reduced bacterial and fungal biomass, and both fire types slightly altered bacterial and fungal composition.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Exotic and native plant diversity differentially affected soil microbial diversity, with native plant diversity leading to increased arbuscular mycorrhizal fungal richness while exotic plant diversity better predicted bacterial richness. However, the remainder of the soil microbial communities were more related to aspects of soil chemistry including cation exchange capacity, organic matter, pH and phosphorous.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Synthesis and applications&lt;/italic&gt;. Understanding the different ecological effects of prescribed fires and wildfires on plant and soil communities are key to enhancing a prevalent management action and to guide potential management opportunities post wildfires. Our coupled plant and soil community sampling allowed us to capture the sensitivity of the fungal community to fire and highlights the importance of potentially incorporating management actions such as soil or fungal amendments to promote this critical community that mediates native plant performance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461426" rel="alternate" title="Prescribed versus wildfire impacts on exotic plants and soil microbes in California grasslands (19 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461237</id><title>On the effect of inheritance of microbes in commensal microbiomes (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.136824+00:00</updated><author><name>Román Zapién-Campos</name></author><author><name>Florence Bansept</name></author><author><name>Michael Sieber</name></author><author><name>Arne Traulsen</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our current view of nature depicts a world where macroorganisms dwell in a landscape full of microbes. Some of these microbes not only transit but establish themselves in or on hosts. Although hosts might be occupied by microbes for most of their lives, a microbe-free stage during their prenatal development seems to be the rule for many hosts. The questions of who the first colonizers of a newborn host are and to what extent these are obtained from the parents follow naturally.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have developed a mathematical model to study the effect of the transfer of microbes from parents to offspring. Even without selection, we observe that microbial inheritance is particularly effective in modifying the microbiome of hosts with a short lifespan or limited colonization from the environment, for example by favouring the acquisition of rare microbes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;By modelling the inheritance of commensal microbes to newborns, our results suggest that, in an eco-evolutionary context, the impact of microbial inheritance is of particular importance for some specific life histories.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461237" rel="alternate" title="On the effect of inheritance of microbes in commensal microbiomes (13 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461517</id><title>Towards a system-level causative knowledge of pollinator communities (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.137201+00:00</updated><author><name>Serguei Saavedra</name></author><author><name>Ignasi Bartomeus</name></author><author><name>Oscar Godoy</name></author><author><name>Rudolf P. Rohr</name></author><author><name>Penguan Zu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pollination plays a central role both in the maintenance of biodiversity and in crop production. However, habitat loss, pesticides, invasive species, and larger environmental fluctuations are contributing to a dramatic decline of numerous pollinators world-wide. This has increased the need for interventions to protect the composition, functioning, and dynamics of pollinator communities. Yet, how to make these interventions successful at the system level remains extremely challenging due to the complex nature of species interactions and the various unknown or unmeasured confounding ecological factors. Here, we propose that this knowledge can be derived by following a probabilistic causal analysis of pollinator communities. This analysis implies the inference of interventional expectations from the integration of observational and synthetic data. We propose that such synthetic data can be generated using theoretical models that can enable the tractability and scalability of unseen confounding ecological factors affecting the behavior of pollinator communities. We discuss a road map for how this probabilistic causal analysis can be accomplished to increase our system-level causative knowledge of natural communities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461517" rel="alternate" title="Towards a system-level causative knowledge of pollinator communities (12 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461764</id><title>Kin discrimination modifies fitness, spatial segregation and matrix sharing between strains with low relatedness in Bacillus subtilis biofilms (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.137458+00:00</updated><author><name>Maja Bolješić</name></author><author><name>Barbara Kraigher</name></author><author><name>Iztok Dogša</name></author><author><name>Barbara Jerič Kokelj</name></author><author><name>Ines Mandić Mulec</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microorganisms in nature form multicellular groups called biofilms. In biofilms bacteria embedded in a matrix of extracellular polymeric substances (EPS) interact intensely, due to their proximity to each other. Most studies have investigated genetically homogeneous biofilms, leaving a gap in knowledge on genetically heterogeneous biofilms. Recent insights show that a Gram-positive model bacterium, &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/italic&gt;, discriminates between strains of high (kin) and low (non-kin) phylogenetic relatedness, reflected in merging (kin) and boundaries (non-kin) between swarms. However, it is not clear how kinship between interacting strains affects their fitness, the genotype distribution, and the EPS sharing in floating biofilms (pellicles). To address this gap in knowledge we cultivate &lt;italic&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; strains as mixtures of kin and non-kin strains in static cultures, allowing them to form pellicles. We show here that in non-kin pellicles only one strain’s fitness was reduced; at the same time, strains segregated into larger patches and exhibited decreased matrix sharing, as compared to kin and isogenic pellicles, in which both strains had comparable colony forming units (CFU) counts and more homogenous cell mixing. Overall, our results emphasize kin discrimination (KD) as a social behavior that shapes fitness, spatial segregation and sharing of the extracellular matrix in genetically heterogenous biofilms of &lt;italic&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Biofilm communities have both beneficial and harmful effects on human societies in natural, medical and industrial environments. &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/italic&gt;, a Gram-positive and biotechnologically important bacterium, serves as a model for studying biofilms. Recent studies have shown that this species engages in kin discriminatory behavior during swarming, which may have implications for community assembly, thus being of fundamental importance. Effects of KD on fitness, genotype segregation and matrix sharing in biofilms is not well understood. By using environmental strains with determined kin types and integrated fluorescent reporters we provide evidence that KD involves antagonism of the dominant strain against non-kin, which has important implications for genotype segregation and sharing of matrix polysaccharides between producers and non-producers. Our results reveal novel consequences of KD and are important for advancing our fundamental understanding of microbial sociality, and its role in the assembly of multicellular groups and in the shaping of microbial diversity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461764" rel="alternate" title="Kin discrimination modifies fitness, spatial segregation and matrix sharing between strains with low relatedness in Bacillus subtilis biofilms (10 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461645</id><title>Dynamics of Aedes albopictus invasion Insights from a spatio-temporal model (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.137647+00:00</updated><author><name>L Roques</name></author><author><name>T Boivin</name></author><author><name>J Papaïx</name></author><author><name>S Soubeyrand</name></author><author><name>O Bonnefon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;France displays a latitudinal range for the expansion of &lt;italic&gt;Aedes albopictus&lt;/italic&gt; invasive populations that is not yet completely colonized providing a critical opportunity to address key invasion processes. We propose a spatio-temporal model (DISTIGRI) to describe and predict current and future expansion at both intra- and inter-annual scales of &lt;italic&gt;A. albopictus&lt;/italic&gt;. This process-based model integrates mechanistic descriptions of the developmental cycle and the dispersal process of &lt;italic&gt;A. albopictus&lt;/italic&gt; within a reaction-diffusion framework, depending on climatic suitability and photoperiod with a high spatio-temporal resolution. Using this model coupled with a climatic database, we propose several maps describing the current intra-annual distribution of &lt;italic&gt;A. albopictus&lt;/italic&gt;, including the date of first emergence and the length of the period with significant adult presence. We also compute its future distribution over the next 10 years under several climatic scenarios, which shows a range expansion with a strong dependence on the climatic scenario. The outputs of the model may constitute a valuable asset for designing control and avoidance strategies, and to anticipate the biting nuisance with a high spatio-temporal resolution. These outputs also emphasize the importance of taking both dispersal and life cycle into account to obtain accurate descriptions of out-of-equilibrium processes such as ongoing invasions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461645" rel="alternate" title="Dynamics of Aedes albopictus invasion Insights from a spatio-temporal model (9 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462303</id><title>Emerging mosquito resistance to piperonyl butoxide-synergized pyrethroid insecticide and its mechanism (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.137916+00:00</updated><author><name>Guofa Zhou</name></author><author><name>Yiji Li</name></author><author><name>Brook Jeang</name></author><author><name>Xiaoming Wang</name></author><author><name>Daibin Zhong</name></author><author><name>Guiyun Yan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Piperonyl butoxide (PBO)-synergized pyrethroid products are widely available for the control of pyrethroid-resistant mosquitoes. To date, no study has formally examined mosquito resistance to PBO-synergized insecticides. We used &lt;italic&gt;Culex quinquefasciatus&lt;/italic&gt; as a model mosquito examined the insecticide resistance mechanisms of mosquitoes to PBO-synergized pyrethroid using modified World Health Organization tube bioassays and biochemical analysis of metabolic enzyme expressions prior- and post-PBO exposure. We measured mosquito mortalities and metabolic enzyme expressions in mosquitoes with/without pre-exposure to different PBO concentrations and exposure durations. We found that field &lt;italic&gt;Culex quinquefasciatus&lt;/italic&gt; mosquitoes were resistant to all insecticides tested, including PBO-synergized pyrethroids (mortality ranged from 3.7±4.7% to 66.7±7.7%), except malathion. Field mosquitoes had elevated levels of carboxylesterase (COE, 3.8-fold) and monooxygenase (P450, 2.1-fold) but not glutathione S-transferase (GST) compared to susceptible mosquitoes. When the field mosquitoes were pre-exposed to 4% PBO, the 50% lethal concentration of deltamethrin was reduced from 0.22% to 0.10%, compare to 0.02% for susceptible mosquitoes. Knockdown resistance gene mutation (L1014F) rate was 62% in field mosquitoes. PBO pre-exposure suppressed P450 enzyme expression levels by 25∼34%, GST by 11%, and had no impact on COE enzyme expression. Even with the optimal PBO concentration and exposure duration, field mosquitoes had significantly higher P450 enzyme expression levels after PBO exposure compared to laboratory controls. These results demonstrate that PBO alone may not be enough to control highly pyrethroid resistant mosquitoes due to the multiple resistance mechanisms. Mosquito resistance to PBO-synergized insecticide should be closely monitored.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Authors’ Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mosquitoes are vectors of many major infectious diseases globally. Insecticides and related products are widely used for mosquito controls and disease preventions. Over time and following repeated use, mosquitoes (including &lt;italic&gt;Aedes, Anopheles&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Culex&lt;/italic&gt;) have developed very high resistance to multiple insecticides all over the world. Target site insensitivity due to mutations in the voltage-gated sodium channel gene and overproduction of metabolic detoxification enzymes such as cytochrome P450 (CYP) monooxygenases play critical role in insecticide resistance in mosquitoes. To enhance the killing power of insecticides, synergized insecticides were developed by mixing insecticide synergists with pyrethroids. Discovered in the 1940s, piperonyl butoxide (PBO) is one of the earliest and most commonly used insecticide synergists. Field application of PBO-synergized insecticides performed far better than mono-pyrethroids. PBO-treated long-lasting insecticidal nets (PBO-LLINs), which also use pyrethroids, outperformed regular LLIN for malaria control in many African countries. PBO-LLIN is soon to be rolled out on a large scale for malaria control in Africa. One important question regarding the use of synergized insecticides is whether they will select for vector population resistance to synergized insecticide products, in other words, are PBO-synergized pyrethroids effective against highly insecticide-resistant mosquitoes? To date, no study has formally examined mosquito resistance to PBO-synergized insecticides. Here, we used &lt;italic&gt;Culex quinquefasciatus&lt;/italic&gt; as a model mosquito, we examined its resistance status to different insecticides including PBO-synergized pyrethrins and tested how PBO exposure affect mosquito mortality and the expressions of metabolic enzymes. We found that field &lt;italic&gt;Culex quinquefasciatus&lt;/italic&gt; mosquitoes were resistant to multiple insecticides tested, including PBO-synergized pyrethroids. Field mosquitoes had elevated levels of carboxylesterase (COE) and monooxygenase (P450) but not glutathione S-transferase (GST) enzyme expressions compared to susceptible mosquitoes. Even with optimal PBO concentration and exposure duration, field mosquitoes had significantly higher P450 enzyme expression levels after PBO exposure compared to laboratory controls, and PBO exposure had no impact on COE enzyme expressions. The phenomena of the insecticide-resistant mosquitoes’ insensitivity to PBO exposure or PBO-synergized insecticides and multiple-resistance mechanisms have also been reported from &lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Anopheles&lt;/italic&gt; mosquitoes in different countries. These results demonstrate that PBO alone is not enough to control highly pyrethroid resistant mosquitoes due to multiple resistance mechanisms. Mosquito resistance to PBO-synergized insecticide should be closely monitored&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462303" rel="alternate" title="Emerging mosquito resistance to piperonyl butoxide-synergized pyrethroid insecticide and its mechanism (9 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461883</id><title>Comammox Nitrospira bacteria outnumber canonical nitrifiers irrespective of electron donor mode and availability (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.138363+00:00</updated><author><name>Katherine J. Vilardi</name></author><author><name>Irmarie Cotto</name></author><author><name>Maria Sevillano Rivera</name></author><author><name>Zihan Dai</name></author><author><name>Christopher L. Anderson</name></author><author><name>Ameet Pinto</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Complete ammonia oxidizing bacteria coexist with canonical ammonia and nitrite oxidizing bacteria in a wide range of environments. Whether this coexistence is due to competitive or cooperative interactions between the three guilds, or a result of niche separation is not yet clear. Understanding the factors driving coexistence of nitrifying guilds is critical to effectively manage nitrification processes occurring in engineered and natural ecosystems. In this study, microcosms-based experiments were used to investigate the impact of electron donor mode (i.e., ammonia and urea) and loading on the population dynamics of nitrifying guilds in drinking water biofilter media. Shotgun sequencing of DNA from select time points followed by co-assembly and re-construction of metagenome assembled genomes (MAGs) revealed multiple clade A2 and one clade A1 comammox bacterial populations coexisted in the microcosms alongside &lt;italic&gt;Nitrosomonas-like&lt;/italic&gt; ammonia oxidizers and &lt;italic&gt;Nitrospira&lt;/italic&gt;-like nitrite oxidizer populations. Clade A2 comammox bacteria were likely the primary nitrifiers within the microcosms and increased in abundance over canonical ammonia and nitrite oxidizing bacteria irrespective of electron donor mode or nitrogen loading rates. This suggests that comammox bacteria will outnumber nitrifying communities sourced from oligotrophic environments irrespective of variable nitrogen regimes. Changes in comammox bacterial abundance were not correlated with either ammonia or nitrite oxidizing bacterial abundance in urea amended systems where metabolic reconstruction indicated potential cross feeding between ammonia and nitrite oxidizing bacteria. In contrast, comammox bacterial abundance demonstrated a negative correlation with that of nitrite oxidizers in ammonia amended systems. This suggests that potentially weaker synergistic relationships between ammonia and nitrite oxidizers might enable comammox bacteria to displace nitrite oxidizers from complex nitrifying communities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A deeper understanding of the interactions between nitrifying microorganisms, including comammox bacteria, is crucial to effectively managing nitrogen in engineered and natural systems. Despite their ubiquitous detection, our understanding of interactions between these coexisting nitrifying groups is limited. Here, we investigate the influence of differing sources of electron donor and loadings on a mixed nitrifier community which includes canonical ammonia and nitrite oxidizers, as well as comammox bacteria. Our results indicate that comammox bacteria will dominate nitrifier communities sourced from low nitrogen environments (e.g., drinking water) irrespective of fluctuations in nitrogen availability or source without directly competing with canonical ammonia oxidizers. However, canonical nitrite oxidizers are likely to get outcompeted by comammox bacteria in situations where metabolic interactions between ammonia and nitrite do not include cross feeding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461883" rel="alternate" title="Comammox Nitrospira bacteria outnumber canonical nitrifiers irrespective of electron donor mode and availability (8 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.17.460862</id><title>Demographic changes of a tropical understory bird in naturally patchy montane habitats in southern India (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.138606+00:00</updated><author><name>V. V. Robin</name></author><author><name>James E. Hines</name></author><author><name>James D. Nichols</name></author><author><name>Madhusudan Katti</name></author><author><name>Anindya Sinha</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The occurrence, density and survival of a species often depend on various aspects of the habitat that it occupies including patch size and disturbance. The demography of most threatened tropical species largely remain unstudied but could provide valuable information about their biology and insights for their conservation. Our study examined the effect of patch size and disturbance on different demographic parameters of an understory, threatened, endemic bird, the white-bellied shortwing in the tropical biodiversity hotspot of the Western Ghats in India. We sampled eight plots on a sky-island using mist-nets for four years in a ‘Robust design’ mark-recapture framework. Based on model selection using AIC values, the model with survival as a function of disturbance fits the data better than models with abundance or with these parameters modeled as functions of forest patch size. Shortwing density and sex ratio were not different across forest patch sizes or differing disturbance regimes. However, the survival rate of the species significantly decreased with increasing disturbance but was not related to forest patch size. Our study is possibly the first to provide critical baseline information on the demography of a tropical understory species from this region.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.17.460862" rel="alternate" title="Demographic changes of a tropical understory bird in naturally patchy montane habitats in southern India (5 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461715</id><title>A lack of repeatability creates the illusion of a trade-off between basal and plastic cold tolerance (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.138862+00:00</updated><author><name>Erica O’Neill</name></author><author><name>Hannah E. Davis</name></author><author><name>Heath A. MacMillan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The thermotolerance-plasticity trade-off hypothesis predicts that ectotherms with greater basal thermal tolerance have a lower acclimation capacity. This hypothesis has been tested at both high and low temperatures but the results often conflict. If basal tolerance constrains plasticity (e.g. through shared mechanisms that create physiological constraints), it should be evident at the level of the individual, provided the trait measured is repeatable. Here, we used chill-coma onset temperature and chill-coma recovery time (CCO and CCRT; non-lethal thermal limits) to quantify cold tolerance of &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; across two trials (pre- and post-acclimation). Cold acclimation improved cold tolerance, as expected, but individual measurements of CCO and CCRT in non-acclimated flies were not (or only slightly) repeatable. Surprisingly, however, there was still a strong correlation between basal tolerance and plasticity in cold-acclimated flies. We argue that this relationship is a statistical artefact (specifically, a manifestation of regression to the mean; RTM) and does not reflect a true trade-off or physiological constraint. Thermal tolerance trade-off patterns in previous studies that used similar methodology are thus likely to be impacted by RTM. Moving forward, controlling and/or correcting for RTM effects is critical to determining whether such a trade-off or physiological constraint truly exists.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461715" rel="alternate" title="A lack of repeatability creates the illusion of a trade-off between basal and plastic cold tolerance (5 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461123</id><title>Diversity and distribution of sediment bacteria across an ecological and trophic gradient (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.139660+00:00</updated><author><name>Hailey M. Sauer</name></author><author><name>Trinity L. Hamilton</name></author><author><name>Rika E. Anderson</name></author><author><name>Charles E. Umbanhowar</name></author><author><name>Adam J. Heathcote</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Can we cluster bacterial sediment communities based on lake size, depth, and trophic status? Or, are bacterial microbial communities an emergent property of their geography, integrating regional physical and climatic conditions? Lakes in Minnesota are uniquely situated to address these questions because of their wide geographic range and variability in size and basin land-use. In this study, we selected twenty lakes with varying morphological and chemical properties across four ecological regions of Minnesota. Our objectives were to (i)) evaluate the diversity and spatial variation of the bacterial community at the sediment-water interface and (ii) determine how lake location and watershed land-use impact aqueous chemistry and influence community structure. Our data indicate that sediment communities from similar depth intervals are more likely to cluster by ecological region rather than any individual lake properties (&lt;italic&gt;e.g&lt;/italic&gt;., trophic status, TP concentration, lake depth). However, composition is tied to a given lake, wherein samples from the same core were more alike than samples at similar depths across lakes. Our results illustrate the diversity within lake sediment microbial communities and provide insight into relationships between taxonomy, physicochemical, and geographic properties of north temperate lakes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461123" rel="alternate" title="Diversity and distribution of sediment bacteria across an ecological and trophic gradient (5 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462407</id><title>Plasticity in female timing may explain current shifts in breeding phenology of a North American songbird (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.139982+00:00</updated><author><name>Abigail A. Kimmitt</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Becker</name></author><author><name>Sara N. Diller</name></author><author><name>Nicole M. Gerlach</name></author><author><name>Kimberly A. Rosvall</name></author><author><name>Ellen D. Ketterson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Climate change has driven changes in breeding phenology. Identifying the magnitude of phenological shifts and whether selection in response to climate change drives these shifts is key for determining species’ reproductive success and persistence in a changing world.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We investigated reproductive timing in a primarily sedentary population of the dark-eyed junco (&lt;italic&gt;Junco hyemalis&lt;/italic&gt;) over 32 years. We predicted that juncos would breed earlier in warmer springs in response to selection favouring earlier breeding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;To test this prediction, we compared the annual median date for reproductive onset (i.e., egg one date) to monthly spring temperatures and examined evidence for selection favouring earlier breeding and for plasticity in timing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Egg one dates occurred earlier over time, with the timing of breeding advancing up to 24 days over the 32-year period. Breeding timing also strongly covaried with maximum April temperature. We found significant overall selection favouring earlier breeding (i.e., higher relative fitness with earlier egg one dates) that became stronger over time, but strength of selection was not predicted by temperature. Lastly, individual females exhibited plastic responses to temperature across years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our findings provide further evidence that phenotypic plasticity plays a crucial role in driving phenological shifts in response to climate change. For multi-brooded bird populations, a warming climate might extend the breeding season and provide more opportunities to re-nest rather than drive earlier breeding in response to potential phenological mismatches. However, as plasticity will likely be insufficient for long-term survival in the face of climate change, further research in understanding the mechanisms of female reproductive timing will be essential for forecasting the effects of climate change on population persistence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462407" rel="alternate" title="Plasticity in female timing may explain current shifts in breeding phenology of a North American songbird (4 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461815</id><title>Simultaneous acoustic monitoring uncovers evidence of biodiversity loss and overlooked temporal variation in a threatened Amazonian bird community (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.140218+00:00</updated><author><name>W. Alexander Hopping</name></author><author><name>Holger Klinck</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Birds are frequently used as indicator taxon in ecology, but traditional surveys are prone to error and largely inadequate in the dense, speciose tropical forests where they are most needed. Passive acoustic monitoring (PAM) has the potential to address many of these pitfalls, providing unique advantages for both long-term monitoring and rapid biodiversity assessment. Here, we evaluate the effectiveness of PAM for characterizing spatiotemporal variation in avian species richness, diversity, vocal activity, and community composition in the Amazon basin global biodiversity hotspot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We employed an array of ten autonomous recording units (ARUs) spanning edge, degraded, and interior forest at a reserve on the deforestation frontier of Madre de Dios, Peru, a region featuring some of the richest, most complex avian assemblages on Earth. Recordings from 21 dawn-hours across three days at seven sites were manually annotated by a single observer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;ARUs and manual annotation performed well as an inventory method, especially for midstory and understory species. Sites in edge and degraded habitats featured significantly lower avian species richness, Shannon diversity, and vocal activity levels than in the forest interior, patterns that replicate the findings of prior high-effort avian censuses in the region. We observed significant temporal variation between days; at all featured sites, vocal activity was highest on January 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; and lowest on January 31&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We demonstrated that novel annotation-generated metrics can work as effective proxies for abundance data and per-capita song rate, correlating with diversity indices and efficiently characterizing habitats at a level of detail unobtainable with human observers. Generalist species were significantly overrepresented in the soundscapes of interior forest, relative to their contributed share of species richness, and interior specialists were underrepresented, suggesting that the entire 191ha site is degraded. The between-days temporal variation that we documented, almost certainly overlooked without simultaneous monitoring, may obfuscate or distort the results of traditional surveys.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;Synthesis &amp;amp; Applications&lt;/bold&gt;. We propose that PAM should become a cornerstone of biodiversity research. The standardization advantages demonstrated in this study, permanent storage, multi-taxa applications, and potential of automated identification make bioacoustics an ideal methodological avenue for guiding management and policy under rapid global change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461815" rel="alternate" title="Simultaneous acoustic monitoring uncovers evidence of biodiversity loss and overlooked temporal variation in a threatened Amazonian bird community (4 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.460834</id><title>On the Origin of Feces: Fungal diversity, distribution, and conservation implications from feces of small mammals (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.140385+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander J Bradshaw</name></author><author><name>Kendra Autumn</name></author><author><name>Eric Rickart</name></author><author><name>Bryn T.M. Dentinger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fungi are extremely diverse, but only a small fraction of the total estimated species have been characterized. Often, the extent of diversity and distribution of fungal communities is difficult or near impossible to assess. This is due to the fact that many Fungi are cryptic and persist predominantly hidden within substrates such as soil or plant material. This is particularly true for hypogeous sporocarps, including truffles, which are extremely difficult to survey in a systematic manner. However, fungi with hypogeous sporocarps have evolved traits that make them highly attractive to animals, such as small mammals, which ingest and disperse fungal spores through defecation. Here, samples of feces from 138 small mammals collected in the western United States were assessed for total fungal diversity using a dual-index metabarcoding, high-throughput Illumina sequencing approach. Our findings exhibit many identifications within &lt;italic&gt;Agaricomycetidae&lt;/italic&gt;, with 65 of the 138 samples containing sequences belonging to several species of the hypogeous truffle genus &lt;italic&gt;Rhizopogon&lt;/italic&gt;. Metadata, such as geospatial coordinates, for each captured small mammal can be used as a proxy for the presence or absence of &lt;italic&gt;Rhizopogon&lt;/italic&gt; species identified in their feces. Utilizing these proxy data, along with publicly available data on observation and occurrence from data repositories such as GBIF and MycoPortal, it is possible to augment our current knowledge of the extent of occurrence and area of occupancy of cryptic hypogeous fungi without direct observation, further enhancing our ability to assess their conservation status.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.460834" rel="alternate" title="On the Origin of Feces: Fungal diversity, distribution, and conservation implications from feces of small mammals (4 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461327</id><title>Explicit expression of mesophyll conductance in the traditional leaf photosynthesis–transpiration coupled model and its physiological significances (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.140538+00:00</updated><author><name>Hong Luo</name></author><author><name>Marc Carriquí</name></author><author><name>Miquel Nadal</name></author><author><name>Tuo Han</name></author><author><name>Christiane Werner</name></author><author><name>Jian-feng Huang</name></author><author><name>Jiao-lin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Zhi-guo Yu</name></author><author><name>Feng-min Li</name></author><author><name>Xiang-wen Fang</name></author><author><name>Wei Xue</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Almost all terrestrial biosphere models (TBMs) still assume infinite mesophyll conductance (&lt;italic&gt;g&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt;) to estimate photosynthesis and transpiration. This assumption has caused low accuracy of TBMs to predict leaf gas exchange under certain conditions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we developed a photosynthesis–transpiration coupled model that explicitly considers &lt;italic&gt;g&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt; and designed an optimized parameterization solution through evaluating four different &lt;italic&gt;g&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt; estimation methods in 19 C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; species at 31 experimental treatments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Temperature responses of the maximum carboxylation rate (&lt;italic&gt;V&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;cmax&lt;/sub&gt;) and the electron transport rate (&lt;italic&gt;J&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;max&lt;/sub&gt;) estimated using the Bayesian retrieval algorithm and the Sharkey online calculator and &lt;italic&gt;g&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt; temperature response estimated using the chlorophyll fluorescence–gas exchange method and anatomy method predicted leaf gas exchange better. The &lt;italic&gt;g&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt; temperature response exhibited activation energy (Δ&lt;italic&gt;H&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;a&lt;/sub&gt;) of 63.13 ± 36.89 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt; and entropy (Δ&lt;italic&gt;S&lt;/italic&gt;) of 654.49 ± 11.36 J K&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt; mol&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt;. The &lt;italic&gt;g&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt; optimal temperature (&lt;italic&gt;T&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;opt_g&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;) explained 58% of variations in photosynthesis optimal temperature (&lt;italic&gt;T&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;optA&lt;/sub&gt;). The &lt;italic&gt;g&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt; explicit expression has equally important effects on photosynthesis and transpiration estimations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Results advanced understandings of better representation of plant photosynthesis and transpiration in TBMs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461327" rel="alternate" title="Explicit expression of mesophyll conductance in the traditional leaf photosynthesis–transpiration coupled model and its physiological significances (4 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461940</id><title>Generative Adversarial Networks (GAN) for the simulation of central-place foraging trajectories (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.140755+00:00</updated><author><name>Amédée Roy</name></author><author><name>Sophie Lanco Bertrand</name></author><author><name>Ronan Fablet</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Miniature electronic device such as GPS have enabled ecologists to document relatively large amount of animal trajectories. Modeling such trajectories may attempt (1) to explain mechanisms underlying observed behaviors and (2) to elucidate ecological processes at the population scale by simulating multiple trajectories. Existing approaches to animal movement modeling mainly addressed the first objective and they are yet soon limited when used for simulation. Individual-based models based on ad-hoc formulation and empirical parametrization lack of generability, while state-space models and stochastic differential equations models, based on rigorous statistical inference, consist in 1st order Markovian models calibrated at the local scale which can lead to overly simplistic description of trajectories.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We introduce a ‘state-of-the-art’ tool from artificial intelligence - Generative Adversarial Networks (GAN) - for the simulation of animal trajectories. GAN consist in a pair of deep neural networks that aim at capturing the data distribution of some experimental dataset, and that enable the generation of new instances of data that share statistical similarity. In this study, we aim on one hand to identify relevant deep networks architecture for simulating central-place foraging trajectories and on the second hand to evaluate GAN benefits over classical methods such as state-switching Hidden Markov Models (HMM).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We demonstrate the outstanding ability of GAN to simulate ‘realistic’ seabirds foraging trajectories. In particular, we show that deep convolutional networks are more efficient than LSTM networks and that GAN-derived synthetic trajectories reproduce better the Fourier spectral density of observed trajectories than those simulated using HMM. Therefore, unlike HMM, GAN capture the variability of large-scale descriptive statistics such as foraging trips distance, duration and tortuosity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;GAN offer a relevant alternative to existing approaches to modeling animal movement since it is calibrated to reproduce multiple scales at the same time, thus freeing ecologists from the assumption of first-order markovianity. GAN also provide an ultra-flexible and robust framework that could further take environmental conditions, social interactions or even bio-energetics model into account and tackle a wide range of key challenges in movement ecology.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461940" rel="alternate" title="Generative Adversarial Networks (GAN) for the simulation of central-place foraging trajectories (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461112</id><title>Plant host shift: The viability and persistence of a polyphagous, non-native insect (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.140904+00:00</updated><author><name>Isabelle Bueno Silva</name></author><author><name>Blake McGrane-Corrigan</name></author><author><name>Oliver Mason</name></author><author><name>Rafael de Andrade Moral</name></author><author><name>Wesley Augusto Conde Godoy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Drosophila suzukii&lt;/italic&gt; (Diptera: Drosophilidae) has become a pervasive pest in several countries around the world. Many studies have investigated the preference and attractiveness of potential hosts on this invasive, polyphagous drosophilid. Thus far, no studies have investigated whether a shift of fruit host could affect its ecological viability or spatiotemporal persistence. In this study, we analysed the fecundity and oviposition period jointly with the survival time of &lt;italic&gt;D. suzukii&lt;/italic&gt; subject to a shift in host fruit, using a joint modelling method for longitudinal outcomes and time-until-event outcomes. The number of eggs laid by females was higher in raspberry than in strawberry and when setting adults of F1 generation underwent a first host shift. The joint modelling also suggested that insects reared on raspberry survived longer. We then combined experimental results with a two-patch dispersal model to investigate how host shift in a species, that exhibits both passive and density-dependent dispersal, may affect its asymptotic dynamics. In line with empirical evidence, we found that a shift in host choice can significantly affect the growth potential and fecundity of a species such as &lt;italic&gt;D. suzukii&lt;/italic&gt;, which ultimately could aid such invasive populations in their ability to persist within a changing environment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461112" rel="alternate" title="Plant host shift: The viability and persistence of a polyphagous, non-native insect (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461154</id><title>GLOBAL PATTERNS OF PLUMAGE COLOUR EVOLUTION IN ISLAND-LIVING PASSERIFORM BIRDS (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.141076+00:00</updated><author><name>Sean M. Mahoney</name></author><author><name>Madison D. Oud</name></author><author><name>Claudie Pageau</name></author><author><name>Marcio Argollo de Menezes</name></author><author><name>Nathan Smith</name></author><author><name>James V. Briskie</name></author><author><name>Matthew W. Reudink</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Plumage coloration is an important trait involved communication and is shaped by a variety of ecological pressures. Island residency has the potential to change the evolutionary trajectory of plumage colour by differences in habitat and resources, or by altering predation pressure and social selection intensity. Latitude, island size, and isolation may further influence colour evolution by biasing colonization. Therefore, general patterns of plumage evolution are difficult to disentangle. We used phylogenetically controlled analyses to assess the influence of island residency on plumage colouration, by calculating chromaticity values from red, blue, green scores extracted from photos of Order Passeriformes birds. Importantly, we controlled for ecological factors hypothesized to influence colour evolution and assessed family-level effects. We found 1) colour varied between islands and mainlands in females, but not males, and both sexes were affected by several ecological factors; 2) patterns of colour evolution varied among families; 3) island size and distance to the mainland and other islands significantly influenced colour; and 4) interactions between ecological factors and latitude were consistently influenced colour, supporting a latitudinal gradient hypothesis. Our results indicate although island residency influences female colour evolution, a myriad of ecological factors drive plumage colour and the patterns vary among families.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461154" rel="alternate" title="GLOBAL PATTERNS OF PLUMAGE COLOUR EVOLUTION IN ISLAND-LIVING PASSERIFORM BIRDS (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462347</id><title>Characterization of morpho-functional traits in mesophotic corals reveals optimized light capture and photosynthesis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.141240+00:00</updated><author><name>Netanel Kramer</name></author><author><name>Jiaao Guan</name></author><author><name>Shaochen Chen</name></author><author><name>Daniel Wangpraseurt</name></author><author><name>Yossi Loya</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The morphology and skeleton architecture of photosynthetic corals modulates the light capture and functioning of the coral-algal symbiosis on shallow-water corals. Since corals can thrive on mesophotic reefs under extreme light-limited conditions, we hypothesized that microskeletal coral features optimize light capture under low-light environments. Using micro-computed tomography scanning, we conducted a comprehensive three-dimensional (3D) assessment of small-scale skeleton morphology of the depth-generalist coral &lt;italic&gt;Stylophora pistillata&lt;/italic&gt; collected from shallow (5 m) and mesophotic (45 m) depths. We detected a high phenotypic diversity between depths, resulting in two distinct morphotypes, with calyx diameter, theca height, and corallite marginal spacing contributing to most of the variation between depths. To determine whether such depth-specific morphotypes affect coral light capture and photosynthesis on the corallite-scale, we developed 3D simulations of light propagation based on photosynthesis-irradiance parameters. We found that corals associated with shallow morphotypes dissipated excess light through self-shading microskeletal features; while mesophotic morphotypes facilitated enhanced light absorption and photosynthesis under low-light conditions. We conclude that the mesophotic coral architecture provides a greater ability to trap solar energy and efficiently exploit the limited light conditions, and suggest that morphological modifications play a key role in the photoadaptation response to low-light.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462347" rel="alternate" title="Characterization of morpho-functional traits in mesophotic corals reveals optimized light capture and photosynthesis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461266</id><title>Elevated alpha diversity in disturbed sites obscures regional decline and homogenization of amphibian diversity (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.141614+00:00</updated><author><name>D. Matthias Dehling</name></author><author><name>J. Maximilian Dehling</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Loss of natural habitat is one of the major threats for biodiversity worldwide. Habitat conversion not only changes diversity and species composition locally (alpha diversity) but might also lead to large-scale homogenization of species communities and decrease in regional species richness (gamma diversity). We investigated the effect of farmland conversion on amphibian communities in Rwanda and compared local and regional (country-wide) taxonomic, functional and phylogenetic diversity between natural and farmland sites (agricultural &lt;italic&gt;marais&lt;/italic&gt;). Alpha diversity was higher in the disturbed farmland than in natural sites. However, species turnover among farmland sites was much lower than among natural sites, resulting in highly homogenized amphibian communities and much lower country-wide taxonomic, functional and phylogenetic gamma diversity in farmland compared to natural sites. The few frog species found in farmland were mostly disturbance-tolerant species that are widespread in Eastern Africa and beyond. In contrast, most of the regionally endemic frog species that make this region a continent-scale hotspot of amphibian diversity were found only in the natural habitats. Ongoing farmland conversion might lead to a loss of regional endemism and a widespread homogenization of species communities across sub-Saharan Africa.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461266" rel="alternate" title="Elevated alpha diversity in disturbed sites obscures regional decline and homogenization of amphibian diversity (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461405</id><title>Metacommunity research can benefit from including context-dependency (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.141893+00:00</updated><author><name>Jurek Kolasa</name></author><author><name>Matthew P. Hammond</name></author><author><name>Joyce Yan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Context-dependency, C-D, of outcomes occurs when several factors affect a focal metric. Remedies for treating milder cases of C-D are readily available but severe cases, where some contributory factors cause non-linear changes in others, escaped routine scrutiny. This poses a universal challenge to standard research strategies. We suggest that metacommunity framework may be particularly vulnerable because its core notions (habitat structure, dispersal, and species interactions) are functionally entangled. When these notions are generalized to include many species and situations, they become interdependent. To illustrate the significance of such interdependence, we test two hypotheses. One that &lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;holding combination of parameters constant in all but one dimension, can alter inference of a study&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt; and the second that the &lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;severity of&lt;/italic&gt; c&lt;italic&gt;ontext-dependency increases when core metacommunity dimensions interact and transform one another through a variety of mechanisms&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt;. The results support these ideas and imply that C-D predicts a dauntingly vast space of possible empirical outcomes and interpretations, most of which can arise from reciprocal interactions among metacommunity core dimensions. We proffer that an adaptable and structured use of macro-variables is a place to start investigating metacommunity mechanisms more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461405" rel="alternate" title="Metacommunity research can benefit from including context-dependency (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461654</id><title>Coat color mismatch improves survival of a keystone boreal herbivore: energetic advantages exceed lost camouflage (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.142130+00:00</updated><author><name>Joanie L. Kennah</name></author><author><name>Michael J. L. Peers</name></author><author><name>Eric Vander Wal</name></author><author><name>Yasmine N. Majchrzak</name></author><author><name>Allyson K. Menzies</name></author><author><name>Emily K. Studd</name></author><author><name>Rudy Boonstra</name></author><author><name>Murray M. Humphries</name></author><author><name>Thomas S. Jung</name></author><author><name>Alice J. Kenney</name></author><author><name>Charles J. Krebs</name></author><author><name>Stan Boutin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Climate warming is causing asynchronies between animal phenology and environments. Mismatched traits, like coat color change mismatched with snow, can decrease survival. However, coat change does not serve a singular adaptive benefit of camouflage, and alternate coat change functions may confer advantages that supersede mismatch costs. We found that mismatch reduced rather than increased, autumn mortality risk of snowshoe hares in Yukon by 86.5 %. We suggest that the increased coat insulation and lower metabolic rates of winter acclimatized hares confer energetic advantages to white mismatched hares that reduce their mortality risk. We found that white mismatched hares forage 17-77 minutes less per day than matched brown hares between 0 and -10 °C, thus lowering their predation risk and increasing survival. We found no effect of mismatch on spring mortality risk, where mismatch occurred at warmer temperatures, suggesting a potential temperature limit where the costs of conspicuousness outweigh energetic benefits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461654" rel="alternate" title="Coat color mismatch improves survival of a keystone boreal herbivore: energetic advantages exceed lost camouflage (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462815</id><title>Effects of productive management of an agroforestry system on the associated diversity of parasitoids (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.142474+00:00</updated><author><name>Cecilia Marisol Pech Cutis</name></author><author><name>Luis Enrique Castillo Sánchez</name></author><author><name>Jorge Rodolfo Canul Solís</name></author><author><name>Ermilo López Coba</name></author><author><name>Nery Maria Ruz Febles</name></author><author><name>Maria Jose Campos-Navarrete</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tropical agroecosystems have emerged from the continuous modification of natural environments, as a sustainability alternative for food production and biodiversity conservation. This work explores how the diversity of parasitoids is modified in environments where plant diversity is limited e.g. crops and when these are adjacent to secondary vegetation, i.e. a scenario fragmented continuously in a limited space. It was found that there is no direct effect of plant diversity in the group of parasitoids studied; but the number of specialist species is high, which indicates that in diversified agroecosystems these probably function as remnants of natural habitat or as a refuge for parasitoids that disperse to different types of management within the agroecosystem. Therefore, it is necessary to consider in future studies the controls exerted by the plant diversity effects bottom-up and consumer top-down. Adding to this the context of the interactions that occur in agroecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462815" rel="alternate" title="Effects of productive management of an agroforestry system on the associated diversity of parasitoids (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461702</id><title>Mammals adjust diel activity across gradients of urbanization (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.142686+00:00</updated><author><name>Travis Gallo</name></author><author><name>Mason Fidino</name></author><author><name>Brian Gerber</name></author><author><name>Adam A. Ahlers</name></author><author><name>Julia L. Angstmann</name></author><author><name>Max Amaya</name></author><author><name>Amy L. Concilio</name></author><author><name>David Drake</name></author><author><name>Danielle Gray</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth W. Lehrer</name></author><author><name>Maureen H. Murray</name></author><author><name>Travis J. Ryan</name></author><author><name>Colleen Cassady St. Clair</name></author><author><name>Carmen M. Salsbury</name></author><author><name>Heather A. Sander</name></author><author><name>Theodore Stankowich</name></author><author><name>Jacque Williamson</name></author><author><name>J. Amy Belaire</name></author><author><name>Kelly Simon</name></author><author><name>Seth B. Magle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Time is a fundamental component of ecological processes. How animal behavior changes over time has been explored through well-known ecological theories like niche partitioning and predator-prey dynamics. Yet, changes in animal behavior within the shorter 24-hour light-dark cycle have largely gone unstudied. Understanding if an animal can adjust their temporal activity to mitigate or adapt to environmental change has become a recent topic of discussion and is important for effective wildlife management and conservation. While spatial habitat is a fundamental consideration in wildlife management and conservation, temporal habitat is often ignored. We formulated a temporal resource selection model to quantify the diel behavior of eight mammal species across ten U.S. cities. We found high variability in diel activity patterns within and among species and species-specific correlations between diel activity and human population density, impervious land cover, available greenspace, vegetation cover, and mean daily temperature. We also found that some species may modulate temporal behaviors to manage both natural and anthropogenic risks. Our results highlight the complexity with which temporal activity patterns interact with local environmental characteristics, and suggest that urban mammals may use time along the 24-hour cycle to reduce risk, adapt, and therefore persist in human-dominated ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461702" rel="alternate" title="Mammals adjust diel activity across gradients of urbanization (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461896</id><title>Using trait data improves correlation between environment and community data only if abundances are considered (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.144516+00:00</updated><author><name>Attila Lengyel</name></author><author><name>Sándor Barabás</name></author><author><name>Boglárka Berki</name></author><author><name>Anikó Csecserits</name></author><author><name>Adrienn Gyalus</name></author><author><name>Barbara Lhotsky</name></author><author><name>Gábor Ónodi</name></author><author><name>Tamás Rédei</name></author><author><name>Zoltán Botta-Dukát</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A straightforward way to explore variation between communities is to calculate dissimilarity indices and relate them with environmental and spatial variables. Communities are most often represented by the (relative) abundances of taxa they comprise; however, more recently, the distribution of traits of organisms included in the communities has been shown more strongly related to ecosystem properties. In this study, we test whether taxon- or trait-based dissimilarity is correlated more tightly with environmental difference and geographical distance and how the abundance scale influences this correlation. Our study system is grassland vegetation in Hungary, where we sampled vegetation plots spanning a long productivity gradient from open dry grasslands to marshes in three sites. We considered three traits for vascular plants: canopy height, specific leaf area and seed mass. We obtained field estimates of normalized vegetation difference index (NDVI) as proxy of productivity (water availability) for each plot. We calculated between-community dissimilarities using a taxon-based and a trait-based index, using raw and square-root transformed abundances and presence/absence data. We fitted distance-based redundancy analysis models with NDVI difference and geographical distance on the dissimilarity matrices and evaluated them using variance partitioning. Then, using the pooled data, we calculated non-metric multidimensional scaling ordinations (NMDS) from all types of dissimilarity matrices and made pairwise comparisons using Procrustes analysis. Data analysis was done separately for the three sites.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found that taxonomical dissimilarity matches environmental and spatial variables better when presence/absence data is used instead of abundance. This pattern was mainly determined by the increasing variation explained by space at the presence/absence scale. In contrast to this trend, with trait-based dissimilarity, accounting for abundance increased explained variation significantly due to the higher explanatory power of NDVI. With abundance data, considering traits improved environmental matching to a great extent in comparison with taxonomical information. However, with presence/absence data, traits brought no advantage over taxon-based dissimilarity in any respect. Changing the abundance scale caused larger difference between ordinations in the case of trait-based dissimilarity than with taxonomical dissimilarity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conclude that considering relevant traits improves environmental matching only if abundances are also accounted for.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Supporting information&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additional graphs supporting the results are presented as appendix.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Open research&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Data used in this research are publicly available from Dryad ###link to be supplied upon acceptance###&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461896" rel="alternate" title="Using trait data improves correlation between environment and community data only if abundances are considered (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461499</id><title>From trend to threat? Assessing the sustainability of wild edible plant foraging by linking local perception to ecological inference (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.144844+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicolas J. Giraud</name></author><author><name>Anneleen Kool</name></author><author><name>Pål Karlsen</name></author><author><name>Alexis Annes</name></author><author><name>Irene Teixidor-Toneu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Wild edible plants as culturally-appropriate sources of nutrition and for food security are now well-recognised. In Europe, the use of wild edible plants is shifting from a subsistence activity to an emerging trend in high-end gastronomy. The environmental impacts of this shift are poorly known. Foraging is increasingly popular for personal consumption and commercially, not least in the Nordic countries where popularity is fuelled by the New Nordic Food movement. Here, we evaluate if this trend entails biodiversity conservation risks in Norway. In collaboration with the Norwegian Association for Mycology and Foraging, we conducted 18 face-to-face interviews with key stakeholders and we published an online questionnaire filled by 219 recreational and professional foragers. We enquired on what species are harvested, by whom and how, where do foragers learn and what are their perspectives on the sustainability of foraging. We combined these data with an assessment of foraging impact based on foraging pressure, ecological traits and conservation assessments. Our results show that 272 different wild edible plants are foraged and that this is mostly sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, some risks arise from the harvest of threatened plants, the potential spread of invasive species, and the overharvesting of extremely popular or ‘fashionable’ species. Foraging fosters a strong connection with the natural environment and the majority of foragers report to forage as part of a sustainable lifestyle. We suggest that careful encouragement to forage and the participatory development of local guidelines for sustainable foraging in Norway can enhance people-nature relationships while safeguarding foraged plant populations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461499" rel="alternate" title="From trend to threat? Assessing the sustainability of wild edible plant foraging by linking local perception to ecological inference (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>