<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv ecology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.444300+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/ecology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445290</id><title>Language barriers in global bird conservation (40 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.444699+00:00</updated><author><name>Pablo Jose Negret</name></author><author><name>Scott C. Atkinson</name></author><author><name>Bradley K. Woodworth</name></author><author><name>Marina Corella Tor</name></author><author><name>James R. Allan</name></author><author><name>Richard A. Fuller</name></author><author><name>Tatsuya Amano</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Multiple languages being spoken within a species’ distribution can impede communication among conservation stakeholders, the compilation of scientific information, and the development of effective conservation actions. Here, we investigate the number of official languages spoken within the distributions of 10,863 bird species to identify which ones might be particularly affected by consequences of language barriers. We show that 1587 species have 10 languages or more spoken within their distributions. Threatened, migratory and wide-ranging species have especially many languages spoken within their distribution. Particularly high numbers of species with many languages within their distribution are found in Eastern Europe, Russia and central and western Asia. Global conservation efforts would benefit from implementing guidelines to overcome language barriers, especially in regions with high species and language diversity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445290" rel="alternate" title="Language barriers in global bird conservation (40 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445402</id><title>Modeling the effects of Aedes aegypti’s larval environment on adult body mass at emergence (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.445098+00:00</updated><author><name>Melody Walker</name></author><author><name>Karthikeyan Chandrasegaran</name></author><author><name>Clément Vinauger</name></author><author><name>Michael A Robert</name></author><author><name>Lauren M Childs</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mosquitoes vector harmful pathogens that infect millions of people every year, and developing approaches to effectively control mosquitoes is a topic of great interest. However, the success of many control measures is highly dependent upon ecological, physiological, and life history traits of the mosquito species. The behavior of mosquitoes and their potential to vector pathogens can also be impacted by these traits. One trait of interest is mosquito body mass, which depends upon many factors associated with the environment in which juvenile mosquitoes develop. Our experiments examined the impact of larval density on the body mass of &lt;italic&gt;Aedes aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; mosquitoes, which are important vectors of dengue, Zika, yellow fever, and other pathogens. To investigate the interactions between the larval environment and mosquito body mass, we built a discrete time mathematical model that incorporates body mass, larval density, and food availability and fit the model to our experimental data. We considered three categories of model complexity informed by data, and selected the best model within each category using Akaike’s Information Criterion. We found that the larval environment is an important determinant of the body mass of mosquitoes upon emergence. Furthermore, we found that larval density has greater impact on body mass of adults at emergence than on development time, and that inclusion of density dependence in the survival of female aquatic stages in models is important. We discuss the implications of our results for the control of &lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; mosquitoes and on their potential to spread disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this work we examined how the environment in which young mosquitoes develop affects their adult body size as measured by adult body mass. Adult size has potential impacts on mosquito behavior and the ability of mosquitoes to transmit disease. We used a combination of experimental work and mathematical modeling to determine important factors affecting adult mosquito body size. In our model, we incorporated potentially interacting aspects of the mosquito life cycle and traits that affect mosquito growth as juveniles. These aspects include body mass, density of the population, and level of available resource. We compared different models to determine the one that best describes the data. As mass at emergence is linked to the success of adult mosquitoes to produce offspring and to their ability transmit pathogens, we discuss how important influences on development and survival of young mosquitoes affect mosquito control and disease spread.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445402" rel="alternate" title="Modeling the effects of Aedes aegypti’s larval environment on adult body mass at emergence (6 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>