<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular ecology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.235224+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/ecology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472649</id><title>Areas Important for Ecological Connectivity Throughout Canada (70 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.235656+00:00</updated><author><name>Richard Pither</name></author><author><name>Paul O'Brien</name></author><author><name>Angela Brennan</name></author><author><name>Kristen Hirsh-Pearson</name></author><author><name>Jeff Bowman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Governments around the world have acknowledged the importance of conserving ecological connectivity to help reverse the decline of biodiversity. In this study we employed recent methodological developments in circuit theory to conduct the first pan-Canadian analysis of multi-species connectivity for all terrestrial regions of the country, at a spatial grain sufficient to support local land-management decisions. We developed a movement cost surface with a limited number of thematic categories using the most recently updated land cover data available for the country. We divided the country into 17 tiles and used a wall-to-wall, omnidirectional mode of Circuitscape on each tile in order to assess ecological connectivity throughout entire landscapes as opposed to strictly among protected areas. The resulting raw current density map of Canada revealed heterogenous patterns of current density across the country, strongly influenced by geography, natural barriers, and human development. We included a validation analysis of the output current density map with independent wildlife data from across the country and found that mammal and herpetofauna locations were predicted by areas of high current density. We believe our current density map can be used to identify areas important for connectivity throughout Canada and thereby contribute to efforts to conserve biodiversity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472649" rel="alternate" title="Areas Important for Ecological Connectivity Throughout Canada (70 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.469125</id><title>imageseg: an R package for deep learning-based image segmentation (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.235949+00:00</updated><author><name>Jürgen Niedballa</name></author><author><name>Jan Axtner</name></author><author><name>Timm Fabian Döbert</name></author><author><name>Andrew Tilker</name></author><author><name>An Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Seth Timothy Wong</name></author><author><name>Christian Fiderer</name></author><author><name>Marco Heurich</name></author><author><name>Andreas Wilting</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Convolutional neural networks (CNNs) and deep learning are powerful and robust tools for ecological applications. CNNs can perform very well in various tasks, especially for visual tasks and image data. Image segmentation (the classification of all pixels in images) is one such task and can for example be used to assess forest vertical and horizontal structure. While such methods have been suggested, widespread adoption in ecological research has been slow, likely due to technical difficulties in implementation of CNNs and lack of toolboxes for ecologists. Here, we present R package imageseg which implements a workflow for general-purpose image segmentation using CNNs and the U-Net architecture in R. The workflow covers data (pre)processing, model training, and predictions. We illustrate the utility of the package with two models for forest structural metrics: tree canopy density and understory vegetation density. We trained the models using large and diverse training data sets from a variety of forest types and biomes, consisting of 3288 canopy images (both canopy cover and hemispherical canopy closure photographs) and 1468 understory vegetation images. Overall classification accuracy of the models was high with a Dice score of 0.91 for the canopy model and 0.89 for the understory vegetation model (assessed with 821 and 367 images, respectively), indicating robustness to variation in input images and good generalization strength across forest types and biomes. The package and its workflow allow simple yet powerful assessments of forest structural metrics using pre-trained models. Furthermore, the package facilitates custom image segmentation with multiple classes and based on color or grayscale images, e.g. in cell biology or for medical images. Our package is free, open source, and available from CRAN. It will enable easier and faster implementation of deep learning-based image segmentation within R for ecological applications and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.469125" rel="alternate" title="imageseg: an R package for deep learning-based image segmentation (17 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472652</id><title>Using Piecewise Regression to Identify Biological Phenomena in Biotelemetry Datasets (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.236171+00:00</updated><author><name>David Wolfson</name></author><author><name>John Fieberg</name></author><author><name>David E Andersen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Technological advances in the field of animal tracking have greatly expanded the potential to remotely monitor animals, opening the door to exploring how animals shift their behavior over time or respond to external stimuli. A wide variety of animal-borne sensors can provide information on an animal's location, movement characteristics, external environmental conditions, and internal physiological status. Here, we demonstrate how piecewise regression can be used to identify the presence and timing of potential shifts in a variety of biological responses using GPS telemetry and other biologging data streams. Different biological latent states can be inferred by partitioning a time-series into multiple segments based on changes in modeled responses (e.g., their mean, variance, trend, degree of autocorrelation) and specifying a unique model structure for each interval. We provide five example applications highlighting a variety of taxonomic species, data streams, timescales, and biological phenomena. These examples include a short-term behavioral response (flee and return) by a trumpeter swan (Cygnus buccinator) immediately following a GPS collar deployment; remote identification of parturition based on movements by a pregnant moose (Alces alces); a physiological response (spike in heart-rate) in a black bear (Ursus americanus) to a stressful stimulus (presence of a drone); a mortality event of a trumpeter swan signaled by changes in collar temperature and Overall Dynamic Body Acceleration; and an unsupervised method for identifying the onset, return, duration, and staging use of sandhill crane (Antigone canadensis) migration. We implement analyses using the mcp package in R, which provides functionality for specifying and fitting a wide variety of user-defined model structures in a Bayesian framework and methods for assessing and comparing models using information criterion and cross-validation measures. This approach uses simple modeling approaches that are accessible to a wide audience and is a straightforward means of assessing a variety of biologically relevant changes in animal behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472652" rel="alternate" title="Using Piecewise Regression to Identify Biological Phenomena in Biotelemetry Datasets (9 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.30.458238</id><title>Transient population dynamics drive the spread of invasive wild pigs in North America (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.236351+00:00</updated><author><name>Ryan S Miller</name></author><author><name>Michael A Tabak</name></author><author><name>Christopher L Burdett</name></author><author><name>David W Wolfson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Invasion of nonindigenous species is considered one of the most urgent problems affecting native ecosystems and agricultural systems. Mechanistic models that account for short-term population dynamics can improve prediction because they incorporate differing demographic processes that link the environmental conditions of a spatial location explicitly with the invasion process. Yet short-term population dynamics are rarely accounted for in spatial models of invasive species spread.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accounting for transient population dynamics, we predict the population growth rate and establishment probability of wild pigs following introduction into any location in North America. We compared predicted population growth rate with observed geographic rates of spread and found significant relationships between the annual rate of spread and population growth rates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used geospatial data on the distribution of mast producing tree species (a principle forage resource of wild pigs) and agricultural crops that can replace mast in their diets to predict population dynamics using transient population simulations. We simulated populations under different initial population sizes (i.e. number of introduced individuals, often termed propagule size) and for different amounts of time following introduction. By varying the initial population size and simulation time, we were able to identify areas in North America with high probability for establishment of wild pigs if introduced. Our findings can be used to inform surveillance and removal efforts to reduce the potential for establishment and spread of wild pigs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.30.458238" rel="alternate" title="Transient population dynamics drive the spread of invasive wild pigs in North America (9 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472579</id><title>Effects of habitat destruction on coevolving metacommunities (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.236590+00:00</updated><author><name>Klementyna A. Gawecka</name></author><author><name>Fernando Pedraza</name></author><author><name>Jordi Bascompte</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Habitat destruction is a growing threat to biodiversity and ecosystem services. The ecological consequences of habitat loss and fragmentation involve reductions in species abundance and even the extinction of species and interactions. However, we do not yet understand how habitat loss can alter the coevolutionary trajectories of the remaining species or how coevolution, in turn, affects their response to habitat loss. To investigate this, we develop a spatially explicit model which couples metacommunity and coevolutionary dynamics. We show that, by changing the size, composition and structure of local networks, habitat destruction increases the diversity of coevolutionary outcomes across the landscape. Furthermore, we show that while coevolution dampens the negative effects of habitat destruction in mutualistic networks, its effects on the persistence of antagonistic communities are less predictable.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472579" rel="alternate" title="Effects of habitat destruction on coevolving metacommunities (6 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.472105</id><title>Following the track: accuracy and reproducibility of predation assessment on artificial caterpillars (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.236721+00:00</updated><author><name>Elena Valdés Correcher</name></author><author><name>Elina Mäntylä</name></author><author><name>Luc Barbaro</name></author><author><name>Thomas Damestoy</name></author><author><name>Katerina Sam</name></author><author><name>Bastien Castagneyrol</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Experimental studies of biotic interactions in real field conditions are essential to understand the structure and functioning of ecological networks. The use of artificial caterpillars to mimic actual prey availability is generally seen as a standard approach to compare the activity and diversity of predators along environmental gradients. Yet, even with standardized material and procedures, biases may still affect data from multiple observers with different expertise. We used pictures of artificial caterpillars with or without various predation marks, in an online survey that was targeted for the participants of the project, to evaluate the reliability of predation marks identification made by non-scientists and by scientists with and without previous experience in predation mark identification. Pictures of artificial caterpillars displayed typical marks left by birds, mammals and arthropods, as well as non-predation marks (‘false positive’). 357 respondents scanned 7140 pictures of these pictures. Self-declared scientists were more confident and accurate in their observations than non-scientists, but the differences in correct identifications among scientists and non-scientists were low. Self-declared scientists with previous experience were also more accurate than scientists without previous experience, while there were no differences in self-confidence among scientists with and without previous experience. Accuracy in predation mark identification did not differ among types of predators, but respondents were more keen to identify marks left by birds or mammals than arthropods. Our results have practical implications for the design of multi-observer projects relying on artificial caterpillars as a proxy to assess predation intensity, in particular in the context of citizen science.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.472105" rel="alternate" title="Following the track: accuracy and reproducibility of predation assessment on artificial caterpillars (5 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472743</id><title>Nest aggregations of wild bees and apoid wasps in urban pavements: a street life to be promoted in urban planning (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.236936+00:00</updated><author><name>Gregoire Noel</name></author><author><name>Violette Van Keymeulen</name></author><author><name>Yvan Barbier</name></author><author><name>Sylvie Smets</name></author><author><name>Olivier Van Damme</name></author><author><name>Gilles Colinet</name></author><author><name>Julien Ruelle</name></author><author><name>Frederic Francis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the last 10 years, knowledges of wild bees and apoid wasps community dynamics have gained interest in urban ecology focusing on the availability of floral resources in cities. Although understudied, the urban environment impacts the conditions of their nesting sites. Recent observations in the Brussels-Capital Region (Belgium) showed that urban pavements can be a novel nesting opportunity for Hymenoptera ground-nesting species such as wild bees and apoid wasps. Here, using citizen science, we investigated the richness of ground-nesting species living under urban pavements, the preferences of the sidewalk joint size related to ground-nesting species size and for sidewalk type or for soils texture under the pavements on the nesting site selection. A total of 22 species belonging to 10 Hymenoptera families of wild bees and digger wasps with their associated kleptoparasites were identified on 89 sites in Brussels. Sandstone setts or concrete slabs with an unbound joint size around 1 cm were found to be best suitable urban pavements for the ground-nesting species. The soil texture under the pavement was highly sandy among our samples. Finally, we also suggest engineering management guidelines to support bee and wasp species nesting under urban pavement in highly urbanized areas. Such observations pave the way for much research in the field of urban ecology to conceive multifunctional pavement promoting biodiversity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472743" rel="alternate" title="Nest aggregations of wild bees and apoid wasps in urban pavements: a street life to be promoted in urban planning (5 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472442</id><title>Using deep convolutional neural networks to forecast spatial patterns of Amazonian deforestation (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.237154+00:00</updated><author><name>James Ball</name></author><author><name>Katerina Petrova</name></author><author><name>David A. Coomes</name></author><author><name>Seth Flaxman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tropical forests are subject to diverse deforestation pressures but their conservation is essential to achieve global climate goals. Predicting the location of deforestation is challenging due to the complexity of the natural and human systems involved but accurate and timely forecasts could enable effective planning and on-the-ground enforcement practices to curb deforestation rates. New computer vision technologies based on deep learning can be applied to the increasing volume of Earth observation data to generate novel insights and make predictions with unprecedented accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we demonstrate the ability of deep convolutional neural networks to learn spatiotemporal patterns of deforestation from a limited set of freely available global data layers, including multispectral satellite imagery, the Hansen maps of historic deforestation (2001-2020) and the ALOS JAXA digital surface model, to forecast future deforestation (2021). We designed four original deep learning model architectures, based on 2D Convolutional Neural Networks (2DCNN), 3D Convolutional Neural Networks (3DCNN), and Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) Recurrent Neural Networks (RNN) to produce spatial maps that indicate the risk to each forested pixel (~30 m) in the landscape of becoming deforested within the next year. They were trained and tested on data from two ~80,000 km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; tropical forest regions in the Southern Peruvian Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found that the networks could predict the likely location of future deforestation to a high degree of accuracy. Our best performing model – a 3DCNN – had the highest pixel-wise accuracy (80-90%) when validated on 2020 deforestation based 2014-2019 training. Visual examination of the forecasts indicated that the 3DCNN network could automatically discern the drivers of forest loss from the input data. For example, pixels around new access routes (e.g. roads) were assigned high risk whereas this was not the case for recent, concentrated natural loss events (e.g. remote landslides).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;CNNs can harness limited time-series data to predict near-future deforestation patterns, an important step in using the growing volume of satellite remote sensing data to curb global deforestation. The modelling framework can be readily applied to any tropical forest location and used by governments and conservation organisations to prevent deforestation and plan protected areas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472442" rel="alternate" title="Using deep convolutional neural networks to forecast spatial patterns of Amazonian deforestation (5 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472788</id><title>Macrogenetics reveals multifaceted influences of environmental variation on vertebrate population genetic diversity across the Americas (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.237310+00:00</updated><author><name>Elizabeth R Lawrence</name></author><author><name>Dylan J Fraser</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Relative to species diversity gradients, the broad scale distribution of population-specific genetic diversity (PGD) across taxa remains understudied. We used nuclear DNA data collected from 6285 vertebrate populations across the Americas to assess the role environmental variables play in structuring the spatial/latitudinal distribution of PGD, a key component of adaptive potential in the face of environmental change. Our results provide key evidence for taxa-specific responses and that temperature variability in addition to mean temperature may be a primary driver of PGD. Additionally, we found some positive influence of precipitation, productivity, and elevation on PGD; identified trends were dependent on the metric of PGD. In contrast to the classic negative relationship between species diversity and latitude, we report either a positive or taxa-dependent relationship between PGD and latitude, depending on the metric of PGD. The inconsistent latitudinal gradient in different metrics of PGD may be due to opposing processes diminishing patterns across latitudes that operate on different timescales, as well as the flattening of large-scale genetic gradients when assessing across species versus within species. Our study highlights the nuance required to assess broad patterns in genetic diversity, and the need for developing balanced conservation strategies that ensure population, species, and community persistence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472788" rel="alternate" title="Macrogenetics reveals multifaceted influences of environmental variation on vertebrate population genetic diversity across the Americas (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473117</id><title>LONG-TERM MONITORING OF THE EUROPEAN ROLLER (CORACIAS GARRULUS) IN UKRAINE: IS CLIMATE BEHIND THE CHANGES? (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.237517+00:00</updated><author><name>Tatiana Shupova</name></author><author><name>Volodymyr Tytar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Since the 1980s there has been a long-term decline in numbers and contraction of range in Europe, including Ukraine. Our specific goals were to reconstruct the climatically suitable range of the species in Ukraine before the 1980s,  gain better knowledge on its requirements,  compare the past and current suitable areas, infer the regional and environmental variables that best explain its occurrence, and quantify the overall range change in the country. For these purposes we created a database consisting of 347 records of the roller made ever in Ukraine. We employed a species distribution modeling (SDM) approach to hindcast changes in the suitable range of the roller during historical times across Ukraine and to derive spatially explicit predictions of climatic suitability for the species under current climate. SDMs were created for three time intervals (before 1980, 1985-2009, 2010-2021) using corresponding climate data extracted from the TerraClim database. SDMs show a decline of suitable for rollers areas in the country from 85 to 46%. Several factors, including land cover and use, human population density and climate, that could have contributed to the decline of the species in Ukraine were considered. We suggest climate change and its speed (velocity) have been responsible for shaping the contemporary home range of the European roller. Key words: Coracias garrulus; species distribution modelling; ecological niche; climate change; velocity of climate change&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473117" rel="alternate" title="LONG-TERM MONITORING OF THE EUROPEAN ROLLER (CORACIAS GARRULUS) IN UKRAINE: IS CLIMATE BEHIND THE CHANGES? (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472362</id><title>Combining δ13C and δ15N from bone and dentine in marine mammal palaeoecological research: insights from toothed whales (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.237701+00:00</updated><author><name>Alba Rey-Iglesia</name></author><author><name>Tess Wilson</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Routledge</name></author><author><name>Mikkel Skovrind</name></author><author><name>Eva Garde</name></author><author><name>Mads Peter Heide-Jørgensen</name></author><author><name>Paul Szpak</name></author><author><name>Eline D. Lorenzen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Stable carbon (δ&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C) and nitrogen (δ&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;N) isotope compositions of bone and dentine collagen extracted from museum specimens have been widely used to study the paleoecology of past populations. Due to possible systematic differences in stable isotope values between bone and dentine, dentine values can be transformed into bone-collagen equivalent using a correction factor. Here, we provide correction factors to transform dentine δ&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C and δ&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;N values into bone-collagen equivalent for two toothed whales: narwhal and beluga. We sampled bone and tooth dentine from the skulls of 11 narwhals and 26 belugas. In narwhals, dentine was sampled from tusk and embedded tooth; in beluga, dentine was sampled from tooth. δ&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C and δ&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;N were measured and intraindividual bone and dentine isotopic compositions were used to calculate correction factors for each species. We detected differences in δ&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C and δ&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;N. In narwhals, we found (i) lower average δ&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C and δ&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;N in bone compared with dentine; (ii) no difference in dentine δ&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C between tusk and embedded tooth. For belugas, we also detected lower δ&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C and δ&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;N in bone compared with tooth dentine. The correction factors provided by the study enable the combined analysis of stable isotope data from bone and dentine in these species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472362" rel="alternate" title="Combining δ13C and δ15N from bone and dentine in marine mammal palaeoecological research: insights from toothed whales (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>