<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular ecology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.919005+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/ecology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468467</id><title>Siderophores as an iron source for Prochlorococcus in deep chlorophyll maximum layers of the oligotrophic ocean (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.919934+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane L Hogle</name></author><author><name>Thomas Hackl</name></author><author><name>Randelle M Bundy</name></author><author><name>Jiwoon Park</name></author><author><name>Brandon Satinsky</name></author><author><name>Teppo Hiltunen</name></author><author><name>Steven Biller</name></author><author><name>Paul M Berube</name></author><author><name>Sallie W Chisholm</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Prochlorococcus&lt;/italic&gt; is one of the most abundant photosynthesizing organisms in the oligotrophic oceans. Gene content variation among &lt;italic&gt;Prochlorococcus&lt;/italic&gt; populations in separate ocean basins often mirrors the selective pressures imposed by the region's distinct biogeochemistry. By pairing genomic datasets with trace metal concentrations from across the global ocean, we show that the genomic capacity for siderophore-mediated iron uptake is widespread in low-light adapted &lt;italic&gt;Prochlorococcus&lt;/italic&gt; populations from iron-depleted regions of the oligotrophic Pacific and S. Atlantic oceans: &lt;italic&gt;Prochlorococcus&lt;/italic&gt; siderophore consumers were absent in the N. Atlantic ocean (higher iron flux) but constituted up to half of all &lt;italic&gt;Prochlorococcus&lt;/italic&gt; genomes from metagenomes in the N. Pacific (lower iron flux). &lt;italic&gt;Prochlorococcus&lt;/italic&gt; siderophore consumers, like many other bacteria with this trait, also lack siderophore biosynthesis genes indicating that they scavenge exogenous siderophores from seawater. Statistical modeling suggests that the capacity for siderophore uptake is endemic to remote ocean regions where atmospheric iron fluxes are the smallest, particularly at deep chlorophyll maximum and primary nitrite maximum layers. We argue that abundant siderophore consumers at these two common oceanographic features could be a symptom of wider community iron stress, consistent with prior hypotheses. Our results provide a clear example of iron as a selective force driving the evolution of &lt;italic&gt;Prochlorococcus&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468467" rel="alternate" title="Siderophores as an iron source for Prochlorococcus in deep chlorophyll maximum layers of the oligotrophic ocean (8 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.467958</id><title>A quantitative synthesis of soil microbial effects on plant species coexistence (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.920730+00:00</updated><author><name>Xinyi Yan</name></author><author><name>Jonathan M. Levine</name></author><author><name>Gaurav S. Kandlikar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Soil microorganisms play a major role in shaping plant diversity, not only through their direct effects as pathogens, mutualists, and decomposers, but also by altering interactions between plants. In particular, previous research has shown that the soil community often generates frequency-dependent feedback loops among plants that can either destabilize species interactions, or generate stabilizing niche differences that promote species coexistence. However, recent insights from modern coexistence theory have shown that microbial effects on plant coexistence depend not only on these stabilizing or destabilizing effects, but also on the degree to which they generate competitive fitness differences. While many previous experiments have generated the data necessary for evaluating microbially mediated fitness differences, these effects have rarely been quantified in the literature. Here we present a meta-analysis of data from 50 studies, which we used to quantify the microbially mediated (de)stabilization and fitness differences derived from a classic plant-soil feedback model. Across 518 pairwise comparisons, we found that soil microbes generated both stabilization (or destabilization) and fitness differences, but also that the microbially mediated fitness differences dominated. As a consequence, if plants are otherwise equivalent competitors, the balance of soil microbe-generated (de)stabilization and fitness differences drives species exclusion much more frequently than coexistence or priority effects. Our work shows that microbially mediated fitness differences are an important but overlooked effect of soil microbes on plant coexistence. This finding paves the way for a more complete understanding of the processes that maintain plant biodiversity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.467958" rel="alternate" title="A quantitative synthesis of soil microbial effects on plant species coexistence (6 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468021</id><title>Foraging behavior and patch size distribution jointly determine population dynamics in fragmented landscapes (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.920982+00:00</updated><author><name>Johannes Nauta</name></author><author><name>Pieter Simoens</name></author><author><name>Yara Khaluf</name></author><author><name>Ricardo Martinez-Garcia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Increased fragmentation caused by habitat loss presents a major threat to the persistence of animal populations. Whereas the negative effects of habitat loss on biodiversity are well-known, the effects of fragmentation &lt;italic&gt;per se&lt;/italic&gt; on population dynamics and ecosystem stability remain less understood. How fragmentation affects populations is strongly determined by the rate at which individuals can move between separated habitat patches within the fragmented landscape. Here, we use a computational, spatially explicit predator-prey model to investigate how the interplay between fragmentation &lt;italic&gt;per se&lt;/italic&gt; and optimal foraging behavior influences predator-prey interactions and, ultimately, ecosystem stability. We study cases where prey occupies isolated habitat patches and let predators disperse between patches following a Lévy random walk. Our results show that both the Lévy exponent and the degree of fragmentation strongly determine coexistence probabilities. Brownian and ballistic predators go extinct in highly fragmented landscapes and only scale-free predators can coexist with prey. Furthermore, our results reveal that predation causes irreversible loss of prey habitat in highly fragmented landscapes due to the overexploitation of smaller patches. Moreover, our results show that predator movement can reduce, but not prevent nor minimize, the amount of irreversibly lost habitat. Our results suggest that incorporating optimal foraging theory into population- and landscape ecology models is crucial to assess the impact of fragmentation on biodiversity and ecosystem stability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Long-term persistence of species in fragmented landscapes critically depends on the ability of individuals to find and exploit patches rich in resources. Here, we use a computational model to investigate how the interplay between predator movement behavior and habitat fragmentation can stabilize predator-prey dynamics. We assume predators exhibit optimal foraging behavior and find that Brownian and ballistic predators go extinct in highly fragmented landscapes, whereas predators that perform scale-free Lévy walk movement persist. Furthermore, we show that scale-free movement additionally reduces irreversible habitat loss caused by local predation. Our results suggest that incorporating optimal foraging behavior into population-based models is essential to assess the impact of fragmentation on species’ persistence, loss of habitat, and ecosystem stability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468021" rel="alternate" title="Foraging behavior and patch size distribution jointly determine population dynamics in fragmented landscapes (4 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468474</id><title>Investigating Increased CO2 concentration on the pH of various plant species (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.921242+00:00</updated><author><name>Joshua Schafer</name></author><author><name>Troy Puga</name></author><author><name>Pearce Harris</name></author><author><name>Nora Strasser</name></author><author><name>Gary Branum</name></author><author><name>Prince N Agbedanu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The concept of bioremediation is quickly becoming the norm in the resolution of environmental issues. The steady increase in carbon dioxide levels, as documented by NASA, inspired scientists to engineer plants to absorb excess carbon dioxide from the atmosphere. Here, we have explored the consequences of the uptake of excess carbon dioxide by select plants. Carbon dioxide dissolves in water to produce carbonic acid, which dissociates to yield H+ ions. We hypothesized that increased carbon dioxide absorption results in decrease in pH of plant sap. Three plants (Byophyllum pinnatum, Romaine Lettuce and Nevada Lettuce), exposed to increased carbon dioxide concentrations (15%), demonstrated a consistent increase in pH towards alkalinity compared to control plants. Based on the outcome being opposite of what we have hypothesized, our results suggest Byophyllum pinnatum, Romaine lettuce and Nevada lettuce, all have a unique homeostatic system to prevent over-absorption of carbon dioxide in a carbon dioxide-rich environment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468474" rel="alternate" title="Investigating Increased CO2 concentration on the pH of various plant species (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>