<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular ecology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.919661+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/ecology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457106</id><title>Trade-driven trapping dampens the biodiversity benefits of forest restoration in Southeast Asia (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.919943+00:00</updated><author><name>H S Sathya Chandra Sagar</name></author><author><name>James J Gilroy</name></author><author><name>Tom Swinfield</name></author><author><name>Ding Li Yong</name></author><author><name>Elva Gemita</name></author><author><name>Novriyanti Novriyanti</name></author><author><name>David C Lee</name></author><author><name>Muhammad Nazri Janra</name></author><author><name>Andrew Balmford</name></author><author><name>Fangyuan Hua</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tropical forest restoration stands to deliver important conservation gains in lowland Southeast Asia, which has suffered some of the world's highest rates of forest degradation and loss. This promise, however, may be undermined by defaunation driven by ubiquitous wildlife trapping in the region, particularly for forest birds that are part of the multi-million-dollar pet trade. To date, quantification of the impacts of trade-driven trapping on rates of biodiversity recovery from forest restoration has been limited. Here, we use a unique long-term survey dataset to ask how trade-driven trapping may interfere with the expected recovery of avian community under forest restoration, at a flagship ecosystem restoration site in the lowland rainforests of Sumatra, Indonesia. We show that tropical forest restoration is associated with the increases in the abundance of 88% of bird species over time. However, impacts of trapping within more accessible areas of the forest meant that this recovery was dampened for 74% of bird species, relative to levels expected as a result of the magnitude of forest recovery observed. Most species (80%) showed increasingly positive relationships between abundance and site remoteness over the period, a pattern that was found for both species targeted for the pet trade (85% of species) and those trapped opportunistically or as 'bycatch' (78% of species). We emphasize the urgency of tackling the emerging threat of pet trade to Southeast Asia's avian diversity, not least to ensure the effectiveness of efforts towards forest restoration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457106" rel="alternate" title="Trade-driven trapping dampens the biodiversity benefits of forest restoration in Southeast Asia (7 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457033</id><title>GinJinn2: Object detection and segmentation for ecology and evolution (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.920187+00:00</updated><author><name>Tankred Ott</name></author><author><name>Ulrich Lautenschlager</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Proper collection and preparation of empirical data still represent one of the most important, but also expensive steps in ecological and evolutionary/systematic research. Modern machine learning approaches, however, have the potential to automate a variety of tasks, which until recently could only be performed manually. Unfortunately, the application of such methods by researchers outside the field is hampered by technical difficulties, some of which, we believe, can be avoided. Here, we present GinJinn2, a user-friendly toolbox for deep learning-based object detection and instance segmentation on image data. Besides providing a convenient command-line interface to existing software libraries, it comprises several additional tools for data handling, pre- and postprocessing, and building advanced analysis pipelines. We demonstrate the application of GinJinn2 for biological purposes using four exemplary analyses, namely the evaluation of seed mixtures, detection of insects on glue traps, segmentation of stomata, and extraction of leaf silhouettes from herbarium specimens. GinJinn2 will enable users with a primary background in biology to apply deep learning-based methods for object detection and segmentation in order to automate feature extraction from image data.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457033" rel="alternate" title="GinJinn2: Object detection and segmentation for ecology and evolution (4 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.456946</id><title>Shaping coral traits: plasticity more than filtering (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.920347+00:00</updated><author><name>Viviana Brambilla</name></author><author><name>Miguel Barbosa</name></author><author><name>Inga Dehnert</name></author><author><name>Joshua Madin</name></author><author><name>Davide Maggioni</name></author><author><name>Clare Peddie</name></author><author><name>Maria Dornelas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The structure of ecosystems is usually determined by the shape of the organisms that build it, commonly known as ecosystem engineers. Understanding to what extent plasticity and environmental filtering determine variation in ecosystem engineer physical structure is necessary to predict how ecosystem structure may change. Here, we explored coral survival and the plasticity of morphological traits that are critical for habitat provision in coral reefs. We conducted a reciprocal clonal transplant experiment in which branching corals from the genus &lt;italic&gt;Porites&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Acropora&lt;/italic&gt; were moved to and from a deep and a shallow site within a lagoon in the Maldives. Survival and trait analyses showed that transplant destination consistently induced the strongest changes, particularly among &lt;italic&gt;Acropora&lt;/italic&gt; spp. The origin of the corals only marginally affected some of the traits. We also detected variation in the way individuals from the same species and site differentiate their shape, showing that traits linked to habitat provision are phenotypically plastic. The results suggest coral phenotypic plasticity plays a stronger role than environmental filtering, in determining zonation of coral morphologies, and consequently the habitats they provide for other taxa.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.456946" rel="alternate" title="Shaping coral traits: plasticity more than filtering (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>