<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular ecology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.134572+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/ecology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470341</id><title>Socioeconomics drive population change in the world’s largest carnivores (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.135058+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas F. Johnson</name></author><author><name>Nick J. B. Isaac</name></author><author><name>Agustin Paviolo</name></author><author><name>Manuela González-Suárez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Land-use&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt; and climate change&lt;sup&gt;3–5&lt;/sup&gt; have been linked to wildlife population declines, but the role of socioeconomic factors in driving declines, and promoting population recoveries, remains relatively unexplored despite its likely importance. Here, we evaluate a comprehensive array of potential drivers of population changes observed in some of the world’s most charismatic species – large mammalian carnivores. Our results reveal a strong role of human socioeconomic development, which we find has a greater impact on population change than habitat loss and climate change. Increases in socioeconomic development are linked to sharp population declines but, importantly, once development is high, carnivore populations have the potential to recover. These links between human development and wildlife population health highlight the challenges ahead to achieve the different UN Sustainable development goals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470341" rel="alternate" title="Socioeconomics drive population change in the world’s largest carnivores (12 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470666</id><title>The influence of sponge-dwelling gobies (Elacatinus horsti) on the feeding efficiency of their Caribbean tube sponge (Aplysina sp.) hosts (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.135448+00:00</updated><author><name>Megan J. Siemann</name></author><author><name>Aldo Turco</name></author><author><name>Shannon D. Brown</name></author><author><name>Rita B.J. Peachey</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mutualistic associations between benthic marine invertebrates and reef taxa are common. Sponge-dwelling gobies benefit from protection within sponge tubes and greater food availability. Sponge-dwelling gobies are hypothesized to increase sponge pump rates by consuming polychaete parasites, but such increases have not yet been demonstrated. We investigated the association between sponge-dwelling gobies (&lt;italic&gt;Elacatinus horsti&lt;/italic&gt;) and two species of tube sponge (&lt;italic&gt;Aplysina lacunosa&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Aplysina archeri&lt;/italic&gt;) in Bonaire, Caribbean Netherlands. We visually assessed goby presence in sponges and used &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; methods with fluorescein dye to measure estimate feeding rates via pump rates. &lt;italic&gt;Aplysina archeri&lt;/italic&gt; were more likely to host a goby than &lt;italic&gt;A. lacunosa&lt;/italic&gt;. For both sponge species, pump rates of tubes with gobies were higher on average than those of tubes without gobies. Our observations, therefore, suggest that &lt;italic&gt;E. horsti&lt;/italic&gt; associations with &lt;italic&gt;Aplysina&lt;/italic&gt; are likely mutualistic relationships in which sponges benefit from higher feeding rates when gobies are present.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470666" rel="alternate" title="The influence of sponge-dwelling gobies (Elacatinus horsti) on the feeding efficiency of their Caribbean tube sponge (Aplysina sp.) hosts (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>