<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular ecology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.016928+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/ecology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474987</id><title>Isolated Grauer’s gorilla populations differ in diet and gut microbiome (21 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.017349+00:00</updated><author><name>Alice Michel</name></author><author><name>Riana Minocher</name></author><author><name>Peter Niehoff</name></author><author><name>Yuhong Li</name></author><author><name>Kevin Nota</name></author><author><name>Maya A. Gadhvi</name></author><author><name>Jiancheng Su</name></author><author><name>Neetha Iyer</name></author><author><name>Amy Porter</name></author><author><name>Urbain Ngobobo-As-Ibungu</name></author><author><name>Escobar Binyinyi</name></author><author><name>Radar Nishuli Pekeyake</name></author><author><name>Laura Parducci</name></author><author><name>Damien Caillaud</name></author><author><name>Katerina Guschanski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Conservation efforts tend to focus on populations that are genetically differentiated without paying attention to their ecological differentiation. However, isolated populations may be ecologically unique, an important aspect for the design of appropriate conservation measures for endangered species. Here we investigate the interplay between diet and gut microbiome in several geographically isolated and genetically differentiated populations of the critically endangered Grauer’s gorilla. We find that dietary and gut microbial profiles are population-specific, likely due to geographic isolation and environmental differences. In addition, social groups within each population also differed in diet and, to a lesser extent, in gut microbial composition and diversity. Individuals at low elevation consumed a larger variety of plant taxa than those at high elevation, consistent with the notion that dietary choice is constrained by food availability that changes with elevation. Despite no detectable correlation between the diet and gut microbiome in richness or evenness, dietary and gut microbial composition covaried significantly. As we did not find evidence for an effect of genetic relatedness on the composition of the gut microbiome of Grauer’s gorillas, this pattern is likely a result of long-term social, ecological, and geographic factors acting on both diet and microbiome. These results reveal that isolated and genetically distinct populations of Grauer’s gorillas are also ecologically distinct, highlighting the need to dedicate separate conservation efforts for each population.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474987" rel="alternate" title="Isolated Grauer’s gorilla populations differ in diet and gut microbiome (21 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475040</id><title>Humanization of wildlife gut microbiota in urban environments (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.017709+00:00</updated><author><name>Brian A. Dillard</name></author><author><name>Albert K. Chung</name></author><author><name>Alex R. Gunderson</name></author><author><name>Shane C. Campbell-Staton</name></author><author><name>Andrew H. Moeller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Urbanization is rapidly altering Earth’s environments, demanding investigations of the impacts on resident wildlife. Here, we show that urban populations of coyotes (&lt;italic&gt;Canis latrans&lt;/italic&gt;) and crested anole lizards (&lt;italic&gt;Anolis cristatellus&lt;/italic&gt;) acquire gut microbiota constituents found in humans, including the gut bacterial lineages most significantly associated with urbanization in humans (e.g., &lt;italic&gt;Bacteroides&lt;/italic&gt;). Comparisons of urban and rural wildlife and human populations revealed significant convergence of the gut microbiota among urban host populations. Remarkably, all microbial lineages found in humans that were overrepresented in urban wildlife relative to rural wildlife were also overrepresented in urban humans relative to rural humans. These results indicate parallel effects of urbanization on human and wildlife gut microbiota and suggest spillover of bacteria from humans into wildlife in cities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475040" rel="alternate" title="Humanization of wildlife gut microbiota in urban environments (11 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.02.474718</id><title>Evidences for newer insecticides and growth regulators resistance in field populations of Helicoverpaarmigera (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) in Karnataka,India (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.017964+00:00</updated><author><name>Honnakerappa S. Ballari</name></author><author><name>Shashikant. S. Udikeri</name></author><author><name>Vinay Kalia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The prominence of &lt;italic&gt;Helicoverpaarmigera&lt;/italic&gt;(Lepidoptera: Noctuidae)averse insecticide resistance was traversed in the course of 2017 in Karnataka,India. The results divulged typical resistance level prostrating in selected newer insecticides, even though exiguous higher resistance airing in insect growth regulator Novaluranwith LC 50of and 13.02 to 18.07 ppm and 1.17 to 1.95 folds resistance) compared to newer group insecticides Spinasad, Indoxacarb, Flubendiamide and Rynaxypyr(3.57 to 10.19 ppm, 1.01 to 1.27 fold). Raichur and Kalaburgi strains comprehend higher resistance to Novaluran and newer insecticides with exception of Flubendiamide (Raichur and Vijayapura strains), respectively and Spinosad (Kalaburgi and Raichur strains), respectively. The morphometric parameters of larval length, pupal length, and weight were most in RCH stain (2.75±0.48 cm, 1.76±0.18 cm, and 0.511±0.04 g, 0.309±0.05 g) respectively, which was pursued by Kalaburgi strain. The morphometric correlation revealed that larval length was a significant positive relation with insecticide resistance which might be an influence of resistance but not merely responsible. Among newer insecticides, a significant positive correlation between Rynaxypyr and Indoxacarb was evident, similarly, Nuvaluran with Indoxacarb and Rynaxypyr as well. Usage pattern revealed that 81.67 % of farmers found to use insecticides more than the recommended dose and 70.83% have habit consecutive applications of products from the same chemical group which bear witness to developing resistance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.02.474718" rel="alternate" title="Evidences for newer insecticides and growth regulators resistance in field populations of Helicoverpaarmigera (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) in Karnataka,India (5 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474818</id><title>Wetland loss in the Ñeembucú Wetlands Complex, Paraguay, using remote sensing (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.018141+00:00</updated><author><name>Frances O’Leary</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;South American wetlands are of global importance, yet limited delineation and monitoring restricts informed decision-making around the drivers of wetland loss. A growing human population and increasing demand for agricultural products has driven wetland loss and degradation in the Neotropics. Understanding of wetland dynamics and land use change can be gained through wetland monitoring. The Ñeembucú Wetlands Complex is the largest wetland in Paraguay, lying within the Paraguay-Paraná-La Plata River system. This study aims to use remotely sensed data to map land cover between 2006 and 2021, quantify wetland change over the 15-year study period and thus identify land cover types vulnerable to change in the Ñeembucú Wetlands Complex. Forest, dryland vegetation, vegetated wetland and open water were identified using Random Forest supervised classifications trained on visual inspection data and field data. Annual change of −0.34, 4.95, −1.65, 0.40 was observed for forest, dryland, vegetated wetland and open water, respectively. Wetland and forest conversion is attributed to agricultural and urban expansion. With ongoing pressures on wetlands, monitoring will be a key tool for addressing change and advising decision-making around development and conservation of valuable ecosystem goods and services in the Ñeembucú Wetlands Complex.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474818" rel="alternate" title="Wetland loss in the Ñeembucú Wetlands Complex, Paraguay, using remote sensing (4 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.475006</id><title>Towards transboundary networks of climate-smart marine reserves in the Southern California Bight (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.018299+00:00</updated><author><name>Nur Arafeh-Dalmau</name></author><author><name>Adrian Munguia-Vega</name></author><author><name>Fiorenza Micheli</name></author><author><name>Ainoa Vilalta-Navas</name></author><author><name>Juan Carlos Villasenor-Derbez</name></author><author><name>Magdalena Précoma-de la Mora</name></author><author><name>David S. Schoeman</name></author><author><name>Alfonso Medellín-Ortíz</name></author><author><name>Kyle C. Cavanaugh</name></author><author><name>Oscar Sosa-Nishizaki</name></author><author><name>Theresa L.U. Burnham</name></author><author><name>Christopher J. Knight</name></author><author><name>C. Brock Woodson</name></author><author><name>Marina Abas</name></author><author><name>Alicia Abadía-Cardoso</name></author><author><name>Octavio Aburto-Oropeza</name></author><author><name>Michael W. Esgro</name></author><author><name>Noemi Espinosa-Andrade</name></author><author><name>Rodrigo Beas-Luna</name></author><author><name>Nirari Cardenas</name></author><author><name>Mark H. Carr</name></author><author><name>Katherine E. Dale</name></author><author><name>Frida Cisneros-Soberanis</name></author><author><name>Ana Laura Flores-Morales</name></author><author><name>Stuart Fulton</name></author><author><name>Emiliano García-Rodríguez</name></author><author><name>Alfredo Giron-Nava</name></author><author><name>Mary G. Gleason</name></author><author><name>Alison L. Green</name></author><author><name>Arturo Hernández-Velasco</name></author><author><name>Beatriz Ibarra-Macías</name></author><author><name>Andrew F. Johnson</name></author><author><name>Julio Lorda</name></author><author><name>Luis Malpica-Cruz</name></author><author><name>Gabriela Montaño-Moctezuma</name></author><author><name>Carolina Olguín-Jacobson</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Parés-Sierra</name></author><author><name>Peter T. Raimondi</name></author><author><name>Georgina Ramírez-Ortiz</name></author><author><name>Arturo Ramirez-Valdez</name></author><author><name>Héctor Reyes-Bonilla</name></author><author><name>Emily Saarman</name></author><author><name>Luz Erandi Saldaña-Ruiz</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Smith</name></author><author><name>Cecilia Soldatini</name></author><author><name>Alvin Suárez</name></author><author><name>Guillermo Torres-Moye</name></author><author><name>Mariana Walther</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Burke Watson</name></author><author><name>Sara Worden</name></author><author><name>Hugh P. Possingham</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Climate-smart conservation addresses the vulnerability of biodiversity to climate change impacts but may require transboundary considerations. Here, we adapt and refine 16 biophysical guidelines for climate-smart marine reserves for the transboundary California Bight ecoregion. We link several climate-adaptation strategies (e.g., maintaining connectivity, representing climate refugia, and forecasting effectiveness of protection) by focusing on kelp forests and associated species. We quantify transboundary larval connectivity along ∼800 km of coast and find that the number of connections and the average density of larvae dispersing through the network under future climate scenarios could decrease by ∼50%, highlighting the need to protect critical steppingstone nodes. We also find that although focal species will generally recover with 30% protection, marine heatwaves could hinder subsequent recovery in the following 50 years, suggesting that protecting climate refugia and expanding the coverage of marine reserves is a priority. Together, these findings provide a first comprehensive framework for integrating climate resilience for networks of marine reserves and highlight the need for a coordinated approach in the California Bight ecoregion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.475006" rel="alternate" title="Towards transboundary networks of climate-smart marine reserves in the Southern California Bight (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>