<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular ecology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.445918+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/ecology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471794</id><title>Fitness of breeders in social Damaraland mole-rats is independent of group size (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.446410+00:00</updated><author><name>Jack Thorley</name></author><author><name>Hanna Bensch</name></author><author><name>Kyle Finn</name></author><author><name>Tim Clutton-Brock</name></author><author><name>Markus Zöttl</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Damaraland mole-rats (Fukomys damarensis) are usually viewed as an obligatorily group living eusocial species in which successful reproduction is dependent on reproductive altruism of closely related group members. However, the reproductive ecology of social mole-rats in their natural environment remains poorly understood and it is unclear to what extent successful reproduction is dependent on assistance from other group members. Using data from a 7-year field study of marked individuals, we show that, after dispersal from their natal group, individuals typically settled alone in new burrow systems where they enjoyed high survival rates, and often remained in good body condition for several years before finding a mate. Unlike most other eusocial or singular cooperative breeders, we found that Damaraland mole-rats reproduced successfully in pairs without helpers and experimentally formed pairs had the same reproductive success as larger established groups. Overall there was only a weak increase in reproductive success with increasing group size and no effect of group size on adult survival rates across the population. Juveniles in large groups grew faster early in life but their growth rates declined subsequently so that they eventually plateaued at a lower maximum body mass than juveniles from small groups. Taken together, our data suggest that the fitness benefits of group living to breeders are small and we suggest that extended philopatry in Damaraland mole-rats has evolved because of the high costs and constraints of dispersal rather than because of strong indirect benefits accrued through cooperative behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471794" rel="alternate" title="Fitness of breeders in social Damaraland mole-rats is independent of group size (22 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471316</id><title>Utilizing occupancy-detection models with museum specimen data: promise and pitfalls (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.446848+00:00</updated><author><name>Vaughn Shirey</name></author><author><name>Rassim Khelifa</name></author><author><name>Leithen K. M’Gonigle</name></author><author><name>Laura Melissa Guzman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Historical museum records provide potentially useful data for identifying drivers of change in species occupancy. However, because museum records are typically obtained via many collection methods, methodological developments are needed in order to enable robust inferences. Occupancy-detection models, a relatively new and powerful suite of methods, are a potentially promising avenue because they can account for changes in collection effort through space and time. Here we present a methodological road-map for using occupancy models to analyze historical museum records. We use simulated data-sets to identify how and when patterns in data and/or modelling decisions can bias inference. We focus primarily on the consequences of contrasting methodological approaches for dealing with species’ ranges and inferring species’ non-detections in both space and time. We find that not all data-sets are suitable for occupancy-detection analysis but, under the right conditions (namely, data-sets that span long durations and contain a high fraction of community-wide collections, or collection events that focus on communities of organisms), models can accurately estimate trends. Finally, we present a case-study on eastern North American odonates where we calculate long-term trends of occupancy by using our most robust workflow.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471316" rel="alternate" title="Utilizing occupancy-detection models with museum specimen data: promise and pitfalls (17 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471216</id><title>Cryptic local adaptation is pervasive across environmental and evolutionary gradients (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.446998+00:00</updated><author><name>Morgan M Sparks</name></author><author><name>Joshua C Kraft</name></author><author><name>Kliffi MS Blackstone</name></author><author><name>Gordon G McNickle</name></author><author><name>Mark R Christie</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cryptic local adaptation, where the environmental effect masks the magnitude of the genetic effect on a phenotype, has long been a topic of interest for ecologists and evolutionary biologists. Nevertheless, much work remains to quantitatively account for cryptic local adaptation across studies. Among the most commonly documented forms of cryptic local adaptation are cogradient and countergradient variation, in which genetic variance for a phenotype either varies additively with or opposes the environmental variance, respectively, and where both mask the true genetic effect on phenotypes. Here, we estimated the genetic variance component of cryptic local adaption using a meta-analytical framework. We used Bayesian hierarchical models to first estimate the full genetic effect of co- and countergradient variation and then a metaregression to assess which abiotic or biotic covariates are the most important drivers of cryptic local adaptation. The overall effect size of countergradient variation was 1.03 and the effect size of cogradient variation was 0.9. We also found that the covariates with the largest mean effect sizes were temperature and gamete size, although there was substantial within and among study variance. Finally, we assessed the magnitude and direction of the compensatory genetic effect of countergradient variation, that is, how different trait values were for countergradient genotypes in their home environments, finding that over- and undercompensation occurred in 74.6% of cases analyzed. Our results demonstrate the large effect of both counter- and cogradient variation expressed in wild populations, as well as the ubiquity across abiotic and biotic covariates. These findings are indicative of the pervasiveness of cryptic local adaptation and highlight the importance of accounting for these effects in ecological studies designed to include measures of phenotypic variance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471216" rel="alternate" title="Cryptic local adaptation is pervasive across environmental and evolutionary gradients (17 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471719</id><title>Estimating abundance of a recovering transboundary brown bear population with capture-recapture models (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.447129+00:00</updated><author><name>Cécile Vanpé</name></author><author><name>Blaise Piédallu</name></author><author><name>Pierre-Yves Quenette</name></author><author><name>Jérôme Sentilles</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Queney</name></author><author><name>Santiago Palazón</name></author><author><name>Ivan Afonso Jordana</name></author><author><name>Ramón Jato</name></author><author><name>Miguel Mari Elósegui Irurtia</name></author><author><name>Jordi Solà de la Torre</name></author><author><name>Olivier Gimenez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Abundance of small populations of large mammals may be assessed using complete counts of the different individuals detected over a time period, so-called minimum detected size (MDS). However, as population is growing larger and its distribution is expanding wider, the risk of under-estimating population size using MDS is increasing sharply due to the rarely fulfilled assumption of perfect detection of all individuals of the population, and as a result, the need to report uncertainty in population size estimates becomes crucial. We addressed these issues within the framework of the monitoring of the critically endangered Pyrenean brown bear population that was on the edge of extinction in the mid-1990s with only five individuals remaining, but was reinforced by 11 bears originated from Slovenia since then. We used Pollock’s closed robust design (PCRD) capture-recapture models applied to the cross-border non-invasive sampling data from France, Spain and Andorra to provide the first published annual abundance estimates of the Pyrenean brown bear population and its trends over time. Annual population size increased and displayed a fivefold rise between 2008 and 2020, reaching &amp;gt; 60 individuals in 2020. Detection heterogeneity among individuals may stem from intraspecific home range size disparities making it more likely to find signs of individuals who move more. We found a lower survival rate in cubs than in adults and subadults, since the formers suffer from more mortality risks (such as infanticides, predations, mother death or abandonments) than the latters. Our study provides evidence that the PCRD capture-recapture modelling approach can provide reliable estimates of the size of and trend in large mammal populations, while minimizing bias due to inter-individual heterogeneity in detection probabilities and allowing the quantification of sampling uncertainty surrounding these estimates. Such information is vital for informing management decision-making and assessing population conservation status.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471719" rel="alternate" title="Estimating abundance of a recovering transboundary brown bear population with capture-recapture models (10 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471959</id><title>Trade-offs among plant reproductive traits determine interactions with floral visitors (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.447298+00:00</updated><author><name>Jose B. Lanuza</name></author><author><name>Romina Rader</name></author><author><name>Jamie Stavert</name></author><author><name>Liam K. Kendall</name></author><author><name>Manu E. Saunders</name></author><author><name>Ignasi Bartomeus</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Plant life-history strategies are constrained by cost-benefit trade-offs that determine plant form and function. However, despite recent advances in the understanding of trade-offs for vegetative and physiological traits, little is known about plant reproductive economics and how they constrain plant life-history strategies and shape interactions with floral visitors. Here, we investigate plant reproductive trade-offs and how these drive interactions with floral visitors using a dataset of 17 reproductive traits for 1,506 plant species from 28 plant-pollinator studies across 18 countries. We tested whether a plant's reproductive strategy predicts its interactions with floral visitors and if the different reproductive traits predict the plant's role within the pollination network. We found that over half of all plant reproductive trait variation was explained by two independent axes that encompassed plant form and function. Specifically, the first axis indicated the presence of a trade-off between flower number and flower size, while the second axis indicated a pollinator dependency trade-off. Plant reproductive trade-offs helped explain partly the presence or absence of interactions with floral visitors, but not differences in visitation rate. However, we did find important differences in the interaction level among floral visitor guilds on the different axes of trait variation. Finally, we found that plant size and floral rewards were the most important traits in the understanding of the plant species network role. Our results highlight the importance of plant reproductive trade-offs in determining plant life-history strategies and plant-pollinator interactions in a global context.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471959" rel="alternate" title="Trade-offs among plant reproductive traits determine interactions with floral visitors (9 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471695</id><title>Severe disturbance overflows the stabilizing buffer of variable biotic interactions (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.447431+00:00</updated><author><name>Koya Hashimoto</name></author><author><name>Daisuke Hayasaka</name></author><author><name>Yuji Eguchi</name></author><author><name>Yugo Seko</name></author><author><name>Ji Cai</name></author><author><name>Koichi Goka</name></author><author><name>Taku Kadoya</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent studies have uncovered that biotic interaction strength varies over time in real ecosystems intrinsically and/or responding to anthropogenic disturbances. Little is known, however, about whether such interaction variability strengthens or weakens community resistance against disturbances. Here, we examine how the change in interaction strength after pesticide application mediates disturbance impacts on a freshwater community using outdoor mesocosms. We show that the change in interaction strength buffered the disturbance impact but amplified it once the disturbance severity exceeded a certain threshold. Importantly, we also show that interactions fluctuating more temporally under no disturbances were more changeable in response to pesticide applications. Our findings suggest that a severe disturbance may have a surprise impact on a biological community amplified by their own interaction variability, but the possibility still remains that we can predict the consequences of the disturbance by measuring the interaction variability before the disturbance occurs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471695" rel="alternate" title="Severe disturbance overflows the stabilizing buffer of variable biotic interactions (7 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471448</id><title>Experimental calibration of trapping methods for addressing bias in arthropod biodiversity monitoring (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.447568+00:00</updated><author><name>Katherine McNamara Manning</name></author><author><name>Christie A. Bahlai</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1.&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;All approaches to biodiversity monitoring have inherent biases in the taxa captured, yet, as environments, sampling goals, and conventions vary, it is not uncommon for sampling approaches to be customized to reflect the study objectives, optimizing findings to be locally relevant but at the cost of transferability. Here, we developed a calibration study to directly examine how researcher trap choice affects observations made in insect biodiversity sampling. Sampling efficiency of four types of traps: pitfalls, yellow ramp traps, a novel jar ramp trap, and yellow sticky cards, were compared with respect to an array of biodiversity metrics associated with the arthropods they captured. We found that trapping efficiency and functional groups of arthropods (flying versus ground-crawling) varied by trap type. Pitfalls and jar ramp traps performed similarly for all biodiversity metrics measured, suggesting that jar ramp traps provide a more comparable measurement of ground-crawling arthropod communities to pitfall sampling than the yellow ramp traps and should be considered when pitfall sampling cannot be used. This study illustrates the implications for biodiversity sampling of arthropods in environments with physical constraints on trapping, and the importance of directly comparing adapted methods to established sampling protocol. Future biodiversity monitoring schemes should conduct calibration experiments to provide important information on performance and potential limitations of sampling methodology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471448" rel="alternate" title="Experimental calibration of trapping methods for addressing bias in arthropod biodiversity monitoring (6 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471475</id><title>Using simulated temperature regimes to test growth and development of an invasive forest insect under climate change (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.447676+00:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan A. Walter</name></author><author><name>Lily M. Thompson</name></author><author><name>Sean D. Powers</name></author><author><name>Dylan Parry</name></author><author><name>Salvatore J. Agosta</name></author><author><name>Kristine L. Grayson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Temperature and its impact on fitness are fundamental for understanding range shifts and population dynamics under climate change. Geographic climate heterogeneity, behavioural and physiological plasticity, and thermal adaptation to local climates makes predicting the responses of species to climate change complex. Using larvae from seven geographically distinct wild populations in the eastern United States of the non-native forest pest &lt;italic&gt;Lymantria dispar dispar&lt;/italic&gt; (L.), we conducted a simulated reciprocal transplant experiment in environmental chambers using six custom temperature regimes representing contemporary conditions near the southern and northern extremes of the US invasion front and projections under two climate change scenarios for the year 2050. Larval growth rates increased with climate warming compared to current thermal regimes and responses differed by population. A significant population-by-treatment interaction indicated that growth rates increased more when a source population experienced the warming scenarios for their region, especially for southern populations. Our study demonstrates the utility of simulating thermal regimes under climate change in environmental chambers and emphasizes how the impacts from future increases in temperature can be heterogeneous due to geographic differences in climate-related performance among populations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471475" rel="alternate" title="Using simulated temperature regimes to test growth and development of an invasive forest insect under climate change (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>