<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular ecology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.363842+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/ecology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475793</id><title>Global monitoring of soil animal communities using a common methodology (88 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.363940+00:00</updated><author><name>Anton M. Potapov</name></author><author><name>Xin Sun</name></author><author><name>Maria J. I. Briones</name></author><author><name>George G. Brown</name></author><author><name>Erin K. Cameron</name></author><author><name>Jérôme Cortet</name></author><author><name>Nico Eisenhauer</name></author><author><name>Saori Fujii</name></author><author><name>Stefan Geisen</name></author><author><name>Konstantin B. Gongalsky</name></author><author><name>Carlos Guerra</name></author><author><name>I.Tanya Handa</name></author><author><name>Charlene Janion-Scheepers</name></author><author><name>Zoë Lindo</name></author><author><name>Jérôme Mathieu</name></author><author><name>Maka Murvanidze</name></author><author><name>Uffe N Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Stefan Scheu</name></author><author><name>Olaf Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Clement Schneider</name></author><author><name>Julia Seeber</name></author><author><name>Jiri Tuma</name></author><author><name>Alexei V. Tiunov</name></author><author><name>Andrey S. Zaitsev</name></author><author><name>Diana H. Wall</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Here we introduce the Soil BON Foodweb Team, a cross-continental collaborative network that aims to monitor soil animal communities and food webs using consistent methodology at a global scale. Soil animals support vital soil processes via soil structure modification, direct consumption of dead organic matter, and interactions with microbial and plant communities. Soil animal effects on ecosystem functions have been demonstrated by correlative analyses as well as in laboratory and field experiments, but these studies typically focus on selected animal groups or species at one or few sites with limited variation in environmental conditions. The lack of comprehensive harmonised large-scale soil animal community data including microfauna, mesofauna, and macrofauna, in conjunction with related soil functions, limits our understanding of biological interactions in soil communities and how these interactions affect ecosystem functioning. To provide such data, the Soil BON Foodweb Team invites researchers worldwide to use a common methodology to address six long-term goals: (1) to collect globally representative harmonised data on soil micro-, meso-, and macrofauna communities; (2) to describe key environmental drivers of soil animal communities and food webs; (3) to assess the efficiency of conservation approaches for the protection of soil animal communities; (4) to describe soil food webs and their association with soil functioning globally; (5) to establish a global research network for soil biodiversity monitoring and collaborative projects in related topics; (6) to reinforce local collaboration networks and expertise and support capacity building for soil animal research around the world. In this paper, we describe the vision of the global research network and the common sampling protocol to assess soil animal communities and advocate for the use of standard methodologies across observational and experimental soil animal studies. We will use this protocol to conduct soil animal assessments and reconstruct soil food webs on the sites included in the global soil biodiversity monitoring network, Soil BON, allowing us to assess linkages among soil biodiversity, vegetation, soil physico-chemical properties, and ecosystem functions. In the present paper, we call for researchers especially from countries and ecoregions that remain underrepresented in the majority of soil biodiversity assessments to join us. Together we will be able to provide science-based evidence to support soil biodiversity conservation and functioning of terrestrial ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475793" rel="alternate" title="Global monitoring of soil animal communities using a common methodology (88 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476254</id><title>Caenorhabditis nematodes colonize ephemeral resource patches in neotropical forests. (29 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.364097+00:00</updated><author><name>Solomon A Sloat</name></author><author><name>Luke M Noble</name></author><author><name>Annalise B Paaby</name></author><author><name>Max Bernstein</name></author><author><name>Audrey Chang</name></author><author><name>Taniya Kaur</name></author><author><name>John Yuen</name></author><author><name>Sophia C. Tintori</name></author><author><name>Jacqueline L. Jackson</name></author><author><name>Arielle Martel</name></author><author><name>Jose A. Salome Correa</name></author><author><name>Lewis Stevens</name></author><author><name>Mark Blaxter</name></author><author><name>Matthew V. Rockman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Factors shaping the distribution and abundance of species include life-history traits, population structure, and stochastic colonization-extinction dynamics. Field studies of model species groups help reveal the roles of these factors. Species of &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis&lt;/italic&gt; nematodes are highly divergent at the sequence level but exhibit highly conserved morphological uniformity, and many of these species live in sympatry on microbe-rich patches of rotten material. Here, we use field experiments and large-scale opportunistic collections to investigate species composition, abundance, and colonization efficiency of &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis&lt;/italic&gt; in two of the world's best studied lowland tropical field sites: Barro Colorado Island in Panamá and La Selva in Sarapiquí, Costa Rica. We observed seven species of &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis&lt;/italic&gt;, four of them known only from these collections. While these localities contain species from many parts of the phylogeny, both localities were dominated by globally distributed androdiecious species. We found that &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis&lt;/italic&gt; were able to colonize baits accessible only by phoresy, preferring to colonize baits making direct contact with the ground. We estimate founder numbers per colonization event to be low.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476254" rel="alternate" title="Caenorhabditis nematodes colonize ephemeral resource patches in neotropical forests. (29 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476129</id><title>The blowfly  Chrysomya latifrons  inhabits fragmented rainforests, but lacks genetic diversity and population structure (16 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.364200+00:00</updated><author><name>Nathan J Butterworth</name></author><author><name>James F Wallman</name></author><author><name>Nikolas P Johnston</name></author><author><name>Blake M Dawson</name></author><author><name>Angela McGaughran</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Climate change and deforestation are causing rainforests to become increasingly fragmented, placing them at heightened risk of biodiversity loss. Invertebrates constitute the greatest proportion of this biodiversity, yet we lack basic knowledge of their population structure and ecology. It is not currently feasible to assess the population structure of every invertebrate species, so there is a compelling need to identify indicator species that are broadly indicative of habitat-level patterns and processes. Blowflies are an ideal candidate, because they are widespread, abundant, and can be easily collected within rainforests. Here, we present the first study of the blowfly &lt;italic&gt; Chrysomya latifrons &lt;/italic&gt;, which is endemic to the rainforests of New South Wales, Australia. We genotyped 188 flies from 15 isolated rainforests and found low overall genetic diversity and a complete lack of genetic structure between populations, suggesting the presence of a single large panmictic population along 1,000 km of the Australian east coast. This highlights that: (1) &lt;italic&gt; Ch. latifrons &lt;/italic&gt; inhabits every rainforest in NSW and undoubtedly plays an important role in these ecosystems, but low genetic diversity may cause it to struggle to adapt to a changing climate; (2) strongly dispersing insects have the capacity to migrate between isolated rainforests, likely carrying pollen, parasites, phoronts, and pathogens with them to form crucial trophic networks; and (3) there is an urgent need for similar studies on poorly dispersing rainforest insects, as these may be the most fragmented and at highest risk of local extinction.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476129" rel="alternate" title="The blowfly  Chrysomya latifrons  inhabits fragmented rainforests, but lacks genetic diversity and population structure (16 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476313</id><title>Utilizing citizen science to model the distribution of Aedes aegypti ([Diptera]: [Culicidae]) in West Africa (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.364272+00:00</updated><author><name>Elizabeth A. Freeman</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth J. Carlton</name></author><author><name>Sara Paull</name></author><author><name>Samuel Dadzie</name></author><author><name>Andrea Buchwald</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In a rapidly urbanizing region such as West Africa, &lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; mosquitoes pose an emerging threat of infectious disease that is compounded by limited vector surveillance. Citizen science has been proposed as a way to fill surveillance gaps by training local residents to collect and share information on disease vectors. Increasing citizen science efforts can begin to bridge the gaps in our current knowledge of &lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; distribution while engaging locals with mosquito control and public health efforts. Understanding the distribution of disease vectors in West Africa can inform researchers and public health officials on where to conduct disease surveillance and focus public health interventions. We aimed to compare citizen science data to published literature observations of &lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; mosquitoes and to quantify how incorporating citizen science changes our understanding of &lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; mosquito distribution in West Africa. We utilized citizen science data collected through NASA’s GLOBE Observer mobile phone application and data from a previously published literature review on &lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; mosquito distribution to examine the contribution of citizen science to understanding the distribution of &lt;italic&gt;Ae. aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; in West Africa using Maximum Entropy modeling. Combining citizen science and literature-derived observations improved the fit of the model compared to models created by each data source alone, but did not alleviate location bias within the models, likely due to lack of widespread observations. Understanding &lt;italic&gt;Ae. aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; distribution will require greater investment in &lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; mosquito surveillance in the region, and citizen science should be utilized as a tool in this mission to increase the reach of surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476313" rel="alternate" title="Utilizing citizen science to model the distribution of Aedes aegypti ([Diptera]: [Culicidae]) in West Africa (11 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475665</id><title>Aedes aegypti and Aedes albopictus abundance, landscape coverage and spectral indices effects in a subtropical city of Argentina (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.364342+00:00</updated><author><name>Mía Elisa Martín</name></author><author><name>Ana Carolina Alonso</name></author><author><name>Janinna Faraone</name></author><author><name>Marina Stein</name></author><author><name>Elizabet Lilia Estallo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The presence, abundance and distribution of &lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Stegomyia&lt;/italic&gt;) &lt;italic&gt;aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; (Linnaeus 1762) and &lt;italic&gt;Aedes&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Stegomyia&lt;/italic&gt;) &lt;italic&gt;albopictus&lt;/italic&gt; (Skuse 1894) could be conditioned by different data obtained from satellite remote sensors. In this paper, we aim to estimate the effect of landscape coverage and spectral indices on the abundance of &lt;italic&gt;Ae. aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Ae. albopictus&lt;/italic&gt; from the use of satellite remote sensors in Eldorado, Misiones, Argentina. Larvae of &lt;italic&gt;Aedes aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Ae. albopictus&lt;/italic&gt; were collected monthly from June 2016 to April 2018, in four outdoor environments: tire repair shops, cemeteries, family dwellings, and an urban natural park. The proportion of each land cover class was determined by Sentinel-2 image classification. Furthermore spectral indices were calculated. Generalized Linear Mixed Models were developed to analyze the possible effects of landscape coverage and vegetation indices on the abundance of mosquitoes. The model’s results showed the abundance of &lt;italic&gt;Ae. aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; was better modeled by the minimum values of the NDVI index, the maximum values of the NDBI index and the interaction between both variables. In contrast, the abundance of &lt;italic&gt;Ae. albopictus&lt;/italic&gt; has to be better explained by the model that includes the variables bare soil, low vegetation and the interaction between both variables.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475665" rel="alternate" title="Aedes aegypti and Aedes albopictus abundance, landscape coverage and spectral indices effects in a subtropical city of Argentina (10 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475781</id><title>Consideration of genetic variation and evolutionary history in future conservation of Indian one-horned rhinoceros (Rhinoceros unicornis) (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.364414+00:00</updated><author><name>Tista Ghosh</name></author><author><name>Shrewshree Kumar</name></author><author><name>Kirtika Sharma</name></author><author><name>Parikshit Kakati</name></author><author><name>Amit Sharma</name></author><author><name>Samrat Mondol</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The extant members of the Eurasian rhino species have experienced severe population and range declines through a combination of natural and anthropogenic factors since Pleistocene. The one-horned rhino is the only Asian species recovered from such strong population decline but most of their fragmented populations in India and Nepal are reaching carrying capacity. Implementation of any future reintroduction-based conservation efforts would greatly benefit from currently unavailable detailed genetic assessments and evolutionary history of these populations. We sequenced wild one-horned rhino mitogenome from all the extant populations (n=16 individuals) for the first time, identified the polymorphic sites and assessed genetic variation (2531bp mtDNA, n=111 individuals) across India. Results showed 30 unique rhino haplotypes distributed as three distinct genetic clades (F&lt;sub&gt;st&lt;/sub&gt; value 0.68-1) corresponding to the states of Assam (n=28 haplotypes), West Bengal and Uttar Pradesh (both monomorphic). Phylogenetic analyses suggest earlier coalescence of Assam (∼0.5 Mya) followed by parallel divergence of West Bengal and Uttar Pradesh/Nepal (∼0.06-0.05Mya), supported by the paleobiogeographic history of the Indian subcontinent. Combined together, we propose recognising three ‘Evolutionary Significant Units (ESUs)’ of Indian rhino. As recent assessments suggest further genetic isolations of Indian rhinos at local scales, future management efforts should focus on identifying genetically variable founder animals and consider periodic supplementation events while planning future rhino reintroduction programs in India. Such well-informed, multidisciplinary approach is the only way to ensure evolutionary, ecological and demographic stability of the species across its range.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475781" rel="alternate" title="Consideration of genetic variation and evolutionary history in future conservation of Indian one-horned rhinoceros (Rhinoceros unicornis) (8 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476136</id><title>A preliminary description of the ecological characteristics of wild waterbird Japanese encephalitis virus hosts in high risk landscapes in India (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.364490+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael Walsh</name></author><author><name>Amrita Pattanaik</name></author><author><name>Navya Vyas</name></author><author><name>Deepak Saxena</name></author><author><name>Cameron Webb</name></author><author><name>Shailendra Sawleshwarkar</name></author><author><name>Chiranjay Mukhopadhyay</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Wild reservoirs of Japanese encephalitis virus are under-studied globally, which presents critical knowledge gaps for JEV infection ecology despite decades of received wisdom regarding this high-impact mosquito-borne virus. As a result, ardeid birds, generally understood to be the primary reservoirs for JEV, as well as other waterbirds occupying landscapes at high risk for spillover to humans, are frequently ignored by current surveillance mechanisms and infrastructure. This is particularly true in India, which experiences a high annual burden of human outbreaks. Incorporating wild reservoirs into surveillance of human and livestock populations is therefore essential but will first require a data-driven approach to target individual host species. The current study sought to define a preliminary ecological profile of JEV hosts based on 1) species ecological traits, and 2) species presence and abundance adjusted for the biotic constraints of sympatry. Optimal host species tended to be generalists and demonstrate regionally-increasing populations. While ardeid bird species richness, abundance, and relative abundance did demonstrate the strongest and most consistent associations with the distribution of human JEV outbreaks, this study also identified several individual species among two other bird families in these landscapes, the Anatidae and the Rallidae, which also exhibited an optimal host profile and were strongly associated with the distribution of outbreaks. The findings from this work provide the first data-driven evidence base to inform wildlife sampling for the monitoring of JEV circulation in outbreak hotspots in India and thus identify good preliminary targets for the development of One Health wildlife JEV surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476136" rel="alternate" title="A preliminary description of the ecological characteristics of wild waterbird Japanese encephalitis virus hosts in high risk landscapes in India (6 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475553</id><title>Detection of bifenthrin, bifenazate, etoxazole resistance in Tetranychus urticae collected from mint fields and hop yards using targeted sequencing and TaqMan approaches (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.364564+00:00</updated><author><name>Silas Shumate</name></author><author><name>Maggie Haylett</name></author><author><name>Brenda Nelson</name></author><author><name>Nicole Young</name></author><author><name>Kurt Lamour</name></author><author><name>Doug Walsh</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Bradford</name></author><author><name>Justin Clements</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Tetranychus urticae&lt;/italic&gt; (Koch) is an economically important pest of many agricultural commodities in the Pacific Northwest. Multiple miticides are currently registered for control including abamectin, bifenazate, bifenthrin, and extoxazole. However, populations of &lt;italic&gt;Tetranychus urticae&lt;/italic&gt; have developed miticide resistance through multiple mechanisms, in many different growing regions. Producers of agricultural commodities where &lt;italic&gt;Tetranychus urticae&lt;/italic&gt; infestations are problematic rely on integrated pest management tools to determine optimal control methods. Within this species multiple single nucleotide polymorphisms have been documented in different genes which are associated with miticide resistance phenotypes. The detection of these mutations through TaqMan qPCR has been suggested as a practical, quick, and reliable tool to inform agricultural producers of miticide resistance phenotypes present within their fields and have potential utility for making appropriate miticide application and integrated pest management decisions. Within this investigation we examined the use of a TaqMan qPCR-based approach to determine miticide resistance genotypes in field-collected populations of &lt;italic&gt;Tetranychus urticae&lt;/italic&gt; from mint fields and hop yards in the Pacific Northwest of the United States and confirmed the results with a multiplex targeted sequencing. The results suggest the TaqMan approach accurately genotypes &lt;italic&gt;Tetranychus urticae&lt;/italic&gt; populations collected from agricultural fields. The interpretation of the results, however, provide additional challenges for integrated pest management practitioners, including making miticide application recommendations where populations of &lt;italic&gt;Tetranychus urticae&lt;/italic&gt; are a mix of resistant and wildtype individuals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475553" rel="alternate" title="Detection of bifenthrin, bifenazate, etoxazole resistance in Tetranychus urticae collected from mint fields and hop yards using targeted sequencing and TaqMan approaches (4 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475598</id><title>Noise source importance in linear stochastic models of biological systems that grow, shrink, wander, or persist (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.364642+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Strang</name></author><author><name>William Huffmyer</name></author><author><name>Hilary Rollins</name></author><author><name>Karen C. Abbott</name></author><author><name>Peter J. Thomas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;While noise is an important factor in biology, biological processes often involve multiple noise sources, whose relative importance can be unclear. Here we develop tools that quantify the importance of noise sources in a network based on their contributions to variability in a quantity of interest. We generalize the edge importance measures proposed by Schmidt and Thomas [1] for first-order reaction networks whose steady-state variance is a linear combination of variance produced by each directed edge. We show that the same additive property extends to a general family of stochastic processes subject to a set of linearity assumptions, whether in discrete or continuous state or time. Our analysis applies to both expanding and contracting populations, as well as populations obeying a martingale (“wandering”) at long times. We show that the original Schmidt-Thomas edge importance measure is a special case of our more general measure, and is recovered when the model satisfies a conservation constraint (“persists”). In the growing and wandering cases we show that the choice of observables (measurements) used to monitor the process does not influence which noise sources are important at long times. In contrast, in the shrinking or persisting case, which noise sources are important depends on what is measured. We also generalize our measures to admit models with affine moment update equations, which admit additional limiting scenarios, and arise naturally after linearization. We illustrate our results using examples from cell biology and ecology: (i) a model for the dynamics of the inositol trisphospate receptor, (ii) a model for an endangered population of white-tailed eagles, and (iii) a model for wood frog dispersal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Biological processes are frequently subject to an ensemble of independent noise sources. Noise sources produce fluctuations that propagate through the system, driving fluctuations in quantities of interest such as population size or ion channel configuration. We introduce a measure that quantifies how much variability each noise source contributes to any given quantity of interest. Using these methods, we identify which binding events contribute significantly to fluctuations in the state of a molecular signalling channel, which life history events contribute the most variability to an eagle population before and after a successful conservation effort rescued the population from the brink of extinction, and which dispersal events, at what times, matter most to variability in the recolonization of a series of ponds by wood frogs after a drought.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475598" rel="alternate" title="Noise source importance in linear stochastic models of biological systems that grow, shrink, wander, or persist (4 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475621</id><title>Ecosystem size-induced environmental fluctuations affect the temporal dynamics of community assembly mechanisms (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.364709+00:00</updated><author><name>Raven L. Bier</name></author><author><name>Máté Vass</name></author><author><name>Anna J. Székely</name></author><author><name>Silke Langenheder</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding processes that determine community membership and abundance is important for many fields from theoretical community ecology to conservation. However, spatial community studies are often conducted only at a single timepoint despite the known influence of temporal variability on community assembly processes. Here we used a spatiotemporal study to determine how environmental fluctuation differences induced by mesocosm volumes (larger volumes were more stable) influence assembly processes of aquatic bacterial metacommunities along a press disturbance gradient. By combining path analysis and network approaches, we found mesocosm size categories had distinct relative influences of assembly process and environmental factors that determined spatiotemporal bacterial community composition, including dispersal and species sorting by conductivity. These processes depended on, but were not affected proportionately by, mesocosm size. Low fluctuation, large mesocosms primarily developed through the interplay of species sorting that became more important over time and transient priority effects as evidenced by more time-delayed associations. High fluctuation, small mesocosms had regular disruptions to species sorting and greater importance of ecological drift and dispersal limitation indicated by lower richness and higher taxa replacement. Together, these results emphasize that environmental fluctuations influence ecosystems over time and its impacts are modified by biotic properties intrinsic to ecosystem size.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475621" rel="alternate" title="Ecosystem size-induced environmental fluctuations affect the temporal dynamics of community assembly mechanisms (4 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476164</id><title>Fiber-parenchyma trade-off underlies changes in tropical forest structure and xylem architecture across a soil water gradient (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.364774+00:00</updated><author><name>Jehová Lourenço</name></author><author><name>Paulo Roberto de Lima Bittencourt</name></author><author><name>Brian J. Enquist</name></author><author><name>Camilla Rozindo Dias Milanez</name></author><author><name>Georg von Arx</name></author><author><name>Kiyomi Morino</name></author><author><name>Luciana Dias Thomaz</name></author><author><name>Lucy Rowland</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wood anatomical traits can underpin tropical forest structural and functional changes across soil water gradients and therefore could improve our mechanistic understanding of how plants adapt to environmental change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We assessed how the variation in the forest maximum height (Hmax), stem diameter, and wood density (WD) is associated with variation in xylem traits (area of fibers and parenchyma, conductive area [CondA, sum of all vessels lumens], vessel lumen area [VLA], vessel density [VD], and vessel wall reinforcement [VWR]) across 42 plots of a Brazilian Atlantic Forest habitat that span strong soil water gradients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found that in wetter communities, greater height and lower WD were associated with greater parenchyma area (capacitance), and lower fibers, VD, VWR. Contrastingly, in drier communities, lower height was associated with higher fiber area (xylem reinforcement), WD, VD, and VWR, while parenchyma area and vessels are reduced.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tree communities vary from conservative resource-use and structurally dependent hydraulic safety (Fibers) to acquisitive resource-use and capacitance dependent hydraulic safety (parenchyma). Such a fiber-parenchyma trade-off (FPT) underlies the variation in tree height across a soil water gradient. Wood anatomy is fundamental to understanding and predicting the impacts of environmental change on forest structure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476164" rel="alternate" title="Fiber-parenchyma trade-off underlies changes in tropical forest structure and xylem architecture across a soil water gradient (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476385</id><title>Phenology effects on productivity and hatching-asynchrony of American kestrels (Falco sparverius) across a continent (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.364855+00:00</updated><author><name>Kathleen R. Callery</name></author><author><name>Sarah E. Schulwitz</name></author><author><name>Anjolene R. Hunt</name></author><author><name>Jason M. Winiarski</name></author><author><name>Christopher J. W. McClure</name></author><author><name>Richard A. Fischer</name></author><author><name>Julie A. Heath</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Climate-driven advances in spring can result in phenological mismatch between brood rearing and prey availability and consequently cause decreased productivity in birds. How consequences of mismatch vary across species’ ranges, and how individual behavior can mitigate mismatch effects is less studied. We quantified the relationship between phenological mismatch, productivity, and behavioral adaptations of American kestrels (&lt;italic&gt;Falco sparverius&lt;/italic&gt;) across their breeding range in the United States and southern Canada. We obtained phenology and productivity data using nest observations from long term nest box monitoring, remote trail cameras, and community-scientist based programs. We collected data on parental incubation behavior and hatch asynchrony using trail cameras in nest boxes. Kestrels that laid eggs after the start of spring had higher rates of nest failure and fewer nestlings than earlier nesters, and effects of mismatch on productivity were most severe in the Northeast. In contrast, kestrels in the Southwest experienced a more gradual decline in productivity with seasonal mismatch. We attribute the effect of location to the growing season and temporal nesting windows (duration of nesting season). Specifically, resource availability in the Northeast is narrow and highly peaked during the breeding season, potentially resulting in shorter nesting windows. Conversely, resource curves may be more prolonged and dampened in the Southwest, and growing seasons are becoming longer with climate change, potentially resulting in longer nesting windows. We found that the onset of male incubation was negatively associated with lay date. Males from breeding pairs that laid eggs after the start of spring began incubation sooner than males from breeding pairs that laid before the start of spring. Early-onset male incubation was positively associated with hatching asynchrony, creating increased age variation in developing young. In sum, we demonstrate that American kestrels are vulnerable to phenological mismatch, and that this vulnerability varies across space. Northeastern populations could be more vulnerable to mismatch consequences, which may be one factor contributing to declines of kestrels in this region. Also, we demonstrate early onset of incubation as a potential adaptive behavior to advance average hatch date and spread out offspring demands, but it is unknown how impactful this will be in mitigating the fitness consequences of phenology mismatch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Climate-driven phenological mismatch is a growing conservation concern.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We studied phenology and productivity of an avian predator across North America.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;American kestrels nesting after the start of spring had lower productivity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Later nesting kestrels altered incubation to create hatching asynchrony.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mismatch effects were strongest in the Northeast and may contribute to population declines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476385" rel="alternate" title="Phenology effects on productivity and hatching-asynchrony of American kestrels (Falco sparverius) across a continent (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476303</id><title>Host related factors determine co-occurrence patterns between pathogenic bacteria, protozoa, and helminths in populations of the multimammate mouse, Mastomys natalensis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.364933+00:00</updated><author><name>joachim Marien</name></author><author><name>Bram Vanden Broecke</name></author><author><name>Pamela June Tafompa</name></author><author><name>Lisse Bernaerts</name></author><author><name>Alexis Ribas Salvador</name></author><author><name>Ladslaus L. Mnyone</name></author><author><name>Loth Mulungu</name></author><author><name>Herwig Leirs</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Advances in experimental and theoretical work increasingly suggest that parasite interactions within a single host can affect the spread and severity of wildlife diseases. Yet empirical data to support predicted co-infection patterns are limited due to the practical challenges of gathering convincing data from animal populations and the stochastic nature of parasite transmission. Here, we investigated co-infection patterns between micro- (bacteria and protozoa) and macroparasites (gastrointestinal helminths) in natural populations of the multimammate mouse (Mastomys natalensis). Fieldwork was performed in Morogoro (Tanzania), where we trapped 211 individual M. natalensis and tested their behavior using a modified open-field arena. All animals were checked on the presence of helminths in their gastrointestinal tract, three bacteria (Anaplasma, Bartonella, and Borrelia) and two protozoan genera (Piroplasma and Hepatozoon). Besides the presence of eight different helminth genera (reported earlier), we found that 21% of M. natalensis were positive for Anaplasma, 13% for Bartonella, and 2% for Hepatozoon species. Hierarchical modelling of species communities was used to investigate the effect of the different host-related factors on these parasites infection probability and community structure. Our results show that the infection probability of Anaplasma and Bartonella was higher in adults than juveniles. We also observed that females and less explorative individuals had a higher infection probability with Bartonella. We found limited support for within-host interactions between micro-and macroparasites, as only animals infected with Bartonella were significantly more likely to be infected with Protospirura, Trichuris, and Trichostrongylidae helminths.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476303" rel="alternate" title="Host related factors determine co-occurrence patterns between pathogenic bacteria, protozoa, and helminths in populations of the multimammate mouse, Mastomys natalensis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476310</id><title>Non-target effects of ten essential oils on the egg-parasitoid Trichogramma evanescens (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.365013+00:00</updated><author><name>Louise van Oudenhove</name></author><author><name>Aurelie Cazier</name></author><author><name>Marine Fillaud</name></author><author><name>Anne-Violette Lavoir</name></author><author><name>Hicham Fatnassi</name></author><author><name>Guy Perez</name></author><author><name>Vincent Calcagno</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Essential oils (EOs) are increasingly used as biopesticides due to their insecticidal potential. This study addresses their non-target effects on a biological control agent: the egg parasitoid &lt;italic&gt;Trichogramma evanescens&lt;/italic&gt;. In particular, we tested whether EOs affected parasitoid fitness either directly, by decreasing pre-imaginal survival, or indirectly, by disrupting parasitoids' orientation abilities. The effect of Anise, Fennel, Sweet orange,
Basil, Coriander, Oregano, Peppermint, Mugwort, Rosemary and Thyme EOs were studied on five strains of &lt;italic&gt;T. evanescens&lt;/italic&gt;. Specific experimental setups were developed, and data obtained from image analysis were interpreted with phenomenological models fitted with Bayesian inference. Results highlight the fumigant toxicity of EOs on parasitoid development. Anise, Fennel, Basil, Coriander, Oregano, Peppermint and Thyme EOs are particularly toxic and drastically reduce the emergence rate of &lt;italic&gt;T. evanescens&lt;/italic&gt;. Most EOs also affect parasitoid behavior: (i) Basil, Coriander, Oregano, Peppermint, Mugwort and Thyme EOs are highly repellent for naive female parasitoids; (ii) Anise and Fennel EOs can have repellent to attractive effects depending on strains; and (iii) Sweet orange, Oregano and Rosemary EOs have no detectable impact on orientation behavior. This study shows that EOs fumigation have non-target effects on egg parasitoids. This highlights the need to cautiously precise the deployment framework of biopesticides in an agroecological perspective.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476310" rel="alternate" title="Non-target effects of ten essential oils on the egg-parasitoid Trichogramma evanescens (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>