<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv ecology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.770748+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/ecology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.09.451734</id><title>Successful microbial colonization of space using an anti-aggregation strategy (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.771146+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaonan Liu</name></author><author><name>Miaoxiao Wang</name></author><author><name>Yong Nie</name></author><author><name>Xiao-Lei Wu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many organisms live in habitats with limited nutrients or space, competition for these resources is ubiquitous. Although spatial factors related to population's manner of colonizing space influences its success in spatial competition, what these factors are and to what extent they influence the outcome remains under-explored. Here, we applied a simulated competitive model to explore the spatial factors affecting outcomes of competition for space. By quantifying spatial factors using 'Space Accessibility', we show that colonizing space in an anti-aggregation manner contributes to microbial competitive success. We also find that the competitive edge derived from being anti-aggregation in colonizing space, which results in a higher 'Space Accessibility', neutralizes the disadvantage arising from either lower growth rate or lower initial abundance. These findings shed light on the role of space colonization manners on maintaining biodiversity within ecosystems and provide novel insights critical for understanding how competition for space drives evolutionary innovation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.09.451734" rel="alternate" title="Successful microbial colonization of space using an anti-aggregation strategy (10 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.451308</id><title>Hurricane-induced population decrease in a Critically Endangered long-lived reptile (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.771383+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthijs P. van den Burg</name></author><author><name>Hannah Madden</name></author><author><name>Timothy P. van Wagensveld</name></author><author><name>Erik Boman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Catastrophic events, like hurricanes, bring lethal conditions that can have population-altering effects. The threatened Caribbean dry forest occurs in a region known for its high-intensity hurricane seasons and high species endemism, highlighting the necessity to better understand hurricane impacts as fragmentation and clearing of natural habitat continues. However, such studies remain rare, and for reptiles are mostly restricted to &lt;italic&gt;Anolis&lt;/italic&gt;. Here we used single-season occupancy modeling to infer the impact of the intense 2017 Atlantic hurricane season on the critically endangered Lesser Antillean Iguana, &lt;italic&gt;Iguana delicatissima&lt;/italic&gt;. We surveyed 30 transects across eight habitats on St. Eustatius during 2017-2019, which resulted in 344 individual surveys and 98 iguana observations. Analyses of abundance and site occupancy indicated both measures for 2018 and 2019 were strongly reduced compared to the pre-hurricane 2017 state. Iguanas at higher elevations were affected more profoundly, likely due to higher wind speeds, tree damage and extensive defoliation. Overall, our results indicate a decrease in population estimates (23.3-26.5%) and abundance (22-23.8%) for 2018 and 2019, and a 75% reduction in the number of opportunistic sightings of tagged iguanas between 2017-2018. As only small and isolated &lt;italic&gt;I&lt;/italic&gt;. &lt;italic&gt;delicatissima&lt;/italic&gt; populations remain, our study further demonstrates their vulnerability to stochastic events. Considering the frequency and intensity of hurricanes are projected to increase, our results stress the urgent need for population-increasing conservation actions in order to secure the long-term survival of &lt;italic&gt;I&lt;/italic&gt;. &lt;italic&gt;delicatissima&lt;/italic&gt; throughout its range.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.451308" rel="alternate" title="Hurricane-induced population decrease in a Critically Endangered long-lived reptile (5 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>