<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular ecology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.420363+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/ecology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465682</id><title>Identifying barriers to gene flow and hierarchical conservation units from seascape genomics: a modelling framework applied to a marine predator (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.421549+00:00</updated><author><name>Germain Boussarie</name></author><author><name>Paolo Momigliano</name></author><author><name>William D. Robbins</name></author><author><name>Lucas Bonnin</name></author><author><name>Jean-François Cornu</name></author><author><name>Cécile Fauvelot</name></author><author><name>Jeremy J. Kiszka</name></author><author><name>Stéphanie Manel</name></author><author><name>David Mouillot</name></author><author><name>Laurent Vigliola</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ongoing decline of large marine vertebrates must be urgently mitigated, particularly under increasing levels of climate change and other anthropogenic pressures. However, characterizing the connectivity among populations remains one of the greatest challenges for the effective conservation of an increasing number of endangered species. Achieving conservation targets requires an understanding of which seascape features influence dispersal and subsequent genetic structure. This is particularly challenging for adult-disperser species, and when distribution-wide sampling is difficult. Here, we developed a two-step modelling framework to investigate how seascape features drive the genetic connectivity of marine species without larval dispersal, to better guide the design of marine protected area networks and corridors. We applied this framework to the endangered grey reef shark, &lt;italic&gt;Carcharhinus amblyrhynchos&lt;/italic&gt;, a reef-associated shark distributed across the tropical Indo-Pacific. In the first step, we developed a seascape genomic approach based on isolation-by-resistance models involving circuit theory applied to 515 shark samples, genotyped for 4,491 nuclear single-nucleotide polymorphisms, to explore which parameters drive their population genetic differentiation. We show that deep oceanic areas act as strong barriers to dispersal, while proximity to habitat facilitates dispersal. In the second step, we predicted the resulting genetic differentiation across the entire distribution range of the species, providing both local and global-scale conservation units for future management guidance. We found that grey reef shark populations are more fragmented than expected for such a mobile species, raising concerns about the resilience of isolated populations under high anthropogenic pressures. We recommend the use of this framework to identify barriers to gene flow and to help in the delineation of conservation units at different scales, together with its integration across multiple species when considering marine spatial planning.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465682" rel="alternate" title="Identifying barriers to gene flow and hierarchical conservation units from seascape genomics: a modelling framework applied to a marine predator (12 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.22.465436</id><title>An updated framework to account for inter-individual variability when quantifying phenotypic variation (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.421952+00:00</updated><author><name>Giacomo Puglielli</name></author><author><name>Carlos P. Carmona</name></author><author><name>Laura Varone</name></author><author><name>Lauri Laanisto</name></author><author><name>Carlo Ricotta</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;In trait-based ecology, phenotypic variation (&lt;italic&gt;PVar&lt;/italic&gt;) is often quantified with measures that express average differences between populations standardized in the range 0-1. A major problem with these measures is that they disregard the within-population trait variability. In addition, most of these measures cannot be decomposed across scales. This can alter their interpretation, thus limiting their applicability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;To overcome these problems, we propose a new measure, the Phenotypic Dissimilarity Index (PhD) that is insensitive to the within-population interindividual trait variability. Likewise, PhD can be used to quantify &lt;italic&gt;PVar&lt;/italic&gt; between individuals in a population while accounting for the &lt;italic&gt;PVar&lt;/italic&gt; within individuals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using simulated and real data, we showed that PhD index correctly quantifies &lt;italic&gt;PVar&lt;/italic&gt; when the within-population trait variability is not negligible, as in many ecological studies. By accounting for within-population trait variability, the PhD index generally provides a more parsimonious quantification of &lt;italic&gt;PVar&lt;/italic&gt; across an environmental gradient compared to other estimators.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Traits sampled within a species have an inherent variability. Accounting for such variability is essential to understand species phenotypic responses to environmental cues. As such, the PhD index will provide ecologists with an asset to reliably quantify and compare &lt;italic&gt;PVar&lt;/italic&gt; within and between species across environmental gradients at different scales. We also provide an R function to calculate the PhD index.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.22.465436" rel="alternate" title="An updated framework to account for inter-individual variability when quantifying phenotypic variation (11 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466299</id><title>Reproduction, seasonal morphology, and juvenile growth in three Malagasy fruit bats (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.422250+00:00</updated><author><name>Angelo Andrianiaina</name></author><author><name>Santino Andry</name></author><author><name>Anecia Gentles</name></author><author><name>Sarah Guth</name></author><author><name>Jean-Michel Heraud</name></author><author><name>Hafaliana Christian Ranaivoson</name></author><author><name>Ny Anjara Fifi Ravelomanantsoa</name></author><author><name>Timothy Treuer</name></author><author><name>Cara E Brook</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The island nation of Madagascar is home to three endemic species of Old World Fruit Bat in the family Pteropodidae: Pteropus rufus, Eidolon dupreanum, and Rousettus madagascariensis, all three of which are IUCN Red Listed under some category of threat. To inform conservation efforts to model population viability for these threatened species, as well understand the mechanisms underpinning persistence of several potentially zoonotic pathogens hosted by these bats, we here define the seasonal limits of a staggered annual birth pulse across the three species. Our field studies in central-eastern Madagascar indicate that this annual birth pulse takes place in September/October for P. rufus, November for E. dupreanum, and December for R. madagascariensis. Juvenile development periods vary across the three Malagasy pteropodids, resulting in near-synchronous weaning of pups for all species in late January-February at the height of the fruiting season for Madagascar, a pattern characteristic of most mammalian frugivores on the island. We here document the size range in morphological traits for the three Malagasy fruit bat species; these traits span the range of those known for pteropodids more broadly, with P. rufus and E. dupreanum among the larger of recorded species and R. madagascariensis among the smaller. All three species demonstrate subtle sexual dimorphism in observed traits with larger-bodied males vs. females. We explore seasonal variation in adult body condition by comparing observed body mass with body mass predicted by forearm length, demonstrating that pregnant females add weight during staggered gestation periods and males lose weight during the nutritionally-deficit Malagasy winter. Finally, we quantify forearm, tibia, and ear length growth rates in juvenile bats, demonstrating both faster growth and more protracted development times for the largest P. rufus species. The longer development period for the already-threatened P. rufus further jeopardizes this species' conservation status as human hunting of bats for subsistence is particularly detrimental to population viability during reproductive periods. The more extreme seasonal variation in the mass to forearm relationship for P. rufus may also modulate immune function, an important consideration given these bats' roles as reservoir hosts for several high profile viral families known to cause severe disease in humans. Our work highlights the importance of longitudinal field studies in collecting critical data for mammalian conservation efforts and human public health alike.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466299" rel="alternate" title="Reproduction, seasonal morphology, and juvenile growth in three Malagasy fruit bats (9 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466118</id><title>How far to build it before they come? Analyzing the use of the Field of Dreams hypothesis to bull kelp restoration (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.422885+00:00</updated><author><name>Jorge Arroyo-Esquivel</name></author><author><name>Marissa L. Baskett</name></author><author><name>Meredith McPherson</name></author><author><name>Alan Hastings</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In restoration ecology, the Field of Dreams Hypothesis posits that restoration efforts that create a suitable environment could lead to eventual recovery of the remaining aspects of the ecosystem through natural processes. Natural processes following partial restoration has lead to ecosystem recovery in both terrestrial and aquatic systems. However, understanding the efficacy of a “field of dreams” approach requires comparison of different approaches to partial restoration in terms of spatial, temporal, and ecological scale to what would happen with more comprehensive restoration efforts. We explore the relative effect of partial restoration and ongoing recovery on restoration efficacy with a dynamical model based on temperate rocky reefs in Northern California. We analyze our model for both the ability and rate of bull kelp forest recovery under different restoration strategies. We compare the efficacy of a partial restoration approach with a more comprehensive restoration effort by exploring how kelp recovery likelihood and rate change with varying intensities of urchin removal and kelp outplanting over different time periods and spatial scales. We find that, for the case of bull kelp forests, setting more favorable initial conditions for kelp recovery through implementing both urchin harvesting and kelp outplanting at the start of the restoration project has a bigger impact on the kelp recovery rate than applying restoration efforts through a longer period of time. Therefore partial restoration efforts, in terms of spatial and temporal scale, can be significantly more effective when applied across multiple ecological scales in terms of both the capacity and rate of achieving the target outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Open Research Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The data used in this work is presented in McPherson et al. (2021). The code used to run the simulations can be found in &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/jarroyoe/kelp-restoration-modeling"&gt;https://github.com/jarroyoe/kelp-restoration-modeling&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466118" rel="alternate" title="How far to build it before they come? Analyzing the use of the Field of Dreams hypothesis to bull kelp restoration (6 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465697</id><title>Uncertainty and precaution in hunting wolves twice in a year (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.423538+00:00</updated><author><name>Adrian Treves</name></author><author><name>Naomi X. Louchouarn</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;When humanity confronts the risk of extinction of species, many people invoke precautions, especially in the face of uncertainty. Although precautionary approaches are value judgments, the timing and effect of precautions or lack thereof are scientific questions. We investigated the Wisconsin gray wolves &lt;italic&gt;Canis lupus&lt;/italic&gt; facing a second wolf-hunt in November 2021 and use three legal thresholds as the societal value judgments about precautions: (1) the 1999 population goal, 350 wolves, (2) the threshold for statutory listing under the state threatened and endangered species act, 250 wolves; and (3) state extirpation &amp;lt;2 wolves. This allows us to explore the quantitative relationship between precaution and uncertainty. Working from estimates of the state wolf population in April 2021 and an estimate of reproduction to November, we constructed a simple linear model with uninformative priors for the period April 2021-April 2022 including an uncertain wolf-hunt in November 2021. Our first result is that the state government under-counted wolf deaths in the year preceding both wolf-hunts. This emphasizes the need for greater precaution in setting wolf-hunt quotas. We find official recommendations for a quota for the November 2021 wolf-hunt risk undesirable outcomes. Even a quota of zero has a 13% chance of crossing threshold 1. Therefore, a zero death toll would be precautionary. Proponents for high quotas bear the burden of proof that their estimates are accurate, precise, and reproducible. We show how scientists have the tools and concepts for quantifying and explaining the probabilities of crossing thresholds set by laws or other social norms. Refusal by scientists to account for uncertainty opens the door to policy-making based on opinion, anecdote, and political rivalries. We recommend instead that scientists grapple with data gaps by explaining what the uncertainty means for policy and the public including the consequences of being wrong.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465697" rel="alternate" title="Uncertainty and precaution in hunting wolves twice in a year (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>