<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular ecology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.799599+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/ecology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.466696</id><title>A paradox of parasite resistance: Disease-driven trophic cascades increase the cost of resistance, selecting for lower resistance with parasites than without them (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.800416+00:00</updated><author><name>Jason Cosens Walsman</name></author><author><name>Alexander T Strauss</name></author><author><name>Jessica Hite</name></author><author><name>Marta S Shocket</name></author><author><name>Spencer R Hall</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Most evolutionary theory predicts that, during epidemics, hosts will evolve higher resistance to parasites that kill them. Here, we provide an alternative to that typical expectation, with an explanation centered on resource feedbacks. When resistance is costly, hosts evolve decreasing resistance without parasites, as expected. But with parasites, hosts can evolve lower resistance than they would in the absence of parasites. This outcome arises in an eco-evolutionary model when four conditions are met: first, resistance has a fecundity cost (here, via decreased foraging/exposure rate); second, resources increase during epidemics via trophic cascades; third, increased resources magnify the benefit of maintaining a fast foraging rate, thereby magnifying the cost of evolving a slower foraging/exposure rate (i.e., resistance); fourth, that amplification of the cost outweighs the benefit of resistance. When these conditions are met, hosts evolve lower resistance than without parasites. This phenomenon was previously observed in a mesocosm experiment with fungal parasites, zooplankton hosts, and algal resources. Re-analyzing this experiment produced evidence for our model's mechanism. Thus, both model and experiment indicate that, via resource feedbacks, parasites can counterintuitively select against resistance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.466696" rel="alternate" title="A paradox of parasite resistance: Disease-driven trophic cascades increase the cost of resistance, selecting for lower resistance with parasites than without them (14 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466905</id><title>Bacterial colonisation dynamics of household plastics in a coastal environment (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.800735+00:00</updated><author><name>Luke Lear</name></author><author><name>Daniel Padfield</name></author><author><name>Tirion Dowsett</name></author><author><name>Maia Jones</name></author><author><name>Suzanne Kay</name></author><author><name>Alex Hayward</name></author><author><name>Michiel Vos</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Accumulation of plastics in the marine environment has widespread detrimental consequences for ecosystems and wildlife. Marine plastics are rapidly colonised by a wide diversity of bacteria, including human pathogens, posing potential risks to human health. Here, we investigate the effect of polymer type, residence time and estuarine location on bacterial colonisation of common household plastics, including pathogenic bacteria. To do so, we submerged five main household plastic types: low-density PE (LDPE), high-density PE (HDPE), polypropylene (PP), polyvinyl chloride (PVC) and polyethylene terephthalate (PET) at an estuarine site in Cornwall (U.K.) and tracked bacterial colonisation dynamics. Using both culture-dependent and culture-independent approaches, we found that bacteria rapidly colonised plastics irrespective of polymer type. While biofilm community composition changed with colonisation time, no difference was observed between polymer types. Likewise, the presence of pathogenic bacteria, quantified using the insect model Galleria mellonella, increased over a five-week period, with no consistent differences observed between polymer types. Pathogens isolated from plastic biofilms using Galleria enrichment included Serratia and Enterococcus species and harboured a wide range of antimicrobial resistance genes. Our findings show that plastics in coastal waters are rapidly colonised by a wide diversity of bacteria, including known human pathogens, independent of polymer type.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466905" rel="alternate" title="Bacterial colonisation dynamics of household plastics in a coastal environment (5 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467033</id><title>A multi-species co-occurrence index to avoid type II errors in null model testing (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.801169+00:00</updated><author><name>Vitalis K. Lagat</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Latombe</name></author><author><name>Cang Hui</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Community structure is determined by the interplay among different processes, including biotic interactions, abiotic filtering and dispersal. Their effects can be detected by comparing observed patterns of co-occurrence between different species (e.g. C-score and the natural metric) to patterns generated by null models based on permutations of species-by-site matrices under constraints on row or column sums. These comparisons enable us to detect significant signals of species association or dissociation, from which the type of biotic interactions between species (e.g. facilitative or antagonistic) can be inferred. Commonly used patterns are based on the levels of co-occurrence between randomly paired species. The level of co-occurrence for three or more species is rarely considered, ignoring the potential existence of functional guilds or motifs composed of multiple species within the community. Null model tests that do not consider multi-species co-occurrence could therefore generate false negatives (Type II error) in detecting non-random forces at play that would only be apparent for such guilds. Here, we propose a multi-species co-occurrence index (hereafter, joint occupancy) that measures the number of sites jointly occupied by multiple species simultaneously, of which the pairwise metric of co-occurrence is a special case. Using this joint occupancy index along with standard permutation algorithms for null model testing, we illustrate nine archetypes of multi-species co-occurrence and explore how frequent they are in the seminal database of 289 species-by-site community matrices published by Atmar and Patterson in 1995. We show that null model testing using pairwise co-occurrence metrics could indeed lead to severe Type II errors in one specific archetype, accounting for 2.4% of the tested community matrices.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467033" rel="alternate" title="A multi-species co-occurrence index to avoid type II errors in null model testing (5 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.462738</id><title>Fungal biodiversity in Arctic paleoecosystems assessed by metabarcoding of lake sedimentary ancient DNA (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.801402+00:00</updated><author><name>Peter A. Seeber</name></author><author><name>Barbara von Hippel</name></author><author><name>Havard Kauserud</name></author><author><name>Ulrike Loeber</name></author><author><name>Kathleen Stoof-Leichsenring</name></author><author><name>Ulrike Herzschuh</name></author><author><name>Laura Epp</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fungi are crucial organisms in most ecosystems as they exert ecological key functions and are closely associated with land plants. Fungal community changes may therefore help reveal biodiversity changes in past ecosystems. Lake sediments contain DNA of organisms in the catchment area, which allows reconstructing past biodiversity by using metabarcoding of ancient sedimentary DNA. We developed a novel PCR primer combination for fungal metabarcoding targeting a short amplicon to account for length bias of amplification due to ancient DNA degradation. In-silico PCRs showed higher diversity using this primer combination than using previously established fungal metabarcoding primers. We analyzed existing data from sediment cores from four artic and one boreal lake in Siberia. These cores had been stored for 2-22 years and examined degradation effects of ancient DNA and storage time-related bias in fungal communities. Amplicon size differed between fungal divisions, however, we observed no significant effect of sample age on amplicon length and GC content, suggesting robust results. We also found no indication of post-coring fungal growth during storage distorting ancient fungal communities. Terrestrial soil fungi, including mycorrhizal fungi and saprotrophs, were predominant in all lakes, which supports the use of lake sedimentary ancient DNA for reconstructing terrestrial communities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.462738" rel="alternate" title="Fungal biodiversity in Arctic paleoecosystems assessed by metabarcoding of lake sedimentary ancient DNA (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466526</id><title>Serial invasions can disrupt the time course of ecosystem recovery (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.815753+00:00</updated><author><name>Vadim A. Karatayev</name></author><author><name>Lars G. Rudstam</name></author><author><name>Alexander Y. Karatayev</name></author><author><name>Lyubov E. Burlakova</name></author><author><name>Boris V. Adamovich</name></author><author><name>Hanna A. Zhukava</name></author><author><name>Kristen T. Holeck</name></author><author><name>Amy Lee Hetherington</name></author><author><name>James R. Jackson</name></author><author><name>Christopher W. Hotaling</name></author><author><name>Tatyana V. Zhukova</name></author><author><name>Tamara M. Mikheyeva</name></author><author><name>Raisa Z. Kovalevskaya</name></author><author><name>Oleg A. Makarevich</name></author><author><name>Darya V. Kruk</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The impacts of species invasions can subside or amplify over time as ecosystems “adapt” or additional invaders arrive. These long-term changes provide important insights into ecosystem dynamics. Yet studies of long-term dynamics are rare and often confound species impacts with coincident environmental change. We synthesize many-decade time-series across ecosystems to resolve shared changes in seven key features following invasion by quagga and zebra mussels, two widespread congeners that re-engineer and increasingly co-invade freshwaters. Six polymictic shallow lakes with long-term data sets reveal remarkably similar trends, with the strongest ecosystem impacts occurring within 5-10 years of zebra mussel invasion. Surprisingly, plankton communities then exhibited a partial, significant recovery. This recovery was absent, and impacts of initial invasion amplified, in lakes where quagga mussels outcompeted zebra mussels and more completely depleted phytoplankton. Thus, invasion impacts subside over time but can amplify with serial introductions of competing, even closely similar, taxa.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466526" rel="alternate" title="Serial invasions can disrupt the time course of ecosystem recovery (3 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>