<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular ecology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.806442+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/ecology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453574</id><title>Bats host the most virulent—but not the most dangerous—zoonotic viruses (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.807583+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah Guth</name></author><author><name>Nardus Mollentze</name></author><author><name>Katia Renault</name></author><author><name>Daniel G. Streicker</name></author><author><name>Elisa Visher</name></author><author><name>Mike Boots</name></author><author><name>Cara E. Brook</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Identifying virus characteristics associated with the largest public health impacts on human populations is critical to informing zoonotic risk assessments and surveillance strategies. Efforts to assess “zoonotic risk” often use trait-based analyses to identify which viral and reservoir host groups are most likely to source zoonoses but have not fully addressed how and why the impacts of zoonotic viruses vary in terms of disease severity (‘virulence’), capacity to spread within human populations (‘transmissibility’), or total human mortality (‘death burden’). We analyzed trends in human case fatality rates, transmission capacities, and total death burdens across a comprehensive dataset of mammalian and avian zoonotic viruses. Bats harbor the most virulent zoonotic viruses even when compared to birds, which alongside bats, have been hypothesized to be “special” zoonotic reservoirs due to molecular adaptations that support the physiology of flight. Reservoir host groups more closely related to humans—in particular, Primates—harbor less virulent, but more highly transmissible viruses. Importantly, disproportionately high human death burden, arguably the most important metric of zoonotic risk, is not associated with any animal reservoir, including bats. Our data demonstrate that mechanisms driving death burdens are diverse and often contradict trait-based predictions. Ultimately, total human mortality is dependent on context-specific epidemiological dynamics, which are shaped by a combination of viral traits and conditions in the animal host population and across and beyond the human-animal interface. Understanding the conditions that predict high zoonotic burden in humans will require longitudinal studies of epidemiological dynamics in wildlife and human populations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The clear need to mitigate zoonotic risk has fueled increased viral discovery in specific reservoir host taxa. We show that a combination of viral and reservoir traits can predict zoonotic virus virulence and transmissibility in humans, supporting the hypothesis that bats harbor exceptionally virulent zoonoses. However, pandemic prevention requires thinking beyond zoonotic capacity, virulence, and transmissibility to consider collective ‘burden’ on human health. For this, viral discovery targeting specific reservoirs may be inefficient as death burden correlates with viral, not reservoir, traits, and depends on context-specific epidemiological dynamics across and beyond the human-animal interface. These findings suggest that longitudinal studies of viral dynamics in reservoir and spillover host populations may offer the most effective strategy for mitigating zoonotic risk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453574" rel="alternate" title="Bats host the most virulent—but not the most dangerous—zoonotic viruses (12 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453807</id><title>The benefits of merging two tracking approaches: passive acoustic telemetry combined with active acoustic tracking by transects provide new insights into riverine migration by salmonid smolts (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.808020+00:00</updated><author><name>Louise Chavarie</name></author><author><name>Hannele M. Honkanen</name></author><author><name>Matthew Newton</name></author><author><name>Jessie M. Lilly</name></author><author><name>Hannah R. Greetham</name></author><author><name>Colin E. Adams</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The process of smolting is a critical phase in the life-cycle of anadromous salmonids and it has been associated with substantial rates of mortality. Survival during freshwater and marine migration is known to have population level effects, thus an understanding of the patterns of mortality has the potential to yield important insights into population bottlenecks. Despite important advancements in tracking techniques, the specifics of mortality events in anadromous salmonids during their initial migration to sea remains somewhat elusive. Here, we develop a framework combining spatial and temporal detections of smolt riverine migration from two tracking techniques, which enable inferences to be made about mortality locations, causes, and rates. We embed this framework into a fine-scale behaviour study of migration and social structure. In this study, we demonstrate that during their initial riverine transitional phase, smolts were particularly vulnerable to predators. Specifically, avian predation appeared to be the main cause of mortality (42%), although piscine predation events were not trivial (14%). Our results suggested some direct and indirect tagging-induced mortality (e.g., through increased predation vulnerability), which highlights the importance of determining tagging mortality in a telemetry study to ensure adequate interpretation of migration success. There is evidence that predation induced selection on smolt morphology. Unsuccessful river salmon migrants with a phenotype comprising a shorter head and jaw and smaller eye had a higher probability of mortality in the later parts of riverine migration where avian and aquatic predation mortality dominated. In contrast, mortality earlier in river migration was independent of phenotype, most likely a result of tagging effects. Successfully river migrants were found to be interacting with each other, often in a pair or as a trio, indicating that a few individuals of Atlantic salmon and sea trout formed notable intra- and interspecific social associations. However, the heterogeneity of the social associations of successful migrants did not support the assumption that social network features attributed any clear specific benefits of reduced predation risk. Overall, by estimating migration loss and its variability, our study framework should help to guide management actions to mitigate the widespread population declines these species are currently facing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453807" rel="alternate" title="The benefits of merging two tracking approaches: passive acoustic telemetry combined with active acoustic tracking by transects provide new insights into riverine migration by salmonid smolts (11 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.30.454541</id><title>Intraspecific interaction of host plant influences local distribution of specialist herbivores through metabolic alterations in leaves (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.808442+00:00</updated><author><name>Haruna Ohsaki</name></author><author><name>Atsuko Miyagi</name></author><author><name>Maki Kawai-Yamada</name></author><author><name>Akira Yamawo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent studies suggest that changes in leaf traits due to interactions between plants affect the resource utilisation and distribution of herbivores. However, this has not yet been confirmed experimentally. Here, we investigated the effects of phenotypic plasticity in leaf traits of &lt;italic&gt;Rumex obtusifolius&lt;/italic&gt; (host plant) in response to the intra and interspecific interaction on distribution of two leaf beetles, &lt;italic&gt;Gastrophysa atrocyanea&lt;/italic&gt; (specialist herbivore) and &lt;italic&gt;Galerucella grisescens&lt;/italic&gt; (generalist herbivore). We investigated the local population density of &lt;italic&gt;R. obtusifolius&lt;/italic&gt; plants and the presence of leaf beetles on the plants at five study sites. Leaf chemicals (condensed tannins and total phenolics) were compared between aggregated and solitary &lt;italic&gt;R. obtusifolius&lt;/italic&gt; plants. To clarify the effects of the interaction environment of &lt;italic&gt;R. obtusifolius&lt;/italic&gt; plants on their leaf traits and resource utilisation by leaf beetles, we conducted cultivation and preference experiments. Leaf chemicals (chlorophylls, organic acids, primary metabolites, condensed tannins and total phenolics) and preferences of adult leaf beetles were compared between intraspecific, interspecific plant interaction, or no-interaction treatments. Finally, we evaluated the effects of interaction between &lt;italic&gt;R. obtusifolius&lt;/italic&gt; on leaf beetle distribution in mesocosm experiments. In the field, the presence of the specialist leaf beetle, &lt;italic&gt;G. atrocyanea&lt;/italic&gt;, was positively correlated with the local population density (rosette overlap ratio) of &lt;italic&gt;R. obtusifolius&lt;/italic&gt; plants; however, no correlation was observed in the case of the generalist leaf beetle, &lt;italic&gt;G. grisescens&lt;/italic&gt;. In the cultivation experiment, plants in the intraspecific interaction treatment increased their leaf contents of condensed tannins and total phenolics, and &lt;italic&gt;G. atrocyanea&lt;/italic&gt; consumed more of these leaves than leaves in other treatments. Similar results were observed in the field. In the mesocosm experiment, larger numbers of &lt;italic&gt;G. atrocyanea&lt;/italic&gt; were distributed on &lt;italic&gt;R. obtusifolius&lt;/italic&gt; plants exposed to below-ground intraspecific interaction than on plants not exposed to intraspecific interaction. Our results provide experimental evidence that leaf trait changes in response to intraspecific interaction between host plants influence specialist herbivore distribution. This highlights the need to integrate plant plant interactions into our understanding of plant animal interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.30.454541" rel="alternate" title="Intraspecific interaction of host plant influences local distribution of specialist herbivores through metabolic alterations in leaves (7 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-07-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.29.454288</id><title>Patterns of morphological diversification in the Ramphastoidea reveal the dramatic divergence of toucans from a conserved morphotype (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.809504+00:00</updated><author><name>Krishnapriya Tamma</name></author><author><name>Anand Krishnan</name></author><author><name>Sushma Reddy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Morphological traits offer insights into an organism s ecological niche, species interactions, and patterns of community organisation. Pantropical lineages - animals and plants distributed across the three tropical continental regions of Asia, Africa, and America - provide a way to test how different environments and communities influence morphological diversification. Here, we examined a monophyletic group of frugivorous birds, the barbets and toucans (Ramphastoidea), which diversified independently on three continents, to investigate whether clades in each region exhibit similar (phylogenetically constrained) or distinct (ecologically influenced) patterns of morphological diversification. Our results show that despite differences in community dynamics in these regions, lineage accumulation patterns through time on all three continents are broadly similar, putatively due to phylogenetic niche conservatism. We quantified morphological variation in light of phylogenetic relatedness to further reveal that all barbet lineages across continents occupy a conserved region of morphospace after correcting for variation in size. However, in the Neotropics, one lineage, the toucans, have diverged dramatically from typical barbet space and converged toward (yet are distinct from) the trait space occupied by the distantly related hornbills in Asia and Africa. Additionally, we found no link between climatic variables and morphological traits. We conclude that barbets exhibit a conserved morphotype across continents and have diversified by scaling mainly in body size. However, the absence of other large frugivorous birds may have allowed toucans to diversify into a different region of morphospace of increased bill/wing to tail/wing ratios. By examining different continental lineages of a single monophyletic bird group, we shed light on the contrasting effects of regional ecological factors and phylogenetic constraints on morphological diversification.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.29.454288" rel="alternate" title="Patterns of morphological diversification in the Ramphastoidea reveal the dramatic divergence of toucans from a conserved morphotype (7 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453227</id><title>Disentangling key species interactions in diverse and heterogeneous communities: A Bayesian sparse modeling approach (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.809688+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher P. Weiss-Lehman</name></author><author><name>Chhaya M. Werner</name></author><author><name>Catherine H. Bowler</name></author><author><name>Lauren M. Hallett</name></author><author><name>Margaret M. Mayfield</name></author><author><name>Oscar Godoy</name></author><author><name>Lina Aoyama</name></author><author><name>György Barabás</name></author><author><name>Chengjin Chu</name></author><author><name>Emma Ladouceur</name></author><author><name>Loralee Larios</name></author><author><name>Lauren G. Shoemaker</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Modeling species interactions in diverse communities traditionally requires a prohibitively large number of species-interaction coefficients, especially when considering environmental dependence of parameters. We implemented Bayesian variable selection via sparsity-inducing priors on non-linear species abundance models to determine which species-interactions should be retained and which can be represented as an average heterospecific interaction term, reducing the number of model parameters. We evaluated model performance using simulated communities, computing out-of-sample predictive accuracy and parameter recovery across different input sample sizes. We applied our method to a diverse empirical community, allowing us to disentangle the direct role of environmental gradients on species’ intrinsic growth rates from indirect effects via competitive interactions. We also identified a few neighboring species from the diverse community that had non-generic interactions with our focal species. This sparse modeling approach facilitates exploration of species-interactions in diverse communities while maintaining a manageable number of parameters.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453227" rel="alternate" title="Disentangling key species interactions in diverse and heterogeneous communities: A Bayesian sparse modeling approach (5 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>