<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv ecology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.579866+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/ecology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443287</id><title>Elucidating the diversity of microeukaryotes and epi-endophytes in the brown algal holobiome (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.580143+00:00</updated><author><name>Marit F. Markussen Bjorbækmo</name></author><author><name>Juliet Brodie</name></author><author><name>Ramiro Logares</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Attwood</name></author><author><name>Stein Fredriksen</name></author><author><name>Janina Fuss</name></author><author><name>Kamran Shalchian-Tabrizi</name></author><author><name>Anders Wold-Dobbe</name></author><author><name>Anders K. Krabberød</name></author><author><name>David Bass</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Brown algae (Phaeophyceae) are essential species in coastal ecosystems where they form kelp forests and seaweed beds that support a wide diversity of marine life. Host- associated microbial communities are an integral part of phaeophyte biology. The bacterial microbial partners of phaeophytes have received far more attention than microbial eukaryotes. The pre-requisite to understand the ecology of phaeophytes and their host-associated microbes is to know their diversity, distribution and community dynamics. To our knowledge, this is the first study to investigate phaeophyte-associated eukaryotes (the eukaryome) using broadly targeting ‘pan-eukaryotic’ primers and high throughput sequencing (HTS). Using this approach, we aimed to unveil the eukaryome of seven large common phaeophyte species. We also aimed to assess whether these macroalgae harbour novel eukaryotic diversity and to ascribe putative functional roles to the host-associated eukaryome, based on taxonomic affiliation and phylogenetic placement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our sequence dataset was dominated by phaeophyte reads, from the host species and potential symbionts. We also detected a broad taxonomic diversity of eukaryotes in the phaeophyte holobiomes, with OTUs taxonomically assigned to ten of the eukaryotic major Kingdoms or supergroups. A total of 265 microeukaryotic and epi-endophytic operational taxonomic units (OTUs) were defined, using 97% similarity cut off during clustering, and were dominated by OTUs assigned to Stramenopiles, Alveolata and Fungi. C Almost one third of the OTUs we detected have not been found in previous molecular environmental surveys, and represented potential novel eukaryotic diversity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This potential novel diversity was particularly diverse in phylogenetic groups comprising heterotrophic and parasitic organisms, such as labyrinthulids and Oomycetes, Cercozoa, and Amoebozoa.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our findings provide important baseline data for future studies of seaweed-associated microorganisms, and demonstrate that microeukaryotes and epi-endophytic eukaryotes should be considered as an integral part of phaeophyte holobionts. The potential novel eukaryotic diversity we found and the fact that the vast majority of macroalgae in marine habitats remain unexplored, demonstrates that brown algae and other seaweeds are potentially rich sources for a large and hidden diversity of novel microeukaryotes and epi-endophytes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443287" rel="alternate" title="Elucidating the diversity of microeukaryotes and epi-endophytes in the brown algal holobiome (18 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443792</id><title>A gene expression panel for estimating age in males and females of the sleeping sickness vector Glossina morsitans (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.580416+00:00</updated><author><name>Eric R. Lucas</name></author><author><name>Alistair C. Darby</name></author><author><name>Stephen J. Torr</name></author><author><name>Martin J. Donnelly</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many vector-borne diseases are controlled by methods that kill the insect vectors responsible for disease transmission. Recording the age structure of vector populations provides information on mortality rates and vectorial capacity, and should form part of the detailed monitoring that occurs in the wake of control programmes, yet tools for obtaining estimates of individual age remain limited. We investigate the potential of using markers of gene expression to predict age in tsetse flies, which are the vectors of deadly and economically damaging African trypanosomiases. We use RNAseq to identify candidate expression markers, and test these markers using qPCR in laboratory-reared &lt;italic&gt;Glossina morstians morsitans&lt;/italic&gt; of known age. Measuring the expression of six genes was sufficient to obtain a prediction of age with root mean squared error of less than 8 days, while just two genes were sufficient to classify flies into age categories of ≤ 15 and &amp;gt;15 days old. Further testing of these markers in field-caught samples and in other species will determine the accuracy of these markers in the field.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443792" rel="alternate" title="A gene expression panel for estimating age in males and females of the sleeping sickness vector Glossina morsitans (13 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443351</id><title>How much pollen do solitary bee larvae consume? : Or establishing realistic exposure estimates of solitary bee larvae via pollen for the use in risk assessment (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.580593+00:00</updated><author><name>Tobias Pamminger</name></author><author><name>Christof Schneider</name></author><author><name>Raffael Maas</name></author><author><name>Matthias Bergtold</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bees foraging in agricultural habitats can be exposed to plant protection products. In order to limit the risk of adverse events to occur a robust risk assessment is needed, which requires reliable estimates for the expected exposure. Especially the exposure pathways to developing solitary bees are not well described and in the currently proposed form rely on limited information. To address this topic, we used a published data set on the volume of pollen solitary bees provide for their larvae to build two scaling models predicting the amount of protein and pollen developing solitary bees need based on adult body weight. We test our models using both literature and experimental data, which both support the validity of the presented models. Using scaling models in the bee risk assessment could complement existing risk assessment approaches, facilitate the further development of accurate risk characterization for solitary bees and ultimately will help to protect them during their foraging activity in agricultural settings.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443351" rel="alternate" title="How much pollen do solitary bee larvae consume? : Or establishing realistic exposure estimates of solitary bee larvae via pollen for the use in risk assessment (11 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443696</id><title>One Hundred and Fifty Years of Warming on Caribbean Coral Reefs (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.580906+00:00</updated><author><name>Colleen B. Bove</name></author><author><name>Laura Mudge</name></author><author><name>John F. Bruno</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Anthropogenic climate change is rapidly altering the characteristics and dynamics of biological communities. This is especially apparent in marine systems as the world’s oceans are warming at an unprecedented rate, causing dramatic changes to coastal marine systems, especially on coral reefs of the Caribbean. We used three complementary ocean temperature databases (HadISST, Pathfinder, and OISST) to quantify change in thermal characteristics of Caribbean coral reefs over the last 150 years (1871–2020). These sea surface temperature (SST) databases included combined &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; and satellite-derived SST (HadISST, OISST), as well as satellite-only observations (Pathfinder) at multiple spatial resolutions. We also compiled a Caribbean coral reef database identifying 5,326 unique reefs across the region. We found that Caribbean reefs have warmed on average by 0.20 °C per decade since 1987, the calculated year that rapid warming began on Caribbean reefs. Further, geographic variation in warming rates ranged from 0.17 °C per decade on Bahamian reefs to 0.26 °C per decade on reefs within the Southern and Eastern Caribbean ecoregions. If this linear rate of warming continues, these already threatened ecosystems would warm by an &lt;italic&gt;additional&lt;/italic&gt; 1.6 °C on average by 2100. We also found that marine heatwave (MHW) events are increasing in both frequency and duration across the Caribbean. Caribbean coral reefs now experience on average 5 MHW events annually, compared to 1 per year in the early 1980s. Combined, these changes have caused a dramatic shift in the composition and function of Caribbean coral reef ecosystems. If reefs continue to warm at this rate, we are likely to lose even the remnant Caribbean coral reef communities of today in the coming decades.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443696" rel="alternate" title="One Hundred and Fifty Years of Warming on Caribbean Coral Reefs (10 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443669</id><title>On the Contribution of Reproductive and Offspring Investment on Fertility: Human and Animal Societies (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.581095+00:00</updated><author><name>Anuraag Bukkuri</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Differences in investment into reproduction or offspring rearing are plentiful throughout the world, from the cells inside our bodies to complex sociological interactions among humans. Such differences can lead to profound impacts on species’ fitness, fertility, and reproductive rates, sometimes in startling ways. In this paper, we create a simple game-theoretical model to &lt;italic&gt;qualitatively&lt;/italic&gt; investigate the effects of such differential investment. We focus on fertility in human societies and show that more wealthy individuals produce more offspring within a a mating group. However, when assortative mating mechanisms are introduced, this effectively leads to a speciation event, and a higher reproduction rate for poorer individuals is noticed, capturing what we call the “wealthy-to-poor switch”. We discuss extensions and implications of this work to nupital gifts in ecology and to clonal competition in cancer cell lines under the influence of treatment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443669" rel="alternate" title="On the Contribution of Reproductive and Offspring Investment on Fertility: Human and Animal Societies (7 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.444034</id><title>Increasing temperature weakens the positive effect of genetic diversity on population growth (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.581229+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexandra L Singleton</name></author><author><name>Samantha Votzke</name></author><author><name>Andrea Yammine</name></author><author><name>Jean P Gibert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genetic diversity and temperature increases associated with global climate change, are known to independently influence population growth and extinction risk. Whether increasing temperature may influence the effect of genetic diversity on population growth, however, is not known. We address this issue in the model protist system Tetrahymena thermophila. We test the hypothesis that at temperatures closer to the species thermal optimum (i.e., the temperature at which population growth is maximal), genetic diversity should have a weaker effect on population growth compared to temperatures away from the thermal optimum. To do so, we grew populations of T. thermophila with varying levels of genetic diversity at increasingly warmer temperatures and quantified their intrinsic population growth rate, r. We found that genetic diversity increases population growth at cooler temperatures, but that as temperature increases, this effect almost completely disappears. We also show that a combination of changes in the amount of expressed genetic diversity (G), plastic changes in population growth across temperatures (E), and strong GxE interactions, underlie this temperature effect. Our results uncover important but largely overlooked temperature effects that have implications for the management of small populations with depauperate genetic stocks in an increasingly warming world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.444034" rel="alternate" title="Increasing temperature weakens the positive effect of genetic diversity on population growth (5 tweets)"/><category term="Ecology"/><published>2021-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>