<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.990916+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475204</id><title>Structure of the human inner kinetochore CCAN complex and its significance for human centromere organization (94 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.991547+00:00</updated><author><name>Marion E. Pesenti</name></author><author><name>Tobias Raisch</name></author><author><name>Duccio Conti</name></author><author><name>Ingrid Hoffmann</name></author><author><name>Dorothee Vogt</name></author><author><name>Daniel Prumbaum</name></author><author><name>Ingrid R. Vetter</name></author><author><name>Stefan Raunser</name></author><author><name>Andrea Musacchio</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Centromeres are specialized chromosome loci that seed the kinetochore, a large protein complex that effects chromosome segregation. The organization of the interface between the kinetochore and the specialized centromeric chromatin, marked by the histone H3 variant CENP-A, remains incompletely understood. A 16-subunit complex, the constitutive centromere associated network (CCAN), bridges CENP-A to the spindle-binding moiety of the kinetochore. Here, we report a cryo-electron microscopy structure of human CCAN. We highlight unique features such as the pseudo GTPase CENP-M and report how a crucial CENP-C motif binds the CENP-LN complex. The CCAN structure has also important implications for the mechanism of specific recognition of the CENP-A nucleosome. A supported model depicts the interaction as fuzzy and identifies the disordered CCAN subunit CENP-C as only determinant of specificity. A more speculative model identifies both CENP-C and CENP-N as specificity determinants, but implies CENP-A may be in a hemisome rather than in a classical octamer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475204" rel="alternate" title="Structure of the human inner kinetochore CCAN complex and its significance for human centromere organization (94 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474985</id><title>Exploring the rules of chimeric antigen receptor phenotypic output using combinatorial signaling motif libraries and machine learning (94 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.992067+00:00</updated><author><name>K.G. Daniels</name></author><author><name>S. Wang</name></author><author><name>M.S. Simic</name></author><author><name>H.K. Bhargava</name></author><author><name>S. Capponi</name></author><author><name>Y. Tonai</name></author><author><name>W. Yu</name></author><author><name>S. Bianco</name></author><author><name>W.A. Lim</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) costimulatory domains steer the phenotypic output of therapeutic T cells. In most cases these domains are derived from native immune receptors, composed of signaling motif combinations selected by evolution. To explore if non-natural combinations of signaling motifs could drive novel cell fates of interest, we constructed a library of CARs containing ∼2,300 synthetic costimulatory domains, built from combinations of 13 peptide signaling motifs. The library produced CARs driving diverse fate outputs, which were sensitive to motif combinations and configurations. Neural networks trained to decode the combinatorial grammar of CAR signaling motifs allowed extraction of key design rules. For example, the non-native combination of TRAF- and PLCγ1-binding motifs was found to simultaneously enhance cytotoxicity and stemness, a clinically desirable phenotype associated with effective and durable tumor killing. The neural network accurately predicts that addition of PLCγ1-binding motifs improves this phenotype when combined with TRAF-binding motifs, but not when combined with other immune signaling motifs (e.g. PI3K-or Grb2-binding motifs). This work shows how libraries built from the minimal building blocks of signaling, combined with machine learning, can efficiently guide engineering of receptors with desired phenotypes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="474985v2_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474985" rel="alternate" title="Exploring the rules of chimeric antigen receptor phenotypic output using combinatorial signaling motif libraries and machine learning (94 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475141</id><title>Redirecting RiPP biosynthetic enzymes to proteins and backbone-modified substrates (39 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.992644+00:00</updated><author><name>Joshua A Walker</name></author><author><name>Noah Hamlish</name></author><author><name>Avery Tytla</name></author><author><name>Daniel D Brauer</name></author><author><name>Matthew B Francis</name></author><author><name>Alanna Schepartz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ribosomally synthesized and post-translationally modified peptides (RiPPs) are peptide-derived natural products that include the FDA-approved analgesic ziconotide1,2 as well as compounds with potent antibiotic, antiviral, and anticancer properties.3 RiPP enzymes known as cyclodehydratases and dehydrogenases represent an exceptionally well-studied enzyme class.3  These enzymes work together to catalyze intramolecular, interresidue condensation3,4 and aromatization reactions that install oxazoline/oxazole and thiazoline/thiazole heterocycles within ribosomally produced polypeptide chains. Here we show that the previously reported enzymes MicD-F and ArtGox accept backbone-modified monomers, including aramids and beta-amino acids, within leader-free polypeptides, even at positions immediately preceding or following the site of cyclization/dehydrogenation. The products are sequence-defined chemical polymers with multiple, diverse, non-alpha-amino acid subunits. We show further that MicD-F and ArtGox can install heterocyclic backbones within protein loops and linkers without disrupting the native tertiary fold. Calculations reveal the extent to which these heterocycles restrict conformational space; they also eliminate a peptide bond. Both features could improve the stability or add function to linker sequences now commonplace in emerging biotherapeutics. Moreover, as thiazoles and thiazoline heterocycles are replete in natural products,5,6,7 small molecule drugs,8,9 and peptide-mimetic therapeutics,10 their installation in protein-based biotherapeutics could improve or augment performance, activity, stability, and/or selectivity.  This work represents a general strategy to expand the chemical diversity of the proteome beyond and in synergy with what can now be accomplished by expanding the genetic code.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475141" rel="alternate" title="Redirecting RiPP biosynthetic enzymes to proteins and backbone-modified substrates (39 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475261</id><title>Target binding triggers hierarchical phosphorylation of human Argonaute-2 to promote target release (38 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.993027+00:00</updated><author><name>Brianna Bibel</name></author><author><name>Elad Elkayam</name></author><author><name>Steve Silletti</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth A. Komives</name></author><author><name>Leemor Joshua-Tor</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Argonaute (Ago) proteins play a central role in post-transcriptional gene regulation through RNA interference (RNAi). Agos bind small RNAs (sRNAs) including small interfering RNAs (siRNAs) and microRNAs (miRNAs) to form the functional core of the RNA Induced Silencing Complex (RISC). The sRNA is used as a guide to target mRNAs containing either partially or fully complementary sequences, ultimately leading to down regulation of the corresponding proteins. It was previously shown that the kinase CK1α phosphorylates a cluster of residues in the eukaryotic insertion (EI) of Ago, leading to the alleviation of miRNA-mediated repression through an undetermined mechanism. We show that binding of miRNA-loaded human Ago2 to target RNA with complementarity to the seed and 3′ supplemental regions of the miRNA primes the EI for hierarchical phosphorylation by CK1α. The added negative charges electrostatically promote target release, freeing Ago to seek out additional targets once it is dephosphorylated. The high conservation of potential phosphosites in the EI suggests that such a regulatory strategy may be a shared mechanism for regulating miRNA-mediated repression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475261" rel="alternate" title="Target binding triggers hierarchical phosphorylation of human Argonaute-2 to promote target release (38 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475280</id><title>Determinants of trafficking, conduction, and disease within a K+ channel revealed through multiparametric deep mutational scanning (35 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.993276+00:00</updated><author><name>Willow Coyote-Maestas</name></author><author><name>David Nedrud</name></author><author><name>Yungui He</name></author><author><name>Daniel Schmidt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A longstanding goal in protein science and clinical genetics is to develop quantitative models of sequence, structure, and function relationships and delineate the mechanisms by which mutations cause disease. Deep Mutational Scanning (DMS) is a promising strategy to map how amino acids contribute to protein structure and function and to advance clinical variant interpretation. Here, we introduce 7,429 single residue missense mutation into the Inward Rectifier K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; channel Kir2.1 and determine how this affects folding, assembly, and trafficking, as well as regulation by allosteric ligands and ion conduction. Our data provide high-resolution information on a cotranslationally-folded biogenic unit, trafficking and quality control signals, and segregated roles of different structural elements in fold-stability and function. We show that Kir2.1 trafficking mutants are underrepresented in variant effect databases, which has implications for clinical practice. By comparing fitness scores with expert-reviewed variant effects, we can predict the pathogenicity of variants of unknown significance and disease mechanisms of know pathogenic mutations. Our study in Kir2.1 provides a blueprint for how multiparametric DMS can help us understand the mechanistic basis of genetic disorders and the structure-function relationships of proteins.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475280" rel="alternate" title="Determinants of trafficking, conduction, and disease within a K+ channel revealed through multiparametric deep mutational scanning (35 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475225</id><title>Validation that human microbiome phages use alternative genetic coding with TAG stop read as Q (33 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.993487+00:00</updated><author><name>Samantha Peters</name></author><author><name>Adair L Borges</name></author><author><name>Richard J Giannone</name></author><author><name>Michael Morowitz</name></author><author><name>Jill Banfield</name></author><author><name>Robert Hettich</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Metagenomic findings suggesting that bacteriophages (phages) can use genetic codes different from those of their host bacteria reveal a new dimension of phage-host interaction dynamics.  Whereas reassignment of stop codons to code for amino acids has been predicted, there has been no proteomic validation of alternative coding in phages. In fact, one code where the stop codon TAG is reassigned to glutamine (code 15) has never been experimentally validated in any biological system. Here, we characterized stop codon reassignment in two crAss-like phages found in the human gut microbiome using LC-MS/MS-based metaproteomics. The proteome data from several phage structural proteins clearly demonstrates reassignment of the TAG stop codon to glutamine, establishing for the first time the expression of genetic code 15.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475225" rel="alternate" title="Validation that human microbiome phages use alternative genetic coding with TAG stop read as Q (33 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475076</id><title>Conserved meiotic mechanisms in the cnidarian Clytia hemisphaerica revealed by Spo11 knockout (32 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.993691+00:00</updated><author><name>Catriona Munro</name></author><author><name>Hugo Cadis</name></author><author><name>Evelyn Houliston</name></author><author><name>Jean-René Huynh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During meiosis, each duplicated chromosome pairs and recombines with its unique homolog to ensure the shuffling of genetic information across generations. Functional studies in classical model organisms have revealed a surprising diversity in the chronology and interdependency of the earliest meiotic steps such as chromosome movements, pairing, association via Synaptonemal Complex formation (synapsis), recombination and the formation of chiasmata. A key player is Spo11, an evolutionarily conserved topoisomerase-related transesterase that initiates meiotic recombination via the catalysis of programmed DNA double stranded breaks (DSBs). While DSBs are required for pairing and synapsis in budding yeast and mouse, alternative pathways are employed during female meiosis of the fruit fly and nematode &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/italic&gt;. Here, to provide a comparative perspective on meiotic regulation from a distinct animal clade, we chart gametogenesis in &lt;italic&gt;Clytia hemisphaerica&lt;/italic&gt; jellyfish and examine the role of Spo11 using CRISPR-Cas9 mutants, generated clonally from F0 polyp colonies. Spo11 mutant females fail to assemble synaptonemal complexes and chiasmata, such that homologous chromosome pairs disperse during oocyte growth. Subsequent meiotic divisions are abnormal but produce viable progeny. &lt;italic&gt;Clytia&lt;/italic&gt; thus shares an ancient eukaryotic dependence of synapsis and chromosome segregation on Spo11-generated DSBs. It provides a valuable additional experimental model for dissecting meiotic mechanisms during animal gametogenesis, and for building a comparative framework for distinguishing evolutionarily conserved versus flexible features of meiosis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475076" rel="alternate" title="Conserved meiotic mechanisms in the cnidarian Clytia hemisphaerica revealed by Spo11 knockout (32 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475020</id><title>Reconstructing Kinetic Models for Dynamical Studies of Metabolism using Generative Adversarial Networks (31 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.993876+00:00</updated><author><name>Subham Choudhury</name></author><author><name>Michael Moret</name></author><author><name>Pierre Salvy</name></author><author><name>Daniel Weilandt</name></author><author><name>Vassily Hatzimanikatis</name></author><author><name>Ljubisa Miskovic</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Kinetic models of metabolic networks relate metabolic fluxes, metabolite concentrations, and enzyme levels through well-defined mechanistic relations rendering them an essential tool for systems biology studies aiming to capture and understand the behavior of living organisms. However, due to the lack of information about the kinetic properties of enzymes and the uncertainties associated with available experimental data, traditional kinetic modeling approaches often yield only a few or no kinetic models with desirable dynamical properties making the computational analysis unreliable and computationally inefficient. We present REKINDLE (REconstruction of KINetic models using Deep LEarning), a deep-learning-based framework for efficiently generating large-scale kinetic models with dynamic properties matching the ones observed in living organisms. We showcase REKINDLE's efficiency and capabilities through three studies where we: (i) generate large populations of kinetic models that allow reliable in silico testing of hypotheses and systems biology designs, (ii) navigate the phenotypic space by leveraging the transfer learning capability of generative adversarial networks, demonstrating that the generators trained for one physiology can be fine-tuned for another physiology using a low amount of data, and (iii) expand upon existing datasets, making them amenable to thorough computational biology and data-science analyses. The results show that data-driven neural networks assimilate implicit kinetic knowledge and structure of metabolic networks and generate novel kinetic models with tailored properties and statistical diversity. We anticipate that our framework will advance our understanding of metabolism and accelerate future research in health, biotechnology, and systems and synthetic biology. REKINDLE is available as an open-access tool.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475020" rel="alternate" title="Reconstructing Kinetic Models for Dynamical Studies of Metabolism using Generative Adversarial Networks (31 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474800</id><title>Caveolae promote successful abscission by controlling intercellular bridge tension during cytokinesis (27 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.994077+00:00</updated><author><name>Virginia Andrade</name></author><author><name>Jian Bai</name></author><author><name>Neetu Gupta-Rossi</name></author><author><name>Ana Jimenez</name></author><author><name>Cédric Delevoye</name></author><author><name>Christophe Lamaze</name></author><author><name>Arnaud Echard</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During cytokinesis, the intercellular bridge (ICB) connecting the daughter cells experiences pulling forces, which delay abscission by preventing the assembly of the ESCRT scission machinery. Abscission is thus triggered by tension release, but how ICB tension is controlled is unknown. Here, we report that caveolae, which are known to control membrane tension upon mechanical stress in interphase cells, are located at the midbody, at the abscission site and at the ICB/cell interface in dividing cells. Functionally, the loss of caveolae delays ESCRT-III recruitment during cytokinesis and impairs abscission. This is the consequence of a 2-fold increase of ICB tension measured by laser ablation, associated with a local increase in myosin II activity at the ICB/cell interface. We thus propose that caveolae buffer membrane tension and limit contractibility at the ICB to promote ESCRT-III assembly and cytokinetic abscission. Altogether, this work reveals an unexpected connection between caveolae and the ESCRT machinery and the first role of caveolae in cell division.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;TEASER&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Caveolae limit the tension in the intercellular bridge during cytokinesis to enable ESCRT-III assembly and successful abscission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474800" rel="alternate" title="Caveolae promote successful abscission by controlling intercellular bridge tension during cytokinesis (27 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474918</id><title>RNA-mediated nucleosome depletion is required for elimination of transposon-derived DNA. (22 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.994284+00:00</updated><author><name>Aditi Singh</name></author><author><name>Xyrus X. Maurer-Alcalá</name></author><author><name>Therese Solberg</name></author><author><name>Silvan Gisler</name></author><author><name>Michael Ignarski</name></author><author><name>Estienne C. Swart</name></author><author><name>Mariusz Nowacki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Small RNAs are known to mediate silencing of transposable elements and other genomic loci, increasing nucleosome density and preventing undesirable gene expression. Post-zygotic development of the Paramecium somatic genome requires elimination of thousands of transposon remnants (IESs) and transposable elements that are scattered throughout the germline genome (Garnier et al. 2004). The elimination process is guided by Piwi-associated small RNAs and leads to precise cleavage at IES boundaries (Bouhouche et al. 2011; Furrer et al. 2017). Previous research suggests that small RNAs induce heterochromatin formation within IESs, which, in turn, is required for DNA elimination (Liu et al. 2007). Here we show that IES recognition and precise excision is facilitated by recruitment of a homolog of a chromatin remodeler ISWI, which depletes target genomic regions of nucleosomes, making the chromatin accessible for DNA cleavage. ISWI knockdown in Paramecium leads to pronounced inhibition of DNA elimination. Furthermore, nucleosome profiling indicates that ISWI is required for IES elimination in nucleosome-dense genomic regions, while other IESs do not require small RNAs or ISWI for excision. ISWI silencing notably also reduces DNA elimination precision, resulting in aberrant excision at alternative IES boundaries. In summary, we demonstrate that chromatin remodeling that increases DNA accessibility together with small RNAs are necessary for efficient and precise DNA elimination in Paramecium.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474918" rel="alternate" title="RNA-mediated nucleosome depletion is required for elimination of transposon-derived DNA. (22 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474978</id><title>Thiamine metabolism genes in diatoms are not regulated by thiamine despite the presence of predicted riboswitches (21 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.994485+00:00</updated><author><name>Marcel Llavero Pasquina</name></author><author><name>Katrin Geisler</name></author><author><name>Andre Holzer</name></author><author><name>Payam Mehrshahi</name></author><author><name>Gonzalo I Mendoza-Ochoa</name></author><author><name>Shelby Newsad</name></author><author><name>Matthew P Davey</name></author><author><name>Alison G. Smith</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thiamine pyrophosphate (TPP), an essential co-factor for all species, is biosynthesised through a metabolically expensive pathway regulated by TPP riboswitches in bacteria, fungi, plants and green algae. Diatoms are microalgae responsible for approximately 20% of global primary production. They have been predicted to contain TPP aptamers in the 3’UTR of some thiamine metabolism-related genes, but little is known about their function and regulation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used bioinformatics, antimetabolite growth assays, RT-qPCR, targeted mutagenesis and reporter constructs to test whether the predicted TPP riboswitches respond to thiamine supplementation in diatoms. Gene editing was used to investigate the functions of the genes with associated TPP riboswitches in &lt;italic&gt;Phaeodactylum tricornutum&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found that thiamine-related genes with putative TPP aptamers are not responsive to thiamine or its precursor 4-amino-5-hydroxymethyl-2-methylpyrimidine (HMP), and the targeted mutation of the TPP aptamer in the HMP-P synthase (&lt;italic&gt;THIC&lt;/italic&gt;) does not deregulate thiamine biosynthesis in &lt;italic&gt;P. tricornutum&lt;/italic&gt;. Through genome editing we established that &lt;italic&gt;PtSSSP&lt;/italic&gt; is necessary for thiamine uptake and that &lt;italic&gt;PtTHIC&lt;/italic&gt; is essential for thiamine biosynthesis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our results highlight the importance of experimentally testing bioinformatic aptamer predictions and provide new insights into the thiamine metabolism shaping the structure of marine microbial communities with global biogeochemical importance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474978" rel="alternate" title="Thiamine metabolism genes in diatoms are not regulated by thiamine despite the presence of predicted riboswitches (21 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474973</id><title>The Mitochondrial RNA Granule is Necessary for Parkinsonism-Associated Metal Toxicity (21 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.994717+00:00</updated><author><name>E. Werner</name></author><author><name>A. Gokhale</name></author><author><name>M. Ackert</name></author><author><name>C. Xu</name></author><author><name>Z. Wen</name></author><author><name>A. M. Roberts</name></author><author><name>B. R. Roberts</name></author><author><name>A. Vrailas-Mortimer</name></author><author><name>A. Crocker</name></author><author><name>V. Faundez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Manganese exposure causes a parkinsonian disorder, manganism, which is viewed as a neurodegenerative disorder minimally related to Parkinson’s disease. We tested this hypothesis asking if there is phenotypic and mechanistic overlap between two genetic models of these diseases. We targeted for study the plasma membrane manganese efflux transporter SLC30A10 and the mitochondrial Parkinson’s gene PARK2. We performed comparative molecular systems studies and found that SLC30A10 and PARK2 mutations compromised the mitochondrial RNA granule as well as mitochondrial transcript processing. These shared RNA granule defects led to impaired assembly and function of the mitochondrial respiratory chain. Notably, CRISPR gene editing of subunits of the mitochondrial RNA granule, FASTKD2 and DHX30, or pharmacological inhibition of mitochondrial transcription-translation were protective rather than deleterious for survival of cells acutely exposed to manganese. Similarly, adult &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; mutants with defects in the mitochondrial RNA granule component &lt;italic&gt;scully&lt;/italic&gt; were safeguarded from manganese-induced mortality. We conclude that the downregulation of the mitochondrial RNA granule function is a protective mechanism for acute metal toxicity. We propose that initially adaptive mitochondrial dysfunction caused by manganese exposure, when protracted, causes neurodegeneration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474973" rel="alternate" title="The Mitochondrial RNA Granule is Necessary for Parkinsonism-Associated Metal Toxicity (21 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475140</id><title>Machine learning guided batched design of a bacterial Ribosome Binding Site (19 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.994962+00:00</updated><author><name>Mengyan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Maciej B Holowko</name></author><author><name>Huw Hayman Zumpe</name></author><author><name>Cheng Soon Ong</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Optimisation of gene expression levels is an essential part of the organism design process. Fine control of this process can be achieved through engineering transcription and translation control elements, including the ribosome binding site (RBS). Unfortunately, design of specific genetic parts can still be challenging due to lack of reliable design methods. To address this problem, we have created a machine learning guided Design-Build-Test-Learn (DBTL) cycle for the experimental design of bacterial RBSs to show how small genetic parts can be reliably designed using relatively small, high-quality data sets. We used Gaussian Process Regression for the Learn phase of cycle and the Upper Confidence Bound multi-armed bandit algorithm for the Design of genetic variants to be tested in vivo. We have integrated these machine learning algorithms with laboratory automation and high-throughput processes for reliable data generation. Notably, by Testing a total of 450 RBS variants in four DBTL cycles, we experimentally validated RBSs with high translation initiation rates equalling or exceeding our benchmark RBS by up to 34%. Overall, our results show that machine learning is a powerful tool for designing RBSs, and they pave the way towards more complicated genetic devices.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475140" rel="alternate" title="Machine learning guided batched design of a bacterial Ribosome Binding Site (19 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.474281</id><title>RETINOBLASTOMA RELATED (RBR) interaction with key factors of the RNA-directed DNA methylation (RdDM) pathway (17 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.995141+00:00</updated><author><name>Jesus Ruiz-Leon</name></author><author><name>Annie Espinal-Centeno</name></author><author><name>Ikram Blilou</name></author><author><name>Ben Scheres</name></author><author><name>Mario Arteaga-Vazquez</name></author><author><name>Alfredo Cruz-Ramirez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;●	Transposable elements and other repetitive elements are silenced by the RNA-directed DNA methylation pathway (RdDM). In RdDM, POLIV-derived transcripts are converted into double stranded RNA (dsRNA) by the activity of RDR2 and subsequently processed into 24 nucleotide short interfering RNAs (24-nt siRNAs) by DCL3. 24-nt siRNAs are recruited by AGO4 and serve as guides to direct AGO4-siRNA complexes to chromatin bound POLV-derived transcripts generated from the template/target DNA. The interaction between POLV, AGO4, DMS3, DRD1, RDM1 and DRM2 promotes DRM2-mediated de novo DNA methylation.

In silico exploration of Arabidopsis RBR protein partners revealed that several members of the RdDM pathway contain a motif that confers high affinity binding to  RBR, including the largest subunits of POLIV and POLV (NRPD1 and NRPE1), the shared second largest subunit of POLIV and POLV (NRPD/E2), RDR1, RDR2, DCL3, DRM2 and SUVR2. We demonstrate that RBR binds to DRM2, DRD1 and SUVR2. We also report that seedlings from loss-of-function mutants in RdDM and in RBR show similar phenotypes in the root apical meristem. Furthermore, we show that  RdDM and SUVR2 targets are up-regulated in the 35S::AmiGO-RBR background. 

Our results suggest a novel mechanism for RBR function in transcriptional gene silencing based on the interaction with key players of the RdDM pathway and opens several new hypotheses, including the convergence of RBR-DRM2 on the transcriptional control of TEs and several cell/tissue and stage-specific target genes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.474281" rel="alternate" title="RETINOBLASTOMA RELATED (RBR) interaction with key factors of the RNA-directed DNA methylation (RdDM) pathway (17 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475253</id><title>A unified view of LCRs across species (16 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.995353+00:00</updated><author><name>Byron Lee</name></author><author><name>Nima Jaberi-Lashkari</name></author><author><name>Eliezer Calo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Low complexity regions (LCRs) in proteins play a major role in the higher order assemblies of organisms, such as the nucleolus and extracellular matrix. Despite recent focus on how certain features affect the function of LCRs in intracellular higher order assemblies, the relationships between LCRs within proteins, captured by their type and copy number, has yet to be systematically studied. Furthermore, we still lack a unified view of how the sequences, features, relationships and functions of LCRs relate to each other. Here, we developed a systematic and comprehensive approach using dotplot matrices and dimensionality reduction to define LCR relationships proteome-wide and to create a map of LCR sequences capable of integrating any LCR features. As a proof of concept of the importance of LCR relationships, we demonstrate the biological significance of LCR copy number for higher order assembly of the nucleolar protein RPA43 both in vitro and in vivo. Using the LCR map, we revealed the boundaries and connections between regions of sequence space occupied by LCRs, and that LCRs of certain higher order assemblies populated specific regions of sequence space. The integration of LCR relationships and the LCR map provided a unified view of LCRs which uncovered the distribution, distinguishing features, and conserved prevalence of glutamic acid-rich LCRs among nucleolar proteins. When applied across multiple species, this approach highlights how differential occupancy of certain regions of LCR sequence space corresponds to the conservation and emergence of higher order assemblies, such as the plant cell wall or metazoan extracellular matrix. Additionally, we identified previously undescribed regions of LCR sequence space, including a teleost-specific threonine/histidine-rich cluster which exhibits signatures of higher order assemblies. By providing this unified view of LCRs, our approach enables discovery of how LCRs encode higher order assemblies of organisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475253" rel="alternate" title="A unified view of LCRs across species (16 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475023</id><title>Structural basis of peptidomimetic agonism revealed by small molecule GLP-1R agonists Boc5 and WB4-24 (15 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.995533+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhaotong Cong</name></author><author><name>Qingtong Zhou</name></author><author><name>Yang Li</name></author><author><name>Li-Nan Chen</name></author><author><name>Zi-Chen Zhang</name></author><author><name>Anyi Liang</name></author><author><name>Qing Liu</name></author><author><name>Xiaoyan Wu</name></author><author><name>Antao Dai</name></author><author><name>Tian Xia</name></author><author><name>Wei Wu</name></author><author><name>Yan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Dehua Yang</name></author><author><name>Ming-Wei Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glucagon-like peptide-1 receptor (GLP-1R) agonists are effective in treating type 2 diabetes and obesity with proven cardiovascular benefits. However, most of them are peptides and require subcutaneous injection except for orally available semaglutide. Boc5 was identified as the first orthosteric non-peptidic agonist of GLP-1R that mimics a broad spectrum of bioactivities of GLP-1 &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Here, we report the cryo-electron microscopy structures of Boc5 and its analog WB4-24 in complex with the human GLP-1R and G&lt;sub&gt;s&lt;/sub&gt; protein. Bound to the extracellular domain, extracellular loop 2, and transmembrane (TM) helices 1, 2, 3 and 7, one arm of both compounds inserted deeply into the bottom of the orthosteric binding pocket that is usually accessible by peptidic agonists, thereby partially overlapping with the residues A8-D15 in GLP-1. The other three arms, meanwhile, extended to the TM1-TM7, TM1-TM2, and TM2-TM3 clefts showing an interaction feature substantially similar to a previously known small molecule agonist LY3502970. Such a unique binding mode creates a distinct conformation that confers both peptidomimetic agonism and biased signaling induced by non-peptidic modulators at GLP-1R. Further, the conformational difference between Boc5 and WB4-24, two closed related compounds, provides a structural framework for fine tuning of pharmacological efficacy in the development of future small molecule therapeutics targeting GLP-1R.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;GLP-1R agonists are efficacious in the treatment of type 2 diabetes and obesity. While most clinically used agents require subcutaneous injection, Boc5, as the first orthosteric non-peptidic agonist of GLP-1R, suffers from poor oral bioavailability that hinders its therapeutic development. The cryo-electron microscopy structures of Boc5 and its closely related analog WB4-24 presented here reveal a previously unknown binding pocket located deeper in the transmembrane domain for non-peptidic GLP-1R agonists. Molecular interaction with this site may facilitate a broad spectrum of in vivo agonistic activities, in addition to that with the upper helical bundles presumably responsible for biased signaling. These findings deepen our understanding of peptidomimetic agonism at GLP-1R and may help design better drug leads against this important target.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475023" rel="alternate" title="Structural basis of peptidomimetic agonism revealed by small molecule GLP-1R agonists Boc5 and WB4-24 (15 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475096</id><title>Biochemical characterization of actin assembly mechanisms with ALS-associated profilin variants (13 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.995795+00:00</updated><author><name>Xinbei Liu</name></author><author><name>Morgan L Pimm</name></author><author><name>Brian Haarer</name></author><author><name>Andrew T Brawner</name></author><author><name>Jessica L. Henty-Ridilla</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Eight separate mutations in the actin-binding protein profilin-1 have been identified as a rare cause of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS).  Profilin is essential for many neuronal cell processes through its regulation of lipids, nuclear signals, and cytoskeletal dynamics, including actin filament assembly. Direct interactions between profilin and actin monomers inhibit actin filament polymerization. In contrast, profilin can also stimulate polymerization by simultaneously binding actin monomers and proline-rich tracts found in other proteins. Whether the ALS-associated mutations in profilin compromise these actin assembly functions is unclear. We performed a quantitative biochemical comparison of the direct and formin-mediated impact for the eight ALS-associated profilin variants on actin assembly using classic protein-binding and single-filament microscopy assays. We determined that the binding constants of each profilin for actin monomers generally correlates with the actin nucleation strength associated with each ALS-related profilin. In the presence of formin, the A20T, R136W, Q139L, and C71G variants failed to activate the elongation phase of actin assembly. This diverse range of formin-activities is not fully explained through profilin-PLP interactions, as all ALS-associated variants bind a formin-derived PLP peptide with similar affinities. However, chemical denaturation experiments suggest that the folding stability of these profilins impact some of these effects on actin assembly. Thus, changes in profilin protein stability and alterations in actin filament polymerization may both contribute to the profilin-mediated actin disruptions in ALS.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475096" rel="alternate" title="Biochemical characterization of actin assembly mechanisms with ALS-associated profilin variants (13 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474810</id><title>Mandatory coupling of zygotic transcription to DNA replication in early Drosophila embryos (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.995980+00:00</updated><author><name>Chun-Yi Cho</name></author><author><name>James P. Kemp</name></author><author><name>Robert J. Duronio</name></author><author><name>Patrick H. O'Farrell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Collisions between transcribing RNA polymerases and DNA replication forks are disruptive. The threat of collisions is particularly acute during the rapid early embryonic cell cycles of Drosophila when S phase occupies the entirety of interphase. We hypothesized that collision-avoidance mechanisms safeguard the onset of zygotic transcription in these cycles. To explore this hypothesis, we used real-time imaging of transcriptional events at the onset of each interphase. Endogenously tagged RNA polymerase II (RNAPII) abruptly formed clusters before nascent transcripts accumulated, indicating recruitment prior to transcriptional engagement. Injection of inhibitors of DNA replication prevented RNAPII clustering, blocked formation of foci of the pioneer factor Zelda, and largely prevented expression of transcription reporters. Knockdown of Zelda or the histone acetyltransferase CBP prevented RNAPII cluster formation except at the replication-dependent (RD) histone gene locus. We suggest a model in which the passage of replication forks allows Zelda and a distinct pathway at the RD histone locus to reconfigure chromatin to nucleate RNAPII clustering and promote transcriptional initiation. The replication dependency of these events defers initiation of transcription and ensures that RNA polymerases transcribe behind advancing replication forks. The resulting coordination of transcription and replication explains how early embryos circumvent collisions and promote genome stability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474810" rel="alternate" title="Mandatory coupling of zygotic transcription to DNA replication in early Drosophila embryos (11 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475054</id><title>Full Spectrum Flow Cytometry for High-Dimensional Immunophenotyping of Murine Innate Lymphoid Cells (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.996160+00:00</updated><author><name>Kyle T Mincham</name></author><author><name>Robert J Snelgrove</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This 25-parameter, 22-colour full spectrum flow cytometry panel was designed and optimised for the comprehensive enumeration and functional characterisation of innate lymphoid cell (ILC) subsets in murine tissues (Table 1). The panel presented here allows the discrimination of ILC progenitors (ILCP), ILC1, ILC2, NCR+ ILC3, NCR- ILC3, CCR6+ ILC3 and mature natural killer (NK) cell populations. Further characterisation of ILC and NK cell functional profiles in response to stimulation is provided by the inclusion of subset-specific cytokine markers, and proliferation markers. Development and optimisation of this panel was performed on freshly isolated cells from adult BALB/c lungs and small intestine lamina propria, and ex vivo stimulation with phorbol 12-myrisate 13-acetate, ionomycin, brefeldin A and pro-ILC activating cytokines.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475054" rel="alternate" title="Full Spectrum Flow Cytometry for High-Dimensional Immunophenotyping of Murine Innate Lymphoid Cells (10 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475289</id><title>Autoantibody and hormone activation of the thyrotropin G protein-coupled receptor (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.996322+00:00</updated><author><name>Bryan Faust</name></author><author><name>Isha Singh</name></author><author><name>Kaihua Zhang</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Hoppe</name></author><author><name>Antonio F.M. Pinto</name></author><author><name>Yagmur Muftuoglu</name></author><author><name>Christian B. Billesboelle</name></author><author><name>Alan Saghatelian</name></author><author><name>Yifan Cheng</name></author><author><name>Aashish Manglik</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Thyroid hormones are vital to growth and metabolism. Thyroid hormone synthesis is controlled by thyrotropin (TSH), which acts at the thyrotropin receptor (TSHR). Autoantibodies that activate the TSHR pathologically increase thyroid hormones in Graves' disease. How autoantibodies mimic TSH function remains unclear. We determined cryogenic-electron microscopy structures of active and inactive TSHR. In inactive TSHR, the extracellular domain lies close to the membrane bilayer. TSH selects an upright conformation of the extracellular domain due to steric clashes between a conserved hormone glycan and the membrane bilayer. An activating autoantibody selects a similar upright conformation of the extracellular domain. Conformational changes in the extracellular domain are transduced to the seven transmembrane domain via a conserved hinge domain, a tethered peptide agonist, and a phospholipid that binds within the seven transmembrane domain. Rotation of the TSHR ECD relative to the membrane bilayer is sufficient for receptor activation, revealing a shared mechanism for other glycoprotein hormone receptors that may also extend to G protein-coupled receptors with large extracellular domains.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475289" rel="alternate" title="Autoantibody and hormone activation of the thyrotropin G protein-coupled receptor (10 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474988</id><title>Rotavirus RNA chaperone mediates global transcriptome-wide increase in RNA backbone flexibility (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.996661+00:00</updated><author><name>Aaztli Coria</name></author><author><name>Anastacia Wienecke</name></author><author><name>Alexander Borodavka</name></author><author><name>Alain Laederach</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Due to genome segmentation, rotaviruses must co-package a set of eleven distinct genomic RNAs. The packaging is mediated by virus-encoded RNA chaperones, such as the rotavirus (RV) NSP2 protein. While the activities of distinct viral RNA chaperones are well studied on synthetic RNA substrates, little is known about their global effect on the entire viral transcriptome. Here we used Selective 2′-hydroxyl Acylation Analyzed by Primer Extension and Mutational Profiling (SHAPE-MaP) to systematically examine the secondary structure of the RV transcriptome composed of eleven distinct transcripts in the absence and presence of increasing concentrations of RV NSP2. Surprisingly, SHAPE-MaP data reveals that despite the well-documented helix-unwinding activity of NSP2 &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, its incubation with cognate RV transcripts does not induce a significant change in the SHAPE reactivities. However, a quantitative analysis of the per nucleotide mutation rate measured by mutational profiling, from which SHAPE reactivities are derived, reveals a global five-fold rate increase in the presence of molar excess of NSP2. We demonstrate that the standard normalization procedure used in deriving SHAPE reactivities from mutation rates can mask an important global effect of an RNA chaperone activity. Further analysis of the mutation rate in the context of structural classification reveals a larger effect on stems rather than loop elements. Together, these data provide the first experimentally derived secondary structure model of the RV transcriptome and reveal that NSP2 acts by globally increasing RNA backbone flexibility in a concentration-dependent manner, consistent with its promiscuous RNA-binding nature.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474988" rel="alternate" title="Rotavirus RNA chaperone mediates global transcriptome-wide increase in RNA backbone flexibility (10 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474891</id><title>Histone deacetylase inhibitor overrides the effect of soft hydrogel on the mechanoresponse of human mesenchymal stem cells (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.996842+00:00</updated><author><name>Rohit Joshi</name></author><author><name>Pooja Murlidharan</name></author><author><name>Puspendra Yadav</name></author><author><name>Vedanshi Dharnidharka</name></author><author><name>Abhijit Majumder</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human Mesenchymal cells (hMSCs) are promising in regenerative medicine for their multi-lineage differentiation capability. It has been demonstrated that lineage specification is governed by both chemical and mechanical cues. Among all the different mechanical cues known to control hMSCs fate, substrate stiffness is the most well-studied. It has been shown that the naive mesenchymal stem cells when cultured on soft gel, they commit towards adipogenic lineage while when cultured on stiff gel they become osteogenic. Soft substrates also cause less cell spreading, less traction, less focal adhesion assembly and stress fibre formation. Furthermore, chromatin condensation increases when cells are cultured on soft substrates. As the nucleus has been postulated to be mechanosensor and mechanotransducer, in this paper we asked the question how mechanosensing and mechanoresponse process will be influenced if we change the chromatin condensation by using an external chemical stimulus. To address this question, we treated hMSCs cultured on soft polyacrylamide (PA) gels with a histone deacetylase inhibitor (HDACi) called Valproic Acid (VA) which decondense the chromatin by hyperacetylation of histone proteins. We found that the treatment with VA overrides the effect of soft substrates on hMSCs morphology, cellular traction, nuclear localization of mechnosensory protein YAP, and differentiation. VA treated cells behaved as if they are on stiff substrates in all aspects tested here. Furthermore, we have shown that VA controls hMSCs differentiation via activation of ERK/MAPK pathway by increasing the p-ERK expression which inhibits adipogenic differentiation potential of mesenchymal stem cells. Collectively, these findings for the first time demonstrate that inhibiting histone acetylation can override the mechanoresponse of hMSCs. This work will help us to fundamentally understand the mechanosignalling process and to control the hMSCs differentiation in tissue engineering and regenerative medicine.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474891" rel="alternate" title="Histone deacetylase inhibitor overrides the effect of soft hydrogel on the mechanoresponse of human mesenchymal stem cells (10 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474820</id><title>mBeRFP, a versatile fluorescent tool to enhance multichannel live imaging and its applications (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.997038+00:00</updated><author><name>Emmanuel Martin</name></author><author><name>Magali Suzanne</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cell and developmental biology increasingly require live imaging of protein dynamics in cells, tissues or living organisms. Thanks to the discovery and the development of a panel of fluorescent proteins over the last decades, live imaging has become a powerful and commonly used approach. However, multicolor live imaging remains challenging. The generation of long Stokes shift red fluorescent proteins, such as mBeRFP, offers interesting new perspectives to bypass this limitation. Here, we constructed a set of mBeRFP-expressing vectors and provided a detailed characterization of this fluorescent protein for &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; live imaging and its applications in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt;. Briefly, we showed that a single illumination source is sufficient to simultaneously stimulate mBeRFP and GFP. We demonstrated that mBeRFP can be easily combined with classical green and red fluorescent protein without any crosstalk. We also showed that the low photobleaching of mBeRFP is suitable for live imaging, and that this protein can be used for quantitative applications such as FRAP or laser ablation. Finally, we believe that this fluorescent protein, with the set of new possibilities it offers, constitutes an important tool for cell, developmental and mechano biologists in their current research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474820" rel="alternate" title="mBeRFP, a versatile fluorescent tool to enhance multichannel live imaging and its applications (10 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474980</id><title>The formation of a fuzzy complex in the negative arm regulates the robustness of the circadian clock (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.997204+00:00</updated><author><name>Meaghan S. Jankowski</name></author><author><name>Daniel Griffith</name></author><author><name>Divya G. Shastry</name></author><author><name>Jacqueline F. Pelham</name></author><author><name>Garrett M. Ginell</name></author><author><name>Joshua Thomas</name></author><author><name>Pankaj Karande</name></author><author><name>Alex S. Holehouse</name></author><author><name>Jennifer M. Hurley</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The circadian clock times cellular processes to the day/night cycle via a Transcription-Translation negative Feedback Loop (TTFL). However, a mechanistic understanding of the negative arm in both the timing of the TTFL and its control of output is lacking. We posited that the formation of negative-arm protein complexes was fundamental to clock regulation stemming from the negative arm. Using a modified peptide microarray approach termed &lt;underline&gt;L&lt;/underline&gt;inear m&lt;underline&gt;o&lt;/underline&gt;tif dis&lt;underline&gt;c&lt;/underline&gt;overy using r&lt;underline&gt;at&lt;/underline&gt;ional d&lt;underline&gt;e&lt;/underline&gt;sign (LOCATE), we characterized the interaction of the disordered negative-arm clock protein FREQUENCY to its partner protein FREQUENCY-Interacting RNA helicase. LOCATE identified a specific Short Linear Motif (SLiM) and interaction “hotspot” as well as positively charged “islands” that mediate electrostatic interactions, suggesting a model where negative arm proteins form a “fuzzy” complex essential for clock timing and robustness. Further analysis revealed that the positively charged islands were an evolutionarily conserved feature in higher eukaryotes and contributed to proper clock function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474980" rel="alternate" title="The formation of a fuzzy complex in the negative arm regulates the robustness of the circadian clock (10 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475133</id><title>Molecular Mechanism of Hyperactivation Conferred by a Truncated TRPA1 Disease Mutant Suggests New Gating Insights (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.997420+00:00</updated><author><name>Avnika Bali</name></author><author><name>Samantha P. Schaefer</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Trier</name></author><author><name>Alice L. Zhang</name></author><author><name>Lilian Kabeche</name></author><author><name>Candice E. Paulsen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The wasabi receptor, TRPA1, is a non-selective homotetrameric cation channel expressed in primary sensory neurons of the pain pathway, where it is activated by diverse chemical irritants. A direct role for TRPA1 in human health has been highlighted by the discovery of genetic variants associated with severe pain disorders. One such TRPA1 mutant was identified in a father-son pair with cramp fasciculation syndrome (CFS) and neuronal hyperexcitability-hypersensitivity symptoms that may be caused by aberrant channel activity, though the mechanism of action for this mutant is unknown. Here, we show the CFS-associated R919* TRPA1 mutant is functionally inactive when expressed alone in heterologous cells, which is not surprising since it lacks the 201 C-terminal amino acids that house critical channel gating machinery including the pore-lining transmembrane helix. Interestingly, the R919* mutant confers enhanced agonist sensitivity when co-expressed with wild type (WT) TRPA1. This channel hyperactivation mechanism is conserved in distant TRPA1 species orthologues and can be recapitulated in the capsaicin receptor, TRPV1. Using a combination of ratiometric calcium imaging, immunostaining, surface biotinylation, pulldown assays, fluorescence size exclusion chromatography, and proximity biotinylation assays, we show that the R919* mutant co-assembles with WT subunits into heteromeric channels. Within these heteromers, we postulate that R919* TRPA1 subunits contribute to hyperactivation by lowering energetic barriers to channel activation contributed by the missing regions. Additionally, we show heteromer activation can originate from the R919* TRPA1 subunits, which suggests an unexpected role for the ankyrin repeat and coiled coil domains in concerted channel gating. Our results demonstrate the R919* TRPA1 mutant confers gain-of-function thereby expanding the physiological impact of nonsense mutations, reveals a novel and genetically tractable mechanism for selective channel sensitization that may be broadly applicable to other receptors, and uncovers new gating insights that may explain the molecular mechanism of temperature sensing by some TRPA1 orthologues.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475133" rel="alternate" title="Molecular Mechanism of Hyperactivation Conferred by a Truncated TRPA1 Disease Mutant Suggests New Gating Insights (8 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474765</id><title>Cystic fibrosis patient-derived bronchial organoids unveil druggable pathways against Mycobacterium abscessus infection (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.997613+00:00</updated><author><name>Stephen Adonai Leon-Icaza</name></author><author><name>Salimata Bagayoko</name></author><author><name>Nino Iakobachvili</name></author><author><name>Chloé Ferrand</name></author><author><name>Talip Aydogan</name></author><author><name>Celia Bernard</name></author><author><name>Angelique Sanchez Dafun</name></author><author><name>Marlène Murris-Espin</name></author><author><name>Julien Mazières</name></author><author><name>Pierre Jean Bordignon</name></author><author><name>Serge Mazères</name></author><author><name>Pascale Bernes-Lasserre</name></author><author><name>Victoria Ramé</name></author><author><name>Jean-Michel Lagarde</name></author><author><name>Julien Marcoux</name></author><author><name>Marie Pierre Bousquet</name></author><author><name>Christian Chalut</name></author><author><name>Christophe Guilhot</name></author><author><name>Hans Clevers</name></author><author><name>Peter J. Peters</name></author><author><name>Virginie Molle</name></author><author><name>Geanncarlo Lugo-Villarino</name></author><author><name>Kaymeuang Cam</name></author><author><name>Laurence Berry</name></author><author><name>Etienne Meunier</name></author><author><name>Céline Cougoule</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium abscessus&lt;/italic&gt; (Mabs) drives life-shortening mortality in cystic fibrosis (CF) patients, primarily because of its resistance to chemotherapeutic agents. Both our knowledge on and models to investigate the host and bacterial determinants that drive Mabs pathology in CF patients remain rudimentary. Here, we evaluated whether the lung organoid technology from CF patients is appropriate for modelling Mabs infection and whether antioxidant treatment is a candidate therapeutic approach in the context of CF disease. We derived airway organoids (AOs) from lung biopsy of a CF patient and characterized these AO by assessing CF transmembrane conductance regulator (CFTR) function, mucus and reactive oxygen species (ROS) production, lipid peroxidation, and cell death. We microinjected smooth (S-) or rough (R-)Mabs in the lumen of AOs to evaluate its fitness, responses of AOs to infection, and treatment efficacy by colony forming unit assay, qPCR and microscopy. We show that CF patient-derived AOs exhibited low residual CFTR function, enhanced mucus accumulation, and increased oxidative stress, lipid peroxidation, and cell death at basal state. While in AOs, S Mabs formed biofilm, R Mabs formed cord serpentines and displayed a higher virulence. S and R Mabs replicated more efficiently in CF AOs than in AOs derived from healthy lung. Pharmacological activation of antioxidant pathways resulted in better control of Mabs growth. In conclusion, we have established CF patient-derived AOs as a suitable human system to decipher mechanisms of CF-enhanced respiratory infection by Mabs and confirmed antioxidant approaches as a potential host-directed strategy to improve Mabs infection control.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474765" rel="alternate" title="Cystic fibrosis patient-derived bronchial organoids unveil druggable pathways against Mycobacterium abscessus infection (7 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475028</id><title>Nucleoplasmic Lamin C Rapidly Accumulates at Sites of Nuclear Envelope Rupture with BAF and cGAS (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.998154+00:00</updated><author><name>Yohei Kono</name></author><author><name>Stephen A. Adam</name></author><author><name>Karen L. Reddy</name></author><author><name>Yixian Zheng</name></author><author><name>Ohad Medalia</name></author><author><name>Robert D. Goldman</name></author><author><name>Hiroshi Kimura</name></author><author><name>Takeshi Shimi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In mammalian cell nuclei, the nuclear lamina (NL) underlies the nuclear envelope (NE) to maintain nuclear structure. The nuclear lamins, the major structural components of the NL, are involved in the protection against NE rupture induced by mechanical stress. However, the specific role of the lamins in repair of NE ruptures has not been fully determined. Our analyses using immunofluorescence and live-cell imaging revealed that lamin C but not the other lamin isoforms rapidly accumulated at sites of NE rupture induced by laser microirradiation in mouse embryonic fibroblasts. The immunoglobulin-like fold domain and the NLS were required for the recruitment from the nucleoplasm to the rupture sites with the Barrier-to-autointegration factor (BAF). The accumulation of nuclear BAF and cytoplasmic cyclic GMP-AMP (cGAMP) synthase (cGAS) at the rupture sites was in part dependent on lamin A/C. These results suggest that nucleoplasmic lamin C, BAF and cGAS concertedly accumulate at sites of NE rupture for repair.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kono et al. show the rapid recruitment of nucleoplasmic lamin C to sites of nuclear envelope rupture with Barrier-to-autointegration factor. Lamin A/C is also involved in nuclear DNA sensing with cytoplasmic cGAS at the ruptured sites.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475028" rel="alternate" title="Nucleoplasmic Lamin C Rapidly Accumulates at Sites of Nuclear Envelope Rupture with BAF and cGAS (7 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.475010</id><title>Spatially unique Shh-Fgf8 distribution in regenerating limb guarantees consistent limb morphogenesis in different limb sizes and contributes to axolotl specific digit patterning (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.998393+00:00</updated><author><name>Saya Furukawa</name></author><author><name>Sakiya Yamamoto</name></author><author><name>Rena Kashimoto</name></author><author><name>Yoshihiro Morishita</name></author><author><name>Akira Satoh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Limb regeneration in &lt;italic&gt;Ambystoma mexicanum&lt;/italic&gt; occurs in various sizes of fields and can recreate consistent limb morphology. It was not known what mechanism supports such stable limb morphogenesis regardless of size. Limb regeneration in urodele amphibians has been basically considered to recapitulate the limb developmental processes. Many molecules in the limb developmental processes are conserved with other tetrapods. SHH and FGF8 play important roles in the morphogenesis of limbs among them. Focusing on these two factors, we investigated the detailed expression pattern of &lt;italic&gt;Shh&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Fgf8&lt;/italic&gt; in the various sizes of blastema in axolotl limb regeneration. &lt;italic&gt;Fgf8&lt;/italic&gt; is expressed in the anterior side of a blastema and &lt;italic&gt;Shh&lt;/italic&gt; is expressed in the posterior side. These are maintained in a mutually dependent manner. We also clarified that the size of &lt;italic&gt;Shh&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Fgf8&lt;/italic&gt; expression domains were scaled as the size of the blastemas increased. However, it was found that the secretion and working range of SHH were kept constant. We also found that the consistent SHH secretion range contributed to promoting cell proliferation and the first digital cartilage differentiation near the &lt;italic&gt;Shh&lt;/italic&gt; expression domain. This would be a reasonable system to guarantees constant limb morphogenesis regardless of the blastema size. We also showed that the &lt;italic&gt;Shh&lt;/italic&gt;-&lt;italic&gt;Fgf8&lt;/italic&gt; expression domain was shifted posteriorly as the digital differentiation progressed. Consistently, slowing the timing of blocking &lt;italic&gt;Shh&lt;/italic&gt; signaling resulted in morphological defects that could be observed in only posterior digits. The revealed posteriorly shifting &lt;italic&gt;Shh-Fgf8&lt;/italic&gt; domain might explain urodele specific digit formation, in which digits are added posteriorly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A unique SHH-FGF8 spatial interaction compensates for robust limb patterning in regeneration in various limb sizes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.475010" rel="alternate" title="Spatially unique Shh-Fgf8 distribution in regenerating limb guarantees consistent limb morphogenesis in different limb sizes and contributes to axolotl specific digit patterning (6 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475007</id><title>Discovery of novel compounds as potent activators of Sirt3 (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.998586+00:00</updated><author><name>Celina Reverdy</name></author><author><name>Gaetan Gitton</name></author><author><name>Xiangying Guan</name></author><author><name>Indranil Adhya</name></author><author><name>Rama Dumpati</name></author><author><name>Samir Roy</name></author><author><name>Gauthier Errasti</name></author><author><name>Thomas Delacroix</name></author><author><name>Raj Chakrabarti</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Among the sirtuin members, Sirt3 is one of the most important deacetylases as it regulates acetylation levels in mitochondria, which are linked to the metabolism of multiple organs and therefore involved in many types of human diseases such as age-related diseases, cancer, heart disease and metabolic diseases. In the current absence of any direct activator of Sirt3, the identification of new modulators could be a key step in the development of new therapeutics. Here we report the discovery of Sirt3 modulators thanks to DNA encoded library technology (ELT). The most enriched compounds after DEL selection against SIRT3 were evaluated according to their activity and affinity. Our best activator seems at least as potent as Honokiol (HKL) while the docking studies tend to show that our modulators probably interact with Sirt3 at an atypical site.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475007" rel="alternate" title="Discovery of novel compounds as potent activators of Sirt3 (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.474964</id><title>In vitro characterization of the full-length human dynein-1 cargo adaptor BicD2 (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.998812+00:00</updated><author><name>Robert Fagiewicz</name></author><author><name>Corinne Crucifix</name></author><author><name>Célia Deville</name></author><author><name>Bruno Kieffer</name></author><author><name>Yves Nomineé</name></author><author><name>Johan Busselez</name></author><author><name>Paola Rossolilo</name></author><author><name>Helgo Schmidt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The cargo adaptors are crucial in coupling motor proteins with their respective cargos and regulatory proteins. BicD2 is one of the most prominent examples within the cargo adaptor family. BicD2 is able to recruit the microtubule motor dynein to RNA, viral particles and nuclei. The BicD2-mediated interaction between the nucleus and dynein is implicated in mitosis as well as interkinetic nuclear migration (INM) in radial glial progenitor cells, and neuron precursor migration during embryonic neocortex development. &lt;italic&gt;In vitro&lt;/italic&gt; studies involving full-length cargo adaptors are difficult to perform due to the hydrophobic character, low-expression levels, and intrinsic flexibility of cargo adaptors. Here we report the recombinant production of full-length human BicD2 and confirm its biochemical activity by interaction studies with RanBP2 and cytoplasmic dynein-1. We also describe pH-dependent conformational changes of BicD2 using cryoEM, template-free structure predictions, and biophysical tools. Our results will help defining the biochemical parameters for the &lt;italic&gt;invitro&lt;/italic&gt; reconstitution of higher order BicD2 protein complexes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.474964" rel="alternate" title="In vitro characterization of the full-length human dynein-1 cargo adaptor BicD2 (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475065</id><title>A Novel Virus Discovered in the Yeast Pichia membranifaciens (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.999085+00:00</updated><author><name>Mark D. Lee</name></author><author><name>Jack W. Creagh</name></author><author><name>Lance R. Fredericks</name></author><author><name>Angela M. Crabtree</name></author><author><name>Jagdish Suresh Patel</name></author><author><name>Paul A. Rowley</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mycoviruses are widely distributed across fungi, including yeasts of the Saccharomycotina subphylum. It was recently discovered that the yeast species &lt;italic&gt;Pichia membranifaciens&lt;/italic&gt; contained double stranded RNAs (dsRNAs) that were predicted to be of viral origin. The fully sequenced dsRNA is 4,578 bp in length, with RNA secondary structures similar to the packaging, replication, and frameshift signals of totiviruses of the family &lt;italic&gt;Totiviridae.&lt;/italic&gt; This novel virus has been named Pichia membranifaciens virus L-A (PmV-L-A) and is related to other totiviruses previously described within the Saccharomycotina yeasts. PmV-L-A is part of a monophyletic subgroup within the I-A totiviruses, implying a common ancestry between mycoviruses isolated from the &lt;italic&gt;Pichiaceae&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomycetaceae&lt;/italic&gt; yeasts. Energy minimized AlphaFold2 molecular models of the PmV-L-A Gag protein revealed structural conservation with the previously solved structure of the &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; virus L-A (ScV-L-A) Gag protein. The predicted tertiary structure of the PmV-L-A Pol and its homologs provide details of the potential mechanism of totivirus RNA-dependent RNA polymerases (RdRps) because of structural similarities to the RdRps of mammalian dsRNA viruses. Insights into the structure, function, and evolution of totiviruses gained from yeasts is important because of their parallels with mammalian viruses and the emerging role of totiviruses in animal disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475065" rel="alternate" title="A Novel Virus Discovered in the Yeast Pichia membranifaciens (6 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474905</id><title>Isolation and Identification of taxonomically diverse bacterial endophytes from citrus in Punjab Pakistan (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.999391+00:00</updated><author><name>Sehrish Mushtaq</name></author><author><name>Muhammad Shafiq</name></author><author><name>Tehseen Ashraf</name></author><author><name>Fahim Qureshi</name></author><author><name>Muhammad Saleem Haider</name></author><author><name>Sagheer Atta</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Citrus is an economically important fruit crop grown in all provinces of Pakistan, while Punjab accounting for 95 percent of total production due to its favorable climate for citrus production. Commercially grown varieties in Pakistan include sweet oranges, grapefruits, Mandarine, Lime, and lemon. The goal of this research was to see how diverse the cultivable bacterial populations are found in citrus cultivars. Out of 90 isolated cultures, 37 endophytic bacterial species and 15 different genera of bacteria were characterized based on morphological, biochemical, and molecular methods from citrus leaves. All the isolated bacteria were subjected to PCR amplification through 16S rDNA followed by sequencing. RDP base classification revealed that class Bacilli has the largest percentage of isolates, whereas class Alpha, Beta, and Gamma Proteobacteria have the lowest percentage among all genotypes used. According to the findings, the phylum Firmicutes contains a common genus (Brevibacterium, 1%; Enterococcus, 6%; Staphylococcus, 7% and Bacillus, 60%). Alpha (Rhizobium) beta (&lt;italic&gt;Burkholderia cepacia&lt;/italic&gt;; &lt;italic&gt;Comamonas terigena&lt;/italic&gt;) gamma Proteobacteria (&lt;italic&gt;Enterobacter hermachei&lt;/italic&gt; (1%), &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt; (1%), &lt;italic&gt;Proteus mirabilis&lt;/italic&gt; (8%), Pseudomonas &lt;italic&gt;aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt; (5%), &lt;italic&gt;Psychrobacter pulmonis&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Yersinia molalretti&lt;/italic&gt; (1%) respectively. These results revealed that cultivars of the plants might contribute to the structure and endophytic bacterial communities associated with citrus. Endophytes extracted from leaf samples of different citrus cultivars in Pakistan are reported for the first time. The idea of employing endophytes bacteria to produce enzymes stimulate plant growth, and its purpose as a biological control agent will be investigated in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474905" rel="alternate" title="Isolation and Identification of taxonomically diverse bacterial endophytes from citrus in Punjab Pakistan (6 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474898</id><title>The crystal structure of TRPM2 MHR1/2 domain reveals a conserved Zn2+-binding domain essential for ligand binding and activity (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.999827+00:00</updated><author><name>Simon Sander</name></author><author><name>Ellen Gattkowski</name></author><author><name>Jelena Pick</name></author><author><name>Ralf Fliegert</name></author><author><name>Henning Tidow</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Transient receptor potential melastatin 2 (TRPM2) is a Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;-permeable, non-selective cation channel involved in diverse physiological processes such as immune response, apoptosis and body temperature sensing. TRPM2 is activated by ADP-ribose (ADPR) and 2′-deoxy-ADPR in a Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;-dependent manner. While two species-specific binding sites exist for ADPR, a binding site for 2′-deoxy-ADPR is not known yet. Here, we report the crystal structure of the MHR1/2 domain of TRPM2 from zebrafish (&lt;italic&gt;Danio rerio&lt;/italic&gt;) and show binding of both ligands to this domain. We identified a so-far unrecognized Zn&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;-binding domain that was not resolved in previous cryo-EM structures and that is conserved in most TRPM channels. In combination with patch clamp experiments, we comprehensively characterize the effect of the Zn&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;-binding domain on TRPM2 activation. Our results provide insight into a conserved structural element essential for channel activity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474898" rel="alternate" title="The crystal structure of TRPM2 MHR1/2 domain reveals a conserved Zn2+-binding domain essential for ligand binding and activity (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474817</id><title>Directed evolution of angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) variants with enhanced peptidase activity profiles for novel therapeutic applications (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.000516+00:00</updated><author><name>Pete Heinzelman</name></author><author><name>Philip A. Romero</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mutants of the Angiotensin Converting-Enzyme 2 (ACE2) carboxypeptidase possessing enhanced hydrolytic activity and specificity hold potential to beneficially modulate the Angiotensin receptor (ATR) therapeutic axis with increased efficacy and reduced potential side effects relative to wild type ACE2. In pursuing this goal, we established a yeast display-based liquid chromatography screen that enabled use of directed evolution to identify ACE2 mutants with improved target peptide substrate, Angiotensin-II (Ang-II), activity and specificity relative to Apelin-13, an off-target peptide substrate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Screening yeast-displayed ACE2 active site residue saturation mutant libraries revealed three substitution-tolerant positions that can be mutated to enhance ACE2’s activity profile. Double mutant libraries combining substitutions at these positions, M360, T371 and Y510, yielded candidate improved ACE2 mutants that were recombinantly expressed and purified at 1 mg/L yield and &amp;gt; 90% homogeneity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Relative to wild type, the leading mutant, T371L/Y510Ile, has seven-fold increased k&lt;sub&gt;cat&lt;/sub&gt; toward Ang-II and six-fold decreased k&lt;sub&gt;cat&lt;/sub&gt;/K&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt; for Apelin-13 hydrolysis. In single substrate hydrolysis assays featuring physiologically relevant substrate concentrations T371L/Y510Ile hydrolyzes more Ang-II than wild type with concomitant Ang-II:Apelin-13 specificity improvements reaching 30-fold. Additionally, T371L/Y510Ile hydrolyzed Ang-II at rates greater than wild type, with Apelin-13 hydrolysis reductions of up to 80 percent, in multiplex assays containing a mixture of peptides relevant to the ATR therapeutic axis. Our efforts have delivered ATR axis-acting therapeutic candidates with relevance to established and unexplored ACE2 therapeutic applications and demonstrate the feasibility of developing ACE2 variants for use in biomedical contexts unrelated to the ATR axis such as localized activation of peptide-based prodrugs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Angiotensin Converting Enzyme 2 (ACE2) carboxypeptidase is being clinically trialed for treatment of acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) related to traumatic injuries and viral infections. We developed a yeast display-based directed evolution method that enabled isolation of mutant ACE2s possessing enhanced peptide substrate hydrolysis activity and specificity profiles with respect to substrates relevant to ARDS. Beyond their potential utility as ARDS therapeutics, our improved ACE2 variants could have an impact in unexplored ACE2 therapeutic contexts such as treating Alzheimer’s Disease. Our directed evolution method has also created an opportunity to develop ACE2 mutants that specifically hydrolyze nonnative peptide sequences; such variants could give rise to additional novel ACE2 biomedical applications including targeted activation of peptide-based prodrugs for cancer therapy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474817" rel="alternate" title="Directed evolution of angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) variants with enhanced peptidase activity profiles for novel therapeutic applications (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474899</id><title>Transglutaminase mediated asprosin oligomerization allows its tissue storage as fibers (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.001032+00:00</updated><author><name>Yousef AT Morcos</name></author><author><name>Galyna Pryymachuk</name></author><author><name>Thorben Hoffmann</name></author><author><name>Steffen Luetke</name></author><author><name>Antje Gerken</name></author><author><name>Nadin Piekarek</name></author><author><name>Margarete Odenthal</name></author><author><name>Uta Drebber</name></author><author><name>Wilhelm Bloch</name></author><author><name>Bert Callewaert</name></author><author><name>Mats Paulsson</name></author><author><name>Eva Hucklenbruch-Rother</name></author><author><name>Gerhard Sengle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Asprosin, the C-terminal furin cleavage product of profibrillin-1, was reported to act as a hormone that circulates at nanomolar levels and is recruited to the liver where it induces G protein-coupled activation of the cAMP-PKA pathway and stimulates rapid glucose release into the circulation. Although derived from profibrillin-1, a multidomain extracellular matrix glycoprotein with a ubiquitous distribution in connective tissues, little is known about the tissue distribution of asprosin. In the current view, asprosin is mainly produced by white adipose tissue from where it is released into the blood in monomeric form. Here, by employing newly generated specific asprosin antibodies we monitored the distribution pattern of asprosin in human and murine connective tissues such as placenta, and muscle. Thereby we detected the presence of asprosin positive extracellular fibers. Further, by screening established cell lines for asprosin synthesis we found that most cells derived from musculoskeletal tissues render asprosin into an oligomerized form. This oligomerization is facilitated by transglutaminase activity and requires an intact fibrillin fiber network for proper linear deposition. Our data suggest a new extracellular storage mechanism of asprosin in oligomerized form which may regulate its cellular bioavailability in tissues.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474899" rel="alternate" title="Transglutaminase mediated asprosin oligomerization allows its tissue storage as fibers (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474826</id><title>Controlled exchange of protein and nucleic acid signals from and between synthetic minimal cells (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.001582+00:00</updated><author><name>Joseph M. Heili</name></author><author><name>Kaitlin Stokes</name></author><author><name>Nathaniel J. Gaut</name></author><author><name>Christopher Deich</name></author><author><name>Jose Gomez-Garcia</name></author><author><name>Brock Cash</name></author><author><name>Matthew R. Pawlak</name></author><author><name>Aaron E Engelhart</name></author><author><name>Katarzyna P. Adamala</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Synthetic minimal cells are a class of small liposome bioreactors that have some, but not all functions of live cells. Here, we report a critical step towards the development of a bottom-up minimal cell: cellular export of functional protein and RNA products. We used cell penetrating peptide tags to translocate payloads across a synthetic cell vesicle membrane. We demonstrated efficient transport of active enzymes, and transport of nucleic acid payloads by RNA binding proteins. We investigated influence of a concentration gradient alongside other factors on the efficiency of the translocation, and we show a method to increase product accumulation in one location. We demonstrate the use of this technology to engineer molecular communication between different populations of synthetic cells, to exchange protein and nucleic acid signals. The synthetic minimal cell production and export of proteins or nucleic acids allows experimental designs that approach the complexity and relevancy of natural biological systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474826" rel="alternate" title="Controlled exchange of protein and nucleic acid signals from and between synthetic minimal cells (5 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.473755</id><title>Gata2, Nkx2-2 and Skor2 form a transcription factor network regulating development of a midbrain GABAergic neuron subtype with characteristics of REM sleep regulatory neurons (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.002290+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna Kirjavainen</name></author><author><name>Parul Singh</name></author><author><name>Laura Lahti</name></author><author><name>Patricia Seja</name></author><author><name>Zoltan Lelkes</name></author><author><name>Aki Makkonen</name></author><author><name>Sami Kilpinen</name></author><author><name>Yuichi Ono</name></author><author><name>Marjo Salminen</name></author><author><name>Teemu Aitta-Aho</name></author><author><name>Tarja Stenberg</name></author><author><name>Svetlana Molchanova</name></author><author><name>Kaia Achim</name></author><author><name>Juha Partanen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The midbrain reticular formation is a mosaic of diverse GABAergic and glutamatergic neurons that have been associated with a variety of functions, including the regulation of sleep. However the molecular characteristics and development of the midbrain reticular formation neurons are poorly understood. As the transcription factor Gata2 is required for the development of all GABAergic neurons derived from the embryonic mouse midbrain, we hypothesized that the genes expressed downstream of Gata2 could contribute to the diversification of GABAergic neuron subtypes in this brain region. Here, we show that Gata2 is indeed required for the expression of several lineage-specific transcription factors in post-mitotic midbrain GABAergic neuron precursors. These include a homeodomain transcription factor Nkx2-2 and a SKI family transcriptional repressor Skor2, which are co-expressed in a restricted group of GABAergic precursors in the midbrain reticular formation. Both Gata2, and Nkx2-2 function is required for the expression of &lt;italic&gt;Skor2&lt;/italic&gt; in GABAergic precursors. In the adult mouse as well as rat midbrain, the &lt;italic&gt;Nkx2-2&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Skor2&lt;/italic&gt; expressing GABAergic neurons locate at the boundary of the ventrolateral periaqueductal gray and the midbrain reticular formation, an area shown to contain REM-off neurons regulating REM sleep. In addition to the characteristic localization, the &lt;italic&gt;Skor2&lt;/italic&gt; positive cells increase their activity upon REM sleep inhibition, send projections to a pontine region associated with sleep control and are responsive to orexins, consistent with the known properties of the midbrain REM-off neurons.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.473755" rel="alternate" title="Gata2, Nkx2-2 and Skor2 form a transcription factor network regulating development of a midbrain GABAergic neuron subtype with characteristics of REM sleep regulatory neurons (5 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475034</id><title>GJA1-20k, an internally translated isoform of Connexin 43, is an actin capping protein (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.002957+00:00</updated><author><name>Rachel Baum</name></author><author><name>Joseph A. Palatinus</name></author><author><name>Miriam Waghalter</name></author><author><name>Daisuke Shimura</name></author><author><name>Qianru Jin</name></author><author><name>Lucas Kuzmanovich</name></author><author><name>Shaohua Xiao</name></author><author><name>André G. Kléber</name></author><author><name>Elena E. Grintsevich</name></author><author><name>TingTing Hong</name></author><author><name>Robin M. Shaw</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Previously, we identified that GJA1-20k, an internally translated isoform of Connexin 43, mediates an actin-dependent protective form of mitochondrial fission (Shimura, Nuebel et al. 2021). We found that when GJA1-20k is present, bands of actin surround mitochondria at locations enriched with GJA1-20k, inducing mitochondrial fission which generates less oxygen free radicals, protecting hearts subjected to ischemia-reperfusion injury. Here, we report that GJA1-20k is a direct actin binding protein and thereby identify the mechanism by which GJA1-20k is able to recruit and stabilize actin filaments around the mitochondria. Surprisingly, GJA1-20k functions as a canonical actin capping protein, producing both truncated actin puncta and stabilized actin filaments. GJA1-20k contains an RPEL-like actin binding motif, and we confirm with both computational modeling and biochemistry, that this domain is crucial for actin capping. The actin capping functionality of GJA1-20k adds GJA1-20k to the family of proteins that regulate actin dynamics. As a stress responsive protein, GJA1-20k can help explain cytoskeletal dependent responses to cellular stress, from delivery of channels to affecting mitochondrial size and function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475034" rel="alternate" title="GJA1-20k, an internally translated isoform of Connexin 43, is an actin capping protein (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474927</id><title>B1 SINE-binding ZFP266 impedes reprogramming through suppression of chromatin opening by pioneering factors (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.003707+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel F Kaemena</name></author><author><name>Masahito Yoshihara</name></author><author><name>James Ashmore</name></author><author><name>Meryam Beniazza</name></author><author><name>Suling Zhao</name></author><author><name>Marten Bertenstam</name></author><author><name>Victor Olariu</name></author><author><name>Shintaro Katayama</name></author><author><name>Keisuke Okita</name></author><author><name>Simon Tomlinson</name></author><author><name>Kosuke Yusa</name></author><author><name>Keisuke Kaji</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Successful generation of induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs) via the overexpression of Oct4 (Pou5f1), Sox2, Klf4 and c-Myc (OSKM) highlights the power of transcription factor (TF)-mediated cellular conversions. Nevertheless, iPSC reprogramming is inherently inefficient and understanding the molecular mechanisms underlying this inefficiency holds the key to control cellular identity successfully. Here, we report 16 novel reprogramming roadblock genes identified by CRISPR/Cas9-mediated genome-wide knockout (KO) screening. Of these, disruption of KRAB zinc finger protein (KRAB-ZFP) Zfp266 strongly and consistently enhanced iPSC generation in several iPSC reprogramming settings, emerging as the most robust roadblock. Further analyses revealed that ZFP266 bound Short Interspersed Nuclear Elements (SINEs) adjacent to OSK binding sites and impedes chromatin opening. This work serves as a resource for better understanding reprogramming mechanisms and proposes SINEs as a critical genetic element that regulates chromatin accessibility at enhancers for efficient pluripotency induction.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474927" rel="alternate" title="B1 SINE-binding ZFP266 impedes reprogramming through suppression of chromatin opening by pioneering factors (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.474696</id><title>Developmental maturation of the hematopoietic system controlled by a Lin28b-let-7-PRC1 axis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.004752+00:00</updated><author><name>Dahai Wang</name></author><author><name>Mayuri Tanaka-Yano</name></author><author><name>Eleanor Meader</name></author><author><name>Melissa Kinney</name></author><author><name>Vivian Morris</name></author><author><name>Edroaldo Lummertz da Rocha</name></author><author><name>Stuart Orkin</name></author><author><name>Trista North</name></author><author><name>George Q. Daley</name></author><author><name>Grant Rowe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hematopoiesis changes over life to meet the demands of maturation and aging.  Here, we find that the definitive hematopoietic stem and progenitor cell (HSPC) compartment is remodeled from gestation into adulthood, a process regulated by the heterochronic Lin28b/let-7 axis.  Native fetal and neonatal HSPCs distribute with a pro-lymphoid/erythroid bias with a shift toward myeloid output in adulthood.  By mining transcriptomic data comparing juvenile and adult HSPCs and reconstructing coordinately activated gene regulatory networks, we uncover the Polycomb repressor complex 1 (PRC1) component Cbx2 as an effector of Lin28b/let-7 control of hematopoietic maturation.  We find that juvenile Cbx2-/- hematopoietic tissues show impairment of B-lymphopoiesis and a precocious adult-like myeloid bias and that Cbx2/PRC1 regulates developmental timing of expression of key hematopoietic transcription factors.  These findings define a novel mechanism of epigenetic regulation of HSPC output as a function of age with potential impact on age-biased pediatric and adult blood disorders.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.474696" rel="alternate" title="Developmental maturation of the hematopoietic system controlled by a Lin28b-let-7-PRC1 axis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475238</id><title>Multifunctional role of GPCR signaling in epithelial tube formation (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.005476+00:00</updated><author><name>Vishakha Vishwakarma</name></author><author><name>Thao Phuong Le</name></author><author><name>SeYeon Chung</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Epithelial tube formation requires Rho1-dependent actomyosin contractility to generate the cellular forces that drive cell shape changes and rearrangement. Rho1 signaling is activated by G protein-coupled receptor (GPCR) signaling at the cell surface. During Drosophila embryonic salivary gland (SG) invagination, the GPCR ligand Folded gastrulation (Fog) activates Rho1 signaling to drive apical constriction. The SG receptor that transduces the Fog signal into Rho1-dependent myosin activation has not been identified. Here, we reveal that the Smog GPCR transduces Fog signal to regulate Rho kinase accumulation and myosin activation in the apicomedial region of cells to control apical constriction during SG invagination. We also report on unexpected Fog-independent roles for Smog in maintaining epithelial integrity and organizing cortical actin. Our data supports a model wherein Smog regulates distinct myosin pools and actin cytoskeleton in a ligand-dependent manner during epithelial tube formation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475238" rel="alternate" title="Multifunctional role of GPCR signaling in epithelial tube formation (4 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474764</id><title>Mito-FUNCAT-FACS reveals cellular heterogeneity in mitochondrial translation (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.005806+00:00</updated><author><name>Yusuke Kimura</name></author><author><name>Hironori Saito</name></author><author><name>Tatsuya Osaki</name></author><author><name>Yasuhiro Ikegami</name></author><author><name>Taisei Wakigawa</name></author><author><name>Yoshiho Ikeuchi</name></author><author><name>Shintaro Iwasaki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mitochondria possess their own genome that encodes components of oxidative phosphorylation (OXPHOS) complexes, and mitochondrial ribosomes within the organelle translate the mRNAs expressed from mitochondrial genome. Given the differential OXPHOS activity observed in diverse cell types, cell growth conditions, and other circumstances, cellular heterogeneity in mitochondrial translation can be expected. Although individual protein products translated in mitochondria have been monitored, the lack of techniques that address the variation in overall mitochondrial protein synthesis in cell populations poses analytic challenges. Here, we adapted mitochondrial-specific fluorescent noncanonical amino acid tagging (FUNCAT) for use with fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) and developed mito-FUNCAT-FACS. The click chemistry-compatible methionine analog L-homopropargylglycine (HPG) enabled the metabolic labeling of newly synthesized proteins. In the presence of cytosolic translation inhibitors, HPG was selectively incorporated into mitochondrial nascent proteins and conjugated to fluorophores via the click reaction (mito-FUNCAT). The application of &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; mito-FUNCAT to flow cytometry allowed us to disentangle changes in net mitochondrial translation activity from those of the organelle mass and detect variations in mitochondrial translation in cancer cells. Our approach provides a useful methodology for examining mitochondrial protein synthesis in individual cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474764" rel="alternate" title="Mito-FUNCAT-FACS reveals cellular heterogeneity in mitochondrial translation (4 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475118</id><title>The biosynthetic-secretory pathway, supplemented by recycling routes, specifies epithelial membrane polarity (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.006225+00:00</updated><author><name>Nan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Hongjie Zhang</name></author><author><name>Liakot A Khan</name></author><author><name>Gholamali Jafari</name></author><author><name>Yong Eun</name></author><author><name>Edward Membreno</name></author><author><name>Verena Gobel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In prevailing epithelial polarity models, membrane-based polarity cues (e.g., the partitioning-defective PARs) position apicobasal cellular membrane domains. Intracellular vesicular trafficking expands these domains by sorting apicobasal cargo towards them. How the polarity cues are polarized and how sorting confers long-range vesicle directionality is still unclear. Here, a systems-based approach using two-tiered C. elegans genomics-genetics screens identifies trafficking molecules that are not implicated in apical sorting yet polarize apical membrane and PAR complex components. Live tracking of polarized membrane biogenesis suggests that the biosynthetic-secretory pathway, linked to recycling routes, is asymmetrically oriented towards the apical domain during its biosynthesis, upstream of PARs and independent of polarized target domains.  This mode of membrane polarization could offer solutions to questions of current models of polarity and polarized trafficking.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475118" rel="alternate" title="The biosynthetic-secretory pathway, supplemented by recycling routes, specifies epithelial membrane polarity (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475068</id><title>Cardiomyocyte differentiation from iPS cells is delayed following knockout of Bcl-2 (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.006548+00:00</updated><author><name>Tim Vervliet</name></author><author><name>Robin Duelen</name></author><author><name>lLewelyn H Roderick</name></author><author><name>Maurilio Sampaolesi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Anti-apoptotic B-cell lymphoma 2 (Bcl-2) regulates a wide array of cellular functions involved in cell death, cell survival decisions and autophagy. Bcl-2 acts by both direct interaction with different components of the pathways involved and by intervening in intracellular Ca2+ signalling. The function of Bcl-2 is in turn regulated by post-translational modifications including phosphorylation at different sites by various kinases. Besides functions in cell death and apoptosis, Bcl-2 regulates cell differentiation processes, including of cardiomyocytes, although the signalling pathways involved are not fully elucidated. To further address the role of Bcl-2 during cardiomyocyte differentiation, we investigated the effect of its genetic knockout by CRISPR/Cas9 on the differentiation and functioning of human induced pluripotent stem cells to cardiomyocytes. Our results indicate that differentiation of iPS cells to cardiomyocytes is delayed by Bcl-2 KO, resulting in reduced size of spontaneously beating cells and reduced expression of cardiomyocyte Ca2+ toolkit and functionality. These data thus indicate that Bcl-2 an essential protein for cardiomyocyte generation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475068" rel="alternate" title="Cardiomyocyte differentiation from iPS cells is delayed following knockout of Bcl-2 (3 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475124</id><title>Signaling modality within gp130 receptor enhances tissue regeneration (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.006759+00:00</updated><author><name>Ruzanna Shkhyan</name></author><author><name>Candace Flynn</name></author><author><name>Emma Lamoure</name></author><author><name>Ben Van Handel</name></author><author><name>Arijita Sarkar</name></author><author><name>Jinxiu Li</name></author><author><name>Jesse York</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Banks</name></author><author><name>Robert Van der Horst</name></author><author><name>Nancy Q. Liu</name></author><author><name>Siyoung Lee</name></author><author><name>Paul Bajaj</name></author><author><name>Kanagasabai Vadivel</name></author><author><name>Hans I-Chen Harn</name></author><author><name>Thomas Lozito</name></author><author><name>Jay R. Lieberman</name></author><author><name>Cheng-Ming Chuong</name></author><author><name>Mark S. Hurtig</name></author><author><name>Denis Evseenko</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Adult mammals are incapable of multi-tissue regeneration and augmentation of this potential may drastically shift current therapeutic paradigms. Here, we found that a common co-receptor of IL-6 cytokines, glycoprotein 130 (gp130), serves as a major nexus integrating various context-specific signaling inputs to either promote regenerative outcomes or aggravate disease progression. Via genetic and pharmacological experiments &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, we demonstrated that a signaling tyrosine 814 (Y814) within gp130 serves as a major cellular stress sensor. Mice with constitutively inactivated Y814 (F814) exhibit regenerative, not reparative, responses after wounding in skin and anti-degenerative responses in the synovial joint. In addition, pharmacological inhibition of gp130 Y814 results in regeneration of multiple tissues in several species as well as disease modification in animal models of osteoarthritis. Our study characterizes a novel molecular mechanism that, if selectively manipulated, enhances the intrinsic regenerative capacity while preventing pathological outcomes in injury and disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gp130 Y814 signaling module serves as a cellular stress sensor responsible for hindering tissue regeneration while triggering pathological outcomes after injury.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475124" rel="alternate" title="Signaling modality within gp130 receptor enhances tissue regeneration (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475260</id><title>Moment-Based Estimation of State-Switching Rates in Cell Populations (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.007521+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael M Saint-Antoine</name></author><author><name>Abhyudai Singh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In isogenic cell populations, cells can switch back and forth between different gene expression states. These expression states can be biologically relevant. For example, a certain expression state may cause a tumor cell to be resistant to treatment, while another state may leave it vulnerable to treatment. However, estimating the rates of state-switching can be difficult, because experimentally measuring a cell's transcriptome often involves destroying the cell, so it can only be measured once. In this paper, we propose a computational method to estimate the rate of switching between expression states, given data from a Luria-Delbrück style fluctuation test that is experimentally simple and feasible. We then benchmark this method using simulated data to test its efficacy, with varying assumptions made about cell cycle timing distribution in the simulations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475260" rel="alternate" title="Moment-Based Estimation of State-Switching Rates in Cell Populations (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474999</id><title>Oligomerization of peripheral membrane proteins provides tunable control of cell surface polarity (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.007968+00:00</updated><author><name>Charles F Lang</name></author><author><name>Edwin Munro</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Asymmetric distributions of peripheral membrane proteins define cell polarity across all kingdoms of life. These asymmetries are shaped by membrane binding, diffusion and transport. Theoretical studies have revealed a general requirement for non-linear positive feedback to spontaneously amplify and/or stabilize asymmetries against dispersion by diffusion and dissociation. But how specific molecular sources of non-linearity shape polarization dynamics remains poorly understood. Here we study how oligomerization of peripheral membrane proteins shapes polarization dynamics in simple feedback circuits. We show that size dependent binding avidity and mobility of membrane bound oligomers endow polarity circuits generically with several key properties. Size-dependent binding avidity confers a form of positive feedback in which the effective rate constant for subunit dissociation decreases with increasing subunit  density. This combined with additional weak linear positive feedback is sufficient for spontaneous emergence of stably polarized states. Size-dependent oligomer mobility makes symmetry-breaking and stable polarity more robust with respect to variation in subunit diffusivities and cell sizes, and slows the approach to a final stable spatial distribution, allowing cells to "remember" polarity boundaries imposed by transient external cues. Together, these findings reveal how oligomerization of peripheral membrane proteins can provide powerful and highly tunable sources of non-linear feedback in biochemical circuits that govern cell-surface polarity. Given its prevalence and widespread involvement in cell polarity, we speculate that self-oligomerization may have provided an accessible path to evolving simple polarity circuits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474999" rel="alternate" title="Oligomerization of peripheral membrane proteins provides tunable control of cell surface polarity (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>