<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.800490+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.27.453996</id><title>Disruption of the TCA cycle reveals an ATF4-dependent integration of redox and amino acid metabolism (113 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.801014+00:00</updated><author><name>Dylan G. Ryan</name></author><author><name>Ming Yang</name></author><author><name>Hiran A. Prag</name></author><author><name>Giovanny Rodriguez Blanco</name></author><author><name>Efterpi Nikitopoulou</name></author><author><name>Marc Segarra-Mondejar</name></author><author><name>Christopher A. Powell</name></author><author><name>Tim Young</name></author><author><name>Nils Burger</name></author><author><name>Jan Lj. Miljkovic</name></author><author><name>Michal Minczuk</name></author><author><name>Michael P. Murphy</name></author><author><name>Alexander von Kriegsheim</name></author><author><name>Christian Frezza</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Tricarboxylic Acid Cycle (TCA) cycle is arguably the most critical metabolic cycle in physiology and exists as an essential interface coordinating cellular metabolism, bioenergetics, and redox homeostasis. Despite decades of research, a comprehensive investigation into the consequences of TCA cycle dysfunction remains elusive. Here, we targeted two TCA cycle enzymes, fumarate hydratase (FH) and succinate dehydrogenase (SDH), and combined metabolomics, transcriptomics, and proteomics analyses to fully appraise the consequences of TCA cycle inhibition (TCAi) in kidney epithelial cells. Our comparative approach shows that TCAi elicits a convergent rewiring of redox and amino acid metabolism dependent on the activation of ATF4 and the integrated stress response (ISR). Furthermore, we also uncover a divergent metabolic response, whereby acute FHi, but not SDHi, can maintain asparagine levels via reductive carboxylation and maintenance of cytosolic aspartate synthesis. Our work highlights an important interplay between the TCA cycle, redox biology and amino acid homeostasis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;TCA cycle inhibition promotes GSH synthesis and impairs &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; aspartate and proline synthesis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Disruption of mitochondrial thiol redox homeostasis phenocopies TCA cycle inhibition by promoting GSH synthesis and impairing proline and aspartate synthesis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Acute FHi, but not SDHi, can maintain asparagine levels via reductive carboxylation and maintenance of cytosolic aspartate synthesis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;TCA cycle inhibition mimics an amino acid deprivation-type response and activates ATF4 via the integrated stress response to maintain redox and amino acid homeostasis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.27.453996" rel="alternate" title="Disruption of the TCA cycle reveals an ATF4-dependent integration of redox and amino acid metabolism (113 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.28.454180</id><title>Cryo-EM reconstructions of inhibitor-bound SMG1 kinase reveal an autoinhibitory state dependent on SMG8 (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.801461+00:00</updated><author><name>Lukas M. Langer</name></author><author><name>Fabien Bonneau</name></author><author><name>Yair Gat</name></author><author><name>Elena Conti</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The PI3K-related kinase (PIKK) SMG1 monitors progression of metazoan nonsense-mediated mRNA decay (NMD) by phosphorylating the RNA helicase UPF1. Previous work has shown that the activity of SMG1 is impaired by small molecule inhibitors, is reduced by the SMG1 interactors SMG8 and SMG9, and is downregulated by the so-called SMG1 insertion domain. However, the molecular basis for this complex regulatory network has remained elusive. Here, we present cryo-electron microscopy reconstructions of human SMG1-9 and SMG1-8-9 complexes bound to either a SMG1 inhibitor or a non-hydrolyzable ATP analogue at overall resolutions ranging from 2.8 to 3.6 Å. These structures reveal the basis with which a small molecule inhibitor preferentially targets SMG1 over other PIKKs. By comparison with our previously reported substrate-bound structure (Langer et al. 2020), we show that the SMG1 insertion domain can exert an autoinhibitory function by directly blocking the substrate binding path as well as overall access to the SMG1 kinase active site. Together with biochemical analysis, our data indicate that SMG1 autoinhibition is stabilized by the presence of SMG8. Our results explain the specific inhibition of SMG1 by an ATP-competitive small molecule, provide insights into regulation of its kinase activity within the NMD pathway, and expand the understanding of PIKK regulatory mechanisms in general.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.28.454180" rel="alternate" title="Cryo-EM reconstructions of inhibitor-bound SMG1 kinase reveal an autoinhibitory state dependent on SMG8 (27 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-07-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453637</id><title>LAMP2A regulates the loading of proteins into exosomes (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.801731+00:00</updated><author><name>João Vasco Ferreira</name></author><author><name>Ana da Rosa Soares</name></author><author><name>José Ramalho</name></author><author><name>Catarina Máximo Carvalho</name></author><author><name>Maria Helena Cardoso</name></author><author><name>Petra Pintado</name></author><author><name>Ana Sofia Carvalho</name></author><author><name>Hans Christian Beck</name></author><author><name>Rune Matthiesen</name></author><author><name>Mónica Zuzarte</name></author><author><name>Henrique Girão</name></author><author><name>Guillaume van Niel</name></author><author><name>Paulo Pereira</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Exosomes are extracellular vesicles of endosomal origin released by virtually all cell types across metazoans. Exosomes are active vehicles of intercellular communication and can transfer lipids, RNAs and proteins between different cells, tissues or organs. However, the mechanisms that regulate the selective loading of cytosolic proteins into these vesicles are still largely unknow. Here we describe a mechanism whereby proteins containing a pentapeptide sequence, biochemically related to the KFERQ-motif, are loaded into a subpopulation of exosomes in a process that is dependent on the membrane protein LAMP2A. Moreover, this mechanism is independent of the ESCRT machinery components TSG101 and VPS4b and dependent on HSC70, CD63, Alix, Syntenin-1, Rab31 and ceramides. The transcription factor and master regulator of hypoxia HIF1A is loaded into exosomes by this mechanism to transport hypoxia signaling to normoxic cells. Additionally, by tagging fluorescent proteins with KFERQ-like sequences we were able to follow inter-organ transfer of exosomes in zebrafish larvae. Our findings identify LAMP2A as a key component in exosome biogenesis while opening new avenues for exosome engineering by allowing the loading of bioactive proteins by tagging them with KFERQ-like motifs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453637" rel="alternate" title="LAMP2A regulates the loading of proteins into exosomes (15 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453733</id><title>AGO1 regulates major satellite transcripts and H3K9me3 distribution at pericentromeric regions in mESCs (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.802130+00:00</updated><author><name>Madlen Müller</name></author><author><name>Tara Fäh</name></author><author><name>Moritz Schäfer</name></author><author><name>Janina Luitz</name></author><author><name>Patrick Stalder</name></author><author><name>Rajika Arora</name></author><author><name>Richard Patryk Ngondo</name></author><author><name>Constance Ciaudo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the past years, several studies reported nuclear roles for the Argonaute (AGO) proteins associating them with transcriptional activation or repression, alternative splicing and, chromatin organization. However, as most of these experiments have been conducted in human cancer cell lines, the nuclear functions of the AGO proteins in mouse early embryonic development still remains elusive. In this study, we investigated possible nuclear functions of the AGO proteins in mouse Embryonic Stem Cells (mESCs). By biochemical assays, we observed that AGO1 and AGO2 are present in a small fraction in the nucleus and even less on chromatin in mESCs. To profile the nuclear interactome of the AGO proteins, we performed immunoprecipitation followed by Mass Spectrometry and identified three novel nuclear interactors for AGO1, namely DNMT3a, HP1&lt;italic&gt;α&lt;/italic&gt;, and ATRX. These interactors are well-known proteins involved in the establishment and maintenance of heterochromatin at pericentromeric regions. Indeed, upon depletion of &lt;italic&gt;Ago1,&lt;/italic&gt; we observed a specific redistribution of the heterochromatin protein HP1&lt;italic&gt;α&lt;/italic&gt; and the repressive histone mark H3K9me3, away from pericentromeric regions. Furthermore, these regions are characterized by AT-rich tandem repeats known as major satellite sequences. We demonstrated that major satellite transcripts are strongly upregulated in &lt;italic&gt;Ago1_KO&lt;/italic&gt; mESCs. Interestingly, this phenotype was not caused by the loss of genome integrity at pericentromeres, as these could still form normally in &lt;italic&gt;Ago1&lt;/italic&gt;_KO mESCs. Lastly, we showed that specific microRNAs loaded in AGO1, regulate the expression of the major satellite transcripts. Overall, our results demonstrate for the first time a novel role for AGO1 in regulating major satellite transcripts and localization of HP1&lt;italic&gt;α&lt;/italic&gt; and H3K9me3 at pericentromeres in mESCs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453733" rel="alternate" title="AGO1 regulates major satellite transcripts and H3K9me3 distribution at pericentromeric regions in mESCs (10 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453751</id><title>Quantitative Profiling of Adaptation to Cyclin E Overproduction (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.802360+00:00</updated><author><name>Juanita C. Limas</name></author><author><name>Amiee N. Littlejohn</name></author><author><name>Amy M. House</name></author><author><name>Katarzyna M. Kedziora</name></author><author><name>Dalia Fleifel</name></author><author><name>Brandon L. Mouery</name></author><author><name>Andrea Walens</name></author><author><name>Maria M. Aleman</name></author><author><name>Daniel Dominguez</name></author><author><name>Jeanette Gowen Cook</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cyclin E/CDK2 drives cell cycle progression from G1 to S phase. Cyclin E overproduction is toxic to mammalian cells, although the gene encoding cyclin E (&lt;italic&gt;CCNE1&lt;/italic&gt;) is overexpressed in some cancers. It is not yet understood how cancer cells tolerate high levels of cyclin E. To address this question, we extensively characterized non-transformed epithelial cells subjected to chronic cyclin E overproduction. Cells overproducing human cyclin E briefly experienced truncated G1 phases, then consistently endured a transient period of DNA replication origin underlicensing, replication stress, and severely impaired proliferation. Individual cells displayed substantial intercellular heterogeneity in both cell cycle dynamics and CDK activity. Each of these phenotypes improved rapidly despite maintaining high cyclin E-associated activity. Transcriptome analysis revealed that adapted cells downregulated a cohort of G1-regulated genes. These cells also shared at least one unique change also found in breast tumors that overproduce cyclin E, expression of the cancer/testis antigen &lt;italic&gt;HORMAD1&lt;/italic&gt;. Withdrawing cyclin E induction partially reversed the intermediate licensing phenotype of adapted cells indicating that adaptation is at least partly independent of genetic alterations. This study provides evidence that mammalian cyclin E/CDK inhibits origin licensing by an indirect mechanism through premature S phase onset. It serves as an example of specific oncogene adaptation that can identify key molecular changes during tumorigenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453751" rel="alternate" title="Quantitative Profiling of Adaptation to Cyclin E Overproduction (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.30.454402</id><title>Structures of SARS-CoV-2 B.1.351 neutralizing antibodies provide insights into cocktail design against concerning variants (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.802568+00:00</updated><author><name>Shuo Du</name></author><author><name>Pulan Liu</name></author><author><name>Zhiying Zhang</name></author><author><name>Tianhe Xiao</name></author><author><name>Ayijiang Yasimayi</name></author><author><name>Weijin Huang</name></author><author><name>Youchun Wang</name></author><author><name>Yunlong Richard Cao</name></author><author><name>Xiaoliang Sunney Xie</name></author><author><name>Junyu Xiao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The spread of the SARS-CoV-2 variants could seriously dampen the global effort to tackle the COVID-19 pandemic. Recently, we investigated the humoral antibody responses of SARS-CoV-2 convalescent patients and vaccinees towards circulating variants, and identified a panel of monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) that could efficiently neutralize the B.1.351 (Beta) variant. Here we investigate how these mAbs target the B.1.351 spike protein using cryo-electron microscopy. In particular, we show that two superpotent mAbs, BD-812 and BD-836, have non-overlapping epitopes on the receptor-binding domain (RBD) of spike. Both block the interaction between RBD and the ACE2 receptor; and importantly, both remain fully efficacious towards the B.1.617.1 (Kappa) and B.1.617.2 (Delta) variants. The BD-812/BD-836 pair could thus serve as an ideal antibody cocktail against the SARS-CoV-2 VOCs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.30.454402" rel="alternate" title="Structures of SARS-CoV-2 B.1.351 neutralizing antibodies provide insights into cocktail design against concerning variants (7 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453829</id><title>Structure and function of the ROR2 cysteine-rich domain in vertebrate noncanonical WNT5A signaling (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.802765+00:00</updated><author><name>Samuel C. Griffiths</name></author><author><name>Jia Tan</name></author><author><name>Armin Wagner</name></author><author><name>Levi Blazer</name></author><author><name>Jarret J. Adams</name></author><author><name>Sachdev S. Sidhu</name></author><author><name>Christian Siebold</name></author><author><name>Hsin-Yi Henry Ho</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The receptor tyrosine kinase ROR2 mediates noncanonical WNT5A signaling to orchestrate tissue morphogenetic processes, and dysfunction of the pathway causes Robinow syndrome, Brachydactyly B and metastatic diseases. The domain(s) and mechanisms required for ROR2 function, however, remain unclear. We solved the crystal structure of the extracellular cysteine-rich (CRD) and Kringle (Kr) domains of ROR2 and found that, unlike other CRDs, the ROR2 CRD lacks the signature hydrophobic pocket that binds lipids/lipid-modified proteins, such as WNTs, suggesting a novel mechanism of receptor action. Functionally, we showed that the ROR2 CRD, but not other domains, is required and minimally sufficient to promote WNT5A signaling, and Robinow mutations in the CRD and the adjacent Kr alter ROR2 function. Moreover, we demonstrated that the activity of the ROR2 CRD requires Frizzled receptors. Thus, ROR2 acts via its CRD to potentiate the function of a receptor supercomplex that includes Frizzleds to transduce WNT5A signals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453829" rel="alternate" title="Structure and function of the ROR2 cysteine-rich domain in vertebrate noncanonical WNT5A signaling (7 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>