<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.482362+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.27.453996</id><title>Disruption of the TCA cycle reveals an ATF4-dependent integration of redox and amino acid metabolism (33 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.482941+00:00</updated><author><name>Dylan Gerard Ryan</name></author><author><name>Ming Yang</name></author><author><name>Hiran A Prag</name></author><author><name>Giovanny Rodriguez Blanco</name></author><author><name>Efterpi Nikitopoulou</name></author><author><name>Marc Segarra-Mondejar</name></author><author><name>Christopher A Powell</name></author><author><name>Tim Young</name></author><author><name>Nils Burger</name></author><author><name>Jan Lj Miljkovic</name></author><author><name>Michal Minczuk</name></author><author><name>Michael P Murphy</name></author><author><name>Alexander Von Kriegsheim</name></author><author><name>Christian Frezza</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Tricarboxylic Acid Cycle (TCA) cycle is arguably the most critical metabolic cycle in physiology and exists as an essential interface coordinating cellular metabolism, bioenergetics, and redox homeostasis. Despite decades of research, a comprehensive investigation into the consequences of TCA cycle dysfunction remains elusive. Here, we targeted two TCA cycle enzymes, fumarate hydratase (FH) and succinate dehydrogenase (SDH), and combined metabolomics, transcriptomics, and proteomics analyses to fully appraise the consequences of TCA cycle inhibition (TCAi) in kidney epithelial cells. Our comparative approach shows that TCAi elicits a convergent rewiring of redox and amino acid metabolism dependent on the activation of ATF4 and the integrated stress response (ISR). Furthermore, we also uncover a divergent metabolic response, whereby acute FHi, but not SDHi, can maintain asparagine levels via reductive carboxylation and maintenance of cytosolic aspartate synthesis. Our work highlights an important interplay between the TCA cycle, redox biology and amino acid homeostasis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.27.453996" rel="alternate" title="Disruption of the TCA cycle reveals an ATF4-dependent integration of redox and amino acid metabolism (33 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453616</id><title>A yeast lysosomal biogenesis map uncovers the cargo spectrum of lysosomal protein targeting pathways (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.483435+00:00</updated><author><name>Sebastian Eising</name></author><author><name>Bianca M. Esch</name></author><author><name>Mike Wälte</name></author><author><name>Prado Vargas Duarte</name></author><author><name>Stefan Walter</name></author><author><name>Christian Ungermann</name></author><author><name>Maria Bohnert</name></author><author><name>Florian Fröhlich</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The lysosome is the major catabolic organelle and a key metabolic signaling center of the cell. Mutations in lysosomal proteins can have catastrophic effects, causing neurodegeneration, cancer, and age-related diseases. The vacuole is the lysosomal analog of &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; that harbors many conserved proteins. Vacuolar proteins reach their destination via the endosomal vacuolar protein sorting (VPS) pathway, via the alkaline phosphatase (ALP or AP-3) pathway, and via the cytosol-to-vacuole transport (CVT) pathway. While these pathways have been extensively studied, a systematic understanding of the cargo spectrum of each pathway is completely lacking. Here we combine quantitative proteomics of purified vacuoles with mutant analyses to generate the lysosomal biogenesis map. This dataset harbors information on the cargo-receptor relationship of virtually all vacuolar proteins. We map binding motifs of Vps10 and the AP-3 complex and identify a novel cargo of the CVT pathway under nutrient-rich conditions. Our data uncover how organelle purification and quantitative proteomics can uncover fundamental insights into organelle biogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453616" rel="alternate" title="A yeast lysosomal biogenesis map uncovers the cargo spectrum of lysosomal protein targeting pathways (19 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453637</id><title>LAMP2A regulates the loading of proteins into exosomes (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.483758+00:00</updated><author><name>João Vasco Ferreira</name></author><author><name>Ana da Rosa Soares</name></author><author><name>José Ramalho</name></author><author><name>Catarina Máximo Carvalho</name></author><author><name>Maria Helena Cardoso</name></author><author><name>Petra Pintado</name></author><author><name>Ana Sofia Carvalho</name></author><author><name>Hans Christian Beck</name></author><author><name>Rune Matthiesen</name></author><author><name>Mónica Zuzarte</name></author><author><name>Henrique Girão</name></author><author><name>Guillaume van Niel</name></author><author><name>Paulo Pereira</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Exosomes are extracellular vesicles of endosomal origin released by virtually all cell types across metazoans. Exosomes are active vehicles of intercellular communication and can transfer lipids, RNAs and proteins between different cells, tissues or organs. However, the mechanisms that regulate the selective loading of cytosolic proteins into these vesicles are still largely unknow. Here we describe a mechanism whereby proteins containing a pentapeptide sequence, biochemically related to the KFERQ-motif, are loaded into a subpopulation of exosomes in a process that is dependent on the membrane protein LAMP2A. Moreover, this mechanism is independent of the ESCRT machinery components TSG101 and VPS4b and dependent on HSC70, CD63, Alix, Syntenin-1, Rab31 and ceramides. The transcription factor and master regulator of hypoxia HIF1A is loaded into exosomes by this mechanism to transport hypoxia signaling to normoxic cells. Additionally, by tagging fluorescent proteins with KFERQ-like sequences we were able to follow inter-organ transfer of exosomes in zebrafish larvae. Our findings identify LAMP2A as a key component in exosome biogenesis while opening new avenues for exosome engineering by allowing the loading of bioactive proteins by tagging them with KFERQ-like motifs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453637" rel="alternate" title="LAMP2A regulates the loading of proteins into exosomes (15 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453733</id><title>AGO1 regulates major satellite transcripts and H3K9me3 distribution at pericentromeric regions in mESCs (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.484112+00:00</updated><author><name>Madlen Müller</name></author><author><name>Tara Fäh</name></author><author><name>Moritz Schäfer</name></author><author><name>Janina Luitz</name></author><author><name>Patrick Stalder</name></author><author><name>Rajika Arora</name></author><author><name>Richard Patryk Ngondo</name></author><author><name>Constance Ciaudo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the past years, several studies reported nuclear roles for the Argonaute (AGO) proteins associating them with transcriptional activation or repression, alternative splicing and, chromatin organization. However, as most of these experiments have been conducted in human cancer cell lines, the nuclear functions of the AGO proteins in mouse early embryonic development still remains elusive. In this study, we investigated possible nuclear functions of the AGO proteins in mouse Embryonic Stem Cells (mESCs). By biochemical assays, we observed that AGO1 and AGO2 are present in a small fraction in the nucleus and even less on chromatin in mESCs. To profile the nuclear interactome of the AGO proteins, we performed immunoprecipitation followed by Mass Spectrometry and identified three novel nuclear interactors for AGO1, namely DNMT3a, HP1&lt;italic&gt;α&lt;/italic&gt;, and ATRX. These interactors are well-known proteins involved in the establishment and maintenance of heterochromatin at pericentromeric regions. Indeed, upon depletion of &lt;italic&gt;Ago1,&lt;/italic&gt; we observed a specific redistribution of the heterochromatin protein HP1&lt;italic&gt;α&lt;/italic&gt; and the repressive histone mark H3K9me3, away from pericentromeric regions. Furthermore, these regions are characterized by AT-rich tandem repeats known as major satellite sequences. We demonstrated that major satellite transcripts are strongly upregulated in &lt;italic&gt;Ago1_KO&lt;/italic&gt; mESCs. Interestingly, this phenotype was not caused by the loss of genome integrity at pericentromeres, as these could still form normally in &lt;italic&gt;Ago1&lt;/italic&gt;_KO mESCs. Lastly, we showed that specific microRNAs loaded in AGO1, regulate the expression of the major satellite transcripts. Overall, our results demonstrate for the first time a novel role for AGO1 in regulating major satellite transcripts and localization of HP1&lt;italic&gt;α&lt;/italic&gt; and H3K9me3 at pericentromeres in mESCs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453733" rel="alternate" title="AGO1 regulates major satellite transcripts and H3K9me3 distribution at pericentromeric regions in mESCs (9 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453751</id><title>Quantitative Profiling of Adaptation to Cyclin E Overproduction (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:49:36.484405+00:00</updated><author><name>Juanita C. Limas</name></author><author><name>Amiee N. Littlejohn</name></author><author><name>Amy M. House</name></author><author><name>Katarzyna M. Kedziora</name></author><author><name>Dalia Fleifel</name></author><author><name>Brandon L. Mouery</name></author><author><name>Andrea Walens</name></author><author><name>Maria M. Aleman</name></author><author><name>Daniel Dominguez</name></author><author><name>Jeanette Gowen Cook</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cyclin E/CDK2 drives cell cycle progression from G1 to S phase. Cyclin E overproduction is toxic to mammalian cells, although the gene encoding cyclin E (&lt;italic&gt;CCNE1&lt;/italic&gt;) is overexpressed in some cancers. It is not yet understood how cancer cells tolerate high levels of cyclin E. To address this question, we extensively characterized non-transformed epithelial cells subjected to chronic cyclin E overproduction. Cells overproducing human cyclin E briefly experienced truncated G1 phases, then consistently endured a transient period of DNA replication origin underlicensing, replication stress, and severely impaired proliferation. Individual cells displayed substantial intercellular heterogeneity in both cell cycle dynamics and CDK activity. Each of these phenotypes improved rapidly despite maintaining high cyclin E-associated activity. Transcriptome analysis revealed that adapted cells downregulated a cohort of G1-regulated genes. These cells also shared at least one unique change also found in breast tumors that overproduce cyclin E, expression of the cancer/testis antigen &lt;italic&gt;HORMAD1&lt;/italic&gt;. Withdrawing cyclin E induction partially reversed the intermediate licensing phenotype of adapted cells indicating that adaptation is at least partly independent of genetic alterations. This study provides evidence that mammalian cyclin E/CDK inhibits origin licensing by an indirect mechanism through premature S phase onset. It serves as an example of specific oncogene adaptation that can identify key molecular changes during tumorigenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453751" rel="alternate" title="Quantitative Profiling of Adaptation to Cyclin E Overproduction (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>