<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.792686+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463671</id><title>High-throughput mutagenesis identifies mutations and RNA binding proteins controlling CD19 splicing and CART-19 therapy resistance (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.793131+00:00</updated><author><name>Mariela Cortés-López</name></author><author><name>Laura Schulz</name></author><author><name>Mihaela Enculescu</name></author><author><name>Claudia Paret</name></author><author><name>Bea Spiekermann</name></author><author><name>Anke Busch</name></author><author><name>Anna Orekhova</name></author><author><name>Fridolin Kielisch</name></author><author><name>Mathieu Quesnel-Vallières</name></author><author><name>Manuel Torres-Diz</name></author><author><name>Jörg Faber</name></author><author><name>Yoseph Barash</name></author><author><name>Andrei Thomas-Tikhonenko</name></author><author><name>Kathi Zarnack</name></author><author><name>Stefan Legewie</name></author><author><name>Julian König</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During CART-19 immunotherapy for B-cell acute lymphoblastic leukaemia (B-ALL), many patients relapse due to loss of the cognate CD19 epitope. Since epitope loss can be caused by aberrant &lt;italic&gt;CD19&lt;/italic&gt; exon 2 processing, we herein investigate the regulatory code that controls CD19 splicing. We combine high-throughput mutagenesis with mathematical modelling to quantitatively disentangle the effects of all mutations in the region comprising &lt;italic&gt;CD19&lt;/italic&gt; exons 1-3. Thereupon, we identify ~200 single point mutations that alter &lt;italic&gt;CD19&lt;/italic&gt; splicing and thus could predispose B-ALL patients to CART-19 resistance. Furthermore, we report almost 100 previously unknown splice isoforms that emerge from cryptic splice sites and likely encode non-functional CD19 proteins. We further identify cis-regulatory elements and trans-acting RNA-binding proteins that control &lt;italic&gt;CD19&lt;/italic&gt; splicing (e.g., PTBP1 and SF3B4) and validate that loss of these factors leads to enhanced &lt;italic&gt;CD19&lt;/italic&gt; mis-splicing. Our dataset represents a comprehensive resource for potential prognostic factors predicting success of CART-19 therapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463671" rel="alternate" title="High-throughput mutagenesis identifies mutations and RNA binding proteins controlling CD19 splicing and CART-19 therapy resistance (15 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463475</id><title>Pseudo-dynamic analysis of heart tube formation in the mouse reveals strong regional variability and early left-right asymmetry (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.793658+00:00</updated><author><name>Isaac Esteban</name></author><author><name>Patrick Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Susana Temino</name></author><author><name>Leif Kobbelt</name></author><author><name>Miguel Torres</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding organ morphogenesis requires a precise geometrical description of the tissues involved in the process. In highly regulative embryos, like those of mammals, morphological variability hinders the quantitative analysis of morphogenesis. In particular, the study of early heart development in mammals remains a challenging problem, due to imaging limitations and innate complexity. Around embryonic day 7.5 (E7.5), the cardiac crescent folds in an intricate and coordinated manner to produce a pumping linear heart tube at E8.25, followed by heart looping at E8.5. In this work we provide a complete morphological description of this process based on detailed imaging of a temporally dense collection of embryonic heart morphologies. We apply new approaches for morphometric staging and quantification of local morphological variations between specimens at the same stage. We identify hot spots of regionalized variability and identify left-right asymmetry in the inflow region starting at the late cardiac crescent stage, which represents the earliest signs of organ left-right asymmetry in the mammalian embryo. Finally, we generate a 3D+t digital model that provides a framework suitable for co-representation of data from different sources and for the computer modelling of the process.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463475" rel="alternate" title="Pseudo-dynamic analysis of heart tube formation in the mouse reveals strong regional variability and early left-right asymmetry (14 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463578</id><title>The DNAPKcs long-range C-NHEJ complex is required for blunt DNA end joining when XLF is weakened (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.793989+00:00</updated><author><name>Metztli Cisneros-Aguirre</name></author><author><name>Felicia Wednesday Lopezcolorado</name></author><author><name>Linda Jillianne Tsai</name></author><author><name>Ragini Bhargava</name></author><author><name>Jeremy M. Stark</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Canonical non-homologous end joining (C-NHEJ) factors can assemble into a long-range (LR) complex with DNA ends relatively far apart that contains DNAPKcs, XLF, XRCC4, LIG4, and the KU heterodimer and a short-range (SR) complex lacking DNAPKcs that has the ends positioned for ligation. Since the SR complex can form &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt;, the role of the LR complex (i.e., DNAPKcs) for chromosomal EJ is unclear. We have examined EJ of chromosomal blunt DNA double-strand breaks (DSBs), and found that DNAPKcs is significantly less important than XLF and XRCC4 for such EJ. However, weakening XLF via disrupting interaction interfaces (e.g., disrupting the XLF homodimer interface) causes a marked requirement for DNAPKcs, its kinase activity, and its ABCDE-cluster autophosphorylation sites for blunt DSB EJ. In contrast, other aspects of genome maintenance are sensitive to DNAPKcs kinase inhibition in a manner that is not further enhanced by XLF loss (i.e., suppression of homology-directed repair and structural variants, and IR-resistance). We suggest that DNAPKcs is required to position a weakened XLF in an LR complex that can transition into a functional SR complex for blunt DSB EJ, but also has distinct functions for other aspects of genome maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463578" rel="alternate" title="The DNAPKcs long-range C-NHEJ complex is required for blunt DNA end joining when XLF is weakened (12 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463511</id><title>Characterization of divalent cation interactions with AASTY nanodiscs (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.794825+00:00</updated><author><name>Milena Timcenko</name></author><author><name>Anton A.A. Autzen</name></author><author><name>Henriette E. Autzen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Amphiphilic copolymers show great promise in extracting membrane proteins directly from lipid bilayers into 'native nanodiscs'. However, many such copolymers are polyanionic and sensitive to divalent cations, limiting their applicability towards Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; or Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; dependent proteins. Here, we characterize the Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; and Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; sensitivity of poly(acrylic acid-co-styrene) (AASTY) copolymers using analytical UV and fluorescent size exclusion chromatography, enabling us to separate signals from nanodiscs, copolymers, and soluble aggregates. Determination of free Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; ion concentrations in the presence of copolymer shows that divalent cation tolerance is dependent on not only specific characteristics of a copolymer, but also on its concentration. We see that high ionic strength protects against aggregation facilitated by divalent cations, which is prominent in nanodiscs isolated from excess free copolymer through dialysis. Overall, we conclude that the behavior of amphiphilic copolymers in the presence of divalent cations is more complex than precipitation beyond a specific cation concentration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463511" rel="alternate" title="Characterization of divalent cation interactions with AASTY nanodiscs (8 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.06.463384</id><title>Development of a Freeze-Dried CRISPR-Cas12 Sensor for Detecting Wolbachia in the Secondary Science Classroom (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.795371+00:00</updated><author><name>Grant A Rybnicky</name></author><author><name>Radeen A Dixon</name></author><author><name>Robert M Kuhn</name></author><author><name>Ashty S Karim</name></author><author><name>Michael C Jewett</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Training the future synthetic biology workforce requires opportunity and exposure to biotechnology concepts and activities in secondary education. Detecting Wolbachia bacteria in arthropods using PCR has become a common way for secondary students to investigate and apply DNA technology in the science classroom. Despite this framework, cutting-edge biotechnologies like CRISPR-based diagnostics have yet to be widely implemented in the classroom. To address this gap, we present a freeze-dried CRISPR-Cas12 sensing reaction to complement traditional DNA technology education and teach synthetic biology concepts. The reactions accurately detect Wolbachia from arthropod-derived PCR samples in under 2 hours and can be stored at room temperature for over a month without appreciable degradation. The reactions are easy-to-use and cost less than $40 to implement for a classroom of 22 students including the cost of reusable equipment. We see this technology as an accessible way to incorporate synthetic biology education into existing biology curriculum, which will expand biology educational opportunities in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) education.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.06.463384" rel="alternate" title="Development of a Freeze-Dried CRISPR-Cas12 Sensor for Detecting Wolbachia in the Secondary Science Classroom (7 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463537</id><title>The archaeal division protein CdvB1 assembles into polymers that are depolymerized by CdvC (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.795882+00:00</updated><author><name>Alberto Blanch Jover</name></author><author><name>Nicola De Franceschi</name></author><author><name>Daphna Fenel</name></author><author><name>Winfried Weissenhorn</name></author><author><name>Cees Dekker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Cdv proteins constitute the cell-division system of the Crenarchaea, in a protein machinery that is closely related to the ESCRT system of eukaryotes. The CdvB paralog CdvB1 is believed to play a major role in the constricting ring that is the central actor in cell division in the crenarchaea. Here, we present an &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; study of purified CdvB1 from the crenarchaeon &lt;italic&gt;M. sedula&lt;/italic&gt; with a combination of TEM imaging and biochemical assays. We show that CdvB1 self-assembles into filamentous polymers that are depolymerized by the action of the Vps4-homolog ATPase CdvC. Using liposome flotation assays, we show that CdvB1 binds to negatively charged lipid membranes and can be detached from the membrane by the action of CdvC. Interestingly, we find that the polymerization and the membrane binding are mutually exclusive properties of the protein. Our findings provide novel insight into one of the main components of the archaeal cell division machinery.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463537" rel="alternate" title="The archaeal division protein CdvB1 assembles into polymers that are depolymerized by CdvC (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463461</id><title>Comparison between Lotka-Volterra and Multivariate Autoregressive models of ecological interaction systems (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.796240+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Vigário Olivença</name></author><author><name>Jacob D. Davis</name></author><author><name>Eberhard O. Voit</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Lotka-Volterra (LV) and Multivariate Autoregressive (MAR) models are computational frameworks with different mathematical structures that have both been proposed for the same purpose of extracting governing features of dynamic interactions among coexisting populations of different species from observed time series data. We systematically compare the feasibility of the two modeling approaches, using four synthetically generated datasets and seven ecological datasets from the literature. The overarching result is that LV models outperform MAR models in most cases and are generally superior for representing cases where the dependent variables deviate greatly from their steady states. A large dynamic range is particularly prevalent when the populations are highly abundant, change considerably over time, and exhibit a large signal-to-noise ratio. By contrast, MAR models are better suited for analyses of populations with low abundances and for investigations where the quantification of noise is important. We conclude that the choice of either one or the other modeling framework should be guided by the specific goals of the analysis and the dynamic features of the data.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463461" rel="alternate" title="Comparison between Lotka-Volterra and Multivariate Autoregressive models of ecological interaction systems (3 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>