<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.240712+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.25.457694</id><title>SOX transcription factors direct TCF-independent WNT/beta-catenin transcription (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.241026+00:00</updated><author><name>Shreyasi Mukherjee</name></author><author><name>David M. Luedeke</name></author><author><name>Leslie Brown</name></author><author><name>Aaron M. Zorn</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;WNT/ß-catenin signaling regulates gene expression across numerous biological contexts including development, stem cell homeostasis and tissue regeneration, and dysregulation of this pathway has been implicated in many diseases including cancer. One fundamental question is how distinct WNT target genes are activated in a context-specific manner, given the dogma that most, if not all, WNT/ß-catenin responsive transcription is mediated by TCF/LEF transcription factors (TFs) that have similar DNA-binding specificities. Here we show that the SOX family of TFs direct lineage-specific WNT/ß-catenin responsive transcription during the differentiation of human pluripotent stem cells (hPSCs) into definitive endoderm (DE) and neuromesodermal progenitors (NMPs). Using time-resolved multi-omics analyses, we show that ß-catenin association with chromatin is highly dynamic, colocalizing with distinct TCFs and/or SOX TFs at distinct stages of differentiation, indicating both cooperative and competitive modes of genomic interactions. We demonstrate that SOX17 and SOX2 are required to recruit ß-catenin to hundreds of lineage-specific WNT-responsive enhancers, many of which are not occupied by TCFs. At a subset of these TCF-independent enhancers, SOX TFs are required to both establish a permissive chromatin landscape and recruit a WNT-enhanceosome complex that includes ß-catenin, BCL9, PYGO and transcriptional coactivators to direct SOX/ß-catenin-dependent transcription. Given that SOX TFs are expressed in almost every cell type, these results have broad mechanistic implications for the specificity of WNT responses across many developmental and disease contexts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.25.457694" rel="alternate" title="SOX transcription factors direct TCF-independent WNT/beta-catenin transcription (20 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.25.457601</id><title>Plant Polymerase IV sensitizes chromatin through histone modifications to preclude spread of silencing into protein-coding domains (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.241472+00:00</updated><author><name>Vivek Hari Sundar G</name></author><author><name>Chenna Swetha</name></author><author><name>Debjani Basu</name></author><author><name>Kannan Pachamuthu</name></author><author><name>Tania Chakraborty</name></author><author><name>Rebecca A. Mosher</name></author><author><name>P. V. Shivaprasad</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Heterochromatin is the predominant architectural feature of genomes that ensures genomic stability across eukaryotes. It mostly functions in restricting expression of repeats, mobile elements such as transposons and other regions. The establishment, maintenance and spreading of heterochromatin requires several factors including chromatin modifiers. However, how exactly heterochromatin formation is avoided in protein-coding domains is poorly understood. Here we show that a plant specific paralogue of RNA polymerase (pol) II, named pol IV, is involved in avoidance of facultative heterochromatic marks in protein coding genes, in addition to silencing the repeats and transposons forming constitutive heterochromatin. In its absence, H3K27 trimethylation mark intrudes the protein coding genes, more profoundly in genes embedded with repeats. In a subset of genes that lack the compensatory silencing, spurious transcriptional activity results in small(s)RNA production leading to post-transcriptional gene silencing. We show that such effects are significantly pronounced in rice, a plant with larger genome with distributed heterochromatin when compared to Arabidopsis. Our results indicate the surprising division of labour among plant-specific polymerases, not just in establishing effective silencing via small RNAs and epigenetics, but also in influencing chromatin boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract Figure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="457601v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-line summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;RNA polymerase IV maintains chromatin states to influence regulation of protein coding genes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.25.457601" rel="alternate" title="Plant Polymerase IV sensitizes chromatin through histone modifications to preclude spread of silencing into protein-coding domains (7 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-08-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.22.457032</id><title>A multiscale spatiotemporal model explains succession in the early infant gut microbiota as a switch from aerobic to anaerobic metabolism (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.241920+00:00</updated><author><name>David M. Versluis</name></author><author><name>Ruud Schoemaker</name></author><author><name>Ellen Looijesteijn</name></author><author><name>Daniël Muysken</name></author><author><name>Prescilla V. Jeurink</name></author><author><name>Marcel Paques</name></author><author><name>Jan M. W. Geurts</name></author><author><name>Roeland M. H. Merks</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The human intestinal microbiome starts to form immediately after birth, and can greatly influence the health of the infant. During the first days facultative anaerobic species generally dominate, followed by a dominance of strictly anaerobic species, particularly &lt;italic&gt;Bifidobacterium&lt;/italic&gt; species. An early transition to &lt;italic&gt;Bifidobacterium&lt;/italic&gt; is associated with health benefits. To study the mechanisms of this transition and its hypothesised relation to oxygen, we introduce a multiscale mathematical model that considers metabolism, spatial bacterial population dynamics and resource sharing. Based on publicly available metabolic network data, the model predicts that differences in oxygen availability explain some of the observed individual variation in succession to anaerobic species. The model also predicts that anaerobic &lt;italic&gt;Bifidobacterium&lt;/italic&gt; species become dominant through metabolizing lactose with a suboptimal yield, but a higher anaerobic growth rate than its competitors. The current work is the first step towards a more comprehensive understanding of the formation of a steady state adult colonic microbiota.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.22.457032" rel="alternate" title="A multiscale spatiotemporal model explains succession in the early infant gut microbiota as a switch from aerobic to anaerobic metabolism (7 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-08-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.22.457102</id><title>Tracheal tube fusion in Drosophila involves release of exosomes from multivesicular bodies (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.242464+00:00</updated><author><name>Carolina Camelo</name></author><author><name>Anna Körte</name></author><author><name>Thea Jacobs</name></author><author><name>Peter Robin Hiesinger</name></author><author><name>Stefan Luschnig</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fusion of endothelial or epithelial tubes is essential for the development of organs like the vertebrate vasculature or the insect tracheal system, but the mechanisms underlying the formation of tubular connections (anastomoses) are not well understood. Tracheal tube fusion in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; is mediated by tip cells that transform into lumenized toroids to connect adjacent tubes. This process depends on the Munc13-4 orthologue Staccato (Stac), which localizes to tip-cell-specific lysosome-related organelles (LROs) that display features of multivesicular bodies (MVBs). We show that the tracheal lumen contains membranous extracellular vesicles (EVs), a subset of which carries Stac/Munc13-4 and is associated with tracheal anastomosis sites. The presence of LROs and luminal Stac-EVs depends on the tip-cell-specific GTPase Arl3, suggesting that Stac-EVs derive from fusion of MVBs with the luminal membrane in tip cells during anastomosis formation. The GTPases Rab27 and Rab35 cooperate downstream of Arl3 to promote Stac-MVB formation and tube fusion. We propose that Stac-MVBs act as membrane reservoirs that facilitate lumen fusion in tip cells, in a process regulated by Arl3, Rab27, Rab35, and Stac/Munc13-4.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.22.457102" rel="alternate" title="Tracheal tube fusion in Drosophila involves release of exosomes from multivesicular bodies (5 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-08-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.24.457481</id><title>A yeast model of the ALS protein Matrin3 uncovers Hsp90 and its co-chaperone Sti1 as modifiers of misfolding and toxicity (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.242853+00:00</updated><author><name>Sonja E. Di Gregorio</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Esmaeili</name></author><author><name>Ahmed Salem</name></author><author><name>Martin L. Duennwald</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The MATR3 gene encoding the protein Matrin3 is implicated in the pathogenesis of the neurodegenerative disease amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS). Matrin3 forms neuronal cytoplasmic and nuclear inclusions in ALS-affected neurons. Additionally, 13 heterozygous missense mutations in MATR3 are identified in ALS patients. To further explore Matrin3 misfolding and toxicity, we established and characterized a yeast model. We demonstrate that wild type Matrin3 and the ALS-associated variant F115C are toxic and form inclusions in yeast. Our further characterization uncovers substantial modification of Matrin3 toxicity and inclusion formation by Hsp90 and its co-chaperones, specifically Sti1. Thus, our study demonstrates how specific branches of cellular protein quality control regulate the misfolding and toxicity of Matrin3.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We established and characterized a yeast model expressing human Matrin3, a protein implicated in the pathogenesis of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS). Using this yeast model and mammalian neuronal cells, we showed that Matrin3 mislocalizes and forms inclusions, is cytotoxic, and increases sensitivity to cellular stress. We also uncovered that Hsp90 and particularly its co-chaperone Sti1 alter Matrin3 toxicity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.24.457481" rel="alternate" title="A yeast model of the ALS protein Matrin3 uncovers Hsp90 and its co-chaperone Sti1 as modifiers of misfolding and toxicity (4 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>