<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.357335+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476471</id><title>The cytoplasmic incompatibility Cif proteins from prophage WO modify sperm genome integrity (55 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.357436+00:00</updated><author><name>Rupinder Kaur</name></author><author><name>Brittany A. Leigh</name></author><author><name>Isabella T. Ritchie</name></author><author><name>Seth R. Bordenstein</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Inherited microorganisms can selfishly manipulate host reproduction to drive through populations. In Drosophila melanogaster, germline expression of the native prophage WO proteins CifA and CifB cause cytoplasmic incompatibility (CI) in which sperms fertilize uninfected embryos that suffer catastrophic mitotic defects and lethality; however in infected females, CifA rescues the embryonic lethality and thus imparts a fitness advantage to Wolbachia. Despite widespread relevance to sex determination, evolution, and vector control, the mechanisms underlying when and how CI impairs male reproduction remain unknown and a topic of debate. Here we use cytochemical, microscopic, and transgenic assays in D. melanogaster to demonstrate that CifA and CifB proteins of wMel localize to nuclear DNA throughout the process of spermatogenesis. Cif proteins cause abnormal histone retention in elongating spermatids and protamine deficiency in mature sperms of CI-causing males. Protamine-deficient sperms travel to the female reproductive tract together with Cif proteins. In female ovaries, CifA localizes to germ cell nuclei and overlaps with Wolbachia in the nurse cell cytoplasm and the oocyte, however Cifs are not present in late-stage oocytes and the embryo. Moreover, CI and rescue are contingent upon a newly annotated CifA bipartite nuclear localization sequence. Our results reveal a previously unrecognized phenomena in which prophage proteins invade animal gametic nuclei and modify the histone-protamine transition of spermatogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476471" rel="alternate" title="The cytoplasmic incompatibility Cif proteins from prophage WO modify sperm genome integrity (55 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476191</id><title>cGAS recruitment to micronuclei is dictated by pre-existing nuclear chromatin status (41 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.357512+00:00</updated><author><name>Kate M. MacDonald</name></author><author><name>Shirony Nicholson-Puthenveedu</name></author><author><name>Maha M. Tageldein</name></author><author><name>Cheryl Arrowsmith</name></author><author><name>Shane M. Harding</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Micronuclei (MN) are aberrant cytosolic compartments containing broken genomic fragments or whole lagging chromosomes. MN envelopes irreversibly rupture, allowing the viral receptor cGAS to localize to MN and initiate an inflammatory signalling cascade. Here, we demonstrate that MN envelope rupture is not sufficient for cGAS localization. Unlike MN that arise following ionizing radiation (IR), ruptured MN generated from acute transcription stressors DRB or siSRSF1 are refractory to cGAS localization. Recruitment of cGAS to MN is blocked by inhibiting the histone methyltransferase DOT1L prior to IR exposure, demonstrating that cGAS recruitment to MN is dictated by nuclear chromatin organization at the time of DNA damage. Loss of cGAS+ MN, caused either by acute transcription stressors or by preventing DOT1L-deposited histone methylation, corresponded to significantly decreased cGAS-dependent inflammatory signalling. These results implicate nuclear chromatin organization in micronuclear composition and activity, influencing the ability of damage-induced MN to retain cytosolic proteins upon rupture.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476191" rel="alternate" title="cGAS recruitment to micronuclei is dictated by pre-existing nuclear chromatin status (41 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.475546</id><title>Identification and Age-dependent Increase of Platelet Biased Human Hematopoietic Stem Cells (41 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.357585+00:00</updated><author><name>Merve Aksöz</name></author><author><name>Grigore-Aristide Gafencu</name></author><author><name>Bilyana Stoilova</name></author><author><name>Mario Buono</name></author><author><name>Yiran Meng</name></author><author><name>Niels Asger Jakobsen</name></author><author><name>Marlen Metzner</name></author><author><name>Sally-Ann Clark</name></author><author><name>Ryan Beveridge</name></author><author><name>Supat Thongjuea</name></author><author><name>Paresh Vyas</name></author><author><name>Claus Nerlov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hematopoietic stem cells (HSC) reconstitute multi-lineage human hematopoiesis after clinical bone marrow transplantation and are the cells-of-origin of hematological malignancies. Though HSC provide multi-lineage engraftment, individual murine HSCs are lineage-biased and contribute unequally to blood cell lineages. Now, by combining xenografting of molecularly barcoded adult human bone marrow (BM) HSCs and high-throughput single cell RNA sequencing we demonstrate that human individual BM HSCs are also functionally and transcriptionally lineage biased. Specifically, we identify platelet-biased and multi-lineage human HSCs. Quantitative comparison of transcriptomes from single HSCs from young, and aged, BM show that both the proportion of platelet-biased HSCs, and their level of transcriptional platelet priming, increases with age. Therefore, platelet-biased HSCs, as well as their increased prevalence and elevated transcriptional platelet priming during ageing, are conserved between human and murine hematopoiesis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;In vivo&lt;/italic&gt; barcoding and single cell RNA sequencing identifies platelet-biased human bone marrow HSCs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.475546" rel="alternate" title="Identification and Age-dependent Increase of Platelet Biased Human Hematopoietic Stem Cells (41 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476080</id><title>A split ribozyme that links detection of a native RNA to orthogonal protein outputs (33 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.357682+00:00</updated><author><name>Lauren Gambill</name></author><author><name>August Staubus</name></author><author><name>Andrea Ameruoso</name></author><author><name>James Chappell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Individual RNA remains a challenging signal to synthetically transduce into different types of cellular information. Here, we describe Ribozyme-ENabled Detection of RNA (RENDR), a plug-and-play strategy that uses cellular transcripts to template the assembly of split ribozymes, triggering splicing reactions that generate orthogonal protein outputs. To identify split ribozymes that require templating for splicing, we used laboratory evolution to evaluate the activities of different split variants of the &lt;italic&gt;Tetrahymena thermophila&lt;/italic&gt; ribozyme. The best design delivered a 93-fold dynamic range of splicing with RENDR controlling fluorescent protein production in response to an RNA input. We resolved a thermodynamic model to guide RENDR design, showed how input signals can be transduced into diverse visual, chemical, and regulatory outputs, and used RENDR to detect an antibiotic resistance phenotype in bacteria. This work shows how transcriptional signals can be monitored &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; using RNA synthetic biology and converted into different types of biochemical information.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476080" rel="alternate" title="A split ribozyme that links detection of a native RNA to orthogonal protein outputs (33 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475536</id><title>In vivo imaging of calcium dynamics in zebrafish hepatocytes (32 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.357746+00:00</updated><author><name>Macarena Pozo-Morales</name></author><author><name>Inés Garteizgogeascoa</name></author><author><name>Camille Perazzolo</name></author><author><name>Sumeet Pal Singh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hepatocytes were the first cell-type for which oscillations of cytoplasmic calcium levels in response to hormones were described. Since then, investigation of calcium dynamics in liver explants and culture has greatly increased our understanding of calcium signaling. A bottleneck, however, exists in observing calcium dynamics in a non-invasive manner due to the optical inaccessibility of the mammalian liver. Here we take advantage of the transparency of the zebrafish larvae to develop a setup that allows &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; imaging of calcium flux in zebrafish hepatocytes at cellular resolution. Using this, we provide quantitative assessment of intracellular calcium dynamics during multiple contexts, including growth, feeding, ethanol-induced stress and cell ablation. Specifically, we show that synchronized calcium oscillations are present &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, which are lost upon starvation. Feeding recommences calcium waves in the liver, but in a spatially restricted manner. Further, ethanol treatment as well as cell ablation induces calcium flux, but with different dynamics. The former causes asynchronous calcium oscillations, while the latter leads to a single calcium spike. Overall, we demonstrate the presence of oscillations, waves and spikes &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Thus, our study introduces a platform for observing diverse calcium dynamics while maintaining the native environment of the liver, which will help investigations into the dissection of molecular mechanisms supporting the intra- and intercellular calcium signaling in the liver.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475536" rel="alternate" title="In vivo imaging of calcium dynamics in zebrafish hepatocytes (32 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.475930</id><title>Cross-linking of the Endolysosomal System Reveals Flotillin Structures and Putative Cargo (27 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.357813+00:00</updated><author><name>Jasjot Singh</name></author><author><name>Hadeer Elhabashy</name></author><author><name>Pathma Muthukottiappan</name></author><author><name>Markus Stepath</name></author><author><name>Martin Eisenacher</name></author><author><name>Oliver Kohlbacher</name></author><author><name>Volkmar Gieselmann</name></author><author><name>Dominic Winter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Lysosomes are well-established as the main cellular organelles for the degradation of macromolecules and emerging as regulatory centers of metabolism. They are of crucial importance for cellular homeostasis, which is exemplified by a plethora of disorders related to alterations in lysosomal function. In this context, protein complexes play a decisive role, regulating not only metabolic lysosomal processes, but also lysosome biogenesis, transport, and interaction with other organelles. Using cross-linking mass spectrometry, we analyzed lysosomes and early endosomes. Based on the identification of 5,376 cross-links, we investigated protein-protein interactions and structures of lysosome- and endosome-related proteins. In particular, we present evidence for a tetrameric assembly of the lysosomal hydrolase PPT1 and heterodimeric/- multimeric structures of FLOT1/FLOT2 at lysosomes and early endosomes. For FLOT1-/FLOT2- positive early endosomes, we identified &amp;gt;300 proteins presenting putative cargo, and confirm the latrophilin family of adhesion G protein-coupled receptors as substrates for flotillin-dependent endocytosis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.475930" rel="alternate" title="Cross-linking of the Endolysosomal System Reveals Flotillin Structures and Putative Cargo (27 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.475527</id><title>Cryo-EM reconstruction of the human 40S ribosomal subunit at 2.15 Å resolution (18 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.357892+00:00</updated><author><name>Simone Pellegrino</name></author><author><name>Kyle C Dent</name></author><author><name>Tobias Spikes</name></author><author><name>Alan J Warren</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The chemical modification of ribosomal RNA and proteins is critical for ribosome assembly, for protein synthesis and may drive ribosome specialization in development and disease. However, the inability to accurately visualize these modifications has limited mechanistic understanding of the role of these modifications in ribosome function. Here we report the 2.15 Å resolution cryo-EM reconstruction of the human 40S ribosomal subunit. We directly visualize post-transcriptional modifications within the 18S rRNA and post-translational modifications at the N-termini of two ribosomal proteins. Additionally, we interpret the solvation shells in the core regions of the 40S ribosomal subunit and reveal how potassium and magnesium ions establish both universally conserved and eukaryote-specific coordination to promote the stabilization and folding of key ribosomal elements. This work provides unprecedented structural details for the human 40S ribosomal subunit that will serve as an important reference for unraveling the functional role of ribosomal RNA modifications.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.475527" rel="alternate" title="Cryo-EM reconstruction of the human 40S ribosomal subunit at 2.15 Å resolution (18 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475875</id><title>The RNA-Binding Protein SAM68 regulates cardiomyocyte differentiation by enhancing Gata4 translation (16 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.357956+00:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Dasti</name></author><author><name>Maria Carla Antonelli</name></author><author><name>Magdalena Arnal Segura</name></author><author><name>Alexandros Armaos</name></author><author><name>Sarah Bonnin</name></author><author><name>Thomas Graf</name></author><author><name>Maria Paola Paronetto</name></author><author><name>Tian V Tian</name></author><author><name>Elias Bechara</name></author><author><name>Gian Gaetano Tartaglia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The signal transduction and activation of RNA (STAR) family is composed of RNA-binding proteins (RBPs) that play a central role in mammalian development. Nonetheless, the functions and modes of action that STAR proteins have in lineage specification are still poorly understood. Here, we characterized the role of STAR proteins SAM68 and QUAKING (QKI) in pluripotency and differentiation by performing their depletion through CRISPR-Cas9 in mouse embryonic stem cells (mESCs). Combining RNA-sequencing, ribosome profiling and advanced computational predictions, we found that both SAM68 and QKI regulate the mESCs self-renewal and are indispensable for cardiomyocyte differentiation. At the molecular level, we discovered that SAM68 and QKI antagonistically control the expression of cardiogenic factors. Our calculations indicated that SAM68, unlike QKI, binds the cardiogenic-specific transcription factor Gata4 in a region spanning nucleotides 500 to 1000 of the mRNA corresponding to part of the 5’ untranslated region and the first exon. We validated the predictions by electrophoretic mobility shift assay and RNA immunoprecipitation showing that SAM68 controls the translation of Gata4 during mESCs differentiation towards the cardiomyocyte lineage.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475875" rel="alternate" title="The RNA-Binding Protein SAM68 regulates cardiomyocyte differentiation by enhancing Gata4 translation (16 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476255</id><title>Location bias contributes to functionally selective responses of biased CXCR3 agonists (14 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.358038+00:00</updated><author><name>Dylan Scott Eiger</name></author><author><name>Noelia Boldizsar</name></author><author><name>Christopher Cole Honeycutt</name></author><author><name>Julia Gardner</name></author><author><name>Stephen Kirchner</name></author><author><name>Chloe Hicks</name></author><author><name>Issac Choi</name></author><author><name>Uyen Pham</name></author><author><name>Kevin Zheng</name></author><author><name>Anmol Warman</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey Smith</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Zhang</name></author><author><name>Sudarshan Rajagopal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Some G protein-coupled receptor (GPCR) ligands act as biased agonists which preferentially activate specific signaling transducers over others. Although GPCRs are primarily found at the plasma membrane, GPCRs can traffic to and signal from many subcellular compartments. Here, we determine that differential subcellular signaling contributes to the biased signaling generated by three endogenous ligands of the chemokine GPCR CXCR3. The signaling profile of CXCR3 changed as it trafficked from the plasma membrane to endosomes in a ligand-specific manner. Endosomal signaling was critical for biased activation of G proteins, β-arrestins, and ERK1/2. In CD8+ T cells, the chemokines promoted unique transcriptional responses predicted to regulate inflammatory pathways. In a mouse model of contact hypersensitivity, β-arrestin-biased CXCR3-mediated inflammation was dependent on receptor internalization. Our work demonstrates that differential subcellular signaling is critical to the overall biased response observed at CXCR3, which has important implications for drugs targeting chemokine receptors and other GPCRs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476255" rel="alternate" title="Location bias contributes to functionally selective responses of biased CXCR3 agonists (14 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475733</id><title>cdon and boc affect trunk neural crest cell migration through a non-cell autonomous reduction of hedgehog signaling in zebrafish slow-twitch muscle (14 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.358131+00:00</updated><author><name>Ezra Lencer</name></author><author><name>Rytis Prekeris</name></author><author><name>Kristin Artinger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The immunoglobin superfamily members &lt;italic&gt;cdon&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;boc&lt;/italic&gt; are transmembrane proteins implicated in regulating hedgehog signaling during vertebrate development. Recent work showing roles for these genes in axon guidance and neural crest cell migration further suggest that &lt;italic&gt;cdon&lt;/italic&gt;/&lt;italic&gt;boc&lt;/italic&gt; may play additional functions in regulating directed cell movements during development. Here we use novel and existing mutants to investigate a role for &lt;italic&gt;cdon&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;boc&lt;/italic&gt; in zebrafish neural crest cell migration. We find that single &lt;italic&gt;cdon&lt;/italic&gt; or &lt;italic&gt;boc&lt;/italic&gt; mutant embryos exhibit normal neural crest phenotypes, but that neural crest migration is strikingly disrupted in double &lt;italic&gt;cdon&lt;/italic&gt;/&lt;italic&gt;boc&lt;/italic&gt; mutant embryos. We further show that this neural crest migration phenotype is associated with defects to the differentiation of slow-twitch muscle cells, and that this slow-twitch muscle phenotype is a consequence of reduced hedgehog signaling in mutant fish. While neural crest migratory ability is not affected in double mutant embryos, neural crest directionality is severely affected. These data suggest that neural crest migration defects are likely to be secondary to defects in slow-twitch muscle differentiation. Combined, our data add to a growing literature showing that &lt;italic&gt;cdon&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;boc&lt;/italic&gt; act synergistically to promote hedgehog signaling during vertebrate development, and provide a foundation for using zebrafish to further study the function of these hedgehog receptor paralogs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475733" rel="alternate" title="cdon and boc affect trunk neural crest cell migration through a non-cell autonomous reduction of hedgehog signaling in zebrafish slow-twitch muscle (14 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476021</id><title>A bacterial secretosome for regulated envelope biogenesis and quality control (13 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.358191+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel W. Watkins</name></author><author><name>Ian Collinson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;As the first line of defence against antibiotics, the Gram-negative bacterial envelope and its biogenesis are of considerable interest to the microbiological and biomedical communities. All bacterial proteins are synthesised in the cytosol, so inner- and outer-membrane proteins, and periplasmic residents have to be transported to their final destinations &lt;italic&gt;via&lt;/italic&gt; specialised protein machinery. The Sec translocon, a ubiquitous integral inner-membrane (IM) complex, is key to this process as the major gateway for protein transit from the cytosol to the cell envelope; this can be achieved during their translation, or afterwards. Proteins need to be directed to the inner-membrane (usually co-translational), otherwise SecA utilises ATP and the proton-motive-force (PMF) to drive proteins across the membrane post-translationally. These proteins are then picked up by chaperones for folding in the periplasm or delivered to the β-barrel assembly machinery (BAM) for incorporation into the outer-membrane. The core heterotrimeric SecYEG-complex forms the hub for an extensive network of interactions that regulate protein delivery and quality control. Here, we conduct a biochemical exploration of this ‘secretosome’ – a very large, versatile and inter-changeable assembly with the Sec-translocon at its core; featuring interactions that facilitate secretion (SecDF), inner- and outer-membrane protein insertion (respectively, YidC and BAM), protein folding and quality control (&lt;italic&gt;e&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;g&lt;/italic&gt;. PpiD, YfgM and FtsH). We propose the dynamic interplay amongst these and other factors act to ensure efficient whole envelope biogenesis, regulated to accommodate the requirements of cell elongation and division. This organisation would be essential for cell wall biogenesis and remodelling and thus its perturbation would be a good strategy for the development of anti-microbials.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476021" rel="alternate" title="A bacterial secretosome for regulated envelope biogenesis and quality control (13 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476291</id><title>CtIP-dependent nascent RNA expression flanking DNA breaks guides the choice of DNA repair pathway (13 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.358247+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Gomez-Cabello</name></author><author><name>Georgios Pappas</name></author><author><name>Diana Aguilar-Morante</name></author><author><name>Christoffel Dinant</name></author><author><name>Jiri Bartek</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The RNA world is changing our views about sensing and resolution of DNA damage. Here, we developed single-molecule DNA/RNA analysis approaches to visualize how nascent RNA facilitates the repair of DNA double-strand breaks (DSBs). RNA polymerase II (RNAPII) is crucial for DSB resolution in human cells. DSB-flanking, RNAPII-generated nascent RNA forms RNA:DNA hybrids, guiding the upstream DNA repair steps towards favouring the error-free Homologous Recombination (HR) pathway over Non-Homologous End Joining. Specific RNAPII inhibitor, THZ1, impairs recruitment of essential HR proteins to DSBs, implicating nascent RNA in DNA end resection, initiation and execution of HR repair. We further propose that resection factor CtIP interacts with and re-activates RNAPII when paused by the RNA:DNA hybrids, collectively promoting faithful repair of chromosome breaks to maintain genomic integrity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476291" rel="alternate" title="CtIP-dependent nascent RNA expression flanking DNA breaks guides the choice of DNA repair pathway (13 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475888</id><title>H2A.Z deposition by SWR1C involves multiple ATP-dependent steps (13 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.358315+00:00</updated><author><name>Jiayi Fan</name></author><author><name>Andrew T. Moreno</name></author><author><name>Alexander S. Baier</name></author><author><name>Joseph J. Loparo</name></author><author><name>Craig L. Peterson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The histone variant H2A.Z is a conserved feature of nucleosomes flanking protein-coding genes. Deposition of H2A.Z requires ATP-dependent replacement of nucleosomal H2A by a chromatin remodeler related to the multi-subunit enzyme, yeast SWR1C. How these enzymes use ATP to promote this nucleosome editing reaction remains unclear. Here we use single-molecule and ensemble methodologies to identify three ATP-dependent phases in the H2A.Z deposition reaction. Real-time analysis of single nucleosome remodeling events reveals an initial, priming step that occurs after ATP addition that likely involves transient DNA unwrapping from the nucleosome. Priming is followed by rapid loss of histone H2A, which is subsequently released from the H2A.Z nucleosomal product. Surprisingly, the rates of both priming and the release of the H2A/H2B dimer are sensitive to ATP concentration. This complex reaction pathway provides multiple opportunities to regulate the timely and accurate deposition of H2A.Z at key genomic locations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475888" rel="alternate" title="H2A.Z deposition by SWR1C involves multiple ATP-dependent steps (13 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476205</id><title>BitterMatch: Recommendation systems for matching molecules with bitter taste receptors (12 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.358383+00:00</updated><author><name>Eitan Margulis</name></author><author><name>Yuli Slavutsky</name></author><author><name>Tatjana Lang</name></author><author><name>Maik Behrens</name></author><author><name>Yuval Benjamini</name></author><author><name>Masha Y Niv</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bitterness is an aversive cue elicited by thousands of chemically diverse compounds.  Bitter taste may prevent consumption of foods and jeopardize drug compliance. The G protein-coupled receptors for bitter taste, TAS2Rs, have species-dependent number of subtypes and varying expression levels in extraoral tissues. Molecular recognition by TAS2R subtypes is physiologically important, and presents a challenging case study for ligand-receptor matchmaking. Inspired by hybrid recommendation systems, we developed a new set of similarity features, and created the BitterMatch algorithm that predicts associations of ligands to receptors with ~80% precision at ~50% recall. Associations for several compounds were tested in-vitro, resulting in 80% precision and 42% recall. The encouraging performance was achieved by including receptor properties and integrating experimentally determined ligand-receptor associations with chemical ligand-to-ligand similarities. BitterMatch can predict off-targets for bitter drugs, identify novel ligands and guide flavor design. Inclusion of neighbor-informed similarities improves as experimental data mounts, and provides a generalizable framework for molecule-biotarget matching.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476205" rel="alternate" title="BitterMatch: Recommendation systems for matching molecules with bitter taste receptors (12 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476097</id><title>Myeloid-biased HSC require Semaphorin 4A from the bone marrow niche for self-renewal under stress and life-long persistence (12 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.358455+00:00</updated><author><name>Dorsa Toghani</name></author><author><name>Sharon Zeng</name></author><author><name>Elmir Mahammadov</name></author><author><name>Edie I. Crosse</name></author><author><name>Negar Seyedhassantehrani</name></author><author><name>Christian Burns</name></author><author><name>David Gravano</name></author><author><name>Stefan Radtke</name></author><author><name>Hans-Peter Kiem</name></author><author><name>Sonia Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Nadia Carlesso</name></author><author><name>Amogh Pradeep</name></author><author><name>Nicola K. Wilson</name></author><author><name>Sarah J. Kinston</name></author><author><name>Berthold Göttgens</name></author><author><name>Claus Nerlov</name></author><author><name>Eric Pietras</name></author><author><name>Marion Mesnieres</name></author><author><name>Christa Maes</name></author><author><name>Atsushi Kumanogoh</name></author><author><name>Thomas Worzfeld</name></author><author><name>Peter Kharchenko</name></author><author><name>David T. Scadden</name></author><author><name>Antonio Scialdone</name></author><author><name>Joel A Spencer</name></author><author><name>Lev Silberstein</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tissue stem cells are hierarchically organized. Those that are most primitive serve as key drivers of regenerative response but the signals that selectively preserve their functional integrity are largely unknown. Here, we identify a secreted factor, Semaphorin 4A (Sema4A), as a specific regulator of myeloid-biased hematopoietic stem cells (myHSC), which are positioned at the top of the HSC hierarchy. Lack of Sema4A leads to exaggerated myHSC (but not downstream “balanced” HSC) proliferation after acute inflammatory stress, indicating that Sema4A enforces myHSC quiescence. Strikingly, aged Sema4A knock-out myHSC expand but almost completely lose reconstitution capacity. The effect of Sema4A is non cell-autonomous, since upon transplantation into Sema4A-deficient environment, wild-type myHSC excessively proliferate but fail to engraft long-term. Sema4A constrains inflammatory signaling in myHSC and acts via a surface receptor Plexin-D1. Our data support a model whereby the most primitive tissue stem cells critically rely on a dedicated signal from the niche for self-renewal and life-long persistence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476097" rel="alternate" title="Myeloid-biased HSC require Semaphorin 4A from the bone marrow niche for self-renewal under stress and life-long persistence (12 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.09.475576</id><title>Frequent co-regulation of splicing and polyadenylation by RNA-binding proteins inferred with MAPP (12 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.358599+00:00</updated><author><name>Maciej Bak</name></author><author><name>Erik van Nimwegen</name></author><author><name>Ralf Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Mihaela Zavolan</name></author><author><name>Andreas J. Gruber</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Maturation of eukaryotic pre-mRNAs via splicing, 3’ end cleavage and polyadenylation is modulated across cell types and conditions by a variety of RNA-binding proteins (RBPs). Although over 1’500 proteins are associated with RNAs in human cells, their binding motifs, targets and functions still remain to be elucidated, especially in the complex environment of human tissues and in the context of diseases. To overcome the lack of methods for systematic and automated detection of sequence motif-guided changes in pre-mRNA processing based on RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) data we have developed MAPP (Motif Activity on Pre-mRNA Processing). We demonstrate MAPP’s functionality by applying it to RNA-seq data from 284 RBP knock-down experiments in the ENCODE project, from which MAPP not only infers position-dependent impact profiles of known regulators, but also reveals RBPs that modulate both the inclusion of cassette exons and the poly(A) site choice. Among these, the Polypyrimidine Tract Binding Protein 1 (PTBP1) has a similar activity in glioblastoma samples. This highlights the ability of MAPP to unveil global regulators of mRNA processing under physiological and pathological conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.09.475576" rel="alternate" title="Frequent co-regulation of splicing and polyadenylation by RNA-binding proteins inferred with MAPP (12 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476166</id><title>Growth orientations, rather than heterogeneous growth rates, dominate jaw joint morphogenesis in the larval zebrafish (12 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.358664+00:00</updated><author><name>Josepha Godivier</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth A. Lawrence</name></author><author><name>Mengdi Wang</name></author><author><name>Chrissy L. Hammond</name></author><author><name>Niamh C. Nowlan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In early limb embryogenesis, synovial joints acquire specific shapes which determine joint motion and function. The process by which the opposing cartilaginous joint surfaces are moulded into reciprocal and interlocking shapes, called joint morphogenesis, is one of the least understood aspect of joint formation and the cell-level dynamics underlying it are yet to be unravelled. In this research, we quantified key cellular dynamics involved in growth and morphogenesis of the zebrafish jaw joint and synthesised them in a predictive computational simulation of joint development. Cells in larval zebrafish jaw joints labelled with cartilage markers were tracked over a forty-eight hour time window using confocal imaging. Changes in distance and angle between adjacent cell centroids resulting from cell rearrangement, volume expansion and extracellular matrix (ECM) deposition were measured and used to calculate the rate and direction of local tissue deformations. We observed spatially and temporally heterogeneous growth patterns with marked anisotropy over the developmental period assessed. There was notably elevated growth at the level of the retroarticular process of the Meckel’s cartilage, a feature known to undergo pronounced shape changes during zebrafish development. Analysis of cell dynamics indicated a dominant role for cell volume expansion in growth, with minor influences from ECM volume increases and cell intercalation. Cell proliferation in the joint was minimal over the timeframe of interest. Synthesising the dynamic cell data into a finite element model of jaw joint development resulted in accurate shape predictions. Our biofidelic computational simulation demonstrated that zebrafish jaw joint growth can be reasonably approximated based on cell positional information over time, where cell positional information derives mainly from cell orientation and cell volume expansion. By modifying the input parameters of the simulation, we were able to assess the relative contributions of heterogeneous growth rates and of growth orientation. The use of uniform rather than heterogeneous growth rates only minorly impacted the shape predictions whereas isotropic growth fields resulted in altered shape predictions. The simulation results suggest that growth anisotropy is the dominant influence on joint growth and morphogenesis. This study addresses the gap of the cellular processes underlying joint morphogenesis, with implications for understanding the aetiology of developmental joint disorders such as developmental dysplasia of the hip and arthrogryposis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476166" rel="alternate" title="Growth orientations, rather than heterogeneous growth rates, dominate jaw joint morphogenesis in the larval zebrafish (12 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476178</id><title>Building programmable multicompartment artificial cells incorporating remotely activated protein channels using microfluidics and acoustic levitation (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.358731+00:00</updated><author><name>Jin Li</name></author><author><name>William David Jamieson</name></author><author><name>Pantelitsa Dimitriou</name></author><author><name>Wen Xu</name></author><author><name>Paul Rohde</name></author><author><name>Boris Martinac</name></author><author><name>Matthew AB Baker</name></author><author><name>Bruce Drinkwater</name></author><author><name>Oliver Castell</name></author><author><name>David Barrow</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Intracellular compartments are functional units that support the metabolic processes within living cells, through spatiotemporal regulation of chemical reactions and biological processes. Consequently, as a step forward in the bottom-up creation of artificial cells, building analogous intracellular architectures is essential for the expansion of cell-mimicking functionality. Herein, we report the development of a droplet laboratory platform to engineer customised complex emulsion droplets as a multicompartment artificial cell chassis, using multiphase microfluidics and acoustic levitation. Such levitated constructs provide free-standing, dynamic, definable droplet networks for the encapsulation and organisation of chemical species. Equally, they can be remotely operated with pneumatic, heating, and magnetic elements for post-processing, including the incorporation of membrane proteins; alpha-hemolysin; and large-conductance mechanosensitive channel (MscL) and their activation. The assembly of droplet networks is three-dimensionally patterned with fluidic inputs configurations determining droplet contents and connectivity. Whilst acoustic manipulation can be harnessed to reconfigure the droplet network in situ. In addition, a mechanosensitive channel, MscL, can be repeatedly activated and deactivated in the levitated artificial cell by the application of acoustic and magnetic fields to modulate membrane tension on demand. This offers possibilities beyond one-time chemically mediated activation to provide repeated, non-contact control of membrane protein function. Collectively, this will expand our capability to program and operate increasingly sophisticated artificial cells as life-like materials.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476178" rel="alternate" title="Building programmable multicompartment artificial cells incorporating remotely activated protein channels using microfluidics and acoustic levitation (11 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.475352</id><title>Structural Insights into Sphingosine-1-phosphate Receptor Activation (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.358814+00:00</updated><author><name>Leiye Yu</name></author><author><name>Licong He</name></author><author><name>Bing Gan</name></author><author><name>Rujuan Ti</name></author><author><name>Qingjie Xiao</name></author><author><name>Hongli Hu</name></author><author><name>Lizhe Zhu</name></author><author><name>Sheng Wang</name></author><author><name>Ruobing Ren</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;As a critical sphingolipid metabolite, sphingosine-1-phosphate (S1P) plays an essential role in immune and vascular systems. There are five S1P receptors, designated as S1PR1-5, encoded in the human genome, and their activities are governed by endogenous S1P, lipid-like S1P mimics, or non-lipid-like therapeutic molecules. Among S1PRs, S1PR1 stands out due to its non-redundant functions, such as the egress of T and B cells from the thymus and secondary lymphoid tissues, making it a potential therapeutic target. However, the structural basis of S1PR1 activation and regulation by various agonists remains unclear. Here we reported four atomic resolution cryo-EM structures of Gi-coupled human S1PR1 complexes: bound to endogenous agonist d18:1 S1P, benchmark lipid-like S1P mimic phosphorylated Fingolimod ((S)-FTY720-P), or non-lipid-like therapeutic molecule CBP-307 in two binding modes. Our results revealed the similarities and differences of activation of S1PR1 through distinct ligands binding to the amphiphilic orthosteric pocket. We also proposed a two-step "shallow to deep" transition process of CBP-307 for S1PR1 activation. Both binding modes of CBP-307 could activate S1PR1, but from shallow to deep transition may trigger the rotation of the N-terminal helix of Gαi and further stabilize the complex by increasing the Gαi interaction with the cell membrane. We combine with extensive biochemical analysis and molecular dynamic simulations to suggest key steps of S1P binding and receptor activation. The above results decipher the common feature of the S1PR1 agonist recognition and activation mechanism and will firmly promote the development of therapeutics targeting S1P receptors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.475352" rel="alternate" title="Structural Insights into Sphingosine-1-phosphate Receptor Activation (8 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476070</id><title>Mitochondrial Network Configuration Influences Sarcomere and Myosin Filament Structure in Striated Muscles (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.358893+00:00</updated><author><name>Prasanna Katti</name></author><author><name>Alexander S. Hall</name></author><author><name>Peter T. Ajayi</name></author><author><name>Yuho Kim</name></author><author><name>T. Bradley Willingham</name></author><author><name>Christopher K. E. Bleck</name></author><author><name>Han Wen</name></author><author><name>Brian Glancy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sustained muscle contraction occurs through interactions between actin and myosin filaments within sarcomeres and requires a constant supply of adenosine triphosphate (ATP) from nearby mitochondria. However, it remains unclear how different physical configurations between sarcomeres and mitochondria alter the energetic support for contractile function. Here, we show that sarcomere cross-sectional area (CSA) varies along its length in a cell type-dependent manner where the reduction in Z-disk CSA relative to the sarcomere center is closely coordinated with mitochondrial network configuration in flies, mice, and humans. Further, we find myosin filaments near the sarcomere periphery are curved relative to interior filaments with greater curvature for filaments near mitochondria compared to sarcoplasmic reticulum. Finally, we demonstrate smaller myosin filament lattice spacing at filament ends than filament centers in a cell type-dependent manner. These data suggest both sarcomere structure and myofilament interactions are influenced by the location and orientation of mitochondria within muscle cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476070" rel="alternate" title="Mitochondrial Network Configuration Influences Sarcomere and Myosin Filament Structure in Striated Muscles (7 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476060</id><title>Approximated Gene Expression Trajectories (AGETs) for Gene Regulatory Network Inference on Cell Tracks (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.358970+00:00</updated><author><name>Kay Spiess</name></author><author><name>Timothy Fulton</name></author><author><name>Seogwon Hwang</name></author><author><name>Kane Toh</name></author><author><name>Dillan Saunders</name></author><author><name>Brooks Paige</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Steventon</name></author><author><name>Berta Verd</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The study of pattern formation has benefited from reverse-engineering gene regulatory network (GRN) structure from spatio-temporal quantitative gene expression data. Traditional approaches omit tissue morphogenesis, hence focusing on systems where the timescales of pattern formation and morphogenesis can be separated. In such systems, pattern forms as an emergent property of the underlying GRN. This is not the case in many animal patterning systems, where patterning and morphogenesis are simultaneous. To address pattern formation in these systems we need to adapt our methodologies to explicitly accommodate cell movements and tissue shape changes. In this work we present a novel framework to reverse-engineer GRNs underlying pattern formation in tissues experiencing morphogenetic changes and cell rearrangements. By combination of quantitative data from live and fixed embryos we approximate gene expression trajectories (AGETs) in single cells and use a subset to reverse-engineer candidate GRNs using a Markov Chain Monte Carlo approach. GRN fit is assessed by simulating on cell tracks (live-modelling) and comparing the output to quantitative data-sets. This framework outputs candidate GRNs that recapitulate pattern formation at the level of the tissue and the single cell. To our knowledge, this inference methodology is the first to integrate cell movements and gene expression data, making it possible to reverse-engineer GRNs patterning tissues undergoing morphogenetic changes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476060" rel="alternate" title="Approximated Gene Expression Trajectories (AGETs) for Gene Regulatory Network Inference on Cell Tracks (6 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.475824</id><title>Functional resilience of mutually repressing motifs embedded in larger networks (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.359046+00:00</updated><author><name>Pradyumna Harlapur</name></author><author><name>Atchuta Srinivas Duddu</name></author><author><name>Kishore Hari</name></author><author><name>Mohit Kumar Jolly</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Elucidating the design principles of regulatory networks driving cellular decision-making has important implications in understanding cell differentiation and guiding the design of synthetic circuits. Mutually repressing feedback loops between ‘master regulators’ of cell-fates can exhibit multistable dynamics, thus enabling multiple “single-positive” phenotypes: (high A, low B) and (low A, high B) for a toggle switch, and (high A, low B, low C), (low A, high B, low C) and (low A, low B, high C) for a toggle triad. However, the dynamics of these two network motifs has been interrogated in isolation &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt;, but &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, they often operate while embedded in larger regulatory networks. Here, we embed these network motifs in complex larger networks of varying sizes and connectivity and identify conditions under which these motifs maintain their canonical dynamical behavior, thus identifying hallmarks of their functional resilience. We show that the in-degree of a motif - defined as the number of incoming edges onto a motif - determines its functional properties. For a smaller in-degree, the functional traits for both these motifs (bimodality, pairwise correlation coefficient(s), and the frequency of “single-positive” phenotypes) are largely conserved, but increasing the in-degree can lead to a divergence from their stand-alone behaviors. These observations offer insights into design principles of biological networks containing these network motifs, as well as help devise optimal strategies for integration of these motifs into larger synthetic networks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.475824" rel="alternate" title="Functional resilience of mutually repressing motifs embedded in larger networks (6 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476371</id><title>Mechanisms of A-type lamin targeting to nuclear ruptures are disrupted in LMNA- and BANF1-associated progerias (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.359109+00:00</updated><author><name>Rhiannon M. Sears</name></author><author><name>Kyle J. Roux</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mutations in the genes &lt;italic&gt;LMNA&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;BANF1&lt;/italic&gt; can lead to accelerated aging syndromes called progeria. The protein products of these genes, A-type lamins and BAF, respectively, are nuclear envelope (NE) proteins that interact and participate in various cellular processes, including nuclear envelope rupture and repair. BAF localizes to sites of nuclear rupture and recruits NE-repair machinery, including the LEM-domain proteins, ESCRT-III complex, A-type lamins, and membranes. Here, we show that it is a mobile, nucleoplasmic population of A-type lamins that is rapidly recruited to ruptures in a BAF-dependent manner via BAF’s association with the Ig-like β fold domain of A-type lamins. These initially mobile lamins become progressively stabilized at the site of rupture. Farnesylated prelamin A and lamin B1 fail to localize to nuclear ruptures, unless that farnesylation is inhibited. Progeria-associated &lt;italic&gt;LMNA&lt;/italic&gt; mutations inhibit the recruitment affected A-type lamin to nuclear ruptures, due to either permanent farnesylation or inhibition of BAF binding. A progeria-associated BAF mutant targets to nuclear ruptures but is unable to recruit A-type lamins. Together, these data reveal the mechanisms that determine how lamins respond to nuclear ruptures and how progeric mutations of &lt;italic&gt;LMNA&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;BANF1&lt;/italic&gt; impair recruitment of A-type lamins to nuclear ruptures.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476371" rel="alternate" title="Mechanisms of A-type lamin targeting to nuclear ruptures are disrupted in LMNA- and BANF1-associated progerias (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.475214</id><title>Modulating CRISPR-Cas genome editing using guide-complementary DNA oligonucleotides (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.359167+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas Swartjes</name></author><author><name>Peng Shang</name></author><author><name>Dennis van den Berg</name></author><author><name>Tim A. Kunne</name></author><author><name>Niels Geijsen</name></author><author><name>Stan J.J. Brouns</name></author><author><name>John van der Oost</name></author><author><name>Raymond Staals</name></author><author><name>Richard A. Notebaart</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;CRISPR-Cas has revolutionized genome editing and has a great potential for applications, such as correcting human genetic disorders. To increase the safety of genome editing applications, CRISPR-Cas may benefit from strict control over Cas enzyme activity. Previously, anti-CRISPR proteins and designed oligonucleotides have been proposed to modulate CRISPR-Cas activity. Here we report on the potential of guide-complementary DNA oligonucleotides as controlled inhibitors of Cas9 ribonucleoprotein complexes. First, we show that DNA oligonucleotides down-regulate Cas9 activity in human cells, reducing both on and off-target cleavage. We then used &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; assays to better understand how inhibition is achieved and under which conditions. Two factors were found to be important for robust inhibition: the length of the complementary region, and the presence of a PAM-loop on the inhibitor. We conclude that DNA oligonucleotides can be used to effectively inhibit Cas9 activity both &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.475214" rel="alternate" title="Modulating CRISPR-Cas genome editing using guide-complementary DNA oligonucleotides (5 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476146</id><title>Overexpression of miR5505 enhanced drought and salt resistance in rice (Orayza sativa) (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.359245+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuanwei Fan</name></author><author><name>Jiankun Xie</name></author><author><name>Fantao Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Rice is one of the most important crops in the world and half of the world population consumes it as their staple food. The abiotic stresses caused by drought, salt and other stresses have severely impacted rice production. MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are a type of small non-coding RNAs which widely reported as gene regulators, suppressing genes expression by degradation mRNA or translation inhibition. Previously, high-throughput sequencing has found a conserved miRNA miR5505 responding to drought stress in Dongxiang wild rice (DXWR). Several other studies also revealed that miR5505 was involved in rice stress responses. We further studied the effect of miRNA in drought and salt tolerance by overexpression it in rice. 2 in 18 successfully transformed transgenic lines with higher miR5505 expression were selected and then drought and salt resistance ability were evaluated. Both transgenic lines showed stronger drought and salt tolerance than wild-type (WT). Putative targets of miR5505 were identified by psRNATarget and several of them were found stress-related. RNA-seq found 1,980 differentially expressed genes (DEGs) in transgenic lines. Among them, 978 genes were down-regulated. Three genes were predicted by psRNATarget and two of them might be stress-related. We also found various environmental stress &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-acting elements in upstream of miR5505 promoter through Software PlantCARE. In all, we improved rice drought and salt tolerance by overexpressing miR5505, and the generated putative targets and &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-acting elements also suggested miR5505 might play important roles in the regulation of drought and salt responses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476146" rel="alternate" title="Overexpression of miR5505 enhanced drought and salt resistance in rice (Orayza sativa) (4 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476211</id><title>Enhancement of RecET-mediated in vivo linear DNA assembly by a xonA mutation (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.359303+00:00</updated><author><name>James A. Sawitzke</name></author><author><name>Nina Costantino</name></author><author><name>Ellen Hutchinson</name></author><author><name>Lynn C. Thomason</name></author><author><name>Donald L. Court</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Assembly of intact, replicating plasmids from linear DNA fragments introduced into bacterial cells, i.e. &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; cloning, is a facile genetic engineering technology that avoids many of the problems associated with standard &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; cloning. Here we report characterization of various parameters of &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; linear DNA assembly mediated by either the RecET recombination system or the bacteriophage λ Red recombination system. As previously observed, RecET is superior to Red for this reaction when the terminal homology is 50 bases. Deletion of the &lt;italic&gt;E. coli xonA&lt;/italic&gt; gene, encoding Exonuclease I, a 3’→5’ single-strand DNA exonuclease, substantially improves the efficiency of &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; linear DNA assembly for both systems. Deletion of ExoI function allowed robust RecET assembly of six DNA segments to create a functional plasmid. The linear DNAs are joined accurately with very few errors. This discovery provides a significant improvement to previously reported &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; linear DNA assembly technologies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476211" rel="alternate" title="Enhancement of RecET-mediated in vivo linear DNA assembly by a xonA mutation (4 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475724</id><title>DNA methylation meta-analysis confirms the division of the genome into two functional groups (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.359367+00:00</updated><author><name>Lev Salnikov</name></author><author><name>Saveli Goldberg</name></author><author><name>Parvathy Sukumaran</name></author><author><name>Eugene Pinsky</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Based on a meta-analysis of human genome methylation data, we tested a theoretical model in which aging is explained by the redistribution of limited resources in cells between two main tasks of the organism: its self-sustenance based on the function of the housekeeping gene group (HG) and functional differentiation, provided by the (IntG) integrative gene group. A meta-analysis of methylation of 100 genes, 50 in the HG group and 50 in IntG, showed significant differences (p&amp;lt;0.0001) between our groups in the level of absolute methylation values of genes bodies and its promoters. We showed a reliable decrease of absolute methylation values in IntG with rising age in contrast to HG, where this level remained constant. The one-sided decrease in methylation in the IntG group is indirectly confirmed by the dispersion data analysis, which also decreased in the genes of this group. The imbalance between HG and IntG in methylation levels suggests that this IntG-shift is a side effect of the ontogenesis grownup program and the main cause of aging. The theoretical model of functional genome division also suggests the leading role of slow dividing and post mitotic cells in triggering and implementing the aging process.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475724" rel="alternate" title="DNA methylation meta-analysis confirms the division of the genome into two functional groups (4 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475678</id><title>Machine learning for exploring microbial inter-kingdom associations in Cystic Fibrosis and Bronchiectasis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.359426+00:00</updated><author><name>L. Cuthbertson</name></author><author><name>J. Ish-Horowicz</name></author><author><name>I.C. Felton</name></author><author><name>P. James</name></author><author><name>E. Turek</name></author><author><name>M.J. Cox</name></author><author><name>M.R. Loebinger</name></author><author><name>N.J. Simmonds</name></author><author><name>S. Filippi</name></author><author><name>M.F. Moffatt</name></author><author><name>W.O.C. Cookson</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cystic fibrosis (CF) and non-CF bronchiectasis (BX) are lung diseases characterised by severe chronic infections. Fungal and bacterial components of infection are both recognized. Recent molecular investigation of sputum from patients with CF and BX has revealed a complex mycobiome. However, little is known about how fungal and bacterial organisms interact or whether the interactions impact on disease outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Quantitative PCR and next generation sequencing of ITS2 and 16S rRNA gene was carried out on 107 patients with CF and BX and defined clinical fungal infection status. Fungal and bacterial communities were explored using supervised and unsupervised machine learning to understand associations between fungal and bacterial communities and their relationship to disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fungal and bacterial communities both had significantly higher biomass and lower diversity in CF compared to BX patients. Random forest modelling demonstrated that the fungal and bacterial communities were distinct between CF and BX patients. Within the CF group, bacterial communities contained no predictive signal for fungal disease status. Neither bacterial nor fungal community composition were predictive of the presence of CF pulmonary exacerbation (CFPE). Intra-kingdom correlations were far stronger than those between the two kingdoms. Dirichlet mixture components analysis identified two distinct clusters of bacteria related to the relative abundance of &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/italic&gt;. Fungal community composition contained no predictive signal for bacterial clusters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clear changes in diversity were observed between patients with different clinical disease status. Although our results demonstrate that bacterial community composition differs in the presence of fungal disease, no direct relationship between bacterial and fungal OTUs was found.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475678" rel="alternate" title="Machine learning for exploring microbial inter-kingdom associations in Cystic Fibrosis and Bronchiectasis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476372</id><title>Structural Basis for the Calmodulin-Mediated Activation of eEF-2K (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.359543+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrea Piserchio</name></author><author><name>Eta A Isiroho</name></author><author><name>Kimberly Long</name></author><author><name>Amanda L Bohanon</name></author><author><name>Eric A Kumar</name></author><author><name>Nathan Will</name></author><author><name>David Jeruzalmi</name></author><author><name>Kevin N Dalby</name></author><author><name>Ranajeet Ghose</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Translation is a highly energy consumptive process tightly regulated for optimal protein quality and adaptation to energy and nutrient availability. A key facilitator of this process is the α-kinase eEF-2K that specifically phosphorylates the GTP-dependent translocase eEF-2, thereby reducing its affinity for the ribosome and suppressing the elongation phase of protein synthesis. eEF-2K activation requires calmodulin binding and auto-phosphorylation at the primary stimulatory site, T348. Biochemical studies have predicted that calmodulin activates eEF-2K through a unique allosteric process mechanistically distinct from other calmodulin-dependent kinases. Here we resolve the atomic details of this mechanism through a 2.3 Å crystal structure of the heterodimeric complex of calmodulin with the functional core of eEF-2K (eEF-2K&lt;sub&gt;TR&lt;/sub&gt;). This structure, which represents the activated T348-phosphorylated state of eEF-2K&lt;sub&gt;TR&lt;/sub&gt;, highlights how through an intimate association with the calmodulin C-lobe, the kinase creates a spine that extends from its N-terminal calmodulin-targeting motif through a conserved regulatory element to its active site. Modification of key spine residues has deleterious functional consequences.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476372" rel="alternate" title="Structural Basis for the Calmodulin-Mediated Activation of eEF-2K (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475967</id><title>Unifying Gene Expression Complexity and Cellular Operational Efficiency: Application of the Locality and Caching Principles via a Cell-to-Computer Analogy (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.359623+00:00</updated><author><name>Wen Jiang</name></author><author><name>Denis Feliers</name></author><author><name>W. Jim Zheng</name></author><author><name>Fangyuan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Degeng Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gene expression is time-consuming, and the delay from transcription activation to produced proteins is sequentially longer from bacteria to yeast and to humans. How human cells bypass the delay and attain operational efficiency, &lt;italic&gt;i&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;e&lt;/italic&gt;., quick proteomic response to signals, is not well understood. The computer has endured the same system latency issue due to much slower information retrieval (hard drive (HD) to memory and to CPU) than CPU execution, and mitigated it via efficient memory management, namely, the spatiotemporal locality principles that control specialized user functions and the permanent caching of core system functions – the operating system (OS) kernel. Thus, in this study, we unified gene expression and HD-memory-CPU information flow as instances of the Shannon information theory, both supporting the respective system operations and consisting of three components: information storage, the execution/decoding step, and the channel for the dynamic storage-to-execution information flow; the gene expression machinery and their regulators, and the OS kernel, were deemed as the respective channels. This abstraction prompted a multi-omic comparative analysis, generating experimental evidence that transcriptome regulation shares the computer memory management principles. First, the temporal locality principle explains the mRNA stabilization-by-translation regulatory mechanism and controls specialized cellular functions. Second, the caching principle explains cytoplasmic mRNA sequestration and the defiance of the locality principle by highly sequestered mRNAs. Third, strikingly, in both systems, the caching principle controls the information channels; similar to permanent caching of OS kernel, basic translation/transcription machinery and their regulators are the top most sequestered mRNAs. Summarily, the locality and the caching principles differentially regulate specialized functions and core system functions, respectively, integrating the complexity of transcriptome regulation with cellular operational latency mitigation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475967" rel="alternate" title="Unifying Gene Expression Complexity and Cellular Operational Efficiency: Application of the Locality and Caching Principles via a Cell-to-Computer Analogy (4 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475766</id><title>Machine Learning-Based Enzyme Engineering of PETase for Improved Efficiency in Degrading Non-Biodegradable Plastic (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.359689+00:00</updated><author><name>Arjun Gupta</name></author><author><name>Sangeeta Agrawal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Globally, nearly a million plastic bottles are produced every minute (1). These non-biodegradable plastic products are composed of Polyethylene terephthalate (PET). In 2016, researchers discovered PETase, an enzyme from the bacteria &lt;italic&gt;Ideonella sakaiensis&lt;/italic&gt; which breaks down PET and nonbiodegradable plastic. However, PETase has low efficiency at high temperatures. In this project, we optimized the rate of PET degradation by PETase by designing new mutant enzymes which could break down PET much faster than PETase, which is currently the gold standard. We used machine learning (ML) guided directed evolution to modify the PETase enzyme to have a higher optimal temperature (Topt), which would allow the enzyme to degrade PET more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;First, we trained three machine learning models to predict Topt with high performance, including Logistic Regression, Linear Regression and Random Forest. We then used Random Forest to perform ML-guided directed evolution. Our algorithm generated hundreds of mutants of PETase and screened them using Random Forest to select mutants with the highest Topt, and then used the top mutants as the enzyme being mutated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After 1000 iterations, we produced a new mutant of PETase with Topt of 71.38°C. We also produced a new mutant enzyme after 29 iterations with Topt of 61.3°C. To ensure these mutant enzymes would remain stable, we predicted their melting temperatures using an external predictor and found the 29-iteration mutant had improved thermostability over PETase.Our research is significant because using our approach and algorithm, scientists can optimize additional enzymes for improved efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475766" rel="alternate" title="Machine Learning-Based Enzyme Engineering of PETase for Improved Efficiency in Degrading Non-Biodegradable Plastic (4 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476336</id><title>Limb Specific Failure of Proliferation and Translation in the Mesenchyme Leads to Skeletal Defects in Diamond Blackfan Anemia (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.359742+00:00</updated><author><name>Jimmy Hom</name></author><author><name>Theodoros Karnavas</name></author><author><name>Emily Hartman</name></author><author><name>Julien Papoin</name></author><author><name>Yuefeng Tang</name></author><author><name>Brian M. Dulmovits</name></author><author><name>Mushran Khan</name></author><author><name>Hiren Patel</name></author><author><name>Jedediah Bondy</name></author><author><name>Morris Edelman</name></author><author><name>Renaud Touraine</name></author><author><name>Geneviève Chanoz-Poulard</name></author><author><name>Gregory Ottenberg</name></author><author><name>Robert Maynard</name></author><author><name>Douglas J. Adams</name></author><author><name>Raymond F. Robledo</name></author><author><name>Daniel A Grande</name></author><author><name>Philippe Marambaud</name></author><author><name>Betsy J Barnes</name></author><author><name>Sébastien Durand</name></author><author><name>Anupama Narla</name></author><author><name>Steven Ellis</name></author><author><name>Leonard I. Zon</name></author><author><name>Luanne L. Peters</name></author><author><name>Lydie Da Costa</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey M. Lipton</name></author><author><name>Cheryl L. Ackert-Bicknell</name></author><author><name>Lionel Blanc</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ribosomopathies are a class of disorders caused by defects in the structure or function of the ribosome and characterized by tissue-specific abnormalities. Diamond Blackfan anemia (DBA) arises from different mutations, predominantly in genes encoding ribosomal proteins (RPs). Apart from the anemia, skeletal defects are among the most common anomalies observed in patients with DBA, but they are virtually restricted to radial ray and other upper limb defects. What leads to these site-specific skeletal defects in DBA remains a mystery. Using a novel mouse model for RP haploinsufficiency, we observed specific, differential defects of the limbs. Using complementary &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; approaches, we demonstrate that reduced WNT signaling and subsequent increased β-catenin degradation in concert with increased expression of p53 contribute to mesenchymal lineage failure. We observed differential defects in the proliferation and differentiation of mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs) from the forelimb versus the hind limbs of the RP haploinsufficient mice that persisted after birth and were partially rescued by allelic reduction of &lt;italic&gt;Trp53&lt;/italic&gt;. These defects are associated with a global decrease in protein translation in RP haploinsufficient MSCs, with the effect more pronounced in cells isolated from the forelimbs. Together these results demonstrate translational differences inherent to the MSC, explaining the site-specific skeletal defects observed in DBA.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476336" rel="alternate" title="Limb Specific Failure of Proliferation and Translation in the Mesenchyme Leads to Skeletal Defects in Diamond Blackfan Anemia (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476349</id><title>The RNA-binding landscape of HAX1 protein indicates its involvement in ribosome biogenesis and translation. (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.359887+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna Balcarak</name></author><author><name>Ewelina Macech-Klicka</name></author><author><name>Maciej Wakula</name></author><author><name>Rafal Tomecki</name></author><author><name>Krzysztof Goryca</name></author><author><name>Malgorzata Rydzanicz</name></author><author><name>Mateusz Chmielarczyk</name></author><author><name>Marta Wisniewska</name></author><author><name>Filip Lyczek</name></author><author><name>Aleksandra Helwak</name></author><author><name>David Tollervey</name></author><author><name>Grzegorz Kudla</name></author><author><name>Ewa Grzybowska</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;HAX1 is a human protein with no known homologues or structural domains, mutations in which cause severe congenital neutropenia through mechanisms that are poorly understood. Previous studies reported RNA-binding capacity of HAX1, but the role of this binding in physiology and pathology remains unexplained. Here we report transcriptome-wide characterization of HAX1 RNA targets using RIP-seq and CRAC, indicating that HAX1 binds transcripts involved in ribosome biogenesis and rRNA processing. Using CRISPR knockouts we find that RNA targets of HAX1 partially overlap with transcripts downregulated in HAX1 KO, implying a role in mRNA stabilization. Gene ontology analysis demonstrated that genes differentially expressed in HAX1 KO (including genes involved in ribosome biogenesis and translation) are also enriched in a subset of genes whose expression correlates with HAX1 expression in four analyzed neoplasms. Functional connection to ribosome biogenesis was also demonstrated by gradient sedimentation ribosome profiles, which revealed differences in the small subunit:monosome ratio in HAX1 WT/KO. We speculate that changes in HAX1 expression may be important for the etiology of HAX1-linked diseases through dysregulation of translation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476349" rel="alternate" title="The RNA-binding landscape of HAX1 protein indicates its involvement in ribosome biogenesis and translation. (4 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476066</id><title>Epac1 regulates cellular SUMOylation by promoting the formation of SUMO-activating nuclear condensates (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.359980+00:00</updated><author><name>Wenli Yang</name></author><author><name>William G. Robichaux</name></author><author><name>Fang C. Mei</name></author><author><name>Wei Lin</name></author><author><name>Li Li</name></author><author><name>Sheng Pan</name></author><author><name>Mark A. White</name></author><author><name>Yuan Chen</name></author><author><name>Xiaodong Cheng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protein SUMOylation plays an essential role in maintaining cellular homeostasis when cells are under stress. However, precisely how SUMOylation is regulated, and a molecular mechanism linking cellular stress to SUMOylation remains elusive. Herein, we report that cAMP, a major stress-response second messenger, acts through Epac1 as a regulator of cellular SUMOylation. The Epac1-associated proteome is highly enriched with components of the SUMOylation pathway. Activation of Epac1 by intracellular cAMP triggers phase separation and the formation of nuclear condensates containing Epac1 and general components of the SUMOylation machinery to promote cellular SUMOylation. Furthermore, genetic knockout of Epac1 obliterates oxidized low-density lipoprotein induced cellular SUMOylation in macrophages, leading to suppression of foam cell formation. These results provide a direct nexus connecting two major cellular stress responses to define a molecular mechanism in which cAMP regulates the dynamics of cellular condensates to modulate protein SUMOylation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476066" rel="alternate" title="Epac1 regulates cellular SUMOylation by promoting the formation of SUMO-activating nuclear condensates (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476006</id><title>Factor VII activating protease (FSAP) inhibits the outcome of ischemic stroke in mouse models (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.360057+00:00</updated><author><name>Jeong Yeon Kim</name></author><author><name>Dipankar Manna</name></author><author><name>Trygve B. Leergaard</name></author><author><name>Sandip M. Kanse</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Factor VII activating protease (FSAP) is a circulating serine protease, and individuals with the Marburg I (MI) single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP), which results in an inactive enzyme, have an increased risk of stroke. The outcome of ischemic stroke is more marked in FSAP-deficient mice compared to their wild-type (WT) counterparts. Plasma FSAP levels are raised in patients as well as mice after stroke. &lt;italic&gt;In vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, FSAP promotes fibrinolysis by cleavage of fibrinogen, activates protease-activated receptors and decreases the cellular cytotoxicity of histones. Since these are desirable properties in stroke treatment, we tested the effect of recombinant serine protease domain of FSAP (FSAP-SPD) on ischemic stroke in mice. A combination of tissue plasminogen activator (tPA) and FSAP-SPD enhanced clot lysis, improved microvascular perfusion and neurological outcome and reduced infarct volumes in a mouse model of thromboembolic stroke. In the tail bleeding model FSAP-SPD treatment provoked a faster clotting time indicating that it has a pro-coagulant effect that is described before. FSAP-SPD improved stroke outcome and diminished the negative effects of co-treatment with tPA in the transient middle cerebral artery occlusion model. The inactive MI-isoform of FSAP did not have any effects in either model. In mice with FSAP deficiency there were minor differences in the outcomes of stroke but the treatment with FSAP-SPD was equally effective. Thus, FSAP represents a promising novel therapeutic strategy in the treatment of ischemic stroke that requires further evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476006" rel="alternate" title="Factor VII activating protease (FSAP) inhibits the outcome of ischemic stroke in mouse models (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.475748</id><title>Cell lineage specification during development of the anterior lateral plate mesoderm and forelimb field (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.360117+00:00</updated><author><name>Axel H Newton</name></author><author><name>Sarah M Williams</name></author><author><name>Andrew T Major</name></author><author><name>Craig A Smith</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The lateral plate mesoderm (LPM) is a transient embryonic tissue that gives rise to a diverse range of mature cell types, including the cardiovascular system, the urogenital system, endoskeleton of the limbs, and mesenchyme of the gut. While the genetic processes that drive development of these tissues are well defined, the early cell fate choices underlying LPM development and specification are poorly understood. In this study, we utilize single-cell transcriptomics to define cell lineage specification during development of the anterior LPM and the forelimb field in the chicken embryo. We identify the molecular pathways directing differentiation of the aLPM towards a somatic or splanchnic cell fate, and subsequent emergence of the forelimb mesenchyme. We establish the first transcriptional atlas of progenitor, transitional and mature cell types throughout the early forelimb field and uncover the global signalling pathways which are active during LPM differentiation and forelimb initiation. Specification of the somatic and splanchnic LPM from undifferentiated mesoderm utilizes distinct signalling pathways and involves shared repression of early mesodermal markers, followed by activation of lineage-specific gene modules. We identify rapid activation of the transcription factor &lt;italic&gt;TWIST1&lt;/italic&gt; in the somatic LPM preceding activation of known limb initiation genes, such as &lt;italic&gt;TBX&lt;/italic&gt;5, which plays a likely role in epithelial-to-mesenchyme transition of the limb bud mesenchyme. Furthermore, development of the somatic LPM and limb is dependent on ectodermal BMP signalling, where BMP antagonism reduces expression of key somatic LPM and limb genes to inhibit formation of the limb bud mesenchyme. Together, these findings provide new insights into molecular mechanisms that drive fate cell choices during specification of the aLPM and forelimb initiation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.475748" rel="alternate" title="Cell lineage specification during development of the anterior lateral plate mesoderm and forelimb field (3 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.475833</id><title>Prom1 and Notch regulate ciliary length and dynamics in multiciliated cells of the airway epithelium (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.360176+00:00</updated><author><name>Carlos F. H. Serra</name></author><author><name>Helu Liu</name></author><author><name>Jun Qian</name></author><author><name>Munemasa Mori</name></author><author><name>Jining Lu</name></author><author><name>Wellington V. Cardoso</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Differences in ciliary morphology and dynamics among multiciliated cells of the respiratory tract have been well reported and known to contribute to efficient mucociliary clearance. Nevertheless, little is known about how phenotypic differences among multiciliated cells are established in the mammalian lung. Here we show that Prominin-1 (Prom1), a transmembrane protein widely used as stem cell and tumor-initiating marker, is crucial to this process. During airway differentiation, Prom1 becomes restricted to multiciliated cells, where it is expressed at distinct levels along the proximal-distal axis of the airways and in the adult airway epithelium in vitro. We found that Prom1 is induced by Notch in post-specified multiciliated cells and that Notch inactivation abolishes the gradients of Prom1 in the developing airways and in differentiating organotypic cultures. Prom1 was not required for multicilia formation and when inactivated resulted in longer cilia, which remained functional but beating at a lower frequency. Disruption of Notch resulted in opposite effects and suggested that Notch fine-tunes Prom1 levels to regulate the multiciliated cell phenotype and generate diversity among these cells in the respiratory tract. By controlling these features, this mechanism contributes to the innate defense of the lung against environmental agents and prevent pulmonary disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Multiciliated cells are integral components of the epithelia from a variety of organs. In the respiratory tract they are crucial for mucociliary clearance, a first line of defense against environmental agents and microorganisms. Regional differences in ciliary morphology and dynamics of multiciliated cells have been well described. However, little is known about the events generating phenotypical and functional differences among these cells in airways. Here we provide evidence of a novel mechanism in post-specified multiciliated progenitors whereby local Notch and Prom1 regulate ciliary length and ciliary beating to generate morphological and functional diversity among the multiciliated cells. The findings provide insights into the impact of these signals in maintaining the integrity and function of the airway epithelium, preventing pulmonary disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.475833" rel="alternate" title="Prom1 and Notch regulate ciliary length and dynamics in multiciliated cells of the airway epithelium (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476424</id><title>FRET monitoring of transcription factor activities in living bacteria (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.360243+00:00</updated><author><name>Pengchao Wang</name></author><author><name>Guangming Zhang</name></author><author><name>Zeling Xu</name></author><author><name>Zhe Chen</name></author><author><name>Xiaohong Liu</name></author><author><name>Chenyin Wang</name></author><author><name>Chaogu Zheng</name></author><author><name>Jiangyun Wang</name></author><author><name>Hongmin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Aixin Yan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacteria adapt to the constantly changing environments largely by transcriptional regulation through the activities of various transcription factors (TFs). However, techniques that monitor the in situ TF-promoter interactions in living bacteria are lacking. Herein, we developed a whole-cell TF-promoter binding assay based on the intermolecular Förster resonance energy transfer (FRET) between a fluorescent unnatural amino acid CouA which is genetically encoded into defined sites in TFs and the live cell fluorescent nucleic acid stain SYTO 9. We show that this new FRET pair monitors the intricate TF-promoter interactions elicited by various types of signal transduction systems with specificity and sensitivity. Furthermore, the assay is applicable to identify novel modulators of the regulatory systems of interest and monitor TF activities in bacteria colonized in &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt;. In conclusion, we established a tractable and sensitive TF-promoter binding assay in living bacteria which not only complements currently available approaches for DNA-protein interactions but also provides novel opportunities for functional annotation of bacterial signal transduction systems and studies of the bacteria-host interface.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476424" rel="alternate" title="FRET monitoring of transcription factor activities in living bacteria (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476460</id><title>Vexitoxins: a novel class of conotoxin-like venom peptides from predatory gastropods of the genus Vexillum (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.360324+00:00</updated><author><name>Ksenia G Kuznetsova</name></author><author><name>Sofia S Zvonareva</name></author><author><name>Rustam Ziganshin</name></author><author><name>Elena S Mekhova</name></author><author><name>Polina Yu Dgebuadze</name></author><author><name>Yen T.H. Dinh</name></author><author><name>Thanh H.T. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Sergey A Moshkovskii</name></author><author><name>Alexander E Fedosov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Venoms of predatory marine cone snails (the family Conidae, order Neogastropoda) are intensely studied because of the broad range of biomedical applications of the neuropeptides that they contain, conotoxins. Meanwhile anatomy in some other neogastropod lineages strongly suggests that they have evolved similar venoms independently of cone snails, nevertheless their venom composition remains unstudied. Here we focus on the most diversified of these lineages, the genus Vexillum (the family Costellariidae). We have generated comprehensive multi-specimen, multi-tissue RNA-Seq data sets for three Vexillum species, and supported our findings in two species by proteomic profiling. We show that venoms of Vexillum are dominated by highly diversified short cysteine-rich peptides that in many aspects are very similar to conotoxins. Vexitoxins possess the same precursor organization, display overlapping cysteine frameworks and share several common post-translational modifications with conotoxins. Some vexitoxins show detectable sequence similarity to conotoxins, and are predicted to adopt similar domain conformations, including a pharmacologically relevant inhibitory cysteine-know motif (ICK). The tubular gL of Vexillum is a notably more recent evolutionary novelty than the conoidean venom gland. Thus, we hypothesize lower divergence between the toxin genes, and their somatic counterparts compared to that in conotoxins, and we find support for this hypothesis in the molecular evolution of the vexitoxin cluster V027. We use this example to discuss how future studies on vexitoxins can inform origin and evolution of conotoxins, and how they may help addressing standing questions in venom evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476460" rel="alternate" title="Vexitoxins: a novel class of conotoxin-like venom peptides from predatory gastropods of the genus Vexillum (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476286</id><title>Transcriptomic analysis reveals a role for the nervous system in regulating growth and development of Fasciola hepatica juveniles (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.360401+00:00</updated><author><name>Emily Robb</name></author><author><name>Erin McCammick</name></author><author><name>Duncan Wells</name></author><author><name>Paul McVeigh</name></author><author><name>Erica Gardiner</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Armstrong</name></author><author><name>Paul McCusker</name></author><author><name>Angela Mousley</name></author><author><name>Nathan Clarke</name></author><author><name>Nikki Marks</name></author><author><name>Aaron G. Maule</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Fasciola&lt;/italic&gt; spp. liver fluke have significant impacts in veterinary and human medicine. The absence of a vaccine and increasing anthelmintic resistance threaten sustainable control and underscore the need for novel flukicides. Functional genomic approaches underpinned by &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; culture of juvenile &lt;italic&gt;Fasciola hepatica&lt;/italic&gt; facilitate control target validation in the most pathogenic life stage. Comparative transcriptomics of &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; maintained 21 day old &lt;italic&gt;F. hepatica&lt;/italic&gt; finds that 86% of genes are expressed at similar levels across maintenance treatments suggesting commonality in core biological functioning within these juveniles. Phenotypic comparisons revealed higher cell proliferation and growth rates in the &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; juveniles compared to their &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; counterparts. These phenotypic differences were consistent with the upregulation of neoblast-like stem cell and cell-cycle associated genes in &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; maintained worms. The more rapid growth/development of &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; juveniles was further evidenced by a switch in cathepsin protease expression profiles, dominated by cathepsin B in &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; juveniles and then by cathepsin L in &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; juveniles. Coincident with more rapid growth/development was the marked downregulation of both classical and peptidergic neuronal signalling components in &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; maintained juveniles, supporting a role for the nervous system in regulating liver fluke growth and development. Differences in the miRNA complements of &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; juveniles identified 31 differentially expressed miRNAs, notably &lt;italic&gt;fhe-let-7a-5p&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;fhe-mir-124-3p&lt;/italic&gt; and, miRNAs predicted to target Wnt-signalling, supporting a key role for miRNAs in driving the growth/developmental differences in the &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; maintained juvenile liver fluke. Widespread differences in the expression of neuronal genes in juvenile fluke grown &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; expose significant interplay between neuronal signalling and the rate of growth/development, encouraging consideration of neuronal targets in efforts to dysregulate growth/development for parasite control.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Parasitic worms are notoriously difficult to study outside of a host organism. However, recent developments in culture methods for &lt;italic&gt;Fasciola hepatica&lt;/italic&gt; liver fluke juveniles support growth and development of these parasites in the laboratory (&lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;) towards adult parasites. Having the ability to grow pathogenic juvenile stages &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; enables functional studies to validate potential drug and vaccine targets. However, comparison of &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; grown juveniles to juveniles retrieved from infected hosts (&lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;) shows considerable size differences suggesting at least some differences in biology that could undermine the relevance of data generated from &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; maintained parasites. This study examines gene expression differences between &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; maintained &lt;italic&gt;F. hepatica&lt;/italic&gt; juveniles via transcriptomic analysis to identify similarities and differences in their biology which may help explain differences in the rate of growth and development. 86% of genes were shown to be expressed at similar levels across treatment groups suggesting a high level of biological similarity between &lt;italic&gt;in vitro and in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; juveniles. However, the genes that are expressed differently between these juveniles will help improve current culture methods and provide a new group of potential drug targets that impact on juvenile growth and development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476286" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptomic analysis reveals a role for the nervous system in regulating growth and development of Fasciola hepatica juveniles (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476296</id><title>A Four-Step Enzymatic Cascade for Efficient Production of L- Phenylglycine from Biobased L-Phenylalanine (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.360489+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuling Zhu</name></author><author><name>Jifeng Yuan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Enantiopure amino acids are of particular interest in the agrochemical and pharmaceutical industries. Here, we reported a multi-enzyme cascade for efficient production of L-phenylglycine (L-Phg) from biobased L-phenylalanine (L-Phe). We first attempted to engineer &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; for expressing L-amino acid deaminase (LAAD) from &lt;italic&gt;Proteus mirabilis&lt;/italic&gt;, hydroxymandelate synthase (HmaS) from &lt;italic&gt;Amycolatopsis orientalis&lt;/italic&gt;, (&lt;italic&gt;S&lt;/italic&gt;)-mandelate dehydrogenase (SMDH) from &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas putida&lt;/italic&gt;, the endogenous aminotransferase (AT) encoded by &lt;italic&gt;ilvE&lt;/italic&gt; and L-glutamate dehydrogenase (GluDH) from &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;. However, 10 mM L-Phe only afforded the synthesis of 7.21 ± 0.15 mM L-Phg. The accumulation of benzoylformic acid suggested that the transamination step might be rate-limiting. We next used leucine dehydrogenase (LeuDH) from &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus cereus&lt;/italic&gt; to bypass the use of L-glutamate as amine donor, and 40 mM L-Phe gave 39.97 ± 3.84 mM (6.04 ± 0.58 g/L) L-Phg, reaching 99.9% conversion. In summary, this work demonstrated a concise four-step enzymatic cascade for the L-Phg synthesis from biobased L-Phe, with a potential for future industrial applications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;a concise four-step enzymatic cascade for the L-phenylglycine synthesis from biobased L-phenylalanine was devised. 40 mM L-phenylalanine afforded the synthesis of 39.97 ± 3.84 mM (6.04 ± 0.58 g/L) L-phenylglycine, reaching 99.9% conversion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="476296v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476296" rel="alternate" title="A Four-Step Enzymatic Cascade for Efficient Production of L- Phenylglycine from Biobased L-Phenylalanine (3 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475884</id><title>Identification of Mfn2-S249 as a Phosphoregulatory Switch of Mitochondrial Fusion Dynamics (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.360543+00:00</updated><author><name>Sanjay Kumar</name></author><author><name>Aaron Ramonett</name></author><author><name>Tasmia Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Eun-A Kwak</name></author><author><name>Paola Cruz Flores</name></author><author><name>Hannah R. Ortiz</name></author><author><name>Paul R. Langlais</name></author><author><name>Karthikeyan Mythreye</name></author><author><name>Nam Y. Lee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mitochondrial remodeling is a fundamental process underlying cellular respiration and metabolism. Here we report TAK1 as a direct regulator of mitochondrial fusion. TAK1 is activated by a variety of mitogenic factors, cytokines and environmental stimuli, which we find induces rapid fragmentation through Mfn2 inactivation. TAK1 phosphorylates Mfn2 at Ser249, which inhibits the binding of GTP required for Mfn trans-dimerization and mitochondrial membrane fusion. Accordingly, expression of Mfn2-S249 phosphomimetics (Mfn2-E/D) constitutively promote fission whereas alanine mutant (Mfn2-A) yields hyperfused mitochondria and increased bioenergetics in cells. In mice, Mfn2-E knock-in yields embryonic lethality in homozygotes whereas heterozygotes are viable but exhibit increased visceral fat accumulation despite normal body weight and cognitive/motor functions compared to wildtype and Mfn2-A mice. Mature white adipocytes isolated from mutant mice reveal cell-autonomous TAK1-related effects on mitochondrial remodeling and lipid metabolism. These results identify Mfn2-S249 as a dynamic phosphoregulatory switch of mitochondrial fusion during development and energy homeostasis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475884" rel="alternate" title="Identification of Mfn2-S249 as a Phosphoregulatory Switch of Mitochondrial Fusion Dynamics (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476046</id><title>Optimal protein production by a synthetic microbial consortium: Coexistence, distribution of labor, and syntrophy (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.360624+00:00</updated><author><name>Carlos Martínez</name></author><author><name>Eugenio Cinquemani</name></author><author><name>Hidde de Jong</name></author><author><name>Jean-Luc Gouzé</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The bacterium &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; is widely used to produce recombinant proteins such as growth hormone and insulin. One inconvenience with &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; cultures is the secretion of acetate through overflow metabolism. Acetate inhibits cell growth and represents a carbon diversion, which results in several negative effects on protein production. One way to over-come this problem is the use of a synthetic consortium of two different &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; strains, one producing recombinant proteins and one reducing the acetate concentration. In this paper, we study a chemostat model of such a synthetic community where both strains are allowed to produce recombinant proteins. We give necessary and sufficient conditions for the existence of a coexistence equilibrium and show that it is unique. Based on this equilibrium, we define a multi-objective optimization problem for the maximization of two important bioprocess performance metrics, process yield and productivity. Solving numerically this problem, we find the best available trade-offs between the metrics. Under optimal operation of the mixed community, both strains must produce the protein of interest, and not only one (distribution instead of division of labor). Moreover, in this regime acetate secretion by one strain is necessary for the survival of the other (syntrophy). The results thus illustrate how complex multi-level dynamics shape the optimal production of recombinant proteins by synthetic microbial consortia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476046" rel="alternate" title="Optimal protein production by a synthetic microbial consortium: Coexistence, distribution of labor, and syntrophy (3 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476048</id><title>Cell adhesion and immune response, two main functions altered in the transcriptome of seasonally regressed testes of two mammalian species (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.360687+00:00</updated><author><name>Francisca M. Real</name></author><author><name>Miguel Lao-Pérez</name></author><author><name>Miguel Burgos</name></author><author><name>Stefan Mundlos</name></author><author><name>Darío G. Lupiáñez</name></author><author><name>Rafael Jiménez</name></author><author><name>Francisco J. Barrionuevo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In species with seasonal breeding, male specimens undergo substantial testicular regression during the non-breeding period of the year. However, the molecular mechanisms that control this biological process are largely unknown. Here, we report a transcriptomic analysis on the Iberian mole, &lt;italic&gt;Talpa occidentalis&lt;/italic&gt;, in which the desquamation of live, non-apoptotic germ cells is the major cellular event responsible for testis regression. By comparing testes at different reproductive states (active, regressing and inactive), we demonstrate that the molecular pathways controlling the cell adhesion function in the seminiferous epithelium, such as the MAPK, ERK and TGF-β signalling, are altered during the regression process. In addition, inactive testes display a global upregulation of genes associated with immune response, indicating a selective loss of the “immune privilege” that normally operates in sexually active testes. Interspecies comparative analyses using analogous data from the Mediterranean pine vole, a rodent species where testis regression is controlled by halting meiosis entry, revealed a common gene expression signature in the regressed testes of these two evolutionary distant species. Our study advances in the knowledge of the molecular mechanisms associated to gonadal seasonal breeding, highlighting the existence of a conserved transcriptional program of testis involution across mammalian clades.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Research Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;By comparing the trascriptomes of the testes from males of the iberian mole, &lt;italic&gt;Talpa occidentalis&lt;/italic&gt; (order Eulipotyphla), captured at different stages of the seasonal breeding cycle of this species, we show that two main functions are altered during seasonal testis regression: cell adhesion and immune response. The fact that the same functions alre also altered in the Mediterranean pine vole, &lt;italic&gt;Microtus duodecimcostatus&lt;/italic&gt; (order Rodentia), evidences the existence of a conserved transcriptional program of testis regression across mammalian clades.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476048" rel="alternate" title="Cell adhesion and immune response, two main functions altered in the transcriptome of seasonally regressed testes of two mammalian species (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475908</id><title>Machine-learning from Pseudomonas putida Transcriptomes Reveals Its Transcriptional Regulatory Network (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.360762+00:00</updated><author><name>Hyun Gyu Lim</name></author><author><name>Kevin Rychel</name></author><author><name>Anand V. Sastry</name></author><author><name>Joshua Mueller</name></author><author><name>Wei Niu</name></author><author><name>Adam M. Feist</name></author><author><name>Bernhard O. Palsson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial gene expression is orchestrated by numerous transcription factors (TFs). Elucidating how gene expression is regulated is fundamental to understanding bacterial physiology and engineering it for practical use. In this study, a machine-learning approach was applied to uncover the genome-scale transcriptional regulatory network (TRN) in &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas putida&lt;/italic&gt;, an important organism for bioproduction. We performed independent component analysis of a compendium of 321 high-quality gene expression profiles, which were previously published or newly generated in this study. We identified 84 groups of independently modulated genes (iModulons) that explain 75.7% of the total variance in the compendium. With these iModulons, we (i) expand our understanding of the regulatory functions of 39 iModulon associated TFs (e.g., HexR, Zur) by systematic comparison with 1,993 previously reported TF-gene interactions; (ii) outline transcriptional changes after the transition from the exponential growth to stationary phases; (iii) capture group of genes required for utilizing diverse carbon sources and increased stationary response with slower growth rates; (iv) unveil multiple evolutionary strategies of transcriptome reallocation to achieve fast growth rates; and (v) define an osmotic stimulon, which includes the Type VI secretion system, as coordination of multiple iModulon activity changes. Taken together, this study provides the first quantitative genome-scale TRN for &lt;italic&gt;P. putida&lt;/italic&gt; and a basis for a comprehensive understanding of its complex transcriptome changes in a variety of physiological states.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475908" rel="alternate" title="Machine-learning from Pseudomonas putida Transcriptomes Reveals Its Transcriptional Regulatory Network (3 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476135</id><title>Optineurin mediates delivery of membrane from transferrin receptor-positive endosomes to autophagosomes (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.360834+00:00</updated><author><name>Megha Bansal</name></author><author><name>Kapil Sirohi</name></author><author><name>Shivranjani C Moharir</name></author><author><name>Ghanshyam Swarup</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Autophagy is a conserved quality control mechanism that removes damaged proteins, organelles and invading bacteria through lysosome-mediated degradation. During autophagy several organelles including endoplasmic reticulum, mitochondria, plasma membrane and endosomes contribute membrane for autophagosome formation. However, the mechanisms and proteins involved in membrane delivery to autophagosomes are not clear. Optineurin (OPTN), a cytoplasmic adaptor protein, is involved in promoting maturation of phagophores into autophagosomes; it is also involved in regulating endocytic trafficking and recycling of transferrin receptor (TFRC). Here, we have examined the role of optineurin in the delivery of membrane from TFRC-positive endosomes to autophagosomes. Only a small fraction of autophagosomes was positive for TFRC, indicating that TFRC-positive endosomes could contribute membrane to a subset of autophagosomes. The percentage of TFRC-positive autophagosomes was reduced in Optineurin knockout mouse embryonic fibroblasts (&lt;italic&gt;Optn&lt;sup&gt;−/−&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; MEFs) in comparison with normal MEFs. Upon over-expression of optineurin, the percentage of TFRC-positive autophagosomes was increased in &lt;italic&gt;Optn&lt;sup&gt;−/−&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; MEFs. Unlike wild-type optineurin, a disease-associated mutant, E478G, defective in ubiquitin binding, was not able to enhance formation of TFRC-positive autophagosomes in &lt;italic&gt;Optn&lt;sup&gt;−/−&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; MEFs. TFRC degradation mediated by autophagy was decreased in optineurin deficient cells. Our results suggest that optineurin mediates delivery of TFRC and perhaps associated membrane from TFRC-positive endosomes to autophagosomes, and this may contribute to autophagosome formation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476135" rel="alternate" title="Optineurin mediates delivery of membrane from transferrin receptor-positive endosomes to autophagosomes (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>