<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.203152+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.23.465463</id><title>The mechano-sensitive ion channel Piezo mediates Rho activation and actin stress fibre formation in Drosophila nephrocytes (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.203492+00:00</updated><author><name>Sybille Koehler</name></author><author><name>Barry Denholm</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mechanotransduction is an important process of sensing physical forces in the environment of organisms, tissues and cells and transducing them into a biochemical response. Due to their position on the glomerular capillaries, podocytes are exposed to near-constant biomechanical force, which can fluctuate widely. These include shear stress and hydrostatic pressure. A pathological increase in these forces can induce morphological change to podocytes, their detachment from the glomerular basement membrane and subsequent loss into the primary urine. The ability to sense and respond to variations in mechanical force would be beneficial to a cell exposed to these conditions. It is likely podocytes have such mechanisms, however their identity are unknown. Here we investigated the hypothesis that the mechanotransducer Piezo is involved in a mechanotransduction pathway in Drosophila nephrocytes, the podocyte homologue in the fly. We find Piezo is expressed in nephrocytes and localizes to the nephrocyte diaphragm. The Piezo agonist YODA, which stimulates channel opening in the absence of mechanical force, leads to a significant increase in intracellular Ca++ upon shear stress in the nephrocyte. This leads to activation of Rho1, delineating a putative Piezo mechanotransductive pathway in these cells. Loss of function analysis revealed minor defects in nephrocyte filtration function. In contrast, we show that elevated Piezo levels resulted in constantly oscillating Ca++ signals even in the absence of shear stress, increased active Rho1 and accumulation of actin stress fibers, culminating in a severe nephrocyte filtration phenotype, suggesting that pathway hyperactivity is detrimental. We asked if this phenotype could be reversed by blocking Piezo activity pharmacologically using the tarantula toxin GsMTx4. Treatment with GsMTx4 brought levels of activated Rho1 into the normal range. This work delineates a mechanotransductive pathway in nephrocytes involving Piezo, Ca++, Rho1 and the actin-cytoskeleton, and suggest this is part of a mechanism by which nephrocytes sense and adapt to changes in mechanical force.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.23.465463" rel="alternate" title="The mechano-sensitive ion channel Piezo mediates Rho activation and actin stress fibre formation in Drosophila nephrocytes (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.22.465449</id><title>Quantitative fragmentomics allow affinity mapping of interactomes (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.203716+00:00</updated><author><name>Gergo Gogl</name></author><author><name>Boglarka Zambo</name></author><author><name>Camille Kostmann</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Cousido-Siah</name></author><author><name>Bastien Morlet</name></author><author><name>Fabien Durbesson</name></author><author><name>Luc Negroni</name></author><author><name>Pascal Eberling</name></author><author><name>Pau Jane</name></author><author><name>Yves Nomine</name></author><author><name>Andras Zeke</name></author><author><name>Soren Ostergaard</name></author><author><name>Elodie Monsellier</name></author><author><name>Renaud Vincentelli</name></author><author><name>Gilles Trave</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human protein networks have been widely explored but most binding affinities remain unknown, hindering quantitative interactome-function studies. Yet interactomes rely on minimal interacting fragments displaying quantifiable affinities. Here we measured the affinities of 65,000 interactions involving PDZ domains and their target PDZ-binding motifs (PBM) within a human interactome region particularly relevant for viral infection and cancer. We calculate interactomic distances, identify hot spots for viral interference, generate binding profiles and specificity logos, and explain selected cases by crystallographic studies. Mass spectrometry experiments on cell extracts and literature surveys show that quantitative fragmentomics effectively complement protein interactomics by providing affinities and completeness of coverage, putting a full human interactome affinity survey within realistic reach. Finally, we show that interactome hijacking by the viral PBM of human papillomavirus (HPV) E6 oncoprotein deeply impacts the host cell proteome way beyond immediate E6 binders, illustrating the complex system-wide relationship between interactome and function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.22.465449" rel="alternate" title="Quantitative fragmentomics allow affinity mapping of interactomes (7 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-10-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.465321</id><title>PI4P and BLOC-1 remodel endosomal membranes into tubules (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.203984+00:00</updated><author><name>Riddhi Atul Jani</name></author><author><name>Aurélie Di Cicco</name></author><author><name>Tal Keren-Kaplan</name></author><author><name>Silvia Vale-Costa</name></author><author><name>Daniel Hamaoui</name></author><author><name>Ilse Hurbain</name></author><author><name>Feng-Ching Tsai</name></author><author><name>Mathilde Dimarco</name></author><author><name>Anne-Sophie Macé</name></author><author><name>Yueyao Zhu</name></author><author><name>Maria João Amorim</name></author><author><name>Patricia Bassereau</name></author><author><name>Juan S. Bonifacino</name></author><author><name>Agathe Subtil</name></author><author><name>Michael S. Marks</name></author><author><name>Daniel Lévy</name></author><author><name>Graça Raposo</name></author><author><name>Cédric Delevoye</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Intracellular trafficking is mediated by transport carriers that originate by membrane remodeling from donor organelles. Tubular carriers play major roles in the flux of membrane lipids and proteins to acceptor organelles. However, how lipids and proteins impose a tubular geometry on the carriers is incompletely understood. By exploiting imaging approaches at different scales on cells and in vitro membrane systems, we show that phosphatidylinositol-4-phosphate (PI4P) and biogenesis of lysosome-related organelles complex 1 (BLOC-1) govern the formation, stability and functions of recycling endosomal tubules. Endosomal PI4P production by type II PI4-kinases is needed to form nascent curved tubules through binding of BLOC-1 that stabilize and elongate them. Membrane remodeling by the PI4P/ BLOC-1 module functions not only in the recycling of endosomal cargoes, but also in the lifecycles of intracellular pathogens such as &lt;italic&gt;Chlamydia&lt;/italic&gt; bacteria and influenza virus. This study demonstrates how a phospholipid and a protein complex coordinate as a minimal machinery to remodel cellular membranes into functional tubes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.465321" rel="alternate" title="PI4P and BLOC-1 remodel endosomal membranes into tubules (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>