<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.214124+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472096</id><title>The ParB clamp docks onto Smc for DNA loading via a joint-ParB interface (40 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.214592+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian P. Bock</name></author><author><name>Anna Anchimiuk</name></author><author><name>Marie-Laure Diebold-Durand</name></author><author><name>Stephan Gruber</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chromosomes readily unlink from one another and segregate to daughter cells during cell division highlighting a remarkable ability of cells to organize long DNA molecules. SMC complexes mediate chromosome folding by DNA loop extrusion. In most bacteria, SMC complexes start loop extrusion at the ParB/&lt;italic&gt;parS&lt;/italic&gt; partition complex formed near the replication origin. Whether they are recruited by recognizing a specific DNA structure in the partition complex or a protein component is unknown. By replacing genes in &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; with orthologous sequences from &lt;italic&gt;Streptococcus pneumoniae&lt;/italic&gt;, we show that the three subunits of the bacterial Smc complex together with the ParB protein form a functional module that can organize and segregate chromosomes when transplanted into another organism. Using chimeric proteins and chemical cross-linking, we find that ParB binds to the Smc subunit directly. We map a binding interface to the Smc joint and the ParB CTP-binding domain. Structure prediction indicates how the ParB clamp presents DNA to the Smc complex to initiate DNA loop extrusion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472096" rel="alternate" title="The ParB clamp docks onto Smc for DNA loading via a joint-ParB interface (40 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472866</id><title>Understanding the source of METTL3-independent m6A in mRNA (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.215316+00:00</updated><author><name>Hui Xian Poh</name></author><author><name>Aashiq H Mirza</name></author><author><name>Brian F Pickering</name></author><author><name>Samie R Jaffrey</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;-methyladenosine (m&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;A) is a highly prevalent mRNA modification which promotes degradation of transcripts encoding proteins that have roles in cell development, differentiation, and other pathways. METTL3 is the major methyltransferase that catalyzes the formation of m&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;A in mRNA. As 30—80% of m&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;A can remain in mRNA after METTL3 depletion by CRISPR/Cas9-based methods, other enzymes are thought to catalyze a sizable fraction of m&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;A. Here, we re-examined the source of m&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;A in the mRNA transcriptome. We characterized mouse embryonic stem cell lines which continue to have m&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;A in their mRNA after &lt;italic&gt;Mettl3&lt;/italic&gt; knockout. We show that these cells express alternatively spliced &lt;italic&gt;Mettl3&lt;/italic&gt; transcript isoforms that bypass the CRISPR/Cas9 mutations and produce functionally active methyltransferases. We similarly show that other reported &lt;italic&gt;METTL3&lt;/italic&gt; knockout cell lines express altered METTL3 proteins. We find that gene dependency datasets show that most cell lines fail to proliferate after &lt;italic&gt;METTL3&lt;/italic&gt; deletion, suggesting that reported &lt;italic&gt;METTL3&lt;/italic&gt; knockout cell lines express altered METTL3 proteins rather than have full knockout. Finally, we reassessed METTL3's role in synthesizing m&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;A using a genomic deletion of &lt;italic&gt;Mettl3&lt;/italic&gt;, and found that METTL3 is responsible for &amp;gt;95% of m&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;A in mRNA. Overall, these studies suggest that METTL3 is responsible for the vast majority of m&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;A in the transcriptome, and that remaining m&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;A in putative &lt;italic&gt;METTL3&lt;/italic&gt; knockout cell lines is due to the expression of altered but functional METTL3 isoforms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472866" rel="alternate" title="Understanding the source of METTL3-independent m6A in mRNA (31 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473016</id><title>Centromere identity is dependent on nuclear spatial organization (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.215617+00:00</updated><author><name>Weifang Wu</name></author><author><name>Toni McHugh</name></author><author><name>David A Kelly</name></author><author><name>Alison L Pidoux</name></author><author><name>Robin C Allshire</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The establishment of centromere-specific CENP-A chromatin is influenced by epigenetic and genetic processes. Central domain sequences from fission yeast centromeres are preferred substrates for CENP-A&lt;sup&gt;Cnp1&lt;/sup&gt; incorporation, but their use is context dependent, requiring adjacent heterochromatin. CENP-A&lt;sup&gt;Cnp1&lt;/sup&gt; overexpression bypasses heterochromatin dependency, suggesting heterochromatin ensures exposure to conditions or locations permissive for CENP-A&lt;sup&gt;Cnp1&lt;/sup&gt; assembly. Centromeres cluster around spindle-pole bodies (SPBs). We show that heterochromatin-bearing minichromosomes localize close to SPBs, consistent with this location promoting CENP-A&lt;sup&gt;Cnp1&lt;/sup&gt; incorporation. We demonstrate that heterochromatin-independent de novo CENP-A&lt;sup&gt;Cnp1&lt;/sup&gt; chromatin assembly occurs when central domain DNA is placed near, but not far from, endogenous centromeres or neocentromeres. Moreover, direct tethering of central domain DNA at SPBs permits CENP-A&lt;sup&gt;Cnp1&lt;/sup&gt; assembly, suggesting that the nuclear compartment surrounding SPBs is permissive for CENP-A&lt;sup&gt;Cnp1&lt;/sup&gt; incorporation because target sequences are exposed to high levels of CENP-A&lt;sup&gt;Cnp1&lt;/sup&gt; and associated assembly factors. Thus, nuclear spatial organization is a key epigenetic factor that influences centromere identity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473016" rel="alternate" title="Centromere identity is dependent on nuclear spatial organization (30 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472599</id><title>Sir2-domain associated short prokaryotic Argonautes provide defence against invading mobile genetic elements through NAD+ depletion (28 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.215953+00:00</updated><author><name>Mindaugas Zaremba</name></author><author><name>Donata Dakineviciene</name></author><author><name>Edvardas Golovinas</name></author><author><name>Edvinas Stankunas</name></author><author><name>Anna Lopatina</name></author><author><name>Rotem Sorek</name></author><author><name>Elena Manakova</name></author><author><name>Audra Ruksenaite</name></author><author><name>Arunas Silanskas</name></author><author><name>Simonas Asmontas</name></author><author><name>Rokas Grigaitis</name></author><author><name>Kęstutis Timinskas</name></author><author><name>Česlovas Venclovas</name></author><author><name>Virginijus Siksnys</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Argonaute (Ago) proteins are found in all three domains of life. The so-called long Agos are composed of four major domains (N, PAZ, MID, and PIWI) and contribute to RNA silencing in eukaryotes (eAgos) or defence against invading mobile genetic elements in prokaryotes (pAgos). Intriguingly, the majority (∼60%) of prokaryotic Agos (pAgos) identified bioinformatically are shorter (comprised of only MID and PIWI domains) and are typically associated with Sir2, Mrr or TIR domain-containing proteins. The cellular function and mechanism of short pAgos remain enigmatic. Here, we show that short pAgos from &lt;italic&gt;Geobacter sulfurreducens, Caballeronia cordobensis&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Paraburkholderia graminis&lt;/italic&gt;, together with the NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;-bound Sir2-proteins form a stable heterodimeric Sir2/Ago complex that recognizes invading plasmid or phage DNA through the pAgos subunit and activates Sir2 subunit triggering the endogenous NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; depletion and cell death thus preventing the propagation of invading DNA. This is the first demonstration that short Sir2-associated pAgos provide defence against phages and plasmids and underscores the diversity of mechanisms of prokaryotic Agos.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472599" rel="alternate" title="Sir2-domain associated short prokaryotic Argonautes provide defence against invading mobile genetic elements through NAD+ depletion (28 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472793</id><title>Dynamic epistasis analysis reveals how chromatin remodeling regulates transcriptional bursting (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.216278+00:00</updated><author><name>Ineke Brouwer</name></author><author><name>Emma Kerklingh</name></author><author><name>Fred van Leeuwen</name></author><author><name>Tineke Laura Lenstra</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Transcriptional bursting has been linked to the stochastic positioning of nucleosomes. However, how bursting is regulated by remodeling of promoter nucleosomes is unknown. Here, we use single-molecule live-cell imaging of &lt;italic&gt;GAL10&lt;/italic&gt; transcription in budding yeast to measure how transcriptional bursting changes upon single and double perturbations of chromatin remodeling factors, the transcription factor Gal4 and preinitiation complex (PIC) components. Using dynamic epistasis analysis, we reveal how remodeling of different nucleosomes regulates individual transcriptional bursting parameters. At the nucleosome covering the Gal4 binding sites, RSC acts synergistically with Gal4 binding to facilitate each burst. Conversely, nucleosome remodeling at the TATA box controls only the first burst upon galactose induction. In the absence of remodelers, nucleosomes at canonical TATA boxes are displaced by TBP binding to allow for transcription activation. Overall, our results reveal how promoter nucleosome remodeling, together with transcription factor and PIC binding regulates the kinetics of transcriptional bursting.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472793" rel="alternate" title="Dynamic epistasis analysis reveals how chromatin remodeling regulates transcriptional bursting (27 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472645</id><title>Retinoic acid signaling mediates peripheral cone photoreceptor survival in a mouse model of retina degeneration (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.216456+00:00</updated><author><name>Ryoji Amamoto</name></author><author><name>Grace K Wallick</name></author><author><name>Constance Cepko</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Retinitis Pigmentosa (RP) is a wide array of progressive, debilitating visual disorders caused by mutations in a diverse set of genes. In both human patients and mouse models of RP, rod photoreceptor dysfunction leads to loss of night vision, and is followed by secondary cone photoreceptor dysfunction and degeneration, leading to loss of daylight color vision. A strategy to prevent secondary cone death could provide a generalized RP therapy to preserve daylight color vision regardless of the underlying mutation. In mouse models of RP, cones in the far peripheral retina survive long-term, despite complete rod loss. The mechanism for such peripheral cone survival had not been explored. Here, we found that active retinoic acid (RA) signaling in peripheral Muller glia is both sufficient and necessary for the extended cone survival. RA depletion by conditional knockout of RA synthesis enzymes, or overexpression of an RA degradation enzyme, abrogated peripheral cone survival. Conversely, constitutive activation of RA signaling in the central retina promoted long-term cone survival. These results indicate that RA signaling mediates the prolonged peripheral cone survival in the rd1 mouse model of retinal degeneration, and provide a basis for a generic strategy for cone survival in the many diseases that lead to loss of cone-mediated vision.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472645" rel="alternate" title="Retinoic acid signaling mediates peripheral cone photoreceptor survival in a mouse model of retina degeneration (19 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472968</id><title>Structure of human CST-pol-α/primase bound to a telomeric overhang poised for initiation of telomere C-strand synthesis (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.216612+00:00</updated><author><name>Qixiang He</name></author><author><name>Xiuhua Lin</name></author><author><name>Bianca L Chavez</name></author><author><name>Benjamin L Lusk</name></author><author><name>Ci Ji Lim</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Telomere replication and regulation protect mammalian chromosome ends and promote genome stability. An essential step in telomere maintenance is the C-strand fill-in process, which is the &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; synthesis of the complementary strand of the telomere overhang. This step is catalyzed by polymerase-alpha/primase complex (pol-α/primase) and coordinated by an accessory factor, CTC1-STN1-TEN1 (CST). Using cryogenic-electron microscopy single-particle analysis, we report the structure of the human telomere C-strand fill-in preinitiation complex (PIC) at 3.9 Å resolution. The structure reveals a CST and a pol-α/primase co-bound to a single telomere overhang, poised for &lt;italic&gt;de novo &lt;/italic&gt; RNA primer synthesis. Upon PIC assembly, the pol-α/primase undergoes large conformation change from its apo-state; CST partitions the DNA and RNA catalytic centers of pol-α/primase into two separate domains and positions the 3' end of an extended telomere single-stranded DNA template towards the RNA catalytic center (PRIM1 or p49). The telomeric single-stranded DNA template is further positioned by the POLA1 (or p180) catalytically dead exonuclease domain. Together with CST, the exonuclease domain forms a tight-fit molecular tunnel for template direction. Given the structural homology of CST to Replication Protein A (RPA), our structure provides the structural basis for a new model of how pol-α/primase lagging-strand DNA synthesis is coordinated by single-stranded DNA-binding accessory factors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472968" rel="alternate" title="Structure of human CST-pol-α/primase bound to a telomeric overhang poised for initiation of telomere C-strand synthesis (18 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472383</id><title>Differentiation signals from glia are fine-tuned to set neuronal numbers during development (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.216790+00:00</updated><author><name>Anadika R. Prasad</name></author><author><name>Matthew P. Bostock</name></author><author><name>Inês Lago-Baldaia</name></author><author><name>Zaynab Housseini</name></author><author><name>Vilaiwan M. Fernandes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Precise neuronal numbers are required for circuit formation and function. Known strategies to control neuronal numbers involve regulating either cell proliferation or survival. In the developing &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; visual system photoreceptors from the eye-disc induce their target field, the lamina, one column at a time. Although each column initially contains ∼6 precursors, only 5 differentiate into neurons of unique identities (L1-L5); the ‘extra’ precursor undergoes apoptosis. We uncovered that Hedgehog signalling patterns columns, such that the 2 precursors experiencing the lowest signalling activity are specified as L5s; only one differentiates while the other ‘extra’ precursor dies. We showed that a glial population called the outer chiasm giant glia (xg&lt;sup&gt;O&lt;/sup&gt;), which reside below the lamina, relays differentiation signals from photoreceptors to induce L5 differentiation. The precursors nearest to xg&lt;sup&gt;O&lt;/sup&gt; differentiate into L5s and antagonise inductive signalling to prevent the ‘extra’ precursors from differentiating, resulting in their death. Thus, tissue architecture and feedback from young neurons fine-tune differentiation signals from glia to limit the number of neurons induced.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472383" rel="alternate" title="Differentiation signals from glia are fine-tuned to set neuronal numbers during development (15 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.469105</id><title>Intrinsic instability of the dysbiotic microbiome revealed through dynamical systems inference at scale (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.217023+00:00</updated><author><name>Travis E Gibson</name></author><author><name>Younhun Kim</name></author><author><name>Sawal Acharya</name></author><author><name>David E Kaplan</name></author><author><name>Nicholas DiBenedetto</name></author><author><name>Richard Lavin</name></author><author><name>Bonnie Berger</name></author><author><name>Jessica R Allegretti</name></author><author><name>Lynn Bry</name></author><author><name>Georg K Gerber</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite the importance of microbial dysbiosis in human disease, the phenomenon remains poorly understood. We provide the first comprehensive and predictive model of dysbiosis at ecosystem-scale, leveraging our new machine learning method for efficiently inferring compact and interpretable dynamical systems models. Coupling this approach with the most densely temporally sampled interventional study of the microbiome to date, using microbiota from healthy and dysbiotic human donors that we transplanted into mice subjected to antibiotic and dietary interventions, we demonstrate superior predictive performance of our method over state-of-the-art techniques. Moreover, we demonstrate that our approach uncovers intrinsic dynamical properties of dysbiosis driven by destabilizing competitive cycles, in contrast to stabilizing interaction chains in the healthy microbiome, which have implications for restoration of the microbiome to treat disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.469105" rel="alternate" title="Intrinsic instability of the dysbiotic microbiome revealed through dynamical systems inference at scale (15 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472149</id><title>Oxoglutarate dehydrogenase coordinates myofibril growth by maintaining amino acid homeostasis (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.217270+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicanor González Morales</name></author><author><name>Océane Marescal</name></author><author><name>Szilárd Szikora</name></author><author><name>Miklos Erdelyi</name></author><author><name>Péter Bíró</name></author><author><name>Tuana Mesquita</name></author><author><name>József Mihály</name></author><author><name>Frieder Schöck</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Myofibrils are long intracellular cables specific to muscles, composed mainly of actin and myosin filaments. The actin and myosin filaments are organized into repeated units called sarcomeres, which form the myofibril cables. Muscle contraction is achieved by the simultaneous shortening of sarcomeres and for a highly coordinated contraction to occur all sarcomeres should have the same size. Muscles have evolved a variety of ways to ensure sarcomere homogeneity, one example being the controlled oligomerization of Zasp proteins that sets the diameter of the myofibril. To understand how Zasp proteins effect myofibril growth, we looked for Zasp-binding proteins at the Z-disc. We found that the E1 subunit of the oxoglutarate dehydrogenase complex is recruited to the Z-disc by Zasp52 and is required to sustain myofibril growth. By making specific mutants, we show that its enzymatic activity is important for myofibril growth, and that the other two subunits of the complex are also required for myofibril formation. Using super resolution microscopy, we revealed the overall organization of the complex at the Z-disc. Then, using metabolomic analysis, we uncovered an amino acid balance defect affecting protein synthesis, that we also confirmed by genetic tools. In summary, we show that Zasp controls the local amino acid pool responsible for myofibril growth by recruiting the OGDH complex to the Z-disc.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472149" rel="alternate" title="Oxoglutarate dehydrogenase coordinates myofibril growth by maintaining amino acid homeostasis (14 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472380</id><title>PTEN inhibits AMPK to control collective migration (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.217603+00:00</updated><author><name>Florent Peglion</name></author><author><name>Lavinia Capuana</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Perfettini</name></author><author><name>Ben Braithwaite</name></author><author><name>Emie Quissac</name></author><author><name>Karin Forsberg-Nilsson</name></author><author><name>Flora Llense</name></author><author><name>Sandrine Etienne-Manneville</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;PTEN is one of the most frequently mutated tumor suppressor gene in cancer. PTEN is generally altered in invasive cancers such as glioblastomas, but its function in collective cell migration and invasion is not fully characterized. Herein, we report that the loss of PTEN increases cell speed during collective migration of non-tumourous cells both in vitro and in vivo. We further show that loss of PTEN promotes LKB1-dependent phosphorylation and activation of the major metabolic regulator AMPK. In turn AMPK increases VASP phosphorylation, reduces VASP localization at cell-cell junctions and decreases the interjunctional transverse actin arcs at the leading front, provoking a weakening of cell-cell contacts and increasing migration speed. Targeting AMPK activity not only slows down PTEN-depleted cells, it also limits PTEN-null glioblastoma cell invasion, opening new opportunities to treat glioblastoma lethal invasiveness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472380" rel="alternate" title="PTEN inhibits AMPK to control collective migration (13 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472361</id><title>Dynamic Boolean modelling reveals the influence of energy supply on bacterial efflux pump expression (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.217819+00:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Kerr</name></author><author><name>Sara Jabbari</name></author><author><name>Jessica M. A. Blair</name></author><author><name>Iain G. Johnston</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antimicrobial resistance (AMR) is a global health issue. One key factor contributing to AMR is the ability of bacteria to export drugs through efflux pumps, which relies on the ATP-dependent expression and interaction of several controlling genes. Recent studies have shown significant cell-to-cell ATP variability exists within clonal bacterial populations, but the contribution of intrinsic cell-to-cell ATP heterogeneity is generally overlooked in understanding efflux pumps. Here, we consider how ATP variability influences gene regulatory networks controlling expression of efflux pump genes in two bacterial species. We develop and apply a generalisable Boolean modelling framework, developed to incorporate the dependence of gene expression dynamics on available cellular energy supply. Theoretical results show differences in energy availability can cause pronounced downstream heterogeneity in efflux gene expression. Cells with higher energy availability have a superior response to stressors. Further, in the absence of stress, model bacteria develop heterogeneous pulses of efflux pump gene expression which contribute to a sustained sub-population of cells with increased efflux expression activity, potentially conferring a continuous pool of intrinsically resistant bacteria. This modelling approach thus reveals an important source of heterogeneity in cell responses to antimicrobials and sheds light on potentially targetable aspects of efflux pump-related antimicrobial resistance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472361" rel="alternate" title="Dynamic Boolean modelling reveals the influence of energy supply on bacterial efflux pump expression (12 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472566</id><title>Embryo-scale epithelial buckling forms a propagating furrow that initiates gastrulation (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.217975+00:00</updated><author><name>Julien Fierling</name></author><author><name>Alphy John</name></author><author><name>Barthélémy Delorme</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Torzynski</name></author><author><name>Guy Blanchard</name></author><author><name>Claire Lye</name></author><author><name>Grégoire Malandain</name></author><author><name>Bénédicte Sanson</name></author><author><name>Jocelyn Étienne</name></author><author><name>Philippe Marmottant</name></author><author><name>Catherine Quilliet</name></author><author><name>Matteo Rauzi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cell apical constriction driven by actomyosin contraction forces is a conserved mechanism during tissue folding in embryo development. While much effort has been made to better understand the molecular mechanisms responsible for apical constriction, it is still not clear if apical actomyosin contraction forces are necessary or sufficient &lt;italic&gt;per se&lt;/italic&gt; to drive tissue folding. To tackle this question, we use the &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; embryo model system that forms a furrow on the ventral side, initiating mesoderm internalization. Past computational models support the idea that cell apical contraction forces may not be sufficient and that active or passive cell apico-basal forces may be necessary to drive cell wedging and tissue furrowing. By using 3D computational modelling and &lt;italic&gt;in toto&lt;/italic&gt; embryo image analysis and manipulation, we now challenge this idea and show that embryo-scale force balance of the tissue surface, rather than cell-autonomous shape changes, is necessary and sufficient to drive a buckling of the epithelial surface forming a furrow which propagates and initiates embryo gastrulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472566" rel="alternate" title="Embryo-scale epithelial buckling forms a propagating furrow that initiates gastrulation (12 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473064</id><title>Nuclear lamins promote protrusion dynamics and collective, confined migration in vivo (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.218188+00:00</updated><author><name>Lauren Penfield</name></author><author><name>Denise Montell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cells migrate collectively through confined environments during development and cancer metastasis. While the nucleus, a large and stiff organelle, impedes cell migration between non-deformable pillars in vitro, its function in vivo may vary depending on the microenvironment. Further, it is unknown how nuclei contribute to collective migration in vivo and whether nuclei in different positions within cell collectives experience different forces. Here, we use border cell migration in the fly ovary as an in vivo model to investigate the effects of confined, collective migration on nuclei and the contribution of nuclear lamins to migration. We found severe yet transient nuclear deformations occur, particularly in the leading cell, as border cells squeeze through tiny crevices between germline cells, termed nurse cells. Leading cells extend protrusions between nurse cells, which may pry open space to allow the cluster to advance. Here we report that the leading cell nuclei deformed as they moved into leading protrusions. Then as protrusions widened, the nucleus recovered a more circular shape. These data suggest that lead cell nuclei may help protrusions expand and thereby enlarge the migration path. To test how nuclei might promote or impede border cell migration, we investigated nuclear lamins, proteins that assemble into intermediate filaments and structurally support the nuclear envelope. Depletion of the Drosophila B-type lamin, Lam, from the outer, motile border cells, but not the inner, nonmotile polar cells, impeded border cell migration, whereas perturbations of the A-type lamin, LamC, did not. While wild type border cell clusters typically have one large leading protrusion as they delaminate from the anterior follicular epithelium, clusters depleted of B-type lamin had multiple, short-lived protrusions, resulting in unproductive cluster movement and failure to progress along the migration path. Further, border cell nuclei depleted of B-type lamins were small, formed blebs, and ruptured. Together, these data indicate that B-type lamin is requied for nuclear integrity, which in turn stabilizes the leading protrusion and promotes overall cluster polarization and collective movement through confined spaces.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473064" rel="alternate" title="Nuclear lamins promote protrusion dynamics and collective, confined migration in vivo (10 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472799</id><title>Discovery of lipid-mediated protein-protein interactions in living cells using metabolic labeling with photoactivatable clickable probes (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.218601+00:00</updated><author><name>Roman O. Fedoryshchak</name></author><author><name>Andrii Gorelik</name></author><author><name>Mengjie Shen</name></author><author><name>Maria M. Shchepinova</name></author><author><name>Inmaculada Pérez-Dorado</name></author><author><name>Edward W. Tate</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protein-protein interactions (PPIs) are essential and pervasive regulatory elements in cell biology. Despite development of a range of techniques to probe PPIs in living systems, there is a dearth of approaches to capture interactions driven by specific post-translational modifications (PTMs). Myristoylation is a lipid PTM added to more than 200 human proteins, where it may regulate membrane localization, stability or activity. Here we report design and synthesis of a panel of novel photocrosslinkable and clickable myristic acid analog probes, and their characterization as efficient substrates for human &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;-myristoyltransferases NMT1 and NMT2, both biochemically and through X-ray co-crystallography. We demonstrate metabolic incorporation of probes to label NMT substrates in cell culture and &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; intracellular photoactivation to form a covalent crosslink between modified proteins and their interactors, capturing a snapshot of interactions driven by the presence of the lipid PTM. Proteomic analyses revealed both known and multiple novel interactors of a series of myristoylated proteins, including ferroptosis suppressor protein FSP1 and spliceosome-associated RNA helicase DDX46. The concept exemplified by these probes offers an efficient approach for exploring the PTM-specific interactome, which may prove broadly applicable to other PTMs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472799" rel="alternate" title="Discovery of lipid-mediated protein-protein interactions in living cells using metabolic labeling with photoactivatable clickable probes (10 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472726</id><title>Artificial intelligence to solve the X-ray crystallography phase problem: a case study report (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.218882+00:00</updated><author><name>Irène Barbarin-Bocahu</name></author><author><name>Marc Graille</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The determination of three dimensional structures of macromolecules is one of the actual challenge in biology with the ultimate objective of understanding their function. So far, X-ray crystallography is the most popular method to solve structure, but this technique relies on the generation of diffracting crystals. Once a correct data set has been obtained, the calculation of electron density maps requires to solve the so-called «phase problem » using different approaches. The most frequently used technique is molecular replacement, which relies on the availability of the structure of a protein sharing strong structural similarity with the studied protein. Its success rate is directly correlated with the quality of the models used for the molecular replacement trials. The availability of models as accurate as possible is then definitely critical.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Very recently, a breakthrough step has been made in the field of protein structure prediction thanks to the use of machine learning approaches as implemented in the AlphaFold or RoseTTAFold structure prediction programs. Here, we describe how these recent improvements helped us to solve the crystal structure of a protein involved in the nonsense-mediated mRNA decay pathway (NMD), an mRNA quality control pathway dedicated to the elimination of eukaryotic mRNAs harboring premature stop codons.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472726" rel="alternate" title="Artificial intelligence to solve the X-ray crystallography phase problem: a case study report (9 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472800</id><title>The MyLo CRISPR-Cas9 Toolkit: A Markerless Yeast Localization and Overexpression CRISPR-Cas9 Toolkit (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.219023+00:00</updated><author><name>Bjorn DM Bean</name></author><author><name>Malcolm Whiteway</name></author><author><name>Vincent JJ Martin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The genetic tractability of the yeast &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; has made it a key model organism for basic research and a target for metabolic engineering. To streamline the introduction of tagged genes and compartmental markers with powerful CRISPR-Cas9-based genome editing tools we constructed a Markerless Yeast Localization and Overexpression (MyLO) CRISPR-Cas9 Toolkit with three components: (i) a set of optimized &lt;italic&gt;S. pyogenes&lt;/italic&gt; Cas9-guide RNA (gRNA) expression vectors with five selectable markers and the option to either pre-clone or co-transform the gRNAs; (ii) vectors for the one-step construction of integration cassettes expressing an untagged or GFP/RFP/HA-tagged gene of interest at one of three levels, supporting localization and overexpression studies; and (iii) integration cassettes containing moderately expressed GFP- or RFP-tagged compartmental markers for colocalization experiments. These components allow rapid, high efficiency genomic integrations and modifications with only transient selection for the Cas9 vector, resulting in markerless transformations. Thus, the MyLO toolkit packages CRISPR-Cas9 technology into a flexible, optimized bundle to simplify yeast research&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472800" rel="alternate" title="The MyLo CRISPR-Cas9 Toolkit: A Markerless Yeast Localization and Overexpression CRISPR-Cas9 Toolkit (9 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473092</id><title>p166 links membrane and intramitochondrial modules of the trypanosomal tripartite attachment complex (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.219161+00:00</updated><author><name>Bernd Schimanski</name></author><author><name>Salome Aeschlimann</name></author><author><name>Sandro Käser</name></author><author><name>Maria Gomez-Fabra Gala</name></author><author><name>Nora Vögtle</name></author><author><name>André Schneider</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The protist parasite Trypanosoma brucei has a single mitochondrion with a single unit genome termed kinetoplast DNA (kDNA). Faithfull segregation of replicated kDNA is ensured by a complicated structure termed tripartite attachment complex (TAC). The TAC physically links the basal body of the flagellum with the kDNA spanning the two mitochondrial membranes. Here, we characterized p166 as the only TAC subunit that is anchored in the inner membrane. Its C-terminal transmembrane domain separates the protein into a large N-terminal region that interacts with the kDNA-localized TAC102 and a 34 aa C-tail that binds to the intermembrane space-exposed loop of the integral outer membrane protein TAC60. Thus, in contrast to the outer membrane TAC region which requires four essential subunits for proper function a single inner membrane TAC subunit is sufficient to bridge the distance from the OM to the kDNA. Surprisingly, non-functional p166 lacking the C-terminal 34 aa still localizes to the TAC region. This suggests the existence of nonessential TAC-associated proteins in the OM. These proteins can loosely bind to non-functional p166 lacking the C-terminal 34 aa and keep it at the TAC but their binding would not be strong enough to withstand the mechanical force upon kDNA segregation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473092" rel="alternate" title="p166 links membrane and intramitochondrial modules of the trypanosomal tripartite attachment complex (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472278</id><title>Using polyacrylamide hydrogels to model physiological aortic stiffness reveals that microtubules are critical regulators of isolated smooth muscle cell morphology and contractility (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.219727+00:00</updated><author><name>Sultan Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Robert. T. Johnson</name></author><author><name>Reesha Solanki</name></author><author><name>Teclino Afewerki</name></author><author><name>Finn Wostear</name></author><author><name>Derek T. Warren</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Vascular smooth muscle cells (VSMCs) are the predominant cell type in the medial layer of the aortic wall and normally exist in a quiescent, contractile phenotype where actomyosin-derived contractile forces maintain vascular tone. However, VSMCs are not terminally differentiated and can dedifferentiate into a proliferative, synthetic phenotype. Actomyosin force generation is essential for the function of both phenotypes. Whilst much is already known about the mechanisms of VSMC actomyosin force generation, existing assays are either low throughput and time consuming, or qualitative and inconsistent. In this study, we use polyacrylamide hydrogels, tuned to mimic the physiological stiffness of the aortic wall, in a VSMC contractility assay. Isolated VSMC area decreases following stimulation with the contractile agonists angiotensin II or carbachol. Importantly, the angiotensin II induced reduction in cell area correlated with increased traction stress generation. Inhibition of actomyosin activity using blebbistatin or Y-27632 prevented angiotensin II mediated changes in VSMC morphology, suggesting that changes in VSMC morphology and actomyosin activity are core components of the contractile response. Furthermore, we show that microtubule stability is an essential regulator of isolated VSMC contractility. Treatment with either colchicine or paclitaxel uncoupled the morphological and/or traction stress responses of angiotensin II stimulated VSMCs. Our findings support the tensegrity model and we demonstrate that microtubules act to balance the actomyosin-derived traction stress generation and regulate the morphological responses of VSMCs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472278" rel="alternate" title="Using polyacrylamide hydrogels to model physiological aortic stiffness reveals that microtubules are critical regulators of isolated smooth muscle cell morphology and contractility (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472491</id><title>Transcription Factor RFX3 Stabilizes Mammary Basal Cell Identity (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.219941+00:00</updated><author><name>Erica M. Tross</name></author><author><name>Christian R. de Caestecker</name></author><author><name>Ken S. Lau</name></author><author><name>Ian G. Macara</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The myoepithelial cell compartment of the murine postnatal mammary gland is generated from basal cap cells in the terminal end bud and maintained by self-renewal. Transdifferentiation to the luminal lineage does not normally occur but can be induced by DNA damage, luminal cell death or transplantation into a recipient mammary fat pad. Myoepithelial cells cultivated in vitro can also transdifferentiate towards the luminal lineage. Little is known about the molecular mechanisms and gene regulatory networks underlying this plasticity. Using a transgenic mouse (Tg11.5kb-GFP) that marks cap cells with GFP, we discovered that mature myoepithelial cells placed in culture begin to express GFP within ∼24 hrs and later express the Keratin 8 (K8) luminal marker. Cell tracking showed that most K8+ cells arose from GFP+ cells, suggesting that myoepithelial cells de-differentiate towards a progenitor state before changing lineage. Differential gene expression analysis, comparing pure GFP+ cap cells with mature myoepithelial cells, identified multiple transcription factors that iRegulon predicted might regulate the myoepithelial to cap cell transition. Knockout of one of these genes, Regulatory Factor 3 (Rfx3), significantly reduced the population of GFP+ cells and increased differentiation to the K8+ luminal lineage. Rfx3 knockout also reduced mammosphere growth and mammary gland regeneration efficiency in a transplantation assay, but had no effect on proliferation in vitro. Together, these data support a key role for Rfx3 in the stabilization of the mammary basal cell lineages.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472491" rel="alternate" title="Transcription Factor RFX3 Stabilizes Mammary Basal Cell Identity (7 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472705</id><title>Pseudomonas response regulators produced in an E. coli heterologous expression host exhibit host-derived post-translational phosphorylation (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.220139+00:00</updated><author><name>Megan E. Garber</name></author><author><name>Rodrigo Fregoso</name></author><author><name>Julie Lake</name></author><author><name>Anne Kakouridis</name></author><author><name>Aindrila Mukhopadhyay</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In this report, we systematically characterize 32 response regulators (RRs) from a metal tolerant groundwater isolate, &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas stutzeri&lt;/italic&gt; RCH2 to assess the impact of host-derived post-translational phosphorylation. As observed by distinct shifted bands in a phos-tag gel, 12 of the 24 detected RRs show homogenous mixtures of phosphorylated proteins or heterogenous mixtures of unphosphorylated and phosphorylated proteins. By evaluating the phosphorylation state of CzcR and CopR II under varying assay parameters, we found that changes to pH and exogenous addition of phospho-donors (e.g. acetyl phosphate) have little to no effect on phosphorylation state. By applying protein production conditions that decrease the pool of intracellular acetyl-phosphate in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;, we found a reduction in the phosphorylated population of CopR II when magnesium was added to the media, but observed no change in phosphorylated population when CopR II is expressed in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; BL21 (DE3) &lt;italic&gt;Δpta&lt;/italic&gt;, a mutant with a metabolic disruption to the acetyl-phosphate pathway. Therefore, the specific mechanism of post-translational phosphorylation of RRs in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; remains obscure. These findings show the importance of characterizing the phosphorylations state of proteins when heterologously expressed, since their biochemical and physiological properties are dependent on post-translational modification.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472705" rel="alternate" title="Pseudomonas response regulators produced in an E. coli heterologous expression host exhibit host-derived post-translational phosphorylation (7 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.470649</id><title>Comparison of extraction methods for intracellular metabolomics (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.220308+00:00</updated><author><name>Carolin Andresen</name></author><author><name>Tobias Boch</name></author><author><name>Hagen M. Gegner</name></author><author><name>Nils Mechtel</name></author><author><name>Andreas Narr</name></author><author><name>Emrullah Birgin</name></author><author><name>Erik Rasbach</name></author><author><name>Nuh Rahbari</name></author><author><name>Andreas Trumpp</name></author><author><name>Gernot Poschet</name></author><author><name>Daniel Hübschmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Measurements of metabolic compounds inside cells or tissues are of high informative potential since they represent the endpoint of biological information flow and a snapshot of the integration of many regulatory processes. However, it requires careful extraction to quantify their abundance. Here we present a comprehensive study using ten extraction protocols on four human sample types (liver tissue, bone marrow, HL60 and HEK cells) targeting 630 metabolites of different chemical classes. We show that the extraction efficiency and stability is highly variable across protocols and tissues by using different quality metrics including the limit of detection and variability between replicates as well as the sum of concentration as a global estimate of extraction stability. The profile of extracted metabolites depends on the used solvents - an observation which has implications for measurements of different sample types and metabolic compounds of interest. To identify the optimal extraction method for future metabolomics studies, the benchmark dataset was implemented in an easy-to-use, interactive and flexible online resource (R/shiny app MetaboExtract).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.470649" rel="alternate" title="Comparison of extraction methods for intracellular metabolomics (7 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472537</id><title>Key features of inhibitor binding to the human mitochondrial pyruvate carrier hetero-dimer (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.220693+00:00</updated><author><name>Sotiria Tavoulari</name></author><author><name>Tom J.J. Schirris</name></author><author><name>Vasiliki Mavridou</name></author><author><name>Chancievan Thangaratnarajah</name></author><author><name>Martin S. King</name></author><author><name>Daniel T.D. Jones</name></author><author><name>Shujing Ding</name></author><author><name>Ian M. Fearnley</name></author><author><name>Edmund R.S. Kunji</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mitochondrial pyruvate carrier (MPC) has emerged as a promising drug target for metabolic disorders, including non-alcoholic steatohepatitis and diabetes, metabolically dependent cancers and neurodegenerative diseases. Human MPC is a protein complex, but the composition of its active form is debated and the mechanisms of transport and inhibition are not resolved. We have recombinantly expressed and purified the human hetero-complex MPC1L/MPC2 and demonstrate that it is a functional hetero-dimer, like the yeast MPC hetero-dimers. Unlike the latter, human MPC1L/MPC2 binds the known inhibitors with high potencies. We identify the essential chemical features shared between these structurally diverse inhibitors and demonstrate that high affinity binding is not attributed to covalent bond formation with MPC cysteines, as previously thought. We also identify 14 new inhibitors of MPC, one outperforming the most potent compound UK5099 by tenfold. Two of them are the commonly prescribed drugs entacapone and nitrofurantoin, suggesting possible off-target mechanisms associated with their adverse effects. This work advances our understanding of MPC inhibition and will accelerate the development of clinically relevant MPC modulators.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472537" rel="alternate" title="Key features of inhibitor binding to the human mitochondrial pyruvate carrier hetero-dimer (6 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472443</id><title>Glutathione binding to the plant AtAtm3 transporter and implications for the conformational coupling of ABC transporters (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.220986+00:00</updated><author><name>Chengcheng Fan</name></author><author><name>Douglas C. Rees</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ATP Binding Cassette (ABC) transporter of mitochondria (Atm) from &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;At&lt;/italic&gt;Atm3) has been implicated in the maturation of cytosolic iron-sulfur proteins and heavy metal detoxification, plausibly by exporting glutathione derivatives. Using single-particle cryo-electron microscopy, we have determined structures of &lt;italic&gt;At&lt;/italic&gt;Atm3 in multiple conformational states. These structures not only provide a structural framework for defining the alternating access transport cycle, but also highlight an unappreciated feature of the glutathione binding site, namely the paucity of cysteine residues that could potentially form inhibitory mixed disulfides with glutathione. Despite extensive efforts, we were unable to prepare the ternary complex of &lt;italic&gt;At&lt;/italic&gt;Atm3 with bound GSSG and MgATP. A survey of structurally characterized type IV ABC transporters that includes &lt;italic&gt;At&lt;/italic&gt;Atm3 establishes that while nucleotides are found associated with all conformational states, they are effectively required to stabilize occluded and outward-facing conformations. In contrast, transport substrates have only been observed associated with inward-facing conformations. The absence of structures containing both nucleotide and transport substrate suggests that this ternary complex exists only transiently during the transport cycle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472443" rel="alternate" title="Glutathione binding to the plant AtAtm3 transporter and implications for the conformational coupling of ABC transporters (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473091</id><title>The Trypanosoma cruzi kinetoplast DNA minicircle sequences transfer biomarker of the multidrug treatment of Chagas disease (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.221152+00:00</updated><author><name>Antonio R. L. Teixeira</name></author><author><name>Alessandro O Sousa</name></author><author><name>Clever C Gomes</name></author><author><name>Adriana A Sá</name></author><author><name>Rubens J Nascimento</name></author><author><name>Liana L Pires</name></author><author><name>Ana M Castro</name></author><author><name>Francisco B Moreno</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: The Trypanosoma cruzi infection renders the transfer of the mitochondrion kinetoplast DNA minicircle sequences into the host’s genome. The Aves are refractory to the infection, but chicks hatched from the T. cruzi inoculated eggs integrate the DNA minicircle sequences into the germ line cells. Rabbits, mice and chickens with the minicircle sequences mutations develop the Chagas cardiomyopathy and the DNA transfer underpins the heart disease.
Methodology: The PCR with the specific primer sets revealed the Protist nuclear DNA and the kinetoplast DNA in the agarose gels bands probed with the radiolabel specific sequences from tissues of the T. cruzi-infected rabbits and of the mice. A targetprimer TAIL-PCR amplification employing primer sets from the chickens, rabbits and mice, in combination with primer sets from the the T. cruzi kinetoplast minicircle sequences was used. This approach led us to disclose the integration sites of the kinetoplast DNA biomarker, then, used to monitor the effect of multidrug treatment of the T. cruzi infected mice.
Principal findings: The Southern hybridization, clone and sequence of the amplification products revealed the DNA minicircle sequences integrations sites in the LINE transposable elements. An array of inhibitors of eukaryote cells division was used to arrest the DNA transfer. It was shown that nine out of 12 inhibitors prevented the kinetoplast DNA integration into the macrophage genome. The multidrug treatment of the acutely T. cruzi-infected mice with Benznidazole, Azidothymidine and Ofloxacin lessened circa 2.5-fold the rate of the minicircle sequences integrations in the mouse genome and inhibited the rejection of the target heart cells.
Conclusion and significance: The T. cruzi mitochondrion kinetoplast minicircle sequences transfer driven pathogenesis of Chagas disease is an ancient Cross-Kingdom DNA phenomenon of evolution and, therefore, paradigm research with effective purposing inhibitors is needed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473091" rel="alternate" title="The Trypanosoma cruzi kinetoplast DNA minicircle sequences transfer biomarker of the multidrug treatment of Chagas disease (6 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472320</id><title>Biocatalytic Formation of Novel Polyesters with para-Hydroxyphenyl groups in the Backbone – Engineering Cupriavidus necator for production of high-performance materials from CO2 and electricity (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.221329+00:00</updated><author><name>Nils JH Averesch</name></author><author><name>Vince E Pane</name></author><author><name>Frauke Kracke</name></author><author><name>Marika Ziesack</name></author><author><name>Shannon N Nangle</name></author><author><name>Pamela A Silver</name></author><author><name>Robert W Waymouth</name></author><author><name>Craig S Criddle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Synthetic materials are integral components of consumables and durable goods and indispensable in our modern world. Polyesters are the most versatile bulk- and specialty-polymers, but their production is not sustainable, and their fate at end-of-life of great concern. Bioplastics are highly regarded alternatives but have shortcomings in material properties and commercial competitiveness with conventional synthetic plastics. These constraints have limited the success in global markets. Enabling bio-production of advanced bioplastics with superior properties from waste-derived feedstocks could change this.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have created microbial cell factories that can produce a range of aliphatic and aromatic polyesters. A Δ&lt;italic&gt;phaC1&lt;/italic&gt; mutant of &lt;italic&gt;Cupriavidus necator&lt;/italic&gt; H16 was complemented with hydroxyacyl-CoA transferases from either &lt;italic&gt;Clostridium propionicum&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;pct540&lt;/italic&gt;) or &lt;italic&gt;Clostridium difficile&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;hadA&lt;/italic&gt;), respectively. These were combined with a mutant PHA synthase (&lt;italic&gt;phaC1437&lt;/italic&gt;) from &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/italic&gt; sp. MBEL 6-19, which rescued the PHA&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt; phenotype of the knock-out mutant and allowed polymerization of various hydroxy carboxylates, including phloretic acid. This is the first-time, incorporation of an aromatic ring in the backbone of a biological polyester was achieved. Polymers contain &lt;italic&gt;para&lt;/italic&gt;-hydroxyphenyl subunits are structurally analogous to synthetic aromatic polyesters like PET and high-strength polyarylates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a further advance, the transgenic strain was cultivated in a bio-electrochemical system under autotrophic conditions, enabling synthesis of aromatic bio-polyesters from H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; generated &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt;, while assimilating CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. Follow-up elementary flux-mode analysis established the feasibility of &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; production of twenty different polyesters from five different carbon- and energy-sources. This comprehensive study opens the door to sustainable bio-production of high-performance thermoplastics and thermosets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;New biomaterials can facilitate transition to a carbon-neutral chemical industry and a circular economy while at the same time preventing accumulation of plastic wastes in the environment. This can be accomplished by developing “drop-in” replacements for existing fossil carbon-based plastics. To that end, this work demonstrates for the first time that biocatalytic polymerization can incorporate an aromatic &lt;italic&gt;para&lt;/italic&gt;-hydroxyphenyl carbonic acid into the backbone of a bio-polyester. This was accomplished using a genetically engineered microbial cell factory that assimilates carbon dioxide using hydrogen that is produced electrochemically &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt;. A bio-electrochemical system eliminates the need for external supply of oxyhydrogen and avoids explosive mixtures, opening the door for sustainable production of biomaterials analogous to aromatic bulk-polyesters such as PET and high-performance “liquid-crystal polymers”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="simple"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Biocatalytic formation of aromatic polyesters with structural analogy to polyarylates&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Production of novel PHAs from CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;+O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; produced &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; in a bio-electrochemical system&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Expression-level of PHA synthase and molecular weight of polyesters are inversely correlated&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;- &lt;italic&gt;In silico&lt;/italic&gt; design and analysis of pathways towards novel PHAs from different carbon-sources&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472320" rel="alternate" title="Biocatalytic Formation of Novel Polyesters with para-Hydroxyphenyl groups in the Backbone – Engineering Cupriavidus necator for production of high-performance materials from CO2 and electricity (5 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472572</id><title>High content screening and computational prediction reveal viral genes that suppress innate immune response (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.221632+00:00</updated><author><name>Tai L. Ng</name></author><author><name>Erika J. Olson</name></author><author><name>Tae Yeon Yoo</name></author><author><name>H. Sloane Weiss</name></author><author><name>Yukiye Koide</name></author><author><name>Peter D. Koch</name></author><author><name>Nathan J. Rollins</name></author><author><name>Pia Mach</name></author><author><name>Tobias Meisinger</name></author><author><name>Trenton Bricken</name></author><author><name>Timothy Z. Chang</name></author><author><name>Colin Molloy</name></author><author><name>Jérôme Zürcher</name></author><author><name>Timothy J. Mitchison</name></author><author><name>John I. Glass</name></author><author><name>Debora S. Marks</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey C. Way</name></author><author><name>Pamela A. Silver</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Suppression of the host innate immune response is a critical aspect of viral replication. Upon infection, viruses may introduce one or more proteins that inhibit key immune pathways, such as the type I interferon pathway. However, the ability to predict and evaluate viral protein bioactivity on targeted pathways remains challenging and is typically done on a single virus/gene basis. Here, we present a medium-throughput high-content cell-based assay to reveal the immunosuppressive effects of viral proteins. To test the predictive power of our approach, we developed a library of 800 genes encoding known, predicted, and uncharacterized human viral genes. We find that previously known immune suppressors from numerous viral families such as &lt;italic&gt;Picornaviridae&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Flaviviridae&lt;/italic&gt; recorded positive responses. These include a number of viral proteases for which we further confirmed that innate immune suppression depends on protease activity. A class of predicted inhibitors encoded by &lt;italic&gt;Rhabdoviridae&lt;/italic&gt; viruses was demonstrated to block nuclear transport, and several previously uncharacterized proteins from uncultivated viruses were shown to inhibit nuclear transport of the transcription factors NF-κB and IRF3. We propose that this pathway-based assay, together with early sequencing, gene synthesis, and viral infection studies, could partly serve as the basis for rapid &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; characterization of novel viral proteins.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Infectious diseases caused by viral pathogens exacerbate healthcare and economic burdens. Numerous viral biomolecules suppress the human innate immune system, enabling viruses to evade an immune response from the host. Despite our current understanding of viral replications and immune evasion, new viral proteins, including those encoded by uncultivated viruses or emerging viruses, are being unearthed at a rapid pace from large scale sequencing and surveillance projects. The use of medium- and high-throughput functional assays to characterize immunosuppressive functions of viral proteins can advance our understanding of viral replication and possibly treatment of infections. In this study we assembled a large viral gene library from diverse viral families and developed a high content assay to test for inhibition of innate immunity pathways. Our work expands the tools that can rapidly link sequence and protein function, representing a practical step towards early-stage evaluation of emerging and understudied viruses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472572" rel="alternate" title="High content screening and computational prediction reveal viral genes that suppress innate immune response (4 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472873</id><title>Transcription factor lineages in plant-pathogenic fungi, connecting diversity with fungal virulence (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.222060+00:00</updated><author><name>Evan John</name></author><author><name>Kar-Chun Tan</name></author><author><name>Richard Peter Oliver</name></author><author><name>Karam Singh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Plant-pathogenic fungi span diverse taxonomic lineages. Their host-infection strategies are often specialised and require the coordinated regulation of molecular virulence factors. Transcription factors (TFs) are fundamental regulators of gene expression, controlling development and virulence in plant pathogenic fungi. Recent research has established regulatory roles for several taxonomically conserved fungal TFs, but the evolution of specific virulence regulators is not well understood. This study sought to explore the representation of TFs across a taxonomically-diverse range of fungi, with a focus on plant pathogens. A significant trend was observed among the obligate, host-associated pathogens, which possess a reduced overall TF repertoire, alluding to a lack of pressure for maintaining diversity. A novel orthology-based analysis is then presented that refined TF classifications, traditionally based on the nature of the DNA-binding domains. Using this analysis, cases of TF over/underrepresentation across fungal pathogen lineages are systematically highlighted. Specific examples are then explored and discussed that included the TF orthologues of Ste12, Pf2 and EBR1, plus phytotoxic secondary-metabolite cluster regulators, which all presented novel and distinct evolutionary insights. Ultimately, as the examples presented demonstrate, this resource can be interrogated to guide functional studies that seek to characterise virulence-specific regulators and shed light on the factors underpinning plant pathogenicity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472873" rel="alternate" title="Transcription factor lineages in plant-pathogenic fungi, connecting diversity with fungal virulence (4 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472604</id><title>Evolution of miRNA binding sites and regulatory networks in cichlids (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.222257+00:00</updated><author><name>Tarang K. Mehta</name></author><author><name>Luca Penso-Dolfin</name></author><author><name>Will Nash</name></author><author><name>Sushmita Roy</name></author><author><name>Federica Di-Palma</name></author><author><name>Wilfried Haerty</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The divergence of regulatory regions and gene regulatory network (GRN) rewiring is a key driver of cichlid phenotypic diversity. However, the contribution of miRNA binding site turnover has yet to be linked to GRN evolution across cichlids. Here, we extend our previous studies by analysing the selective constraints driving evolution of miRNA and transcription factor binding sites (TFBSs) of target genes, to infer instances of cichlid GRN rewiring associated with regulatory binding site turnover. Comparative analyses identified increased species-specific networks that are functionally associated to traits of cichlid phenotypic diversity. The evolutionary rewiring is associated with differential models of transcription factor (TF) and miRNA binding site turnover, driven by a high proportion of fast-evolving polymorphic sites in adaptive trait genes compared to subsets of random genes. Positive selection acting upon discrete mutations in these regulatory regions is likely to be an important mechanism in rewiring GRNs in rapidly radiating cichlids. Regulatory variants of functionally associated TF and miRNA binding sites of visual opsin genes differentially segregate according to phylogeny and ecology of Lake Malawi species, identifying both rewired e.g. clade-specific and conserved network motifs of adaptive trait associated GRNs. Our approach revealed several novel candidate regulators, regulatory regions and three-node motifs across cichlid genomes with previously reported associations to known adaptive evolutionary traits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472604" rel="alternate" title="Evolution of miRNA binding sites and regulatory networks in cichlids (4 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472598</id><title>Cell polarity determinant Dlg1 facilitates epithelial invagination by promoting tissue-scale mechanical coordination (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.222726+00:00</updated><author><name>Melisa Andrea Fuentes</name></author><author><name>Bing He</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Epithelial folding mediated by apical constriction serves as a fundamental mechanism to convert flat epithelial sheets into multilayered structures. It remains elusive whether additional mechanical inputs are required for folding mediated by apical constriction. Using &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; mesoderm invagination as a model, we identified an important role for the non-constricting, lateral mesodermal cells adjacent to the constriction domain ("flanking cells") in facilitating epithelial folding. We found that depletion of the basolateral determinant, Dlg1, disrupts the transition between apical constriction and invagination without affecting the rate of apical constriction. Strikingly, the observed delay in invagination is associated with ineffective apical myosin contractions in the flanking cells that lead to overstretching of their apical domain. The defects in the flanking cells impede ventral-directed movement of the lateral ectoderm, suggesting reduced mechanical coupling between tissues. Specifically disrupting the flanking cells in wildtype embryos by laser ablation or optogenetic depletion of cortical actin is sufficient to delay the apical constriction-to-invagination transition. Our findings indicate that effective mesoderm invagination requires intact flanking cells and suggest a role for tissue-scale mechanical coupling during epithelial folding.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472598" rel="alternate" title="Cell polarity determinant Dlg1 facilitates epithelial invagination by promoting tissue-scale mechanical coordination (4 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472595</id><title>NAD+ capping of RNA in Archaea and Mycobacteria (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.222913+00:00</updated><author><name>Olatz Ruiz-Larrabeiti</name></author><author><name>Roberto Benoni</name></author><author><name>Viacheslav Zemlianski</name></author><author><name>Nikola Hanišáková</name></author><author><name>Marek Schwarz</name></author><author><name>Barbora Brezovská</name></author><author><name>Barbora Benoni</name></author><author><name>Jarmila Hnilicová</name></author><author><name>Vladimir R. Kaberdin</name></author><author><name>Hana Cahová</name></author><author><name>Monika Vítězová</name></author><author><name>Martin Převorovský</name></author><author><name>Libor Krásný</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chemical modifications of RNA affect essential properties of transcripts, such as their translation, localization and stability. 5’-end RNA capping with the ubiquitous redox cofactor nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;) has been discovered in organisms ranging from bacteria to mammals. However, the hypothesis that NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; capping might be universal in all domains of life has not been proven yet, as information on this RNA modification is missing for Archaea. Likewise, this RNA modification has not been studied in the clinically important &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium&lt;/italic&gt; genus. Here, we demonstrate that NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; capping occurs in the archaeal and mycobacterial model organisms &lt;italic&gt;Methanosarcina barkeri&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium smegmatis.&lt;/italic&gt; Moreover, we identify the NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;-capped transcripts in &lt;italic&gt;M. smegmatis,&lt;/italic&gt; showing that this modification is more prevalent in stationary phase, and revealing that mycobacterial NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;-capped transcripts include non-coding small RNAs, such as Ms1. Furthermore, we show that mycobacterial RNA polymerase incorporates NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; into RNA, and that the genes of NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;-capped transcripts are preceded by promoter elements compatible with σ&lt;sup&gt;A&lt;/sup&gt;/σ&lt;sup&gt;F&lt;/sup&gt; dependent expression. Taken together, our findings demonstrate that NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; capping exists in the archaeal domain of life, suggesting that it is universal to all living organisms, and define the NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;-capped RNA landscape in mycobacteria, providing a basis for its future exploration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472595" rel="alternate" title="NAD+ capping of RNA in Archaea and Mycobacteria (4 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472782</id><title>DNMT3A knockouts in human iPSCs prevent de novo DNA methylation and reveal growth advantage during hematopoietic differentiation (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.223208+00:00</updated><author><name>Olivia Cypris</name></author><author><name>Julia Franzen</name></author><author><name>Joana Frobel</name></author><author><name>Philipp Glück</name></author><author><name>Chao-Chung Kuo</name></author><author><name>Stephani Schmitz</name></author><author><name>Selina Nüchtern</name></author><author><name>Martin Zenke</name></author><author><name>Wolfgang Wagner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;DNA methyltransferase 3A (&lt;italic&gt;DNMT3A&lt;/italic&gt;) is a frequently mutated gene in many hematological malignancies, indicating that it may be essential for hematopoietic differentiation. Here, we addressed the functional relevance of DNMT3A for differentiation of human induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs) by knocking out exon 2, 19, or 23. Exon 19&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; and 23&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; lines revealed absence of almost the entire &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; DNA methylation during mesenchymal and hematopoietic differentiation. Yet, differentiation was only slightly reduced in exon 19&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; and increased in exon 23&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; lines, whereas there was no significant impact on gene expression in hematopoietic progenitors (iHPCs). Notably, &lt;italic&gt;DNMT3A&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; iHPCs recapitulate some DNA methylation differences of acute myeloid leukemia with &lt;italic&gt;DNMT3A&lt;/italic&gt; mutations. Furthermore, multicolor genetic barcoding revealed competitive growth advantage of exon 23&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; iHPCs. Our results demonstrate that &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; DNA methylation during hematopoietic differentiation of iPSCs is almost entirely dependent on DNMT3A and exon 23&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; iHPCs even gained growth advantage.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472782" rel="alternate" title="DNMT3A knockouts in human iPSCs prevent de novo DNA methylation and reveal growth advantage during hematopoietic differentiation (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472736</id><title>Photoaffinity capture compounds to profile the Magic Spot Nucleotide interactomes (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.223393+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas M. Haas</name></author><author><name>Benoît-Joseph Laventie</name></author><author><name>Simon Lagies</name></author><author><name>Caroline Harter</name></author><author><name>Isabel Prucker</name></author><author><name>Danilo Ritz</name></author><author><name>Raspudin Saleem Batcha</name></author><author><name>Danye Qiu</name></author><author><name>Wolfgang Hüttel</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Andexer</name></author><author><name>Urs Jenal</name></author><author><name>Henning J. Jessen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Magic Spot Nucleotides (MSN) regulate the stringent response, a highly conserved bacterial stress adaptation mechanism, enabling survival when confronted with adverse external challenges. In times of antibiotic crisis, a detailed understanding of the stringent response is of critical importance, as potentially new targets for pharmacological intervention could be identified. In this study, we delineate the MSN interactome in &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella typhimurium&lt;/italic&gt; cell lysates applying a family of trifunctional photoaffinity capture compounds. We introduce different MSN probes covering diverse phosphorylation patterns, such as pppGpp, ppGpp, and pGpp. Our chemical proteomics approach provides datasets of diverse putative MSN receptors both from cytosolic and membrane fractions that, upon validation, unveil new MSN targets. We find, for example, that the dinucleoside polyphosphate hydrolase activity of the non-Nudix hydrolase ApaH is potently inhibited by pppGpp, which itself is converted to pGpp by ApaH. The photoaffinity capture compounds described herein will be useful to identify MSN interactomes under varying conditions and across bacterial species.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec id="s4"&gt;&lt;title&gt;TOC&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;caption&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Molecular fishing:&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt; a family of trifunctional photoaffinity capture compounds enables the identification of Magic Spot Nucleotide receptors by a chemoproteomics approach.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/caption&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="472736v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472736" rel="alternate" title="Photoaffinity capture compounds to profile the Magic Spot Nucleotide interactomes (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472434</id><title>Adenine Base Editing in vivo with a Single Adeno-Associated Virus Vector (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.223571+00:00</updated><author><name>Han Zhang</name></author><author><name>Nathan Bamidele</name></author><author><name>Pengpeng Liu</name></author><author><name>Ogooluwa Ojelabi</name></author><author><name>Xin D. Gao</name></author><author><name>Tomas Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Haoyang Cheng</name></author><author><name>Scot A. Wolfe</name></author><author><name>Wen Xue</name></author><author><name>Erik J. Sontheimer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Base editors (BEs) have opened new avenues for the treatment of genetic diseases. However, advances in delivery approaches are needed to enable disease targeting of a broad range of tissues and cell types. Adeno-associated virus (AAV) vectors remain one of the most promising delivery vehicles for gene therapies. Currently, most BE/guide combinations and their promoters exceed the packaging limit (~5 kb) of AAVs. Dual-AAV delivery strategies often require high viral doses that impose safety concerns. In this study, we engineered an adenine base editor using a compact Cas9 from Neisseria meningitidis (Nme2Cas9). Compared to the well-characterized Streptococcus pyogenes Cas9-containing ABEs, Nme2-ABE possesses a distinct PAM (N4CC) and editing window, exhibits fewer off-target effects, and can efficiently install therapeutically relevant mutations in both human and mouse genomes. Importantly, we show that in vivo delivery of Nme2-ABE and its guide RNA by a single-AAV vector can efficiently edit mouse genomic loci and revert the disease mutation and phenotype in an adult mouse model of tyrosinemia. We anticipate that Nme2-ABE, by virtue of its compact size and broad targeting range, will enable a range of therapeutic applications with improved safety and efficacy due in part to packaging in a single-vector system.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472434" rel="alternate" title="Adenine Base Editing in vivo with a Single Adeno-Associated Virus Vector (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472753</id><title>ZEB2 transduces HIF1α dependent regulation of Transglutaminase 2 in glomerular podocytes (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.223729+00:00</updated><author><name>Lakshmi P Kolligundla</name></author><author><name>Ashish K Singh</name></author><author><name>Rajesh Kavvuri</name></author><author><name>Anil K Pasupulati</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glomerular podocytes are instrumental in ensuring glomerular permselectivity and regulating the integrity of glomerular biology. However, podocytes are vulnerable to various noxious stimuli such as hypoxia, and podocyte injury presented with glomerulosclerosis and impaired kidney function. The mechanism of hypoxia-induced podocyte injury vis-a-vis glomerulosclerosis has remained enigmatic. Hypoxia inducible factor 1α (HIF1α) that transduces hypoxic adaptations, induces Transglutaminase 2 (TG2), a calcium dependent enzyme that catalyzes intramolecular ε-(γ-glutamyl) lysine cross-links of extracellular matrix (ECM) proteins. In this study, we investigated the mechanism of regulation of TG2 by HIF1α. Stabilization of HIF1α by FG4592 (Roxadustat) and physiological hypoxia, resulted in elevated expression of ZEB2 (zinc-finger E-box-homeobox 2) and its downstream target TRPC6 (transient receptor potential channel 6). ZEB2 transcriptionally activates TG2 expression, whereas, via TRPC6, it induces calcium influx, inturn it increases the TG2 activity. Blocking the TRPC6 action or suppressing its expression only partially attenuated FG4592 induced TG2 activity, whereas suppression of ZEB2 expression significantly abolished TG2 activity. This study demonstrates that stabilization of HIF1α stimulates both TG2 expression and activity, whereas abrogation of HIF1α by metformin prevented HIF1α regulated TG2 and consequent glomerular injury.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472753" rel="alternate" title="ZEB2 transduces HIF1α dependent regulation of Transglutaminase 2 in glomerular podocytes (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472925</id><title>The p97 cofactor Ubxn7 facilitates replisome disassembly during S-phase (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.224005+00:00</updated><author><name>Zeynep Tarcan</name></author><author><name>Divyasree Poovathumkadavil</name></author><author><name>Aggeliki Skagia</name></author><author><name>Agnieszka Gambus</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Complex cellular processes are driven by the regulated assembly and disassembly of large multi-protein complexes. In eukaryotic DNA replication, whilst we are beginning to understand the molecular mechanism for assembly of the replication machinery (replisome), we still know relatively little about the regulation of its disassembly at replication termination. Over recent years, the first elements of this process have emerged, revealing that the replicative helicase, at the heart of the replisome, is polyubiquitylated prior to unloading and that this unloading requires p97 segregase activity. Two different E3 ubiquitin ligases are now known to ubiquitylate the helicase under different conditions: Cul2Lrr1 and TRAIP. Here we have found two p97 cofactors, Ubxn7 and Faf1, which can interact with p97 during replisome disassembly in S-phase. Only Ubxn7 however facilitates efficient replisome disassembly through its interaction with both Cul2Lrr1 and p97. Our data therefore characterise Ubxn7 as the first substrate-specific p97 cofactor regulating replisome disassembly in vertebrates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472925" rel="alternate" title="The p97 cofactor Ubxn7 facilitates replisome disassembly during S-phase (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472944</id><title>Understanding p300-transcription factor interactions using sequence variation and hybridization (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.224139+00:00</updated><author><name>Fruzsina Hobor</name></author><author><name>Zsofia Hegedus</name></author><author><name>Amaurys Avila Ibarra</name></author><author><name>Vencel L. Petrovicz</name></author><author><name>Gail J. Bartlett</name></author><author><name>Richard B Sessions</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Wilson</name></author><author><name>Thomas A. Edwards</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The hypoxic response is central to cell function and plays a significant role in the growth and survival of solid tumours. HIF-1 regulates the hypoxic response by activating over 100 genes responsible for adaptation to hypoxia, making it a potential target for anticancer drug discovery. Although there is significant structural and mechanistic understanding of the interaction between HIF-1α and p300 alongside negative regulators of HIF-1α such as CITED2, there remains a need to further understand the sequence determinants of binding. In this work we use a combination of protein expression, chemical synthesis, fluorescence anisotropy and isothermal titration calorimetry for HIF-1α sequence variants and a HIF-1α- CITED hybrid sequence which we term CITIF. We show the HIF-1α sequence is highly tolerant to sequence variation through reduced enthalpic and less unfavourable entropic contributions, These data imply backbone as opposed to side chain interactions and ligand folding control the binding interaction and that sequence variations are tolerated as a result of adopting a more disordered bound interaction or fuzzy complex.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472944" rel="alternate" title="Understanding p300-transcription factor interactions using sequence variation and hybridization (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472863</id><title>Mitotic spindle formation in the absence of Polo kinase (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.224289+00:00</updated><author><name>Juyoung Kim</name></author><author><name>Gohta Goshima</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mitosis is a fundamental process in every eukaryote, in which chromosomes are segregated into two daughter cells by the action of the microtubule (MT)-based spindle. Despite this common principle, genes essential for mitosis are variable among organisms. This indicates that the loss of essential genes or bypass-of-essentiality (BOE) occurred multiple times during evolution. While many BOE relationships have been recently revealed experimentally, the BOE of mitosis regulators (BOE-M) has been scarcely reported and how this occurs remains largely unknown. Here, by mutagenesis and subsequent evolutionary repair experiments, we isolated viable fission yeast strains that lacked the entire coding region of Polo-like kinase (Plk), a versatile essential mitotic kinase. The BOE of Plk was enabled by specific mutations in the downstream machinery, including the MT-nucleating gamma-tubulin complex, and more surprisingly, through downregulation of glucose uptake, which is not readily connected to mitosis. The latter bypass was dependent on casein kinase I (CK1), which has not been considered as a major mitotic regulator. Our genetic and phenotypic data suggest that CK1 constitutes an alternative mechanism of MT nucleation, which is normally dominated by Plk. A similar relationship was observed in a human colon cancer cell line. Thus, our study shows that BOE-M can be achieved by simple genetic or environmental changes, consistent with the occurrence of BOE-M during evolution. Furthermore, the identification of BOE-M constitutes a powerful means to uncover a hitherto under-studied mechanism driving mitosis and also hints at the limitations and solutions for selecting chemotherapeutic compounds targeting mitosis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472863" rel="alternate" title="Mitotic spindle formation in the absence of Polo kinase (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472679</id><title>Cdc42 GTPase activating proteins Rga4 and Rga6 coordinate septum synthesis and membrane trafficking at the division plane during cytokinesis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.224405+00:00</updated><author><name>Bethany F. Campbell</name></author><author><name>Brian S. Hercyk</name></author><author><name>Ashlei R. Williams</name></author><author><name>Ema San Miguel</name></author><author><name>Haylee G. Young</name></author><author><name>Maitreyi E. Das</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fission yeast cytokinesis is driven by simultaneous septum synthesis, membrane furrowing and actomyosin ring constriction. The septum consists of a primary septum flanked by secondary septa. First, delivery of the glucan synthase Bgs1 and membrane vesicles initiate primary septum synthesis and furrowing. Next, Bgs4 is delivered for secondary septum formation. It is unclear how septum synthesis is coordinated with membrane furrowing. Cdc42 promotes delivery of Bgs1 but not Bgs4. We find that after primary septum initiation, Cdc42 inactivators Rga4 and Rga6 localize to the division site. In &lt;italic&gt;rga4Δrga6Δ&lt;/italic&gt; mutants Cdc42 activity is enhanced during late cytokinesis and cells take longer to separate. Electron micrographs of the division site in these mutants exhibit malformed septum with irregular membrane structures. These mutants have a larger division plane with enhanced Bgs1 delivery but fail to enhance accumulation of Bgs4 and several exocytic proteins. Additionally, these mutants show endocytic defects at the division site. This suggests that Cdc42 regulates only specific membrane trafficking events. Our data indicate that while active Cdc42 promotes primary septum synthesis, as cytokinesis progresses Rga4 and Rga6 localize to the division site to decrease Cdc42 activity. This couples specific membrane trafficking events with septum formation to allow proper septum morphology.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract Figure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="472679v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Synopsis&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The GTPase Cdc42 regulates cytokinesis in cell-walled fission yeast. Active Cdc42 promotes the initiation of septum (new cell wall) synthesis to physically divide daughter cells. Here we show that Cdc42 activity must be decreased at the later stages of cytokinesis to enable proper septum formation. Mutants lacking Cdc42 inactivators, Rga4 and Rga6, lead to membrane trafficking defects and malformed septa consequently delaying cell separation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472679" rel="alternate" title="Cdc42 GTPase activating proteins Rga4 and Rga6 coordinate septum synthesis and membrane trafficking at the division plane during cytokinesis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472979</id><title>Chemoproteomics of microbiota metabolites reveals small-molecule agonists for orphan receptor GPRC5A (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.224583+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaohui Zhao</name></author><author><name>Kathryn R. Stein</name></author><author><name>Victor Chen</name></author><author><name>Matthew E. Griffin</name></author><author><name>Howard C. Hang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The microbiota generates diverse metabolites that can engage multiple pathways to modulate host physiology and disease, but their protein targets and mechanism(s) of action have not been fully elucidated. To address this challenge, we focused on indole-3-acetic acid (IAA), a prominent microbiota metabolite, and developed IAA-based chemical reporters for proteomic studies. We discovered that IAA interacts with many proteins in host cells, including small-molecule transporters, receptors and metabolic enzymes. Notably, our functional studies revealed that IAA binds to orphan G protein-coupled receptors such as GPRC5A, but only aromatic monoamines were capable of inducing GPRC5A signaling. Functional profiling of microbiota uncovered specific bacterial species and enzymes that generate GPRC5A agonists. Finally, biochemical characterization of GPRC5A activation identified more potent synthetic agonists as well as key amino acid residues involved in ligand binding. These studies highlight the utility of chemoproteomics to dissect protein targets and mechanisms of action for microbiota metabolites.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472979" rel="alternate" title="Chemoproteomics of microbiota metabolites reveals small-molecule agonists for orphan receptor GPRC5A (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472325</id><title>Monosomy X in isogenic human iPSC-derived trophoblast model impacts expression modules preserved in human placenta (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.224898+00:00</updated><author><name>Darcy T. Ahern</name></author><author><name>Prakhar Bansal</name></author><author><name>Isaac Faustino</name></author><author><name>Yuvabharath Kondaveeti</name></author><author><name>Heather R. Glatt-Deeley</name></author><author><name>Erin C. Banda</name></author><author><name>Stefan F. Pinter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mammalian sex chromosomes encode homologous X/Y gene pairs that were retained on the male Y and escape X chromosome inactivation (XCI) in females. Inferred to reflect X/Y-pair dosage sensitivity, monosomy X is a leading cause of miscarriage in humans with near full penetrance. This phenotype is shared with many other mammals but not the mouse, which offers sophisticated genetic tools to generate sex chromosomal aneuploidy but also tolerates its developmental impact. To address this critical gap, we generated X-monosomic human induced pluripotent stem cells (hiPSCs) alongside otherwise isogenic euploid controls from male and female mosaic samples. Phased genomic variants of these hiPSC panels enable systematic investigation of X/Y dosage-sensitive features using &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; models of human development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we demonstrate the utility of these validated hiPSC lines to test how X/Y-linked gene dosage impacts a widely-used model for the human syncytiotrophoblast. While these isogenic panels trigger a &lt;italic&gt;GATA2/3&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;TFAP2A/C&lt;/italic&gt; -driven trophoblast gene circuit irrespective of karyotype, differential expression implicates monosomy X in altered levels of placental genes, and in secretion of placental growth factor (PlGF) and human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG). Remarkably, weighted gene co-expression network modules that significantly reflect these changes are also preserved in first-trimester chorionic villi and term placenta. Our results suggest monosomy X may skew trophoblast cell type composition, and that the pseudoautosomal region likely plays a key role in these changes, which may facilitate prioritization of haploinsufficient drivers of 45,X extra-embryonic phenotypes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472325" rel="alternate" title="Monosomy X in isogenic human iPSC-derived trophoblast model impacts expression modules preserved in human placenta (3 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473074</id><title>Caveolae mediated endocytosis of VLDL particles in macrophages requires NPC1 and STARD3 for further lysosomal processing (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.225157+00:00</updated><author><name>Lei Deng</name></author><author><name>Frank Vrieling</name></author><author><name>Rinke Stienstra</name></author><author><name>Guido Hooiveld</name></author><author><name>Anouk L. Feitsma</name></author><author><name>Sander Kersten</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Macrophages accumulate triglycerides under certain pathological conditions such as atherosclerosis. Triglycerides are carried in the bloodstream as part of very low-density lipoproteins (VLDL) and chylomicrons. How macrophages take up and process VLDL-lipids is not very well known. Here, using VLDL-sized triglyceride-rich emulsion particles, we aimed to study the mechanism by which VLDL-triglycerides are taken up, processed, and stored in macrophages. Our results show that macrophage uptake of emulsion particles mimicking VLDL (VLDLm) is dependent on lipoproteins lipase (LPL) and requires the lipoprotein-binding C-terminal domain of LPL but not the catalytic N-terminal domain. Subsequent internalization of VLDLm-triglycerides by macrophages is carried out by caveolae-mediated endocytosis, followed by triglyceride hydrolysis catalyzed by lysosomal acid lipase. Transfer of lysosomal fatty acids to the ER for subsequent storage as triglycerides is mediated by Stard3, whereas NPC1 was found to promote the extracellular efflux of fatty acids from lysosomes. Our data provide novel insights into how macrophages process VLDL-derived triglycerides and suggest that macrophages have the remarkable capacity to excrete part of the internalized triglycerides as fatty acids.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473074" rel="alternate" title="Caveolae mediated endocytosis of VLDL particles in macrophages requires NPC1 and STARD3 for further lysosomal processing (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472378</id><title>Water droplet-in-oil digestion method for single-cell proteomics (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.225379+00:00</updated><author><name>Takeshi Masuda</name></author><author><name>Yuma Inamori</name></author><author><name>Arisu Furukawa</name></author><author><name>Kazuki Momosaki</name></author><author><name>Chih-Hsiang Chang</name></author><author><name>Daiki Kobayashi</name></author><author><name>Hiroto Ohguchi</name></author><author><name>Yawara Kawano</name></author><author><name>Shingo Ito</name></author><author><name>Norie Araki</name></author><author><name>Shao-En Ong</name></author><author><name>Sumio Ohtsuki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent advances in single-cell proteomics highlight the promise of sensitive analyses in limited cell populations. However, technical challenges remain for sample recovery, throughput, and versatility. Here, we first report a water droplet-in-oil digestion (WinO) method based on carboxyl-coated beads and phase transfer surfactants for proteomic analysis using limited sample amounts. This method was developed to minimize the contact area between the sample solution and the container to reduce the loss of proteins and peptides by adsorption. This method increased protein and peptide recovery 10-fold as well as the number of quantified transmembrane proteins compared to an in-solution digestion (ISD) method. The proteome profiles obtained from 100 cells using the WinO method highly correlated with those from 10000 cells using the ISD method. We successfully applied the WinO method to single-cell proteomics and quantified 462 proteins. Using the WinO method, samples can be easily prepared in a multi-well plate, making it a widely applicable and suitable method for single-cell proteomics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472378" rel="alternate" title="Water droplet-in-oil digestion method for single-cell proteomics (3 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472381</id><title>A rare human centenarian variant of SIRT6 enhances genome stability and interaction with Lamin A (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.225582+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Simon</name></author><author><name>Jiping Yang</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Gigas</name></author><author><name>Eric J. Earley</name></author><author><name>Tory M. Schaff</name></author><author><name>Lei Zhang</name></author><author><name>Maria Zagorulya</name></author><author><name>Greg Tombline</name></author><author><name>Michael Gilbert</name></author><author><name>Samantha L. Yuen</name></author><author><name>Alexis Pope</name></author><author><name>Michael Van Meter</name></author><author><name>Stephan Emmrich</name></author><author><name>Jeehae Han</name></author><author><name>Seungjin Ryu</name></author><author><name>Archana Tare</name></author><author><name>Yizhou Zhu</name></author><author><name>Adam Hudgins</name></author><author><name>Gil Atzmon</name></author><author><name>Nir Barzilai</name></author><author><name>Aaron Wolfe</name></author><author><name>Kelsey Moody</name></author><author><name>Benjamin A. Garcia</name></author><author><name>David D. Thomas</name></author><author><name>Paul D. Robbins</name></author><author><name>Jan Vijg</name></author><author><name>Andrei Seluanov</name></author><author><name>Yousin Suh</name></author><author><name>Vera Gorbunova</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sirtuin 6 (SIRT6) is a deacylase and mono-ADP ribosyl transferase (mADPr) enzyme involved in multiple cellular pathways implicated in the regulation of aging and metabolism. Targeted sequencing identified a SIRT6 allele containing two linked substitutions (N308K/A313S) as enriched in Ashkenazi Jewish (AJ) centenarians as compared to AJ control individuals. Characterization of this SIRT6 (centSIRT6) allele demonstrated it to be a stronger suppressor of LINE1 retrotransposons, confer enhanced stimulation of DNA double strand break repair, and more robust cancer cell killing compared to the wild type. Surprisingly, centSIRT6 displayed weaker deacetylase activity, but stronger mADPr activity, over a range of NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; concentrations and substrates. Additionally, centSIRT6 displayed a stronger interaction with Lamin A/C (LMNA), which correlated with enhanced ribosylation of LMNA. Our results suggest that enhanced SIRT6 function contributes to human longevity by improving genome maintenance via increased mADPr activity and enhanced interaction with LMNA.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472381" rel="alternate" title="A rare human centenarian variant of SIRT6 enhances genome stability and interaction with Lamin A (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>