<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.737983+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466936</id><title>Bright, fluorogenic and photostable avidity probes for RNA imaging (113 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.738418+00:00</updated><author><name>Bastian Bühler</name></author><author><name>Anja Benderoth</name></author><author><name>Daniel Englert</name></author><author><name>Franziska Grün</name></author><author><name>Janin Schokolowski</name></author><author><name>Andres Jäschke</name></author><author><name>Murat Sunbul</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fluorescent light-up aptamers (FLAPs) emerged as valuable tools to visualize RNA, but are mostly limited by poor brightness, low photostability and high fluorescence background. In this study, we combine bivalent (silicon) rhodamine fluorophores with dimeric FLAPs to yield bright and photostable complexes with low picomolar dissociation constants. Our avidity-based approach resulted in extreme binding strength and high fluorogenicity, enabling single mRNA tracking in living cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466936" rel="alternate" title="Bright, fluorogenic and photostable avidity probes for RNA imaging (113 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467131</id><title>A molecular network of conserved factors keeps ribosomes dormant in the egg (68 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.738855+00:00</updated><author><name>Friederike Leesch</name></author><author><name>Laura Lorenzo-Orts</name></author><author><name>Carina Pribitzer</name></author><author><name>Irina Grishkovskaya</name></author><author><name>Manuel Matzinger</name></author><author><name>Elisabeth Roitinger</name></author><author><name>Katarina Belačić</name></author><author><name>Susanne Kandolf</name></author><author><name>Tzi-Yang Lin</name></author><author><name>Karl Mechtler</name></author><author><name>Anton Meinhart</name></author><author><name>David Haselbach</name></author><author><name>Andrea Pauli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ribosomes are produced in large quantities during oogenesis and stored in the egg. However, the egg and early embryo are translationally repressed. Using mass-spectrometry and cryo-EM analyses of ribosomes isolated from zebrafish and &lt;italic&gt;Xenopus&lt;/italic&gt; eggs and embryos, we provide molecular evidence that ribosomes transition from a dormant to an active state during the first hours of embryogenesis. Dormant ribosomes are associated with four conserved factors that form two modules and occupy functionally important sites of the ribosome: a Habp4-eEF2 module that stabilizes ribosome levels and a Dap1b/Dapl1-eIF5a module that represses translation. Dap1b/Dapl1 is a newly discovered translational inhibitor that stably inserts into the polypeptide exit tunnel. Thus, a developmentally programmed, conserved ribosome state plays a key role in ribosome storage and translational repression in the egg.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467131" rel="alternate" title="A molecular network of conserved factors keeps ribosomes dormant in the egg (68 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466915</id><title>RBBP6 activates the pre-mRNA 3’-end processing machinery in humans (58 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.739310+00:00</updated><author><name>Vytaute Boreikaite</name></author><author><name>Thomas Elliott</name></author><author><name>Jason Chin</name></author><author><name>Lori A Passmore</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;3’-end processing of most human mRNAs is carried out by the cleavage and polyadenylation specificity factor (CPSF; CPF in yeast). Endonucleolytic cleavage of the nascent pre-mRNA defines the 3’-end of the mature transcript, which is important for mRNA localization, translation and stability. Cleavage must therefore be tightly regulated. Here, we reconstitute specific and efficient 3’-endonuclease activity of human CPSF with purified proteins. This requires the sevensubunit CPSF as well as three additional protein factors: cleavage stimulatory factor (CStF), cleavage factor IIm (CFIIm) and, importantly, the multi-domain protein RBBP6. Unlike its yeast homologue Mpe1, which is a stable subunit of CPF, RBBP6 does not copurify with CPSF and is recruited in an RNA-dependent manner. Sequence and mutational analyses suggest that RBBP6 interacts with the WDR33 and CPSF73 subunits of CPSF. Thus, it is likely that the role of RBBP6 is conserved from yeast to human. Overall, our data are consistent with CPSF endonuclease activation and site-specific pre-mRNA cleavage being highly controlled to maintain fidelity in RNA processing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466915" rel="alternate" title="RBBP6 activates the pre-mRNA 3’-end processing machinery in humans (58 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466817</id><title>A powerful and versatile new fixation protocol for immunohistology and in situ hybridization that preserves delicate tissues in planaria (41 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.739762+00:00</updated><author><name>Carlos Guerrero-Hernández</name></author><author><name>Viraj Doddihal</name></author><author><name>Frederick G. Mann</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Sánchez Alvarado</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Whole-mount &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; hybridization (WISH) is a powerful and widely used technique to visualize the expression pattern of genes in different biological systems. Here we describe a new protocol for ISH and immunostaining in the planarian &lt;italic&gt;Schmidtea mediterranea&lt;/italic&gt;. The new Nitric Acid/Formic Acid (NAFA) protocol is compatible with both assays and prevents degradation of the epidermis or blastema. Instead of proteinase K digestion, formic acid treatment is used to permeabilize tissues and preserve antigen epitopes. We show that the NAFA protocol successfully permits development of chromogenic and fluorescent signals &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt;, while preserving the anatomy of the animal. Further, the immunostaining of different proteins was compatible with the NAFA protocol following fluorescent &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; hybridization. Finally, we demonstrate with high resolution confocal imaging that the regeneration blastema is preserved when using the new method. This new NAFA protocol will be a valuable technique to study the process of wounding response and regeneration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466817" rel="alternate" title="A powerful and versatile new fixation protocol for immunohistology and in situ hybridization that preserves delicate tissues in planaria (41 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.465409</id><title>Structural insights into human excitatory amino acid transporter EAAT2 (35 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.740201+00:00</updated><author><name>Takafumi Kato</name></author><author><name>Tsukasa Kusakizako</name></author><author><name>Chunhuan Jin</name></author><author><name>LiLi Quan</name></author><author><name>Ryuichi Ohgaki</name></author><author><name>Suguru Okuda</name></author><author><name>Kan Kobayashi</name></author><author><name>Keitaro Yamashita</name></author><author><name>Tomohiro Nishizawa</name></author><author><name>Yoshikatsu Kanai</name></author><author><name>Osamu Nureki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glutamate is a pivotal excitatory neurotransmitter in mammalian brains, but excessive glutamate causes numerous neural disorders. Almost all extracellular glutamate is retrieved by the glial transporter, Excitatory Amino Acid Transporter 2 (EAAT2), belonging to the SLC1A family. However, in some cancers, EAAT2 expression is enhanced and causes resistance to therapies by metabolic disturbance. Despite its crucial roles, the detailed structural information about EAAT2 has not been available. Here, we report cryo-EM structures of human EAAT2 in substrate-free and selective inhibitor WAY213613-bound states. EAAT2 forms a trimer, with each protomer consisting of transport and scaffold domains. Along with a glutamate-binding site, the transport domain possesses a cavity, that could be disrupted during the transport cycle. WAY213613 occupies both the glutamate-binding site and cavity of EAAT2 to interfere with its alternating access, where the sensitivity is defined by the inner environment of the cavity. This is the first characterization of molecular features of EAAT2 and the selective inhibition mechanism, underlying structure-based drug design for EAAT2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.465409" rel="alternate" title="Structural insights into human excitatory amino acid transporter EAAT2 (35 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.466369</id><title>Structure of mammalian V-ATPase with the TLDc domain protein mEAK7 bound (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.740478+00:00</updated><author><name>Yong Zi Tan</name></author><author><name>Yazan M. Abbas</name></author><author><name>Jing Ze Wu</name></author><author><name>Di Wu</name></author><author><name>Geoffrey G. Hesketh</name></author><author><name>Stephanie A. Bueler</name></author><author><name>Anne-Claude Gingras</name></author><author><name>Carol V. Robinson</name></author><author><name>Sergio Grinstein</name></author><author><name>John L. Rubinstein</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;V-ATPases are rotary proton pumps that serve as signaling hubs, with numerous proposed binding partners in cells. We used cryoEM to detect endogenous proteins that associate with V-ATPase from porcine kidney. A super-stoichiometric copy of subunit C was found in ∼3% of complexes, while an additional ∼1.6% of complexes bound mEAK7, a protein with proposed roles in dauer formation in nematodes and mTOR signaling in mammals. High-resolution cryoEM of porcine kidney V-ATPase with recombinant mEAK7 shows that mEAK7’s TLDc domain, which is found in other proteins proposed to bind V-ATPase, interacts with V-ATPase’s stator while its C-terminal α helix binds V-ATPase’s rotor. This crosslink would be expected to inhibit rotary catalysis. However, exogenous mEAK7 does not inhibit purified V-ATPase activity and mEAK7 overexpression in cells does not alter lysosomal or phagosomal pH. Instead, cryoEM suggests that interaction of mEAK7 with V-ATPase is disrupted by ATP-induced rotation of the rotor. Together, these results reveal how TLDc domains bind V-ATPases and suggest that V-ATPase binding proteins can form labile interactions that are sensitive to the enzyme’s activity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.466369" rel="alternate" title="Structure of mammalian V-ATPase with the TLDc domain protein mEAK7 bound (31 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.464583</id><title>Marker-free coselection for successive rounds of prime editing in human cells (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.740693+00:00</updated><author><name>Sébastien Levesque</name></author><author><name>Diana Mayorga</name></author><author><name>Jean-Philippe Fiset</name></author><author><name>Claudia Goupil</name></author><author><name>Alexis Duringer</name></author><author><name>Andréanne Loiselle</name></author><author><name>Eva Bouchard</name></author><author><name>Daniel Agudelo</name></author><author><name>Yannick Doyon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Prime editing enables the introduction of precise point mutations, small insertions, or short deletions without requiring donor DNA templates. However, editing efficiency remains a key challenge in a broad range of cell types. We designed a robust coselection strategy to perform successive rounds of genetic changes in human cells using CRISPR-Cas nucleases and prime editors. Through coediting, the recovery of cells modified at a target gene of interest is coupled to selection for dominant alleles of the ubiquitous and essential sodium/potassium pump (Na&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;/K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; ATPase). The method improves prime editing efficiency 1.5–10-fold in K562 and HeLa cells, reaching up to 83% of desired alleles in cell populations, for previously optimized prime editing guide RNAs (pegRNAs). Using pegRNAs designed &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt;, we readily engineered homozygous cell lines with cancer-associated or drug resistant &lt;italic&gt;MTOR&lt;/italic&gt; mutations displaying altered mTORC1 signaling. Our approach streamlines the production of cell lines with multiple genetic modifications to create cellular models for biological research and lays the foundation for the development of cell-type specific coselection strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.464583" rel="alternate" title="Marker-free coselection for successive rounds of prime editing in human cells (26 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467109</id><title>Reciprocal zebrafish-medaka hybrids reveal maternal control of zygotic genome activation timing (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.740896+00:00</updated><author><name>Krista R. Gert</name></author><author><name>Luis Enrique Cabrera Quio</name></author><author><name>Maria Novatchkova</name></author><author><name>Yixuan Guo</name></author><author><name>Bradley R. Cairns</name></author><author><name>Andrea Pauli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;After fertilization, the sperm and egg contribute unequally to the newly formed zygote. While the sperm contributes mainly paternal DNA, the egg provides both maternal DNA and the bulk of the future embryonic cytoplasm. Most embryonic processes (like the onset of zygotic transcription) depend on maternally-provided cytoplasmic components, and it is largely unclear whether paternal components besides the centrosome play a role in the regulation of early embryogenesis. Here we report a reciprocal zebrafish-medaka hybrid system as a powerful tool to investigate paternal vs. maternal influence during early development. By combining expression of zebrafish Bouncer on the medaka egg with artificial egg activation, we demonstrate the &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; generation of paternal zebrafish x maternal medaka (reripes) hybrids. These hybrids complement the previously established paternal medaka x maternal zebrafish (latio) hybrids (Herberg et al., 2018). As proof of concept, we investigated maternal vs. paternal control of zygotic genome activation (ZGA) timing using this reciprocal hybrid system. RNA-seq analysis of the purebred fish species and hybrids revealed that the onset of ZGA is primarily governed by the egg. Overall, our study establishes the reciprocal zebrafish-medaka hybrid system as a versatile tool to dissect parental control mechanisms during early development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467109" rel="alternate" title="Reciprocal zebrafish-medaka hybrids reveal maternal control of zygotic genome activation timing (23 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.467034</id><title>NASP maintains histone H3–H4 homeostasis through two distinct H3 binding modes (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.741300+00:00</updated><author><name>Hongyu Bao</name></author><author><name>Massimo Carraro</name></author><author><name>Valentin Flury</name></author><author><name>Yanhong Liu</name></author><author><name>Min Luo</name></author><author><name>Liu Chen</name></author><author><name>Anja Groth</name></author><author><name>Hongda Huang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Histone chaperones regulate all aspects of histone metabolism. NASP is a major histone chaperone for H3–H4 dimers critical for preventing histone degradation. Here, we identify two distinct histone binding modes of NASP and reveal how they cooperate to ensure histone H3–H4 supply. We determine the structures of a sNASP dimer, a complex of sNASP with an H3 α3 peptide, and the sNASP–H3–H4–ASF1b co-chaperone complex. This captures distinct functionalities of NASP and identifies two distinct binding modes involving the H3 α3 helix and the H3 αN region, respectively. Functional studies demonstrate the H3 αN-interaction represents the major binding mode of NASP in cells and shielding of the H3 αN region by NASP is essential in maintaining the H3–H4 histone soluble pool. In conclusion, our studies uncover the molecular basis of NASP as a major H3–H4 chaperone in guarding histone homeostasis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.467034" rel="alternate" title="NASP maintains histone H3–H4 homeostasis through two distinct H3 binding modes (21 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467477</id><title>Age-induced P-bodies become detrimental and shorten the lifespan of yeast (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.741582+00:00</updated><author><name>Joonhyuk Choi</name></author><author><name>Shuhao Wang</name></author><author><name>Yang Li</name></author><author><name>Nan Hao</name></author><author><name>Brian M Zid</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aging is an irreversible process characterized by a progressive loss of homeostasis in cells, which often manifests as protein aggregates. Recently, it has been speculated that aggregates of RNA-binding proteins (RBPs) may go through pathological transitions during aging and drive the progression of age-associated neurodegenerative diseases. Using Saccharomyces cerevisiae as a model system of aging, we find that P-bodies - an RBP granule that is formed and can be beneficial for cell growth during stress conditions - naturally form during aging without any external stresses and an increase in P-body intensity is negatively correlated with the future lifespan of yeast cells. When mother cells transfer age-induced P-bodies to daughter cells, the mother cells extend lifespan, while the daughter cells grow poorly, suggesting that these age-induced P-bodies may be directly pathological. Furthermore, we find that suppressing acidification of the cytosol during aging slows down the increase in the intensity of P-body foci and extends lifespan. Our data suggest that acidification of the cytosol may facilitate the pathological transition of RBP granules during aging.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467477" rel="alternate" title="Age-induced P-bodies become detrimental and shorten the lifespan of yeast (19 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467461</id><title>Design, construction and optimization of a synthetic RNA polymerase operon in Escherichia coli. (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.741907+00:00</updated><author><name>Joep Houkes</name></author><author><name>Lorenzo Olivi</name></author><author><name>Zacharie Paquet</name></author><author><name>Nico J Claassens</name></author><author><name>John van der Oost</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Prokaryotic genes encoding functionally related proteins are often clustered in operons. The compact structure of operons allows for co-transcription of the genes, and for co-translation of the polycistronic messenger RNA to the corresponding proteins. This leads to reduced regulatory complexity and enhanced gene expression efficiency, and as such to an overall metabolic benefit for the protein production process in bacteria and archaea. Interestingly, the genes encoding the subunits of one of the most conserved and ubiquitous protein complexes, the RNA polymerase, are not clustered in a single operon. Rather, its genes are scattered in all known prokaryotic genomes, generally integrated in different ribosomal operons. To analyze the impact of this genetic organization on the fitness of Escherichia coli, we constructed a bacterial artificial chromosome harboring the genes encoding the RNA polymerase complex in a single operon. Subsequent deletion of the native chromosomal genes led to a reduced growth on minimal medium. However, by using adaptive laboratory evolution the growth rate was restored to wild-type level. Hence, we show that a highly conserved genetic organization of core genes in a bacterium can be reorganized by a combination of design, construction and optimization, yielding a well-functioning synthetic genetic architecture.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467461" rel="alternate" title="Design, construction and optimization of a synthetic RNA polymerase operon in Escherichia coli. (16 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.06.467542</id><title>Shaping the size of a neuronal lineage: the role of Imp and Syp RBPs in the precise elimination of neurons by apoptosis. (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.742155+00:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan ENRIQUEZ</name></author><author><name>Wenyue GUAN</name></author><author><name>Mathilde BOUCHET</name></author><author><name>Aurelien DARMAS</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neuronal stem cells produce a finite and stereotyped number of neuronal progenies. This process must be finely regulated during development and adult stages to ensure proper brain function.  In Drosophila, stem cells, called Neuroblasts, produce an invariant number of neurons. Two RNA binding proteins, Imp and Syp, play a central role in controlling the speed of division and the end of the proliferative phase of individual NBs, two parameters that influences the final number of neurons produced. Here, we have discovered a novel function for Imp and Syp, where both RBPs shape the number of neurons produced by a stem cell by controlling program cell death (PCD) in immature neurons. By studying a neuroblast lineage, called Lin A/15, which produces motoneurons (MNs) and glia, we have demonstrated that Lin A/15 stem cell spends 40% of its time producing immature MNs which are eliminated by apoptosis. We have revealed that only the first born MNs (Imp +) survive while the last born MNs (Imp- Syp+) are eliminated by apoptosis. Both RBPs play a central role in neuronal survival, Imp promotes neuronal survival while Syp promotes cell death in immature motoneurons. Interestingly their opposite temporal gradient in Lin A/15 stem cell also determines the end of Lin A/15 stem cell neurogenesis by PCD. Both RNA binding proteins are conserved in vertebrates and seem to play a central role in the number of neurons produce during development. The Drosophila model and its genetic tools offer a unique chance to decipher their function in neural stem cell versus immature neurons.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.06.467542" rel="alternate" title="Shaping the size of a neuronal lineage: the role of Imp and Syp RBPs in the precise elimination of neurons by apoptosis. (15 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467106</id><title>Cas9-Assisted Biological Containment of a Genetically Engineered Human Commensal Bacterium and Genetic Elements (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.742505+00:00</updated><author><name>Naoki Hayashi</name></author><author><name>Yong Lai</name></author><author><name>Mark Mimee</name></author><author><name>Timothy K. Lu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sophisticated gene circuits built by synthetic biology can enable bacteria to sense their environment and respond predictably. Biosensing bacteria can potentially probe the human gut microbiome to prevent, diagnose, or treat disease. To provide robust biocontainment for engineered bacteria, we devised a Cas9-assisted auxotrophic biocontainment system combining thymidine auxotrophy, an Engineered Riboregulator (ER) for controlled gene expression, and a CRISPR Device (CD). The CD prevents the engineered bacteria from acquiring &lt;italic&gt;thyA&lt;/italic&gt; via horizontal gene transfer, which would disrupt the biocontainment system, and inhibits the spread of genetic elements by killing bacteria harboring the gene cassette. This system tunably controlled gene expression in the human gut commensal bacterium &lt;italic&gt;Bacteroides thetaiotaomicron&lt;/italic&gt;, prevented escape from thymidine auxotrophy, and blocked transgene dissemination for at least 10 days. These capabilities were validated &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo.&lt;/italic&gt; This biocontainment system exemplifies a powerful strategy for bringing genetically engineered microorganisms safely into biomedicine.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467106" rel="alternate" title="Cas9-Assisted Biological Containment of a Genetically Engineered Human Commensal Bacterium and Genetic Elements (13 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.466744</id><title>Live-cell chromosome dynamics in Arabidopsis thaliana reveals increased chromatin mobility in response to DNA damage (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.742720+00:00</updated><author><name>Anis Meschichi</name></author><author><name>Svenja Reeck</name></author><author><name>Adrien Sicard</name></author><author><name>Frédéric Pontvianne</name></author><author><name>Stefanie Rosa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Double-strand breaks (DSBs) are a particularly deleterious type of DNA damage potentially leading to translocations and genome instability. Homologous recombination (HR) is a conservative repair pathway in which intact homologous sequences are used as a template for repair. How damaged DNA molecules search for homologous sequences in the crowded space of the cell nucleus is, however, still poorly understood. Here, we measured global chromosome and DSB site mobility, in &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt;, using &lt;italic&gt;lacO&lt;/italic&gt;/LacI tagged lines and two GFP-tagged HR regulators, RAD51 and RAD54. We observed an increase in chromatin mobility upon the induction of DNA damage, specifically at the S/G2 phases of the cell cycle. Importantly, this increase in mobility was lost in &lt;italic&gt;sog1-1&lt;/italic&gt; mutant, a central transcription factor of the DNA damage response (DDR), indicating that repair mechanisms actively regulate chromatin mobility upon DNA damage. Interestingly, we observed that DSB sites show remarkably high mobility levels at the early HR stage. Subsequently, a drastic decrease of DSB mobility is observed, which seems to be associated to the relocation of DSBs to the nucleus periphery. Altogether, our data suggest that changes in chromatin mobility are triggered in response to DNA damage, and that this may act as a mechanism to enhance the physical search within the nuclear space to locate a homologous template during homology-directed DNA repair.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.466744" rel="alternate" title="Live-cell chromosome dynamics in Arabidopsis thaliana reveals increased chromatin mobility in response to DNA damage (12 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.467017</id><title>RAP1 regulates TIP60 function during fate transition between 2 cell-like and pluripotent states (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.742887+00:00</updated><author><name>Raymond Mario Barry</name></author><author><name>Olivia Sacco</name></author><author><name>Amel Mameri</name></author><author><name>Martin Stojaspal</name></author><author><name>William Kartsonis</name></author><author><name>Pooja Shah</name></author><author><name>Pablo De Ioannes</name></author><author><name>Ctirad Hofr</name></author><author><name>Jacques Côté</name></author><author><name>Agnel Sfeir</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In mammals, the conserved telomere binding protein RAP1 serves a diverse set of non- telomeric functions including activation of the NF-kB signaling pathway, maintenance of metabolic function &lt;italic&gt;in vivo,&lt;/italic&gt; and transcriptional regulation. Here, we uncover the mechanism by which RAP1 modulates gene expression. Using a separation-of-function allele, we show that RAP1 transcriptional regulation is independent of TRF2-mediated binding to telomeres and does not involve direct binding to genomic loci. Instead, RAP1 interacts with the TIP60/p400 complex and modulates its histone acetyltransferase activity. Notably, we show that deletion of RAP1 in mouse embryonic stem cells increases the fraction of 2-cell-like cells. Specifically, RAP1 enhances the repressive activity of Tip60/p400 across a subset of 2-cell-stage genes, including &lt;italic&gt;Zscan4&lt;/italic&gt; and the endogenous retrovirus MERVL. Preferential upregulation of genes proximal to MERVL elements in Rap1 deficient settings implicate these endogenous retroviral elements in the de- repression of proximal genes. Altogether, our study reveals an unprecedented link between RAP1 and TIP60/p400 complex in the regulation of totipotency.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.467017" rel="alternate" title="RAP1 regulates TIP60 function during fate transition between 2 cell-like and pluripotent states (12 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466589</id><title>Loop-extrusion and polymer phase-separation can co-exist at the single-molecule level to shape chromatin folding (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.743081+00:00</updated><author><name>Mattia Conte</name></author><author><name>Ehsan Irani</name></author><author><name>Andrea M. Chiariello</name></author><author><name>Alex Abraham</name></author><author><name>Simona Bianco</name></author><author><name>Andrea Esposito</name></author><author><name>Mario Nicodemi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Loop-extrusion and phase-separation have been proposed as mechanisms that shape chromosome large-scale spatial organization. It is unclear, however, how they perform relative to each other in explaining chromatin architecture data and whether they compete or co-exist at the single-molecule level. Here, we compare models of polymer physics based on loop-extrusion and phase-separation, as well as models where both mechanisms act simultaneously in a single molecule, against multiplexed FISH data available in human loci in IMR90 and HCT116 cells. We find that the different models recapitulate bulk Hi-C and average microscopy data. Single-molecule chromatin conformations are also well captured, especially by phase-separation based models that better reflect the experimentally reported segregation in globules of the considered genomic loci and their cell-to-cell structural variability. Such a variability is consistent with two main concurrent causes: single-cell epigenetic heterogeneity and an intrinsic thermodynamic conformational degeneracy of folding. Overall, the model combining loop-extrusion and polymer phase-separation provides a very good description of the data, particularly higher-order contacts, showing that the two mechanisms can co-exist in shaping chromatin architecture in single cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466589" rel="alternate" title="Loop-extrusion and polymer phase-separation can co-exist at the single-molecule level to shape chromatin folding (10 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467241</id><title>Intracellular development and impact of a eukaryotic parasite on its zombified microalgal host in the marine plankton (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.743255+00:00</updated><author><name>Johan Decelle</name></author><author><name>Ehsan Kayal</name></author><author><name>Estelle Bigeard</name></author><author><name>Benoit Gallet</name></author><author><name>Jeremy Bougoure</name></author><author><name>Peta Clode</name></author><author><name>Nicole Schieber</name></author><author><name>Rachel Templin</name></author><author><name>Elisabeth Hegenberger</name></author><author><name>Gerard Prensier</name></author><author><name>Fabien Chevalier</name></author><author><name>Yannick Schwab</name></author><author><name>Laure Guillou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Parasites are widespread and diverse in the oceanic plankton, and many of them infect single-celled algae for survival. How these parasites develop and scavenge energy within the host and whether the cellular organization and metabolism of the host is altered remain open questions. Combining quantitative structural and chemical imaging with time-resolved transcriptomics, we unveil dramatic morphological and metabolic changes of the parasite Amoebophrya (Syndiniales) during intracellular infection (e.g. 200-fold increase of mitochondrion volume), particularly following digestion of nutrient-rich host chromosomes. Some of these changes are also found in the apicomplexan parasites (e.g. sequential acristate and cristate mitochondrion, switch from glycolysis to TCA), thus underlining key evolutionary-conserved mechanisms. In the algal host, energy-producing organelles (chloroplast) remain intact during most of the infection, but sugar reserves diminish while lipid droplets increase. Thus, rapid infection of the host nucleus could be a zombifying strategy to digest nutrient-rich chromosomes and escape cytoplasmic defense while benefiting from the maintained C-energy production of the host cell.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467241" rel="alternate" title="Intracellular development and impact of a eukaryotic parasite on its zombified microalgal host in the marine plankton (10 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467377</id><title>Discrete-to-analog signal conversion in human pluripotent stem cells (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.743760+00:00</updated><author><name>Laura Prochazka</name></author><author><name>Peter W Zandstra</name></author><author><name>Yale S Michaels</name></author><author><name>Charles Lau</name></author><author><name>Mona Siu</name></author><author><name>Ting Yin</name></author><author><name>Diana Wu</name></author><author><name>Esther Jang</name></author><author><name>Ross D Jones</name></author><author><name>Mercedes Vazquez-Cantu</name></author><author><name>Penney M Gilbert</name></author><author><name>Himanshu Kaul</name></author><author><name>Yaakov Benenson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During development, state transitions are coordinated through changes in the identity of molecular regulators in a cell state- and dose specific manner. The ability to rationally engineer such functions in human pluripotent stem cells (hPSC) will enable numerous applications in regenerative medicine. Herein we report the generation of synthetic gene circuits that can detect a discrete cell state, and upon state detection, produce fine-tuned effector proteins in a programmable manner. Effectively, these gene circuits convert a discrete (digital-like) cell state into an analog signal by merging AND-like logic integration of endogenous miRNAs (classifiers) with a miRNA-mediated output fine-tuning technology (miSFITs). Using an automated miRNA identification and model-guided circuit optimization approach, we were able to produce robust cell state specific and graded output production in undifferentiated hPSC. We further finely controlled the levels of endogenous BMP4 secretion, which allowed us to document the effect of endogenous factor secretion in comparison to exogenous factor addition on early tissue development using the hPSC-derived gastruloid system.  Our work provides the first demonstration of a discrete-to-analog signal conversion circuit operating in living hPSC, and a platform for customized cell state-specific control of desired physiological factors, laying the foundation for programming cell compositions in hPSC-derived tissues and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467377" rel="alternate" title="Discrete-to-analog signal conversion in human pluripotent stem cells (9 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467226</id><title>Disease-linked mutations trigger exposure of a protein quality control degron in the DHFR protein (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.746426+00:00</updated><author><name>Caroline Kampmeyer</name></author><author><name>Sven Larsen-Ledet</name></author><author><name>Morten Rose Wagnkilde</name></author><author><name>Mathias Michelsen</name></author><author><name>Henriette K. M. Iversen</name></author><author><name>Sofie V. Nielsen</name></author><author><name>Søren Lindemose</name></author><author><name>Alberto Caregnato</name></author><author><name>Tommer Ravid</name></author><author><name>Amelie Stein</name></author><author><name>Kaare Teilum</name></author><author><name>Kresten Lindorff-Larsen</name></author><author><name>Rasmus Hartmann-Petersen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Degrons are short stretches of amino acids or structural motifs that are embedded in proteins. They mediate recognition by E3 ubiquitin-protein ligases and thus confer protein degradation via the ubiquitin-proteasome system. Well-described degrons include the N-degrons, destruction boxes, and the PIP degrons, which mediate the controlled degradation of various proteins including signaling components and cell cycle regulators. In comparison, the so-called protein quality control (PQC) degrons that mediate the degradation of structurally destabilized or misfolded proteins are not well described. Here, we show that disease-linked DHFR missense variants are structurally destabilized and chaperone-dependent proteasome targets. We systematically mapped regions within DHFR to assess those that act as cytosolic PQC degrons in yeast cells. Two regions, DHFR-Deg13-36 (here Deg1) and DHFR-Deg61-84 (here Deg2), act as degrons and conferred degradation to unrelated fusion partners. The proteasomal turnover of Deg2 was dependent on the molecular chaperone Hsp70. Structural analyses by NMR and hydrogen/deuterium exchange revealed that Deg2 is buried in wild-type DHFR, but becomes transiently exposed in the disease-linked missense variants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467226" rel="alternate" title="Disease-linked mutations trigger exposure of a protein quality control degron in the DHFR protein (8 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466973</id><title>Fendrr synergizes with Wnt signalling to regulate fibrosis related genes during lung development (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.747058+00:00</updated><author><name>Tamer Ali</name></author><author><name>Sandra Rogala</name></author><author><name>Maria-Theodora Melissari</name></author><author><name>Sandra Währisch</name></author><author><name>Bernhard G Herrmann</name></author><author><name>Phillip Grote</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Long non-coding RNAs are a very versatile class of molecules that can have important roles in regulating a cells function, including regulating other genes on the transcriptional level. One of these mechanisms is that RNA can directly interact with DNA thereby recruiting additional components such as proteins to these sites via a RNA:dsDNA triplex formation. We genetically deleted the triplex forming sequence (&lt;italic&gt;FendrrBox&lt;/italic&gt;) from the lncRNA &lt;italic&gt;Fendrr&lt;/italic&gt; in mice and find that this &lt;italic&gt;FendrrBox&lt;/italic&gt; is partially required for &lt;italic&gt;Fendrr&lt;/italic&gt; function &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. We find that the loss of the triplex forming site in developing lungs causes a dysregulation of gene programs, associated with lung fibrosis. A set of these genes contain a triplex site directly at their promoter and are expressed in fibroblasts. We find that &lt;italic&gt;Fendrr&lt;/italic&gt; with the Wnt signaling pathway regulates these genes, implicating that &lt;italic&gt;Fendrr&lt;/italic&gt; synergizes with Wnt signaling in lung fibrosis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466973" rel="alternate" title="Fendrr synergizes with Wnt signalling to regulate fibrosis related genes during lung development (8 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466992</id><title>Epithelial-mesenchymal transition is the main driver of intrinsic metabolism in cancer cell lines (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.747436+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah Cherkaoui</name></author><author><name>Stephan Durot</name></author><author><name>Jenna Bradley</name></author><author><name>Susan Critchlow</name></author><author><name>Sebastien Dubuis</name></author><author><name>Mauro Miguel Masiero</name></author><author><name>Rebekka Wegmann</name></author><author><name>Berend Snijder</name></author><author><name>Alaa Othman</name></author><author><name>Claus Bendtsen</name></author><author><name>Nicola Zamboni</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A fundamental feature of cancer cells is genomic heterogeneity. It is a main driver of phenotypic differences, including the response to drugs, and therefore a key factor in therapy selection. Motivated by the increasing role attributed to metabolic reprogramming in tumor development, we wondered how genomic heterogeneity affects metabolic phenotype. To this end, we profiled the intracellular metabolome of 180 cancer cell lines grown in similar conditions to exclude environmental factors. For each cell line, we estimate activity for 49 pathways across the whole metabolic network. Upon clustering of activity data, we found a convergence into only two major metabolic types. These were further characterized by 13C-flux analysis, lipidomics, and analysis of sensitivity to perturbations. These experiments revealed differences in lipid, mitochondrial, and carbohydrate metabolism between the two major types. Finally, a thorough integration of our metabolic data with multiple omics data revealed a strong association with markers of epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT). Our analysis indicates that in absence of variations imposed by the microenvironment, the metabolism of cancer cell lines falls into only two major classes despite genetic heterogeneity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466992" rel="alternate" title="Epithelial-mesenchymal transition is the main driver of intrinsic metabolism in cancer cell lines (8 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466921</id><title>A life cycle alteration can correct molting defects in Caenorhabditis elegans (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.747976+00:00</updated><author><name>Shaonil Binti</name></author><author><name>Rosa V. Melinda</name></author><author><name>Braveen B. Joseph</name></author><author><name>Phil Edeen</name></author><author><name>Sam D. Miller</name></author><author><name>David S. Fay</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Molting is a widespread feature in the development of many invertebrates, including nematodes and arthropods. In &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/italic&gt;, the highly conserved protein kinases NEKL-2/NEK8/9 and NEKL-3/NEK6/7 (NEKLs) promote molting through their involvement in the uptake and intracellular trafficking of epidermal cargos. We found that the relative requirements for NEKL-2 and NEKL-3 differed at different life-cycle stages and under different environmental conditions. Most notably, the transition from the second to the third larval stage (L2→L3 molt) required a higher level of NEKL function than during several other life stages or when animals had experienced starvation at the L1 stage. Specifically, larvae that entered the pre-dauer L2d stage could escape molting defects when transiting to the (non-dauer) L3 stage. Consistent with this, mutations that promote entry into L2d suppressed &lt;italic&gt;nekl&lt;/italic&gt;-associated molting defects, whereas mutations that inhibit L2d entry reduced starvation-mediated suppression. We further showed that loss or reduction of NEKL functions led to defects in the transcription of cyclically expressed molting genes, many of which are under the control of systemic steroid hormone regulation. Moreover, the timing and severity of these transcriptional defects correlated closely with the strength of &lt;italic&gt;nekl&lt;/italic&gt; alleles and with their stage of arrest. Interestingly, transit through L2d rescued &lt;italic&gt;nekl&lt;/italic&gt;-associated expression defects in suppressed worms, providing an example of how life-cycle decisions can impact subsequent developmental events. Given that NEKLs are implicated in the uptake of sterols by the epidermis, we propose that loss of NEKLs leads to a physiological reduction in steroid-hormone signaling and consequent defects in the transcription of genes required for molting.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466921" rel="alternate" title="A life cycle alteration can correct molting defects in Caenorhabditis elegans (7 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.466970</id><title>PGC-1α in the myofibers regulates the balance between myogenic and adipogenic progenitors affecting muscle regeneration (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.748440+00:00</updated><author><name>Marc Beltrà</name></author><author><name>Fabrizio Pin</name></author><author><name>Domiziana Costamagna</name></author><author><name>Robin Duelen</name></author><author><name>Alessandra Renzini</name></author><author><name>Riccardo Ballarò</name></author><author><name>Lorena Garcia-Castillo</name></author><author><name>Ambra Iannuzzi</name></author><author><name>Viviana Moresi</name></author><author><name>Dario Coletti</name></author><author><name>Maurilio Sampaolesi</name></author><author><name>Fabio Penna</name></author><author><name>Paola Costelli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Skeletal muscle repair is accomplished by satellite cells (MuSC) in cooperation with interstitial stromal cells (ISCs). So far, the relationship between the function of these cells and the metabolic state of myofibers remains unclear. The present study reports alterations in the proportion of both MuSCs and adipogenesis regulators (Aregs) induced by overexpression of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma coactivator 1-alpha (PGC-1α) in the myofibers (MCK-PGC-1α mice). Although PGC-1α–driven increase of MuSCs does not accelerate muscle regeneration, myogenic progenitors isolated from MCK-PGC-1α mice and transplanted into intact and regenerating muscles are more prone to fuse with recipient myofibers than those derived from WT donors. Moreover, both young and aged MCK-PGC-1α animals show reduced perilipin-positive areas when challenged with an adipogenic stimulus, demonstrating low propensity to accumulate adipocytes within the muscle. These results provide new insights on the role played by PGC-1α in promoting myogenesis and hindering adipogenesis in the skeletal muscle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.466970" rel="alternate" title="PGC-1α in the myofibers regulates the balance between myogenic and adipogenic progenitors affecting muscle regeneration (7 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466878</id><title>Reconstitution of ATP-dependent 3’-cleavage of mammalian pre-mRNA reveals a central role of RBBP6 (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.749867+00:00</updated><author><name>Moritz Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Florian Kluge</name></author><author><name>Felix Sandmeir</name></author><author><name>Peter Schäfer</name></author><author><name>Christian Tüting</name></author><author><name>Christian Ihling</name></author><author><name>Uwe Kühn</name></author><author><name>Elena Conti</name></author><author><name>Elmar Wahle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The 3’ ends of almost all eukaryotic mRNAs are generated in an essential two-step processing reaction, endonucleolytic cleavage of an extended precursor followed by the addition of a poly(A) tail. By reconstituting the reaction from overproduced and purified proteins, we provide a minimal list of fourteen polypeptides essential and two stimulatory for RNA cleavage. In a reaction depending on the polyadenylation signal AAUAAA, the reconstituted system cleaves pre-mRNA at a single preferred site corresponding to the one used &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Among the proteins, Cleavage Factor I stimulates cleavage but is not essential, consistent with its prominent role in alternative polyadenylation. RBBP6 is required, structural data showing it to contact and presumably activate the endonuclease CPSF73 through its DWNN domain. The C-terminal domain of RNA polymerase II is dispensable. ATP, but not its hydrolysis, supports RNA cleavage by binding to the hClp1 subunit of cleavage factor II with submicromolar affinity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466878" rel="alternate" title="Reconstitution of ATP-dependent 3’-cleavage of mammalian pre-mRNA reveals a central role of RBBP6 (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467472</id><title>Discovery of a carbonic anhydrase-Rubisco supercomplex within the alpha-carboxysome (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.750283+00:00</updated><author><name>Cecilia Blikstad</name></author><author><name>Eli J Dugan</name></author><author><name>Thomas G Laughlin</name></author><author><name>Mira D Liu</name></author><author><name>Sophie R Shoemaker</name></author><author><name>Jonathan P Remis</name></author><author><name>David F Savage</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Carboxysomes are proteinaceous organelles that encapsulate key enzymes of CO2 fixation, Rubisco and carbonic anhydrase, and are the centerpiece of the bacterial CO2 concentrating mechanism (CCM). In the CCM, actively accumulated cytosolic bicarbonate diffuses into the carboxysome and is converted to CO2 by carbonic anhydrase, producing a high CO2 concentration near Rubisco and ensuring efficient carboxylation. Self-assembly of the α-carboxysome is orchestrated by the intrinsically disordered scaffolding protein, CsoS2, which interacts with both Rubisco and carboxysomal shell proteins, but it is unknown how CsoSCA, the carbonic anhydrase, is incorporated into the α-carboxysome. Here, we present the structural basis of carbonic anhydrase encapsulation into α-carboxysomes from Halothiobacillus neapolitanus. We find that CsoSCA interacts directly with Rubisco via an intrinsically disordered N-terminal domain. A 1.98 Å single-particle cryo-electron microscopy structure of Rubisco in complex with this peptide reveals that CsoSCA binding is predominantly mediated by a network of hydrogen bonds. CsoSCAs binding site overlaps with that of CsoS2 but the two proteins utilize substantially different motifs and modes of binding, revealing a plasticity of the Rubisco binding site. Our results advance the understanding of biogenesis of carboxysomes and highlights the importance of Rubisco, not only as an enzyme, but also as a hub protein central for assembling supercomplexes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467472" rel="alternate" title="Discovery of a carbonic anhydrase-Rubisco supercomplex within the alpha-carboxysome (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467353</id><title>SHIP164 is a Chorein Motif Containing Lipid Transport Protein that Controls Membrane Dynamics and Traffic at the Endosome-Golgi Interface. (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.750528+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael G Hanna</name></author><author><name>Patreece Suen</name></author><author><name>Yumei Wu</name></author><author><name>Karin M Reinisch</name></author><author><name>Pietro De Camilli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cellular membranes differ in protein and lipid composition as well as in the protein-lipid ratio. Thus, progression of membranous organelles along traffic routes requires mechanisms to control bilayer lipid chemistry and their abundance relative to proteins. The recent structural and functional characterization of VPS13-family proteins has suggested a mechanism through which lipids can be transferred in bulk from one membrane to another at membrane contact sites, and thus independently of vesicular traffic. Here we show that SHIP164 (UHRF1BP1L) shares structural and lipid transfer properties with these proteins and is localized on a subpopulation of vesicle clusters in the early endocytic pathway whose membrane cargo includes the cation-independent mannose-6-phosphate receptor (MPR) and ATG9.  Loss of SHIP164 disrupts retrograde traffic of these organelles to the Golgi complex.  Our findings raise the possibility that bulk transfer of lipids to endocytic membranes may play a role in their traffic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467353" rel="alternate" title="SHIP164 is a Chorein Motif Containing Lipid Transport Protein that Controls Membrane Dynamics and Traffic at the Endosome-Golgi Interface. (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467176</id><title>A microRNA cluster downstream of the selector gene Fezf2 coordinates fate specification with dendritic branching in cortical neurons (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.750855+00:00</updated><author><name>Asha Iyer</name></author><author><name>Verl B Siththanandan</name></author><author><name>Victoria Lu</name></author><author><name>Ramesh Nair</name></author><author><name>Lee O. Vaasjo</name></author><author><name>Maria J Galazo</name></author><author><name>Suzanne Tharin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the cerebral cortex, cortical projection neurons comprise classes of neurons project to distant regions of the central nervous system. These neurons develop from the same progenitor pool, but they acquire strikingly different inputs and outputs to underpin strikingly different functions. The question of how corticospinal projection neurons - involved in motor function and implicated in paralysis - and callosal projection neurons - involved in cognitive function and implicated in autism - develop represents a fundamental and clinically important question in neurodevelopment. A network of transcription factors, including the selector gene Fezf2, is central to specifying cortical projection neuron fates. Gene regulation up- and down-stream of these transcription factors, however, is not well understood, particularly as it relates to the development of the major inputs to cortical projection neurons. Here we show that the miR-193b~365 microRNA cluster downstream of Fezf2 cooperatively represses the signaling molecule Mapk8, and impacts dendritic branching of cortical projection neurons.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467176" rel="alternate" title="A microRNA cluster downstream of the selector gene Fezf2 coordinates fate specification with dendritic branching in cortical neurons (5 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467016</id><title>Repeats Mimic Immunostimulatory Viral Features Across a Vast Evolutionary Landscape (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.751273+00:00</updated><author><name>Petr Šulc</name></author><author><name>Alexander Solovyov</name></author><author><name>Sajid A Marhon</name></author><author><name>Siyu Sun</name></author><author><name>John A LaCava</name></author><author><name>Omar I. Abdel-Wahab</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Vabret</name></author><author><name>Daniel De Carvalho</name></author><author><name>Rémi Monasson</name></author><author><name>Simona Cocco</name></author><author><name>Benjamin D. Greenbaum</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;An emerging hallmark across many human diseases – such as cancer, autoimmune and neurodegenerative disorders – is the aberrant transcription of typically silenced repetitive elements. Once transcribed they can mimic pathogen-associated molecular patterns and bind pattern recognition receptors, thereby engaging the innate immune system and triggering inflammation in a process known as viral mimicry. Yet how to quantify pathogen mimicry, and the degree to which it is shaped by natural selection, remains a gap in our understanding of both genome evolution and the immunological basis of disease. Here we propose a theoretical framework that combines recent biological observations with statistical physics and population genetics to quantify the selective forces on virus-like features generated by repeats and integrate these forces into predictive evolutionary models. We establish that many repeat families have evolutionarily maintained specific classes of viral mimicry. We show that for HSATII and intact LINE-1 selective forces maintain CpG motifs, while for a set of SINE and LINE elements the formation of long double-stranded RNA is more prevalent than expected from a neutral evolutionary model. We validate our models by showing predicted immunostimulatory inverted SINE elements bind the MDA5 receptor under conditions of epigenetic dysregulation and that they are disproportionately present during intron retention when RNA splicing is pharmacologically inhibited. We conclude viral mimicry is a general evolutionary mechanism whereby genomes co-opt features generated by repetitive sequences to trigger the immune system, acting as a quality control system to flag genome dysregulation. We demonstrate these evolutionary principles can be learned and applied to predictive models. Our work therefore serves as a resource to identify repeats with candidate immunostimulatory features and leverage them therapeutically.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467016" rel="alternate" title="Repeats Mimic Immunostimulatory Viral Features Across a Vast Evolutionary Landscape (5 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466736</id><title>Optimality of extracellular enzyme production and activity in dynamic flux balance modeling (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.751608+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael Quintin</name></author><author><name>Ilija Dukovski</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Bhatnagar</name></author><author><name>Daniel Segrè</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In microbial communities, many vital metabolic functions, including the degradation of cellulose, proteins and other complex macromolecules, are carried out by costly, extracellularly secreted enzymes. While significant effort has been dedicated to analyzing genome-scale metabolic networks for individual microbes and communities, little is known about the interplay between global allocation of metabolic resources in the cell and extracellular enzyme secretion and activity. Here we introduce a method for modeling the secretion and catalytic functions of extracellular enzymes using dynamic flux balance analysis. This new addition, implemented within COMETS (Computation Of Microbial Ecosystems in Time and Space), simulates the costly production and secretion of enzymes and their diffusion and activity throughout the environment, independent of the producing organism. After tuning our model based on data for a &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; strain engineered to produce exogenous cellulases, we explored the dynamics of the system at different cellulose concentrations and enzyme production rates. We found that there are distinct rates of constitutive enzyme secretion which maximize either growth rate or biomass yield. These optimal rates are strongly dependent on enzyme kinetic properties and environmental conditions, including the amount of cellulose substrate available. Our framework will facilitate the development of more realistic simulations of microbial community dynamics within environments rich in complex macromolecules, with applications in the study of soil and plant-associated ecosystems, and other natural and engineered microbiomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many organisms - including soil, marine and human-associated bacteria and fungi - perform part of their metabolic functions outside of the boundary of the cell, through the secretion of extracellular enzymes that can diffuse and facilitate reactions independently of the organism that produced them. In order to better understand and predict microbial ecosystems, it would be helpful to create mathematical models incorporating these extracellular reactions within simulations of metabolism at the whole-cell level. In this paper we demonstrate the implementation of such a methodology and apply it to study a cellulase-secreting yeast. This work will be useful for a number of microbial ecology applications, including modeling of microbiome dynamics, engineering of bioproducts (e.g. biofuels) from plant biomass through synthetic communities or modified organisms, and testing of basic ecological hypotheses about the balance between cost and benefits of the production of common goods in microbial communities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466736" rel="alternate" title="Optimality of extracellular enzyme production and activity in dynamic flux balance modeling (5 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467269</id><title>The Conformational Plasticity of the Selectivity Filter Methionines Controls the In-Cell Cu(I) Uptake through the CTR1 transporter (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.752010+00:00</updated><author><name>Pavel Janoš</name></author><author><name>Jana Aupič</name></author><author><name>Sharon Ruthstein</name></author><author><name>Alessandra Magistrato</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Copper is a trace element vital to many cellular functions. Yet its abnormal levels are toxic to cells, provoking a variety of severe diseases. The high affinity Copper Transporter 1 (CTR1), being the main in-cell copper (Cu(I)) entry route, tightly regulates its cellular uptake via a still elusive mechanism. Here, all-atoms simulations unlock the molecular terms of Cu(I) transport in eukaryotes disclosing that the two Methionine triads, forming the selectivity filter, play an unprecedented dual role both enabling selective Cu(I) transport and regulating its uptake-rate thanks to an intimate coupling between the conformational plasticity of their bulky side chains and the number of bound Cu(I) ions. Namely, the Met residues act as a gate reducing the Cu(I) import-rate when two ions simultaneously bind to CTR1. This may represent an elegant autoregulatory mechanism through which CTR1 protects the cells from excessively high, and hence toxic, in-cell Cu(I) levels. Overall, these outcomes resolve fundamental questions in CTR1 biology and open new windows of opportunity to tackle diseases associated with an imbalanced copper uptake.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467269" rel="alternate" title="The Conformational Plasticity of the Selectivity Filter Methionines Controls the In-Cell Cu(I) Uptake through the CTR1 transporter (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467338</id><title>Direct addition of poly-lysine or poly-ethylenimine to the medium, a simple alternative to plate pre-coating (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.753337+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Faussner</name></author><author><name>Matthias Manfred Deininger</name></author><author><name>Chrisitan Weber</name></author><author><name>Sabine Steffens</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;For most cell culture experiments, it is indispensable that the cells are firmly anchored to the culture plates, tolerating several rinsing steps, and withstanding shear forces or temperature changes without detaching. For semi-adherent cells such as the very common HEK 293 cells, this could so far be obtained only by time-consuming plate pre-coating with cationic polymer solutions. We report here, that i) pre-coating with the cheaper poly-ethylenimine (PEI) works as well as the commonly used poly-D-lysine (PDL), but more importantly and novel ii) that simple direct addition of either PEI (1.5 µg/ml) or PDL (2 µg/ml) to the cell culture medium results in strongly anchored HEK 293 cells, indistinguishable from ones seeded on pre-coated plates. Therefore, the replacement of plate pre-coating by direct addition of either PEI or PDL gives comparable excellent results, but is highly labour-, time-, and cost-efficient. Interestingly, additional experiments in this context showed that strong cell attachment requires only cationic polymers but not fetal calf serum added to the medium. Fetal calf serum is, however, of course required for further maintenance and growth of the cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467338" rel="alternate" title="Direct addition of poly-lysine or poly-ethylenimine to the medium, a simple alternative to plate pre-coating (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467007</id><title>Increasing the throughput of sensitive proteomics by plexDIA (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.754181+00:00</updated><author><name>Jason Derks</name></author><author><name>Andrew Leduc</name></author><author><name>R. Gray Huffman</name></author><author><name>Harrison Specht</name></author><author><name>Markus Ralser</name></author><author><name>Vadim Demichev</name></author><author><name>Nikolai Slavov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Current mass-spectrometry methods enable high-throughput proteomics of large sample amounts, but proteomics of low sample amounts remains limited in depth and throughput. We aimed to increase the throughput of high-sensitivity proteomics while achieving high proteome coverage and quantitative accuracy. We developed a general experimental and computational framework, plexDIA, for simultaneously multiplexing the analysis of both peptides and samples. Multiplexed analysis with plexDIA increases throughput multiplicatively with the number of labels without reducing proteome coverage or quantitative accuracy. Specifically, plexDIA using 3-plex nonisobaric mass tags enables quantifying 3-fold more protein ratios among nanogram-level samples. Using 1 hour active gradients and first-generation Q Exactive, plexDIA quantified about 8,000 proteins in each sample of labeled 3-plex sets. Furthermore, plexDIA increases the consistency of protein quantification, resulting in over 2-fold reduction of missing data across samples. We applied plexDIA to quantify proteome dynamics during the cell division cycle in cells isolated based on their DNA content. The high sensitivity and accuracy of plexDIA detected many classical cell cycle proteins and discovered new ones. These results establish a general framework for increasing the throughput of highly sensitive and quantitative protein analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467007" rel="alternate" title="Increasing the throughput of sensitive proteomics by plexDIA (4 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467105</id><title>Transcription factor induction of vascular blood stem cell niches in vivo (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.755704+00:00</updated><author><name>Elliott J. Hagedorn</name></author><author><name>Julie R. Perlin</name></author><author><name>Rebecca J. Freeman</name></author><author><name>Samuel J. Wattrus</name></author><author><name>Tianxiao Han</name></author><author><name>Clara Mao</name></author><author><name>Ji Wook Kim</name></author><author><name>Inés Fernández-Maestre</name></author><author><name>Madeleine L. Daily</name></author><author><name>Christopher D’Amato</name></author><author><name>Michael J. Fairchild</name></author><author><name>Raquel Riquelme</name></author><author><name>Brian Li</name></author><author><name>Dana A.V.E. Ragoonanan</name></author><author><name>Khaliun Enkhbayar</name></author><author><name>Emily L. Henault</name></author><author><name>Helen G. Wang</name></author><author><name>Shelby E. Redfield</name></author><author><name>Samantha H. Collins</name></author><author><name>Asher Lichtig</name></author><author><name>Song Yang</name></author><author><name>Yi Zhou</name></author><author><name>Balvir Kunar</name></author><author><name>Jesus Maria Gomez-Salinero</name></author><author><name>Thanh T. Dinh</name></author><author><name>Junliang Pan</name></author><author><name>Karoline Holler</name></author><author><name>Henry A. Feldman</name></author><author><name>Eugene C. Butcher</name></author><author><name>Alexander van Oudenaarden</name></author><author><name>Shahin Rafii</name></author><author><name>J. Philipp Junker</name></author><author><name>Leonard I. Zon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The hematopoietic niche is a supportive microenvironment comprised of distinct cell types, including specialized vascular endothelial cells that directly interact with hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells (HSPCs). The molecular factors that specify niche endothelial cells and orchestrate HSPC homeostasis remain largely unknown. Using multi-dimensional gene expression and chromatin accessibility analyses, we define a conserved gene expression signature and &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-regulatory landscape unique to sinusoidal endothelial cells in the HSPC niche. Using enhancer mutagenesis and transcription factor overexpression, we elucidate a transcriptional code involving members of the Ets, Sox and Nuclear Hormone Receptor families that is sufficient to induce ectopic niche endothelial cells that associate with mesenchymal stromal cells and support the recruitment, maintenance and division of HSPCs &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. These studies set forth an approach for generating synthetic HSPC niches, &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; or &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, and for effective therapies to modulate the endogenous niche.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467105" rel="alternate" title="Transcription factor induction of vascular blood stem cell niches in vivo (4 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467127</id><title>Adar1 deletion causes degeneration of exocrine pancreas via Mavs-dependent interferon signaling (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.756460+00:00</updated><author><name>Dhwani N. Rupani</name></author><author><name>Robert W. Cowan</name></author><author><name>Fredrik I. Thege</name></author><author><name>Vidhi Chandra</name></author><author><name>Sonja M. Wörmann</name></author><author><name>Hajar Rajaei</name></author><author><name>Prerna Malaney</name></author><author><name>Olivereen Le Roux</name></author><author><name>Sara L. Manning</name></author><author><name>Jack Hashem</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Bailey-Lundberg</name></author><author><name>Florencia McAllister</name></author><author><name>Andrew D. Rhim</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Adenosine deaminase acting on RNA 1 (ADAR1) is an RNA-binding protein that deaminates adenosine(A) to inosine(I). A-to-I editing alters post-transcriptional RNA processing making ADAR1 a critical regulator of gene expression. Consequently, Adar1 has been implicated in organogenesis. To determine the role of Adar1 in pancreatic development and homeostasis, we specifically deleted &lt;italic&gt;Adar1&lt;/italic&gt; from the murine pancreas (&lt;italic&gt;Ptf1a&lt;sup&gt;Cre/+&lt;/sup&gt;; Adar1&lt;sup&gt;Fl/Fl&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt;). The resulting mice had stunted growth likely due to malabsorption associated with exocrine pancreas insufficiency. Analyses of pancreases revealed ductal expansion, heightened interferon-stimulated gene expression and an increased influx of immune cells. In addition, we observed an increased prevalence of CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T and natural killer cells in their splenic tissue. These results indicate an association between loss of pancreatic Adar1 with dysregulation of systemic immunity. Concurrent deletion of &lt;italic&gt;Adar1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Mavs&lt;/italic&gt;, a signaling protein implicated in the innate immune pathway rescued the degenerative phenotype and resulted in normal pancreatic development. Taken together, our work suggests that the primary function of Adar1 in the pancreas is to prevent aberrant activation of the Mavs-mediated innate immune pathway, thereby maintaining pancreatic homeostasis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This work defines the role of Adar1 in pancreatic development and homeostasis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467127" rel="alternate" title="Adar1 deletion causes degeneration of exocrine pancreas via Mavs-dependent interferon signaling (4 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467147</id><title>Chigno/CG11180 and SUMO are Chinmo-Interacting Proteins with a Role in Drosophila Testes Stem Cells (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.756797+00:00</updated><author><name>Leanna Rinehart</name></author><author><name>Wendy E. Stewart</name></author><author><name>Natalie Luffman</name></author><author><name>Matthew Wawersik</name></author><author><name>Oliver Kerscher</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Maintenance of sexual identity on the cellular level ensures the proper function of sexually dimorphic genes expressed in the brain and gonads. Disruption of genes that regulate sex maintenance alters the cellular structure of these tissues and leads to infertility and diseases, such as diabetes, obesity, and gonadal cancers. Sex maintenance in the testis of &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; depends on the previously identified gene &lt;italic&gt;chinmo&lt;/italic&gt; (Chronologically inappropriate morphogenesis). Chinmo’s effect on testis differentiation has been investigated in detail, but there is still much to be elucidated about its structure, function, and interactions with other proteins. Using a two-hybrid screen, we find that Chinmo interacts with itself, the small ubiquitin-like modifier SUMO, the novel protein CG11180, and four other proteins (CG4318, Ova (Ovaries absent), Taf3 (TBP-associated factor 3), and CG18269). Since both Chinmo and CG11180 contain sumoylation sites and SUMO-interacting motifs (SIMs), we analyzed their interaction in more detail. Using site-directed mutagenesis of a unique SIM in CG11180, we demonstrate that Chinmo’s interaction with CG11180 is SUMOdependent. Furthermore, to assess the functional relevance of both SUMO and CG11180, we performed RNAi-mediated knockdown of both proteins in somatic cells of the &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; testis. Using this approach, we find that CG11180 and SUMO are required in somatic cells of adult testes, and that reduction of either protein causes formation of germ cell tumors. Overall, our work indicates that SUMO functionally links Chinmo and CG11180 in somatic cells of the adult &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; testis. Consistent with the CG11180 knockdown phenotype in male testes, and to underscore its connection to Chinmo, we propose the name Childless Gambino (Chigno) for CG11180.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467147" rel="alternate" title="Chigno/CG11180 and SUMO are Chinmo-Interacting Proteins with a Role in Drosophila Testes Stem Cells (4 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467045</id><title>Trim41 is essential for preventing X chromosome chaotic synapsis in male mice (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.757232+00:00</updated><author><name>Seiya Oura</name></author><author><name>Toshiaki Hino</name></author><author><name>Takashi Satoh</name></author><author><name>Taichi Noda</name></author><author><name>Takayuki Koyano</name></author><author><name>Ayako Isotani</name></author><author><name>Makoto Matsuyama</name></author><author><name>Shizuo Akira</name></author><author><name>Kei-ichiro Ishiguro</name></author><author><name>Masahito Ikawa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Meiosis is a hallmark event in germ cell development that accompanies sequential chromosome events executed by numerous molecules. Therefore, characterization of these factors is one of the best strategies to clarify the mechanism of meiosis. Here, we report tripartite motif-containing 41 (TRIM41), a ubiquitin ligase E3, as an essential factor for proper meiotic progression and fertility in male mice. &lt;italic&gt;Trim41&lt;/italic&gt; KO spermatocytes exhibited synaptonemal complex protein 3 (SYCP3) overloading, especially on the X chromosome, showing extensive self-synapsis of X chromosome and non-homologous synapsis between the X chromosome and autosomes. Furthermore, the mutant mice lacking the RING domain of TRIM41, required for the ubiquitin ligase E3 activity, phenocopied &lt;italic&gt;Trim41&lt;/italic&gt; KO mice. We then examined the behavior of mutant TRIM41 (ΔRING-TRIM41) and found that ΔRING-TRIM41 accumulated on the chromosome axes with overloaded SYCP3. This result showed that TRIM41 exerts the function on the chromosome axes. In summary, our study revealed that &lt;italic&gt;Trim41&lt;/italic&gt; is essential for preventing SYCP3 overloading and chaotic synapsis of the X chromosome, suggesting a TRIM41-mediated mechanism for regulating unsyapsed axes during male meiotic progression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Trim41&lt;/italic&gt;-disruption caused abnormal synapsis configuration of the X chromosome and complete infertility in male mice. Thus, TRIM41 prevents the sex chromosome from chaotic synapsis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467045" rel="alternate" title="Trim41 is essential for preventing X chromosome chaotic synapsis in male mice (4 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.07.467592</id><title>Construction of a bioluminescence-based assay for bitter taste receptors (TAS2Rs) (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.757534+00:00</updated><author><name>Shi Min Tan</name></author><author><name>Wei-Guang Seetoh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In humans, a family of 25 bitter taste receptors (TAS2Rs) mediates bitter taste perception. A common approach to characterize bitter causative agents involves expressing TAS2Rs and the appropriate signal transducers in heterologous cell systems, and monitoring changes in the intracellular free calcium levels upon ligand exposure using a fluorescence-based modality. However, a fluorescence-based assay typically suffers from a low signal window, and is susceptible to interference by autofluorescence, therefore limiting its application to screening of plant or food extracts, which are likely to contain autofluorescent compounds. Here, we report the development and validation of a bioluminescence-based intracellular calcium release assay for TAS2Rs that has a better assay performance than a fluorescence-based assay. Furthermore, the bioluminescence-based assay enables the evaluation of TAS2R agonists within an autofluorescent matrix, highlighting its potential utility in the assessment of the bitterness-inducing properties of plant or food fractions by the food industry. Additionally, further improvement to the bioluminescence-based assay for some TAS2Rs was achieved by altering their N-terminal signal sequences, leading to signal window enhancement. Altogether, the bioluminescence-based TAS2R assay can be used to perform functional studies of TAS2Rs, evaluate TAS2R-modulating properties of autofluorescent samples, and facilitate the discovery of compounds that can function as promising bitter taste modulators.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.07.467592" rel="alternate" title="Construction of a bioluminescence-based assay for bitter taste receptors (TAS2Rs) (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467160</id><title>Metabolic heritage mapping: heterogenous pools of cytoplasmic nucleotide sugars are selectively utilized by various glycosyltransferases (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.757765+00:00</updated><author><name>Paulina Sosicka</name></author><author><name>Bobby G. Ng</name></author><author><name>Lauren E. Pepi</name></author><author><name>Asif Shajahan</name></author><author><name>Maurice Wong</name></author><author><name>David A. Scott</name></author><author><name>Kenjiroo Matsumoto</name></author><author><name>Zhi-Jie Xia</name></author><author><name>Carlito B. Lebrilla</name></author><author><name>Robert S. Haltiwanger</name></author><author><name>Parastoo Azadi</name></author><author><name>Hudson H. Freeze</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Biosynthesis of macromolecules requires precursors such as sugars or amino acids, originating from exogenous/dietary sources, reutilization/salvage of degraded molecules or &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; synthesis. Since these sources are assumed to contribute to one homogenous pool, their individual contributions are often overlooked. Protein glycosylation uses monosaccharides from all the above sources to produce nucleotide sugars required to assemble hundreds of distinct glycans. Here we demonstrate that cells identify the origin/heritage of the monosaccharide, fucose, for glycosylation. We measured the contribution of GDP-fucose from each of these sources for glycan synthesis and found that different fucosyltransferases, individual glycoproteins, and linkage-specific fucose residues identify and select different GDP-fucose pools dependent on their heritage. This supports the hypothesis that GDP-fucose exists in multiple, distinct pools, not as a single homogenous pool. The selection is tightly regulated since the overall pool size remains constant. We present novel perspectives on monosaccharide metabolism, which may have general applicability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467160" rel="alternate" title="Metabolic heritage mapping: heterogenous pools of cytoplasmic nucleotide sugars are selectively utilized by various glycosyltransferases (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467119</id><title>Distinct roles for CDK-Mediator in controlling Polycomb-dependent chromosomal interactions and priming genes for induction (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.758188+00:00</updated><author><name>Emilia Dimitrova</name></author><author><name>Angelika Feldmann</name></author><author><name>Robin H van der Weide</name></author><author><name>Koen D Flach</name></author><author><name>Anna Lastuvkova</name></author><author><name>Elzo de Wit</name></author><author><name>Robert J Klose</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Precise control of gene expression underpins normal development. This relies on mechanisms that enable communication between gene promoters and other regulatory elements. In embryonic stem cells (ESCs), the CDK-Mediator (CDK-MED) complex has been reported to physically link gene regulatory elements to enable gene expression and also prime genes for induction during differentiation. Here we discover that CDK-MED contributes little to 3D genome organisation in ESCs, but has a specific and essential role in controlling interactions between inactive gene regulatory elements bound by Polycomb repressive complexes (PRCs).  These interactions are established by the canonical PRC1 (cPRC1) complex but rely on CDK-MED, which facilitates binding of cPRC1 to its target sites.  Importantly, through separation of function experiments, we reveal that this collaboration between CDK-MED and cPRC1 in creating long-range interactions does not function to prime genes for induction during differentiation. Instead, we discover that priming relies on an interaction-independent mechanism whereby the CDK module supports core Mediator engagement with gene promoters to enable gene activation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467119" rel="alternate" title="Distinct roles for CDK-Mediator in controlling Polycomb-dependent chromosomal interactions and priming genes for induction (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467237</id><title>Dynamic spreading of chromatin-mediated gene silencing and reactivation between neighboring genes in single cells (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.758482+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah Lensch</name></author><author><name>Michael H. Herschl</name></author><author><name>Connor H. Ludwig</name></author><author><name>Joydeb Sinha</name></author><author><name>Michaela M. Hinks</name></author><author><name>Adi Mukund</name></author><author><name>Taihei Fujimori</name></author><author><name>Lacramioara Bintu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In mammalian cells genes that are in close proximity are coupled transcriptionally: silencing or activating one gene can affect its neighbors. Understanding these dynamics is important for natural processes, such as heterochromatin spreading during development and aging, and when designing synthetic gene regulation. Here, we systematically dissect this process in single cells by recruiting and releasing repressive chromatin regulators at dual-gene synthetic reporters, and measuring how fast gene silencing and reactivation spread as a function of intergenic distance and configuration of insulator elements. We find that silencing by KRAB, associated with histone methylation, spreads between two genes within hours, with a time delay that increases with distance. This fast KRAB-mediated spreading is not blocked by the classical cHS4 insulators. Silencing by histone deacetylase HDAC4 of the upstream gene can also lead to downstream gene silencing, but with a days-long delay that does not change with distance. This slower silencing can sometimes be stopped by insulators. Gene reactivation of neighboring genes is also coupled, with strong promoters and insulators determining the order of reactivation. We propose a new model of multi-gene regulation, where both gene silencing and gene reactivation can act at a distance, allowing for coordinated dynamics via chromatin regulator recruitment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467237" rel="alternate" title="Dynamic spreading of chromatin-mediated gene silencing and reactivation between neighboring genes in single cells (3 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466852</id><title>Comprehensive identification of fetal cis-regulatory elements in the human genome by single-cell multi-omics analysis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.758925+00:00</updated><author><name>Hao Yu</name></author><author><name>Na Ai</name></author><author><name>Ping Peng</name></author><author><name>Yuwen Ke</name></author><author><name>Xuepeng Chen</name></author><author><name>Yun Li</name></author><author><name>Ting Zhao</name></author><author><name>Shan Jiang</name></author><author><name>Jiang Liu</name></author><author><name>Lan Jiang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The regulatory programs driving early organogenesis in human is complex and still poorly understood. We performed parallel profiling of gene expression and chromatin accessibility to 28 human fetal tissue samples representing 14 organs in the first trimester. Collectively, we have generated 415,793 single-cell profiles. By integration analysis of transcriptome and chromatin accessibility, we detected 225 distinct cell types and 848,475 candidate accessible cis-regulatory elements (aCREs). By linking regulatory elements to their putative target genes, we identified not only 108,699 enhancers, but also 23,392 silencers elements. We uncovered thousands of genes regulated by both enhancers and silencers in an organ or cell-type-specific manner. Furthermore, our unique approach revealed a substantial proportion of distal DNA elements are transcribed CREs (tCREs), which show both open chromatin signal and transcription initiation activity of non-coding transcript. The landscape of fetal cis-regulatory elements facilitates the interpretation of the genetic variant of complex disease and infer the cell type of origin for cancer. Overall, our data provide a comprehensive map of the fetal cis-regulatory elements at single-cell resolution and a valuable resource for future study of human development and disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466852" rel="alternate" title="Comprehensive identification of fetal cis-regulatory elements in the human genome by single-cell multi-omics analysis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466952</id><title>Dynamic Flux Balance Analysis Game (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.759180+00:00</updated><author><name>Garud Iyengar</name></author><author><name>Mitchell Perry</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Flux balance analysis (FBA) for microbial communities often assumes a global objective function that all species cooperatively maximize in addition to maximizing their own growth. Combining communityFBA with dynamic FBA to understand the time course and steady states of communities typically entails discretizing time and solving a community FBA model at each time point, a time-intensive process. We propose a dynamic community FBA model where species compete for metabolites to grow off of without needing to  cooperate to maximize a community-level objective. An efficient method for computing steady state community compositions is provided, as well as methods for determining the stability of a steady state community to perturbations in biomass and invasion by species outside the community. The model and methods are applied to a model of four E. Coli. mutants with elements of competition (for shared metabolites) and cooperation (via mutants being auxotrophic for metabolites exported by other mutants).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466952" rel="alternate" title="Dynamic Flux Balance Analysis Game (3 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466821</id><title>A deep exon cryptic splice site promotes aberrant intron retention in a von Willebrand disease patient (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.759462+00:00</updated><author><name>John G. Conboy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A translationally silent single nucleotide mutation, in exon 44 of the von Willebrand factor (VWF) gene, is associated with inefficient removal of intron 44 in a von Willebrand disease (VWD) patient. This intron retention (IR) event was previously attributed to altered secondary structure that sequesters the normal splice donor site. We propose an alternative mechanism: that the mutation introduces a cryptic splice donor site that interferes with function of the annotated site to favor IR. We evaluated both models using minigene splicing reporters engineered to vary in secondary structure and/or cryptic splice site content. Analysis of reporter splicing efficiency in transfected K562 cells suggested that the mutation-generated internal splice site was sufficient to induce substantial IR. Mutations predicted to vary secondary structure at the annotated site had modest effects on IR, and also shifted the balance of residual splicing between the cryptic site and annotated site, supporting competition between the sites. Further studies demonstrated that introduction of cryptic splice donor motifs at other positions in E44 did not promote IR, indicating that interference with the annotated site is context-dependent. We conclude that mutant deep exon splice sites can interfere with proper splicing by inducing IR.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466821" rel="alternate" title="A deep exon cryptic splice site promotes aberrant intron retention in a von Willebrand disease patient (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466861</id><title>A critical role for E2-p53 interaction during the HPV16 life cycle (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.765322+00:00</updated><author><name>Christian T. Fontan</name></author><author><name>Claire D. James</name></author><author><name>Molly L. Bristol</name></author><author><name>Apurva T. Prabhakar</name></author><author><name>Raymonde Otoa</name></author><author><name>Xu Wang</name></author><author><name>Elmira Karimi</name></author><author><name>Pavithra Rajagopalan</name></author><author><name>Devraj Basu</name></author><author><name>Iain M. Morgan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human papillomaviruses (HPV) are causative agents in ano-genital and oral cancers; HPV16 is the most prevalent type detected in human cancers. The HPV16 E6 protein targets p53 for proteasomal degradation to facilitate proliferation of the HPV16 infected cell. However, in HPV16 immortalized cells E6 is predominantly spliced (E6*) and unable to degrade p53. Here we demonstrate that human foreskin keratinocytes immortalized by HPV16 (HFK+HPV16), and HPV16 positive oropharyngeal cancers, retain significant expression of p53. In addition, p53 levels can be increased in HPV16+ head and neck cancer cell lines following treatment with cisplatin. Introduction of full-length E6 into HFK+HPV16 resulted in attenuation of cellular growth (in hTERT immortalized HFK, E6 expression promoted enhanced proliferation). An understudied interaction is that between E2 and p53 and we investigated whether this was important for the viral life cycle. We generated mutant genomes with E2 unable to interact with p53 resulting in profound phenotypes in primary HFK. The mutant induced hyper-proliferation, but an ultimate arrest of cell growth; β-galactosidase staining demonstrated increased senescence, and COMET assays showed increased DNA damage compared with HFK+HPV16 wild type cells. There was failure of the viral life cycle in organotypic rafts with the mutant HFK resulting in premature differentiation and reduced proliferation. The results indicate that the E2-p53 interaction is critical during the HPV16 life cycle, and that disruption of this interaction has anti-viral potential. We discuss potential mechanisms to explain these phenotypes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Human papillomaviruses are causative agents in around 5% of all cancers. There are currently no antivirals available to combat these infections and cancers, therefore it remains a priority to enhance our understanding of the HPV life cycle. Here we demonstrate that an interaction between the viral replication/transcription/segregation factor E2 and the tumor suppressor p53 is critical for the HPV16 life cycle. HPV16 immortalized cells retain significant expression of p53, and the critical role for the E2-p53 interaction demonstrates why this is the case. If the E2-p53 interaction is disrupted then HPV16 immortalized cells fail to proliferate, have enhanced DNA damage and senescence, and there is premature differentiation during the viral life cycle. Results suggest that targeting the E2-p53 interaction would have therapeutic benefits, potentially attenuating the spread of HPV16.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466861" rel="alternate" title="A critical role for E2-p53 interaction during the HPV16 life cycle (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.465785</id><title>Arp2/3 complex activity is necessary for mouse ESC differentiation, times formative pluripotency, and enables lineage specification (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.766033+00:00</updated><author><name>Francesca M. Aloisio</name></author><author><name>Diane L. Barber</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mouse embryonic stem cells (mESCs), a model for differentiation into primed epiblast-like cells (EpiLCs), have revealed transcriptional and epigenetic control of early embryonic development. The control and significance of morphological changes, however, remain less defined. We show marked changes in morphology and actin architectures during differentiation that depend on Arp2/3 complex but not formin activity. Inhibiting Arp2/3 complex activity pharmacologically or genetically does not block exit from naive pluripotency but attenuates increases in EpiLC markers. We find that inhibiting Arp2/3 complex activity delays formative pluripotency and causes globally defective lineage specification as indicated by RNA-sequencing, with significant effects on TBX3-depedendent transcriptional programs. We also identify two previously unreported indicators of mESC differentiation; MRTF and FHL2, which have inverse Arp2/3 complex-dependent nuclear translocation. Our findings on Arp2/3 complex activity in differentiation and the established role of formins in EMT indicate that these two actin nucleators regulate distinct modes of epithelial plasticity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arp2/3 complex activity is necessary for morphology changes during differentiation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arp2/3 complex activity regulates transcriptional markers of differentiation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Inhibiting Arp2/3 complex activity delays entry into formative pluripotency&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arp2/3 complex activity-dependent shuttling of FHL2 and MRTF occurs in mESCs&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.465785" rel="alternate" title="Arp2/3 complex activity is necessary for mouse ESC differentiation, times formative pluripotency, and enables lineage specification (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.463467</id><title>Comprehensive O-GlcNAc glycoproteomics on NOTCH1 EGF repeats refined sequons for O-GlcNAcylation and uncovered unique Lewis X epitopes in mammals (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.766447+00:00</updated><author><name>Yohei Tsukamoto</name></author><author><name>Mitsutaka Ogawa</name></author><author><name>Kentarou Yogi</name></author><author><name>Hideyuki Takeuchi</name></author><author><name>Tetsuya Okajima</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The O-GlcNAc modification of Notch receptors regulates Notch ligand interactions in a manner distinct from other forms of O-glycans on epidermal growth factor-like (EGF) repeats of Notch receptors. Although many proteins, besides Notch receptors, are expected to be O-GlcNAcylated by EGF domain-specific O-GlcNAc transferase (EOGT), only a small number of proteins have been reported to be modified &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, and elongated O-GlcNAc glycans have not been extensively explored. To extend our view of the specificity and variety of the glycan modification, we conducted a comprehensive analysis of O-GlcNAc glycans on NOTCH1 in mammals. Mass spectrometric analysis of NOTCH1 fragments expressed in HEK293T cells revealed that several EGF domains with putative O-GlcNAcylation sites were hardly modified with O-GlcNAc. Although amino acid residues before the modification site are preferentially occupied with aromatic residues, Phe and Tyr are preferable to Trp for the apparent modification with O-GlcNAc. Furthermore, a minor form of fucosylated O-GlcNAc glycans was detected in a subset of EGF domains. Fucosylation of O-GlcNAc glycans was enhanced by &lt;italic&gt;FUT1, FUT2&lt;/italic&gt;, or &lt;italic&gt;FUT9&lt;/italic&gt; expression. The FUT9-dependent Lewis X epitope was confirmed by immunoblotting using an anti-Lewis X antibody. As expected from the similarity in the glycan structures, the Lexis X antigen was detected on O-fucose glycans. Notably, the Lewis X structure on O-glycans was identified in endogenous NOTCH1 isolated from MCF7 cells. Our results refined the putative consensus sequence for the EOGT-dependent extracellular O-GlcNAc modification in mammals and revealed the structural diversity of functional Notch O-glycans.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Comprehensive analysis of O-GlcNAc glycan on NOTCH1 refined O-GlcNAcylation sequons&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;FUT1, FUT2&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;FUT9&lt;/italic&gt; modify O-GlcNAc glycans in the selective EGF domains of NOTCH1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Lewis X epitope can be formed on both O-GlcNAc and O-fucose glycans on NOTCH1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;In Brief&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study performed comprehensive mass spectrometric analyses of O-GlcNAc glycans in the NOTCH1 extracellular region in cultured mammalian cells. The results indicated that EOGT-dependent O-GlcNAcylation occurs on a limited number of EGF repeats harboring putative O-GlcNAcylation sites, refining the sequons for extracellular O-GlcNAc modification in mammals. Moreover, novel structures with fucosylated O-GlcNAc glycans were identified, and a similar structure was detectable on O-fucose glycans, extending the view of structural diversity of functional Notch O-glycans.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.463467" rel="alternate" title="Comprehensive O-GlcNAc glycoproteomics on NOTCH1 EGF repeats refined sequons for O-GlcNAcylation and uncovered unique Lewis X epitopes in mammals (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467076</id><title>Trehalose-6-phosphate links singlet oxygen-induced signalling with metabolic signalling in Chlamydomonas reinhardtii (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.766730+00:00</updated><author><name>Waeil Al Youssef</name></author><author><name>Regina Feil</name></author><author><name>Maureen Saint-Sorny</name></author><author><name>Xenie Johnson</name></author><author><name>John E. Lunn</name></author><author><name>Bernhard Grimm</name></author><author><name>Pawel Brzezowski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Singlet oxygen (&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) induces retrograde signalling in chloroplasts. Using a novel mutant screen, we identified a mutation in the &lt;italic&gt;TREHALOSE-6-PHOSPHATE PHOSPHATASE 1&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;T6PP1&lt;/italic&gt;) gene that results in accumulation of trehalose 6-phosphate, a reprogramming of cell metabolism, and impairment of &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-induced retrograde signalling in &lt;italic&gt;Chlamydomonas reinhardtii&lt;/italic&gt;. From transcriptomic analysis and metabolite profiling, we conclude that accumulation or deficiency of certain metabolites directly affect &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-signalling. &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-inducible &lt;italic&gt;GLUTATHIONE PEROXIDASE 5&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;GPX5&lt;/italic&gt;) gene expression is suppressed by increased content of fumarate, an intermediate in the tricarboxylic acid cycle (TCA cycle) in mitochondria and dicarboxylate metabolism in the cytosol, while it is promoted by another TCA cycle intermediate, aconitate. Furthermore, genes encoding known essential components of chloroplast-to-nucleus &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-signalling show decreased transcript levels in a &lt;italic&gt;t6pp1&lt;/italic&gt; mutant, which can be rescued by exogenous application of aconitate. We demonstrate that chloroplast retrograde signalling involving &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; depends on mitochondrial and cytosolic processes and that the metabolic status of the cell determines the response to &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467076" rel="alternate" title="Trehalose-6-phosphate links singlet oxygen-induced signalling with metabolic signalling in Chlamydomonas reinhardtii (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467145</id><title>A phosphoinositide and RAB switch controls early macropinocytosis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.766961+00:00</updated><author><name>Hélène Spangenberg</name></author><author><name>Marte Sneeggen</name></author><author><name>Maria Mateo Tortola</name></author><author><name>Camila Valenzuela</name></author><author><name>Yuen-Yan Chang</name></author><author><name>Harald Stenmark</name></author><author><name>Camilla Raiborg</name></author><author><name>Kay Oliver Schink</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Macropinocytosis is a non-selective endocytic process by which cells take up large amounts of extracellular fluids into giant vesicles known as macropinosomes. This mechanism is used by immune cells to sample the surroundings for antigens and can be exploited by cancer cells for nutrient uptake. What determines the fate of macropinosomes after they have been internalized is largely unknown. Here we investigate the role of the phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase VPS34/PIK3C3 and its product phosphatidylinositol 3-phosphate (PtdIns3P) in macropinosome fate determination. Inhibition of VPS34 led to a decrease in macropinosome survival and fluid phase uptake as well as preventing recruitment of early endosomal factors, including the small GTPase RAB5 and its effectors, to the forming macropinosomes. Instead, forming macropinosomes under VPS34 inhibition accumulated regulators of endocytic recycling, including RAB8A, RAB10, RAB11A, and PtdIns4P, which led to fusion of macropinosomes with the plasma membrane.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whereas RAB5 was critical for macropinosome formation, macropinosome fusion with the plasma membrane depended on RAB8A. Thus, macropinosome maturation is regulated by a PtdIns3P-controlled switch that balances macropinosome fate between the default, endolysosomal maturation and an alternative, secretory route.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467145" rel="alternate" title="A phosphoinositide and RAB switch controls early macropinocytosis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.467039</id><title>Inhibition of BET family proteins suppresses African swine fever virus infection (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.767398+00:00</updated><author><name>Yaru Zhao</name></author><author><name>Qingli Niu</name></author><author><name>Saixia Yang</name></author><author><name>Jifei Yang</name></author><author><name>Zhonghui Zhang</name></author><author><name>Shuxian Geng</name></author><author><name>Jie Fan</name></author><author><name>Zhijie Liu</name></author><author><name>Guiquan Guan</name></author><author><name>Zhiqing Liu</name></author><author><name>Jia Zhou</name></author><author><name>Haitao Hu</name></author><author><name>Jianxun Luo</name></author><author><name>Hong Yin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;African swine fever (ASF), an acute, severe, highly contagious disease caused by African swine fever virus (ASFV) infection in domestic pigs and boars, has a mortality rate of up to 100%. Because effective vaccines and treatments for ASF are lacking, effective control of the spread of ASF remains a great challenge for the pig industry. Host epigenetic regulation is essential for the viral gene transcription. Bromodomain and extraterminal (BET) family proteins, including BRD2, BRD3, BRD4, and BRDT, are epigenetic “readers” critical for gene transcription regulation. Among these proteins, BRD4 recognizes acetylated histones via its two bromodomains (BD1 and BD2) and recruits transcription factors, thereby playing a pivotal role in transcriptional regulation and chromatin remodeling during viral infection. However, how BET/BRD4 regulates ASFV replication and gene transcription is unknown. Here, we randomly selected 12 representative BET family inhibitors and compared their effects on ASFV infection in pig’s primary alveolar macrophages (PAMs). They were found to inhibit viral infection by interfering with the different stages of viral life cycle (attachment, internalization, desencapsidation and formation of viral factories). The four most effective inhibitors (ARV-825, ZL0580, I-BET-762 and PLX51107) were selected for further antiviral activity analysis. These BET/BRD4 inhibitors dose-dependently decreased the ASFV titer, viral RNA transcription and protein production in PAMs. Collectively,our study reported novel activity of BET/BRD4 inhibitors in inducing suppression of ASFV infection, providing insights into role of BET/BRD4 in epigenetic regulation of ASFV and potential new strategies for ASF prevention and control.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the continuing spread of the ASFV in the world, and lack of commercial vaccines, the development of improved control strategies including antiviral drugs are urgently needed. BRD4 is an important epigenetic factor and has been commonly used for drug development for tumor treatment. Furthermore, the latest research showed that BET/BRD4 inhibition could suppress replication of virus. In this study, we first showed the inhibitory effect of agents targeting BET/BRD4 on ASFV infection with no significant host cytotoxicity. Then, we found 4 BET/BRD4 inhibitors which can inhibit ASFV replication, RNA transcription and protein synthesis. Finally, we analyzed 4 inhibitors’ biological effect on BRD4 according to the structure of BRD4, and docking analysis of BET-762, PLX51107, ARV-825 and ZL0580 binding to BD1 and BD2 domains of BRD4 was performed. Our findings support the hypothesis that BET/BRD4 can be considered as attractive host targets in antiviral drug discovery against ASFV.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.467039" rel="alternate" title="Inhibition of BET family proteins suppresses African swine fever virus infection (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>