<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.043585+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462231</id><title>Structures of core eukaryotic protein complexes (75 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.044094+00:00</updated><author><name>Ian R. Humphreys</name></author><author><name>Jimin Pei</name></author><author><name>Minkyung Baek</name></author><author><name>Aditya Krishnakumar</name></author><author><name>Ivan Anishchenko</name></author><author><name>Sergey Ovchinnikov</name></author><author><name>Jing Zhang</name></author><author><name>Travis J. Ness</name></author><author><name>Sudeep Banjade</name></author><author><name>Saket Bagde</name></author><author><name>Viktoriya G. Stancheva</name></author><author><name>Xiao-Han Li</name></author><author><name>Kaixian Liu</name></author><author><name>Zhi Zheng</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Barrero</name></author><author><name>Upasana Roy</name></author><author><name>Israel S. Fernández</name></author><author><name>Barnabas Szakal</name></author><author><name>Dana Branzei</name></author><author><name>Eric C. Greene</name></author><author><name>Sue Biggins</name></author><author><name>Scott Keeney</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth A. Miller</name></author><author><name>J. Christopher Fromme</name></author><author><name>Tamara L. Hendrickson</name></author><author><name>Qian Cong</name></author><author><name>David Baker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protein-protein interactions play critical roles in biology, but despite decades of effort, the structures of many eukaryotic protein complexes are unknown, and there are likely many interactions that have not yet been identified. Here, we take advantage of recent advances in proteome-wide amino acid coevolution analysis and deep-learning-based structure modeling to systematically identify and build accurate models of core eukaryotic protein complexes, as represented within the &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; proteome. We use a combination of RoseTTAFold and AlphaFold to screen through paired multiple sequence alignments for 8.3 million pairs of &lt;italic&gt;S. cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; proteins and build models for strongly predicted protein assemblies with two to five components. Comparison to existing interaction and structural data suggests that these predictions are likely to be quite accurate. We provide structure models spanning almost all key processes in Eukaryotic cells for 104 protein assemblies which have not been previously identified, and 608 which have not been structurally characterized.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We take advantage of recent advances in proteome-wide amino acid coevolution analysis and deep-learning-based structure modeling to systematically identify and build accurate models of core eukaryotic protein complexes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462231" rel="alternate" title="Structures of core eukaryotic protein complexes (75 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462199</id><title>Cell-ACDC: a user-friendly toolset embedding state-of-the-art neural networks for segmentation, tracking and cell cycle annotations of live-cell imaging data (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.044677+00:00</updated><author><name>Francesco Padovani</name></author><author><name>Benedikt Mairhörmann</name></author><author><name>Pascal Falter-Braun</name></author><author><name>Jette Lengefeld</name></author><author><name>Kurt M. Schmoller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Live-cell imaging is a powerful tool to study dynamic cellular processes on the level of single cells with quantitative detail. Microfluidics enables parallel high-throughput imaging, creating a downstream bottleneck at the stage of data analysis. Recent progress on deep learning image analysis dramatically improved cell segmentation and tracking. Nevertheless, manual data validation and correction is typically still required and broadly used tools spanning the complete range of live-cell imaging analysis, from cell segmentation to pedigree analysis and signal quantification, are still needed. Here, we present Cell-ACDC, a user-friendly graphical user-interface (GUI)-based framework written in Python, for segmentation, tracking and cell cycle annotation. We included two state-of-the-art and high-accuracy deep learning models for single-cell segmentation of yeast and mammalian cells implemented in the most used deep learning frameworks TensorFlow and PyTorch. Additionally, we developed and implemented a cell tracking method and embedded it into an intuitive, semi-automated workflow for label-free cell cycle annotation of single cells. The open-source and modularized nature of Cell-ACDC will enable simple and fast integration of new deep learning-based and traditional methods for cell segmentation or downstream image analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Source code&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/SchmollerLab/Cell_ACDC"&gt;https://github.com/SchmollerLab/Cell_ACDC&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462199" rel="alternate" title="Cell-ACDC: a user-friendly toolset embedding state-of-the-art neural networks for segmentation, tracking and cell cycle annotations of live-cell imaging data (11 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462548</id><title>Prime Editing Efficiency and Fidelity are Enhanced in the Absence of Mismatch Repair (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.044980+00:00</updated><author><name>J Ferreira da Silva</name></author><author><name>GP Oliveira</name></author><author><name>EA Arasa-Verge</name></author><author><name>A Moretton</name></author><author><name>G Timelthaler</name></author><author><name>J Jiricny</name></author><author><name>JI Loizou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Prime editing is a powerful genome engineering approach that enables the introduction of base substitutions, insertions and deletions, into any given genomic locus. But prime editing, at even the same locus, can exhibit wildly different efficiencies in various cell backgrounds. It is unclear what determines these variations in efficiencies in a given cellular context. Through a focused genetic screen targeting DNA repair factors, we show that the efficiency of prime editing is attenuated by the mismatch repair pathway. The accumulation of the mismatch repair protein MLH1 at sites of prime editing, indicates that mismatch repair acts at these regions to directly counteract the insertion of the edit. Consequently, ablation of mismatch repair yields an up to 17-fold increase in prime editing efficiency across different human cell lines, several types of edits and multiple genomic loci. Our results shed new light on the cellular requirements for prime editing and identify that ablation of mismatch repair increases editing efficiency and fidelity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462548" rel="alternate" title="Prime Editing Efficiency and Fidelity are Enhanced in the Absence of Mismatch Repair (9 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462730</id><title>Deep mutational scan of a drug efflux pump reveals its structure-function landscape (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.045577+00:00</updated><author><name>Gianmarco Meier</name></author><author><name>Sujani Thavarasah</name></author><author><name>Kai Ehrenbolger</name></author><author><name>Cedric A. J. Hutter</name></author><author><name>Lea M. Hürlimann</name></author><author><name>Jonas Barandun</name></author><author><name>Markus A. Seeger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Drug efflux is a common resistance mechanism found in bacteria and cancer cells. Although several structures of drug efflux pumps are available, they provide only limited functional information on the phenomenon of drug efflux. Here, we performed deep mutational scanning (DMS) on the bacterial ATP binding cassette (ABC) transporter EfrCD to determine the drug efflux activity profile of more than 1500 single variants. These systematic measurements revealed that the introduction of negative charges at different locations within the large substrate binding pocket results in strongly increased efflux activity towards positively charged ethidium, while additional aromatic residues did not display the same effect. Data analysis in the context of an inward-facing cryo-EM structure of EfrCD uncovered a high affinity binding site, which releases bound drugs through a peristaltic transport mechanism as the transporter transits to its outward-facing conformation. Finally, we identified substitutions resulting in rapid Hoechst influx without affecting the efflux activity for ethidium and daunorubicin. Hence, single mutations can convert the ABC exporter EfrCD into a drug-specific ABC importer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462730" rel="alternate" title="Deep mutational scan of a drug efflux pump reveals its structure-function landscape (9 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462603</id><title>Regulation of the Evolutionarily Conserved Muscle Myofibrillar Matrix by Cell Type Dependent and Independent Mechanisms (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.045915+00:00</updated><author><name>Peter T. Ajayi</name></author><author><name>Prasanna Katti</name></author><author><name>T. Bradley Willingham</name></author><author><name>Ye Sun</name></author><author><name>Christopher K.E. Bleck</name></author><author><name>Brian Glancy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Skeletal muscles play a central role in human movement through forces transmitted by contraction of the sarcomere. We recently showed that mammalian sarcomeres are connected through frequent branches forming a singular, mesh-like myofibrillar matrix. However, the extent to which myofibrillar connectivity is evolutionarily conserved as well as mechanisms which regulate the specific architecture of sarcomere branching remain unclear. Here, we demonstrate the presence of a myofibrillar matrix in the tubular, but not indirect flight (IF) muscles within &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt;. Moreover, we find that loss of transcription factor &lt;italic&gt;H15&lt;/italic&gt; increases sarcomere branching frequency in the tubular jump muscles, and we show that sarcomere branching can be turned on in IF muscles by &lt;italic&gt;salm&lt;/italic&gt;-mediated conversion to tubular muscles. Finally, we demonstrate that &lt;italic&gt;neurochondrin&lt;/italic&gt; knockdown results in myofibrillar connectivity in IF muscles without conversion to tubular muscles. These data indicate an evolutionarily conserved myofibrillar matrix regulated by both cell-type dependent and independent mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462603" rel="alternate" title="Regulation of the Evolutionarily Conserved Muscle Myofibrillar Matrix by Cell Type Dependent and Independent Mechanisms (7 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462226</id><title>Osteoblasts pattern endothelium and somatosensory axons during zebrafish caudal fin organogenesis (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.046208+00:00</updated><author><name>Rosalind G. Bump</name></author><author><name>Camille E. A. Goo</name></author><author><name>Emma C. Horton</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey P. Rasmussen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Skeletal elements frequently associate with vasculature and somatosensory nerves, which regulate bone development and homeostasis. However, the deep, internal location of bones in many vertebrates has limited &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; exploration of the neurovascular-bone relationship. Here, we use the zebrafish caudal fin, an optically accessible organ formed of repeating bony ray skeletal units, to determine the cellular relationship between nerves, bones, and endothelium. In adults, we establish the presence of somatosensory axons running through the inside of the bony fin rays, juxtaposed with osteoblasts on the inner hemiray surface. During development, we show the caudal fin progresses through sequential stages of endothelial plexus formation, bony ray addition, ray innervation, and endothelial remodeling. Surprisingly, the initial stages of fin morphogenesis proceed normally in animals lacking either fin endothelium or somatosensory nerves. Instead, we find that &lt;italic&gt;sp7+&lt;/italic&gt; osteoblasts are required for endothelial remodeling and somatosensory axon innervation in the developing fin. Overall, this study demonstrates that the proximal neurovascular-bone relationship in the adult caudal fin is established during fin organogenesis and suggests that ray-associated osteoblasts pattern axons and endothelium.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Analysis of cellular interdependence during caudal fin development reveals roles for osteoblasts in patterning endothelium and somatosensory axon innervation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462226" rel="alternate" title="Osteoblasts pattern endothelium and somatosensory axons during zebrafish caudal fin organogenesis (7 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462168</id><title>Neurofibromin 1 controls metabolic balance and Notch-dependent quiescence of juvenile myogenic progenitors (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.046496+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaoyan Wei</name></author><author><name>Matthias Lienhard</name></author><author><name>Arunima Murgai</name></author><author><name>Julia Franke</name></author><author><name>Sophie Pöhle-Kronawitter</name></author><author><name>Georgios Kotsaris</name></author><author><name>Hao Wu</name></author><author><name>Stefan Börno</name></author><author><name>Bernd Timmermann</name></author><author><name>Rainer Glauben</name></author><author><name>Sigmar Stricker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Patients affected by neurofibromatosis type 1 (NF1) frequently show muscle weakness with unknown etiology. Here we show that Neurofibromin-1 (Nf1) is not required in muscle fibers, but specifically in early postnatal myogenic progenitors (MPs), where Nf1 loss led to cell cycle exit and differentiation blockade, depleting the MP pool resulting in reduced myonuclear accrual as well as reduced muscle stem cell numbers. This was caused by precocious induction of stem cell quiescence coupled to metabolic reprogramming of MPs impinging on glycolytic shutdown, which was conserved in muscle fibers. We show that a Mek/Erk/NOS pathway hypersensitizes Nf1-deficient MPs to Notch signaling, consequently, early postnatal Notch pathway inhibition ameliorated premature quiescence, metabolic reprogramming and muscle growth. This reveals an unexpected role of Ras/Mek/Erk signaling supporting postnatal MP quiescence in concert with Notch signaling, which is controlled by Nf1 safeguarding coordinated muscle growth and muscle stem cell pool establishment. Furthermore, our data suggest transmission of metabolic reprogramming across cellular differentiation, affecting fiber metabolism and function in NF1.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462168" rel="alternate" title="Neurofibromin 1 controls metabolic balance and Notch-dependent quiescence of juvenile myogenic progenitors (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462384</id><title>Bromodomain factor 5 is an essential transcriptional regulator of the Leishmania genome (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.046902+00:00</updated><author><name>Nathaniel G. Jones</name></author><author><name>Vincent Geoghegan</name></author><author><name>Gareth Moore</name></author><author><name>Juliana B. T. Carnielli</name></author><author><name>Katherine Newling</name></author><author><name>Félix Calderón</name></author><author><name>Raquel Gabarró</name></author><author><name>Julio Martín</name></author><author><name>Rab Prinjha</name></author><author><name>Inmaculada Rioja</name></author><author><name>Anthony J. Wilkinson</name></author><author><name>Jeremy C. Mottram</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; are unicellular parasites that cause human and animal disease. Alongside other organisms in kinetoplastida, they have evolved an unusual genome architecture that requires all RNA polymerase II transcribed genes to be expressed constitutively, with transcriptional start regions denoted by histone variants and histone lysine acetylation. However, the way these chromatin marks are interpreted by the cell is not understood. Seven predicted bromodomain factors (BDF1-7), the reader modules for acetyl-lysine, were identified across &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; genomes. Using &lt;italic&gt;L. mexicana&lt;/italic&gt; as a model, Cas9-driven gene deletions indicate that BDF1-5 are essential for promastigote survival, whilst DiCre inducible gene deletion of the dual bromodomain factor &lt;italic&gt;BDF5&lt;/italic&gt; identified it to be essential for both promastigotes and amastigotes. ChIP-seq assessment of BDF5s genomic distribution revealed it as highly enriched at transcriptional start sites. Using an optimised proximity proteomic and phosphoproteomic technique, XL-BioID, we defined the BDF5-proximal environment to be enriched for other bromodomain factors, histone acetyltransferase 2, and proteins essential for transcriptional activity and RNA processing. Inducible deletion of BDF5, led to a disruption of pol II transcriptional activity and global defects in gene expression. Our results indicate the requirement of &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; to interpret histone acetylation marks for normal levels of gene expression and thus cellular viability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462384" rel="alternate" title="Bromodomain factor 5 is an essential transcriptional regulator of the Leishmania genome (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.461806</id><title>Progranulin deficiency results in reduced bis(monoacylglycero)phosphate (BMP) levels and gangliosidosis (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.047304+00:00</updated><author><name>Sebastian Boland</name></author><author><name>Sharan Swarup</name></author><author><name>Yohannes A. Ambaw</name></author><author><name>Ruth C. Richards</name></author><author><name>Alexander W. Fischer</name></author><author><name>Shubham Singh</name></author><author><name>Geetika Aggarwal</name></author><author><name>Salvatore Spina</name></author><author><name>Alissa L. Nana</name></author><author><name>Lea T. Grinberg</name></author><author><name>William W. Seeley</name></author><author><name>Michal A. Surma</name></author><author><name>Christian Klose</name></author><author><name>Joao A. Paulo</name></author><author><name>Andrew D. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>J. Wade Harper</name></author><author><name>Tobias C. Walther</name></author><author><name>Robert V. Farese</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Homozygous mutations of granulin precursor (&lt;italic&gt;GRN&lt;/italic&gt;) lead to neuronal ceroid lipofuscinosis&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;, a severe neurodevelopmental disease, in humans and neuroinflammation in mice&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. Haploinsufficiency of &lt;italic&gt;GRN&lt;/italic&gt; almost invariably causes frontotemporal dementia (FTD)&lt;sup&gt;3,4&lt;/sup&gt;. The &lt;italic&gt;GRN&lt;/italic&gt; locus produces progranulin (PGRN), a lysosomal precursor protein that is cleaved to granulin peptides&lt;sup&gt;5,6&lt;/sup&gt;. Despite intensive investigation, the function of granulins and the reason why their absence causes neurodegeneration remain unclear. Here, we investigated PGRN function in lipid degradation, a major function of lysosomes. We show that PGRN-knockout human cells, PGRN-deficient murine brain, and frontal lobes of human brains from patients with &lt;italic&gt;GRN&lt;/italic&gt; mutation-related FTD have increased levels of gangliosides, highly abundant sialic acid–containing glycosphingolipids (GSL) that are degraded in lysosomes. Probing how PGRN deficiency causes these changes, we found normal levels and activities of enzymes that catabolize gangliosides. However, levels of bis(monoacylglycero)phosphate (BMP), a lysosomal lipid required for ganglioside catabolism&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;, were markedly reduced in PGRN-deficient cells and patient brain tissues. These data indicate that granulins are required to maintain BMP levels, which regulate ganglioside catabolism, and that PGRN deficiency in lysosomes leads to gangliosidosis. This aberrant accumulation of gangliosides may contribute to neuroinflammation and neurodegeneration susceptibility.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.461806" rel="alternate" title="Progranulin deficiency results in reduced bis(monoacylglycero)phosphate (BMP) levels and gangliosidosis (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462463</id><title>Optogenetic EB1 inactivation shortens metaphase spindles by disrupting cortical force-producing interactions with astral microtubules (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.047758+00:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Dema</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey van Haren</name></author><author><name>Torsten Wittmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chromosome segregation is accomplished by the mitotic spindle, a bipolar micromachine built primarily from microtubules. Different microtubule populations contribute to spindle function: Kinetochore microtubules attach and transmit forces to chromosomes, antiparallel interpolar microtubules support spindle structure, and astral microtubules connect spindle poles to the cell cortex [1,2]. In mammalian cells, End Binding (EB) proteins associate with all growing microtubule plus ends throughout the cell cycle and serve as adaptors for a diverse group of +TIPs that control microtubule dynamics and interactions with other intracellular structures [3]. Because binding of many +TIPs to EB1 and thus microtubule-end association is switched off by mitotic phosphorylation [4–6] the mitotic function of EBs remains poorly understood. To analyze how EB1 and associated +TIPs on different spindle microtubule populations contribute to mitotic spindle dynamics, we use a light sensitive EB1 variant, π-EB1, that allows local, acute and reversible inactivation of +TIP association with growing microtubule ends in live cells [7]. We find that acute π-EB1 photoinactivation results in rapid and reversible metaphase spindle shortening and transient relaxation of tension across the central spindle. However, in contrast to interphase, π-EB1 photoinactivation does not inhibit microtubule growth in metaphase, but instead increases astral microtubule length and number. Yet, in the absence of EB1 activity astral microtubules fail to engage the cortical dynein/dynactin machinery and spindle poles move away from regions of π-EB1 photoinactivation. In conclusion, our optogenetic approach reveals mitotic EB1 functions that remain hidden in genetic experiments likely due to compensatory molecular systems regulating vertebrate spindle dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462463" rel="alternate" title="Optogenetic EB1 inactivation shortens metaphase spindles by disrupting cortical force-producing interactions with astral microtubules (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462204</id><title>An Evolutionarily Conserved Regulatory Pathway of Muscle Mitochondrial Network Organization (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.048059+00:00</updated><author><name>Prasanna Katti</name></author><author><name>Peter T. Ajayi</name></author><author><name>Angel Aponte</name></author><author><name>Christopher K.E. Bleck</name></author><author><name>Brian Glancy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mitochondrial networks provide coordinated energy distribution throughout muscle cells. However, pathways specifying mitochondrial network-type separately from contractile fiber-type remain unclear. Here, we show that natural energetic demands placed on &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; muscles yield native cell-types among which contractile and mitochondrial network-types are regulated independently. Proteomic analyses of indirect flight, jump, and leg muscles together with muscles misexpressing known fiber-type specification factor &lt;italic&gt;salm&lt;/italic&gt; identified transcription factors &lt;italic&gt;H15&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;cut&lt;/italic&gt; as potential mitochondrial network regulators. We demonstrate &lt;italic&gt;H15&lt;/italic&gt; operates downstream of &lt;italic&gt;salm&lt;/italic&gt; regulating flight muscle contractile and mitochondrial network-type. Conversely, &lt;italic&gt;H15&lt;/italic&gt; regulates mitochondrial network configuration but not contractile type in jump and leg muscles. Further, we find that &lt;italic&gt;cut&lt;/italic&gt; regulates &lt;italic&gt;salm&lt;/italic&gt; expression in flight muscles and mitochondrial network configuration in leg muscles. These data indicate cell type-specific regulation of muscle mitochondrial network organization separately from contractile type, mitochondrial content, and mitochondrial size through an evolutionarily conserved pathway involving &lt;italic&gt;cut, salm&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;H15&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462204" rel="alternate" title="An Evolutionarily Conserved Regulatory Pathway of Muscle Mitochondrial Network Organization (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462432</id><title>Natural and designed proteins inspired by extremotolerant organisms can form condensates and attenuate apoptosis in human cells (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.048469+00:00</updated><author><name>Mike T. Veling</name></author><author><name>Dan T. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Nicole N. Thadani</name></author><author><name>Michela E. Oster</name></author><author><name>Nathan J. Rollins</name></author><author><name>Kelly P. Brock</name></author><author><name>Neville P. Bethel</name></author><author><name>David Baker</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey C. Way</name></author><author><name>Debora S. Marks</name></author><author><name>Roger L. Chang</name></author><author><name>Pamela A. Silver</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many organisms can survive extreme conditions and successfully recover to normal life. This extremotolerant behavior has been attributed in part to repetitive, amphipathic, and intrinsically disordered proteins that are upregulated in the protected state. Here, we assemble a library of approximately 300 naturally-occurring and designed extremotolerance-associated proteins to assess their ability to protect human cells from chemically-induced apoptosis. We show that proteins from tardigrades, nematodes, and the Chinese giant salamander are apoptosis protective. Notably, we identify a region of the human ApoE protein with similarity to extremotolerance-associated proteins that also protects against apoptosis. This region mirrors the phase separation behavior seen with such proteins, like the tardigrade protein CAHS2. Moreover, we identify a synthetic protein, DHR81, that shares this combination of elevated phase separation propensity and apoptosis protection. Finally, we demonstrate that driving protective proteins into the condensate state increases apoptosis protection, and highlight the ability for DHR81 condensates to sequester caspase-7. Taken together, this work draws a link between extremotolerance-associated proteins, condensate formation, and human cellular protection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462432" rel="alternate" title="Natural and designed proteins inspired by extremotolerant organisms can form condensates and attenuate apoptosis in human cells (4 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462632</id><title>Direct Reprogramming of Non-limb Fibroblasts to Cells with Properties of Limb Progenitors (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.048943+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuji Atsuta</name></author><author><name>Changhee Lee</name></author><author><name>Alan R. Rodrigues</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Colle</name></author><author><name>Reiko R. Tomizawa</name></author><author><name>Ernesto G. Lujan</name></author><author><name>Patrick Tschopp</name></author><author><name>Joshua M. Gorham</name></author><author><name>Jean-Pierre Vannier</name></author><author><name>Christine E. Seidman</name></author><author><name>Jonathan G. Seidman</name></author><author><name>Olivier Pourquié</name></author><author><name>Clifford J. Tabin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The early limb bud consists of mesenchymal progenitors (limb progenitors) derived from the lateral plate mesoderm (LPM) that produce most of the tissues of the mature limb bud. The LPM also gives rise to the mesodermal components of the trunk, flank and neck. However, the mesenchymal cells generated at these other axial levels cannot produce the variety of cell types found in the limb bud, nor can they be directed to form a patterned appendage-like structure, even when placed in the context of the signals responsible for organizing the limb bud. Here, by taking advantage of a direct reprogramming approach, we find a set of factors (Prdm16, Zbtb16, and Lin28) normally expressed in the early limb bud, that are capable of imparting limb progenitor-like properties to non-limb fibroblasts. Cells reprogrammed by these factors show similar gene expression profiles, and can differentiate into similar cell types, as endogenous limb progenitors. The further addition of Lin41 potentiates proliferation of the reprogrammed cells while suppressing differentiation. These results suggest that these same four key factors may play pivotal roles in the specification of endogenous limb progenitors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462632" rel="alternate" title="Direct Reprogramming of Non-limb Fibroblasts to Cells with Properties of Limb Progenitors (4 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462340</id><title>Single-cell transcriptomic analysis unveils spinal motor neuron subtype diversity underpinning the water-to-land transition in vertebrates (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.049332+00:00</updated><author><name>Ee Shan Liau</name></author><author><name>Suoqin Jin</name></author><author><name>Yen-Chung Chen</name></author><author><name>Wei-Szu Liu</name></author><author><name>Luok Wen Yong</name></author><author><name>Chang-Tai Tsai</name></author><author><name>Maëliss Calon</name></author><author><name>Jr-Kai Yu</name></author><author><name>Yi-Hsien Su</name></author><author><name>Stéphane Nedelec</name></author><author><name>Qing Nie</name></author><author><name>Jun-An Chen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spinal motor neurons (MNs) integrate sensory stimuli and brain commands to generate motor movements in vertebrates. Distinct MN populations and their diversity has long been hypothesized to co-evolve with motor circuit to provide the neural basis from undulatory to ambulatory locomotion during aquatic-to-terrestrial transition of vertebrates. However, how these subtypes are evolved remains largely enigmatic. Using single-cell transcriptomics, we investigate heterogeneity in mouse MNs and discover novel segment-specific subtypes. Among limb-innervating MNs, we reveal a diverse neuropeptide code for delineating putative motor pool identities. We further uncovered that axial MNs are subdivided by three conserved and molecularly distinct subpopulations, defined by Satb2, Nr2f2 or Bcl11b expression. Although axial MNs are conserved from cephalochordates to humans, subtype diversity becomes prominent in land animals and appears to continue evolving in humans. Overall, our study provides a unified classification system for spinal MNs and paves the way towards deciphering how neuronal subtypes are evolved.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462340" rel="alternate" title="Single-cell transcriptomic analysis unveils spinal motor neuron subtype diversity underpinning the water-to-land transition in vertebrates (4 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462124</id><title>Neuronal glucose metabolism sets cholinergic tone and controls thermo-regulated signaling at the neuromuscular junction (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.049973+00:00</updated><author><name>Yan Tang</name></author><author><name>Haihong Zong</name></author><author><name>Hyokjoon Kwon</name></author><author><name>Yunping Qiu</name></author><author><name>Jacob B. Pessin</name></author><author><name>Licheng Wu</name></author><author><name>Katherine A. Buddo</name></author><author><name>Ilya Boykov</name></author><author><name>Cameron A. Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Chien-Te Lin</name></author><author><name>P. Darrell Neufer</name></author><author><name>Gary J. Schwartz</name></author><author><name>Irwin J. Kurland</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey E. Pessin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cholinergic and sympathetic counter-regulatory networks control numerous physiologic functions including learning/memory/cognition, stress responsiveness, blood pressure, heart rate and energy balance. As neurons primarily utilize glucose as their primary metabolic energy source, we generated mice with increased glycolysis in cholinergic neurons by specific deletion of the fructose-2,6-phosphatase protein TIGAR. Steady-state and stable isotope flux analyses demonstrated increased rates of glycolysis, acetyl-CoA production, acetylcholine levels and density of neuromuscular synaptic junction clusters with enhanced acetylcholine release. The increase in cholinergic signaling reduced blood pressure and heart rate with a remarkable resistance to cold-induced hypothermia. These data directly demonstrate that increased cholinergic signaling through the modulation of glycolysis has several metabolic benefits particularly to increase energy expenditure and heat production upon cold exposure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deficiency of a negative regulator of glycolysis (TIGAR) in cholinergic neurons increases the biosynthesis and content of the neurotransmitter acetylcholine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Increased cholinergic tone reduces blood pressure and heart rate while enhancing signaling at neuromuscular junction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Upregulation of neuromuscular junction activation provides protection against the paralytic curare and cold-induced hypothermia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Modulation of cholinergic neuron glycolysis may provide a novel therapeutic approach for treatment of diseases stemming from reduced acetylcholine signaling such as myasthenia gravis and sarcopenic pre-synaptic dysfunction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462124" rel="alternate" title="Neuronal glucose metabolism sets cholinergic tone and controls thermo-regulated signaling at the neuromuscular junction (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462164</id><title>A yeast with muscle doesn’t run faster: full humanization of the glycolytic pathway in Saccharomyces cerevisiae (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.050654+00:00</updated><author><name>Francine J. Boonekamp</name></author><author><name>Ewout Knibbe</name></author><author><name>Marcel A. Vieira-Lara</name></author><author><name>Melanie Wijsman</name></author><author><name>Marijke A.H. Luttik</name></author><author><name>Karen van Eunen</name></author><author><name>Maxime den Ridder</name></author><author><name>Reinier Bron</name></author><author><name>Ana Maria Almonacid Suarez</name></author><author><name>Patrick van Rijn</name></author><author><name>Justina C. Wolters</name></author><author><name>Martin Pabst</name></author><author><name>Jean-Marc Daran</name></author><author><name>Barbara Bakker</name></author><author><name>Pascale Daran-Lapujade</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;While transplantation of single genes in yeast plays a key role in elucidating gene functionality in metazoans, technical challenges hamper the humanization of full pathways and processes. Empowered by advances in synthetic biology, this study demonstrates the feasibility and implementation of full humanization of glycolysis in yeast. Single gene and full pathway transplantation revealed the remarkable conservation of both glycolytic and moonlighting functions and, combined with evolutionary strategies, brought to light novel, context-dependent responses. Remarkably, human hexokinase 1 and 2, but not 4, required mutations in their catalytic or allosteric sites for functionality in yeast, while hexokinase 3 was unable to complement its yeast ortholog. Comparison with human tissues cultures showed the preservation of turnover numbers of human glycolytic enzymes in yeast and human cell cultures. This demonstration of transplantation of an entire, essential pathway paves the way to the establishment of species, tissue and disease-specific metazoan models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This work demonstrates the successful humanization of an entire pathway in &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; and establishes an attractive strategy to study (human) glycolysis architecture and regulation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The successful humanization of the entire glycolytic pathway in yeast offers new microbial models for both fundamental and applied studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both glycolytic and moonlighting functions and turnover numbers of glycolytic enzymes are highly conserved between yeast and human.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Functionality of human hexokinases 1 and 2 in yeast requires mutations in the catalytic or allosteric binding sites.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Combination of single gene and full transplantation with laboratory evolution reveals context-dependent activity and evolution of glycolytic enzymes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462164" rel="alternate" title="A yeast with muscle doesn’t run faster: full humanization of the glycolytic pathway in Saccharomyces cerevisiae (3 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462562</id><title>A standardized method to purify cardiomyocytes from individual mouse hearts of any age (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.051585+00:00</updated><author><name>Amy M Nicks</name></author><author><name>Sara R Holman</name></author><author><name>Andrea Y Chan</name></author><author><name>Michael Tsang</name></author><author><name>Paul E Young</name></author><author><name>David T Humphreys</name></author><author><name>Nawazish Naqvi</name></author><author><name>Ahsan Husain</name></author><author><name>Ming Li</name></author><author><name>Nicola J Smith</name></author><author><name>Siiri E Iismaa</name></author><author><name>Robert M Graham</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Rationale&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Primary cardiomyocytes are invaluable for understanding postnatal heart development and elucidating disease mechanisms in genetic and pharmacological models, however, a method to obtain freshly purified cardiomyocytes at any postnatal age, without using different age-dependent isolation procedures and cell culture, is lacking.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To develop a standardized method that allows rapid isolation and purification of cardiomyocytes in high yield and viability from individual neonatal, infant, and adult mice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods and Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hearts of C57BL/6J mice were cannulated using a novel &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; aortic cannulation procedure optimized to allow cannulation of even the very small vessel of neonates (postnatal day 0-2, P0-2). Hearts were then subjected to Langendorff retrograde perfusion and enzymatic digestion. Cardiomyocytes were isolated after subsequent tissue disaggregation and filtration, in high yield (1.56-2.2×10&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; cardiomyocytes/heart) and viability (~70-100%). The larger size of infant (P10 and P13) and adult (P70), but not neonatal, cardiomyocytes relative to non-myocytes, allowed enrichment by differential centrifugation. Cardiomyocytes from all ages were further purified by immunomagnetic bead-based depletion of non-myocytes. Together, these procedures resulted in the isolation of highly purified cardiomyocytes (~94%) within 1 hour, enabling experiments using individual replicates. For example, RNA-sequencing of cardiomyocytes purified from one P2 male and female heart per litter (n=4 litters) showed distinct clustering by litters and sex differences for nine differentially expressed genes (FDR&amp;lt;0.005). &lt;italic&gt;In situ&lt;/italic&gt; fixation via coronary perfusion, performed immediately after tissue digestion, preserved the cytoarchitecture of isolated cardiomyocytes (yielding ~94% rod-shaped cardiomyocytes at all ages), allowing capture of spindle-shaped neonatal cells undergoing mitosis, as well as enabling accurate quantitation of cardiomyocyte area and nucleation state.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The procedures developed here provide a universal protocol for the rapid isolation and purification of high-quality cardiomyocytes from hearts of any postnatal age, even those of neonates, thereby enabling direct comparisons between individual hearts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462562" rel="alternate" title="A standardized method to purify cardiomyocytes from individual mouse hearts of any age (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462529</id><title>Dynamical modeling of the H3K27 epigenetic landscape in mouse embryonic stem cells (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.052648+00:00</updated><author><name>Kapil Newar</name></author><author><name>Eric Fanchon</name></author><author><name>Daniel Jost</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Polycomb system via the methylation of the lysine 27 of histone H3 (H3K27) plays central roles in the silencing of many lineage-specific genes during development. Recent experimental evidence suggested that the recruitment of histone modifying enzymes like the Polycomb repressive complex 2 (PRC2) at specific sites and their spreading capacities from these sites are key to the establishment and maintenance of a proper epigenomic landscape around Polycomb-target genes. Here, based on previous biochemical knowledge, we turned this hypothesis into a mathematical model that can predict the locus-specific distributions of H3K27 modifications. Within the biological context of mouse embryonic stem cells, our model showed quantitative agreement with experimental profiles of H3K27 acetylation and methylation around Polycomb-target genes in wild-type and mutants. In particular, we demonstrated the key role of the reader-writer module of PRC2 and of the competition between the binding of activating and repressing enzymes in shaping the H3K27 landscape around transcriptional start sites. The predicted dynamics of establishment and maintenance of the repressive trimethylated H3K27 state suggest a slow accumulation, in perfect agreement with experiments. Our approach represents a first step towards a quantitative description of PcG regulation in various cellular contexts and provides a generic framework to better characterize epigenetic regulation in normal or disease situations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462529" rel="alternate" title="Dynamical modeling of the H3K27 epigenetic landscape in mouse embryonic stem cells (3 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462573</id><title>Structural Insights into the BRAF Monomer-to-dimer Transition Mediated by RAS Binding (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.052949+00:00</updated><author><name>Juliana A. Martinez Fiesco</name></author><author><name>David E. Durrant</name></author><author><name>Deborah K. Morrison</name></author><author><name>Ping Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;An unresolved issue in RAF kinase signaling is how binding of autoinhibited RAF monomers to activated RAS initiates the conformational changes required to form active RAF dimers. Here, we present cryo-electron microscopy structures of full-length BRAF complexes derived from mammalian cells: autoinhibited monomeric BRAF:14-3-3&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;:MEK and BRAF:14-3-3&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; complexes and an inhibitor-bound, dimeric BRAF&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;:14-3-3&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; complex, at 3.7, 4.1, and 3.9 Å resolution, respectively. The RAS binding domain (RBD) of BRAF is resolved in the autoinhibited structures, and we find that neither MEK nor ATP binding is required to stabilize the autoinhibited complexes. Notably, the RBD was found to interact extensively with the 14-3-3 protomer bound to the BRAF C-terminal site. Moreover, through structure-guided mutational studies, our findings indicate that RAS-RAF binding is a dynamic process and that RBD residues at the 14-3-3 interface have a dual function, first stabilizing RBD orientation in the autoinhibited state and then contributing to full RAS contact.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462573" rel="alternate" title="Structural Insights into the BRAF Monomer-to-dimer Transition Mediated by RAS Binding (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462237</id><title>Regulation of Blos1 by IRE1 prevents the accumulation of Huntingtin protein aggregates (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.053227+00:00</updated><author><name>Donghwi Bae</name></author><author><name>Rachel Elizabeth Jones</name></author><author><name>Julie Hollien</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Huntington’s Disease is characterized by accumulation of the aggregation-prone mutant Huntingtin (mHTT) protein. Here, we show that expression of mHTT in mouse cultured cells activates IRE1, the transmembrane sensor of stress in the endoplasmic reticulum, leading to degradation of the &lt;italic&gt;Blos1&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA and repositioning of lysosomes and late endosomes toward the microtubule organizing center. Overriding &lt;italic&gt;Blos1&lt;/italic&gt; degradation results in accumulation of larger mHTT aggregates and increased cell death. Although mHTT is degraded by macroautophagy when highly expressed, we show that prior to the formation of large aggregates, mHTT is degraded via an ESCRT-dependent, endosomal microautophagy pathway. This pathway is enhanced by &lt;italic&gt;Blos1&lt;/italic&gt; degradation and appears to protect cells from a toxic, less aggregated form of mHTT.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Condensed title&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Blos1&lt;/italic&gt; regulation protects from Huntingtin protein aggregation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462237" rel="alternate" title="Regulation of Blos1 by IRE1 prevents the accumulation of Huntingtin protein aggregates (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>