<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.244634+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469877</id><title>Young transposable elements rewired gene regulatory networks in human and chimpanzee hippocampal intermediate progenitors (59 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.244954+00:00</updated><author><name>Sruti Patoori</name></author><author><name>Samantha Barnada</name></author><author><name>Marco Trizzino</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The hippocampus is associated with essential brain functions such as learning and memory. Human hippocampal volume is significantly greater than expected when compared to non-human apes, suggesting a recent expansion. Intermediate progenitors, which are able to undergo multiple rounds of proliferative division before a final neurogenic division, may have played a role in the evolutionary hippocampal expansion. To investigate the evolution of gene regulatory networks underpinning hippocampal neurogenesis in apes, we leveraged the differentiation of human and chimpanzee induced Pluripotent Stem Cells into TBR2-positive hippocampal intermediate progenitors (hpIPCs). We find that the gene networks active in hpIPCs are significantly different between humans and chimpanzees, with ~2,500 genes differentially expressed. We demonstrate that species-specific transposon-derived enhancers contribute to these transcriptomic differences. Young transposons, predominantly Endogenous Retroviruses (ERVs) and SINE-Vntr-Alus (SVAs), were co-opted as enhancers in a species-specific manner. Human-specific SVAs provided substrates for thousands of novel TBR2 binding sites, and CRISPR-mediated repression of these SVAs attenuates the expression of ~25% of the genes that are upregulated in human intermediate progenitors relative to the same cell population in the chimpanzee.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Evolution of human and chimpanzee hippocampal development was mediated by co-option of young retrotransposons into species-specific enhancers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469877" rel="alternate" title="Young transposable elements rewired gene regulatory networks in human and chimpanzee hippocampal intermediate progenitors (59 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469668</id><title>A bioactive phlebovirus-like envelope protein in a hookworm endogenous virus (46 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.245141+00:00</updated><author><name>Monique Merchant</name></author><author><name>Carlos P. Mata</name></author><author><name>Yangci Liu</name></author><author><name>Haoming Zhai</name></author><author><name>Anna V. Protasio</name></author><author><name>Yorgo Modis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Endogenous viral elements (EVEs), accounting for 15% of our genome, serve as a genetic reservoir from which new genes can emerge. Nematode EVEs are particularly diverse and informative of virus evolution. We identify Atlas virus – an intact retrovirus-like EVE in the human hookworm Ancylostoma ceylanicum, with an envelope protein genetically related to GN- GC glycoproteins from phleboviruses. A cryo-EM structure of Atlas GC reveals a class II viral membrane fusion protein fold not previously seen in retroviruses. Atlas GC has the structural hallmarks of an active fusogen. Atlas GC trimers insert into membranes with endosomal lipid compositions and low pH. When expressed on the plasma membrane, Atlas GC has cell-cell fusion activity. RNA-Seq data analysis detected transcripts mapping to Atlas virus at different stages of hookworm development. With its preserved biological activities, Atlas GC has the potential to acquire a cellular function. Our work reveals structural plasticity in reverse-transcribing RNA viruses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469668" rel="alternate" title="A bioactive phlebovirus-like envelope protein in a hookworm endogenous virus (46 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.470006</id><title>Cryo-EM structure of the Smc5/6 holo-complex (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.245328+00:00</updated><author><name>Stephen T. Hallett</name></author><author><name>Isabella Campbell Harry</name></author><author><name>Pascale Schellenberger</name></author><author><name>Lihong Zhou</name></author><author><name>Nora B. Cronin</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Baxter</name></author><author><name>Thomas J. Etheridge</name></author><author><name>Johanne M. Murray</name></author><author><name>Antony W. Oliver</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Smc5/6 complex plays an essential role in the resolution of recombination intermediates formed during mitosis or meiosis, or as a result of the cellular response to replication stress. It also functions as a restriction factor preventing viral integration. Here, we report the cryo-EM structure of the six-subunit budding yeast Smc5/6 holo-complex, reconstituted from recombinant proteins expressed in insect cells – providing a full overview of the complex in its apo / non-liganded form, and revealing how the Nse1/3/4 subcomplex binds to the hetero-dimeric SMC protein core. In addition, we demonstrate that a region within the head domain of Smc5, equivalent to the ‘W-loop’ of Smc4 or ‘F-loop’ of Smc1, mediates an essential interaction with Nse1. Taken together, these data confirm a degree of functional equivalence between the structurally unrelated KITE and HAWK accessory subunits associated with SMC complexes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.470006" rel="alternate" title="Cryo-EM structure of the Smc5/6 holo-complex (29 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469588</id><title>Single organoid RNA-sequencing reveals high organoid-to-organoid variability (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.245526+00:00</updated><author><name>Kristin Gehling</name></author><author><name>Swati Parekh</name></author><author><name>Farina Schneider</name></author><author><name>Marcel Kirchner</name></author><author><name>Vangelis Kondylis</name></author><author><name>Chrysa Nikopoulou</name></author><author><name>Peter Tessarz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Over the last decades, organoids have been established from the majority of tissue resident stem and iPS cells. They hold great promise for our understanding of mammalian organ development, but also for the study of disease or even personalized medicine. In recent years, several reports hinted at intraculture organoid variability, but a systematic analysis of such a heterogeneity has not been performed before. Here, we used RNA-seq of individual organoids to address this question. Importantly, we find that batch-to-batch variation is very low, even when prepared by different researchers. On the other hand, there is organoid-to-organoid variability within a culture. Using differential gene expression, we did not identify specific pathways that drive this variability, pointing towards possible effects of the microenvironment within the culture condition. Taken together, our study provides a framework for organoid researchers to properly consider experimental design.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469588" rel="alternate" title="Single organoid RNA-sequencing reveals high organoid-to-organoid variability (27 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469675</id><title>Improved peptide backbone fragmentation is the primary advantage of MS-cleavable crosslinkers (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.245676+00:00</updated><author><name>Lars Kolbowski</name></author><author><name>Swantje Lenz</name></author><author><name>Lutz Fischer</name></author><author><name>Ludwig R Sinn</name></author><author><name>Francis J O’Reilly</name></author><author><name>Juri Rappsilber</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Proteome-wide crosslinking mass spectrometry studies have coincided with the advent of MS-cleavable crosslinkers that can reveal the individual masses of the two crosslinked peptides. However, recently such studies have also been published with non-cleavable crosslinkers suggesting that MS-cleavability is not essential. We therefore examined in detail the advantages and disadvantages of using the most popular MS-cleavable crosslinker, DSSO. Indeed, DSSO gave rise to signature peptide fragments with a distinct mass difference (doublet) for nearly all identified crosslinked peptides. Surprisingly, we could show that it was not these peptide masses that proved the main advantage of MS-cleavability of the crosslinker, but improved peptide backbone fragmentation that allowed for more confident peptide identification. We also show that the more intricate MS3-based data acquisition approaches lack sensitivity and specificity, causing them to be outperformed by the simpler and faster stepped HCD method. This understanding will guide future developments and applications of proteome-wide crosslinking mass spectrometry.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469675" rel="alternate" title="Improved peptide backbone fragmentation is the primary advantage of MS-cleavable crosslinkers (26 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469693</id><title>A target expression threshold dictates invader defense and autoimmunity by CRISPR-Cas13 (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.245816+00:00</updated><author><name>Elena Vialetto</name></author><author><name>Yanying Yu</name></author><author><name>Scott P. Collins</name></author><author><name>Katharina G. Wandera</name></author><author><name>Lars Barquist</name></author><author><name>Chase L. Beisel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Immune systems must recognize and clear foreign invaders without eliciting autoimmunity. CRISPR-Cas immune systems in prokaryotes manage this task by following two criteria: extensive guide:target complementarity and a defined target-flanking motif. Here we report an additional requirement for RNA-targeting CRISPR-Cas13 systems: expression of the target transcript exceeding a threshold. This finding is based on targeting endogenous non-essential transcripts, which rarely elicited dormancy through collateral RNA degradation. Instead, eliciting dormancy required over-expressing targeted transcripts above a threshold. A genome-wide screen confirmed target expression levels as the principal determinant of cytotoxic autoimmunity and revealed that the threshold shifts with the guide:target pair. This expression threshold ensured defense against a lytic bacteriophage yet allowed tolerance of a targeted beneficial gene expressed from an invading plasmid. These findings establish target expression levels as a third criterion for immune activation by RNA-targeting CRISPR-Cas systems, buffering against autoimmunity and distinguishing pathogenic and benign invaders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec id="s1"&gt;&lt;title&gt;HIGHLIGHTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cas13-induced dormancy requires RNA target levels to exceed an expression threshold&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The expression threshold can prevent cytotoxic self-targeting for endogenous transcripts&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The threshold shifts depending on the CRISPR RNA guide:target pair&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The threshold allows cells to distinguish pathogenic and benign infections&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469693" rel="alternate" title="A target expression threshold dictates invader defense and autoimmunity by CRISPR-Cas13 (20 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469560</id><title>A Field-Deployable Diagnostic Assay for the Visual Detection of Misfolded Prions (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.245951+00:00</updated><author><name>Peter R. Christenson</name></author><author><name>Manci Li</name></author><author><name>Gage Rowden</name></author><author><name>Marc Schwabenlander</name></author><author><name>Tiffany M. Wolf</name></author><author><name>Sang-Hyun Oh</name></author><author><name>Peter A. Larsen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Diagnostic tools for the detection of protein-misfolding diseases (i.e., proteopathies) are limited. Gold nanoparticles (AuNPs) facilitate sensitive diagnostic techniques via visual color change for the detection of a variety of targets. In parallel, recently developed quaking-induced conversion (QuIC) assays leverage protein-amplification and fluorescent signaling for the accurate detection of misfolded proteins. Here, we combine AuNP and QuIC technologies for the visual detection of amplified misfolded prion proteins from tissues of wild white-tailed deer infected with chronic wasting disease (CWD), a prion disease of cervids. Our newly developed assay, MN-QuIC™, enables both naked-eye and light-absorbance measurements for detection of misfolded prions. MN-QuIC™ leverages basic laboratory equipment that is cost-effective and portable, thus facilitating real-time prion diagnostics across a variety of settings. To test the portability of our assay, we deployed to a rural field-station in southeastern Minnesota and tested for CWD on site. We successfully demonstrated that MN-QuIC™ is functional in a non-traditional laboratory setting by performing a blinded analysis in the field and correctly identifying all CWD positive and CWD not detected deer at the field site in less than 24 hours, thus documenting the portability of the assay. Additionally, we show that electrostatic forces help govern the AuNP/prion interactions. Importantly, all of our white-tailed deer (n=37) were independently tested using ELISA, IHC, and/or RT-QuIC technologies and results secured with MN-QuIC™ were 100% consistent with these tests. We conclude that hybrid AuNP and QuIC assays, such as MN-QuIC™, have great potential for sensitive, field-deployable diagnostics of a variety of protein misfolding diseases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Statement of Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Portable diagnostic tools for the detection of prion and protein-misfolding diseases are limited. Using chronic wasting disease (CWD) as a model, we demonstrate the functionality of a gold nanoparticle (AuNP)-based assay for the field-based detection of prion diseases. CWD is spreading through cervid populations across North America and the disease poses significant threats to a number of economic sectors, with global implications. Our newly developed diagnostic assay leverages the visible color change of AuNPs to detect the presence of CWD-causing prions. The assay can be performed using lowcost equipment and reagents, thus having great potential to expand prion disease surveillance efforts and prevent infectious prions from entering the human food chain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469560" rel="alternate" title="A Field-Deployable Diagnostic Assay for the Visual Detection of Misfolded Prions (19 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.470029</id><title>Directed evolution of colE1 plasmid replication compatibility: a fast tractable tunable model for investigating biological orthogonality (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.246093+00:00</updated><author><name>Santiago Chaillou</name></author><author><name>Eleftheria-Pinelopi Stamou</name></author><author><name>Leticia Torres</name></author><author><name>Ana B. Riesco</name></author><author><name>Warren Hazelton</name></author><author><name>Vitor B. Pinheiro</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Plasmids of the ColE1 family are among the most frequently used plasmids in molecular biology. They were adopted early in the field for many biotechnology applications, and as model systems to study plasmid biology. The mechanism of replication of ColE1 plasmids is well understood, involving the interaction between a plasmid-encoded sense-antisense gene pair (RNAI and RNAII). Because of its mechanism of replication, bacterial cells cannot maintain two different plasmids with the same origin, with one being rapidly lost from the population – a process known as plasmid incompatibility. While mutations in the regulatory genes RNAI and RNAII have been reported to make colE1 plasmids more compatible, there has been no attempt to engineer compatible colE1 origins, which can be used for multi-plasmid applications and that can bypass design constrains created by the current limited plasmid origin repertoire available. Here, we show that by targeting sequence diversity to the loop regions of RNAI (and RNAII), it is possible to select new viable colE1 origins that are compatible with the wild-type one. We demonstrate origin compatibility is not simply determined by sequence divergence in the loops, and that pairwise compatibility is not an accurate guide for higher order interactions. We identify potential principles to engineer plasmid copy number independently from other regulatory strategies and we propose plasmid compatibility as a tractable model to study biological orthogonality. New characterised plasmid origins increase flexibility and accessible complexity of design for challenging synthetic biology applications where biological circuits can be dispersed between multiple independent genetic elements.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.470029" rel="alternate" title="Directed evolution of colE1 plasmid replication compatibility: a fast tractable tunable model for investigating biological orthogonality (18 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470087</id><title>High resolution species detection: accurate long read eDNA metabarcoding of North Sea fish using Oxford Nanopore sequencing (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.246637+00:00</updated><author><name>Karlijn Doorenspleet</name></author><author><name>Lara Jansen</name></author><author><name>Saskia Oosterbroek</name></author><author><name>Oscar Bos</name></author><author><name>Pauline Kamermans</name></author><author><name>Max Janse</name></author><author><name>Erik Wurz</name></author><author><name>Albertinka Murk</name></author><author><name>Reindert Nijland</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To monitor the effect of nature restoration projects in North Sea ecosystems, accurate and intensive biodiversity assessments are vital. DNA based techniques and especially environmental DNA (eDNA) metabarcoding from seawater is becoming a powerful monitoring tool. However, current approaches are based on genetic target regions of &amp;lt;500 nucleotides, which offer limited taxonomic resolution. This study aims to develop and validate a long read nanopore sequencing method for eDNA that enables improved identification of fish species. We designed a universal primer pair targeting a 2kb region covering the 12S and 16S rRNA genes of fish mitochondria. eDNA was amplified and sequenced using the Oxford Nanopore MiniON. Sequence data was processed using the new pipeline Decona, and accurate consensus identities of above 99.9% were retrieved. The primer set efficiency was tested with eDNA from a 3.000.000 L zoo aquarium with 31 species of bony fish and elasmobranchs. Over 55% of the species present were identified on species level and over 75% on genus level. Next, our long read eDNA metabarcoding approach was applied to North Sea eDNA field samples collected at ship wreck sites, the Gemini Offshore Wind Farm, the Borkum Reef Grounds and a bare sand bottom. Here, location specific fish and vertebrate communities were obtained. Incomplete reference databases still form a major bottleneck in further developing high resolution long read metabarcoding. Yet, the method has great potential for rapid and accurate fish species monitoring in marine field studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470087" rel="alternate" title="High resolution species detection: accurate long read eDNA metabarcoding of North Sea fish using Oxford Nanopore sequencing (15 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469707</id><title>The RNA-binding protein Orb2 is associated with microcephaly and supports centrosome asymmetry in neural stem cells (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.247030+00:00</updated><author><name>Beverly V. Robinson</name></author><author><name>Junnan Fang</name></author><author><name>Dipen S. Mehta</name></author><author><name>Joseph Buehler</name></author><author><name>Dorothy A. Lerit</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To maintain a balance of self-renewal versus neurogenesis, neural stem cells (NSCs) undergo repeated cycles of asymmetric cell division along an invariant polarity axis instructed by centrosomes. During interphase, the NSC centrosomes are defined by marked asymmetries in protein composition and functional activity as microtubule-organizing centers. Here, we show a conserved RNA-binding protein, Orb2, supports centrosome asymmetry in interphase NSCs. While Orb2 localizes to the active apical centrosome, it promotes the transient inactivation of the basal centrosome required for centrosome segregation and spindle morphogenesis. Orb2 is required cell autonomously within NSCs to support centrosome asymmetry and maintenance of the stem cell pool. Conversely, loss of &lt;italic&gt;orb2&lt;/italic&gt; manifests in microcephaly independent of Orb2 function in NSCs. We suggest Orb2 plays opposing roles in centrosome activation and inactivation, possibly through the translational regulation of multiple mRNA substrates. Bioinformatics uncovers a significant overlap among RNA targets between &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; Orb2 and human CPEB4, consistent with a conserved role for CPEB proteins in centrosome regulation and neurodevelopment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469707" rel="alternate" title="The RNA-binding protein Orb2 is associated with microcephaly and supports centrosome asymmetry in neural stem cells (15 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469329</id><title>Directing iPSC Differentiation into iTenocytes using Combined Scleraxis Overexpression and Cyclic Loading (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.247312+00:00</updated><author><name>Angela Papalamprou</name></author><author><name>Victoria Yu</name></author><author><name>Angel Chen</name></author><author><name>Tina Stefanovic</name></author><author><name>Giselle Kaneda</name></author><author><name>Khosrowdad Salehi</name></author><author><name>Chloe Castaneda</name></author><author><name>Arkadiusz Gertych</name></author><author><name>Juliane D Glaeser</name></author><author><name>Dmitriy Sheyn</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Regenerative therapies for tendon are falling behind other tissues due to the lack of an appropriate and potent cell therapeutic candidate. This study aimed to induce cell tenogenesis using stable Scleraxis (Scx) overexpression in combination with uniaxial mechanical stretch of mesenchymal stromal cells (MSCs) of different origins. Scleraxis (Scx) is the single direct molecular regulator of tendon differentiation known so far. Mechanoregulation is known to be a central element guiding tendon development and healing. Cells explored were bone marrow-derived (BM-)MSCs as well as MSCs differentiated from induced pluripotent stem cells (iMSCs). Upregulation of early and late tendon markers, increased collagen deposition, and morphometric and cytoskeleton-related changes in mechanically stimulated Scx-overexpressing iMSCs compared to BM-MSCs and controls. Our findings suggest that these cells can be differentiated into tenocytes and may be a better candidate for tendon cell therapy applications than BM-MSCs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469329" rel="alternate" title="Directing iPSC Differentiation into iTenocytes using Combined Scleraxis Overexpression and Cyclic Loading (15 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.470051</id><title>Genetic perturbation enhances functional heterogeneity in alkaline phosphatase (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.247528+00:00</updated><author><name>Morito Sakuma</name></author><author><name>Shingo Honda</name></author><author><name>Hiroshi Ueno</name></author><author><name>Kentaro Miyazaki</name></author><author><name>Nobuhiko Tokuriki</name></author><author><name>Hiroyuki Noji</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Enzymes inherently exhibit molecule-to-molecule heterogeneity in catalytic activity or function, which underlies the acquisition of new functions in evolutionary processes. However, correlations between the functional heterogeneity of an enzyme and its multi-functionality or promiscuity remain elusive. In addition, the modulation of functional heterogeneity upon genetic perturbation is currently unexplored. Here, we quantitatively analyzed functional heterogeneity in the wild-type and 69 single-point mutants of &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; alkaline phosphatase (AP) by employing single-molecule assay with a femtoliter reactor array device. Most mutant enzymes exhibited higher functional heterogeneity than the wild-type enzyme, irrespective of catalytic activity. These results indicated that the wild-type AP minimizes functional heterogeneity, and single-point mutations can significantly expand the span of functional heterogeneity in AP. Moreover, we identified a clear correlation between functional heterogeneity and promiscuous activities. These findings suggest that enzymes can acquire greater functional heterogeneity following marginal genetic perturbations that concomitantly promote catalytic promiscuity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.470051" rel="alternate" title="Genetic perturbation enhances functional heterogeneity in alkaline phosphatase (13 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469619</id><title>Thermodynamic Constraints on Electromicrobial Protein Production (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.247700+00:00</updated><author><name>Lucas Wise</name></author><author><name>Sabrina Marecos</name></author><author><name>Katie Randolph</name></author><author><name>Eric Nshimyumukiza</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Hassan</name></author><author><name>Jacob Strouse</name></author><author><name>Farshid Salimijazi</name></author><author><name>Buz Barstow</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Global consumption of protein is projected to double by the middle of the 21&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; century&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. However, protein production is one of the most energy intensive and environmentally damaging parts of the food supply system today. Electromicrobial production technologies that combine renewable electricity and CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-fixing microbial metabolism could dramatically increase the energy efficiency of commodity chemical production&lt;sup&gt;2–5&lt;/sup&gt;. Here we present a molecular-scale model that sets an upper limit on the performance of any organism performing electromicrobial protein production. We show that engineered microbes that fix CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; using reducing equivalents produced by H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-oxidation or extracellular electron uptake could produce amino acids with energy inputs as low as 64 MJ kg&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. This work provides a roadmap for development of engineered microbes that could significantly expand access to proteins produced with a low environmental footprint.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469619" rel="alternate" title="Thermodynamic Constraints on Electromicrobial Protein Production (12 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469129</id><title>Fast surveillance response and genome sequencing reveal the circulation of a new Yellow Fever Virus sublineage in 2021, in Minas Gerais, Brazil (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.247881+00:00</updated><author><name>Miguel S. Andrade</name></author><author><name>Fabrício S. Campos</name></author><author><name>Cirilo H. de Oliveira</name></author><author><name>Ramon Silva Oliveira</name></author><author><name>Aline A. S. Campos</name></author><author><name>Marco A. B. Almeida</name></author><author><name>Danilo Simonini-Teixeira</name></author><author><name>Anaiá da P. Sevá</name></author><author><name>Andrea Oliveira Dias Temponi</name></author><author><name>Fernando Maria Magalhães</name></author><author><name>Danielle Costa Capistrano Chaves</name></author><author><name>Maira Alves Pereira</name></author><author><name>Ludmila Oliveira Lamounier</name></author><author><name>Givaldo Gomes de Menezes</name></author><author><name>Sandy Micaele Aquino Teixeira</name></author><author><name>Maria Eduarda Gonçalves dos Santos</name></author><author><name>Sofía Bernal-Valle</name></author><author><name>Nicolas F. D. Müller</name></author><author><name>Jader da C. Cardoso</name></author><author><name>Edmilson dos Santos</name></author><author><name>Maria A. Mares-Guia</name></author><author><name>George R. Albuquerque</name></author><author><name>Alessandro P. M. Romano</name></author><author><name>Ana C. Franco</name></author><author><name>Bergmann M. Ribeiro</name></author><author><name>Paulo M. Roehe</name></author><author><name>Filipe V. S. Abreu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Yellow fever virus (YFV) exhibits a sylvatic cycle of transmission involving wild mosquitoes and non-human primates (NHP). In Brazil, YFV is endemic in the Amazon region, from where waves of epidemic expansion towards other Brazilian states eventually occur. During such waves, the virus usually follows the route from North to the Central-West and Southeast Brazilian regions. Amidst these journeys, outbreaks of Yellow Fever (YF) in NHPs, with spillovers to humans have been observed. In the present work, we describe a surveillance effort encompassing the technology of smartphone applications and the coordinated action of several research institutions and health services that succeeded in the first confirmation of YFV in NHPs in the state of Minas Gerais (MG), Southeast region, in 2021, followed by genome sequencing in an interval of only ten days. Samples from two NHPs (one of the species &lt;italic&gt;Alouatta caraya&lt;/italic&gt; in the municipality of Icaraí de Minas and the other of the species &lt;italic&gt;Callithrix penicillata&lt;/italic&gt; in the municipality of Ubaí) were collected and the presence of YFV was confirmed by RT-qPCR. We generated three near-complete by Nanopore sequencer MinION. Phylogenetic analysis revealed that all viral genomes recovered are equal and related to lineage South America 1, clustering with a genome detected in the Amazon region (Pará state) in 2017. These findings reveal the occurrence of a new wave of viral expansion in MG, six years after the beginning of the major outbreak in the state, between 2015-2018. No human cases were reported to date, showing the importance of coordinated work between local surveillance based on available technologies and support laboratories to ensure a quick response and implementation of contingency measures towards avoiding the occurrence of YF cases in humans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469129" rel="alternate" title="Fast surveillance response and genome sequencing reveal the circulation of a new Yellow Fever Virus sublineage in 2021, in Minas Gerais, Brazil (12 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469679</id><title>Interplay Between KRAS and LZTR1 Protein Turnover, Controlled by CUL3/LZTR1 E3 Ubiquitin Ligase, is Disrupted by KRAS Mutations (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.248320+00:00</updated><author><name>Andreas Damianou</name></author><author><name>Zhu Liang</name></author><author><name>Frederik Lassen</name></author><author><name>George Vere</name></author><author><name>Svenja Hester</name></author><author><name>Philip D Charles</name></author><author><name>Adan Pinto-Fernandez</name></author><author><name>Alberto Santos-Delgado</name></author><author><name>Roman Fischer</name></author><author><name>Benedikt M Kessler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;KRAS is a proto-oncogene encoding a small GTPase. Mutations contribute up to 30% of human solid tumours including lung adenocarcinoma, pancreatic and colorectal carcinomas. Most KRAS activating mutations interfere with GTP hydrolysis, essential for its role as a molecular switch, leading to alterations in their molecular environment and oncogenic signalling. Here, APEX-2 proximity labelling was used to profile the molecular environment of wild type and G12D, G13D and Q61H activating mutants of KRAS under both, starvation and stimulation conditions. We demonstrate by quantitative proteomics the presence of known interactors of KRAS including a-RAF and LZTR1, which varied in abundance with wildtype and KRAS mutants. Notably, the KRAS mutations G12D, G13D and Q61H abrogate association with LZTR1. Wildtype KRAS and LZTR1, as part of the CUL3 ubiquitin E3 ligase complex, affect each other’s protein stability, revealing a direct feedback loop mechanism. KRAS mutations disconnect this regulatory circuit, thereby contributing to oncogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469679" rel="alternate" title="Interplay Between KRAS and LZTR1 Protein Turnover, Controlled by CUL3/LZTR1 E3 Ubiquitin Ligase, is Disrupted by KRAS Mutations (10 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.470010</id><title>Lipid droplets are required for lipid mediator production and cancer cell proliferation (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.249175+00:00</updated><author><name>Toni Petan</name></author><author><name>Thomas O. Eichmann</name></author><author><name>Robert Zimmermann</name></author><author><name>Anja Pucer Janež</name></author><author><name>Jana Gerstmeier</name></author><author><name>Gérard Lambeau</name></author><author><name>Eva Jarc Jovičić</name></author><author><name>Paul Mike Jordan</name></author><author><name>Oliver Werz</name></author><author><name>Vesna Brglez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Lipid droplets are dynamic organelles with a central role in fatty acid metabolism. They protect cells from lipotoxicity by sequestering excess fatty acids but also provide fatty acids for metabolic reactions and signalling events. Here we show that lipid droplet turnover in cancer cells is required for production of ω-3 and ω-6 polyunsaturated fatty acid (PUFA)-derived inflammatory lipid mediators, including eicosanoids and specialised pro-resolving mediators. We show that incorporation of PUFAs into triglycerides mediated by diacylglycerol acyltransferase 1 (DGAT1), and their release by adipose triglyceride lipase (ATGL), are required for cyclooxygenase- and lipoxygenase-dependent lipid mediator production and cancer cell proliferation. The human group X secreted phospholipase A2 (hGX sPLA2) drives the delivery of membrane-derived PUFAs into lipid droplets, while ATGL promotes the incorporation of lipid droplet-derived PUFAs into phospholipids. The group IVA cytosolic PLA2 (cPLA2α) acts on membrane phospholipids and complements ATGL in the regulation of PUFA trafficking between phospholipids and triglycerides. This study identifies lipid droplets as essential cellular hubs that control PUFA availability for production of lipid mediators involved in inflammation and tumorigenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.470010" rel="alternate" title="Lipid droplets are required for lipid mediator production and cancer cell proliferation (9 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470134</id><title>Allelic correlation is a marker of tradeoffs between barriers to transmission of expression variability and signal responsiveness in genetic networks (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.249424+00:00</updated><author><name>Ryan H Boe</name></author><author><name>Vinay Ayyappan</name></author><author><name>Lea Schuh</name></author><author><name>Arjun Raj</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Accurately functioning genetic networks should be responsive to signals but prevent transmission of stochastic bursts of expression. Existing data in mammalian cells suggests that such transcriptional "noise" is transmitted by some genes and not others, suggesting that noise transmission is tunable, perhaps at the expense of other signal processing capabilities. However, systematic claims about noise transmission in genetic networks have been limited by the inability to directly measure noise transmission. Here we build a mathematical framework capable of modeling allelic correlation and noise transmission. We find that allelic correlation and noise transmission correspond across a broad range of model parameters and network architectures. We further find that limiting noise transmission comes with the trade-off of being unresponsive to signals, and that within the parameter regimes that are responsive to signals, there is a further trade-off between response time and basal noise transmission. Using a published allele specific single cell RNA-sequencing dataset, we found that genes with high allelic odds ratios are enriched for cell-type specific functions, and that within multiple signaling pathways, factors which are upstream in the pathway have higher allelic odds ratios than downstream factors. Overall, our findings suggest that some degree of noise transmission is required to be responsive to signals, but that minimization of noise transmission can be accomplished by trading-off for a slower response time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470134" rel="alternate" title="Allelic correlation is a marker of tradeoffs between barriers to transmission of expression variability and signal responsiveness in genetic networks (9 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470272</id><title>Analysis of 8000 proteins and reduced carry over significantly increase the throughput of single-shot proteomics (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.249703+00:00</updated><author><name>Karel Stejskal</name></author><author><name>Jeff Op de Beeck</name></author><author><name>Manuel Matzinger</name></author><author><name>Gerhard Duernberger</name></author><author><name>Oleksandr Boychenko</name></author><author><name>Paul Jacobs</name></author><author><name>Karl Mechtler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the field of LC-MS based proteomics, increases in sampling depth and proteome coverage have mainly been accomplished by rapid advances in mass spectrometer technology. The comprehensiveness and quality of data that can be generated do however also depend on the performance provided by nano liquid chromatography (nanoLC) separations. Proper selection of reversed-phase separation columns can be of paramount importance to provide the MS instrument with peptides at the highest possible concentration and separated at the highest possible resolution. As an alternative to traditional packed bed LC column technology that uses beads packed into capillary tubing, we present a novel LC column format based on photolithographic definition and Deep Reactive Ion Etching (DRIE) into silicon wafers. With a next generation pillar array column designed for universal use in bottom-up proteomics, the critical dimensions of the stationary phase support structures have been reduced by a factor of 2 to provide further increases in separation power. To demonstrate the potential for single-shot proteomics workflows, we report on a series of optimization and benchmarking experiments where we combine LC separation on a new generation of pillar array columns using Vanquish Neo UHPLC with fast Orbitrap Tribrid MS data-dependent acquisition (DDA) and High-Field Asymmetric Waveform Ion Mobility Spectrometry (FAIMS). In addition to providing superior proteome coverage, robust operation over more than 1 month with a single nanoESI emitter and reduction of the column related sample carry over are additional figures of merit that can help improve proteome research sensitivity, productivity and standardization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470272" rel="alternate" title="Analysis of 8000 proteins and reduced carry over significantly increase the throughput of single-shot proteomics (8 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469742</id><title>Molecular Basis of Antibiotic Self-Resistance in a Bee Larvae Pathogen (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.250083+00:00</updated><author><name>Tam Dang</name></author><author><name>Bernhard Loll</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Müller</name></author><author><name>Ranko Skobalj</name></author><author><name>Julia Ebeling</name></author><author><name>Timur Bulatov</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Gensel</name></author><author><name>Josefine Göbel</name></author><author><name>Markus C. Wahl</name></author><author><name>Elke Genersch</name></author><author><name>Andi Mainz</name></author><author><name>Roderich D. Süssmuth</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Paenibacillus larvae&lt;/italic&gt;, the causative agent of the devastating honey-bee disease American Foulbrood, produces the cationic polyketide-peptide hybrid paenilamicin that displays high antibacterial and antifungal activity. Its biosynthetic gene cluster contains a gene coding for the &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;-acetyltransferase PamZ. We show that PamZ acts as self-resistance factor in &lt;italic&gt;P. larvae&lt;/italic&gt; by deactivation of paenilamicin. Using tandem MS, NMR spectroscopy and synthetic diastereomers, we identified the N-terminal amino group of the agmatinamic acid as the &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;-acetylation site. These findings highlight the pharmacophore region of paenilamicin, which we very recently identified as a new ribosome inhibitor. Here, we further elucidated the crystal structure of PamZ:acetyl-CoA complex at 1.34 Å resolution. An unusual tandem-domain architecture provides a well-defined substrate-binding groove decorated with negatively-charged residues to specifically attract the cationic paenilamicin. Our results will help to understand the mode of action of paenilamicin and its role in pathogenicity of &lt;italic&gt;P. larvae&lt;/italic&gt; to fight American Foulbrood.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469742" rel="alternate" title="Molecular Basis of Antibiotic Self-Resistance in a Bee Larvae Pathogen (8 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469626</id><title>Host tissue proteomics reveal insights into the molecular basis of Schistosoma haematobium-induced bladder pathology (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.250414+00:00</updated><author><name>Derick N. M. Osakunor</name></author><author><name>Kenji Ishida</name></author><author><name>Olivia K. Lamanna</name></author><author><name>Mario Rossi</name></author><author><name>Michael H. Hsieh</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Urogenital schistosomiasis remains a major public health concern worldwide. In response to egg deposition, the host bladder undergoes gross and molecular morphological changes relevant for disease manifestation. However, limited mechanistic studies to date imply that the molecular mechanisms underlying pathology have not been well-defined. We leveraged a mouse model of urogenital schistosomiasis to perform for the first time, proteome profiling of the early molecular events that occur in the bladder after exposure to &lt;italic&gt;S. haematobium&lt;/italic&gt; eggs, and to elucidate the protein pathways involved in urogenital schistosomiasis-induced pathology.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Purified &lt;italic&gt;S. haematobium&lt;/italic&gt; eggs or control vehicle were microinjected into the bladder walls of mice. Mice were sacrificed seven days post-injection and bladder proteins isolated and processed for proteome profiling using mass spectrometry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We demonstrate that biological processes including carcinogenesis, immune and inflammatory responses, increased protein translation or turnover, oxidative stress responses, reduced cell adhesion and epithelial barrier integrity, and increased glucose metabolism were significantly enriched in &lt;italic&gt;S. haematobium&lt;/italic&gt; infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;S. haematobium&lt;/italic&gt; egg deposition in the bladder results in significant changes in proteins and pathways that play a role in pathology. Our findings highlight the potential bladder protein indicators for host-parasite interplay and provide new insights into the complex dynamics of pathology and characteristic bladder tissue changes in urogenital schistosomiasis. The findings will be relevant for development of improved interventions for disease control.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The molecular mechanisms underlying the urinary and genital pathology from urogenital schistosomiasis have not been well-defined. This has mainly been due to limited mechanistic studies and the lack of a suitable animal model for &lt;italic&gt;S. haematobium&lt;/italic&gt; infection. We leveraged a mouse model of urogenital schistosomiasis, along with proteomics analysis, to determine the early molecular events that occur in the bladder after exposure to &lt;italic&gt;S. haematobium&lt;/italic&gt; eggs, and to define protein pathways that may be involved in morbidity from urogenital schistosomiasis infection. Our results show that &lt;italic&gt;S. haematobium&lt;/italic&gt; egg deposition in the bladder results in significant changes in proteins and pathways that play a role in pathology. Biological processes including carcinogenesis, immune and inflammatory responses, increased protein translation or turnover, oxidative stress responses, reduced cell adhesion and epithelial barrier integrity, and increased glucose metabolism are significantly enriched in &lt;italic&gt;S. haematobium&lt;/italic&gt; infection. Our findings highlight important protein indicators of host-parasite interactions in the bladder and their association with tissue changes in urogenital schistosomiasis. The findings presented here will be relevant for development of improved interventions for disease control, and contribute to realizing the 2021-2030 NTD goals by demonstrating evidence on the early events that occur during schistosome infection..&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469626" rel="alternate" title="Host tissue proteomics reveal insights into the molecular basis of Schistosoma haematobium-induced bladder pathology (7 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470222</id><title>Inference of Rift Valley Fever pathogenesis in Bos taurus using a gene co-expression network (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.250574+00:00</updated><author><name>John Kaniaru Gitau</name></author><author><name>Rosaline Wanjiru Macharia</name></author><author><name>Kennedy Wanjau Mwangi</name></author><author><name>Nehemiah Mosioma Ongeso</name></author><author><name>Edwin Murungi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Rift Valley Fever (RVF) is a viral disease caused by the Rift Valley Fever virus and spread mainly by the Aedes and Culex mosquito species. The disease primarily infects domestic animals such as sheep, goats, and cattle, resulting in a spectrum of clinical outcomes including morbidity, massive storm abortions, and neonatal fatalities. RVF outbreaks are closely linked to above-average rainfall and flooding, which create an ideal environment for mosquitos to breed, multiply, and transmit the virus to animals. The outcomes of human RVF infection range from self-limiting febrile illness to potentially fatal hemorrhagic diatheses and miscarriage in pregnant women. Collectively, the economic losses due to the zoonotic RVF disease is immense. Methods: Using the Weighted Gene Co-expression Network Analysis (WGCNA) package, RNA-Seq data generated from five healthy Bos taurus steer calves aged 4-6 months was obtained from the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) database (Accession number GSE71417). The data was utilized to construct a gene co-expression network. Enriched modules containing genes potentially involved in RVF infection progression were identified. Moreover, using the Multiple Expectation Maximizations for Motif Elicitation (MEME) suite, consensus regulatory motifs of enriched gene clusters were deciphered and the most abundant putative regulatory motif in each enriched module unveiled by comparative analysis with publicly available motifs using the TOMTOM motif comparison tool. The potential roles of the identified regulatory motifs were inferred by literature mining. Results: The constructed gene co-expression network revealed thirty-three (33) modules, nine of which were enriched for Gene Ontology terms linked to RVF pathogenesis. Functional enrichment in two (red and turquoise) of the nine modules was significant. ASH1-like histone lysine methyltransferase and Astrotactin were the hub genes for the red and turquoise modules respectively. ASH1-like histone lysine methyltransferase gene is involved in chromatin epigenetic modification while Astrotactin is a vertebrate-specific gene that plays an important role in neurodevelopment. Additionally, consensus regulatory motifs located on the 3' end of genes in each enriched module was identified. Conclusions: In this study, we have developed a gene co-expression network that has aided in the unveiling of functionally related genes, intramodular hub genes, and immunity genes potentially involved in RVF pathogenesis. The discovery of functional genes with putative critical roles in the establishment of RVF infection establishment will contribute to the understanding of the molecular mechanism of RVF pathogenesis. Importantly, the putative regulatory motifs identified are plausible targets for RVF drug and vaccine development. Keywords: Rift Valley Fever, Bos taurus, Gene co-expression network, modules, hub genes, Regulatory motifs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470222" rel="alternate" title="Inference of Rift Valley Fever pathogenesis in Bos taurus using a gene co-expression network (6 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469697</id><title>Modulation of PKM1/2 levels by steric blocking morpholinos alters the metabolic and pluripotent state of murine pluripotent stem cells (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.250740+00:00</updated><author><name>Joshua G. Dierolf</name></author><author><name>Hailey L.M. Hunter</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Watson</name></author><author><name>Dean H. Betts</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cellular metabolism plays both an active and passive role in embryonic development, pluripotency, and cell-fate decisions. However, little is known regarding the role of metabolism in regulating the recently described “formative” pluripotent state. The pluripotent developmental continuum features a metabolic switch from a bivalent metabolism (both glycolysis and oxidative phosphorylation) in naïve cells, to predominantly glycolysis in primed cells. We investigated the role of pyruvate kinase muscle isoforms (PKM1/2) in naïve, formative, and primed mouse embryonic stem cells through modulation of PKM1/2 mRNA transcripts using steric blocking morpholinos that downregulate PKM2 and upregulate PKM1. We have examined these effects in naïve, formative, and primed cells by quantifying the effects of PKM1/2 modulation on pluripotent and metabolic transcripts and by measuring shifts in the population frequencies of cells expressing naïve and primed cell surface markers by flow cytometry. Our results demonstrate that modulating PKM1 and PKM2 levels alters the transition from the naïve state into a primed pluripotent state by enhancing the proportion of the affected cells seen in the “formative” state. Therefore, we conclude that PKM1/2 actively contributes to mechanisms that oversee early stem pluripotency and their progression towards a primed pluripotent state.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469697" rel="alternate" title="Modulation of PKM1/2 levels by steric blocking morpholinos alters the metabolic and pluripotent state of murine pluripotent stem cells (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469686</id><title>Using light-sheet microscopy to study spontaneous activity in the developing lateral-line system (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.250935+00:00</updated><author><name>Qiuxiang Zhang</name></author><author><name>Katie Kindt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hair cells are the sensory receptors in the auditory and vestibular systems of all vertebrates, and in the lateral-line system of aquatic vertebrates. During development, spontaneous activity in hair cells shapes the formation of these sensory systems. In auditory hair cells of mice, coordinated waves of spontaneous activity can be triggered by concomitant activity in nearby supporting cells. But in mammals, developing auditory and vestibular hair cells can also autonomously generate spontaneous events independent of supporting cell activity. To date, significant progress has been made studying spontaneous activity in the auditory and vestibular systems of mammals, in isolated cultures. The purpose of this work is to explore the zebrafish lateral-line system as a model to study and understand spontaneous activity &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Our work applies genetically encoded calcium indicators along with light-sheet fluorescence microscopy to visualize spontaneous calcium activity in the developing lateral-line system. Consistent with our previous work, we show that spontaneous calcium activity is present in developing lateral-line hair cells. We now show that supporting cells that surround hair cells, and cholinergic efferent terminals that directly contact hair cells are also spontaneously active. Using two-color functional imaging we demonstrate that spontaneous activity in hair cells does not correlate with activity in either supporting cells or cholinergic terminals. We find that during lateral-line development, hair cells autonomously generate spontaneous events. Using localized calcium indicators, we show that within hair cells, spontaneous calcium activity occurs in two distinct domains–the mechanosensory bundle and the presynapse. Further, spontaneous activity in the mechanosensory bundle ultimately drives spontaneous calcium influx at the presynapse. Comprehensively, our results indicate that in developing lateral-line hair cells, autonomously generated spontaneous activity originates with spontaneous mechanosensory events. Overall, with robust spontaneous activity three different cell types, the developing lateral line is a rich model to study these activities in an intact sensory organ. Future work studying this model may further our understanding of these activities and their role in sensory system formation, function and regeneration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469686" rel="alternate" title="Using light-sheet microscopy to study spontaneous activity in the developing lateral-line system (6 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469940</id><title>Cryo-EM structure of hexameric yeast Lon (PIM1) highlights importance of conserved structural elements (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.251138+00:00</updated><author><name>Jie Yang</name></author><author><name>Albert S. Song</name></author><author><name>R. Luke Wiseman</name></author><author><name>Gabriel C. Lander</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Lon protease is a conserved ATP-dependent serine protease composed of an AAA+ domain that mechanically unfolds substrates and a serine protease domain that degrades unfolded substrates. In yeast, dysregulation of Lon protease (PIM1) attenuates lifespan and leads to gross mitochondrial morphologic perturbations. Although structures of bacterial and human Lon protease reveal a hexameric assembly, PIM1 was speculated to form a heptameric assembly, and is uniquely characterized by a ~50 residue insertion between the ATPase and protease domains. To understand the yeast-specific properties of PIM1, we determined a high-resolution cryo-EM structure of PIM1 in a substrate-translocating state. Here, we reveal that PIM1 forms a hexamer, conserved with that of bacterial and human Lon proteases, wherein the ATPase domains form a canonical closed spiral that enables pore loop residues to translocate substrate to the protease chamber. In the substrate-translocating state, PIM1 protease domains form a planar protease chamber in an active conformation and are uniquely characterized by a ~15 residue C-terminal extension. These additional C-terminal residues form an alpha-helix that is located along the base of the protease domain. Finally, we did not observe density for the yeast-specific insertion between the ATPase and protease domains, likely due to high conformational flexibility. Biochemical studies to investigate the insertion using constructs that truncated or replaced the insertion with a glycine-serine linker suggest that the yeast-specific insertion is dispensable for PIM1’s enzymatic function. Altogether, our structural and biochemical studies highlight unique components of PIM1 machinery and demonstrate evolutionary conservation of Lon protease function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469940" rel="alternate" title="Cryo-EM structure of hexameric yeast Lon (PIM1) highlights importance of conserved structural elements (6 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469498</id><title>Stochastic Simulation Algorithm for effective spreading dynamics on Time-evolving Adaptive NetworX (SSATAN-X) (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.251931+00:00</updated><author><name>Nadezdha Malysheva</name></author><author><name>Max von Kleist</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Modelling and simulating the dynamics of pathogen spreading has been proven crucial to inform public heath decisions, containment strategies, as well as cost-effectiveness calculations. Pathogen spreading is often modelled as a stochastic process that is driven by pathogen exposure on time-evolving contact networks. In &lt;italic&gt;adaptive networks&lt;/italic&gt;, the spreading process depends not only on the dynamics of a contact network, but vice versa, infection dynamics may alter risk behaviour and thus feed back onto contact dynamics, leading to emergent complex dynamics. However, stochastic simulation of pathogen spreading processes on &lt;italic&gt;adaptive networks&lt;/italic&gt; is currently computationally prohibitive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this manuscript, we propose SSATAN-X, a new algorithm for the accurate stochastic simulation of pathogen spreading on &lt;italic&gt;adaptive networks&lt;/italic&gt;. The key idea of SSATAN-X is to only capture the contact dynamics that are relevant to the spreading process. We show that SSATAN-X captures the contact dynamics and consequently the spreading dynamics accurately. The algorithm achieves up to 100 fold speed-up over the state-of-art stochastic simulation algorithm (SSA). The speed-up with SSATAN-X further increases when the contact dynamics are fast in relation to the spreading process, i.e. if contacts are short-lived and per-exposure infection risks are small, as applicable to most infectious diseases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We envision that SSATAN-X may extend the scope of analysis of pathogen spreading on &lt;italic&gt;adaptive networks&lt;/italic&gt;. Moreover, it may serve to create benchmark data sets to validate novel numerical approaches for simulation, or for the data-driven analysis of the spreading dynamics on &lt;italic&gt;adaptive networks&lt;/italic&gt;. A C++ implementation of the algorithm is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/nmalysheva/SSATAN-X"&gt;https://github.com/nmalysheva/SSATAN-X&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Modelling and simulating of infectious disease spreading supports public heath decisions, such as prevention and containment strategies and allows to perform cost-effectiveness calculations. Detailed modelling approaches consider stochastic pathogen spreading on time-evolving contact networks. In &lt;italic&gt;adaptive networks&lt;/italic&gt;, the spreading process depends not only on the dynamics of a contact network, but vice versa, infection dynamics may alter risk behaviour and thus feed back onto contact dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stochastic simulation of these complex dynamics is currently computationally prohibitive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We propose a new algorithm (SSATAN-X) that can significantly speed up stochastic simulations on &lt;italic&gt;adaptive networks&lt;/italic&gt;, while being accurate at the same time. Our algorithm achieves this speed-up by only considering the contact dynamics that are relevant to the spreading process. The benefit of algorithm is particularly pronounced when contacts are short-lived and per-exposure infection risks are small, which is applicable to most infectious diseases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We envision that SSATAN-X may allow simulation and analysis of pathogen spreading on more complex &lt;italic&gt;adaptive networks&lt;/italic&gt; than previously possible. Moreover, data sets may be created with SSATAN-X that are useful for benchmarking novel numerical schemes and analytic approaches.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469498" rel="alternate" title="Stochastic Simulation Algorithm for effective spreading dynamics on Time-evolving Adaptive NetworX (SSATAN-X) (5 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469581</id><title>Mechanically induced nuclear shuttling of β-catenin requires co-transfer of actin (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.252134+00:00</updated><author><name>Buer Sen</name></author><author><name>Zhihui Xie</name></author><author><name>Sean Howard</name></author><author><name>Maya Styner</name></author><author><name>Andre J van Wijnen</name></author><author><name>Gunes Uzer</name></author><author><name>Janet Rubin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mesenchymal stem cells (MSC) respond to environmental forces with both cytoskeletal re-structuring and activation of protein chaperones of mechanical information, β-catenin and Yes-Associated Protein 1 (YAP1). To function, MSCs must differentiate between dynamic forces such as cyclic strains of extracellular matrix due to physical activity and static strains due to ECM stiffening. To delineate how MSCs recognize and respond differently to both force types, we compared effects of dynamic (200 cycles x 2%) and static (1 × 2% hold) strain on nuclear translocation of β-catenin and YAP1 at 3h after force application. Dynamic strain induced nuclear accumulation of β-catenin, and increased cytoskeletal actin structure and cell stiffness, but had no effect on nuclear YAP1 levels. Critically, both nuclear actin and nuclear stiffness increased along with dynamic strain-induced β-catenin transport. Augmentation of cytoskeletal structure using either static strain or lysophosphatidic acid (LPA) did not increase nuclear content of β–catenin or actin, but induced robust nuclear increase in YAP1. As actin binds β-catenin, we considered whether β-catenin, which lacks a nuclear localization signal, was dependent on actin to gain entry to the nucleus. Knockdown of cofilin-1 (&lt;italic&gt;Cfl1&lt;/italic&gt;) or importin-9 (&lt;italic&gt;Ipo9&lt;/italic&gt;), which co-mediate nuclear transfer of G-actin, prevented dynamic strain-mediated nuclear transfer of both β-catenin and actin. In sum, dynamic strain induction of actin re-structuring promotes nuclear transport of G-actin, concurrently supporting nuclear access of β-catenin via mechanisms utilized for actin transport. Thus, dynamic and static strain activate alternative mechanoresponses reflected by differences in the cellular distributions of actin, β-catenin and YAP1.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cells integrate both static and dynamic mechanical signals through the actin cytoskeleton which is attached to the nuclear envelope, affecting nuclear transport of β-catenin and YAP1. Dynamic strain induces nuclear translocation of β-catenin, but not YAP1, while static strain causes nuclear translocation of YAP1, but not β-catenin. Importantly, nuclear transport of actin is induced by dynamic but not static force. Furthermore, nuclear import of β-catenin depends on cofilin/importin-9 dependent actin transport mechanisms. Thus the presence of β-catenin and YAP1 in the nucleus represent specific responses to regulatory mechanical signals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469581" rel="alternate" title="Mechanically induced nuclear shuttling of β-catenin requires co-transfer of actin (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469676</id><title>Single-cell Transcriptomic Analysis Reveals the Cellular Heterogeneity of Mesenchymal Stem Cells (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.252333+00:00</updated><author><name>Chen Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xueshuai Han</name></author><author><name>Jingkun Liu</name></author><author><name>Lei Chen</name></author><author><name>Ying Lei</name></author><author><name>Kunying Chen</name></author><author><name>Jia Si</name></author><author><name>Tian-yi Wang</name></author><author><name>Hui Zhou</name></author><author><name>Xiaoyun Zhao</name></author><author><name>Xiaohui Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yihua An</name></author><author><name>Yueying Li</name></author><author><name>Qian-fei Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt;-expanded mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs) have been demonstrated to be a heterogeneous mixture of cells exhibiting varying proliferative, multipotential, and immunomodulatory capacities. However, the exact characteristics of MSCs remain largely unknown. By single-cell RNA sequencing of 61,296 MSCs derived from bone marrow and Wharton’s jelly, we revealed five distinct subpopulations. The developmental trajectory of these five MSC subpopulations were mapped, revealing a differentiation path from stem-like active proliferative cells (APCs) to multipotent progenitor cells, followed by the branching into two paths – adipogenesis or osteochondrogenesis – and subsequent differentiation into unipotent prechondrocytes. The stem-like APCs, expressing the perivascular mesodermal progenitor markers &lt;italic&gt;CSPG4/MCAM/NES&lt;/italic&gt;, uniquely exhibited strong proliferation and stemness signatures. Remarkably, the prechondrocyte subpopulation specifically expressed immunomodulatory genes and was able to suppress activated CD3&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cell proliferation &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, supporting the role of this population in immunoregulation. In summary, our analysis mapped the heterogeneous subpopulations of MSCs and identified two subpopulations with potential functions in self-renewal and immunoregulation. Our findings advance the definition of MSCs by identifying the specific functions of its heterogeneous cellular composition, allowing for more specific and effective MSC application through the purification of its functional subpopulations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469676" rel="alternate" title="Single-cell Transcriptomic Analysis Reveals the Cellular Heterogeneity of Mesenchymal Stem Cells (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469757</id><title>TFAP2 paralogs pioneer chromatin access for MITF and directly inhibit genes associated with cell migration (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.252538+00:00</updated><author><name>Colin Kenny</name></author><author><name>Ramile Dilshat</name></author><author><name>Hannah Seberg</name></author><author><name>Eric Van Otterloo</name></author><author><name>Gregory Bonde</name></author><author><name>Annika Helverson</name></author><author><name>Eiríkur Steingrímsson</name></author><author><name>Robert A. Cornell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Transcription factors in the Activating-enhancer-binding Protein 2 (TFAP2) family redundantly regulate gene expression in melanocytes and melanoma. Previous ChIP-seq experiments indicate that TFAP2A and Microphthalmia-associated Transcription Factor (MITF), a master regulator in these cell types, co-activate enhancers of genes promoting pigmentation. Evidence that TFAP2 paralogs can serve as pioneer factors supports the possibility that TFAP2 facilitates MITF binding at co-bound enhancers, although this model has not been tested. In addition, while MITF and TFAP2 paralogs both appear to repress genes that promote invasion, whether they do so by co-repressing enhancers is unknown. To address these questions we evaluated gene expression, chromatin accessibility, TFAP2A and MITF binding, and chromatin marks characteristic of active enhancers in SK-MEL-28 melanoma cells that were wild-type or deleted of the two &lt;italic&gt;TFAP2&lt;/italic&gt; paralogs with highest expression, &lt;italic&gt;TFAP2A&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;TFAP2C&lt;/italic&gt; (i.e., &lt;italic&gt;TFAP2&lt;/italic&gt;-KO cells). Integrated analyses revealed distinct subsets of enhancers bound by TFAP2A in WT cells that are inactivated and activated, respectively, in &lt;italic&gt;TFAP2&lt;/italic&gt;-KO cells. At enhancers bound by both MITF and TFAP2A, MITF is generally lost in &lt;italic&gt;TFAP2A/TFAP2C&lt;/italic&gt; double mutants, but not vice versa, implying TFAP2 pioneers chromatin access for MITF. There is a strong correlation between the sets of genes inhibited by MITF and TFAP2, although we did not find evidence that TFAP2 and MITF inhibit enhancers cooperatively. The findings imply that MITF and TFAP2 paralogs cooperatively affect the melanoma phenotype.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469757" rel="alternate" title="TFAP2 paralogs pioneer chromatin access for MITF and directly inhibit genes associated with cell migration (4 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469712</id><title>A novel TREM2 splice isoform lacking the ligand binding is expressed in brain and shares localization (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.252753+00:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin C. Shaw</name></author><author><name>Henry C. Snider</name></author><author><name>Andrew K. Turner</name></author><author><name>Diana J. Zajac</name></author><author><name>James F. Simpson</name></author><author><name>Steven Estus</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Genetic variants in &lt;italic&gt;TREM2&lt;/italic&gt; are strongly associated with Alzheimer’s Disease (AD) risk but alternative splicing in &lt;italic&gt;TREM2&lt;/italic&gt; transcripts has not been comprehensively described.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recognizing that alternative splice variants can result in reduced gene expression and/or altered function, we sought to fully characterize splice variation in &lt;italic&gt;TREM2&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Human blood and anterior cingulate autopsy tissue from 61 donors were used for genotyping and cDNA synthesis followed by both end-point and quantitative PCR to identify and quantify novel &lt;italic&gt;TREM2&lt;/italic&gt; isoforms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition to previously described transcripts lacking exon 3 or exon 4, or retaining part of intron 3, we identified novel isoforms lacking exon 2, along with isoforms lacking multiple exons. Isoforms lacking exon 2 were predominant at approximately 10% of TREM2 mRNA in the brain. Expression of &lt;italic&gt;TREM2&lt;/italic&gt; and frequency of exon 2 skipping did not differ between AD samples and non-AD controls (p = 0.1268 and p = 0.4909, respectively). Further, these novel splice isoforms were also observed across multiple tissues with similar frequency (range 5.3 – 13.0%). Using ectopic expression, we found that the exon 2 skipped isoform &lt;italic&gt;D2-TREM2&lt;/italic&gt; is translated to protein and localizes similarly to full-length TREM2 protein, and that both proteins are primarily retained in the Golgi complex.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the TREM2 ligand binding domain is encoded by exon 2, and skipping this exon retains reading frame while conserving localization, we hypothesize that &lt;italic&gt;D2-TREM2&lt;/italic&gt; acts as an inhibitor of &lt;italic&gt;TREM2&lt;/italic&gt; and that targeting &lt;italic&gt;TREM2&lt;/italic&gt; splicing may be a novel therapeutic pathway for AD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469712" rel="alternate" title="A novel TREM2 splice isoform lacking the ligand binding is expressed in brain and shares localization (4 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469597</id><title>Identification of a genomic DNA sequence that quantitatively modulates KLF1 expression in differentiating human hematopoietic cells (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.252895+00:00</updated><author><name>Merlin Nithya Gnanapragasam</name></author><author><name>Antanas Planutis</name></author><author><name>Jeffery A Glassberg</name></author><author><name>James J Bieker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Expression of the  β-like globin genes is under strict developmental control, with both direct and indirect inputs responsible for this effect. One of the major players regulating their transition is KLF1/EKLF, where even a two-fold difference in its level alters the regulation of globin switching. We have reproduced this change in KLF1 expression in both cell lines and primary human cells, thus demonstrating that directed, quantitative control of KLF1 expression can be attained by genomic manipulation, and suggest a new way in which modulation of transcription factor levels may be used for clinical benefit.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469597" rel="alternate" title="Identification of a genomic DNA sequence that quantitatively modulates KLF1 expression in differentiating human hematopoietic cells (4 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.27.470183</id><title>Obesity impairs therapeutic efficacy of mesenchymal stem cells by inhibiting cardiolipin-dependent mitophagy and intercellular mitochondrial transfer in mouse models of airway allergic inflammation (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.253018+00:00</updated><author><name>Shakti Sagar</name></author><author><name>Md. Imam Faizan</name></author><author><name>Nisha Chaudhary</name></author><author><name>Atish Gheware</name></author><author><name>Khushboo Sharma</name></author><author><name>Iqbal Azmi</name></author><author><name>Vijay Pal Singh</name></author><author><name>Gaurav Kharya</name></author><author><name>Ulaganathan Mabalirajan</name></author><author><name>Anurag Agrawal</name></author><author><name>Tanveer Ahmad</name></author><author><name>Soumya Sinha Roy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mesenchymal stem cell (MSC) transplantation alleviates metabolic defects in diseased recipient cells by intercellular mitochondrial transport (IMT). However, the effect of host metabolic conditions on MSCs in general, and IMT in particular, has largely remained unexplored. This study has identified a molecular pathway that primarily governs the metabolic function and IMT of MSCs. We found underlying mitochondrial dysfunction, impaired mitophagy, and reduced IMT in MSCs derived from high-fat diet (HFD)-induced obese mice (MSC-Ob). Mechanistically, MSC-Ob failed to sequester their damaged mitochondria into LC3-dependent autophagosomes due to decrease in mitochondrial cardiolipin content, which we propose as a putative mitophagy receptor for LC3 in MSCs. Functionally, MSC-Ob exhibited diminished potential to rescue metabolic deficits and cell death in stress-induced epithelial cells. In a small molecule screen, we found pyrroloquinoline quinone (PQQ) as a regulator of mitophagy and IMT. Long-term culture of MSC-Ob with PQQ (MSC-ObPQQ) restored cardiolipin content and sequestration of mitochondria to autophagosomes with concomitant activation of mitophagy. Upon co-culture, MSC-ObPQQ rescued cell death in stress-induced epithelial cells by enhancing IMT. The beneficial effect of PQQ was also evident in MSCs derived from human subjects in an in vitro model. In two independent mice models, the transplantation of MSC-ObPQQ restored IMT to airway epithelial cells, improved their mitochondrial metabolism and attenuated features of allergic airway inflammation (AAI). However, unmodulated MSC-Ob failed to do so. In summary, we uncover the molecular mechanism leading to the therapeutic decline of obese-derived MSCs and highlight the importance of pharmacological modulation of these cells for therapeutic intervention.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.27.470183" rel="alternate" title="Obesity impairs therapeutic efficacy of mesenchymal stem cells by inhibiting cardiolipin-dependent mitophagy and intercellular mitochondrial transfer in mouse models of airway allergic inflammation (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469914</id><title>Over 400 million years of cooperation: Untangling the chondrocranium-dermatocranium connection (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.253222+00:00</updated><author><name>Susan M. Motch Perrine</name></author><author><name>M. Kathleen Pitirri</name></author><author><name>Emily L. Durham</name></author><author><name>Mizuho Kawasaki</name></author><author><name>Hao Zheng</name></author><author><name>Danny Z. Chen</name></author><author><name>Kazuhiko Kawasaki</name></author><author><name>Joan T. Richtsmeier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The cranial endo- and dermal skeletons, which comprise the vertebrate skull, evolved independently and form separately during embryogenesis. In mammals, the mostly cartilaginous cranial endoskeleton forms prior to the bony dermatocranium. Many features of the chondrocranium are transient, undergoing endochondral ossification or disappearing, so its role in skull morphogenesis is not understood The fibroblast growth factor (FGF) and receptor (FGFR) signaling pathway contributes significantly to the regulation of osteochondroprogenitor cell function. Mutations in FGFR genes are associated with diseases that impact the skull including dwarfing chondrodyplasia and craniosynostosis syndromes. We investigate the developing chondrocranium and dermatocranium using a mouse model for craniosynostosis carrying a gain of function mutation in Fgfr2 to assess development of these cranial skeleton systems. Dermatocrania and chondrocrania of &lt;italic&gt;Fgfr2c&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;C342Y/+&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; mice and their &lt;italic&gt;Fgfr2c&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;+/+&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; littermates were quantified in 3D from microcomputed tomography images of mouse embryos. Chondrocrania of embryonic mice carrying the Fgfr2 mutation are larger than their &lt;italic&gt;Fgfr2c&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;+/+&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; littermates and include novel extensions of cartilage over the lateral and dorsal aspect of the brain. Like the forming chondrocranium, the embryonic dermatocranium is larger in &lt;italic&gt;Fgfr2c&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;C342Y/+&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; mice throughout embryogenesis but after disappearance of much of the chondrocranium, the dermatocranium becomes progressively smaller relative to &lt;italic&gt;Fgfr2c&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;+/+&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; littermates during postnatal growth. Results reveal the direct effects of this Fgfr2c mutation on embryonic cranial cartilage, the impact of chondrocranial structure on developing dermatocranial elements, the importance of the chondrocranium in decoding the impact of specific genetic variants on head morphogenesis, and the potential for harnessing these effects as therapeutic targets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present the first fully complete three-dimensional (3D) reconstructions of the mouse embryonic chondrocranium using a novel methodology of uncertainty guided segmentation of microcomputed tomography images with sparse annotation. We provide 3D reconstructions of chondrocrania of the &lt;italic&gt;Fgfr2c&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;C342Y/+&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Crouzon syndrome mouse and typically developing littermates for embryonic days 13.5, 14.5, 15.5, 16.5, and 17.5. This is the first study of the effects of an FGFR2 mutation on embryonic chondrocranial cartilage. 3D reconstructions of embryonic dermal bones reveal that the dermatocranium develops outside of, and in shapes that conform to the chondrocranium. Our findings have implications for the study and treatment of human craniofacial disease and for understanding the impact of chondrocranial morphology on the evolution of skull morphology.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469914" rel="alternate" title="Over 400 million years of cooperation: Untangling the chondrocranium-dermatocranium connection (3 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469894</id><title>RyR2/IRBIT regulates insulin gene transcription, insulin content, and secretion in the insulinoma cell line INS-1 (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.253390+00:00</updated><author><name>Kyle E. Harvey</name></author><author><name>Emily K. LaVigne</name></author><author><name>Mohd Saleem Dar</name></author><author><name>Amy E. Salyer</name></author><author><name>Evan P.S. Pratt</name></author><author><name>Paxton A. Sample</name></author><author><name>Uma Aryal</name></author><author><name>Humaira Gowher</name></author><author><name>Gregory H. Hockerman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The role of ER Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; release via ryanodine receptors (RyR) in pancreatic β-cell function is not well defined. Deletion of RyR2 from the rat insulinoma INS-1 (RyR2&lt;sup&gt;KO&lt;/sup&gt;) enhanced the Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; integral (AUC) stimulated by 7.5 mM glucose, and rendered it sensitive to block by the IP&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; receptor inhibitor xestospongin C, coincident with reduced levels of the protein IP&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;underline&gt;R&lt;/underline&gt;eceptor &lt;underline&gt;B&lt;/underline&gt;inding protein released with Inositol 1,4,5 &lt;underline&gt;T&lt;/underline&gt;risphosphate (IRBIT; aka AHCYL1). Deletion of IRBIT from INS-1 cells (IRBIT&lt;sup&gt;KO&lt;/sup&gt;) increased the Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; AUC in response to 7.5 mM glucose and induced xestospongin sensitivity. Insulin content and basal (2.5 mM glucose) and 7.5 mM glucose-stimulated insulin secretion were reduced in RyR2&lt;sup&gt;KO&lt;/sup&gt; cells and more modestly reduced in IRBIT&lt;sup&gt;KO&lt;/sup&gt; cells compared to controls. &lt;italic&gt;INS2&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA levels were reduced in both RyR2&lt;sup&gt;KO&lt;/sup&gt; and IRBIT&lt;sup&gt;KO&lt;/sup&gt; cells, but &lt;italic&gt;INS1&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA levels were specifically decreased in RyR2&lt;sup&gt;KO&lt;/sup&gt; cells. Nuclear localization of S-adenosylhomocysteinase (AHCY) was increased in RyR2&lt;sup&gt;KO&lt;/sup&gt; and IRBIT&lt;sup&gt;KO&lt;/sup&gt; cells. DNA methylation of the &lt;italic&gt;INS1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;INS2&lt;/italic&gt; gene promotor regions was very low, and not different among RyR2&lt;sup&gt;KO&lt;/sup&gt;, IRBIT&lt;sup&gt;KO&lt;/sup&gt;, and controls. In contrast, exon 2 of the &lt;italic&gt;INS1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;INS2&lt;/italic&gt; genes was more extensively methylated in RyR2&lt;sup&gt;KO&lt;/sup&gt; and IRBIT&lt;sup&gt;KO&lt;/sup&gt; cells than in controls. Proteomics analysis using LC-MS/MS revealed that deletion of RyR2 or IRBIT resulted in differential regulation of 314 and 137 proteins, respectively, with 41 in common. These results suggest that RyR2 regulates IRBIT levels and activity in INS-1 cells, and together maintain insulin content and secretion, and regulate the proteome, perhaps via DNA methylation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deletion of RyR2 from INS-1 cells had the unanticipated effect of reducing IRBIT proteins levels, and both RyR2 and IRBIT contribute to maintenance of glucose- stimulated insulin secretion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469894" rel="alternate" title="RyR2/IRBIT regulates insulin gene transcription, insulin content, and secretion in the insulinoma cell line INS-1 (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470255</id><title>Functionalizing lipid sponge droplets with DNA (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.253580+00:00</updated><author><name>Christy Cho</name></author><author><name>Henrike Niederholtmeyer</name></author><author><name>Hyeonglim Seo</name></author><author><name>Ahanjit Bhattacharya</name></author><author><name>Neal K. Devaraj</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nucleic acids are among the most versatile molecules for the construction of biomimetic systems because they can serve as information carriers and programmable construction materials. How nucleic acids interact with membranous coacervate compartments such as lipid sponge droplets is not known. Here we systematically characterize the potential of DNA to functionalize lipid sponge droplets and demonstrate a strong size dependence for sequestration into the sponge phase. Double stranded DNA molecules of more than 300 bp are excluded and form a corona on the surface of droplets they are targeted to. Shorter DNA molecules partition efficiently into the lipid sponge phase and can direct DNA-templated reactions to droplets. We demonstrate repeated capture and release of labeled DNA strands by dynamic hybridization and strand displacement reactions that occur inside droplets. Our system opens new opportunities for DNA-encoded functions in lipid sponge droplets such as cargo control and signaling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470255" rel="alternate" title="Functionalizing lipid sponge droplets with DNA (3 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469672</id><title>Tom70-based transcriptional regulation of mitochondrial biogenesis and aging (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.253779+00:00</updated><author><name>Qingqing Liu</name></author><author><name>Catherine E. Chang</name></author><author><name>Alexandra C. Wooldredge</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Fong</name></author><author><name>Brian K. Kennedy</name></author><author><name>Chuankai Zhou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mitochondrial biogenesis has two major steps: the transcriptional activation of nuclear genome-encoded mitochondrial proteins and the import of nascent mitochondrial proteins that are synthesized in the cytosol. These nascent mitochondrial proteins are aggregation-prone and can cause cytosolic proteostasis stress. The transcription factor-dependent transcriptional regulations and the TOM-TIM complex-dependent import of nascent mitochondrial proteins have been extensively studied. Yet, little is known regarding how these two steps of mitochondrial biogenesis coordinate with each other to avoid the cytosolic accumulation of these aggregation-prone nascent mitochondrial proteins. Here we show that in budding yeast, Tom70, a conserved receptor of the TOM complex, moonlights to regulate the transcriptional activity of mitochondrial proteins. Tom70’s transcription regulatory role is conserved in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt;. The dual roles of Tom70 in both transcription/biogenesis and import of mitochondrial proteins allow the cells to accomplish mitochondrial biogenesis without compromising cytosolic proteostasis. The age-related reduction of Tom70, caused by reduced biogenesis and increased degradation of Tom70, is associated with the loss of mitochondrial membrane potential, mtDNA, and mitochondrial proteins. While loss of Tom70 accelerates aging and age-related mitochondrial defects, overexpressing TOM70 delays these mitochondrial dysfunctions and extends the replicative lifespan. Our results reveal unexpected roles of Tom70 in mitochondrial biogenesis and aging.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469672" rel="alternate" title="Tom70-based transcriptional regulation of mitochondrial biogenesis and aging (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469780</id><title>A chemical method to sequence 5-formylcytosine on RNA (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.253999+00:00</updated><author><name>Ang Li</name></author><author><name>Xuemeng Sun</name></author><author><name>A. Emilia Arguello</name></author><author><name>Ralph E. Kleiner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Epitranscriptomic RNA modifications can regulate biological processes, but there remains a major gap in our ability to identify and measure individual modifications at nucleotide resolution. Here we present Mal-Seq, a chemical method to sequence 5-formylcytosine (f&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;C) modifications on RNA based upon selective and efficient malononitrile-mediated labeling of f&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;C residues to generate adducts that are read as C-to-T mutations upon reverse transcription and PCR amplification. We apply Mal-Seq to characterize the prevalence of f&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;C at the wobble position of mt-tRNA(Met) in different organisms and tissue types and find that high-level f&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;C modification is present in mammals but lacking in lower eukaryotes. Our work sheds light on mitochondrial tRNA modifications throughout eukaryotic evolution and provides a general platform for characterizing the f&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;C epitranscriptome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469780" rel="alternate" title="A chemical method to sequence 5-formylcytosine on RNA (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>