<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.379302+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465776</id><title>Artificial intelligence reveals nuclear pore complexity (202 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.379680+00:00</updated><author><name>Shyamal Mosalaganti</name></author><author><name>Agnieszka Obarska-Kosinska</name></author><author><name>Marc Siggel</name></author><author><name>Beata Turonova</name></author><author><name>Christian E. Zimmerli</name></author><author><name>Katarzyna Buczak</name></author><author><name>Florian H. Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Erica Margiotta</name></author><author><name>Marie-Therese Mackmull</name></author><author><name>Wim Hagen</name></author><author><name>Gerhard Hummer</name></author><author><name>Martin Beck</name></author><author><name>Jan Kosinski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nuclear pore complexes (NPCs) mediate nucleocytoplasmic transport. Their intricate 120 MDa architecture remains incompletely understood. Here, we report a near-complete structural model of the human NPC scaffold with explicit membrane and in multiple conformational states. We combined AI-based structure prediction with &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in cellulo&lt;/italic&gt; cryo-electron tomography and integrative modeling. We show that linker Nups spatially organize the scaffold within and across subcomplexes to establish the higher-order structure. Microsecond-long molecular dynamics simulations suggest that the scaffold is not required to stabilize the inner and outer nuclear membrane fusion, but rather widens the central pore. Our work exemplifies how AI-based modeling can be integrated with &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; structural biology to understand subcellular architecture across spatial organization levels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;An AI-based, dynamic model of the human nuclear pore complex reveals how the protein scaffold and the nuclear envelope are coupled inside cells.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465776" rel="alternate" title="Artificial intelligence reveals nuclear pore complexity (202 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-10-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.24.465614</id><title>Tension-driven multi-scale self-organisation in human iPSC-derived muscle fibers (100 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.380164+00:00</updated><author><name>Qiyan Mao</name></author><author><name>Achyuth Acharya</name></author><author><name>Alejandra Rodríguez-delaRosa</name></author><author><name>Fabio Marchiano</name></author><author><name>Benoit Dehapoit</name></author><author><name>Ziad Al Tanoury</name></author><author><name>Jyoti Rao</name></author><author><name>Margarete Díaz-Cuadros</name></author><author><name>Arian Mansur</name></author><author><name>Erica Wagner</name></author><author><name>Claire Chardes</name></author><author><name>Vandana A. Gupta</name></author><author><name>Pierre-François Lenne</name></author><author><name>Bianca H. Habermann</name></author><author><name>Olivier Pourquie</name></author><author><name>Frank Schnorrer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human muscle is a hierarchically organised tissue with its contractile cells called myofibers packed into large myofiber bundles. Each myofiber contains periodic myofibrils built by hundreds of contractile sarcomeres that generate large mechanical forces. To better understand the mechanisms that coordinate human muscle morphogenesis from tissue to molecular scales, we adopted a simple &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; system using induced pluripotent stem cell-derived human myogenic precursors. When grown on an unrestricted two-dimensional substrate, developing myofibers spontaneously align and self-organise into higher-order myofiber bundles, which grow and consolidate to stable sizes. Following a transcriptional boost of sarcomeric components, myofibrils assemble into chains of periodic sarcomeres that emerge across the entire myofiber. By directly probing tension we found that tension build-up precedes sarcomere assembly and increases within each assembling myofibril. Furthermore, we found that myofiber ends stably attach to other myofibers using integrin-based attachments and thus myofiber bundling coincides with stable myofiber bundle attachment &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. A failure in stable myofiber attachment results in a collapse followed by a disassembly of the myofibrils. Overall, our results strongly suggest that mechanical tension across sarcomeric components as well as between differentiating myofibers is key to coordinate the multi- scale self-organisation of muscle morphogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.24.465614" rel="alternate" title="Tension-driven multi-scale self-organisation in human iPSC-derived muscle fibers (100 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466091</id><title>Cryo-electron microscopy structure of the H3-H4 octasome without histones H2A and H2B (43 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.380567+00:00</updated><author><name>Kayo Nozawa</name></author><author><name>Yoshimasa Takizawa</name></author><author><name>Leonidas Pierrakeas</name></author><author><name>Kazumi Saikusa</name></author><author><name>Satoko Akashi</name></author><author><name>Ed Luk</name></author><author><name>Hitoshi Kurumizaka</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The canonical nucleosome, which represents the predominant packaging unit in eukaryotic chromatin, has an octameric core made up of two histone H2A-H2B and H3-H4 dimers with ~147 base-pair (bp) DNA wrapping around it. Non-nucleosome particles with alterative histone stoichiometries and DNA wrapping configurations have been found, and they could profoundly influence genome architecture and function. Here we solved the structure of the H3-H4 octasome, which is a nucleosome-like particle with a core made up of four H3-H4 dimers. Two conformations, open and closed, are determined at 3.9 Å and 3.6 Å resolutions by cryo-electron microscopy, respectively. The H3-H4 octasome, made up of a di-tetrameric core, is wrapped by ~120 bp DNA in 1.5 negative superhelical turns. The symmetrical halves are connected by a unique H4-H4’ interface along the dyad axis. &lt;italic&gt;In vivo&lt;/italic&gt; crosslinking of cysteine probes placed at another unique H3-H3’ interface demonstrated the existence of the H3-H4 octasome in cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466091" rel="alternate" title="Cryo-electron microscopy structure of the H3-H4 octasome without histones H2A and H2B (43 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466387</id><title>Discovery of a conserved rule behind the assembly of β-barrel membrane proteins. (43 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.380798+00:00</updated><author><name>Edward M Germany</name></author><author><name>Yue Ding</name></author><author><name>Kenichiro Imai</name></author><author><name>Rebecca S Bamert</name></author><author><name>Rhys A Dunstan</name></author><author><name>Yukari Nakajima</name></author><author><name>XiangFeng Lai</name></author><author><name>Chaille T Webb</name></author><author><name>Christopher J Stubenrauch</name></author><author><name>Kentaro Hidaka</name></author><author><name>Nakajohn Thewasano</name></author><author><name>Kher Shing Tan</name></author><author><name>Hsin-Hui Shen</name></author><author><name>Trevor Lithgow</name></author><author><name>Takuya Shiota</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gram-negative bacteria, mitochondria and chloroplasts contain outer membrane proteins (OMPs) characterized by a transmembrane domain with a β barrel structure. Most OMPs have a diagnostic β-signal imprinted in the amino acid sequence of the final β-strand (-1 strand) of the β barrel. Molecular chaperones of the Omp85 superfamily, such as BamA in the bacterial BAM complex, recognizes the β-signal and then catalyze the folding of the OMP into its membrane-embedded β barrel structure. Here, we reconstituted OMP assembly in vitro to study this process with five model OMPs, revealing that a critical assembly signal exists in the fifth β-strand from the C-terminus (-5 strand). This signal was shown to drive a critical insertion step of the OMP assembly process but is not required for the initial recognition step between the OMP and BamA. Furthermore, we identified the receptor for this -5 signal as BamD, a second essential subunit of the BAM complex. Distinct binding sites for the β-signal and the -5 signal, were identified on BamD. Comparative sequence analysis showed that the -5 signal is a conserved feature in bacterial OMPs, and that mitochondrial OMPs also contains -5 signal motif positioned in the fifth from last strand of their β barrel structure. We propose the -5 rule as a conserved feature of the process of OMP assembly in bacteria and the organelles of eukaryotes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466387" rel="alternate" title="Discovery of a conserved rule behind the assembly of β-barrel membrane proteins. (43 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466484</id><title>Clamping of DNA shuts the condensin neck gate (34 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.381062+00:00</updated><author><name>Byung-Gil Lee</name></author><author><name>James Rhodes</name></author><author><name>Jan Löwe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Condensin is a Structural Maintenance of Chromosomes (SMC) complex needed for the compaction of DNA into chromatids during mitosis. Lengthwise DNA compaction by condensin is facilitated by ATPase-driven loop extrusion, a process that is believed to be the fundamental activity of most, if not all SMC complexes. In order to obtain molecular insights, we obtained cryo-EM structures of yeast condensin in the presence of a slowly-hydrolysable ATP analogue and linear, as well as circular DNAs. The DNAs were shown to be clamped between the engaged heterodimeric SMC ATPase heads and the Ycs4 subunit, in a manner similar to previously reported DNA-bound SMC complex structures. Ycg1, the other non-SMC subunit was only flexibly bound to the complex, while also binding DNA tightly, and often remaining at a distance from the head module. In the clamped state, the DNA is encircled, or topologically entrapped, by the kleisin Brn1 and the two engaged head domains of Smc2 and Smc4, and this tripartite ring is closed at all interfaces, including at the neck of Smc2. We show that the neck gate opens upon head engagement in the absence of DNA, but it remains shut when DNA is present. Our work demonstrates that condensin and other SMC complexes go through similar conformations of the head modules during their ATPase cycle. In contrast, the behaviour of the Ycg1 subunit in the condensin complex might indicate differences in the implementation of the extrusion reactions and our findings will constrain further mechanistic models of loop extrusion by SMC complexes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466484" rel="alternate" title="Clamping of DNA shuts the condensin neck gate (34 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465916</id><title>MLF2 modulates phase separated nuclear envelope condensates that provoke dual proteotoxicity (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.381349+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah M Prophet</name></author><author><name>Anthony J Rampello</name></author><author><name>Robert F Niescier</name></author><author><name>Juliana E Shaw</name></author><author><name>Anthony J Koleske</name></author><author><name>Christian Schlieker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;DYT1 dystonia is a highly debilitating neurological movement disorder arising from mutation in the AAA+ ATPase TorsinA. The hallmark of Torsin dysfunction is nuclear envelope blebbing resulting from defects in nuclear pore complex biogenesis. Whether blebs actively contribute to disease manifestation is presently unknown. We report that FG-nucleoporins in the bleb lumen undergo phase separation and contribute to DYT1 dystonia by provoking two proteotoxic insults. Short-lived ubiquitinated proteins that are normally rapidly degraded in healthy cells partition into the bleb lumen and become stabilized. Additionally, blebs selectively sequester a chaperone network composed of HSP70s and HSP40s. The composition of this chaperone network is altered by the bleb component MLF2. We further demonstrate that MLF2 is a catalyst of phase separation that suppresses the ectopic accumulation of FG-nucleoporins and modulates the selective properties and size of condensates &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. Our studies identify unprecedented, dual mechanisms of proteotoxicity in the context of liquid-liquid phase separation with direct implications for our understanding of disease etiology and treatment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465916" rel="alternate" title="MLF2 modulates phase separated nuclear envelope condensates that provoke dual proteotoxicity (31 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466259</id><title>Modelling human zygotic genome activation in 8C-like cells in vitro (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.381967+00:00</updated><author><name>Jasmin Taubenschmid-Stowers</name></author><author><name>Maria Rostovskaya</name></author><author><name>Fatima Santos</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Ljung</name></author><author><name>Ricard Argelaguet</name></author><author><name>Felix Krueger</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Nichols</name></author><author><name>Wolf Reik</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The remodelling of the epigenome and transcriptome of the fertilised oocyte to establish totipotency in the zygote and developing embryo is one of the most critical processes in mammalian embryogenesis. Zygotic or embryonic genome activation (ZGA, EGA) in the 2-cell embryo in mouse, and the 8-cell embryo in humans, constitutes the first major wave of transcription. Failure to initiate ZGA leads to developmental defects, and contributes to the high attrition rates of human pre-implantation embryos. Due to limitations in cell numbers and experimental tractability, the mechanisms that regulate human embryonic genome activation in the totipotent embryo remain poorly understood. Here we report the discovery of human 8-cell like cells (8CLCs) specifically among naive embryonic stem cells, but not primed pluripotent cells. 8CLCs express ZGA marker genes such as ZSCAN4, LEUTX and DUXA and their transcriptome closely resembles that of the 8-cell human embryo. 8-cell like cells reactivate 8-cell stage specific transposable elements such as HERVL and MLT2A1 and are characterized by upregulation of the DNA methylation regulator DPPA3. 8CLCs show reduced SOX2 protein, and can be identified based on expression of the novel ZGA-associated protein markers TPRX1 and H3.Y in vitro. Overexpression of the transcription factor DUX4 as well as spliceosome inhibition increase ZGA-like transcription and enhance TPRX1+ 8CLCs formation. Excitingly, the in vitro identified 8CLC marker proteins TPRX1 and H3.Y are also expressed in 8-cell human embryos at the time of genome activation and may thus be relevant in vivo. The discovery of 8CLCs provides a unique opportunity to model and manipulate human ZGA-like transcriptional programs in vitro, and might provide critical functional insights into one of the earliest events in human embryogenesis in vivo.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466259" rel="alternate" title="Modelling human zygotic genome activation in 8C-like cells in vitro (26 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466356</id><title>Elevated Hoxb5b expands vagal neural crest pool and blocks enteric neuronal development in zebrafish (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.382240+00:00</updated><author><name>Aubrey G. Adam Howard</name></author><author><name>Aaron C Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Joshua Tworig</name></author><author><name>Priya Ravisankar</name></author><author><name>Eileen Willey Singleton</name></author><author><name>Can Li</name></author><author><name>Grayson Kotzur</name></author><author><name>Joshua S Waxman</name></author><author><name>Rosa A Uribe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neural crest cells (NCCs) are a migratory, transient, and multipotent stem cell population essential to vertebrate embryonic development, contributing to numerous cell lineages in the adult organism. While great strides have been made in elucidating molecular and cellular events that drive NCC specification, comprehensive knowledge of the genetic factors that orchestrate NCC developmental programs is still far from complete. We discovered that elevated Hoxb5b levels promoted an expansion of zebrafish NCCs, which persisted throughout multiple stages of development. Correspondingly, elevated Hoxb5b also specifically expanded expression domains of the vagal NCC markers foxd3 and phox2bb. Increases in NCCs were most apparent after pulsed ectopic Hoxb5b expression at early developmental stages, rather than later during differentiation stages, as determined using a novel transgenic zebrafish line. The increase in vagal NCCs early in development led to supernumerary Phox2b+ enteric neural progenitors, while leaving many other NCC-derived tissues without an overt phenotype. Surprisingly, these NCC-derived enteric progenitors failed to expand properly into sufficient quantities of enterically fated neurons and stalled in the gut tissue. These results suggest that while Hoxb5b participates in vagal NCC development as a driver of progenitor expansion, the supernumerary, ectopically localized NCC fail to initiate expansion programs in timely fashion in the gut.  All together, these data point to a model in which Hoxb5b regulates NCCs both in a tissue specific and temporally restricted manner.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466356" rel="alternate" title="Elevated Hoxb5b expands vagal neural crest pool and blocks enteric neuronal development in zebrafish (26 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466170</id><title>Inducible transcriptional condensates drive 3D genome reorganization in the heat shock response (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.382478+00:00</updated><author><name>Surabhi Chowdhary</name></author><author><name>Amoldeep S. Kainth</name></author><author><name>Sarah Paracha</name></author><author><name>David S. Gross</name></author><author><name>David Pincus</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mammalian developmental and disease-associated genes concentrate large quantities of the transcriptional machinery by forming membrane-less compartments known as transcriptional condensates. However, it is unknown whether these structures are evolutionarily conserved, capable of stress-inducible gene activation or involved in 3D genome reorganization. Here, we identify inducible transcriptional condensates in the yeast heat shock response (HSR). HSR condensates are biophysically dynamic spatiotemporal clusters of the sequence-specific transcription factor Heat shock factor 1 (Hsf1) with Mediator and RNA Pol II. Uniquely, HSR condensates drive the coalescence of multiple Hsf1 target genes, even those located on different chromosomes. Binding of the chaperone Hsp70 to a site on Hsf1 represses clustering, while an intrinsically disordered region on Hsf1 promotes condensate formation and intergenic interactions. Mutation of both Hsf1 determinants reprograms HSR condensates to become mammalian-like: constitutively active without intergenic coalescence. These results suggest that transcriptional condensates are ancient and flexible compartments of eukaryotic gene control.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466170" rel="alternate" title="Inducible transcriptional condensates drive 3D genome reorganization in the heat shock response (24 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465912</id><title>RNA compensation: A positive feedback insulation strategy for RNA-based networks (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.382709+00:00</updated><author><name>Baiyang Liu</name></author><author><name>Christian Cuba Samaniego</name></author><author><name>Matthew Bennett</name></author><author><name>James Chappell</name></author><author><name>Elisa Franco</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The lack of signalling modularity of biomolecular systems poses major challenges toward engineering complex networks. An important problem is posed by the consumption of signaling molecules upon circuit interconnection, which makes it possible to control a downstream circuit but compromises the performance of the upstream circuit. This issue has been previously addressed with insulation strategies including high-gain negative feedback and phosphorylation-dephosphorylation reaction cycle. In this paper, we focus on RNA-based circuits and propose a new positive-feedback insulation strategy to mitigate signal consumption. An RNA input is added in tandem with transcription output to compensate the RNA consumption, leading to concentration robustness of the input RNA molecule regardless of the amount of downstream modules. We term this strategy RNA compensation, and it can be applied to systems that have a stringent input-output gain, such as Small Transcription Activating RNAs (STARs). Our analysis shows that RNA compensation not only eliminates the signaling consumption in individual STAR-based regulators, but also improves the composability of STAR cascades and the modularity of RNA bistable systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465912" rel="alternate" title="RNA compensation: A positive feedback insulation strategy for RNA-based networks (23 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465695</id><title>Mother centrioles generate a local pulse of Polo/PLK1 activity to initiate mitotic centrosome assembly (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.382973+00:00</updated><author><name>Siu-Shing Wong</name></author><author><name>Zachary M. Wilmott</name></author><author><name>Saroj Saurya</name></author><author><name>Felix Y. Zhou</name></author><author><name>Kwai-Yin Chau</name></author><author><name>Alain Goriely</name></author><author><name>Jordan W. Raff</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mitotic centrosomes are formed when centrioles recruit large amounts of pericentriolar material (PCM) around themselves. This centrosome “maturation” requires the centrioles and also Polo/PLK1 protein kinase. The PCM comprises several hundred proteins and, in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt;, Polo cooperates with the conserved centrosome proteins Spd-2/CEP192 and Cnn/CDK5RAP2 to assemble a PCM scaffold around the mother centriole that then recruits other PCM client proteins. We show here that in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; syncytial blastoderm embryos, centrosomal Polo levels rise and fall during the assembly process—peaking, and then starting to decline, even as levels of the PCM scaffold continue to rise. Experiments and mathematical modelling indicate that a centriolar pulse of Polo activity, potentially generated by the interaction between Polo and its centriole receptor Ana1 (CEP295 in humans), could explain these unexpected scaffold assembly dynamics. We propose that centrioles generate a local pulse of Polo activity prior to mitotic entry to initiate centrosome maturation, explaining why centrioles and Polo/PLK1 are normally essential for this process.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465695" rel="alternate" title="Mother centrioles generate a local pulse of Polo/PLK1 activity to initiate mitotic centrosome assembly (17 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466254</id><title>Activating natural product synthesis using CRISPR interference and activation systems in Streptomyces (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.383237+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrea Ameruoso</name></author><author><name>Maria Claudia Villegas Kcam</name></author><author><name>Katherine Piper Cohen</name></author><author><name>James Chappell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The rise of antibiotic-resistant bacteria represents a major threat to global health, creating an urgent need to discover new antibiotics. Natural products derived from the genus &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt; represent a rich and diverse repertoire of chemical molecules from which new antibiotics are likely to be found. However, a major challenge is that the biosynthetic gene clusters (BGCs) responsible for natural product synthesis are often poorly expressed under laboratory culturing conditions, thus preventing isolation and screening of novel chemicals. To address this, we describe a novel approach to activate silent BGCs through rewiring endogenous regulation using synthetic gene regulators based upon CRISPR-Cas. First, we create CRISPR interference (CRISPRi) and CRISPR activation (CRISPRa) systems that allow for highly programmable and effective gene repression and activation in &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt;. We then harness these tools to activate a silent BGC through perturbing its endogenous regulatory network. Together, this work advances the synthetic regulatory toolbox for &lt;italic&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/italic&gt; and facilitates the programmable activation of silent BGCs for novel chemical discovery.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466254" rel="alternate" title="Activating natural product synthesis using CRISPR interference and activation systems in Streptomyces (17 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465978</id><title>PDGFR dimer-specific activation, trafficking and downstream signaling dynamics (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.383746+00:00</updated><author><name>Madison A. Rogers</name></author><author><name>Katherine A. Fantauzzo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Signaling through the platelet-derived growth factor receptors (PDGFRs) plays a critical role in multiple cellular processes during development. The two PDGFRs, PDGFRα and PDGFRβ, dimerize to form homodimers and/or heterodimers. Here, we overcome previous limitations in studying PDGFR dimer-specific dynamics by generating cell lines stably expressing C-terminal fusions of each PDGFR with bimolecular fluorescence complementation (BiFC) fragments corresponding to the N-terminal or C-terminal regions of the Venus fluorescent protein. We find that PDGFRβ receptors homodimerize more quickly than PDGFRα receptors in response to PDGF ligand, with increased levels of autophosphorylation. Further, we demonstrate that PDGFRα homodimers are trafficked and degraded more quickly, while PDGFRβ homodimers are more likely to be recycled back to the cell membrane. We show that PDGFRβ homodimer activation results in a greater amplitude of phospho-ERK1/2 and phospho-AKT signaling, as well as increased proliferation and migration. Collectively, our findings provide significant insight into how biological specificity is introduced to generate unique responses downstream of PDGFR engagement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The authors utilize a novel bimolecular fluorescence complementation approach to investigate PDGFR homodimer-specific dynamics. They uncover differences in the timing and extent of receptor dimerization, activation and trafficking, which lead to changes in downstream signaling and cellular activity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465978" rel="alternate" title="PDGFR dimer-specific activation, trafficking and downstream signaling dynamics (16 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466256</id><title>Tubular lysosome induction couples animal starvation to healthy aging (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.385107+00:00</updated><author><name>Tatiana V Villalobos</name></author><author><name>Bhaswati Ghosh</name></author><author><name>Sanaa Alam</name></author><author><name>Tyler J Butsch</name></author><author><name>Brennan M Mercola</name></author><author><name>Cara D Ramos</name></author><author><name>Suman Das</name></author><author><name>Eric D Eymard</name></author><author><name>K. Adam Bohnert</name></author><author><name>Alyssa E Johnson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Dietary restriction promotes longevity via autophagy activation. However, changes to lysosomes underlying this effect remain unclear. Using the nematode Caenorhabditis elegans, we show that induction of autophagic tubular lysosomes, which occurs upon dietary restriction or mTOR inhibition, is a critical event linking reduced food intake to lifespan extension. We find that starvation induces tubular lysosomes not only in affected individuals but also in well-fed descendants, and the presence of gut tubular lysosomes in well-fed progeny is predictive of enhanced lifespan. Furthermore, we demonstrate that expression of Drosophila SVIP, a tubular-lysosome activator in flies, artificially induces tubular lysosomes in well-fed worms and improves C. elegans health in old age. These findings identify tubular lysosomes as a new class of lysosomes that couples starvation to healthy aging.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466256" rel="alternate" title="Tubular lysosome induction couples animal starvation to healthy aging (12 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466411</id><title>The synthetic triterpenoids CDDO-TFEA and CDDO-Me, but not CDDO, are potent BACH1 inhibitors (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.385565+00:00</updated><author><name>Laura Casares</name></author><author><name>Rita Moreno</name></author><author><name>Maureen Higgins</name></author><author><name>Sharada Dayalan Naidu</name></author><author><name>Graham Neill</name></author><author><name>Lena Cassin</name></author><author><name>Anders E Kiib</name></author><author><name>Esben B Svenningsen</name></author><author><name>Tadashi Honda</name></author><author><name>Thomas B Poulsen</name></author><author><name>Albena T Dinkova-Kostova</name></author><author><name>David Olagnier</name></author><author><name>Laureano de la Vega</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The transcription factor BACH1 is a potential target against a variety of chronic conditions linked to oxidative stress and inflammation, and formation of cancer metastasis. However, only a few BACH1 degraders/inhibitors have been described. BACH1 is a transcriptional repressor of heme oxygenase 1 (HMOX1), which is positively regulated by transcription factor NRF2 and is highly inducible by derivatives of the synthetic oleanane triterpenoid 2-cyano-3,12-dioxooleana-1,9(11)-dien-28-oic acid (CDDO). Most of the therapeutic activities of these compounds are due to their anti-inflammatory and antioxidant properties, which are widely attributed to their ability to activate NRF2. However, with such a broad range of action, these drugs may have other molecular targets that have not been fully identified and could also be of importance for their therapeutic profile. Herein we identified BACH1 as a target of CDDO-derivatives, but not CDDO. While both CDDO and CDDO-derivatives activate NRF2 similarly, only CDDO-derivatives inhibit BACH1, which explains the much higher potency of CDDO-derivatives as HMOX1 inducers compared with unmodified CDDO. Notably, we demonstrate that CDDO-derivatives inhibit BACH1 via a novel mechanism that reduces BACH1 nuclear levels while accumulating its cytoplasmic form. Altogether, our study identifies CDDO-derivatives as dual KEAP1/BACH1 inhibitors, providing a rationale for further therapeutic uses of these drugs&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466411" rel="alternate" title="The synthetic triterpenoids CDDO-TFEA and CDDO-Me, but not CDDO, are potent BACH1 inhibitors (12 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465842</id><title>Somatostatin venom analogs evolved by fish-hunting cone snails: From prey capture behavior to identifying drug leads (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.385867+00:00</updated><author><name>Iris Bea. L. Ramiro</name></author><author><name>Walden E. Bjørn-Yoshimoto</name></author><author><name>Julita S. Imperial</name></author><author><name>Joanna Gajewiak</name></author><author><name>Maren Watkins</name></author><author><name>Dylan Taylor</name></author><author><name>William Resager</name></author><author><name>Beatrix Ueberheide</name></author><author><name>Hans Bräuner-Osborne</name></author><author><name>Frank G. Whitby</name></author><author><name>Christopher P. Hill</name></author><author><name>Laurent F. Martin</name></author><author><name>Amol Patwardhan</name></author><author><name>Gisela P. Concepcion</name></author><author><name>Baldomero M. Olivera</name></author><author><name>Helena Safavi-Hemami</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Somatostatin (SS) is a peptide hormone with diverse physiological roles. By investigating a deep-water clade of fish-hunting cone snails, we show that predator-prey evolution has generated a diverse set of SS analogs, each optimized to elicit specific systemic physiological effects in prey. The increased metabolic stability, distinct SS receptor activation profiles, and chemical diversity of the venom analogs make them suitable leads for therapeutic application, including pain, cancer and endocrine disorders. Our findings not only establish the existence of SS-like peptides in animal venoms, but also serve as a model for the synergy gained from combining molecular phylogenetics and behavioral observations to optimize the discovery of natural products with biomedical potential.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Somatostatin drug design by fish-hunting cone snails&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465842" rel="alternate" title="Somatostatin venom analogs evolved by fish-hunting cone snails: From prey capture behavior to identifying drug leads (11 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466305</id><title>Differential regulation of cranial and cardiac neural crest by Serum Response Factor (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.386320+00:00</updated><author><name>Colin J Dinsmore</name></author><author><name>Philippe Soriano</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Serum response factor (SRF) is an essential transcription factor that influences many cellular processes including cell proliferation, migration, and differentiation. SRF directly regulates and is required for immediate early gene (IEG) and actin cytoskeleton-related gene expression. SRF coordinates these competing transcription programs through discrete sets of cofactors, the Ternary Complex Factors (TCFs) and Myocardin Related Transcription Factors (MRTFs). The relative contribution of these two programs to in vivo SRF activity and mutant phenotypes is not fully understood. To study how SRF utilizes its cofactors during development, we generated a knock-in Srfα1I allele in mice harboring point mutations that disrupt SRF-MRTF-DNA complex formation but leave SRF-TCF activity unaffected. Homozygous Srfα1I/α1I mutants die at E10.5 with notable cardiovascular phenotypes, and neural crest conditional mutants succumb at birth to defects of the cardiac outflow tract but display none of the craniofacial phenotypes associated with complete loss of SRF in that lineage. Our studies further support an important role for MRTF mediating SRF function in cardiac neural crest and suggest new mechanisms by which SRF regulates transcription during development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466305" rel="alternate" title="Differential regulation of cranial and cardiac neural crest by Serum Response Factor (9 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466147</id><title>A hold-and-feed mechanism drives directional DNA loop extrusion by condensin (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.386512+00:00</updated><author><name>Indra A Shaltiel</name></author><author><name>Sumanjit Datta</name></author><author><name>Léa Lecomte</name></author><author><name>Markus Hassler</name></author><author><name>Marc Kschonsak</name></author><author><name>Sol Bravo</name></author><author><name>Catherine Stober</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Eustermann</name></author><author><name>Christian H Haering</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SMC protein complexes structure genomes by extruding DNA loops, but the molecular mechanism that underlies their activity has remained unknown. We show that the active condensin complex entraps the bases of a DNA loop in two separate chambers. Single-molecule and cryo-electron microscopy provide evidence for a power-stroke movement at the first chamber that feeds DNA into the SMC-kleisin ring upon ATP binding, while the second chamber holds on upstream of the same DNA double helix. Unlocking the strict separation of 'motor' and 'anchor' chambers turns condensin from a one-sided into a bidirectional DNA loop extruder. We conclude that the orientation of two topologically bound DNA segments during the course of the SMC reaction cycle determines the directionality of DNA loop extrusion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466147" rel="alternate" title="A hold-and-feed mechanism drives directional DNA loop extrusion by condensin (9 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466204</id><title>The return of the rings: evolutionary role of aromatic residues in liquid-liquid phase separation (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.386825+00:00</updated><author><name>Wen-Lin Ho</name></author><author><name>Jie-rong Huang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aromatic residues appeared relatively late in the evolution of protein sequences. They stabilize the hydrophobic core of globular proteins and are typically absent from intrinsically disordered regions (IDRs). However, recent advances in protein liquid-liquid phase separation (LLPS) studies have shown that aromatic residues in IDRs often act as important “stickers”, promoting multivalent interactions and the formation of higher-order oligomers. To reconcile this apparent contradiction, we compared levels of sequence disorder in RNA binding proteins and the human proteome and found that aromatic residues appear more frequently than expected in the IDRs of RNA binding proteins, which are often found to undergo LLPS. Phylogenetic analysis shows that aromatic residues are highly conserved among chordates, highlighting their importance in LLPS-driven functional assembly. These results suggest therefore that aromatic residues have contributed twice to evolution: in stabilizing structured proteins and in the assembly of biomolecular condensates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466204" rel="alternate" title="The return of the rings: evolutionary role of aromatic residues in liquid-liquid phase separation (9 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465762</id><title>A basement membrane discovery pipeline uncovers network complexity, new regulators, and human disease associations (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.387123+00:00</updated><author><name>Ranjay Jayadev</name></author><author><name>Mychel RPT Morais</name></author><author><name>Jamie M Ellingford</name></author><author><name>Sandhya Srinivasan</name></author><author><name>Richard W Naylor</name></author><author><name>Craig Lawless</name></author><author><name>Anna S Li</name></author><author><name>Jack F Ingham</name></author><author><name>Eric Hastie</name></author><author><name>Qiuyi Chi</name></author><author><name>Maryline Fresquet</name></author><author><name>Nikki-Maria Koudis</name></author><author><name>Huw B Thomas</name></author><author><name>Raymond T O’Keefe</name></author><author><name>Emily Williams</name></author><author><name>Antony Adamson</name></author><author><name>Helen M Stuart</name></author><author><name>Siddharth Banka</name></author><author><name>Damian Smedley</name></author><author><name>David R Sherwood</name></author><author><name>Rachel Lennon</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Basement membranes (BMs) are ubiquitous extracellular matrices whose composition remains elusive, limiting our understanding of BM regulation and function. By developing a bioinformatic and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; discovery pipeline, we define a network of 222 human proteins localized to BMs. Network analysis and screening in &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; and zebrafish identified new BM regulators, including ADAMTS, ROBO, and TGFβ. More than 100 BM-network genes associate with human phenotypes and by screening 63,039 genomes from families with rare disorders, we discovered loss-of-function variants in &lt;italic&gt;LAMA5&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;MPZL2&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;MATN2,&lt;/italic&gt; and show they regulate BM composition and function. This cross-disciplinary study establishes the immense complexity and role of BMs in human health.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465762" rel="alternate" title="A basement membrane discovery pipeline uncovers network complexity, new regulators, and human disease associations (9 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.23.464780</id><title>Double-check the zebrafish 18s rRNA qPCR primers: they may be wrong (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.387643+00:00</updated><author><name>Jianing Wang</name></author><author><name>Zhipeng Yang</name></author><author><name>An Xiao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A widely used qPCR primer for zebrafish gene &lt;italic&gt;rna18s&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;18s rRNA&lt;/italic&gt;, or &lt;italic&gt;18s&lt;/italic&gt;), with the sequence of 5’-TCGC&lt;underline&gt;&lt;bold&gt;ta&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;/underline&gt;GT&lt;underline&gt;&lt;bold&gt;t&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;/underline&gt;GGCATCGTTTA&lt;underline&gt;&lt;bold&gt;t&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;/underline&gt;G-3’, is found to be incorrect. Initially designed for rainbow trout (&lt;italic&gt;Oncorhynchus mykiss&lt;/italic&gt;) &lt;italic&gt;rna18s&lt;/italic&gt;, the primer has four different nucleotides from the zebrafish sequence 5’-TCGC&lt;underline&gt;&lt;bold&gt;GG&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;/underline&gt;GT&lt;underline&gt;&lt;bold&gt;C&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;/underline&gt;GGCATCGTTTA&lt;underline&gt;&lt;bold&gt;C&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;/underline&gt;G-3’ (indicated in bold/underlined, lowercase letters for rainbow trout and uppercase letters for zebrafish). Since its first use in zebrafish in 2006, this mismatched primer has been clearly stated to be used in at least 50 publications and may have affected hundreds or more in publications citing them. For a sensitive, quantitative method as qPCR, this error must be corrected as soon as possible in the zebrafish community by using &lt;italic&gt;rna18s&lt;/italic&gt; primer sets with accurate sequences, such as those summarized and newly designed in this article.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.23.464780" rel="alternate" title="Double-check the zebrafish 18s rRNA qPCR primers: they may be wrong (8 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465780</id><title>TGFβ signaling is required for sclerotome resegmentation during development of the spinal column in Gallus gallus (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.388770+00:00</updated><author><name>Sade W. Clayton</name></author><author><name>Ronisha McCardell</name></author><author><name>Rosa Serra</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We previously showed the importance of TGFβ signaling in development of the mouse axial skeleton. Here, we provide the first direct evidence that TGFβ signaling is required for resegmentation of the sclerotome using chick embryos. Lipophilic fluorescent tracers, DiO and DiD, were microinjected into adjacent somites of embryos treated with or without TGFβR1 inhibitor, SB431542, at developmental day E2.5 (HH16). Lineage tracing of labeled cells was observed over the course of 4 days until the completion of resegmentation at E6.5 (HH32). Vertebrae were malformed and intervertebral discs were small and misshapen in SB431542 injected embryos. Inhibition of TGFβ signaling resulted in alterations in resegmentation that ranged between full, partial, and slanted shifts in distribution of DiO or DiD labeled cells within vertebrae. Patterning of rostro- caudal markers within sclerotome was disrupted at E3.5 after treatment with SB431542 with rostral domains expressing both rostral and caudal markers. Hypaxial myofibers were also increased in thickness after treatment with the inhibitor. We propose that TGFβ signaling regulates rostro-caudal polarity and subsequent resegmentation in sclerotome during spinal column development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465780" rel="alternate" title="TGFβ signaling is required for sclerotome resegmentation during development of the spinal column in Gallus gallus (8 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465782</id><title>Interaction Between Transcribing RNA Polymerase and Topoisomerase I Prevents R-loop Formation in E. coli (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.389007+00:00</updated><author><name>Dmitry Sutormin</name></author><author><name>Alina Galivondzhyan</name></author><author><name>Olga Musharova</name></author><author><name>Dmitrii Travin</name></author><author><name>Anastasiya Rusanova</name></author><author><name>Kseniya Obraztsova</name></author><author><name>Sergei Borukhov</name></author><author><name>Konstantin Severinov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial topoisomerase I (TopoI) removes excessive negative supercoiling and is thought to relax DNA molecules during transcription, replication and other processes. Using ChIP-Seq, we show that TopoI of &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; (EcTopoI) is co-localized, genome-wide, with RNA polymerase (RNAP) in transcription units. Treatment with transcription elongation inhibitor rifampicin leads to EcTopoI relocation to promoter regions, where RNAP also accumulates. When a 14 kDa RNAP-binding EcTopoI C-terminal domain (CTD) is overexpressed, co-localization of EcTopoI and RNAP along the transcription units is reduced. Pull-down experiments directly show that the two enzymes interact &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Using ChIP-Seq and Topo-Seq, we demonstrate that EcTopoI is enriched and in and upstream (within up to 12-15 Kbs) of highly-active transcription units, indicating that EcTopoI relaxes negative supercoiling generated by transcription. Uncoupling of the RNAP-EcTopoI interaction by either overexpression of EcTopoI CTD or deletion of EcTopoI domains involved in the interaction is toxic for cells and leads to excessive negative plasmid supercoiling. Moreover, the CTD overexpression leads to R-loops accumulation genome-wide, indicating that the RNAP-EcTopoI interaction is required for prevention of R-loops formation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Article Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;TopoI colocalizes genome-wide and interacts with RNAP in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Disruption of the interaction between TopoI and RNAP decreases cells viability, leads to hypernegative DNA supercoiling, and R-loops accumulation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;TopoI and DNA gyrase are enriched, respectively, upstream and downstream of transcription units in accordance with twin-domain model of Liu and Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;TopoI recognizes its cleavage sites through a specific motif and by sensing negative supercoiling&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465782" rel="alternate" title="Interaction Between Transcribing RNA Polymerase and Topoisomerase I Prevents R-loop Formation in E. coli (7 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466388</id><title>Orb-dependent polyadenylation contributes to PLP expression and centrosome scaffold assembly (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.389376+00:00</updated><author><name>Junnan Fang</name></author><author><name>Dorothy Lerit</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;As the microtubule-organizing centers (MTOCs) of most cells, centrosomes engineer the bipolar mitotic spindle required for error-free mitosis. &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; Pericentrin (PCNT)-like protein (PLP) is a key centrosome component that directs formation of a pericentriolar material (PCM) scaffold required for PCM organization and MTOC function. Here, we investigate the post-transcriptional regulation of &lt;italic&gt;plp&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA. We identify conserved binding sites for cytoplasmic polyadenylation element binding (CPEB) proteins within the &lt;italic&gt;plp&lt;/italic&gt; 3′-untranslated region and examine the role of the CPEB ortholog, oo18 RNA-binding protein (Orb), in &lt;italic&gt;plp&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA regulation. Our data show Orb biochemically interacts with &lt;italic&gt;plp&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA and promotes PLP protein expression. Loss of &lt;italic&gt;orb&lt;/italic&gt;, but not &lt;italic&gt;orb2&lt;/italic&gt;, diminishes PLP levels in embryonic extracts. Consequently, PLP localization to centrosomes and function in PCM scaffolding is compromised in orb mutant embryos, resulting in genome instability and embryonic lethality. Moreover, we find PLP over-expression can restore centrosome scaffolding and rescue the cell division defects caused by orb depletion. Our data suggest Orb modulates PLP expression at the level of &lt;italic&gt;plp&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA polyadenylation and showcases the post-transcriptional regulation of core, conserved centrosomal mRNAs as critical for centrosome function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466388" rel="alternate" title="Orb-dependent polyadenylation contributes to PLP expression and centrosome scaffold assembly (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466469</id><title>A Notch-dependent transcriptional mechanism controls expression of temporal patterning factors in Drosophila medulla (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.405056+00:00</updated><author><name>Alokananda Ray</name></author><author><name>Xin Li</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Temporal patterning is an important mechanism for generating a great diversity of neuron subtypes from a seemingly homogenous progenitor pool in both vertebrates and invertebrates. Drosophila neuroblasts have been shown to be temporally patterned by sequentially expressed Temporal Transcription Factors (TTFs). These TTFs are proposed to form a transcriptional cascade based on mutant phenotypes, although direct transcriptional regulation between TTFs has not been verified in most cases.  Furthermore, it is not known how the temporal transitions are coupled with generation of the appropriate number of neurons at each stage. We use neuroblasts of the Drosophila optic lobe medulla to address these questions, and show that the expression of TTFs Sloppy-paired 1/ 2 (Slp1/2) is regulated at transcriptional level directly by two other TTFs and the cell-cycle dependent Notch signaling through two cis-regulatory elements.   We also show that supplying transcriptional active Notch can rescue the delayed transition into the Slp stage in cell cycle arrested neuroblasts. Our findings reveal how an interplay between temporal patterning, the neuroblast cell cycle and key signaling pathways such as Notch achieves precise regulation of patterning transcription factor gene expression that is characteristic of these programs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466469" rel="alternate" title="A Notch-dependent transcriptional mechanism controls expression of temporal patterning factors in Drosophila medulla (6 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465660</id><title>Multi-omics analysis reveals cross-organism interactions in coral holobiont (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.405623+00:00</updated><author><name>Toru Maruyama</name></author><author><name>Michihiro Ito</name></author><author><name>Satoshi Wakaoji</name></author><author><name>Yusuke Okubo</name></author><author><name>Keigo Ide</name></author><author><name>Yohei Nishikawa</name></author><author><name>Hiroyuki Fujimura</name></author><author><name>Shoichiro Suda</name></author><author><name>Yoshikatsu Nakano</name></author><author><name>Noriyuki Satoh</name></author><author><name>Chuya Shinzato</name></author><author><name>Kei Yura</name></author><author><name>Haruko Takeyama</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Corals create an ecosystem, called a holobiont, with intracellular algae (zooxanthellae) and resident bacteria. Zooxanthellae and some bacteria play major roles in the physiological properties of the coral host. However, because of the difficulties in experimental verification of cross-organism interactions, the mechanisms underpinning these interactions are largely unknown. To address this, we here generated and then analyzed multi-omics datasets for corals, zooxanthellae, and bacteria collected at Okinawa, Japan, from November 2014 to September 2016. Using cross-organism co-expression analysis, we successfully characterized the host–alga relationship in the coral holobiont. Specifically, we observed that the coral host dominates the zooxanthellae. The multi-omics analysis also suggested that infection with coral-associated bacteria &lt;italic&gt;Endozoicomonas&lt;/italic&gt; likely involves coral-like ephrin ligands, triggering an immune response of the coral host. This study highlights the potential of the multi-omics approach to elucidate coral–microbe interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465660" rel="alternate" title="Multi-omics analysis reveals cross-organism interactions in coral holobiont (6 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.465104</id><title>Genetic Diversity of Non-Tuberculous Mycobacteria among Symptomatic TB negative Patients in Kenya (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.406124+00:00</updated><author><name>Zakayo Maingi Maingi</name></author><author><name>Nellie Mukiri</name></author><author><name>Frank Gekara Onyambu</name></author><author><name>Wallace Bulimo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Non-Tuberculous Mycobacteria (NTM) transmission to humans occurs through inhalation of dust particles or vaporized water containing NTM leading to pulmonary manifestations. NTM infections are often misdiagnosed for tuberculosis (TB) due to their similar clinical and radiological manifestations. We, therefore, performed a species-level identification of NTM in symptomatic TB negative patients through sequencing of the hsp65 gene. We conducted a cross-sectional study at the National Tuberculosis Reference Laboratory in the period between January to November 2020. One hundred and sixty-six mycobacterial culture-positive samples that tested negative for TB using capilia underwent Polymerase Chain Reaction targeting the hsp65 gene. Isolates showing a band with gel electrophoresis at 441 bp position were sequenced using Sanger technology. Geneious software was used to analyze the obtained sequences, and the National Center for Biotechnology Information gene database identified NTM species for each isolate. A phylogenetic tree was constructed from the DNA sequences and evolutionary distances computed using the general time-reversible method. Pearson chi-square was used to determine the association between NTM infection and participants characteristics. Our study identified 43 different NTM species. The dominant NTM belonged to Mycobacterium avium complex 37 (31%). Slow-growing NTM were the majority at 86 (71%) while rapid-growing NTM were 36 (29%). A significant association (p&amp;lt;0.05) was observed for regions and age, while patient type had a week likelihood of NTM infection. Our study characterized the diversity of NTM in Kenya for the first time and showed a high diversity of NTM species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.465104" rel="alternate" title="Genetic Diversity of Non-Tuberculous Mycobacteria among Symptomatic TB negative Patients in Kenya (5 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465969</id><title>The endoplasmic reticulum adopts two distinct tubule forms (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.406448+00:00</updated><author><name>Bowen Wang</name></author><author><name>Zhiheng Zhao</name></author><author><name>Michael Xiong</name></author><author><name>Rui Yan</name></author><author><name>Ke Xu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The endoplasmic reticulum (ER) is a versatile organelle with diverse functions. Through super-resolution microscopy, we show that the peripheral ER in the mammalian cell adopts two distinct forms of tubules. Whereas an ultrathin form, R1, is consistently covered by ER-membrane curvature-promoting proteins, &lt;italic&gt;e&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;g&lt;/italic&gt;., Rtn4 in the native cell, in the second form, R2, Rtn4 and analogs are arranged into two parallel lines at a conserved separation of ∼105 nm over long ranges. The two tubule forms together account for ∼90% of the total tubule length in the cell, with either one being dominant in different cell types. The R1-R2 dichotomy and the final tubule geometry are both co-regulated by Rtn4 (and analogs) and the ER sheet-maintaining protein Climp63, which respectively define the edge curvature and lumen height of the R2 tubules to generate a ribbon-like structure of well-defined width. Accordingly, the R2 tubule width correlates positively with the Climp63 intralumenal size. The R1 and R2 tubules undergo active remodeling at the second/sub-second time scales as they differently accommodate proteins, with the former effectively excluding ER-luminal proteins and ER-membrane proteins with large intraluminal domains. We thus uncover a dynamic structural dichotomy for ER tubules with intriguing functional implications.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465969" rel="alternate" title="The endoplasmic reticulum adopts two distinct tubule forms (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466346</id><title>inPOSE: a flexible toolbox for chromosomal cloning and amplification of bacterial transgenes (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.407016+00:00</updated><author><name>Ranti Dev Shukla</name></author><author><name>Agnes Zvara</name></author><author><name>Akos Avramucz</name></author><author><name>Alyona Biketova</name></author><author><name>Akos Nyerges</name></author><author><name>Laszlo G. Puskas</name></author><author><name>Tamas Feher</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cloning genes and operons encoding heterologous functions in bacterial hosts is almost exclusively carried out today using plasmid vectors. This has multiple drawbacks, including the need for constant selection and the variation in copy numbers. Chromosomal integration of transgenes has always offered a viable alternative, however, to date it has been of limited use due to its tedious nature and to being limited often to a single copy. We introduce here a strategy that uses bacterial insertion sequences, the simplest autonomous transposable elements to insert and amplify genetic cargo into a bacterial chromosome. Transgene insertion can take place either as transposition or homologous recombination, and copy-number amplification is achieved using controlled copy-paste transposition. We display successful use of IS&lt;italic&gt;1&lt;/italic&gt; and IS&lt;italic&gt;3 &lt;/italic&gt;for this purpose in &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; cells, using various selection markers.  We demonstrate the insertion of selectable genes, an unselectable gene, and a five-gene operon in up to two copies in a single step. We continue with the amplification of the inserted cassette to double-digit copy numbers within two rounds of transposase induction and selection. Finally, we analyze the stability of the cloned genetic constructs in the lack of selection, and find it to be superior to all investigated plasmid-based systems. Due to the ubiquitous nature of transposable elements we believe that with proper design, this strategy can be adapted to numerous further bacterial species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466346" rel="alternate" title="inPOSE: a flexible toolbox for chromosomal cloning and amplification of bacterial transgenes (4 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466358</id><title>A phosphoregulated RhoGEF feedback loop tunes cortical flow driven amoeboid migration in vivo (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.407401+00:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Lin</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Luo</name></author><author><name>Ruth Lehmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cortical flow driven amoeboid migration utilizes friction from retrograde cortical actin flow to generate motion. Many cell types, including cancer cells, can assemble a cortical flow engine to migrate under confinement and low adhesion in vitro, but it remains unclear whether this engine is endogenously utilized in vivo. Moreover, in the context of a changing environment, it is not known how upstream regulation can set in motion and sustain a mutual feedback between flow and polarity. Here, we establish that Drosophila primordial germ cells (PGCs) utilize cortical flow driven amoeboid migration and that flows are oriented by external cues during developmental homing in vivo. The molecular basis of flow modulation is a phosphoregulated feedback loop involving RhoGEF2, a microtubule plus-end tracking RhoA specific RhoGEF, enriched at the rear of PGCs. RhoGEF2 depletion slows and disorganizes cortical flow, reducing migration speed, while RhoGEF2 activation accelerates cortical flow, thereby augmenting myosin II polarity and migration speed. Both perturbations impair PGC pathfinding, suggesting cortical flows must be tuned for accurate guidance. We surprisingly find that RhoGEF2 polarity and activation are independent of upstream canonical Gα12/13 signaling. Instead, its PDZ domain and conserved RhoA binding residues in its PH domain are required to establish a positive feedback loop that augments its basal activity. Upstream regulation of this feedback loop occurs via AMPK dependent multisite phosphorylation near a conserved EB1 binding SxIP motif, which releases RhoGEF2 from EB1 dependent inhibition. Thus, we reveal cortical flows as versatile, tunable engines for directed amoeboid migration in vivo.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466358" rel="alternate" title="A phosphoregulated RhoGEF feedback loop tunes cortical flow driven amoeboid migration in vivo (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466502</id><title>Hidden pathway for cytokine receptor activation: Structural insights into a marine sponge-derived lectin that activates the thrombopoietin receptor via recognition of the fucose moiety (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.407639+00:00</updated><author><name>Hiromi Watari</name></author><author><name>Hiromu Kageyama</name></author><author><name>Nami Masubuchi</name></author><author><name>Hiroya Nakajima</name></author><author><name>Kako Onodera</name></author><author><name>Pamela J Focia</name></author><author><name>Takumi Oshiro</name></author><author><name>Takashi Matsui</name></author><author><name>Yoshio Kodera</name></author><author><name>Tomohisa Ogawa</name></author><author><name>Takeshi Yokoyama</name></author><author><name>Makoto Hirayama</name></author><author><name>Kanji Hori</name></author><author><name>Douglas M Freymann</name></author><author><name>Norio Komatsu</name></author><author><name>Marito Araki</name></author><author><name>Yoshikazu Tanaka</name></author><author><name>Ryuichi Sakai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;N-glycan-mediated activation of the thrombopoietin receptor (MPL) under pathological conditions has been implicated in myeloproliferative neoplasms induced by mutant calreticulin, which forms an endogenous receptor-agonist complex that constitutively activates the receptor. However, the molecular basis for this mechanism remains unstudied because no external agonist has been discovered. Here, we describe the structure and function of a marine sponge-derived MPL agonist, thrombocorticin (ThC). ThC-induced activation persists due to limited receptor internalization. Strong synergy between ThC and thrombopoietin suggests that ThC catalyzes the formation of receptor dimers on the cell surface. We show that MPL is subject to sugar-mediated activation and that lectin-mediated activation kinetics differ from cytokine-mediated activation kinetics. Our data demonstrated the potential of lectins to provide deeper insight into human pathogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466502" rel="alternate" title="Hidden pathway for cytokine receptor activation: Structural insights into a marine sponge-derived lectin that activates the thrombopoietin receptor via recognition of the fucose moiety (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466404</id><title>In vitro reconstituted quorum sensing pathways enable rapid evaluation of quorum sensing inhibitors (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.408119+00:00</updated><author><name>Dingchen Yu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Quorum sensing, as inner- or inter-species microbial communication process orchestrated by diffusible autoinducers, typically results in collective pathogenic behaviours, being recognized as a promising druggable target for anti-virulence. Here, we reconstituted las and rhl quorum sensing pathways of Pseudomonas aeruginosa, mediated by acyl-homoserine lactones (AHLs) and LuxI/LuxR-family proteins, with fluorescence output in Escherichia coli cell-free expression system, offering a platform to rapidly evaluate quorum sensing inhibitors (QSIs) in vitro. Previously reported small-molecule quorum sensing inhibitors for interfering with P. aeruginosa quorum sensing systems were tested and showed mild to high on-target inhibition as well as off-target toxicity. Of note, quercetin displayed potent on-target inhibition to quorum sensing pathways as well as acceptable off-target toxicity to cell-free expression machinery. Upon our work, cell-free platform is anticipated to further facilitate automated and high-throughput drug screening, bridge in silico and in vivo drug-screening methods, and accelerate the upgrading of antimicrobial arsenal.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466404" rel="alternate" title="In vitro reconstituted quorum sensing pathways enable rapid evaluation of quorum sensing inhibitors (4 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.464584</id><title>Molecular identification of rhizobacterial isolates from Prosopis limensis and their effect on the growth of Raphanus sativus under salt stress (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.408906+00:00</updated><author><name>Rene Flores Clavo</name></author><author><name>Esteban A Valladolid Suyón</name></author><author><name>Karin Reinoza Farroñan</name></author><author><name>Cristian Asmat Ortega</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Zuñiga Valdera</name></author><author><name>Fabiana Fantinatti Garboggini</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Iglesias-Osores</name></author><author><name>Carmen Rosa Carreño Farfán</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Soil salinity negatively affects the development of agricultural crops. The utilization of plant growth-promoting rhizobacteria is a biotechnological alternative to mitigate this problem. Rhizobacteria were isolated from the roots and rhizosphere of &lt;italic&gt;Prosopis limensis&lt;/italic&gt; Bentham “carob” to identify them and determine their potential as plant growth-promoters under salt stress. First, ACC deaminase activity was determined in Dworkin &amp;amp; Foster (DF) minimum medium with 3.0 mM ACC as a source of nitrogen; besides, tolerance to sodium chloride was determined in Nutrient Broth (NB) supplemented with 10% NaCI. Then, bacteria displaying ACC deaminase activity and a 10% NaCI tolerance were selected, identified through genomic analysis targeting the 16s rRNA gene, and inoculated into &lt;italic&gt;Raphanus sativus&lt;/italic&gt; L. “radish” seeds to determine the effect on germination percentage under salt stress (80 mM NaCI) and, also on indole production and phosphate solubilization. Isolates were also utilized to evaluate their effect on the growth of radish in saline soils. Genomic analysis showed two bacterial isolates from the genus &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/italic&gt; and one from the genus &lt;italic&gt;Bordetella&lt;/italic&gt;: Isolate MW604823 was identified as &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/italic&gt; sp.; isolate MW604824, as &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas hunanensis;&lt;/italic&gt; and isolate MW604826 as &lt;italic&gt;Bordetella muralis&lt;/italic&gt;. Thee isolates demonstrated ACC deaminase activity and tolerance to 10% NaCI. Inoculation of the isolates on radish seeds increased germination percentage compared to the control. The isolates displayed &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; indole production and phosphate solubilization capacity. Moreover, the isolates promoted the growth of radish under salt stress conditions, increasing, leave number, root number, aerial, and root biomass, demonstrating their potential as a biofertilizers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.464584" rel="alternate" title="Molecular identification of rhizobacterial isolates from Prosopis limensis and their effect on the growth of Raphanus sativus under salt stress (4 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465931</id><title>A system for CBAF reconstitution reveals roles for BAF47 domains and BCL7 in nucleosome ejection (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.409305+00:00</updated><author><name>Timothy S. Mulvihill</name></author><author><name>Mary L. Nelson</name></author><author><name>Naveen Verma</name></author><author><name>Kevin B. Jones</name></author><author><name>Bradley R. Cairns</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Canonical BAF (CBAF) is an essential 12-protein chromatin-remodeling complex that slides and/or ejects nucleosomes using the alternative catalytic ATP-dependent DNA translocases BRG1 or BRM. Currently, the regulation of BRG1/BRM activity and nucleosome ejection remain incompletely understood. To address this, we developed a system for full CBAF reconstitution and purification, and created a novel nucleosome ejection assay. ARID1A and DPF2 were dispensable for assembly and chromatin remodeling activity, contrasting with prior work. The actin-related protein BAF53A and β-actin components interacted and enhanced DNA translocation, and were required for BCL7A incorporation, which potentiated ejection. BAF47 also regulated ejection, utilizing two stimulatory domains and an autoinhibitory domain. Finally, we provide evidence for ‘direct’ nucleosome ejection at low nucleosome density on closed circular arrays. Taken together, we provide powerful new tools for CBAF mechanistic investigation and reveal new roles for several CBAF components.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465931" rel="alternate" title="A system for CBAF reconstitution reveals roles for BAF47 domains and BCL7 in nucleosome ejection (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.23.465424</id><title>Infants’ attention to eyes is an independent, heritable trait predicting later verbal competence (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.409645+00:00</updated><author><name>Charlotte Viktorsson</name></author><author><name>Ana Maria Portugal</name></author><author><name>Danyang Li</name></author><author><name>Maja Rudling</name></author><author><name>Monica Siqueiros Sanchez</name></author><author><name>Kristiina Tammimies</name></author><author><name>Mark J. Taylor</name></author><author><name>Angelica Ronald</name></author><author><name>Terje Falck-Ytter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;From birth, infants orient preferentially to faces, and when looking at the face, they attend primarily to eyes and mouth – two areas that convey different types of information. Here, in a sample of 535 5-month-old infant twins, we assessed eye (relative to mouth) preference in early infancy. Eye preference was independent from all other concurrent traits measured, and had a moderate-to-high contribution from genetic influences (A = .57; 95% CI: .45, .66). Preference for eyes over mouth at 5 months predicted higher parent ratings of verbal competence in toddlerhood, but did not predict autistic traits. These results suggest that variation in eye looking reflects a type of biological niche picking emerging before infants can select their environments by other means (crawling or walking).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.23.465424" rel="alternate" title="Infants’ attention to eyes is an independent, heritable trait predicting later verbal competence (3 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.465954</id><title>R-loop mapping and characterization during Drosophila embryogenesis reveals developmental plasticity in R-loop signatures (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.410035+00:00</updated><author><name>Alex Munden</name></author><author><name>Mary Lauren Benton</name></author><author><name>John A Capra</name></author><author><name>Jared Nordman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;R-loops are involved in transcriptional regulation, DNA and histone post-translational modifications, genome replication and genome stability. To what extent R-loop abundance and genome-wide localization is actively regulated during metazoan embryogenesis is unknown. The developmental program of Drosophila embryogenesis provides a powerful system to study address these questions due to its well-characterized developmental program, the sudden onset of zygotic transcription and available genome-wide ChIP and transcription data sets. Here, we measure the overall abundance and genome localization of R-loops in early and late-stage embryos relative to Drosophila cultured cells. We demonstrate that proper absolute R-loop levels change during embryogenesis and that resolution of R-loops is critical for embryonic development. R-loop mapping by strand-specific DRIP-seq revealed that R-loop localization is plastic across development, both in the genes which form R-loops and where they localize relative to gene bodies. Importantly, these changes are not driven by changes in the transcriptional program. Rather, negative GC skew and absolute changes in AT skew are associated with R-loop formation in Drosophila. Furthermore, we demonstrate that while some chromatin binding proteins and histone modification such as H3K27me3 are associated with R-loops throughout development, other chromatin factors associated with R-loops in a developmental specific manner. Our findings highlight the importance and developmental plasticity of R-loops during Drosophila development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.465954" rel="alternate" title="R-loop mapping and characterization during Drosophila embryogenesis reveals developmental plasticity in R-loop signatures (3 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466520</id><title>The early embryonic transcriptome of a Hawaiian 	Drosophila picture-wing fly shows evidence of altered gene expression and novel gene evolution (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.410345+00:00</updated><author><name>Madeline Chenevert</name></author><author><name>Bronwyn Miller</name></author><author><name>Ahmad Karkoutli</name></author><author><name>Anna Rusnak</name></author><author><name>Susan Lott</name></author><author><name>Joel Atallah</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A massive adaptive radiation on the Hawaiian archipelago has produced approximately one quarter of the fly species in the family Drosophilidae. The Hawaiian &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; clade has long been recognized as a model system for the study of both the ecology of island endemics and the evolution of developmental mechanisms, but relatively few genomic and transcriptomic datasets are available for this group. We present here a differential expression analysis of the transcriptional profiles of two highly conserved embryonic stages in the Hawaiian picture-wing fly &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila grimshawi&lt;/italic&gt;. When we compared our results to previously published datasets across the family Drosophilidae, we identified cases of both gains and losses of gene representation in &lt;italic&gt;D. grimshawi&lt;/italic&gt;, including an apparent delay in Hox gene activation. We also found high expression of unannotated genes. Most transcripts of unannotated genes with open reading frames do not have homologs in non-Hawaiian &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; species, although the vast majority have sequence matches in other genomes of the Hawaiian picture-wing flies. Some of these genes may have arisen from non-coding sequence in the ancestor of Hawaiian flies or during the evolution of the clade. Our results suggests that both the modified use of ancestral genes and the evolution of new ones may occur in rapid radiations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466520" rel="alternate" title="The early embryonic transcriptome of a Hawaiian &#9;Drosophila picture-wing fly shows evidence of altered gene expression and novel gene evolution (3 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>