<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.482845+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456551</id><title>Tuning levels of low-complexity domain interactions to modulate endogenous oncogenic transcription (59 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.483346+00:00</updated><author><name>Shasha Chong</name></author><author><name>Thomas G.W. Graham</name></author><author><name>Claire Dugast-Darzacq</name></author><author><name>Gina M. Dailey</name></author><author><name>Xavier Darzacq</name></author><author><name>Robert Tjian</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gene activation by mammalian transcription factors (TFs) requires dynamic, multivalent, and selective interactions of their intrinsically disordered low-complexity domains (LCDs), but how such interactions mediate transcription remains unclear. It has been proposed that extensive LCD-LCD interactions culminating in liquid-liquid phase separation (LLPS) of TFs is the dominant mechanism underlying transactivation. Here, we investigated how tuning the amount and localization of LCD-LCD interactions &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; affects transcription of endogenous human genes. Quantitative single-cell and single-molecule imaging reveals that the oncogenic TF EWS/FLI1 requires a finely tuned range of LCD-LCD interactions to efficiently activate target genes. Modest or more dramatic increases in LCD-LCD interactions toward putative LLPS repress EWS/FLI1-driven transcription in patient cells. Likewise, ectopically creating LCD-LCD interactions to sequester EWS/FLI1 into a bona fide LLPS compartment, the nucleolus, inhibits EWS/FLI1-driven transcription and oncogenic transformation. Our findings reveal fundamental principles underlying LCD-mediated transcription and suggest mislocalizing specific LCD-LCD interactions as a novel therapeutic strategy for targeting disease-causing TFs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456551" rel="alternate" title="Tuning levels of low-complexity domain interactions to modulate endogenous oncogenic transcription (59 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-08-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457167</id><title>Evolving a generalist biosensor for bicyclic monoterpenes (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.483840+00:00</updated><author><name>Simon d'Oelsnitz</name></author><author><name>Vylan Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Hal S Alper</name></author><author><name>Andrew D Ellington</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Prokaryotic transcription factors can be repurposed as analytical and synthetic tools for precise chemical measurement and regulation. Monoterpenes encompass a broad chemical family that are commercially valuable as flavors, cosmetics, and fragrances, but have proven difficult to measure, especially in cells. Herein, we develop genetically-encoded, generalist monoterpene biosensors by using directed evolution to expand the effector specificity of the camphor-responsive TetR-family regulator CamR from Pseudomonas putida. Using a novel negative selection coupled with a high-throughput positive screen (Seamless Enrichment of Ligand-Inducible Sensors, SELIS), we evolve CamR biosensors that can recognize four distinct monoterpenes: borneol, fenchol, eucalyptol, and camphene. Different evolutionary trajectories surprisingly yielded common mutations, emphasizing the utility of CamR as a platform for creating generalist biosensors. Systematic promoter optimization driving the reporter increased the system's signal-to-noise ratio to 150-fold. These sensors can serve as a starting point for the high-throughput screening and dynamic regulation of bicyclic monoterpene production strains.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457167" rel="alternate" title="Evolving a generalist biosensor for bicyclic monoterpenes (14 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456464</id><title>RSC-mediated nucleosome positioning and GRFs form barriers in promoters to limit divergent noncoding transcription (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.484391+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew Wu</name></author><author><name>Claudia Vivori</name></author><author><name>Harshil Patel</name></author><author><name>Theodora Sideri</name></author><author><name>Folkert J. van Werven</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The directionality of gene promoters - the ratio of protein-coding over divergent noncoding transcription - is highly variable and regulated. How promoter directionality is controlled remains poorly understood. We show that the chromatin remodelling complex RSC and general regulatory factors (GRFs) dictate promoter directionality by attenuating divergent transcription. Depletion of RSC increased divergent noncoding transcription and decreased protein-coding transcription at promoters with strong directionality. Consistent with RSC’s role in regulating chromatin, RSC depletion impacts nucleosome occupancy upstream of the nucleosome depleted region where divergent transcription initiates, suggesting that nucleosome positioning at the 5’ border of gene promoters physically blocks the recruitment of the transcription machinery and inhibits initiation of divergent transcription. Highly directional promoters were also enriched for the binding of GRFs such as Reb1 and Abf1. Furthermore, ectopic targeting of divergent transcription initiation sites with GRFs or the dCas9 protein can suppress divergent transcription. Our data suggest that RSC-mediated nucleosome positioning and GRFs play a pervasive role in repressing divergent transcription. We propose that any DNA binding factor, when stably associated with cryptic transcription start sites, can form a barrier for repressing divergent transcription. Our study provides an explanation as to why certain promoters are more directional than others.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456464" rel="alternate" title="RSC-mediated nucleosome positioning and GRFs form barriers in promoters to limit divergent noncoding transcription (10 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.21.457182</id><title>Decoding cellular deformation from pseudo-simultaneously observed Rho GTPase activities (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.484927+00:00</updated><author><name>Katsuyuki Kunida</name></author><author><name>Nobuhiro Takagi</name></author><author><name>Kazushi Ikeda</name></author><author><name>Takeshi Nakamura</name></author><author><name>Yuichi Sakumura</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The inability to simultaneously observe all of the important Rho GTPases (Cdc42, Rac1, and RhoA) has prevented us from obtaining evidence of their coordinated regulation during cell deformation. Here, we propose Motion-Triggered Average (MTA), an algorithm that converts individually observed GTPases into pseudo-simultaneous observations. Using the time series obtained by MTA and mathematical model, we succeeded for the first time in decoding the cell edge velocity from the three GTPase activities to provide clear numerical evidence for coordinated cell edge regulation by the three GTPases. We found that the characteristics of the obtained activities were consistent with those of previous studies, and that GTPase activities and their derivatives were involved in edge regulation. Our approach provides an effective strategy for using single-molecule observations to elucidate problems hampered by the lack of simultaneous observations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.21.457182" rel="alternate" title="Decoding cellular deformation from pseudo-simultaneously observed Rho GTPase activities (8 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457124</id><title>Spacer2PAM: A computational framework for identification of functional PAM sequences for endogenous CRISPR systems (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.485570+00:00</updated><author><name>Grant A Rybnicky</name></author><author><name>Nicholas A Fackler</name></author><author><name>Ashty S Karim</name></author><author><name>Michael Köpke</name></author><author><name>Michael C Jewett</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;RNA-guided nucleases from clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats (CRISPR) systems expand opportunities for precise, targeted genome modification. Endogenous CRISPR systems in many bacteria and archaea are particularly attractive to circumvent expression, functionality, and unintended activity hurdles posed by heterologous CRISPR effectors. However, each CRISPR system recognizes a unique set of PAM sequences, which requires extensive screening of randomized DNA libraries. This challenge makes it difficult to develop endogenous CRISPR systems, especially in organisms that are slow-growing or have transformation idiosyncrasies. To address this limitation, we present Spacer2PAM, an easy-to-use, easy-to-interpret R package built to identify potential PAM sequences for any CRISPR system given its corresponding CRISPR array as input. Spacer2PAM can be used in Quick mode to generate a single PAM prediction that is likely to be functional or in Comprehensive mode to inform targeted, unpooled PAM libraries small enough to screen in difficult to transform organisms. We demonstrate Spacer2PAM by predicting PAM sequences for industrially relevant organisms and experimentally identifying seven PAM sequences that mediate interference from the Spacer2PAM-predicted PAM library for the type I-B CRISPR system from Clostridium autoethanogenum. We anticipate that Spacer2PAM will facilitate the use of endogenous CRISPR systems for industrial biotechnology and synthetic biology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457124" rel="alternate" title="Spacer2PAM: A computational framework for identification of functional PAM sequences for endogenous CRISPR systems (7 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457043</id><title>Constitutive signal bias mediated by the human GHRHR splice variant 1 (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.485878+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhaotong Cong</name></author><author><name>Fulai Zhou</name></author><author><name>Chao Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xinyu Zou</name></author><author><name>Huibing Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yuzhe Wang</name></author><author><name>Qingtong Zhou</name></author><author><name>Xiaoqing Cai</name></author><author><name>Qiaofeng Liu</name></author><author><name>Jie Li</name></author><author><name>Lijun Shao</name></author><author><name>Chunyou Mao</name></author><author><name>Xi Wang</name></author><author><name>Jihong Wu</name></author><author><name>Tian Xia</name></author><author><name>Lihua Zhao</name></author><author><name>Hualiang Jiang</name></author><author><name>Yan Zhang</name></author><author><name>H. Eric Xu</name></author><author><name>Xi Cheng</name></author><author><name>Dehua Yang</name></author><author><name>Ming-Wei Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Alternative splicing of G protein-coupled receptors has been observed, but their functions are largely unknown. Here, we report that a splice variant (SV1) of the human growth hormone releasing hormone receptor (GHRHR) is capable of transducing biased signal. Differing only at the receptor N terminus, GHRHR predominantly activates G&lt;sub&gt;s&lt;/sub&gt; while SV1 selectively couples to β-arrestins. Based on the cryo-electron microscopy structures of SV1 in the apo state or in complex with the G&lt;sub&gt;s&lt;/sub&gt; protein, molecular dynamics simulations reveal that the N termini of GHRHR and SV1 differentiate the downstream signaling pathways, G&lt;sub&gt;s&lt;/sub&gt; vs. β-arrestins. Suggested by mutagenesis and functional studies, it appears that GHRH-elicited signal bias towards β-arrestin recruitment is constitutively mediated by SV1. The level of SV1 expression in prostate cancer cells is also positively correlated with ERK1/2 phosphorylation but negatively correlated with cAMP response. Our findings imply that constitutive signal bias may be a mechanism that ensures cancer cell proliferation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457043" rel="alternate" title="Constitutive signal bias mediated by the human GHRHR splice variant 1 (6 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457062</id><title>Quantification of macromolecular biomass composition for constraint-based metabolic modeling (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.486525+00:00</updated><author><name>Vetle Simensen</name></author><author><name>Christian Schulz</name></author><author><name>Emil Karlsen</name></author><author><name>Signe Bråtelund</name></author><author><name>Idun Burgos</name></author><author><name>Lilja Brekke Thorfinnsdottir</name></author><author><name>Laura García-Calvo</name></author><author><name>Per Bruheim</name></author><author><name>Eivind Almaas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genome-scale metabolic models (GEMs) are mathematical representations of metabolism that allow for &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; simulation of metabolic phenotypes and capabilities. A prerequisite for these predictions is an accurate representation of the biomolecular composition of the cell necessary for replication and growth, implemented in GEMs as the so-called biomass objective function (BOF). The BOF contains the metabolic precursors required for synthesis of the cellular macro- and micromolecular constituents (e.g. protein, RNA, DNA), and its composition is highly dependent on the particular organism, strain, and growth condition. Despite its critical role, the BOF is rarely constructed using specific measurements of the modeled organism, drawing the validity of this approach into question. Thus, there is a need to establish robust and reliable protocols for experimental condition-specific biomass determination. Here, we address this challenge by presenting a general pipeline for biomass quantification, evaluating its performance on &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; K-12 MG1655 sampled during balanced exponential growth under controlled conditions in a batch-fermentor set-up. We significantly improve both the coverage and molecular resolution compared to previously published workflows, quantifying 91.6% of the biomass. Our measurements display great correspondence with previously reported measurements, and we were also able to detect subtle characteristics specific to the particular &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; strain. Using the modified &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; GEM &lt;italic&gt;i&lt;/italic&gt;ML1515a, we compare the feasible flux ranges of our experimentally determined BOF with the original BOF, finding that the changes in BOF coefficients considerably affect the attainable fluxes at the genome-scale.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457062" rel="alternate" title="Quantification of macromolecular biomass composition for constraint-based metabolic modeling (6 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.18.456812</id><title>Improved radiation expression profiling by sequential application of sensitive and specific gene signatures (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.487340+00:00</updated><author><name>Eliseos J Mucaki</name></author><author><name>Ben C Shirley</name></author><author><name>Peter K Rogan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Purpose: Combinations of expressed genes can discriminate radiation-exposed from normal control blood samples by machine learning based signatures (with 8 to 20% misclassification rates). These signatures can quantify therapeutically-relevant as well as accidental radiation exposures. The prodromal symptoms of Acute Radiation Syndrome (ARS) overlap some viral infections. We recently showed that these radiation signatures produced unexpected false positive misclassification of influenza and dengue infected samples. The present study investigates these and other confounders, and then mitigates their effects on signature accuracy.
Methods: This study investigated recall by previous and novel radiation signatures independently derived from multiple Gene Expression Omnibus datasets on common and rare non-malignant blood disorders and blood-borne infections (thromboembolism, S. aureus bacteremia, malaria, sickle cell disease, polycythemia vera, and aplastic anemia). Normalized expression levels of signature genes are used as input to machine learning-based classifiers to predict radiation exposure in other hematological conditions. 
Results: Except for aplastic anemia, these confounders modify the normal baseline expression values, leading to false-positive misclassification of radiation exposures in 8 to 54% of individuals. Shared changes were predominantly in DNA damage response and apoptosis-related gene transcripts in radiation and confounding hematological conditions compromise the utility of these signatures for radiation assessment. These confounding conditions are known to induce neutrophil extracellular traps, initiated by chromatin decondensation, fragmentation and often, programmed cell death. Ribovirus infections are proposed to deplete RNA binding proteins, inducing R-loops in chromatin which collide with replication forks resulting in DNA damage and apoptosis. To mitigate the effects of confounders, we evaluated predicted radiation positive samples with novel gene expression signatures derived from radiation-responsive transcripts of secreted blood plasma proteins whose expression levels are unperturbed in these confounding conditions. 
Conclusions: This approach identifies and eliminates misclassified samples with underlying hematological or infectious conditions, leaving only samples with true radiation exposures. Diagnostic accuracy is significantly improved by selecting genes that maximize both sensitivity and specificity in the appropriate tissue using combinations of the best signatures for each of these classes of signatures.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.18.456812" rel="alternate" title="Improved radiation expression profiling by sequential application of sensitive and specific gene signatures (4 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.17.456507</id><title>A micro-evolutionary change in target binding sites as key determinant of Ultrabithorax function in Drosophila (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.487970+00:00</updated><author><name>Soumen Khan</name></author><author><name>Saurabh J. Pradhan</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Giraud</name></author><author><name>Françoise Bleicher</name></author><author><name>Rachel Paul</name></author><author><name>Samir Merabet</name></author><author><name>LS Shashidhara</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;All Hox proteins are known to recognize, in vitro, similar DNA-binding sites containing a TAAT core sequence. This poor DNA-binding specificity is in sharp contrast with their specific functions in vivo. Here we report a new binding motif with TAAAT core sequence to which the Hox protein Ultrabithorax (Ubx) binds with higher affinity and specificity. Using transgenic and luciferase assays, we show that this new motif is critical for Ubx-mediated regulation of a target gene in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt;. Interestingly, this new motif with TAAAT core sequences is not associated with the targets of Ubx in the honeybee, &lt;italic&gt;Apis mellifera&lt;/italic&gt;, wherein hindwings are nearly identical to the forewings. We show that introduction of TAAAT motif in the place of TAAT motif is sufficient to bring an enhancer of a wing-promoting gene of &lt;italic&gt;A. mellifera&lt;/italic&gt; under the regulation of Ubx. Our results, thus, suggest that binding motifs with a TAAAT core sequence may help identify functionally relevant direct targets of Ubx in &lt;italic&gt;D. melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; and the emergence of these binding sites may be crucial for Hox-mediated morphological changes during insect evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.17.456507" rel="alternate" title="A micro-evolutionary change in target binding sites as key determinant of Ultrabithorax function in Drosophila (4 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-08-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456439</id><title>SUMO E2/E3 Enzyme Co-Recognize Substrates and Confers High Substrates Specificity (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.488409+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhehao Xiong</name></author><author><name>Ling Jiang</name></author><author><name>Yan Liu</name></author><author><name>Jun Li</name></author><author><name>Jiayu Liao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Although various technologies can determine protein-protein interaction affinity, Kd, current approaches require at least one interacting protein to be purified. Here, we present a development of high-throughput approach to determine protein interaction affinity for un-purified interacting proteins using quantitative FRET assay. We developed this approach first using SUMO E2 conjugating enzyme, Ubc9, and SUMO substrate, RanGap1c. The interaction affinities from two purified proteins and two un-purified proteins in the presence of BSA, bacterial extracts or two mixtures are all in excellent agreement with that obtained from the SPR measurement. We then applied this approach to determine the interaction affinities of SUMO E3 PIAS1 and Ubc9 with a SUMO substrate, influenza virus protein, NS1, and, for the first time, the SUMO E3 ligase-substrate interaction affinity is determined, which enables us to provide a kinetics explanation for the two-enzyme substrate recognition mode. In general, our studies allow high-throughput determination of protein interacting affinity without any purification, and both the approach and scientific discoveries can be applied to proteins that are difficult to be expressed in general.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456439" rel="alternate" title="SUMO E2/E3 Enzyme Co-Recognize Substrates and Confers High Substrates Specificity (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.456998</id><title>Structures of the Human SPAK and OSR1 Conserved C-Terminal (CCT) Domains (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.488806+00:00</updated><author><name>Karen T. Elvers</name></author><author><name>Magdalena Lipka-Lloyd</name></author><author><name>Rebecca C. Trueman</name></author><author><name>Benjamin D. Bax</name></author><author><name>Youcef Mehellou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;STE20/SPS1-related proline/alanine-rich kinase (SPAK) and Oxidative Stress Responsive 1 (OSR1) kinase are two serine/threonine protein kinase that regulate the function of ion co-transporters through phosphorylation. The highly conserved C-terminal (CCT) domains of SPAK and OSR1 bind to RFx[V/I] peptide sequences from their upstream With No Lysine Kinases (WNKs), facilitating their activation via phosphorylation. Thus, the inhibition of SPAK and OSR1 binding, via their CCT domains, to WNK kinases is a plausible strategy for inhibiting SPAK and OSR1 kinases. To facilitate structure-guided drug design of such inhibitors, we expressed and purified human SPAK and OSR1 CCT domains and solved their crystal structures. We also employed a biophysical strategy and determined the affinity of SPAK and OSR1 CCT domains to an 18-mer peptide derived from WNK4. Together, the crystal structures and affinity data reported herein provide a robust platform to facilitate the design of CCT domain specific small molecule inhibitors of SPAK-activation by WNK kinases, potentially leading to new improved treatments for hypertension and ischemic stroke.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.456998" rel="alternate" title="Structures of the Human SPAK and OSR1 Conserved C-Terminal (CCT) Domains (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.456516</id><title>Spatial and temporal expression of PORCN is highly dynamic in the developing mouse cochlea. (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T07:11:17.489023+00:00</updated><author><name>Brianna L Oliver</name></author><author><name>Caryl A Young</name></author><author><name>Vidhya Munnamalai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mammalian organ of Corti is a highly specialized sensory organ of the cochlea with fine-grained pattern that is essential for auditory function. Previous studies show that the Wnt pathway regulates proliferation, promotes medial compartment formation in the cochlea, differentiation of the mechanosensory hair cells and axon guidance of Type II afferent neurons. WNT ligand expressions are highly dynamic throughout development but are insufficient to explain the roles of the Wnt pathway. We address a potential way for how WNTs specify the medial compartment by characterizing the expression of Porcupine (PORCN), an O-acyltransferase that palmitoylates WNT ligands for secretion. We show PORCN expression across embryonic ages (E)12.5 - E14.5, E16.5, and postnatal day (P)1.  Our results showed enriched PORCN in the medial domains during early stages of development, indicating that WNTs have a stronger influence on patterning of the medial compartment. PORCN was rapidly downregulated after E14.5, following the onset of sensory cell differentiation; residual expression remained in some hair cells and supporting cells. On E14.5 and E16.5, we also examined the spatial expression of Gsk3β, an inhibitor of canonical Wnt signaling to determine its potential role in radial patterning of the cochlea. Gsk3β was broadly expressed across the radial axis of the epithelium; therefore, unlikely to control WNT-mediated medial specification. In conclusion, the spatial expression of PORCN enriches WNT secretion from the medial domains of the cochlea to influence the specification of cell fates in the medial sensory domain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.456516" rel="alternate" title="Spatial and temporal expression of PORCN is highly dynamic in the developing mouse cochlea. (3 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>