<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.796970+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468024</id><title>Predicting efficiency of writing short sequences into the genome using prime editing (115 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.798005+00:00</updated><author><name>Jonas Koeppel</name></author><author><name>Elin Madli Peets</name></author><author><name>Juliane Weller</name></author><author><name>Ananth Pallaseni</name></author><author><name>Fabio Liberante</name></author><author><name>Leopold Parts</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Short sequences can be precisely written into a selected genomic target using prime editing. This ability facilitates protein tagging, correction of pathogenic deletions, and many other exciting applications. However, it remains unclear what types of sequences prime editors can easily insert, and how to choose optimal reagents for a desired outcome. To characterize features that influence insertion efficiency, we designed a library of 2,666 sequences up to 69 nt in length and measured the frequency of their insertion into four genomic sites in three human cell lines, using different prime editor systems. We discover that insertion sequence length, nucleotide composition and secondary structure all affect insertion rates, and that mismatch repair proficiency is a strong determinant for the shortest insertions. Combining the sequence and repair features into a machine learning model, we can predict insertion frequency for new sequences with R = 0.69. The tools we provide allow users to choose optimal constructs for DNA insertion using prime editing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468024" rel="alternate" title="Predicting efficiency of writing short sequences into the genome using prime editing (115 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468258</id><title>Multi-omic rejuvenation and lifespan extension upon exposure to youthful circulation (63 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.798308+00:00</updated><author><name>Bohan Zhang</name></author><author><name>David E Lee</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Trapp</name></author><author><name>Alexander Tyshkovskiy</name></author><author><name>Ake T Lu</name></author><author><name>Akshay Bareja</name></author><author><name>Csaba Kerepesi</name></author><author><name>Lauren H McKay</name></author><author><name>Anastasia V Shindyapina</name></author><author><name>Sergey E Dmitriev</name></author><author><name>Gurpreet S Baht</name></author><author><name>Steve Horvath</name></author><author><name>Vadim N Gladyshev</name></author><author><name>James P White</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Heterochronic parabiosis (HPB) is known for its functional rejuvenation effects across several mouse tissues. However, its impact on the biological age of organisms and their long-term health remains unknown. Here, we performed extended (3-month) HPB, followed by a 2-month detachment period of anastomosed pairs. Old detached mice exhibited improved physiological parameters and lived longer than control isochronic mice. HPB drastically reduced the biological age of blood and liver based on epigenetic analyses across several clock models on two independent platforms; remarkably, this rejuvenation effect persisted even after 2 months of detachment. Transcriptomic and epigenomic profiles of anastomosed mice showed an intermediate phenotype between old and young, suggesting a comprehensive multi-omic rejuvenation effect. In addition, old HPB mice showed transcriptome changes opposite to aging, but akin to several lifespan-extending interventions. Altogether, we reveal that long-term HPB can decrease the biological age of mice, in part through long-lasting epigenetic and transcriptome remodeling, culminating in the extension of lifespan and healthspan.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468258" rel="alternate" title="Multi-omic rejuvenation and lifespan extension upon exposure to youthful circulation (63 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468045</id><title>Reduced platelet forces underlie impaired hemostasis in mouse models of MYH9-related disease (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.798517+00:00</updated><author><name>Juliane Baumann</name></author><author><name>Laura Sachs</name></author><author><name>Otto Oliver</name></author><author><name>Ingmar Schoen</name></author><author><name>Peter Nestler</name></author><author><name>Carlo Zaninetti</name></author><author><name>Martin Kenny</name></author><author><name>Ruth Kranz</name></author><author><name>Hendrik von Eysmondt</name></author><author><name>Johanna Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Tilman E. Schäffer</name></author><author><name>Zoltan Nagy</name></author><author><name>Andreas Greinacher</name></author><author><name>Raghavendra Palankar</name></author><author><name>Markus Bender</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;MYH9-related&lt;/italic&gt; disease patients with mutations in the contractile protein non-muscle myosin heavy chain IIA display, among others, macrothrombocytopenia and a mild to moderate bleeding tendency. In this study, we used three mouse lines, each with one point mutation in the &lt;italic&gt;Myh9&lt;/italic&gt; gene at positions 702, 1424, or 1841, to investigate mechanisms underlying the increased bleeding risk. Agonist-induced activation of &lt;italic&gt;Myh9&lt;/italic&gt; mutant platelets was comparable to controls. However, myosin light chain phosphorylation after activation was reduced in mutant platelets, which displayed altered biophysical characteristics and generated lower adhesion, interaction, and traction forces. Treatment with tranexamic acid restored clot retraction and reduced bleeding. We verified our findings from the mutant mice with platelets from patients with the respective mutation. These data suggest that reduced platelet forces lead to an increased bleeding tendency in &lt;italic&gt;MYH9&lt;/italic&gt;-related disease patients, and treatment with tranexamic acid can improve the hemostatic function.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Teaser&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Impaired hemostasis in &lt;italic&gt;Myh9&lt;/italic&gt; mutant mice due to reduced platelet forces can be improved by tranexamic acid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468045" rel="alternate" title="Reduced platelet forces underlie impaired hemostasis in mouse models of MYH9-related disease (31 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467732</id><title>Lagging strand gap suppression connects BRCA-mediated fork protection to nucleosome assembly by ensuring PCNA-dependent CAF-1 recycling (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.798716+00:00</updated><author><name>Tanay Thakar</name></author><author><name>Joshua Straka</name></author><author><name>Claudia M. Nicolae</name></author><author><name>George-Lucian Moldovan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The inability to protect stalled replication forks from nucleolytic degradation drives genome instability and is associated with chemosensitivity in BRCA-deficient tumors. An emerging hallmark of BRCA deficiency is the inability to suppress replication-associated single-stranded DNA (ssDNA) gaps. Here, we report that ssDNA gaps on the lagging strand interfere with the ASF1-CAF-1 pathway of nucleosome assembly, and drive fork degradation in BRCA-deficient cells. We show that CAF-1 function at replication forks is lost in BRCA-deficient cells, due to its sequestration at inactive replication factories during replication stress. This CAF-1 recycling defect is caused by the accumulation of Polα-dependent lagging strand gaps, which preclude PCNA unloading, causing sequestration of PCNA-CAF-1 complexes on chromatin. Importantly, correcting PCNA unloading defects in BRCA-deficient cells restores fork stability in a CAF-1-dependent manner. We also show that the activation of a HIRA-dependent compensatory histone deposition pathway restores fork stability to BRCA-deficient cells upon CAF-1 loss. We thus define nucleosome assembly as a critical determinant of BRCA-mediated fork stability. We further reveal lagging strand ssDNA gaps as drivers of fork degradation in BRCA-deficient cells, which operate by inhibiting PCNA unloading and CAF-1-dependent nucleosome assembly.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467732" rel="alternate" title="Lagging strand gap suppression connects BRCA-mediated fork protection to nucleosome assembly by ensuring PCNA-dependent CAF-1 recycling (26 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467681</id><title>In vitro reconstitution of divisome activation (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.798847+00:00</updated><author><name>Philipp Radler</name></author><author><name>Natalia Baranova</name></author><author><name>Paulo Caldas</name></author><author><name>Christoph Sommer</name></author><author><name>Mar López-Pelegrín</name></author><author><name>David Michalik</name></author><author><name>Martin Loose</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial cell division is coordinated by the Z-ring, a cytoskeletal structure of treadmilling filaments of FtsZ and their membrane anchors, FtsA and ZipA. For divisome maturation and initiation of constriction, the widely conserved actin-homolog FtsA plays a central role, as it links downstream cell division proteins in the membrane to the Z-ring in the cytoplasm. According to the current model, FtsA initiates cell constriction by switching from an inactive polymeric conformation to an active monomeric form, which then stabilizes the Z-ring and recruits downstream proteins such as FtsN. However, direct biochemical evidence for this mechanism is missing so far. Here, we used biochemical reconstitution experiments in combination with quantitative fluorescence microscopy to study the mechanism of divisome activation &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. By comparing the properties of wildtype FtsA and FtsA R286W, a gain-of-function mutant thought to mimic its active state, we found that active FtsA outperforms the wildtype protein in replicating FtsZ treadmilling dynamics, filament stabilization and FtsN recruitment. We could attribute these differences to a faster membrane exchange of FtsA R286W as well as its higher packing density below FtsZ filaments. Using FRET microscopy, we also show that binding of FtsN does not compete with, but promotes FtsA self-interaction. Together, our findings shed new light on the assembly and activation of the bacterial cell division machinery and the mechanism of how FtsA initiates cell constriction.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467681" rel="alternate" title="In vitro reconstitution of divisome activation (26 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468392</id><title>Systematic assessment of lipid profiles for the discovery of tissue contributors to the circulating lipid pool in cold exposure (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.798993+00:00</updated><author><name>Raghav Jain</name></author><author><name>Gina Wade</name></author><author><name>Irene Ong</name></author><author><name>Bhagirath Chaurasia</name></author><author><name>Judith Simcox</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Plasma lipid levels are altered in chronic conditions such as type 2 diabetes and cardiovascular disease as well as acute stresses such as fasting and cold exposure. Advances in mass spectrometry based lipidomics have uncovered the complexity of the plasma lipidome which includes over 500 lipids that serve functional roles including energy substrate and signaling molecule. The plasma lipid pool is maintained through regulation of tissue production, secretion, and uptake. A major challenge is establishing the tissues of origin and uptake for various plasma lipids, which is necessary to determine the lipid function. Using cold exposure as an acute stress, we performed global lipidomics on the plasma and nine tissues that may contribute to the circulating pool. We found that numerous species of plasma acylcarnitines (ACars) and ceramides were significantly changed with cold exposure. Through computational assessment, we identified the liver and brown adipose tissue (BAT) as major contributors and consumers of circulating ACars, in agreement with our previous work. We further identified the kidney and intestine as novel contributors to the circulating ACar pool and validated these findings with gene expression analysis. Regression analysis also identified that the BAT and kidney as regulators of the plasma ceramide pool. These studies provide an adaptable computational tool to assess tissue contribution to the plasma lipid pool. Our findings have implications in understanding the function of plasma ACars and ceramides, which are elevated in metabolic diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468392" rel="alternate" title="Systematic assessment of lipid profiles for the discovery of tissue contributors to the circulating lipid pool in cold exposure (22 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467972</id><title>Coordinated conformational changes in the V1 complex during V-ATPase reversible dissociation (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.799125+00:00</updated><author><name>Thamiya Vasanthakumar</name></author><author><name>Kristine A. Keon</name></author><author><name>Stephanie A. Bueler</name></author><author><name>Michael C. Jaskolka</name></author><author><name>John L. Rubinstein</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Vacuolar-type ATPases (V-ATPases) are rotary enzymes that acidify intracellular compartments in eukaryotic cells. These multi-subunit complexes consist of a cytoplasmic V&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; region that hydrolyzes ATP and a membrane-embedded V&lt;sub&gt;O&lt;/sub&gt; region that transports protons. V-ATPase activity is regulated by reversible dissociation of the two regions, with the isolated V&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; and V&lt;sub&gt;O&lt;/sub&gt; complexes becoming autoinhibited upon disassembly and subunit C subsequently detaching from V&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;. In yeast, assembly of the V&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; and V&lt;sub&gt;O&lt;/sub&gt; regions is mediated by the RAVE complex through an unknown mechanism. We used cryoEM of yeast V-ATPase to determine structures of the intact enzyme, the dissociated but complete V&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; complex, and the V&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; complex lacking subunit C. Upon separation, V&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; undergoes a dramatic conformational rearrangement, with its rotational state becoming incompatible for reassembly with V&lt;sub&gt;O&lt;/sub&gt;. Loss of subunit C allows V&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; to match the rotational state of V&lt;sub&gt;O&lt;/sub&gt;, suggesting how RAVE could reassemble V&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; and V&lt;sub&gt;O&lt;/sub&gt; by recruiting subunit C.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467972" rel="alternate" title="Coordinated conformational changes in the V1 complex during V-ATPase reversible dissociation (19 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467992</id><title>Quantitative analysis of transcription start site selection in Saccharomyces cerevisiae determines contributions of DNA sequence and RNA Polymerase II activity (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.799257+00:00</updated><author><name>Yunye Zhu</name></author><author><name>Irina O. Vvedenskaya</name></author><author><name>Bryce E. Nickels</name></author><author><name>Craig D. Kaplan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;DNA sequence at Transcription Start Sites (TSSs) is a key determinant of initiation by RNA Polymerase II (Pol II). To function as a TSS, an initiation compatible sequence must be specified by a promoter in an appropriate chromatin context. We report the development of a method for quantitative analysis of transcription initiation by Pol II that involves construction of DNA libraries of barcoded promoter variants, production of RNA transcripts, and analysis of transcript 5’ ends and transcript yields (Pol II MAssively Systematic Transcript End Readout, “Pol II MASTER”). Using Pol II MASTER, we measure the efficiency of transcription initiation during “promoter scanning” by &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; Pol II for ~1 million unique TSS sequences. Furthermore, we employ Pol II MASTER to determine how Pol II activity, known to widely alter TSS selection &lt;italic&gt;in vivo,&lt;/italic&gt; alters TSS efficiencies across our promoter variants. Pol II MASTER recapitulates known critical qualities of &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; TSS −8, −1, and +1 positions while demonstrating that surrounding sequences modulate initiation efficiency over a wide range. We discover functional interactions between neighboring sequence positions, indicating that adjacent positions likely function together. We demonstrate that initiation efficiencies are altered for +1 A TSSs relative to +1 G TSSs when Pol II activity is perturbed through genetic means. Pol II MASTER provides data for predictive models of TSS initiation efficiency at genomic promoters.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467992" rel="alternate" title="Quantitative analysis of transcription start site selection in Saccharomyces cerevisiae determines contributions of DNA sequence and RNA Polymerase II activity (18 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468081</id><title>Sonic hedgehog is basolaterally sorted from the TGN and transcytosed to the apical domain involving Dispatched-1 at Rab11-ARE (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.799382+00:00</updated><author><name>Lisette Sandoval</name></author><author><name>Mariana Labarca</name></author><author><name>Claudio Retamal</name></author><author><name>Juan Larraín</name></author><author><name>Alfonso González</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hedgehog (Hh) secretion from apical and/or basolateral domains occurs in different epithelial cells impacting development and tissue homeostasis. Palmitoylation and cholestyrolation attach Hh proteins to membranes and Dispatched-1 (Disp-1) promotes their release. How these lipidated proteins are handled by the complex secretory and endocytic pathways of polarized epithelial cells remains unknown. We show that MDCK cells address newly synthesized sonic hedgehog (Shh) from the TGN to the basolateral cell surface and then to the apical domain through a transcytosis pathway that includes Rab11-apical recycling endosomes (Rab11-ARE). Both palmitoylation and cholestyrolation contribute to this sorting behavior, otherwise Shh lacking these lipid modifications is unpolarized. Disp-1 mediates first basolateral secretion from the TGN and then transcytosis from the Rab11-ARE. At steady state, Shh predominates apically and can be basolaterally transcytosed. This complex Shh trafficking provides several steps for regulation and variation in different epithelia, subordinating the apical to the basolateral secretion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468081" rel="alternate" title="Sonic hedgehog is basolaterally sorted from the TGN and transcytosed to the apical domain involving Dispatched-1 at Rab11-ARE (18 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468440</id><title>A novel mechanism of bulk cytoplasmic transport by cortical dynein in Drosophila ovary (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.799515+00:00</updated><author><name>Wen Lu</name></author><author><name>Margot Lakonishok</name></author><author><name>Anna S. Serpinskaya</name></author><author><name>Vladimir I Gelfand</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cytoplasmic dynein, a major minus-end directed microtubule motor, plays essential roles in eukaryotic cells. Drosophila oocyte growth is mainly dependent on the contribution of cytoplasmic contents from the interconnected sister cells, nurse cells. We have previously shown that cytoplasmic dynein is required for Drosophila oocyte growth, and assumed that it transports cargoes along microtubule tracks from nurse cells to the oocyte. Here we report that instead transporting cargoes along microtubules into the oocyte, cortical dynein actively moves microtubules in nurse cells and from nurse cells to the oocyte via the cytoplasmic bridges, the ring canals. We demonstrate this microtubule movement is sufficient to drag even inert cytoplasmic particles through the ring canals to the oocyte. Furthermore, replacing dynein with a minus-end directed plant kinesin linked to the actin cortex is sufficient for transporting organelles and cytoplasm to the oocyte and driving its growth. These experiments show that cortical dynein can perform bulk cytoplasmic transport by gliding microtubules along the cell cortex and through the ring canals to the oocyte. We propose that the dynein-driven microtubule flow could serve as a novel mode of cargo transport for fast cytoplasmic transfer to support rapid oocyte growth.  &lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468440" rel="alternate" title="A novel mechanism of bulk cytoplasmic transport by cortical dynein in Drosophila ovary (17 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467897</id><title>Sequestration of LINE-1 in novel cytosolic bodies by MOV10 restricts retrotransposition (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.799639+00:00</updated><author><name>Rajika Arora</name></author><author><name>Maxime Bodak</name></author><author><name>Laura Penouty</name></author><author><name>Cindy Hackman</name></author><author><name>Constance Ciaudo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;LINE-1 (L1) are autonomous retroelements that have retained their ability to mobilize. Mechanisms regulating L1 mobility include DNA methylation in somatic cells and the Piwi-interacting RNA pathway in the germline. During pre-implantation stages of mouse embryonic development, however, both pathways are inactivated leading to a critical window necessitating alternate means of L1 regulation. We previously reported an increase in L1 levels in &lt;italic&gt;Dicer_&lt;/italic&gt;KO mouse embryonic stem cells (mESCs). Intriguingly this was accompanied by only a marginal increase in retrotransposition, suggestive of additional mechanisms suppressing L1 mobility. Here, we demonstrate that L1 Ribonucleoprotein complexes (L1 RNP) accumulate as aggregates in &lt;italic&gt;Dicer_&lt;/italic&gt;KO cytoplasm along with the RNA helicase MOV10. The combined overexpression of L1 RNAs and MOV10 is sufficient to create L1 RNP aggregates in stem cells. In &lt;italic&gt;Dicer&lt;/italic&gt;_KO mESCs, MOV10 is upregulated due to the loss of its direct regulation by miRNAs. The newly discovered post-transcriptional regulation of &lt;italic&gt;Mov10&lt;/italic&gt; expression, and its role in preventing L1 retrotransposition by driving novel cytosolic aggregation affords alternate routes to explore for therapy and disease progression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467897" rel="alternate" title="Sequestration of LINE-1 in novel cytosolic bodies by MOV10 restricts retrotransposition (17 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467622</id><title>Interchromosomal interaction of homologous Stat92E alleles regulates transcriptional switch during stem-cell differentiation (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.799769+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Antel</name></author><author><name>Madona Masoud</name></author><author><name>Romir Raj</name></author><author><name>Ziwei Pan</name></author><author><name>Sheng Li</name></author><author><name>Barbara G. Mellone</name></author><author><name>Mayu Inaba</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The strength of pairing of homologous chromosomes differs in a locus-specific manner and is correlated to gene expression states. However, the functional impact of homolog pairing on local transcriptional activity is still unclear. &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; male germline stem cells (GSCs) constantly divide asymmetrically to produce one GSC and one differentiating gonialblast (GB). The GB then enters the differentiation program in which stem cell specific genes are quickly downregulated. Here we demonstrate that a change in local pairing state of the Stat92E locus is required for the downregulation of the Stat92E gene during differentiation. Using OligoPaint fluorescent in situ hybridization (FISH), we show that the interaction between homologous regions of Stat92E is always tight in GSCs and immediately loosened in GBs. When one of the Stat92E locus was absent or relocated to another chromosome, Stat92E did not pair and failed to downregulate, suggesting that the pairing is required for switching of transcriptional activity. The defect in downregulation of Stat92E was also observed upon knockdown of global pairing or anti-pairing factors. Moreover, the Stat92E enhancer element, but not cis-transcription, is required for the change in pairing state, indicating that it is not a consequence of transcriptional changes. GSCs are known to inherit pre-existing histones H3 and H4, while newly synthesized histones are distributed in GBs. When this histone inheritance was compromised, the change in Stat92E pairing did not occur, suggesting that it is an intrinsically programmed process during asymmetric stem cell division. We propose that the change of local pairing state may be a common process to reprogram gene activity during cell-differentiation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467622" rel="alternate" title="Interchromosomal interaction of homologous Stat92E alleles regulates transcriptional switch during stem-cell differentiation (16 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468448</id><title>A Multi-Omics and Bioenergetics Longitudinal Aging Dataset in Primary Human Fibroblasts with Mitochondrial Perturbations (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.799910+00:00</updated><author><name>Gabriel Sturm</name></author><author><name>Anna S Monzel</name></author><author><name>Kalpita R Karan</name></author><author><name>Jeremy Michelson</name></author><author><name>Sarah A Ware</name></author><author><name>Andres Cardenas</name></author><author><name>Jue Lin</name></author><author><name>Celine Bris</name></author><author><name>Balaji Santhanam</name></author><author><name>Michael P Murphy</name></author><author><name>Morgan E Levine</name></author><author><name>Steve Horvath</name></author><author><name>Daniel W Belsky</name></author><author><name>Shuang Wang</name></author><author><name>Vincent Procaccio</name></author><author><name>Brett A Kaufman</name></author><author><name>Michio Hirano</name></author><author><name>Martin Picard</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aging is a process of progressive change. In order to develop biological models of aging, longitudinal datasets with high temporal resolution are needed. Here we report a multi-omic longitudinal dataset for cultured primary human fibroblasts measured across their replicative lifespans. Based on the accelerated nature of epigenetic aging in vitro, these longitudinal data are equivalent to ~40 years of follow-up sampling at a frequency of every ~3 years. Fibroblasts were sourced from both healthy donors (n=6) and individuals with lifespan-shortening mitochondrial disease (n=3). The dataset includes cytological (cell size, morphology), bioenergetic (energy expenditure, derived ATP synthesis rates), epigenetic (DNA methylation), gene expression (RNA sequencing), secreted proteins, mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) copy number and mutations, cell-free DNA, telomere length, and whole-genome sequencing data. This dataset enables the bridging of mechanistic processes of aging as outlined by the "hallmarks of aging", with the descriptive characterization of aging provided by epigenetic clocks and other metrics. Here we focus on bridging the gap for the hallmark mitochondrial metabolism. Our dataset includes measurement of healthy cells replicating through senescence without intervention, as well as cells subjected to over a dozen experimental manipulations targeting oxidative phosphorylation (OxPhos), glycolysis, and glucocorticoid signaling, among others. These experiments provide opportunities to test how cellular energetics affect the biology of cellular aging. All data are publicly available at our webtool: https://columbia-picard.shinyapps.io/shinyapp-Lifespan_Study/&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468448" rel="alternate" title="A Multi-Omics and Bioenergetics Longitudinal Aging Dataset in Primary Human Fibroblasts with Mitochondrial Perturbations (14 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468347</id><title>Three-dimensional structure of the kinetochore-fibers in human mitotic spindles (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.800401+00:00</updated><author><name>Robert Kiewisz</name></author><author><name>Gunar Fabig</name></author><author><name>William Conway</name></author><author><name>Daniel Needleman</name></author><author><name>Thomas Muller-Reichert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During cell division, kinetochore microtubules (KMTs) provide a physical linkage between the spindle poles and the chromosomes. KMTs in mammalian cells are organized into bundles, so-called kinetochore-fibers (k-fibers), but the ultrastructure of these fibers is currently not well characterized. Here we show by large-scale electron tomography that each k-fiber in HeLa cells in metaphase is composed of approximately nine KMTs, only half of which reach the spindle pole. Our comprehensive reconstructions allowed us to analyze the three-dimensional (3D) morphology of k-fibers in detail, and we find that they exhibit remarkable variation. K-fibers display differences in circumference and KMT density along their length, with the pole-facing side showing a splayed-out appearance. We further observed that the association of KMTs with non-KMTs predominantly occurs in the spindle pole regions. Our 3D reconstructions have implications for models of KMT behavior and k-fiber self-organization as covered in a parallel publication applying complementary live-cell imaging in combination with biophysical modeling (Conway et al., 2021). The presented data will also serve as a resource for further studies on mitosis in human cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468347" rel="alternate" title="Three-dimensional structure of the kinetochore-fibers in human mitotic spindles (13 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.465336</id><title>The Immune Signatures Data Resource: A compendium of systems vaccinology datasets (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.800545+00:00</updated><author><name>Joann Diray-Arce</name></author><author><name>Helen E.R. Miller</name></author><author><name>Evan Henrich</name></author><author><name>Bram Gerritsen</name></author><author><name>Matthew P. Mulè</name></author><author><name>Slim Fourati</name></author><author><name>Jeremy Gygi</name></author><author><name>Thomas Hagan</name></author><author><name>Lewis Tomalin</name></author><author><name>Dmitry Rychkov</name></author><author><name>Dmitri Kazmin</name></author><author><name>Daniel G. Chawla</name></author><author><name>Hailong Meng</name></author><author><name>Patrick Dunn</name></author><author><name>John Campbell</name></author><author><name>Minnie Sarwal</name></author><author><name>John S. Tsang</name></author><author><name>Ofer Levy</name></author><author><name>Bali Pulendran</name></author><author><name>Rafick Sekaly</name></author><author><name>Aris Floratos</name></author><author><name>Raphael Gottardo</name></author><author><name>Steven H. Kleinstein</name></author><author><name>Mayte Suárez-Fariñas</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Vaccines are among the most cost-effective public health interventions for preventing infection-induced morbidity and mortality, yet much remains to be learned regarding the mechanisms by which vaccines protect. Systems immunology combines traditional immunology with modern ‘omic profiling techniques and computational modeling to promote rapid and transformative advances in vaccinology and vaccine discovery. The NIH/NIAID Human Immunology Project Consortium (HIPC) has leveraged systems immunology approaches to identify molecular signatures associated with the immunogenicity of many vaccines, including those targeting seasonal influenza, yellow fever, and hepatitis B. These data are made available to the broader scientific community through the &lt;italic&gt;ImmuneSpace&lt;/italic&gt; data portal and analysis engine leveraging the NIH/NIAID &lt;italic&gt;ImmPort&lt;/italic&gt; repository&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt;. However, a barrier to progress in this area is that comparative analyses have been limited by the distributed nature of some data, potential batch effects across studies, and the absence of multiple relevant studies from non-HIPC groups in &lt;italic&gt;ImmPort.&lt;/italic&gt; To support comparative analyses across different vaccines, we have created the Immune Signatures Data Resource, a compendium of standardized systems vaccinology datasets. This data resource is available through &lt;italic&gt;ImmuneSpace&lt;/italic&gt;, along with code to reproduce the processing and batch normalization starting from the underlying study data in &lt;italic&gt;ImmPort&lt;/italic&gt; and the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO). The current release comprises 1405 participants from 53 cohorts profiling the response to 24 different vaccines and includes transcriptional profiles and antibody response measurements. This novel systems vaccinology data release represents a valuable resource for comparative and meta-analyses that will accelerate our understanding of mechanisms underlying vaccine responses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;table-wrap orientation="portrait" position="anchor"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="465336v1_utbl1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/table-wrap&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.465336" rel="alternate" title="The Immune Signatures Data Resource: A compendium of systems vaccinology datasets (11 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467706</id><title>ICOR: Improving codon optimization with recurrent neural networks (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.801058+00:00</updated><author><name>Rishab Jain</name></author><author><name>Aditya Jain</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Mauro</name></author><author><name>Kevin LeShane</name></author><author><name>Douglas Densmore</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In protein sequences—as there are 61 sense codons but only 20 standard amino acids—most amino acids are encoded by more than one codon. Although such synonymous codons do not alter the encoded amino acid sequence, their selection can dramatically affect the expression of the resulting protein. Codon optimization of synthetic DNA sequences is important for heterologous expression. However, existing solutions are primarily based on choosing high-frequency codons only, neglecting the important effects of rare codons. In this paper, we propose a novel recurrent-neural-network based codon optimization tool, ICOR, that aims to learn codon usage bias on a genomic dataset of &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt;. We compile a dataset of over 7,000 non-redundant, high-expression, robust genes which are used for deep learning. The model uses a bidirectional long short-term memory-based architecture, allowing for the sequential context of codon usage in genes to be learned. Our tool can predict synonymous codons for synthetic genes toward optimal expression in &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt;. We demonstrate that sequential context achieved via RNN may yield codon selection that is more similar to the host genome, therefore improving protein expression more than frequency-based approaches. ICOR is evaluated on 1,481 &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; genes as well as a benchmark set of 40 select DNA sequences whose heterologous expression has been previously characterized. ICOR’s performance across five metrics is compared to that of five different codon optimization techniques. The codon adaptation index -- a metric indicative of high real-world expression -- was utilized as the primary benchmark in this study. ICOR is shown to improve the codon adaptation index by 41.69% and 17.25% compared to the original and Genscript’s GenSmart-optimized sequences, respectively. Our tool is provided as an open-source software package that includes the benchmark set of sequences used in this study.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467706" rel="alternate" title="ICOR: Improving codon optimization with recurrent neural networks (10 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468234</id><title>Scaling between DNA and cell size governs bacterial growth homeostasis and resource allocation (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.801218+00:00</updated><author><name>Boyan Li</name></author><author><name>Songyuan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Le Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xiaoying Qiao</name></author><author><name>Yiqiang Shi</name></author><author><name>Cheng Li</name></author><author><name>Qi Ouyang</name></author><author><name>Ping Wei</name></author><author><name>Long Qian</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacteria maintain a stable cell size and a certain DNA content through proliferation as described by classic growth laws. How cells behave when this inherent scaling is broken, however, has rarely been interrogated. Here we engineered Escherichia coli cells with extremely low DNA contents using a tunable synthetic tool CRISPRori that temporarily inhibited chromosome replication initiation. A detailed mechanistic model coupling DNA replication, cell growth, and division revealed a fundamental DNA-centric growth law, which was validated by two observations. First, lineage dynamics were robust to large CRISPRori perturbations with division cycles rapidly restoring through a timer mechanism rather than the adder rule. Second, cellular growth transitioned into a linear regime at low DNA-cytoplasm ratios. Experiments and theory showed that in this regime, cellular resource was redirected to plasmid-borne gene expression. Together with the ability of CRISPRori to bi-directionally modulate plasmid copy numbers, these findings suggest a novel strategy for bio-production enhancement.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468234" rel="alternate" title="Scaling between DNA and cell size governs bacterial growth homeostasis and resource allocation (10 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467962</id><title>Pentameric assembly of the Kv2.1 tetramerization domain (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.801380+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhen Xu</name></author><author><name>Saif Khan</name></author><author><name>Nicholas J. Schnicker</name></author><author><name>Sheila A. Baker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Kv family of voltage-gated potassium channels regulate neuronal excitability. The biophysical characteristic of Kv channels can be matched to the needs of different neurons by forming homotetrameric or heterotetrameric channels within one of four subfamilies. The cytoplasmic tetramerization (T1) domain plays a major role in dictating the compatibility of different Kv subunits. The only Kv subfamily missing a representative structure of the T1 domain is the Kv2 family. We used X-ray crystallography to solve the structure of the human Kv2.1 T1 domain. The structure is similar to other T1 domains but surprisingly formed a pentamer instead of a tetramer. In solution the Kv2.1 T1 domain also formed a pentamer as determined with in-line SEC-MALS-SAXS and negative stain EM. The Kv2.1 T1-T1 interface involves electrostatic interactions including a salt bridge formed by the negative charges in a previously described CDD motif, and inter-subunit coordination of zinc. We show that zinc binding is important for stability. In conclusion, the Kv2.1 T1 domain behaves differently from the other Kv T1 domains which may reflect the versatility of Kv2.1, the only Kv subfamily that can assemble with the regulatory KvS subunits and scaffold ER-plasma membrane contacts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467962" rel="alternate" title="Pentameric assembly of the Kv2.1 tetramerization domain (8 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467832</id><title>Structure-Activity Relationships in the Design of Mitochondria-Targeted Peptide Therapeutics (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.801510+00:00</updated><author><name>Wayne Mitchell</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey D. Tamucci</name></author><author><name>Emery L. Ng</name></author><author><name>Shaoyi Liu</name></author><author><name>Hazel H. Szeto</name></author><author><name>Eric R. May</name></author><author><name>Andrei T. Alexandrescu</name></author><author><name>Nathan N. Alder</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mitochondria play a central role in metabolic homeostasis; hence, dysfunction of this organelle underpins the etiology of many heritable and aging-related diseases. Mitochondria-targeted tetrapeptides with alternating cationic and aromatic residues, such as SS-31 (Elamipretide), show promise as therapeutic compounds. In this study, we conducted a quantitative structure-activity analysis of three alternative tetrapeptide analogs that differed with respect to aromatic side chain composition and sequence register, benchmarked against SS-31. Using NMR and molecular dynamics approaches, we obtained the first structural models for this class of compounds, showing that all analogs except for SS-31 form compact reverse turn conformations in the membrane-bound state. All peptide analogs bound cardiolipin-containing membranes, yet they had significant differences in equilibrium binding behavior and membrane interactions. Notably, the analogs had markedly different effects on membrane surface charge, supporting a mechanism in which modulation of membrane electrostatics is a key feature of their mechanism of action. All peptide analogs preserved survival and energy metabolism more effectively than SS-31 in cell stress models. Within our peptide set, the analog containing tryptophan side chains, SPN10, had the strongest impact on most membrane properties and showed greatest efficacy in cell culture studies. Taken together, these results show that side chain composition and register strongly influence the activity of these mitochondria-targeted peptides. Furthermore, this work helps provide a framework for the rational design of next-generation therapeutics with enhanced potency.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467832" rel="alternate" title="Structure-Activity Relationships in the Design of Mitochondria-Targeted Peptide Therapeutics (8 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467823</id><title>PccGEO: prior constraints conditioned genetic elements optimization (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.801659+00:00</updated><author><name>Hanwen Xu</name></author><author><name>Pengcheng Zhang</name></author><author><name>Haochen Wang</name></author><author><name>Lei Wei</name></author><author><name>Zhirui Hu</name></author><author><name>Xiaowo Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Functional genetic elements are one of the most essential units for synthetic biology. However, both knowledge-driven and data-driven methodology can hardly accomplish the complicated task of genetic elements design efficiently due to the lack of explicit regulatory logics and training samples. Here, we proposed a knowledge-constraint deep learning model named PccGEO to automatically design functional genetic elements with high success rate and efficiency. PccGEO utilized a novel “fill-in-the-flank” strategy with a conditional generative adversarial network structure to optimize the flanking regions of known functional sequences derived from the biological prior knowledge, which can efficiently capture the implicit patterns with a reduced searching space. We applied PccGEO in the design of &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; promoters, and found that the implicit patterns in flanking regions matter to the properties of promoters such as the expression level. The PccGEO-designed constitutive and inducible promoters showed more than 91.6% chance of success by in vivo validation. We further utilized PccGEO by setting a limited frequency of nucleotide modifications and surprisingly found that the expression level of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; sigma 70 promoters could show up to a 159.3-fold increase with only 10-bp nucleotide modifications. The results supported that the implicit patterns are important in the design of functional gene elements and validated the strong capacity of our method in the efficient design of functional genetic elements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/WangLabTHU/PccGEO"&gt;https://github.com/WangLabTHU/PccGEO&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467823" rel="alternate" title="PccGEO: prior constraints conditioned genetic elements optimization (8 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467859</id><title>2-Guanidino-quinazoline promotes the readthrough of nonsense mutations underlying human genetic diseases (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.801798+00:00</updated><author><name>Laure Bidou</name></author><author><name>Olivier Bugaud</name></author><author><name>Goulven Merer</name></author><author><name>Matthieu Coupet</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Hatin</name></author><author><name>Egor Chirkin</name></author><author><name>Pauline François</name></author><author><name>Jean-Christophe Cintrat</name></author><author><name>Olivier Namy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Premature termination codons (PTCs) account for 10% to 20% of genetic diseases in humans. The gene inactivation resulting from PTC can be counteracted by the use of drugs stimulating PTC readthrough, thereby restoring production of the full-length protein. However, a greater chemical variety of readthrough inducers is required to broaden the medical applications of this therapeutic strategy. In this study, we developed a new reporter cell line and performed high-throughput screening (HTS) to identify potential new readthrough inducers. After three successive assays, we isolated 2-guanidino-quinazoline (TLN468). We assessed the clinical potential of this drug as a potent readthrough inducer on the 40 PTCs most frequently responsible for Duchenne muscular dystrophy. We found that TLN468 was more efficient than gentamicin, and acted on a broader range of sequences, without inducing the readthrough of natural stop codons.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467859" rel="alternate" title="2-Guanidino-quinazoline promotes the readthrough of nonsense mutations underlying human genetic diseases (7 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467934</id><title>Data independent acquisition enables deep and fast label-free dynamic organellar mapping (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.801955+00:00</updated><author><name>Julia P. Schessner</name></author><author><name>Vincent Albrecht</name></author><author><name>Alexandra K. Davies</name></author><author><name>Pavel Sinitcyn</name></author><author><name>Georg H.H. Borner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The membrane compartments of eukaryotic cells organize the proteome into dynamic reaction spaces that control protein activity. This ‘spatial proteome’ and its changes can be captured systematically by our previously established Dynamic Organellar Maps (DOMs) approach, which combines cell fractionation and shotgun-proteomics into a profiling analysis of subcellular localization. Our original method relied on data dependent acquisition (DDA), which is inherently stochastic, and thus offers limited depth of analysis across replicates. Here we adapt DOMs to data independent acquisition (DIA), in a label-free format, and establish an automated data quality control tool to benchmark performance. Matched for mass spectrometry (MS) runtime, DIA-DOMs provide double the depth relative to DDA-DOMs, with substantially improved precision and localization prediction performance. Matched for depth, DIA-DOMs provide organellar maps in a third of the runtime. To test the DIA-DOMs performance for comparative applications, we mapped subcellular localization changes in response to starvation/disruption of lysosomal pH in HeLa cells, revealing a subset of Golgi proteins that cycle through endosomes. DIA-DOMs offer a superior workflow for label-free spatial proteomics, with a broad application spectrum in cell and biomedical research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467934" rel="alternate" title="Data independent acquisition enables deep and fast label-free dynamic organellar mapping (7 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467803</id><title>XomicsToModel: Multiomics data integration and generation of thermodynamically consistent metabolic models (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.802086+00:00</updated><author><name>German Preciat</name></author><author><name>Agnieszka B. Wegrzyn</name></author><author><name>Ines Thiele</name></author><author><name>Thomas Hankemeier</name></author><author><name>Ronan M.T. Fleming</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Constraint-based modelling can mechanistically simulate the behaviour of a biochemical system, permitting hypotheses generation, experimental design and interpretation of experimental data, with numerous applications, including modelling of metabolism. Given a generic model, several methods have been developed to extract a context-specific, genome-scale metabolic model by incorporating information used to identify metabolic processes and gene activities in a given context. However, existing model extraction algorithms are unable to ensure that the context-specific model is thermodynamically feasible. This protocol introduces &lt;monospace&gt;XomicsToModel&lt;/monospace&gt;, a semi-automated pipeline that integrates bibliomic, transcriptomic, proteomic, and metabolomic data with a generic genome-scale metabolic reconstruction, or model, to extract a context-specific, genome-scale metabolic model that is stoichiometrically, thermodynamically and flux consistent. The &lt;monospace&gt;XomicsToModel&lt;/monospace&gt; pipeline is exemplified for extraction of a specific metabolic model from a generic metabolic model, but it enables multi-omic data integration and extraction of physicochemically consistent mechanistic models from any generic biochemical network. With all input data fully prepared, algorithmic completion of the pipeline takes ~10 min, however manual review of intermediate results may also be required, e.g., when inconsistent input data lead to an infeasible model.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467803" rel="alternate" title="XomicsToModel: Multiomics data integration and generation of thermodynamically consistent metabolic models (6 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467882</id><title>Accurate inference of stochastic gene expression from nascent transcript heterogeneity (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.802216+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaoming Fu</name></author><author><name>Heta P. Patel</name></author><author><name>Stefano Coppola</name></author><author><name>Libin Xu</name></author><author><name>Zhixing Cao</name></author><author><name>Tineke L. Lenstra</name></author><author><name>Ramon Grima</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Transcriptional rates are often estimated by fitting the distribution of mature mRNA numbers measured using smFISH (single molecule fluorescence &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; hybridization) with the distribution predicted by the telegraph model of gene expression, which defines two promoter states of activity and inactivity. However, fluctuations in mature mRNA numbers are strongly affected by processes downstream of transcription. In addition, the telegraph model assumes one gene copy, but in experiments cells may have two gene copies as cells replicate their genome during the cell cycle. It is thus unclear how accurately the inferred parameters reflect transcription. To address these issues, here we measure both mature and nascent mRNA distributions of &lt;italic&gt;GAL10&lt;/italic&gt; in yeast cells using smFISH and classify each cell according to its cell cycle stage. We infer transcriptional parameters from mature and nascent mRNA distributions, with and without accounting for cell cycle stage and compare the results to live-cell transcription measurements of the same gene. We conclude that: (i) not accounting for cell cycle dynamics in nascent mRNA data overestimates the magnitude of promoter switching rates and the initiation rate, and underestimates the fraction of time spent in the active state and the burst size. (ii) use of mature mRNA data, instead of nascent data, significantly increases the errors in parameter estimation and can mistakenly classify a gene as non-bursting. Furthermore, we show how to correctly adjust for measurement noise in sm-FISH at low nascent transcript numbers. Simulations with parameters estimated from nascent smFISH data corrected for cell cycle phases and measurement noise leads to autocorrelation functions that agree with those obtained from live-cell imaging. Therefore, our novel data curation method yields a quantitatively accurate picture of gene expression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467882" rel="alternate" title="Accurate inference of stochastic gene expression from nascent transcript heterogeneity (6 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467757</id><title>Ribosomal ubiquitination facilitates mRNA cleavage and ribosome rescue during No-Go and Nonstop mRNA Decay (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.802780+00:00</updated><author><name>Parissa C. Monem</name></author><author><name>Audrey L. Piatt</name></author><author><name>Nitin Vidyasagar</name></author><author><name>Marissa L. Glover</name></author><author><name>Thea A. Egelhofer</name></author><author><name>Joshua A. Arribere</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During translational surveillance, ribosomes play a critical role in detecting problematic mRNAs and signaling cellular machinery to repress the offending messages. Prior work has shown that problematic mRNAs identified by two surveillance pathways (Nonstop and No-Go mRNA Decay) are detected by ribosome collisions and subsequent ribosomal ubiquitination, yet how ribosomal ubiquitination leads to repression has remained unclear. Here, we deploy &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; to unravel the series of coordinated events during Nonstop and No-Go mRNA Decay. We probe the metazoan SKI RNA helicase complex to uncover functionally significant residues and reveal divergence of the SKI-exosome interface. We define a functional requirement for ubiquitination on at least two ribosomal proteins during No-Go mRNA Decay, and illustrate how ubiquitination recruits the endonuclease NONU-1 via CUE domains and the ribosome rescue factor HBS-1 via its poorly characterized N-terminus. Our molecular characterization (1) underscores the importance of ribosomal ubiquitination in mRNA degradation, (2) shows similar and distinct genetic dependencies of factors in Nonstop and No-Go mRNA Decay, and (3) uncovers a conspicuous absence of distinct ribosomal stalls at No-Go mRNA Decay substrates. Our work demonstrates mechanisms by which translation signals to effectors of co-translational mRNA repression and has implications for the study of translation and ribosomal species &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467757" rel="alternate" title="Ribosomal ubiquitination facilitates mRNA cleavage and ribosome rescue during No-Go and Nonstop mRNA Decay (5 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467863</id><title>Assessing and enhancing foldability in designed proteins (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.803035+00:00</updated><author><name>Dina Listov</name></author><author><name>Rosalie Lipsh-Sokolik</name></author><author><name>Che Yang</name></author><author><name>Bruno E Correia</name></author><author><name>Sarel J Fleishman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent advances in protein-design methodology have led to a dramatic increase in its reliability and scale. With these advances, dozens and even thousands of designed proteins are automatically generated and screened. Nevertheless, the success rate, particularly in design of functional proteins, is low and fundamental goals such as reliable &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; design of efficient enzymes remain beyond reach. Experimental analyses have consistently indicated that a major cause of design failure is inaccuracy and misfolding relative to the design model. To address this challenge, we describe complementary methods to diagnose and ameliorate suboptimal regions in designed proteins: first, we develop a Rosetta atomistic computational mutation scanning approach to detect energetically suboptimal positions in designs; second, we demonstrate that the AlphaFold2 &lt;italic&gt;ab initio&lt;/italic&gt; structure prediction method flags regions that may misfold in designed enzymes and binders; and third, we focus FuncLib design calculations on suboptimal positions in a previously designed low-efficiency enzyme, thereby improving its catalytic efficiency by 330 fold. Thus, foldability analysis and enhancement may dramatically increase the success rate in design of functional proteins.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467863" rel="alternate" title="Assessing and enhancing foldability in designed proteins (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467755</id><title>High Throughput Intact Protein Analysis Using Infrared Matrix-Assisted Laser Desorption Electrospray Ionization Mass Spectrometry (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.807050+00:00</updated><author><name>Fan Pu</name></author><author><name>Scott Ugrin</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Radosevich</name></author><author><name>David Chang-Yen</name></author><author><name>James W. Sawicki</name></author><author><name>Nari N. Talaty</name></author><author><name>Nathaniel L. Elsen</name></author><author><name>Jon D. Williams</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mass spectrometry (MS) is the primary analytical tool used to characterize proteins within the biopharmaceutical industry. Electrospray ionization (ESI) coupled to liquid chromatography is the gold standard technique for intact protein analysis. However, speed limitations prevent analysis of large sample numbers (&amp;gt;1000) in a day. Infrared matrix-assisted laser desorption electrospray ionization (IR-MALDESI) MS, an ambient ionization MS technology, has recently been established as a platform for high throughput small molecule analysis. Here we report the application of such system for intact protein analysis. Up to 150 kDa proteins are detectable on a high throughput IR-MALDESI-MS system and we have evaluated how matrix affects signal. The system can analyze up to 22 protein samples in a second. Protein autophosphorylation, compound binding kinetics and compound modifications to a probe protein are demonstrated as applications. Top-down protein sequencing was conducted to identify a cysteine modification site. Two plate-based high throughput sample cleanup methods were coupled to IR-MALDESI-MS to enable analysis of samples containing high amounts of salts and buffers without compromising speed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="467755v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467755" rel="alternate" title="High Throughput Intact Protein Analysis Using Infrared Matrix-Assisted Laser Desorption Electrospray Ionization Mass Spectrometry (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.466986</id><title>Attractor Landscapes as a Model Selection Criterion in Data Poor Environments (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.807226+00:00</updated><author><name>Cole A. Lyman</name></author><author><name>Spencer Richman</name></author><author><name>Matthew C. Morris</name></author><author><name>Hongbao Cao</name></author><author><name>Antony Scerri</name></author><author><name>Chris Cheadle</name></author><author><name>Gordon Broderick</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Modeling of systems for which data is limited often leads to underdetermined model identification problems, where multiple candidate models are equally adherent to data. In such situations additional optimality criteria are useful in model selection apart from the conventional minimization of error and model complexity. This work presents the attractor landscape as a domain for novel model selection criteria, where the number and location of attractors impact desirability. A set of candidate models describing immune response dynamics to SARS-CoV infection is used as an example for model selection based on features of the attractor landscape. Using this selection criteria, the initial set of 18 models is ranked and reduced to 7 models that have a composite objective value with a p-value &amp;lt; 0.05. Additionally, the impact of pharmacologically induced remolding of the attractor landscape is presented.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.466986" rel="alternate" title="Attractor Landscapes as a Model Selection Criterion in Data Poor Environments (4 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467619</id><title>A multiscale computational study of the conformation of the full-length intrinsically disordered protein MeCP2 (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.807376+00:00</updated><author><name>Cecilia Chávez-García</name></author><author><name>Jérôme Hénin</name></author><author><name>Mikko Karttunen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The malfunction of the Methyl CpG binding protein 2 (MeCP2) is associated to the Rett syndrome, one of the most common causes of cognitive impairment in females. MeCP2 is an intrinsically disordered protein (IDP), making its experimental characterization a challenge. There is currently no structure available for the full-length MeCP2 in any of the databases, and only the structure of its MBD domain has been solved. We used this structure to build a full-length model of MeCP2 by completing the rest of the protein via &lt;italic&gt;ab initio&lt;/italic&gt; modelling. Using a combination of all-atom and coarse-grained simulations, we characterized its structure and dynamics as well as the conformational space sampled by the ID and TRD domains in the absence of the rest of the protein. The present work is the first computational study of the full-length protein. Two main conformations were sampled in the coarse-grained simulations: a globular structure similar to the one observed in the all-atom force field and a two-globule conformation. Our all-atom model is in good agreement with the available experimental data, predicting amino acid W104 to be buried, amino acids R111 and R133 to be solvent accessible, and having 4.1% of α-helix content, compared to the 4% found experimentally. Finally, we compared the model predicted by AlphaFold to our Modeller model. The model was not stable in water and underwent further folding. Together, these simulations provide a detailed (if perhaps incomplete) conformational ensemble of the full-length MeCP2, which is compatible with experimental data and can be the basis of further studies, e.g., on mutants of the protein or its interactions with its biological partners.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467619" rel="alternate" title="A multiscale computational study of the conformation of the full-length intrinsically disordered protein MeCP2 (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468478</id><title>Poly ADP-ribosylation of SET8 leads to aberrant H4K20me1 domains in mammalian cells (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.807502+00:00</updated><author><name>Pierre-Olivier Esteve</name></author><author><name>Vishnu Udayakumaran Nair Sunitha Kumary</name></author><author><name>Christian Ruse</name></author><author><name>Hang Gyeong Chin</name></author><author><name>Sriharsa Pradhan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In mammalian cells, SET8 mediated Histone H4 Lys 20 monomethylation (H4K20me1) has been implicated in regulating mitotic condensation, DNA replication, DNA damage response, and gene expression. Here we show SET8, the only known enzyme for H4K20me1 is post-translationally poly ADP-ribosylated by PARP1 on lysine residues. PARP1 interacts with SET8 in a cell cycle-dependent manner. Poly ADP-ribosylation on SET8 renders it catalytically compromised and it undergoes degradation via ubiquitylation pathway. Knockdown of PARP1 shifted the relative dynamic equilibrium of H4K20me2 to H4k20me3 in cells. Overexpression or knockdown of PARP1 led to aberrant H4K20me1 domains genome-wide, impacting Wnt signaling pathways genes and transcription factor binding site enrichment. Therefore, SET8 mediated chromatin remodeling and gene expression in mammalian cells are influenced by poly ADP-ribosylation by PARP1.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468478" rel="alternate" title="Poly ADP-ribosylation of SET8 leads to aberrant H4K20me1 domains in mammalian cells (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468051</id><title>GutMicroNet: an interactive platform for gut microbiome interaction exploration (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.823382+00:00</updated><author><name>Muhammad Arif</name></author><author><name>Theo Portlock</name></author><author><name>Cem Güngör</name></author><author><name>Elif Koç</name></author><author><name>Berkay Özcan</name></author><author><name>Oğuzhan Subaş</name></author><author><name>Buğra Çakmak</name></author><author><name>Mathias Uhlén</name></author><author><name>Adil Mardinoglu</name></author><author><name>Saeed Shoaie</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The human gut microbiome data has been proven to be a powerful tool to understand the human body in both health and disease conditions. However, understanding their complex interactions and impact on the human body remains a challenging task. Unravelling the species-level interactions could allow us to study the causality of the microbiome. Moreover, it could lead us to better understand the underlying mechanisms of complex diseases and, subsequently, the discovery of new therapeutic targets. Given these challenges and benefits, it has become evident that a freely accessible and centralized platform for presenting gut microbiome interaction is essential to untangle the complexity and open multiple new paths and opportunities in disease- and drug-related research. Here, we present GutMicroNet, an interactive visualization platform of human gut microbiome interaction networks. We generated 45 gut microbiome co-abundance networks from various geographical origins, gender, and diseases based on the data presented in the Human Gut Microbiome Atlas. This interactive platform includes more than 1900 gut microbiome species and allows users to query multiple species at the same time based on their interests and adjust it based on the statistical properties. Moreover, users can download publication-ready figures or network information for further analysis. The platform can be accessed freely on &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://gutmicro.net"&gt;https://gutmicro.net&lt;/ext-link&gt; without any login requirements or limitations, including access to the full networks data.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468051" rel="alternate" title="GutMicroNet: an interactive platform for gut microbiome interaction exploration (3 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.467071</id><title>An efficient and adaptable workflow for editing disease-relevant single nucleotide variants using CRISPR/Cas9 (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.824056+00:00</updated><author><name>Inga Usher</name></author><author><name>Lorena Ligammari</name></author><author><name>Sara Ahrabi</name></author><author><name>Emily Hepburn</name></author><author><name>Calum Connolly</name></author><author><name>Gareth L Bond</name></author><author><name>Adrienne M Flanagan</name></author><author><name>Lucia Cottone</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single nucleotide variants are the commonest genetic alterations in the human genome. At least 60,000 have been reported to be associated with disease. The CRISPR/Cas9 system has transformed genetic research, making it possible to edit single nucleotides and study the function of genetic variants in vitro. While significant advances have improved the efficiency of CRISPR/Cas9, the editing of single nucleotides remains challenging. There are two major obstacles: low efficiency of accurate editing and the isolation of these cells from a pool of cells with other editing outcomes. We present data from 85 transfections of induced pluripotent stem cells and an immortalised cell line, comparing the effects of altering CRISPR/Cas9 design and experimental conditions on rates of single nucleotide substitution. We targeted variants in TP53, which predispose to several cancers, and in TBXT which is implicated in the pathogenesis of the bone cancer, chordoma. We describe a scalable and adaptable workflow for single nucleotide editing that incorporates contemporary techniques including Illumina MiSeq sequencing, TaqMan qPCR and digital droplet PCR for screening transfected cells as well as quality control steps to mitigate against common pitfalls. This workflow can be applied to CRISPR/Cas9 and other genome editing systems to maximise experimental efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.467071" rel="alternate" title="An efficient and adaptable workflow for editing disease-relevant single nucleotide variants using CRISPR/Cas9 (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468406</id><title>Experimental and Biophysical Modeling of Transcription and Translation Dynamics in Bacterial- and Mammalian-based Cell-Free Expression Systems (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.824576+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuwen Zhao</name></author><author><name>Shue Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cell-free expression (CFE) systems have been used extensively in system and synthetic biology as a promising platform for manufacturing proteins and chemicals. Currently, the most widely used CFE system is in vitro protein transcription and translation platform. As the rapidly increased applications and uses, it is crucial to have a standard biophysical model for quantitative studies of gene circuits, which will provide a fundamental understanding of basic working mechanisms of CFE systems. Current modeling approaches mainly focus on the characterization of E. coli-based CFE systems, a computational model that can be utilized to both bacterial- and mammalian-based CFE has not been investigated. Here, we developed a simple ODE (ordinary differential equation)-based biophysical model to simulate transcription and translation dynamics for both bacterial- and mammalian-based CFE systems. The key parameters were estimated and adjusted based on experimental results. We next tested four gene circuits to characterize kinetic dynamics of transcription and translation in E. coli- and HeLa-based CFE systems. The real-time transcription and translation were monitored using Broccoli aptamer, double stranded locked nucleic acid (dsLNA) probe and fluorescent protein. We demonstrated the difference of kinetic dynamics for transcription and translation in both systems, which will provide valuable information for quantitative genomic and proteomic studies. This simple biophysical model and the experimental data for both E. coli- and HeLa-based CFE will be useful for researchers that are interested in genetic engineering and CFE bio-manufacturing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468406" rel="alternate" title="Experimental and Biophysical Modeling of Transcription and Translation Dynamics in Bacterial- and Mammalian-based Cell-Free Expression Systems (3 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467787</id><title>The C. elegans gonadal sheath Sh1 cells extend asymmetrically over a differentiating germ cell population in the proliferative zone (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.824785+00:00</updated><author><name>Xin Li</name></author><author><name>Noor Singh</name></author><author><name>Camille Miller</name></author><author><name>India Washington</name></author><author><name>Bintou Sosseh</name></author><author><name>Kacy Lynn Gordon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; adult hermaphrodite germ line is surrounded by a thin tube formed by somatic sheath cells that support germ cells as they mature from the stem-like mitotic state through meiosis, gametogenesis and ovulation. Recently, we discovered that the distal-most Sh1 sheath cells associate with mitotic germ cells as they exit the niche. Here we report that these distal sheath-associated germ cells differentiate first in animals with temperature-sensitive mutations affecting germ cell state, and stem-like germ cells are maintained distal to the Sh1 boundary. We analyze several markers of the distal sheath, which is best visualized with endogenously tagged membrane proteins, as overexpressed fluorescent proteins fail to localize to distal membrane processes and can cause gonad morphology defects. However, such reagents with highly variable expression can be used to determine the relative positions of the two Sh1 cells, one of which often extends further distal than the other.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467787" rel="alternate" title="The C. elegans gonadal sheath Sh1 cells extend asymmetrically over a differentiating germ cell population in the proliferative zone (3 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>