<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.129681+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.455288</id><title>Generation and diversification of recombinant monoclonal antibodies for studying mitosis (75 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.130786+00:00</updated><author><name>Keith F DeLuca</name></author><author><name>Jeanne E Mick</name></author><author><name>Amy L Hodges</name></author><author><name>Wanessa C Lima</name></author><author><name>Lori Sherman</name></author><author><name>Kristin L Schaller</name></author><author><name>Steven M Anderson</name></author><author><name>Ning Zhao</name></author><author><name>Timothy J Stasevich</name></author><author><name>Dileep Varma</name></author><author><name>Gary J Gorbsky</name></author><author><name>Jakob Nilsson</name></author><author><name>Jennifer G. DeLuca</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antibodies are indispensable tools used for a large number of applications in both foundational and translational bioscience research; however, there are drawbacks to using traditional antibodies generated in animals. These include a lack of standardization leading to problems with reproducibility, high costs of antibodies purchased from commercial sources, and ethical concerns regarding the large number of animals used to generate antibodies. To address these issues, we have developed practical methodologies and tools for generating low-cost, high-yield preparations of recombinant monoclonal antibodies and antibody fragments directed to protein epitopes from primary sequences. We describe these methods here, as well as approaches to diversify monoclonal antibodies, including customization of antibody species specificity, generation of genetically encoded small antibody fragments, and conversion of single chain antibody fragments (e.g. scFv) into full-length, bivalent antibodies. This study focuses on antibodies directed to epitopes important for mitotic cell division; however, the methods and reagents described here are applicable to antibodies and antibody fragments for use in any field.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.455288" rel="alternate" title="Generation and diversification of recombinant monoclonal antibodies for studying mitosis (75 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.08.459528</id><title>Maternal SMCHD1 regulates Hox gene expression and patterning in the mouse embryo (54 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.131763+00:00</updated><author><name>Natalia Benetti</name></author><author><name>Quentin Gouil</name></author><author><name>Andres Tapia del Fierro</name></author><author><name>Tamara Beck</name></author><author><name>Kelsey Breslin</name></author><author><name>Andrew Keniry</name></author><author><name>Edwina McGlinn</name></author><author><name>Marnie E. Blewitt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Parents transmit genetic and epigenetic information to their offspring. Maternal effect genes regulate the offspring epigenome to ensure normal development. Here we report that the epigenetic regulator SMCHD1 has a maternal effect on &lt;italic&gt;Hox&lt;/italic&gt; gene expression and skeletal patterning. Maternal SMCHD1, present in the oocyte and preimplantation embryo, prevents precocious activation of &lt;italic&gt;Hox&lt;/italic&gt; genes postimplantation. Without maternal SMCHD1, highly penetrant posterior homeotic transformations occur in the embryo. &lt;italic&gt;Hox&lt;/italic&gt; genes are decorated with Polycomb marks H2AK119ub and H3K27me3 from the oocyte throughout early embryonic development; however, loss of maternal SMCHD1 does not alter these marks. Therefore, we propose maternal SMCHD1 acts downstream of Polycomb marks to establish a chromatin state necessary for persistent epigenetic silencing and appropriate &lt;italic&gt;Hox&lt;/italic&gt; gene expression later in the developing embryo. This is a striking role for maternal SMCHD1 in long-lived epigenetic effects impacting offspring phenotype.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.08.459528" rel="alternate" title="Maternal SMCHD1 regulates Hox gene expression and patterning in the mouse embryo (54 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-09-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.06.459138</id><title>Mapping of a N-terminal α-helix domain required for human PINK1 stabilisation, Serine228 autophosphorylation and activation in cells (45 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.132062+00:00</updated><author><name>Poonam Kakade</name></author><author><name>Hina Ojha</name></author><author><name>Olawale G. Raimi</name></author><author><name>Andrew Shaw</name></author><author><name>Andrew D. Waddell</name></author><author><name>James R. Ault</name></author><author><name>Sophie Burel</name></author><author><name>Kathrin Brockmann</name></author><author><name>Atul Kumar</name></author><author><name>Mohd Syed Ahangar</name></author><author><name>Ewelina M. Krysztofinska</name></author><author><name>Thomas Macartney</name></author><author><name>Richard Bayliss</name></author><author><name>Julia C. Fitzgerald</name></author><author><name>Miratul M. K. Muqit</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human autosomal recessive mutations in the &lt;italic&gt;PINK1&lt;/italic&gt; gene are causal for Parkinson’s disease (PD). PINK1 encodes a mitochondrial localised protein kinase that is a master-regulator of mitochondrial quality control pathways. Structural studies to date have elaborated the mechanism of how mutations located within the kinase domain disrupt PINK1 function, however, the molecular mechanism of PINK1 mutations located upstream and downstream of the kinase domain are unknown. We have employed mutagenesis studies of human PINK1 in cells to define the minimal region of PINK1, required for optimal ubiquitin phosphorylation, beginning at residue Ile111. Bioinformatic analysis of the region spanning Ile111 to the kinase domain and inspection of the AlphaFold human PINK1 structure model predicts a conserved N-terminal α-helical domain extension (NTE domain) within this region corroborated by hydrogen/deuterium exchange mass spectrometry (HDX-MS) of recombinant insect PINK1 protein. The AlphaFold structure also predicts the NTE domain forms an intramolecular interaction with the C-terminal extension (CTE). Cell-based analysis of human PINK1 reveals that PD-associated mutations (e.g. Q126P), located within the NTE:CTE interface, markedly inhibit stabilization of PINK1; autophosphorylation at Serine228 (Ser228); and Ubiquitin Serine65 (Ser65) phosphorylation. Furthermore, we provide evidence that NTE domain mutants do not affect intrinsic catalytic kinase activity but do disrupt PINK1 stabilisation at the mitochondrial Translocase of outer membrane (TOM) complex. The clinical relevance of our findings is supported by the demonstration of defective stabilization and activation of endogenous PINK1 in human fibroblasts of a patient with early-onset PD due to homozygous PINK1 Q126P mutations. Overall, we define a functional role of the NTE:CTE interface towards PINK1 stabilisation and activation and show that loss of NTE:CTE interactions is a major mechanism of PINK1-associated mutations linked to PD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.06.459138" rel="alternate" title="Mapping of a N-terminal α-helix domain required for human PINK1 stabilisation, Serine228 autophosphorylation and activation in cells (45 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.05.458952</id><title>Community science designed ribosomes with beneficial phenotypes (42 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.132444+00:00</updated><author><name>Antje Kruger</name></author><author><name>Andrew M Watkins</name></author><author><name>Roger Wellington-Oguri</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Romano</name></author><author><name>Camila Kofman</name></author><author><name>Alysse DeFoe</name></author><author><name>Yejun Kim</name></author><author><name>Jeff Anderson-Lee</name></author><author><name>Eli Fisker</name></author><author><name>Jill Townley</name></author><author><name>Anne E d'Aquino</name></author><author><name>Rhiju Das</name></author><author><name>Michael C Jewett</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Functional design of ribosomes with mutant ribosomal RNA (rRNA) could expand opportunities for understanding molecular translation, building cells from the bottom-up, and engineering ribosomes with altered capabilities. However, such efforts have been hampered by cell viability constraints, an enormous combinatorial sequence space, and limitations on large-scale, 3D design of RNA structures and functions. To address these challenges, we developed an integrated community science and experimental screening approach for rational design of ribosomes. This approach couples Eterna, an online video game that crowdsources RNA sequence design to community scientists in the form of puzzles, with in vitro ribosome synthesis, assembly, and translation in multiple design-build-test-learn cycles. We applied our framework to discover mutant rRNA sequences that improve protein synthesis in vitro and cell growth in vivo, relative to wild type ribosomes, under diverse environmental conditions. This work provides new insights into ribosome rRNA sequence-function relationships, with implications for synthetic biology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.05.458952" rel="alternate" title="Community science designed ribosomes with beneficial phenotypes (42 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.11.459888</id><title>Activation of stably silenced genes by recruitment of a synthetic de-methylating module (34 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.133356+00:00</updated><author><name>Wing Fuk Chan</name></author><author><name>Christine R. Keenan</name></author><author><name>Timothy M Johanson</name></author><author><name>Rhys S Allan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Stably silenced genes that display a high level of CpG dinucleotide methylation are refractory to the current generation of dCas9-based activation systems. To counter this, we created an improved activation system by coupling the catalytic domain of DNA demethylating enzyme TET1 with transcriptional activators (TETact). TETact induces transcription of heavily suppressed non-coding RNA and surface protein, and the reactivation of embryonic haemoglobin genes in non-erythroid cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.11.459888" rel="alternate" title="Activation of stably silenced genes by recruitment of a synthetic de-methylating module (34 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.459858</id><title>Engineered bacteria detect tumor DNA in vivo (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.133760+00:00</updated><author><name>Robert M Cooper</name></author><author><name>Josephine A Wright</name></author><author><name>Jia Q Ng</name></author><author><name>Jarrad M Goyne</name></author><author><name>Nobumi Suzuki</name></author><author><name>Young K Lee</name></author><author><name>Mari Ichinose</name></author><author><name>Georgette Radford</name></author><author><name>Elaine M Thomas</name></author><author><name>Laura Vrbanac</name></author><author><name>Rob Knight</name></author><author><name>Susan L Woods</name></author><author><name>Daniel L Worthley</name></author><author><name>Jeff Hasty</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In vitro nucleic acid analysis has become a valuable diagnostic tool. However, in vitro measurements have many disadvantages when compared to in vivo techniques. Synthetic bacterial biosensors have been engineered to sense many target signals in vivo, but no biosensor exists to detect specific DNA sequences. Here, we engineered naturally competent Acinetobacter baylyi bacteria to detect engineered donor DNA inserted into the genomes of colorectal cancer (CRC) cells and organoids. The DNA biosensor concept was developed in vitro and then validated in vivo with sensor bacteria delivered orally or rectally to mice that had been injected with orthotopic donor CRC organoids. Horizontal gene transfer occurred from the donor tumor to the sensor bacteria in vivo, conferring antibiotic resistance to the sensor bacteria and allowing their detection in stool. The sensor bacteria differentiated mice with and without CRC. Life detecting life has many implications for future diagnosis, prevention, and treatment of disease. This approach may also be useful in any application that requires the detection of mutations or organisms within environments that are difficult to sample.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.459858" rel="alternate" title="Engineered bacteria detect tumor DNA in vivo (31 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459228</id><title>Differentially optimized cell-free buffer enables robust expression from unprotected linear DNA in exonuclease-deficient extracts (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.134264+00:00</updated><author><name>Angelo Cardoso Batista</name></author><author><name>Antoine Levrier</name></author><author><name>Paul Soudier</name></author><author><name>Peter Voyvodic</name></author><author><name>Tatjana Achmedov</name></author><author><name>Tristan Reif-Trauttmansdorff</name></author><author><name>Angelique DeVisch</name></author><author><name>Martin Cohen Gonsaud</name></author><author><name>Jean-Loup Faulon</name></author><author><name>Chase Beisel</name></author><author><name>Jerome Bonnet</name></author><author><name>Manish Kushwaha</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The use of linear DNA templates in cell-free systems promises to accelerate the prototyping and engineering of synthetic gene circuits. A key challenge is that linear templates are rapidly degraded by exonucleases present in cell extracts. Current approaches tackle the problem by adding exonuclease inhibitors and DNA-binding proteins to protect the linear DNA, requiring additional time- and resource-intensive steps. Here, we delete the &lt;italic&gt;recBCD&lt;/italic&gt; exonuclease gene cluster from the &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; BL21 genome. We show that the resulting cell-free systems, with buffers optimized specifically for linear DNA, enable near-plasmid levels of expression from σ70 promoters in linear DNA templates without employing additional protection strategies. When using linear or plasmid DNA templates at the buffer calibration step, we found that the optimal potassium glutamate concentrations obtained when using linear DNA were consistently lower than those obtained when using plasmid DNA for the same extract. We demonstrate the robustness of the exonuclease deficient extracts across seven different batches and a wide range of experimental conditions. Finally, we illustrate the use of the Δ&lt;italic&gt;recBCD&lt;/italic&gt; extracts for two applications: toehold switch characterization and enzyme screening. Our work provides a simple, efficient, and costeffective solution for using linear DNA templates in cell-free systems and highlights the importance of specifically tailoring buffer composition for the final experimental setup. Our data also suggest that similar exonuclease deletion strategies can be applied to other species suitable for cell-free synthetic biology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459228" rel="alternate" title="Differentially optimized cell-free buffer enables robust expression from unprotected linear DNA in exonuclease-deficient extracts (22 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-09-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.06.459145</id><title>A DCL3 dicing code within Pol IV-RDR2 transcripts diversifies the siRNA pool guiding RNA-directed DNA methylation (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.134802+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew Loffer</name></author><author><name>Jasleen Singh</name></author><author><name>Akihito Fukudome</name></author><author><name>Vibhor Mishra</name></author><author><name>Feng Wang</name></author><author><name>Craig S. Pikaard</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In plants, selfish genetic elements including retrotransposons and DNA viruses are transcriptionally silenced by RNA-directed DNA methylation. Guiding the process are short interfering RNAs (siRNAs) cut by DICER-LIKE 3 (DCL3) from double-stranded precursors of ∼30 bp synthesized by NUCLEAR RNA POLYMERASE IV (Pol IV) and RNA-DEPENDENT RNA POLYMERASE 2 (RDR2). We show that Pol IV initiating nucleotide choice, RDR2 initiation 1-2 nt internal to Pol IV transcript ends and RDR2 terminal transferase activity collectively yield a code that influences which end of the precursor is diced and whether 24 or 23 nt siRNAs are generated from the Pol IV or RDR2-transcribed strands. By diversifying the size, sequence, and strand polarity of siRNAs derived from a given precursor, alternative patterns of DCL3 dicing allow maximal siRNA coverage at methylated target loci.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.06.459145" rel="alternate" title="A DCL3 dicing code within Pol IV-RDR2 transcripts diversifies the siRNA pool guiding RNA-directed DNA methylation (20 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459266</id><title>The temporal dynamics of the sea urchin regulome (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.135167+00:00</updated><author><name>Roberto Feuda</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In this work, we used Nanostring N-counter technology, to evaluate the mRNA expression level of more than 330 regulatory genes over 34-time points covering the first three days of development of the sea urchin larvae. The hierarchical clustering of the mRNAs expression levels has identified groups corresponding to the major developmental landmarks (e.g., maternal to zygotic transition and gastrulation). Furthermore, comparison with previous experiments indicates high reproducibility of mRNA level temporal dynamics across batches. Finally, we generated an online tool to visualize gene expression during sea urchin larval development. The site can be accessed at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nanostring2021.herokuapp.com/"&gt;https://nanostring2021.herokuapp.com/&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459266" rel="alternate" title="The temporal dynamics of the sea urchin regulome (17 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-09-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.08.459542</id><title>Distal regulation, silencers and a shared combinatorial syntax are hallmarks of animal embryogenesis (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.135488+00:00</updated><author><name>Paola Cornejo-Páramo</name></author><author><name>Kathrein Roper</name></author><author><name>Sandie M Degnan</name></author><author><name>Bernard M Degnan</name></author><author><name>Emily S Wong</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The chromatin environment plays a central role in regulating developmental gene expression in metazoans. Yet, the basal regulatory landscape of metazoan embryogenesis is unknown. Here, we generate chromatin accessibility profiles for six embryonic, plus larval and adult stages in the sponge &lt;italic&gt;Amphimedon queenslandica&lt;/italic&gt;. These profiles are reproducible within stages, reflect histone modifications, and identify transcription factor (TF) binding sequence motifs predictive of &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-regulatory elements during embryogenesis in other metazoans but not the unicellular relative &lt;italic&gt;Capsaspora&lt;/italic&gt;. Motif analysis of chromatin accessibility profiles across &lt;italic&gt;Amphimedon&lt;/italic&gt; embryogenesis identifies three major developmental periods. As in bilaterian embryogenesis, early development in &lt;italic&gt;Amphimedon&lt;/italic&gt; involves activating and repressive chromatin in regions both proximal and distal to transcription start sites. Transcriptionally repressive elements (‘silencers’) are prominent during late embryogenesis and coincide with an increase in &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-regulatory regions harbouring metazoan TF binding motifs, and an increase in the expression of metazoan-specific genes. Changes in chromatin state and gene expression in &lt;italic&gt;Amphimedon&lt;/italic&gt; suggest the conservation of distal enhancers, dynamically silenced chromatin, and TF-DNA binding specificity in animal embryogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.08.459542" rel="alternate" title="Distal regulation, silencers and a shared combinatorial syntax are hallmarks of animal embryogenesis (12 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.459613</id><title>Distinct, opposing functions for CFIm59 and CFIm68 in mRNA alternative polyadenylation of Pten and in the PI3K/Akt signalling cascade (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.135877+00:00</updated><author><name>Hsin-Wei Tseng</name></author><author><name>Anthony Mota-Sydor</name></author><author><name>Rania Leventis</name></author><author><name>Ivan Topisirovic</name></author><author><name>Thomas F. Duchaine</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The precise maintenance of PTEN dosage is crucial for tumor suppression across a wide variety of cancers. Post-transcriptional regulation of &lt;italic&gt;Pten&lt;/italic&gt; heavily relies on regulatory elements encoded by its 3’UTR. We previously reported the important diversity of 3’UTR isoforms of &lt;italic&gt;Pten&lt;/italic&gt; mRNAs produced through alternative polyadenylation (APA). Here, we reveal the direct regulation of &lt;italic&gt;Pten&lt;/italic&gt; APA by the mammalian cleavage factor I (CFIm) complex, which in turn contributes to PTEN protein dosage. CFIm consists of the UGUA-binding CFIm25 and APA regulatory subunits CFIm59 or CFIm68. Deep sequencing analyses of perturbed (KO and KD) cell lines uncovered the differential regulation of &lt;italic&gt;Pten&lt;/italic&gt; APA by CFIm59 and CFIm68 and further revealed that their divergent functions have widespread impact for APA in transcriptomes. Differentially regulated genes include numerous factors within the phosphoinositide 3-kinase (PI3K)/protein kinase B (Akt) signalling pathway that PTEN counter-regulates. We further reveal a stratification of APA dysregulation among a subset of &lt;italic&gt;PTEN-driven&lt;/italic&gt; cancers, with recurrent alterations among PI3K/Akt pathway genes regulated by CFIm. Our results refine the transcriptome selectivity of the CFIm complex in APA regulation, and the breadth of its impact in &lt;italic&gt;PTEN&lt;/italic&gt;-driven cancers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.459613" rel="alternate" title="Distinct, opposing functions for CFIm59 and CFIm68 in mRNA alternative polyadenylation of Pten and in the PI3K/Akt signalling cascade (10 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.459524</id><title>Distinct proteostasis states drive pharmacologic chaperone susceptibility for Cystic Fibrosis Transmembrane Conductance Regulator misfolding mutants (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.136367+00:00</updated><author><name>Eli Fritz McDonald</name></author><author><name>Carleen Mae P. Sabusap</name></author><author><name>Minsoo Kim</name></author><author><name>Lars Plate</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pharmacological chaperones represent a class of therapeutic compounds for treating protein misfolding diseases. One of the most prominent examples is the FDA-approved pharmacological chaperone lumacaftor (VX-809), which has transformed cystic fibrosis (CF) therapy. CF is a fatal disease caused by mutations in the cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator (CFTR). VX-809 corrects folding of F508del CFTR, the most common patient mutation, yet F508del exhibits only mild VX-809 response. In contrast, rarer mutations P67L and L206W are &lt;italic&gt;hyper-responsive&lt;/italic&gt; to VX-809, while G85E is &lt;italic&gt;non-responsive&lt;/italic&gt;. Despite the clinical success of VX-809, the mechanistic origin for the distinct susceptibility of mutants remains unclear. Here, we use interactomics to characterize the impact of VX-809 on proteostasis interactions of P67L and L206W and compare these to F508del and G85E. We determine &lt;italic&gt;hyper-responsive&lt;/italic&gt; mutations P67L and L206W exhibit decreased interactions with proteasomal, and autophagy degradation machinery compared to F508del and G85E. We then show inhibiting the proteasome attenuates P67L and L206W VX-809 response, and inhibiting the lysosome attenuates F508del VX-809 response. Our data suggests a previously unidentified but required role for protein degradation in VX-809 correction. Furthermore, we present an approach for identifying proteostasis characteristics of mutant-specific therapeutic response to pharmacological chaperones.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.459524" rel="alternate" title="Distinct proteostasis states drive pharmacologic chaperone susceptibility for Cystic Fibrosis Transmembrane Conductance Regulator misfolding mutants (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.06.459125</id><title>Synthetic deconstruction of hunchback regulation by Bicoid (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.136735+00:00</updated><author><name>Goncalo Fernandes</name></author><author><name>Huy Tran</name></author><author><name>Maxime Andrieu</name></author><author><name>Youssoupha Diaw</name></author><author><name>Carmina Perez-Romero</name></author><author><name>Cécile Fradin</name></author><author><name>Mathieu Coppey</name></author><author><name>Aleksandra M. Walczak</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Dostatni</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During development, cell identity is established reproducibly among individuals through the expression of specific genes at the correct time and correct location in space. How genes extract and combine both positional and temporal information from different transcription factor (TF) profiles along polarity axes remain largely unexplored. Here, we showcase the classic &lt;italic&gt;hunchback&lt;/italic&gt; gene in fruit fly embryos, with focus on 3 of its main TFs: Bicoid, Zelda and Hunchback proteins. We constructed a series of synthetic MS2 reporters, where the numbers and combination of binding sites for each TF are varied. Using live imaging of transcription dynamics by these synthetic reporters and modeling tools, we show that &lt;italic&gt;i)&lt;/italic&gt; a Bicoid-only synthetic reporter needs 3 more Bicoid binding sites than found in the &lt;italic&gt;hunchback&lt;/italic&gt; promoter to recapitulates almost all spatial features of early &lt;italic&gt;hb&lt;/italic&gt; expression but takes more time to reach steady state; &lt;italic&gt;ii)&lt;/italic&gt; Hunchback and Zelda binding sites combined with Bicoid sites both reduce the time to reach steady state and increase expression at a different step in the activation process: Zld sites lower the Bicoid threshold required for activation while Hb sites increase the polymerase firing rate and reduce bursting; &lt;italic&gt;iii)&lt;/italic&gt; the shift of the Bicoid-only reporter induced by a reduction by half of Bicoid concentrations indicates that the decay length of the Bicoid activity gradient is lower than the decay length of the Bicoid protein gradient. Altogether, this work indicates that Bicoid is the main source of positional information for &lt;italic&gt;hunchback&lt;/italic&gt; expression and places back the Bicoid system within the physical limits of an equilibrium model.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.06.459125" rel="alternate" title="Synthetic deconstruction of hunchback regulation by Bicoid (5 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.11.459880</id><title>The histone deacetylase activity of HDAC1/2 is required to safeguard zygotic genome activation in mice and cattle (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.136971+00:00</updated><author><name>Yanna Dang</name></author><author><name>Shuang Li</name></author><author><name>Panpan Zhao</name></author><author><name>Lieying Xiao</name></author><author><name>Lefeng Wang</name></author><author><name>Yan Shi</name></author><author><name>Lei Luo</name></author><author><name>Shaohua Wang</name></author><author><name>Huanan Wang</name></author><author><name>Kun Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The genome is transcriptionally inert at fertilization and must be activated through a remarkable developmental process called zygotic genome activation (ZGA). The gene expression pattern formed over the course of ZGA is required for establishing totipotency in early embryos and subsequent development. Substantial epigenetic reprogramming contributes significantly to the pronounced change in gene expression during ZGA, however the mechanism has yet to be resolved. Here, we find histone deacetylase 1 and 2 (HDAC1/2) are critical histone modifiers that regulate ZGA through the histone deacetylase activity. Notably, we show that H3K27ac level declines dramatically during ZGA with a dynamic change in its genome-wide distribution. In mouse embryos, ectopic expression of HDAC1/2 dominant negative mutant leads to a failure of H3K27ac removal and a developmental arrest at 2-cell stage. RNA-seq results reveal a remarkable transcriptomic change with 6565 differentially expressed genes identified. Further analysis shows 64% of down-regulated genes are ZGA genes and 49% of up-regulated genes are developmental genes. Low input ChIP-seq analysis exhibits an increase and decrease of H3K27ac enrichment at the promoter region of up- and down-regulated genes, respectively. Moreover, HDAC1 mutants prohibited removal of broad H3K4me3 domain via impeding the expression of Kdm5s during ZGA. Importantly, the developmental block can be greatly overcome through injection of Kdm5b mRNA and expression of the majority of dysregulated genes partially corrected. Similar functional significance of HDAC1/2 in ZGA is conserved in bovine embryos. Together, we propose that HDAC1/2 is indispensable for mouse and bovine ZGA via creating correct transcriptional repressive and active states.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.11.459880" rel="alternate" title="The histone deacetylase activity of HDAC1/2 is required to safeguard zygotic genome activation in mice and cattle (3 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>