<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.502296+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.30.458146</id><title>The control of transcriptional memory by stable mitotic bookmarking (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.502759+00:00</updated><author><name>Maëlle Bellec</name></author><author><name>Jérémy Dufourt</name></author><author><name>George Hunt</name></author><author><name>Hélène Lenden-Hasse</name></author><author><name>Antonio Trullo</name></author><author><name>Amal Zine El Aabidine</name></author><author><name>Marie Lamarque</name></author><author><name>Marissa M Gaskill</name></author><author><name>Heloïse Faure-Gautron</name></author><author><name>Mattias Mannervik</name></author><author><name>Melissa M Harrison</name></author><author><name>Jean-Christophe Andrau</name></author><author><name>Cyril Favard</name></author><author><name>Ovidiu Radulescu</name></author><author><name>Mounia Lagha</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To maintain cellular identities during development, gene expression profiles must be faithfully propagated through cell generations. The reestablishment of gene expression patterns upon mitotic exit is thought to be mediated, in part, by mitotic bookmarking by transcription factors (TF). However, the mechanisms and functions of TF mitotic bookmarking during early embryogenesis remain poorly understood. In this study, taking advantage of the naturally synchronized mitoses of &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; early embryos, we provide evidence that the pioneer-like transcription factor GAF acts as stable mitotic bookmarker during zygotic genome activation. We report that GAF remains associated to a large fraction of its interphase targets including at &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-regulatory sequences of key developmental genes, with both active and repressive chromatin signatures. GAF mitotic targets are globally accessible during mitosis and are bookmarked via histone acetylation (H4K8ac). By monitoring the kinetics of transcriptional activation in living embryos, we provide evidence that GAF binding establishes competence for rapid activation upon mitotic exit.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.30.458146" rel="alternate" title="The control of transcriptional memory by stable mitotic bookmarking (24 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-08-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.31.458428</id><title>Characterisation of a nucleo-adhesome (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.503359+00:00</updated><author><name>Adam Byron</name></author><author><name>Billie G. C. Griffith</name></author><author><name>Ana Herrero</name></author><author><name>Alexander E. P. Loftus</name></author><author><name>Emma S. Koeleman</name></author><author><name>John C. Dawson</name></author><author><name>Linda Kogerman</name></author><author><name>Niamh McGivern</name></author><author><name>Jayne Culley</name></author><author><name>Graeme R. Grimes</name></author><author><name>Bryan Serrels</name></author><author><name>Alex von Kriegsheim</name></author><author><name>Valerie G. Brunton</name></author><author><name>Margaret C. Frame</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In addition to central functions in cell adhesion signalling, integrin-associated proteins have wider roles at sites distal to adhesion receptors. In experimentally defined adhesomes, we noticed that there is clear enrichment of proteins that localise to the nucleus, and conversely, we now report that nuclear proteomes contain a class of adhesome components that localise to the nucleus. We here defined a nucleo-adhesome, providing experimental evidence for a remarkable scale of nuclear localisation of adhesion proteins, establishing a framework for interrogating nuclear adhesion protein functions. In adding to nuclear FAK’s known roles in regulating transcription, we now show that nuclear FAK regulates expression of many adhesion-related proteins that localise to the nucleus and that nuclear FAK binds to the adhesome component and nuclear protein Hic-5. FAK and Hic-C work together in the nucleus, co-regulating a subset of genes transcriptionally. We describe the first nucleo-adhesome using a squamous cancer cell model, and demonstrate the new principle that there are nuclear adhesion protein subcomplexes that cooperate to control transcription.
&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="458428v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.31.458428" rel="alternate" title="Characterisation of a nucleo-adhesome (9 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.29.458102</id><title>Exo1-protected DNA nicks direct crossover formation in meiosis (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.503827+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael Gioia</name></author><author><name>Lisette Payero</name></author><author><name>Gianno Pannafino</name></author><author><name>Jun Jie Chen</name></author><author><name>Sagar Salim</name></author><author><name>Ghanim Fajith</name></author><author><name>Amamah F. Farnaz</name></author><author><name>Sherikat Momoh</name></author><author><name>Michelle Scotland</name></author><author><name>Vandana Raghavan</name></author><author><name>Carol Manhart</name></author><author><name>Akira Shinohara</name></author><author><name>K.T. Nishant</name></author><author><name>Eric Alani</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In most sexually reproducing organisms crossing over between chromosome homologs during meiosis is critical for the viability of haploid gametes. Most crossovers that form in meiosis in budding yeast result from the biased resolution of double Holliday Junction (dHJ) intermediates. This dHJ resolution step involves the actions Rad2/XPG family nuclease Exo1 and the Mlh1-Mlh3 mismatch repair endonuclease. At present little is known about how these factors act in meiosis at the molecular level. Here we show that Exo1 promotes meiotic crossing over by protecting DNA nicks from ligation. We found that structural elements in Exo1 required for interactions with DNA, such as bending of DNA during nick/flap recognition, are critical for its role in crossing over. Consistent with these observations, meiotic expression of the Rad2/XPG family member Rad27 partially rescued the crossover defect in &lt;italic&gt;exo1&lt;/italic&gt; null mutants, and meiotic overexpression of Cdc9 ligase specifically reduced the crossover levels of &lt;italic&gt;exo1&lt;/italic&gt; DNA binding mutants to levels approaching the &lt;italic&gt;exo1&lt;/italic&gt; null. In addition, our work identified a role for Exo1 in crossover interference that appears independent of its resection activity. Together, these studies provide experimental evidence for Exo1-protected nicks being critical for the formation of meiotic crossovers and their distribution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.29.458102" rel="alternate" title="Exo1-protected DNA nicks direct crossover formation in meiosis (8 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-08-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.01.458557</id><title>Functional fluorescently-tagged human profilin (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.504349+00:00</updated><author><name>Morgan L. Pimm</name></author><author><name>Xinbei Liu</name></author><author><name>Farzana Tuli</name></author><author><name>Ashley Lojko</name></author><author><name>Jessica L. Henty-Ridilla</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Profilin is an essential regulator of actin and microtubule dynamics and therefore a critical control point for the normal division, motility, and morphology of cells. Most studies of profilin have focused on biochemical investigations using purified protein because high cellular concentrations (121 µM) present challenges for conventional imaging modalities. In addition, past studies that employed direct labeling or conventional fusion protein strategies compromised different facets of profilin function. We engineered a fluorescently-labeled profilin that retains native activities with respect to phosphoinositide lipids, actin monomers, formin-mediated actin assembly, and microtubule polymerization. This fluorescent profilin directly binds to dimers of tubulin (k&lt;sub&gt;D&lt;/sub&gt; = 1.7 µM) and the microtubule lattice (k&lt;sub&gt;D&lt;/sub&gt; = 10 µM) to stimulate microtubule assembly. In cells, our tagged profilin fully rescues profilin-1&lt;sup&gt;(-/-)&lt;/sup&gt; cells from knockout-induced perturbations to cell shape, actin filament architecture, and microtubule arrays. Thus, this labeled profilin-1 is a reliable tool to investigate the dynamic interactions of profilin with actin or microtubules in live cell and in vitro applications.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.01.458557" rel="alternate" title="Functional fluorescently-tagged human profilin (7 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.31.458373</id><title>A Cytosolic Reductase Pathway is Required for Complete N-Glycosylation of an STT3B-Dependent Acceptor Site (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.504756+00:00</updated><author><name>Marcel van Lith</name></author><author><name>Marie Anne Pringle</name></author><author><name>Bethany Fleming</name></author><author><name>Giorgia Gaeta</name></author><author><name>Jisu Im</name></author><author><name>Reid Gilmore</name></author><author><name>Neil J Bulleid</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;N-linked glycosylation of proteins entering the secretory pathway is an essential post-translational modification required for protein stability and function. Previously, it has been shown that there is a temporal relationship between protein folding and glycosylation, which influences the occupancy of specific glycosylation sites. Here we use an &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; translation system that reproduces the initial stages of secretory protein translocation, folding and glycosylation under defined redox conditions. We found that the efficiency of glycosylation of hemopexin was dependent upon a robust NADPH-dependent cytosolic reductive pathway, which could also be mimicked by the addition of a membrane impermeable reducing agent. The identified hypoglycosylated acceptor site is adjacent to a cysteine involved in a short range disulfide bond, which has been shown to be dependent on the STT3B-containing oligosaccharyl transferase. We also show that efficient glycosylation at this site is dependent on the STT3A-containing oligosaccharide transferase. Our results provide further insight into the important role of the ER redox conditions in glycosylation site occupancy and demonstrate a link between redox conditions in the cytosol and glycosylation efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.31.458373" rel="alternate" title="A Cytosolic Reductase Pathway is Required for Complete N-Glycosylation of an STT3B-Dependent Acceptor Site (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.31.458377</id><title>Multicenter reverse-phase protein array data integration (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.506224+00:00</updated><author><name>Leanne de Koning</name></author><author><name>Stephan Bernhardt</name></author><author><name>Kenneth G. Macleod</name></author><author><name>Bérengère Ouine</name></author><author><name>Aurélie Cartier</name></author><author><name>Vonick Sibut</name></author><author><name>Neil O. Carragher</name></author><author><name>Ulrike Korf</name></author><author><name>Bryan Serrels</name></author><author><name>Adam Byron</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Among the technologies available for protein biomarker discovery and validation, reverse-phase protein array (RPPA) benefits from unequalled sample throughput. Panels of high-quality antibodies enable the quantification by RPPA of protein abundance and posttranslational modifications in biological specimens with high precision and sensitivity. Incorporation of RPPA technology into clinical and drug development pipelines requires robust assays that generate reproducible results across multiple laboratories. We implemented the first international multicenter pilot study to investigate RPPA workflow variability. We characterized the proteomic responses of a series of breast cancer cells to two cancer drugs. This analysis quantified 86,832 sample spots, representing 108 biological samples, arrayed at three independent RPPA platforms. This unique integrated set of data is publicly available as a resource to the proteomic and cancer research communities to catalyse further analysis and investigation. We anticipate that this dataset will form a reference for the comparison of RPPA workflows and reagents, which can be expanded in the future, and will aid the identification of platform-robust treatment-marker antigens in breast cancer cells.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="458377v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.31.458377" rel="alternate" title="Multicenter reverse-phase protein array data integration (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.29.458141</id><title>Exploiting flow cytometry for the unbiased quantification of protein inclusions in Caenorhabditis elegans (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.507221+00:00</updated><author><name>Kristian Claesson</name></author><author><name>Yee Lian Chew</name></author><author><name>Heath Ecroyd</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The aggregation of proteins into inclusions or plaques is a prominent hallmark of a diverse range of pathologies including neurodegenerative diseases. The quantification of such inclusions in &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/italic&gt; models of aggregation is usually achieved by fluorescence microscopy or other techniques involving biochemical fractionation of worm lysates. Here, we describe a simple and rapid flow cytometry-based approach that allows fluorescently-tagged inclusions to be enumerated in whole worm lysate in a quantitative and unbiased fashion. We demonstrate that this technique is applicable to multiple &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; models of aggregation and importantly, can be used to monitor the dynamics of inclusion formation in response to heat shock and during aging. This includes the characterisation of physicochemical properties of inclusions, such as their size, which may reveal how aggregate formation is distinct in different tissues or at different stages of pathology or aging. This new method can be used as a powerful technique for the medium- to high-throughput quantification of inclusions in future studies of genetic or chemical modulators of aggregation in &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.29.458141" rel="alternate" title="Exploiting flow cytometry for the unbiased quantification of protein inclusions in Caenorhabditis elegans (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>