<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.114875+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470782</id><title>A Nascent Peptide Code for Translational Control of mRNA Stability in Human Cells (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.115275+00:00</updated><author><name>Phillip C. Burke</name></author><author><name>Heungwon Park</name></author><author><name>Arvind Rasi Subramaniam</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Stability of eukaryotic mRNAs is associated with their codon, amino acid, and GC content. Yet, coding sequence motifs that predictably alter mRNA stability in human cells remain poorly defined. Here, we develop a massively parallel assay to measure mRNA effects of thousands of synthetic and endogenous coding sequence motifs in human cells. We identify several families of simple dipeptide repeats whose translation triggers acute mRNA instability. Rather than individual amino acids, specific combinations of bulky and positively charged amino acids are critical for the destabilizing effects of dipeptide repeats. Remarkably, dipeptide sequences that form extended β strands &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; drive ribosome stalling and mRNA instability &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. The resulting nascent peptide code underlies ribosome stalling and mRNA-destabilizing effects of hundreds of endogenous peptide sequences in the human proteome. Our work reveals an intrinsic role for the ribosome as a selectivity filter against the synthesis of bulky and aggregation-prone peptides.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470782" rel="alternate" title="A Nascent Peptide Code for Translational Control of mRNA Stability in Human Cells (37 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470639</id><title>Topoisomerases I and II facilitate condensin DC translocation to organize and repress X chromosomes in C. elegans (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.115599+00:00</updated><author><name>Ana Karina Morao</name></author><author><name>Jun Kim</name></author><author><name>Daniel Obaji</name></author><author><name>Siyu Sun</name></author><author><name>Sevinc Ercan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Condensin complexes are evolutionarily conserved molecular motors that translocate along DNA and form loops. While condensin-mediated DNA looping is thought to direct the chain-passing activity of topoisomerase II to separate sister chromatids, it is not known if topological constraints in turn regulate loop formation &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Here we applied auxin inducible degradation of topoisomerases I and II to determine how DNA topology affects the translocation of an X chromosome specific condensin that represses transcription for dosage compensation in &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; (condensin DC). We found that both topoisomerases colocalize with condensin DC and control its movement at different genomic scales. TOP-2 depletion hindered condensin DC translocation over long distances, resulting in accumulation around its X-specific recruitment sites and shorter Hi-C interactions. In contrast, TOP-1 depletion did not affect long-range spreading but resulted in accumulation of condensin DC within expressed gene bodies. Both TOP-1 and TOP-2 depletions resulted in X chromosome transcriptional upregulation indicating that condensin DC translocation at both scales is required for its function in gene repression. Together the distinct effects of TOP-1 and TOP-2 on condensin DC distribution revealed two distinct modes of condensin DC association with chromatin: long-range translocation that requires decatenation/unknotting of DNA and short-range translocation across genes that requires resolution of transcription-induced supercoiling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470639" rel="alternate" title="Topoisomerases I and II facilitate condensin DC translocation to organize and repress X chromosomes in C. elegans (37 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470829</id><title>Ikaros family proteins regulate developmental windows in the mouse retina through convergent and divergent transcriptional programs (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.116012+00:00</updated><author><name>Awais Javed</name></author><author><name>Pierre Mattar</name></author><author><name>Allie Cui</name></author><author><name>Michel Cayouette</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Temporal identity factors regulate the competence of neural progenitors to generate specific cell types in a time-dependent manner, but how they operate remains poorly defined. In the developing mouse retina, the Ikaros zinc finger transcription factor Ikzf1 regulates the production of early-born cell types, except cone photoreceptors. In this study we show that Ikzf4, another Ikaros family protein, cooperates with Ikzf1 to control cone photoreceptor production during early stages of retinal development, whereas at late stages, when Ikzf1 is no longer expressed in progenitors, Ikzf4 is instead required for Müller glia production. Using CUT&amp;amp;RUN sequencing, we find that both Ikzf1 and Ikzf4 generally bind to the same genes involved in cone development and other early-born fates, but at different cis-regulatory elements. In late-stage progenitors, Ikzf4 re-localizes to bind target genes involved in Müller glia development and regulate their expression. Specifically, we show that Ikzf4 maintains Hes1 expression in differentiating cells using two Ikzf GGAA binding sites at the &lt;italic&gt;Hes1&lt;/italic&gt; promoter, thereby favouring Müller glia fate commitment. These results uncover a combinatorial role for Ikaros family members in nervous system development and provide mechanistic insights on how they temporally regulate cell fate output.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470829" rel="alternate" title="Ikaros family proteins regulate developmental windows in the mouse retina through convergent and divergent transcriptional programs (23 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470814</id><title>Distinct ribosome states trigger diverse mRNA quality control pathways (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.116323+00:00</updated><author><name>Anthony J. Veltri</name></author><author><name>Karole N. D’Orazio</name></author><author><name>Laura N. Lessen</name></author><author><name>Raphael Loll-Krippleber</name></author><author><name>Grant W. Brown</name></author><author><name>Rachel Green</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Key protein adapters couple translation to mRNA decay on specific classes of problematic mRNAs in eukaryotes. Slow decoding on non-optimal codons leads to codon-optimality-mediated decay (COMD) and prolonged arrest at stall sites leads to no-go decay (NGD). The identities of the decay factors underlying these processes and the mechanisms by which they respond to translational distress remain open areas of investigation. We use carefully-designed reporter mRNAs to perform genetic screens and functional assays in &lt;italic&gt;S. cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt;. We characterize the roles of Hel2 and Syh1 in coordinating translational repression and mRNA decay on NGD reporter mRNAs, finding that Syh1 acts as the primary link to mRNA decay in NGD. Importantly, we observe that these NGD factors are not involved in the degradation of mRNAs enriched in non-optimal codons. Further, we establish that a key factor previously implicated in COMD, Not5, contributes modestly to the degradation of an NGD-targeted mRNA. Finally, we use ribosome profiling to reveal distinct ribosomal states associated with each reporter mRNA that readily rationalize the contributions of NGD and COMD factors to degradation of these reporters. Taken together, these results provide new mechanistic insight into the role of Syh1 in NGD and define the molecular triggers that determine how distinct pathways target mRNAs for degradation in yeast.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470814" rel="alternate" title="Distinct ribosome states trigger diverse mRNA quality control pathways (20 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.468750</id><title>Emergence of planar cell polarity from the interplay of asymmetric interaction and tissue-level gradients (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.116542+00:00</updated><author><name>Divyoj Singh</name></author><author><name>Mohit Kumar Jolly</name></author><author><name>Mohd. Suhail Rizvi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Planar cell polarity (PCP) – asymmetric localization of proteins at cell-cell interface – is essential for embryonic development and physiological functions. Abnormalities in PCP can lead to neural tube closure defects, misalignment in hair follicles etc. Thus, decoding the mechanism responsible for PCP establishment and maintenance remains an open fundamental question. While various molecules – broadly classified into “global” and “local” modules – have been well investigated, their necessity and sufficiency in explaining PCP and connecting their perturbations and defects in experimentally observed patterns has not been examined. Here, we develop a minimal model that captures the proposed features of these two modules- a &lt;italic&gt;global&lt;/italic&gt; tissue level gradient and &lt;italic&gt;local&lt;/italic&gt; asymmetric distribution of protein complexes. Our model results suggest that while polarity can emerge in absence of a gradient, the gradient can provide the direction of polarity as well as offer robustness for maintenance of PCP in presence of stochastic perturbations. We also recapitulated swirling patterns (seen experimentally) and the features of non-domineering autonomy, using only three free parameters in the model - protein binding rate, concentration of proteins forming heterodimer across cell boundaries and steepness of gradient. Our results explain how self-stabilizing asymmetric localisations in presence of tissue-level gradient can lead to robust PCP patterns in diverse biological systems and reveals the minimal design principles for a polarized system.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.468750" rel="alternate" title="Emergence of planar cell polarity from the interplay of asymmetric interaction and tissue-level gradients (18 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470687</id><title>High Efficiency Recombinant Protein Purification Using mCherry and YFP Nanobody Affinity Matrices (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.116767+00:00</updated><author><name>Anh T.Q. Cong</name></author><author><name>Taylor L. Witter</name></author><author><name>Matthew J. Schellenberg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mammalian cell lines are important expression systems for large proteins and protein complexes, particularly when the acquisition of post-translational modifications in the protein’s native environment is desired. However, low or variable transfection efficiencies are challenges that must be overcome to use such an expression system. Expression of recombinant proteins as a fluorescent protein fusion enables real-time monitoring of protein expression, and also provides an affinity handle for one-step protein purification using a suitable affinity reagent. Here we describe a panel of anti-GFP and anti-mCherry nanobody affinity matrices and their efficacy for purification of GFP/YFP or mCherry fusion proteins. We define the molecular basis by which they bind their target protein using X-ray crystallography. From these analyses we define an optimal pair of nanobodies for purification of recombinant protein tagged with GFP/YFP or mCherry, and demonstrate these nanobody-sepharose supports are stable to many rounds of cleaning and extended incubation in denaturing conditions. Finally, we demonstrate the utility of the mCherry-tag system by using it to purify recombinant human Topoisomerase 2α expressed in HEK293F cells. The mCherry-tag and GFP/YFP-tag expression systems can be utilized for recombinant protein expression individually or in tandem for mammalian protein expression systems where real-time monitoring of protein expression levels and a high-efficiency purification step is needed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470687" rel="alternate" title="High Efficiency Recombinant Protein Purification Using mCherry and YFP Nanobody Affinity Matrices (16 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470441</id><title>The developing kidney actively negotiates geometric packing conflicts to avoid defects (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.117011+00:00</updated><author><name>Louis S. Prahl</name></author><author><name>John M. Viola</name></author><author><name>Jiageng Liu</name></author><author><name>Alex J. Hughes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The physiological functions of several organs rely on branched tubular networks, but little is known about conflicts in development between building enough tubules for adequate function and geometric constraints imposed by organ size. We show that the mouse embryonic kidney epithelium negotiates a physical packing conflict between tubule tip duplication and limited area at the organ surface. Imaging, computational, and soft material modeling of tubule ‘families’ identifies six geometric packing phases, including two defective ones. Experiments in kidney explants show that a retrograde tension on tubule families is necessary and sufficient for them to avoid defects by switching to a vertical orientation that increases packing density. These results reveal developmental contingencies in response to physical limitations, and create a framework for classifying kidney defects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Epithelial branching in the kidney causes a geometric packing conflict that is resolved through internally generated tensions&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470441" rel="alternate" title="The developing kidney actively negotiates geometric packing conflicts to avoid defects (15 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470738</id><title>Structure of Mycobacterium tuberculosis Cya, an evolutionary ancestor of the mammalian membrane adenylyl cyclases (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.117947+00:00</updated><author><name>Ved Mehta</name></author><author><name>Basavraj Khanppnavar</name></author><author><name>Dina Schuster</name></author><author><name>Irene Vercellino</name></author><author><name>Angela Kosturanova</name></author><author><name>Tarun Iype</name></author><author><name>Sasa Stefanic</name></author><author><name>Paola Picotti</name></author><author><name>Volodymyr M. Korkhov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; adenylyl cyclase (AC) Cya is an evolutionary ancestor of the mammalian membrane ACs and a model system for studies of their structure and function. Although the vital role of ACs in cellular signaling is well established, the function of their transmembrane (TM) regions remains unknown. Here we describe the cryo-EM structure of Cya bound to a stabilizing nanobody at 3.6 Å resolution. The TM helices 1-5 form a structurally conserved domain that facilitates the assembly of the helical and catalytic domains. The TM region contains discrete pockets accessible from the extracellular and cytosolic side of the membrane. Neutralization of the negatively charged extracellular pocket Ex1 destabilizes the cytosolic helical domain and reduces the catalytic activity of the enzyme. The TM domain acts as a functional component of Cya, guiding the assembly of the catalytic domain and providing the means for direct regulation of catalytic activity in response to extracellular ligands.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cryo-EM structure of &lt;italic&gt;M. tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; adenylyl cyclase Cya provides clues to the role of its transmembrane domain&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470738" rel="alternate" title="Structure of Mycobacterium tuberculosis Cya, an evolutionary ancestor of the mammalian membrane adenylyl cyclases (14 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470463</id><title>Spatiotemporal NF-κB dynamics encodes the position, amplitude and duration of local immune inputs (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.118299+00:00</updated><author><name>Minjun Son</name></author><author><name>Tino Frank</name></author><author><name>Thomas Holst-Hansen</name></author><author><name>Andrew Wang</name></author><author><name>Michael Junkin</name></author><author><name>Sara S Kashaf</name></author><author><name>Ala Trusina</name></author><author><name>Savaş Tay</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Infected cells communicate through secreted signaling molecules like cytokines, which inform nearby cells about the type, severity and location of pathogens. How differences in cytokine secretion affect inflammatory signaling over space and time, and how responding cells decode information from propagating cytokine signals are not understood. By computationally and experimentally studying NF-κB dynamics in co-cultures of signal sending cells (macrophages) and receiving cells (fibroblasts), we found that cytokine signals are transmitted by wave-like propagation of NF-κB activity and create well-defined cellular activation zones in a responding cell population. Remarkably, NF-κB dynamics in responding cells can simultaneously encode information about cytokine dose, duration, and distance to the cytokine source. Spatially-resolved transcriptional analysis revealed that responding cells transmit local cytokine information to distance specific pro-inflammatory gene expression patterns, creating “gene expression zones” in the population. Despite single-cell variability, the size and duration of the signaling zone is tightly controlled by the macrophage cytokine secretion profile. Our results highlight how macrophages tune their cytokine secretion dynamics to control signal transmission distance, and how NF-κB interprets these signals to coordinate inflammatory response in space and time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470463" rel="alternate" title="Spatiotemporal NF-κB dynamics encodes the position, amplitude and duration of local immune inputs (13 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470609</id><title>Rolling Circle RNA Synthesis Catalysed by RNA (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.118626+00:00</updated><author><name>Emil Laust Kristoffersen</name></author><author><name>Matthew Burman</name></author><author><name>Agnes Noy</name></author><author><name>Philipp Holliger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;RNA-catalysed RNA replication is widely considered a key step in the emergence of life’s first genetic system. However, RNA replication can be impeded by the extraordinary stability of duplex RNA products, which must be dissociated for re-initiation of the next replication cycle. Here we have explored rolling circle synthesis (RCS) as a potential solution to this strand separation problem. RCS on small circular RNAs - as indicated by molecular dynamics simulations - induces a progressive build-up of conformational strain with destabilisation of nascent strand 5’ and 3’ ends. At the same time, we observe sustained RCS by a triplet polymerase ribozyme on small circular RNAs over multiple orbits with strand displacement yielding concatemeric RNA products. Furthermore, we show RCS of a circular Hammerhead ribozyme capable of self-cleavage and re-circularisation. Thus, all steps of a viroid-like RNA replication pathway can be catalysed by RNA alone. Our results have implications for the emergence of RNA replication and for understanding the potential of RNA to support complex genetic processes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470609" rel="alternate" title="Rolling Circle RNA Synthesis Catalysed by RNA (11 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470669</id><title>Single-cell transcriptome reveals insights into the development and function of the zebrafish ovary (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.118906+00:00</updated><author><name>Yulong Liu</name></author><author><name>Michelle E. Kossack</name></author><author><name>Matthew E. Mcfaul</name></author><author><name>Lana N. Christensen</name></author><author><name>Stefan Siebert</name></author><author><name>Sydney R. Wyatt</name></author><author><name>Caramai Kamei</name></author><author><name>Samuel Horst</name></author><author><name>Nayeli Arroy</name></author><author><name>Iain Drummond</name></author><author><name>Celina E. Juliano</name></author><author><name>Bruce W. Draper</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Zebrafish are an established research organism that has made many contributions to our understanding of vertebrate tissue and organ development, yet there are still significant gaps in our understanding of the genes that regulate gonad development, sex, and reproduction. Unlike the development of many organs, such as the brain and heart that form during the first few days of development, zebrafish gonads do not begin to form until the larval stage ( ≥5 dpf). Thus, forward genetic screens have identified very few genes required for gonad development. In addition, bulk RNA sequencing studies which identify genes expressed in the gonads do not have the resolution necessary to define minor cell populations that may play significant roles in development and function of these organs. To overcome these limitations, we have used single-cell RNA sequencing to determine the transcriptomes of cells isolated from juvenile zebrafish ovaries. This resulted in the profiles of 10,658 germ cells and 14,431 somatic cells. Our germ cell data represents all developmental stages from germline stem cells to early meiotic oocytes. Our somatic cell data represents all known somatic cell types, including follicle cells, theca cells and interstitial stromal cells. Further analysis revealed an unexpected number of cell subpopulations within these broadly defined cell types. To further define their functional significance, we determined the location of these cell subpopulations within the ovary. Finally, for select examples, we used gene knockout experiments to determine the role of newly identified genes. Our results reveal novel insights into ovarian development and function and the sequencing information will provide a valuable resource for future studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470669" rel="alternate" title="Single-cell transcriptome reveals insights into the development and function of the zebrafish ovary (9 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471050</id><title>Regulation with cell size ensures mitochondrial DNA homeostasis during cell growth (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.119258+00:00</updated><author><name>Anika Seel</name></author><author><name>Francesco Padovani</name></author><author><name>Alissa Finster</name></author><author><name>Moritz Mayer</name></author><author><name>Daniela Bureik</name></author><author><name>Christof Osman</name></author><author><name>Till Klecker</name></author><author><name>Kurt M Schmoller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To maintain stable DNA concentrations, proliferating cells need to coordinate DNA replication with cell growth. For nuclear DNA, eukaryotic cells achieve this by coupling DNA replication to cell cycle progression, ensuring that DNA is doubled exactly once per cell cycle. By contrast, mitochondrial DNA replication is typically not strictly coupled to the cell cycle, leaving the open question of how cells maintain the correct amount of mitochondrial DNA during cell growth. Here, we show that in budding yeast, mitochondrial DNA copy number increases with cell volume, both in asynchronously cycling populations and during G1 arrest. Our findings suggest that cell-volume-dependent mitochondrial DNA maintenance is achieved through nuclear encoded limiting factors, including the mitochondrial DNA polymerase Mip1 and the packaging factor Abf2, whose amount increases in proportion to cell volume. By directly linking mitochondrial DNA maintenance to nuclear protein synthesis, and thus cell growth, constant mitochondrial DNA concentrations can be robustly maintained without a need for cell-cycle-dependent regulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471050" rel="alternate" title="Regulation with cell size ensures mitochondrial DNA homeostasis during cell growth (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471086</id><title>DExCon, DExogron, LUXon: on-demand expression control of endogenous genes reveals differential dynamics of Rab11 family members (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.121555+00:00</updated><author><name>Jakub Gemperle</name></author><author><name>Thomas Harrison</name></author><author><name>Chloe Flett</name></author><author><name>Antony D Adamson</name></author><author><name>Patrick T Caswell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;CRISPR technology has made generation of gene knockouts widely achievable in cells. However, once inactivated, their reactivation remains difficult, especially in diploid cells. Here, we present DExCon (Doxycycline-mediated endogenous gene Expression Control), DExogron (DExCon combined with auxin-mediated targeted protein degradation) and LUXon (light responsive DExCon), approaches which combine one-step CRISPR-Cas9 mediated targeted knock-in of fluorescent proteins with an advanced Tet-inducible TRE3GS promoter. These approaches combine blockade of active gene transcription with the ability to reactivate transcription on demand, including activation of silenced genes. Systematic control can be exerted using doxycycline or spatiotemporally by light, and we demonstrate functional knockout/rescue in the closely related Rab11 family of vesicle trafficking regulators. Fluorescent protein knock-in results in bright signals compatible with low-light live microscopy from monoallelic modification, the potential to simultaneously image different alleles of the same gene and bypasses the need to work with clones. Protein levels are easily tunable to correspond with endogenous expression through cell sorting (DExCon), timing of light illumination (LUXon) or by exposing cells to different levels of auxin (DExogron). Furthermore, our approach allowed us to quantify previously unforeseen differences in vesicle dynamics, expression kinetics and protein stability among highly similar endogenous Rab11 family members and their colocalization in triple knock-in cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471086" rel="alternate" title="DExCon, DExogron, LUXon: on-demand expression control of endogenous genes reveals differential dynamics of Rab11 family members (8 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471092</id><title>The structure of HiSiaQM defines the architecture of tripartite ATP-independent periplasmic (TRAP) transporters (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.121917+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin F. Peter</name></author><author><name>Peer Depping</name></author><author><name>Niels Schneberger</name></author><author><name>Emmanuele Severi</name></author><author><name>Karl Gatterdam</name></author><author><name>Sarah Tindall</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Durand</name></author><author><name>Veronika Heinz</name></author><author><name>Paul A. Koenig</name></author><author><name>Matthias Geyer</name></author><author><name>Christine Ziegler</name></author><author><name>Gavin H. Thomas</name></author><author><name>Gregor Hagelueken</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tripartite ATP-independent periplasmic (TRAP) transporters are widespread in bacteria and archaea and provide important uptake routes for many metabolites. They consist of three structural domains, a soluble substrate-binding protein (P-domain), and two transmembrane domains (Q- and M-domains) that form a functional unit. While the structures of the P-domains are well-known, an experimental structure of any QM-domain has been elusive. HiSiaPQM is a TRAP transporter for the monocarboxylate sialic acid, which plays a key role in the virulence of pathogenic bacteria. Here, we present the first cryo-electron microscopy structure of the membrane domains of HiSiaPQM reconstituted in lipid nanodiscs. The reconstruction reveals that TRAP transporters consist of 15 transmembrane helices and are structurally related to elevator-type transporters, such as GltPh and VcINDY. Whereas the latter proteins function as multimers, the idiosyncratic Q-domain of TRAP transporters enables the formation of a monomeric elevator architecture. Structural and mutational analyses together with an AlphaFold model of the tripartite (PQM) complex reveal the structural and conformational coupling of the substrate-binding protein to the transporter domains. Furthermore, we characterize high-affinity VHHs that bind to the periplasmic side of HiSiaQM and inhibit sialic acid uptake in vivo. Thereby, they also confirm the orientation of the protein in the membrane. Our study provides the first structure of any binding-protein dependent secondary transporter and provides starting points for the development of specific inhibitors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471092" rel="alternate" title="The structure of HiSiaQM defines the architecture of tripartite ATP-independent periplasmic (TRAP) transporters (7 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470734</id><title>Paracrine role for endothelial IGF-1 receptor in white adipocyte beiging (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.122355+00:00</updated><author><name>Natalie J Haywood</name></author><author><name>Katherine I Bridge</name></author><author><name>Cheukyau Luk</name></author><author><name>Nele Warmke</name></author><author><name>Katie J Simmons</name></author><author><name>Michael Drozd</name></author><author><name>Amy Moran</name></author><author><name>Sam Straw</name></author><author><name>Jason L Scragg</name></author><author><name>Jessica Smith</name></author><author><name>Sunti Limumpornpetch</name></author><author><name>Claire H Ozber</name></author><author><name>Chloe G Wilkinson</name></author><author><name>Anna Skromna</name></author><author><name>Natallia Makava</name></author><author><name>Andrew Walker</name></author><author><name>Nicole T Watt</name></author><author><name>Romana Mughal</name></author><author><name>Kathryn J Griffin</name></author><author><name>Hema Viswambharan</name></author><author><name>Nadira Y Yuldasheva</name></author><author><name>David J Beech</name></author><author><name>Piruthivi Sukumar</name></author><author><name>Antonio Vidal-Puig</name></author><author><name>Klaus K Witte</name></author><author><name>Stephen B Wheatcroft</name></author><author><name>Richard M Cubbon</name></author><author><name>Lee D Roberts</name></author><author><name>Mark T Kearney</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;There are at least two distinct types of thermogenic adipocyte in mammals: a pre-existing form established during development, termed classical brown adipocytes and an inducible form, ‘beige’ adipocytes&lt;sup&gt;1–3&lt;/sup&gt;. Various environmental cues can stimulate a process frequently referred to as ‘beiging’ of white adipose tissue (WAT), leading to enhanced thermogenesis and obesity resistance &lt;sup&gt;4, 5&lt;/sup&gt;. Whilst beiging of WAT as a therapeutic goal for obesity and obesity-related complications has attracted much attention&lt;sup&gt;6–9&lt;/sup&gt;; therapeutics stimulating beiging without deleterious side-effects remain elusive&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;. The endothelium lines all blood vessels and is therefore in close proximity to all cells. Many studies support the possibility that the endothelium acts as a paracrine organ&lt;sup&gt;11–14&lt;/sup&gt;. We explored the potential role of endothelial insulin-like growth factor-1 receptor (IGF-1R) as a paracrine modulator of WAT phenotype. Here we show that a reduction in endothelial IGF-1R expression in the presence of nutrient excess leads to white adipocyte beiging, increases whole-body energy expenditure and enhances insulin sensitivity via a non-cell autonomous paracrine mechanism. We demonstrate that this is mediated by endothelial release of malonic acid, which we show, using prodrug analogues, has potentially therapeutically-relevant properties in the treatment of metabolic disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470734" rel="alternate" title="Paracrine role for endothelial IGF-1 receptor in white adipocyte beiging (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470822</id><title>Allosteric Regulation of Human Plastins (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.123804+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher L. Schwebach</name></author><author><name>Elena Kudryashova</name></author><author><name>Richa Agrawal</name></author><author><name>Weili Zheng</name></author><author><name>Edward H. Egelman</name></author><author><name>Dmitri S. Kudryashov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Plastins/fimbrins are conserved actin-bundling proteins contributing to motility, cytokinesis, and other cellular processes by organizing actin assemblies of strikingly different geometries as in aligned bundles and branched networks. We propose that this unique ability stems from an allosteric communication between plastins’ two actin-binding domains (ABD1/2) engaged in a tight spatial association. We found that although ABD1 binds actin first, ABD2 can bind to actin three orders of magnitude stronger if not inhibited by an equally strong allosteric engagement with ABD1. Binding of ABD1 to actin lessened the inhibition, enabling weak bundling within aligned bundles. A mutation mimicking physiologically relevant phosphorylation at the ABD1-ABD2 interface strongly reduced their association, dramatically potentiating actin cross-linking. Cryo-EM reconstruction revealed the ABD1-actin interface and enabled modeling of the plastin bridge to confirm domain separation in parallel bundles. The characteristic domain organization with a strong allosteric inhibition imposed by ABD1 on ABD2 allows plastins to tune cross-linking, contributing to the assembly and remodeling of actin assemblies with different morphological and functional properties defining the unique place of plastins in actin organization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470822" rel="alternate" title="Allosteric Regulation of Human Plastins (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470303</id><title>Asgard ESCRT-III and VPS4 reveal evolutionary conserved chromatin binding properties of the ESCRT machinery (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.124768+00:00</updated><author><name>Dikla Nachmias</name></author><author><name>Nataly Melnikov</name></author><author><name>Alvah Zorea</name></author><author><name>Yasmin De-picchoto</name></author><author><name>Raz Zarivach</name></author><author><name>Itzhak Mizrahi</name></author><author><name>Natalie Elia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ESCRT machinery drive membrane remodeling in numerous processes in eukaryotes. Genes encoding for ESCRT proteins have been identified in Asgard archaea, a newly discovered superphylum, currently recognized as the ancestor of all eukaryotes. This begs the question of the functional evolutionary origin of this machinery and its conservation across lineages. Here, we find that Asgard-ESCRT’s exhibit conserved DNA-binding properties, which is derived from recruitment of specific members. We show that Asgard-ESCRT-III/VPS4 homologs interact with one another inside mammalian cells, associate with chromatin, and recruit their counterparts to organize in discrete foci in the mammalian nucleus. This is congruent with human-ESCRT-III homologs. We find that human- and Asgard-ESCRT-IIIs associate with chromatin via the same N terminal domain, and that human-ESCRT-III can recruit Asgard-VPS4 to the nucleus to form foci. Therefore, ESCRTs possess chromatin binding properties that were preserved through the billion years of evolution that separate Asgard and human cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470303" rel="alternate" title="Asgard ESCRT-III and VPS4 reveal evolutionary conserved chromatin binding properties of the ESCRT machinery (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471138</id><title>Plasmodium SAS4/CPAP is a flagellum basal body component during male gametogenesis but is not essential for parasite transmission (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.125421+00:00</updated><author><name>Mohammad Zeeshan</name></author><author><name>Declan Brady</name></author><author><name>Robert Markus</name></author><author><name>Sue Vaughan</name></author><author><name>David Ferguson</name></author><author><name>Anthony A Holder</name></author><author><name>Rita Tewari</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The centriole/basal body (CBB) is an evolutionarily conserved organelle acting as a microtubule organising centre (MTOC) to nucleate cilia, flagella and the centrosome. SAS4/CPAP is a conserved component associated with BB biogenesis in many model flagellated cells. Plasmodium, a divergent unicellular eukaryote and causative agent of malaria, displays an atypical closed mitosis with an MTOC, reminiscent of the acentriolar MTOC, embedded in the nuclear membrane at most proliferative stages. Mitosis during male gamete formation is accompanied by flagellum formation: within 15 minutes, genome replication (from 1N to 8N) and three successive rounds of mitosis without nuclear division occur, with coordinated axoneme biogenesis in the cytoplasm resulting in eight flagellated gametes. There are two MTOCs in male gametocytes. An acentriolar MTOC located with the nuclear envelope and a centriolar MTOC (basal body) located within the cytoplasm that are required for flagellum assembly. To study the location and function of SAS4 during this rapid process, we examined the spatial profile of SAS4 in real time by live cell imaging and its function by gene deletion. We show its absence during asexual proliferation but its presence and coordinated association and assembly of SAS4 with another basal body component, kinesin8B, which is involved in axoneme biogenesis. In contrast, its separation from the nuclear kinetochore marker NDC80 suggests that SAS4 is part of the basal body and outer centriolar MTOC residing in the cytoplasm. However, deletion of the SAS4 gene produced no phenotype, indicating that it is not essential for male gamete formation or parasite transmission through the mosquito.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471138" rel="alternate" title="Plasmodium SAS4/CPAP is a flagellum basal body component during male gametogenesis but is not essential for parasite transmission (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470571</id><title>CADHERIN mediated AMIS localisation (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.125740+00:00</updated><author><name>Xuan Liang</name></author><author><name>Antonia Weberling</name></author><author><name>Chun Yuan Hii</name></author><author><name>Magdalena Zernicka-Goetz</name></author><author><name>Clare Buckley</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Individual cells within &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; polarising tubes and cavities must integrate their forming apical domains into a centralised apical membrane initiation site (AMIS). This is necessary to enable organised lumen formation within multi-cellular tissue. Despite the well documented importance of cell division in localising the AMIS, we have found a division-independent mechanism of AMIS localisation that relies instead on CADHERIN-mediated cell-cell adhesion. Our study of &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; polarising mESCs suggest that cell-cell adhesion directs the localisation of apical proteins such as PAR-6 to a centralised AMIS. Unexpectedly, we also found that mESC cell clusters lacking functional E-CADHERIN were still able to form a lumen-like cavity in the absence of AMIS localisation and did so at a later stage of development via a ‘closure’ mechanism, instead of via hollowing. This work suggests that there are two, interrelated mechanisms of apical polarity localisation: cell adhesion and cell division. Alignment of these mechanisms allows for redundancy in the system and ensures the localisation of a coherent epithelial structure within a growing organ.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470571" rel="alternate" title="CADHERIN mediated AMIS localisation (4 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.471005</id><title>In vitro neurons learn and exhibit sentience when embodied in a simulated game-world (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.126000+00:00</updated><author><name>Brett J. Kagan</name></author><author><name>Andy C. Kitchen</name></author><author><name>Nhi Thao Tran</name></author><author><name>Bradyn J. Parker</name></author><author><name>Anjali Bhat</name></author><author><name>Ben Rollo</name></author><author><name>Adeel Razi</name></author><author><name>Karl Friston</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Integrating neurons into digital systems to leverage their innate intelligence may enable performance infeasible with silicon alone, along with providing insight into the cellular origin of intelligence. We developed DishBrain, a system which exhibits natural intelligence by harnessing the inherent adaptive computation of neurons in a structured environment. In vitro neural networks from human or rodent origins, are integrated with in silico computing via high-density multielectrode array. Through electrophysiological stimulation and recording, cultures were embedded in a simulated game-world, mimicking the arcade game 'Pong'. Applying a previously untestable theory of active inference via the Free Energy Principle, we found that learning was apparent within five minutes of real-time gameplay, not observed in control conditions. Further experiments demonstrate the importance of closed-loop structured feedback in eliciting learning over time. Cultures display the ability to self-organise in a goal-directed manner in response to sparse sensory information about the consequences of their actions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.471005" rel="alternate" title="In vitro neurons learn and exhibit sentience when embodied in a simulated game-world (3 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470847</id><title>CRISPR gene-drive systems based on Cas9 nickases promote super-Mendelian inheritance in Drosophila (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.126292+00:00</updated><author><name>Víctor López Del Amo</name></author><author><name>Sara Sanz Juste</name></author><author><name>Valentino M. Gantz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;CRISPR-based gene drive systems can be used to modify entire wild populations due to their ability to bias their own inheritance towards super-Mendelian rates (&amp;gt;100%). Current gene drives contain a Cas9 and a gRNA gene inserted at the location targeted by the gRNA. These gene products are able to cut the opposing wildtype allele, and lead to its replacement with a copy of the gene drive through the homology-directed DNA repair pathway. When this allelic conversion occurs in the germline it leads to the preferential inheritance of the engineered allele — a property that has been proposed to disseminate engineered traits for managing disease-transmitting mosquito populations. Here, we report a novel gene-drive strategy relying on Cas9 nickases which operates by generating staggered paired-nicks in the DNA to promote propagation of the gene drive allele. We show that only when 5’ overhangs are generated, the system efficiently leads to allelic conversion. Further, the nickase gene-drive arrangement produces large stereotyped deletions, providing potential advantages for targeting essential genes. Indeed, the nickase-gene-drive design should expand the options available for gene drive designs aimed at applications in mosquitoes and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470847" rel="alternate" title="CRISPR gene-drive systems based on Cas9 nickases promote super-Mendelian inheritance in Drosophila (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470700</id><title>Transcription factor competition facilitates self-sustained oscillations in single gene genetic circuits (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.126543+00:00</updated><author><name>Jasper Landman</name></author><author><name>Sjoerd M. Verduyn Lunel</name></author><author><name>Willem K. Kegel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genetic feedback loops can be used by cells as a means to regulate internal processes or keep track of time. It is often thought that, for a genetic circuit to display self-sustained oscillations, a degree of cooperativity is needed in the binding and unbinding of actor species. This cooperativity is usually modeled using a Hill function, regardless of the actual promoter architecture. Moreover, genetic circuits do not operate in isolation and often transcription factors are shared between different promoters. In this work we show how mathematical modelling of genetic feedback loops can be facilitated with a mechanistic fold-change function that takes into account the titration effect caused by competing binding sites for transcription factors. The model shows how the titration effect aids self-sustained oscillations in a minimal genetic feedback loop: a gene that produces its own repressor directly — without cooperative transcription factor binding. The use of delay-differential equations leads to a stability contour that predicts whether a genetic feedback loop will show self-sustained oscillations, even when taking the bursty nature of transcription into account.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470700" rel="alternate" title="Transcription factor competition facilitates self-sustained oscillations in single gene genetic circuits (3 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470691</id><title>Label-free characterisation of amyloids and alpha-Synuclein polymorphs by exploiting their intrinsic fluorescence property (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.126928+00:00</updated><author><name>Chyi Wei Chung</name></author><author><name>Amberley D. Stephens</name></author><author><name>Edward Ward</name></author><author><name>Yuqing Feng</name></author><author><name>Molly Jo Davis</name></author><author><name>Clemens F. Kaminski</name></author><author><name>Gabriele S. Kaminski Schierle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Conventional &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; aggregation assays often involve tagging with extrinsic fluorophores which can interfere with aggregation. We propose the use of intrinsic amyloid fluorescence lifetime probed using two-photon excitation and represented by model-free phasor plots, as a label-free assay to characterise amyloid structure. Intrinsic amyloid fluorescence arises from structured packing of β-sheets in amyloids and is independent of aromatic-based fluorescence. We show that different amyloids (i.e., α-Synuclein (αS), β-Lactoglobulin and TasA) and different polymorphic populations of αS (induced by aggregation in salt-free and salt buffers mimicking the intra-/extracellular environments) can be differentiated by their unique fluorescence lifetimes. Moreover, we observe that disaggregation of pre-formed fibrils of αS and βLG leads to increased fluorescence lifetimes, distinct to those of their fibrillar counterpart. Our assay presents a medium-throughput method for rapid classification of amyloids and their polymorphs (the latter of which recent studies have shown lead to different disease pathology), and for testing small molecule inhibitory compounds.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470691" rel="alternate" title="Label-free characterisation of amyloids and alpha-Synuclein polymorphs by exploiting their intrinsic fluorescence property (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470632</id><title>Deciphering the Molecular Mechanism of HCV Protease Inhibitor Fluorination as a General Approach to Avoid Drug Resistance (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.127103+00:00</updated><author><name>Jacqueto Zephyr</name></author><author><name>Desaboini Nageswara Rao</name></author><author><name>Sang V. Vo</name></author><author><name>Mina Henes</name></author><author><name>Klajdi Kosovrasti</name></author><author><name>Ashley N. Matthew</name></author><author><name>Adam K. Hedger</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Timm</name></author><author><name>Elise T. Chan</name></author><author><name>Akbar Ali</name></author><author><name>Nese Kurt Yilmaz</name></author><author><name>Celia A. Schiffer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Third generation Hepatitis C virus (HCV) NS3/4A protease inhibitors (PIs), glecaprevir and voxilaprevir, are highly effective across genotypes and against many resistant variants. Unlike earlier PIs, these compounds have fluorine substitutions on the P2-P4 macrocycle and P1 moieties. Fluorination has long been used in medicinal chemistry as a strategy to improve physicochemical properties and potency. However, the molecular basis by which fluorination improves potency and resistance profile of HCV NS3/4A PIs is not well understood. To systematically analyze the contribution of fluorine substitutions to inhibitor potency and resistance profile, we used a multi-disciplinary approach involving inhibitor design and synthesis, enzyme inhibition assays, co-crystallography, and structural analysis. A panel of inhibitors in matched pairs were designed with and without P4 cap fluorination, tested against WT protease and the D168A resistant variant, and a total of 22 high-resolution co-crystal structures were determined. While fluorination did not significantly improve potency against the WT protease, PIs with fluorinated P4 caps retained much better potency against the D168A protease variant. Detailed analysis of the co-crystal structures revealed that PIs with fluorinated P4 caps can sample alternate binding conformations that enable adapting to structural changes induced by the D168A substitution. Our results elucidate molecular mechanisms of fluorine-specific inhibitor interactions that can be leveraged in avoiding drug resistance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470632" rel="alternate" title="Deciphering the Molecular Mechanism of HCV Protease Inhibitor Fluorination as a General Approach to Avoid Drug Resistance (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470885</id><title>A versatile new ubiquitin detection and purification tool derived from a bacterial deubiquitylase (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.127292+00:00</updated><author><name>Mengwen Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jason M. Berk</name></author><author><name>Adrian B. Mehrtash</name></author><author><name>Jean Kanyo</name></author><author><name>Mark Hochstrasser</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protein ubiquitylation is an important post-translational modification affecting an wide range of cellular processes. Due to the low abundance of ubiquitylated species in biological samples, considerable effort has been spent on developing methods to purify and detect ubiquitylated proteins. We have developed and characterized a novel tool for ubiquitin detection and purification based on OtUBD, a high-affinity ubiquitin-binding domain derived from an &lt;italic&gt;Orientia tsutsugamushi&lt;/italic&gt; deubiquitylase. We demonstrate that OtUBD can be used to purify both monoubiquitylated and polyubiquitylated substrates from yeast and human tissue culture samples and compare their performance with existing methods. Importantly, we found conditions for either selective purification of covalently ubiquitylated proteins or co-isolation of both ubiquitylated proteins and their interacting proteins. As a proof-of-principle for these newly developed methods, we profiled the ubiquitylome and ubiquitin-associated proteome of the yeast &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt;. Combining OtUBD affinity purification with quantitative proteomics, we identified potential substrates for E3 ligases Bre1 and Pib1. OtUBD provides a versatile, efficient, and economical tool for ubiquitin researchers with specific advantages over other methods, such as in detecting monoubiquitylation or ubiquitin linkages to noncanonical sites.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470885" rel="alternate" title="A versatile new ubiquitin detection and purification tool derived from a bacterial deubiquitylase (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470899</id><title>Structural basis of dynamic P5CS filaments (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.127441+00:00</updated><author><name>Jiale Zhong</name></author><author><name>Chen-Jun Guo</name></author><author><name>Xian Zhou</name></author><author><name>Chia-Chun Chang</name></author><author><name>Boqi Yin</name></author><author><name>Tianyi Zhang</name></author><author><name>Huan-Huan Hu</name></author><author><name>Guang-Ming Lu</name></author><author><name>Ji-Long Liu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The bifunctional enzyme Δ&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;-pyrroline-5-carboxylate synthase (P5CS) is central to the synthesis of proline and ornithine. Pathogenic mutations in P5CS gene (ALDH18A1) lead to neurocutaneous syndrome and skin relaxation connective tissue disease in humans, and P5CS deficiency seriously damages the ability to resist adversity in plants, which has an essential role in agriculture and human health. Recently, P5CS has been demonstrated forming the cytoophidium in vivo and filaments in vitro. However, the underlying mechanism for the function of P5CS filamentation and catalyze the synthesis of P5C is hardly accessible without structural basis. Here, we have succeeded in determining the full-length structures of &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; P5CS filament in three states at resolution from 3.1 to 4.3 Å under cryo-electron microscopy, we observed the distinct ligand-binding states and conformational changes for GK and GPR domain separately. These structures show the distinctive spiral filament is assembled by P5CS tetramers and stabilized by multiple interfaces. Point mutations that deplete such interactions disturb P5CS filamentation and greatly reduce the activity. Our findings reveal a previously undescribed mechanism that filamentation is crucial for the coordination between GK and GPR domains, and provide insights into structural basis for catalysis function of P5CS filament.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470899" rel="alternate" title="Structural basis of dynamic P5CS filaments (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>