<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.961425+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469088</id><title>Structural basis for Cas9 off-target activity (117 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.961888+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Pacesa</name></author><author><name>Chun-Han Lin</name></author><author><name>Antoine Cléry</name></author><author><name>Katja Bargsten</name></author><author><name>Matthew J. Irby</name></author><author><name>Frédéric H.T. Allain</name></author><author><name>Peter Cameron</name></author><author><name>Paul D. Donohoue</name></author><author><name>Martin Jinek</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The target DNA specificity of the CRISPR-associated genome editor nuclease Cas9 is determined by complementarity to a 20-nucleotide segment in its guide RNA. However, Cas9 can bind and cleave partially complementary off-target sequences, which raises safety concerns for its use in clinical applications. Here we report crystallographic structures of Cas9 bound to &lt;italic&gt;bona fide&lt;/italic&gt; off-target substrates, revealing that off-target binding is enabled by a range of non-canonical base pairing interactions and preservation of base stacking within the guide–off-target heteroduplex. Off-target sites containing single-nucleotide deletions relative to the guide RNA are accommodated by base skipping rather than RNA bulge formation. Additionally, PAM-distal mismatches result in duplex unpairing and induce a conformational change of the Cas9 REC lobe that perturbs its conformational activation. Together, these insights provide a structural rationale for the off-target activity of Cas9 and contribute to the improved rational design of guide RNAs and off-target prediction algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469088" rel="alternate" title="Structural basis for Cas9 off-target activity (117 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469005</id><title>Robust temporal map of human in vitro myelopoiesis using single-cell genomics (33 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.962352+00:00</updated><author><name>Clara Alsinet</name></author><author><name>Maria Primo</name></author><author><name>Valentina Lorenzi</name></author><author><name>Andrew J Knights</name></author><author><name>Carmen Sancho-Serra</name></author><author><name>Jong-Eun Park</name></author><author><name>Beata S Wyspianska</name></author><author><name>David F Tough</name></author><author><name>Damiana Alvarez</name></author><author><name>Daniel J Gaffney</name></author><author><name>Roser Vento-Tormo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Myeloid cells have a central role in homeostasis and tissue defence. Characterising the current in vitro protocols of myelopoiesis is imperative for their use in research and immunotherapy as well as for understanding the early stages of myeloid differentiation in humans. Here, we profiled the transcriptome of more than 400k cells and generated a robust molecular map of the differentiation of human induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSC) into macrophages. By integrating our in vitro datasets with in vivo single-cell developmental atlases, we found that in vitro macrophage differentiation recapitulates features of in vivo yolk sac hematopoiesis, which happens prior to the appearance of definitive hematopoietic stem cells (HSC). During in vitro myelopoiesis, a wide range of myeloid cells are generated, including erythrocytes, mast cells and monocytes, suggesting that, during early human development, the HSC-independent immune wave gives rise to multiple myeloid cell lineages. We leveraged this model to characterize the transition of hemogenic endothelium into myeloid cells, uncovering poorly described myeloid progenitors and regulatory programs. Taking advantage of the variety of myeloid cells produced, we developed a new protocol to produce type 2 conventional dendritic cells (cDC2) in vitro. We found that the underlying regulatory networks coding for myeloid identity are conserved in vivo and in vitro. Using genetic engineering techniques, we validated the effects of key transcription factors important for cDC2 and macrophage identity and ontogeny. This roadmap of early myeloid differentiation will serve as an important resource for investigating the initial stages of hematopoiesis, which are largely unexplored in humans, and will open up new therapeutic opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469005" rel="alternate" title="Robust temporal map of human in vitro myelopoiesis using single-cell genomics (33 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468712</id><title>Structures of the Cyanobacterial Phycobilisome (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.962571+00:00</updated><author><name>Paul V. Sauer</name></author><author><name>Maria Agustina Dominguez-Martin</name></author><author><name>Henning Kirst</name></author><author><name>Markus Sutter</name></author><author><name>David Bina</name></author><author><name>Basil J. Greber</name></author><author><name>Eva Nogales</name></author><author><name>Tomáš Polívka</name></author><author><name>Cheryl A. Kerfeld</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The phycobilisome is an elaborate antenna that is responsible for light-harvesting in cyanobacteria and red-algae. This large macromolecular complex captures incident sunlight and transfers the energy via a network of pigment molecules called bilins to the photosynthetic reaction centers. The phycobilisome of the model organism Synechocystis PCC 6803 consists of a core to which six rods are attached but its detailed molecular architecture and regulation in response to environmental conditions is not well understood. Here we present cryo-electron microscopy structures of the 6.2 MDa phycobilisome from Synechocystis PCC 6803 resolved at 2.1 Å (rods) to 2.7 Å (core), revealing three distinct conformations, two previously unknown. We found that two of the rods are mobile and can switch conformation within the complex, revealing a layer of regulation not described previously. In addition, we found a novel linker protein in the structure, that may represent a long-sought subunit that tethers the phycobilisome to the thylakoid membrane. Finally, we show how excitation energy is transferred within the phycobilisome and correlate our structures with known spectroscopic properties. Together, our results provide detailed insights into the biophysical underpinnings of cyanobacterial light harvesting and lay the foundation for bioengineering of future phycobilisome variants and artificial light harvesting systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468712" rel="alternate" title="Structures of the Cyanobacterial Phycobilisome (29 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.468884</id><title>A glycerol shunt functions as a glucose excess security valve in pancreatic β-cells (28 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.962880+00:00</updated><author><name>Anfal Al-Mass</name></author><author><name>Pegah Poursharifi</name></author><author><name>Marie-Line Peyot</name></author><author><name>Roxane Lussier</name></author><author><name>Emily J Levens</name></author><author><name>Julian Guida</name></author><author><name>Yves Mugabo</name></author><author><name>Elite Possik</name></author><author><name>Rasheed Ahmad</name></author><author><name>Fahd Al-Mulla</name></author><author><name>Rob Sladek</name></author><author><name>S.R.Murthy Madiraju</name></author><author><name>Marc Prentki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The recently identified glycerol-3-phosphate (Gro3P) phosphatase (G3PP) in mammalian cells, encoded by the PGP gene, was shown to regulate intermediary metabolism by hydrolyzing Gro3P and to control glucose-stimulated insulin secretion (GSIS) in β-cells, in vitro. We now examined in inducible β-cell specific G3PP-KO (BKO) mice, the role of G3PP in the control of insulin secretion in vivo, β-cell function and glucotoxicity. BKO mice, compared to MCre controls, showed increased body weight, adiposity, fed insulinemia, GSIS, reduced plasma triglycerides and mildly altered glucose tolerance. Isolated BKO mouse islets at high (16.7 mM) but not low or intermediate glucose (3-8 mM) showed elevated GSIS, Gro3P, metabolites reflecting β-cell activation, O2 consumption, ATP production and reduced glycerol release. BKO islets chronically exposed to elevated glucose showed increased apoptosis, reduced insulin content and expression of Pdx-1, MafA and Ins-2 genes. As G3PP channels glucose carbons towards glycerol formation and release, the results demonstrate that β-cell are endowed with a glycerol shunt acting as a glucose excess security valve. We propose that the glycerol shunt plays a role in glucodetoxification, the prevention of insulin hypersecretion, acts as a defense against excess body weight gain and contributes to β-cell mass preservation in the face of hyperglycemia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.468884" rel="alternate" title="A glycerol shunt functions as a glucose excess security valve in pancreatic β-cells (28 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468719</id><title>Structure of the Quenched Cyanobacterial OCP-Phycobilisome Complex (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.963259+00:00</updated><author><name>Maria Agustina Dominguez-Martin</name></author><author><name>Paul V. Sauer</name></author><author><name>Markus Sutter</name></author><author><name>Henning Kirst</name></author><author><name>David Bina</name></author><author><name>Basil J. Greber</name></author><author><name>Eva Nogales</name></author><author><name>Tomáš Polívka</name></author><author><name>Cheryl A. Kerfeld</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Photoprotection is an essential mechanism in photosynthetic organisms to balance the harvesting of light energy against the risks of photodamage. In cyanobacteria, photoprotective non-photochemical quenching relies on the interaction between a photoreceptor, the Orange Carotenoid Protein (OCP), and the antenna, the phycobilisome (PBS). Here we report the first structure of the OCP-PBS complex at 2.7 Å overall resolution obtained by cryo-electron microscopy. The structure shows that the 6.2 MDa PBS is quenched by four 34 kDa OCP organized as two dimers. The complex also reveals that the structure of the active form of the OCP is drastically different than its resting, non-quenching form, with an ∼60 Å displacement of its regulatory domain. These results provide a high-resolution blueprint of the structural basis of the protective quenching of excess excitation energy that enables cyanobacteria to harvest light energy and fix CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; across environmentally diverse and dynamic surface of our planet.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468719" rel="alternate" title="Structure of the Quenched Cyanobacterial OCP-Phycobilisome Complex (24 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468613</id><title>Live imaging of the co-translational recruitment of XBP1 mRNA to the ER and its processing by diffuse, non-polarized IRE1α (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.963578+00:00</updated><author><name>Silvia Gómez-Puerta</name></author><author><name>Roberto Ferrero</name></author><author><name>Tobias Hochstoeger</name></author><author><name>Ivan Zubiri</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey A. Chao</name></author><author><name>Tomás Aragón</name></author><author><name>Franka Voigt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Endoplasmic reticulum (ER) to nucleus homeostatic signalling, known as the unfolded protein response (UPR), relies on the non-canonical splicing of XBP1 mRNA. The molecular switch that initiates splicing is the oligomerization of the ER stress sensor and UPR endonuclease IRE1α. While IRE1α can form large clusters that have been proposed to function as XBP1 processing centers on the ER, the actual oligomeric state of active IRE1α complexes as well as the targeting mechanism that recruits XBP1 to IRE1α oligomers, remain unknown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we used a single molecule imaging approach to directly monitor the recruitment of individual XBP1 transcripts to the ER surface. We confirmed that stable ER association of unspliced XBP1 mRNA is established through HR2-dependent targeting and relies on active translation. In addition, we show that IRE1α-catalyzed splicing mobilizes XBP1 mRNA from the ER membrane in response to ER stress. Surprisingly, we find that XBP1 transcripts are not recruited into large IRE1α clusters, which only assemble upon overexpression of fluorescently-tagged IRE1α during ER stress. Our findings support a model where ribosome-engaged, ER-poised XBP1 mRNA is processed by functional IRE1α assemblies that are homogenously distributed throughout the ER membrane.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468613" rel="alternate" title="Live imaging of the co-translational recruitment of XBP1 mRNA to the ER and its processing by diffuse, non-polarized IRE1α (22 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468614</id><title>Wolbachia endosymbionts in two Anopheles species indicates independent acquisitions and lack of prophage elements (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.966390+00:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quek</name></author><author><name>Louise Cerdeira</name></author><author><name>Claire L Jeffries</name></author><author><name>Sean Tomlinson</name></author><author><name>Thomas Walker</name></author><author><name>Grant L. Hughes</name></author><author><name>Eva Heinz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; is a genus of obligate bacterial endosymbionts that infect a diverse range of arthropod species as well as filarial nematodes, with its single described species, &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia pipientis,&lt;/italic&gt; divided into several ‘supergroups’ based on multilocus sequence typing. &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; strains in mosquitoes have been shown to inhibit the transmission of human pathogens including &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium&lt;/italic&gt; malaria parasites and arboviruses. Despite their large host range, &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; strains within the major malaria vectors of the &lt;italic&gt;Anopheles (A.) gambiae&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;A. funestus&lt;/italic&gt; complexes appear at low density based solely on PCR-based methods. Questions have been raised as to whether this represents a true endosymbiotic relationship. However, recent definitive evidence for two distinct, high-density strains of supergroup B &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; within &lt;italic&gt;A. demeilloni&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;A. moucheti&lt;/italic&gt; has opened exciting possibilities to explore naturally occurring &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; endosymbionts in &lt;italic&gt;Anopheles&lt;/italic&gt; for biocontrol strategies to block &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium&lt;/italic&gt; transmission. Here we utilise genomic analyses to demonstrate that both &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; strains have retained all key metabolic and transport pathways despite their smaller genome size. We further confirm the presence of cytoplasmic incompatibility factor genes, despite noticeably few prophage regions. Additionally, phylogenetic analysis indicates that these &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; strains may have been introduced into these two &lt;italic&gt;Anopheles&lt;/italic&gt; species via horizontal transmission events, and unlikely to be by ancestral acquisition and subsequent loss events in the &lt;italic&gt;Anopheles gambiae&lt;/italic&gt; species complex. These are the first &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; genomes that enable us to study the relationship between natural strains &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium&lt;/italic&gt; malaria parasites and their &lt;italic&gt;Anopheline&lt;/italic&gt; hosts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Impact statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; naturally infects a wide range of arthropod species, including insect vectors of human pathogens, where they may play a role in inhibiting their replication. These bacteria have been commonly found within &lt;italic&gt;Aedes (Ae.) albopictus&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Culex pipiens&lt;/italic&gt; mosquitoes but have been noticeably absent in the &lt;italic&gt;Anopheles&lt;/italic&gt; mosquito genera, which includes all species responsible for malaria transmission. Recent PCR-based methods have suggested the potential for natural &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; strains within the &lt;italic&gt;A. gambiae&lt;/italic&gt; species complex, which includes major malaria vector species including &lt;italic&gt;A. gambiae&lt;/italic&gt; s.s., &lt;italic&gt;A. coluzzii&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;A. arabiensis&lt;/italic&gt;. We recently reported the presence of stable &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; strains naturally occurring within two different &lt;italic&gt;Anopheles&lt;/italic&gt; species (&lt;italic&gt;A. demeilloni&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;A. moucheti)&lt;/italic&gt;. In this study, we perform comparative genomic analysis of these two &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; genomes against each other and published &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; strains. The current assemblies are some of the smallest sequenced &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; strains of insects, although their metabolic pathway repertoire is comparable to other strains. Interestingly, prophage fragments were identified within only one of the two strains. The findings of this study will be of significant interest to researchers investigating &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; as a potential malaria biocontrol strategy, giving greater insight into the evolution and diversity of this obligate intracellular endosymbiont.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Data summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sequence data generated and used for this analysis are available in the National Centre for Biotechnology Information Sequence Read Archive (NCBI SRA bioproject number PRJNA642000). The two assembled &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; genomes are available with genome accession numbers GCA_018491735.2 and GCA_018491625.2. Additional &lt;italic&gt;Wolbachia&lt;/italic&gt; genomes used for comparative analysis are described in the supplementary material.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The authors confirm all supporting data, code and protocols have been provided within the article or through supplementary data files. Additional supplementary data files used to generate several figures can be found at: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://figshare.com/projects/Wolbachia_endosymbionts_in_two_Anopheles_species_indicates_independent_acquisitions_and_lack_of_prophage_elements/126533"&gt;https://figshare.com/projects/Wolbachia_endosymbionts_in_two_Anopheles_species_indicates_independent_acquisitions_and_lack_of_prophage_elements/126533&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468614" rel="alternate" title="Wolbachia endosymbionts in two Anopheles species indicates independent acquisitions and lack of prophage elements (21 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468548</id><title>Reconstitution of Spiroplasma swimming by expressing two bacterial actins in synthetic minimal bacterium (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.966739+00:00</updated><author><name>Hana Kiyama</name></author><author><name>Shigeyuki Kakizawa</name></author><author><name>Yuya Sasajima</name></author><author><name>Yuhei O Tahara</name></author><author><name>Makoto Miyata</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Motility is one of the most important features of life, but its evolutionary origin is still unknown. Here, we focus on &lt;italic&gt;Spiroplasma&lt;/italic&gt;, commensal or parasitic bacteria. They swim by the helicity switching of a ribbon-like cytoskeleton composed of six proteins each evolved from a nucleosidase and a bacterial actin called MreB. We expressed these proteins in a synthetic minimal bacterium, JCVI-syn3B whose genome was computer-designed and chemically synthesized. The synthetic bacterium showed swimming motility with the features common with &lt;italic&gt;Spiroplasma&lt;/italic&gt; swimming. Moreover, some combinations of two proteins showed helical cell shape and swimming, suggesting that the swimming was originated from differentiation and coupling of the bacterial actin.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Expression of two bacterial actins gave cell helicity and swimming to a synthetic minimal cell.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468548" rel="alternate" title="Reconstitution of Spiroplasma swimming by expressing two bacterial actins in synthetic minimal bacterium (21 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468694</id><title>Structure and functionality of a multimeric human COQ7:COQ9 complex (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.966915+00:00</updated><author><name>Mateusz Manicki</name></author><author><name>Halil Aydin</name></author><author><name>Luciano A. Abriata</name></author><author><name>Katherine A. Overmyer</name></author><author><name>Rachel M. Guerra</name></author><author><name>Joshua J. Coon</name></author><author><name>Matteo Dal Peraro</name></author><author><name>Adam Frost</name></author><author><name>David J. Pagliarini</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Coenzyme Q (CoQ, ubiquinone) is a redox-active lipid essential for core metabolic pathways and antioxidant defense. CoQ is synthesized upon the mitochondrial inner membrane by an ill-defined ‘complex Q’ metabolon. Here we present a structure and functional analyses of a substrate- and NADH-bound oligomeric complex comprised of two complex Q subunits: the hydroxylase COQ7, which performs the penultimate step in CoQ biosynthesis, and the prenyl lipid-binding protein COQ9. We reveal that COQ7 adopts a modified ferritin-like fold with an extended hydrophobic access channel whose substrate binding capacity is enhanced by COQ9. Using molecular dynamics simulations, we further show that two COQ7:COQ9 heterodimers form a curved tetramer that deforms the membrane, potentially opening a pathway for CoQ intermediates to translocate from within the bilayer to the proteins’ lipid-binding sites. Two such tetramers assemble into a soluble octamer, closed like a capsid, with lipids captured within. Together, these observations indicate that COQ7 and COQ9 cooperate to access hydrophobic precursors and coordinate subsequent synthesis steps toward producing mature CoQ.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468694" rel="alternate" title="Structure and functionality of a multimeric human COQ7:COQ9 complex (20 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.468982</id><title>Activating silent glycolysis bypasses in Escherichia coli (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.967096+00:00</updated><author><name>Camillo Iacometti</name></author><author><name>Katharina Marx</name></author><author><name>Maria Hönick</name></author><author><name>Viktoria Biletskaia</name></author><author><name>Helena Schulz-Mirbach</name></author><author><name>Ari Satanowski</name></author><author><name>Beau Dronsella</name></author><author><name>Valérie A. Delmas</name></author><author><name>Anne Berger</name></author><author><name>Ivan Dubois</name></author><author><name>Madeleine Bouzon</name></author><author><name>Volker Döring</name></author><author><name>Elad Noor</name></author><author><name>Arren Bar-Even</name></author><author><name>Steffen N. Lindner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;All living organisms share similar reactions within their central metabolism to provide precursors for all essential building blocks and reducing power. To identify whether alternative metabolic routes of glycolysis can operate in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;, we complementarily employed &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; design, rational engineering, and adaptive laboratory evolution. First, we used a genome-scale model and identified two potential pathways within the metabolic network of this organism replacing canonical Embden-Meyerhof-Parnas (EMP) glycolysis to convert phosphosugars into organic acids. One of these glycolytic routes proceeds via methylglyoxal, the other via serine biosynthesis and degradation. Then, we implemented both pathways in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; strains harboring defective EMP glycolysis. Surprisingly, the pathway via methylglyoxal immediately operated in a triosephosphate isomerase deletion strain cultivated on glycerol. By contrast, in a phosphoglycerate kinase deletion strain, the overexpression of methylglyoxal synthase was necessary for implementing a functional methylglyoxal pathway. Furthermore, we engineered the ‘serine shunt’ which converts 3-phosphoglycerate via serine biosynthesis and degradation to pyruvate, bypassing an enolase deletion. Finally, to explore which of these alternatives would emerge by natural selection we performed an adaptive laboratory evolution study using an enolase deletion strain. The evolved mutants were shown to use the serine shunt. Our study reveals the flexible repurposing of metabolic pathways to create new metabolite links and rewire central metabolism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.468982" rel="alternate" title="Activating silent glycolysis bypasses in Escherichia coli (20 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468975</id><title>Recognition and deubiquitination of free 40S for translational reset by Otu2 (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.967917+00:00</updated><author><name>Ken Ikeuchi</name></author><author><name>Nives Ivic</name></author><author><name>Jingdong Cheng</name></author><author><name>Robert Buschauer</name></author><author><name>Yoshitaka Matsuo</name></author><author><name>Thomas Fröhlich</name></author><author><name>Otto Berninghausen</name></author><author><name>Toshifumi Inada</name></author><author><name>Thomas Becker</name></author><author><name>Roland Beckmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In actively translating 80S ribosomes the ribosomal protein eS7 of the 40S subunit is monoubiquitinated by the E3 ligase Not4&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt; and deubiquitinated by the deubiquitination enzyme Otu2 upon ribosomal subunit recycling&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;. Despite its importance for general efficiency of translation the exact role and structural basis for this specific translational reset are only poorly understood. Here we present biochemical and structural data showing that Otu2 can engage the recycled 40S subunit together with the recycling factors ABCE1 and Tma64 immediately after 60S dissociation for mRNA recycling, and that it dissociates before 48S initiation complex formation. A combined structural analysis of Otu2 and Otu2-40S complexes by X-ray crystallography, AlphaFold2 prediction&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; and cryo-EM revealed how Otu2 can specifically be recruited to the 40S, but not to the 80S ribosome, for removal of the eS7-bound ubiquitin moiety. Here, interactions of the largely helical N-terminal domain of Otu2 to sites that are masked and therefore inaccessible in the 80S ribosome are of crucial importance. Collectively, we provide the structural basis for the Otu2 driven deubiquitination step providing a first mechanistic understanding of this translational reset step during ribosome recycling/(re)initiation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468975" rel="alternate" title="Recognition and deubiquitination of free 40S for translational reset by Otu2 (19 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468906</id><title>Dithiothreitol causes toxicity in C. elegans by modulating the methionine-homocysteine cycle (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.968514+00:00</updated><author><name>G Gokul</name></author><author><name>Jogender Singh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The redox reagent dithiothreitol (DTT) causes stress in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) by disrupting its oxidative protein folding environment, which results in the accumulation and misfolding of the newly synthesized proteins. DTT may potentially impact cellular physiology by ER-independent mechanisms; however, such mechanisms remain poorly characterized. Using the nematode model &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/italic&gt;, here we show that DTT toxicity is modulated by the bacterial diet. Specifically, the dietary component vitamin B12 alleviates DTT toxicity in a methionine synthase-dependent manner. Using a forward genetic screen, we identify that loss-of-function of &lt;italic&gt;R08E5&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;3&lt;/italic&gt;, an S-adenosylmethionine (SAM)-dependent methyltransferase, imparts resistance to DTT. DTT upregulates &lt;italic&gt;R08E5&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;3&lt;/italic&gt; expression and modulates the activity of the methionine-homocysteine cycle. Employing genetic studies, we show that DTT toxicity is a result of the depletion of SAM. Finally, we show that a functional IRE-1/XBP-1 unfolded protein response pathway is required to counteract toxicity at high, but not low, DTT concentrations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468906" rel="alternate" title="Dithiothreitol causes toxicity in C. elegans by modulating the methionine-homocysteine cycle (16 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468831</id><title>Building an RNA-based Toggle Switch using Inhibitory RNA Aptamers (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.969025+00:00</updated><author><name>Alicia Climent-Catala</name></author><author><name>Thomas E. Ouldridge</name></author><author><name>Guy-Bart V. Stan</name></author><author><name>Wooli Bae</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Synthetic RNA systems offer unique advantages such as faster response, increased specificity, and programmability compared to conventional protein-based networks. Here, we demonstrate an in-vitro RNA-based toggle switch using RNA aptamers capable of inhibiting the transcriptional activity of T7 or SP6 RNA polymerases. The activities of both polymerases are monitored simultaneously by using Broccoli and Malachite green light-up aptamer systems. In our toggle switch, a T7 promoter drives the expression of SP6 inhibitory aptamers, and an SP6 promoter expresses T7 inhibitory aptamers. We show that the two distinct states originating from the mutual inhibition of aptamers can be toggled by adding DNA sequences to sequester the RNA inhibitory aptamers. Finally, we assessed our RNA-based toggle switch in cell-like conditions by introducing controlled degradation of RNAs using a mix of RNases. Our results demonstrate that the RNA-based toggle switch could be used as a control element for nucleic acid networks in synthetic biology applications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical TOC Entry&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="468831v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468831" rel="alternate" title="Building an RNA-based Toggle Switch using Inhibitory RNA Aptamers (15 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468554</id><title>Reversible regulation of Cas12a activities by AcrVA5-mediated acetylation and CobB-mediated deacetylation (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.969595+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaoman Kang</name></author><author><name>Lei Yin</name></author><author><name>Songkuan Zhuang</name></author><author><name>Tianshuai Hu</name></author><author><name>Zhile Wu</name></author><author><name>Guoping Zhao</name></author><author><name>Yijian Chen</name></author><author><name>Yong Xu</name></author><author><name>Jin Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeat (CRISPR)/CRISPR associated (Cas) system protects bacteria and archaea from the invasion of foreign genetic elements. To cope with the host CRISPR systems, phages have evolved many strategies, including the anti-CRISPR (Acr) proteins, to inactivate the Cas nucleases. Recently, it has been reported that the type V-A Cas12a effector can be acetylated and inactivated by AcrVA5, which is a GNAT-family acetyltransferase. However, it is unclear whether the host has any coping strategies to reactivate the defense system. Here we show that the AcrVA5-acetylated Cas12a can be deacetylated by bacterial deacetylase CobB, reactivating Cas12a for both in vitro cleavage of target DNA sequences and in vivo protection of the host from invasion of foreign nucleic acids. Therefore, this study not only shows the reversible regulation of Cas12a activities by post-translational modification but also reveals CobB as a secondary safeguard to bacterial CRISPR defense systems. In addition, we demonstrate that AcrVA5 is a wide-spectrum acetyltransferase, acetylating a large number of target proteins besides Cas12a, and the AcrVA5-acetylated targets can also be deacetylated by CobB.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468554" rel="alternate" title="Reversible regulation of Cas12a activities by AcrVA5-mediated acetylation and CobB-mediated deacetylation (13 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468710</id><title>Cryo-EM of the yeast VO complex reveals distinct binding sites for macrolide V-ATPase inhibitors (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.969871+00:00</updated><author><name>Kristine A. Keon</name></author><author><name>Samir Benlekbir</name></author><author><name>John L. Rubinstein</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Vacuolar-type adenosine triphosphatases (V-ATPases) are proton pumps found in almost all eukaryotic cells. These enzymes consist of a soluble catalytic V&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; region that hydrolyzes ATP and a membrane-embedded V&lt;sub&gt;O&lt;/sub&gt; region responsible for proton translocation. V-ATPase activity leads to acidification of endosomes, phagosomes, lysosomes, secretory vesicles, and the trans-Golgi network, with extracellular acidification occurring in some specialized cells. Small molecule inhibitors of V-ATPase have played a crucial role in elucidating numerous aspects of cell biology by blocking acidification of intracellular compartments, while therapeutic use of V-ATPase inhibitors has been proposed for treatment of cancer, osteoporosis, and some infections. Here, we determine structures of the isolated V&lt;sub&gt;O&lt;/sub&gt; complex from &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; bound to two well-known macrolide inhibitors: bafilomycin A1 and archazolid A. The structures reveal different binding sites for the inhibitors on the surface of the proton-carrying c ring, with only a small amount of overlap between the two sites. Binding of both inhibitors is mediated primarily through van der Waals interactions in shallow pockets and suggests that the inhibitors block rotation of the ring. Together, these structures indicate the existence of a large chemical space available for V-ATPase inhibitors that block acidification by binding the c ring.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468710" rel="alternate" title="Cryo-EM of the yeast VO complex reveals distinct binding sites for macrolide V-ATPase inhibitors (12 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469224</id><title>Cleavage of PGAM5 by the intramembrane protease PARL is governed by transmembrane helix dynamics and oligomeric state (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.972230+00:00</updated><author><name>Varena Siebert</name></author><author><name>Mara Silber</name></author><author><name>Elena Heuten</name></author><author><name>Claudia Muhle-Goll</name></author><author><name>Marius K. Lemberg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The intramembrane protease PARL is a crucial mitochondrial safeguard by cleaving the mitophagy regulators PINK1 and PGAM5. PGAM5 substrate determinates have not been rigorously investigated and it is unclear how uncoupling the mitochondrial membrane potential regulates its processing inversely to PINK1. Here we show that in PGAM5 several hydrophilic residues distant from the cleavage site serve as key determinant for PARL-catalyzed cleavage. NMR analysis indicates that a short N-terminal amphipathic helix, followed by a kink and a C-terminal helix harboring the scissile peptide bond, is key for a productive interaction with PARL. In difference to PINK1, PGAM5 is stably inserted into the inner mitochondrial membrane until uncoupling the membrane potential triggers its disassembly into monomers that are vulnerable to PARL-catalyzed processing. We suggest a model in which PGAM5 is a slowly processed substrate with PARL-catalyzed cleavage that is influenced by multiple hierarchical substrate features including a membrane-potential-dependent oligomeric switch.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469224" rel="alternate" title="Cleavage of PGAM5 by the intramembrane protease PARL is governed by transmembrane helix dynamics and oligomeric state (11 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468130</id><title>Genome editing of Capsaspora owczarzaki suggests an ancestral function of the Hippo signaling effector YAP/TAZ/Yorkie in cytoskeletal dynamics but not proliferation (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.972473+00:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan E Phillips</name></author><author><name>Maribel Santos</name></author><author><name>Mohammed Kanchwala</name></author><author><name>Chao Xing</name></author><author><name>Duojia Pan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many genes that function in animal development are present in the close unicellular relatives of animals, but little is known regarding the premetazoan function of these genes. Here, we develop techniques for genetic manipulation in the filasterean &lt;italic&gt;Capsaspora owczarzaki&lt;/italic&gt; and use these tools to characterize the &lt;italic&gt;Capsaspora&lt;/italic&gt; ortholog of the Hippo signaling nuclear effector YAP/TAZ/Yorkie (coYki). In contrast to its potent oncogene activity in metazoans, we show that coYki is dispensable for cell proliferation but regulates cytoskeletal dynamics and the morphology of multicellular aggregates in &lt;italic&gt;Capsaspora&lt;/italic&gt;. Our results suggest an ancestral role for the Hippo pathway in cytoskeletal regulation, which was later co-opted to regulate cell proliferation in animals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gene disruption in a unicellular holozoan suggests an ancestral role for YAP/TAZ/Yorkie in cytoskeletal regulation and cell aggregation but not cell proliferation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468130" rel="alternate" title="Genome editing of Capsaspora owczarzaki suggests an ancestral function of the Hippo signaling effector YAP/TAZ/Yorkie in cytoskeletal dynamics but not proliferation (10 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469306</id><title>Enhancer and super-enhancer landscape in polycystic kidney disease (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.972705+00:00</updated><author><name>Ronak Lakhia</name></author><author><name>Abheepsa Mishra</name></author><author><name>Laurence Biggers</name></author><author><name>Venakt Malladi</name></author><author><name>Patricia Cobo-Stark</name></author><author><name>Sachin Hajarnis</name></author><author><name>Vishal Patel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Widespread aberrant gene expression is pathological hallmark of polycystic kidney disease (PKD). Numerous pathogenic signaling cascades, including c-Myc, Fos, and Jun are transactivated. However, the underlying epigenetic regulators are poorly defined. Here we show that H3K27ac, a histone modification that marks active enhancers, is elevated in mouse and human ADPKD samples. Using comparative H3K27ac ChIP-Seq analysis, we mapped &amp;gt;16000 active intronic and intergenic enhancer elements in Pkd1-mutant mouse kidneys. We find that the cystic kidney epigenetic landscape resembles that of a developing kidney, and &amp;gt;90% of upregulated genes in Pkd1-mutant kidneys are co-housed with activated enhancers in the same topologically associated domains. Furthermore, we identify an evolutionarily-conserved enhancer cluster downstream of the c-Myc gene and super-enhancers flanking both Jun and Fos loci in mouse and human ADPKD models. Deleting these regulatory elements reduces c-Myc, Jun, or Fos abundance and suppresses proliferation and 3D cyst growth of Pkd1-mutant cells. Finally, inhibiting glycolysis and glutaminolysis or activating Ppara in Pkd1-mutant cells lowers global H3K27ac levels and on c-Myc enhancers. Thus, our work suggests that epigenetic rewiring mediates the transcriptomic dysregulation in PKD, and the regulatory elements can be targeted to slow cyst growth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469306" rel="alternate" title="Enhancer and super-enhancer landscape in polycystic kidney disease (9 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468903</id><title>Orthogonal control of gene expression in plants using synthetic promoters and CRISPR-based transcription factors (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.972949+00:00</updated><author><name>Shaunak Kar</name></author><author><name>Yogendra Bordiya</name></author><author><name>Nestor Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Junghyun Kim</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth C. Gardner</name></author><author><name>Jimmy Gollihar</name></author><author><name>Sibum Sung</name></author><author><name>Andrew D. Ellington</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The construction and application of synthetic genetic circuits is frequently improved if gene expression can be orthogonally controlled, relative to the host. In plants, orthogonality can be achieved via the use of CRISPR-based transcription factors that are programmed to act on natural or synthetic promoters. The construction of complex gene circuits can require multiple, orthogonal regulatory interactions, and this in turn requires that the full programmability of CRISPR elements be adapted to non-natural and non-standard promoters that have few constraints on their design. Therefore, we have developed synthetic promoter elements in which regions upstream of the minimal 35S CaMV promoter are designed from scratch to interact via programmed gRNAs with dCas9 fusions that allow activation of gene expression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A panel of three, mutually orthogonal promoters that can be acted on by artificial gRNAs bound by CRISPR regulators were designed. Guide RNA expression targeting these promoters was in turn controlled by either Pol III (U6) or ethylene-inducible Pol II promoters, implementing for the first time a fully artificial Orthogonal Control System (OCS). Following demonstration of the complete orthogonality of the designs, the OCS was tied to cellular metabolism by putting gRNA expression under the control of an endogenous plant signaling molecule, ethylene. The ability to form complex circuitry was demonstrated via the ethylene-driven, ratiometric expression of fluorescent proteins in single plants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The design of synthetic promoters is highly generalizable to large tracts of sequence space, allowing Orthogonal Control Systems of increasing complexity to potentially be generated at will. The ability to tie in several different basal features of plant molecular biology (Pol II and Pol III promoters, ethylene regulation) to the OCS demonstrates multiple opportunities for engineering at the system level. Moreover, given the fungibility of the core 35S CaMV promoter elements, the derived synthetic promoters can potentially be utilized across a variety of plant species.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468903" rel="alternate" title="Orthogonal control of gene expression in plants using synthetic promoters and CRISPR-based transcription factors (9 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468978</id><title>Identification of antibiotic resistance proteins via MiCId's augmented workflow. A mass spectrometry-based proteomics approach (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.973208+00:00</updated><author><name>Gelio Alves</name></author><author><name>Aleksey Y Ogurtsov</name></author><author><name>Roger Karlsson</name></author><author><name>Daniel Jaen-Luchoro</name></author><author><name>Beatriz Pineiro-Iglesias</name></author><author><name>Francisco Salva-Serra</name></author><author><name>Bjorn Andersson</name></author><author><name>Edward Moore</name></author><author><name>Yi-Kuo Yu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fast and accurate identifications of pathogenic bacteria along with their associated antibiotic resistance proteins are  of paramount importance for patient treatments and public health. While mass spectrometry has become an important, technique for diagnostics of infectious disease, there is a need for mass spectrometry workflows offering this capability. To meet this need, we have augmented the previously published Microorganism Classification and Identification (MiCId) workflow for this capability. To evaluate the performance of the newly augmented MiCId workflow, we have used  MS/MS datafiles from samples of 10 antibiotic resistance bacterial strains belonging to three different species: Escherichia coli, Klebsiella pneumoniae, and Pseudomonas aeruginosa. The evaluation results show that MiCId's workflow has a sensitivity value around 85% (with a lower bound at about 72%) and a precision greater than 95% in the identification of antibiotic resistance  proteins. Using MS/MS datasets from samples of two bacterial clonal isolates, one being antibiotic-sensitive while the other (obtained from the same patient at different times) being multidrug-resistant, we applied MiCId's workflow to investigate possible mechanisms of antibiotic resistance in these pathogenic bacteria; the results showed that MiCId's conclusions are in agreement with the published study. Furthermore, we show that MiCId's workflow is fast. It provides microorganismal identifications, protein identifications, sample biomass estimates, and antibiotic resistance protein identifications in 6-17 minutes per MS/MS sample using computing resources that are available in most desktop and laptop computers, making it a highly portable workflow. This study demonstrated that MiCId's workflow is fast, portable, and with high sensitivity and high precision, making it a valuable tool for rapid identifications of bacteria as well as detection of their antibiotic resistance  proteins. The new version of MiCId (v.07.01.2021) is freely available for download at https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/CBBresearch/Yu/downloads.html.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468978" rel="alternate" title="Identification of antibiotic resistance proteins via MiCId's augmented workflow. A mass spectrometry-based proteomics approach (9 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468561</id><title>pGlycoQuant with a deep residual network for precise and minuscule-missing-value quantitative glycoproteomics enabling the functional exploration of site-specific glycosylation (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.973578+00:00</updated><author><name>Weiqian Cao</name></author><author><name>Siyuan Kong</name></author><author><name>Wenfeng Zeng</name></author><author><name>Pengyun Gong</name></author><author><name>Biyun Jiang</name></author><author><name>Xinhang Hou</name></author><author><name>Yang Zhang</name></author><author><name>Huanhuan Zhao</name></author><author><name>Mingqi Liu</name></author><author><name>Xihua Qiao</name></author><author><name>Mengxi Wu</name></author><author><name>Guoquan Yan</name></author><author><name>Chao Liu</name></author><author><name>Pengyuan Yang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Interpreting large-scale glycoproteomic data for intact glycopeptide identification has been tremendously advanced by software tools. However, software tools for quantitative analysis of intact glycopeptides remain lagging behind, which greatly hinders exploring the differential expression and functions of site-specific glycosylation in organisms. Here, we report pGlycoQuant, a generic software tool for accurate and convenient quantitative intact glycopeptide analysis, supporting both primary and tandem mass spectrometry quantitation for multiple quantitative strategies. pGlycoQuant enables intact glycopeptide quantitation with very low missing values via a deep residual network, thus greatly expanding the quantitative function of several powerful search engines, currently including pGlyco 2.0, pGlyco3, Byonic and MSFragger-Glyco. The pGlycoQuant-based site-specific N-glycoproteomic study conducted here quantifies 6435 intact N-glycopeptides in three hepatocellular carcinoma cell lines with different metastatic potentials and, together with in vitro molecular biology experiments, illustrates core fucosylation at site 979 of the L1 cell adhesion molecule (L1CAM) as a potential regulator of HCC metastasis. pGlycoQuant is freely available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/expellir-arma/pGlycoQuant/releases/"&gt;https://github.com/expellir-arma/pGlycoQuant/releases/&lt;/ext-link&gt;. We have demonstrated pGlycoQuant to be a powerful tool for the quantitative analysis of site-specific glycosylation and the exploration of potential glycosylation-related biomarker candidates, and we expect further applications in glycoproteomic studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468561" rel="alternate" title="pGlycoQuant with a deep residual network for precise and minuscule-missing-value quantitative glycoproteomics enabling the functional exploration of site-specific glycosylation (8 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468597</id><title>Protein Engineering with A Glycosylation Circuit Enables Improved Enzyme Characteristics (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.973897+00:00</updated><author><name>Eray Ulaş Bozkurt</name></author><author><name>İrem Niran Çağıl</name></author><author><name>Ebru Şahin Kehribar</name></author><author><name>Musa Efe Işılak</name></author><author><name>Urartu Özgür Şafak Şeker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protein glycosylation is one of the most crucial and common post-translational modifications. It plays a fate-determining role and can alter many properties of proteins, making it an interesting for many biotechnology applications. The discovery of bacterial glycosylation mechanisms, opened a new perspective and transfer of &lt;italic&gt;C&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;jejuni&lt;/italic&gt; N-linked glycosylation into laboratory work-horse &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; increased research pace in the field exponentially. It has been previously showed that utilizing &lt;italic&gt;N-Linked Glycosylation&lt;/italic&gt;, certain recombinant proteins have been furnished with improved features, such as stability and solubility. In this study, we utilized &lt;italic&gt;N-linked Glycosylation&lt;/italic&gt; to glycosylate alkaline phosphatase (ALP) enzyme in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; and investigate the effects of glycosylation on an enzyme. Considering the glycosylation mechanism is highly dependent on the acceptor protein, ALP constructs carrying glycosylation tag at different locations of the gene has been created and glycosylation rates have been calculated. The most glycosylated construct has been selected for comparison with the native enzyme. We investigated the performance of glycosylated ALP in terms of its thermostability, proteolytic stability, tolerance to suboptimal pH and under denaturing conditions. Studies showed that glycosylated ALP performed remarkably better at optimal and harsh conditions Therefore, &lt;italic&gt;N-linked Glycosylation&lt;/italic&gt; mechanism can be employed for enzyme engineering purposes and is a useful tool for industrial applications that require enzymatic activity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468597" rel="alternate" title="Protein Engineering with A Glycosylation Circuit Enables Improved Enzyme Characteristics (8 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469338</id><title>RIF1-ASF1-mediated high-order chromatin structure safeguards genome integrity (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.974202+00:00</updated><author><name>Dongyi Xu</name></author><author><name>Sumin Feng</name></author><author><name>Sai Ma</name></author><author><name>Kejiao Li</name></author><author><name>Shengxian Gao</name></author><author><name>Shaokai Ning</name></author><author><name>Jinfeng Shang</name></author><author><name>Ruiyuan Guo</name></author><author><name>Qing Li</name></author><author><name>Rong Guo</name></author><author><name>Britny Blumenfeld</name></author><author><name>Itamar Simon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The 53BP1-RIF1 pathway antagonizes resection of DNA broken ends and confers PARP inhibitor sensitivity on BRCA1-mutated tumors. However, it is unclear how this pathway suppresses initiation of resection. Here, we identify ASF1 as a partner of RIF1 via an interacting manner similar to its interactions with histone chaperones CAF-1 and HIRA. ASF1 is recruited to distal chromatin flanking DNA breaks by 53BP1-RIF1 and promotes non-homologous end joining (NHEJ) using its histone chaperone activity. Epistasis analysis shows that ASF1 acts in the same NHEJ pathway as RIF1, but via a parallel pathway with the shieldin complex, which suppresses resection after initiation. Moreover, defects in end resection and homologous recombination (HR) in BRCA1-deficient cells are largely suppressed by ASF1 deficiency. Mechanistically, ASF1 compacts adjacent chromatin by heterochromatinization to protect broken DNA ends from BRCA1-mediated resection. Taken together, our findings identified a RIF1-ASF1 histone chaperone complex that promotes changes in high-order chromatin structure to stimulate the NHEJ pathway for DSB repair.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469338" rel="alternate" title="RIF1-ASF1-mediated high-order chromatin structure safeguards genome integrity (8 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469000</id><title>The distinct effects of MEK and GSK3 inhibition upon the methylome and transcriptome of mouse embryonic stem cells (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.974516+00:00</updated><author><name>Julia Spindel</name></author><author><name>Christel Krueger</name></author><author><name>Felix Krueger</name></author><author><name>Evangelia K Papachristou</name></author><author><name>Kamal Kishore</name></author><author><name>Clive S D'Santos</name></author><author><name>Wolf Reik</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mouse embryonic stem cells (mESCs) were first cultured &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; in serum-containing medium with leukaemia inhibitory factor, in which they exhibit heterogeneous expression of both pluripotency and some early differentiation markers. Over the last decade, however, it has become commonplace to grow mESCs with inhibitors of MEK and GSK3 signalling, which together elicit a more homogeneously 'naive' state of pluripotency. Whilst 2i/L-cultured mESCs have been shown to be globally hypomethylated, a comprehensive understanding of the distinct effects of these signalling inhibitors upon the DNA methylome is still lacking. Here we carried out whole genome bisulphite and RNA sequencing of mESCs grown with MEK or GSK3 inhibition alone, including different time points and concentrations of MEK inhibitor treatment. This demonstrated that MEK inhibition causes a dose-dependent impairment of maintenance methylation via loss of UHRF1 protein, as well as rapid impairment of &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; methylation. In contrast, GSK3 inhibition triggers impairment of &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; methylation alone, and consequent hypomethylation is enriched at enhancers with a 2i/L-specific chromatin signature and coincides with upregulation of nearby genes. Our study provides detailed insights into the epigenetic and transcriptional impacts of inhibiting MEK or GSK3 signalling in mouse pluripotent cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469000" rel="alternate" title="The distinct effects of MEK and GSK3 inhibition upon the methylome and transcriptome of mouse embryonic stem cells (8 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468809</id><title>DeepProjection: Rapid and structure-specific projections of tissue sheets embedded in 3D microscopy stacks using deep learning (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.974786+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Haertter</name></author><author><name>Xiaolei Wang</name></author><author><name>Stephanie M Fogerson</name></author><author><name>Nitya Ramkumar</name></author><author><name>Janice M Crawford</name></author><author><name>Kenneth D Poss</name></author><author><name>Stefano Di Talia</name></author><author><name>Daniel P Kiehart</name></author><author><name>Christoph F Schmidt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The efficient extraction of local high-resolution content from massive amounts of imaging data remains a serious and unsolved problem in studies of complex biological tissues. Here we present DeepProjection, a trainable projection algorithm based on deep learning. This algorithm rapidly and robustly extracts image content contained in curved manifolds from time-lapse recorded 3D image stacks by binary masking of background content, stack by stack. The masks calculated for a given movie, when predicted, e.g., on fluorescent cell boundaries on one channel, can subsequently be applied to project other fluorescent channels from the same manifold. We apply DeepProjection to follow the dynamic movements of 2D-tissue sheets in embryonic development. We show that we can selectively project the amnioserosa cell sheet during dorsal closure in Drosophila melanogaster embryos and the periderm layer in the elongating zebrafish embryo while masking highly fluorescent out-of-plane artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468809" rel="alternate" title="DeepProjection: Rapid and structure-specific projections of tissue sheets embedded in 3D microscopy stacks using deep learning (8 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468727</id><title>A Cryptic K48 Ubiquitin Chain Binding Site on UCH37 is Required for its Role in Proteasomal Degradation (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.975074+00:00</updated><author><name>Jiale Du</name></author><author><name>Sandor Babik</name></author><author><name>Yanfeng Li</name></author><author><name>Kirandeep K. Deol</name></author><author><name>Stephen J. Eyles</name></author><author><name>Jasna Fejzo</name></author><author><name>Marco Tonelli</name></author><author><name>Eric R. Strieter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Degradation by the 26S proteasome is an intricately regulated process fine-tuned by the precise nature of ubiquitin modifications attached to a protein substrate. By debranching ubiquitin chains composed of K48 linkages, the proteasome-associated ubiquitin C-terminal hydrolase UCHL5/UCH37 serves as a positive regulator of protein degradation. How UCH37 achieves specificity for K48 chains is unclear. Here, we use a combination of hydrogen-deuterium mass spectrometry, chemical crosslinking, small-angle X-ray scattering, NMR, molecular docking, and targeted mutagenesis to uncover a cryptic K48 ubiquitin chain specific binding site on the opposite face of UCH37 relative to the canonical S1 ubiquitin-binding site. Biochemical assays demonstrate the K48 chain-specific binding site is required for chain debranching and proteasome-mediated degradation of proteins modified with branched chains. Using quantitative proteomics, translation shutoff experiments, and linkage-specific affinity tools, we then identify specific proteins whose degradation depends on the debranching activity of UCH37. Our findings suggest that UCH37 and potentially other DUBs could use more than one S1 site to perform different biochemical functions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468727" rel="alternate" title="A Cryptic K48 Ubiquitin Chain Binding Site on UCH37 is Required for its Role in Proteasomal Degradation (8 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468632</id><title>Nieman-Pick Type C2 proteins in Aedes aegypti: Their Structure-Function relationships and Expression in Uninfected versus Virus-infected Mosquitos (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.975447+00:00</updated><author><name>Prathigna Jaishankar Thambi</name></author><author><name>Cassandra M. Modahl</name></author><author><name>R. Manjunatha Kini</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Aedes aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; is a major vector that transmits arboviruses through the saliva injected into the host. Salivary proteins help in uninterrupted blood intake and enhance the transmission of pathogens. We studied Nieman-Pick Type C2 (NPC2) proteins, a superfamily of saliva proteins that play important role in arbovirus infections. In vertebrates, a single conserved gene encodes for the NPC2 protein that functions in cholesterol trafficking. Arthropods, in contrast, have several genes that encode for divergent NPC2 proteins. We compared the sequences of 20 &lt;italic&gt;A. aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; NPC2 proteins to the cholesterol-binding residues of human and bovine, and fatty acid-binding residues of ant NPC2 proteins. We identified four and one mosquito NPC2 proteins as potential sterol- and fatty acid-binding proteins, respectively. From the published data, we analysed the expression of NPC2 genes in various tissues and their differential expression in midgut and salivary gland post-arbovirus infections. NPC2 genes are downregulated rather than upregulated in virus-infected tissues. Interestingly, AAEL012064 is the only gene that is downregulated in both the midgut and salivary gland in all virus infections. In addition, AAEL001650 is downregulated in the salivary gland infected with CHIKV, DENV2 or ZIKV. This gene in the midgut is downregulated infected with DENV1 but upregulated with DENV2. We studied the variation in &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt; elements in the promoter regions of two groups of closely related NPC2 genes and the expression of relevant transcription factors (TFs). In the midgut infected with DENV1 or DENV2, six TFs (CRE-BP1, AP1, c-Jun, c-Fos, Odd, and NF-kB) appear to play an opposing role in the expression of AAEL006854. Two TFs (RXR-beta/alpha and USF) have a potential role in the downregulation of AAEL009556 in CHIKV-infected midgut and salivary gland. Similarly, two TFs (COUP and Ftz) may have a key role in the downregulation of AAEL009555 and AAEL009556 in DENV2-infected salivary gland.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468632" rel="alternate" title="Nieman-Pick Type C2 proteins in Aedes aegypti: Their Structure-Function relationships and Expression in Uninfected versus Virus-infected Mosquitos (7 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468920</id><title>A general model of the dynamics of genes with dual σ factor preference (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.975659+00:00</updated><author><name>Ines S. C. Baptista</name></author><author><name>Vinodh Kandavalli</name></author><author><name>Vatsala Chauhan</name></author><author><name>Mohammed Bahurudeen</name></author><author><name>Bilena Almeida</name></author><author><name>Cristina Palma</name></author><author><name>Suchintak Dash</name></author><author><name>Andre S. Ribeiro</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; uses the ability of σ factors to recognize specific DNA sequences in order to quickly control large gene cohorts. While most genes respond to only one σ factor, approximately 5% have dual σ factor preference. The ones in significant numbers are ‘σ&lt;sup&gt;70+38&lt;/sup&gt; genes’, responsive to σ&lt;sup&gt;70&lt;/sup&gt;, which controls housekeeping genes, as well as to σ&lt;sup&gt;38&lt;/sup&gt;, which activates genes during stationary growth and stresses. We show that σ&lt;sup&gt;70+38&lt;/sup&gt; genes are almost as upregulated in stationary growth as genes responsive to σ&lt;sup&gt;38&lt;/sup&gt; alone. Also, their response strengths to σ&lt;sup&gt;38&lt;/sup&gt; are predictable from their promoter sequences. Next, we propose a sequence- and σ&lt;sup&gt;38&lt;/sup&gt; level-dependent, analytical model of σ&lt;sup&gt;70+38&lt;/sup&gt; genes applicable in the exponential, stationary, and in the transition period between the two growth phases. Finally, we propose a general model, applicable to other σ factors as well. This model can guide the design of synthetic circuits with sequence-dependent sensitivity and plasticity to transitions between the exponential and stationary growth phases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Present challenges in Synthetic Biology include the design of genetic circuits that are robust to growth phase transitions and whose responsiveness is sequence-dependent, and, thus predictable prior to design. We present and validate an empirical-based, sequence-dependent analytical model of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; genes with dual responsiveness to the regulators σ&lt;sup&gt;70&lt;/sup&gt; and σ&lt;sup&gt;38&lt;/sup&gt;. These genes, supported by our sequence-dependent model, could become building blocks for synthetic genetic circuits functional in both the exponential and the stationary growth phases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468920" rel="alternate" title="A general model of the dynamics of genes with dual σ factor preference (6 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.468628</id><title>A non-transcriptional function of Yap orchestrates the DNA replication program (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.977694+00:00</updated><author><name>Rodrigo Meléndez García</name></author><author><name>Olivier Haccard</name></author><author><name>Albert Chesneau</name></author><author><name>Hemalatha Narassimprakash</name></author><author><name>Jerome E Roger</name></author><author><name>Muriel Perron</name></author><author><name>Kathrin Marheineke</name></author><author><name>Odile Bronchain</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In multicellular eukaryotic organisms, the initiation of DNA replication occurs asynchronously throughout S-phase according to a regulated replication timing program. Here, using &lt;italic&gt;Xenopus&lt;/italic&gt; egg extracts, we showed that Yap (Yes-associated protein 1), a downstream effector of the Hippo signaling pathway, is required for the control of DNA replication dynamics. We found that Yap is recruited to chromatin at the start of DNA replication and that Yap depletion accelerates DNA replication dynamics by increasing the number of activated replication origins. Furthermore, we identified Rif1, a major regulator of the DNA replication timing program, as a novel Yap binding protein. In &lt;italic&gt;Xenopus&lt;/italic&gt; embryos, using a Trim-Away approach during cleavage stages devoid of transcription, we found that both Yap and Rif1 depletion trigger an acceleration of cell divisions, suggesting a shorter S-phase by alterations of the replication program. Finally, our data show that Rif1 knockdown leads to defects in the partitioning of early versus late replication foci in retinal stem cells, as we previously showed for Yap. Altogether, our findings unveil a non-transcriptional role for Yap in regulating replication dynamics. We propose that Yap and Rif1 function as breaks to control the DNA replication program in early embryos and post-embryonic stem cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.468628" rel="alternate" title="A non-transcriptional function of Yap orchestrates the DNA replication program (6 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469142</id><title>TWIST1 methylation by SETD6 selectively antagonizes LINC-PINT expression in Glioblastoma multiforme (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.978166+00:00</updated><author><name>Lee Admoni-Elisha</name></author><author><name>Michal Feldman</name></author><author><name>Tzofit Elbaz</name></author><author><name>Anand Chopra</name></author><author><name>Guy Shapira</name></author><author><name>Christopher J Fry</name></author><author><name>Noam Shomron</name></author><author><name>Kyle Biggar</name></author><author><name>Dan Levy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glioblastoma multiforme (GBM) is the most common and aggressive malignant brain tumor among adults, which is characterized by high invasion, migration and proliferation abilities. One important process that contributes to the invasiveness of GBM is the epithelial to mesenchymal transition (EMT). EMT is regulated by a set of defined transcription factors which tightly regulate this process, among them is the basic helix-loop-helix family member, TWIST1. Here we show that TWIST1 is methylated on lysine-33 at chromatin by SETD6, a methyltransferase with expression levels correlating with poor survival in GBM patients. RNA-seq analysis in U251 GBM cells suggested that both SETD6 and TWIST1 regulate cell adhesion and migration processes. We further show that TWIST1 methylation attenuates the expression of the long-non-coding RNA, LINC-PINT, thereby suppressing EMT in GBM. Mechanistically, TWIST1 methylation represses the transcription of LINC-PINT by increasing the occupancy of EZH2 and the catalysis of the repressive H3K27me3 mark at the LINC-PINT locus. Under un-methylated conditions, TWIST1 dissociates from the LINC-PINT locus, allowing the expression of LINC-PINT which leads to increased cell adhesion and decreased cell migration. Together, our findings unravel a new mechanistic dimension for selective expression of LINC-PINT mediated by TWIST1 methylation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469142" rel="alternate" title="TWIST1 methylation by SETD6 selectively antagonizes LINC-PINT expression in Glioblastoma multiforme (6 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.469315</id><title>Conformational Changes in the Negative Arm of the Circadian Clock Correlate with Dynamic Interactomes Involved in Post-transcriptionally Regulated Processes (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.978377+00:00</updated><author><name>Jacqueline F Pelham</name></author><author><name>Alexander E Mosier</name></author><author><name>Samuel C Altshuler</name></author><author><name>Christopher L Kirchhoff</name></author><author><name>William B Fall</name></author><author><name>Lisa S Baik</name></author><author><name>Joanna C Chiu</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Marie Hurley</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The circadian clock employs a transcriptional/translational negative feedback loop (TTFL) to anticipate environmental changes due to the Earth′s diurnal cycle, with regulation of organismal physiology believed to stem from temporal transcriptional activation by the positive arm. However, up to 80% of oscillating proteins do not have rhythmic mRNA, establishing circadian post-transcriptional regulation through unknown mechanisms. Given the pervasive conservation of the intrinsically disordered nature of negative-arm clock proteins, we hypothesized that post-transcriptional regulation may stem from conformational shifts in negative-arm proteins that time vacillations in the constituents of negative-arm macromolecular complexes to time cellular physiology. Our investigation of the negative arm clock protein in &lt;italic&gt;Neurospora crassa&lt;/italic&gt;, FREQUENCY (FRQ), demonstrated temporal conformational fluidity correlated with daily changes in physiologically diverse macromolecular complex components. A parallel investigation of the macromolecular complexes centered around &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; PERIOD (dPER) and human PERIOD (hPER2) found a similar number and physiological diversity of interacting partners in higher eukaryotes. Short linear motifs (SLiMs) associated with the interactors localized to disordered and phosphorylated regions on the PERs and FRQ, with disordered interactors oscillating in the macromolecular complexes over circadian time. This oscillation correlated with oscillations in post-transcriptionally regulated proteins, suggesting the negative arm may tune cellular physiology and proteostasis post-transcriptionally via vacillations in the circadian negative-arm macromolecular protein complexes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.469315" rel="alternate" title="Conformational Changes in the Negative Arm of the Circadian Clock Correlate with Dynamic Interactomes Involved in Post-transcriptionally Regulated Processes (5 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469045</id><title>Ubiquitous mRNA decay fragments in E. coli redefine the functional transcriptome (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.978560+00:00</updated><author><name>Lydia Herzel</name></author><author><name>Julian A. Stanley</name></author><author><name>James C. Taggart</name></author><author><name>Gene-Wei Li</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial mRNAs have short life cycles, in which transcription is rapidly followed by translation and degradation within seconds to minutes. The resulting diversity of mRNAs impacts their functionality but has remained unresolved. Here we quantitatively map the 3’ status of cellular RNAs in &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; during steady-state growth and report a large fraction of molecules (median&amp;gt;60%) that are fragments of canonical full-length mRNAs. The majority of RNA fragments are decay intermediates following endonuclease cleavage by RNase E and yet-unknown nucleases, whereas nascent RNAs contribute to a smaller fraction. Despite the prevalence of decay intermediates in total RNA, they are underrepresented in the pool of ribosome-associated transcripts and can thus distort quantifications for the abundance of full-length, functional mRNAs. The large heterogeneity within mRNA molecules &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; highlights the importance in discerning functional transcripts and provides a lens for studying the dynamic life cycle of mRNAs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469045" rel="alternate" title="Ubiquitous mRNA decay fragments in E. coli redefine the functional transcriptome (5 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468802</id><title>NUDT18 catalyzes hydrolysis of active metabolites of the antivirals Remdesivir and Ribavirin (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.978709+00:00</updated><author><name>Ann-Sofie Jemth</name></author><author><name>Emma Rose Scaletti</name></author><author><name>Evert Homan</name></author><author><name>Pål Stenmark</name></author><author><name>Thomas Helleday</name></author><author><name>Maurice Michel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Remdesivir (GS-5734) has gained considerable interest due to its activity against replication of SARS-CoV2. Remdesivir is a broad-spectrum antiviral prodrug that is hydrolyzed intracellularly and phosphorylated by cellular kinases to its active triphosphate form (Remdesivir-TP). Here we tested Remdesivir-TP as a substrate for a panel of human hydrolases and found that NUDIX hydrolase 18 (NUDT18) catalyzes the hydrolysis of Remdesivir-TP. NUDT18 is expressed in respiratory epithelial cells suggesting that NUDT18 may limit the antiviral efficacy of Remdesivir by decreasing the intracellular concentration of its active metabolite at its intended site of action. The k&lt;sub&gt;cat&lt;/sub&gt; of NUDT18 for Remdesivir-TP was determined to 2.6 s&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; and the K&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt; value was 156 μM, suggesting that NUDT18 catalyzed hydrolysis occurs in cells. In addition, we found that the triphosphate of the antiviral Ribavirin, with broad-spectrum activity against several RNA and DNA viruses, was hydrolyzed by NUDT18, albeit with a lower efficiency compared to Remdesivir-TP. NUDT18 activity was also tested with the triphosphates of the antivirals Sofosbuvir and Aciclovir for which low activity, in comparison to activities with Remdesivir-TP and Ribavirin-TP, was detected. These results suggest that NUDT18 can act as a cellular sanitizer and may influence the antiviral efficacy of Remdesivir and Ribavirin.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468802" rel="alternate" title="NUDT18 catalyzes hydrolysis of active metabolites of the antivirals Remdesivir and Ribavirin (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468742</id><title>Tunable Transcription Factor Library for Robust Quantification of Gene Expression Dynamics in E. coli (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.978868+00:00</updated><author><name>Vinuselvi Parisutham</name></author><author><name>Shivani Chhabra</name></author><author><name>Md Zulfikar Ali</name></author><author><name>Robert C. Brewster</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Predicting the quantitative regulatory function of a TF based on factors such as binding sequence, binding location and promoter type is not possible. The interconnected nature of gene networks and the difficulty in tuning individual TF concentrations makes the isolated study of TF function challenging. Here we present a library of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; strains designed to allow for precise control of the concentration of individual TFs enabling the study of the role of TF concentration on physiology and regulation. We demonstrate the usefulness of this resource by measuring the regulatory function of the zinc responsive TF, ZntR and the paralogous TF pair, GalR/GalS. For ZntR, we find that zinc alters ZntR regulatory function in a way that enables activation of the regulated gene to be robust with respect to ZntR concentration. For GalR and GalS, we are able to demonstrate that these parlogous TFs have fundamentally distinct regulatory roles beyond differences in binding affinity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468742" rel="alternate" title="Tunable Transcription Factor Library for Robust Quantification of Gene Expression Dynamics in E. coli (5 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.468847</id><title>Common variation in EDN1 regulatory regions highlights the role of PPARγ as a key regulator of Endothelin in vitro (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.979010+00:00</updated><author><name>Mauro Lago-Docampo</name></author><author><name>Carlos Solarat</name></author><author><name>Luis Mendez-Martinez</name></author><author><name>Adolfo Baloira</name></author><author><name>Diana Valverde</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension (PAH) is a rare disease caused by the obliteration of the pulmonary arterioles, increasing pulmonary vascular resistance and eventually causing right heart failure. Endothelin-1 is a vasoconstrictor peptide whose levels are indicators of disease progression and its pathway is one of the commonest targeted by current treatments.
We sequenced the EDN1 untranslated regions of a small subset of PAH patients, predicted the effect in silico, and used a luciferase assay with the different genotypes to analyze its influence on gene expression. Finally, we used siRNAs against the major transcription factors predicted for these regions (PPARγ, KLF4, and VDR) to assess Endothelin-1 expression in cell culture and validate the binding sites.
First, we detected a SNP in the 5'UTR (rs397751713) and another in the 3'regulatory region (rs2859338) that increased luciferase activity in vitro depending on their genotype. We determined in silico that KLF4/PPARγ could be binding in the rs397751713 and VDR in rs2859338. By using siRNAs and luciferase, we determined that PPARγ binds differentially in rs397751713. PPARγ and VDR Knock-Down, increased EDN1 mRNA levels and Endothelin-1 production in PAECs, while PPARγ and KLF4 Knock-Down increased the Endothelin-1 production in HeLa. 
In conclusion, common variants in EDN1 regulatory regions could alter Endothelin-1 levels. We were able to validate that PPARγ binds in rs397751713 and is key to regulate Endothelin-1. Also, KLF4 and VDR regulate Endothelin-1 production in a cell-dependent manner, but for VDR this interaction does not happen by binding directly to the regions we studied.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.468847" rel="alternate" title="Common variation in EDN1 regulatory regions highlights the role of PPARγ as a key regulator of Endothelin in vitro (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469324</id><title>The sperm protein Spaca6 is essential for fertilization in zebrafish (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.979161+00:00</updated><author><name>Mirjam Isabel Binner</name></author><author><name>Anna Kogan</name></author><author><name>Karin Panser</name></author><author><name>Alexander Schleiffer</name></author><author><name>Victoria Eugenia Deneke</name></author><author><name>Andrea Pauli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fertilization is a key process in all sexually reproducing species, yet the molecular mechanisms that underlie this event remain unclear. To date, only a few proteins have been shown to be essential for sperm-egg binding and fusion in mice, and only some are conserved across vertebrates. One of these conserved, testis-expressed factors is SPACA6, yet its function has not been investigated outside of mammals. Here we show that zebrafish spaca6 encodes for a sperm membrane protein which is essential for fertilization. Zebrafish spaca6 knockout males are sterile. Furthermore, Spaca6-deficient sperm have normal morphology, are motile, and can approach the egg, but fail to bind to the egg and therefore cannot complete fertilization. Interestingly, sperm lacking Spaca6 have decreased levels of another essential and conserved sperm fertility factor, Dcst2, revealing a previously unknown dependence of Dcst2 expression on Spaca6. Together, our results show that zebrafish Spaca6 regulates Dcst2 levels and is required for binding between the sperm membrane and the oolemma. This is in contrast to murine SPACA6, which was reported not to be required for sperm-egg membrane binding but necessary for fusion. These findings demonstrate that Spaca6 is essential for zebrafish fertilization and is a conserved sperm factor in vertebrate reproduction.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469324" rel="alternate" title="The sperm protein Spaca6 is essential for fertilization in zebrafish (4 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468502</id><title>Structure and mechanism of oxalate transporter OxlT in an oxalate-degrading bacterium in the gut microbiota (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.979325+00:00</updated><author><name>Titouan Jaunet-Lahary</name></author><author><name>Tatsuro Shimamura</name></author><author><name>Masahiro Hayashi</name></author><author><name>Norimichi Nomura</name></author><author><name>Kouta Hirasawa</name></author><author><name>Tetsuya Shimizu</name></author><author><name>Masao Yamashita</name></author><author><name>Keiichi Kojima</name></author><author><name>Yuki Sudo</name></author><author><name>Takashi Tamura</name></author><author><name>Hiroko Iwanari</name></author><author><name>Takao Hamakubo</name></author><author><name>So Iwata</name></author><author><name>Kei-ichi Okazaki</name></author><author><name>Teruhisa Hirai</name></author><author><name>Atsuko Yamashita</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Oxalobacter formigenes&lt;/italic&gt; is an oxalate-degrading bacterium in the gut microbiota that absorbs food-derived oxalate to use this as a carbon and energy source and thereby helps reduce the risk of kidney stone formation of the host animals &lt;sup&gt;1–4&lt;/sup&gt;. The bacterial oxalate transporter OxlT uptakes oxalate from the gut to bacterial cells and excrete formate as a degradation product, with a strict discrimination from other carboxylates that serve as nutrients &lt;sup&gt;5–7&lt;/sup&gt;. Nevertheless, the underlying mechanism remains unclear. Here, we present crystal structures of oxalate-bound and ligand-free OxlT in two different conformations, occluded and outward-facing states. The oxalate binding site contains two basic residues that form salt bridges with a dicarboxylate substrate while preventing the conformational switch to the occluded state without an acidic substrate, a ‘disallowed’ state for an antiporter &lt;sup&gt;8, 9&lt;/sup&gt;. The occluded ligand-binding pocket can accommodate oxalate but not larger dicarboxylates, such as metabolic intermediates. The permeation pathways from the binding pocket are completely blocked by extensive interdomain hydrophobic and ionic interactions. Nevertheless, a molecular dynamics simulation showed that a flip of a single side chain neighbouring the substrate is sufficient to trigger the gate opening. The OxlT structure indicates the underlying metabolic interactions enabling favourable symbiosis at a molecular level.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468502" rel="alternate" title="Structure and mechanism of oxalate transporter OxlT in an oxalate-degrading bacterium in the gut microbiota (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468952</id><title>Multiple trajectory alignment reconstructs disease dynamics for discovery and clinical benefit (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.979550+00:00</updated><author><name>Amit Frishberg</name></author><author><name>Neta Milman</name></author><author><name>Ayelet Alpert</name></author><author><name>Fabian J Theis</name></author><author><name>Joachim L. Schultze</name></author><author><name>Shai S. Shen-Orr</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Biological processes are changes occurring concomitantly over time. Therefore, any comparison ignorant of temporal changes is greatly deficient. Even in longitudinal experimental designs, data is usually collected at fixed intervals, whereas process dynamics vary between individuals. We developed TimeAx, which brings time into the equation by building a comparative framework for capturing biological processes dynamics from omic data. We used TimeAx to study influenza infection dynamics and Urothelial bladder cancer tumorigenesis, discovering molecular mechanisms that drive disease progression as well as promoting clinical symptoms, for short and long term biological processes. Specifically, we detected an inflection point, where the tumor progresses into an advanced, pro-metastatic state. Overall, we present a powerful framework for studying high resolution temporal dynamics, providing improved molecular interoperability and clinical benefit.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468952" rel="alternate" title="Multiple trajectory alignment reconstructs disease dynamics for discovery and clinical benefit (3 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469193</id><title>Histidine-rich protein 2: a new pathogenic factor of 
Plasmodium falciparum
 malaria (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.979709+00:00</updated><author><name>Takashi Iwasaki</name></author><author><name>Mayu Shimoda</name></author><author><name>Haru Kanayama</name></author><author><name>Tsuyoshi Kawano</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; causes serious malaria symptoms; when this protozoan parasite infects human erythrocytes, it produces and secretes large amounts of histidine–rich protein 2 (PfHRP2) into human blood. Thus, PfHRP2 is a well–known diagnostic marker for malaria infection. Here, however, we also identified PfHRP2 as a pathogenic factor produced by &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt;. PfHRP2 showed cell penetration and cytotoxicity against various human cells. In particular, PfHRP2 showed significant cytotoxicity over 5 days at the same concentration as in &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt;–infected patients′ blood (90–100 nM). This result is consistent with the mortality rate of &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; malaria, which increases rapidly in untreated cases for 3–7 days. In addition, the cell penetration and cytotoxicity of PfHRP2 increased 2.5– and 2.6–fold, respectively, in the absence of serum, which suggests that low serum protein concentrations (occurring during malnutrition, for example) increase the risk of adverse effects from PfHRP2 (consistent with malnutrition increasing the lethality of malaria infection). We also showed that PfHRP2 bound to Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; ions, localized to intracellular lysosomes, increased lysosomal Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; levels, and inhibited the basal level of autophagy by inhibiting autolysosome formation. Furthermore, the Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;–dependent cytotoxicity of PfHRP2 was suppressed by the metal ion chelator ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA). In summary, our findings suggest that PfHRP2 acts as a pathogenic factor in &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt;–infected patients and is associated with the exacerbation of malaria. Furthermore, EDTA is a promising candidate as a therapeutic agent for the suppression of PfHRP2 pathogenicity. Overall, this study provides new insights into &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; malaria pathogenesis and treatment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469193" rel="alternate" title="Histidine-rich protein 2: a new pathogenic factor of &#10;Plasmodium falciparum&#10; malaria (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469012</id><title>DNA Breaks and Gaps Target Retroviral Integration (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.980674+00:00</updated><author><name>Gayan Senavirathne</name></author><author><name>Anne Gardner</name></author><author><name>James London</name></author><author><name>Ryan K. Messer</name></author><author><name>Yow Yong Tan</name></author><author><name>Kristine E. Yoder</name></author><author><name>Richard Fishel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Integration into a host genome is essential for retrovirus infection and is catalyzed by a nucleoprotein complex (Intasome) containing the virus-encoded integrase (IN) and the reverse transcribed (RT) virus copy DNA (cDNA). Previous studies suggested that integration was limited by intasome-host DNA recognition progressions. Using single molecule Förster resonance energy transfer (smFRET) we show that PFV intasomes pause at nicked and gapped DNA, which targeted site-directed integration without inducing significant intasome conformational alterations. Base excision repair (BER) components that affect retroviral integration &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; produce similar nick/gap intermediates during DNA lesion processing. Intasome pause dynamics was modified by the 5’-nick/gap chemistry, while an 8-oxo-guanine lesion, a mismatch, or a nucleotide insertion that induce backbone flexibility and/or static bends had no effect. These results suggest that dynamic often non-productive intasome-DNA interactions may be modulated to target retroviral integration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469012" rel="alternate" title="DNA Breaks and Gaps Target Retroviral Integration (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468795</id><title>Stimulation of immunity-linked genes by membrane disruption is linked to Golgi function and the ARF-1 GTPase (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.980844+00:00</updated><author><name>Christofer M. Welsh</name></author><author><name>Lorissa J. Smulan</name></author><author><name>Matthew J. Fanelli</name></author><author><name>Dominique S. Lui</name></author><author><name>Amy K. Walker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Immune-linked genes (ILGs) are activated in response to pathogens but can also be activated by lipid imbalance. Why pathogen attack and metabolic changes both impact ILG activation is unclear. Organelles in the secretory pathway have distinct protein and lipid components and genetically separable stress programs. These stress pathways activate restorative transcriptional programs when lipid ratios become unbalanced or during dysregulated protein folding and trafficking. We find that ILGs are specifically activated when membrane phosphatidylcholine ratios change in the secretory pathway. Consistent with this result, disruption of Golgi function after RNAi targeting the ADP-ribosylation factor ARF-1 also activates ILG expression. Since increased protein secretion is altered by metabolic changes and pathogen responses, our data argue that ILG upregulation is a conserved, coordinated response to changes in trafficking resulting from intrinsic cues (lipid changes) or extrinsic stimulation (during the immune response). These findings uncover important and previously unexplored links between metabolism and the stress response.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468795" rel="alternate" title="Stimulation of immunity-linked genes by membrane disruption is linked to Golgi function and the ARF-1 GTPase (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469337</id><title>Nonenzymatic loop-closing ligation generates RNA hairpins and is a template-free way to assemble functional RNAs (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.980984+00:00</updated><author><name>Long-Fei Wu</name></author><author><name>Ziwei Liu</name></author><author><name>Samuel J Roberts</name></author><author><name>Meng Su</name></author><author><name>Jack W Szostak</name></author><author><name>John D Sutherland</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;RNA hairpin loops are the predominant element of secondary structure in functional RNAs. The emergence of primordial functional RNAs, such as ribozymes that fold into complex structures that contain multiple hairpin loops, is generally thought to have been supported by template-directed ligation. However, template inhibition and RNA misfolding problems impede the emergence of function. Here we demonstrate that RNA hairpin loops can be synthesized directly from short RNA duplexes with single-stranded overhangs by nonenzymatic loop-closing ligation chemistry. We show that loop-closing ligation allows full-length functional ribozymes containing a hairpin loop to be assembled free of inhibitory template strands. This approach to the assembly of structurally complex RNAs suggests a plausible pathway for the emergence of functional RNAs before a full-length RNA copying process became available.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469337" rel="alternate" title="Nonenzymatic loop-closing ligation generates RNA hairpins and is a template-free way to assemble functional RNAs (3 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469067</id><title>LiveCellMiner: A New Tool to Analyze Mitotic Progression (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.981240+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Moreno-Andrés</name></author><author><name>Anuk Bhattacharyya</name></author><author><name>Anja Scheufen</name></author><author><name>Johannes Stegmaier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Live-cell imaging has become state of the art to accurately identify the nature of mitotic and cell cycle defects. Low- and high-throughput microscopy setups have yield huge data amounts of cells recorded in different experimental and pathological conditions. Tailored semi-automated and automated image analysis approaches allow the analysis of high-content screening data sets, saving time and avoiding bias. However, they were mostly designed for very specific experimental setups, which restricts their flexibility and usability. The general need for dedicated experiment-specific user-annotated training sets and experiment-specific user-defined segmentation parameters remains a major bottleneck for fully automating the analysis process. In this work we present LiveCellMiner, a highly flexible open-source software tool to automatically extract, analyze and visualize both aggregated and time-resolved image features with potential biological relevance. The software tool allows analysis across high-content data sets obtained in different platforms, in a quantitative and unbiased manner. As proof of principle application, we analyze here the dynamic chromatin and tubulin cytoskeleton features in human cells passing through mitosis highlighting the versatile and flexible potential of this tool set.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469067" rel="alternate" title="LiveCellMiner: A New Tool to Analyze Mitotic Progression (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.468818</id><title>Transcriptome and fatty-acid signatures of adipocyte hypertrophy and its non-invasive MR-based characterization in human adipose tissue (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.981384+00:00</updated><author><name>Julius Honecker</name></author><author><name>Stefan Ruschke</name></author><author><name>Claudine Seeliger</name></author><author><name>Samantha Laber</name></author><author><name>Sophie Strobel</name></author><author><name>Priska Proell</name></author><author><name>Christoffer Nellaker</name></author><author><name>Cecilia Lindgren</name></author><author><name>Ulrich Kulozik</name></author><author><name>Josef Ecker</name></author><author><name>Dimitrios Karampinos</name></author><author><name>Melina Claussnitzer</name></author><author><name>Hans Hauner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Adipose tissue is an organ with great plasticity and its hypertrophic expansion is associated with adipocyte dysfunction. How changes in adipocyte morphology are linked to gene expression and which cellular functions are affected remains elusive. We show that adipocyte hypertrophy is associated with transcriptomic changes using RNA-Seq data obtained from adipose tissue and size-separated adipocytes. Genes involved in oxidative phosphorylation, protein biosynthesis and fatty acid metabolism were down-regulated in large adipocytes while genes involved in inflammation were upregulated. For mitochondrial function, a reduction in the expression of thermogenesis related genes and estimated brown/beige adipocyte content was observed in individuals with large adipocytes. As a novel finding the total adipose tissue fatty acid composition was dependent on cell size and depot. MR spectroscopy methods for clinical scanning were developed to characterize adipocyte size and fatty acid composition in a fast and non-invasive manner. Together, the present data provides mechanistic insights on how adipocyte hypertrophy contributes to the manifestation of metabolic disease at the molecular and cellular level. MR spectroscopy was identified as a promising technique for an in-parallel assessment of adipose morphology and fatty acid composition allowing to translate our findings into an improved, non-invasive phenotyping of adipose tissue.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.468818" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptome and fatty-acid signatures of adipocyte hypertrophy and its non-invasive MR-based characterization in human adipose tissue (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>