<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.820560+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464039</id><title>Histone H1 regulates non-coding RNA turnover on chromatin in a m6A-dependent manner (72 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.821108+00:00</updated><author><name>José Miguel Fernández-Justel</name></author><author><name>Cristina Santa-María</name></author><author><name>Alberto Ferrera-Lagoa</name></author><author><name>Mónica Salinas-Pena</name></author><author><name>Magdalena M. Maslon</name></author><author><name>Albert Jordan</name></author><author><name>Javier F. Cáceres</name></author><author><name>María Gómez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Linker histones are highly abundant chromatin-associated proteins with well-established structural roles in chromatin and as general transcriptional repressors. In addition, it has been long proposed that histone H1 exerts context-specific effects on gene expression. Here, we have identified a new function of histone H1 in chromatin structure and transcription using a range of genomic approaches. We show that histone H1-depleted cells accumulate nascent non-coding RNAs on chromatin, suggesting that histone H1 prevents non-coding RNA transcription and regulates non-coding transcript turnover on chromatin. Accumulated non-coding transcripts have reduced levels of m6A modification and cause replication-transcription conflicts. Accordingly, altering the m6A RNA methylation pathway rescues the replicative phenotype of H1 loss. This work unveils unexpected regulatory roles of histone H1 on non-coding RNA turnover and m6A deposition, highlighting the intimate relationship between chromatin conformation, RNA metabolism and DNA replication to maintain genome performance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464039" rel="alternate" title="Histone H1 regulates non-coding RNA turnover on chromatin in a m6A-dependent manner (72 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464066</id><title>Tissue-wide coordination of calcium signaling regulates the epithelial stem cell pool during homeostasis (41 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.821807+00:00</updated><author><name>Jessica L Moore</name></author><author><name>Feng Gao</name></author><author><name>Catherine Matte-Martone</name></author><author><name>Shuangshuang Du</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Lathrop</name></author><author><name>Smirthy Ganesan</name></author><author><name>Lin Shao</name></author><author><name>Dhananjay Bhaskar</name></author><author><name>Andy Cox</name></author><author><name>Caroline Hendry</name></author><author><name>Bastian Rieck</name></author><author><name>Smita Krishnaswamy</name></author><author><name>Valentina Greco</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Regenerative processes in the mammalian skin require coordinated cell-cell communication. Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signaling can coordinate tissue-level responses in developing and wounded epithelia in tissue explants and invertebrates[1, 2, 3, 4]. However, its role in the homeostatic, regenerative basal layer of the skin epithelium is unknown due to significant challenges in studying signaling dynamics in a spatially complex tissue context in live mice. Here we combine &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; imaging of dynamic Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signaling at the single cell level across thousands of cells with a novel computational approach, Geometric Scattering Trajectory Homology (GSTH). GSTH models Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; as signals over a cell adjacency graph and uses a multi-level wavelet-like transform (called a scattering transform) to extract signaling patterns from our high dimensional &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; datasets. We discover local Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signaling patterns are orchestrated so that signals flow in a coordinated and directed manner across the tissue, distinct from topographically uncoordinated Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signaling in excitatory tissues. Directed Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signaling is regulated by the major gap junction protein in the epidermal stem cell layer, Connexin 43 (Cx43). Cx43 gap junctions are dissociated as cells progress through the cell cycle out of G1 and play an essential role in the progression of stem cells from G2 towards mitosis. Finally, G2 cells display related signaling patterns and are essential for tissue-level signaling coordination. Together, our results provide insight into how such a ubiquitous signaling pathway regulates highly specific behaviors and outcomes at a tissue-wide level to maintain proper homeostasis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464066" rel="alternate" title="Tissue-wide coordination of calcium signaling regulates the epithelial stem cell pool during homeostasis (41 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.463965</id><title>Ferroptosis Regulation by the NGLY1/NFE2L1 Pathway (39 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.822416+00:00</updated><author><name>Giovanni C. Forcina</name></author><author><name>Lauren Pope</name></author><author><name>Magdalena Murray</name></author><author><name>Wentao Dong</name></author><author><name>Monther Abu-Remaileh</name></author><author><name>Carolyn R. Bertozzi</name></author><author><name>Scott J. Dixon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ferroptosis is an oxidative form of non-apoptotic cell death whose transcriptional regulation is poorly understood. Cap’n’collar (CNC) transcription factors including Nuclear Factor Erythroid-2 Related Factor 1 (NFE2L1/NRF1) and NFE2L2 (NRF2) are important regulators of oxidative stress responses. Here, we report that NFE2L1 expression inhibits ferroptosis, independent of NFE2L2. NFE2L1 inhibits ferroptosis by promoting expression of the key anti-ferroptotic lipid hydroperoxidase glutathione peroxidase 4 (GPX4). NFE2L1 abundance and function are regulated post-translationally by N-glycosylation. Functional maturation of NFE2L1 requires deglycosylation by cytosolic peptide:N-glycanase 1 (NGLY1). We find that loss of NGLY1 or NFE2L1 enhances ferroptosis sensitivity. Expression of wild-type NGLY1 but not a disease-associated NGLY1 mutant inhibits ferroptosis, and this effect is dependent on the presence of NFE2L1. Enhanced ferroptosis sensitivity in NFE2L1 and NFE2L2 knockout cells can be potently reverted by expression of an NFE2L1 mutant containing eight asparagine-to-aspartate protein sequence substitutions, which mimic NGLY1-catalyzed sequence editing. Enhanced ferroptosis sensitivity in NGLY1/NFE2L1 pathway mutants could also be reversed by overexpression of NFE2L2. These results suggest that ferroptosis sensitivity is regulated by NGLY1-catalyzed NFE2L1 deglycosylation, and highlight a broad role for CNC transcription factors in ferroptosis regulation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ferroptosis is an oxidative form of cell death whose biochemical regulation remains incompletely understood. NFE2L1/NRF1 is a cap’n’collar (CNC) transcription factor whose role in ferroptosis regulation is unclear. Unlike the CNC family member NFE2L2/NRF2, NFE2L1 is an N-glycoprotein whose abundance is regulated by post-translational deglycosylation catalyzed by the enzyme peptide:N-glycanase 1 (NGLY1). Our results indicate that NGLY1-mediated NFE2L1 deglycosylation, resulting in ‘editing’ of the NFE2L1 amino acid sequence, is necessary for NFE2L1 to inhibit ferroptosis. Mechanistically, NFE2L1 inhibits ferroptosis by via the anti-ferroptotic protein GPX4. This work demonstrates that CNC transcription factors beyond NFE2L2 can regulate ferroptosis. This work may suggest a role of misregulation of ferroptosis in NGLY1 deficiency, an ultrarare genetic disorder.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.463965" rel="alternate" title="Ferroptosis Regulation by the NGLY1/NFE2L1 Pathway (39 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.464136</id><title>Replication Fork Uncoupling Causes Nascent Strand Degradation and Fork Reversal (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.822981+00:00</updated><author><name>Tamar Kavlashvili</name></author><author><name>James M Dewar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genotoxins cause nascent strand degradation (NSD) and fork reversal during DNA replication. NSD and fork reversal are crucial for genome stability and exploited by chemotherapeutic approaches. However, it is unclear how NSD and fork reversal are triggered. Additionally, the fate of the replicative helicase during these processes is unknown. We developed a biochemical approach to study synchronous, localized NSD and fork reversal using &lt;italic&gt;Xenopus&lt;/italic&gt; egg extracts. We show that replication fork uncoupling stimulates NSD of both nascent strands and progressive conversion of uncoupled forks to reversed forks. The replicative helicase remains bound during NSD and fork reversal, indicating that both processes take place behind the helicase. Unexpectedly, NSD occurs before and after fork reversal, indicating that multiple degradation steps take place. Overall, our data show that uncoupling causes NSD and fork reversal and identify key steps involved in these processes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.464136" rel="alternate" title="Replication Fork Uncoupling Causes Nascent Strand Degradation and Fork Reversal (16 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.464196</id><title>A linear programming-based strategy to save pipette tips in automated DNA assembly (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.823440+00:00</updated><author><name>Kirill Sechkar</name></author><author><name>Zoltan A Tuza</name></author><author><name>Guy-Bart V Stan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Laboratory automation and mathematical optimisation are key to improving the efficiency of synthetic biology research. While there are algorithms optimising the construct designs and synthesis strategies for DNA assembly, the optimisation of how DNA assembly reaction mixes are prepared remains largely unexplored. Here, we focus on reducing the pipette tip consumption of a liquid-handling robot as it delivers DNA parts across a multi-well plate where several constructs are being assembled in parallel. We propose a linear programming formulation of this problem based on the capacitated vehicle routing problem, along with an algorithm which applies a linear programming solver to our formulation, hence providing a strategy to prepare a given set of DNA assembly mixes using fewer pipette tips. The algorithm performed well in randomly generated and real-life scenarios concerning several modular DNA assembly standards, proving capable of reducing the pipette tip consumption by up to 61% in large-scale cases. Combining automatic process optimisation and robotic liquid-handling, our strategy promises to greatly improve the efficiency of DNA assembly, either used alone or in combination with other algorithmic methods.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.464196" rel="alternate" title="A linear programming-based strategy to save pipette tips in automated DNA assembly (13 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.11.463377</id><title>Environmentally dependent and independent control of cell shape determination by Rho GTPase regulators in melanoma (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.823791+00:00</updated><author><name>L. G. Dent</name></author><author><name>N. Curry</name></author><author><name>H. Sparks</name></author><author><name>V. Bousgouni</name></author><author><name>V. Maioli</name></author><author><name>S. Kumar</name></author><author><name>I. Munro</name></author><author><name>C. Dunsby</name></author><author><name>C. Bakal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In order to invade 3D tissues, cancer cells dynamically change cell morphology in response to geometric and mechanical cues in the environment. But how cells determine their shape in 3D versus 2D environments is poorly understood. Studying 2D versus 3D single cell shape determination has historically been technically difficult due to the lack of methodologies to directly compare the two environments. We developed an approach to study cell shape in 2D versus 3D by measuring cell shape at different depths in collagen using stage-scanning oblique plane microscopy (ssOPM). We find characteristic shape changes occur in melanoma cells depending on whether a cell is attached to a 2D surface or 3D environment, and that these changes can be modulated by Rho GTPase regulatory proteins. Our data suggest that regulation of cell protrusivity undergoes a ‘switch’ of control between different Rho GTPase regulators depending on the physical microenvironment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.11.463377" rel="alternate" title="Environmentally dependent and independent control of cell shape determination by Rho GTPase regulators in melanoma (11 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.464175</id><title>Modular, robust and extendible multicellular circuit design in yeast (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.824403+00:00</updated><author><name>Alberto Carignano</name></author><author><name>Dai Hua Chen</name></author><author><name>Cannon Mallory</name></author><author><name>Clay Wright</name></author><author><name>Georg Seelig</name></author><author><name>Eric Klavins</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Division of labor between cells is ubiquitous in biology but the use of multi-cellular consortia for engineering applications is only beginning to be explored. A significant advantage of multi-cellular circuits is their potential to be modular with respect to composition but this claim has not yet been extensively tested using experiments and quantitative modeling. Here, we construct a library of 24 yeast strains capable of sending, receiving or responding to three molecular signals, characterize them experimentally and build quantitative models of their input-output relationships. We then compose these strains into two- and three-strain cascades as well a four-strain bistable switch and show that experimentally measured consortia dynamics can be predicted from the models of the constituent parts. To further explore the achievable range of behaviors, we perform a fully automated computational search over all two-, three- and four-strain consortia to identify combinations that realize target behaviors including logic gates, band-pass filters and time pulses. Strain combinations that are predicted to map onto a target behavior are further computationally optimized and then experimentally tested. Experiments closely track computational predictions. The high reliability of these model descriptions further strengthens the feasibility and highlights the potential for distributed computing in synthetic biology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.464175" rel="alternate" title="Modular, robust and extendible multicellular circuit design in yeast (11 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.464275</id><title>Benchmarking imputation methods for network inference using a novel method of synthetic scRNA-seq data generation (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.824951+00:00</updated><author><name>Ayoub Lasri</name></author><author><name>Vahid Shahrezaei</name></author><author><name>Marc Sturrock</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single cell RNA-sequencing (scRNA-seq) has very rapidly become the new workhorse of modern biology providing an unprecedented global view on cellular diversity and heterogeneity. In particular, the structure of gene-gene expression correlation contains information on the underlying gene regulatory networks. However, interpretation of scRNA-seq data is challenging due to specific experimental error and biases that are unique to this kind of data including drop-out (or technical zeros). To deal with this problem several methods for imputation of zeros for scRNA-seq have been developed. However, it is not clear how these processing steps affect inference of genetic networks from single cell data. Here, we introduce Biomodelling.jl, a tool for generation of synthetic scRNA-seq data using multiscale modelling of stochastic gene regulatory networks in growing and dividing cells. Our tool produces realistic transcription data with a known ground truth network topology that can be used to benchmark different approaches for gene regulatory network inference. Using this tool we investigate the impact of different imputation methods on the performance of several network inference algorithms. Biomodelling.jl provides a versatile and useful tool for future development and benchmarking of network inference approaches using scRNA-seq data.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.464275" rel="alternate" title="Benchmarking imputation methods for network inference using a novel method of synthetic scRNA-seq data generation (10 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.463740</id><title>RNAi screening of RING/U-box domain ubiquitin ligases identifies critical regulators of stem cells and tissue regeneration in planarians (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.825346+00:00</updated><author><name>John M. Allen</name></author><author><name>Madison Balagtas</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Barajas</name></author><author><name>Carolina Cano Macip</name></author><author><name>Sarai Alvarez Zepeda</name></author><author><name>Ionit Iberkleid</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth M. Duncan</name></author><author><name>Ricardo M. Zayas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Regenerative processes depend on the interpretation of signals to coordinate cell behaviors. The role of ubiquitin-mediated signaling in regeneration is not well understood. To investigate how ubiquitylation might specifically impact tissue regeneration, we are studying planarians that are capable of regenerating from nearly any injury using a population of stem cells. Here we used RNAi to screen RING/U-box E3 ubiquitin ligases that are highly expressed in planarian stem cells and stem cell progeny. RNAi screening identified nine genes with functions in regeneration, including the spliceosomal factor &lt;italic&gt;prpf19&lt;/italic&gt; and epigenetic regulator &lt;italic&gt;rnf2&lt;/italic&gt;; based on roles in developmental processes, we further explored these two genes. We found that &lt;italic&gt;prpf19&lt;/italic&gt; was required for survival but not for stem cell maintenance, suggesting a role in promoting cell differentiation. Because RNF2 is the catalytic subunit of the Polycomb Repressive Complex 1 (PRC1), we also examined other cofactors of &lt;italic&gt;rnf2&lt;/italic&gt; and observed a striking phenotype of regional tissue misspecification in &lt;italic&gt;cbx&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;phc&lt;/italic&gt; RNAi planarians. To identify genes regulated by PRC1, we performed RNA-seq after knocking down &lt;italic&gt;rnf2&lt;/italic&gt; or &lt;italic&gt;phc&lt;/italic&gt; and found that the set of genes differentially expressed were largely non-overlapping despite being predicted to function in the same complex. Using &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; hybridization, we showed that &lt;italic&gt;rnf2&lt;/italic&gt; regulates gene expression levels within a tissue type, whereas &lt;italic&gt;phc&lt;/italic&gt; is necessary for the spatial restriction of gene expression. This work uncovered roles for RING/U-box E3 ligases in stem cell regulation and regeneration and identified differential gene targets for PRC1 factors required for maintaining cell-type-specific gene expression in planarians.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.463740" rel="alternate" title="RNAi screening of RING/U-box domain ubiquitin ligases identifies critical regulators of stem cells and tissue regeneration in planarians (6 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464107</id><title>Topoisomerase II poisons inhibit vertebrate DNA replication through distinct mechanisms (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.825584+00:00</updated><author><name>Sabrina X. Van Ravenstein</name></author><author><name>Kavi P. Mehta</name></author><author><name>Tamar Kavlashvili</name></author><author><name>Jo Ann Byl</name></author><author><name>Runxiang Zhao</name></author><author><name>Neil Osheroff</name></author><author><name>David Cortez</name></author><author><name>James M. Dewar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Topoisomerase II (Top2) unlinks chromosomes during vertebrate DNA replication. Top2 ‘poisons’ are widely-used chemotherapeutics that stabilize Top2 complexes on DNA, leading to cytotoxic DNA breaks. However, it is unclear how these drugs affect DNA replication, which is a major target of Top2 poisons. Using &lt;italic&gt;Xenopus&lt;/italic&gt; egg extracts, we show that the Top2 poisons etoposide and doxorubicin both inhibit DNA replication through different mechanisms. Etoposide induces Top2-dependent DNA breaks and induces Top2-dependent fork stalling by trapping Top2 behind replication forks. In contrast, doxorubicin does not lead to appreciable break formation and instead intercalates into parental DNA to inhibit replication fork progression. In human cells, etoposide stalls replication forks in a Top2-dependent manner, while doxorubicin stalls forks independently of Top2. However, both drugs exhibit Top2-dependent cytotoxicity. Thus, despite shared genetic requirements for cytotoxicity etoposide and doxorubicin inhibit DNA replication through distinct mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464107" rel="alternate" title="Topoisomerase II poisons inhibit vertebrate DNA replication through distinct mechanisms (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.17.464158</id><title>Distinct phases within large RNP granules of C. elegans oocytes are associated with differential stress responses of RNA binding proteins (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.825901+00:00</updated><author><name>Brooklynne Watkins</name></author><author><name>Mohamed T. Elaswad</name></author><author><name>Chloe Pestrue</name></author><author><name>Katherine Sharp</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Breton</name></author><author><name>Jennifer A Schisa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;One emerging paradigm of cellular organization of RNA and RNA binding proteins is the formation of membraneless organelles (MLOs). Examples of MLOs include several types of RNP (ribonucleoprotein) granules that form via phase separation. Proper regulation of the phase transitions of RNA binding proteins is critical as dysregulation can lead to disease states. Germ granules are small RNP granules conserved across metazoa. In &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt;, when oogenesis undergoes an extended meiotic arrest, germ granules assemble into much larger, more complex RNP granules whose hypothesized function is to regulate RNA metabolism and maintain oocyte quality. As a step towards gaining insight into the function of RNP granules, in this report we characterize distinct phases for four RNA binding proteins in arrested oocytes. We find that PGL-1 is dynamic and has liquid-like properties, while MEG-3 has gel-like properties, both similar to their properties in small germ granules of embryos. We also show that MEX-3 exhibits gel-like properties in many regards but is more dynamic than MEG-3. We find CGH-1 is dynamic but does not consistently behave liquid-like, and may be an intermediate phase within RNP granules. We also show that the distinct phases of the RNA binding proteins are associated with differential responses to stress.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.17.464158" rel="alternate" title="Distinct phases within large RNP granules of C. elegans oocytes are associated with differential stress responses of RNA binding proteins (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.17.464727</id><title>T7Max transcription system (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.826211+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher Deich</name></author><author><name>Brock Cash</name></author><author><name>Wakana Sato</name></author><author><name>Judee Sharon</name></author><author><name>Lauren Aufdembrink</name></author><author><name>Nathaniel J Gaut</name></author><author><name>Joseph Heili</name></author><author><name>Kaitlin Stokes</name></author><author><name>Aaron E Engelhart</name></author><author><name>Katarzyna P Adamala</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Efficient cell-free protein expression from linear DNA templates has remained a challenge primarily due to template degradation. Here we present a modified T7 RNA polymerase promoter that acts to significantly increase the yields of both transcription and translation within in vitro systems. The modified promoter, termed T7Max, recruits standard T7 RNA polymerase, so no protein engineering is needed to take advantage of this method. This technique could be used with any T7 RNA polymerase- based in vitro protein expression system. Unlike other methods of limiting linear template degradation, the T7Max promoter increases transcript concentration in a T7 transcription reaction, providing more mRNA for translation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.17.464727" rel="alternate" title="T7Max transcription system (4 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-10-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.10.463866</id><title>STAG2 promotes the myelination transcriptional program in oligodendrocytes (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.826595+00:00</updated><author><name>Ningyan Cheng</name></author><author><name>Mohammed Kanchwala</name></author><author><name>Bret M. Evers</name></author><author><name>Chao Xing</name></author><author><name>Hongtao Yu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cohesin folds chromosomes via DNA loop extrusion. Cohesin-mediated chromosome loops regulate transcription by shaping long-range enhancer-promoter interactions, among other mechanisms. Mutations of cohesin subunits and regulators cause human developmental diseases termed cohesinopathy. Vertebrate cohesin consists of SMC1, SMC3, RAD21, and either STAG1 or STAG2. To probe the physiological functions of cohesin, we created conditional knockout (cKO) mice with &lt;italic&gt;Stag2&lt;/italic&gt; deleted in the nervous system. &lt;italic&gt;Stag2&lt;/italic&gt; cKO mice exhibit growth retardation, neurological defects, and premature death, in part due to insufficient myelination of nerve fibers. &lt;italic&gt;Stag2&lt;/italic&gt; cKO oligodendrocytes exhibit delayed maturation and downregulation of myelination-related genes. &lt;italic&gt;Stag2&lt;/italic&gt; loss reduces promoter-anchored loops at downregulated genes in oligodendrocytes. Thus, STAG2-cohesin generates promoter-anchored loops at myelination-promoting genes to facilitate their transcription. Our study implicates defective myelination as a contributing factor to cohesinopathy and establishes oligodendrocytes as a relevant cell type to explore the mechanisms by which cohesin regulates transcription.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.10.463866" rel="alternate" title="STAG2 promotes the myelination transcriptional program in oligodendrocytes (3 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.11.464003</id><title>A bacterial Argonaute with efficient DNA and RNA cleavage activity guided by small DNA and RNA (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.827027+00:00</updated><author><name>Longyu Wang</name></author><author><name>Xiaochen Xie</name></author><author><name>Yang Liu</name></author><author><name>Wenqiang Li</name></author><author><name>Bin Lv</name></author><author><name>Zhiwei Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jun Yang</name></author><author><name>Guangbo Yan</name></author><author><name>Wanping Chen</name></author><author><name>Cheng Zhang</name></author><author><name>Fei Wang</name></author><author><name>Lixin Ma</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Argonaute proteins are widespread in prokaryotes and eukaryotes. Most prokaryotic Argonaute proteins (pAgos) use 5’P-gDNA to target complementary DNA. However, more and more studies on the properties of pAgos make their functions more diversified. Previously reported pAgos only possess several forms of high activity in all eight cleavage patterns, which limits their practical applications. Here, we described a unique pAgo from &lt;italic&gt;Marinitoga hydrogenitolerans&lt;/italic&gt; (MhAgo) with eight cleavage activities. MhAgo can utilize all four types of guides (5’OH-gDNA, 5’P-gDNA, 5’OH-gRNA, and 5’P-gRNA) for ssDNA and RNA cleavage. Further studies demonstrated that MhAgo had high activities with 16-21 nt guides and no obvious preferences for the 5’-end nucleotides of 5’OH-guides. Unexpectedly, MhAgo had different preferences for the 5’-end nucleotides of 5’P-guides depending on the types of targets. Although the specificity of MhAgo was related to the types of guides, single mismatches in the central and 3’-supplementary regions of guides greatly reduced the cleavage efficiency. Additionally, the electrophoretic mobility shift assay (EMSA) demonstrated MhAgo had the weakest affinity for 5’P-gRNA:tRNA duplex, which was consistent with its cleavage efficiency. In conclusion, MhAgo is highly active under a wide range of conditions and can be used for programmable endonucleolytic cleavage of both ssDNA and RNA substrates. The abundant biochemical characteristics of MhAgo broaden our understanding of pAgos and expand the potential application in nucleic acids manipulations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.11.464003" rel="alternate" title="A bacterial Argonaute with efficient DNA and RNA cleavage activity guided by small DNA and RNA (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.14.464379</id><title>The β-amylase7 gene in Zea mays encodes a protein with structural and catalytic properties similar to Arabidopsis BAM2 (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.827538+00:00</updated><author><name>Claire M Ravenburg</name></author><author><name>McKayla B Riney</name></author><author><name>Jonathan D Monroe</name></author><author><name>Christopher E Berndsen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Starch accumulates in the plastids of green plant tissue during the day to provide carbon for metabolism at night. Starch hydrolysis is catalyzed by members of the β-amylase (BAM) family, which in Arabidopsis thaliana (At), includes nine structurally and functionally diverse members. One of these enzymes, AtBAM2, is a plastid-localized enzyme that is unique among characterized β-amylases since it is tetrameric and exhibits sigmoidal kinetics. Sequence alignments show that the BAM domains of AtBAM7, a catalytically inactive, nuclear-localized transcription factor with an N-terminal DNA binding domain, and AtBAM2 are more closely related to each other than they are to any other AtBAM. Since BAM2 is found in more ancient lineages, it was hypothesized that BAM7 evolved from BAM2. However, analysis of the genomes of 48 flowering plants revealed 12 species that appear to have a BAM7 gene but lack a BAM2 gene. Upon closer inspection, these BAM7 proteins have a greater percent identity to AtBAM2 than to AtBAM7, and they share all of the AtBAM2 functional residues that BAM7 proteins normally lack. We hypothesize that these genes may encode a BAM2-like protein although they are currently annotated as BAM7-like genes. To test this hypothesis, we designed a cDNA of the short form of corn BAM7 (ZmBAM7-S) for expression in E. coli. Small Angle X-Ray Scattering data indicate that ZmBAM7-S has a tetrameric solution structure more similar to that of AtBAM2 than AtBAM1. In addition, partially purified ZmBAM7-S is catalytically active and exhibits sigmoidal kinetics. Together these data suggest that some BAM7 genes may encode a functional BAM2. Exploring and understanding β-amylase gene structure could have impacts on the current annotation of genes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.14.464379" rel="alternate" title="The β-amylase7 gene in Zea mays encodes a protein with structural and catalytic properties similar to Arabidopsis BAM2 (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>