<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.794976+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455990</id><title>Reconstructing transcriptional histories by CRISPR acquisition of retron-based genetic barcodes (83 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.795283+00:00</updated><author><name>Santi Bhattarai-Kline</name></author><author><name>Elana Lockshin</name></author><author><name>Max G. Schubert</name></author><author><name>Jeff Nivala</name></author><author><name>George Church</name></author><author><name>Seth L. Shipman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Biological processes depend on the differential expression of genes over time, but methods to make true physical recordings of these processes are limited. Here we report a strategy for making time-ordered recordings of transcriptional events into living genomes. We do this via engineered RNA barcodes, based on prokaryotic retrons, which are reverse-transcribed into DNA and integrated into the genome using the CRISPR-Cas system. This approach enables the targeted recording of time-ordered transcriptional events in cells. The unidirectional integration of barcodes by CRISPR integrases enables reconstruction of transcriptional event timing based on a physical record via simple, logical rules rather than relying on pre-trained classifiers or post-hoc inferential methods.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455990" rel="alternate" title="Reconstructing transcriptional histories by CRISPR acquisition of retron-based genetic barcodes (83 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455418</id><title>Probing 3’UTRs as modular regulators of gene expression (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.795498+00:00</updated><author><name>Jamie Auxillos</name></author><author><name>Samuel Haynes</name></author><author><name>Abhishek Jain</name></author><author><name>Clemence Alibert</name></author><author><name>Weronika Danecka</name></author><author><name>Edward Wallace</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genes are commonly abstracted into a coding sequence and cis-regulatory elements (CREs), such as promoter and terminator regions, and short sequence motifs within these regions. Modern cloning techniques allow easy assembly of synthetic genetic constructs from discrete cis-regulatory modules. However, it is unclear how much the contributions of CREs to gene expression depend on other CREs in the host gene. Using budding yeast, we probe the extent of composability, or independent effects, of distinct CREs. We confirm that the quantitative effect of a terminator on gene expression depends on both promoter and coding sequence. We then explore whether individual cis-regulatory motifs within terminator regions display similar context dependence, focusing on putative regulatory motifs inferred using transcriptome-wide datasets of mRNA decay. We construct a library of diverse reporter genes, consisting of different combinations of motifs within various terminator contexts, paired with different promoters, to test the extent of composability. Our results show that the effect of a motif on RNA abundance depends both on its host terminator, and also on the associated promoter sequence. Consequently, this emphasises the need for improved motif inference algorithms that include both local and global context effects, which in turn could aid researchers in the accurate use of diverse CREs for the engineering of synthetic genetic constructs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455418" rel="alternate" title="Probing 3’UTRs as modular regulators of gene expression (37 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456059</id><title>Microtubule deacetylation reduces cell stiffness to allow the onset of collective cell migration in vivo (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.795683+00:00</updated><author><name>CL Marchant</name></author><author><name>AN Malmi-Kakkada</name></author><author><name>JA Espina</name></author><author><name>EH Barriga</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Embryogenesis, tissue repair and cancer metastasis rely on collective cell migration (CCM). &lt;italic&gt;In vitro&lt;/italic&gt; studies propose that migrating cells are stiffer when exposed to stiff substrates, known to allow CCM, but softer when plated in compliant non-permissive surfaces. Here, by combining &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; atomic force microscopy (&lt;italic&gt;i&lt;/italic&gt;AFM) and modelling we reveal that to collectively migrate &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, cells require to dynamically decrease their stiffness in response to the temporal stiffening of their native substrate. Moreover, molecular and mechanical perturbations of embryonic tissues uncover that this unexpected cell mechanical response is achieved by a new mechanosensitive pathway involving Piezo1-mediated microtubule deacetylation. Finally, lowering microtubule acetylation and consequently cell stiffness was sufficient to allow CCM in soft non-permissive substrates, suggesting that a fixed value of substrate stiffness is not as essential for CCM as it is reaching an optimal cell-to-substrate stiffness value. These &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; insights on cell-to-substrate mechanical interplay have major implications to our re-interpretation of physiological and pathological contexts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456059" rel="alternate" title="Microtubule deacetylation reduces cell stiffness to allow the onset of collective cell migration in vivo (31 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456252</id><title>Engineering Bacillus subtilis for the formation of a durable living biocomposite material (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.795846+00:00</updated><author><name>Sun-Young Kang</name></author><author><name>Anaya Pokhrel</name></author><author><name>Sara Bratsch</name></author><author><name>Joey J Benson</name></author><author><name>Seung-Oh Seo</name></author><author><name>Maureen B Quin</name></author><author><name>Alptekin Aksan</name></author><author><name>Claudia Schmidt-Dannert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Engineered living materials (ELMs) are a fast-growing area of research that combine approaches in synthetic biology and material science. Here, we engineer B. subtilis to become a living component of a silica material composed of self-assembling protein scaffolds for functionalization and cross-linking of cells. B. subtilis was engineered to display SpyTags on polar flagella for cell attachment and cross-linking of SpyCatcher modified secreted scaffolds. Through deletion of the autolysis LytC, endospore limited B. subtilis cells become a structural component of the material with spores for long-term storage of genetic programming. Known silica biomineralization peptides were screened and scaffolds designed for silica polymerization to fabricate biocomposite materials with enhanced mechanical properties. We show that the resulting ELM can be regenerated from a piece of silica material and that new functions can be readily incorporated by co-cultivation of engineered B. subtilis strains. We believe that this work will serve as a framework for the future design of resilient ELMs as functional, self-healing materials for use as responsive coatings and plasters.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456252" rel="alternate" title="Engineering Bacillus subtilis for the formation of a durable living biocomposite material (24 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456150</id><title>Nano-scale Architecture of Blood-Brain Barrier Tight-Junctions (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.796030+00:00</updated><author><name>Esther Sasson</name></author><author><name>Shira Anzi</name></author><author><name>Batia Bell</name></author><author><name>Oren Yakovian</name></author><author><name>Meshi Zorsky</name></author><author><name>Urban Deutsch</name></author><author><name>Britta Engelhardt</name></author><author><name>Eilon Sherman</name></author><author><name>Gad D Vatine</name></author><author><name>Ron Dzikowski</name></author><author><name>Ayal Ben-Zvi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tight junctions (TJs) between blood-brain barrier (BBB) endothelial cells construct a robust physical barrier, whose damage underlies BBB dysfunctions related to several neurodegenerative diseases. What makes these highly specialized BBB-TJs extremely restrictive remains unknown. Here, we use super-resolution microscopy (dSTORM) to uncover new structural and functional properties of BBB TJs. Focusing on three major components, Nano-scale resolution revealed sparse (occludin) vs. clustered (ZO1/claudin-5) molecular architecture. Developmentally, permeable TJs become first restrictive to large molecules, and only later to small molecules, with claudin-5 proteins arrangement compacting during this maturation process. Mechanistically, we reveal that ZO1 clustering is independent of claudin-5 in-vivo. In contrast to accepted knowledge, we found that in the developmental context, total levels of claudin-5 inversely correlate with TJ functionality. Our super-resolution studies provide a unique perspective of BBB TJs and open new directions for understanding TJ functionality in biological barriers, ultimately enabling restoration in disease or modulation for drug delivery.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456150" rel="alternate" title="Nano-scale Architecture of Blood-Brain Barrier Tight-Junctions (24 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456062</id><title>Virulence determinant, PTP7, controls vesicle budding from the Maurer’s clefts, adhesin protein trafficking and host cell remodeling in Plasmodium falciparum (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.796331+00:00</updated><author><name>Olivia M. S. Carmo</name></author><author><name>Gerald J. Shami</name></author><author><name>Dezerae Cox</name></author><author><name>Boyin Liu</name></author><author><name>Adam J. Blanch</name></author><author><name>Snigdha Tiash</name></author><author><name>Leann Tilley</name></author><author><name>Matthew W.A. Dixon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Presentation of the variant antigen, &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; erythrocyte membrane protein 1 (EMP1), at knob-like protrusions on the surface of infected red blood cells, underpins &lt;italic&gt;P. falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; malaria pathogenicity. Here we describe a protein PF3D7_0301700 (PTP7), that functions at the nexus between the intermediate trafficking organelle, the Maurer’s cleft, and the infected red blood cell surface. Genetic disruption of PTP7 leads to accumulation of vesicles at the Maurer’s clefts, grossly aberrant knob morphology, and failure to deliver EMP1 to the red blood cell surface. We show that an expanded low complexity sequence in the C-terminal region of PTP7, found only in the &lt;italic&gt;Laverania&lt;/italic&gt; clade of &lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium&lt;/italic&gt;, is critical for efficient virulence protein trafficking.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We describe a malaria parasite protein involved in virulence factor trafficking (PTP7) that moves between different compartments in the host red blood cell cytoplasm in a stage-dependent manner. Upon disruption of the PTP7 locus, the Maurer’s cleft trafficking compartments become decorated with vesicles; the knobby protrusions on the host red blood cell surface are depleted and distorted; and trafficking of the virulence protein, EMP1, to the host red blood cell surface is ablated. We provide evidence that a region of PTP7 with low sequence complexity plays an important role in driving fission of vesicles from the Maurer’s clefts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456062" rel="alternate" title="Virulence determinant, PTP7, controls vesicle budding from the Maurer’s clefts, adhesin protein trafficking and host cell remodeling in Plasmodium falciparum (23 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.454968</id><title>Global prediction of candidate R-loop binding and R-loop regulatory proteins (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.796675+00:00</updated><author><name>Louis-Alexandre Fournier</name></author><author><name>Arun Kumar</name></author><author><name>Theodore Smith</name></author><author><name>Edmund Su</name></author><author><name>Michelle Moksa</name></author><author><name>Martin Hirst</name></author><author><name>Peter C Stirling</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the past decade there has been a growing appreciation for R-loop structures as important regulators of the epigenome, telomere maintenance, DNA repair and replication. Given these numerous functions, dozens, or potentially hundreds, of proteins could serve as direct or indirect regulators of R-loop writing, reading, and erasing. In order to understand common properties shared amongst potential R-loop binding proteins (RLBPs) we mined published proteomic studies and distilled 10 features that were enriched in RLBPs compared to the rest of the proteome. We used these RLBP-specific features along with their amino acid composition to create a random forest classifier which predicts the likelihood of a protein to bind to R-loops. In parallel, we employed a whole-genome CRISPR screen coupled with flow-cytometry using the S9.6 monoclonal antibody to sort guide RNAs associated with induction of high S9.6 staining. Known R-loop regulating pathways such as splicing and DNA damage repair are highly enriched in our datasets, and we validate two new R-loop modulating proteins. Together these resources provide a reference to pursue analyses of novel R-loop regulatory proteins.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.454968" rel="alternate" title="Global prediction of candidate R-loop binding and R-loop regulatory proteins (22 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456143</id><title>Reconstitution of monoterpene indole alkaloid biosynthesis in Nicotiana benthamiana (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.796860+00:00</updated><author><name>Quentin M. Dudley</name></author><author><name>Seohyun Jo</name></author><author><name>Delia Ayled Serna Guerrero</name></author><author><name>Sarah E. O’Connor</name></author><author><name>Lorenzo Caputi</name></author><author><name>Nicola J. Patron</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Monoterpene indole alkaloids (MIAs) are a diverse and important class of plant natural products that include a number of medicinally significant compounds, often present at low concentrations within their native plant species. The complex biosynthesis of MIAs requires the assembly of tryptamine with a secoiridoid to produce the central intermediate, strictosidine, from which all known MIAs derive. Structural complexity makes chemical synthesis challenging, but recent efforts to identify the biosynthetic enzymes provide options for pathway reconstruction in a heterologous host. Previous attempts have had limited success, with yield in microorganisms limited by the poor expression of some enzymes. Here, we reconstitute the pathway for strictosidine biosynthesis from central metabolism without the need for supplementation of any metabolite precursors or intermediates in &lt;italic&gt;Nicotiana benthamiana&lt;/italic&gt;. The best yields were obtained by the co-expression of 14 enzymes, of which a major latex protein-like enzyme (MLPL) from &lt;italic&gt;Nepeta&lt;/italic&gt; (catmint) was critical for improving flux through the secoiridoid pathway. The production of strictosidine &lt;italic&gt;in planta&lt;/italic&gt; expands the range of MIA products amenable to biological synthesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456143" rel="alternate" title="Reconstitution of monoterpene indole alkaloid biosynthesis in Nicotiana benthamiana (19 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456228</id><title>A diabetic milieu increases cellular susceptibility to SARS-CoV-2 infections in engineered human kidney organoids and diabetic patients (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.797031+00:00</updated><author><name>Elena Garreta</name></author><author><name>Praticia Prado</name></author><author><name>Megan L. Stanifer</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Monteil</name></author><author><name>Carmen Hurtado del Pozo</name></author><author><name>Asier Ullate-Agote</name></author><author><name>Amaia Vilas-Zornoza</name></author><author><name>Juan Pablo Romero</name></author><author><name>Gustav Jonsson</name></author><author><name>Roger Oria</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Leopoldi</name></author><author><name>Astrid Hagelkrueys</name></author><author><name>Daniel Moya-Rull</name></author><author><name>Federico Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Andres Marco</name></author><author><name>Carolina Tarantino</name></author><author><name>Pere Domingo-Pedrol</name></author><author><name>Omar HasanAli</name></author><author><name>Pedro Ventura-Aguiar</name></author><author><name>Josep Maria Campistol</name></author><author><name>Felipe Prosper</name></author><author><name>Ali Mirazimi</name></author><author><name>Steeve Boulant</name></author><author><name>Josef Penninger</name></author><author><name>Nuria Montserrat</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 infections lead to a high risk of hospitalization and mortality in diabetic patients. Why diabetic individuals are more prone to develop severe COVID-19 remains unclear. Here, we established a novel human kidney organoid model that mimics early hallmarks of diabetic nephropathy. High oscillatory glucose exposure resulted in metabolic changes, expansion of extracellular membrane components, gene expression changes determined by scRNAseq, and marked upregulation of angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2). Upon SARS-CoV-2 infection, hyperglycemic conditions lead to markedly higher viral loads in kidney organoids compared to normoglycemia. Genetic deletion of ACE2, but not of the candidate receptor BSG/CD147, in kidney organoids demonstrated the essential role of ACE2 in SARS-CoV-2 infections and completely prevented SARS-CoV-2 infection in the diabetogenic microenvironment. These data introduce a novel organoid model for diabetic kidney disease and show that diabetic-induced ACE2 licenses the diabetic kidney to enhanced SARS-CoV-2 replication.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456228" rel="alternate" title="A diabetic milieu increases cellular susceptibility to SARS-CoV-2 infections in engineered human kidney organoids and diabetic patients (18 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456187</id><title>Mistargeting of hydrophobic mitochondrial proteins activates a nucleus-mediated posttranscriptional quality control pathway in trypanosomes (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.797304+00:00</updated><author><name>Caroline E. Dewar</name></author><author><name>Silke Oeljeklaus</name></author><author><name>Jan Mani</name></author><author><name>Wignand W. D. Mühlhäuser</name></author><author><name>Bettina Warscheid</name></author><author><name>André Schneider</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mitochondrial protein import in the parasitic protozoan &lt;italic&gt;Trypanosoma brucei&lt;/italic&gt; is mediated by the atypical outer membrane translocase, ATOM. It consists of seven subunits including ATOM69, the import receptor for hydrophobic proteins. Ablation of ATOM69, but not of any other subunit, triggers a unique quality control pathway resulting in the proteasomal degradation of non-imported mitochondrial proteins. The process requires a protein of unknown function, an E3 ubiquitin ligase and the ubiquitin-like protein (TbUbL1), which all are recruited to the mitochondrion upon ATOM69 depletion. TbUbL1 is a nuclear protein, a fraction of which is released to the cytosol upon triggering of the pathway. Nuclear release is essential as cytosolic TbUbL1 can bind mislocalised mitochondrial proteins and likely transfers them to the proteasome. Mitochondrial quality control has previously been studied in yeast and metazoans. Finding such a pathway in the highly diverged trypanosomes suggests such pathways are an obligate feature of all mitochondria.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456187" rel="alternate" title="Mistargeting of hydrophobic mitochondrial proteins activates a nucleus-mediated posttranscriptional quality control pathway in trypanosomes (13 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.452439</id><title>Matrix stiffness controls ciliogenesis and centriole position (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.797502+00:00</updated><author><name>Ivanna Williantarra</name></author><author><name>Sophia Leung</name></author><author><name>Yu Suk Choi</name></author><author><name>Ashika Channa</name></author><author><name>Sue R McGlashan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mechanical stress and the stiffness of the extracellular matrix are key drivers of tissue development and homeostasis. Aberrant mechanosensation is associated with a wide range of pathologies, including diseases such as osteoarthritis. Substrate stiffness is one of the well-known mechanical properties of the matrix that enabled establishing the central dogma of an integrin-mediated mechanotransduction using stem cells. However, how specific cells ‘feel’ or sense substrate stiffness requires further study. The primary cilium is an essential cellular organelle that senses and integrates mechanical and chemical signals from the extracellular environment. We hypothesised that the primary cilium dynamically alters its length and position to fine-tune cell mechanosignalling based on substrate stiffness alone. We used a hydrogel system of varying substrate stiffness to examine the role of substrate stiffness on cilia frequency, length and centriole position as well as cell and nuclei area over time. Contrary to other cell types, we show that chondrocyte primary cilia shorten on softer substrates demonstrating tissue-specific mechanosensing which is aligned with the tissue stiffness the cells originate from. We further show that stiffness alone determines centriole positioning to either the basal or apical membrane during attachment and spreading, with centriole positioned towards the basal membrane on stiffer substrates. These phenomena are mediated by force generation actin-myosin stress fibres in a time-dependent manner. Based on these findings, we propose that substrate stiffness plays a central role in cilia positioning, regulating cellular response to external forces, and may be a key driver of mechanosignalling-associated diseases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The primary cilium has been thrust into the limelight owing to its role as a cellular sensor in embryonic development and adult tissue maintenance. How the primary cilium interacts with the mechanical environment still remains unclear. We show that substrate stiffness dynamically regulates primary cilium length and position through integrin-mediated traction forces, the cilia are a key determinant of cell shape on certain stiffnesses. Our data support the promising potential of primary cilia as a novel target in mechanotherapy for improved clinical outcomes in cartilage pathobiology.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.452439" rel="alternate" title="Matrix stiffness controls ciliogenesis and centriole position (9 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456190</id><title>Screening of cell-virus, cell-cell, gene-gene interactions among kingdoms of life at single cell resolution (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.797685+00:00</updated><author><name>Dongsheng Chen</name></author><author><name>Zhihua Ou</name></author><author><name>Jiacheng Zhu</name></author><author><name>Peiwen Ding</name></author><author><name>Haoyu Wang</name></author><author><name>Lihua Luo</name></author><author><name>Xiangning Ding</name></author><author><name>Tianming Lan</name></author><author><name>Weiying Wu</name></author><author><name>Yuting Yuan</name></author><author><name>Wendi Wu</name></author><author><name>Jiaying Qiu</name></author><author><name>Yixin Zhu</name></author><author><name>Yi Jia</name></author><author><name>Yanan Wei</name></author><author><name>Qiuyu Qin</name></author><author><name>Runchu Li</name></author><author><name>Chengcheng Sun</name></author><author><name>Wandong Zhao</name></author><author><name>Zhiyuan Lv</name></author><author><name>Mingyi Pu</name></author><author><name>Shangchen Yang</name></author><author><name>Ashley Chang</name></author><author><name>Xiaofeng Wei</name></author><author><name>Fengzhen Chen</name></author><author><name>Tao Yang</name></author><author><name>Zhenyong Wei</name></author><author><name>Fan Yang</name></author><author><name>Yuejiao Li</name></author><author><name>Yan Hua</name></author><author><name>Huan Liu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The outbreak of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) issued a significant and urgent threat to global health. The exact animal origin of SARS-CoV-2 remains obscure and understanding its host range is vital for preventing interspecies transmission of this virus. Previously, we have assessed the target cell profiles of SARS-CoV-2 in pets, livestock, poultry and wild animals. With the reverse zoonotic transmission of SARS-CoV-2 to farm animals. Herein, we expand this investigation to a wider range of animal species and viruses to provide it is urgent to expand the a comprehensive source for large-scale susceptible host screening of potential virus hosts to a larger scale. Therefore, we constructed the single cell atlas for several representative mammalian species (alpaca, hamster, hedgehog, chinchilla etc.), as well as comparative atlas for lung, brain and peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) for various lineages of animals were constructed, from which we systemically analyzed the virus entry factors for SARS-CoV-2 to identify potential host species. Moreover, to fully apply these resources to the prevention of other infectious diseases, we further evaluated the target cells for 113 viruses over 10 million single cells covering 102 species from mammalians, birds, reptiles, amphibians and invertebrates. Conserved cellular connectomes and regulomes were also identified, with great implication for revealing the fundamental cell-cell and gene-gene cross-talks between these species. Overall, our study could help understand the transmission identify the potential host range and tissue tropism of SARS-CoV-2 and, as well as many other diverse set of viruses and, revealing the host-virus co-evolution footprints and throw light upon the control and prevention of current and future pandemics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456190" rel="alternate" title="Screening of cell-virus, cell-cell, gene-gene interactions among kingdoms of life at single cell resolution (9 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456094</id><title>Automated Design of Robust Genetic Circuits: Structural Variants and Parameter Uncertainty (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.821015+00:00</updated><author><name>Tobias Schladt</name></author><author><name>Nicolai Engelmann</name></author><author><name>Erik Kubaczka</name></author><author><name>Christian Hochberger</name></author><author><name>Heinz Koeppl</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genetic design automation methods for combinational circuits often rely on standard algorithms from electronic design automation in their circuit synthesis and technology mapping. However, those algorithms are domain-specific and are hence often not directly suitable for the biological context. In this work we identify aspects of those algorithms that require domain-adaptation. We first demonstrate that enumerating structural variants for a given Boolean specification allows us to find better performing circuits and that stochastic gate assignment methods need to be properly adjusted in order to find the best assignment. Second, we present a general circuit scoring scheme that accounts for the limited accuracy of biological device models including the variability across cells and show that circuits selected according to this score exhibit higher robustness with respect to parametric variations. If gate characteristics in a library are just given in terms of intervals, we provide means to efficiently propagate signals through such a circuit and compute corresponding scores. We demonstrate the novel design approach using the Cello gate library and 33 logic functions that were synthesized and implemented in vivo recently. We show that an average 1.3-fold and a peak 6.5-fold performance increase can be achieved by simply considering structural variants and that an average 1.8-fold and a peak 30-fold gain in the novel robustness score can be obtained when selecting circuits according to it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456094" rel="alternate" title="Automated Design of Robust Genetic Circuits: Structural Variants and Parameter Uncertainty (8 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456214</id><title>Microtubule-associated proteins promote microtubule generation in the absence of γ-tubulin in human colon cancer cells (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.821253+00:00</updated><author><name>Kenta Tsuchiya</name></author><author><name>Gohta Goshima</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;γ-Tubulin complex acts as the predominant microtubule (MT) nucleator that initiates MT formation and is therefore an essential factor for cell proliferation. Nonetheless, cellular MTs are formed after experimental depletion of the γ-tubulin complex, suggesting that cells possess other factors that drive MT nucleation. Here, by combining gene knockout, auxin-inducible degron, RNA interference, MT depolymerisation/regrowth assay, and live microscopy, we identified four microtubule-associated proteins (MAPs), ch-TOG, CLASP1, CAMSAPs, and TPX2, which are involved in γ-tubulin-independent MT generation in human colon cancer cells. In the mitotic MT regrowth assay, nucleated MTs organised non-centriolar MT organising centres (ncMTOCs) in the absence of γ-tubulin. Depletion of CLASP1 or TPX2 substantially delayed ncMTOC formation, suggesting that they promote MT nucleation in the absence of γ-tubulin. In contrast, depletion of CAMSAPs or ch-TOG did not affect the timing of ncMTOC appearance. CLASP1 also accelerates γ-tubulin-independent MT regrowth during interphase. Thus, MT generation can be promoted by MAPs without the γ-tubulin template.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456214" rel="alternate" title="Microtubule-associated proteins promote microtubule generation in the absence of γ-tubulin in human colon cancer cells (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455989</id><title>Structural basis of adenylyl cyclase 9 activation (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.821437+00:00</updated><author><name>Chao Qi</name></author><author><name>Pia Lavriha</name></author><author><name>Ved Mehta</name></author><author><name>Basavraj Khanppnavar</name></author><author><name>Inayathulla Mohammed</name></author><author><name>Yong Li</name></author><author><name>Michalis Lazaratos</name></author><author><name>Jonas V. Schaefer</name></author><author><name>Birgit Dreier</name></author><author><name>Andreas Plückthun</name></author><author><name>Ana-Nicoleta Bondar</name></author><author><name>Carmen W. Dessauer</name></author><author><name>Volodymyr M. Korkhov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Adenylyl cyclase 9 (AC9) is a membrane-bound enzyme that converts ATP into cAMP. The enzyme is weakly activated by forskolin, fully activated by the G protein Gαs subunit and is autoinhibited by the AC9 C-terminus. Although our recent structural studies of the AC9-Gαs complex provided the framework for understanding AC9 autoinhibition, the conformational changes that AC9 undergoes in response to activator binding remains poorly understood. Here, we present the cryo-EM structures of AC9 in several distinct states: (i) AC9 bound to a nucleotide inhibitor MANT-GTP, (ii) bound to an artificial activator (DARPin C4) and MANT-GTP, (iii) bound to DARPin C4 and a nucleotide analogue ATPαS, (iv) bound to Gαs and MANT-GTP. The artificial activator DARPin C4 partially activates AC9 by binding at a site that overlaps with the Gαs binding site. Together with the previously observed occluded and forskolin-bound conformations, structural comparisons of AC9 in the four new conformations show that secondary structure rearrangements in the region surrounding the forskolin binding site are essential for AC9 activation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cryo-EM reveals activator-induced conformational changes in adenylyl cyclase AC9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455989" rel="alternate" title="Structural basis of adenylyl cyclase 9 activation (8 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455983</id><title>A method for the fast and photon-efficient analysis of time-domain fluorescence lifetime image data over large dynamic ranges (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.821701+00:00</updated><author><name>Romain F. Laine</name></author><author><name>Clemens F. Kaminski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fluorescence lifetime imaging (FLIM) allows the quantification of subcellular processes &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt;, in living cells. A number of approaches have been developed to extract the lifetime from time-domain FLIM data, but they are often limited in terms of dynamic range, speed, photon efficiency or precision. Here, we focus on one of the best performing methods in the field, the center-of-mass (CMM) method, that conveys advantages in terms of speed and photon efficiency over others. In this paper, however, we identify a loss of photon efficiency of CMM for short lifetimes when background noise is present. We sub-sequently present a new development and generalization of the CMM method that provides for the rapid and accurate extraction of fluorescence lifetime over a large lifetime dynamic range. We provide software tools to simulate, validate and analyze FLIM data sets and compare the performance of our approach against the standard CMM and the commonly employed leastsquare minimization (LSM) methods. Our method features a better photon efficiency than standard CMM and LSM and is robust in the presence of background noise. The algorithm is applicable to any time-domain FLIM dataset.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455983" rel="alternate" title="A method for the fast and photon-efficient analysis of time-domain fluorescence lifetime image data over large dynamic ranges (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456045</id><title>Autophagy cargo receptors are secreted via extracellular vesicles and particles in response to endolysosomal inhibition or impaired autophagosome maturation (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.821950+00:00</updated><author><name>Tina A. Solvik</name></author><author><name>Tan A. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Yu-Hsiu Tony Lin</name></author><author><name>Timothy Marsh</name></author><author><name>Eric J. Huang</name></author><author><name>Arun P. Wiita</name></author><author><name>Jayanta Debnath</name></author><author><name>Andrew M. Leidal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The endosome-lysosome (endolysosome) system plays central roles in both autophagic degradation and secretory pathways, including the exocytic release of extracellular vesicles and particles (EVPs). Although previous work has revealed important interconnections between autophagy and EVP-mediated secretion, our molecular understanding of these secretory events during endolysosome inhibition remains incomplete. Here, we delineate a secretory autophagy pathway upregulated in response to endolysosomal inhibition that mediates the EVP-associated extracellular release of autophagic cargo receptors, including p62/SQSTM1. This extracellular secretion is highly regulated and critically dependent on multiple ATGs required for the progressive steps of early autophagosome formation as well as Rab27a-dependent exocytosis. Furthermore, the disruption of autophagosome maturation, either due to genetic inhibition of the autophagosome-to-autolyosome fusion machinery or blockade via the SARS-CoV2 viral protein ORF3a, is sufficient to induce robust EVP-associated secretion of autophagy cargo receptors. Finally, we demonstrate that this ATG-dependent, EVP-mediated secretion pathway buffers against the intracellular accumulation of autophagy cargo receptors when classical autophagic degradation is impaired. Based on these results, we propose that secretory autophagy via EVPs functions as an alternate route to clear sequestered material and maintain proteostasis in response to endolysosomal dysfunction or impaired autophagosome maturation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456045" rel="alternate" title="Autophagy cargo receptors are secreted via extracellular vesicles and particles in response to endolysosomal inhibition or impaired autophagosome maturation (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456107</id><title>BubR1 recruitment to the kinetochore via Bub1 enhances Spindle Assembly Checkpoint signaling (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.822229+00:00</updated><author><name>Anand Banerjee</name></author><author><name>Chu Chen</name></author><author><name>Lauren Humphrey</name></author><author><name>John J. Tyson</name></author><author><name>Ajit P. Joglekar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During mitosis, unattached kinetochores in a dividing cell generate the anaphase-inhibitory Mitotic Checkpoint Complex (MCC) to activate the Spindle Assembly Checkpoint (SAC) and delay anaphase onset. To generate MCC, these kinetochores recruit MCC constituent proteins including the protein BubR1. The increased local concentration of BubR1 resulting from this recruitment should enhance MCC generation, but prior studies found this not to be the case. We analyzed the contribution of two BubR1 recruitment pathways to MCC generation in human kinetochores. For these analyses, we isolated a subset of the MCC generation reactions to the cytosol using ectopic SAC activation systems. These analyses and mathematical modeling show that BubR1 binding to the SAC protein Bub1, but not to the ‘KI’ motifs in the kinetochore protein Knl1, significantly enhances the rate of Bub1-mediated MCC generation in the kinetochore. Our work also suggests that Bub1-BubR1 stoichiometry will strongly influence the dose-response characteristics of SAC signaling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456107" rel="alternate" title="BubR1 recruitment to the kinetochore via Bub1 enhances Spindle Assembly Checkpoint signaling (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456279</id><title>Comparative Analysis and Rational Design of dCas9-VP64 Variants for CRISPR Activation (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.822452+00:00</updated><author><name>Kohei Omachi</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey H Miner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;CRISPR/Cas9-mediated transcriptional activation (CRISPRa) is a powerful tool for investigating complex biological phenomena. Although CRISPRa approaches based on VP64 have been widely studied in both cultured cells and in animal models and exhibit great versatility for various cell types and developmental stages in vivo, different dCas9-VP64 versions have not been rigorously compared. Here, we compared different dCas9-VP64 constructs in identical contexts, including the cell lines used and the transfection conditions, for their ability to activate endogenous and exogenous genes. Moreover, we investigated the optimal approach for VP64 addition to VP64- and p300-based constructs. We found that MS2-MCP-scaffolded VP64 enhanced dCas9-VP64 and dCas9-p300 activity better than did direct VP64 fusion to the N-terminus of dCas9. dCas9-VP64+MCP-VP64 and dCas9-p300+MCP-VP64 were superior to VP64-dCas9-VP64 for all target genes tested. Furthermore, multiplexing gRNA expression with dCas9-VP64+MCP-VP64 or dCas9-p300+MCP-VP64 significantly enhanced endogenous gene activation to a level comparable to CRISPRa-SAM with a single gRNA. Our findings demonstrate improvement of the dCas9-VP64 CRISPRa system and contribute to development of a versatile, efficient CRISPRa platform.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456279" rel="alternate" title="Comparative Analysis and Rational Design of dCas9-VP64 Variants for CRISPR Activation (6 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456061</id><title>Integrin signaling via actin cytoskeleton activates MRTF/SRF to entrain circadian clock (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.822627+00:00</updated><author><name>Xuekai Xiong</name></author><author><name>Weini Li</name></author><author><name>Jin Nam</name></author><author><name>Ke Ma</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The circadian clock is entrained to daily environmental cues. Integrin-linked intracellular signaling &lt;italic&gt;via&lt;/italic&gt; actin cytoskeleton dynamics transduces cellular niche signals to induce Myocardin-related Transcription Factor (MRTF)/Serum Response Factor (SRF)-mediated transcription. So far, how the integrin-associated signaling cascade may transmit cellular physical cues to entrain circadian clock remains to be defined. Using combined pharmacological and genetic approaches, here we show that the transcription factors mediating integrin to actin cytoskeleton signaling, MRTF-A and SRF, exert direct transcriptional control of core clock components, and that this signaling cascade modulates key properties of clock circadian activity. Pharmacological inhibition of MRTF/SRF activity by disrupting actin polymerization significantly augmented clock amplitude with period shortening, whereas an actin polymerizing compound attenuated oscillation amplitude with period lengthening. Genetic loss-of-function of &lt;italic&gt;Srf&lt;/italic&gt; or &lt;italic&gt;Mrtf&lt;/italic&gt; mimics that of actin-depolymerizing agents, validating the role of actin dynamics in driving clock function. Furthermore, integrin-mediated focal adhesion with extracellular matrix and its downstream signaling modulates the circadian clock, as blockade of integrin, focal adhesion kinase or Rho-associated kinase (ROCK) increased clock amplitude and shortened period length. Mechanistically, we identify specific core clock transcription regulators, &lt;italic&gt;Per1, Per2&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Nr1d1&lt;/italic&gt;, as direct target genes of MRTF-A/SRF. Collectively, our findings uncovered an integrin-actin cytoskeleton-MRTF/SRF signaling cascade in linking clock entrainment to its extracellular microenvironment, which may mediate cellular adaptation to its physical niche.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The circadian clock anticipates and adapts to environmental changes. Interestingly, serum, as a universal clock synchronizing signal, drives intracellular actin cytoskeleton reorganization through modulation of MRTF/SRF activity. However, mechanisms that may transduce extracellular niche signals to circadian clock remains to be defined. We hypothesize that integrin-mediated intracellular signaling to actin cytoskeleton links extracellular microenvironment with MRTF/SRF transcriptional regulation to control clock function. Using small molecules and genetic approaches targeting distinct steps of integrin-actin cytoskeleton-MRTF/SRF signaling cascade, we uncover the effects of this pathway in controlling circadian clock oscillation. We also identify specific core clock regulators as direct gene target genes of MRTF and SRF-mediated transcriptional control. Our study revealed how integrin-mediated cellular interaction with its physical environment influences its intrinsic clock properties through signaling transduction &lt;italic&gt;via&lt;/italic&gt; actin cytoskeleton remodeling, and that this mechanism may facilitate circadian clock adaptation to cellular physical niche.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456061" rel="alternate" title="Integrin signaling via actin cytoskeleton activates MRTF/SRF to entrain circadian clock (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.455965</id><title>O-GlcNAcylation is essential for rapid Pomc expression and cell proliferation in corticotropic tumor cells (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.822812+00:00</updated><author><name>Logan J Massman</name></author><author><name>Michael Pereckas</name></author><author><name>Nathan T Zwagerman</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Olivier-Van Stichelen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pituitary adenomas have a staggering 16.7% lifetime prevalence and can be devastating in many patients due to profound endocrine and neurologic dysfunction. To date, no clear genomic or epigenomic markers correlates with their onset or severity. Herein, we investigate the impact of the &lt;italic&gt;O&lt;/italic&gt;-GlcNAc post-translational modification in their etiology. Found in over 5000 human proteins to date, &lt;italic&gt;O&lt;/italic&gt;-GlcNAcylation dynamically regulates proteins in critical signaling pathways, and its deregulation is involved in cancers progression and endocrine diseases such as diabetes. In this study, we demonstrate that &lt;italic&gt;O&lt;/italic&gt;-GlcNAcylation enzymes were upregulated, particularly in aggressive ACTH-secreting tumors, suggesting a role for &lt;italic&gt;O&lt;/italic&gt;-GlcNAcylation in pituitary adenoma etiology. In addition to the demonstration that &lt;italic&gt;O&lt;/italic&gt;-GlcNAcylation was essential for their proliferation, we show that the endocrine function of pituitary adenoma is also dependent on &lt;italic&gt;O&lt;/italic&gt;-GlcNAcylation. In corticotropic tumors, hyper-secretion of the proopiomelanocortin (POMC)-derived hormone ACTH leads to Cushing disease, materialized by severe endocrine disruption and increased mortality. We demonstrate that &lt;italic&gt;Pomc&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA is stabilized in an &lt;italic&gt;O&lt;/italic&gt;-GlcNAc-dependent manner in response to corticotropic-stimulating hormone (CRH). By impacting &lt;italic&gt;Pomc&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA splicing and stability, &lt;italic&gt;O&lt;/italic&gt;-GlcNAcylation contributes to this new mechanism of fast hormonal response in corticotropes. Thus, this study stresses the essential role of &lt;italic&gt;O&lt;/italic&gt;-GlcNAcylation in ACTH-secreting adenomas pathophysiology, including cellular proliferation and hypersecretion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.455965" rel="alternate" title="O-GlcNAcylation is essential for rapid Pomc expression and cell proliferation in corticotropic tumor cells (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456145</id><title>Sclerostin Small Molecule Inhibitors Promote Osteogenesis by Activating Canonical Wnt and BMP Pathways (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.822995+00:00</updated><author><name>Sreedhara Sangadala</name></author><author><name>Chi Heon Kim</name></author><author><name>Lorenzo M. Fernandes</name></author><author><name>Pooja Makkar</name></author><author><name>Scott D. Boden</name></author><author><name>George R. Beck</name></author><author><name>Hicham Drissi</name></author><author><name>Steven M. Presciutti</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The healing environment within the posterolateral lumbar spine is one of the most clinically challenging bone healing environments in all of orthopaedics due to a lack of a contained space and the need to form &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; bone in a non-bony environment. Our group has previously published data that suggests that sclerostin in expressed locally at high levels throughout the process of a spinal fusion mass maturing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We computationally identified multiple FDA-approved drugs, as well as a novel drug, for their ability to disrupt the interaction between sclerostin and its receptor, LRP5/6. The drugs were tested in several in vitro biochemical assays using murine MC3T3 and MSCs, assessing their ability to (1) enhance canonical Wnt signaling, (2) promote the accumulation of the active (non-phosphorylated) form of β-catenin, and (3) enhance the intensity and signaling duration of BMP signaling. These drugs were then tested subcutaneously in rats as standalone osteoinductive agents on plain collagen sponges. Finally, the top drug candidates (called VA1 and C07) were tested in a rabbit posterolateral spine fusion model for their ability to achieve a successful fusion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We show that by controlling GSK3b phosphorylation, these SMIs simultaneously enhance canonical Wnt signaling and potentiate canonical BMP signaling intensity and duration. We also demonstrate that the SMIs produce dose-dependent ectopic mineralization &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; in rats as well as significantly increase posterolateral spine fusion rates in rabbits &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, both as standalone osteogenic drugs and in combination with autologous iliac crest bone graft.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Few if any osteogenic small molecules have been described that possess the osteoinductive potency of BMP itself – that is, the ability to form &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; ectopic bone as a standalone agent, particularly in stringent &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; environments. Herein, we describe two such SMIs that have this unique ability and thus may have potential application as novel cost-effective biologic bone graft substitutes for achieving consistent spinal fusion or even or critical-sized fracture defects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This work was supported by a Veteran Affairs Career Development Award (IK2-BX003845).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456145" rel="alternate" title="Sclerostin Small Molecule Inhibitors Promote Osteogenesis by Activating Canonical Wnt and BMP Pathways (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455802</id><title>Quantifying the antimicrobial activity of CRISPR-Cas9-accA modified ΔB. subtilis mutants against V. harveyi and E. Coli (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.823208+00:00</updated><author><name>Tatiana Hillman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Probiotics are increasingly popular, currently. Probiotics have been described with the ability to treat many disorders of the gastrointestinal tract (GIT) such as irritable bowel syndrome (IBS) and Crohn’s disease. Types of probiotics include bacterial strains from &lt;italic&gt;Lactobacillus&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Bifidobacterium&lt;/italic&gt;. Probiotics can restore balance to gut microbiota by outcompeting pathogenic bacteria for nutrients and secrete antimicrobials to eliminate these bacterial pathogens. However, the viability of most advertised probiotics lose their potency due to being freeze dried into powders during storage or for consuming. Many probiotics become ineffective and produce lower CFUs while traversing through the gastric acids of the digestive system. For these reasons, this study sought to enhance the antimicrobial response of a highly potent probiotic known as &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus subtilis. B. subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; has been used to treat many disorders of the gut and secrete many antimicrobials lethal for pathogenic microbes. &lt;italic&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; was genetically modified to express CRISPR-Cas9 nuclease deletion of the &lt;italic&gt;accA&lt;/italic&gt; gene (Δ&lt;italic&gt;B.subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; mutants), which inhibits expression of an essential &lt;italic&gt;accA&lt;/italic&gt; gene a part of the fatty acid synthesis (FAS) metabolic pathway. The CRISPR-Cas9-&lt;italic&gt;accA ΔB.subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; mutants were co-cultured with &lt;italic&gt;V. harveyi&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;E. Coli&lt;/italic&gt;. Bacterial growth, biofilm formation, antimicrobial activity, and antibiotic resistance were quantified. It was found that &lt;italic&gt;ΔB.subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; mutants co-cultured with &lt;italic&gt;V. harveyi&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;E. Coli&lt;/italic&gt; lessened bacterial growth, amplified biofilm with &lt;italic&gt;V. harveyi&lt;/italic&gt;, reduced biofilm formation of &lt;italic&gt;E. Coli&lt;/italic&gt;, the co-cultures with the mutants lacked antimicrobial activity, and increased the antibiotic resistance of &lt;italic&gt;V. harveyi&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;E. Coli&lt;/italic&gt;. It can be concluded that there is an immense potential for using genetically engineered probiotic strains to enhance the antimicrobial activity of &lt;italic&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/italic&gt;, which can amplify the reduction of pathogenic bacteria. However, the safety and frugality of using &lt;italic&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; as a probiotic requires further consideration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455802" rel="alternate" title="Quantifying the antimicrobial activity of CRISPR-Cas9-accA modified ΔB. subtilis mutants against V. harveyi and E. Coli (4 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456080</id><title>Sphingosine 1-Phosphate Mediates Adiponectin Receptor Signaling Essential For Lipid Homeostasis and Embryogenesis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.823372+00:00</updated><author><name>Mario Ruiz</name></author><author><name>Ranjan Devkota</name></author><author><name>Dimitra Panagaki</name></author><author><name>Per-Olof Bergh</name></author><author><name>Delaney Kaper</name></author><author><name>Marcus Henricsson</name></author><author><name>Ali Nik</name></author><author><name>Kasparas Petkevicius</name></author><author><name>Johanna L. Höög</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Bohlooly-Y</name></author><author><name>Peter Carlsson</name></author><author><name>Jan Borén</name></author><author><name>Marc Pilon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cells and organisms require proper membrane composition to function and develop. Phospholipids are the major component of membranes and are primarily acquired through the diet. Given great variability in diet composition, cells must be able to deploy mechanisms that correct deviations from optimal membrane composition and properties. Here, using unbiased lipidomics and proteomics, we found that the embryonic lethality in mice lacking the fluidity regulators Adiponectin Receptors 1 and 2 (AdipoR1/2) is associated with aberrant high saturation of the membrane phospholipids. Using mouse embryonic fibroblasts (MEFs) derived from AdipoR1/2-KO embryos, human cell lines and the model organism &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; we found that, mechanistically, AdipoR1/2-derived sphingosine 1-phosphate (S1P) signals in parallel through S1PR3-SREBP1 and PPARγ to sustain the expression of the fatty acid desaturase SCD and maintain membrane properties. Thus, our work identifies an evolutionary conserved pathway by which cells and organism maintain membrane homeostasis and adapt to a variable environment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="456080v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;In Brief&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cells and organisms require proper membrane composition to function and develop. Ruiz et al. identified AdipoR1/2-derived S1P as essential for membrane homeostasis in mammals and invertebrates. S1P signals through SREBP and PPARγ to sustain fatty acid desaturation. Targeting AdipoR1/2 pathway may be a therapeutic approach for disorders with dysfunctional membranes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="simple"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;-&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Excess membrane phospholipid saturation explains AdipoR1/2 DKO embryonic lethality&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;-&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;AdipoR1/2 DKO membrane defects are rescued by S1P&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;-&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Parallel activation of S1PR3 and PPARγ by S1P mediates AdipoR2 membrane protection&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;-&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fatty acid desaturation is the final outputs of the AdipoR2-S1P signaling pathway&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456080" rel="alternate" title="Sphingosine 1-Phosphate Mediates Adiponectin Receptor Signaling Essential For Lipid Homeostasis and Embryogenesis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.454108</id><title>Independently paced calcium oscillations in progenitor and differentiated cells in an ex vivo epithelial organ (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.823621+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna A. Kim</name></author><author><name>Amanda Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Marco Marchetti</name></author><author><name>Denise Montell</name></author><author><name>Beth. L. Pruitt</name></author><author><name>Lucy Erin O’Brien</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cytosolic calcium is a highly dynamic, tightly regulated, and broadly conserved cellular signal. Calcium dynamics have been studied widely in cellular monocultures, yet &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; most organs comprise heterogeneous populations of stem and differentiated cells. We examined calcium dynamics in each cell type of the adult &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; intestine, a self-renewing epithelial organ where multipotent stem cells give rise to mature absorptive enterocytes and secretory enteroendocrine cells. Here we perform live imaging of whole organs &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, and we employ orthogonal expression of red and green calcium sensors to determine whether calcium oscillations between different cell types are coupled. We show that stem cell daughters adopt strikingly distinct patterns of calcium oscillations when they acquire their terminal fates: Enteroendocrine cells exhibit single-cell calcium oscillations, while long-range calcium waves propagate rhythmically across large fields of enterocytes. These multicellular waves do not propagate through progenitor cells (stem cells and undifferentiated enterocyte precursors), whose oscillation frequency is approximately half that of enteroendocrine cells. Organ-scale inhibition of gap junctions eliminates calcium oscillations in all three cell types, even, intriguingly, in progenitor and enteroendocrine cells that are surrounded only by enterocytes. Our findings establish that cells adopt fate-specific modes of calcium dynamics as they terminally differentiate and reveal that the oscillatory dynamics of different cell types in the same epithelium are paced independently.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.454108" rel="alternate" title="Independently paced calcium oscillations in progenitor and differentiated cells in an ex vivo epithelial organ (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455626</id><title>Identification and characterization of distinct cell cycle stages in cardiomyocytes using the FUCCI transgenic system (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.823820+00:00</updated><author><name>Marion Baniol</name></author><author><name>Francesca Murganti</name></author><author><name>Agata Smialowska</name></author><author><name>Joni Panula</name></author><author><name>Enikö Lazar</name></author><author><name>Viveka Brockman</name></author><author><name>Sarantis Giatrellis</name></author><author><name>Wouter Derks</name></author><author><name>Olaf Bergmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the regulatory mechanism by which cardiomyocyte proliferation transitions to endoreplication and cell cycle arrest during the neonatal period is crucial for identifying proproliferative factors and developing regenerative therapies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used a transgenic mouse model based on the fluorescent ubiquitination-based cell cycle indicator (FUCCI) system to isolate and characterize cycling cardiomyocytes at different cell cycle stages at a single-cell resolution. Single-cell transcriptome analysis of cycling and noncycling cardiomyocytes was performed at postnatal days 0 (P0) and 7 (P7).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FUCCI system proved to be efficient for the identification of cycling cardiomyocytes with the highest mitotic activity at birth, followed by a gradual decline in the number of cycling and mitotic cardiomyocytes during the neonatal period. Cardiomyocytes showed premature cell cycle exit at G1/S shortly after birth and delayed G1/S progression during endoreplication at P7. Single-cell RNA-seq confirmed previously described signaling pathways involved in cardiomyocyte proliferation (Erbb2 and Hippo/YAP), cardiomyocyte motility, and maturation-related transcriptional changes during postnatal development, including the metabolic switch from glycolysis to fatty acid oxidation in cardiomyocytes. Additionally, we generated transcriptional profiles specific to cell division and endoreplication in cardiomyocytes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deciphering transcriptional changes at different developmental stages and in a cell cycle-specific manner may facilitate the identification of genes important for adult cardiomyocyte proliferation and heart regeneration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;FUCCI reliably identifies cycling cardiomyocytes at distinct cell cycle stages in neonatal, juvenile, and adult hearts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cell cycle activity decreases as the metabolic switch transitions from glycolysis to fatty acid metabolism in postnatal cardiomyocytes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cell cycle arrest at G1/S is linked to the DNA damage response in postnatal cardiomyocytes.
Distinct gene expression patterns are linked to different cell cycle phases in dividing and endoreplicating postnatal cardiomyocytes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455626" rel="alternate" title="Identification and characterization of distinct cell cycle stages in cardiomyocytes using the FUCCI transgenic system (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455999</id><title>Physiologically based modeling of the effect of physiological and anthropometric variability on indocyanine green based liver function tests (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.824037+00:00</updated><author><name>Adrian Köller</name></author><author><name>Jan Grzegorzewski</name></author><author><name>Matthias König</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Accurate evaluation of liver function is a central task in hepatology. Dynamic liver function tests (DLFT) based on the time-dependent elimination of a test substance provide an important tool for such a functional assessment. These tests are used in the diagnosis and monitoring of liver disease as well as in the planning of hepatobiliary surgery. A key challenge in the evaluation of liver function with DLFTs is the large inter-individual variability. Indocyanine green (ICG) is a widely applied test compound used for the evaluation of liver function. After an intravenous administration, pharmacokinetic (PK) parameters are calculated from the plasma disappearance curve of ICG which provide an estimate of liver function. The hepatic elimination of ICG is affected by physiological factors such as hepatic blood flow or binding of ICG to plasma proteins, anthropometric factors such as body weight, age, and sex, or the protein amount of the organic anion-transporting polypeptide 1B3 (OATP1B3) mediating the hepatic uptake of ICG. Being able to account for and better understand these various sources of inter-individual variability would allow to improve the power of ICG based DLFTs and move towards an individualized evaluation of liver function. Within this work we systematically analyzed the effect of various factors on ICG elimination by the means of computational modeling. For the analysis, a recently developed and validated physiologically based pharmacokinetics (PBPK) model of ICG distribution and hepatic elimination was utilized. Key results are (i) a systematic analysis of the variability in ICG elimination due to hepatic blood flow, cardiac output, OATP1B3 abundance, liver volume, body weight and plasma bilirubin level; (ii) the evaluation of the inter-individual variability in ICG elimination via a large &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; cohort of n=100000 subjects based on the NHANES cohort with special focus on stratification by age, sex, and body weight; (iii) the evaluation of the effect of various degrees of cirrhosis on variability in ICG elimination. The presented results are an important step towards individualizing liver function tests by elucidating the effects of confounding physiological and anthropometric parameters in the evaluation of liver function via ICG.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455999" rel="alternate" title="Physiologically based modeling of the effect of physiological and anthropometric variability on indocyanine green based liver function tests (3 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456222</id><title>Quantifying cumulative phenotypic and genomic evidence for procedural generation of metabolic network reconstructions (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.824214+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas James Moutinho</name></author><author><name>Benjamin C Neubert</name></author><author><name>Matthew L Jenior</name></author><author><name>Jason A. Papin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genome-scale metabolic network reconstructions (GENREs) are valuable tools for understanding microbial community metabolism. The process of automatically generating GENREs includes identifying metabolic reactions supported by sufficient genomic evidence to generate a draft metabolic network. The draft GENRE is then gapfilled with additional reactions in order to recapitulate specific growth phenotypes as indicated with associated experimental data. Previous methods have implemented absolute mapping thresholds for the reactions automatically included in draft GENREs; however, there is growing evidence that integrating annotation evidence in a continuous form can improve model accuracy. There is a need for flexibility in the structure of GENREs to better account for uncertainty in biological data, unknown regulatory mechanisms, and context specificity associated with data inputs. To address this issue, we present a novel method that provides a framework for quantifying combined genomic, biochemical, and phenotypic evidence for each biochemical reaction during automated GENRE construction. Our method, Constraint-based Analysis Yielding reaction Usage across metabolic Networks (CANYUNs), generates accurate GENREs with a quantitative metric for the cumulative evidence for each reaction included in the network. The structure of a CANYUN GENRE allows for the simultaneous integration of three data inputs while maintaining all supporting evidence for biochemical reactions that may be active in an organism. CANYUNs is designed to maximize the utility of experimental and annotation datasets and to ultimately assist in the curation of the reference datasets used for the automatic reconstruction of metabolic networks. We validated CANYUNs by generating an  E. coli  K-12 model and compared it to the manually curated reconstruction iML1515. Finally, we demonstrated the use of CANYUNs to build a model by generating an  E. coli  Nissle CANYUN GENRE using novel phenotypic data that we collected. This method may address key challenges for the procedural construction of metabolic networks by leveraging uncertainty and redundancy in biological data.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456222" rel="alternate" title="Quantifying cumulative phenotypic and genomic evidence for procedural generation of metabolic network reconstructions (3 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>