<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.075039+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462231</id><title>Structures of core eukaryotic protein complexes (93 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.075654+00:00</updated><author><name>Ian R. Humphreys</name></author><author><name>Jimin Pei</name></author><author><name>Minkyung Baek</name></author><author><name>Aditya Krishnakumar</name></author><author><name>Ivan Anishchenko</name></author><author><name>Sergey Ovchinnikov</name></author><author><name>Jing Zhang</name></author><author><name>Travis J. Ness</name></author><author><name>Sudeep Banjade</name></author><author><name>Saket Bagde</name></author><author><name>Viktoriya G. Stancheva</name></author><author><name>Xiao-Han Li</name></author><author><name>Kaixian Liu</name></author><author><name>Zhi Zheng</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Barrero</name></author><author><name>Upasana Roy</name></author><author><name>Israel S. Fernández</name></author><author><name>Barnabas Szakal</name></author><author><name>Dana Branzei</name></author><author><name>Eric C. Greene</name></author><author><name>Sue Biggins</name></author><author><name>Scott Keeney</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth A. Miller</name></author><author><name>J. Christopher Fromme</name></author><author><name>Tamara L. Hendrickson</name></author><author><name>Qian Cong</name></author><author><name>David Baker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protein-protein interactions play critical roles in biology, but despite decades of effort, the structures of many eukaryotic protein complexes are unknown, and there are likely many interactions that have not yet been identified. Here, we take advantage of recent advances in proteome-wide amino acid coevolution analysis and deep-learning-based structure modeling to systematically identify and build accurate models of core eukaryotic protein complexes, as represented within the &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; proteome. We use a combination of RoseTTAFold and AlphaFold to screen through paired multiple sequence alignments for 8.3 million pairs of &lt;italic&gt;S. cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; proteins and build models for strongly predicted protein assemblies with two to five components. Comparison to existing interaction and structural data suggests that these predictions are likely to be quite accurate. We provide structure models spanning almost all key processes in Eukaryotic cells for 104 protein assemblies which have not been previously identified, and 608 which have not been structurally characterized.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We take advantage of recent advances in proteome-wide amino acid coevolution analysis and deep-learning-based structure modeling to systematically identify and build accurate models of core eukaryotic protein complexes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462231" rel="alternate" title="Structures of core eukaryotic protein complexes (93 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461575</id><title>Cryo-EM structures reveal high-resolution mechanism of a DNA polymerase sliding clamp loader (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.076196+00:00</updated><author><name>Christl Gaubitz</name></author><author><name>Xingchen Liu</name></author><author><name>Joshua Pajak</name></author><author><name>Nicholas P. Stone</name></author><author><name>Janelle A. Hayes</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Demo</name></author><author><name>Brian A Kelch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sliding clamps are ring-shaped protein complexes that are integral to the DNA replication machinery of all life. Sliding clamps are opened and installed onto DNA by clamp loader AAA+ ATPase complexes. However, how a clamp loader opens and closes the sliding clamp around DNA is still unknown. Here, we describe structures of the &lt;italic&gt;S. cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; clamp loader Replication Factor C (RFC) bound to its cognate sliding clamp Proliferating Cell Nuclear Antigen (PCNA) en route to successful loading. RFC first binds to PCNA in a dynamic, closed conformation that blocks both ATPase activity and DNA binding. RFC then opens the PCNA ring through a large-scale ‘crab-claw’ expansion of both RFC and PCNA that explains how RFC prefers initial binding of PCNA over DNA. Next, the open RFC:PCNA complex binds DNA and interrogates the primer-template junction using a surprising base-flipping mechanism. Our structures indicate that initial PCNA opening and subsequent closure around DNA do not require ATP hydrolysis, but are driven by binding energy. ATP hydrolysis, which is necessary for RFC release, is triggered by interactions with both PCNA and DNA, explaining RFC’s switch-like ATPase activity. Our work reveals how a AAA+ machine undergoes dramatic conformational changes for achieving binding preference and substrate remodeling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461575" rel="alternate" title="Cryo-EM structures reveal high-resolution mechanism of a DNA polymerase sliding clamp loader (37 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461577</id><title>Tracking extracellular vesicle (EV) cargo as a platform for studying EVomics, signaling, and targeting in vivo (32 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.076486+00:00</updated><author><name>Inna A. Nikonorova</name></author><author><name>Juan Wang</name></author><author><name>Alexander L. Cope</name></author><author><name>Peter Tilton</name></author><author><name>Kaiden M. Power</name></author><author><name>Jonathon D. Walsh</name></author><author><name>Jyothi S. Akella</name></author><author><name>Amber R. Krauchunas</name></author><author><name>Premal Shah</name></author><author><name>Maureen M. Barr</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Extracellular vesicle (EV)-based signaling is a challenge to study, due to EV small size, heterogeneity, and limited information on cargo content &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. We present &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/italic&gt; as a discovery platform that allows single EV tracking from source to target tissue in living animals. We enriched ciliary EVs using GFP-tagged PKD-2 cargo followed by mass spectrometry analysis to identify 2,888 cargo candidates. By integrating our dataset with single-cell transcriptomic data, we identified EV cargo produced by individual neurons and other cell and tissue types. A single cilium produces multiple EVs with distinct protein content. Ciliary EVs carry nucleic acid binding proteins. We observed transfer of EV cargo from the male reproductive tract to the hermaphrodite uterus during mating, a direct demonstration of animal-to-animal EV targeting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we present a discovery platform for studying animal extracellular vesicle composition and biogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461577" rel="alternate" title="Tracking extracellular vesicle (EV) cargo as a platform for studying EVomics, signaling, and targeting in vivo (32 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461247</id><title>Solvent Precipitation SP3 (SP4) enhances recovery for proteomics sample preparation without magnetic beads (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.076940+00:00</updated><author><name>Harvey E. Johnston</name></author><author><name>Kranthikumar Yadav</name></author><author><name>Joanna M. Kirkpatrick</name></author><author><name>George S. Biggs</name></author><author><name>David Oxley</name></author><author><name>Holger B. Kramer</name></author><author><name>Rahul S. Samant</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Complete, reproducible extraction of protein material is essential for comprehensive and unbiased proteome analyses. A current gold standard is single-pot, solid-phase-enhanced sample preparation (SP3), in which organic solvent and magnetic beads are used to denature and capture proteins, with subsequently washes allowing contaminant removal. However, SP3 is dependent on effective protein immobilisation onto beads, risks losses during wash steps, and experiences a drop-off in protein recovery at higher protein inputs. Magnetic beads may also contaminate samples and instruments, and become costly for larger scale protein preparations. Here, we propose solvent precipitation SP3 (SP4) as an alternative to SP3, omitting magnetic beads and employing brief centrifugation—either with or without low-cost inert glass beads—as the means of aggregated protein capture. SP4 recovered equivalent or greater protein yields for 1–5000 µg preparations and improved reproducibility (median protein &lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 0.99 (SP4) &lt;italic&gt;vs&lt;/italic&gt;. 0.97 (SP3)). Deep proteome profiling (n = 9,076) also demonstrated improved recovery by SP4 and a significant enrichment of membrane and low-solubility proteins vs. SP3. The effectiveness of SP4 was verified in three other labs, each confirming equivalent or improved proteome characterisation over SP3. This work suggests that protein precipitation is the primary mechanism of SP3, and reliance on magnetic beads presents protein losses, especially at higher concentrations and amongst hydrophobic proteins. SP4 represents an efficient and effective alternative to SP3, provides the option to omit beads entirely, and offers virtually unlimited scalability of input and volume—all whilst retaining the speed and universality of SP3.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;BRIEF&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Solvent precipitation SP3 (SP4) captures aggregated protein for proteomics sample clean-up by omitting magnetic beads, instead employing brief centrifugation—with or without low-cost inert glass beads. SP4 offers improvements to protein yields, higher reproducibility, and greater recovery of membrane proteins, with verifications from three labs. Protein precipitation appears to be the primary mechanism of SP3, with reliance on magnetic beads presenting protein losses, especially at higher concentrations. SP4 presents an effective alternative to SP3 with improved scalability and equal speed and universality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;GRAPHICAL ABSTRACT&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="461247v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461247" rel="alternate" title="Solvent Precipitation SP3 (SP4) enhances recovery for proteomics sample preparation without magnetic beads (29 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461725</id><title>Eco1-dependent cohesin acetylation anchors chromatin loops and cohesion to define functional meiotic chromosome domains (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.077138+00:00</updated><author><name>Rachael E. Barton</name></author><author><name>Lucia F. Massari</name></author><author><name>Daniel Robertson</name></author><author><name>Adele L. Marston</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cohesin organizes the genome by forming intra-chromosomal loops and inter-sister chromatid linkages. During gamete formation by meiosis, chromosomes are reshaped to support crossover recombination and two consecutive rounds of chromosome segregation. Here we show that Eco1 acetyltransferase positions both chromatin loops and sister chromatid cohesion to organize meiotic chromosomes into functional domains in budding yeast. Eco1 acetylates the Smc3 cohesin subunit in meiotic S phase to establish chromatin boundaries, independently of DNA replication. Boundary formation by Eco1 is critical for prophase exit and for the maintenance of cohesion until meiosis II, but is independent of the ability of Eco1 to antagonize the cohesin-release factor, Wpl1. Conversely, prevention of cohesin release by Wpl1 is essential for centromeric cohesion, kinetochore monoorientation and co-segregation of sister chromatids in meiosis I. Our findings establish Eco1 as a key determinant of chromatin boundaries and cohesion positioning, revealing how local chromosome structuring directs genome transmission into gametes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461725" rel="alternate" title="Eco1-dependent cohesin acetylation anchors chromatin loops and cohesion to define functional meiotic chromosome domains (27 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461878</id><title>A serotonergic axon-cilium synapse drives nuclear signaling to maintain chromatin accessibility (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.077410+00:00</updated><author><name>Shu-Hsien Sheu</name></author><author><name>Srigokul Upadhyayula</name></author><author><name>Vincent Dupuy</name></author><author><name>Song Pang</name></author><author><name>Andrew L. Lemire</name></author><author><name>Deepika Walpita</name></author><author><name>H. Amalia Pasolli</name></author><author><name>Fei Deng</name></author><author><name>Jinxia Wan</name></author><author><name>Lihua Wang</name></author><author><name>Justin Houser</name></author><author><name>Silvia Sanchez-Martinez</name></author><author><name>Sebastian E. Brauchi</name></author><author><name>Sambashiva Banala</name></author><author><name>Melanie Freeman</name></author><author><name>C. Shan Xu</name></author><author><name>Tom Kirchhausen</name></author><author><name>Harald F. Hess</name></author><author><name>Luke Lavis</name></author><author><name>Yu-Long Li</name></author><author><name>Séverine Chaumont-Dubel</name></author><author><name>David E. Clapham</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chemical synapses between axons and dendrites mediate much of the brain’s intercellular communication. Here we describe a new kind of synapse – the axo-ciliary synapse - between axons and primary cilia. By employing enhanced focused ion beam – scanning electron microscopy on samples with optimally preserved ultrastructure, we discovered synapses between the serotonergic axons arising from the brainstem, and the primary cilia of hippocampal CA1 pyramidal neurons. Functionally, these cilia are enriched in a ciliary-restricted serotonin receptor, 5-hydroxytryptamine receptor 6 (HTR6), whose mutation is associated with learning and memory defects. Using a newly developed cilia-targeted serotonin sensor, we show that optogenetic stimulation of serotonergic axons results in serotonin release onto cilia. Ciliary HTR6 stimulation activates a non-canonical G&lt;sub&gt;αq/11&lt;/sub&gt;-RhoA pathway. Ablation of this pathway results in nuclear actin and chromatin accessibility changes in CA1 pyramidal neurons. Axo-ciliary synapses serve as a distinct mechanism for neuromodulators to program neuron transcription through privileged access to the nuclear compartment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461878" rel="alternate" title="A serotonergic axon-cilium synapse drives nuclear signaling to maintain chromatin accessibility (27 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461693</id><title>Neutron crystallography reveals novel mechanisms used by Pseudomonas aeruginosa for host-cell binding (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.077842+00:00</updated><author><name>Lukas Gajdos</name></author><author><name>Matthew P. Blakeley</name></author><author><name>Michael Haertlein</name></author><author><name>V. Trevor Forsyth</name></author><author><name>Juliette M. Devos</name></author><author><name>Anne Imberty</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The opportunistic pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt;, a major cause of nosocomial infections, uses carbohydrate-binding proteins (lectins) as part of its binding to host cells. The fucose-binding lectin, LecB, displays a unique carbohydrate-binding site that incorporates two closely located calcium ions bridging between the ligand and protein, providing specificity and unusually high affinity. Here, we investigate the mechanisms involved in binding based on neutron crystallography studies of a fully deuterated LecB/fucose/calcium complex. The neutron structure, which includes the positions of all the hydrogen atoms, reveals that the high affinity of binding may be related to the occurrence of a low barrier hydrogen bond induced by the proximity of the two calcium ions, the presence of coordination rings between the sugar, calcium and LecB, and the dynamic behaviour of bridging water molecules at room temperature. These key structural details may assist in the design of anti-adhesive compounds to combat multi-resistance bacterial infections.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461693" rel="alternate" title="Neutron crystallography reveals novel mechanisms used by Pseudomonas aeruginosa for host-cell binding (22 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461690</id><title>Reconstitution and use of highly active human CDK1:Cyclin-B:CKS1 complexes (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.078051+00:00</updated><author><name>Pim J. Huis in ’t Veld</name></author><author><name>Sabine Wohlgemuth</name></author><author><name>Carolin Koerner</name></author><author><name>Franziska Mueller</name></author><author><name>Petra Janning</name></author><author><name>Andrea Musacchio</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;As dividing cells transition into mitosis, hundreds of proteins are phosphorylated by a complex of cyclin-dependent kinase 1 (CDK1) and Cyclin-B, often at multiple sites. CDK1:Cyclin-B phosphorylation patterns alter conformations, interaction partners, and enzymatic activities and need to be recapitulated &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; for the structural and functional characterization of the mitotic protein machinery. This requires a pure and active recombinant kinase complex. The kinase activity of CDK1 critically depends on the phosphorylation of a Threonine residue in its activation loop by a CDK1 activating kinase (CAK). We developed protocols to activate CDK1:Cyclin-B either &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; with purified CDK1 activating kinases (CAK) or in insect cells through CDK-CAK co-expression. To boost kinase processivity, we reconstituted a tripartite complex consisting of CDK1, Cyclin-B, and CKS1. In this work, we provide and compare detailed protocols to obtain and use highly active CDK1:Cyclin-B (CC) and CDK1:Cyclin-B:CKS1 (CCC).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461690" rel="alternate" title="Reconstitution and use of highly active human CDK1:Cyclin-B:CKS1 complexes (20 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461516</id><title>Early anteroposterior regionalisation of human neural crest is shaped by a pro-mesodermal factor (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.078279+00:00</updated><author><name>Antigoni Gogolou</name></author><author><name>Celine Souilhol</name></author><author><name>Ilaria Granata</name></author><author><name>Filip J Wymeersch</name></author><author><name>Ichcha Manipur</name></author><author><name>Matthew Wind</name></author><author><name>Thomas JR Frith</name></author><author><name>Maria Guarini</name></author><author><name>Alessandro Bertero</name></author><author><name>Christoph Bock</name></author><author><name>Florian Halbritter</name></author><author><name>Minoru Takasato</name></author><author><name>Mario R Guarracino</name></author><author><name>Anestis Tsakiridis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The neural crest (NC) is an important multipotent embryonic cell population and its impaired specification leads to various developmental defects, often in an anteroposterior (A-P) axial level-specific manner. The mechanisms underlying the correct A-P regionalisation of human NC cells remain elusive. Recent studies have indicated that trunk NC cells, the presumed precursors of the childhood tumour neuroblastoma, are derived from neuromesodermal-potent progenitors of the postcranial body (NMPs). Here we employ human embryonic stem cell differentiation to define how NMP-derived NC cells acquire a posterior axial identity. We show that TBXT, a pro-mesodermal transcription factor, mediates early posterior NC regionalisation together with WNT signalling effectors. This occurs by TBXT-driven chromatin remodelling via its binding in key enhancers within HOX gene clusters and other posterior regulator-associated loci. In contrast, posteriorisation of NMP-derived spinal cord cells is TBXT/WNT-independent and takes place under the influence of FGF signalling. Our work reveals a previously unknown role of TBXT in influencing posterior NC fate and points to the existence of temporally discrete, cell type-dependent modes of posterior axial identity control.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461516" rel="alternate" title="Early anteroposterior regionalisation of human neural crest is shaped by a pro-mesodermal factor (19 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461284</id><title>The nuclear transport factor CSE1 drives macronuclear volume increase and macronuclear node condensation in Stentor coeruleus (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.078498+00:00</updated><author><name>Rebecca M. McGillivary</name></author><author><name>Pranidhi Sood</name></author><author><name>Katherine Hammar</name></author><author><name>Wallace F. Marshall</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The giant ciliate, &lt;italic&gt;Stentor coeruleus&lt;/italic&gt;, provides a unique opportunity to study nuclear shape because its macronucleus undergoes a rapid, dramatic, and developmentally regulated shape change. During a 2 hour time period within cell division and regeneration, the 400 um long moniliform macronucleus condenses into a single mass, elongates into a vermiform shape, and then renodulates, returning to its original beads-on-a-string morphology.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Previous work from the 1960’s - 1980’s demonstrated that the macronuclear shape change is a highly regulated part of cell division and regeneration, but there were no molecular studies into this process.&lt;sup&gt;2,3&lt;/sup&gt; With the recent availability of a sequenced &lt;italic&gt;Stentor&lt;/italic&gt; genome, a transcriptome during regeneration, and molecular tools like RNAi, it is now possible to investigate the molecular mechanisms that drive macronuclear shape change.&lt;sup&gt;4–6&lt;/sup&gt; We found that the volume of the macronucleus increases during condensation, suggesting an inflation-like mechanism. When the nuclear transport factor, CSE1, is knocked down by RNAi, this volume increase is reduced, and the nodes are unable to fuse. This leads to a long-lasting change in nuclear morphology. We found that CSE1 is mainly cytoplasmic during interphase and in early regeneration, and then accumulates inside the macronucleus during condensation. At the end of regeneration CSE1 is degraded while the macronucleus returns to its pre-condensation volume. We propose a model in which nuclear transport via CSE1 increases the volume of the macronucleus, driving the condensation of the many nodes into a single mass.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461284" rel="alternate" title="The nuclear transport factor CSE1 drives macronuclear volume increase and macronuclear node condensation in Stentor coeruleus (19 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.460132</id><title>Maturation of human intestinal epithelium from pluripotency in vitro (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.078653+00:00</updated><author><name>Umut Kilik</name></author><author><name>Qianhui Yu</name></author><author><name>Rene Holtackers</name></author><author><name>Makiko Seimiya</name></author><author><name>Aline Xavier da Silveira dos Santos</name></author><author><name>Barbara Treutlein</name></author><author><name>Jason R. Spence</name></author><author><name>J. Gray Camp</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Methods to generate human intestinal tissue from pluripotent stem cells (PSCs) open new inroads into modeling intestine development and disease. However, current protocols require organoid transplantation into an immunocompromised mouse to achieve matured and differentiated epithelial cell states. Inspired by developmental reconstructions from primary tissues, we establish a regimen of inductive cues that enable stem cell maturation and epithelial differentiation entirely &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. We show that the niche factor Neuregulin1 (NRG1) promotes morphological change from proliferative epithelial cysts to matured epithelial tissue in three-dimensional cultures. Single-cell transcriptome analyses reveal differentiated epithelial cell populations, including diverse secretory and absorptive lineages. Comparison to multi-organ developmental and adult intestinal cell atlases confirm the specificity and maturation state of cell populations. Altogether, this work opens a new direction to use &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; matured epithelium from human PSCs to study human intestinal epithelium development, disease, and evolution in controlled culture environments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.460132" rel="alternate" title="Maturation of human intestinal epithelium from pluripotency in vitro (18 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461672</id><title>SyNPL: Synthetic Notch pluripotent cell lines to monitor and manipulate cell interactions in vitro and in vivo (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.081887+00:00</updated><author><name>Mattias Malaguti</name></author><author><name>Rosa Portero Migueles</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Annoh</name></author><author><name>Daina Sadurska</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Blin</name></author><author><name>Sally Lowell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cell-cell interactions govern differentiation and cell competition in pluripotent cells during early development, but the investigation of such processes is hindered by a lack of efficient analysis tools. Here we introduce SyNPL: clonal pluripotent stem cell lines which employ optimised Synthetic Notch (SynNotch) technology to report cell-cell interactions between engineered “sender” and “receiver” cells in cultured pluripotent cells and chimaeric mouse embryos. A modular design makes it straightforward to adapt the system for programming differentiation decisions non-cell-autonomously in receiver cells in response to direct contact with sender cells. We demonstrate the utility of this system by enforcing neuronal differentiation at the boundary between two cell populations. In summary, we provide a new tool which could be used to identify cell interactions and to profile changes in gene or protein expression that result from direct cell-cell contact with defined cell populations in culture and in early embryos, and which can be adapted to generate synthetic patterning of cell fate decisions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461672" rel="alternate" title="SyNPL: Synthetic Notch pluripotent cell lines to monitor and manipulate cell interactions in vitro and in vivo (17 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461473</id><title>Mechanosensitive control of mitotic entry (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.083845+00:00</updated><author><name>Margarida Dantas</name></author><author><name>Andreia Oliveira</name></author><author><name>Paulo Aguiar</name></author><author><name>Helder Maiato</name></author><author><name>Jorge G. Ferreira</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;As cells prepare to divide, they must ensure that enough space is available to assemble the mitotic machinery without perturbing tissue homeostasis&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. To do so, cells undergo a series of biochemical reactions regulated by cyclin B1-CDK1 that trigger the reorganization of the actomyosin cytoskeleton&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; and ensure the coordination of cytoplasmic and nuclear events&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Along with the biochemical events that control mitotic entry, mechanical forces have recently emerged as important players in the regulation of cell cycle events&lt;sup&gt;4–6&lt;/sup&gt;. However, the exact link between mechanical forces and the biochemical events that control mitotic progression remains to be established.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we identify a mechanical signal on the nucleus that sets the time for nuclear envelope permeabilization and mitotic entry. This signal relies on nuclear unfolding during the G2-M transition, which activates the stretch-sensitive cPLA2 on the nuclear envelope. This activation upregulates actomyosin contractility, determining the spatiotemporal translocation of cyclin B1 in the nucleus. Our data demonstrate how the mechanosensitive behaviour of cyclin B1 ensures timely and efficient mitotic spindle assembly and prevents chromosomal instability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461473" rel="alternate" title="Mechanosensitive control of mitotic entry (15 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461108</id><title>Experimental reproducibility limits the correlation between mRNA and protein abundances in tumour proteomic profiles (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.084189+00:00</updated><author><name>Swathi Ramachandra Upadhya</name></author><author><name>Colm J. Ryan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Large-scale studies of human proteomes have revealed only a moderate correlation between mRNA and protein abundances. It is unclear to what extent this moderate correlation reflects post-transcriptional regulation and to what extent it reflects measurement error. Here, by analysing replicate proteomic profiles of tumour samples, we show that there is considerable variation in the reproducibility of measurements of individual proteins. We show that proteins with more reproducible measurements tend to have higher mRNA-protein correlation, suggesting that a substantial fraction of the unexplained variation between mRNA and protein abundances may be attributed to limitations in the reproducibility of proteomic quantification. We find that proteins that have high reproducibility in one study tend to have high reproducibility in others and exploit this to develop an ‘aggregate protein reproducibility’ score. This score can explain a substantial amount of the variation in mRNA-protein correlation across multiple studies of both healthy and tumour samples.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461108" rel="alternate" title="Experimental reproducibility limits the correlation between mRNA and protein abundances in tumour proteomic profiles (13 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462199</id><title>Cell-ACDC: a user-friendly toolset embedding state-of-the-art neural networks for segmentation, tracking and cell cycle annotations of live-cell imaging data (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.085227+00:00</updated><author><name>Francesco Padovani</name></author><author><name>Benedikt Mairhörmann</name></author><author><name>Pascal Falter-Braun</name></author><author><name>Jette Lengefeld</name></author><author><name>Kurt M. Schmoller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Live-cell imaging is a powerful tool to study dynamic cellular processes on the level of single cells with quantitative detail. Microfluidics enables parallel high-throughput imaging, creating a downstream bottleneck at the stage of data analysis. Recent progress on deep learning image analysis dramatically improved cell segmentation and tracking. Nevertheless, manual data validation and correction is typically still required and broadly used tools spanning the complete range of live-cell imaging analysis, from cell segmentation to pedigree analysis and signal quantification, are still needed. Here, we present Cell-ACDC, a user-friendly graphical user-interface (GUI)-based framework written in Python, for segmentation, tracking and cell cycle annotation. We included two state-of-the-art and high-accuracy deep learning models for single-cell segmentation of yeast and mammalian cells implemented in the most used deep learning frameworks TensorFlow and PyTorch. Additionally, we developed and implemented a cell tracking method and embedded it into an intuitive, semi-automated workflow for label-free cell cycle annotation of single cells. The open-source and modularized nature of Cell-ACDC will enable simple and fast integration of new deep learning-based and traditional methods for cell segmentation or downstream image analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Source code&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/SchmollerLab/Cell_ACDC"&gt;https://github.com/SchmollerLab/Cell_ACDC&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462199" rel="alternate" title="Cell-ACDC: a user-friendly toolset embedding state-of-the-art neural networks for segmentation, tracking and cell cycle annotations of live-cell imaging data (12 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461707</id><title>γ-TuRCs are required for asymmetric microtubule nucleation from the somatic Golgi of Drosophila neurons (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.085554+00:00</updated><author><name>Amrita Mukherjee</name></author><author><name>Paul T. Conduit</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microtubules are polarised polymers nucleated by multi-protein γ-tubulin ring complexes (γ-TuRCs). Within neurons, microtubule polarity is plus-end-out in axons and mixed or minus-end-out in dendrites. Previously we showed that within the soma of &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; sensory neurons γ-tubulin localises asymmetrically to Golgi stacks, Golgi-derived microtubules grow asymmetrically towards the axon, and growing microtubule plus-ends are guided towards the axon and restricted from entering dendrite in a Kinesin-2-dependent manner (Mukerjee et al., 2020). Here we show that depleting γ-TuRCs perturbs the direction of microtubule growth from the Golgi stacks, consistent with a model for asymmetric microtubule nucleation involving γ-TuRCs and other nucleation-promoting factors. We also directly observe microtubule turning along microtubule bundles and show that depleting APC, proposed to link Kinesin-2 to plus ends, reduces microtubule turning and increases plus end growth into dendrites. These results support a model of asymmetric nucleation and guidance within the neuronal soma that helps establish and maintain overall microtubule polarity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461707" rel="alternate" title="γ-TuRCs are required for asymmetric microtubule nucleation from the somatic Golgi of Drosophila neurons (12 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461774</id><title>Instant Taq: Rapid Autoinducible Expression and Chromatography-free Purification of Taq polymerase (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.085786+00:00</updated><author><name>Romel Menacho-Melgar</name></author><author><name>Tian Yang</name></author><author><name>Michael D. Lynch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;DNA modifying enzymes are ubiquitous reagents in synthetic biology. Producing these enzymes often requires large culture volumes, purified nucleases and chromatographic separations to make enzymes of necessary quality. We sought to leverage synthetic biology tools to develop engineered strains allowing for not only the production but rapid purification of these reagents. Toward this goal, we report an &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; strain enabling the rapid production and purification of Taq polymerase. The method relies on 1) autoinducible expression achieving high protein titers, 2) autolysis and auto DNA/RNA hydrolysis via lysozyme and a mutant benzonase™, and 3) heat denaturation under reducing conditions to precipitate contaminating proteins including the mutant benzonase™. Taq polymerase is obtained at high purities (&amp;gt;95% pure by SDS-PAGE) and is readily usable in standard reactions. The method takes less than 1 hour of hands-on time, does not require special equipment, expensive reagents or affinity purification. We expect this simple methodology and approach will improve access not only to Taq polymerase but to numerous additional commonly utilized reagent proteins.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Protein titers ~ 1g/L achieved in 20 mL shakeflasks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;4 mg of purified Taq (corresponding to 5,000 Units, or 4,000 PCR reactions) per 20 mL shake flask.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instant Taq is equivalent to commercial preparations in routine PCR&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461774" rel="alternate" title="Instant Taq: Rapid Autoinducible Expression and Chromatography-free Purification of Taq polymerase (11 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461983</id><title>Deep Learning Enables Design of Multifunctional Synthetic Human Gut Microbiome Dynamics (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.086013+00:00</updated><author><name>Mayank Baranwal</name></author><author><name>Ryan L. Clark</name></author><author><name>Jaron Thompson</name></author><author><name>Zeyu Sun</name></author><author><name>Alfred O. Hero</name></author><author><name>Ophelia Venturelli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Predicting the dynamics and functions of microbiomes constructed from the bottom-up is a key challenge in exploiting them to our benefit. Current ordinary differential equation-based models fail to capture complex behaviors that fall outside of a predetermined ecological theory and do not scale well with increasing community complexity and in considering multiple functions. We develop and apply a long short-term memory (LSTM) framework to advance our understanding of community assembly and health-relevant metabolite production using a synthetic human gut community. A mainstay of deep learning, the LSTM learns a high dimensional data-driven non-linear dynamical system model used to design communities with desired metabolite profiles. We show that the LSTM model can outperform the widely used generalized Lotka-Volterra model. We build methods decipher microbe-microbe and microbe-metabolite interactions from an otherwise black-box model. These methods highlight that Actinobacteria, Firmicutes and Proteobacteria are significant drivers of metabolite production whereas &lt;italic&gt;Bacteroides&lt;/italic&gt; shape community dynamics. We use the LSTM model to navigate a large multidimensional functional landscape to identify communities with unique health-relevant metabolite profiles and temporal behaviors. In sum, the accuracy of the LSTM model can be exploited for experimental planning and to guide the design of synthetic microbiomes with target dynamic functions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461983" rel="alternate" title="Deep Learning Enables Design of Multifunctional Synthetic Human Gut Microbiome Dynamics (10 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462548</id><title>Prime Editing Efficiency and Fidelity are Enhanced in the Absence of Mismatch Repair (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.086244+00:00</updated><author><name>J Ferreira da Silva</name></author><author><name>GP Oliveira</name></author><author><name>EA Arasa-Verge</name></author><author><name>A Moretton</name></author><author><name>G Timelthaler</name></author><author><name>J Jiricny</name></author><author><name>JI Loizou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Prime editing is a powerful genome engineering approach that enables the introduction of base substitutions, insertions and deletions, into any given genomic locus. But prime editing, at even the same locus, can exhibit wildly different efficiencies in various cell backgrounds. It is unclear what determines these variations in efficiencies in a given cellular context. Through a focused genetic screen targeting DNA repair factors, we show that the efficiency of prime editing is attenuated by the mismatch repair pathway. The accumulation of the mismatch repair protein MLH1 at sites of prime editing, indicates that mismatch repair acts at these regions to directly counteract the insertion of the edit. Consequently, ablation of mismatch repair yields an up to 17-fold increase in prime editing efficiency across different human cell lines, several types of edits and multiple genomic loci. Our results shed new light on the cellular requirements for prime editing and identify that ablation of mismatch repair increases editing efficiency and fidelity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462548" rel="alternate" title="Prime Editing Efficiency and Fidelity are Enhanced in the Absence of Mismatch Repair (10 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462000</id><title>Growing Glycans in Rosetta: Accurate de novo glycan modeling, density fitting, and rational sequon design (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.086420+00:00</updated><author><name>Jared Adolf-Bryfogle</name></author><author><name>Jason W. Labonte</name></author><author><name>John C. Kraft</name></author><author><name>Maxim Shapovalov</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Raemisch</name></author><author><name>Thomas Lütteke</name></author><author><name>Frank DiMaio</name></author><author><name>Christopher D. Bahl</name></author><author><name>Jesper Pallesen</name></author><author><name>Neil P. King</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey J. Gray</name></author><author><name>Daniel W. Kulp</name></author><author><name>William R. Schief</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Carbohydrates and glycoproteins modulate key biological functions. Computational approaches inform function to aid in carbohydrate structure prediction, structure determination, and design. However, experimental structure determination of sugar polymers is notoriously difficult as glycans can sample a wide range of low energy conformations, thus limiting the study of glycan-mediated molecular interactions. In this work, we expanded the &lt;italic&gt;RosettaCarbohydrate&lt;/italic&gt; framework, developed and benchmarked effective tools for glycan modeling and design, and extended the Rosetta software suite to better aid in structural analysis and benchmarking tasks through the SimpleMetrics framework. We developed a glycan-modeling algorithm, &lt;italic&gt;GlycanTreeModeler&lt;/italic&gt;, that computationally builds glycans layer-by-layer, using adaptive kernel density estimates (KDE) of common glycan conformations derived from data in the Protein Data Bank (PDB) and from quantum mechanics (QM) calculations. After a rigorous optimization of kinematic and energetic considerations to improve near-native sampling enrichment and decoy discrimination, &lt;italic&gt;GlycanTreeModeler&lt;/italic&gt; was benchmarked on a test set of diverse glycan structures, or “trees”. Structures predicted by &lt;italic&gt;GlycanTreeModeler&lt;/italic&gt; agreed with native structures at high accuracy for both &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; modeling and experimental density-guided building. &lt;italic&gt;GlycanTreeModeler&lt;/italic&gt; algorithms and associated tools were employed to design &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; glycan trees into a protein nanoparticle vaccine that are able to direct the immune response by shielding regions of the scaffold from antibody recognition. This work will inform glycoprotein model prediction, aid in both X-ray and electron microscopy density solutions and refinement, and help lead the way towards a new era of computational glycobiology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462000" rel="alternate" title="Growing Glycans in Rosetta: Accurate de novo glycan modeling, density fitting, and rational sequon design (10 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462016</id><title>The short flagella 1 (SHF1) gene in Chlamydomonas encodes a Crescerin TOG-domain protein required for late stages of flagellar growth (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.086650+00:00</updated><author><name>Karina Perlaza</name></author><author><name>Mariya Mirvis</name></author><author><name>Hiroaki Ishikawa</name></author><author><name>Wallace Marshall</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Length control of flagella represents a simple and tractable system to investigate the dynamics of organelle size. Models for flagellar length control in the model organism, &lt;italic&gt;Chlamydomonas reinhardtii&lt;/italic&gt; have focused on the length-dependence of the intraflagellar transport (IFT) system which manages the delivery and removal of axonemal subunits at the tip of the flagella. One of these cargoes, tubulin, is the major axonemal subunit, and its frequency of arrival at the tip plays a central role in size control models. However, the mechanisms determining tubulin dynamics at the tip are still poorly understood. We discovered a loss-of-function mutation that leads to shortened flagella, and found that this was an allele of a previously described gene, SHF1, whose molecular identity had not previously been determined. We found that SHF1 encodes a &lt;italic&gt;Chlamydomonas&lt;/italic&gt; ortholog of Crescerin, previously identified as a cilia-specific TOG-domain array protein that can bind tubulin via its TOG domains and increase tubulin polymerization rates. In this mutant, flagellar regeneration occurs with the same initial kinetics as wild-type cells, but plateaus at a shorter length. Using a computational model in which the flagellar microtubules are represented by a differential equation for flagellar length combined with a stochastic model for cytoplasmic microtubule dynamics, we found that our experimental results are best described by a model in which Crescerin/SHF1 binds tubulin dimers in the cytoplasm and transports them into the flagellum. We suggest that this TOG-domain protein is necessary to efficiently and preemptively increase intra-flagella tubulin levels to offset decreasing IFT cargo at the tip as flagellar assembly progresses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462016" rel="alternate" title="The short flagella 1 (SHF1) gene in Chlamydomonas encodes a Crescerin TOG-domain protein required for late stages of flagellar growth (10 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462730</id><title>Deep mutational scan of a drug efflux pump reveals its structure-function landscape (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.087006+00:00</updated><author><name>Gianmarco Meier</name></author><author><name>Sujani Thavarasah</name></author><author><name>Kai Ehrenbolger</name></author><author><name>Cedric A. J. Hutter</name></author><author><name>Lea M. Hürlimann</name></author><author><name>Jonas Barandun</name></author><author><name>Markus A. Seeger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Drug efflux is a common resistance mechanism found in bacteria and cancer cells. Although several structures of drug efflux pumps are available, they provide only limited functional information on the phenomenon of drug efflux. Here, we performed deep mutational scanning (DMS) on the bacterial ATP binding cassette (ABC) transporter EfrCD to determine the drug efflux activity profile of more than 1500 single variants. These systematic measurements revealed that the introduction of negative charges at different locations within the large substrate binding pocket results in strongly increased efflux activity towards positively charged ethidium, while additional aromatic residues did not display the same effect. Data analysis in the context of an inward-facing cryo-EM structure of EfrCD uncovered a high affinity binding site, which releases bound drugs through a peristaltic transport mechanism as the transporter transits to its outward-facing conformation. Finally, we identified substitutions resulting in rapid Hoechst influx without affecting the efflux activity for ethidium and daunorubicin. Hence, single mutations can convert the ABC exporter EfrCD into a drug-specific ABC importer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462730" rel="alternate" title="Deep mutational scan of a drug efflux pump reveals its structure-function landscape (10 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462053</id><title>Large-scale mapping of positional changes of hypoxia-responsive genes upon activation (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.087237+00:00</updated><author><name>Koh Nakayama</name></author><author><name>Sigal Shachar</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth H. Finn</name></author><author><name>Hiroyuki Sato</name></author><author><name>Akihiro Hirakawa</name></author><author><name>Tom Misteli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chromosome structure and nuclear organization are important factors in the regulation of gene expression. Transcription of a gene is influenced by local and global chromosome features such as condensation status and histone modifications. The relationship between the position of a gene in the cell nucleus and its activity is less clear. Here, we used high-throughput imaging to perform a large-scale analysis of the spatial location of a set of nearly 100 hypoxia-inducible genes to determine whether their location within the nucleus is correlated with their activity state upon stimulation. Radial distance analysis demonstrated that the majority of HIF- and CREB-inducible hypoxia responsive genes are located in the intermediate region of the nucleus. Radial position of numerous responsive genes changed upon hypoxic treatment. Analysis of the relative distances amongst a subset of HIF target gene groups revealed that some gene pairs also altered their relative location to each other upon hypoxic treatment, suggesting higher order chromatin rearrangements. While these changes in location occurred in response to hypoxic activation of the target genes, they did not correlate with the extent of their activation. These results suggest that induction of the hypoxia-responsive gene expression program is accompanied by spatial alterations of the genome, but that radial and relative gene positions are not directly related to gene activity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462053" rel="alternate" title="Large-scale mapping of positional changes of hypoxia-responsive genes upon activation (9 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461736</id><title>RNA helicase DDX6 in P-bodies is essential for the assembly of stress granules (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.087478+00:00</updated><author><name>Vladimir Majerciak</name></author><author><name>Tongqing Zhou</name></author><author><name>Zhi-Ming Zheng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Two prominent cytoplasmic RNA granules, ubiquitous RNA-processing bodies (PB) and inducible stress granules (SG), regulate storage of translationally arrested mRNAs and are intimately related. In this study, we found the dependence of SG formation on PB in the cells under arsenite (ARS) stress, but not the other way around. GW182, 4E-T and DDX6 essential for PB formation differentially affect SG formation in the cells under ARS stress, with DDX6 being the most prominent. The cells with DDX6 deficiency display irregular shape of SG which could be rescued by ectopic wt DDX6, but not its helicase mutant E247A DDX6, which induces SG in the cells without stress, indicating that DDX6 helicase activity is essential for PB, but suppressive for SG. DDX6’s dual roles are independent of DDX6 interactors EDC3, CNOT1, and PAT1B. This study provides a conceptual advance of how DDX6 involves in the biogenesis of PB and SG.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;PB act as the seeds for SG nucleation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;PB components colocalize with SG&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;DDX6 plays a critical role in biogenesis of both PB and SG&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;DDX6 helicase activity prevents SG formation in normal cells&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461736" rel="alternate" title="RNA helicase DDX6 in P-bodies is essential for the assembly of stress granules (9 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462463</id><title>Optogenetic EB1 inactivation shortens metaphase spindles by disrupting cortical force-producing interactions with astral microtubules (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.087653+00:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Dema</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey van Haren</name></author><author><name>Torsten Wittmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chromosome segregation is accomplished by the mitotic spindle, a bipolar micromachine built primarily from microtubules. Different microtubule populations contribute to spindle function: Kinetochore microtubules attach and transmit forces to chromosomes, antiparallel interpolar microtubules support spindle structure, and astral microtubules connect spindle poles to the cell cortex [1,2]. In mammalian cells, End Binding (EB) proteins associate with all growing microtubule plus ends throughout the cell cycle and serve as adaptors for a diverse group of +TIPs that control microtubule dynamics and interactions with other intracellular structures [3]. Because binding of many +TIPs to EB1 and thus microtubule-end association is switched off by mitotic phosphorylation [4–6] the mitotic function of EBs remains poorly understood. To analyze how EB1 and associated +TIPs on different spindle microtubule populations contribute to mitotic spindle dynamics, we use a light sensitive EB1 variant, π-EB1, that allows local, acute and reversible inactivation of +TIP association with growing microtubule ends in live cells [7]. We find that acute π-EB1 photoinactivation results in rapid and reversible metaphase spindle shortening and transient relaxation of tension across the central spindle. However, in contrast to interphase, π-EB1 photoinactivation does not inhibit microtubule growth in metaphase, but instead increases astral microtubule length and number. Yet, in the absence of EB1 activity astral microtubules fail to engage the cortical dynein/dynactin machinery and spindle poles move away from regions of π-EB1 photoinactivation. In conclusion, our optogenetic approach reveals mitotic EB1 functions that remain hidden in genetic experiments likely due to compensatory molecular systems regulating vertebrate spindle dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462463" rel="alternate" title="Optogenetic EB1 inactivation shortens metaphase spindles by disrupting cortical force-producing interactions with astral microtubules (9 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462226</id><title>Osteoblasts pattern endothelium and somatosensory axons during zebrafish caudal fin organogenesis (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.087802+00:00</updated><author><name>Rosalind G. Bump</name></author><author><name>Camille E. A. Goo</name></author><author><name>Emma C. Horton</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey P. Rasmussen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Skeletal elements frequently associate with vasculature and somatosensory nerves, which regulate bone development and homeostasis. However, the deep, internal location of bones in many vertebrates has limited &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; exploration of the neurovascular-bone relationship. Here, we use the zebrafish caudal fin, an optically accessible organ formed of repeating bony ray skeletal units, to determine the cellular relationship between nerves, bones, and endothelium. In adults, we establish the presence of somatosensory axons running through the inside of the bony fin rays, juxtaposed with osteoblasts on the inner hemiray surface. During development, we show the caudal fin progresses through sequential stages of endothelial plexus formation, bony ray addition, ray innervation, and endothelial remodeling. Surprisingly, the initial stages of fin morphogenesis proceed normally in animals lacking either fin endothelium or somatosensory nerves. Instead, we find that &lt;italic&gt;sp7+&lt;/italic&gt; osteoblasts are required for endothelial remodeling and somatosensory axon innervation in the developing fin. Overall, this study demonstrates that the proximal neurovascular-bone relationship in the adult caudal fin is established during fin organogenesis and suggests that ray-associated osteoblasts pattern axons and endothelium.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Analysis of cellular interdependence during caudal fin development reveals roles for osteoblasts in patterning endothelium and somatosensory axon innervation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462226" rel="alternate" title="Osteoblasts pattern endothelium and somatosensory axons during zebrafish caudal fin organogenesis (8 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461756</id><title>Structure insights of the human peroxisomal ABC transporter ALDP (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.087955+00:00</updated><author><name>Yutian Jia</name></author><author><name>Yanming Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jianlin Lei</name></author><author><name>Guanghui Yang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Adrenoleukodystrophy protein (ALDP) is responsible for the transport of free very-long-chain fatty acids (VLCFAs) and corresponding CoA-esters across the peroxisomal membrane. ALDP belongs to the ATP-binding cassette sub-family D, which is also named as ABCD1. Dysfunction of ALDP leads to peroxisomal metabolic disorder exemplified by X-linked adrenoleukodystrophy (ALD). Hundreds of ALD-causing mutations are identified on ALDP. However, the pathogenic mechanisms of these mutations are restricted to clinical description due to limited structural information. Furthermore, ALDP plays a role in myelin maintenance, which is tightly associated with axon regeneration. Here we report the cryo-electron microscopy (cryo-EM) structure of human ALDP with nominal resolution of 3.4 Å in nucleotide free state. The structure of ALDP exhibits a typical assembly of ABC transporters. The nucleotide binding domains (NBDs) displays a ligand free state. ALDP exhibits an inward-open conformation to the cytosol. A short helix is located at the peroxisomal side, which is different from other three members of ABCD transporters. The two transmembrane domains (TMDs) of ALDP form a cavity, in which two lipid-like densities can be recognized as the head group of an coenzyme-A ester of a lipid. This structure provides a framework for understanding the working mechanism of ALDP and classification of the disease-causing mutations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461756" rel="alternate" title="Structure insights of the human peroxisomal ABC transporter ALDP (8 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461847</id><title>An innate immune activation state prior to vaccination predicts responsiveness to multiple vaccines (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.088105+00:00</updated><author><name>S. Fourati</name></author><author><name>LE. Tomalin</name></author><author><name>MP. Mulè</name></author><author><name>DG. Chawla</name></author><author><name>B. Gerritsen</name></author><author><name>D. Rychkov</name></author><author><name>E. Henrich</name></author><author><name>HER. Miller</name></author><author><name>T. Hagan</name></author><author><name>J. Diray-Arce</name></author><author><name>P. Dunn</name></author><author><name>O. Levy</name></author><author><name>R. Gottardo</name></author><author><name>M. Sarwal</name></author><author><name>J. Tsang</name></author><author><name>M. Suárez-Fariñas</name></author><author><name>B. Pulendran</name></author><author><name>RP. Sékaly</name></author><author><name>SH. Kleinstein</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many factors determine whether an individual responding to vaccination will generate an immune response that can lead to protection. Several studies have shown that the prevaccination immune state associate with the antibody response to vaccines. However, the generalizability and mechanisms that underlie this association remain poorly defined. Here, we sought to identify a common pre-vaccination signature and mechanisms that could predict the immune response across a wide variety of vaccines. We leveraged the “Immune Signatures Data Resource” created by the NIH Human Immunology Project Consortium (HIPC) to integrate data from 28 studies involving 13 different vaccines and associate the blood transcriptional status of 820 healthy young adults with their responses. An unsupervised analysis of blood transcriptional profiles across studies revealed three distinct pre-vaccination states, characterized by the differential expression of genes associated with a pro-inflammatory response, cell proliferation, and metabolism alterations downstream of NFκB and IRF7. Innate and adaptive immune cell subsetspecific genes were also associated with the three pre-vaccination states. Importantly, individuals whose pre-vaccination state was enriched in pro-inflammatory response genes known to be downstream of NFκB tended to have higher serum antibody responses one month after vaccination. A supervised analysis of the same data resulted in a single classifier, also enriched for NFκB regulated genes, that predicted the antibody response across most of the vaccines. Projection into single-cell RNA-sequencing data suggested that this pre-vaccination state was attributable to the signature of activation of non-classical monocytes and myeloid dendritic cells. Transcriptional signatures of recent exposure to bacterial and not viral infections were enriched in the high pro-inflammatory pre-vaccination state and also included NFκB regulated genes. The pro-inflammatory prevaccination state was highly reminiscent of the innate activation state triggered by TLR ligands or adjuvants. These results demonstrate that wide variations in the transcriptional state of the immune system in humans can be a key determinant of responsiveness to vaccination. They also define a transcriptional signature NFκB activation at baseline, that is associated with a greater magnitude of antibody response to 13 different vaccines, and suggest that modulation of the innate immune system by next-generation adjuvants targeting NFκB before vaccine administration may improve vaccine responsiveness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461847" rel="alternate" title="An innate immune activation state prior to vaccination predicts responsiveness to multiple vaccines (7 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461331</id><title>Nano3P-seq: transcriptome-wide analysis of gene expression and tail dynamics using end-capture nanopore sequencing (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.088421+00:00</updated><author><name>Oguzhan Begik</name></author><author><name>Huanle Liu</name></author><author><name>Anna Delgado-Tejedor</name></author><author><name>Cassandra Kontur</name></author><author><name>Antonio J. Giraldez</name></author><author><name>Jean-Denis Beaudoin</name></author><author><name>John S. Mattick</name></author><author><name>Eva Maria Novoa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;RNA polyadenylation plays a central role in RNA maturation, fate and stability. In response to developmental cues, polyA tail lengths can vary, affecting the translatability and stability of mRNAs. Here we develop Nano3P-seq, a novel method that relies on nanopore sequencing to simultaneously quantify RNA abundance and tail length dynamics at per-read resolution. By employing a template switching-based sequencing protocol, Nano3P-seq can sequence any given RNA molecule from its 3’end, regardless of its polyadenylation status, without the need of PCR amplification or ligation of RNA adapters. We demonstrate that Nano3P-seq captures a wide diversity of RNA biotypes, providing quantitative estimates of RNA abundance and tail lengths in mRNAs, lncRNAs, sn/snoRNAs, scaRNAs and rRNAs. We find that, in addition to mRNAs and lncRNAs, polyA tails can be identified in 16S mitochondrial rRNA in both mouse and zebrafish. Moreover, we show that mRNA tail lengths are dynamically regulated during vertebrate embryogenesis at the isoform-specific level, correlating with mRNA decay. Overall, Nano3P-seq is a simple and robust method to accurately estimate transcript levels and tail lengths in full-length individual reads, with minimal library preparation biases, both in the coding and non-coding transcriptome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461331" rel="alternate" title="Nano3P-seq: transcriptome-wide analysis of gene expression and tail dynamics using end-capture nanopore sequencing (7 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461979</id><title>Small extracellular vesicles from iPSC-MSC lose their regenerative potential upon UV-C irradiation (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.089254+00:00</updated><author><name>M.C. Biani</name></author><author><name>A. Lombardi</name></author><author><name>A. Norris</name></author><author><name>P. Bucci</name></author><author><name>A. La Greca</name></author><author><name>A. Waisman</name></author><author><name>L.N. Moro</name></author><author><name>G. Sevlever</name></author><author><name>J. Montanari</name></author><author><name>S. Miriuka</name></author><author><name>C. Luzzani</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mesenchymal Stem Cells derived from induced Pluripotent Stem cells (iPSC-MSC) have become a promising alternative to classical Mesenchymal Stem Cells in regenerative medicine. Their properties -as immunomodulatory and regenerative capacities-are in part due to the secretion of Extracellular Vesicles (EVs). Small EVs (sEVs) with sizes that range from 50 to 120 nm contain proteins, lipids, and nucleic acids that exert a role in cellular communication. Their content will depend on the cell of origin and its physiological state, thus the message they convey might change in response to changes in cellular conditions. In particular, the DNA damage response (DDR) has been reported to modulate sEVs secretion. In this work, we analyze how UV-C radiation upon iPSC-MSC alter sEVs secretion, cargo and bystander effect. Here, we confirm that UV-C radiation causes DDR in a dose dependent manner. In addition, we found that UV-C induced stress did not modulate the expression of genes that participate in sEVs biogenesis pathway. Consequently, we found that the amount of sEVs secreted by radiated and non-irradiated cells remained stable. However, sEVs from radiated cells were unable to promote cell migration in their target cells. Moreover, a label-free proteomic analysis revealed that UV-C induced DDR produces sEVs with an altered cargo, rich in migration-inhibiting proteins, and resulting in a less stromal-oriented repertoire.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461979" rel="alternate" title="Small extracellular vesicles from iPSC-MSC lose their regenerative potential upon UV-C irradiation (7 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461589</id><title>CHEK2 SIGNALING IS THE KEY REGULATOR OF OOCYTE SURVIVAL AFTER CHEMOTHERAPY (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.089493+00:00</updated><author><name>Chihiro Emori</name></author><author><name>Zachary Boucher</name></author><author><name>Ewelina Bolcun-Filas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Radiation and chemotherapy can damage the primordial follicle reserve in female cancer patients leading to ovarian failure and infertility. Preservation of ovarian function requires treatment strategies that prevent loss of immature oocytes in primordial follicles during cancer therapy. Checkpoint kinase 2 (CHEK2) inhibition prevents loss of primordial oocytes caused by DNA damage and thus is a promising target for ovoprotective treatment against genotoxic agents. To determine which cancer treatments could benefit from ovoprotective activity of CHEK2 inhibition we investigated oocyte survival in &lt;italic&gt;Chek2&lt;/italic&gt;-/- mice exposed to different chemotherapy drugs. Here, we show that loss of CHEK2 function prevents elimination of primordial oocytes damaged by cisplatin, cyclophosphamide, mafosfamide, doxorubicin, and etoposide, suggesting it could be used to reduce ovarian damage caused by wide range of drugs. Using genetic knockouts we reveal a critical role for TRP53 in oocyte response to chemotherapy drugs and show that both targets of CHEK2—TAp63 and TRP53— are activated by cisplatin and cyclophosphamide. Furthermore, we show that checkpoint kinase inhibitor and radiation- and chemotherapy sensitizer AZD7762 reduces oocyte elimination after radiation and chemotherapy treatments, despite its cytotoxic effect on ovarian somatic cells. Altogether, these findings demonstrate the role for CHEK2 as the master regulator of primordial oocyte survival or death and credential its targeting for ovoprotective treatments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SIGNIFICANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chemotherapy and radiation are ovotoxic and increase the risk of premature ovarian insufficiency and infertility in women cancer survivors. Development of treatment strategies preserving ovarian function and ensuring future reproductive health of female cancer patients depends on better understanding of the mechanisms underlying ovarian toxicity caused by different chemotherapy treatments. Preservation of long-term ovarian function can only be achieved by preventing the loss of immature oocytes in primordial follicles during toxic cancer therapies. Checkpoint kinase 2 (CHEK2) inhibition is an attractive strategy for protecting ovarian reserve with a potential additional benefit of sensitizing cancer cells to radiation and chemotherapy. Using a genetic approach, we show that blocking CHEK2 function is sufficient to prevent elimination of primordial oocytes damaged by chemotherapy drugs such as cisplatin, cyclophosphamide, mafosfamide, doxorubicin and etoposide. Many chemotherapy drugs are used in combination (e.g. cyclophosphamide with doxorubicin), thus the protective effect of CHEK2 inhibition is likely to be beneficial for a broad spectrum of patient treatments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461589" rel="alternate" title="CHEK2 SIGNALING IS THE KEY REGULATOR OF OOCYTE SURVIVAL AFTER CHEMOTHERAPY (7 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461716</id><title>The retromer complex regulates C. elegans development and mammalian ciliogenesis (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.089658+00:00</updated><author><name>Shuwei Xie</name></author><author><name>Ellie Smith</name></author><author><name>Carter Dierlam</name></author><author><name>Danita Mathew</name></author><author><name>Angelina Davis</name></author><author><name>Allana Williams</name></author><author><name>Naava Naslavsky</name></author><author><name>Jyoti Iyer</name></author><author><name>Steve Caplan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mammalian retromer is comprised of subunits VPS26, VPS29 and VPS35, and a more loosely-associated sorting nexin (SNX) heterodimer. Despite known roles for the retromer in multiple trafficking events in yeast and mammalian cells, its role in development is poorly understood, and its potential function in primary ciliogenesis remains unknown. Using CRISPR-Cas9 editing, we demonstrated that &lt;italic&gt;vps-26&lt;/italic&gt; homozygous knockout &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; have reduced brood sizes and impaired vulval development, as well as decreased body length which has been linked to defects in primary ciliogenesis. Since many endocytic proteins are implicated in the generation of primary cilia, we addressed whether the retromer regulates ciliogenesis in mammalian cells. We observed VPS35 localized to the primary cilium, and depletion of VPS26, VPS35 or SNX1/SNX5 led to decreased ciliogenesis. Retromer also coimmunoprecipitated with the capping protein, CP110, and was required for its removal from the mother centriole. Herein, we characterize new roles for the retromer in &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; development and in the regulation of ciliogenesis in mammalian cells, and suggest a novel role for the retromer in CP110 removal from the mother centriole.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461716" rel="alternate" title="The retromer complex regulates C. elegans development and mammalian ciliogenesis (7 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461712</id><title>Conserved structural elements specialize ATAD1 as a membrane protein extraction machine (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.089850+00:00</updated><author><name>Lan Wang</name></author><author><name>Hannah Toutkoushian</name></author><author><name>Vladislav Belyy</name></author><author><name>Claire Kokontis</name></author><author><name>Peter Walter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mitochondrial AAA protein ATAD1 (in humans; Msp1 in yeast) removes mislocalized membrane proteins, as well as stuck import substrates from the mitochondrial outer membrane, facilitating their re-insertion into their cognate organelles and maintaining mitochondria’s protein import capacity. In doing so, it helps to maintain proteostasis in mitochondria. How ATAD1 tackles the energetic challenge to extract hydrophobic membrane proteins from the lipid bilayer and what structural features adapt ATAD1 for its particular function has remained a mystery. Previously, we determined the structure of Msp1 in complex with a peptide substrate (Wang et al., 2020). The structure showed that Msp1’s mechanism follows the general principle established for AAA proteins while adopting several structural features that specialize it for its function. We used the yeast growth assay to test the function of key amino acids within these structural elements. In this work, we determined the cryo-EM structures of the human ATAD1 in complex with a peptide substrate at near atomic resolution. The structures show that phylogenetically conserved structural elements adapt ATAD1 for its function while generally adopting a conserved mechanism shared by many AAA proteins. ATAD1’s distinguishing features include an abundance of aromatic amino acids that line the central pore proposed to give ATAD1 a firm grip on its substrate and a short α-helix at the C-terminus that strongly facilitates ATAD1’s oligomerization. We also developed a microscopy-based assay reporting on protein mislocalization, with which we directly assessed ATAD1’s activity in live cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461712" rel="alternate" title="Conserved structural elements specialize ATAD1 as a membrane protein extraction machine (7 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462204</id><title>An Evolutionarily Conserved Regulatory Pathway of Muscle Mitochondrial Network Organization (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.090104+00:00</updated><author><name>Prasanna Katti</name></author><author><name>Peter T. Ajayi</name></author><author><name>Angel Aponte</name></author><author><name>Christopher K.E. Bleck</name></author><author><name>Brian Glancy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mitochondrial networks provide coordinated energy distribution throughout muscle cells. However, pathways specifying mitochondrial network-type separately from contractile fiber-type remain unclear. Here, we show that natural energetic demands placed on &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; muscles yield native cell-types among which contractile and mitochondrial network-types are regulated independently. Proteomic analyses of indirect flight, jump, and leg muscles together with muscles misexpressing known fiber-type specification factor &lt;italic&gt;salm&lt;/italic&gt; identified transcription factors &lt;italic&gt;H15&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;cut&lt;/italic&gt; as potential mitochondrial network regulators. We demonstrate &lt;italic&gt;H15&lt;/italic&gt; operates downstream of &lt;italic&gt;salm&lt;/italic&gt; regulating flight muscle contractile and mitochondrial network-type. Conversely, &lt;italic&gt;H15&lt;/italic&gt; regulates mitochondrial network configuration but not contractile type in jump and leg muscles. Further, we find that &lt;italic&gt;cut&lt;/italic&gt; regulates &lt;italic&gt;salm&lt;/italic&gt; expression in flight muscles and mitochondrial network configuration in leg muscles. These data indicate cell type-specific regulation of muscle mitochondrial network organization separately from contractile type, mitochondrial content, and mitochondrial size through an evolutionarily conserved pathway involving &lt;italic&gt;cut, salm&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;H15&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462204" rel="alternate" title="An Evolutionarily Conserved Regulatory Pathway of Muscle Mitochondrial Network Organization (7 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.460548</id><title>LOICA: Logical Operators for Integrated Cell Algorithms (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.090355+00:00</updated><author><name>Gonzalo Vidal</name></author><author><name>Carlos Vidal-Céspedes</name></author><author><name>Timothy James Rudge</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mathematical and computational modeling is essential to genetic design automation and for the synthetic biology design-build-test-learn cycle. The construction and analysis of models is enabled by abstraction based on a hierarchy of components, devices, and systems that can be used to compose genetic circuits. These abstract elements must be parameterized from data derived from relevant experiments, and these experiments related to the part composition of the abstract components of the circuits measured. Here we present LOICA (Logical Operators for Integrated Cell Algorithms), a Python package for modeling and characterizing genetic circuits based on a simple object-oriented design abstraction. LOICA uses classes to represent different biological and experimental components, which generate models through their interactions. High-level designs are linked to their part composition via SynBioHub. Furthermore, LOICA communicates with Flapjack, a data management and analysis tool, to link to experimental data, enabling abstracted elements to characterize themselves.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.460548" rel="alternate" title="LOICA: Logical Operators for Integrated Cell Algorithms (7 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.461806</id><title>Progranulin deficiency results in reduced bis(monoacylglycero)phosphate (BMP) levels and gangliosidosis (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.090578+00:00</updated><author><name>Sebastian Boland</name></author><author><name>Sharan Swarup</name></author><author><name>Yohannes A. Ambaw</name></author><author><name>Ruth C. Richards</name></author><author><name>Alexander W. Fischer</name></author><author><name>Shubham Singh</name></author><author><name>Geetika Aggarwal</name></author><author><name>Salvatore Spina</name></author><author><name>Alissa L. Nana</name></author><author><name>Lea T. Grinberg</name></author><author><name>William W. Seeley</name></author><author><name>Michal A. Surma</name></author><author><name>Christian Klose</name></author><author><name>Joao A. Paulo</name></author><author><name>Andrew D. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>J. Wade Harper</name></author><author><name>Tobias C. Walther</name></author><author><name>Robert V. Farese</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Homozygous mutations of granulin precursor (&lt;italic&gt;GRN&lt;/italic&gt;) lead to neuronal ceroid lipofuscinosis&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;, a severe neurodevelopmental disease, in humans and neuroinflammation in mice&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. Haploinsufficiency of &lt;italic&gt;GRN&lt;/italic&gt; almost invariably causes frontotemporal dementia (FTD)&lt;sup&gt;3,4&lt;/sup&gt;. The &lt;italic&gt;GRN&lt;/italic&gt; locus produces progranulin (PGRN), a lysosomal precursor protein that is cleaved to granulin peptides&lt;sup&gt;5,6&lt;/sup&gt;. Despite intensive investigation, the function of granulins and the reason why their absence causes neurodegeneration remain unclear. Here, we investigated PGRN function in lipid degradation, a major function of lysosomes. We show that PGRN-knockout human cells, PGRN-deficient murine brain, and frontal lobes of human brains from patients with &lt;italic&gt;GRN&lt;/italic&gt; mutation-related FTD have increased levels of gangliosides, highly abundant sialic acid–containing glycosphingolipids (GSL) that are degraded in lysosomes. Probing how PGRN deficiency causes these changes, we found normal levels and activities of enzymes that catabolize gangliosides. However, levels of bis(monoacylglycero)phosphate (BMP), a lysosomal lipid required for ganglioside catabolism&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;, were markedly reduced in PGRN-deficient cells and patient brain tissues. These data indicate that granulins are required to maintain BMP levels, which regulate ganglioside catabolism, and that PGRN deficiency in lysosomes leads to gangliosidosis. This aberrant accumulation of gangliosides may contribute to neuroinflammation and neurodegeneration susceptibility.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.461806" rel="alternate" title="Progranulin deficiency results in reduced bis(monoacylglycero)phosphate (BMP) levels and gangliosidosis (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461622</id><title>Integrative analysis allows a global and precise identification of functional miRNA target genes in mESCs (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.090952+00:00</updated><author><name>Moritz Schäfer</name></author><author><name>Amena Nabih</name></author><author><name>Daniel Spies</name></author><author><name>Maxime Bodak</name></author><author><name>Harry Wischnewski</name></author><author><name>Patrick Stalder</name></author><author><name>Richard Patryk Ngondo</name></author><author><name>Luz Angelica Liechti</name></author><author><name>Tatjana Sajic</name></author><author><name>Ruedi Aebersold</name></author><author><name>David Gatfield</name></author><author><name>Constance Ciaudo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;MicroRNA (miRNA) loaded Argonaute (AGO) complexes regulate gene expression via direct base pairing with their mRNA targets. Current prediction approaches identified that between 20 to 60% of mammalian transcriptomes are regulated by miRNAs, but it remains largely unknown which fraction of these interactions are functional in a specific cellular context. Here, we integrated transcriptome data from a set of miRNA-depleted mouse embryonic stem cell (mESC) lines with published miRNA interaction predictions and AGO-binding profiles. This integrative approach, combined with molecular validation data, identified that only 6% of expressed genes are functionally and directly regulated by miRNAs in mESCs. In addition, analyses of the stem cell-specific miR-290-295 cluster target genes identified TFAP4 as an important transcription factor for early development. The extensive datasets developed in this study will support the development of improved predictive models for miRNA-mRNA functional interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461622" rel="alternate" title="Integrative analysis allows a global and precise identification of functional miRNA target genes in mESCs (6 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461805</id><title>Cryo-EM structure of a single-chain β1-adrenoceptor – AmpC β-lactamase fusion protein (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.091244+00:00</updated><author><name>Gabriella Collu</name></author><author><name>Inayathulla Mohammed</name></author><author><name>Aleix Lafita</name></author><author><name>Tobias Bierig</name></author><author><name>Emiliya Poghosyan</name></author><author><name>Spencer Bliven</name></author><author><name>Roger M. Benoit</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The insertion of fusion proteins has enabled the crystallization of a wide range of G-protein-coupled receptors (GPCRs). Here, we explored the possibility of using a larger fusion protein, inserted into the third intracellular loop (ICL3) of β1-adrenoceptor (β1AR) via rigid chimeric helix fusions. The aim was to engineer a single-chain fusion protein that comprises sufficient mass and rigidity to allow single-particle cryo-EM data collection, without depending on binding proteins, such as G-proteins or nanobodies. Through parsing of the protein data bank (PDB), we identified the protein AmpC β-lactamase as a suitable candidate. Both termini of this protein are α-helical and the helices are antiparallel to each other. The distance between their centroids measures ∼11 Å. Such a geometry is ideal to design extended chimeric helices with transmembrane (TM) helices 5 and 6 of β1AR, and the insertion of the protein adds ∼39 kDa of mass to the receptor. We expressed the β1AR - AmpC β-lactamase fusion protein in mammalian cells. The binding of the antagonists propranolol and cyanopindolol to the purified fusion protein was confirmed by CPM-based thermofluor assays. The cryo-EM structure was solved to a nominal overall resolution of 3.6 Å and the seven helix architecture and helix eight were clearly resolved. Superimposition of the structure with known X-ray crystal structures of β1AR suggests that the protein is in its inactive conformation. The fusion protein described here provides a basis for high-throughput structure elucidation of class A GPCRs by cryo-EM for drug discovery research as well as for the elucidation of inactive state or wild-type GPCR structures. The fusion protein geometry theoretically fits a wide range of class A GPCRs and therefore can be applied to a multitude of receptors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461805" rel="alternate" title="Cryo-EM structure of a single-chain β1-adrenoceptor – AmpC β-lactamase fusion protein (6 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461400</id><title>How the naked mole-rat resists senescence: a constraints-based theory (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.091544+00:00</updated><author><name>Felipe A. Veloso</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Here, I present a theory describing how the stabilization of constraints imposed on chromatin dynamics by the naked mole-rat’s histone H1.0 protein—which in terminally differentiated cells constrains the accessibility of the nucleosome core particle for histone-modifying enzymes and chromatin remodeling factors—explains its resistance to both senescence and cancer. Further, this theory predicts that a mutant house mouse displaying such stabilization will be similarly resistant to both senescence and cancer. A proof-of-concept computational analysis is presented and two predictions for the direct testing of the theory are provided. These experiments comprise, as test subjects, mutant naked mole-rats synthesizing a house mouse (Mus &lt;italic&gt;musculus&lt;/italic&gt;)-like histone H1.0, and mutant house mice synthesizing a naked mole-rat-like histone H1.0. The predictions are that the constraints on chromatin dynamics embodied by the respective mutant histone H1.0 proteins will negate the otherwise significant resistance to both senescence and cancer of the naked mole-rats and, conversely, confer such resistance to the house mice. A verification of these predictions will imply that constraints on chromatin dynamics embodied by naked mole-rat-like histone H1.0 proteins may confer significant resistance to both senescence and age-related cancer to otherwise senescence-prone and/or cancer-susceptible multicellular species, including humans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461400" rel="alternate" title="How the naked mole-rat resists senescence: a constraints-based theory (6 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461448</id><title>A phylogenetically-restricted essential cell cycle progression factor in the human pathogen Candida albicans (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.091776+00:00</updated><author><name>Priya Jaitly</name></author><author><name>Mélanie Legrand</name></author><author><name>Abhijit Das</name></author><author><name>Tejas Patel</name></author><author><name>Murielle Chauvel</name></author><author><name>Christophe d’Enfert</name></author><author><name>Kaustuv Sanyal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chromosomal instability in fungal pathogens caused by cell division errors is associated with antifungal drug resistance. To identify mechanisms underlying such instability and to uncover new potential antifungal targets, we conducted an overexpression screen monitoring chromosomal stability in the human fungal pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Candida albicans&lt;/italic&gt;. Analysis of ~1000 genes uncovered six chromosomal stability (CSA) genes, five of which are related to cell division genes in other organisms. The sixth gene, &lt;italic&gt;CSA6&lt;/italic&gt;, is selectively present in the CUG-Ser clade species that includes &lt;italic&gt;C. albicans&lt;/italic&gt; and other human fungal pathogens. The protein encoded by &lt;italic&gt;CSA6&lt;/italic&gt; localizes to the spindle pole bodies, is required for exit from mitosis, and induces a checkpoint-dependent metaphase arrest upon overexpression. Together, Csa6 defines an essential CUG-Ser fungal clade-specific cell cycle progression factor, highlighting the existence of phylogenetically-restricted cell division genes which may serve as potential unique therapeutic targets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Teaser&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Csa6 is essential for mitotic progression and mitotic exit in the human fungal pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Candida albicans&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461448" rel="alternate" title="A phylogenetically-restricted essential cell cycle progression factor in the human pathogen Candida albicans (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462168</id><title>Neurofibromin 1 controls metabolic balance and Notch-dependent quiescence of juvenile myogenic progenitors (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.092044+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaoyan Wei</name></author><author><name>Matthias Lienhard</name></author><author><name>Arunima Murgai</name></author><author><name>Julia Franke</name></author><author><name>Sophie Pöhle-Kronawitter</name></author><author><name>Georgios Kotsaris</name></author><author><name>Hao Wu</name></author><author><name>Stefan Börno</name></author><author><name>Bernd Timmermann</name></author><author><name>Rainer Glauben</name></author><author><name>Sigmar Stricker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Patients affected by neurofibromatosis type 1 (NF1) frequently show muscle weakness with unknown etiology. Here we show that Neurofibromin-1 (Nf1) is not required in muscle fibers, but specifically in early postnatal myogenic progenitors (MPs), where Nf1 loss led to cell cycle exit and differentiation blockade, depleting the MP pool resulting in reduced myonuclear accrual as well as reduced muscle stem cell numbers. This was caused by precocious induction of stem cell quiescence coupled to metabolic reprogramming of MPs impinging on glycolytic shutdown, which was conserved in muscle fibers. We show that a Mek/Erk/NOS pathway hypersensitizes Nf1-deficient MPs to Notch signaling, consequently, early postnatal Notch pathway inhibition ameliorated premature quiescence, metabolic reprogramming and muscle growth. This reveals an unexpected role of Ras/Mek/Erk signaling supporting postnatal MP quiescence in concert with Notch signaling, which is controlled by Nf1 safeguarding coordinated muscle growth and muscle stem cell pool establishment. Furthermore, our data suggest transmission of metabolic reprogramming across cellular differentiation, affecting fiber metabolism and function in NF1.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462168" rel="alternate" title="Neurofibromin 1 controls metabolic balance and Notch-dependent quiescence of juvenile myogenic progenitors (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.17.460748</id><title>Physical and functional interactome atlas of human receptor tyrosine kinases (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.092386+00:00</updated><author><name>Kari Salokas</name></author><author><name>Tiina Öhman</name></author><author><name>Xiaonan Liu</name></author><author><name>Iftekhar Chowdhury</name></author><author><name>Lisa Gawriyski</name></author><author><name>Salla Keskitalo</name></author><author><name>Markku Varjosalo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Much cell-to-cell communication is facilitated by cell surface receptor tyrosine kinases (RTKs). These proteins phosphorylate their downstream cytoplasmic substrates in response to stimuli such as growth factors. Despite their central roles, the functions of many RTKs are still poorly understood. To resolve the lack of systematic knowledge, we used three complementary methods to map the molecular context and substrate profiles of RTKs. We used affinity purification coupled to mass spectrometry (AP-MS) to characterize stable binding partners and RTK-protein complexes, proximity-dependent biotin identification (BioID) to identify transient and proximal interactions, and an &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; kinase assay to identify RTK substrates. To identify how kinase interactions depend on kinase activity, we also used kinase-deficient mutants. Our data represent a comprehensive, systemic mapping of RTK interactions and substrates. This resource adds information regarding well-studied RTKs, offers insights into the functions of less well-studied RTKs, and highlights RTK-RTK interactions and shared signaling pathways.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.17.460748" rel="alternate" title="Physical and functional interactome atlas of human receptor tyrosine kinases (5 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461663</id><title>Glycosylation-on-a-chip: a flow-based microfluidic system for cell-free glycoprotein biosynthesis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.092670+00:00</updated><author><name>Alicia K. Aquino</name></author><author><name>Zachary A. Manzer</name></author><author><name>Susan Daniel</name></author><author><name>Matthew P. DeLisa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In recent years, cell-free synthetic glycobiology technologies have emerged that enable production and remodeling of glycoproteins outside the confines of the cell. However, many of these systems combine multiple synthesis steps into one pot where there can be competing reactions and side products that ultimately lead to low yield of the desired product. In this work, we describe a microfluidic platform that integrates cell-free protein synthesis, glycosylation, and purification of a model glycoprotein in separate compartments where each step can be individually optimized. Microfluidics offer advantages such as reaction compartmentalization, tunable residence time, the ability to tether enzymes for reuse, and the potential for continuous manufacturing. Moreover, it affords an opportunity for spatiotemporal control of glycosylation reactions that is difficult to achieve with existing cell-based and cell-free glycosylation systems. In this work, we demonstrate a flow-based glycoprotein synthesis system that promotes enhanced cell-free protein synthesis, efficient protein glycosylation with an immobilized oligosaccharyltransferase, and enrichment of the protein product from cell-free lysate. Overall, this work represents a first-in-kind glycosylation-on-a-chip prototype that could find use as a laboratory tool for mechanistic dissection of the protein glycosylation process as well as a biomanufacturing platform for small batch, decentralized glycoprotein production.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461663" rel="alternate" title="Glycosylation-on-a-chip: a flow-based microfluidic system for cell-free glycoprotein biosynthesis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461328</id><title>A method to enrich and purify centromeric DNA from human cells (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.093036+00:00</updated><author><name>Riccardo Gamba</name></author><author><name>Giulia Mazzucco</name></author><author><name>Therese Wilhelm</name></author><author><name>Florian Chardon</name></author><author><name>Leonid Velikovsky</name></author><author><name>Julien Picotto</name></author><author><name>Ylli Doksani</name></author><author><name>Daniele Fachinetti</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Centromeres are key elements for chromosome segregation. Canonical centromeres are built over long-stretches of tandem repetitive arrays. Despite being quite abundant compared to other loci, centromere sequences overall still represent only 2 to 5% of the human genome, therefore studying their genetic and epigenetic features is a major challenge. Furthermore, sequencing of centromeric regions requires high coverage to fully analyze length and sequence variations, which can be extremely costly. To bypass these issues, we have developed a technique based on selective restriction digestion and size fractionation to enrich for centromeric DNA from human cells. Combining enzymes capable of cutting at high frequency throughout the genome, except within most human centromeres, with size-selection of &amp;gt;20 kb fragments resulted in over 25-fold enrichment in centromeric DNA. Sequencing of the enriched fractions revealed that up to 60% of the enriched material is made of centromeric DNA. This approach has great potential for making sequencing of centromeric DNA more affordable and efficient and for single DNA molecule studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461328" rel="alternate" title="A method to enrich and purify centromeric DNA from human cells (5 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462603</id><title>Regulation of the Evolutionarily Conserved Muscle Myofibrillar Matrix by Cell Type Dependent and Independent Mechanisms (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.093296+00:00</updated><author><name>Peter T. Ajayi</name></author><author><name>Prasanna Katti</name></author><author><name>T. Bradley Willingham</name></author><author><name>Ye Sun</name></author><author><name>Christopher K.E. Bleck</name></author><author><name>Brian Glancy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Skeletal muscles play a central role in human movement through forces transmitted by contraction of the sarcomere. We recently showed that mammalian sarcomeres are connected through frequent branches forming a singular, mesh-like myofibrillar matrix. However, the extent to which myofibrillar connectivity is evolutionarily conserved as well as mechanisms which regulate the specific architecture of sarcomere branching remain unclear. Here, we demonstrate the presence of a myofibrillar matrix in the tubular, but not indirect flight (IF) muscles within &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt;. Moreover, we find that loss of transcription factor &lt;italic&gt;H15&lt;/italic&gt; increases sarcomere branching frequency in the tubular jump muscles, and we show that sarcomere branching can be turned on in IF muscles by &lt;italic&gt;salm&lt;/italic&gt;-mediated conversion to tubular muscles. Finally, we demonstrate that &lt;italic&gt;neurochondrin&lt;/italic&gt; knockdown results in myofibrillar connectivity in IF muscles without conversion to tubular muscles. These data indicate an evolutionarily conserved myofibrillar matrix regulated by both cell-type dependent and independent mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462603" rel="alternate" title="Regulation of the Evolutionarily Conserved Muscle Myofibrillar Matrix by Cell Type Dependent and Independent Mechanisms (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462384</id><title>Bromodomain factor 5 is an essential transcriptional regulator of the Leishmania genome (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.093533+00:00</updated><author><name>Nathaniel G. Jones</name></author><author><name>Vincent Geoghegan</name></author><author><name>Gareth Moore</name></author><author><name>Juliana B. T. Carnielli</name></author><author><name>Katherine Newling</name></author><author><name>Félix Calderón</name></author><author><name>Raquel Gabarró</name></author><author><name>Julio Martín</name></author><author><name>Rab Prinjha</name></author><author><name>Inmaculada Rioja</name></author><author><name>Anthony J. Wilkinson</name></author><author><name>Jeremy C. Mottram</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; are unicellular parasites that cause human and animal disease. Alongside other organisms in kinetoplastida, they have evolved an unusual genome architecture that requires all RNA polymerase II transcribed genes to be expressed constitutively, with transcriptional start regions denoted by histone variants and histone lysine acetylation. However, the way these chromatin marks are interpreted by the cell is not understood. Seven predicted bromodomain factors (BDF1-7), the reader modules for acetyl-lysine, were identified across &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; genomes. Using &lt;italic&gt;L. mexicana&lt;/italic&gt; as a model, Cas9-driven gene deletions indicate that BDF1-5 are essential for promastigote survival, whilst DiCre inducible gene deletion of the dual bromodomain factor &lt;italic&gt;BDF5&lt;/italic&gt; identified it to be essential for both promastigotes and amastigotes. ChIP-seq assessment of BDF5s genomic distribution revealed it as highly enriched at transcriptional start sites. Using an optimised proximity proteomic and phosphoproteomic technique, XL-BioID, we defined the BDF5-proximal environment to be enriched for other bromodomain factors, histone acetyltransferase 2, and proteins essential for transcriptional activity and RNA processing. Inducible deletion of BDF5, led to a disruption of pol II transcriptional activity and global defects in gene expression. Our results indicate the requirement of &lt;italic&gt;Leishmania&lt;/italic&gt; to interpret histone acetylation marks for normal levels of gene expression and thus cellular viability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462384" rel="alternate" title="Bromodomain factor 5 is an essential transcriptional regulator of the Leishmania genome (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462029</id><title>Optogenetic control of NOTCH1 signalling (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.093852+00:00</updated><author><name>Joanna Kałafut</name></author><author><name>Jakub Czapiński</name></author><author><name>Alicja Przybyszewska-Podstawka</name></author><author><name>Arkadiusz Czerwonka</name></author><author><name>Cecilia Sahlgren</name></author><author><name>Adolfo Rivero-Müller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Notch signalling pathway is a crucial regulator of cell differentiation as well as tissue organisation. Dysregulation of Notch signalling has been linked to the pathogenesis of different diseases. Notch plays a key role in breast cancer progression by controlling the interaction between the tumour cells and the microenvironment as well as by increasing cell motility and invasion. NOTCH1 is a mechanosensitive receptor, where mechanical force is required to activate the proteolytic cleavage and release of the Notch intracellular domain (NICD). Here, we circumvent this step by regulating Notch activity by light. To achieve this, we have engineered a membrane-bound optogenetic NOTCH1 receptor (optoNotch) to control the activation of NOTCH1 intracellular domain (N1ICD) and its downstream transcriptional activities. Using optoNotch we confirm that NOTCH1 activation increases cell proliferation in MCF7 and MDA-MB-468 breast cancer cells in 2D and spheroid 3D cultures. OptoNotch allows fine-tuning ligand-independent regulation of N1ICD to understand the spatiotemporal complexity of Notch signalling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462029" rel="alternate" title="Optogenetic control of NOTCH1 signalling (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461954</id><title>Reconstructing Sample-Specific Networks using LIONESS (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.094109+00:00</updated><author><name>Marieke L. Kuijjer</name></author><author><name>Kimberly Glass</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We recently developed LIONESS, a method to estimate sample-specific networks based on the output of an aggregate network reconstruction approach. In this manuscript, we describe how to apply LIONESS to different network reconstruction algorithms and data types. We highlight how decisions related to data preprocessing may affect the output networks, discuss expected outcomes, and give examples of how to analyze and compare single sample networks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461954" rel="alternate" title="Reconstructing Sample-Specific Networks using LIONESS (5 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461113</id><title>The Integrator complex regulates microRNA abundance through RISC loading (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.094313+00:00</updated><author><name>Nina Kirstein</name></author><author><name>Sadat Dokaneheifard</name></author><author><name>Pradeep Reddy Cingaram</name></author><author><name>Monica Guiselle Valencia</name></author><author><name>Felipe Beckedorff</name></author><author><name>Helena Gomes Dos Santos</name></author><author><name>Ezra Blumenthal</name></author><author><name>Mina Masoumeh Tayari</name></author><author><name>Ramin Shiekhattar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;MicroRNA (miRNA) homeostasis is crucial for the post-transcriptional regulation of their target genes and miRNA dysregulation has been linked to multiple diseases, including cancer. The molecular mechanisms underlying miRNA biogenesis from processing of primary miRNA transcripts to formation of mature miRNA duplex are well understood&lt;sup&gt;1-4&lt;/sup&gt;. Loading of miRNA duplex into members of the Argonaute (Ago) protein family, representing the core of the RNA-induced silencing complex (RISC), is pivotal to miRNA-mediated gene silencing&lt;sup&gt;5-7&lt;/sup&gt;. The Integrator complex has been previously shown to be an important regulator of RNA maturation, RNA polymerase II pause-release, and premature transcriptional termination&lt;sup&gt;8-11&lt;/sup&gt;. Here, we report that loss of Integrator results in global diminution of mature miRNAs. By incorporating 4-Thiouridine (s4U) in nascent transcripts, we traced miRNA fate from biogenesis to stabilization and identified Integrator to be essential for proper miRNA assembly into RISC. Enhanced UV crosslinking and immunoprecipitation (eCLIP) of Integrator confirms a robust association with mature miRNAs. Indeed, Integrator potentiates Ago2-mediated cleavage of target RNAs. These findings highlight an essential role for Integrator in miRNA abundance and RISC function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461113" rel="alternate" title="The Integrator complex regulates microRNA abundance through RISC loading (5 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-09-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461468</id><title>High-content analysis of proteostasis capacity in cellular models of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.094571+00:00</updated><author><name>Isabella A. Lambert-Smith</name></author><author><name>Justin J. Yerbury</name></author><author><name>Darren N. Saunders</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Disrupted proteome homeostasis (proteostasis) in amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) has been a major focus of research in the past two decades. Yet the exact processes that normally maintain proteostasis, but that are uniquely disturbed in motor neurons expressing diverse genetic mutations, remain to be established. Obtaining a better understanding of proteostasis disruption in association with different ALS-causing mutations will improve our understanding of ALS pathophysiology and may identify novel therapeutic targets and strategies for ALS patients. Here we describe the development and use of a novel high-content analysis (HCA) assay to investigate proteostasis disturbances caused by the expression of ALS-causing gene variants. This assay involves the use of conformationally-destabilised mutants of firefly luciferase (Fluc) to examine protein folding/re-folding capacity in NSC-34 cells expressing ALS-associated mutations in the genes encoding superoxide dismutase-1 (SOD1&lt;sup&gt;A4V&lt;/sup&gt;) and cyclin F (CCNF&lt;sup&gt;S621G&lt;/sup&gt;). We demonstrate that these Fluc isoforms can be used in high-throughput format to report on reductions in the activity of the chaperone network that result from the expression of SOD1&lt;sup&gt;A4V&lt;/sup&gt;, providing multiplexed information at single-cell resolution. In addition to SOD1&lt;sup&gt;A4V&lt;/sup&gt; and CCNF&lt;sup&gt;S621G&lt;/sup&gt;, NSC-34 models of ALS-associated TDP-43, FUS, UBQLN2, OPTN, VCP and VAPB mutants were generated that could be screened using this assay in future work. For ALS-associated mutant proteins that do cause reductions in protein quality control capacity, such as SOD1&lt;sup&gt;A4V&lt;/sup&gt;, this assay has potential to be applied in drug screening studies to identify candidate compounds that can ameliorate this deficiency.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="461468v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Destabilised firefly luciferase (Fluc) mutants can be used in high-content analysis (HCA) assay format&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fluc HCA assay enables information-rich reporting on chaperone network activity in cell models of ALS&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Expression of SOD1&lt;sup&gt;A4V&lt;/sup&gt; reduces chaperone network activity in NSC-34 cells&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461468" rel="alternate" title="High-content analysis of proteostasis capacity in cellular models of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461467</id><title>NF90 Interacts with Components of RISC and Modulates Association of Ago2 with mRNA (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.094779+00:00</updated><author><name>Giuseppa Grasso</name></author><author><name>Celine Franckhauser</name></author><author><name>Rima Nait-Saidi</name></author><author><name>Maxime Bello</name></author><author><name>Jérôme Barbier</name></author><author><name>Rosemary Kiernan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nuclear Factor 90 (NF90) is a double-stranded RNA-binding protein involved in a multitude of different cellular mechanisms such as transcription, translation, viral infection and mRNA stability. Recent data suggest that NF90 might influence the abundance of target mRNAs in the cytoplasm through miRNA- and Argonaute 2 (Ago2)-dependent activity. Here, we identified the interactome of NF90 in the cytoplasm, which revealed several components of the RNA-induced silencing complex (RISC) and associated factors. Co-immunoprecipitation analysis confirmed the interaction of NF90 with the RISC-associated RNA helicase, Moloney leukemia virus 10 (MOV10), and other proteins involved in RISC-mediated silencing, including Ago2. Furthermore, NF90 association with MOV10 and Ago2 was found to be RNA-dependent. Glycerol gradient sedimentation of NF90 immune complexes indicates that these proteins occur in the same protein complex. At target RNAs predicted to bind both NF90 and MOV10 in their 3’ UTRs, NF90 association was increased upon loss of MOV10 and &lt;italic&gt;vice versa&lt;/italic&gt;, suggesting that the two proteins may compete for the binding of common target mRNAs. Interestingly, loss of NF90 led to an increase in association of Ago2 as well as a decrease in the abundance of the target mRNA. Similarly, during hypoxia, the binding of Ago2 to vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) mRNA increased after loss of NF90, while the level of VEGF mRNA decreased. These findings suggest a role for NF90 in the regulation of RISC-mediated silencing which stabilizes target mRNAs, such as VEGF, during cancer-induced hypoxia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461467" rel="alternate" title="NF90 Interacts with Components of RISC and Modulates Association of Ago2 with mRNA (5 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461102</id><title>Acoustic Force Spectroscopy Reveals Subtle Differences in Cellulose Unbinding Behavior of Carbohydrate-Binding Modules (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.095218+00:00</updated><author><name>Markus Hackl</name></author><author><name>Edward V. Contrada</name></author><author><name>Jonathan E. Ash</name></author><author><name>Atharv Kulkarni</name></author><author><name>Jinho Yoon</name></author><author><name>Hyeon-Yeol Cho</name></author><author><name>Ki-Bum Lee</name></author><author><name>John M. Yarbrough</name></author><author><name>Shishir P. S. Chundawat</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To rationally engineer more efficient cellulolytic enzymes for cellulosic biomass deconstruction into sugars for biofuels production, it is necessary to better understand the complex enzyme-substrate interfacial interactions. Carbohydrate binding modules (CBM) are often associated with microbial surface-tethered cellulosomal or freely secreted cellulase enzymes to increase substrate accessibility. However, it is not well known how CBM recognize, bind, and dissociate from polysaccharide surfaces to facilitate efficient cellulolytic activity due to the lack of mechanistic understanding of CBM-substrate interactions. Our work outlines a general approach to methodically study the unbinding behavior of CBMs from model polysaccharide surfaces using single-molecule force spectroscopy. Here, we apply acoustic force spectroscopy (AFS) to probe a &lt;italic&gt;Clostridium thermocellum&lt;/italic&gt; cellulosomal scaffoldin protein (CBM3a) and measure its dissociation from nanocellulose surfaces at physiologically relevant, low force loading rates. An automated microfluidic setup and methodology for uniform deposition of insoluble polysaccharides on the AFS chip surfaces is demonstrated. The rupture forces of wild-type CBM3a, and its Y67A mutant, unbinding from nanocellulose surface suggests distinct CBM binding conformations that can also explain the improved cellulolytic activity of cellulase tethered to CBM. Applying established dynamic force spectroscopy theory, the single-molecule unbinding rate at zero force is extrapolated and found to agree well with bulk equilibrium unbinding rates estimated independently using quartz crystal microbalance with dissipation monitoring. However, our results highlight the limitations of applying classical theory to explain the highly multivalent CBM-cellulose interactions seen at higher cellulose-CBM bond rupture forces (&amp;gt;15pN).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cellulases are multi-modular enzymes produced by numerous microbes that catalyze cellulose hydrolysis into glucose. These enzymes play an important role in global carbon cycling as well as cellulosic biofuels production. CBMs are essential components of cellulolytic enzymes involved in facilitating hydrolysis of polysaccharides by tethered catalytic domains (CD). The subtle interplay between CBM binding and CD activity is poorly understood particularly for heterogeneous reactions at solid-liquid interfaces. Here, we report a highly multiplexed single-molecule force spectroscopy method to study CBM dissociation from cellulose to infer the molecular mechanism governing substrate recognition and dissociation. This approach can be broadly applied to study multivalent protein-polysaccharide binding interactions relevant to other carbohydrates such as starch, chitin, or hyaluronan to engineer efficient biocatalysts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461102" rel="alternate" title="Acoustic Force Spectroscopy Reveals Subtle Differences in Cellulose Unbinding Behavior of Carbohydrate-Binding Modules (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462632</id><title>Direct Reprogramming of Non-limb Fibroblasts to Cells with Properties of Limb Progenitors (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.095864+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuji Atsuta</name></author><author><name>Changhee Lee</name></author><author><name>Alan R. Rodrigues</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Colle</name></author><author><name>Reiko R. Tomizawa</name></author><author><name>Ernesto G. Lujan</name></author><author><name>Patrick Tschopp</name></author><author><name>Joshua M. Gorham</name></author><author><name>Jean-Pierre Vannier</name></author><author><name>Christine E. Seidman</name></author><author><name>Jonathan G. Seidman</name></author><author><name>Olivier Pourquié</name></author><author><name>Clifford J. Tabin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The early limb bud consists of mesenchymal progenitors (limb progenitors) derived from the lateral plate mesoderm (LPM) that produce most of the tissues of the mature limb bud. The LPM also gives rise to the mesodermal components of the trunk, flank and neck. However, the mesenchymal cells generated at these other axial levels cannot produce the variety of cell types found in the limb bud, nor can they be directed to form a patterned appendage-like structure, even when placed in the context of the signals responsible for organizing the limb bud. Here, by taking advantage of a direct reprogramming approach, we find a set of factors (Prdm16, Zbtb16, and Lin28) normally expressed in the early limb bud, that are capable of imparting limb progenitor-like properties to non-limb fibroblasts. Cells reprogrammed by these factors show similar gene expression profiles, and can differentiate into similar cell types, as endogenous limb progenitors. The further addition of Lin41 potentiates proliferation of the reprogrammed cells while suppressing differentiation. These results suggest that these same four key factors may play pivotal roles in the specification of endogenous limb progenitors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462632" rel="alternate" title="Direct Reprogramming of Non-limb Fibroblasts to Cells with Properties of Limb Progenitors (4 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462438</id><title>Biochemical and structural characterization of the fused Bacteroides fragilis NFeoAB domain reveals a role for FeoA (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.096263+00:00</updated><author><name>Alex E. Sestok</name></author><author><name>Janae B. Brown</name></author><author><name>Juliet O. Obi</name></author><author><name>Sean M. O’Sullivan</name></author><author><name>Elsa D. Garcin</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Deredge</name></author><author><name>Aaron T. Smith</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Iron is an essential element for nearly all organisms, and under anoxic and/or reducing conditions, Fe&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; is the dominant form of iron available to bacteria. The ferrous iron transport (Feo) system has been identified as the primary prokaryotic Fe&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; import machinery, and two proteins (FeoA and FeoB) are conserved across most bacterial species. However, how FeoA and FeoB function relative to one another remained enigmatic. In this work we explored the distribution of &lt;italic&gt;feoAB&lt;/italic&gt; operons predicted to encode for a fusion of FeoA tethered to the soluble N-terminal, G-protein domain of FeoB via a connecting linker region. We hypothesized that this fusion might poise FeoA to interact with FeoB in order to affect function. To test this hypothesis, we cloned, expressed, purified, and biochemically characterized the soluble NFeoAB fusion protein from &lt;italic&gt;Bacteroides fragilis&lt;/italic&gt;, a commensal organism implicated in drug-resistant peritoneal infections. Using X-ray crystallography, we determined to 1.50 Å resolution the structure of &lt;italic&gt;Bf&lt;/italic&gt;FeoA, which adopts an SH3-like fold implicated in protein-protein interactions. In combination with structural modeling, small-angle X-ray scattering, and hydrogen-deuterium exchange mass spectrometry, we show that FeoA and NFeoB indeed interact in a nucleotide-dependent manner, and we have mapped the protein-protein interaction interface. Finally, using GTP hydrolysis assays, we demonstrate that &lt;italic&gt;Bf&lt;/italic&gt;NFeoAB exhibits one of the slowest known rates of Feo-mediated GTP hydrolysis and is not potassium-stimulated, indicating that FeoA-NFeoB interactions may function to stabilize the GTP-bound form of FeoB. Our work thus reveals a role for FeoA function in the fused FeoAB systems and suggests a broader role for FeoA function amongst prokaryotes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462438" rel="alternate" title="Biochemical and structural characterization of the fused Bacteroides fragilis NFeoAB domain reveals a role for FeoA (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461017</id><title>Opening the side exit pores of ClpP by lowering the pH of proteolytic chamber coupled with substrate hydrolysis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.096566+00:00</updated><author><name>Leehyeon Kim</name></author><author><name>Byung-Gil Lee</name></author><author><name>Min Kyung Kim</name></author><author><name>Do Hoon Kwon</name></author><author><name>Hyunmin Kim</name></author><author><name>Heike Brötz-Oesterhelt</name></author><author><name>Soung-Hun Roh</name></author><author><name>Hyun Kyu Song</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ClpP serine peptidase is a tetradecameric degradation machine involved in many physiological processes. It becomes a competent ATP-dependent protease with Clp-ATPases. Small chemical compounds, acyldepsipeptides (ADEPs), are known to cause dysregulation and activation of ClpP without ATPases, and have potential as novel antibiotics. Previously, structural studies of ClpP from various species revealed the structural details, conformational changes, and activation mechanism. Although product release by the side exit pores has been proposed, the detailed driving force for product release remains elusive. Here, we report crystal structures of ClpP from &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/italic&gt; (BsClpP) in unforeseen ADEP-bound states. Cryo-electron microscopy structures revealed various conformational states at different pH conditions. To understand the conformational change for product release, we investigated the relationship between substrate hydrolysis and the pH lowering process. Our data, together with previous findings, provide insight into the molecular mechanism of product release by ClpP self-compartmentalizing protease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461017" rel="alternate" title="Opening the side exit pores of ClpP by lowering the pH of proteolytic chamber coupled with substrate hydrolysis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-09-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462367</id><title>Transcriptional interference in toehold switch-based RNA circuits (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.096785+00:00</updated><author><name>Elisabeth Falgenhauer</name></author><author><name>Andrea Mückl</name></author><author><name>Matthaeus Schwarz-Schilling</name></author><author><name>Friedrich C. Simmel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gene regulation based on regulatory RNA is an important mechanism in cells and is increasingly used for regulatory circuits in synthetic biology. Toehold switches are rationally designed post-transcriptional riboregulators placed in the 5’ untranslated region of mRNA molecules. In the inactive state of a toehold switch, the ribosome-binding site is inaccessible for the ribosome. In the presence of a trigger RNA molecule protein production is turned on. Using antisense RNA against trigger molecules (anti-trigger RNA), gene expression can also be switched off again. We here study the utility and regulatory effect of antisense transcription in this context, which enables a particularly compact circuit design. Our circuits utilize two inducible promoters that separately regulate trigger and anti-trigger transcription, whereas their cognate toehold switch, regulating expression of a reporter protein, is transcribed from a constitutive promoter. We explore various design options for the arrangement of the promoters and demonstrate that the resulting dynamic behavior is strongly influenced by transcriptional interference (TI) effects, leading to more than four-fold differences in expression levels. Our experimental results are consistent with previous findings that enhanced local RNA polymerase concentrations due to active promoters in close proximity lead to an increase in transcriptional activity of the strongest promoter in the circuits. Based on this insight, we selected optimum promoter designs and arrangements for the realization of a genetic circuit comprised of two toehold switches, two triggers and two anti-triggers that function as a post-transcriptional RNA regulatory exclusive OR (XOR) gate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462367" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptional interference in toehold switch-based RNA circuits (4 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462340</id><title>Single-cell transcriptomic analysis unveils spinal motor neuron subtype diversity underpinning the water-to-land transition in vertebrates (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.097039+00:00</updated><author><name>Ee Shan Liau</name></author><author><name>Suoqin Jin</name></author><author><name>Yen-Chung Chen</name></author><author><name>Wei-Szu Liu</name></author><author><name>Luok Wen Yong</name></author><author><name>Chang-Tai Tsai</name></author><author><name>Maëliss Calon</name></author><author><name>Jr-Kai Yu</name></author><author><name>Yi-Hsien Su</name></author><author><name>Stéphane Nedelec</name></author><author><name>Qing Nie</name></author><author><name>Jun-An Chen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spinal motor neurons (MNs) integrate sensory stimuli and brain commands to generate motor movements in vertebrates. Distinct MN populations and their diversity has long been hypothesized to co-evolve with motor circuit to provide the neural basis from undulatory to ambulatory locomotion during aquatic-to-terrestrial transition of vertebrates. However, how these subtypes are evolved remains largely enigmatic. Using single-cell transcriptomics, we investigate heterogeneity in mouse MNs and discover novel segment-specific subtypes. Among limb-innervating MNs, we reveal a diverse neuropeptide code for delineating putative motor pool identities. We further uncovered that axial MNs are subdivided by three conserved and molecularly distinct subpopulations, defined by Satb2, Nr2f2 or Bcl11b expression. Although axial MNs are conserved from cephalochordates to humans, subtype diversity becomes prominent in land animals and appears to continue evolving in humans. Overall, our study provides a unified classification system for spinal MNs and paves the way towards deciphering how neuronal subtypes are evolved.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462340" rel="alternate" title="Single-cell transcriptomic analysis unveils spinal motor neuron subtype diversity underpinning the water-to-land transition in vertebrates (4 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461061</id><title>Aldh2 dependent formaldehyde metabolism fuels purine demands in melanocyte stem cells (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.097342+00:00</updated><author><name>Hannah Brunsdon</name></author><author><name>Alessandro Brombin</name></author><author><name>Samuel Peterson</name></author><author><name>John H. Postlethwait</name></author><author><name>E. Elizabeth Patton</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aldehyde-processing enzymes are viewed as essential clearing agents that rapidly deactivate harmful aldehydes. In the bone marrow, two specific enzymes, aldehyde dehydrogenase (ALDH) 2 and alcohol dehydrogenase (ADH) 5, were previously reported to protect hematopoietic stem cells from endogenous formaldehyde accumulation. Unexpectedly, we found that melanocyte stem cells (McSCs) in zebrafish depend on formate, an Aldh2-generated reaction product, to drive regeneration. Activated McSCs require Aldh2 (but not Adh5) to generate differentiated progeny, and by using scRNA-sequencing analysis, we identified a &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; purine biosynthesis program that is uniquely present in activated McSCs. Consistent with formate serving as one-carbon units for nucleotide biosynthesis, we found that purine supplementation (but not pyrimidine supplementation) was able to restore melanocyte regeneration in the absence of Aldh2. This work shows that Aldh2 enzymes generate reaction products that are needed to meet metabolic demands in regeneration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461061" rel="alternate" title="Aldh2 dependent formaldehyde metabolism fuels purine demands in melanocyte stem cells (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461687</id><title>Age of diabetes onset in the mutant proinsulin syndrome correlates with mutational impairment of protein foldability and stability (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.097600+00:00</updated><author><name>Balamurugan Dhayalan</name></author><author><name>Yen-Shan Chen</name></author><author><name>Yanwu Yang</name></author><author><name>Mark Jarosinski</name></author><author><name>Deepak Chatterjee</name></author><author><name>Rachel Grabowski</name></author><author><name>Shayan Poordian</name></author><author><name>Nelson F.B. Phillips</name></author><author><name>Peter Arvan</name></author><author><name>Faramarz Ismail-Beigi</name></author><author><name>Michael A. Weiss</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Diverse heterozygous mutations in the human insulin gene cause a monogenic diabetes mellitus (DM) syndrome due to toxic misfolding of the variant proinsulin. Whereas mutations that add or remove cysteines (thereby leading to an odd number of thiol groups) generally lead to neonatal-onset DM, non-Cys-related mutations can be associated with a broad range of ages of onset. Here, we compare two mutations at a conserved position in the central B-chain α-helix: one neonatal in DM onset (Val&lt;sup&gt;B18&lt;/sup&gt;→Gly) and the other with onset delayed until adolescence (Ala&lt;sup&gt;B18&lt;/sup&gt;). The substitutions were introduced within a 49-residue single-chain insulin precursor optimized for folding efficiency (Zaykov, A., et al. &lt;italic&gt;ACS Chem. Biol&lt;/italic&gt;. 9, 683-91 (2014)). Although mutations are each unfavorable, Gly&lt;sup&gt;B18&lt;/sup&gt; (a) more markedly perturbs DesDi folding efficiency &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; than does Ala&lt;sup&gt;B18&lt;/sup&gt; and (b) more severely induces endoplasmic reticulum (ER) stress in cell-based studies of the respective proinsulin variants. In corresponding two-chain hormone analogs, Gly&lt;sup&gt;B18&lt;/sup&gt; more markedly perturbs structure, function and thermodynamic stability than does Ala&lt;sup&gt;B18&lt;/sup&gt;. Indeed, the Gly&lt;sup&gt;B18&lt;/sup&gt;-insulin analog forms a molten globule with attenuated α-helix content whereas the Ala&lt;sup&gt;A18&lt;/sup&gt; analog retains a nativelike cooperative structure with reduced free energy of unfolding (ΔΔG&lt;sub&gt;u&lt;/sub&gt; 1.2(±0.2) kcal/mole relative to Val&lt;sup&gt;B18&lt;/sup&gt; parent). We propose that mutations at B18 variably impede nascent pairing of Cys&lt;sup&gt;B19&lt;/sup&gt; and Cys&lt;sup&gt;A20&lt;/sup&gt; to an extent correlated with perturbed core packing once native disulfide pairing is achieved. Differences in age of disease onset (neonatal or adolescent) reflect relative biophysical perturbations (severe or mild) of an obligatory on-pathway protein folding intermediate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461687" rel="alternate" title="Age of diabetes onset in the mutant proinsulin syndrome correlates with mutational impairment of protein foldability and stability (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461361</id><title>Combinatorial G x G x E CRISPR screening and functional analysis highlights SLC25A39 in mitochondrial GSH transport (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.097964+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaojian Shi</name></author><author><name>Bryn Reinstadler</name></author><author><name>Hardik Shah</name></author><author><name>Tsz-Leung To</name></author><author><name>Katie Byrne</name></author><author><name>Luanna Summer</name></author><author><name>Sarah E. Calvo</name></author><author><name>Olga Goldberger</name></author><author><name>John G. Doench</name></author><author><name>Vamsi K. Mootha</name></author><author><name>Hongying Shen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The SLC25 carrier family consists of 53 transporters that shuttle nutrients and co-factors across mitochondrial membranes&lt;sup&gt;1-3&lt;/sup&gt;. The family is highly redundant and their transport activities coupled to metabolic state. Here, we introduce a pooled, dual CRISPR screening strategy that knocks out pairs of transporters in four metabolic states — glucose, galactose, OXPHOS inhibition, and absence of pyruvate — designed to unmask the inter-dependence of these genes. In total, we screened 63 genes in four metabolic states, corresponding to 2016 single and pair-wise genetic perturbations. We recovered 19 gene-by-environment (GxE) interactions and 9 gene-by-gene (GxG) interactions. One GxE interaction hit illustrated that the fitness defect in the mitochondrial folate carrier (SLC25A32) KO cells was genetically buffered in galactose due to a lack of substrate in &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; purine biosynthesis. Another GxE interaction hit revealed non-equivalence of the paralogous ATP/ADP exchangers (ANTs) with ANT2 specifically required during OXPHOS inhibition. GxG analysis highlighted a buffering interaction between the iron transporter SLC25A37 and the poorly characterized SLC25A39. Mitochondrial metabolite profiling, organelle transport assays, and structure-guided mutagenesis suggests SLC25A39 is critical for mitochondrial glutathione (GSH) transport. Our work underscores the importance of systemetically investigating family-wide genetic interactions between mitochondrial transporters across many metabolic environments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461361" rel="alternate" title="Combinatorial G x G x E CRISPR screening and functional analysis highlights SLC25A39 in mitochondrial GSH transport (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462012</id><title>Green light perception paved the way for the diversification of GAF domain photoreceptors (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.098312+00:00</updated><author><name>Nibedita Priyadarshini</name></author><author><name>Niklas Steube</name></author><author><name>Dennis Wiens</name></author><author><name>Rei Narikawa</name></author><author><name>Annegret Wilde</name></author><author><name>Georg K. A. Hochberg</name></author><author><name>Gen Enomoto</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Photoreceptors are proteins that sense incident light and then trigger downstream signaling events. Phytochromes are linear tetrapyrrole-binding photoreceptors present in plants, algae, fungi, and various bacteria. Most phytochromes respond to red and far-red light signals. Among the phytochrome superfamily, cyanobacteria-specific cyanobacteriochromes show much more diverse optical properties covering the entire visible region. Both phytochromes and cyanobacteriochromes share the GAF domain scaffold to cradle the chromophore as the light-sensing region. It is unknown what physiological demands drove the evolution of cyanobacteriochromes in cyanobacteria. Here we utilize ancestral sequence reconstruction and report that the resurrected ancestral cyanobacteriochrome proteins reversibly respond to green and red light signals. pH titration analyses indicate that the deprotonation of the bound phycocyanobilin chromophore enables the photoreceptor to perceive green light. The ancestral cyanobacteriochromes show modest thermal reversion to the green light-absorbing form, suggesting that they evolved to sense green-rich irradiance rather than red light, which is preferentially utilized for photosynthesis. In contrast to plants and green algae, many cyanobacteria can utilize green light for photosynthesis with their special light-harvesting complexes, phycobilisomes. The evolution of green/red sensing cyanobacteriochromes may therefore have allowed ancient cyanobacteria to acclimate to different light environments by rearranging the absorption capacity of the cyanobacterial antenna complex by chromatic acclimation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Light serves as a crucial environmental stimulus affecting the physiology of organisms across all kingdoms of life. Photoreceptors serve as important players of light responses, absorbing light and actuating biological processes. Among a plethora of photoreceptors, cyanobacteriochromes arguably have the wealthiest palette of color sensing, largely contributing to the success of cyanobacteria in various illuminated habitats. Our ancestral sequence reconstruction and the analysis of the resurrected ancestral proteins suggest that the very first cyanobacteriochrome most probably responded to the incident green-to-red light ratio, in contrast to modern red/far-red absorbing plant phytochromes. The deprotonation of the light-absorbing pigment for green light-sensing was a crucial molecular event for the invention of the new class of photoreceptors with their huge color tuning capacity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462012" rel="alternate" title="Green light perception paved the way for the diversification of GAF domain photoreceptors (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462049</id><title>Expanding the Molecular Alphabet of DNA-Based Data Storage Systems with Neural Network Nanopore Readout Processing (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.098572+00:00</updated><author><name>S. Kasra Tabatabaei</name></author><author><name>Bach Pham</name></author><author><name>Chao Pan</name></author><author><name>Jingqian Liu</name></author><author><name>Shubham Chandak</name></author><author><name>Spencer A. Shorkey</name></author><author><name>Alvaro G. Hernandez</name></author><author><name>Aleksei Aksimentiev</name></author><author><name>Min Chen</name></author><author><name>Charles M. Schroeder</name></author><author><name>Olgica Milenkovic</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;DNA is a promising next-generation data storage medium, but the recording latency and synthesis cost of oligos using the four natural nucleotides remain high. Here, we describe an improved DNA-based storage system that uses an extended 11-letter molecular alphabet combining natural and chemically modified nucleotides. Our extended-alphabet molecular storage paradigm offers a nearly two-fold increase in storage density and potentially the same order of reduction in the recording time. Experimental results involving a library of 77 custom-designed hybrid sequences reveal that one can readily detect and discriminate different combinations and orders of monomers via MspA nanopores. Furthermore, a neural network architecture designed to classify raw current signals generated by Oxford Nanopore Technologies sequencing ensures an average accuracy exceeding 60%, which is 39 times higher than that of random guessing. Molecular dynamics simulations reveal that the majority of modified nucleotides do not induce dramatic disruption of the DNA double helix, making the extended alphabet system potentially compatible with PCR-based random access data retrieval. The methodologies proposed provide a forward path for new implementations of molecular recorders.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462049" rel="alternate" title="Expanding the Molecular Alphabet of DNA-Based Data Storage Systems with Neural Network Nanopore Readout Processing (3 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462002</id><title>Reovirus infection is regulated by NPC1 and endosomal cholesterol homeostasis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.098865+00:00</updated><author><name>Paula Ortega-Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Gwen Taylor</name></author><author><name>Rohit K. Jangra</name></author><author><name>Raquel Tenorio</name></author><author><name>Isabel Fernández de Castro</name></author><author><name>Bernardo A. Mainou</name></author><author><name>Robert C. Orchard</name></author><author><name>Craig B. Wilen</name></author><author><name>Pamela H. Brigleb</name></author><author><name>Jorna Sojati</name></author><author><name>Kartik Chandran</name></author><author><name>Cristina Risco</name></author><author><name>Terence S. Dermody</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cholesterol homeostasis is required for the replication of many viruses, including Ebola virus, hepatitis C virus, and human immunodeficiency virus-1. Niemann-Pick C1 (NPC1) is an endosomal-lysosomal membrane protein involved in cholesterol trafficking from late endosomes and lysosomes to the endoplasmic reticulum. We identified NPC1 in CRISPR and RNA interference screens as a putative host factor for infection by mammalian orthoreovirus (reovirus). Following internalization via clathrin-mediated endocytosis, the reovirus outer capsid is proteolytically removed, the endosomal membrane is disrupted, and the viral core is released into the cytoplasm where viral transcription, genome replication, and assembly take place. We found that reovirus infection is significantly impaired in cells lacking NPC1, but infection is restored by treatment of cells with hydroxypropyl-β-cyclodextrin, which binds and solubilizes cholesterol. Absence of NPC1 did not dampen infection by infectious subvirion particles, which are reovirus disassembly intermediates that bypass the endocytic pathway for infection of target cells. NPC1 is not required for reovirus attachment to the plasma membrane, internalization into cells, or uncoating within endosomes. Instead, NPC1 is required for delivery of transcriptionally active reovirus core particles into the cytoplasm. These findings suggest that cholesterol homeostasis, ensured by NPC1 transport activity, is required for reovirus penetration into the cytoplasm, pointing to a new function for NPC1 and cholesterol homeostasis in viral infection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Genetic screens are useful strategies to identify host factors required for viral infection. NPC1 was identified in independent CRISPR and RNA interference screens as a putative host factor required for reovirus replication. We discovered that NPC1-mediated cholesterol transport is dispensable for reovirus attachment, internalization, and disassembly but required for penetration of the viral disassembly intermediate from late endosomes into the cytoplasm. These findings pinpoint an essential function for cholesterol in the entry of reovirus and raise the possibility that cholesterol homeostasis regulates the entry of other viruses that penetrate late endosomes to initiate replication.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462002" rel="alternate" title="Reovirus infection is regulated by NPC1 and endosomal cholesterol homeostasis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461487</id><title>Ratiometric RNA labeling allows dynamic multiplexed analysis of gene circuits in single cells (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.099204+00:00</updated><author><name>Shuhui Xu</name></author><author><name>Kai Li</name></author><author><name>Liang Ma</name></author><author><name>Jianhan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Shinae Yoon</name></author><author><name>Michael B. Elowitz</name></author><author><name>Yihan Lin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Biological processes are highly dynamic and are regulated by genes that connect with one and another, forming regulatory circuits and networks. Understanding how gene regulatory circuits operate dynamically requires monitoring the expression of multiple genes in the same cell. However, it is limited by the relatively few distinguishable fluorescent proteins. Here, we developed a multiplexed real-time transcriptional imaging method based on two RNA stem-loop binding proteins, and employed it to analyze the temporal dynamics of synthetic gene circuits. By incorporating different ratios of MS2 and PP7 stem-loops, we were able to monitor the real-time nascent transcriptional activities of up to five genes in the same cell using only two fluorescent proteins. Applying this multiplexing capability to synthetic linear or branched gene regulatory cascades revealed that propagation of transcriptional dynamics is enhanced by non-stationary dynamics and is dictated by the slowest regulatory branch in the presence of combinatorial regulation. Mathematical modeling provided further insight into temporal multi-gene interactions and helped to understand potential challenges in regulatory inference using snapshot single-cell data. Ratiometric multiplexing should scale exponentially with additional labelling channels, providing a way to track the dynamics of larger circuits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461487" rel="alternate" title="Ratiometric RNA labeling allows dynamic multiplexed analysis of gene circuits in single cells (3 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461942</id><title>Quantitative phosphoproteomics reveals regulatory state dependent efficacy of chemical Cdk1 inhibition and distinct Cdk5 complexes as novel Wee1 substrates (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.099556+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew V. Grassetti</name></author><author><name>Rufus Hards</name></author><author><name>Scott A. Gerber</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Wee1 kinase plays a central role in the eukaryotic cell cycle via its well-known negative regulation of Cdk1 activity at the G2/M transition, preventing progression into mitosis until DNA replication and/or DNA damage repair is complete. Recent genetic evidence in yeast, flies and human cells have suggested additional functions of Wee1 in mitosis and during mitotic exit, respectively. To discover new candidate substrates of Wee1 kinase, we used SILAC-based phosphoproteomics and selective chemical inhibition to quantitatively compare phosphorylation site abundances in the presence and absence of Wee1 activity. Unexpectedly, we uncovered a role for the Wee1-dependent phosphorylation of Cdk1-cyclin B at tyrosine 15 (Y15) in facilitating chemical inhibition of Cdk1-cyclin B by the inhibitor RO3306. Thermal shift stability assays demonstrated greater binding affinity of RO3306 for Y15-phosphorylated Cdk1-cyclin B versus unphosphorylated complex, providing an additional molecular basis for the observed Wee1 inhibitor-based toxicity in human cells. In addition, our experiments identified Cdk5-CABLES and Cdk5-cyclin B as novel substrates of Wee1 during chemically induced exit from mitosis. Collectively, these experiments facilitate a greater understanding of the Wee1-Cdk1 signaling axis and uncover new candidate substrates for Wee1.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461942" rel="alternate" title="Quantitative phosphoproteomics reveals regulatory state dependent efficacy of chemical Cdk1 inhibition and distinct Cdk5 complexes as novel Wee1 substrates (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461918</id><title>The exocyst complex and intracellular vesicles mediate soluble protein trafficking to the primary cilium (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.102002+00:00</updated><author><name>SM Niedziółka</name></author><author><name>S Datta</name></author><author><name>T Uśpieński</name></author><author><name>B Baran</name></author><author><name>EW Humke</name></author><author><name>R Rohatgi</name></author><author><name>P Niewiadomski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Efficient transport of proteins into the primary cilium is a crucial step for many signaling pathways. Dysfunction of this process can lead to the disruption of signaling cascades or cilium assembly, resulting in developmental disorders and cancer. Previous studies on ciliary trafficking were mostly focused on the membrane-embedded receptors. In contrast, how soluble proteins are delivered into the cilium is poorly understood. In our work, we identify the exocyst complex as a key player in the ciliary trafficking of soluble Gli transcription factors. Considering that the exocyst mediates intracellular vesicle transport, we demonstrate that soluble proteins, including Gli2/3 and Lkb1, can use the endosome recycling machinery for their delivery to the primary cilium. Finally, we identify GTPases: Rab14, Rab18, Rab23, and Arf4 involved in vesicle-mediated Gli protein ciliary trafficking. Our data pave the way for a better understanding of ciliary transport and uncover novel transport mechanisms inside the cell.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461918" rel="alternate" title="The exocyst complex and intracellular vesicles mediate soluble protein trafficking to the primary cilium (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.460276</id><title>Determining cardiac structure by diffuse reflectance of different wavelengths (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.102792+00:00</updated><author><name>Philip Gemmell</name></author><author><name>Martin Bishop</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Catheter ablation in patients suffering from chronic arrhythmias requires detailed knowledge of the underlying cardiac anatomy; such real-time, high resolution mapping is currently unavailable in a clinical setting. We present here preliminary work towards a novel optical strategy based on diffuse optical reflectance to provide quantitative anatomical measurements of the cardiac structure, including tissue thickness and presence of scar. An in-depth literature search is conducted to collate available experimental data regarding optical parameters in cardiac tissue and scar. Computational simulations of photon movement through cardiac tissue using Monte Carlo modelling are performed, with analysis being focussed on the effects on surface emission profiles of (i) optical parameters; (ii) tissue thickness; (iii) presence of scar. Our results demonstrate (i) sensitivity of the approach to changes in optical parameters within tissue, (ii) difference of results depending on light wavelength. These suggest that this can be used to detect cardiac anatomical structure to a depth of ∼ 2 mm, for both thickness of cardiac tissue and presence of scar. This study demonstrates the feasibility of using diffuse optical reflectance to determine cardiac structure, enabling a potential route for high-resolution, real-time structural information to guide catheter ablation and similar surgeries.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.460276" rel="alternate" title="Determining cardiac structure by diffuse reflectance of different wavelengths (3 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461959</id><title>Heterologous expression of the human ZIP4 zinc transporter in Saccharomyces cerevisiae (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.103335+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuting Liu</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth M. Bafaro</name></author><author><name>Robert E. Dempski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The human (h) transporter, hZIP4 is the primary zinc importer in the intestine and is also expressed in a variety of organs such as the pancreas and brain. Dysfunction of hZIP4 can result in the zinc deficiency disease &lt;italic&gt;acrodermatitis enteropathica&lt;/italic&gt; (AE), which disrupts digestive and immune system homeostasis. Structure-function studies of hZIP4 have been greatly hindered by the absence of a robust heterologous expression system. Here, we report the heterologous expression of hZIP4 in &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt;. Both a wild type and a mutant &lt;italic&gt;S. cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; strain, in which the endogenous zinc transporters are deleted, were used to test the expression and localization of an hZIP4-GFP fusion protein. A full-length hZIP4-GFP and a truncated membrane domain only (mhZIP4-GFP) protein were successfully produced and targeted to the plasma membrane in yeast.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461959" rel="alternate" title="Heterologous expression of the human ZIP4 zinc transporter in Saccharomyces cerevisiae (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.461976</id><title>M-Phase oscillations in PP1 activity are essential for accurate progression through mammalian oocyte meiosis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.103576+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicole J. Camlin</name></author><author><name>Ilakkiya Venkatachalam</name></author><author><name>Janice P. Evans</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tightly controlled fluctuations in kinase and phosphatase activity play important roles in regulating M-Phase transitions (e.g., G2/M). Protein Phosphatase 1 (PP1) is one of these phosphatases, with oscillations in activity driving mitotic M-Phase entry, progression, and exit, with evidence from a variety of experimental systems pointing to roles in meiosis as well. Here we report that PP1 is important for M-Phase transitions through mouse oocyte meiosis. Employing a unique small-molecule approach to inhibit or activate PP1 at distinct phases of mouse oocyte meiosis, we found that aberrations in normal cyclical PP1 activity leads to meiotic abnormalities. We report here that temporal control of PP1 activity is essential for G2/M transition, metaphase I/anaphase I transition, and the formation of a normal metaphase II oocyte. Our data also reveal that inappropriate activation of PP1 is more deleterious at G2/M transition than at prometaphase I-to-metaphase I, and that an active pool of PP1 during prometaphase I is vital for metaphase I/anaphase I transition and metaphase II chromosome alignment. Taken together, these results establish that loss of oscillations in PP1 activity causes a range of severe meiotic defects, pointing to essential roles for PP1 in oocytes and female fertility, and more broadly, M-Phase regulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.461976" rel="alternate" title="M-Phase oscillations in PP1 activity are essential for accurate progression through mammalian oocyte meiosis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461268</id><title>How Our Cells Become Our Selves: The Cellular Phylodynamic Biology of Growth and Development (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.103773+00:00</updated><author><name>Philip Chodrow</name></author><author><name>Jessica Su</name></author><author><name>Daniel Lee</name></author><author><name>Tahmid Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Neil He</name></author><author><name>De Man Ruben</name></author><author><name>Ankur Tiwari</name></author><author><name>William Mannherz</name></author><author><name>Luca Citi</name></author><author><name>Daniel DiCorpo</name></author><author><name>James Selib Michaelson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Our lives begin with 1 cell, then 2, then 4, then the trillion cell adult, comprised of cell lineages, tissues, organs. How does this occur? Examination in numbers of cells, &lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;N, Cellular Phylodynamics&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt;, revealed two previously unappreciated processes: &lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;UNI-GROWTH&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt;, the slowing of growth that occurs as we become larger, caused by fewer cells dividing, captured by the &lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Universal Mitotic Fraction&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt; and &lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Universal Growth Equations&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt;, with accuracy confirmed for 13 species, including nematodes, mollusks, and vertebrates; and &lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;ALLO-GROWTH&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt;, the creation of body parts from &lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Founder Cells&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt;, captured by the &lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Cellular Allometric Growth Equation&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt;, which describes mitotic expansion by &lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Cell-Heritable&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt; change in the &lt;bold&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Cell Cycle Time&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/bold&gt;. These equations can generate cell lineage approximations, bringing the power of coalescent theory to developmental biology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461268" rel="alternate" title="How Our Cells Become Our Selves: The Cellular Phylodynamic Biology of Growth and Development (3 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462164</id><title>A yeast with muscle doesn’t run faster: full humanization of the glycolytic pathway in Saccharomyces cerevisiae (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.103983+00:00</updated><author><name>Francine J. Boonekamp</name></author><author><name>Ewout Knibbe</name></author><author><name>Marcel A. Vieira-Lara</name></author><author><name>Melanie Wijsman</name></author><author><name>Marijke A.H. Luttik</name></author><author><name>Karen van Eunen</name></author><author><name>Maxime den Ridder</name></author><author><name>Reinier Bron</name></author><author><name>Ana Maria Almonacid Suarez</name></author><author><name>Patrick van Rijn</name></author><author><name>Justina C. Wolters</name></author><author><name>Martin Pabst</name></author><author><name>Jean-Marc Daran</name></author><author><name>Barbara Bakker</name></author><author><name>Pascale Daran-Lapujade</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;While transplantation of single genes in yeast plays a key role in elucidating gene functionality in metazoans, technical challenges hamper the humanization of full pathways and processes. Empowered by advances in synthetic biology, this study demonstrates the feasibility and implementation of full humanization of glycolysis in yeast. Single gene and full pathway transplantation revealed the remarkable conservation of both glycolytic and moonlighting functions and, combined with evolutionary strategies, brought to light novel, context-dependent responses. Remarkably, human hexokinase 1 and 2, but not 4, required mutations in their catalytic or allosteric sites for functionality in yeast, while hexokinase 3 was unable to complement its yeast ortholog. Comparison with human tissues cultures showed the preservation of turnover numbers of human glycolytic enzymes in yeast and human cell cultures. This demonstration of transplantation of an entire, essential pathway paves the way to the establishment of species, tissue and disease-specific metazoan models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This work demonstrates the successful humanization of an entire pathway in &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; and establishes an attractive strategy to study (human) glycolysis architecture and regulation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The successful humanization of the entire glycolytic pathway in yeast offers new microbial models for both fundamental and applied studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both glycolytic and moonlighting functions and turnover numbers of glycolytic enzymes are highly conserved between yeast and human.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Functionality of human hexokinases 1 and 2 in yeast requires mutations in the catalytic or allosteric binding sites.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Combination of single gene and full transplantation with laboratory evolution reveals context-dependent activity and evolution of glycolytic enzymes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462164" rel="alternate" title="A yeast with muscle doesn’t run faster: full humanization of the glycolytic pathway in Saccharomyces cerevisiae (3 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462140</id><title>A microfluidic platform for sequential assembly and separation of synthetic cell models (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.104203+00:00</updated><author><name>Ran Tivony</name></author><author><name>Marcus Fletcher</name></author><author><name>Kareem Al Nahas</name></author><author><name>Ulrich F Keyser</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cell-sized vesicles like giant unilamellar vesicles (GUVs) are established as a promising biomimetic model for studying cellular phenomena in isolation. However, the presence of residual components and by-products, generated during vesicles preparation and manipulation, severely limits the utility of GUVs in applications like synthetic cells. Therefore, with the rapidly growing field of synthetic biology, there is an emergent demand for techniques that can continuously purify cell-like vesicles from diverse residues, while GUVs are being simultaneously synthesized and manipulated. We developed a microfluidic platform capable of purifying GUVs through stream bifurcation, where a stream of vesicles suspension is partitioned into three fractions - purified GUVs, residual components, and a washing solution. Using our purification approach, we showed that giant vesicles can be separated from various residues – that range in size and chemical composition – with a very high efficiency (&lt;italic&gt;e&lt;/italic&gt; = 0.99), based on size and deformability of the filtered objects. In addition, by incorporating the purification module with a microfluidic-based GUV-formation method, octanol-assisted liposome assembly (OLA), we established an integrated production-purification microfluidic unit that sequentially produces, manipulates, and purifies GUVs. We demonstrate the applicability of the integrated device to synthetic biology through sequentially fusing SUVs with freshly prepared GUVs and separating the fused GUVs from extraneous SUVs and oil droplets at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462140" rel="alternate" title="A microfluidic platform for sequential assembly and separation of synthetic cell models (3 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462237</id><title>Regulation of Blos1 by IRE1 prevents the accumulation of Huntingtin protein aggregates (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.104358+00:00</updated><author><name>Donghwi Bae</name></author><author><name>Rachel Elizabeth Jones</name></author><author><name>Julie Hollien</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Huntington’s Disease is characterized by accumulation of the aggregation-prone mutant Huntingtin (mHTT) protein. Here, we show that expression of mHTT in mouse cultured cells activates IRE1, the transmembrane sensor of stress in the endoplasmic reticulum, leading to degradation of the &lt;italic&gt;Blos1&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA and repositioning of lysosomes and late endosomes toward the microtubule organizing center. Overriding &lt;italic&gt;Blos1&lt;/italic&gt; degradation results in accumulation of larger mHTT aggregates and increased cell death. Although mHTT is degraded by macroautophagy when highly expressed, we show that prior to the formation of large aggregates, mHTT is degraded via an ESCRT-dependent, endosomal microautophagy pathway. This pathway is enhanced by &lt;italic&gt;Blos1&lt;/italic&gt; degradation and appears to protect cells from a toxic, less aggregated form of mHTT.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Condensed title&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Blos1&lt;/italic&gt; regulation protects from Huntingtin protein aggregation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462237" rel="alternate" title="Regulation of Blos1 by IRE1 prevents the accumulation of Huntingtin protein aggregates (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462327</id><title>Trypanosome morphogenesis involves recruitment of a pleckstrin homology domain protein by an orphan kinesin to the microtubule quartet (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.104503+00:00</updated><author><name>Corinna Benz</name></author><author><name>Nora Müller</name></author><author><name>Marie Vancová</name></author><author><name>Sabine Kaltenbrunner</name></author><author><name>Hana Váchová</name></author><author><name>Vladimír Varga</name></author><author><name>Julius Lukeš</name></author><author><name>Hassan Hashimi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Kinesins are motor proteins found in all eukaryotic lineages that move along microtubule tracks to mediate numerous cellular processes such as mitosis and intracellular transport of cargo. In trypanosomatids, the kinesin protein superfamily has undergone a prominent expansion, giving these protists one of the most diverse kinesin repertoires. This has led to the emergence of two trypanosomatid-restricted groups of kinesins. Here, we characterize in &lt;italic&gt;Trypanosoma brucei&lt;/italic&gt; TbKifX2, a hitherto orphaned kinesin that belongs to one of these groups. TbKifX2 tightly interacts with TbPH1, a kinesin-like protein named after a pleckstrin homology (PH) domain present within its carboxy terminal tail. TbKifX2 recruits TbPH1 to the microtubule quartet (MtQ), a characteristic cytoskeletal structure that is part of the multipartite flagellum attachment zone (FAZ) and extends from the basal body to the anterior of the cell body. The proximal proteome of TbPH1 is comprised of four proteins that localize to the FAZ, consistent with the notion that the TbKifX2/TbPH1 complex binds the MtQ along its whole length. Simultaneous ablation of both TbKifX2 and TbPH1 leads to the formation of prominent protrusions from the cell posterior. Thus, we have attributed a morphogenesis role to these two trypanosomatid-restricted proteins, and their remarkably specific localization to the MtQ in a microtubule-rich cell. We hypothesize that the putative TbKifX2/TbPH1 complex transports a cytokinesis auxiliary factor(s) along the MtQ to or from the &lt;italic&gt;T. brucei&lt;/italic&gt; posterior. The cohort of proteins found in proximity to TbPH1 may represent one of these factors directly or be involved in their trafficking during cell division in trypanosomatids.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;AUTHOR SUMMARY&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trypanosomatids are a group of unicellular parasites that infect a wide range of hosts from land plants to animals. They are also eukaryotes that have been shaped by prolonged independent evolution since this domain of life has radiated from a common ancestor almost 2 billion years ago. Thus, any resulting unique biological properties can be potentially exploited for treatment of infectious diseases caused by trypanosomatids. The cytoskeleton of trypanosomatids represents an ancient organelle that has undergone such modification. Here, we show that two trypanosomatid-specific proteins named TbPH1 and TbKifX2 form a complex that localizes to the microtubule quartet, a cytoskeletal structure characteristic to trypanosomatids. Ablation of these proteins in &lt;italic&gt;Trypansoma brucei&lt;/italic&gt; leads to severe morphological defects, making them not only intrinsically interesting topics of study, but potential therapeutic targets as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462327" rel="alternate" title="Trypanosome morphogenesis involves recruitment of a pleckstrin homology domain protein by an orphan kinesin to the microtubule quartet (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462267</id><title>De novo biosynthesis of para-nitro-L-phenylalanine in Escherichia coli (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.104681+00:00</updated><author><name>Neil D. Butler</name></author><author><name>Sabyasachi Sen</name></author><author><name>Minwei Lin</name></author><author><name>Aditya M. Kunjapur</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nitroaromatic functional groups can impart valuable properties to chemicals and to biological macromolecules including polypeptides. &lt;italic&gt;Para&lt;/italic&gt;-nitro-L-phenylalanine (pN-Phe) is a nitroaromatic amino acid with uses including immune stimulation and fluorescence quenching. As the chemical synthesis of pN-Phe does not follow green chemistry principles and impedes provision of pN-Phe to engineered bacterial cells in some contexts, we sought to design a &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; biosynthetic pathway for pN-Phe in &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt;. To generate the nitro chemical functional group, we identified natural diiron monooxygenases with measurable &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; activity on envisioned amine-containing precursors of &lt;italic&gt;para&lt;/italic&gt;-amino-L-phenylalanine (pA-Phe) and &lt;italic&gt;para&lt;/italic&gt;-aminophenylpyruvate. By expressing one of these &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;-oxygenase genes together with previously characterized genes for the biosynthesis of pA-Phe, we achieved the synthesis of pN-Phe from glucose. Through further optimization of the chassis, plasmid constructs, and media conditions, we were able to improve the selectivity of pN-Phe biosynthesis, resulting in a maximum titer of 819 µM in rich defined media under shake-flask conditions. These results provide a foundation for the biosynthesis of related nitroaromatic chemicals and for downstream biological applications that could utilize pN-Phe as a building block.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Para&lt;/italic&gt;-nitro-L-phenylalanine (pN-Phe) is a valuable small molecule for its applications in genetic code expansion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We establish &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; biosynthesis of pN-Phe from glucose in &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;, which is also the first example of a &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; pathway design for an unnatural but commonly used non-standard amino acid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We show the first use of an &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;-oxygenase enzyme in the &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; synthesis of a nitroaromatic product.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Screening of natural &lt;italic&gt;N-&lt;/italic&gt;oxygenases and strain engineering resulted in final pN-Phe titers of 820 ± 130 µM in shake flask experiments with rich defined media.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462267" rel="alternate" title="De novo biosynthesis of para-nitro-L-phenylalanine in Escherichia coli (3 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462432</id><title>Natural and designed proteins inspired by extremotolerant organisms can form condensates and attenuate apoptosis in human cells (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.104832+00:00</updated><author><name>Mike T. Veling</name></author><author><name>Dan T. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Nicole N. Thadani</name></author><author><name>Michela E. Oster</name></author><author><name>Nathan J. Rollins</name></author><author><name>Kelly P. Brock</name></author><author><name>Neville P. Bethel</name></author><author><name>David Baker</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey C. Way</name></author><author><name>Debora S. Marks</name></author><author><name>Roger L. Chang</name></author><author><name>Pamela A. Silver</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many organisms can survive extreme conditions and successfully recover to normal life. This extremotolerant behavior has been attributed in part to repetitive, amphipathic, and intrinsically disordered proteins that are upregulated in the protected state. Here, we assemble a library of approximately 300 naturally-occurring and designed extremotolerance-associated proteins to assess their ability to protect human cells from chemically-induced apoptosis. We show that proteins from tardigrades, nematodes, and the Chinese giant salamander are apoptosis protective. Notably, we identify a region of the human ApoE protein with similarity to extremotolerance-associated proteins that also protects against apoptosis. This region mirrors the phase separation behavior seen with such proteins, like the tardigrade protein CAHS2. Moreover, we identify a synthetic protein, DHR81, that shares this combination of elevated phase separation propensity and apoptosis protection. Finally, we demonstrate that driving protective proteins into the condensate state increases apoptosis protection, and highlight the ability for DHR81 condensates to sequester caspase-7. Taken together, this work draws a link between extremotolerance-associated proteins, condensate formation, and human cellular protection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462432" rel="alternate" title="Natural and designed proteins inspired by extremotolerant organisms can form condensates and attenuate apoptosis in human cells (3 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462825</id><title>Structural basis of ATP-dependent high-fidelity epigenome maintenance (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.105524+00:00</updated><author><name>Juncheng Wang</name></author><author><name>Sandra Catania</name></author><author><name>Chongyuan Wang</name></author><author><name>M. Jason de la Cruz</name></author><author><name>Beiduo Rao</name></author><author><name>Hiten D. Madhani</name></author><author><name>Dinshaw J. Patel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Epigenetic evolution occurs over million-year timescales in &lt;italic&gt;Cryptococcus neoformans&lt;/italic&gt; and is mediated by DNMT5, the first maintenance-type cytosine methyltransferase identified in the fungal or protist kingdoms. DNMT5 requires ATP and displays exquisite hemimethyl-DNA specificity. To understand these novel properties, we solved cryo-EM structures of &lt;italic&gt;Cn&lt;/italic&gt;DNMT5 in three states. These studies reveal an elaborate allosteric cascade in which hemimethylated DNA first activates the SNF2 ATPase domain by a large rigid body rotation while the target cytosine partially flips out the DNA duplex. ATP binding then triggers a striking structural reconfiguration of the methyltransferase catalytic pocket that enables cofactor binding, completion of base-flipping, and catalysis. Unmethylated DNA binding fails to open cofactor pocket and subsequent ATP binding triggers its ejection to ensure fidelity. This chaperone-like, enzyme-remodeling role of the SNF2 domain illuminates how energy can be used to enable faithful epigenetic memory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Structures of DNMT5 reveal mechanism of ATP-dependent DNA methylation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hemimethylated CpG recognition triggers partial base flipping of the target cytosine&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hemimethylated DNA induces rigid body rotation to activate the SNF2 ATPase domain&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;MTase catalytic pocket is remodeled by the SNF2 ATPase to achieve specificity&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462825" rel="alternate" title="Structural basis of ATP-dependent high-fidelity epigenome maintenance (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461880</id><title>How to model DNA replication in stochastic models of synthetic gene circuits (and why) (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.105804+00:00</updated><author><name>Samuel E. Clamons</name></author><author><name>Richard M. Murray</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Biocircuit modeling sometimes requires explicit tracking of a self-replicating DNA species. The most obvious, straightforward way to model a replicating DNA is structurally unstable and leads to pathological model behavior. We describe a simple, stable replication mechanism with good model behavior and show how to derive it from a mechanistic model of ColE1 replication.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461880" rel="alternate" title="How to model DNA replication in stochastic models of synthetic gene circuits (and why) (3 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462597</id><title>Cytoskeletal regulation of a transcription factor by DNA mimicry (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.106762+00:00</updated><author><name>Farah Haque</name></author><author><name>Christian Freniere</name></author><author><name>Qiong Ye</name></author><author><name>Nandini Mani</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth M. Wilson-Kubalek</name></author><author><name>Pei-I Ku</name></author><author><name>Ronald A. Milligan</name></author><author><name>Radhika Subramanian</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A long-established strategy for transcription regulation is the tethering of transcription factors to cellular membranes. In contrast, the principal effectors of Hedgehog signaling, the Gli transcription factors, are regulated by microtubules in the primary cilium and the cytoplasm. How Gli is tethered to microtubules remains unclear. We uncover DNA mimicry by the ciliary kinesin Kif7 as a mechanism for the recruitment of Gli to microtubules, revealing a new mode of tethering a DNA-binding protein to the cytoskeleton. Gli increases the Kif7-microtubule affinity and consequently modulates the localization of both proteins to microtubules and the cilium tip. Thus, the kinesin-microtubule system is not a passive Gli tether but a regulatable platform tuned by the kinesin-transcription factor interaction. We re-tooled the unique DNA-mimicry-based Gli-Kif7 interaction for inhibiting the nuclear and cilium localization of Gli. This strategy can be potentially exploited for downregulating erroneously activated Gli in human cancers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462597" rel="alternate" title="Cytoskeletal regulation of a transcription factor by DNA mimicry (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461561</id><title>FAIR enough? A perspective on the status of nucleotide sequence data and metadata on public archives (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.107203+00:00</updated><author><name>Christiane Hassenrück</name></author><author><name>Tobias Poprick</name></author><author><name>Véronique Helfer</name></author><author><name>Massimiliano Molari</name></author><author><name>Raissa Meyer</name></author><author><name>Ivaylo Kostadinov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Knowledge derived from nucleotide sequence data is increasing in importance in the life sciences, as well as decision making (mainly in biodiversity policy). Metadata standards have been established to facilitate sustainable sequence data management according to the FAIR principles (Findability, Accessibility, Interoperability, Reusability). Here, we review the status of metadata available for raw read Illumina amplicon and whole genome shotgun sequencing data derived from ecological metagenomic material that are accessible at the European Nucleotide Archive (ENA), as well as the compliance of the primary sequence data (fastq files) with data submission requirements. While overall basic metadata, such as geographic coordinates, were retrievable in 98% of the cases for this type of sequence data, interoperability was not always ensured and other (mainly conditionally) mandatory parameters were often not provided at all. Metadata standards, such as the ‘Minimum Information about any(x) Sequence (MIxS)’, were only infrequently used despite a demonstrated positive impact on metadata quality. Furthermore, the sequence data itself did not meet the prescribed requirements in 31 out of 39 studies that were manually inspected. To tackle the most immediate needs to improve FAIR sequence data management, we provide a list of minimal suggestions to researchers, research institutions, funding agencies, reviewers, publishers, and databases, that we believe might have a potentially large positive impact on sequence data and metadata FAIRness, which is crucial for further research and its derived applications.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461561" rel="alternate" title="FAIR enough? A perspective on the status of nucleotide sequence data and metadata on public archives (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>