<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.378785+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.472081</id><title>De Novo Design of Immunoglobulin-like Domains (50 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.379178+00:00</updated><author><name>Tamuka M. Chidyausiku</name></author><author><name>Soraia R. Mendes</name></author><author><name>Jason C. Klima</name></author><author><name>Ulrich Eckhard</name></author><author><name>Scott Houliston</name></author><author><name>Marta Nadal</name></author><author><name>Jorge Roel-Touris</name></author><author><name>Tibisay Guevara</name></author><author><name>Hugh K. Haddox</name></author><author><name>Adam Moyer</name></author><author><name>Cheryl H. Arrowsmith</name></author><author><name>F. Xavier Gomis-Rüth</name></author><author><name>David Baker</name></author><author><name>Enrique Marcos</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antibodies and antibody derivatives such as nanobodies contain immunoglobulin-like (Ig) β-sandwich scaffolds which anchor the hypervariable antigen-binding loops and constitute the largest growing class of drugs. Current engineering strategies for this class of compounds rely on naturally existing Ig frameworks, which can be hard to modify and have limitations in manufacturability, designability and range of action. Here we develop design rules for the central feature of the Ig fold architecture – the non-local cross-β structure connecting the two β-sheets – and use these to &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; design highly stable seven-stranded Ig domains, confirm their structures through X-ray crystallography, and show they can correctly scaffold functional loops. Our approach opens the door to the design of a new class of antibody-like scaffolds with tailored structures and superior biophysical properties.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.472081" rel="alternate" title="De Novo Design of Immunoglobulin-like Domains (50 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473809</id><title>Multi-Pathway DNA Double-Strand Break Repair Reporters Reveal Extensive Cross-Talk Between End-Joining, Single Strand Annealing, and Homologous Recombination (36 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.379524+00:00</updated><author><name>Bert van de Kooij</name></author><author><name>Alex Kruswick</name></author><author><name>Haico van Attikum</name></author><author><name>Michael B. Yaffe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;DNA double-strand breaks (DSB) are repaired by multiple distinct pathways, with outcomes ranging from error-free repair to extensive mutagenesis and genomic loss. Repair pathway cross-talk and compensation within the DSB-repair network is incompletely understood, despite its importance for genomic stability, oncogenesis, and the outcome of genome editing by CRISPR/Cas9. To address this, we constructed and validated three fluorescent Cas9-based reporters, named DSB-Spectrum, that simultaneously quantify the contribution of multiple distinct pathways to repair of a DSB. These reporters distinguish between DSB-repair by error-free canonical non-homologous end-joining (c-NHEJ) versus homologous recombination (HR; reporter 1), mutagenic repair versus HR (reporter 2), and mutagenic end-joining versus single strand annealing (SSA) versus HR (reporter 3). Using these reporters, we show that inhibition of the essential c-NHEJ factor DNA-PKcs not only increases repair by HR, but also results in a substantial increase in mutagenic repair by SSA. We show that SSA-mediated repair of Cas9-generated DSBs can occur between Alu elements at endogenous genomic loci, and is enhanced by inhibition of DNA-PKcs. Finally, we demonstrate that the short-range end-resection factors CtIP and Mre11 promote both SSA and HR, whereas the long-range end-resection factors DNA2 and Exo1 promote SSA, but reduce HR, when both pathways compete for the same substrate. These new Cas9-based DSB-Spectrum reporters facilitate the rapid and comprehensive analysis of repair pathway crosstalk and DSB-repair outcome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473809" rel="alternate" title="Multi-Pathway DNA Double-Strand Break Repair Reporters Reveal Extensive Cross-Talk Between End-Joining, Single Strand Annealing, and Homologous Recombination (36 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473384</id><title>Negative autoregulation mitigates collateral RNase activity of repeat-targeting CRISPR-Cas13d in mammalian cells (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.379719+00:00</updated><author><name>Chase P Kelley</name></author><author><name>Maja C Haerle</name></author><author><name>Eric T Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cas13 is a unique family of CRISPR endonucleases exhibiting programmable binding and cleavage of RNAs and is a strong candidate for eukaryotic RNA knockdown in the laboratory and the clinic. However, sequence-specific binding of Cas13 to the target RNA unleashes non-specific bystander RNA cleavage, or collateral activity, which may confound knockdown experiments and raises concerns for therapeutic applications. Although conserved across orthologs and robust in cell-free and bacterial environments, the extent of collateral activity in mammalian cells remains disputed. Here, we investigate Cas13d collateral activity in the context of an RNA-targeting therapy for myotonic dystrophy type 1, a disease caused by a transcribed long CTG repeat expansion. We find that when targeting CUGn RNA in HeLa and other cell lines, Cas13d depletes endogenous and transgenic RNAs, interferes with critical cellular processes, and activates stress response and apoptosis pathways. We also observe collateral effects when targeting other repetitive and unique transgenic sequences, and we provide evidence for collateral activity when targeting highly expressed endogenous transcripts. To minimize collateral activity for repeat-targeting Cas13d therapeutics, we introduce gRNA excision for negative-autoregulatory optimization (GENO), a simple strategy that leverages crRNA processing to control Cas13d expression and is easily integrated into an AAV gene therapy. We argue that thorough assessment of collateral activity is necessary when applying Cas13d in mammalian cells and that implementation of GENO illustrates the advantages of compact and universally robust regulatory systems for Cas-based gene therapies. &lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473384" rel="alternate" title="Negative autoregulation mitigates collateral RNase activity of repeat-targeting CRISPR-Cas13d in mammalian cells (29 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473728</id><title>Mediator is broadly recruited to gene promoters via a Tail-independent mechanism (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.379893+00:00</updated><author><name>Linda Warfield</name></author><author><name>Rafal Donczew</name></author><author><name>Lakshmi Mahendrawada</name></author><author><name>Steven Hahn</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mediator (MED) is a conserved factor with important roles in both basal and activated transcription. It is believed that MED plays a direct role in transcriptional regulation at most genes by functionally bridging enhancers and promoters. Here, we investigate the genome-wide roles of yeast MED by rapid depletion of its activator-binding domain (Tail) and monitoring changes in nascent transcription. We find that MED Tail and activator-mediated MED recruitment regulate only a small subset of genes. At most genes, MED bypasses the UAS and is directly recruited to promoters to facilitate transcription initiation. Our results define three classes of genes that differ in PIC assembly pathways and the requirements for MED Tail, SAGA, TFIID and BET factors Bdf1/2. We also find that the depletion of the MED middle module subunit Med7 mimics inactivation of Tail, suggesting a functional link. Our combined results have broad implications for the roles of MED, other coactivators, and mechanisms of transcriptional regulation at different gene classes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473728" rel="alternate" title="Mediator is broadly recruited to gene promoters via a Tail-independent mechanism (19 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473789</id><title>HSP70-binding motifs function as protein quality control degrons (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.380072+00:00</updated><author><name>Amanda B. Abildgaard</name></author><author><name>Søren D. Petersen</name></author><author><name>Fia B. Larsen</name></author><author><name>Caroline Kampmeyer</name></author><author><name>Kristoffer E. Johansson</name></author><author><name>Amelie Stein</name></author><author><name>Tommer Ravid</name></author><author><name>Claes Andréasson</name></author><author><name>Michael K. Jensen</name></author><author><name>Kresten Lindorff-Larsen</name></author><author><name>Rasmus Hartmann-Petersen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protein quality control (PQC) degrons are short protein segments that target misfolded proteins for degradation through the ubiquitin-proteasome system (UPS). To uncover how PQC degrons function, we performed a screen in &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; by fusing a library of flexible tetrapeptides to the C-terminus of the Ura3-HA-GFP reporter. The identified degrons exhibited high sequence variation but with marked hydrophobicity. Notably, the best scoring degrons constitute predicted Hsp70-binding motifs. When directly tested, a canonical Hsp70 binding motif (RLLL) functioned as a dose-dependent PQC degron that was targeted by Hsp70, Hsp110, Fes1, several Hsp40 J-domain co-chaperones and the PQC E3 ligase Ubr1. Our results suggest that multiple PQC degrons overlap with chaperone-binding sites and that PQC-linked degradation achieves specificity via chaperone binding. Thus, the PQC system has evolved to exploit the intrinsic capacity of chaperones to recognize misfolded proteins, thereby placing them at the nexus of protein folding and degradation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473789" rel="alternate" title="HSP70-binding motifs function as protein quality control degrons (18 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.472858</id><title>MIAAIM: Multi-omics image integration and tissue state mapping using topological data analysis and cobordism learning (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.380324+00:00</updated><author><name>Joshua M. Hess</name></author><author><name>Iulian Ilieş</name></author><author><name>Denis Schapiro</name></author><author><name>John J. Iskra</name></author><author><name>Walid M. Abdelmoula</name></author><author><name>Michael S. Regan</name></author><author><name>Georgios Theocharidis</name></author><author><name>Chin Lee Wu</name></author><author><name>Aristidis Veves</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Y.R. Agar</name></author><author><name>Ann E. Sluder</name></author><author><name>Mark C. Poznansky</name></author><author><name>Patrick M. Reeves</name></author><author><name>Ruxandra F. Sîrbulescu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;High-parameter tissue imaging enables detailed molecular analysis of single cells in their spatial environment. However, the comprehensive characterization and mapping of tissue states through multimodal imaging across different physiological and pathological conditions requires data integration across multiple imaging systems. Here, we introduce MIAAIM (Multi-omics Image Alignment and Analysis by Information Manifolds) a modular, reproducible computational framework for aligning data across bioimaging technologies, modeling continuities in tissue states, and translating multimodal measures across tissue types. We demonstrate MIAAIM’s workflows across diverse imaging platforms, including histological stains, imaging mass cytometry, and mass spectrometry imaging, to link cellular phenotypic states with molecular microenvironments in clinical biopsies from multiple tissue types with high cellular complexity. MIAAIM provides a robust foundation for the development of computational methods to integrate multimodal, high-parameter tissue imaging data and enable downstream computational and statistical interrogation of tissue states.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.472858" rel="alternate" title="MIAAIM: Multi-omics image integration and tissue state mapping using topological data analysis and cobordism learning (14 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.472683</id><title>An Atypical RNA Quadruplex Marks RNAs as Vectors for Gene Silencing (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.380799+00:00</updated><author><name>Saeed Roschdi</name></author><author><name>Jenny Yan</name></author><author><name>Yuichiro Nomura</name></author><author><name>Cristian A Escobar</name></author><author><name>Riley J Petersen</name></author><author><name>Craig A Bingman</name></author><author><name>Marco Tonelli</name></author><author><name>Eric J Montemayor</name></author><author><name>Scott Kennedy</name></author><author><name>SAMUEL BUTCHER</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The addition of poly(UG) ("pUG") repeats to 3' termini of mRNAs drives gene silencing and trans-generational epigenetic inheritance in the metazoan C. elegans. pUG tails promote silencing by recruiting an RNA-dependent RNA Polymerase (RdRP) that synthesizes small interfering (si)RNAs. Here we show that active pUG tails require a minimum of 11.5 repeats and adopt a quadruplex (G4)2 structure we term the pUG fold. The pUG fold differs from known G4s in that it has a left-handed backbone similar to Z-RNA, no consecutive guanosines in its sequence, and three G quartets and one U quartet stacked non-sequentially. Its biological importance is emphasized by our observations that porphyrin molecules bind to the pUG fold and inhibit both gene silencing and binding of RdRP. Moreover, specific N7-deaza RNA substitutions that do not adopt the pUG fold neither bind RdRP nor induce RNA silencing. These data define the pUG fold as a previously unrecognized RNA secondary structure motif that drives gene silencing. The pUG fold can also form internally within larger RNA molecules. Approximately 20,000 pUG-fold sequences are found in non-coding regions of human RNAs, suggesting the fold likely has biological roles beyond gene silencing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.472683" rel="alternate" title="An Atypical RNA Quadruplex Marks RNAs as Vectors for Gene Silencing (13 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473284</id><title>Nucleolar targeting in an early-branching eukaryote suggests a general physicochemical mechanism for ribosome protein sorting (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.381091+00:00</updated><author><name>Milad Jeilani</name></author><author><name>Karen Billington</name></author><author><name>Jack Daniel Sunter</name></author><author><name>Samuel Dean</name></author><author><name>Richard John Wheeler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The eukaryotic cell targets proteins to the organelles in which they function, both membrane-bound (like the nucleus) and non-membrane-bound (like the nucleolus). Nucleolar targeting relies on positively charged localisation signals, and has received rejuvenated interest since the widespread recognition of liquid-liquid phase separation (LLPS) as a mechanism contributing to nucleolus formation. Here, we exploit a new genome-wide analysis of protein localisation in an early-branching eukaryote, &lt;italic&gt;Trypanosoma brucei&lt;/italic&gt;, to analyse general nucleolar protein properties. &lt;italic&gt;T. brucei&lt;/italic&gt; nucleolar proteins have similar properties to those in common model eukaryotes, specifically basic amino acids. Using protein truncations and addition of candidate targeting sequences to proteins, we show both homopolymer runs and distributed basic amino acids give nucleolar partition, further aided by a nuclear localisation signal (NLS). These findings are consistent with phase separation models of nucleolar formation and protein physical properties being a major contributing mechanism for eukaryotic nucleolar targeting, conserved from the last eukaryotic common ancestor. Importantly, cytoplasmic ribosome proteins in comparison to mitochondrial ribosome proteins followed the same pattern – pointing to adaptation of physicochemical properties to assist segregation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We show protein targeting to the nucleolus is mediated by positive charge, likely across eukaryotes, and contributes to sorting of mitochondrial from cytoplasmic ribosome proteins.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473284" rel="alternate" title="Nucleolar targeting in an early-branching eukaryote suggests a general physicochemical mechanism for ribosome protein sorting (9 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473926</id><title>Intramolecular interactions enhance the potency of gallinamide A analogs against Trypanosoma cruzi (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.381359+00:00</updated><author><name>Elany Barbosa Da Silva</name></author><author><name>Vandna Sharma</name></author><author><name>Lilian Hernandez-Alvarez</name></author><author><name>Arthur H Tang</name></author><author><name>Alexander Stoye</name></author><author><name>Anthony J O'Donoghue</name></author><author><name>William H Gerwick</name></author><author><name>Richard J Payne</name></author><author><name>James H McKerrow</name></author><author><name>Larissa M Podust</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gallinamide A, a metabolite of the marine cyanobacterium &lt;italic&gt;Schizothrix&lt;/italic&gt; sp., selectively inhibits cathepsin L-like cysteine proteases. We evaluated potency of gallinamide A and 23 synthetic analogs against intracellular &lt;italic&gt;Trypanosoma cruzi&lt;/italic&gt; amastigotes and the cysteine protease, cruzain. We determined the co-crystal structures of cruzain with gallinamide A and two synthetic analogs at ~2Å. SAR data revealed that the N-terminal end of gallinamide A is loosely bound and weakly contributes in drug-target interactions. At the C-terminus, the intramolecular π-π stacking interactions between the aromatic substituents at P1	′ and P1 restrict the bioactive conformation of the inhibitors, thus minimizing the entropic loss associated with target binding. Molecular dynamics simulations showed that in the absence of an aromatic group at P1, the substituent at P1′ interacts with tryptophan-184. The P1-P1′ interactions had no effect on anti-cruzain activity whereas anti-&lt;italic&gt;T. cruzi&lt;/italic&gt; potency increased by ~5-fold, likely due to an increase in solubility/permeability of the analogs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473926" rel="alternate" title="Intramolecular interactions enhance the potency of gallinamide A analogs against Trypanosoma cruzi (8 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473529</id><title>Structural and biophysical characterization of HNF-1A as a tool to study MODY3 diabetes variants (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.381725+00:00</updated><author><name>Laura Kind</name></author><author><name>Arne Raasakka</name></author><author><name>Janne Molnes</name></author><author><name>Ingvild Aukrust</name></author><author><name>Lise Bjørkhaug</name></author><author><name>Pål Rasmus Njølstad</name></author><author><name>Petri Kursula</name></author><author><name>Thomas Arnesen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hepatocyte nuclear factor 1A (HNF-1A) is a transcription factor expressed in several embryonic and adult tissues, modulating expression of numerous target genes. Pathogenic variants in the &lt;italic&gt;HNF1A&lt;/italic&gt; gene cause maturity-onset diabetes of the young 3 (MODY3 or &lt;italic&gt;HNF1A&lt;/italic&gt; MODY), characterized by dominant inheritance, age of onset before 25-35 years of age, and pancreatic β-cell dysfunction. A precise diagnosis alters management as insulin can be exchanged with sulfonylurea tablets and genetic counselling differs from polygenic forms of diabetes. More knowledge on mechanisms of HNF-1A function and the level of pathogenicity of the numerous &lt;italic&gt;HNF1A&lt;/italic&gt; variants identified by exome sequencing is required for precise diagnostics. Here, we have structurally and biophysically characterized an HNF-1A protein containing both the DNA binding domain and the dimerization domain. We also present a novel approach to characterize HNF-1A variants. The folding and DNA binding capacity of two established MODY3 HNF-1A variant proteins (P112L, R263C) and one variant of unknown significance (N266S) were determined. All three variants showed reduced functionality compared to the wild-type protein. While the R263C and N266S variants displayed reduced binding to an HNF-1A target promoter, the P112L variant was unstable &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and in cells. Our results support and mechanistically explain disease causality for all investigated variants and allow for the dissection of structurally unstable and DNA binding defective variants. This points towards structural and biochemical investigation of HNF-1A being a valuable aid in reliable variant classification needed for precision diagnostics and management.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473529" rel="alternate" title="Structural and biophysical characterization of HNF-1A as a tool to study MODY3 diabetes variants (8 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473441</id><title>Glycolytic flux-signaling controls mouse embryo mesoderm development (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.381965+00:00</updated><author><name>Hidenobu Miyazawa</name></author><author><name>Marteinn T. Snaebjornsson</name></author><author><name>Nicole Prior</name></author><author><name>Eleni Kafkia</name></author><author><name>Henrik M Hammarén</name></author><author><name>Nobuko Tsuchida-Straeten</name></author><author><name>Kiran Raosaheb Patil</name></author><author><name>Martin Beck</name></author><author><name>Alexander Aulehla</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;How cellular metabolic state impacts cellular programs is a fundamental, unresolved question. Here we investigated how glycolytic flux impacts embryonic development, using presomitic mesoderm (PSM) patterning as the experimental model. First, we identified fructose 1,6-bisphosphate (FBP) as an in vivo sentinel metabolite that mirrors glycolytic flux within PSM cells of post-implantation mouse embryos. We found that medium-supplementation with FBP, but not with other glycolytic metabolites, such as fructose 6-phosphate and 3-phosphoglycerate, impaired mesoderm segmentation. To genetically manipulate glycolytic flux and FBP levels, we generated a mouse model enabling the conditional overexpression of dominant active, cytoplasmic Pfkfb3 (cytoPfkfb3).  Overexpression of cytoPfkfb3 indeed led to increased glycolytic flux/FBP levels and caused an impairment of mesoderm segmentation, paralleled by the downregulation of Wnt-signaling, reminiscent of the effects seen upon FBP-supplementation. To probe for mechanisms underlying glycolytic flux-signaling, we performed subcellular proteome analysis and revealed that cytoPfkfb3 overexpression altered subcellular localization of certain proteins, including glycolytic enzymes, in PSM cells. Specifically, we revealed that FBP supplementation caused depletion of Pfkl and Aldoa from the nuclear-soluble fraction. Combined, we propose that FBP functions as a flux-signaling metabolite connecting glycolysis and PSM patterning, potentially through modulating subcellular protein localization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473441" rel="alternate" title="Glycolytic flux-signaling controls mouse embryo mesoderm development (7 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.25.474160</id><title>Short OGA is targeted to the mitochondria and regulates mitochondrial reactive oxygen species level (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.382200+00:00</updated><author><name>Patrick Pagesy</name></author><author><name>Abdelouhab Bouaboud</name></author><author><name>Zhihao Feng</name></author><author><name>Philippe Hulin</name></author><author><name>Tarik Issad</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;O-GlcNAcylation is a reversible post-translational modification involved the regulation of cytosolic, nuclear and mitochondrial proteins. Only two enzymes, OGT and OGA, control attachment and removal of O-GlcNAc on proteins, respectively.  Whereas a variant OGT (mOGT) has been proposed as the main isoform that O-GlcNAcylates proteins in mitochondria, identification of a mitochondrial OGA has not been performed yet. Two splice variants of OGA (short and long isoforms) have been described previously. In this work, using cell fractionation experiments, we show that short-OGA is preferentially recovered in mitochondria-enriched fractions from HEK-293T cells as well as mouse embryonic fibroblasts. Moreover, fluorescent microscopy imaging confirmed that GFP-tagged short-OGA is addressed to mitochondria. In addition, using a BRET-based mitochondrial O-GlcNAcylation biosensor, we show that co-transfection of short-OGA markedly reduced O-GlcNAcylation of the biosensor, whereas long-OGA had no significant effect. Finally, using genetically encoded or chemical fluorescent mitochondrial probes, we showed that short-OGA overexpression increases mitochondrial ROS levels, whereas long-OGA had no significant effect. Together, our work reveals that the short-OGA isoform is targeted to the mitochondria where it regulates ROS homoeostasis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.25.474160" rel="alternate" title="Short OGA is targeted to the mitochondria and regulates mitochondrial reactive oxygen species level (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473674</id><title>Metabarcoding malaise trap plant components enables monitoring the diversity of plant-insect interactions (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.382461+00:00</updated><author><name>Stephanie J. Swenson</name></author><author><name>Lisa Eichler</name></author><author><name>Thomas Hörren</name></author><author><name>Gerlind U. C. Lehmann</name></author><author><name>Martin Sorg</name></author><author><name>Birgit Gemeinholzer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The declines observed in insect abundance and diversity in the past decades has also been observed in plants, and these events are most certainly correlated. Rapid largescale biomonitoring of both plants and insects can help monitor these changes and inform decisions for land management and species protection. Malaise traps have been used for nearly 80 years for passive insect sampling of primarily flying insects, and when they enter these traps, they carry the fragments of the plants they have visited, either as plant fragments and pollen on the body surface, or as digested food material in gut contents. DNA metabarcoding is a potential method to identify these plant traces in the ethanol of the malaise bottles, which is not possible with traditional microscopy. Metabarcoding could offer more insight into what plants insects are directly interacting with at a given time, and allow for the detection of rare plants, and neophyte species visited by insects. This study, to our knowledge, is the first examination of DNA metabarcoding plant traces from Malaise trap samples, we examine 105 samples from 21 sites throughout Germany collected in a 2-week period in May of 2020. Here we report on the feasibility of sequencing these sample types, analysis of the resulting taxa, the usage of cultivated plants by insects near nature conservancy areas, and the detection of rare and neophyte species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473674" rel="alternate" title="Metabarcoding malaise trap plant components enables monitoring the diversity of plant-insect interactions (6 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473985</id><title>Functional design of bacterial superoxide:quinone oxidoreductase (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.382676+00:00</updated><author><name>Christoph von Ballmoos</name></author><author><name>Abbas Abou-Hamdan</name></author><author><name>Roman Mahler</name></author><author><name>Philipp Grossenbacher</name></author><author><name>Olivier Biner</name></author><author><name>Dan Sjöstrand</name></author><author><name>Martin Lochner</name></author><author><name>Martin Högbom</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The superoxide anion - molecular oxygen reduced by a single electron - is produced in large amounts by enzymatic and adventitious reactions and can perform a range of cellular functions, including bacterial warfare and iron uptake, signalling and host immune response in eukaryotes. However, it also serves as precursor for more deleterious species such as the hydroxyl anion or peroxynitrite and therefore, cellular defense mechanisms for superoxide neutralization have evolved. In addition to the soluble proteins superoxide dismutase and superoxide reductase, recently the membrane embedded diheme cytochrome b561 (CybB) from E. coli has been proposed to act as a superoxide:quinone oxidoreductase. Here, we confirm superoxide and cellular ubiquinones or menaquinones as natural substrates and show that quinone binding to the enzyme accelerates the reaction with superoxide. The reactivity of the substrates is in accordance with the here determined midpoint potential of the two b hemes (+48 and -23 mV / NHE). Our data suggest that the enzyme can work near the diffusion limit in the forward direction and can also catalyse the reverse reaction efficiently under physiological conditions. The data is discussed in context of described cytochrome b561 proteins and potential physiological roles of CybB.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473985" rel="alternate" title="Functional design of bacterial superoxide:quinone oxidoreductase (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.25.472549</id><title>Mature Neurons sensitivity to oxidative stress is epigenetically programmed by alternative splicing and mRNA stability (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.382979+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhou Yuan</name></author><author><name>Sherif Rashad</name></author><author><name>Teiji Tominaga</name></author><author><name>Kuniyasu Niizuma</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neuronal differentiation is a complex process that entails extensive morphological, transcriptional, metabolic, and functional changes that dictate neuronal lineage commitment. Much less understood is the role that epigenetic and epi-transcriptional reprogramming plays in the process of neuronal differentiation and maturation. To depict the whole landscape of transcriptomics and epigenetic changes during neuronal differentiation and maturation, we differentiated SH-SY5Y cells and performed RNA sequencing on differentiated and undifferentiated cells. 728 differentially expressed genes (DEGs) enriched in synaptic signaling and cell morphogenesis pathways were observed. Moreover, transcriptome-wide mRNA stability profiling revealed that genes with altered stability were exceptionally enriched for redox homeostasis pathways. Mature neurons are known to be highly sensitive to oxidative stress, which is crucial in the pathophysiology of neurodegenerative disease. Our results suggest that this heightened sensitivity is regulated at the mRNA stability level (i.e., epigenetic) rather than at the transcriptional level. Alternative splicing analysis revealed the exon skipping and alternative mRNA isoforms enriched for morphogenesis related pathway. Alternatively, alternative 5 and 3 prime splicing site, intron retention and mutually exclusive exon events exclusively clustered in the translation and translation initiation pathways, suggesting the potential effect of alternative splicing on translation following neuronal maturation. Splice motif analysis revealed enriched motifs for RBPs that regulate various splice types and can be further correlated to distinct phenotypical changes during neuronal differentiation and maturation. Here we present an extensive exploration of the transcriptional and epigenetic changes and their potential association with the process of neuronal differentiation, providing a new insight into understanding the molecular mechanism of neuronal function and behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.25.472549" rel="alternate" title="Mature Neurons sensitivity to oxidative stress is epigenetically programmed by alternative splicing and mRNA stability (5 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473796</id><title>Experimental platform for the functional investigation of membrane proteins in giant unilamellar vesicles (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.383509+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicolas Dolder</name></author><author><name>Philipp Mueller</name></author><author><name>Christoph von Ballmoos</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Giant unilamellar vesicles (GUVs) are micrometer-sized model membrane systems that can be viewed directly under the microscope. They serve as scaffolds for the bottom-up creation of synthetic cells, targeted drug delivery and have been used in many in vitro studies of membrane related phenomena. GUVs are also of interest for the functional investigation of membrane proteins that carry out many key cellular functions. A major hurdle to a wider application of GUVs in this field is the diversity of existing protocols that are optimized for individual proteins. Here, we compare PVA assisted and electroformation techniques for GUV formation under physiologically relevant conditions, and analyze the effect of immobilization on vesicle structure and membrane tightness towards small substrates and protons. There, differences in terms of yield, size, and leakage of GUVs produced by PVA assisted swelling and electroformation were found, dependent on salt and buffer composition. Using fusion of oppositely charged membranes to reconstitute a model membrane protein, we find that empty vesicles and proteoliposomes show similar fusion behavior, which allows for a rapid estimation of protein incorporation using fluorescent lipids.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473796" rel="alternate" title="Experimental platform for the functional investigation of membrane proteins in giant unilamellar vesicles (5 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473788</id><title>Glycan engineering using synthetic ManNAc analogues enhances sialyl-Lewis-X expression and adhesion of leukocytes (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.383897+00:00</updated><author><name>Anam Tasneem</name></author><author><name>Shubham Parashar</name></author><author><name>Tanya Jain</name></author><author><name>Simran Aittan</name></author><author><name>Jyoti Rautela</name></author><author><name>Kaisar Raza</name></author><author><name>Srinivasa-Gopalan Sampathkumar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cell surface glycans, depending on their structures and dynamic modifications, act as the first point of contact and regulate cell-cell, cell-matrix, and cell-pathogen interactions. Particularly, the sialyl-Lewis-X (sLeX, CD15s) tetrasaccharide epitope, expressed on both gangliosides and glycoproteins, participates in leukocyte extravasation &lt;italic&gt;via&lt;/italic&gt; interactions with selectins expressed on endothelial cells, lymphocytes, and platelets (CD62-E/L/P). Neutrophils carrying sLeX epitopes are thought to be responsible for chronic inflammatory diseases resulting in plaque formation and atherosclerosis. Intense efforts have been devoted to the development of sLeX mimetics for inhibition of cell adhesion. On the other hand, dysregulated expression of sLeX and poor extravasation are the major underlying causes of leukocyte adhesion deficiency-II (LAD-II) disorders that result in frequent infections and poor immune response. We hypothesized that metabolic processing of peracetyl &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;-(cycloalkyl)acyl-D-mannosamine derivatives, through the sialic acid pathway, might result in the expression of sialoglycans with altered hydrophobicity which in-turn could modulate their binding to endogenous lectins, including selectins. Herein, we show that treatment of HL-60 (human acute myeloid leukemia) cells with peracetyl &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;-cyclobutanoyl-D-mannosamine (Ac&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;ManNCb), at 50 microM for 48 h, resulted in a robust three to four fold increase in the binding of anti-sLeX (CSLEX1) antibody and enhanced cell adhesion to E-selectin coated surfaces; while the corresponding straight-chain analogue, peracetyl &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;-pentanoyl-D-mannosamine (Ac&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;ManNPent), and peracetyl &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;-cyclopropanoyl-D-mannosamine (Ac&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;ManNCp) both resulted in ∼2.5-fold increase compared to controls. The ability to enhance sLeX expression using small molecules has the potential to provide novel opportunities to address challenges in the treatment of immune deficiency disorders.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473788" rel="alternate" title="Glycan engineering using synthetic ManNAc analogues enhances sialyl-Lewis-X expression and adhesion of leukocytes (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.18.473301</id><title>Integrated Proteomic and Metabolomic Analyses of the Mitochondrial Neurodegenerative Disease MELAS (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.384345+00:00</updated><author><name>Haorong Li</name></author><author><name>Martine Uittenbogaard</name></author><author><name>Ryan Navarro</name></author><author><name>Mustafa Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Andrea Gropman</name></author><author><name>Anne Chiaramello</name></author><author><name>Ling Hao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;MELAS (mitochondrial encephalomyopathy, lactic acidosis, stroke-like episodes) is a progressive neurodegenerative disease caused by pathogenic mitochondrial DNA variants. The pathogenic mechanism of MELAS remains enigmatic due to the exceptional clinical heterogeneity and the obscure genotype-phenotype correlation among MELAS patients. To gain insights into the pathogenic signature of MELAS, we designed a comprehensive strategy integrating proteomics and metabolomics in patient-derived dermal fibroblasts harboring the ultra-rare MELAS pathogenic variant m.14453G&amp;gt;A, specifically affecting the mitochondrial respiratory Complex I. Global proteomics was achieved by data-dependent acquisition (DDA) and verified by data-independent acquisition (DIA) using both Spectronaut and the recently launched MaxDIA platforms. Comprehensive metabolite coverage was achieved for both polar and nonpolar metabolites in both reverse phase and HILIC LC-MS/MS analyses. Our proof-of-principle MELAS study with multi-omics integration revealed OXPHOS dysregulation with a predominant deficiency of Complex I subunits, as well as alterations in key bioenergetic pathways, glycolysis, tricarboxylic acid cycle, and fatty acid β-oxidation. The most clinically relevant discovery is the downregulation of the arginine biosynthesis pathway, likely due to blocked argininosuccinate synthase, which is congruent with the MELAS cardinal symptom of stroke-like episodes and its current treatment by arginine infusion. In conclusion, we demonstrated an integrated proteomic and metabolomic strategy for patient-derived fibroblasts, which has great clinical potential to discover therapeutic targets and design personalized interventions after validation with a larger patient cohort in the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract Figure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;caption&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphic Abstract:&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Integrated proteomics and metabolomics of patient fibroblasts revealed dysregulations in arginine biosynthesis, OXPHOS complexes, and bioenergetic pathways in MELAS, a mitochondrial neurodegenerative disease caused by mitochondrial DNA mutations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/caption&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="473301v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.18.473301" rel="alternate" title="Integrated Proteomic and Metabolomic Analyses of the Mitochondrial Neurodegenerative Disease MELAS (4 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473597</id><title>Multi-layered networks of SalmoNet2 enable strain comparisons of the Salmonella genus on a molecular level (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.384977+00:00</updated><author><name>Marton Laszlo Olbei</name></author><author><name>Balazs Bohar</name></author><author><name>David Fazekas</name></author><author><name>Matthew Madgwick</name></author><author><name>Padhmanand Sudhakar</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Hautefort</name></author><author><name>Aline Métris</name></author><author><name>Jozsef Baranyi</name></author><author><name>Robert A Kingsley</name></author><author><name>Tamas Korcsmaros</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Serovars of the genus &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; primarily evolved as gastrointestinal pathogens in a wide range of hosts. Some serotypes later evolved further, adopting a more invasive lifestyle in a narrower host range associated with systemic infections. A system-level knowledge of these pathogens has the potential to identify the complex adaptations associated with the evolution of serovars with distinct pathogenicity, host range and risk to human health. This promises to aid the design of interventions and serve as a knowledge base in the &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; research community. Here we present SalmoNet2, a major update to SalmoNet, the first multi-layered interaction resource for &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; strains, containing protein-protein, transcriptional regulatory and enzyme-enzyme interactions. The new version extends the number of &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; genomes from 11 to 20, including strains such as &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; Typhimurium D23580, an epidemic multidrug-resistant strain leading to invasive non-typhoidal &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; Disease (iNTS), and a strain from &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella bongori&lt;/italic&gt;, another species in the &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; genus. The database now uses strain specific metabolic models instead of a generalised model to highlight differences between strains. This has increased the coverage of high-quality protein-protein interactions, and enhances interoperability with other computational resources by adopting standardised formats. The resource website has been updated with tutorials to help researchers analyse their &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella&lt;/italic&gt; data using molecular interaction networks from SalmoNet2. SalmoNet2 is accessible at http://salmonet.org/.&amp;lt;/SPAN&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473597" rel="alternate" title="Multi-layered networks of SalmoNet2 enable strain comparisons of the Salmonella genus on a molecular level (4 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473142</id><title>Control-based continuation: a new approach to prototype synthetic gene networks (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.385511+00:00</updated><author><name>Irene de Cesare</name></author><author><name>Davide Salzano</name></author><author><name>Mario di Bernardo</name></author><author><name>Ludovic Renson</name></author><author><name>Lucia Marucci</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Control-Based Continuation (CBC) is a general and systematic method to carry out the bifurcation analysis of physical experiments. CBC does not rely on a mathematical model and thus overcomes the uncertainty introduced when identifying bifurcation curves indirectly through modelling and parameter estimation. We demonstrate, &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt;, CBC applicability to biochemical processes by tracking the equilibrium curve of a toggle switch which includes additive process noise and exhibits bistability. We compare results obtained when CBC uses a model-free and model-based control strategy and show that both can track stable and unstable solutions, revealing bistability. We then demonstrate CBC in conditions more representative of a real experiment using an agent-based simulator describing cells growth and division, cell-to-cell variability, spatial distribution, and diffusion of chemicals. We further show how the identified curves can be used for parameter estimation and discuss how CBC can significantly accelerate the prototyping of synthetic gene regulatory networks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473142" rel="alternate" title="Control-based continuation: a new approach to prototype synthetic gene networks (4 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473137</id><title>An Agent-Based Model of monocyte differentiation into Tumour-Associated Macrophages in Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.386038+00:00</updated><author><name>Nina Verstraete</name></author><author><name>Malvina Marku</name></author><author><name>Marcin Domagala</name></author><author><name>Julie Bordenave</name></author><author><name>Hélène Arduin</name></author><author><name>Jean-Jacques Fournié</name></author><author><name>Loïc Ysebaert</name></author><author><name>Mary Poupot</name></author><author><name>Vera Pancaldi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Monocyte-derived macrophages are immune cells which help maintain tissue homeostasis and defend the organism against pathogens. In solid tumours, recent studies have uncovered complex macrophage populations, among which tumour-associated macrophages, supporting tumorigenesis through multiple cancer hallmarks such as immunosuppression, angiogenesis or matrix remodelling. In the case of chronic lymphocytic leukemia, these macrophages are known as nurse-like cells and have been shown to protect leukemic cells from spontaneous apoptosis and contribute to their chemoresistance. We propose an agent-based model of monocytes differentiation into nurse-like cells upon contact with leukemic B cells in-vitro. We studied monocyte differentiation and cancer cells survival dynamics depending on diverse hypotheses on monocytes and cancer cells relative proportions, sensitivity to their surrounding environment and cell-cell interactions. Peripheral blood mononuclear cells from patients were cultured and monitored during 13 days to calibrate the model parameters, such as phagocytosis efficiency, death rates or protective effect from the nurse-like cells. Our model is able to reproduce experimental results and predict cancer cells survival dynamics in a patient-specific manner. Our results shed light on important factors at play in cancer cells survival, highlighting a potentially important role of phagocytosis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473137" rel="alternate" title="An Agent-Based Model of monocyte differentiation into Tumour-Associated Macrophages in Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (4 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473177</id><title>Rapid profiling of protein complex re-organization in perturbed systems (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.386707+00:00</updated><author><name>Isabell Bludau</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Nicod</name></author><author><name>Claudia Martelli</name></author><author><name>Peng Xue</name></author><author><name>Moritz Heusel</name></author><author><name>Andrea Fossati</name></author><author><name>Federico Uliana</name></author><author><name>Fabian Frommelt</name></author><author><name>Ruedi Aebersold</name></author><author><name>Ben C. Collins</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protein complexes constitute the primary functional modules of cellular activity. To respond to perturbations, complexes undergo changes in their abundance, subunit composition or state of modification. Understanding the function of biological systems requires global strategies to capture this contextual state information on protein complexes and interaction networks. Methods based on co-fractionation paired with mass spectrometry have demonstrated the capability for deep biological insight but the scope of studies using this approach has been limited by the large measurement time per biological sample and challenges with data analysis. As such, there has been little uptake of this strategy beyond a few expert labs into the broader life science community despite rich biological information content. We present a rapid integrated experimental and computational workflow to assess the re-organization of protein complexes across multiple cellular states. It enables complex experimental designs requiring increased sample/condition numbers. The workflow combines short gradient chromatography and DIA/SWATH mass spectrometry with a data analysis toolset to quantify changes in complex organization. We applied the workflow to study the global protein complex rearrangements of THP-1 cells undergoing monocyte to macrophage differentiation and a subsequent stimulation of macrophage cells with lipopolysaccharide. We observed massive proteome organization in functions related to signaling, cell adhesion, and extracellular matrix during differentiation, and less pronounced changes in processes related to innate immune response induced by the macrophage stimulation. We therefore establish our integrated differential pipeline for rapid and state-specific profiling of protein complex organization with broad utility in complex experimental designs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473177" rel="alternate" title="Rapid profiling of protein complex re-organization in perturbed systems (4 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473506</id><title>Extracellular Matrix protein gelatin provides higher expansion, reduces size heterogeneity, and maintains cell stiffness in a long-term culture of mesenchymal stem cells (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.387483+00:00</updated><author><name>Pankaj Mogha</name></author><author><name>Shruti Iyer</name></author><author><name>Abhijit Majumder</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Extracellular matrices (ECM) present in our tissues play a significant role in maintaining tissue homeostasis through various physical and chemical cues such as topology, stiffness, and secretion of biochemicals. They are known to influence the behaviour of resident stem cells. It is also known that ECM type and coating density on cell culture plates strongly influence &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; cellular behaviour. However, the influence of ECM protein coating on long term mesenchymal stem cell expansion has not been studied yet. To address this gap, we cultured bone-marrow derived hMSCs for multiple passages on the tissue culture plastic plates coated with 25 μg/ml of various ECM proteins. We found that cells on plates coated with ECM proteins had much higher proliferation compared to the regular tissue culture plates. Further, gelatin coated plates helped the cells to grow faster compared to collagen, fibronectin, and laminin coated plates. Additionally, the use of Gelatin showed less size heterogeneity among the cells when expanded from passages P3 to P9. Gelatin also helped in maintaining cellular stiffness which was not observed across other ECM proteins. In summary, in this research, we have shown that gelatin which is the least expensive compared to other ECM proteins provides a better platform for mesenchymal stem cell expansion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473506" rel="alternate" title="Extracellular Matrix protein gelatin provides higher expansion, reduces size heterogeneity, and maintains cell stiffness in a long-term culture of mesenchymal stem cells (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473891</id><title>The human RNA polymerase I structure reveals an HMG-like transcription factor docking domain specific to metazoans (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.387832+00:00</updated><author><name>Julia L. Daiß</name></author><author><name>Michael Pilsl</name></author><author><name>Kristina Straub</name></author><author><name>Andrea Bleckmann</name></author><author><name>Mona Höcherl</name></author><author><name>Florian B. Heiss</name></author><author><name>Guillermo Abascal-Palacios</name></author><author><name>Ewan Ramsay</name></author><author><name>Katarina Tlučková</name></author><author><name>Jean-Clement Mars</name></author><author><name>Astrid Bruckmann</name></author><author><name>Carrie Bernecky</name></author><author><name>Valérie Lamour</name></author><author><name>Konstantin Panov</name></author><author><name>Alessandro Vannini</name></author><author><name>Tom Moss</name></author><author><name>Christoph Engel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Transcription of the ribosomal RNA precursor by RNA polymerase (Pol) I is a major determinant of cellular growth and dysregulation is observed in many cancer types. Here, we present the purification of human Pol I from cells carrying a genomic GFP-fusion on the largest subunit allowing the structural and functional analysis of the enzyme across species. In contrast to yeast, human Pol I carries a single-subunit stalk and &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; transcription indicates a reduced proofreading activity. Determination of the human Pol I cryo-EM reconstruction in a close-to-native state rationalizes the effects of disease-associated mutations and uncovers an additional domain that is built into the sequence of Pol I subunit RPA1. This ‘dock II’ domain resembles a truncated HMG-box incapable of DNA-binding which may serve as a downstream-transcription factor binding platform in metazoans. Biochemical analysis and ChIP data indicate that Topoisomerase 2a can be recruited to Pol I via the domain and cooperates with the HMG-box domain containing factor UBF. These adaptations of the metazoan Pol I transcription system may allow efficient release of positive DNA supercoils accumulating downstream of the transcription bubble.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473891" rel="alternate" title="The human RNA polymerase I structure reveals an HMG-like transcription factor docking domain specific to metazoans (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.471999</id><title>Single cell RNA-seq identifies developing corneal cell fates in the human cornea organoid (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.388200+00:00</updated><author><name>George Maiti</name></author><author><name>Maithe Rocha Monteiro de Barros</name></author><author><name>Nan Hu</name></author><author><name>Mona Roshan</name></author><author><name>Karl J Wahlin</name></author><author><name>Shukti Chakravarti</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The cornea is a protective and refractive barrier in the eye crucial for vision. Understanding the human cornea in health, disease and cell-based treatments can be greatly advanced with cornea organoids developed in culture from induced pluripotent stem cells. While a limited number of studies have investigated the single-cell transcriptomic composition of the human cornea, its organoids have not been examined similarly.  Here we elucidated the transcriptomic cell fate map of 4 month-old human cornea organoids and the central cornea from three donors. The organoids harbor cell clusters representing corneal epithelium, stroma and endothelium with sub populations that capture signatures of early developmental states. Unlike the adult cornea where the largest cell population is stromal, the organoids develop almost equal proportion of the three major cell types. These corneal organoids offer a three-dimensional platform to model corneal diseases and integrated responses of the different cell types to treatments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.471999" rel="alternate" title="Single cell RNA-seq identifies developing corneal cell fates in the human cornea organoid (3 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473848</id><title>Limited, but potentially functional translation of non-coding transcripts in the HEK293T cellular cytosol (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.388529+00:00</updated><author><name>Annelies Bogaert</name></author><author><name>Daria Fijalkowska</name></author><author><name>An Staes</name></author><author><name>Tessa Van de Steene</name></author><author><name>Hans Demol</name></author><author><name>Kris Gevaert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ribosome profiling has revealed translation outside of canonical coding sequences (CDSs) including translation of short upstream ORFs, long non-coding RNAs, overlapping ORFs, ORFs in UTRs or ORFs in alternative reading frames. Studies combining mass spectrometry, ribosome profiling and CRISPR-based screens showed that hundreds of ORFs derived from non-coding transcripts produce (micro)proteins, while other studies failed to find evidence for such types of non-canonical translation products. Here, we attempted to discover translation products from non-coding regions by strongly reducing the complexity of the sample prior to mass spectrometric analysis. We used an extended database as the search space and applied stringent filtering of the identified peptides to find evidence for novel translation events. Theoretically, we show that our strategy facilitates the detection of translation events of transcripts from non-coding regions, but experimentally only find 19 peptides (less than 1% of all identified peptides) that might originate from such translation events. Virotrap based interactome analysis of two N-terminal proteoforms originating from non-coding regions finally showed the functional potential of these novel proteins.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473848" rel="alternate" title="Limited, but potentially functional translation of non-coding transcripts in the HEK293T cellular cytosol (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473703</id><title>SHOT-R: A next generation algorithm for particle kinematics analysis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.389225+00:00</updated><author><name>Eloina Corradi</name></author><author><name>Walter Boscheri</name></author><author><name>Marie-Laure Baudet</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Analysis of live-imaging experiments is crucial to decipher a plethora of cellular mechanisms within physiological and pathological contexts. Kymograph, i.e. graphical representations of particle spatial position over time, and single particle tracking (SPT) are the currently available tools to extract information on particle transport and velocity. However, the spatiotemporal approximation applied in particle trajectory reconstruction with those methods intrinsically prevents an accurate analysis of particle kinematics and of instantaneous behaviours. Here, we present SHOT-R, a novel numerical method based on polynomial reconstruction of 4D (3D+time) particle trajectories. SHOT-R, contrary to other tools, computes &lt;italic&gt;bona fide&lt;/italic&gt; instantaneous and directional velocity, and acceleration. Thanks to its high order continuous reconstruction it allows, for the first time, kinematics analysis of co-trafficked particles. Overall, SHOT-R is a novel, versatile, and physically reliable numerical method that achieves all-encompassing particle kinematics studies at unprecedented accuracy on any live-imaging experiment where the spatiotemporal coordinates can be retrieved.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473703" rel="alternate" title="SHOT-R: A next generation algorithm for particle kinematics analysis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473744</id><title>A vascularized 3D model of the human pancreatic islet for ex vivo study of immune cell-islet interaction (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.389827+00:00</updated><author><name>R. Hugh F. Bender</name></author><author><name>Benjamen T O'Donnell</name></author><author><name>Bhupinder Shergill</name></author><author><name>Brittany Q Pham</name></author><author><name>Damie J Juat</name></author><author><name>Michaela S Hatch</name></author><author><name>Venktesh S Shirure</name></author><author><name>Matthew Wortham</name></author><author><name>Kim-Vy Nguyen-Ngoc</name></author><author><name>Yesl Jun</name></author><author><name>Roberto Gaetani</name></author><author><name>Karen L Christman</name></author><author><name>Luc Teyton</name></author><author><name>Steven C George</name></author><author><name>Maike Sander</name></author><author><name>Christopher C Hughes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Insulin is an essential regulator of blood glucose homeostasis that is produced exclusively by β cells within the pancreatic islets of healthy individuals. In those affected by diabetes, immune inflammation, damage, and destruction of islet β cells leads to insulin deficiency and hyperglycemia. Current efforts to understand the mechanisms underlying β cell damage in diabetes rely on in vitro-cultured cadaveric islets. However, isolation of these islets involves removal of crucial matrix and vasculature that supports islets in the intact pancreas. Unsurprisingly, these islets demonstrate reduced functionality over time in standard culture conditions, thereby limiting their value for understanding native islet biology. Leveraging a novel, vascularized micro-organ (VMO) approach, we have recapitulated elements of the native pancreas by incorporating isolated human islets within a three-dimensional matrix nourished by living, perfusable blood vessels. Importantly, these islets show long-term viability and maintain robust glucose-stimulated insulin responses. Furthermore, vessel-mediated delivery of immune cells to these tissues provides a model to assess islet-immune cell interactions and subsequent islet killing -- key steps in type 1 diabetes pathogenesis. Together, these results establish the islet-VMO as a novel, ex vivo platform for studying human islet biology in both health and disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473744" rel="alternate" title="A vascularized 3D model of the human pancreatic islet for ex vivo study of immune cell-islet interaction (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473881</id><title>Myopathy mutations in DNAJB6 slow conformer specific substrate processing that is corrected by NEF modulation (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.390500+00:00</updated><author><name>Ankan K. Bhadra</name></author><author><name>Michael J. Rau</name></author><author><name>Jil A. Daw</name></author><author><name>James A.J. Fitzpatrick</name></author><author><name>Conrad C. Weihl</name></author><author><name>Heather L. True</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Molecular chaperones, or heat shock proteins (HSPs), protect against the toxic misfolding and aggregation of proteins. As such, mutations or deficiencies within the chaperone network can lead to disease. In fact, dominant mutations in DNAJB6 (Hsp40/Sis1), an Hsp70 co-chaperone, leads to a protein aggregate myopathy termed Limb-Girdle Muscular Dystrophy Type D1 (LGMDD1). DNAJB6 client proteins and co-chaperone interactions in skeletal muscle are not known. Here, we used the yeast prion model client in conjunction with &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; chaperone activity assays to gain mechanistic insights, and found that LGMDD1 mutants affect Hsp40 functions. Strikingly, the mutants changed the structure of client protein aggregates, as determined by altered distribution of prion strains. They also impair the Hsp70 ATPase cycle, dimerization, and substrate processing and consequently poison the function of wild-type protein. These results define the mechanisms by which LGMDD1 mutations alter chaperone activity and provide avenues for therapeutic intervention.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473881" rel="alternate" title="Myopathy mutations in DNAJB6 slow conformer specific substrate processing that is corrected by NEF modulation (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473903</id><title>Biological regulatory networks are less nonlinear than expected by chance (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.391200+00:00</updated><author><name>Santosh Manicka</name></author><author><name>Kathleen Johnson</name></author><author><name>David Murrugarra</name></author><author><name>Michael Levin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nonlinearity is a characteristic of complex biological regulatory networks that has implications ranging from therapy to control. To better understand its nature, we analyzed a suite of published Boolean network models, containing a variety of complex nonlinear interactions, with an approach involving a probabilistic generalization of Boolean logic that George Boole himself had proposed. Leveraging the continuous-nature of this formulation using Taylor-decomposition methods revealed the distinct layers of nonlinearity of the models. A comparison of the resulting series of model approximations with the corresponding sets of randomized ensembles furthermore revealed that the biological networks are relatively more linearly approximable. We hypothesize that this is a result of optimization by natural selection for the purpose of controllability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473903" rel="alternate" title="Biological regulatory networks are less nonlinear than expected by chance (3 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>