<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-09T06:15:39.386702+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.05.455304</id><title>Structure of PINK1 reveals autophosphorylation dimer and provides insights into binding to the TOM complex (48 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-09T06:15:39.387320+00:00</updated><author><name>Shafqat Rasool</name></author><author><name>Simon Veyron</name></author><author><name>Naoto Soya</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Eldeeb</name></author><author><name>Gergely L. Lukacs</name></author><author><name>Edward A. Fon</name></author><author><name>Jean-François Trempe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mutations in PINK1 causes autosomal-recessive Parkinson’s disease. Mitochondrial damage results in PINK1 import arrest on the Translocase of the Outer Mitochondrial Membrane (TOM) complex, resulting in the activation of its ubiquitin kinase activity by autophosphorylation and initiation of Parkin-dependent mitochondrial clearance. Herein we report crystal structures of the entire cytosolic domain of insect PINK1. Our structures reveal a dimeric autophosphorylation complex targeting phosphorylation at the invariant Ser205 (human Ser228). The dimer interface requires insert 2, which is unique to PINK1. The structures also reveal how an N-terminal helix binds to the C-terminal extension and provide insights into stabilization of PINK1 on the core TOM complex.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.05.455304" rel="alternate" title="Structure of PINK1 reveals autophosphorylation dimer and provides insights into binding to the TOM complex (48 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.06.455369</id><title>Microtubule rescue at midzone edges promotes overlap stability and prevents spindle collapse during anaphase B (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-09T06:15:39.388030+00:00</updated><author><name>Manuel Lera-Ramirez</name></author><author><name>Francois Nedelec</name></author><author><name>Phong T Tran</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During anaphase B, molecular motors slide interpolar microtubules to elongate the mitotic spindle, contributing to the separation of chromosomes. However, sliding of antiparallel microtubules reduces their overlap, which may lead to spindle breakage, unless microtubules grow to compensate sliding. How sliding and growth are coordinated is still poorly understood. In this study, we have used the fission yeast &lt;italic&gt;S. pombe&lt;/italic&gt; to measure microtubule dynamics during anaphase B. We report that the coordination of microtubule growth and sliding relies on promoting rescues at the midzone edges. This makes microtubules stable from pole to midzone, while their distal parts including the plus ends alternate between assembly and disassembly. Consequently, the midzone keeps a constant length throughout anaphase, enabling sustained sliding without the need for a precise regulation of microtubule growth speed. Additionally, we found that in &lt;italic&gt;S. pombe&lt;/italic&gt;, which undergoes closed mitosis, microtubule growth speed decreases when the nuclear membrane wraps around the spindle midzone.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.06.455369" rel="alternate" title="Microtubule rescue at midzone edges promotes overlap stability and prevents spindle collapse during anaphase B (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.05.455211</id><title>Constructing a warhead of PROTAC with aptamer for tumor-selective degradation of nucleolin (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-09T06:15:39.388468+00:00</updated><author><name>Lin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Ling Li</name></author><author><name>Xia Wang</name></author><author><name>Jing Dai</name></author><author><name>Linglli Zhou</name></author><author><name>Yibin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Tiantian Xie</name></author><author><name>Hui Zhang</name></author><author><name>Tianhuan Peng</name></author><author><name>Xing Sun</name></author><author><name>Hui Li</name></author><author><name>Jing Liu</name></author><author><name>Wencan Wu</name></author><author><name>Mao Ye</name></author><author><name>Weihong Tan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;PROteolysis TArgeting Chimeras (PROTACs) induce targeted protein degradation by hijacking the intracellular ubiquitin proteasome system, thus emerging as a new strategy for drug development. However, although PROTACs are highly efficient for protein degradation, most PROTACs generated lack cell-type selectivity, resulting in potential off-tissue, on-target toxicity. To address this drawback, we herein developed an aptamer-based PROTAC ZL216 using aptamer AS1411 as a targeting ligand for nucleolin, and it showed both excellent serum stability and water solubility. Based on the differential expression of nucleolin on the cell surface, ZL216 can specifically bind to and internalize into breast cancer cells, but not normal breast cells. Furthermore, we revealed that ZL216 promoted the formation of a nucleolin-ZL216-VHL ternary complex in breast cancer cells and potently induced the degradation of nucleolin in vitro and in vivo, thereby inhibiting the proliferation and migration of breast cancer cells. These studies demonstrated the potential of utilizing aptamers to construct PROTACs to achieve the selective degradation of targeted protein in tumor cells and provided a promising strategy for the development of tumor-selective PROTACs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.05.455211" rel="alternate" title="Constructing a warhead of PROTAC with aptamer for tumor-selective degradation of nucleolin (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>