<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.422806+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471393</id><title>SAVED by a toxin: Structure and function of the CRISPR Lon protease (50 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.423101+00:00</updated><author><name>Christophe Rouillon</name></author><author><name>Niels Schneberger</name></author><author><name>Haotian Chi</name></author><author><name>Martin F. Peter</name></author><author><name>Matthias Geyer</name></author><author><name>Wolfgang Boenigk</name></author><author><name>Reinhard Seifert</name></author><author><name>Malcolm F. White</name></author><author><name>Gregor Hagelueken</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;CRISPR antiviral defense systems such as the well-known DNA-targeting Cas9- and the more complex RNA-targeting type III systems are widespread in bacteria and archea &lt;sup&gt;1, 2&lt;/sup&gt;. The type III systems can orchestrate a complex antiviral response that is initiated by the synthesis of cyclic oligoadenylates (cOAs) upon foreign RNA recognition &lt;sup&gt;3–5&lt;/sup&gt;. These second messenger molecules bind to the CARF (CRISPR associated Rossmann-fold) domains of dedicated effector proteins that are often DNAses, RNAses, or putative transcription factors &lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;. The activated effectors interfere with cellular pathways of the host, inducing cell death or a dormant state of the cell that is better suited to avoid propagation of the viral attack &lt;sup&gt;7, 8&lt;/sup&gt;. Among a large set of proteins that were predicted to be linked to the type III systems &lt;sup&gt;9, 10&lt;/sup&gt;, the CRISPR-Lon protein caught our attention. The protein was predicted to be an integral membrane protein containing a SAVED-instead of a CARF-domain as well as a Lon protease effector domain. Here, we report the crystal structure of CRISPR-Lon. The protein is a soluble monomer and indeed contains a SAVED domain that accommodates cA&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;. Further, we show that CRISPR-Lon forms a stable complex with the 34 kDa CRISPR-T protein. Upon activation by cA&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;, CRISPR-Lon specifically cleaves CRISRP-T, releasing CRISPR-T&lt;sub&gt;23&lt;/sub&gt;, a 23 kDa fragment that is structurally very similar to MazF toxins and is likely a sequence specific nuclease. Our results describe the first cOA activated proteolytic enzyme and provide the first example of a SAVED domain connected to a type III CRISPR defense system. The use of a protease as a means to unleash a fast response against a threat has intriguing parallels to eukaryotic innate immunity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471393" rel="alternate" title="SAVED by a toxin: Structure and function of the CRISPR Lon protease (50 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471413</id><title>FPCountR: Absolute quantification of fluorescent proteins for synthetic biology (45 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.423646+00:00</updated><author><name>Eszter Csibra</name></author><author><name>Guy-Bart Stan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This paper presents a generalisable method for the calibration of fluorescence readings on microplate readers, in order to convert arbitrary fluorescence units into absolute units. FPCountR relies on the generation of bespoke fluorescent protein (FP) calibrants, assays to determine protein concentration and activity, and a corresponding analytical workflow. We systematically characterise the assay protocols for accuracy, sensitivity and simplicity, and describe a novel ‘ECmax’ assay that outperforms the others and even enables accurate calibration without requiring the purification of FPs. To obtain cellular protein concentrations, we consider methods for the conversion of optical density to either cell counts or alternatively to cell volumes, as well as examining how cells can interfere with protein counting via fluorescence quenching, which we quantify and correct for the first time. Calibration across different instruments, disparate filter sets and mismatched gains is demonstrated to yield equivalent results. It can also reveal that mCherry absorption at 600nm does not confound cell density measurements unless expressed to over 100,000 proteins per cell. FPCountR is presented as pair of open access tools (protocol and R package) to enable the community to use this method, and ultimately to facilitate the quantitative characterisation of synthetic microbial circuits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471413" rel="alternate" title="FPCountR: Absolute quantification of fluorescent proteins for synthetic biology (45 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471942</id><title>A genetic disorder reveals a hematopoietic stem cell regulatory network co-opted in leukemia (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.425620+00:00</updated><author><name>Richard A. Voit</name></author><author><name>Liming Tao</name></author><author><name>Fulong Yu</name></author><author><name>Liam D. Cato</name></author><author><name>Blake Cohen</name></author><author><name>Xiaotian Liao</name></author><author><name>Claudia Fiorini</name></author><author><name>Satish K. Nandakumar</name></author><author><name>Lara Wahlster</name></author><author><name>Kristian Teichert</name></author><author><name>Aviv Regev</name></author><author><name>Vijay G. Sankaran</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The molecular regulation of human hematopoietic stem cell (HSC) self-renewal is therapeutically important, but limitations in experimental systems and interspecies variation have constrained our knowledge of this process. Here, we have studied a rare genetic disorder due to &lt;italic&gt;MECOM&lt;/italic&gt; haploinsufficiency, characterized by an early-onset absence of HSCs &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. By generating a faithful model of this disorder in primary human HSCs and coupling functional studies with integrative single-cell genomic analyses, we uncover a key transcriptional network involving hundreds of genes that is required for HSC self-renewal. Through our analyses, we nominate cooperating transcriptional regulators and identify how MECOM prevents the CTCF-dependent genome reorganization that occurs as HSCs exit quiescence. Strikingly, we show that this transcriptional network is co-opted in high-risk leukemias, thereby enabling these cancers to acquire stem cell properties. Collectively, we illuminate a regulatory network necessary for HSC self-renewal through the study of a rare experiment of nature.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471942" rel="alternate" title="A genetic disorder reveals a hematopoietic stem cell regulatory network co-opted in leukemia (26 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471303</id><title>Subcellular spatial transcriptomics identifies three mechanistically different classes of localizing RNAs (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.426928+00:00</updated><author><name>Lucia Cassella</name></author><author><name>Anne Ephrussi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Intracellular RNA localization is a widespread and dynamic phenomenon that compartmentalizes gene expression and contributes to the functional polarization of cells. Thus far, mechanisms of RNA localization identified in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; have been based on a few RNAs in different tissues, and a comprehensive mechanistic analysis of RNA localization in a single tissue is lacking. Here, by subcellular spatial transcriptomics we identify RNAs localized in the apical and basal domains of the columnar follicular epithelium (FE) and we analyze the mechanisms mediating their localization. Whereas the dynein/BicD/Egl machinery controls apical RNA localization, basally-targeted RNAs require kinesin-1 to overcome a “default” dynein-mediated transport. Moreover, a non-canonical, translation- and dynein-dependent mechanism mediates apical localization of a subgroup of dynein-activating adaptor RNAs (&lt;italic&gt;BicD&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;Bsg25D&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;hook&lt;/italic&gt;). Altogether, our study identifies at least three mechanisms underlying RNA localization in the FE, and suggests a possible link between RNA localization and dynein/dynactin/adaptor complex formation &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471303" rel="alternate" title="Subcellular spatial transcriptomics identifies three mechanistically different classes of localizing RNAs (16 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471598</id><title>Stem cell specific interferon stimulated gene expression is regulated by the formative pluripotency network through IRF1 (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.427128+00:00</updated><author><name>Merrit Romeike</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Spach</name></author><author><name>Marie Huber</name></author><author><name>Songjie Feng</name></author><author><name>Gintautas Vainorius</name></author><author><name>Ulrich Elling</name></author><author><name>Christa Buecker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Stem cells intrinsically express a subset of genes which are normally associated with interferon stimulation, and thus the innate immunity response. Expression of these interferon stimulated genes (ISG) in stem cells is independent of external stimuli such as viral infection. Here we show that the interferon regulatory factor 1, &lt;italic&gt;Irf1&lt;/italic&gt;, is directly controlled by the murine formative pluripotency gene regulatory network and therefore upregulated in the transition from naive to formative pluripotency. IRF1 in turn binds to regulatory regions of a conserved set of ISGs and is required for their faithful expression in formative pluripotent cells. IRF1 also binds to an enhancer of the formative pluripotency transcription factor &lt;italic&gt;Oct6&lt;/italic&gt; and is partially required for upregulation of &lt;italic&gt;Oct6&lt;/italic&gt;. IRF1 therefore acts as a link between the formative pluripotency network and the regulation of innate immunity genes in formative pluripotency.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471598" rel="alternate" title="Stem cell specific interferon stimulated gene expression is regulated by the formative pluripotency network through IRF1 (15 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471515</id><title>Quantitative and temporal measurement of dynamic autophagy rates (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.427342+00:00</updated><author><name>Nitin Sai Beesabathuni</name></author><author><name>Priya S. Shah</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Autophagy is a multistep degradative process that is essential for maintaining cellular homeostasis. Systematically quantifying flux through this pathway is critical for gaining fundamental insights and effectively modulating this process that is dysregulated during many diseases. Established methods to quantify flux use steady state measurements, which provide limited information about the perturbation and the cellular response. We present a theoretical and experimental framework to measure autophagic steps in the form of rates under non-steady state conditions. We use this approach to measure temporal responses to rapamycin and wortmannin treatments, two commonly used autophagy modulators. We quantified changes in autophagy rates in as little as 10 minutes, which can establish direct mechanisms for autophagy perturbation before feedback begins. We identified concentration-dependent effects of rapamycin on the initial and temporal progression of autophagy rates. We also found variable recovery time from wortmannin’s inhibition of autophagy, which is further accelerated by rapamycin. In summary, this new approach enables the quantification of autophagy flux with high sensitivity and temporal resolution and facilitates a comprehensive understanding of this process.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471515" rel="alternate" title="Quantitative and temporal measurement of dynamic autophagy rates (13 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471275</id><title>Prdm16 and Notch functionally and physically interact during artery development (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.427513+00:00</updated><author><name>Manu Beerens</name></author><author><name>Jore Van Wauwe</name></author><author><name>Sander Craps</name></author><author><name>Margo Daems</name></author><author><name>KC Ashmita</name></author><author><name>Chris Finck</name></author><author><name>Shane Wright</name></author><author><name>Nicholas D. Leigh</name></author><author><name>Calum A. MacRae</name></author><author><name>Aernout Luttun</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Rationale&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Proper functionality of the circulatory system requires correct arteriovenous (AV) endothelial cell (EC) differentiation. While Notch signaling and its downstream effector Hes- Related Family bHLH Transcription Factor with YRPW Motif (Hey)2 favor arterial specification, transcription factor (TF) chicken ovalbumin upstream transcription factor 2 (Coup-TFII) inhibits canonical Notch activity to induce venous identity. However, transcriptional programs that compete with Coup-TFII to orchestrate arterial specification upstream of Notch remain largely unknown. We identified positive regulatory domain-containing protein (Prdm)16 as an arterial EC- specific TF, but its role during arterial EC specification and development remains unexplored.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To unravel the role of Prdm16 during arterial endothelial lineage specification and artery formation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods and Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transcriptomic data of freshly isolated arterial and venous ECs from humans and mice revealed that Prdm16 is exclusively expressed by arterial ECs throughout development. This expression pattern was independent of hemodynamic factors and conserved in zebrafish. Accordingly, loss of &lt;italic&gt;prdm16&lt;/italic&gt; in zebrafish perturbed AV endothelial specification and caused AV malformations in an EC-autonomous manner. This coincided with reduced canonical Notch activity in arterial ECs and was amplified when &lt;italic&gt;prdm16&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;notch&lt;/italic&gt; pathway members were concomitantly knocked down. &lt;italic&gt;In vitro&lt;/italic&gt; studies further indicated that Prdm16 not only amplified Notch signaling, but also physically and functionally interacted with Hey2 to drive proper arterial specification.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We showed that Prdm16 plays a pivotal role during arterial development through its physical and functional interaction with canonical Notch. As both Hey2 and Prdm16 have been associated with diverse vascular disorders including migraine and atherosclerosis, Prdm16 represents an attractive new target to treat these vascular disorders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471275" rel="alternate" title="Prdm16 and Notch functionally and physically interact during artery development (12 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471781</id><title>iMUT-seq: high-resolution mapping of DSB mutational landscapes reveals new insights into the mutagenic mechanisms of DSB repair (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.427680+00:00</updated><author><name>Aldo S. Bader</name></author><author><name>Martin Bushell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;DNA double-strand breaks (DSBs) are the most mutagenic form of DNA damage, and play a significant role in cancer biology, neurodegeneration and aging. However, studying DSB-induced mutagenesis is currently limited by the tools available for mapping these mutations. Here, we describe iMUT-seq, a technique that profiles DSB-induced mutations at high-sensitivity and single-nucleotide resolution around endogenous DSBs spread across the genome. By depleting 20 different DSB-repair factors we defined their mutational signatures in detail, revealing remarkable insights into the mechanisms of DSB-induced mutagenesis. We find that homologous-recombination (HR) is mutagenic in nature, displaying high levels of base substitutions and mononucleotide deletions due to DNA-polymerase errors, but simultaneously reduced translocation events, suggesting the primary role of HR is the specific suppression of genomic rearrangements. The results presented here offer new fundamental insights into DSB-induced mutagenesis and have significant implications for our understanding of cancer biology and the development of DDR-targeting chemotherapeutics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471781" rel="alternate" title="iMUT-seq: high-resolution mapping of DSB mutational landscapes reveals new insights into the mutagenic mechanisms of DSB repair (11 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471534</id><title>Decoupling growth and production by removing the origin of replication from a bacterial chromosome (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.427795+00:00</updated><author><name>Marje Kasari</name></author><author><name>Villu Kasari</name></author><author><name>Mirjam Kärmas</name></author><author><name>Arvi Jõers</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Efficient production of biochemicals and proteins in cell factories frequently benefits from a two-stage bioprocess in which growth and production phases are decoupled. Here we describe a novel growth switch based on the permanent removal of the origin of replication (&lt;italic&gt;oriC&lt;/italic&gt;) from the &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; chromosome. Without &lt;italic&gt;oriC&lt;/italic&gt;, cells cannot initiate a new round of replication and they stop growing while their metabolism remains active. Our system relies on a serine recombinase from bacteriophage phiC31 whose expression is controlled by the temperature-sensitive cI857 repressor from phage lambda. Reporter protein expression in switched cells continues after cessation of growth, leading to protein levels up to five times higher compared to non-switching cells. Switching induces a unique physiological state that is different from both normal exponential and stationary phases. Switched cells remain in this state even when not growing, retain their protein synthesis capacity, and do not induce proteins associated with the stationary phase. Our switcher technology is potentially useful for a range of products and applicable in many bacterial species for decoupling growth and production.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471534" rel="alternate" title="Decoupling growth and production by removing the origin of replication from a bacterial chromosome (9 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471477</id><title>Ubiquitylation by Rab40b/Cul5 regulates Rap2 localization and activity during cell migration (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.427919+00:00</updated><author><name>Emily D. Duncan</name></author><author><name>Ke-Jun Han</name></author><author><name>Margaret A. Trout</name></author><author><name>Rytis Prekeris</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cell migration is a complex process that involves coordinated changes in membrane transport, actin cytoskeleton dynamics, and extracellular matrix remodeling. Ras-like small monomeric GTPases, such as Rap2, play a key role in regulating actin cytoskeleton dynamics and cell adhesions. However, how Rap2 function, localization, and activation are regulated during cell migration is not fully understood. We previously identified the small GTPase Rab40b as a regulator of breast cancer cell migration. Rab40b contains a Suppressor of Cytokine Signaling (SOCS) box, which facilitates binding to Cullin5, a known E3 Ubiquitin Ligase component responsible for protein ubiquitylation. In this study, we show that the Rab40b/Cullin5 complex ubiquitylates Rap2. Importantly, we demonstrate that ubiquitylation regulates Rap2 activation, as well as recycling of Rap2 from the endolysosomal compartment to the lamellipodia of migrating breast cancer cells. Based on these data, we propose that Rab40b/Cullin5 ubiquitylates and regulates Rap2-dependent actin dynamics at the leading-edge, a process that is required for breast cancer cell migration and invasion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Rab40b/Cul5 complex is an emerging pro-migratory molecular machine. Duncan et al. identify the small GTPase Rap2 as a substrate of the Rab40b/Cul5 complex. They provide evidence that Rab40b/Cul5 ubiquitylates Rap2 to regulate its localization and activity during breast cancer cell migration, ultimately proposing a model by which Rap2 is targeted to the leading-edge plasma membrane to regulate actin dynamics during cell migration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471477" rel="alternate" title="Ubiquitylation by Rab40b/Cul5 regulates Rap2 localization and activity during cell migration (9 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471932</id><title>Toxoplasma ERK7 defends the apical complex from premature degradation (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.428096+00:00</updated><author><name>William S O'Shaughnessy</name></author><author><name>Xiaoyu Hu</name></author><author><name>Sarah Ana Henriquez</name></author><author><name>Michael L Reese</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Accurate cellular replication balances the biogenesis and turnover of complex structures. Apicomplexan parasites such as Plasmodium and Toxoplasma replicate by forming daughter cells within an intact mother cell, creating additional challenges to ensuring fidelity of division. Critical to these parasites' infectivity is an intricate cytoskeleton structure called the apical complex. Before the daughter apical complex can be inserted into the plasma membrane, the maternal material must be turned over. We previously identified the kinase ERK7 as required for the maturation of the apical complex in Toxoplasma gondii. Here we define the Toxoplasma ERK7 interactome, and identify a putative E3 ligase, CSAR1, as the downstream effector responsible for the phenotype. Genetic disruption of CSAR1 fully suppresses loss of the apical complex upon ERK7 knockdown. Furthermore, we show that CSAR1 is normally responsible for turnover of maternal cytoskeleton during cytokinesis, and that its aberrant function is driven by a mislocalization from the parasite residual body to the maternal and daughter apical complexes. These data identify a protein homeostasis pathway critical for Toxoplasma replication and fitness and suggest an unappreciated role for the parasite residual body in compartmentalizing processes that threaten the fidelity of parasite development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471932" rel="alternate" title="Toxoplasma ERK7 defends the apical complex from premature degradation (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471813</id><title>Biophysical Characterisation of Human LincRNA-p21 Sense and Antisense Alu Inverted Repeats (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.428438+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael H. D’Souza</name></author><author><name>Tyler Mrozowich</name></author><author><name>Maulik D. Badmalia</name></author><author><name>Mitchell Geeraert</name></author><author><name>Angela Frederickson</name></author><author><name>Amy Henrickson</name></author><author><name>Borries Demeler</name></author><author><name>Michael T. Wolfinger</name></author><author><name>Trushar R. Patel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human Long Intergenic Noncoding RNA-p21 (LincRNA-p21) is a regulatory noncoding RNA that plays an important role in promoting apoptosis. LincRNA-p21 is also critical in down-regulating many p53 target genes through its interaction with a p53 repressive complex. The interaction between LincRNA-p21 and the repressive complex is likely dependent on the RNA tertiary structure. Previous studies have determined the two-dimensional secondary structures of the sense and antisense human LincRNA-p21 &lt;italic&gt;AluSx1&lt;/italic&gt; IRs using SHAPE. However, there were no insights into its three-dimensional structure. Therefore, we &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; transcribed the sense and antisense regions of LincRNA-p21 &lt;italic&gt;AluSx1&lt;/italic&gt; Inverted Repeats (IRs) and performed analytical ultracentrifugation, size exclusion chromatography, light scattering, and small angle X-ray scattering (SAXS) studies. Based on these studies, we determined low-resolution, three-dimensional structures of sense and antisense LincRNA-p21. By adapting previously known two-dimensional information, we calculated their sense and antisense high-resolution models and determined that they agree with the low-resolution structures determined using SAXS. Thus, our integrated approach provides insights into the structure of LincRNA-p21 Alu IRs. Our study also offers a viable pipeline for combining the secondary structure information with biophysical and computational studies to obtain high-resolution atomistic models for long noncoding RNAs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471813" rel="alternate" title="Biophysical Characterisation of Human LincRNA-p21 Sense and Antisense Alu Inverted Repeats (8 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.472019</id><title>Manipulating the microbiome alters regenerative outcomes in Xenopus laevis tadpoles vis lipopolysaccharide signalling (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.428618+00:00</updated><author><name>Phoebe A Chapman</name></author><author><name>Campbell B Gilbert</name></author><author><name>Thomas J Devine</name></author><author><name>Daniel T Hudson</name></author><author><name>Joanna Ward</name></author><author><name>Xochitl C Morgan</name></author><author><name>Caroline W Beck</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Xenopus laevis&lt;/italic&gt; tadpoles can regenerate functional tails, containing spinal cord, notochord, muscle, fin, blood vessels and nerves, except for a brief refractory period at around one week of age. At this stage, amputation of the tadpole's tail may either result in scarless wound healing, or the activation of a regeneration programme, which replaces the lost tissues. We recently demonstrated a link between bacterial lipopolysaccharides and successful tail regeneration in refractory stage tadpoles, and proposed that this could result from lipopolysaccharides binding to Toll-like receptor 4 (TLR4). Here, we have used 16S rRNA sequencing to show that the tadpole skin microbiome is highly variable between sibships and that the community can be altered by raising embryos in the antibiotic gentamicin. Six gram-negative genera, including &lt;italic&gt;Delftia&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Chryseobacterium&lt;/italic&gt;, were over-represented in tadpoles that underwent tail regeneration. Lipopolysaccharides purified from a commensal &lt;italic&gt;Chryseobacterium spp. XDS4&lt;/italic&gt;, an exogenous &lt;italic&gt;Delftia spp&lt;/italic&gt;. or &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; could significantly increase the number of antibiotic-raised tadpoles that attempted regeneration. Conversely, the quality of regeneration was impaired in native-raised tadpoles exposed to the antagonistic lipopolysaccharide of &lt;italic&gt;Rhodobacter sphaeroides&lt;/italic&gt;. Knocking down TLR4 using CRISPR/Cas9 also reduced regeneration quality, but not quantity, at the level of the cohort. However, we found that the editing level of individual tadpoles was a poor predictor of regenerative outcome. In conclusion, our results suggest that variable regeneration in refractory stage tadpoles depends at least in part on the skin microbiome and lipopolysaccharide signalling, but that signalling via TLR4 cannot account for all of this effect.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.472019" rel="alternate" title="Manipulating the microbiome alters regenerative outcomes in Xenopus laevis tadpoles vis lipopolysaccharide signalling (7 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.470951</id><title>Evaluation of odorant-binding protein-1 as a molecular marker for identifying biological forms and delimitating sibling species of Anopheles stephensi (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.428762+00:00</updated><author><name>Om P. Singh</name></author><author><name>Shobhna Mishra</name></author><author><name>Ankita Sindhania</name></author><author><name>Taranjeet Kaur</name></author><author><name>U. Sreehari</name></author><author><name>Manoj K. Das</name></author><author><name>Gunjan Sharma</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Anopheles stephensi&lt;/italic&gt;, an invasive malaria vector, has been reported to have three biological forms identifiable based on the number of ridges present on the egg’s floats and the dimension of eggs. Recently, these forms have been designated as sibling species based on the fixed differences in the DNA sequence of the first intron of the odorant-binding protein-1 (&lt;italic&gt;AsteObp1&lt;/italic&gt;). In this study, we evaluated the utility of this neutral marker in designating sibling species or identifying biological forms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Field collected and laboratory-reared &lt;italic&gt;An. stephensi&lt;/italic&gt; were characterized for biological forms based on the number of floats on egg-ridge. DNA sequencing of the partial &lt;italic&gt;AsteObp1&lt;/italic&gt; gene of &lt;italic&gt;An. stephensi&lt;/italic&gt; individuals were performed by Sanger’s method, either directly or after cloning with a plasmid vector.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;AsteObp1&lt;/italic&gt; intron-1 in Indian &lt;italic&gt;An. stephensi&lt;/italic&gt; populations are highly polymorphic with the presence of more than 12 haplotypes exhibiting nucleotide-as well as length-polymorphism (90-to-121 bp). A majority of the field samples were heterozygous (up to 89% in the field populations). The phasing of haplotypes in heterozygotes through Sanger’s sequencing was challenging due to indels (1-to-24 bp) at multiple loci. No specific haplotype or monophyletic clade of intron-1 was found associated with a specific biological form. The inbreeding coefficient for this marker was close to zero in field and laboratory populations which refute the existence of sibling species based on the &lt;italic&gt;AsteObp1&lt;/italic&gt; marker.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;AsteObp1&lt;/italic&gt; cannot serve as a marker for the identification of biological forms of &lt;italic&gt;An. stephensi&lt;/italic&gt;. The probable existence of sibling species in &lt;italic&gt;An. stephensi&lt;/italic&gt; based on the &lt;italic&gt;AsteObp1&lt;/italic&gt; intron-1 is refuted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.470951" rel="alternate" title="Evaluation of odorant-binding protein-1 as a molecular marker for identifying biological forms and delimitating sibling species of Anopheles stephensi (7 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471572</id><title>Chemical induction of gut β-like-cells by combined FoxO1/Notch inhibition as a glucose-lowering treatment for diabetes (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.428901+00:00</updated><author><name>Takumi Kitamoto</name></author><author><name>Yun-Kyoung Lee</name></author><author><name>Wendy M. McKimpson</name></author><author><name>Hitoshi Watanabe</name></author><author><name>Nishat Sultana</name></author><author><name>Wen Du</name></author><author><name>Jason Fan</name></author><author><name>Bryan Diaz</name></author><author><name>Hua V. Lin</name></author><author><name>Rudolph L. Leibel</name></author><author><name>Sandro Belvedere</name></author><author><name>Domenico Accili</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Lifelong insulin replacement remains the mainstay of type 1 diabetes treatment. Genetic FoxO1 ablation promotes enteroendocrine cell (EECs) conversion into glucose-responsive β-like cells. Here, we tested whether chemical FoxO1 inhibitors can generate β-like gut cells. Pan-intestinal epithelial FoxO1 ablation expanded the EEC pool, induced β-like cells, and improved glucose tolerance in &lt;italic&gt;Ins2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Akita/+&lt;/sup&gt; mice. This genetic effect was phenocopied by small molecule FoxO1 inhibitor, Cpd10. Cpd10 induced β-like cells that released insulin in response to glucose in mouse gut organoids, and this effect was strengthened by the Notch inhibitor, DBZ. In &lt;italic&gt;Ins2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Akita/+&lt;/sup&gt; mice, a five-day course of either Cpd10 or DBZ induced insulin-immunoreactive β-like cells in the gut, lowered glycemia, and increased plasma insulin levels without apparent adverse effects. These results provide proof of principle of gut cell conversion into β-like cells by a small molecule FoxO1 inhibitor, paving the way for clinical applications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gut FoxO1 ablation enriched enteroendocrine cells (EECs) in mice small intestine&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gut FoxO1 ablation can reversed hyperglycemia in diabetic Akita mice&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;FoxO1 ablation in Neurog3 cells more efficiently altered EEC lineage than in pan-intestinal epithelial cells&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dual FoxO1/Notch inhibition synergistically boosted EEC lineage and β-like-cells&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Orally available small molecule FoxO1 inhibitor phenocopied genetic FoxO1 ablation in generating gut β-like cells&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471572" rel="alternate" title="Chemical induction of gut β-like-cells by combined FoxO1/Notch inhibition as a glucose-lowering treatment for diabetes (7 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471763</id><title>The p97-UBXD8 complex modulates ER-Mitochondria contact sites by modulating membrane lipid saturation and composition (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.429070+00:00</updated><author><name>Rakesh Ganji</name></author><author><name>Joao A. Paulo</name></author><author><name>Yuecheng Xi</name></author><author><name>Ian Kline</name></author><author><name>Jiang Zhu</name></author><author><name>Christoph S. Clemen</name></author><author><name>Conrad C. Weihl</name></author><author><name>John G. Purdy</name></author><author><name>Steve P. Gygi</name></author><author><name>Malavika Raman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The intimate association between the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) and mitochondrial membranes at ER-mitochondria contact sites serves as a platform for several critical cellular processes, in particular lipid synthesis. Enzymes involved in lipid biosynthesis are enriched at contacts and membrane lipid composition at contacts is distinct relative to surrounding membranes. How contacts are remodeled and the subsequent biological consequences of altered contacts such as perturbed lipid metabolism remains poorly understood. Here we show that the p97 AAA-ATPase and its ER-tethered ubiquitin-X domain adaptor 8 (UBXD8) regulate the prevalence of ER-mitochondria contacts. The p97-UBXD8 complex localizes to contacts and loss of this complex increases contacts in a manner that is dependent on p97 catalytic activity. Quantitative proteomics of purified contacts demonstrates alterations in proteins regulating lipid metabolism upon loss of UBXD8. Furthermore, lipidomics studies indicate significant changes in distinct lipid species in UBXD8 knockout cells. We show that loss of p97-UBXD8 results in perturbed contacts due to an increase in membrane lipid saturation via SREBP1 and the lipid desaturase SCD1. Aberrant contacts in p97-UBXD8 loss of function cells can be rescued by supplementation with unsaturated fatty acids or overexpression of SCD1. Perturbation of contacts and inherent lipid synthesis is emerging as a hallmark to a variety of human disorders such as neurodegeneration. Notably, we find that the SREBP1-SCD1 pathway is negatively impacted in the brains of mice with p97 mutations that cause neurodegeneration. Our results suggest that contacts are exquisitely sensitive to alterations to membrane lipid composition and saturation in a manner that is dependent on p97-UBXD8.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471763" rel="alternate" title="The p97-UBXD8 complex modulates ER-Mitochondria contact sites by modulating membrane lipid saturation and composition (7 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471399</id><title>Nucleotide imbalance decouples cell growth from cell proliferation (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.429223+00:00</updated><author><name>Frances F. Diehl</name></author><author><name>Teemu P. Miettinen</name></author><author><name>Ryan Elbashir</name></author><author><name>Christopher S. Nabel</name></author><author><name>Scott R. Manalis</name></author><author><name>Caroline A. Lewis</name></author><author><name>Matthew G. Vander Heiden</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nucleotide metabolism supports RNA synthesis and DNA replication to enable cell growth and division. Nucleotide depletion can accordingly inhibit cell growth and proliferation, but how cells sense and respond to changes in the relative levels of individual nucleotides is unclear. Moreover, the nucleotide requirement for biomass production changes over the course of the cell cycle, and how cells coordinate differential nucleotide demands with cell cycle progression is also not well understood. Here we find that excess levels of individual nucleotides can inhibit proliferation by disrupting the relative levels of nucleotide bases needed for DNA replication. The resulting purine and pyrimidine imbalances are not sensed by canonical growth regulatory pathways, causing aberrant biomass production and excessive cell growth despite inhibited proliferation. Instead, cells rely on replication stress signaling to survive during, and recover from, nucleotide imbalance during S phase. In fact, replication stress signaling is activated during unperturbed S phases and promotes nucleotide availability to support DNA replication. Together, these data reveal that imbalanced nucleotide levels are not detected until S phase, rendering cells reliant on replication stress signaling to cope with this metabolic problem, and disrupting the coordination of cell growth and division.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471399" rel="alternate" title="Nucleotide imbalance decouples cell growth from cell proliferation (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471408</id><title>Single cell quantification of ribosome occupancy in early mouse development (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.429357+00:00</updated><author><name>Tori Tonn</name></author><author><name>Hakan Ozadam</name></author><author><name>Crystal Han</name></author><author><name>Alia Segura</name></author><author><name>Duc Tran</name></author><author><name>David Catoe</name></author><author><name>Marc Salit</name></author><author><name>Can Cenik</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Technological limitations precluded transcriptome-wide analyses of translation at single cell resolution. To solve this challenge, we developed a novel microfluidic isotachophoresis approach, named RIBOsome profiling via IsoTachoPhoresis (Ribo-ITP), and characterized translation in single oocytes and embryos during early mouse development. We identified differential translation efficiency as a key regulatory mechanism of genes involved in centrosome organization and N&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;-methyladenosine modification of RNAs. Our high coverage measurements enabled the first analysis of allele-specific ribosome engagement in early development and led to the discovery of stage-specific differential engagement of zygotic RNAs with ribosomes. Finally, by integrating our measurements with proteomics data, we discovered that ribosome occupancy in germinal vesicle stage oocytes is the predominant determinant of protein abundance in the zygote. Taken together, these findings resolve the long-standing paradox of low correlation between RNA expression and protein abundance in early embryonic development. The novel Ribo-ITP approach will enable numerous applications by providing high coverage and high resolution ribosome occupancy measurements from ultra-low input samples including single cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471408" rel="alternate" title="Single cell quantification of ribosome occupancy in early mouse development (6 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471433</id><title>Creation of photocyclic vertebrate rhodopsin by single amino acid substitution (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.429690+00:00</updated><author><name>Kazumi Sakai</name></author><author><name>Yoshinori Shichida</name></author><author><name>Yasushi Imamoto</name></author><author><name>Takahiro Yamashita</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Opsins are universal photoreceptive proteins in animals and can be classified into three types based on their photoreaction properties. Upon light irradiation, vertebrate rhodopsin forms a metastable active state, which cannot revert back to the original dark state via either photoreaction or thermal reaction. By contrast, after photoreception, most opsins form a stable active state which can photo-convert back to the dark state. Moreover, we recently found a novel type of opsins whose activity is regulated by photocycling. However, the molecular mechanism underlying this diversification of opsins remains unknown. In this study, the molecular property of vertebrate rhodopsin successfully converted to the photocyclic and photoreversible properties by a single mutation at position 188. This revealed that the residue at position 188 contributes to the diversification of photoreaction properties of opsins by the regulation of the recovery from the active state to the original dark state.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471433" rel="alternate" title="Creation of photocyclic vertebrate rhodopsin by single amino acid substitution (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471174</id><title>Tailer: A Pipeline for Sequencing-Based Analysis of Non-Polyadenylated RNA 3’ End Processing (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.429850+00:00</updated><author><name>Tim Nicholson-Shaw</name></author><author><name>Jens Lykke-Andersen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Post-transcriptional trimming and tailing of RNA 3’ ends play key roles in the processing and quality control of non-coding RNAs (ncRNAs). However, bioinformatic tools to examine changes in the RNA 3’ “tailome” are sparse and not standardized. Here we present Tailer, a bioinformatic pipeline in two parts that allows for robust quantification and analysis of tail information from next generation sequencing experiments that preserve RNA 3’ end information. The first part of Tailer, Tailer-Processing, uses genome annotation or reference FASTA gene sequences to quantify RNA 3’ ends from SAM-formatted alignment files or FASTQ sequence read files produced from sequencing experiments. The second part, Tailer-Analysis, uses the output of Tailer-Processing to identify statistically significant RNA targets of trimming and tailing and create graphs for data exploration. We apply Tailer to RNA 3’ end sequencing experiments from three published studies and find that it accurately and reproducibly recapitulates key findings. Thus, Tailer should be a useful and easily accessible tool to globally investigate tailing dynamics of non-polyadenylated RNAs and conditions that perturb them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471174" rel="alternate" title="Tailer: A Pipeline for Sequencing-Based Analysis of Non-Polyadenylated RNA 3’ End Processing (6 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471409</id><title>Rab40c Regulates Focal Adhesions and Protein Phosphatase 6 Activity by Controlling ANKRD28 Ubiquitylation and Degradation (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.430164+00:00</updated><author><name>Ke-Jun Han</name></author><author><name>Rytis Prekeris</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Rab40c is a SOCS box–containing protein which binds Cullin5 to form a ubiquitin E3 ligase complex (Rab40c/CRL5) to regulate protein ubiquitylation. However, the exact functions of Rab40c remain to be determined, and what proteins are the targets of Rab40c-Cullin5 mediated ubiquitylation in mammalian cells are unknown. Here we showed that in migrating MDA-MB-231 cells Rab40c regulates focal adhesion’s number, size, and distribution. Mechanistically, we found that Rab40c binds the protein phosphatase 6 (PP6) complex and ubiquitylates one of its subunits, ankyrin repeat domain 28 (ANKRD28), thus, leading to its lysosomal degradation. Furthermore, we identified that phosphorylation of FAK and MOB1 is decreased in Rab40c knock-out cells, which may contribute to focal adhesion site regulation by Rab40c. Thus, we propose a model where Rab40c/CRL5 regulates ANKRD28 ubiquitylation and degradation, leading to a decrease in PP6 activity, which ultimately affects FAK and Hippo pathway signaling to alter focal adhesion dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471409" rel="alternate" title="Rab40c Regulates Focal Adhesions and Protein Phosphatase 6 Activity by Controlling ANKRD28 Ubiquitylation and Degradation (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471652</id><title>Rapid and robust directed differentiation of mouse epiblast stem cells into definitive endoderm and forebrain organoids (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.430479+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Medina-Cano</name></author><author><name>Emily K. Corrigan</name></author><author><name>Rachel Glenn</name></author><author><name>Mohammed Islam</name></author><author><name>Yuan Lin</name></author><author><name>Juliet Kim</name></author><author><name>Hyunwoo Cho</name></author><author><name>Thomas Vierbuchen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Directed differentiation of pluripotent stem cells (PSCs) is a powerful model system for deconstructing embryonic development. Although mice are the most advanced mammalian model system for genetic studies of embryonic development, state-of-the-art protocols for directed differentiation of mouse PSCs into defined lineages tend to be slower and generate target cell types with lower purity than analogous protocols for human PSCs, limiting their application as models for mechanistic studies of development. Here, we examine the potential of mouse epiblast stem cells (EpiSCs) cultured in media containing Wnt pathway inhibitors (primed ground state conditions) as a starting point for directed differentiation. As a proof-of-concept, we focused our efforts on two specific cell/tissue types that have proven difficult to generate efficiently and reproducibly from mouse embryonic stem cells: definitive endoderm and neural organoids. First, we developed a new protocol that can rapidly generate nearly pure definitive endoderm from EpiSCs. Second, we developed a protocol for generating forebrain organoids that model the development of prethalamic and hippocampal neurons. These significantly improved differentiation models present new possibilities for combining mouse genetic tools and resources with &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; differentiation to characterize the molecular and cellular mechanisms of embryonic development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SUMMARY STATEMENT&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;New optimized protocols for directed differentiation of mouse epiblast stem cells into definitive endoderm and forebrain-patterned organoids.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471652" rel="alternate" title="Rapid and robust directed differentiation of mouse epiblast stem cells into definitive endoderm and forebrain organoids (5 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471495</id><title>Age-dependent aggregation of ribosomal RNA-binding proteins links deterioration in chromatin stability with loss of proteostasis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.430651+00:00</updated><author><name>Julie Paxman</name></author><author><name>Zhen Zhou</name></author><author><name>Richard O’Laughlin</name></author><author><name>Yang Li</name></author><author><name>Wanying Tian</name></author><author><name>Hetian Su</name></author><author><name>Yanfei Jiang</name></author><author><name>Shayna E. Holness</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Stasiowski</name></author><author><name>Lev S. Tsimring</name></author><author><name>Lorraine Pillus</name></author><author><name>Jeff Hasty</name></author><author><name>Nan Hao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chromatin instability and loss of protein homeostasis (proteostasis) are two well-established hallmarks of aging, which have been considered largely independent of each other. Using microfluidics and single-cell imaging approaches, we observed that, during the replicative aging of &lt;italic&gt;S.cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt;, proteostasis decline occurred specifically in the fraction of cells with decreased stability at the ribosomal DNA (rDNA) region. A screen of 170 yeast RNA-binding proteins identified ribosomal RNA (rRNA)- binding proteins as the most enriched group that aggregate upon a decrease in rDNA stability. We further found that loss of rDNA stability contributes to age-dependent aggregation of rRNA-binding proteins through aberrant overproduction of rRNAs. These aggregates negatively impact nucleolar integrity and global proteostasis and hence limit cellular lifespan. Our findings reveal a mechanism underlying the interconnection between chromatin instability and proteostasis decline and highlight the importance of cell-to-cell variability in aging processes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471495" rel="alternate" title="Age-dependent aggregation of ribosomal RNA-binding proteins links deterioration in chromatin stability with loss of proteostasis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471616</id><title>Characterization of mutations causing steroid 21-hydroxylase deficiency in Brazilian and Portuguese populations (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.430832+00:00</updated><author><name>Mayara J. Prado</name></author><author><name>Shripriya Singh</name></author><author><name>Rodrigo Ligabue-Braun</name></author><author><name>Bruna V. Meneghetti</name></author><author><name>Thaiane Rispoli</name></author><author><name>Cristiane Kopacek</name></author><author><name>Karina Monteiro</name></author><author><name>Arnaldo Zaha</name></author><author><name>Maria L. R. Rossetti</name></author><author><name>Amit V. Pandey</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Deficiency of Cytochrome P450 Steroid 21-hydroxylase (CYP21A2) represents 90% of cases in congenital adrenal hyperplasia (CAH), an autosomal recessive disease caused by defects in cortisol biosynthesis. Computational prediction along with functional studies are often the only way to classify variants to understand the links to disease-causing effects. Here we investigated the pathogenicity of uncharacterized variants in the CYP21A2 gene reported in the Brazilian and Portuguese populations. Physicochemical alterations, residue conservation, and effect on protein structure were accessed by computational analysis. The enzymatic performance was obtained by functional assay with the wild-type and mutant CYP21A2 proteins expressed in HEK293 cells. Computational analysis showed that p.W202R, p.E352V, and p.R484L have severely impaired the protein structure, while p.P35L, p.L199P, and p.P433L have moderate effects. The p.W202R, p.E352V, p.P433L, and p.R484L variants showed residual 21OH activity consistent with the simple virilizing phenotype. The p.P35L and p.L199P variants showed partial 21OH efficiency associated with the non-classical phenotype. Additionally, p.W202R, p.E352V and p.R484L also modified the protein expression level. We have determined how the selected CYP21A2 gene mutations affect the 21OH activity through structural and activity alteration contributing to the future diagnosis and management of 21OH deficiency.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471616" rel="alternate" title="Characterization of mutations causing steroid 21-hydroxylase deficiency in Brazilian and Portuguese populations (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471529</id><title>Decoding the absolute stoichiometric composition and structural plasticity of α-carboxysomes (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.430988+00:00</updated><author><name>Yaqi Sun</name></author><author><name>Victoria M. Harman</name></author><author><name>James R. Johnson</name></author><author><name>Taiyu Chen</name></author><author><name>Gregory F. Dykes</name></author><author><name>Yongjun Lin</name></author><author><name>Robert J. Beynon</name></author><author><name>Lu-Ning Liu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Carboxysomes are anabolic bacterial microcompartments that play an essential role in carbon fixation in cyanobacteria and some chemoautotrophs. This self-assembling organelle encapsulates the key CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-fixing enzymes, Rubisco, and carbonic anhydrase using a polyhedral protein shell that is constructed by hundreds of shell protein paralogs. The α-carboxysome from the chemoautotroph &lt;italic&gt;Halothiobacillus neapolitanus&lt;/italic&gt; serves as a model system in fundamental studies and synthetic engineering of carboxysomes. Here we adopt a QconCAT-based quantitative mass spectrometry to determine the absolute stoichiometric composition of native α-carboxysomes from &lt;italic&gt;H. neapolitanus&lt;/italic&gt;. We further performed an in-depth comparison of the protein stoichiometry of native and recombinant α-carboxysomes heterologously generated in &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; to evaluate the structural variability and remodeling of α-carboxysomes. Our results provide insight into the molecular principles that mediate carboxysome assembly, which may aid in rational design and reprogramming of carboxysomes in new contexts for biotechnological applications.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471529" rel="alternate" title="Decoding the absolute stoichiometric composition and structural plasticity of α-carboxysomes (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.472021</id><title>Rec8 cohesin-mediated loop-axis chromatin architecture is required for meiotic recombination (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.431131+00:00</updated><author><name>Takeshi Sakuno</name></author><author><name>Sanki Tashiro</name></author><author><name>Hideki Tanizawa</name></author><author><name>Osamu Iwasaki</name></author><author><name>Da-Qiao Ding</name></author><author><name>Tokuko Haraguchi</name></author><author><name>Ken-ichi Noma</name></author><author><name>Yasushi Hiraoka</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During meiotic prophase, cohesin-dependent axial structures are formed in the synaptonemal complex (SC). However, the functional correlation between these structures and cohesion remains elusive. Here, we examined the formation of the cohesin-dependent axial structure in fission yeast, which forms atypical SCs composed of linear elements (LinEs) resembling the lateral elements of SC but lacking the central elements. The results demonstrated that Rec8 cohesin is crucial for the formation of the loop-axis structure within the atypical SC. Furthermore, the Rec8-mediated loop-axis structure is formed in the absence of LinEs and provides a structural platform for aligning homologous chromosomes. We also identified a rec8 mutant that lost the ability to assemble the loop-axis structure without losing cohesion. Remarkably, this mutant showed defects in the LinE assembly, resulting in a significant reduction in meiotic recombination. Collectively, our results demonstrate an essential role for the Rec8-dependent loop-axis structure in LinE assembly, facilitating meiotic recombination.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.472021" rel="alternate" title="Rec8 cohesin-mediated loop-axis chromatin architecture is required for meiotic recombination (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471332</id><title>Functional Anatomy of the TDP-43 Redox Sensor (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.431270+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaoming Zhou</name></author><author><name>Lily Sumrow</name></author><author><name>Lillian Sutherland</name></author><author><name>Daifei Liu</name></author><author><name>Tian Qin</name></author><author><name>Steven L. McKnight</name></author><author><name>Glen Liszczak</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;TAR binding protein 43 (TDP-43) is an RNA binding protein that assists in the maturation, export and sub-cellular localization of mRNA. The carboxyl terminal 153 residues of TDP-43 are of low sequence complexity and allow for self-association of the protein in a manner leading to its phase separation from an aqueous environment. These interactions assist TDP-43 in forming cytoplasmic RNA granules involved in the transport of mRNA for localized translation. Self-association of the TDP-43 low complexity (LC) domain is facilitated by a region of twenty five residues that are of extreme evolutionary conservation. The molecular basis for self-adherence of the protein through this region has been illuminated by a combination of structural and biochemical studies, allowing definition of a morphologically specific cross-β structure predicted to be weakly assembled by main chain hydrogen bonds. In this study we have investigated the importance of individual, Pauling hydrogen bonds hypothesized to facilitate self-adherence of the TDP-43 LC domain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471332" rel="alternate" title="Functional Anatomy of the TDP-43 Redox Sensor (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471285</id><title>Mathematical expressions describing enzyme velocity and inhibition at high enzyme concentration (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.431404+00:00</updated><author><name>Agustin Hernandez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Enzyme behaviour is typically characterised in the laboratory using very diluted solutions of enzyme. However, &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; processes usually occur at [S&lt;sub&gt;T&lt;/sub&gt;] ≈ [E&lt;sub&gt;T&lt;/sub&gt;] ≈ K&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt;. Furthermore, the study of enzyme action usually involves analysis and characterisation of inhibitors and their mechanisms. However, to date, there have been no reports proposing mathematical expressions that can be used to describe enzyme activity at high enzyme concentration apart from the simplest single substrate, irreversible case. Using a continued fraction approach, equations can be easily derived to apply to the most common cases in monosubstrate reactions, such as irreversible or reversible reactions and small molecule (inhibitor or activator) kinetic interactions. These expressions are simple and can be understood as an extension of the classical Michaelis-Menten equations. A first analysis of these expressions permits to deduce some differences at high &lt;italic&gt;vs&lt;/italic&gt; low enzyme concentration, such as the greater effectiveness of allosteric inhibitors compared to catalytic ones. Also, they can be used to understand catalyst saturation in a reaction. Although they can be linearised following classical approaches, these equations also show some differences that need to be taken into account. The most important one may be the different meaning of line intersection points in Dixon plots. All in all, these expressions may be useful tools for the translation &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; of &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; experimental data or for modelling &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and biotechnological processes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471285" rel="alternate" title="Mathematical expressions describing enzyme velocity and inhibition at high enzyme concentration (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471807</id><title>A novel multi-functional role for the MCM8/9 helicase complex in maintaining fork integrity during replication stress (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.431504+00:00</updated><author><name>Wezley C. Griffin</name></author><author><name>David R. McKinzey</name></author><author><name>Kathleen N. Klinzing</name></author><author><name>Rithvik Baratam</name></author><author><name>Michael A. Trakselis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The minichromosome maintenance (MCM) 8/9 helicase is a AAA&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; complex involved in DNA replication-associated repair. Despite high sequence homology to the MCM2-7 helicase, an active role for MCM8/9 has remained elusive. We interrogated fork progression in cells lacking MCM8 or 9 and find there is a functional partitioning. Loss of MCM8 or 9 slows overall replication speed and increases markers of genomic damage and fork instability, further compounded upon treatment with hydroxyurea. MCM8/9 acts upstream and antagonizes the recruitment of BRCA1 in nontreated conditions. However, upon treatment with fork stalling agents, MCM9 recruits Rad51 to protect and remodel persistently stalled forks. The helicase function of MCM8/9 aids in normal replication fork progression, but upon excessive stalling, MCM8/9 directs additional stabilizers to protect forks from degradation. This evidence defines novel multifunctional roles for MCM8/9 in promoting normal replication fork progression and promoting genome integrity following stress.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471807" rel="alternate" title="A novel multi-functional role for the MCM8/9 helicase complex in maintaining fork integrity during replication stress (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471334</id><title>Tracing the genetics of neurological disease to the mutation-directed addition of single hydrogen bonds (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.431628+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaoming Zhou</name></author><author><name>Kyuto Tashiro</name></author><author><name>Lily Sumrow</name></author><author><name>Lillian Sutherland</name></author><author><name>Glen Liszczak</name></author><author><name>Steven L. McKnight</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mutations causative of neurological and neurodegenerative disease can occur in coding regions that specify protein domains of low sequence complexity. These autosomal dominant mutations can be idiosyncratic in their recurrent appearance at the same amino acid. Here we report studies of recurrent mutations in proline residues located within low complexity (LC) domains associated with the neurofilament light chain protein, the microtubule-associated tau protein, and the heterogeneous nuclear RNPA2 protein. All such mutations manifest their effects by directing formation of variant proteins endowed with the addition of a single, main chain hydrogen bond specified by the variant amino acid replacing proline. Here we show that methylation of the peptide backbone nitrogen atom associated with these variant amino acids eliminates the aberrant hydrogen bond and restores normal protein function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471334" rel="alternate" title="Tracing the genetics of neurological disease to the mutation-directed addition of single hydrogen bonds (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471957</id><title>Human cellular homeostasis buffers trans-acting translational effects of heterologous gene expression with very different codon usage bias (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.431756+00:00</updated><author><name>Arthur J JALLET</name></author><author><name>Antonin Demange</name></author><author><name>Fiona Leblay</name></author><author><name>Mathilde Decourcelle</name></author><author><name>Khadija El Koulali</name></author><author><name>Marion AL Picard</name></author><author><name>Ignacio G Bravo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The frequency of synonymous codons in protein coding genes is non-random and varies both between species and between genes within species. Whether this codon usage bias (CUBias) reflects underlying neutral mutational processes or is instead shaped by selection remains an open debate, especially regarding the role of selection for enhanced protein production. Variation in CUBias of a gene (be it natural synonymous mutations or biotechnological synonymous recoding) can have an enormous impact on its expression by diverse cis- acting mechanisms. But expression of genes with extreme CUBias can also lead to strong phenotypic effects by altering the overall intracellular translation homeostasis via competition for ribosomal machinery or tRNA depletion. In this study, we expressed at high levels in human cells six different synonymous versions of a gene and used matched transcriptomic and proteomic data to evaluate the impact of CUBias of the heterologous gene on the translation of cellular transcripts. Our experimental design focused specifically on differences during translation elongation. Response to expression of the different synonymous sequences was assessed by various approaches, ranging from analyses performed on a per-gene basis to more integrated approaches of the cell as a whole. We observe that the transcriptome displayed substantial changes as a result of heterologous gene expression by triggering an intense antiviral and inflammatory response, but that changes in the proteomes were very modest. Most importantly we notice that changes in translation efficiency of cellular transcripts were not associated with the direction of the CUBias of the heterologous sequences, thereby providing only limited support for trans- acting effects of synonymous changes. We interpret that, in human cells in culture, changes in CUBias can lead to important cis- acting effects in gene expression, but that cellular homeostasis can buffer the phenotypic impact of overexpression of heterologous genes with extreme CUBias.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471957" rel="alternate" title="Human cellular homeostasis buffers trans-acting translational effects of heterologous gene expression with very different codon usage bias (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.470227</id><title>Chronic kidney disease alters Pin1 phosphorylation and parathyroid hormone mRNA binding proteins leading to secondary hyperparathyroidism (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.431888+00:00</updated><author><name>Alia Hasan</name></author><author><name>Yael E. Pollak</name></author><author><name>Rachel Levin</name></author><author><name>Justin Silver</name></author><author><name>Nir London</name></author><author><name>Morris Nechama</name></author><author><name>Iddo Z. Ben-Dov</name></author><author><name>Tally Naveh-Many</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Parathyroid hormone (PTH) regulates calcium metabolism and bone strength. Chronic kidney disease (CKD) leads to secondary hyperparathyroidism (SHP) which increases morbidity and mortality. High PTH expression in SHP is due to increased &lt;italic&gt;PTH&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA stability mediated by changes in &lt;italic&gt;PTH&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA interaction with stabilizing AUF1 and destabilizing KSRP. Pin1 isomerizes target proteins, including mRNA binding proteins. In SHP, Pin1 isomerase activity is decreased and phosphorylated KSRP fails to bind &lt;italic&gt;PTH&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA, resulting in high &lt;italic&gt;PTH&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA stability and levels. The molecular mechanisms underlying Pin1 regulation and their effect to increase &lt;italic&gt;PTH&lt;/italic&gt; expression are unknown. We show by mass-spectrometry (MS) the CKD induced changes in rat parathyroid proteome and phosphoproteome profiles. Parathyroid Pin1 Ser16 and Ser71 phosphorylation, that disrupts Pin1 activity, is enhanced in acute and chronic kidney failure rats. Accordingly, pharmacologic Pin1 inhibition increases PTH expression in parathyroid organ cultures and transfected cells, through the &lt;italic&gt;PTH&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA protein binding &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt; element and KSRP phosphorylation. Therefore, CKD leads to parathyroid loss of Pin1 activity by inducing Pin1 phosphorylation. This predisposes parathyroids to increase PTH production through modified &lt;italic&gt;PTH&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA-KSRP interaction that is dependent on KSRP phosphorylation. CKD induced Pin1 and KSRP phosphorylation and the Pin1-KSRP-&lt;italic&gt;PTH&lt;/italic&gt; mRNA axis thus drive secondary hyperparathyroidism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.470227" rel="alternate" title="Chronic kidney disease alters Pin1 phosphorylation and parathyroid hormone mRNA binding proteins leading to secondary hyperparathyroidism (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471417</id><title>EB3-informed dynamics of the microtubule stabilizing cap during stalled growth (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.432024+00:00</updated><author><name>Maurits Kok</name></author><author><name>Florian Huber</name></author><author><name>Svenja-Marei Kalisch</name></author><author><name>Marileen Dogterom</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microtubule stability is known to be governed by a stabilizing GTP/GDP-Pi cap, but the exact relation between growth velocity, GTP hydrolysis and catastrophes remains unclear. We investigate the dynamics of the stabilizing cap through &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; reconstitution of microtubule dynamics in contact with micro-fabricated barriers, using the plus-end binding protein GFP-EB3 as a marker for the nucleotide state of the tip. The interaction of growing microtubules with steric objects is known to slow down microtubule growth and accelerate catastrophes. We show that the lifetime distributions of stalled microtubules, as well as the corresponding lifetime distributions of freely growing microtubules, can be fully described with a simple phenomenological 1D model based on noisy microtubule growth and a single EB3-dependent hydrolysis rate. This same model is furthermore capable of explaining both the previously reported mild catastrophe dependence on microtubule growth rates and the catastrophe statistics during tubulin washout experiments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471417" rel="alternate" title="EB3-informed dynamics of the microtubule stabilizing cap during stalled growth (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471516</id><title>Protein-protein interactions on membrane surfaces analysed using SUPER template pull-downs (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.432141+00:00</updated><author><name>Devika S. Andhare</name></author><author><name>Thomas J. Pucadyil</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Discovery-based proteomics workflows that identify novel interactors rely on immunoprecipitations or pull-downs with genetically-tagged bait proteins displayed on sepharose matrices. But strategies to analyse protein interactions on a diffusible membrane surface combined with the practical ease of pull-downs remain unavailable. Such strategies are important to analyse protein complexes that mature in composition and stability because of diffusion-based interactions between participant proteins. Here, we describe a generic pull-down strategy to analyse such complexes using &lt;underline&gt;sup&lt;/underline&gt;ported membranes with &lt;underline&gt;e&lt;/underline&gt;xcess reservoir templates displaying His-tagged bait proteins. Using clathrin-mediated endocytosis as a paradigm, we find that the clathrin-binding adaptor protein epsin1 displayed as bait on these templates pulls down significantly higher amounts of clathrin from brain lysates than conventional sepharose matrices. Together, our results establish the potential of SUPER templates as superior matrices for analysing protein-protein interactions and resultant complexes formed on membrane surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471516" rel="alternate" title="Protein-protein interactions on membrane surfaces analysed using SUPER template pull-downs (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471646</id><title>The oscillation of mitotic kinase governs cell cycle latches (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.432247+00:00</updated><author><name>Bela Novak</name></author><author><name>John J Tyson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In order to transmit a eukaryotic cell’s genome accurately from mother cell to daughter cells, it is essential that the basic events of the cell division cycle (DNA synthesis and mitosis) occur once and only once per cycle, i.e., that a cell progresses irreversibly from G&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; to S to G&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; to M and back to G&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;. Irreversible progression through the cell cycle is assured by a sequence of ‘latching’ molecular switches, based on molecular interactions among cyclin-dependent kinases and their auxiliary partners. Positive feedback loops (++ or −−) create bistable switches with latching properties, and negative feedback loops drive progression from one stage to the next. In budding yeast (&lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt;) these events are coordinated by double-negative feedback loops between Clb-dependent kinases (Clb1-6) and their antagonists (APC:Cdh1 and Sic1). If the coordinating signal is compromised, either by deletion of Clb1-5 proteins or expression of non-degradable Clb2, then irreversibility is lost and yeast cells exhibit multiple rounds of DNA replication or mitotic exit events (Cdc14 endocycles). Using mathematical modelling of a stripped-down control network, we show how endocycles arise because the switches fail to latch, and the gates swing back and forth by the action of the negative feedback loops.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471646" rel="alternate" title="The oscillation of mitotic kinase governs cell cycle latches (3 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>