<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.743290+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460138</id><title>Structure of a bacterial Rhs effector exported by the type VI secretion system (39 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.750740+00:00</updated><author><name>Patrick Günther</name></author><author><name>Dennis Quentin</name></author><author><name>Shehryar Ahmad</name></author><author><name>Kartik Sachar</name></author><author><name>Christos Gatsogiannis</name></author><author><name>John C. Whitney</name></author><author><name>Stefan Raunser</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The type VI &lt;underline&gt;s&lt;/underline&gt;ecretion &lt;underline&gt;s&lt;/underline&gt;ystem (T6SS) is a widespread protein export apparatus found in Gram-negative bacteria. The majority of T6SSs deliver toxic effector proteins into competitor bacteria. Yet, the structure, function, and activation of many of these effectors remains poorly understood. Here, we present the structures of the T6SS effector RhsA from &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas protegens&lt;/italic&gt; and its cognate T6SS spike protein, VgrG1, at 3.3 Å resolution. The structures reveal that the &lt;underline&gt;r&lt;/underline&gt;earrangement &lt;underline&gt;h&lt;/underline&gt;ot&lt;underline&gt;s&lt;/underline&gt;pot (Rhs) repeats of RhsA assemble into a closed anticlockwise β-barrel spiral similar to that found in bacterial insecticidal Tc toxins and in metazoan teneurin proteins. We find that the C-terminal toxin domain of RhsA is autoproteolytically cleaved but remains inside the Rhs ‘cocoon’ where, with the exception of three ordered structural elements, most of the toxin is disordered. The N-terminal ‘plug’ domain is unique to T6SS Rhs proteins and resembles a champagne cork that seals the Rhs cocoon at one end while also mediating interactions with VgrG1. Interestingly, this domain is also autoproteolytically cleaved inside the cocoon but remains associated with it. We propose that mechanical force is required to remove the cleaved part of the plug, resulting in the release of the toxin domain as it is delivered into a susceptible bacterial cell by the T6SS.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460138" rel="alternate" title="Structure of a bacterial Rhs effector exported by the type VI secretion system (39 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-09-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460206</id><title>Network visualisation of synthetic biology designs (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.752444+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Crowther</name></author><author><name>Anil Wipat</name></author><author><name>Ángel Goñi-Moreno</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Visualising the complex information captured by synthetic biology designs is still a major challenge. The popular glyph approach where each genetic part is displayed on a linear sequence allows researchers to generate diagrams and visualise abstract designs [2], but only represents a single, static representation that results in visualisation that is not specific to the requirements of a user resulting in a one-size-fits-all visualisation. We developed a network visualisation technique that automatically turns all design information into a graph, displaying otherwise hidden data. The structure of the resulting graphs can be dynamically adjusted according to specific visualisation requirements, such as highlighting proteins, interactions or hierarchy. Since biological systems have an inherent affinity with network visualization [6], we advocate for adopting this approach to standardise and automate the representation of complex information.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460206" rel="alternate" title="Network visualisation of synthetic biology designs (15 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-09-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460283</id><title>Multiplexed profiling of kinase interactomes quantifies cellular network plasticity (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.753184+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Golkowski</name></author><author><name>Andrea Lius</name></author><author><name>Tanmay Sapre</name></author><author><name>Ho-Tak Lau</name></author><author><name>Taylor Moreno</name></author><author><name>Dustin J. Maly</name></author><author><name>Shao-En Ong</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cells utilize protein-protein interaction (PPI) networks to receive, transduce, and respond to stimuli. Interaction network rewiring drives devastating diseases like cancers, making PPIs attractive targets for pharmacological intervention. Kinases are druggable nodes in PPI networks but high-throughput proteomics approaches to quantify disease-associated kinome PPI rewiring are lacking. We introduce kinobead competition and correlation analysis (Ki-CCA), a chemoproteomics approach to simultaneously map hundreds of endogenous kinase PPIs. We identified 2,305 PPIs of 300 kinases across 18 diverse cancer lines, quantifying the high plasticity of interaction networks between cancer types, signaling, and phenotypic states; this database of dynamic kinome PPIs provides deep insights into cancer cell signaling. We discovered an AAK1 complex promoting epithelial-mesenchymal transition and drug resistance, and depleting its components sensitized cells to targeted therapy. Ki-CCA enables rapid and highly multiplexed mapping of kinome PPIs in native cell and tissue lysates, without epitope tagged baits, protein labeling, or antibodies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460283" rel="alternate" title="Multiplexed profiling of kinase interactomes quantifies cellular network plasticity (14 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460150</id><title>Gsx2 but not Gsx1 is necessary for early forebrain patterning and long-term survival in zebrafish (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.753486+00:00</updated><author><name>RA Coltogirone</name></author><author><name>EI Sherfinski</name></author><author><name>ZA Dobler</name></author><author><name>SN Peterson</name></author><author><name>AR Andlinger</name></author><author><name>LC Fadel</name></author><author><name>RL Patrick</name></author><author><name>SA Bergeron</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Central nervous system (CNS) development is regulated by regionally expressed transcription factors that impart initial cell identity, connectivity, and function to neural circuits through complex molecular genetic cascades. &lt;italic&gt;genomic screen homeobox 1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;2&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;gsx1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;gsx2&lt;/italic&gt;) encode homeobox transcription factors expressed in the developing CNS in multiple vertebrates examined to date. However, we have limited knowledge of the expression of these transcription factors and the gene networks that they regulate across developing brain regions in zebrafish. The objective of this study was to comprehensively examine &lt;italic&gt;gsx1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;gsx2&lt;/italic&gt; expression throughout neurodevelopment and characterize &lt;italic&gt;gsx1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;gsx2&lt;/italic&gt; mutants to study the essential roles of these closely related transcription factors. Using RT-PCR, whole-mount &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; hybridization (WISH), and fluorescence &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; hybridization, we examine &lt;italic&gt;gsx1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;gsx2&lt;/italic&gt; expression from early embryonic to late larval stages. &lt;italic&gt;gsx1&lt;/italic&gt; is expressed initially in the hindbrain and diencephalon and later in the optic tectum, pretectum, and cerebellar plate. Comparatively, &lt;italic&gt;gsx2&lt;/italic&gt; is expressed in the early telencephalon and later in the pallium and olfactory bulb. &lt;italic&gt;gsx1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;gsx2&lt;/italic&gt; are regionally co-expressed in the hypothalamus, preoptic area, and hindbrain, however rarely co-localize in the same cells. To identify forebrain target genes, we utilize mutants made with Transcription activator-like effector nucleases (TALEN). &lt;italic&gt;gsx1&lt;/italic&gt; mutant zebrafish exhibit stunted growth, however, they survive through adulthood and are fertile. &lt;italic&gt;gsx2&lt;/italic&gt; mutant zebrafish experience swim bladder inflation failure that prevents survival past larval stage. Using WISH and RT-qPCR we demonstrate altered expression of genes including, &lt;italic&gt;distal-less homeobox&lt;/italic&gt; genes and &lt;italic&gt;forkhead box&lt;/italic&gt; gene &lt;italic&gt;foxp2&lt;/italic&gt;. This work provides novel tools with which other target genes and functions of Gsx1 and Gsx2 can be characterized across the CNS to better understand the unique and overlapping roles of these highly conserved transcription factors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460150" rel="alternate" title="Gsx2 but not Gsx1 is necessary for early forebrain patterning and long-term survival in zebrafish (8 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460205</id><title>Forkhead transcription factor FKH-8 is a master regulator of primary cilia in C. elegans (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.753725+00:00</updated><author><name>Rebeca Brocal-Ruiz</name></author><author><name>Ainara Esteve-Serrano</name></author><author><name>Carlos Mora-Martinez</name></author><author><name>Juan Tena</name></author><author><name>Nuria Flames</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cilia, either motile or non-motile (a.k.a primary or sensory), are complex evolutionary conserved eukaryotic structures composed of hundreds of proteins required for their assembly, structure and function that are collectively known as the ciliome. Ciliome mutations underlie a group of pleiotropic genetic diseases known as ciliopathies. Proper cilium function requires the tight coregulation of ciliome gene transcription, which is only fragmentarily understood. RFX transcription factors (TF) have an evolutionarily conserved role in the direct activation of ciliome genes both in motile and non-motile cilia cell types. In vertebrates, FoxJ1 and FoxN4 Forkhead (FKH) TFs work with RFX in the direct activation of ciliome genes, exclusively in motile cilia cell-types. No additional TFs have been described to act together with RFX in primary cilia cell-types in any organism. Here we describe FKH-8, a FKH TF, as master regulator of the primary ciliome in &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/italic&gt;. &lt;italic&gt;fkh-8&lt;/italic&gt; is expressed in all ciliated neurons in C. &lt;italic&gt;elegans&lt;/italic&gt;, binds the regulatory regions of ciliome genes, regulates ciliome gene expression, cilium morphology and a wide range of behaviours mediated by sensory cilia. Importantly, we find FKH-8 function can be replaced by mouse FOXJ1 and FOXN4 but not by members of other mouse FKH subfamilies. In conclusion, our results show that RFX and FKH TF families act as master regulators of ciliogenesis also in sensory ciliated cell types and suggest that this regulatory logic could be an ancient trait predating functional cilia sub-specialization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460205" rel="alternate" title="Forkhead transcription factor FKH-8 is a master regulator of primary cilia in C. elegans (4 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460067</id><title>Mitochondrial dynamics regulate genome stability via control of caspase-dependent DNA damage (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.753928+00:00</updated><author><name>Kai Cao</name></author><author><name>Joel S Riley</name></author><author><name>Catherine Cloix</name></author><author><name>Yassmin Elmasry</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Ichim</name></author><author><name>Kirsteen J Campbell</name></author><author><name>Stephen WG Tait</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mitochondrial dysfunction is interconnected with cancer. Nevertheless, how defective mitochondria promote cancer is poorly understood. We find that mitochondrial dysfunction promotes DNA damage under conditions of increased apoptotic priming. Underlying this process, we reveal a key role for mitochondrial dynamics in the regulation of DNA damage and genome instability. The ability of mitochondrial dynamics to regulate oncogenic DNA damage centres upon the control of minority MOMP, a process that enables non-lethal caspase activation leading to DNA damage. Mitochondrial fusion suppresses minority MOMP, and its associated DNA damage, by enabling homogenous mitochondrial expression of anti-apoptotic BCL-2 proteins. Finally, we find that mitochondrial dysfunction inhibits pro-apoptotic BAX retrotranslocation, causing BAX mitochondrial localization thereby promoting minority MOMP. Unexpectedly, these data reveal oncogenic effects of mitochondrial dysfunction that are mediated via mitochondrial dynamics and caspase-dependent DNA damage.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460067" rel="alternate" title="Mitochondrial dynamics regulate genome stability via control of caspase-dependent DNA damage (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460068</id><title>The Paradox of the Plankton: Coexistence of Structured Microbial Communities (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.754166+00:00</updated><author><name>Alberto Scarampi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the framework of resource-competition models, it has been argued that the number of species stably coexisting in an ecosystem cannot exceed the number of shared resources. However, plankton seems to be an exception of this so-called “competitive-exclusion principle”. In planktic ecosystems, a large number of different species stably coexist in an environment with limited resources. This contradiction between theoretical expectations and empirical observations is often referred to as “The Paradox of the Plankton”. This project aims to investigate biophysical models that can account for the large biodiversity observed in real ecosystems in order to resolve this paradox. A model is proposed that combines classical resource competition models, metabolic trade-offs and stochastic ecosystem assembly. Simulations of the model match empirical observations, while relaxing some unrealistic assumptions from previous models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;Paradox:&lt;/bold&gt; from Greek &lt;italic&gt;para&lt;/italic&gt;: “distinct from”, and &lt;italic&gt;doxa&lt;/italic&gt;: opinion. Sainsbury (1995) defines a paradox as “an apparently unacceptable conclusion derived by apparently acceptable reasoning from apparently acceptable premises”. Paradoxes are useful research tools as they suggest logical inconsistencies. In order to spot the flaw, the validity of all the premises has to be carefully assessed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;Plankton:&lt;/bold&gt; refers to the collection of organisms that spend part or all of their lives in suspension in water (Reynolds 2006). Plankton, or &lt;italic&gt;plankters&lt;/italic&gt;, are “organisms that have velocities significantly smaller than oceanic currents and thus are considered to travel with the water parcel they occupy” (Lombard et al. 2019). &lt;italic&gt;Phytoplankters&lt;/italic&gt; refer to the members of the plankton that perform photosynthesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460068" rel="alternate" title="The Paradox of the Plankton: Coexistence of Structured Microbial Communities (4 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460064</id><title>High interaction valency ensures cohesion and persistence of a microtubule +TIP body at the plus-end of a single specialized microtubule in yeast (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.754343+00:00</updated><author><name>Sandro M. Meier</name></author><author><name>Ana-Maria Farcas</name></author><author><name>Anil Kumar</name></author><author><name>Mahdiye Ijavi</name></author><author><name>Robert T. Bill</name></author><author><name>Jörg Stelling</name></author><author><name>Eric Dufresne</name></author><author><name>Michel O. Steinmetz</name></author><author><name>Yves Barral</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microtubule plus-end tracking proteins (+TIPs) control microtubule specialization and are as such essential notably during eukaryotic cell division. Here, we investigated interactions and functions of the budding yeast Kar9 network consisting of the core +TIPs components Kar9 (functional homologue of APC, MACF, and SLAIN), Bim1 (orthologue of EB1), and Bik1 (orthologue of CLIP-170). Our data indicate that a redundant, multivalent web of interactions links the three +TIPs together to form a “Kar9 body” at the tip of a single cytoplasmic microtubule. They further suggest that this body is a liquid-like condensate, allowing it to persist on both growing and shrinking microtubule tips, and functions as a mechanical coupling device between microtubules and actin cables during mitosis. Our study underlines the power of dissecting the web of low-affinity interactions driving liquid-liquid phase separation of proteins in order to demonstrate the importance and establish the functional roles of condensation processes in vivo.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460064" rel="alternate" title="High interaction valency ensures cohesion and persistence of a microtubule +TIP body at the plus-end of a single specialized microtubule in yeast (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>