<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.649732+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474455</id><title>Nerve-mediated amputation-induced stem cell activation primes distant appendages for future regeneration events in axolotl (62 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.650194+00:00</updated><author><name>Duygu Payzin-Dogru</name></author><author><name>Sarah E. Wilson</name></author><author><name>Steven J. Blair</name></author><author><name>Burcu Erdogan</name></author><author><name>Shifa Hossain</name></author><author><name>Louis V. Cammarata</name></author><author><name>Juan C. Velazquez Matos</name></author><author><name>Alan Y. Wong</name></author><author><name>Julia Losner</name></author><author><name>Sangwon Min</name></author><author><name>Hani Singer</name></author><author><name>Jessica L. Whited</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Animals exhibit extreme diversity in regenerative ability. This likely reflects different, lineage-specific selective pressures in their evolutionary histories, but how specific molecular features of regenerative programs help solve species-specific challenges has not been examined in detail.  Here we discover that, in the highly-regenerative axolotl salamander, a conserved, body-wide stem cell activation response triggered in response to limb removal primes undisturbed limbs for regeneration upon subsequent amputation. This response should be particularly useful to salamanders, which frequently lose limbs in response to cannibalism. We further demonstrate the body-wide response requires both peripheral nervous system input at these distant sites and mTOR signaling. We defined gene expression changes within the nerves and nearby tissues, harboring responsive stem cells, leading to identification of candidate genetic pathways influencing distant stem cell activation following amputation. Functional experimentation confirmed a requirement for adrenergic signaling in amputation-induced activation of distant stem cells. These findings reveal a direct link between systemic cellular activation responses to local tissue damage and overall regenerative ability. Similar systemic activation responses to tissue removal have been observed in animals with widely differing regenerative abilities (e.g., planaria to mice), suggesting that it is the responses downstream of these signals, likely sculpted by differing evolutionary pressures, that ultimately distinguish regenerators from non-regenerators.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474455" rel="alternate" title="Nerve-mediated amputation-induced stem cell activation primes distant appendages for future regeneration events in axolotl (62 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474382</id><title>Precise measurement of nanoscopic septin ring structures in deep learning-assisted quantitative superresolution microscopy (46 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.650831+00:00</updated><author><name>Amin Zehtabian</name></author><author><name>Paul Markus Müller</name></author><author><name>Maximilian Goisser</name></author><author><name>Leon Obendorf</name></author><author><name>Lea Jänisch</name></author><author><name>Nadja Hümpfer</name></author><author><name>Jakob Rentsch</name></author><author><name>Helge Ewers</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The combination of image analysis and fluorescence superresolution microscopy methods allows for unprecedented insight into the organization of macromolecular assemblies in cells. Advances in deep learning-based object recognition enables the automated processing of large amounts of data, resulting in high accuracy through averaging. However, while the analysis of highly symmetric structures of constant size allows for a resolution approaching the dimensions of structural biology, deep learning methods are prone to different forms of bias. A biased recognition of structures may prohibit the development of readouts for processes that involve significant changes in size or shape of amorphous macromolecular complexes. What is required to overcome this problem is a detailed investigation of potential sources of bias and the rigorous testing of trained models using real or simulated data covering a wide dynamic range of possible results. Here we combine single molecule localization-based superresolution microscopy of septin ring structures with the training of several different deep learning models for a quantitative investigation of bias resulting from different training approaches and finally quantitative changes in septin ring structures. We find that trade-off exists between measurement accuracy and the dynamic range of recognized phenotypes. Using our trained models, we furthermore find that septin ring size can be explained by the number of subunits they are assembled from alone. Our work provides a new experimental system for the investigation of septin polymerization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474382" rel="alternate" title="Precise measurement of nanoscopic septin ring structures in deep learning-assisted quantitative superresolution microscopy (46 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474323</id><title>A versatile active learning workflow for optimization of genetic and metabolic networks (30 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.651183+00:00</updated><author><name>Amir Pandi</name></author><author><name>Christoph Diehl</name></author><author><name>Ali Yazdizadeh Kharrazi</name></author><author><name>Léon Faure</name></author><author><name>Scott A. Scholz</name></author><author><name>Maren Nattermann</name></author><author><name>David Adam</name></author><author><name>Nils Chapin</name></author><author><name>Yeganeh Foroughijabbari</name></author><author><name>Charles Moritz</name></author><author><name>Nicole Paczia</name></author><author><name>Niña Socorro Cortina</name></author><author><name>Jean-Loup Faulon</name></author><author><name>Tobias J. Erb</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The study, engineering and application of biological networks require practical and efficient approaches. Current optimization efforts of these systems are often limited by wet lab labor and cost, as well as the lack of convenient, easily adoptable computational tools. Aimed at democratization and standardization, we describe METIS, a modular and versatile active machine learning workflow with a simple online interface for the optimization of biological target functions with minimal experimental datasets. We demonstrate our workflow for various applications, from simple to complex gene circuits and metabolic networks, including several cell-free transcription and translation systems, a &lt;italic&gt;LacI&lt;/italic&gt;-based multi-level controller and a 27-variable synthetic CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-fixation cycle (CETCH cycle). Using METIS, we could improve above systems between one and two orders of magnitude compared to their original setup with minimal experimental efforts. For the CETCH cycle, we explored the combinatorial space of ~10&lt;sup&gt;25&lt;/sup&gt; conditions with only 1,000 experiments to yield the most efficient CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-fixation cascade described to date. Beyond optimization, our workflow also quantifies the relative importance of individual factors to the performance of a system. This allows to identify so far unknown interactions and bottlenecks in complex systems, which paves the way for their hypothesis-driven improvement, which we demonstrate for the &lt;italic&gt;LacI&lt;/italic&gt; multi-level controller that we were able to improve by 34-fold after having identified resource competition as limiting factor. Overall, our workflow opens the way for convenient optimization and prototyping of genetic and metabolic networks with customizable adjustments according to user experience, experimental setup, and laboratory facilities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474323" rel="alternate" title="A versatile active learning workflow for optimization of genetic and metabolic networks (30 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474379</id><title>FastCAT accelerates absolute quantification of proteins by using multiple short non-purified chimeric standards (12 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.651545+00:00</updated><author><name>Ignacy Rzagalinski</name></author><author><name>Aliona Bogdanova</name></author><author><name>Bharath Kumar Raghuraman</name></author><author><name>Eric R. Geertsma</name></author><author><name>Lena Hersemann</name></author><author><name>Tjalf Ziemssen</name></author><author><name>Andrej Shevchenko</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Absolute (molar) quantification of proteins provides the analytical rationale for system-level modelling of diverse molecular mechanisms. FastCAT method employs multiple short (&amp;lt;50 kDa) stable-isotope labeled chimeric proteins (CPs) composed of concatenated quantotypic (Q-) peptides representing the quantified proteins. Each CP also comprises scrambled sequences of reference (R-) peptides that relate its abundance to a single protein standard (BSA). FastCAT not only alleviates the need in purifying CP or using SDS-PAGE, but also improves the accuracy, precision and dynamic range of the absolute quantifications by grouping Q-peptides according to the expected abundance of target proteins. We benchmarked FastCAT against the reference method of MS Western and tested it in the direct molar quantifications of neurological markers in human cerebrospinal fluid at the low ng/mL level.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474379" rel="alternate" title="FastCAT accelerates absolute quantification of proteins by using multiple short non-purified chimeric standards (12 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474474</id><title>A NEUROGENIC GENE EXPRESSION SIGNATURE SUPPORTS HUMAN THERMOGENIC ADIPOSE TISSUE DEVELOPMENT IN VIVO. (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.651961+00:00</updated><author><name>Javier Solivan-Rivera</name></author><author><name>Zinger Yang Loureiro</name></author><author><name>Tiffany DeSouza</name></author><author><name>Anand Desai</name></author><author><name>Qin Yang</name></author><author><name>Raziel Rojas-Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Pantos Skritakis</name></author><author><name>Shannon Joyce</name></author><author><name>Denise Zhong</name></author><author><name>Tammy Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Silvia Corvera</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human beige/brite thermogenic adipose tissue exerts beneficial metabolic effects and may be harnessed to improve metabolic health. To uncover mechanisms by which thermogenic adipose tissue is generated and maintained we developed a species-hybrid model in which human mesenchymal progenitor cells are induced in vitro to differentiate into white or thermogenic adipocytes and are then implanted into immuno-compromised mice. Upon implantation, thermogenic adipocytes form a more densely vascularized and innervated adipose tissue compared to non-thermogenic adipocytes. Mouse endothelial and stem/progenitor cells recruited by implanted human thermogenic adipocytes are also qualitatively different, with differentially expressed genes mapping predominantly to circadian rhythm pathways. We trace the formation of this enhanced neurovascular architecture to higher expression of a distinct set of genes directly associated with neurogenesis (THBS4, TNC, NTRK3 and SPARCL1), and to lower expression of genes associated with neurotransmitter degradation (MAOA, ACHE) by adipocytes in the developed tissue. Further analysis reveals that MAOA is abundant in human adipocytes but absent in mouse adipocytes, revealing species-specific mechanisms of neurotransmitter tone regulation. In summary, our work discovers specific neurogenic genes associated with development and maintenance of human thermogenic adipose tissue,  reveals species-specific mechanisms of control of neurotransmitter tone, and suggests that targeting adipocyte MAOA may be a strategy for enhancing thermogenic adipose tissue activity in humans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474474" rel="alternate" title="A NEUROGENIC GENE EXPRESSION SIGNATURE SUPPORTS HUMAN THERMOGENIC ADIPOSE TISSUE DEVELOPMENT IN VIVO. (11 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.31.474679</id><title>PlasmidMaker: a Versatile, Automated, and High Throughput End-to-End Platform for Plasmid Construction (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.652486+00:00</updated><author><name>Behnam Enghiad</name></author><author><name>Pu Xue</name></author><author><name>Nilmani Singh</name></author><author><name>Aashutosh Girish Boob</name></author><author><name>Chengyou Shi</name></author><author><name>Vassily Andrew Petrov</name></author><author><name>Roy Liu</name></author><author><name>Siddhartha Suryanarayana Peri</name></author><author><name>Stephan Thomas Lane</name></author><author><name>Emily Danielle Gaither</name></author><author><name>Huimin Zhao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Plasmids are used extensively in basic and applied biology. However, design and construction of plasmids, specifically the ones carrying complex genetic information, remains one of the most time-consuming, labor-intensive, and rate-limiting steps in performing sophisticated biological experiments. Here, we report the development of a versatile, robust, automated end-to-end platform named PlasmidMaker that allows error-free construction of plasmids with virtually any sequences in a high-throughput manner. This platform consists of a most versatile DNA assembly method using Pyrococcus furiosus Argonaute (PfAgo)-based artificial restriction enzymes, a user-friendly frontend for plasmid design, and a backend that streamlines the workflow and integration with a robotic system. As a proof of concept, we used this platform to generate 101 plasmids from six different species ranging from 5 to 18 kb in size from up to 11 DNA fragments within 3 days. PlasmidMaker should greatly expand the potential of synthetic biology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.31.474679" rel="alternate" title="PlasmidMaker: a Versatile, Automated, and High Throughput End-to-End Platform for Plasmid Construction (8 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2022-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.27.474252</id><title>Dichotomous Feedback: A Signal Sequestration-based Feedback Mechanism for Biocontroller Design (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.653303+00:00</updated><author><name>Aivar Sootla</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Delalez</name></author><author><name>Emmanouil Alexis</name></author><author><name>Arthur Norman</name></author><author><name>Harrison Steel</name></author><author><name>George Wadhams</name></author><author><name>Antonis Papachristodoulou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We introduce a new design framework for implementing negative feedback regulation in Synthetic Biology, which we term "dichotomous feedback". Our approach is different from current methods, in that it sequesters existing fluxes in the process to be controlled, and in this way takes advantage of the process's architecture to design the control law. This signal sequestration mechanism appears in many natural biological systems and can potentially be easier to realise than 'molecular sequestration' and other comparison motifs that are nowadays common in biomolecular feedback control design. The loop is closed by linking the strength of signal sequestration to the process output. Our feedback regulation mechanism is motivated by two-component signalling systems, where we introduce a second response regulator competing with the natural response regulator thus sequestering kinase activity. Here, dichotomous feedback is established by increasing the concentration of the second response regulator as the level of the output of the natural process increases. Extensive analysis demonstrates how this type of feedback shapes the signal response, attenuates intrinsic noise while increasing robustness and reducing crosstalk.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.27.474252" rel="alternate" title="Dichotomous Feedback: A Signal Sequestration-based Feedback Mechanism for Biocontroller Design (7 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474375</id><title>Introducing a New Bond-Forming Activity in an Archaeal DNA Polymerase by Structure-Guided Enzyme Redesign (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.653983+00:00</updated><author><name>Tushar Aggarwal</name></author><author><name>William A Hansen</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Hong</name></author><author><name>Abir Ganguly</name></author><author><name>Darrin M York</name></author><author><name>Sagar D Khare</name></author><author><name>Enver C Izgu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;DNA polymerases have evolved to feature a highly conserved activity across the tree of life: formation of, without exception, phosphodiester linkages that create the repeating sugar-phosphate backbone of DNA. Can this linkage selectivity observed in nature be overcome by design to produce non-natural nucleic acids? Here, we report that structure-guided redesign of an archaeal DNA polymerase (9°N) enables a new polymerase activity that is undetectable in the wild type enzyme: catalyzing the formation of N3′→P5′ phosphoramidate linkages in the presence of 3′-amino-2′,3′-dideoxynucleoside 5′-triphosphate (3′-NH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-ddNTP) building blocks. Replacing a highly conserved metal-binding aspartate in the 9°N active site (Asp-404) with asparagine was key to the emergence of this unnatural enzyme activity. Molecular dynamics simulations provided insights into how a single substitution could enhance the productive positioning of the 3′-amino nucleophile in the active site. Further remodeling of the protein-nucleic acid interface with substitutions in the finger subdomain led to a quadruple-mutant variant (9°N-NRQS) that incorporated 3′-NH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-ddNTPs into a 3′-amino-primer on various DNA templates. This work presents the first example of an active-site substitution of a metal-binding residue that leads to a novel activity in a DNA polymerase, and sheds light on the molecular basis of substrate fidelity and latent promiscuity in enzymes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474375" rel="alternate" title="Introducing a New Bond-Forming Activity in an Archaeal DNA Polymerase by Structure-Guided Enzyme Redesign (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474508</id><title>Sequestration of histidine kinases by non-cognate response regulators establishes a threshold level of stimulation for bacterial two-component signaling (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.654548+00:00</updated><author><name>Gaurav D Sankhe</name></author><author><name>Rubesh Raja</name></author><author><name>Narendra M Dixit</name></author><author><name>Deepak Kumar Saini</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Two-component signaling systems (TCSs) in bacteria are often positively auto-regulated, where the histidine kinase (HK) and response regulator (RR) proteins comprising a TCS are expressed downstream of the signal they transduce. This auto-regulation improves the sensitivity of the TCS to stimuli and amplifies adaptive responses. The downside, however, is that the TCS may mount disproportionately large responses to weak or fleeting signals. How bacteria prevent such disproportionate responses is not known. Here, we show that sequestration of phosphorylated HKs by non-cognate RRs serves as a design to prevent such disproportionate responses. Using TCSs of M. tuberculosis as model systems, we found that with every one of the five HKs we studied, there was at least one non-cognate RR with higher affinity than that of the cognate RR for the HK. Phosphorylated HKs would thus preferentially bind the non-cognate RRs, suppressing signal transduction through the cognate pathways, which we demonstrated in vitro. Using mathematical modeling of TCS signaling in vivo, we predicted that this sequestration would introduce a threshold level of stimulation for a significant response, preventing responses to signals below this threshold. Finally, we showed in vivo using tunable expression systems in M. bovis that upregulation of a higher affinity non-cognate RR substantially suppressed the output from the cognate TCS pathway, presenting strong evidence of sequestration by non-cognate RRs as a design to regulate TCS signaling. Blocking this sequestration may be a novel intervention strategy, as it would compromise bacterial fitness by letting it respond unnecessarily to signals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474508" rel="alternate" title="Sequestration of histidine kinases by non-cognate response regulators establishes a threshold level of stimulation for bacterial two-component signaling (4 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474498</id><title>Macrophages break interneuromast cell quiescence by intervening the inhibition of Schwann cells in zebrafish lateral line (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.655312+00:00</updated><author><name>Meng-Ju Lin</name></author><author><name>Chia-Ming Lee</name></author><author><name>Wei-Lin Hsu</name></author><author><name>Bi-Chang Chen</name></author><author><name>Shyh-Jye Lee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the zebrafish lateral line system, interneuromast cells (INCs) between neuromasts are normally kept quiescent by underlying Schwann cells (SWCs). Upon severe injuries that cause the complete loss of an entire NM, INCs can occasionally differentiate into NMs but how they escape from the inhibition by SWCs is still unclear. Using a genetic/chemical method to specifically ablate a neuromast, we found a small portion of larvae can regenerate a new neuromast, but the regeneration was hindered by inhibiting macrophages. We also demonstrated that the inhibition of macrophage can reduce the percentage of tail fin-amputated larvae to regenerate a new NM. By in toto imaging, we further discovered heterogeneities in macrophage behavior and distribution along lateral line. We witnessed the crawling of macrophages in between injured lateral line and SWCs during regeneration and also in between the second primordium and the first mature lateral line during development. It implies that macrophages may physically separate and alleviate the inhibition from pLLn and SWCs to break the quiescence of INCs during regeneration and development in the zebrafish lateral line.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474498" rel="alternate" title="Macrophages break interneuromast cell quiescence by intervening the inhibition of Schwann cells in zebrafish lateral line (4 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.471467</id><title>Engineered chimeras unveil swappable modular features of fatty acid and polyketide synthase acyl carrier proteins (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.655886+00:00</updated><author><name>Yae In Cho</name></author><author><name>Claire L Armstrong</name></author><author><name>Ariana Sulpizio</name></author><author><name>Kofi K Acheampong</name></author><author><name>Kameron N Banks</name></author><author><name>Oishi Bardhan</name></author><author><name>Sydney J Churchill</name></author><author><name>Annie E Connolly-Sporing</name></author><author><name>Callie E.W. Crawford</name></author><author><name>Peter L Cruz Parrilla</name></author><author><name>Sarah M Curtis</name></author><author><name>Lauren M De La Ossa</name></author><author><name>Samuel C Epstein</name></author><author><name>Clara J Farrehi</name></author><author><name>Grayson S Hamrick</name></author><author><name>William J Hillegas</name></author><author><name>Austin Kang</name></author><author><name>Olivia C Laxton</name></author><author><name>Joie Ling</name></author><author><name>Sara M Matsumura</name></author><author><name>Victoria M Marino</name></author><author><name>Shahla H Mukhtar</name></author><author><name>Neel J Shah</name></author><author><name>Casey H Londergan</name></author><author><name>Clyde A Daly</name></author><author><name>Bashkim Kokona</name></author><author><name>Louise K Charkoudian</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The strategic redesign of microbial biosynthetic pathways is a compelling route to access molecules of diverse structure and function in a potentially environmentally sustainable fashion. The promise of this approach hinges on an improved understanding of acyl carrier proteins (ACPs), which serve as central hubs in biosynthetic pathways. These small, flexible proteins mediate the transport of molecular building blocks and intermediates to enzymatic partners that extend and tailor the growing natural products. Past combinatorial biosynthesis efforts have failed due to incompatible ACP-enzyme pairings. Herein we report the design of chimeric ACPs with features of the actinorhodin polyketide synthase ACP (ACT) and of the E. coli fatty acid synthase (FAS) ACP (AcpP). We evaluate the ability of the chimeric ACPs to interact with the E. coli FAS ketosynthase FabF, which represents an interaction essential to building the carbon backbone of the synthase molecular output. Given that AcpP interacts with FabF but ACT does not, we sought to exchange modular features of ACT with AcpP to confer functionality with FabF. The interactions of chimeric ACPs with FabF were interrogated using sedimentation velocity experiments, surface plasmon resonance analyses, mechanism-based crosslinking assays, and molecular dynamics simulations. Results suggest that the residues guiding AcpP-FabF compatibility and ACT-FabF incompatibility may reside in the loop I, α-helix II region. These findings can inform the development of strategic secondary element swaps that expand the enzyme compatibility of ACPs across systems and therefore represent a critical step towards the strategic engineering of unnatural natural products.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.471467" rel="alternate" title="Engineered chimeras unveil swappable modular features of fatty acid and polyketide synthase acyl carrier proteins (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474528</id><title>The effects of protein crowders on small molecule drug diffusion (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.656993+00:00</updated><author><name>Debabrata Dey</name></author><author><name>Ariane Nunes-Alves</name></author><author><name>Rebecca C. Wade</name></author><author><name>Gideon Schreiber</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Crowded environments affect the pharmacokinetics of drug molecules. Here, we investigate how three macromolecular protein crowders, bovine serum albumin, hen egg-white lysozyme and myoglobin, influence the translational diffusion rates and interactions of four low molecular-weight drugs, fluorescein, doxorubicin, glycogen synthase kinase-3 inhibitor SB216763 and quinacrine. Using Fluorescence Recovery After Photo-bleaching in Line mode (Line FRAP), Brownian dynamics simulations and molecular docking, we find that the diffusive behavior of the small molecules is highly affected by self-aggregation, interactions with the proteins, and surface adhesion. Fluorescein diffusion is decreased by protein crowders due to their interactions. On the other hand, for doxorubicin, the presence of protein crowders increases diffusion by reducing surface interactions. SB216763 shows a third scenario, where BSA, but not myoglobin or lysozyme, reduces self-aggregation, resulting in faster diffusion. Quinacrine was the only small molecule whose diffusion was not affected by the presence of protein crowders. The mechanistic insights gained here into the effects of interactions of small molecules with proteins and surfaces on the translational diffusion of small molecules can assist in optimizing the design of compounds for higher mobility and lower occlusion in complex macromolecular environments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474528" rel="alternate" title="The effects of protein crowders on small molecule drug diffusion (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474544</id><title>pixOL: pixel-wise dipole-spread function engineering for simultaneously measuring the 3D orientation and 3D localization of dipole-like emitters (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.657628+00:00</updated><author><name>Tingting Wu</name></author><author><name>Jin Lu</name></author><author><name>Matthew D. Lew</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Interactions between biomolecules are characterized by both where they occur and how they are organized, e.g., the alignment of lipid molecules to form a membrane. However, spatial and angular information are mixed within the image of a fluorescent molecule-the microscopy's dipole spread function (DSF). We demonstrate the pixOL algorithm for simultaneously optimizing all pixels within a phase mask to produce an engineered Green's tensor-the dipole extension of point-spread function engineering. The pixOL DSF achieves optimal precision for measuring simultaneously the 3D orientation and 3D location of a single molecule, i.e., 1.14 degree orientation, 0.24 sr wobble angle, 8.17 nm lateral localization, and 12.21 nm axial localization precisions over an 800-nm depth range using 2500 detected photons. The pixOL microscope accurately and precisely resolves the 3D positions and 3D orientations of Nile red within a spherical supported lipid bilayer, resolving both membrane defects and differences in cholesterol concentration, in 6 dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474544" rel="alternate" title="pixOL: pixel-wise dipole-spread function engineering for simultaneously measuring the 3D orientation and 3D localization of dipole-like emitters (3 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474582</id><title>NETISCE: A Network-Based Tool for Cell Fate Reprogramming (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.658220+00:00</updated><author><name>Lauren Marazzi</name></author><author><name>Milan Shah</name></author><author><name>Shreedula Balakrishnan</name></author><author><name>Ananya Patil</name></author><author><name>Paola Vera-Licona</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The search for effective therapeutic targets in fields like regenerative medicine and cancer research has generated interest in cell fate reprogramming. This cellular reprogramming paradigm can drive cells to a desired target state from any initial state. However, methods for identifying reprogramming targets remain limited for biological systems that lack large sets of experimental data or a dynamical characterization. We present NETISCE, a novel computational tool for identifying cell fate reprogramming targets in static networks. NETISCE identifies reprogramming targets through the innovative use of control theory within a dynamical systems framework. Through validations in studies of cell fate reprogramming from developmental, stem cell, and cancer biology, we show that NETISCE can predict previously identified cell fate reprogramming targets and identify potentially novel combinations of targets. NETISCE extends cell fate reprogramming studies to larger-scale biological networks without the need for full model parameterization and can be implemented by experimental and computational biologists to identify parts of a biological system that are relevant for the desired reprogramming task.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474582" rel="alternate" title="NETISCE: A Network-Based Tool for Cell Fate Reprogramming (3 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>