<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular biochemistry and cell biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-13T12:54:26.672578+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biochemistry_cell-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.05.455304</id><title>Structure of PINK1 reveals autophosphorylation dimer and provides insights into binding to the TOM complex (48 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-13T12:54:26.674291+00:00</updated><author><name>Shafqat Rasool</name></author><author><name>Simon Veyron</name></author><author><name>Naoto Soya</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Eldeeb</name></author><author><name>Gergely L. Lukacs</name></author><author><name>Edward A. Fon</name></author><author><name>Jean-François Trempe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mutations in PINK1 causes autosomal-recessive Parkinson’s disease. Mitochondrial damage results in PINK1 import arrest on the Translocase of the Outer Mitochondrial Membrane (TOM) complex, resulting in the activation of its ubiquitin kinase activity by autophosphorylation and initiation of Parkin-dependent mitochondrial clearance. Herein we report crystal structures of the entire cytosolic domain of insect PINK1. Our structures reveal a dimeric autophosphorylation complex targeting phosphorylation at the invariant Ser205 (human Ser228). The dimer interface requires insert 2, which is unique to PINK1. The structures also reveal how an N-terminal helix binds to the C-terminal extension and provide insights into stabilization of PINK1 on the core TOM complex.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.05.455304" rel="alternate" title="Structure of PINK1 reveals autophosphorylation dimer and provides insights into binding to the TOM complex (48 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.01.454633</id><title>Regulatory perturbations of ribosome allocation results in a trade-off between fast growth and adaptation capacity (32 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-13T12:54:26.674975+00:00</updated><author><name>David Hidalgo</name></author><author><name>César A. Martínez-Ortiz</name></author><author><name>Bernhard O. Palsson</name></author><author><name>José I. Jiménez</name></author><author><name>José Utrilla</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacteria regulate their cellular resource allocation to enable their fast growth-adaptation to a variety of environmental niches. We studied the ribosomal allocation, growth and expression profile of two sets of fast-growing mutants of &lt;italic&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/italic&gt; K-12 MG1655. Mutants with 3 copies of the stronger ribosomal RNA operons grew faster than the wild-type strain in minimal media and show similar phenotype to previously studied &lt;italic&gt;rpoB&lt;/italic&gt; mutants. All of them displayed increased ribosomal content, a longer diauxic shift and a reduced activity of the &lt;italic&gt;aceBAK&lt;/italic&gt; operon, indicative of repressed gluconeogenic pathways. Transcriptomic profiles of fast-growing mutants showed common downregulation of hedging functions and upregulated growth functions. Proteome allocation estimations showed an increase in the growth-related proteome for fast-growing strains, but not an increased cellular budget for recombinant protein production. These results show that two different regulatory perturbations (rRNA promoters or &lt;italic&gt;rpoB&lt;/italic&gt; mutations) increasing ribosomal allocation optimize the proteome for growth with a concomitant fitness cost.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strains with the 3 stronger ribosomal operons grow faster than the wild-type&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fast-growing strains show higher ribosomal content&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Comparison among &lt;italic&gt;rrn&lt;/italic&gt; and RNAP mutants shows commonalities&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fast-growing strains show adaptation trade-offs&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mutant’s proteome is larger and optimized for growth&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.01.454633" rel="alternate" title="Regulatory perturbations of ribosome allocation results in a trade-off between fast growth and adaptation capacity (32 tweets)"/><category term="Systems Biology"/><published>2021-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.02.454837</id><title>Broadening the toolkit for quantitatively evaluating noncanonical amino acid incorporation in yeast (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-13T12:54:26.675516+00:00</updated><author><name>J.T. Stieglitz</name></author><author><name>K.A. Potts</name></author><author><name>J.A. Van Deventer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genetic code expansion is a powerful approach for advancing critical fields such as biological therapeutic discovery. However, the machinery for genetically encoding noncanonical amino acids (ncAAs) is only available in limited plasmid formats, constraining potential applications. In extreme cases, the introduction of two separate plasmids, one containing an orthogonal translation system (OTS) to facilitate ncAA incorporation and a second for expressing a ncAA-containing protein of interest, is not possible due to lack of convenient selection markers. One strategy to circumvent this challenge is to express the OTS and protein of interest from a single vector. For what we believe is the first time in yeast, we describe here several sets of single plasmid systems (SPSs) for performing genetic code manipulation and compare the ncAA incorporation capabilities of these plasmids against the capabilities of previously described dual plasmid systems (DPSs). For both dual fluorescent protein reporters and yeast display reporters tested with multiple OTSs and ncAAs, measured ncAA incorporation efficiencies with SPSs were determined to be equal to or improved relative to efficiencies determined with DPSs. Click chemistry on yeast cells displaying ncAA-containing proteins was also shown to be feasible in both formats, although differences in reactivity between formats suggest the need for caution when using such approaches. Additionally, we investigated whether these reporters would support separation of yeast strains known to exhibit distinct ncAA incorporation efficiencies. Model sorts conducted with mixtures of two strains transformed with the same SPS or DPS led to enrichment of a strain known to support higher efficiency ncAA incorporation, suggesting that these reporters will be suitable for conducting screens for strains exhibiting enhanced ncAA incorporation efficiencies. Overall, our results confirm that SPSs are well-behaved in yeast and provide a convenient alternative to DPSs. In particular, SPSs are expected to be invaluable for conducting high-throughput investigations of the effects of genetic or genomic changes on ncAA incorporation efficiency and, more fundamentally, the eukaryotic translation apparatus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract Figure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="454837v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.02.454837" rel="alternate" title="Broadening the toolkit for quantitatively evaluating noncanonical amino acid incorporation in yeast (10 tweets)"/><category term="Synthetic Biology"/><published>2021-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.06.455369</id><title>Microtubule rescue at midzone edges promotes overlap stability and prevents spindle collapse during anaphase B (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-13T12:54:26.675884+00:00</updated><author><name>Manuel Lera-Ramirez</name></author><author><name>Francois Nedelec</name></author><author><name>Phong T Tran</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During anaphase B, molecular motors slide interpolar microtubules to elongate the mitotic spindle, contributing to the separation of chromosomes. However, sliding of antiparallel microtubules reduces their overlap, which may lead to spindle breakage, unless microtubules grow to compensate sliding. How sliding and growth are coordinated is still poorly understood. In this study, we have used the fission yeast &lt;italic&gt;S. pombe&lt;/italic&gt; to measure microtubule dynamics during anaphase B. We report that the coordination of microtubule growth and sliding relies on promoting rescues at the midzone edges. This makes microtubules stable from pole to midzone, while their distal parts including the plus ends alternate between assembly and disassembly. Consequently, the midzone keeps a constant length throughout anaphase, enabling sustained sliding without the need for a precise regulation of microtubule growth speed. Additionally, we found that in &lt;italic&gt;S. pombe&lt;/italic&gt;, which undergoes closed mitosis, microtubule growth speed decreases when the nuclear membrane wraps around the spindle midzone.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.06.455369" rel="alternate" title="Microtubule rescue at midzone edges promotes overlap stability and prevents spindle collapse during anaphase B (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><published>2021-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.05.455211</id><title>Constructing a warhead of PROTAC with aptamer for tumor-selective degradation of nucleolin (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-13T12:54:26.676243+00:00</updated><author><name>Lin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Ling Li</name></author><author><name>Xia Wang</name></author><author><name>Jing Dai</name></author><author><name>Linglli Zhou</name></author><author><name>Yibin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Tiantian Xie</name></author><author><name>Hui Zhang</name></author><author><name>Tianhuan Peng</name></author><author><name>Xing Sun</name></author><author><name>Hui Li</name></author><author><name>Jing Liu</name></author><author><name>Wencan Wu</name></author><author><name>Mao Ye</name></author><author><name>Weihong Tan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;PROteolysis TArgeting Chimeras (PROTACs) induce targeted protein degradation by hijacking the intracellular ubiquitin proteasome system, thus emerging as a new strategy for drug development. However, although PROTACs are highly efficient for protein degradation, most PROTACs generated lack cell-type selectivity, resulting in potential off-tissue, on-target toxicity. To address this drawback, we herein developed an aptamer-based PROTAC ZL216 using aptamer AS1411 as a targeting ligand for nucleolin, and it showed both excellent serum stability and water solubility. Based on the differential expression of nucleolin on the cell surface, ZL216 can specifically bind to and internalize into breast cancer cells, but not normal breast cells. Furthermore, we revealed that ZL216 promoted the formation of a nucleolin-ZL216-VHL ternary complex in breast cancer cells and potently induced the degradation of nucleolin in vitro and in vivo, thereby inhibiting the proliferation and migration of breast cancer cells. These studies demonstrated the potential of utilizing aptamers to construct PROTACs to achieve the selective degradation of targeted protein in tumor cells and provided a promising strategy for the development of tumor-selective PROTACs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.05.455211" rel="alternate" title="Constructing a warhead of PROTAC with aptamer for tumor-selective degradation of nucleolin (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biochemistry"/><published>2021-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>