<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.848657+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.464285</id><title>Respiratory syncytial virus matrix protein assembles as a lattice with local and extended order that coordinates the position of the fusion glycoprotein (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.849020+00:00</updated><author><name>Bryan S Sibert</name></author><author><name>Joseph Y Kim</name></author><author><name>Jie E Yang</name></author><author><name>Zunlong Ke</name></author><author><name>Christopher C. Stobart</name></author><author><name>Martin M Moore</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth R Wright</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) is a significant cause of respiratory illness in young children and adults worldwide. There is currently no vaccine or targeted antiviral for RSV. RSV is an enveloped, filamentous, negative-strand RNA virus. Individual virions vary in both diameter and length, with an average diameter of ~130 nm and ranging from ~500 nm to over 10 μm in length. The RSV matrix (M) protein is peripherally associated with the interior of the viral membrane. Though the general arrangement of structural proteins within the virion is known, the molecular organization of M and other structural proteins was previously unknown. Here, using whole-cell cryo-electron tomography and sub-tomogram averaging, we show that M is arranged in a packed helical-like lattice of M-dimers ordered at an angle of ~47˚ to the viral long axis. Sub-tomogram averages including F and M indicate that the position of F on the viral surface is correlated with the underlying M lattice. Finally, we report that RSV F is frequently observed as pairs, with the F trimers oriented in an anti-parallel conformation to support potential interaction between trimers. These results provide insight into RSV assembly and virion organization and may aid in the identification and development of RSV vaccines and anti-viral targets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.464285" rel="alternate" title="Respiratory syncytial virus matrix protein assembles as a lattice with local and extended order that coordinates the position of the fusion glycoprotein (13 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464113</id><title>Single-particle cryo-EM structures from iDPC-STEM at near-atomic resolution (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.849247+00:00</updated><author><name>Ivan Lazić</name></author><author><name>Maarten Wirix</name></author><author><name>Max Leo Leidl</name></author><author><name>Felix de Haas</name></author><author><name>Maximilian Beckers</name></author><author><name>Evgeniya V. Pechnikova</name></author><author><name>Knut Müller-Caspary</name></author><author><name>Ricardo Egoavil</name></author><author><name>Eric G.T. Bosch</name></author><author><name>Carsten Sachse</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Electron cryo-microscopy (cryo-EM) is becoming one of the routine tools for structure determination of biological macromolecules. Commonly, molecular images are obtained by conventional transmission electron microcopy (CTEM) using underfocus and subsequently computationally combined into a high-resolution 3D structure. Here, we apply scanning transmission electron microscopy (STEM) using the integrated differential phase contrast mode also known as iDPC-STEM to the cryo-EM test specimen of tobacco mosaic virus (TMV). The micrographs show complete contrast transfer to high resolution and enable the cryo-EM structure determination at 3.5 Å resolution using single-particle based helical reconstruction. A series of cryo-EM TMV maps was resolved at near-atomic resolution taken at different convergence semi-angle (CSA) beams and share identical features with maps obtained by CTEM of a previously acquired same-sized TMV data set. The associated map B-factors from iDPC-STEM match those obtained by CTEM recordings using 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; generation direct electron detection devices. These data show that STEM imaging in general, and in particular the iDPC-STEM approach, can be applied to vitrified single-particle specimens to determine near-atomic resolution cryo-EM structures of biological macromolecules.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464113" rel="alternate" title="Single-particle cryo-EM structures from iDPC-STEM at near-atomic resolution (10 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464058</id><title>Control of protein activity by photoinduced spin polarized charge reorganization (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.849468+00:00</updated><author><name>Shirsendu Ghosh</name></author><author><name>Koyel Banerjee-Ghosh</name></author><author><name>Dorit Levy</name></author><author><name>David Scheerer</name></author><author><name>Inbal Riven</name></author><author><name>Jieun Shin</name></author><author><name>Harry B. Gray</name></author><author><name>Ron Naaman</name></author><author><name>Gilad Haran</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Biomolecules within the living cell are subject to extensive electrical fields, particularly next to membranes. Indeed, a role for bioelectricity has been well established at the organismal level. While the importance of electrostatics in protein functions such as protein-protein association and enzymatic activity has been well documented, very little is known on how biomolecules respond to external electric fields, or in other words, what may be the potential contribution of polarizability to protein function. Here we use phototriggered charge injection from a site-specifically attached ruthenium photosensitizer to directly demonstrate the effects of charge redistribution within a protein. We find that binding of an antibody to phosphoglycerate kinase (PGK) is increased two folds under illumination. Remarkably, illumination is found to suppress the enzymatic activity of PGK by a factor as large as three. These responses are sensitive to the photosensitizer position on the protein. Surprisingly, left (but not right) circularly polarized light elicits these responses, indicating that the electrons involved in the observed dynamics are spin polarized, due to spin filtration by protein chiral structures. Our results directly establish the contribution of electrical polarization and the importance of the spin-dependent charge reorganization in the function of proteins. Future experiments with phototriggered charge injection will allow delineation of charge rearrangement pathways within proteins and will further depict their effects on protein function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464058" rel="alternate" title="Control of protein activity by photoinduced spin polarized charge reorganization (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>