<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.046541+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474952</id><title>Control of bacterial anti-phage signaling by a WYL domain transcription factor (23 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.047069+00:00</updated><author><name>Chelsea L. Blankenchip</name></author><author><name>Justin V. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Rebecca K. Lau</name></author><author><name>Qiaozhen Ye</name></author><author><name>Yajie Gu</name></author><author><name>Kevin D. Corbett</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacteria use diverse immune systems to defend themselves from ubiquitous viruses termed bacteriophages (phages). Many anti-phage systems function by abortive infection to kill a phage-infected cell, raising the question of how these systems are regulated to avoid activation and cell killing outside the context of infection. Here, we identify a transcription factor associated with the widespread CBASS bacterial immune system, that we term CapW. CapW forms a homodimer and binds a palindromic DNA sequence in the CBASS promoter region. Two crystal structures of CapW reveal how the protein switches from a DNA binding-competent state to a ligand-bound state that cannot bind DNA due to misalignment of dimer-related DNA binding domains. We show that CapW strongly represses CBASS gene expression in uninfected cells, and that CapW disruption likely results in toxicity due to uncontrolled CBASS expression. Our results parallel recent findings with BrxR, a transcription factor associated with the BREX anti-phage system, and suggest that CapW and BrxR are the founding members of a family of universal anti-phage signaling proteins.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474952" rel="alternate" title="Control of bacterial anti-phage signaling by a WYL domain transcription factor (23 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474986</id><title>Mobility of nucleosomes is regulated by their binding partners (16 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.047429+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniël P. Melters</name></author><author><name>Keir C. Neuman</name></author><author><name>Tatini Rakshit</name></author><author><name>Yamini Dalal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chromatin accessibility is modulated in a variety of ways, both to create open and closed chromatin states which are critical for eukaryotic gene regulation. At the mechanistic single molecule level, how accessibility is regulated remains a fundamental question in the field. Here, we use single molecule tracking by high-speed atomic force microscopy to investigate this question using chromatin arrays and extend our findings into the nucleus. By high-speed atomic force microscopy, we tracked chromatin dynamics in real time and observed that the essential kinetochore protein CENP-C reduces the diffusion constant of CENP-A nucleosomes and the linker H1.5 protein restricts H3 nucleosome mobility. We subsequently interrogated how CENP-C modulates CENP-A chromatin dynamics &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Overexpressing CENP-C resulted in reduced centromeric transcription and impaired loading of new CENP-A molecules. These data suggest a model in which inner kinetochore proteins are critically involved in modulating chromatin accessibility and consequently, noncoding transcription at human centromeres.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474986" rel="alternate" title="Mobility of nucleosomes is regulated by their binding partners (16 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.474995</id><title>Cryo-EM structure of human somatostatin receptor 2 complex with its agonist somatostatin delineates the ligand binding specificity (12 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.047771+00:00</updated><author><name>Yunseok Heo</name></author><author><name>Eojin Yoon</name></author><author><name>Ye-Eun Jeon</name></author><author><name>Ji-Hye Yun</name></author><author><name>Naito Ishimoto</name></author><author><name>Hyeonuk Woo</name></author><author><name>Sam-Yong Park</name></author><author><name>Ji-Joon Song</name></author><author><name>Weontae Lee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Somatostatin is a peptide hormone regulating endocrine systems through binding to G-protein-coupled somatostatin receptors. somatostatin receptor 2 (SSTR2) is one of the human somatostatin receptors and highly implicated in cancers and neurological disorders. Here, we report the high resolution cryo-EM structure of full-length human SSTR2 bound to the agonist somatostatin (SST-14) complex with inhibitory G (G&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;) proteins. Our structure shows that seven transmembrane helices form a deep pocket for ligand binding and that the highly conserved Trp-Lys motif of SST-14 positions at the bottom of the pocket. Furthermore, our sequence analysis combined with AlphaFold modeled structures of other SSTR isoforms provide how SSTR family proteins specifically interact with their cognate ligands. This work provides the first glimpse into the molecular recognition of somatostatin receptor and crucial resource to develop therapeutics targeting somatostatin receptors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.474995" rel="alternate" title="Cryo-EM structure of human somatostatin receptor 2 complex with its agonist somatostatin delineates the ligand binding specificity (12 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475120</id><title>Nanometer-Resolution Long-term Tracking of Single Cargos Reveals Dynein Motor Mechanisms (12 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.048236+00:00</updated><author><name>Chunte Sam Peng</name></author><author><name>Yunxiang Zhang</name></author><author><name>Qian Liu</name></author><author><name>G. Edward Marti</name></author><author><name>Yu-Wen Alvin Huang</name></author><author><name>Thomas C. Südhof</name></author><author><name>Bianxiao Cui</name></author><author><name>Steven Chu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cytoplasmic dynein is essential for intracellular transport, but because of its complexity, we still do not fully understand how this 1.5 megadalton protein works. Here, we used novel optical probes that enable single-particle tracking (SPT) of individual cargos transported by dynein motors in live neurons over 900 &lt;italic&gt;μm&lt;/italic&gt;. Analyses using the Fluctuation Theorem (FT) showed that the number of dynein molecules switches between 1-5 motors during the transport. Clearly resolved single-molecular steps revealed that the dwell times between individual steps were accurately described by an enzymatic cycle dominated by two equal and thermally-activated rate constants. Based on these data, we propose a new molecular model whereby each step requires the hydrolysis of 2 ATPs. The model is consistent with extensive structural, single-molecule and biochemical measurements.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475120" rel="alternate" title="Nanometer-Resolution Long-term Tracking of Single Cargos Reveals Dynein Motor Mechanisms (12 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474893</id><title>Theoretical model of efficient phagocytosis driven by curved membrane proteins and active cytoskeleton forces (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.048505+00:00</updated><author><name>Raj Kumar Sadhu</name></author><author><name>Sarah R. Barger</name></author><author><name>Samo Penic</name></author><author><name>Ales Iglic</name></author><author><name>Mira Krendel</name></author><author><name>Nils Gauthier</name></author><author><name>Nir Gov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Phagocytosis is the process of engulfment and internalization of comparatively large particles by the cell, that plays a central role in the functioning of our immune system. We study the process of phagocytosis by considering a simplified coarse grained model of a three-dimensional vesicle, having uniform adhesion interaction with a rigid particle, in the presence of curved membrane proteins and active cytoskeletal forces. Complete engulfment is achieved when the bending energy cost of the vesicle is balanced by the gain in the adhesion energy. The presence of curved (convex) proteins reduces the bending energy cost by self-organizing with higher density at the highly curved leading edge of the engulfing membrane, which forms the circular rim of the phagocytic cup that wraps around the particle. This allows the engulfment to occur at much smaller adhesion strength. When the curved proteins exert outwards protrusive forces, representing actin polymerization, at the leading edge, we find that engulfment is achieved more quickly and at lower protein density. We consider spherical as well as non-spherical particles, and find that non-spherical particles are more difficult to engulf in comparison to the spherical particles of the same surface area. For non-spherical particles, the engulfment time crucially depends upon the initial orientation of the particles with respect to the vesicle. Our model offers a mechanism for the spontaneous self-organization of the actin cytoskeleton at the phagocytic cup, in good agreement with recent high-resolution experimental observations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474893" rel="alternate" title="Theoretical model of efficient phagocytosis driven by curved membrane proteins and active cytoskeleton forces (10 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474796</id><title>Structure-function-dynamics relationships in the peculiar Planktothrix PCC7805 OCP1: impact of his-tagging and carotenoid type. (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.048755+00:00</updated><author><name>Adjele Wilson</name></author><author><name>Elena A. Andreeva</name></author><author><name>Stanislaw Nizinski</name></author><author><name>Lea Talbot</name></author><author><name>Elisabeth Hartmann</name></author><author><name>Ilme Schlichting</name></author><author><name>Gotard Burdzinski</name></author><author><name>Michel Sliwa</name></author><author><name>Diana KIRILOVSKY</name></author><author><name>Jacques-Philippe Colletier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The orange carotenoid protein (OCP) is a photoactive protein involved in cyanobacterial photoprotection. Here, we report on the functional, spectral and structural characteristics of the peculiar Planktothrix PCC7805 OCP (Plankto-OCP). We show that this OCP variant is characterized by higher photoactivation and recovery rates, and a stronger energy-quenching activity, compared to other OCPs studied thus far. We characterize the effect of the functionalizing carotenoid and of his-tagging on these reactions, and the time scales on which these modifications affect photoactivation. The presence of a His-tag at the C-terminus has a large influence on photoactivation, thermal recovery and PBS-fluorescence quenching, and likewise for the nature of the carotenoid that additionally affects the yield and characteristics of excited states and the ns-s dynamics of photoactivated OCP. By solving the structures of Plankto-OCP in the ECN- and CAN-functionalized states, each in two closely-related crystal forms, we further unveil the molecular breathing motions that animate Plankto-OCP at the monomer and dimer levels. We finally discuss the structural changes that could explain the peculiar properties of Plankto-OCP.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474796" rel="alternate" title="Structure-function-dynamics relationships in the peculiar Planktothrix PCC7805 OCP1: impact of his-tagging and carotenoid type. (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474911</id><title>Front propagation and arrival times in networks with application to neurodegenerative diseases (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.049310+00:00</updated><author><name>Prama Setia Putra</name></author><author><name>Hadrien Oliveri</name></author><author><name>Travis B Thompson</name></author><author><name>Alain Goriely</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many physical, epidemiological, or physiological dynamical processes on networks support front-like propagation, where an initial localized perturbation grows and systematically invades all nodes in the network. A key question is then to extract estimates for the dynamics. In particular, if a single node is seeded at a small concentration, when will other nodes reach the same initial concentration? Here, motivated by the study of toxic protein propagation in neurodegenerative diseases, we present and compare three different estimates for the arrival time in order of increasing analytical complexity: the linear arrival time, obtained by linearizing the underlying system; the Lambert time, obtained by considering the interaction of two nodes;  and the nonlinear arrival time, obtained by asymptotic techniques. We use the classic Fisher-Kolmogorov-Petrovsky-Piskunov equation as a paradigm for the dynamics and show that each method provides  different insight and time estimates. Further, we show that the nonlinear asymptotic method also gives an approximate solution valid in the entire domain and the correct ordering of arrival regions over large regions of parameters and initial conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474911" rel="alternate" title="Front propagation and arrival times in networks with application to neurodegenerative diseases (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475267</id><title>Stimulating the sir2-pgc-1α axis rescues exercise capacity and mitochondrial respiration in Drosophila tafazzin mutants. (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.049741+00:00</updated><author><name>Deena Damschroder</name></author><author><name>Rubén Zapata-Pérez</name></author><author><name>Riekelt H. Houtkooper</name></author><author><name>Robert Wessells</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cardiolipin (CL) is a phospholipid required for proper mitochondrial function. Tafazzin remodels CL to create highly unsaturated fatty acid chains. However, when tafazzin is mutated, CL remodeling is impeded, leading to mitochondrial dysfunction and the disease Barth syndrome. Patients with Barth syndrome often have severe exercise intolerance, which negatively impacts their overall quality of life. Boosting NAD+ levels can improve symptoms of other mitochondrial diseases, but its effect in the context of Barth syndrome has not been examined. We demonstrate for the first time that nicotinamide riboside (NR) can rescue exercise tolerance and mitochondrial respiration in a Drosophila tafazzin mutant and that the beneficial effects are dependent on sir2 and pgc-1α . Overexpressing pgc-1α increased the total abundance of cardiolipin in mutants. In addition, muscles and neurons were identified as key targets for future therapies because sir2 or pgc-1α overexpression in either of these tissues is sufficient to restore the exercise capacity of Drosophila tafazzin mutants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475267" rel="alternate" title="Stimulating the sir2-pgc-1α axis rescues exercise capacity and mitochondrial respiration in Drosophila tafazzin mutants. (4 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.07.475334</id><title>Resolving Protein Conformational Plasticity and Substrate Binding Through the Lens of Machine-Learning (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.050321+00:00</updated><author><name>Navjeet Ahalawat</name></author><author><name>Jagannath Mondal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A long-standing target in elucidating the biomolecular recognition process is the identification of  binding-competent conformations of the receptor protein. However, protein conformational plasticity and the stochastic nature of the recognition processes often preclude the assignment of a specific protein conformation to an individual ligand-bound pose. In particular, we consider multi-microsecond long Molecular dynamics simulation trajectories of ligand recognition process in solvent-inaccessible cavity of two archtypal systems: L99A mutant of T4 Lysozyme and Cytochrome P450. We first show that if the substrate-recognition occurs via long-lived intermediate, the protein conformations can be automatically classified into substrate-bound and unbound state through an unsupervised dimensionality reduction technique. On the contrary, if the recognition process is mediated by selection of transient protein conformation by the ligand,  a clear correspondence between protein conformation and binding-competent macrostates can only be established via a combination of supervised machine learning (ML) and unsupervised dimension reduction approach.
  In such scenario, we demonstrate that  a priori random forest based supervised classification of the simulated trajectories  recognition process would help characterize key amino-acid residue-pairs of the protein that are deemed sensitive for ligand binding. A subsequent unsupervised dimensional reduction via  time-lagged independent component analysis of the selected residue-pairs would delineate a conformational landscape of protein which is able to demarcate ligand-bound pose from the unbound ones. As a key breakthrough, the ML-based protocol would identify distal protein locations which would be allosterically important for ligand binding and characterise their roles in recognition pathways.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.07.475334" rel="alternate" title="Resolving Protein Conformational Plasticity and Substrate Binding Through the Lens of Machine-Learning (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2022-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475229</id><title>Development and Validation of Fluorinated Amino Acid Parameters for use with the AMBER ff15ipq Protein Force Field (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.050652+00:00</updated><author><name>Darian Yang</name></author><author><name>Angela Gronenborn</name></author><author><name>Lillian Chong</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We developed force field parameters for fluorinated aromatic amino acids enabling molecular dynamics (MD) simulations of fluorinated proteins. These parameters are tailored to the AMBER ff15ipq protein force field and enable the modeling of 4, 5, 6, and 7F-tryptophan, 3F- and 3,5F-tyrosine, and 4F- or 4-CF3-phenylalanine. The parameters include 181 unique atomic charges derived using the Implicitly Polarized Charge (IPolQ) scheme in the presence of SPC/Eb explicit water molecules and 9 unique bond, angle, or torsion terms. Our simulations of benchmark peptides and proteins maintain expected conformational propensities on the μs-timescale. In addition, we have developed an open-source Python program to calculate fluorine relaxation rates from MD simulations. The extracted relaxation rates from protein simulations are in good agreement with experimental values determined by 19F NMR. Collectively, our results illustrate the power and robustness of the IPolQ lineage of force fields for modeling structure and dynamics of fluorine containing proteins at the atomic level.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475229" rel="alternate" title="Development and Validation of Fluorinated Amino Acid Parameters for use with the AMBER ff15ipq Protein Force Field (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>