<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.271521+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472242</id><title>Dynamics of CTCF and cohesin mediated chromatin looping revealed by live-cell imaging (291 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.271860+00:00</updated><author><name>Michele Gabriele</name></author><author><name>Hugo B. Brandão</name></author><author><name>Simon Grosse-Holz</name></author><author><name>Asmita Jha</name></author><author><name>Gina M. Dailey</name></author><author><name>Claudia Cattoglio</name></author><author><name>Tsung-Han S. Hsieh</name></author><author><name>Leonid Mirny</name></author><author><name>Christoph Zechner</name></author><author><name>Anders S. Hansen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Animal genomes are folded into loops and topologically associating domains (TADs) by CTCF and cohesin, but whether these loops are stable or dynamic is unknown. Here, we directly visualize chromatin looping at the &lt;italic&gt;Fbn2&lt;/italic&gt; TAD in mouse embryonic stem cells using super-resolution live-cell imaging and quantify looping dynamics by Bayesian inference. Our results are consistent with cohesin-mediated loop extrusion in cells, and with CTCF both stopping and stabilizing cohesin. Surprisingly, the &lt;italic&gt;Fbn2&lt;/italic&gt; loop is both rare and dynamic, with a looped fraction of ~3-6.5% and a median loop lifetime of ~10-30 minutes. Instead of a stable loop, our results establish a highly dynamic view of TADs and loops where the &lt;italic&gt;Fbn2&lt;/italic&gt; TAD exists predominantly in a partially extruded conformation. This dynamic and quantitative view of TADs may facilitate a mechanistic understanding of their functions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472242" rel="alternate" title="Dynamics of CTCF and cohesin mediated chromatin looping revealed by live-cell imaging (291 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472146</id><title>AutoMicroED: A semi-automated MicroED processing pipeline (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.272089+00:00</updated><author><name>Samantha M Powell</name></author><author><name>Irina V Novikova</name></author><author><name>Doo Nam Kim</name></author><author><name>James E Evans</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite rapid adaptation of micro-electron diffraction (MicroED) for protein and small molecule structure determination to sub-angstrom resolution, the lack of automation tools for easy MicroED data processing remains a challenge for expanding to the broader scientific community. In particular, automation tools, which are novice user friendly, compatible with heterogenous datasets and can be run in unison with data collection to judge the quality of incoming data (similar to cryosparc LIVE for single particle cryoEM) do not exist. Here, we present AutoMicroED, a cohesive and semi-automatic MicroED data processing pipeline that runs through image conversion, indexing, integration and scaling of data, followed by merging of successful datasets that are pushed through phasing and final structure determination. AutoMicroED is compatible with both small molecule and protein datasets and creates a straightforward and reproducible method to solve single structures from pure samples, or multiple structures from mixed populations. The immediate feedback on data quality, data completeness and more parameters, aids users to identify whether they have collected enough data for their needs. Overall, AutoMicroED permits efficient structure elucidation for both novice and experienced users with comparable results to more laborious manual processing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472146" rel="alternate" title="AutoMicroED: A semi-automated MicroED processing pipeline (17 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472254</id><title>Individualized isometric neuromuscular electrical stimulation training promotes myonuclear accretion in mouse skeletal muscle (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.272232+00:00</updated><author><name>Aliki Zavoriti</name></author><author><name>Aurélie Fessard</name></author><author><name>Masoud Rahmati</name></author><author><name>Peggy Del Carmine</name></author><author><name>Bénédicte Chazaud</name></author><author><name>Julien Gondin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Skeletal muscle is a plastic tissue that adapts to exercise through fusion of muscle stem cells (MuSCs) with myofibers, a physiological process referred to as myonuclear accretion. However, it is still unclear whether myonuclear accretion is driven by increased mechanical loading &lt;italic&gt;per se&lt;/italic&gt;, or occurs, at least in part, in response to exercise-induced muscle injury. Here, we developed a carefully monitored and individualized neuromuscular electrical stimulation (NMES) training protocol of the mouse plantar flexor muscles. Each NMES training session consisted of 80 isometric contractions at a submaximal mechanical intensity corresponding to ~ 15% of maximal tetanic force to avoid muscle damage. NMES trained mice were stimulated for 2 × 3 consecutive days separated by one day of rest, for a total of 6 sessions. Experiments were conducted on C57BL/6J and BALB/c males at 10-12 weeks of age. NMES led to a robust myonuclear accretion and higher MuSC content in &lt;italic&gt;gastrocnemius&lt;/italic&gt; muscle of both mouse lines, without overt signs of muscle damage/regeneration or muscle hypertrophy or force improvement. This new mouse model of myonuclear accretion relying on the main function of skeletal muscles, &lt;italic&gt;i.e.&lt;/italic&gt;, force production in response to electrical stimuli, will be of utmost interest to further understand the role of MuSCs in skeletal muscle adaptations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472254" rel="alternate" title="Individualized isometric neuromuscular electrical stimulation training promotes myonuclear accretion in mouse skeletal muscle (13 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473088</id><title>Structural, functional and computational studies of membrane recognition by Plasmodium Perforin-Like Proteins 1 and 2. (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.272386+00:00</updated><author><name>Sophie Williams</name></author><author><name>Xiulian Yu</name></author><author><name>Tao Ni</name></author><author><name>Robert Gilbert</name></author><author><name>Phillip Stansfeld</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Perforin-like proteins (PLPs) play key roles in the mechanisms associated with parasitic disease caused by apicomplexans such as  Plasmodium  (malaria) and Toxoplasma. The  T. gondii  PLP1 (TgPLP1) mediates tachyzoite egress from cells, while the five  Plasmodium  PLPs carry out various roles in the life cycle of the parasite and with respect to the molecular basis of disease. Here we focus on  Plasmodium vivax  PLP1 and PLP2 (PvPLP1 and PvPLP2) compared to TgPLP1; PvPLP1 is important for invasion of mammalian hosts by the parasite and establishment of a chronic infection, PvPLP2 is important during the symptomatic blood stage of the parasite life cycle. Determination of the crystal structure of the membrane-binding APCβ domain of PvPLP1 reveals notable differences with that of TgPLP1, which are reflected in its inability to bind lipid bilayers in the way that TgPLP1 and PvPLP2 can be shown to. Molecular dynamics simulations combined with site-directed mutagenesis and functional assays allow a dissection of the binding interactions of TgPLP1 and PvPLP2 on lipid bilayers, and reveal a similar tropism for lipids found enriched in the inner leaflet of the mammalian plasma membrane. In addition to this shared mode of membrane binding PvPLP2 displays a secondary synergistic interaction side-on from its principal bilayer interface. This study underlines the substantial differences between the biophysical properties of the APCβ domains of Apicomplexan PLPs, which reflect their significant sequence diversity. Such differences will be important factors in determining the cell targeting and membrane-binding activity of the different proteins, in their different developmental roles within parasite life cycles.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473088" rel="alternate" title="Structural, functional and computational studies of membrane recognition by Plasmodium Perforin-Like Proteins 1 and 2. (9 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472369</id><title>Single-molecule sizing through nano-cavity confinement (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.272530+00:00</updated><author><name>Raphael P. B. Jacquat</name></author><author><name>Georg Krainer</name></author><author><name>Quentin Peter</name></author><author><name>Ali Nawaz Babar</name></author><author><name>Oliver Vanderpoorten</name></author><author><name>Catherine K. Xu</name></author><author><name>Clemens F. Kaminski</name></author><author><name>Ulrich F. Keyser</name></author><author><name>Jeremy J. Baumberg</name></author><author><name>Tuomas P. J. Knowles</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;An approach relying on nano-cavity confinement is developed in this paper for the sizing of nanoscale particles and single biomolecules in solution. The approach, termed nano-cavity diffusional sizing (NDS), measures particle residence times within fluidic nano-cavities to determine their hydrodynamic radii. Using theoretical modelling and simulation, we show that the residence time of particles within nano-cavities above a critical timescale depends on the diffusion coefficient of the particle, which allows estimation of the particle’s size. We demonstrate this approach experimentally through measurement of particle residence times within nano-fluidic cavities using single-molecule confocal microscopy. Our data show that the residence times scale linearly with the sizes of nanoscale colloids, protein aggregates and single DNA oligonucleotides. NDS thus constitutes a new single molecule optofluidic approach that allows rapid and quantitative sizing of nanoscale objects for potential application in nanobiotechnology, biophysics, and clinical diagnostics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472369" rel="alternate" title="Single-molecule sizing through nano-cavity confinement (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473004</id><title>Galvanotaxis of ciliates: Spatiotemporal dynamics of Coleps hirtus under electric fields (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.272704+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna Daul</name></author><author><name>Marie-Louise Lemloh</name></author><author><name>Marcel Hörning</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Galvanotaxis describes the functional response of organisms to electric fields. In ciliates, the electric field influences the electrophysiology and thus the cilia beat dynamics. This leads to a change of the swimming direction towards the cathode. The dynamical response to electric fields of Coleps hirtus has not been studied since the observations of Verworn in 1890 (1). While galvanotaxis has been studied in other cilitates, C. hirtus exhibit properties not found elsewhere, such as biomineralization-processes of alveolar plates with impact on the intracellular calcium regulation and a bimodal resting membrane potential, which leads unique electrophysiological driven bimodal swimming dynamics. Here, we statistically analyze the galvanotactic dynamics of C. hirtus by automated cell tracking routines. We found that the number of cells that show a galvanotactic response, increases with the increase of the applied electric field strength with a mean at about 2.1 V/cm. The spatiotemporal swimming dynamics change and lead to a statistical increase of linear elongated cell trajectories that point toward the cathode. Further, the increase of the electric fields decreases the mean velocity variance for electric fields larger than about 1.3 V/cm, while showing no significant change in the absolute velocity for any applied electric field. Fully functional galvanotactic responses were observed at a minimum extracellular calcium concentration of 20 μM. The results add important insights to the current understanding of cellular dynamics of ciliates and suggest that the currently accepted model lags the inclusion of the swimming dynamics and the complex calcium regulatory system of the cell. The results of this study do not only extend the fundamental understanding of C. hirtus dynamics, but also open possibilities for technical applications, such as biosensors or microrobots in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473004" rel="alternate" title="Galvanotaxis of ciliates: Spatiotemporal dynamics of Coleps hirtus under electric fields (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472453</id><title>Physical model of electrical synapses in a neural network (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.272837+00:00</updated><author><name>M. Pekker</name></author><author><name>M.N. Shneider</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A theoretical model of electrical synapses is proposed, in which connexons play the role of “nails” that hold unmyelinated areas of neurons at a distance of about 3.5 nm, and the electrical connection between them is provided by charging the membrane of an inactive neuron with currents generated in the intercellular electrolyte (saline) by the action potential in the active neuron. This mechanism is similar to the salutatory conduction of the action potential between the nodes of Ranvier in myelinated axons and the ephaptic coupling of sufficiently close spaced neurons.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472453" rel="alternate" title="Physical model of electrical synapses in a neural network (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472795</id><title>Inferring the DNA replication origin density landscape in human cells from replication timing and fork directionality data (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.272959+00:00</updated><author><name>Jean-Michel Arbona</name></author><author><name>Hadi Kabalane</name></author><author><name>Arach Goldar</name></author><author><name>Olivier Hyrien</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Audit</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The determinants of the locations and firing times of the multiple replication origins are still elusive in human and other metazoan organisms. Experiments can independently profile mean replication timing (MRT) and replication fork directionality (RFD) genome-wide. In the hypothesis of a constant replication fork speed, MRT and RFD are related to each other by an analytical formula so are a priori equivalent. However, we show here that experimental noises result in MRT and RFD profiles containing information at different spatial frequencies. We further demonstrate that one can compute an origin density landscape that, when inserted in an appropriate simulation framework, jointly predicts experimental MRT and RFD profiles with an unprecedented precision. We also extract an analytical formula linking intrinsic origin efficiency with observed origin efficiency and MRT. We then compare the computed origin density landscape with experimental distributions of potential origins (ORC, MCM) or actual initiation events (Bubble-seq, SNS-seq, OK-seq). The results indicate that MRT and RFD data are highly consistent with each other, that our simple model suffices to capture the replication dynamics during S phase given an appropriate initiation probability landscape, but that the density of potential origins is not the sole determinant of this landscape.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472795" rel="alternate" title="Inferring the DNA replication origin density landscape in human cells from replication timing and fork directionality data (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472676</id><title>Discrete LAT condensates encode antigen information from single pMHC:TCR binding events (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.273099+00:00</updated><author><name>Darren B. McAffee</name></author><author><name>Mark K. O'Dair</name></author><author><name>Jenny J. Lin</name></author><author><name>Shalini T. Low-Nam</name></author><author><name>Kiera B. Wilhelm</name></author><author><name>Sungi Kim</name></author><author><name>Shumpei Morita</name></author><author><name>Jay T. Groves</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;LAT assembly into a two-dimensional protein condensate is a prominent feature of antigen discrimination by T cells.  Here, we use single-molecule imaging techniques to resolve the spatial position and temporal duration of each pMHC:TCR molecular binding event while simultaneously monitoring LAT condensation at the membrane. An individual binding event is sufficient to trigger a LAT condensate, which is self-limiting, and neither its size nor lifetime is correlated with the duration of the originating pMHC:TCR binding event.  Only the probability of the LAT condensate forming is related to the pMHC:TCR binding dwell time.  LAT condenses abruptly, but after an extended delay from the originating binding event.  A LAT mutation that facilitates phosphorylation at the PLC-γ1 recruitment site shortens the delay time to LAT condensation and alters T cell antigen specificity.  These results identify a role for the LAT protein condensation phase transition in setting antigen discrimination thresholds in T cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472676" rel="alternate" title="Discrete LAT condensates encode antigen information from single pMHC:TCR binding events (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>