<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.475615+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466120</id><title>Risk-utility tradeoff shapes memory strategies for evolving patterns (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.476962+00:00</updated><author><name>Oskar H Schnaack</name></author><author><name>Luca Peliti</name></author><author><name>Armita Nourmohammad</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Keeping a memory of evolving stimuli is ubiquitous in biology, an example of which is immune memory for evolving pathogens. However, learning and memory storage for dynamic patterns still pose challenges in machine learning. Here, we introduce an analytical energy-based framework to address this problem. By accounting for the tradeoff between utility in keeping a high-affinity memory and the risk in forgetting some of the diverse stimuli, we show that a moderate tolerance for risk enables a repertoire to robustly classify evolving patterns, without much fine tuning. Our approach offers a general guideline for learning and memory storage in systems interacting with diverse and evolving signals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466120" rel="alternate" title="Risk-utility tradeoff shapes memory strategies for evolving patterns (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466246</id><title>Detecting ice artefacts in processed macromolecular diffraction data with machine learning (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.482980+00:00</updated><author><name>Kristopher Nolte</name></author><author><name>Yunyun Gao</name></author><author><name>Sabrina Staeb</name></author><author><name>Philip Kollmansberger</name></author><author><name>Andrea Thorn</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Contamination with diffraction from ice crystals can negatively affect, or even impede macromolecular structure determination and therefore, detecting the resulting artefacts in diffraction data is crucial. However, once the data have been processed, it can be very difficult to automatically recognize this problem. To address this, a set of convolutional neural networks named Helcaraxe has been developed which can detect ice diffraction artefacts in processed diffraction data from macromolecular crystals. The networks outperform previous algorithms and will be available as part of the AUSPEX webserver and CCP4-distributed software.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466246" rel="alternate" title="Detecting ice artefacts in processed macromolecular diffraction data with machine learning (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465985</id><title>Ligand-induced unfolding mechanism of an RNA G-quadruplex (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.484579+00:00</updated><author><name>Susanta Haldar</name></author><author><name>Yashu Zhang</name></author><author><name>Ying Xia</name></author><author><name>Barira Islam</name></author><author><name>Sisi Liu</name></author><author><name>Francesco L Gervasio</name></author><author><name>Adrian J. Mulholland</name></author><author><name>Zoë A. E. Waller</name></author><author><name>Dengguo Wei</name></author><author><name>Shozeb Haider</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The cationic porphyrin, TMPyP4, is a well-established DNA G-quadruplex (G4) binding ligand that can stabilize different topologies via multiple binding modes. However, TMPyP4 has completely opposite destabilizing and unwinding effect on RNA G4 structures. The structural mechanisms that mediate RNA G4 unfolding remains unknown. Here, we report on the TMPyP4-induced RNA G4 unfolding mechanism studied by well-tempered metadynamics (WT-MetaD) with supporting biophysical experiments. The simulations predict a two-state mechanism of TMPyP4 interaction via a groove-bound and a top-face bound conformation. The dynamics of TMPyP4 stacking on the top tetrad disrupts Hoogsteen H-bonds between guanine bases resulting in the consecutive TMPyP4 intercalation from top-to-bottom G-tetrads. The results reveal a striking correlation between computational and experimental approaches and validate WT-MetaD simulations as a powerful tool for studying RNA G4-ligand interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465985" rel="alternate" title="Ligand-induced unfolding mechanism of an RNA G-quadruplex (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466339</id><title>Emergent phases of ecological diversity and dynamics mapped in microcosms (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.485215+00:00</updated><author><name>Jiliang Hu</name></author><author><name>Daniel R. Amor</name></author><author><name>Matthieu Barbier</name></author><author><name>Guy Bunin</name></author><author><name>Jeff Gore</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Natural ecological communities display striking features, such as high biodiversity and a wide range of dynamics, that have been difficult to explain in a unified framework. Using experimental bacterial microcosms, we perform the first direct test of recent complex systems theory predicting that simple aggregate parameters dictate emergent behaviors of the community. As either the number of species or the strength of species interactions is increased, we show that microbial ecosystems transition between distinct qualitative dynamical phases in the predicted order, from a stable equilibrium where all species coexist, to partial coexistence, to emergence of persistent fluctuations in species abundance. Under the same conditions, high biodiversity and fluctuations allow and require each other. Our results demonstrate predictable emergent diversity and dynamics in ecological communities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466339" rel="alternate" title="Emergent phases of ecological diversity and dynamics mapped in microcosms (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466261</id><title>Longitudinal to transverse metachronal wave transitions in an in-vitro model of ciliated bronchial epithelium (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.485544+00:00</updated><author><name>Olivier Mesdjian</name></author><author><name>Chenglei Wang</name></author><author><name>Simon Gsell</name></author><author><name>Umberto D'Ortona</name></author><author><name>Julien Favier</name></author><author><name>Annie Viallat</name></author><author><name>Etienne Loiseau</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Myriads of cilia beat on ciliated epithelia, which are ubiquitous in life. When ciliary beats are synchronized, metachronal waves emerge, whose direction of propagation depends on the living system in an unexplained way. We show on a reconstructed human bronchial epithelium in-vitro that the direction of propagation is determined by the ability of mucus to be transported at the epithelial surface. Numerical simulations show that longitudinal waves maximise the transport of mucus while transverse waves, observed when the mucus is rigid and still, minimize the energy dissipated by the cilia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466261" rel="alternate" title="Longitudinal to transverse metachronal wave transitions in an in-vitro model of ciliated bronchial epithelium (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466275</id><title>Direct precise measurement of the stall torque of the flagellar motor in E. coli (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.486675+00:00</updated><author><name>Bin Wang</name></author><author><name>Guanhua Yue</name></author><author><name>Rongjing Zhang</name></author><author><name>Junhua Yuan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The flagellar motor drives the rotation of flagellar filaments, propeling the swimming of flagellated bacteria. The maximum torque the motor generates, the stall torque, is a key characteristics of the motor function. Direct measurements of the stall torque carried out three decades ago suffered from large experimental uncertainties, and subsequently there were only indirect measurements. Here, we applied magnetic tweezer to directly measure the stall torque in E. coli. We precisely calibrated the torsional stiffness of the magnetic tweezer, and performed motor resurrection experiments at stall, accomplishing a precise determination of the stall torque per torque-generating unit (stator unit). From our measurements, each stator passes 2 protons per step, indicating a tight coupling between motor rotation and proton flux.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466275" rel="alternate" title="Direct precise measurement of the stall torque of the flagellar motor in E. coli (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>