<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.906362+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455846</id><title>Structural basis for context-specific inhibition of translation by oxazolidinone antibiotics (34 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.906700+00:00</updated><author><name>Kaitlyn Tsai</name></author><author><name>Vanja Stojković</name></author><author><name>D. John Lee</name></author><author><name>Iris D. Young</name></author><author><name>Teresa Szal</name></author><author><name>Nora Vazquez-Laslop</name></author><author><name>Alexander S. Mankin</name></author><author><name>James S. Fraser</name></author><author><name>Danica Galonić Fujimori</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The antibiotic linezolid, the first clinically approved member of the oxazolidinone class, inhibits translation of bacterial ribosomes by binding to the peptidyl transferase center. Recent work has demonstrated that linezolid does not inhibit peptide bond formation at all sequences but rather acts in a context-specific manner, namely when alanine occupies the penultimate position of the nascent chain. In this study, we determined that the second-generation oxazolidinone radezolid also induces stalling with alanine at the penultimate position. However, the molecular basis for context-specificity of these inhibitors has not been elucidated. In this study, we determined high-resolution cryo-EM structures of both linezolid and radezolid-stalled ribosome complexes. These structures reveal that the alanine side chain fits within a small hydrophobic crevice created by oxazolidinone, resulting in improved ribosome binding. Modification of the ribosome by the antibiotic resistance enzyme Cfr disrupts stalling by forcing the antibiotic to adopt a conformation that narrows the hydrophobic alanine pocket. Together, the structural and biochemical findings presented in this work provide molecular understanding of context-specific inhibition of translation by clinically important oxazolidinone antibiotics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455846" rel="alternate" title="Structural basis for context-specific inhibition of translation by oxazolidinone antibiotics (34 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455294</id><title>Assessment of 3D MINFLUX data for quantitative structural biology in cells (32 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.906921+00:00</updated><author><name>Kirti Prakash</name></author><author><name>Alistair P. Curd</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;MINFLUX is a promising new development in single-molecule localization microscopy, claiming a resolution of 1-3 nm in living and fixed biological specimens. While MINFLUX can achieve very high localisation precision, quantitative analysis of reported results leads us to dispute the resolution claim and question reliability for imaging sub-100-nm structural features, in its current state.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455294" rel="alternate" title="Assessment of 3D MINFLUX data for quantitative structural biology in cells (32 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456308</id><title>Structural transitions in the GTP cap visualized by cryo-EM of catalytically inactive microtubules (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.907066+00:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin J LaFrance</name></author><author><name>Johanna Roostalu</name></author><author><name>Gil Henkin</name></author><author><name>Basil J Greber</name></author><author><name>Rui Zhang</name></author><author><name>Davide Normanno</name></author><author><name>Chloe McCollum</name></author><author><name>Thomas Surrey</name></author><author><name>Eva Nogales</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microtubules (MTs) are polymers of alphabeta-tubulin heterodimers that stochastically switch between growth and shrinkage phases. This dynamic instability is critically important for MT function. It is believed that GTP hydrolysis within the MT lattice is accompanied by destabilizing conformational changes, and that MT stability depends on a transiently existing GTP cap at the growing MT end. Here we use cryo-EM and TIRF microscopy of GTP hydrolysis-deficient MTs assembled from mutant recombinant human tubulin to investigate the structure of a GTP-bound MT lattice. We find that the GTP-MT lattice of two mutants in which the catalytically active glutamate in α-tubulin was substituted by inactive amino acids (E254A and E254N) is remarkably plastic. Undecorated E254A and E254N MTs with 13 protofilaments both have an expanded lattice, but display opposite protofilament twists, making these lattices distinct from the compacted lattice of wildtype GDP-MTs. End binding proteins of the EB family have the ability to compact both mutant GTP-lattices and to stabilize a negative twist, suggesting that they promote this transition also in the GTP cap of wildtype MTs, thereby contributing to the maturation of the MT structure. We also find that the MT seam appears to be stabilized in mutant GTP-MTs and destabilized in GDP-MTs, supporting the proposal that the seam plays an important role in MT stability. Together, these first high-resolution structures of truly GTP-bound MTs add mechanistic insight to our understanding of MT dynamic instability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456308" rel="alternate" title="Structural transitions in the GTP cap visualized by cryo-EM of catalytically inactive microtubules (24 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456048</id><title>Bending-torsional elasticity and energetics of the plus-end microtubule tip (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.907244+00:00</updated><author><name>Maxim Igaev</name></author><author><name>Helmut Grubmueller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microtubules (MTs), mesoscopic cellular filaments, grow primarily by the addition of GTP-bound tubulin dimers at their dynamic flaring plus-end tips. They operate as chemomechanical energy transducers with stochastic transitions to an astounding shortening motion upon hydrolyzing GTP to GDP. Time-resolved dynamics of the MT tip - a key determinant of this behavior - as a function of nucleotide state, internal lattice strain, and stabilizing lateral interactions have not been fully understood. Here, we use atomistic simulations to study the spontaneous relaxation of complete GTP-MT and GDP-MT tip models from unfavorable straight to relaxed splayed conformations and to comprehensively characterize the elasticity of MT tips. Our simulations reveal the dominance of viscoelastic dynamics of MT protofilaments during the relaxation process, driven by the stored bending-torsional strain and counterbalanced by the inter-protofilament interactions. We show that the post-hydrolysis MT tip is exposed to higher activation energy barriers for straight lattice formation, which translates into its inability to elongate. Our study provides an 'information ratchet' mechanism for the elastic energy conversion and release by MT tips and offers new insights into the mechanoenzymatics of MTs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456048" rel="alternate" title="Bending-torsional elasticity and energetics of the plus-end microtubule tip (18 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455998</id><title>Mapping the peptide binding groove of MHC class I (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.907383+00:00</updated><author><name>Janine-Denise Kopicki</name></author><author><name>Ankur Saikia</name></author><author><name>Stephan Niebling</name></author><author><name>Christian G&amp;uumlnther</name></author><author><name>Maria M. Garcia-Alai</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Springer</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Uetrecht</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;An essential element of adaptive immunity is the selective binding of peptide antigens by major histocompatibility complex (MHC) class I proteins and their presentation to cytotoxic T lymphocytes on the cell surface. Using native mass spectrometry, we here analyze the binding of peptides to an empty disulfide-stabilized HLA-A*02:01 molecule. This novel approach allows us to examine the binding properties of diverse peptides. The unique stability of our MHC class I even enables us to determine the binding affinity of complexes, which are suboptimally loaded with truncated or charge-reduced peptides. Notably, a unique erucamide adduct decouples affinity analysis from peptide identity alleviating issues usually attributed to clustering. We discovered that two anchor positions at the binding surface between MHC and peptide can be stabilized independently and further analyze the contribution of other peptidic amino acids on the binding. We propose this as an alternative, likely universally applicable method to artificial prediction tools to estimate the binding strength of peptides to MHC class I complexes quickly and efficiently. This newly described MHC class I-peptide binding affinity quantitation represents a much needed orthogonal, confirmatory approach to existing computational affinity predictions and has the potential to eliminate binding affinity biases and thus accelerate drug discovery in infectious diseases autoimmunity, vaccine design, and cancer immunotherapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455998" rel="alternate" title="Mapping the peptide binding groove of MHC class I (7 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455935</id><title>FAILURE OF PANCREATIC ALPHA CELLS TO RESPOND TO HYPOGLYCEMIA IS LINKED TO IMPAIRED GLUTAMATE RECEPTOR SIGNALING IN DIABETES (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.907548+00:00</updated><author><name>Julia K. Panzer</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Tamayo</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Caicedo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glucagon secretion from the pancreatic alpha cells is crucial to prevent hypoglycemia. People with type 1 diabetes, however, lose this glucoregulatory mechanism and are susceptible to dangerous insulin treatment-induced hypoglycemia. We established that activating glutamate receptors of the AMPA/kainate type in alpha cells is needed for decreases in glucose levels to elicit full glucagon responses from mouse and human islets. We performed functional studies using living pancreas slices from donors with type 1 diabetes and found that alpha cells had normal glucagon content and responded typically to KCl depolarization, but failed to respond to decreases in glucose concentration and had severely impaired AMPA/kainate receptor signaling. Reactivating residual AMPA/kainate receptor function with the positive allosteric modulators cyclothiazide and aniracetam partially rescued glucagon secretion in response to hypoglycemia. Positive allosteric modulators of AMPA/kainate receptors already approved to treat other conditions could thus be repurposed to prevent hypoglycemia and improve management of diabetes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455935" rel="alternate" title="FAILURE OF PANCREATIC ALPHA CELLS TO RESPOND TO HYPOGLYCEMIA IS LINKED TO IMPAIRED GLUTAMATE RECEPTOR SIGNALING IN DIABETES (7 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456130</id><title>Structurally distinct polymorphs of Tau aggregates revealed by nanoscale infrared spectroscopy (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.907688+00:00</updated><author><name>Siddhartha Banerjee</name></author><author><name>Ayanjeet Ghosh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aggregation of the tau protein plays a central role in several neurodegenerative diseases collectively known as tauopathies, including Alzheimers and Parkinsons disease. Tau misfolds into fibrillar beta sheet structures that constitute the paired helical filaments found in Neurofibrillary tangles. It is known that there can be significant structural heterogeneities in tau aggregates associated with different diseases. However, while structures of mature fibrils have been studied, the structural distributions in early stage tau aggregates is not well understood. In the present study, we use AFM-IR to investigate nanoscale spectra of individual tau fibrils at different stages of aggregation and demonstrate the presence of multiple fibrillar polymorphs that exhibit different secondary structures. We further show that mature fibrils contain significant amounts of antiparallel beta sheets. Our results are the very first application of nanoscale infrared spectroscopy to tau aggregates and underscore the promise of spatially resolved infrared spectroscopy for investigating protein aggregation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456130" rel="alternate" title="Structurally distinct polymorphs of Tau aggregates revealed by nanoscale infrared spectroscopy (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456287</id><title>Novel murine models of post-implantation and midgestional malaria-induced preterm birth (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.907824+00:00</updated><author><name>Alicer Keendalyn Andrew</name></author><author><name>Caitlin Cooper</name></author><author><name>Julie Moore</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite major advances made in malaria treatment and control over recent decades, the development of new models for studying disease pathogenesis remains a vital part of malaria research efforts. The study of malaria infection during pregnancy is particularly reliant on mouse models, as a means of circumventing many challenges and costs associated with pregnancy studies in endemic human populations. Here, we introduce three novel murine models that will further our understanding of how post-implantation and midgestional malaria infection affects pregnancy outcomes. When C57BL/6J (B6) mice are infected with  Plasmodium chabaudi chabaudi  AS on either embryonic day (E) 6.5, 8.5, or 10.5, preterm birth occurs in all animals by E16.5, E17.5, or E18.5 respectively, with no evidence of intrauterine growth restriction. We found that the time to delivery, placental inflammatory and antioxidant transcript upregulation, and the relationships between parasitemia and transcript expression prior to preterm birth are different based on the embryonic day of infection. On the day before preterm delivery, E6.5 infected mice did not experience significant upregulation of the inflammatory or antioxidant gene transcripts examined; however, parasitemia correlated positively with  Il1β  ,  Cox1  , and  Hmox1  placental transcript abundance. E8.5 infected mice had elevated transcripts for  Ifn  g  ,  Tnf  ,  Il10  ,  Cox1  ,  Cox2  ,  Sod1  ,  Sod2  ,  Cat  , and  Nrf2  , while  Sod3  was the only transcript that correlated with parasitemia. Finally, E10.5 infected mice had elevated transcripts for  Ifn  g  only, with a tendency for  Tnf  transcripts to correlate with parasitemia. Tumor necrosis factor deficient (TNF  -/-  ) and TNF receptor 1 deficient (TNFR1  -/-  ) mice infected on E8.5 experienced preterm birth at the same time as B6 controls. Further characterization of these models is necessary to discover new and/or existing mechanism(s) or trigger(s) responsible for malaria-driven preterm birth that is determined by gestational age upon maternal infection, parasite-host dynamics, or both.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456287" rel="alternate" title="Novel murine models of post-implantation and midgestional malaria-induced preterm birth (6 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456082</id><title>Effect of A-tract-mediated linker histone orientation on trinucleosome compaction (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.907962+00:00</updated><author><name>Madhura De</name></author><author><name>Martin Wuertz</name></author><author><name>Gabriele Mueller</name></author><author><name>Katalin Toth</name></author><author><name>Rebecca C. Wade</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Linker histones (LH) have been shown to preferentially bind to AT-rich DNA, and specifically to A-tracts, contiguous stretches of adenines. Recently, using spFRET (single pair Foerster/Fluorescence Resonance Energy Transfer), we showed that the globular domain (gH) of Xenopus laevis H1.0b LH  orients towards A-tracts present on the linker-DNA (L-DNA) in LH:mononucleosome complexes. We investigated the impact of this A-tract mediated orientation of the gH on the compaction of higher-order structures by studying trinucleosomes as minimal models for chromatin. Two 600 bp DNA sequences were constructed containing three Widom 601 core sequences separated by about 40 bp linkers and A-tracts inserted on either the outer or the inner L-DNAs flanking the 1st and the 3rd Widom 601 sequences. The two inner L-DNAs were fluorescently labelled at their midpoints. Trinucleosomes were reconstituted using the doubly-labelled 600 bp DNA, core histone octamers and the full-length H1.0b LH. SpFRET was performed for a range of NaCl concentrations. While the LH compacted the trinucleosomes, surprisingly, the extent of compaction was similar for trinucleosomes with A-tracts either on the two outer or on the two inner L-DNAs. Modeling constrained by the FRET efficiency suggests that the trinucleosomes adopt a zig-zagged conformation with the 1st and 3rd nucleosomes stacked on top of each other. Even though we expect that the gH of neighbouring (1st and 3rd) LHs are oriented towards the A-tracts, our models suggest that they are not sufficiently close to dimerize and affect compaction. Thus, despite differences in A-tract placements, the LH compacts trinucleosomes similarly.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456082" rel="alternate" title="Effect of A-tract-mediated linker histone orientation on trinucleosome compaction (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455816</id><title>Light-sheet photonic force optical coherence elastography for high-throughput quantitative 3D micromechanical imaging (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.908113+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuechuan Lin</name></author><author><name>Nichaluk Leartprapun</name></author><author><name>Justin C. Luo</name></author><author><name>Steven G. Adie</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microscale mechanical properties of the extracellular matrix (ECM) and dynamic cell-ECM interactions play an important role in physiological processes and disease. However, it remains a challenge for current mechanical characterization methods to combine quantitative 3D imaging of ECM mechanics with cellular-scale resolution and dynamic monitoring of cell-mediated changes to pericellular viscoelasticity. Here, we present light-sheet photonic force optical coherence elastography (LS-pfOCE) to address these challenges by leveraging a light-sheet for parallelized, non-invasive, and localized mechanical loading. We demonstrate the capabilities of LS-pfOCE by imaging the micromechanical heterogeneity of fibrous 3D collagen matrices and perform a live-cell study to image micromechanical heterogeneity induced by NIH-3T3 cells seeded in 3D fibrin constructs. We also show that LS-pfOCE is able to quantify temporal variations in pericellular viscoelasticity in response to altered cellular activity. By providing access to the spatiotemporal variations in the micromechanical properties of 3D complex biopolymer constructs and engineered cellular systems, LS-pfOCE has the potential to drive new discoveries in the rapidly growing field of mechanobiology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455816" rel="alternate" title="Light-sheet photonic force optical coherence elastography for high-throughput quantitative 3D micromechanical imaging (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455991</id><title>Cancer cell hyper-proliferation disrupts the topological invariance of epithelial monolayers (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.908298+00:00</updated><author><name>Daria S. Roshal</name></author><author><name>Marianne Martin</name></author><author><name>Kirill Fedorenko</name></author><author><name>Virginie MOLLE</name></author><author><name>Stephen Baghdiguian</name></author><author><name>Sergey B. Rochal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Although the polygonal shape of epithelial cells has drawn the attention of scientists for several centuries, only recently, it has been demonstrated that distributions of polygon types (DOPTs) are similar in proliferative epithelia of many different plant and animal species. In this study we show that hyper-proliferation of cancer cells disrupts this universality paradigm and results in random epithelial structures. Examining non-synchronized and synchronized HeLa cervix cells, we suppose that the cell size spread is the single parameter controlling the DOPT in these monolayers. We test this hypothesis by considering morphologically similar random polygonal packings. By analyzing the differences between tumoral and non-tumoral epithelial monolayers, we uncover that the latter have more ordered structures and argue that the relaxation of mechanical stresses associated with cell division induces more effective ordering in the epithelia with lower proliferation rates. The proposed theory also explains the specific highly ordered structures of some post-mitotic unconventional epithelia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455991" rel="alternate" title="Cancer cell hyper-proliferation disrupts the topological invariance of epithelial monolayers (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455914</id><title>The Microtubule Associated Protein Tau Regulates KIF1A Pausing Behavior and Motility (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.908453+00:00</updated><author><name>DV Lessard</name></author><author><name>CL Berger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many neurodegenerative diseases result from dysfunction of axonal transport, a highly regulated cellular process responsible for site-specific neuronal cargo delivery. The kinesin-3 family member KIF1A is a key mediator of this process by facilitating long-distance cargo delivery in a spatiotemporally regulated manner. While misregulation of KIF1A cargo delivery is observed in many neurodegenerative diseases, the regulatory mechanisms responsible for KIF1A cargo transport are largely unexplored. Our lab has recently characterized a mechanism for a unique pausing behavior of KIF1A in between processive segments on the microtubule. This behavior, mediated through an interaction between the KIF1A K-loop and the polyglutamylated C-terminal tails of tubulin, helps us further understand how KIF1A conducts long-range cargo transport. However, how this pausing behavior is influenced by other regulatory factors on the microtubule is an unexplored concept. The microtubule associated protein Tau is one potential regulator, as altered Tau function is a pathological marker in many neurodegenerative diseases. However, while the effect of Tau on kinesin-1 and -2 has been extensively characterized, its role in regulating KIF1A transport is greatly unexplored at the behavioral level. Using single-molecule imaging, we have identified Tau-mediated regulation of KIF1A pausing behavior and motility. Specifically, our findings imply a competitive interaction between Tau and KIF1A for the C-terminal tails of tubulin. We introduce a new mechanism of Tau-mediated kinesin regulation by inhibiting the ability of KIF1A to use C-terminal tail reliant pauses to connect multiple processive segments into a longer run length. Moreover, we have correlated this regulatory mechanism to the behavioral dynamics of Tau, further elucidating the function of Tau diffusive and static behavioral state on the microtubule surface. In summary, we introduce a new mechanism of Tau-mediated motility regulation, providing insight on how disruptions in axonal transport can lead to disease state pathology.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SIGNIFICANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;KIF1A mediated cargo transport is essential in many cellular processes such as axonal transport and neuronal development. Defects in KIF1A transport have been implicated in neurodegenerative diseases including Alzheimer’s disease and frontotemporal dementia. However, the mechanism of KIF1A’s pathological misregulation remains elusive, highlighting the importance of identifying regulators of KIF1A function. The microtubule associated protein Tau is an attractive potential regulator of KIF1A motility as Tau dysfunction is a hallmark of these neurodegenerative diseases. Here, we demonstrate a direct connection between Tau and KIF1A motility, revealing a unique form of Tau-mediated regulation of axonal transport. Our results provide a molecular foundation for understanding the role of motor protein misregulation in neurodegenerative disease progression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455914" rel="alternate" title="The Microtubule Associated Protein Tau Regulates KIF1A Pausing Behavior and Motility (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>