<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.502890+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471645</id><title>Structural insights into distinct signaling profiles of the μOR activated by diverse agonists (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.503322+00:00</updated><author><name>Qianhui Qu</name></author><author><name>Weijiao Huang</name></author><author><name>Deniz Aydin</name></author><author><name>Joseph M. Paggi</name></author><author><name>Alpay B. Seven</name></author><author><name>Haoqing Wang</name></author><author><name>Soumen Chakraborty</name></author><author><name>Tao Che</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey F. DiBerto</name></author><author><name>Michael J. Robertson</name></author><author><name>Asuka Inoue</name></author><author><name>Bryan L. Roth</name></author><author><name>Susruta Majumdar</name></author><author><name>Ron O. Dror</name></author><author><name>Brian K. Kobilka</name></author><author><name>Georgios Skiniotis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Drugs targeting the G protein-coupled μ-opioid receptor (μOR) are the most effective analgesics available but are also associated with fatal respiratory depression. While some partial opioid agonists appear to be safer than full agonists, the signaling pathways responsible for respiratory depression have yet to be elucidated. Here we investigated the structural and mechanistic basis of action of lofentanil (LFT) and mitragynine pseudoindoxyl (MP), two μOR agonists with different safety profiles. LFT, one of the most potent and lethal opioids, and MP, a derivative from the kratom plant with reduced respiratory depression in animal studies at equianalgesic doses, exhibited markedly different signaling efficacy profiles for G protein subtype activation and recruitment of β-arrestins. Cryo-EM structures of the μOR-Gi1 complex with MP (2.5Å) and LFT (3.2Å) revealed that the two ligands engage distinct sub-pockets, and molecular dynamics (MD) simulations showed additional differences in the binding site that propagate to the intracellular side of the receptor where G proteins and β-arrestins bind. While MP favors the precise G protein-bound active state observed in the cryo-EM structures, LFT favors a distinct active state. These results highlight how drugs engaging different parts of the μOR orthosteric pocket can lead to distinct signaling outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471645" rel="alternate" title="Structural insights into distinct signaling profiles of the μOR activated by diverse agonists (31 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471821</id><title>eIF5B and eIF1A remodel human translation initiation complexes to mediate ribosomal subunit joining (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.503611+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher P. Lapointe</name></author><author><name>Rosslyn Grosely</name></author><author><name>Masaaki Sokabe</name></author><author><name>Carlos Alvarado</name></author><author><name>Jinfan Wang</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Montabana</name></author><author><name>Nancy Villa</name></author><author><name>Byung-Sik Shin</name></author><author><name>Thomas E. Dever</name></author><author><name>Christopher S. Fraser</name></author><author><name>Israel S. Fernández</name></author><author><name>Joseph D. Puglisi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Joining of the ribosomal subunits at a translation start site on a messenger RNA during initiation commits the ribosome to synthesize a protein. Here, we combined single-molecule spectroscopy and structural methods using an in vitro reconstituted system to examine how the human ribosomal subunits join. Single-molecule fluorescence revealed when universally-conserved eukaryotic initiation factors (eIFs) eIF1A and eIF5B associate with and depart from initiation complexes. Guided by single-molecule dynamics, we examined initiation complexes that contained both eIF1A and eIF5B using single-particle electron cryo-microscopy. The resulting structure illuminated how eukaryote-specific contacts between eIF1A and eIF5B remodel the initiation complex to orient initiator tRNA in a conformation compatible with ribosomal subunit joining. Collectively, our findings provide a quantitative and architectural framework for the molecular choreography orchestrated by eIF1A and eIF5B during human translation initiation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471821" rel="alternate" title="eIF5B and eIF1A remodel human translation initiation complexes to mediate ribosomal subunit joining (31 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471614</id><title>Rapid 40S scanning and its regulation by mRNA structure during eukaryotic translation initiation (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.503790+00:00</updated><author><name>Jinfan Wang</name></author><author><name>Carlos Alvarado</name></author><author><name>Byung-Sik Shin</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Bohlen</name></author><author><name>Thomas E. Dever</name></author><author><name>Joseph D. Puglisi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;How the eukaryotic 43S preinitiation complex scans along the 5′ untranslated region (5′UTR) of a capped mRNA to locate the correct start codon remains elusive. Here, we directly track yeast 43S-mRNA binding, scanning, and 60S subunit joining by real-time single-molecule fluorescence spectroscopy. Once engaged with the mRNA, 43S scanning occurs at &amp;gt;100 nucleotides per second, independent of multiple cycles of ATP-hydrolysis by RNA helicases. The scanning ribosomes can proceed through RNA secondary structures, but 5′UTR hairpin sequences near start codons drive scanning ribosomes at start codons back in the 5′ direction, requiring rescanning to arrive once more at a start codon. Direct observation of scanning ribosomes provides a mechanistic framework for translational regulation by 5′UTR structures and upstream near-cognate start codons.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Direct observation of scanning eukaryotic ribosomes establishes a quantitative framework of scanning and its regulation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471614" rel="alternate" title="Rapid 40S scanning and its regulation by mRNA structure during eukaryotic translation initiation (29 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471009</id><title>Kinetic frustration by limited bond availability controls the LAT protein condensation phase transition on membranes (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.504025+00:00</updated><author><name>Simou Sun</name></author><author><name>Trevor GrandPre</name></author><author><name>David T. Limmer</name></author><author><name>Jay T. Groves</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;LAT is a membrane-linked scaffold protein that undergoes a phase transition to form a two-dimensional protein condensate on the membrane during T cell activation. Governed by tyrosine phosphorylation, LAT recruits various proteins that ultimately enable condensation through a percolation network of discrete and selective protein-protein interactions. Here we describe detailed kinetic measurements of the phase transition, along with coarse-grained model simulations, that reveal LAT condensation is kinetically frustrated by the availability of bonds to form the network. Unlike typical miscibility transitions in which compact domains may coexist at equilibrium, the LAT condensates are dynamically arrested in extended states, kinetically trapped out of equilibrium. Modeling identifies the structural basis for this kinetic arrest as the formation of spindle arrangements, favored by limited multivalent binding interactions along the flexible, intrinsically disordered LAT protein. These results reveal how local factors controlling the kinetics of LAT condensation enable formation of different, stable condensates, which may ultimately coexist within the cell.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471009" rel="alternate" title="Kinetic frustration by limited bond availability controls the LAT protein condensation phase transition on membranes (20 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471280</id><title>WESTPA 2.0: High-performance upgrades for weighted ensemble simulations and analysis of longer-timescale applications (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.504151+00:00</updated><author><name>John D. Russo</name></author><author><name>She Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jeremy M. G. Leung</name></author><author><name>Anthony T. Bogetti</name></author><author><name>Jeff P. Thompson</name></author><author><name>Alex J. DeGrave</name></author><author><name>Paul A. Torrillo</name></author><author><name>A. J. Pratt</name></author><author><name>Kim F. Wong</name></author><author><name>Junchao Xia</name></author><author><name>Jeremy Copperman</name></author><author><name>Joshua L. Adelman</name></author><author><name>Matthew C. Zwier</name></author><author><name>David N. LeBard</name></author><author><name>Daniel M. Zuckerman</name></author><author><name>Lillian T. Chong</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The weighted ensemble (WE) family of methods is one of several statistical-mechanics based path sampling strategies that can provide estimates of key observables (rate constants, pathways) using a fraction of the time required by direct simulation methods such as molecular dynamics or discrete-state stochastic algorithms. WE methods oversee numerous parallel trajectories using intermittent overhead operations at fixed time intervals, enabling facile interoperability with any dynamics engine. Here, we report on major upgrades to the WESTPA software package, an open-source, high-performance framework that implements both basic and recently developed WE methods. These upgrades offer substantial improvements over traditional WE. Key features of the new WESTPA 2.0 software enhance efficiency and ease of use: an adaptive binning scheme for more efficient surmounting of large free energy barriers, streamlined handling of large simulation datasets, exponentially improved analysis of kinetics, and developer-friendly tools for creating new WE methods, including a Python API and resampler module for implementing both binned and “binless” WE strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471280" rel="alternate" title="WESTPA 2.0: High-performance upgrades for weighted ensemble simulations and analysis of longer-timescale applications (10 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471346</id><title>Oscillatory movement of a dynein-microtubule complex crosslinked with DNA origami (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.504430+00:00</updated><author><name>Shimaa A. Abdellatef</name></author><author><name>Hisashi Tadakuma</name></author><author><name>Kangmin Yan</name></author><author><name>Takashi Fujiwara</name></author><author><name>Kodai Fukumoto</name></author><author><name>Yuichi Kondo</name></author><author><name>Hiroko Takazaki</name></author><author><name>Rofia Boudria</name></author><author><name>Takuo Yasunaga</name></author><author><name>Hideo Higuchi</name></author><author><name>Keiko Hirose</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During repetitive bending of cilia and flagella, axonemal dynein molecules move in an oscillatory manner along a microtubule (MT), but how the minus-end-directed motor dynein can oscillate back and forth is unknown. There are various factors that may regulate the dynein activities, e.g., the nexin-dynein regulatory complex, radial spokes, and central apparatus. In order to understand the basic mechanism of the oscillatory movement, we constructed a simple model system composed of MTs, outer-arm dyneins, and DNA origami that crosslinks the MTs. Electron microscopy (EM) showed patches of dynein molecules crossbridging two MTs in two opposite orientations; the oppositely oriented dyneins are expected to produce opposing forces. The optical trapping experiments showed that the dynein-MT-DNA-origami complex actually oscillate back and forth after photolysis of caged ATP. Intriguingly, the complex, when held at one end, showed repetitive bending motions. The results show that a simple system composed of ensembles of oppositely oriented dyneins, MTs, and inter-MT crosslinkers, without the additional regulatory structures, has an intrinsic ability to cause oscillation and repetitive bending motions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471346" rel="alternate" title="Oscillatory movement of a dynein-microtubule complex crosslinked with DNA origami (7 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471478</id><title>Neuron-like function of the nephron central command (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.504632+00:00</updated><author><name>Georgina Gyarmati</name></author><author><name>Urvi Nikhil Shroff</name></author><author><name>Anne Riquier-Brison</name></author><author><name>Sean D. Stocker</name></author><author><name>Audrey Izuhara</name></author><author><name>Sachin Deepak</name></author><author><name>Yibu Chen</name></author><author><name>Daniel Biemesderfer</name></author><author><name>Aaron W. James</name></author><author><name>Liliana Minichiello</name></author><author><name>Berislav V. Zlokovic</name></author><author><name>Janos Peti-Peterdi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Interoceptive neurons that sense and regulate our internal milieu have been identified in several organs except in the kidney cortex despite its major importance in maintaining body homeostasis. Here we report that the chief kidney cell type of the macula densa (MD) forms coordinated neural networks in each nephron that resemble peripheral ganglia. A combined in vivo single-cell 4D physiology (sc4DP) and scRNA sequencing approach identified the MD mechanisms of neuronal differentiation, heterogeneity (pacemaker MD cells), sensing of the local and systemic environment via multi-organ crosstalk, and regulation of organ functions by acting as the nephron central command. Consistent with their neuron-like nature, MD cells express the molecular fingerprint of neurodegeneration. Here we put forth the single-cell MD model and concept of local neural networks that control organ and body functions via interoception in normal physiological state and use an integrated mechanism of neurodegeneration in disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471478" rel="alternate" title="Neuron-like function of the nephron central command (7 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471749</id><title>Ca2+ oscillations, waves, and networks in islets from human donors with and without type 2 diabetes (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.505107+00:00</updated><author><name>Marko Gosak</name></author><author><name>Richard Yan-Do</name></author><author><name>Haopeng Lin</name></author><author><name>Patrick E. MacDonald</name></author><author><name>Andraž Stožer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pancreatic islets are highly interconnected structures that produce pulses of insulin and other hormones, maintaining normal homeostasis of glucose and other nutrients. Normal stimulus-secretion and intercellular coupling are essential to regulated secretory responses and these hallmarks are known to be altered in diabetes. In the present study, we used calcium imaging of isolated human islets to assess their collective cell behavior. The activity occurred in the form of calcium oscillations, was synchronized across different regions of islets through calcium waves, and was glucose-dependent: higher glucose enhanced the activity, elicited a greater proportion of global calcium waves, and led to denser and less fragmented functional networks. Hub regions were identified in stimulatory conditions, and they represented the most active islet regions. Moreover, calcium waves were found to be initiated in different subregions and the roles of initiators and hubs did not overlap. In type 2 diabetes, glucose-dependence was retained, but a reduced activity, locally restricted waves, and more segregated networks were detected compared with control islets. Interestingly, hub regions seemed to suffer the most by losing a disproportionately large fraction of connections. These changes affected islets from donors with diabetes in a heterogeneous manner.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471749" rel="alternate" title="Ca2+ oscillations, waves, and networks in islets from human donors with and without type 2 diabetes (7 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471313</id><title>Efemp1 modulates elastic fiber formation and mechanics of the extrahepatic bile duct (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.505257+00:00</updated><author><name>Jessica Llewellyn</name></author><author><name>Emilia Roberts</name></author><author><name>Chengyang Liu</name></author><author><name>Ali Naji</name></author><author><name>Richard K. Assoian</name></author><author><name>Rebecca G. Wells</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;EGF-Containing Fibulin Extracellular Matrix Protein 1 (EFEMP1, also called fibulin 3) is an extracellular matrix protein linked in a genome-wide association study to biliary atresia, a fibro-inflammatory disease of the neonatal extrahepatic bile duct. EFEMP1 is expressed in most tissues and &lt;italic&gt;Efemp1&lt;/italic&gt; null mice have decreased elastic fibers in visceral fascia; however, in contrast to other short fibulins (fibulins 4 and 5), EFEMP1 does not have a role in the development of large elastic fibers, and its overall function remains unclear. We demonstrated that EFEMP1 is expressed in the submucosa of both neonatal and adult mouse and human extrahepatic bile ducts and that, in adult &lt;italic&gt;Efemp1&lt;sup&gt;+/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice, elastin organization into fibers is decreased. We used pressure myography, a technique developed to study the mechanics of the vasculature, to show that &lt;italic&gt;Efemp1&lt;sup&gt;+/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; extrahepatic bile ducts are more compliant to luminal pressure, leading to increased circumferential stretch. We conclude that EFEMP1 has an important role in the formation of elastic fibers and mechanical properties of the extrahepatic bile duct. These data suggest that altered expression of EFEMP1 in the extrahepatic bile duct leads to an abnormal response to mechanical stress such as obstruction, potentially explaining the role of EFEMP1 in biliary atresia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471313" rel="alternate" title="Efemp1 modulates elastic fiber formation and mechanics of the extrahepatic bile duct (5 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471972</id><title>Skopi: a simulation package for diffractive imaging of noncrystalline biomolecules (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.505398+00:00</updated><author><name>Ariana Peck</name></author><author><name>Hsing-Yin Chang</name></author><author><name>Antoine Dujardin</name></author><author><name>Deeban Ramalingam</name></author><author><name>Monarin Uervirojnangkoorn</name></author><author><name>Zhaoyou Wang</name></author><author><name>Adrian Mancuso</name></author><author><name>Frédéric Poitevin</name></author><author><name>Chun Hong Yoon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;X-ray free electron lasers (XFEL) have the ability to produce ultra-bright femtosecond X-ray pulses for coherent diffraction imaging of biomolecules. While the development of methods and algorithms for macromolecular crystallography is now mature, XFEL experiments involving aerosolized or solvated biomolecular samples offer new challenges both in terms of experimental design and data processing. &lt;italic&gt;Skopi&lt;/italic&gt; is a simulation package that can generate single-hit diffraction images for reconstruction algorithms, multi-hit diffraction images of aggregated particles for training machine learning classification tasks using labeled data, diffraction images of randomly distributed particles for fluctuation X-ray scattering (FXS) algorithms, and diffraction images of reference and target particles for holographic reconstruction algorithms. We envision &lt;italic&gt;skopi&lt;/italic&gt; as a resource to aid the development of on-the-fly feedback during non-crystalline experiments at XFEL facilities, which will provide critical insights into biomolecular structure and function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471972" rel="alternate" title="Skopi: a simulation package for diffractive imaging of noncrystalline biomolecules (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471609</id><title>Collinearity of alpha-helices or beta strands in membrane proteins causes a characteristic peak centred on 4.9 Å resolution in diffraction intensity profiles, inducing higher diffraction anisotropy (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.505554+00:00</updated><author><name>Juliette Martin</name></author><author><name>Xavier Robert</name></author><author><name>Patrice Gouet</name></author><author><name>Pierre Falson</name></author><author><name>Vincent Chaptal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Diffraction anisotropy is a phenomenon that impacts more specifically membrane proteins, compared to soluble ones, but the reasons for this discrepancy remained unclear. Often, it is referred to a difference in resolution limits between highest and lowest diffraction limits as a signature for anisotropy. We show in this article that there is no simple correlation between anisotropy and difference in resolution limits, with notably a substantial number of structures displaying various anisotropy with no difference in resolution limits. We further investigated diffraction intensity profiles, and observed a peak centred on 4.9Å resolution more predominant in membrane proteins. Since this peak is in the region corresponding to secondary structures, we investigated the influence of secondary structure ratio. We showed that secondary structure content has little influence on this profile, while secondary structure collinearity in membrane proteins correlate with a stronger peak. Finally, we could further show that the presence of this peak is linked to higher diffraction anisotropy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Synopsis&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Membrane protein diffraction anisotropy originates from a peak at 4.9 Å resolution in intensity profiles, due to secondary structure collinearity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471609" rel="alternate" title="Collinearity of alpha-helices or beta strands in membrane proteins causes a characteristic peak centred on 4.9 Å resolution in diffraction intensity profiles, inducing higher diffraction anisotropy (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471817</id><title>The structural basis of mRNA recognition and binding by eukaryotic pseudouridine synthase PUS1 (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.505688+00:00</updated><author><name>Sebastian Grünberg</name></author><author><name>Lindsey A. Doyle</name></author><author><name>Nan Dai</name></author><author><name>Ivan R. Corrêa</name></author><author><name>Erbay Yigit</name></author><author><name>Barry L. Stoddard</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The chemical modification of RNA bases represents a ubiquitous activity that spans all domains of life. The formation of pseudouridine is the most common RNA modification and is observed within tRNA, rRNA, ncRNA and mRNAs. The catalysts of pseudouridylation, termed pseudouridine synthase or ‘PUS’ enzymes, include those that rely on guide RNA molecules and others that function as ‘stand-alone’ enzymes. Among the latter, up to ten are encoded in eukaryotic genomes, including several that modify uracil within mRNA transcripts. Neither the biological purpose of mRNA pseudouridylation, nor the mechanism by which individual mRNA bases are targeted, are well understood. In this study, we describe the high-resolution crystal structure of yeast PUS1 bound to an RNA target that we identified as being a hot spot for recognition, binding, and activity within a model mRNA. The enzyme recognizes RNA structural features corresponding to a base-paired duplex, which appears to act as a docking site leading to subsequent modification of the transcript. The study also allows us to visualize the divergence of related PUS-1 enzymes and their corresponding RNA target specificities, and to speculate on the basis by which this single PUS enzyme can bind and modify mRNA or tRNA substrates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471817" rel="alternate" title="The structural basis of mRNA recognition and binding by eukaryotic pseudouridine synthase PUS1 (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471325</id><title>I-M-150847, a novel GLP-1 and GIP receptor dual agonist, reduces body weight gain and improves glycemic control in the rodent model of type 2 diabetes and obesity (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.505825+00:00</updated><author><name>Rathin Bauri</name></author><author><name>Shilpak Bele</name></author><author><name>Jhansi Edelli</name></author><author><name>Sourav Dasadhikari</name></author><author><name>Neelesh C. Reddy</name></author><author><name>Sreenivasulu Kurukuti</name></author><author><name>Kanchan Garai</name></author><author><name>Tom Devasia</name></author><author><name>Ahamed Ibrahim</name></author><author><name>Vishal Rai</name></author><author><name>Prasenjit Mitra</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We report the discovery of a novel glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1) and glucose-dependent insulinotropic polypeptide (GIP) receptor dual agonist that shows balanced agonism towards both the incretin receptor. The dual agonism of GLP-1 and GIP receptor was achieved by replacing the tryptophan cage of exendin-4 with the C-terminal undecapeptide sequence of oxyntomodulin along with a single amino acid substitution from histidine to tyrosine at the amino terminus of the peptide. The structural modification places lysine 30 of the novel incretin agonist in frame with the corresponding lysine residue in the native GIP sequence. The novel incretin agonist, named I-M-150847, promotes robust glucose-stimulated insulin exocytosis in cultured pancreatic beta cells. Chronic administration of I-M-150847 to mice fed on the high-fat diet improves glucose tolerance, decreases food intake, decreases visceral adiposity and body weight gain demonstrating its therapeutic potential in ameliorating type 2 Diabetes and Obesity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Replacement of the Trp-cage with the C-terminal oxyntomodulin undecapeptide along with the tyrosine substitution at the amino terminus converts the selective GLP-1R agonist exendin-4 to a novel GLP-1R and GIPR dual agonist.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The GLP-1R and GIPR dual agonist enhances insulin secretion, improve glucose tolerance, reduces food intake, and decreases visceral adiposity and body-weight gain in the rodent model of diabetes and obesity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="471325v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471325" rel="alternate" title="I-M-150847, a novel GLP-1 and GIP receptor dual agonist, reduces body weight gain and improves glycemic control in the rodent model of type 2 diabetes and obesity (3 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>