<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.380305+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475847</id><title>High-fructose feeding suppresses cold-stimulated brown adipose tissue glucose uptake in young men independently of changes in thermogenesis and the gut microbiome (21 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.380401+00:00</updated><author><name>Gabriel Richard</name></author><author><name>Denis P. Blondin</name></author><author><name>Saad A. Syed</name></author><author><name>Laura Rossi</name></author><author><name>Michelle E. Fontes</name></author><author><name>Mélanie Fortin</name></author><author><name>Serge Phoenix</name></author><author><name>Frédérique Frisch</name></author><author><name>Stéphanie Dubreuil</name></author><author><name>Brigitte Guérin</name></author><author><name>Éric E. Turcotte</name></author><author><name>Martin Lepage</name></author><author><name>Michael G. Surette</name></author><author><name>Jonathan D. Schertzer</name></author><author><name>Gregory R. Steinberg</name></author><author><name>Katherine M. Morrison</name></author><author><name>André C. Carpentier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Diets rich in added sugars, especially high in fructose, are associated with metabolic diseases such as insulin resistance, and non-alcoholic fatty liver disease. Studies have shown a link between these pathologies and changes in the microbiome and its metabolites. Given the reported associations in animal models between the microbiome and brown or beige adipose tissue (BAT) function, and the alterations in the microbiome induced by high glucose or high fructose diets, we investigated the potential causal link between high glucose or fructose diets and BAT dysfunction in humans. We show that BAT glucose uptake, but not thermogenesis, is impaired by a high fructose but not high glucose diet, in the absence of changes in body mass, the gastrointestinal microbiome, and faecal short-chain fatty acids. We conclude that BAT metabolic dysfunction occurs independently from changes in gut microbiome composition, and earlier than other pathophysiological abnormalities associated with insulin resistance and dyslipidemia during fructose overconsumption in humans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475847" rel="alternate" title="High-fructose feeding suppresses cold-stimulated brown adipose tissue glucose uptake in young men independently of changes in thermogenesis and the gut microbiome (21 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.475405</id><title>Characterizing the conformational free-energy landscape of RNA using single-molecule field-effect transistors (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.380519+00:00</updated><author><name>Sukjin S. Jang</name></author><author><name>Sarah Dubnik</name></author><author><name>Jason Hon</name></author><author><name>Colin Nuckolls</name></author><author><name>Ruben L. Gonzalez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We have developed and used high-time-resolution, single-molecule field-effect transistors (smFETs) to characterize the conformational free-energy landscape of RNA stem-loops. Stem-loops are some of the most common RNA structural motifs and serve as building blocks for the formation of more complex RNA structures. Given their prevalence and integral role in RNA folding, the kinetics of stem-loop (un)folding has been extensively characterized using both experimental and computational approaches. Interestingly, these studies have reported vastly disparate timescales of (un)folding, which has been recently interpreted as evidence that (un)folding of even simple stem-loops occurs on a highly rugged conformational energy landscape. Because smFETs do not rely on fluorophore reporters of conformation or on the application of mechanical (un)folding forces, they provide a unique and complementary approach that has allowed us to directly monitor tens of thousands of (un)folding events of individual stem-loops at a 200 μs time resolution. Our results show that under our experimental conditions, stem-loops fold and unfold over a 1-200 ms timescale during which they transition between ensembles of unfolded and folded conformations, the latter of which is composed of at least two sub-populations. The 1-200 ms timescale of (un)folding we observe here indicates that smFETs report on complete (un)folding trajectories in which relatively extended unfolded conformations of the RNA spend long periods of time wandering the free-energy landscape before sampling one of several misfolded conformations or, alternatively, the natively folded conformation. Our findings demonstrate how the combination of single-molecule sensitivity and high time resolution makes smFETs unique and powerful tools for characterizing the conformational free-energy landscape of RNA and highlight the extremely rugged landscape on which even the simplest RNA structural elements fold.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.475405" rel="alternate" title="Characterizing the conformational free-energy landscape of RNA using single-molecule field-effect transistors (7 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476289</id><title>Asymmetric Pendrin Homodimer Reveals its Molecular Mechanism as Anion Exchanger (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.380588+00:00</updated><author><name>Qianying Liu</name></author><author><name>Xiang Zhang</name></author><author><name>Hui Huang</name></author><author><name>Yuxin Chen</name></author><author><name>Fang Wang</name></author><author><name>Aihua Hao</name></author><author><name>Wuqiang Zhan</name></author><author><name>Qiyu Mao</name></author><author><name>Yuxia Hu</name></author><author><name>Lin Han</name></author><author><name>Yifang Sun</name></author><author><name>Meng Zhang</name></author><author><name>Zhimin Liu</name></author><author><name>Genglin Li</name></author><author><name>Weijia Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yilai Shu</name></author><author><name>Lei Sun</name></author><author><name>Zhenguo Chen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pendrin SLC26A4 is an anion exchanger expressed in apical membranes of selected epithelia. Pendrin ablation causes Pendred syndrome, a genetic disorder disease associated with sensorineural hearing loss, hypothyroid goiter, and reduced blood pressure. However, its molecular structure has remained unknown limiting our understanding. Here, we determined the structures of mouse pendrin with symmetric and characteristically asymmetric homodimer conformations by cryo-electron microscopy. The asymmetric homodimer consists of an inward-facing protomer and an intermediate-state protomer, representing the coincident uptake and secretion process, and exhibits the unique state of pendrin as an electroneutral exchanger. This previously unrevealed conformation, together with other conformations we captured, provides an inverted alternate-access mechanism for anion exchange. Furthermore, our structural and functional data disclosed the properties of anion exchange cleft and interpreted the important pathogenetic mutations. These investigations shed light on the pendrin exchange mechanism and extend our structure-guided understanding of pathogenetic mutations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476289" rel="alternate" title="Asymmetric Pendrin Homodimer Reveals its Molecular Mechanism as Anion Exchanger (7 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.476501</id><title>Escherichia coli response to subinhibitory concentration of Colistin: Insights from study of membrane dynamics and morphology. (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.380701+00:00</updated><author><name>Ilanila Ilangumaran Ponmalar</name></author><author><name>Jitendriya Swain</name></author><author><name>Jaydeep Kumar Basu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Prevalence of wide spread bacterial infections bring forth a critical need in understanding the molecular mechanisms of the antibiotics as well as the bacterial response to those antibiotics. Improper usage of antibiotics, which can be in sub-lethal concentrations is one among the multiple reasons for acquiring antibiotic resistance which makes it vital to understand the bacterial response towards sub-lethal concentrations of antibiotics. In this work, we have used colistin, a well-known membrane active antibiotic used to treat severe bacterial infections and explored the impact of its subminimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) on the lipid membrane dynamics and morphological changes of E. coli. Upon investigation of live cell membrane properties such as lipid dynamics using fluorescence correlation spectroscopy, we observed that colistin disrupts the lipid membrane at sub-MIC by altering the lipid diffusivity. Interestingly, filamentationlike cell elongation was observed upon colistin treatment which led to further exploration of surface morphology with the help of atomic force spectroscopy. The changes in the surface roughness upon colistin treatment provides additional insight on the colistin-membrane interaction corroborating with the altered lipid diffusion. Although altered lipid dynamics could be attributed to an outcome of lipid rearrangement due to direct disruption by antibiotic molecules on the membrane or an indirect consequence of disruptions in lipid biosynthetic pathways, we were able to ascertain that altered bacterial membrane dynamics is due to direct disruptions. Our results provide a broad overview on the consequence of the cyclic polypeptide, colistin on membrane specific lipid dynamics and morphology of a live Gram-negative bacterial cell.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.476501" rel="alternate" title="Escherichia coli response to subinhibitory concentration of Colistin: Insights from study of membrane dynamics and morphology. (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476392</id><title>Phase Separation of Shell Protein and Enzyme: An Insight into the Biogenesis of a Prokaryotic Metabolosome (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.380761+00:00</updated><author><name>Gaurav Kumar</name></author><author><name>Sharmistha Sinha</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial microcompartments are substrate specific metabolic modules that are conditionally expressed in certain bacterial species. These all protein structures have size in the range of 100-150 nm and are formed by the self-assembly of thousands of protein subunits, all encoded by genes belonging to a single operon. The operon contains genes that encode for both enzymes and shell proteins. The shell proteins self-assemble to form the outer coat of the compartment and enzymes are encapsulated within. A perplexing question in MCP biology is to understand the mechanism which governs the formation of these small yet complex assemblages of proteins. In this work we use 1,2-propanediol utilization microcompartments (PduMCP) as a paradigm to identify the factors that drive the self-assembly of MCP proteins. We find that a major shell protein PduBB tend to self-assemble under macromolecular crowded environment and suitable ionic strength. Microscopic visualization and biophysical studies reveal phase separation to be the principle mechanism behind the self-association of shell protein in the presence of salts and macromolecular crowding. The shell protein PduBB interacts with the enzyme diol-dehydratase PduCDE and co-assemble into phase separated liquid droplets. The co-assembly of PduCDE and PduBB results in the enhancement of catalytic activity of the enzyme. A combination of spectroscopic and biochemical techniques shows the relevance of divalent cation Mg2+ in providing stability to intact PduMCP in vivo. Together our results suggest a combination of protein-protein interactions and phase separation guiding the self-assembly of Pdu shell protein and enzyme in solution phase.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476392" rel="alternate" title="Phase Separation of Shell Protein and Enzyme: An Insight into the Biogenesis of a Prokaryotic Metabolosome (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476140</id><title>Histone chaperones exhibit conserved functionality in nucleosome remodeling (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.380816+00:00</updated><author><name>P. Buzón</name></author><author><name>A. Velázquez-Cruz</name></author><author><name>K. González-Arzola</name></author><author><name>A. Díaz-Quintana</name></author><author><name>I. Díaz-Moreno</name></author><author><name>W.H. Roos</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chromatin homeostasis mediates some of the most fundamental processes in the eukaryotic cell. In this regard, histone chaperones have emerged as major regulatory factors during DNA replication, repair, and transcription. However, the dynamic nature of these processes has severely impeded their characterization at the molecular level. Here we apply single-molecule probing by fluorescence optical tweezers to follow histone chaperone dynamics in real-time. The molecular action of SET/template-activating factor-Iβ and nucleophosmin 1—representing the two most common histone chaperone folds—were examined using both nucleosomes and isolated core histones. We show that these chaperones present binding specificity for partially dismantled nucleosomes and are able to recognize and disrupt non-native histone-DNA interactions. Furthermore, we reveal that cytochrome &lt;italic&gt;c&lt;/italic&gt; inhibition of histone chaperones is coupled to chaperone accumulation on DNA-bound histones. Our single-molecule approach shows that despite the drastically different structures of these chaperones, they present conserved modes of action mediating nucleosome remodeling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476140" rel="alternate" title="Histone chaperones exhibit conserved functionality in nucleosome remodeling (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.475960</id><title>BECN1 F121A mutation increases autophagic flux in aged mice and improves aging phenotypes in an organ-dependent manner (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.380887+00:00</updated><author><name>Salwa Sebti</name></author><author><name>Zhongju Zou</name></author><author><name>Michael U. Shiloh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Autophagy is necessary for lifespan extension in multiple model organisms and autophagy dysfunction impacts age-related phenotypes and diseases. Introduction of an F121A mutation into the essential autophagy protein BECN1 constitutively increases basal autophagy in young mice and reduces cardiac and renal age-related changes in longer-lived &lt;italic&gt;Becn1&lt;sup&gt;F121A&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mutant mice. However, both autophagic and lysosomal activity have been described to decline with age. Thus, whether autophagic flux is maintained during aging and whether it is enhanced in &lt;italic&gt;Becn1&lt;sup&gt;F121A&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice is unknown. Here we demonstrate that old wild type mice maintained functional autophagic flux in heart, kidney and skeletal muscle but not liver, and old &lt;italic&gt;Becn1&lt;sup&gt;F121A&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice had increased autophagic flux in those same organs compared to wild type. In parallel, &lt;italic&gt;Becn1&lt;sup&gt;F121A&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice were not protected against age-associated hepatic phenotypes but demonstrated reduced skeletal muscle fiber atrophy. These findings identify an organ-specific role for the ability of autophagy to impact organ aging phenotypes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.475960" rel="alternate" title="BECN1 F121A mutation increases autophagic flux in aged mice and improves aging phenotypes in an organ-dependent manner (4 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476462</id><title>The coupling between healthspan and lifespan in Caenorhabditis depends on complex interactions between compound intervention and genetic background (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.380945+00:00</updated><author><name>Stephen A Banse</name></author><author><name>E Grace Jackson</name></author><author><name>Christine A Sedore</name></author><author><name>Brian Onken</name></author><author><name>David Hall</name></author><author><name>Anna L Coleman-Hulbert</name></author><author><name>Phu Huynh</name></author><author><name>Theo Garrett</name></author><author><name>Erik Johnson</name></author><author><name>Girish Harinath</name></author><author><name>Delaney Inman</name></author><author><name>Suzhen Guo</name></author><author><name>Mackenzie Morshead</name></author><author><name>Jian Xue</name></author><author><name>Ron Falkowski</name></author><author><name>Esteban Chen</name></author><author><name>Christopher Herrera</name></author><author><name>Allie J Kirsch</name></author><author><name>Viviana I Perez</name></author><author><name>Max Guo</name></author><author><name>Gordon J Lithgow</name></author><author><name>Monica Driscoll</name></author><author><name>Patrick C Phillips</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aging is characterized by declining health that results in decreased neuromuscular function and cellular resilience. The relationship between lifespan and health, and the influence of genetic background on that relationship, has important implications in the development of anti-aging interventions. Here we combined survival under thermal and oxidative stress with swimming performance, to evaluate health effects across a nematode genetic diversity panel for three compounds previously studied in the &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis&lt;/italic&gt; Intervention Testing Program - NP1, propyl gallate, and resveratrol. We show that oxidative stress resistance and thermotolerance vary with compound intervention, genetic background, and age. The effects of tested compounds on swimming locomotion, in contrast, are largely species-specific. Additionally, thermotolerance, but not oxidative stress or swimming ability, correlates with lifespan. Our results demonstrate the importance of assessing health and lifespan across genetic backgrounds in the effort to identify reproducible aging interventions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476462" rel="alternate" title="The coupling between healthspan and lifespan in Caenorhabditis depends on complex interactions between compound intervention and genetic background (4 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476359</id><title>Kynurenine metabolism is altered in mdx mice: a potential muscle to brain connection (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.381075+00:00</updated><author><name>Emily N Copeland</name></author><author><name>Kennedy C Whitley</name></author><author><name>Colton JF Watson</name></author><author><name>Bradley J Baranowski</name></author><author><name>Nigel Kurgan</name></author><author><name>Adam J MacNeil</name></author><author><name>Rebecca EK MacPherson</name></author><author><name>Val A. Fajardo</name></author><author><name>David J Allison</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Regular exercise can direct muscle kynurenine (KYN) metabolism toward the neuroprotective branch of the kynurenine pathway thereby limiting the accumulation of neurotoxic metabolites in the brain and contributing to mental resilience. While the effect of regular exercise has been studied, the effect of muscle disease on KYN metabolism has not yet been investigated. Previous work has highlighted anxiety-like behaviors in approximately 25% of patients with DMD, possibly due to altered KYN metabolism. Here, we characterized KYN metabolism in mdx mouse models of Duchenne muscular dystrophy (DMD). Young (8-10 week old) DBA/2J (D2) mdx mice, but not age-matched C57BL/10 (C57) mdx mice, had lower levels of circulating KYNA and KYNA:KYN ratio compared with their respective wild-type (WT) controls. Moreover, only D2 mdx mice displayed signs of anxiety-like behaviour, spending more time in the corners of their cages during a novel object recognition test when compared with WT. Along with this, we found that muscles from D2 mdx mice had less peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-gamma coactivator 1-alpha and kynurenine amino transferase-1 enzyme content as well as elevated expression of inflammatory cytokines compared with WT muscles. Thus, our pilot work shows that KYN metabolism is altered in D2 mdx mice, with a potential contribution from altered muscle health.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476359" rel="alternate" title="Kynurenine metabolism is altered in mdx mice: a potential muscle to brain connection (3 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476318</id><title>Glucose-stimulated calcium dynamics in beta cells from C57BL/6J, C57BL/6N, and NMRI mice: A systematic comparison of activation, activity, and deactivation properties in tissue slices (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.381154+00:00</updated><author><name>Viljem Pohorec</name></author><author><name>Lidija Krizancic Bombek</name></author><author><name>Masa Skelin Klemen</name></author><author><name>Jurij Dolensek</name></author><author><name>Andraz Stozer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Although mice are a very instrumental model in islet beta cell research, possible phenotypic differences between strains and substrains are largely neglected in the scientific community. In this study, we show important phenotypic differences in beta cell responses to glucose between NMRI, C57BL/6J, and C57BL/6N mice, i.e., the three most commonly used strains. High-resolution multicellular confocal imaging of beta cells in acute pancreas tissue slices was used to measure and quantitatively compare the calcium dynamics in response to a wide range of glucose concentrations. Strain- and substrain-specific features were found in all three phases of beta cell responses to glucose: a shift in the dose-response curve characterizing the delay to activation and deactivation in response to stimulus onset and termination, respectively, and distinct concentration-encoding principles during the plateau phase in terms of frequency, duration, and active time changes with increasing glucose concentrations. Our results underline the significance of carefully choosing and reporting the strain to enable comparison and increase reproducibility, emphasize the importance of analyzing a number of different beta cell physiological parameters characterizing the response to glucose, and provide a valuable standard for future studies on beta cell calcium dynamics in health and disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476318" rel="alternate" title="Glucose-stimulated calcium dynamics in beta cells from C57BL/6J, C57BL/6N, and NMRI mice: A systematic comparison of activation, activity, and deactivation properties in tissue slices (3 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476270</id><title>Graphics processing unit-accelerated Monte Carlo simulation of polarized light in complex three-dimensional media (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.381218+00:00</updated><author><name>Shijie Yan</name></author><author><name>Steven L Jacques</name></author><author><name>Jessica C. Ramella-Roman</name></author><author><name>Qianqian Fang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Significance: Monte Carlo (MC) methods have been applied for studying interactions between polarized light and biological tissues, but most existing MC codes supporting polarization modeling can only simulate homogeneous or multi-layered domains, resulting in approximations when handling realistic tissue structures. Aim: Over the past decade, the speed of MC simulations has seen dramatic improvement with massively-parallel computing techniques. Developing hardware-accelerated MC simulation algorithms that can accurately model polarized light inside 3-D heterogeneous tissues can greatly expand the utility of polarization in biophotonics applications. Approach: Here we report a highly efficient polarized MC algorithm capable of modeling arbitrarily complex media defined over a voxelated domain. Each voxel of the domain can be associated with spherical scatters of various radii and densities. The Stokes vector of each simulated photon packet is updated through photon propagation, creating spatially resolved polarization measurements over the detectors or domain surface. Results: We have implemented this algorithm in our widely disseminated MC simulator, Monte Carlo eXtreme (MCX). It is validated by comparing with a reference CPU-based simulator in both homogeneous and layered domains, showing excellent agreement and a 931-fold speedup. Conclusion: The polarization-enabled MCX (pMCX) offers biophotonics community an efficient tool to explore polarized light in bio-tissues, and is freely available at http://mcx.space/.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476270" rel="alternate" title="Graphics processing unit-accelerated Monte Carlo simulation of polarized light in complex three-dimensional media (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.476525</id><title>RT-qPCR as a screening platform for mutational and small molecule impacts on structural stability of RNA tertiary structures (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.381279+00:00</updated><author><name>Martina Zafferani</name></author><author><name>Dhanasheel Muralidharan</name></author><author><name>Amanda E Hargrove</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The exponential increase in the discovery and characterization of RNA tertiary structures has highlighted their active role in a variety of human disease, yet often their interactome and specific function remain unknown. Small molecules offer opportunities to both decode these cellular roles and develop therapeutics, yet there are few examples of small molecules that target biologically relevant RNA tertiary structures. While RNA triple helices are a particular attractive target, discovery of triple helix modulators has been hindered by the lack of correlation between small molecule affinity and effect on structural modulation, thereby limiting the utility of affinity-based screening as a primary filtering method. To address this challenge, we developed a high-throughput RT-qPCR screening platform that reports on the effect of mutations and additives, such as small molecules, on the structuredness of triple helices. Using the 3'-end of the oncogenic non-coding RNA MALAT1 as an example, we demonstrated the applicability of both a two-step and a one-pot method to assess the impact of mutations and small molecules on the stability of the triple helix. Employment of a functional high-throughput assay as a primary screen will significantly expedite the discovery of probes that modulate RNA triple helices structural landscape and, consequently, help gain insight into the roles of these pervasive structures.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.476525" rel="alternate" title="RT-qPCR as a screening platform for mutational and small molecule impacts on structural stability of RNA tertiary structures (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.476512</id><title>Blocking Kir6.2 channels with SpTx1 potentiates glucose-stimulated insulin secretion from murine pancreatic β cells and lowers blood glucose in diabetic mice (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.381337+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhe Lu</name></author><author><name>Yajamana Ramu</name></author><author><name>Jayden Yamakaze</name></author><author><name>Yufeng Zhou</name></author><author><name>Toshinori Hoshi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;ATP-sensitive K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; (K&lt;sub&gt;ATP&lt;/sub&gt;) channels in pancreatic β cells comprise pore-forming subunits (Kir6.2) and modulatory sulfonylurea receptor subunits (SUR1). The ATP sensitivity of these channels enables them to couple metabolic state to insulin secretion in β cells. Antidiabetic sulfonylureas such as glibenclamide target SUR1 and indirectly suppress Kir6.2 activity. Glibenclamide acts as both primary and secondary secretagogues to trigger insulin secretion and potentiate glucose-stimulated insulin secretion, respectively. We tested whether blocking Kir6.2 itself causes the same effects as glibenclamide, and found that the Kir6.2 pore-blocker SpTx1 acts as a strong secondary, but not a primary, secretagogue. SpTx1 triggered a transient rise of plasma insulin and lowered the elevated blood glucose of diabetic mice over-expressing Kir6.2 but did not affect those of non-diabetic mice. This proof-of-concept study suggests that blocking Kir6.2 may serve as an effective treatment for diabetes and other diseases stemming from Kir6.2 hyperactivity that cannot be suppressed with sulfonylureas.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.16.476512" rel="alternate" title="Blocking Kir6.2 channels with SpTx1 potentiates glucose-stimulated insulin secretion from murine pancreatic β cells and lowers blood glucose in diabetic mice (3 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475716</id><title>How many bits of information can be transferred between residues in a protein and how fast? (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.381403+00:00</updated><author><name>Aysima Hacisuleyman</name></author><author><name>Burak Erman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Time resolved Raman and infrared spectroscopy experiments show the basic features of information transfer between residues in proteins. Here, we present the theoretical basis of information transfer using a simple elastic net model and recently developed entropy transfer concept in proteins. Mutual information between two residues is a measure of communication in proteins which shows the maximum amount of information that may be transferred between two residues. However, it does not explain the actual amount of transfer nor the transfer rate of information between residues. For this, dynamic equations of the system are needed. We used the Schreiber theory of information transfer and the Gaussian network Model of proteins, together with the solution of the Langevin equation, to quantify allosteric information transfer. Results of the model are in perfect agreement with ultraviolet resonance Raman measurements. Analysis of the allosteric protein Human NAD-dependent isocitrate dehydrogenase shows that a multitude of paths contribute collectively to information transfer. While the peak values of information transferred are small relative to information content of residues, considering the estimated transfer rates, which are in the order of megabits per second, sustained transfer during the activity time-span of proteins may be significant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475716" rel="alternate" title="How many bits of information can be transferred between residues in a protein and how fast? (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>