<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.060856+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469090</id><title>Mechanics of cell integration in vivo (82 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.061317+00:00</updated><author><name>Guilherme B. Ventura</name></author><author><name>Aboutaleb Amiri</name></author><author><name>Raghavan Thiagarajan</name></author><author><name>Mari Tolonen</name></author><author><name>Amin Doostmohammadi</name></author><author><name>Jakub Sedzinski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During embryonic development, regeneration and homeostasis, cells have to physically integrate into their target tissues, where they ultimately execute their function. Despite a significant body of research on how mechanical forces instruct cellular behaviors within the plane of an epithelium, very little is known about the mechanical interplay at the interface between migrating cells and their surrounding tissue, which has its own dynamics, architecture and identity. Here, using quantitative in vivo imaging and molecular perturbations, together with a theoretical model, we reveal that multiciliated cell (MCC) precursors in the Xenopus embryo form dynamic filopodia that pull at the vertices of the overlying epithelial sheet to probe their stiffness and identify the preferred positions for their integration into the tissue. Moreover, we report a novel function for a structural component of vertices, the lipolysis-stimulated lipoprotein receptor (LSR), in filopodia dynamics and show its critical role in cell intercalation. Remarkably, we find that pulling forces equip the MCCs to remodel the epithelial junctions of the neighboring tissue, enabling them to generate a permissive environment for their integration. Our findings reveal the intricate physical crosstalk at the cell-tissue interface and uncover previously unknown functions for mechanical forces in orchestrating cell integration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469090" rel="alternate" title="Mechanics of cell integration in vivo (82 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468729</id><title>NAD precursors cycle between host tissues and the gut microbiome (41 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.061505+00:00</updated><author><name>Karthikeyani Chellappa</name></author><author><name>Melanie R. McReynolds</name></author><author><name>Wenyun Lu</name></author><author><name>Xianfeng Zeng</name></author><author><name>Mikhail Makarov</name></author><author><name>Faisal Hayat</name></author><author><name>Sarmistha Mukherjee</name></author><author><name>Yashaswini R. Bhat</name></author><author><name>Siddharth R. Lingala</name></author><author><name>Rafaella T. Shima</name></author><author><name>Hélène C. Descamps</name></author><author><name>Timothy Cox</name></author><author><name>Lixin Ji</name></author><author><name>Connor Jankowski</name></author><author><name>Qingwei Chu</name></author><author><name>Shawn M. Davidson</name></author><author><name>Christoph A. Thaiss</name></author><author><name>Marie E. Migaud</name></author><author><name>Joshua D. Rabinowtiz</name></author><author><name>Joseph A. Baur</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NAD) is an essential redox cofactor in both mammals and microbes. Here we use isotope tracing to investigate the precursors supporting NAD synthesis in the gut microbiome. We find that preferred dietary NAD precursors are absorbed in the proximal part of the gastrointestinal tract and not available to microbes in the distal gut. Instead, circulating host nicotinamide enters the gut lumen and supports gut microbiome NAD synthesis. In addition, the microbiome converts nicotinamide, originating from the host circulation, into nicotinic acid. Host tissues uptake and utilize this microbiome-derived nicotinic acid for NAD synthesis, maintaining circulating nicotinic acid levels even in the absence of dietary consumption. Moreover, the main route from oral nicotinamide riboside, a widely used nutraceutical, to host NAD is via conversion into nicotinic acid by the gut microbiome. Thus, NAD precursors cycle between the host and gut microbiome to maintain NAD homeostasis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468729" rel="alternate" title="NAD precursors cycle between host tissues and the gut microbiome (41 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468745</id><title>Emergence of order in condensates composed of multi-valent, multi-domain proteins (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.061797+00:00</updated><author><name>Srivastav Ranganathan</name></author><author><name>Eugene Shakhnovich</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many RNA-binding proteins (RBPs) that assemble into membraneless organelles, have a common architecture including disordered prion-like domain (PLD) and folded RNA-binding domain (RBD). An enrichment of PLD within the condensed phase gives rise to formation, on longer time scales, amyloid-like fibrils (aging). In this study, we employ coarse-grained Langevin dynamics simulations to explore the physical basis for the structural diversity in condensed phases of multi-domain RBPs. We discovered a highly cooperative first order transition between disordered (liquid-like) structures and an ordered (solid-like) phase whereby chains of PLD organize in fibrils with high nematic orientational order. Cooperativity of this liquid-solid transition makes fibril formation highly malleable to mutations or post-translational modifications. An interplay between homo-domain (PLD-PLD) and hetero-domain (PLD-RBD) interactions results in variety of structures with distinct spatial architectures. Our results provide a mechanistic understanding of how multi-domain RBPs could form assemblies with distinct structural and, potentially, material properties.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assembly of proteins and nucleic acids into dense, liquid-like pockets is associated with several key functions including stress response, gene-regulation, DNA-repair and RNA processing. Several RNA binding proteins such as FUS are known to form liquid-like condensates that progressively harden into more dynamically, solid-like structures, a phenomenon that gets accelerated by disease mutations. In this study, we discover the mechanistic origins of this transition and show that small mutational or posttranslational modifications could result in sharp disorder-order transitions that could characterize accelerated liquid-solid transition in disease mutants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468745" rel="alternate" title="Emergence of order in condensates composed of multi-valent, multi-domain proteins (15 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469114</id><title>Double mutant of chymotrypsin inhibitor 2 stabilized through increased conformational entropy (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.061925+00:00</updated><author><name>Yulian Gavrilov</name></author><author><name>Felix Kümmerer</name></author><author><name>Simone Orioli</name></author><author><name>Andreas Prestel</name></author><author><name>Kresten Lindorff-Larsen</name></author><author><name>Kaare Teilum</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The conformational heterogeneity of a folded protein can affect both its function but also stability and folding. We recently discovered and characterized a stabilized double mutant (L49I/I57V) of the protein CI2 and showed that state-of-the-art prediction methods could not predict the increased stability relative to the wild-type protein. Here we have examined whether changed native state dynamics, and resulting entropy changes, can explain the stability changes in the double mutant protein, as well as the two single mutant forms. We have combined NMR relaxation measurements of the ps-ns dynamics of amide groups in the backbone and the methyl groups in the side-chains with molecular dynamics simulations to quantify the native state dynamics. The NMR experiments reveal that the mutations have different effects on the conformational flexibility of CI2: A reduction in conformational dynamics (and entropy) of the native state of L49I variant correlates with its decreased stability, while increased dynamics of the I57V and L49I/I57V variants correlates with their increased stability. These findings suggest that explicitly accounting for changes in native state entropy might be needed to improve the predictions of the effect of mutations on protein stability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469114" rel="alternate" title="Double mutant of chymotrypsin inhibitor 2 stabilized through increased conformational entropy (8 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.468550</id><title>Ca2+-inactivation of the mammalian ryanodine receptor type 1 in a lipidic environment revealed by cryo-EM (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.062224+00:00</updated><author><name>Ashok R. Nayak</name></author><author><name>Montserrat Samsó</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Activation of the intracellular Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; channel ryanodine receptor (RyR) triggers a cytosolic Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; surge, while elevated cytosolic Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; inhibits the channel in a negative feedback mechanism. Cryo-EM carried out under partially inactivating Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; conditions revealed two conformations of RyR1, an open state and an inactivated state, resolved at 4.0 and 3.3 Å resolution, respectively. RyR1s were embedded in nanodiscs with two lipids resolved at each inter-subunit crevice. Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; binding to the high affinity site engages the central (CD) and C-terminal domains (CTD) into a quasi-rigid unit, which separates the S6 four-helix bundle and opens the channel. Further out-of-plane rotation of the quasi-rigid unit pushes S6 towards the central axis, closing (inactivating) the channel. The inactivated conformation is characterized by a downward conformation of the cytoplasmic assembly, a tightly-knit subunit interface contributed by a fully occupied and partially remodeled Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; activation site, and two salt bridges between the EF hand domain and the S2-S3 loop of the neighboring subunit validated by naturally-occurring diseasecausing mutations. Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; also bound to ATP, mediating a tighter interaction between S6 and CTD. Our study suggests that the &lt;italic&gt;closed-inactivated&lt;/italic&gt; is a distinctive state of the RyR1 and its transition to the &lt;italic&gt;closed-activable&lt;/italic&gt; state is not a simple reverse of the Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; mediated activation pathway.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.468550" rel="alternate" title="Ca2+-inactivation of the mammalian ryanodine receptor type 1 in a lipidic environment revealed by cryo-EM (8 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.468928</id><title>Deciphering a hexameric protein complex with Angstrom optical resolution (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.062397+00:00</updated><author><name>Hisham Mazal</name></author><author><name>Franz-Ferdinand Wieser</name></author><author><name>Vahid Sandoghdar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cryogenic optical localization in three dimensions (COLD) was recently shown to resolve up to four binding sites on a single protein. However, because COLD relies on intensity fluctuations that result from the blinking behavior of fluorophores, it is limited to cases, where individual emitters show different brightness. This significantly lowers the measurement yield. To extend the number of resolved sites as well as the measurement yield, we employ partial labeling and combine it with polarization encoding in order to identify single fluorophores during their stochastic blinking. We then use a particle classification scheme to identify and resolve heterogenous subsets and combine them to reconstruct the three-dimensional arrangement of large molecular complexes. We showcase this method (polarCOLD) by resolving the trimer arrangement of proliferating cell nuclear antigen (PCNA) and the hexamer geometry of Caseinolytic Peptidase B (ClpB) of Thermus thermophilus in its quaternary structure, both with Angstrom resolution. The combination of polarCOLD and single-particle cryogenic electron microscopy (cryoEM) promises to provide crucial insight into intrinsic, environmental and dynamic heterogeneities of biomolecular structures. Furthermore, our approach is fully compatible with fluorescent protein labeling and can, thus, be used in a wide range of studies in cell and membrane biology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.468928" rel="alternate" title="Deciphering a hexameric protein complex with Angstrom optical resolution (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.467680</id><title>Loss of soluble guanylyl cyclase in platelets contributes to atherosclerotic plaque formation and vascular inflammation (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.062593+00:00</updated><author><name>Carina Mauersberger</name></author><author><name>Hendrik B. Sager</name></author><author><name>Jana Wobst</name></author><author><name>Tan An Dang</name></author><author><name>Laura Lambrecht</name></author><author><name>Simon Koplev</name></author><author><name>Marlène Stroth</name></author><author><name>Noomen Bettaga</name></author><author><name>Jens Schlossmann</name></author><author><name>Frank Wunder</name></author><author><name>Andreas Friebe</name></author><author><name>Johan L.M. Björkegren</name></author><author><name>Lisa Dietz</name></author><author><name>Peter Sandner</name></author><author><name>Oliver Soehnlein</name></author><author><name>Heribert Schunkert</name></author><author><name>Thorsten Kessler</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aim&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The role of platelets in atherosclerosis remains incompletely understood. Variants in genes encoding the soluble guanylyl cyclase (sGC) in platelets are associated with coronary artery disease (CAD) risk. Here we sought to investigate the contribution of platelet sGC to atherosclerosis and the therapeutic potential of targeting sGC in atherosclerosis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods and Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We genetically deleted sGC in platelets of atherosclerosis-prone &lt;italic&gt;Ldlr&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; mice. By intravital fluorescence microscopy such Pf4-&lt;italic&gt;Cre&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Gucy1b1&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;flox&lt;/sup&gt;/&lt;sup&gt;flox&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Ldlr&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; mice displayed enhanced leukocyte adhesion to atherosclerotic plaques in comparison with their litter mates. Moreover, histological and flow cytometry analyses revealed more numerous inflammatory leukocytes and larger plaque sizes in aortic tissue of &lt;italic&gt;Ldlr&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; mice lacking sGC in platelets. &lt;italic&gt;In vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, supernatant from activated platelets lacking sGC promoted leukocyte adhesion to endothelial cells (EC) via enhanced EC activation. Using cytokine profiling, we identified reduced angiopoietin-1 release by Pf4-&lt;italic&gt;Cre&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Gucy1b1&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;flox&lt;/sup&gt;/&lt;sup&gt;flox&lt;/sup&gt; and human &lt;italic&gt;GUCY1A1&lt;/italic&gt; risk allele carrier platelets to be responsible for enhanced activation of EC and subsequent leukocyte adhesion. Pharmacological sGC stimulation increased platelet angiopoietin-1 release &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and reduced recruitment of adoptively transferred leukocytes in &lt;italic&gt;Ldlr&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; mice fed a Western diet. Pharmacological sGC stimulation further reduced atherosclerotic plaque formation and vascular inflammation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Loss of sGC in platelets contributes to atherosclerotic plaque formation via reduced release of the soluble factor angiopoietin-1 and, subsequently, enhanced leukocyte recruitment. Pharmacological sGC stimulation might represent a novel therapeutic strategy to prevent and treat CAD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Translational perspective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reduced platelet soluble guanylyl cyclase activity contributes to atherosclerotic plaque formation and vascular inflammation. Stimulators of the soluble guanylyl cyclase, an emerging class of drugs already used in pulmonary hypertension and heart failure, are able to reduce atherosclerosis and inflammation in this preclinical model. Together with evidence from human genetics, our findings suggest a promising role of soluble guanylyl cyclase stimulation to prevent coronary artery disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.467680" rel="alternate" title="Loss of soluble guanylyl cyclase in platelets contributes to atherosclerotic plaque formation and vascular inflammation (5 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469073</id><title>Adhesion strength between cells regulate non-monotonic growth by a biomechanical feedback mechanism (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.062800+00:00</updated><author><name>Abdul Malmi-Kakkada</name></author><author><name>Sumit Sinha</name></author><author><name>Xin Li</name></author><author><name>Dave Thirumalai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We probe the interplay between intercellular interactions and pressure fluctuations associated with single cells in regulating cell proliferation using simulations of a minimal model for three-dimensional multicellular spheroid (MCS) growth. The emergent spatial variations in the cell division rate, that depends on the location of the cells within the MCS, is regulated by intercellular adhesion strength (f^{ad}). This in turn results in non-monotonic proliferation of cells in the MCS with varying adhesion strength, which accords well with experimental results. A biomechanical feedback mechanism coupling the f^{ad} and cell-dependent pressure fluctuations relative to a threshold value (p_c) determines the onset of a dormant phase, and explains the non-monotonic proliferation response. Increasing f^{ad} from low values enhances cell proliferation because pressure on individual cells is smaller compared to p_c. In contrast, at high f^{ad}, cells readily become dormant and cannot rearrange effectively, leading to arrested cell proliferation. Our work, which shows that proliferation is regulated by pressure-adhesion feedback loop, may be a general feature of tumor growth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469073" rel="alternate" title="Adhesion strength between cells regulate non-monotonic growth by a biomechanical feedback mechanism (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468716</id><title>Rigid DNA nanotube tethers suppress high frequency noise in dual-trap optical tweezers systems (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.062929+00:00</updated><author><name>Alan Shaw</name></author><author><name>Rohit Satija</name></author><author><name>Eduardo Antunez de Mayolo De la Matta</name></author><author><name>Susan Marqusee</name></author><author><name>Carlos Bustamante</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Dual trap optical tweezers are a powerful tool to trap and characterize the biophysical properties of single biomolecules such as the folding pathways of proteins and nucleic acids, and the chemomechanical activity of molecular motors. Despite its vastly successful application, noise from drift and fluctuation of the optics, and Brownian motion of the trapped beads still hinder the technique’s ability to directly visualize folding of small biomolecules or the single nucleotide stepping of polymerases, especially at low forces (&amp;lt;10 pN) and sub-millisecond timescales. Rigid DNA nanotubes have been used to replace the conventional dsDNA linker to reduce optical tweezers noise in the low force range. However, optical tweezers are used to study a wide range of biophysical events, with timescales ranging from microseconds to seconds, and length changes ranging from sub nanometers to tens of nanometers. In this study, we systematically evaluate how noise is distributed across different frequencies in dual trap optical tweezers systems–and show that rigid DNA nanotube tethers suppress only high frequency noise (kHz), while the low frequency noise remains the same when compared to that of dsDNA tethers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468716" rel="alternate" title="Rigid DNA nanotube tethers suppress high frequency noise in dual-trap optical tweezers systems (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469147</id><title>Moderate-intensity exercise might be a competitive protocol to prevent obesity and obesity-related metabolic diseases (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.063060+00:00</updated><author><name>Ryeo-Won Kwon</name></author><author><name>Seung-Jea Lee</name></author><author><name>Tae-Wook Kim</name></author><author><name>Jeong Beom Lee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To determine effects of exercise intensity on expression levels of cytokines and neurotransmitters beneficial for the prevention and improvement of obesity and obesity-related metabolic diseases. Expression levels of irisin, fibroblast growth factor-21 (FGF21), adiponectin, free fatty acid (FFA), dopamine (DA), and serotonin (5-HT) levels after moderate-intensity (50% of maximal oxygen uptake (VO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;max)) and high-intensity treadmill running (80% VO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;max) for 30 min in 20 healthy men were compared. Blood samples were collected at three time points: before treadmill running (pre-EX), immediately after treadmill running (post-EX), and at 60 min after treadmill running (60 min post-EX). Expression levels of irisin, FGF21, adiponectin, FFA, DA, and 5-HT were increased after 30 min of treadmill running exercise regardless of exercise intensity. Their levels were increased at 60 min post-EX. They showed no significant difference immediately after exercise regardless of exercise intensity. Only irisin, FGF21, FFA, and DA levels showed significant differences between moderate-intensity (50% VO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;max) group and high-intensity group (80% VO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;max) at 60 min post-EX. Considering that FFA level at 80% VO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;max was significantly lower than that at 50% VO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;max during post-EX and side effects of high-intensity exercise, moderate-intensity exercise would be a more competitive method compared to high-intensity for the prevention and improvement of obesity and obesity-related metabolic diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469147" rel="alternate" title="Moderate-intensity exercise might be a competitive protocol to prevent obesity and obesity-related metabolic diseases (3 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469049</id><title>Prostaglandin PGE2 receptor EP4 regulates microglial phagocytosis and increases susceptibility to diet-induced obesity (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.063182+00:00</updated><author><name>Anzela Niraula</name></author><author><name>Rachael D Fasnacht</name></author><author><name>Kelly M Ness</name></author><author><name>Jeremy M Frey</name></author><author><name>Mauricio D Dorfman</name></author><author><name>Joshua P Thaler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: In rodents, susceptibility to diet-induced obesity requires microglial activation, but the molecular components of this pathway remain incompletely defined. Prostaglandin E2 (PGE2) levels increase in the mediobasal hypothalamus during high fat diet (HFD) feeding, and the PGE2 receptor EP4 regulates microglial activation state and phagocytic activity, suggesting a potential role for microglial EP4 signaling in obesity pathogenesis. Method: Metabolic phenotyping, as assessed by body weight, energy expenditure, glucose, and insulin tolerance, was performed in microglia-specific EP4 knockout (MG-EP4 KO) mice and littermate controls on HFD. Morphological and gene expression analysis of microglia, and a histological survey of microglia-neuron interactions in the arcuate nucleus was performed. Phagocytosis was assessed using in vivo and in vitro pharmacological techniques. Results: Microglial EP4 deletion markedly reduced weight gain and food intake in response to HFD feeding. In correspondence with this lean phenotype, insulin sensitivity was also improved in the HFD-fed MG-EP4 KO mice though glucose tolerance remained surprisingly unaffected. Mechanistically, EP4-deficient microglia showed an attenuated phagocytic state marked by reduced CD68 expression and fewer contacts with POMC neuron soma and processes. These cellular changes observed in the microglial EP4 knockout mice corresponded with an increased density of POMC neurites extending into the paraventricular nucleus. Conclusion: These findings reveal that microglial EP4 signaling promotes body weight gain and insulin resistance during HFD feeding. Furthermore, the data suggest that curbing microglial phagocytic function may preserve POMC cytoarchitecture and PVN input to limit overconsumption during diet-induced obesity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469049" rel="alternate" title="Prostaglandin PGE2 receptor EP4 regulates microglial phagocytosis and increases susceptibility to diet-induced obesity (3 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469302</id><title>Heterogeneous run-and-tumble motion accounts for transient non-Gaussian super-diffusion in haematopoietic multi-potent progenitor cells (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.063316+00:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Partridge</name></author><author><name>Sara Gonzalez Anton</name></author><author><name>Reema Khorshed</name></author><author><name>George Adams</name></author><author><name>Constandina Pospori</name></author><author><name>Cristina Lo Celso</name></author><author><name>Chiu Fan Lee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Multi-potent progenitor (MPP) cells act as a key intermediary step between haematopoietic stem cells and the entirety of the mature blood cell system. Their eventual fate determination is thought to be achieved through migration in and out of spatially distinct niches. Here we first analyze statistically MPP cell trajectory data obtained from a series of long time-course 3D in-vivo imaging experiments on irradiated mouse calvaria, and report that MPPs display transient super-diffusion with apparent non-Gaussian displacement distributions. Second, we explain these experimental findings using a run-and-tumble model of cell motion which incorporates the observed dynamical heterogeneity of the MPPs. Third, we use our model to extrapolate the dynamics to time-periods currently inaccessible experimentally,  which enables us to quantitatively estimate the time and length scales at which super-diffusion transitions to Fickian diffusion. Our work sheds light on the potential importance of motility in early haematopoietic progenitor function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469302" rel="alternate" title="Heterogeneous run-and-tumble motion accounts for transient non-Gaussian super-diffusion in haematopoietic multi-potent progenitor cells (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469265</id><title>Partial prevention of glucocorticoid-induced osteocyte deterioration with osteocrin gene therapy (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.063455+00:00</updated><author><name>Courtney M Mazur</name></author><author><name>Christian D Castro Andrade</name></author><author><name>Tadatoshi Sato</name></author><author><name>Michael Bruce</name></author><author><name>Mary L Bouxsein</name></author><author><name>Jialiang S Wang</name></author><author><name>Marc N Wein</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glucocorticoid (GC)-induced osteoporosis and subsequent bone fragility are preceded by death and dysfunction at the cellular level. In particular, short-term glucocorticoid excess suppresses osteocyte remodeling of the surrounding bone mineral, causes apoptosis of osteoblasts and osteocytes, and disrupts homeostatic bone remodeling. Preventing apoptosis and preserving osteocyte morphology and function could be effective means of preventing bone loss during glucocorticoid excess. We hypothesized that osteocrin, which preserves osteocyte viability and morphology in other models where osteocyte defects exist, could prevent osteocyte death and dysfunction in a GC excess model. We used a liver-targeted adeno-associated virus (AAV8) to induce osteocrin overexpression in mice one week prior to implantation with prednisolone or placebo pellets. After 28 days, tissues were collected for micro-CT and histological analysis. GC excess caused the expected reduction in cortical bone thickness and osteocyte canalicular length in control AAV8-treated mice, and these effects were blunted in mice overexpressing osteocrin. However, GC-induced changes in cortical porosity, trabecular bone mass, and gene expression were not prevented by osteocrin. While the mechanism of osteocrin's effects on osteocyte morphology warrants further investigation, this study does not support a role for this model of osteocrin supplementation to combat the full skeletal effects of GC excess.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469265" rel="alternate" title="Partial prevention of glucocorticoid-induced osteocyte deterioration with osteocrin gene therapy (3 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>