<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.774886+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460226</id><title>Enhanced Specificity Mutations Perturb Allosteric Signaling in CRISPR-Cas9 (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.775279+00:00</updated><author><name>Łukasz Nierzwicki</name></author><author><name>Kyle W. East</name></author><author><name>Uriel N. Morzan</name></author><author><name>Pablo R. Arantes</name></author><author><name>Victor S. Batista</name></author><author><name>George P. Lisi</name></author><author><name>Giulia Palermo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;CRISPR-Cas9 is a molecular tool with transformative genome editing capabilities. At the molecular level, an intricate allosteric signaling is critical for DNA cleavage, but its role in the specificity enhancement of the Cas9 endonuclease is poorly understood. Here, solution NMR is combined with multi-microsecond molecular dynamics and graph theory-derived models to probe the allosteric role of key enhancement specificity mutations. We show that the mutations responsible for increasing the specificity of Cas9 alter the allosteric structure of the catalytic HNH domain, impacting the signal transmission from the DNA recognition region to the catalytic sites for cleavage. Specifically, the K855A mutation strongly disrupts the HNH domain allosteric structure, exerting the highest perturbation on the signaling transfer, while K810A and K848A result in more moderate effects on the allosteric intercommunication. This differential perturbation of the allosteric signaling reflects the different capabilities of the single mutants to increase Cas9 specificity, with the mutation achieving the highest specificity also strongly perturbing the signaling transfer. These outcomes reveal that the allosteric regulation is critical for the specificity enhancement of the Cas9 enzyme, and are valuable to harness the signaling network to improve the system’s specificity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460226" rel="alternate" title="Enhanced Specificity Mutations Perturb Allosteric Signaling in CRISPR-Cas9 (13 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.15.460093</id><title>Structural Basis of Substrate Recognition by the Mitochondrial ADP/ATP Transporter (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.775564+00:00</updated><author><name>Shihao Yao</name></author><author><name>Qiuzi Yi</name></author><author><name>Boyuan Ma</name></author><author><name>Xiaoting Mao</name></author><author><name>Ye Chen</name></author><author><name>Min-Xin Guan</name></author><author><name>Xiaohui Cang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Specific import of ADP and export of ATP by ADP/ATP carrier (AAC) across the inner mitochondrial membrane are crucial for sustainable energy supply in all eukaryotes. However, mechanism for highly specific substrate recognition in the dynamic transport process remains largely elusive. Here, unguided MD simulations of 22 microseconds in total reveal that AAC in ground c-state uses the second basic patch (K91K95R187), tyrosine ladder (Y186Y190Y194), F191 and N115 in the upper region of the cavity to specifically recognize ADP and confer selectivity for ADP over ATP. Mutations of these residues in yeast AAC2 reduce ADP transport across the &lt;italic&gt;L. lactis&lt;/italic&gt; membrane and induce defects in OXPHOS and ATP production in yeast. Sequence analyses also suggest that AAC and other adenine nucleotide transporters use the upper region of the cavity, rather than the central binding site to discriminate their substrates. Identification of the new site unveils the unusually high substrate specificity of AAC, and together with central binding site support early biochemical findings about existence of two substrate binding sites. Our results imply that using different sites for substrate recognition and conformational transition could be a smart strategy for transporters to cope with substrate recognition problem in the highly dynamic transport process.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.15.460093" rel="alternate" title="Structural Basis of Substrate Recognition by the Mitochondrial ADP/ATP Transporter (9 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460297</id><title>Mitochondrial ATP production is required for endothelial cell control of vascular tone (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.775758+00:00</updated><author><name>Calum Wilson</name></author><author><name>Matthew D. Lee</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Buckley</name></author><author><name>Xun Zhang</name></author><author><name>John G. McCarron</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Arteries and veins are lined by non-proliferating endothelial cells that play a critical role in regulating blood flow. Endothelial cells also regulate tissue perfusion, metabolite exchange, and thrombosis. It is thought that endothelial cells rely on ATP generated via glycolysis to fuel each of these energy-demanding processes. However, endothelial metabolism has mainly been studied in the context of proliferative cells in angiogenesis, and little is known about energy production in endothelial cells within the fully-formed vascular wall. Using intact arteries isolated from rats and mice, we show that inhibiting mitochondrial oxidative phosphorylation disrupts endothelial control of vascular tone. The role for endothelial cell energy production is independent of species, sex, or vascular bed. Basal, mechanically-activated, and agonist-evoked calcium activity in intact artery endothelial cells are each prevented by inhibiting mitochondrial ATP synthesis. This effect is mimicked by blocking the transport of pyruvate, the master fuel for mitochondrial energy production, through the mitochondrial pyruvate carrier. These data show that mitochondrial ATP is necessary for calcium-dependent, nitric oxide mediated endothelial control of vascular tone, and identifies the critical role of endothelial mitochondrial energy production in fueling perfused blood vessel function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460297" rel="alternate" title="Mitochondrial ATP production is required for endothelial cell control of vascular tone (7 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.16.460651</id><title>Unlabeled salivary gland organoids have distinct Raman signatures following FGF2-induced proacinar cell differentiation (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.775934+00:00</updated><author><name>Kate Tubbesing</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Moskwa</name></author><author><name>Ting Chean Khoo</name></author><author><name>Deirdre A. Nelson</name></author><author><name>Anna Sharikova</name></author><author><name>Melinda Larsen</name></author><author><name>Alexander Khmaladze</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Organoids are self-organized three-dimensional (3D) tissue cultures that model the structure and function of organs to provide insights into signaling during organ formation and have translational applications in disease modeling and assessing drug responses. Due to their heterogeneity, there is a need for non-destructive methods to identify the differentiation state, or the phenotype, of organoids. As organoids often contain complex mixtures of basement membrane and/or extracellular matrix proteins, which are often highly auto-fluorescent, it typically makes low-resolution Raman measurements a challenge. We developed Raman confocal micro-spectroscopy methods to avoid and minimize the matrix signal and define specific Raman signatures for growth factor-differentiated and non-differentiated organoids. In complex, branched salivary gland organoids derived from mouse embryonic epithelial and stromal cells embedded within the laminin-rich basement membrane matrix, Matrigel, we identified specific Raman spectral signatures for organoids in different differentiation states. We report that either comparison of spectral signatures or multivariate SVD analysis can be used to distinguish between organoids treated with FGF2, organoids treated with EGF, and non-treated controls. Raman spectral signatures can be used to non-invasively distinguish between different phenotypes in the 3D context of unlabeled organoids.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;FGF2-dependent proacinar cell differentiation in salivary organoids have unique Raman signatures detected with a novel confocal-based Raman imaging approach.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;These signatures can be used in unlabeled salivary organoids to monitor proacinar cell differentiation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Confocal-based Raman imaging may be applicable to monitoring differentiation state of other types of organoids.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.16.460651" rel="alternate" title="Unlabeled salivary gland organoids have distinct Raman signatures following FGF2-induced proacinar cell differentiation (7 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460235</id><title>Paramagnetic spin labeling of a bacterial DnaB helicase for solid-state NMR (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.776899+00:00</updated><author><name>Johannes Zehnder</name></author><author><name>Riccardo Cadalbert</name></author><author><name>Maxim Yulikov</name></author><author><name>Georg Künze</name></author><author><name>Thomas Wiegand</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Labeling of biomolecules with a paramagnetic probe for nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy enables determining long-range distance restraints, which are otherwise not accessible by classically used dipolar coupling-based NMR approaches. Distance restraints derived from paramagnetic relaxation enhancements (PREs) can facilitate the structure determination of large proteins and protein complexes. We herein present the site-directed labeling of the large oligomeric bacterial DnaB helicase from &lt;italic&gt;Helicobacter pylori&lt;/italic&gt; with cysteine-reactive maleimide tags carrying either a nitroxide radical or a lanthanide ion. The success of the labeling reaction was followed by quantitative continuous-wave electron paramagnetic resonance (EPR) experiments performed on the nitroxide-labeled protein. PREs were extracted site-specifically from 2D and 3D solid-state NMR spectra. A good agreement with predicted PRE values, derived by computational modeling of nitroxide and Gd&lt;sup&gt;3+&lt;/sup&gt; tags in the low-resolution DnaB crystal structure, was found. Comparison of experimental PREs and model-predicted spin label-nucleus distances indicated that the size of the “blind sphere” around the paramagnetic center, in which NMR resonances are not detected, is slightly larger for Gd&lt;sup&gt;3+&lt;/sup&gt; (~14 Å) than for nitroxide (~11 Å) in &lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C-detected 2D spectra of DnaB. We also present Gd&lt;sup&gt;3+&lt;/sup&gt;-Gd&lt;sup&gt;3+&lt;/sup&gt; dipolar electron-electron resonance EPR experiments on DnaB supporting the conclusion that DnaB was present as a hexameric assembly.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460235" rel="alternate" title="Paramagnetic spin labeling of a bacterial DnaB helicase for solid-state NMR (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460151</id><title>Allosteric modulation of the adenosine A2A receptor by cholesterol (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.777172+00:00</updated><author><name>Shuya Kate Huang</name></author><author><name>Omar Almurad</name></author><author><name>Reizel J. Pejana</name></author><author><name>Zachary A. Morrison</name></author><author><name>Aditya Pandey</name></author><author><name>Louis-Philippe Picard</name></author><author><name>Mark Nitz</name></author><author><name>Adnan Sljoka</name></author><author><name>R. Scott Prosser</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cholesterol is a major component of the cell membrane and commonly regulates membrane protein function. Here, we investigate how cholesterol modulates the conformational equilibria and signaling of the adenosine A&lt;sub&gt;2A&lt;/sub&gt; receptor (A&lt;sub&gt;2A&lt;/sub&gt;R) in reconstituted phospholipid bilayers. GTP hydrolysis assays show that cholesterol is a weak positive allosteric modulator of A&lt;sub&gt;2A&lt;/sub&gt;R, as seen through enhanced basal signaling and a small decrease in agonist EC&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;. Fluorine nuclear magnetic resonance (&lt;sup&gt;19&lt;/sup&gt;F NMR) spectroscopy suggests that this enhancement arises from an increase in the receptor’s active state populations and stronger G protein coupling. &lt;sup&gt;19&lt;/sup&gt;F NMR of fluorinated cholesterol analogs reveals transient and non-specific interactions with A&lt;sub&gt;2A&lt;/sub&gt;R, indicating a lack of high-affinity binding sites or direct allosteric modulation. This is confirmed by computational analysis which suggests that cholesterol contacts confer a weak and possibly negative allosteric effect. The combined results suggest that the observed cholesterol allostery in A&lt;sub&gt;2A&lt;/sub&gt;R is likely a result of indirect membrane effects through cholesterol-mediated changes in membrane properties, as shown by membrane fluidity measurements and high-pressure NMR.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460151" rel="alternate" title="Allosteric modulation of the adenosine A2A receptor by cholesterol (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460366</id><title>The polyol pathway is an evolutionarily conserved system for sensing glucose uptake (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.777679+00:00</updated><author><name>Hiroko Sano</name></author><author><name>Akira Nakamura</name></author><author><name>Mariko Yamane</name></author><author><name>Hitoshi Niwa</name></author><author><name>Takashi Nishimura</name></author><author><name>Kimi Araki</name></author><author><name>Kazumasa Takemoto</name></author><author><name>Kei-ichiro Ishiguro</name></author><author><name>Hiroki Aoki</name></author><author><name>Masayasu Kojima</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cells must adjust the expression levels of metabolic enzymes in response to fluctuating nutrient supply. For glucose, such metabolic remodeling is highly dependent on a master transcription factor ChREBP/MondoA. However, it remains elusive how glucose fluctuations are sensed by ChREBP/MondoA despite the stability of major glycolytic pathways. Here we show that in both flies and mice, ChREBP/MondoA activation in response to glucose ingestion depends on an evolutionarily conserved glucose-metabolizing pathway: the polyol pathway. The polyol pathway converts glucose to fructose via sorbitol. It has been believed that this pathway is almost silent, and its activation in hyperglycemic conditions has deleterious effects on human health. We show that the polyol pathway is required for the glucose-induced nuclear translocation of Mondo, a &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; homologue of ChREBP/MondoA, which directs gene expression for organismal growth and metabolism. Likewise, inhibition of the polyol pathway in mice impairs ChREBP’s nuclear localization and reduces glucose tolerance. We propose that the polyol pathway is an evolutionarily conserved sensing system for the glucose uptake that allows metabolic remodeling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460366" rel="alternate" title="The polyol pathway is an evolutionarily conserved system for sensing glucose uptake (3 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460073</id><title>Addition of a carboxy terminal tail to the normally tailless gonadotropin-releasing hormone receptor impairs fertility in female mice (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.777996+00:00</updated><author><name>Chirine Toufaily</name></author><author><name>Jérôme Fortin</name></author><author><name>Carlos A. I. Alonso</name></author><author><name>Evelyn Lapointe</name></author><author><name>Xiang Zhou</name></author><author><name>Yorgui Santiago-Andres</name></author><author><name>Yeu-Farn Lin</name></author><author><name>Yimming Cui</name></author><author><name>Ying Wang</name></author><author><name>Dominic Devost</name></author><author><name>Ferdinand Roelfsema</name></author><author><name>Frederik Steyn</name></author><author><name>Aylin C. Hanyaloglu</name></author><author><name>Terence E. Hébert</name></author><author><name>Tatiana Fiordelisio</name></author><author><name>Derek Boerboom</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Bernard</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) is the primary neuropeptide controlling reproduction in vertebrates. GnRH stimulates follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) and luteinizing hormone (LH) synthesis via a G protein-coupled receptor, GnRHR, in the pituitary gland. In mammals, GnRHR lacks a C-terminal cytosolic tail (Ctail) and does not exhibit homologous desensitization. This might be an evolutionary adaptation that enables LH surge generation and ovulation. To test this idea, we fused the chicken GnRHR Ctail to the endogenous murine GnRHR in a transgenic model. The LH surge was blunted, but not blocked in these mice. In contrast, they showed reductions in FSH production, ovarian follicle development, and fertility. Addition of the Ctail altered the nature of agonist-induced calcium signaling required for normal FSH production. The loss of the GnRHR Ctail during mammalian evolution is unlikely to have conferred a selective advantage by enabling the LH surge. The adaptive significance of this specialization remains to be determined.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460073" rel="alternate" title="Addition of a carboxy terminal tail to the normally tailless gonadotropin-releasing hormone receptor impairs fertility in female mice (3 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>