<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.526548+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.04.458950</id><title>Versatile, do-it-yourself, low-cost spinning disk confocal microscope (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.527865+00:00</updated><author><name>Aaron R. Halpern</name></author><author><name>Min Yen Lee</name></author><author><name>Marco D. Howard</name></author><author><name>Marcus A. Woodworth</name></author><author><name>Philip R. Nicovich</name></author><author><name>Joshua C. Vaughan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Confocal microscopy is an invaluable tool for 3D imaging of biological specimens, however, accessibility is often limited to core facilities due to the high cost of the hardware. We describe an inexpensive do-it-yourself (DIY) spinning disk confocal microscope (SDCM) module based on a commercially fabricated chromium photomask that can be added on to a laser-illuminated epifluorescence microscope. The SDCM achieves strong performance across a wide wavelength range (~400-800 nm) as demonstrated through a series of biological imaging applications that include conventional microscopy (immunofluorescence, small-molecule stains, and fluorescence in situ hybridization) and super-resolution microscopy (single-molecule localization microscopy and expansion microscopy). This low-cost and simple DIY SDCM is well-documented and should help increase accessibility to confocal microscopy for researchers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.04.458950" rel="alternate" title="Versatile, do-it-yourself, low-cost spinning disk confocal microscope (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.31.458345</id><title>Cryo-ET of HIV reveals Env positioning on Gag lattice and structural variation among Env trimers (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.528315+00:00</updated><author><name>Vidya Mangala Prasad</name></author><author><name>Daniel P. Leaman</name></author><author><name>Klaus N. Lovendahl</name></author><author><name>Mark A. Benhaim</name></author><author><name>Edgar A. Hodge</name></author><author><name>Michael B. Zwick</name></author><author><name>Kelly K. Lee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;HIV-1 Env mediates viral entry into host cells and is the sole target for neutralizing antibodies. However, Env structure and organization in its native virion context has eluded detailed characterization. Here we used cryo-electron tomography to analyze Env in mature and immature HIV-1 particles. Immature particles showed distinct Env positioning relative to the underlying Gag lattice, providing insights into long-standing questions about Env incorporation. A 9.1Å sub-tomogram averaged reconstruction of virion-bound Env in conjunction with structural mass spectrometry revealed unexpected features, including a variable central core of the gp41 subunit, heterogeneous glycosylation between protomers plus a flexible stalk that allows Env tilting and variable exposure of neutralizing epitopes. Together, our results provide an integrative understanding of HIV assembly and structural variation in Env antigen presentation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.31.458345" rel="alternate" title="Cryo-ET of HIV reveals Env positioning on Gag lattice and structural variation among Env trimers (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>