<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.310021+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469536</id><title>Sampling the conformational landscapes of transporters and receptors with AlphaFold2 (179 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.310382+00:00</updated><author><name>Diego del Alamo</name></author><author><name>Davide Sala</name></author><author><name>Hassane S. Mchaourab</name></author><author><name>Jens Meiler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Equilibrium fluctuations and triggered conformational changes often underlie the functional cycles of membrane proteins. For example, transporters mediate the passage of molecules across cell membranes by alternating between inward-facing (IF) and outward-facing (OF) states, while receptors undergo intracellular structural rearrangements that initiate signaling cascades. Although the conformational plasticity of these proteins has historically posed a challenge for traditional &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; protein structure prediction pipelines, the recent success of AlphaFold2 (AF2) in CASP14 culminated in the modeling of a transporter in multiple conformations to high accuracy. Given that AF2 was designed to predict static structures of proteins, it remains unclear if this result represents an underexplored capability to accurately predict multiple conformations and/or structural heterogeneity. Here, we present an approach to drive AF2 to sample alternative conformations of topologically diverse transporters and G-protein coupled receptors (GPCRs) that are absent from the AF2 training set. Whereas models generated using the default AF2 pipeline are conformationally homogeneous and nearly identical to one another, reducing the depth of the input multiple sequence alignments (MSAs) led to the generation of accurate models in multiple conformations. In our benchmark, these conformations were observed to span the range between two experimental structures of interest, suggesting that our protocol allows sampling of the conformational landscape at the energy minimum. Nevertheless, our results also highlight the need for the next generation of deep learning algorithms to be designed to predict ensembles of biophysically relevant states.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469536" rel="alternate" title="Sampling the conformational landscapes of transporters and receptors with AlphaFold2 (179 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469671</id><title>Inferring kinetic rate constants from single-molecule FRET trajectories – a blind benchmark of kinetic analysis tools (47 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.310555+00:00</updated><author><name>Markus Götz</name></author><author><name>Anders Barth</name></author><author><name>Søren S.-R. Bohr</name></author><author><name>Richard Börner</name></author><author><name>Jixin Chen</name></author><author><name>Thorben Cordes</name></author><author><name>Dorothy A. Erie</name></author><author><name>Christian Gebhardt</name></author><author><name>Mélodie C.A.S. Hadzic</name></author><author><name>George L. Hamilton</name></author><author><name>Nikos S. Hatzakis</name></author><author><name>Thorsten Hugel</name></author><author><name>Lydia Kisley</name></author><author><name>Don C. Lamb</name></author><author><name>Carlos de Lannoy</name></author><author><name>Chelsea Mahn</name></author><author><name>Dushani Dunukara</name></author><author><name>Dick de Ridder</name></author><author><name>Hugo Sanabria</name></author><author><name>Julia Schimpf</name></author><author><name>Claus A.M. Seidel</name></author><author><name>Roland K.O. Sigel</name></author><author><name>Magnus Berg Sletfjerding</name></author><author><name>Johannes Thomsen</name></author><author><name>Leonie Vollmar</name></author><author><name>Simon Wanninger</name></author><author><name>Keith R. Weninger</name></author><author><name>Pengning Xu</name></author><author><name>Sonja Schmid</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single-molecule FRET (smFRET) is a versatile technique to study the dynamics and function of biomolecules since it makes nanoscale movements detectable as fluorescence signals. The powerful ability to infer quantitative kinetic information from smFRET data is, however, complicated by experimental limitations. Diverse analysis tools have been developed to overcome these hurdles but a systematic comparison is lacking. Here, we report the results of a blind benchmark study assessing eleven analysis tools used to infer kinetic rate constants from smFRET trajectories. We tested them against simulated and experimental data containing the most prominent difficulties encountered in analyzing smFRET experiments: different noise levels, varied model complexity, non-equilibrium dynamics, and kinetic heterogeneity. Our results highlight the current strengths and limitations in inferring kinetic information from smFRET trajectories. In addition, we formulate concrete recommendations and identify key targets for future developments, aimed to advance our understanding of biomolecular dynamics through quantitative experiment-derived models.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469671" rel="alternate" title="Inferring kinetic rate constants from single-molecule FRET trajectories – a blind benchmark of kinetic analysis tools (47 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470086</id><title>Multi-state Modeling of G-protein Coupled Receptors at Experimental Accuracy (41 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.311302+00:00</updated><author><name>Lim Heo</name></author><author><name>Michael Feig</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The family of G-protein coupled receptors (GPCRs) is one of the largest protein families in the human genome. GPCRs transduct chemical signals from extracellular to intracellular regions via a conformational switch between active and inactive states upon ligand binding. While experimental structures of GPCRs remain limited, high-accuracy computational predictions are now possible with AlphaFold2. However, AlphaFold2 only predicts one state and is biased towards the inactive conformation. Here, a multi-state prediction protocol is introduced that extends AlphaFold2 to predict either active or inactive states at very high accuracy using state-annotated templated GPCR databases. The predicted models accurately capture the main structural changes upon activation of the GPCR at the atomic level. The models were also highly successful in predicting ligand binding poses via protein-ligand docking. We expect that high accuracy GPCR models in both activation states will promote understanding in GPCR activation mechanisms and drug discovery for GPCRs. At the time, the new protocol paves the way towards capturing the dynamics of proteins at high-accuracy via machine-learning methods.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470086" rel="alternate" title="Multi-state Modeling of G-protein Coupled Receptors at Experimental Accuracy (41 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469684</id><title>Cryo-EM structure of the octameric pore of Clostridium perfringens β-toxin (32 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.311511+00:00</updated><author><name>Julia Bruggisser</name></author><author><name>Ioan Iacovache</name></author><author><name>Samuel C. Musson</name></author><author><name>Matteo T. Degiacomi</name></author><author><name>Horst Posthaus</name></author><author><name>Benoît Zuber</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We describe the cryo-EM structure of &lt;italic&gt;Clostridium perfringens&lt;/italic&gt; β-toxin (CBP) in styrene maleic acid (SMA) discs, which represents the membrane-inserted pore form, at near atomic resolution. We show that CPB forms an octamer, which though having a similar conformation to the hetero-oligomeric pores of bicomponent leukocidins, features a different receptor binding region and a novel N-terminal β-barrel. The latter contains an additional selectivity filter and creates a bipolar pore. We propose that the N-terminal β-barrel domain may regulate oligomerization and solubility of the complex and influence channel conductance and monomer stability. In addition, we show that the β-barrel protrusion domain can be modified or exchanged without affecting the pore forming ability, thus making the pore particularly attractive for macromolecule sensing and nanotechnology. The cryo-EM structure of the octameric pore of CPB will facilitate future developments in both nanotechnology and basic research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469684" rel="alternate" title="Cryo-EM structure of the octameric pore of Clostridium perfringens β-toxin (32 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469591</id><title>Chemo-mechanical Diffusion Waves Orchestrate Collective Dynamics of Immune Cell Podosomes (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.311658+00:00</updated><author><name>Ze Gong</name></author><author><name>Koen van den Dries</name></author><author><name>Alessandra Cambi</name></author><author><name>Vivek B. Shenoy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Immune cells, such as macrophages and dendritic cells, can utilize podosomes, actin-rich protrusions, to generate forces, migrate, and patrol for foreign antigens. In these cells, individual podosomes exhibit periodic protrusion and retraction cycles (vertical oscillations) to probe their microenvironment, while multiple podosomes arranged in clusters demonstrate coordinated wave-like spatiotemporal dynamics. However, the mechanisms governing both the individual vertical oscillations and the coordinated oscillation waves in clusters remain unclear. By integrating actin polymerization, myosin contractility, actin diffusion, and mechanosensitive signaling, we develop a chemo-mechanical model for both the oscillatory growth of individual podosomes and wave-like dynamics in clusters. Our model reveals that podosomes show oscillatory growth when the actin polymerization-associated protrusion and the signaling-associated myosin contraction occur at similar rates, while the diffusion of actin monomers within the cluster drives mesoscale coordination of individual podosome oscillations in an apparent wave-like fashion. Our model predicts the influence of different pharmacological treatments targeting myosin activity, actin polymerization, and mechanosensitive pathways, as well as the impact of the microenvironment stiffness on the wavelengths, frequencies, and speeds of the chemo-mechanical waves. Overall, our integrated theoretical and experimental approach reveals how collective wave dynamics arise due to the coupling between chemo-mechanical signaling and actin diffusion, shedding light on the role of podosomes in immune cell mechanosensing within the context of wound healing and cancer immunotherapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469591" rel="alternate" title="Chemo-mechanical Diffusion Waves Orchestrate Collective Dynamics of Immune Cell Podosomes (30 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.469928</id><title>Systemic LSD1 inhibition prevents aberrant remodeling of metabolism in obesity (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.311787+00:00</updated><author><name>Bastian Ramms</name></author><author><name>Dennis P. Pollow</name></author><author><name>Han Zhu</name></author><author><name>Chelsea Nora</name></author><author><name>Austin R. Harrington</name></author><author><name>Ibrahim Omar</name></author><author><name>Philip L.S.M. Gordts</name></author><author><name>Matthew Wortham</name></author><author><name>Maike Sander</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The transition from lean to obese states involves systemic metabolic remodeling that impacts insulin sensitivity, lipid partitioning, inflammation, and glycemic control. Here, we have taken a pharmacological approach to test the role of a nutrient-regulated chromatin modifier, lysine-specific demethylase (LSD1), in obesity-associated metabolic reprogramming. We show that systemic administration of an LSD1 inhibitor (GSK-LSD1) reduces food intake and body weight, ameliorates non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD), and improves insulin sensitivity and glycemic control in mouse models of obesity. GSK-LSD1 has little effect on systemic metabolism of lean mice, suggesting LSD1 has a context-dependent role in promoting maladaptive changes in obesity. Analysis of insulin target tissues identified white adipose tissue as the major site of insulin sensitization by GSK-LSD1, where it reduces adipocyte inflammation and lipolysis. We demonstrate that GSK-LSD1 reverses NAFLD in a non-hepatocyte-autonomous manner, suggesting an indirect mechanism via inhibition of adipocyte lipolysis and subsequent effects on lipid partitioning. Pair-feeding experiments further revealed that effects of GSK-LSD1 on hyperglycemia and NAFLD are not a consequence of reduced food intake and weight loss. These findings suggest that targeting LSD1 could be a strategy for treatment of obesity and its associated complications including type 2 diabetes and NAFLD.
&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="469928v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.469928" rel="alternate" title="Systemic LSD1 inhibition prevents aberrant remodeling of metabolism in obesity (21 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.470048</id><title>The structure of the enigmatic ripple phase in saturated bilayers resolved: Machine learning reveals four lipid populations (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.311942+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Davies</name></author><author><name>A. D. Reyes-Figueroa</name></author><author><name>Andrey A. Gurtovenko</name></author><author><name>Daniel Frankel</name></author><author><name>Mikko Karttunen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A new mixed radial-angular, three-particle correlation function method in combination with unsupervised machine learning (ML) was applied to examine the emergence of the ripple phase in dipalmitoyphosphatidylcholine (DPPC) lipid bilayers using data from atomistic molecular dynamics (MD) simulations of system sizes ranging from 128 to 4,096 lipids. Based on the acyl tail conformations, the analysis revealed the presence of four distinct conformational populations of lipids in the ripple phases of the DPPC lipid bilayers. The expected gel- (ordered; &lt;italic&gt;L&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;o&lt;/sub&gt;) and fluid-like (disordered; &lt;italic&gt;L&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;d&lt;/sub&gt;) lipids are found along with their splayed tail equivalents (&lt;italic&gt;L&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;o,s&lt;/sub&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;L&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;d,s&lt;/sub&gt;). These lipids differ based on their gauche distribution and tail packing. The disordered (&lt;italic&gt;L&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;d&lt;/sub&gt;) and disordered splayed (&lt;italic&gt;L&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;d,s&lt;/sub&gt;) lipids spatially cluster in the ripple in the groove side, that is, in an asymmetric manner across the bilayer leaflets. The ripple phase does not contain large numbers of &lt;italic&gt;L&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;d&lt;/sub&gt; lipids, instead they only exist on the interface of the groove side of the undulation. The bulk of the groove side is a complex coexistence of &lt;italic&gt;L&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;o&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;L&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;o,s&lt;/sub&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;L&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;d,s&lt;/sub&gt; lipids. The convex side of the undulation contains predominantly &lt;italic&gt;L&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;o&lt;/sub&gt; lipids. Thus, the structure of the ripple phase is neither a simple coexistence of ordered and disordered lipids nor a coexistence of ordered interdigitating gel-like (&lt;italic&gt;L&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;o&lt;/sub&gt;) and ordered splayed (&lt;italic&gt;L&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;o,s&lt;/sub&gt;) lipids, but instead a coexistence of an ordered phase and a complex mixed phase. Principal component analysis (PCA) further confirmed the existence of the four lipid groups.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.470048" rel="alternate" title="The structure of the enigmatic ripple phase in saturated bilayers resolved: Machine learning reveals four lipid populations (17 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469620</id><title>In Diverse Conditions Intrinsic Chromatin Condensates Have Liquid-like Material Properties (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.312074+00:00</updated><author><name>Bryan A. Gibson</name></author><author><name>Claudia Blaukopf</name></author><author><name>Tracy Lou</name></author><author><name>Lynda K. Doolittle</name></author><author><name>Ilya Finkelstein</name></author><author><name>Geeta J. Narlikar</name></author><author><name>Daniel W. Gerlich</name></author><author><name>Michael K. Rosen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Eukaryotic nuclear DNA is wrapped around histone proteins to form nucleosomes, which further assemble to package and regulate the genome. Understanding of the physical mechanisms that contribute to higher order chromatin organization is limited. Previously, we reported the intrinsic capacity of chromatin to undergo phase separation and form dynamic liquid-like condensates, which can be regulated by cellular factors. Recent work from Hansen, Hendzel, and colleagues suggested these intrinsic chromatin condensates are solid in all but a specific set of conditions. Here we show that intrinsic chromatin condensates are fluid in diverse solutions, without need for specific buffering components. Exploring experimental differences in sample preparation and imaging between these two studies, we suggest what may have led Hansen, Hendzel, and colleagues to mischaracterize the innate properties of chromatin condensates. We also describe how liquid-like in vitro behaviors can translate to the locally dynamic but globally constrained movement of chromatin in cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469620" rel="alternate" title="In Diverse Conditions Intrinsic Chromatin Condensates Have Liquid-like Material Properties (11 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469572</id><title>Influenza A virus hemagglutinin prevents extensive membrane damage upon dehydration (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.312221+00:00</updated><author><name>Maiara A. Iriarte-Alonso</name></author><author><name>Alexander M. Bittner</name></author><author><name>Salvatore Chiantia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;While the molecular mechanisms of virus infectivity are rather well known, the detailed consequences of environmental factors on virus biophysical properties are poorly understood. Seasonal influenza outbreaks are usually connected to the low winter temperature, but also to the low relative air humidity. Indeed, transmission rates increase in cold regions during winter. While low temperature must slow degradation processes, the role of low humidity is not clear. We studied the effect of relative humidity on a model of influenza A H1N1 virus envelope, a supported lipid bilayer containing the surface glycoprotein hemagglutinin (HA), which is present in the viral envelope in very high density. For complete cycles of hydration, dehydration and rehydration, we evaluate the membrane properties in terms of structure and dynamics, which we assess by combining confocal fluorescence microscopy, raster image correlation spectroscopy, line-scan fluorescence correlation spectroscopy and atomic force microscopy. Our findings indicate that the presence of HA prevents macroscopic membrane damage after dehydration. Without HA, fast membrane disruption is followed by irreversible loss of lipid and protein mobility. Although our model is principally limited by the membrane composition, the macroscopic effects of HA under dehydration stress reveal new insights on the stability of the virus at low relative humidity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469572" rel="alternate" title="Influenza A virus hemagglutinin prevents extensive membrane damage upon dehydration (10 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470105</id><title>Mars, a molecule archive suite for reproducible analysis and reporting of single molecule properties from bioimages (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.312338+00:00</updated><author><name>Nadia M Huisjes</name></author><author><name>Thomas M Retzer</name></author><author><name>Matthias J Scherr</name></author><author><name>Rohit Agarwal</name></author><author><name>Barbara Safaric</name></author><author><name>Anita Minnen</name></author><author><name>Karl E Duderstadt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The rapid development of new imaging approaches is generating larger and more complex datasets revealing the time evolution of individual cells and biomolecules. Single-molecule techniques, in particular, provide access to rare intermediates in complex, multistage molecular pathways, but few standards exist for processing these information-rich datasets, posing challenges for wider dissemination. Here, we present Mars, an open-source platform for storage and processing of image-derived properties of biomolecules. Mars provides Fiji/ImageJ2 commands written in Java for common single-molecule analysis tasks using a Molecule Archive architecture that is easily adapted to complex, multistep analysis workflows. Three diverse workflows involving molecule tracking, multichannel fluorescence imaging, and force spectroscopy, demonstrate the range of analysis applications. A comprehensive graphical user interface written in JavaFX enhances biomolecule feature exploration by providing charting, tagging, region highlighting, scriptable dashboards, and interactive image views. The interoperability of ImageJ2 ensures Molecule Archives can easily be opened in multiple environments, including those written in Python using PyImageJ, for interactive scripting and visualization. Mars provides a flexible solution for reproducible analysis of image-derived properties facilitating the discovery and quantitative classification of new biological phenomena with an open data format accessible to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470105" rel="alternate" title="Mars, a molecule archive suite for reproducible analysis and reporting of single molecule properties from bioimages (9 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469507</id><title>Biomechanical characteristics of scapula and glenohumeral movements during pitching motion in injury-prone college baseball pitchers (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.312477+00:00</updated><author><name>Koji Miyashita</name></author><author><name>Sentaro Koshida</name></author><author><name>Taro Koyama</name></author><author><name>Kenicihro Ota</name></author><author><name>Yusuke Tani</name></author><author><name>Ryoji Okamune</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Coordination of glenohumeral and scapular movements plays an important role in the injury prevention of baseball pitchers. However, there is no objective data establishing the direct relationship between pitching injuries and associated glenohumeral and scapular movements. Therefore, the objectives of the present study were to demonstrate biomechanical differences in scapular and glenohumeral movements during pitching between injury-prone pitchers and healthy college baseball pitchers. Thirty collegiate baseball pitchers were classified into two groups according to their injury status: injury-prone group (N=15, 20.7±1.4 years, 180.1±6.5 cm, 78.9±5.4 kg) and control group (N=15, 20.9±1.1 years, 177.1±6.6 cm, 72.3±6.7 kg). We obtained the pitching motion data using the three-dimensional motion analysis technique with four high-speed cameras. The horizontal abduction angles of the glenohumeral joint during cocking and acceleration phases were significantly greater in injury-prone pitchers [19.0° (95% CI: 14.4–23.6) at foot contact, −4.0° (95% CI: −7.7 to −0.2) at maximum external rotation (MER), and −0.3° (95% CI: −4.8 to −4.2) at ball release] than in healthy controls [11.7 °(95%CI:7.1 to 16.3) at foot contact, −10.0°(95%CI: −13.7 to −6.3) at MER, and −6.9°(95%CI: −11.4 to −2.4)](&lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt;&amp;lt;0.01). In addition, the external rotation angle (ER) of the scapula at MER was significantly greater in the injury-prone group [−0.1° (95% CI: −5.0 to 4.8)] than in the control group [−12.3° (95% CI: −17.2 to −7.4)] (p&amp;lt;0.01), but there was no difference in the scapular ER during foot contact between the two groups. These results suggests that injury-prone pitchers have less internal rotation of the scapula and more horizontal abduction of the glenohumeral joint during cocking and acceleration phases. Therefore, sports medicine practitioners may need to pay more attention to coordination of scapular and glenohumeral movements during the cocking and acceleration phases of pitching for prevention of shoulder injuries.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469507" rel="alternate" title="Biomechanical characteristics of scapula and glenohumeral movements during pitching motion in injury-prone college baseball pitchers (6 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470237</id><title>High-throughput phenotyping reveals a link between transpiration efficiency and transpiration restriction under high evaporative demand and new loci controlling water use-related traits in African rice, Oryza glaberrima Steud. (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.312611+00:00</updated><author><name>Pablo Affortit</name></author><author><name>Branly Effa Effa</name></author><author><name>Mame Sokhatil Ndoye</name></author><author><name>Daniel Moukouanga</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Luchaire</name></author><author><name>Llorenc Cabrera-Bosquet</name></author><author><name>Marie Carmen Peralvarez</name></author><author><name>Raphael Pilloni</name></author><author><name>Claude Welcker</name></author><author><name>Antony Champion</name></author><author><name>Pascal Gantet</name></author><author><name>Abdala Gamby Diedhiou</name></author><author><name>Baboucarr Manneh</name></author><author><name>Ricardo Aroca</name></author><author><name>Vincent Vadez</name></author><author><name>Laurent Laplaze</name></author><author><name>Philippe Cubry</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Grondin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Because water availability is the most important environmental factor limiting crop production, improving water use efficiency, the amount of carbon fixed per water used, is a major target for crop improvement. In rice, the genetic bases of transpiration efficiency, the derivation of water use efficiency at the whole-plant scale, and its putative component trait transpiration restriction under high evaporative demand, remain unknown. These traits were measured in a panel of 147 African rice Oryza glaberrima genotypes, known as potential sources of tolerance genes to biotic and abiotic stresses. Our results reveal that higher transpiration efficiency is associated with transpiration restriction in African rice. Detailed measurements in a subset of highly differentiated genotypes confirmed these associations and suggested that the root to shoot ratio played an important role in transpiration restriction. Genome wide association studies identified marker-trait associations for transpiration response to evaporative demand, transpiration efficiency and its residuals, that links to genes involved in water transport and cell wall patterning. Our data suggest that root shoot partitioning is an important component of transpiration restriction that has a positive effect on transpiration efficiency in African rice. Both traits are heritable and define targets for breeding rice with improved water use strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470237" rel="alternate" title="High-throughput phenotyping reveals a link between transpiration efficiency and transpiration restriction under high evaporative demand and new loci controlling water use-related traits in African rice, Oryza glaberrima Steud. (6 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469602</id><title>Loss of hepatic Lgr4 and Lgr5 promotes nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.313018+00:00</updated><author><name>Enrica Saponara</name></author><author><name>Carlos Penno</name></author><author><name>Meztli L. Matadamas Guzmán</name></author><author><name>Virginie Brun</name></author><author><name>Benoit Fischer</name></author><author><name>Margaret Brousseau</name></author><author><name>Zhong-Yi Wang</name></author><author><name>Peter ODonnell</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Turner</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Graff Meyer</name></author><author><name>Laura Bollepalli</name></author><author><name>Giovanni d’Ario</name></author><author><name>Guglielmo Roma</name></author><author><name>Walter Carbone</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Orsini</name></author><author><name>Stefano Annunziato</name></author><author><name>Michael Obrecht</name></author><author><name>Nicolau Beckmann</name></author><author><name>Chandra Saravanan</name></author><author><name>Arnaud Osmont</name></author><author><name>Philipp Tropberger</name></author><author><name>Shola Richards</name></author><author><name>Christel Genoud</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Aebi</name></author><author><name>Svenja Ley</name></author><author><name>Iwona Ksiazek</name></author><author><name>Florian Nigsch</name></author><author><name>Luigi Terraciano</name></author><author><name>Tewis Bouwmeester</name></author><author><name>Jan Tchorz</name></author><author><name>Heinz Ruffner</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background &amp;amp; Aims&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Rspo-Lgr4/5-Znrf3/Rnf43 module is a master regulator of hepatic Wnt/β-catenin signaling and metabolic zonation, but its impact on nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) remains unclear. We studied whether liver-specific loss of the Wnt/β-catenin modulators Leucine-Rich Repeat-Containing G Protein-Coupled Receptor 4/5 (Lgr4/5) promotes nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mice with liver-specific deletion of both receptors Lgr4/5 (Lgr4/5dLKO) were fed with normal diet (ND) or high fat diet (HFD). Livers of these mice were analyzed for lipid and fibrotic content by tissue staining and immunohistochemistry (IHC), and lipoproteins, inflammation and liver enzyme markers were measured in blood. Mechanistic insights into hepatic lipid accumulation were obtained by using &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; primary hepatocyte cultures derived from the Lgr4/5dLKO mice. Lipid analysis of mouse livers was performed by mass spectrometry (MS)-based untargeted lipidomic analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We demonstrated that liver-specific ablation of Lgr4/5-mediated Wnt signaling resulted in hepatic steatosis, impaired bile acid (BA) secretion and predisposition to liver fibrosis. Under HFD conditions, we observed progressive intrahepatic fat accumulation, developing into macro-vesicular steatosis. Serum lipoprotein levels in HFD-fed Lgr4/5dLKO mice were decreased, rather than increased, suggesting that accumulation of fat in the liver was due to impaired lipid secretion by hepatocytes. Our lipidome analysis revealed a severe alteration of several lipid species in livers of Lgr4/5dLKO mice, including triacylglycerol estolides (TG-EST), a storage form of bioactive free fatty acid (FA) esters of hydroxy FAs (FAHFAs).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Loss of hepatic Wnt/β-catenin activity by Lgr4/5 deletion led to deregulation of lipoprotein pathways, loss of BA secretion, intrinsic alterations of lipid homeostasis and the onset of NAFLD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Lay summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Wnt/β-catenin pathway plays an important role during development and tissue homeostasis. Loss of Wnt/β-catenin activity in mouse liver leads to loss of liver zonation, but the impact on nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) remains unclear. We show that livers of mice developed steatosis upon deletion of the positive pathway regulators Lgr4/5. Livers of knock-out (KO) mice exhibited altered lipid composition due to impaired lipid secretion. Furthermore, livers of these mice developed a nonalcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH)-like phenotype and fibrotic features derived from activated hepatic stellate cells. Our data demonstrate a protective role of Wnt/β-catenin pathway activity towards the development of NAFLD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abrogation of hepatic Wnt/β-catenin activity and liver zonation upon Lgr4/5 deletion in mice led to hepatic steatosis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Liver fat accumulation was caused by impaired lipid secretion from hepatocytes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Steatotic livers contained increased levels of diverse lipid species, including polyunsaturated fatty acids and triglycerol-estolides.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;These data confirmed that a decrease in Wnt/β-catenin signaling led to the development of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) in mice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469602" rel="alternate" title="Loss of hepatic Lgr4 and Lgr5 promotes nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (5 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470122</id><title>The role of four cholesterol-recognition motifs localized between amino acid residues 400-550 in regulating translocation and lytic activity of Adenylate Cyclase Toxin (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.313671+00:00</updated><author><name>Jone Amuategi</name></author><author><name>Rocio Alonso</name></author><author><name>Helena Ostolaza</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Adenylate Cyclase Toxin (ACT or CyaA) is an important virulence factor secreted by Bordetella pertussis, the bacterium causative of whooping cough, playing an essential role in the establishment of infection in the respiratory tract. ACT is a pore-forming cytolysin belonging to the RTX (Repeats in ToXin) family of leukotoxins, capable of permeabilizing several cell types and pure lipid vesicles. Besides, the toxin delivers its N-terminal adenylate cyclase domain into the target cytosol, where catalyzes the conversion of ATP into cAMP, which affects cell signalling. In this study we have made two major observations. First, we show that ACT binds free cholesterol, and identify in its sequence 38 potential cholesterol-recognition motifs. Second, we reveal that four of those motifs are real, functional cholesterol-binding sites. Mutations of the central phenylalanine residues in said motifs have an important impact on the ACT lytic and translocation activities, suggesting their direct intervention in cholesterol recognition and toxin functionality. From our data a likely transmembrane topology can be inferred for the ACT helices constituting the translocation and the hydrophobic regions. From this topology a simple and plausible mechanism emerges by which ACT could translocate its AC domain into target cells, challenging previous views in the field. Blocking the ACT-cholesterol interactions might thus be an effective approach for inhibiting ACT toxicity on cells, and this could help in mitigating the severity of pertussis disease in humans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470122" rel="alternate" title="The role of four cholesterol-recognition motifs localized between amino acid residues 400-550 in regulating translocation and lytic activity of Adenylate Cyclase Toxin (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.469965</id><title>Molecular architecture of nucleosome remodeling and deacetylase sub-complexes by integrative structure determination (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.313939+00:00</updated><author><name>Shreyas Arvindekar</name></author><author><name>Matthew J. Jackman</name></author><author><name>Jason K.K. Low</name></author><author><name>Michael J. Landsberg</name></author><author><name>Joel P. Mackay</name></author><author><name>Shruthi Viswanath</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Nucleosome Remodeling and Deacetylase (NuRD) complex is a chromatin-modifying assembly that regulates gene expression and DNA damage repair. Despite its importance, limited structural information is available on the complex and a detailed understanding of its mechanism is lacking. We investigated the molecular architecture of three NuRD sub-complexes: MTA1-HDAC1-RBBP4 (MHR), MTA1&lt;sup&gt;N&lt;/sup&gt;-HDAC1-MBD3&lt;sup&gt;GATAD2CC&lt;/sup&gt; (MHM), and MTA1-HDAC1-RBBP4-MBD3-GATAD2 (NuDe) using Bayesian integrative structure determination with IMP (Integrative Modeling Platform), drawing on information from SEC-MALLS, DIA-MS, XLMS, negative stain EM, X-ray crystallography, NMR spectroscopy, secondary structure and homology predictions. The structures were corroborated by independent cryo-EM maps, biochemical assays, and known cancer-associated mutations. Our integrative structure of the 2:2:2 MHM complex shows asymmetric binding of MBD3, whereas our structure of the NuDe complex shows MBD3 localized precisely to a single position distant from the MTA1 dimerization interface. Our models suggest a possible mechanism by which asymmetry is introduced in NuRD, and indicate three previously unrecognized subunit interfaces in NuDe: HDAC1&lt;sup&gt;C&lt;/sup&gt;-MTA1&lt;sup&gt;BAH&lt;/sup&gt;, MTA1&lt;sup&gt;BAH&lt;/sup&gt;-MBD3, and HDAC1&lt;sup&gt;60-100&lt;/sup&gt;-MBD3. We observed that a significant number of cancer-associated mutations mapped to protein-protein interfaces in NuDe. Our approach also allows us to localize regions of unknown structure, such as HDAC1&lt;sup&gt;C&lt;/sup&gt; and MBD3&lt;sup&gt;IDR&lt;/sup&gt;, thereby resulting in the most complete structural characterization of these NuRD sub-complexes so far.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.469965" rel="alternate" title="Molecular architecture of nucleosome remodeling and deacetylase sub-complexes by integrative structure determination (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469691</id><title>Global Structure of the Intrinsically Disordered Protein Tau Emerges from its Local Structure (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.314242+00:00</updated><author><name>Lukas S. Stelzl</name></author><author><name>Lisa M. Pietrek</name></author><author><name>Andrea Holla</name></author><author><name>Javier Oroz</name></author><author><name>Mateusz Sikora</name></author><author><name>Jürgen Köfinger</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Schuler</name></author><author><name>Markus Zweckstetter</name></author><author><name>Gerhard Hummer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The paradigmatic disordered protein tau plays an important role in neuronal function and neurodegenerative diseases. To disentangle the factors controlling the balance between functional and disease-associated conformational states, we build a structural ensemble of the tau K18 fragment containing the four pseudorepeat domains involved in both microtubule binding and amyloid fibril formation. We assemble 129-residue-long tau K18 chains at atomic resolution from an extensive fragment library constructed with molecular dynamics simulations. We introduce a reweighted hierarchical chain growth (RHCG) algorithm that integrates experimental data reporting on the local structure into the assembly process in a systematic manner. By combining Bayesian ensemble refinement with importance sampling, we obtain well-defined ensembles and overcome the problem of exponentially varying weights in the integrative modeling of long-chain polymeric molecules. The resulting tau K18 ensembles capture nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) chemical shift and J-coupling measurements. Without further fitting, we achieve excellent agreement with measurements of NMR residual dipolar couplings. The good agreement with experimental measures of global structures such as singlemolecule Förster resonance energy transfer (FRET) efficiencies is improved further by ensemble refinement. By comparing wild-type and mutant ensembles, we show that pathogenic single-point P301 mutations shift the population from the turn-like conformations of the functional microtubule-bound state to the extended conformations of disease-associated tau fibrils. RHCG thus provides us with an atomically resolved view of the population equilibrium between functional and aggregation-prone states of tau K18, and demonstrates that global structural characteristics of this intrinsically disordered protein emerge from its local structure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469691" rel="alternate" title="Global Structure of the Intrinsically Disordered Protein Tau Emerges from its Local Structure (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.469847</id><title>Centripetal nuclear shape fluctuations associate with chromatin condensation towards mitosis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.314892+00:00</updated><author><name>Viola Introini</name></author><author><name>Gururaj Rao Kidiyoor</name></author><author><name>Giancarlo Porcella</name></author><author><name>Marco Foiani</name></author><author><name>Pietro Cicuta</name></author><author><name>Marco Cosentino Lagomarsino</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The cell nucleus plays a central role in several key cellular processes, including chromosome organisation, replication and transcription. Recent work intriguingly suggests an association between nuclear mechanics and cell-cycle progression, but many aspects of this connection remain unexplored. Here, by monitoring nuclear shape fluctuations at different cell cycle stages, we uncover increasing inward fluctuations in late G2 and early mitosis, which are initially transient, but develop into instabilities that culminate into nuclear-envelope breakdown in mitosis. Perturbation experiments and correlation analysis reveal an association of these processes with chromatin condensation. We propose that the contrasting forces between an extensile stress and centripetal pulling from chromatin condensation could link mechanically chromosome condensation and nuclear- envelope breakdown, the two main nuclear processes during mitosis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nucleus was recently shown to exhibit shape fluctuations that vary with cell-cycle stage, but we know very little about the possible links between nuclear mechanics and cell cycle- progression. Through flickering analysis, this study monitors radius and nuclear envelope fluctuations across the cell cycle. The authors discover that as the cell cycle progresses towards mitosis, localised inward invaginations of the nuclear shape form initially transiently and gradually increasing their amplitude, in association with chromatin condensation. This phenomenon develops into nuclear envelope breakdown, suggesting a novel link between cell cycle, chromatin mechanics and nuclear shape fluctuations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.469847" rel="alternate" title="Centripetal nuclear shape fluctuations associate with chromatin condensation towards mitosis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469711</id><title>Single virus assay reveals membrane determinants and mechanistic features of Sendai virus binding (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.315105+00:00</updated><author><name>Amy Lam</name></author><author><name>Orville O. Kirkland</name></author><author><name>Papa Freduah Anderson</name></author><author><name>Nandini Seetharaman</name></author><author><name>Dragan Vujovic</name></author><author><name>Patricia A. Thibault</name></author><author><name>Kristopher D. Azarm</name></author><author><name>Benhur Lee</name></author><author><name>Robert J. Rawle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sendai virus (SeV, formally murine respirovirus) is a membrane-enveloped, negative sense RNA virus in the &lt;italic&gt;Paramyxoviridae&lt;/italic&gt; family, and is closely related to human parainfluenza viruses. SeV has long been utilized as a model paramyxovirus and has recently gained attention as a viral vector candidate for both laboratory and clinical applications. To infect host cells, SeV must first bind to sialic-acid glycolipid or glycoprotein receptors on the host cell surface via its hemagglutinin-neuraminidase (HN) protein. Receptor binding induces a conformational change in HN, which allosterically triggers the viral fusion (F) protein to catalyze membrane fusion. While it is known that SeV binds to α2,3-linked sialic acid receptors, and there has been some study into the chemical requirements of those receptors, key mechanistic features of SeV binding remain unknown, in part because traditional approaches often convolve binding and fusion. Here, we develop and employ a fluorescence microscopy-based assay to observe SeV binding to supported lipid bilayers (SLBs) at the single particle level, which easily disentangles binding from fusion. Using this assay, we investigate mechanistic questions of SeV binding. We identify chemical structural features of ganglioside receptors that influence viral binding and demonstrate that binding is cooperative with respect to receptor density. We measure the characteristic decay time of unbinding and provide evidence supporting a “rolling” mechanism of viral mobility following receptor binding. We also study the dependence of binding on target cholesterol concentration. Interestingly, we find that while SeV binding shows striking parallels in cooperative binding with a prior report of Influenza A virus, it does not demonstrate a similar sensitivity to cholesterol concentration and receptor nano-cluster formation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;STATEMENT OF SIGNIFICANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Paramyxoviruses are a family of membrane-enveloped viruses with many notable human and animal pathogens. In this study, we develop and use an assay to observe the initial step of infection – virus binding to the host membrane – for Sendai virus, the prototypical paramyxovirus, at the single virus level. This assay uses cell membrane mimics – supported lipid bilayers – as targets for virus binding to enable easy control of the membrane components with which the virus interacts. Using our assay, we gain insight into basic biophysical questions about Sendai virus binding, including the chemical characteristics of the receptor, the cooperative nature of binding, the influence of cholesterol, and the mechanism of viral mobility following binding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469711" rel="alternate" title="Single virus assay reveals membrane determinants and mechanistic features of Sendai virus binding (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>