<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.457864+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473372</id><title>A transcriptomic atlas of Aedes aegypti reveals detailed functional organization of major body parts and gut regional specializations in sugar-fed and blood-fed adult females (49 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.458389+00:00</updated><author><name>Bretta Hixson</name></author><author><name>Xiao-Li Bing</name></author><author><name>Xiaowei Yang</name></author><author><name>Alessandro Bonfini</name></author><author><name>Peter Nagy</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Buchon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mosquito vectors transmit numerous pathogens, but large gaps remain in our understanding of their physiology. To facilitate future explorations of mosquito biology, with specific attention to the major vector &lt;italic&gt;Aedes aegypti&lt;/italic&gt;, we have created Aegypti-Atlas (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aegyptiatlas.buchonlab.com/"&gt;http://aegyptiatlas.buchonlab.com/&lt;/ext-link&gt;), an online resource hosting RNAseq profiles of &lt;italic&gt;Ae. Aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; body parts (head, thorax, abdomen, gut, Malpighian tubules, and ovaries), gut regions (crop, proventriculus, anterior and posterior midgut, and hindgut), and a time course of blood meal digestion in the gut. Using Aegypti-Atlas, we provide new insights into the regionalization of gut function, blood feeding response, and immune defenses. We find that the anterior and posterior regions of the mosquito midgut possess clearly delineated digestive specializations which are preserved in the blood-fed state. Blood feeding initiates the sequential transcriptional induction and repression/depletion of multiple cohorts of peptidases throughout blood meal digestion. With respect to defense, immune signaling components, but not recognition or effector molecules, show enrichment in ovaries. Basal expression of antimicrobial peptides is dominated by two genes, holotricin and gambicin, that are expressed in the carcass and the digestive tissues, respectively, in a near mutually exclusive manner. In the midgut, gambicin and other immune effector genes are almost exclusively expressed in the anterior regions, while the posterior midgut exhibits the hallmarks of immune tolerance. Finally, in a cross-species comparison between the midguts of &lt;italic&gt;Ae. aegypti&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Anopheles gambiae&lt;/italic&gt;, we observe that regional digestive and immune specializations are closely conserved, indicating that our data may yield inferences that are broadly relevant to multiple mosquito vector species. We further demonstrate that the expression of orthologous genes is highly correlated, with the exception of a ‘species signature’ comprising a small number of highly/disparately expressed genes. With this work, we show the potential of Aegypti-Atlas to unlock a more complete understanding of mosquito biology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473372" rel="alternate" title="A transcriptomic atlas of Aedes aegypti reveals detailed functional organization of major body parts and gut regional specializations in sugar-fed and blood-fed adult females (49 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473495</id><title>Single cell RNA sequencing and lineage tracing confirm mesenchyme to epithelial transformation (MET) contributes to repair of the endometrium at menstruation (36 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.458700+00:00</updated><author><name>Phoebe M Kirkwood</name></author><author><name>Douglas A Gibson</name></author><author><name>Isaac Shaw</name></author><author><name>Ross Dobie</name></author><author><name>Olympia Kelepouri</name></author><author><name>Neil C Henderson</name></author><author><name>Philippa TK Saunders</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The human endometrium experiences repetitive cycles of tissue wounding characterised by piecemeal shedding of the surface epithelium and rapid restoration of tissue homeostasis. In this study we used a validated mouse model of endometrial repair in combination with three transgenic lines of mice to investigate whether epithelial cells that become incorporated into the newly formed luminal epithelium have their origins in one or more of the mesenchymal cell types present in the stromal compartment of the cycling endometrium. Using scRNAseq we identified a novel population of PDGFRb+ cells that arose in the endometrium in response to endometrial breakdown/repair. These cells expressed genes usually considered specific to epithelial cells and in silico trajectory analysis suggested they arose from stromal fibroblasts and were in transition to becoming epithelial cells. To confirm our hypothesis we used a lineage tracing strategy to compare the fate of stromal fibroblasts (PDGFRa+) and stromal perivascular cells (NG2+). We demonstrate for the first time that stromal fibroblasts can undergo a mesenchyme to epithelial transformation and become incorporated into the re-epithelialised luminal surface of the repaired tissue. This study is the first to discover a novel population of wound-responsive, plastic endometrial stromal fibroblasts that contribute to restoration of tissue integrity during endometrial repair. These findings form a platform for comparisons both to endometrial pathologies which involve a fibrotic response (Ashermans syndrome, endometriosis) as well as other mucosal tissues which have a variable response to wounding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Single cell RNA sequencing identified a population of PDGFRβ+ mesenchymal cells with a unique transcriptomic signature that arises in response to induction of a menseslike wound&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The repair-specific mesenchymal cells express genes considered specific to both mesenchymal and epithelial lineages indicative of an intermediate phenotype and a mesenchymal to epithelial transition (MET)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; trajectory analysis revealed that repair-specific cells originate from the fibroblast cell clusters, were distinct from perivascular cells, and had a predicted trans-differentiation trajectory towards definitive epithelial cells&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; lineage tracing in adult mice provides definitive evidence that PDGFRα+ endometrial fibroblasts, and not NG2+ perivascular cells, undergo MET and can become incorporated into the luminal epithelium of the post repair tissue&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473495" rel="alternate" title="Single cell RNA sequencing and lineage tracing confirm mesenchyme to epithelial transformation (MET) contributes to repair of the endometrium at menstruation (36 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473924</id><title>A discovery-based proteomics approach identifies protein disulfide isomerase (PDIA1) as a biomarker of β cell stress in type 1 diabetes (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.458936+00:00</updated><author><name>Farooq Syed</name></author><author><name>Divya Singhal</name></author><author><name>Koen Raedschelders</name></author><author><name>Preethi Krishnan</name></author><author><name>Robert N. Bone</name></author><author><name>Madeline R. McLaughlin</name></author><author><name>Jennifer E. Van Eyk</name></author><author><name>Raghavendra G. Mirmira</name></author><author><name>Mei-Ling Yang</name></author><author><name>Mark J. Mamula</name></author><author><name>Huanmei Wu</name></author><author><name>Xiaowen Liu</name></author><author><name>Carmella Evans-Molina</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Activation of stress pathways intrinsic to the β cell are thought to both accelerate β cell death and increase β cell immunogenicity in type 1 diabetes (T1D). However, information on the timing and scope of these responses is lacking. Methods: To identify temporal and disease-related changes in islet β cell protein expression, data independent acquisition-mass spectrometry was performed on islets collected longitudinally from NOD mice and NOD-SCID mice rendered diabetic through T cell adoptive transfer. Findings: In islets collected from female NOD mice at 10, 12, and 14 weeks of age, we found a time-restricted upregulation of proteins involved in the maintenance of β cell function and stress mitigation, followed by loss of expression of protective proteins that heralded diabetes onset. Pathway analysis identified EIF2 signaling and the unfolded protein response, mTOR signaling, mitochondrial function, and oxidative phosphorylation as commonly modulated pathways in both diabetic NOD mice and NOD-SCID mice rendered acutely diabetic by adoptive transfer, highlighting this core set of pathways in T1D pathogenesis. In immunofluorescence validation studies, β cell expression of protein disulfide isomerase A1 (PDIA1) and 14-3-3b were found to be increased during disease progression in NOD islets, while PDIA1 plasma levels were increased in pre-diabetic NOD mice and in the serum of children with recent-onset T1D compared to age and sex-matched non-diabetic controls. Interpretation: We identified a common and core set of modulated pathways across distinct mouse models of T1D and identified PDIA1 as a potential human biomarker of β cell stress in T1D.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473924" rel="alternate" title="A discovery-based proteomics approach identifies protein disulfide isomerase (PDIA1) as a biomarker of β cell stress in type 1 diabetes (27 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473625</id><title>From climate warming to accelerated cellular ageing: an experimental study in wild birds (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.459229+00:00</updated><author><name>Antoine Stier</name></author><author><name>Bin-Yan Hsu</name></author><author><name>Nina Cossin-Sevrin</name></author><author><name>Natacha Garcin</name></author><author><name>Suvi Ruuskanen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Climate change is increasing both the average ambient temperature and the frequency and severity of heat waves. While direct mortality induced by heat waves is increasingly reported, sub-lethal effects are also likely to impact wild populations. We hypothesized that accelerated ageing could be a cost of being exposed to higher ambient temperature, especially in early-life when thermoregulatory capacities are not fully developed. We tested this hypothesis in wild great tit (&lt;italic&gt;Parus major&lt;/italic&gt;) by experimentally increasing nest box temperature by &lt;italic&gt;ca&lt;/italic&gt;. 2°C during postnatal growth and measuring telomere length, a biomarker of cellular ageing predictive of survival prospects in many bird species. While increasing early-life temperature does not affect growth or survival to fledging, it accelerates telomere shortening and reduces medium-term survival from 34% to 19%. Heat-induced telomere shortening was not explained by oxidative stress, but more likely by an increase in energy demand (&lt;italic&gt;i&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;e&lt;/italic&gt;. higher thyroid hormones levels, increased expression of glucocorticoid receptor, increased mitochondrial density) leading to a reduction in telomere maintenance mechanisms (&lt;italic&gt;i&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;e&lt;/italic&gt;. decrease in the gene expression of telomerase and protective shelterin). Our results thus suggest that climate warming can affect ageing rate in wild birds, with potential impact on population dynamics and persistence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stressful environmental conditions are known to accelerate cellular ageing, especially when experienced early in life. One unexplored avenue through which climate warming might affect wild animal populations is accelerated ageing. Here we show that increasing nest temperature by &lt;italic&gt;ca&lt;/italic&gt;. 2°C during postnatal growth in a wild bird species can impact numerous physiological pathways and medium-term survival. Notably, artificially warming nests accelerates the shortening of telomeres, which are the protective end-caps of chromosomes considered as a hallmark of ageing. We thus suggest that warm ambient temperatures might accelerate ageing in wild animals, which can potentially impact population dynamics and extinction risk in the face of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473625" rel="alternate" title="From climate warming to accelerated cellular ageing: an experimental study in wild birds (26 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473473</id><title>Isotropic Three-Dimensional Dual-Color Super-Resolution Microscopy with Metal-Induced Energy Transfer (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.459498+00:00</updated><author><name>Jan Christoph Thiele</name></author><author><name>Marvin Jungblut</name></author><author><name>Dominic A. Helmerich</name></author><author><name>Roman Tsukanov</name></author><author><name>Anna Chizhik</name></author><author><name>Alexey I. Chizhik</name></author><author><name>Martin Schnermann</name></author><author><name>Markus Sauer</name></author><author><name>Oleksii Nevskyi</name></author><author><name>Jörg Enderlein</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Over the last two decades, super-resolution microscopy has seen a tremendous development in speed and resolution, but for most of its methods, there exists a remarkable gap between lateral and axial resolution. Similar to conventional optical microscopy, the axial resolution is by a factor three to five worse than the lateral resolution. One recently developed method to close this gap is metal-induced energy transfer (MIET) imaging which achieves an axial resolution down to nanometers. It exploits the distance dependent quenching of fluorescence when a fluorescent molecule is brought close to a metal surface. In the present manuscript, we combine the extreme axial resolution of MIET imaging with the extraordinary lateral resolution of single-molecule localization microscopy, in particular with direct stochastic optical reconstruction microscopy (&lt;italic&gt;d&lt;/italic&gt;STORM). This combination allows us to achieve isotropic three-dimensional super-resolution imaging of sub-cellular structures. Moreover, we employed spectral demixing for implementing dualcolor MIET-&lt;italic&gt;d&lt;/italic&gt;STORM that allows us to image and co-localize, in three dimensions, two different cellular structures simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473473" rel="alternate" title="Isotropic Three-Dimensional Dual-Color Super-Resolution Microscopy with Metal-Induced Energy Transfer (21 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473677</id><title>A DNA-based optical force sensor for live-cell applications (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.459754+00:00</updated><author><name>Christina Jayachandran</name></author><author><name>Arindam Ghosh</name></author><author><name>Meenakshi Prabhune</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Bath</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Turberfield</name></author><author><name>Lara Hauke</name></author><author><name>J&amp;oumlrg Enderlein</name></author><author><name>Florian Rehfeldt</name></author><author><name>Christoph F. Schmidt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mechanical forces are relevant for many biological processes, from wound healing or tumour formation to cell migration and differentiation. Cytoskeletal actin is largely responsible for responding to forces and transmitting them in cells, while also maintaining cell shape and integrity. Here, we describe a novel approach to employ a FRET-based DNA force sensor &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in cellulo&lt;/italic&gt; for non-invasive optical monitoring of intracellular mechanical forces. We use fluorescence lifetime imaging to determine the FRET efficiency of the sensor, which makes the measurement robust against intensity variations. We demonstrate the applicability of the sensor by monitoring cross-linking activity in &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; actin networks by bulk rheology and confocal microscopy. We further demonstrate that the sensor readily attaches to stress fibers in living cells which opens up the possibility of live-cell force measurements.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473677" rel="alternate" title="A DNA-based optical force sensor for live-cell applications (20 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473778</id><title>ATP:Mg2+ shapes condensate properties of rRNA-NPM1 in vitro nucleolus model and its partitioning of ribosomes (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.459985+00:00</updated><author><name>N. Amy Yewdall</name></author><author><name>Alain A. M. André</name></author><author><name>Merlijn H. I. van Haren</name></author><author><name>Frank H.T. Nelissen</name></author><author><name>Aafke Jonker</name></author><author><name>Evan Spruijt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nucleoli have viscoelastic gel-like condensate dynamics that are not well represented &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. Nucleoli models, such as those formed by nucleophosmin 1 (NPM1) and ribosomal RNA (rRNA), exhibit condensate dynamics orders of magnitude faster than &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; nucleoli. Here we show that an interplay between magnesium ions (Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;) and ATP governs rRNA dynamics, and this ultimately shapes the physical state of these condensates. Using quantitative fluorescence microscopy, we demonstrate that increased RNA compaction occurs in the condensates at high Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; concentrations, contributing to the slowed RNA dynamics. At Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; concentrations above 7 mM, rRNA is fully arrested and the condensates are gels. Below the critical gel point, NPM1-rRNA droplets age in a temperature-dependent manner, suggesting that condensates are viscoelastic materials, undergoing maturation driven by weak multivalent interactions. ATP addition reverses the dynamic arrest of rRNA, resulting in liquefaction of these gel-like structures. Surprisingly, ATP and Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; both act to increase partitioning of NPM1-proteins as well as rRNA, which influences the partitioning of small client molecules. By contrast, larger ribosomes form a halo around NPM1-rRNA coacervates when Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; concentrations are higher than ATP concentrations. Within cells, ATP levels fluctuate due to biomolecular reactions, and we demonstrate that a dissipative enzymatic reaction can control the biophysical properties of &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; condensates through depletion of ATP. This enzymatic ATP depletion also reverses the formation of the ribosome halos. Our results illustrate how cells, by changing local ATP concentrations, may regulate the state and client partitioning of RNA-containing condensates such as the nucleolus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a significant discrepancy between the dynamics of &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; nucleolus models and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; nucleoli – with the latter more gel-like.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The interplay between Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; ions, ATP and the nucleolus components – specifically RNA – governs the dynamics, and ultimately the physical state, of nucleolus-like condensates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We show that the nucleolus are dynamically adapting condensates, responding to local ATP concentrations through Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;-induced compaction of the RNA, and reversible relaxation when ATP binds Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; again. Other condensates containing RNA probably respond in similar ways to Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; and ATP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473778" rel="alternate" title="ATP:Mg2+ shapes condensate properties of rRNA-NPM1 in vitro nucleolus model and its partitioning of ribosomes (18 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.474049</id><title>Fusion protein strategies for cryo-EM study of G protein-coupled receptors (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.460204+00:00</updated><author><name>Kaihua Zhang</name></author><author><name>Hao Wu</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Hoppe</name></author><author><name>Aashish Manglik</name></author><author><name>Yifan Cheng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single particle cryogenic-electron microscopy (cryo-EM) is used extensively to determine structures of activated G protein-coupled receptors (GPCRs) in complex with G proteins or arrestins. However, applying it to GPCRs without signaling proteins remains challenging because most receptors lack structural features in their soluble domains to facilitate image alignment. In GPCR crystallography, inserting a fusion protein between transmembrane helices 5 and 6 is a highly successful strategy for crystallization. Although the similar strategy has the potential to broadly facilitate cryo-EM structure determination of GPCRs alone without signaling protein, the critical determinants that make this approach successful are not yet clear. Here, we address this shortcoming by exploring different fusion protein designs, which led to structures of antagonist bound A&lt;sub&gt;2A&lt;/sub&gt; adenosine receptor at 3.4&amp;amp;Aring resolution and unliganded Smoothened at 3.7&amp;amp;Aring resolution. The fusion strategies explored here are likely applicable to cryo-EM interrogation of other GPCRs and small integral membrane proteins.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.474049" rel="alternate" title="Fusion protein strategies for cryo-EM study of G protein-coupled receptors (13 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473430</id><title>Hydrogen properties and charges in a sub-1.2 Å resolution cryo-EM structure revealed by a cold field emission beam (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.460394+00:00</updated><author><name>Saori Maki-Yonekura</name></author><author><name>Keisuke Kawakami</name></author><author><name>Tasuku Hamaguchi</name></author><author><name>Kiyofumi Takaba</name></author><author><name>Koji Yonekura</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The cold field emission (CFE) beam produces the less-attenuated contrast transfer function of electron microscopy, thereby enhancing high-resolution signals and this particularly benefits higher-resolution single particle cryogenic electron microscopy. Here, we present a sub-1.2 Å resolution structure of a standard protein sample, apoferritin. Image data were collected with the CFE beam in a high-throughput scheme while minimizing beam tilt deviations from the coma-free axis. A difference map reveals positive densities for most hydrogen atoms in the core region of the protein complex including those in water molecules, while negative densities around acidic amino-acid side chains likely represent negative charges. The position of the hydrogen densities depends on parent bonded-atom type, which is validated by an estimated level of coordinate errors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473430" rel="alternate" title="Hydrogen properties and charges in a sub-1.2 Å resolution cryo-EM structure revealed by a cold field emission beam (12 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473106</id><title>Polyphosphate affects cytoplasmic and chromosomal dynamics in nitrogen-starved Pseudomonas aeruginosa (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.460592+00:00</updated><author><name>Sofia Magkiriadou</name></author><author><name>Amanda Habel</name></author><author><name>Willi L. Stepp</name></author><author><name>Dianne K. Newman</name></author><author><name>Suliana Manley</name></author><author><name>Lisa R. Racki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Polyphosphate (polyP) synthesis is a ubiquitous stress and starvation response in bacteria. In diverse species, mutants unable to make polyP have a wide variety of physiological defects, but the mechanisms by which this simple polyanion exerts its effects remain unclear. One possibility is that polyP′s many functions stem from global effects on the biophysical properties of the cell. We characterize the effect of polyphosphate on cytoplasmic mobility under nitrogen-starvation conditions in the opportunistic pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/italic&gt;. Using fluorescence microscopy and particle tracking, we characterize the motion of chromosomal loci and free tracer particles in the cytoplasm. In the absence of polyP and upon starvation, we observe an increase in mobility both for chromosomal loci and for tracer particles. Tracer particles reveal that polyP also modulates the partitioning between a ′more mobile′ and a ′less mobile′ population: small particles in cells unable to make polyP are more likely to be ′mobile′ and explore more of the cytoplasm, particularly during starvation. We speculate that this larger freedom of motion may be a consequence of nucleoid decompaction, which we also observe in starved cells deficient in polyP. Our observations suggest that polyP limits cytoplasmic mobility and accessibility during nitrogen starvation, which may help to explain the pleiotropic phenotypes observed in the absence of polyP.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473106" rel="alternate" title="Polyphosphate affects cytoplasmic and chromosomal dynamics in nitrogen-starved Pseudomonas aeruginosa (12 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473588</id><title>Light-induced Patterning of Electroactive Bacterial Biofilms (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.460791+00:00</updated><author><name>Fengjie Zhao</name></author><author><name>Marko S. Chavez</name></author><author><name>Kyle L. Naughton</name></author><author><name>Christina M. Cole</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey A. Gralnick</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Y. El-Naggar</name></author><author><name>James Q. Boedicker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Electroactive bacterial biofilms can function as living biomaterials that merge the functionality of living cells with electronic components. However, the development of such advanced living electronics has been challenged by the inability to control the geometry of electroactive biofilms relative to solid-state electrodes. Here, we developed a lithographic strategy to pattern conductive biofilms of &lt;italic&gt;Shewanella oneidensis&lt;/italic&gt; by controlling aggregation protein CdrAB expression with a blue light-induced genetic circuit. This controlled deposition enabled &lt;italic&gt;S. oneiensis&lt;/italic&gt; biofilm patterning on transparent electrode surfaces and measurements demonstrated tunable biofilm conduction dependent on pattern size. Controlling biofilm geometry also enabled us, for the first time, to quantify the intrinsic conductivity of living &lt;italic&gt;S. oneidensis&lt;/italic&gt; biofilms and experimentally confirm predictions based on simulations of a recently proposed collision-exchange electron transport mechanism. Overall, we developed a facile technique for controlling electroactive biofilm formation on electrodes, with implications for both studying and harnessing bioelectronics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473588" rel="alternate" title="Light-induced Patterning of Electroactive Bacterial Biofilms (9 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.472748</id><title>Oxytocin Signaling Regulates the Homeostatic Response to Cold Stress in Poikilothermic Vertebrates (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.461000+00:00</updated><author><name>Adi Segev-Hadar</name></author><author><name>Shani Krispin</name></author><author><name>Anouk M. Olthof</name></author><author><name>Katery C. Hyatt</name></author><author><name>Liran Haller</name></author><author><name>Assaf Barki</name></author><author><name>Tali Nitzan</name></author><author><name>Gil Levkowitz</name></author><author><name>Rahul N. Kanadia</name></author><author><name>Avner Cnaani</name></author><author><name>Jakob Biran</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;When exposed to low temperature, homeothermic vertebrates maintain internal body temperature by activating thermogenesis and by altered metabolism, synchronized by neuroendocrine responses. Although such physiological responses also occur in poikilothermic vertebrates, the prevailing notion is that their reactions are passive. Here, we explored molecular hypothalamic and physiological responses to cold stress in the tropical poikilotherm Nile tilapia (&lt;italic&gt;Oreochromis niloticus&lt;/italic&gt;). We show that cold exposed tilapia exhibit complex homeostatic responses, including increased hypothalamic oxytocin, plasma glucose and cortisol concomitant with reduced plasma lactate and metabolic rate. Pharmacological or genetic blockage of oxytocin signaling further affected metabolic rate in two cold-exposed poikilothermic models. This indicates that oxytocin, a known thermoregulator in homeotherms, actively regulates temperature-related homeostasis in poikilotherms. Overall, our findings show that the brain of poikilotherms actively responds to cold temperature by regulating metabolic physiology. Moreover, we identify oxytocin signaling as an adaptive and evolutionarily conserved metabolic regulator of temperature-related homeostasis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.472748" rel="alternate" title="Oxytocin Signaling Regulates the Homeostatic Response to Cold Stress in Poikilothermic Vertebrates (7 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473833</id><title>A rhythmically pulsing leaf-spring nanoengine that drives a passive follower (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.461249+00:00</updated><author><name>Mathias Centola</name></author><author><name>Erik Poppleton</name></author><author><name>Martin Centola</name></author><author><name>Julian Valero</name></author><author><name>Petr Sulc</name></author><author><name>Michael Famulok</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Molecular engineering seeks to create functional entities for the modular use in the bottom-up design of nanoassemblies that can perform complex tasks. Such systems require fuel-consuming nanomotors that can actively drive downstream passive followers. Most molecular motors are driven by Brownian motion, but the generated forces are scattered and insufficient for efficient transfer to passive second-tier components, which is why nanoscale driver-follower systems have not been realized. Here, we describe bottom-up construction of a DNA-nanomachine that engages in an active, autonomous and rhythmical pulsing motion of two rigid DNA-origami arms, driven by chemical energy. We show the straightforward coupling of the active nanomachine to a passive follower unit, to which it then transmits its own motion, thus constituting a genuine driver-follower pair. Our work introduces a versatile fuel-consuming nanomachine that can be coupled with passive modules in nanoassemblies, the function of which depends on downstream sequences of motion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473833" rel="alternate" title="A rhythmically pulsing leaf-spring nanoengine that drives a passive follower (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473222</id><title>Hepatocyte-specific activity of TSC22D4 triggers progressive NAFLD by impairing mitochondrial function (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.461622+00:00</updated><author><name>Gretchen Wolff</name></author><author><name>Minako Sakurai</name></author><author><name>Amit Mhamane</name></author><author><name>Adriano Maida</name></author><author><name>Ioannis K. Deligiannis</name></author><author><name>Kelvin Yin</name></author><author><name>Peter Weber</name></author><author><name>Annika Weider</name></author><author><name>Maria Troullinaki</name></author><author><name>Anja Zeigerer</name></author><author><name>Michael Roden</name></author><author><name>Nadine Volk</name></author><author><name>Tanja Poth</name></author><author><name>Thilo Hackert</name></author><author><name>Lena Wiedmann</name></author><author><name>Francesca De Angelis Rigotti</name></author><author><name>Juan Rodriguez-Vita</name></author><author><name>Andreas Fischer</name></author><author><name>Rajesh Mukthavaram</name></author><author><name>Pattraranee Limphong</name></author><author><name>Kiyoshi Tachikawa</name></author><author><name>Priya Karmali</name></author><author><name>Joseph Payne</name></author><author><name>Padmanabh Chivukula</name></author><author><name>Bilgen Ekim-Üstünel</name></author><author><name>Celia P. Martinez-Jimenez</name></author><author><name>Julia Szendrödi</name></author><author><name>Peter Nawroth</name></author><author><name>Stephan Herzig</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fibrotic organ responses have recently been identified as long-term complication in diabetes. Indeed, insulin resistance and aberrant hepatic lipid accumulation represent driving features of progressive non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD), ranging from simple steatosis and non-alcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH) to fibrosis. Effective pharmacological regimens to stop progressive liver disease are still lacking to-date.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on our previous discovery of transforming growth factor beta-like stimulated clone (TSC)22D4 as a key driver of insulin resistance and glucose intolerance in obesity and type 2 diabetes, we generated a TSC22D4-hepatocyte specific knockout line (TSC22D4-HepaKO) and exposed mice to control or NASH diet models. Mechanistic insights were generated by metabolic phenotyping and single cell liver sequencing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hepatic TSC22D4 expression was significantly correlated with markers of liver disease progression and fibrosis in both murine and human livers. Indeed, hepatic TSC22D4 levels were elevated in human NASH patients as well as in several murine NASH models. Specific genetic deletion of TSC22D4 in hepatocytes led to reduced liver lipid accumulation, improvements in steatosis and inflammation scores and decreased apoptosis in mice. Single cell RNA sequencing revealed a distinct gene signature identifying an upregulation of mitochondrial-related processes. An enrichment of genes involved in the TCA cycle, mitochondrial organization, and triglyceride metabolism underscored the hepatocyte-protective phenotype and overall decreased liver damage as seen in mouse models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Together, our data uncover a new connection between targeted depletion of TSC22D4 and intrinsic metabolic processes in progressive liver disease. Cell-specific reduction of TSC22D4 improves hepatic steatosis, inflammation and promotes hepatocyte survival thus paving the way for further preclinical therapy developments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473222" rel="alternate" title="Hepatocyte-specific activity of TSC22D4 triggers progressive NAFLD by impairing mitochondrial function (6 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473581</id><title>Correlated STORM-homoFRET Imaging: Applications to the Study of Membrane Receptor Self-Association and Clustering (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.462117+00:00</updated><author><name>Amine Driouchi</name></author><author><name>Scott D. Gray-Owen</name></author><author><name>Christopher M. Yip</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mapping the self-organization and spatial distribution of membrane proteins is key to understanding their function. We report here on a correlated STORM/homoFRET imaging approach for resolving the nanoscale distribution and oligomeric state of membrane proteins. Live cell homoFRET imaging of CEACAM1, a cell-surface receptor known to exist in a complex equilibrium between monomer and dimer/oligomer states, revealed highly heterogenous diffraction-limited structures on the surface of HeLa cells. Correlated super-resolved STORM imaging revealed that these structures comprised a complex mixture and spatial distribution of self-associated CEACAM1 molecules. This correlated approach provides a compelling strategy for addressing challenging questions about the interplay between membrane protein concentration, distribution, interaction, clustering, and function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473581" rel="alternate" title="Correlated STORM-homoFRET Imaging: Applications to the Study of Membrane Receptor Self-Association and Clustering (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473491</id><title>BACE1 – but not BACE2 – function is critical for metabolic disorders induced by high-fat diets in C57BL/6N mice (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.462327+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas W. Rosahl</name></author><author><name>Lynn A. Hyde</name></author><author><name>Patrick T. Reilly</name></author><author><name>Marie-France Champy</name></author><author><name>Kirstine J. Belongie</name></author><author><name>Benoit Petit-Demouliere</name></author><author><name>Tania Sorg</name></author><author><name>Hugues Jacobs</name></author><author><name>Robert Terry</name></author><author><name>Jack D. Scott</name></author><author><name>Jared N. Cumming</name></author><author><name>Eric M. Parker</name></author><author><name>Matthew E. Kennedy</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aims/hypothesis&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beta-site amyloid precursor protein-cleaving enzyme 1 (BACE1) is required for the production of toxic amyloid peptides and is highly expressed in the brain, but also to a lesser extent in major peripheral organs such as muscle and liver. In contrast, BACE2 is mainly expressed in peripheral tissues and is enriched in pancreatic beta cells, where it regulates beta- cell function and mass. Previous reports demonstrated that loss of BACE1 function decreases body weight, protects against diet-induced obesity and enhances insulin sensitivity in mice, whereas mice lacking &lt;italic&gt;Bace2&lt;/italic&gt; exhibit reduced blood glucose levels, improved intraperitoneal glucose tolerance and increased beta-cell mass. Impaired glucose homeostasis and insulin resistance are hallmarks of type 2 diabetes and have been implicated in Alzheimer’s disease. Therefore, we tested the contribution of the individual BACE isoforms to those metabolic phenotypes by placing &lt;italic&gt;Bace1&lt;/italic&gt; knockout (KO), &lt;italic&gt;Bace2&lt;/italic&gt; KO, &lt;italic&gt;Bace1/2&lt;/italic&gt; double knockout (dKO) and wild-type (WT) mice on a high-fat high-cholesterol diet (HFD) for 16 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Bace1&lt;/italic&gt; KO (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; = 18), &lt;italic&gt;Bace2&lt;/italic&gt; KO (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; = 18), &lt;italic&gt;Bace1/2&lt;/italic&gt; dKO (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; = 18) and WT C57BL/6N mice (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; = 54) were fed a HFD for 16 weeks (age 9–25 weeks). Body composition was measured before initiation of the HFD and after 11 weeks of HFD. Oral glucose tolerance and insulin sensitivity tests were performed after 12 and 13 weeks of HFD, respectively, and full blood chemistry was analyzed after 16 weeks of HFD. The effects of subchronic BACE1/2 inhibition were assessed by administration of 10 mg/kg/day of the dual BACE1/2 inhibitor MBi-3 in a HFD fed to C57BL/6N mice for 3 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Bace1&lt;/italic&gt; KO and &lt;italic&gt;Bace1/2&lt;/italic&gt; dKO mice showed decreased body weight and improved glucose tolerance and insulin resistance vs. WT mice. Conversely, &lt;italic&gt;Bace2&lt;/italic&gt; KO mice did not show any significant differences in body weight, glucose tolerance or insulin resistance under our experimental conditions. Finally, subchronic MBi-3–mediated BACE1/2 inhibition in mice in conjunction with a HFD resulted in a modest improvement of glucose tolerance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions/interpretation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our data indicate that lack of BACE1 – but not BACE2 – function contributes mainly to the metabolic phenotypic changes observed in &lt;italic&gt;Bace1/2&lt;/italic&gt; dKO mice, suggesting that inhibition of BACE1 has the greater role (vs. BACE2) in any potential improvements in metabolic homeostasis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;HIGHLIGHTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Insulin resistance may develop in the brains of patients with Alzheimer’s disease (83/85 characters)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;BACE1 and BACE2 may play a role in glucose homeostasis and insulin sensitivity (80/85 characters)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Body weight in mice decreased with &lt;italic&gt;Bace1&lt;/italic&gt; KO and &lt;italic&gt;Bace1/2&lt;/italic&gt; KO but not &lt;italic&gt;Bace2&lt;/italic&gt; KO alone (83/85 characters)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Bace1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Bace1/2,&lt;/italic&gt; but not &lt;italic&gt;Bace2,&lt;/italic&gt; KO improved glucose tolerance/insulin resistance (84/85 characters)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improved metabolic homeostasis may follow loss of BACE1 rather than BACE 2 activity (85/85 characters)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473491" rel="alternate" title="BACE1 – but not BACE2 – function is critical for metabolic disorders induced by high-fat diets in C57BL/6N mice (4 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473131</id><title>Temporal in vivo platelet labelling in mice reveals age-dependent receptor expression and conservation of specific mRNAs (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.462704+00:00</updated><author><name>Paul C Armstrong</name></author><author><name>Harriet E Allan</name></author><author><name>Nicholas S Kirkby</name></author><author><name>Abhishek Joshi</name></author><author><name>Clemens Gutmann</name></author><author><name>Marilena Crescente</name></author><author><name>Jane A Mitchell</name></author><author><name>Manuel Mayr</name></author><author><name>Timothy D Warner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The proportion of young platelets, also known as newly formed or reticulated, within the overall platelet population has been clinically correlated with adverse cardiovascular outcomes. Our understanding of this is incomplete, however, because of limitations in the technical approaches available to study platelets of different ages. In this study we have developed and validated an &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; ‘temporal labelling’ approach using injectable fluorescent anti-platelet antibodies to sub-divide platelets by age and assess differences in functional and molecular characteristics. With this approach we found that young platelets (&amp;lt;24h old) in comparison to older platelets respond to stimuli with greater calcium flux and degranulation, and contribute more to the formation of thrombi &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Sequential sampling confirmed this altered functionality to be independent of platelet size with no size differences or changes relative to the global population seen at any age. The age associated decrease in thrombotic function was accompanied by significant decreases in the surface expression of GPVI and CD31 (PECAM-1) and an increase in CD9. Platelet mRNA content also decreased with age but at different rates for individual mRNAs indicating apparent conservation of those encoding granule proteins. Our pulse-chase type approach to define circulating platelet age has allowed timely re-examination of commonly held beliefs regarding size and reactivity of young platelets whilst providing novel insights into the temporal regulation of receptor and protein expression. Overall, future application of this validated tool will inform on age-based platelet heterogeneity in physiology and disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473131" rel="alternate" title="Temporal in vivo platelet labelling in mice reveals age-dependent receptor expression and conservation of specific mRNAs (3 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473336</id><title>Intracranial Electric Field Recording During Multichannel Transcranial Electrical Stimulation (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.462947+00:00</updated><author><name>Minmin Wang</name></author><author><name>Jiawei Han</name></author><author><name>Hongjie Jiang</name></author><author><name>Junming Zhu</name></author><author><name>Wuwei Feng</name></author><author><name>Pratik Y. Chhatbar</name></author><author><name>Jianmin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Shaomin Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Multichannel transcranial electrical stimulation (tES) modeling and optimization have been widely studied in recent years. Its theoretical bases include quasi-static assumption and linear superposition. However, there is still a lack of direct &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; evidence to validate the simulation model and theoretical assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We directly measured the multichannel tES-induced voltage changes with implanted stereotactic-electroencephalographic (sEEG) electrodes in 12 epilepsy subjects. By combining these measured data, we investigate the linear superposition and prediction accuracy of simulation models for multi-electrode stimulation and further compare the induced EF differences between transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) and transcranial alternating current stimulation (tACS).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; measurements demonstrated that the multi-electrode tES-induced voltages were almost equal to the sum of the voltages generated independently by bipolar stimulation. Both measured voltages and electric fields obtained &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; were highly correlated with the predicted values in our cohort (Voltages: &lt;italic&gt;r&lt;/italic&gt; = 0.92, &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt; &amp;lt; 0.001; electric fields: &lt;italic&gt;r&lt;/italic&gt; = 0.74, &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt; &amp;lt; 0.001). Under the same stimulation intensity, the tDCS-induced peak-zero voltages were highly correlated with the values of tACS (&lt;italic&gt;r&lt;/italic&gt; = 0.99, &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt; &amp;lt; 0.001; &lt;italic&gt;s&lt;/italic&gt; = 0.99).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; measurements provides confirmatory results for linear superposition and quasi-static assumption within the human brain. Furthermore, we found that the individualized simulation model reliably predicted the multi-electrode tES-induced electric fields.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473336" rel="alternate" title="Intracranial Electric Field Recording During Multichannel Transcranial Electrical Stimulation (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473656</id><title>Depriving mice of sleep also deprives of food (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.463175+00:00</updated><author><name>Nina Đukanović</name></author><author><name>Francesco La Spada</name></author><author><name>Yann Emmenegger</name></author><author><name>Guy Niederhäuser</name></author><author><name>Frédéric Preitner</name></author><author><name>Paul Franken</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Both sleep-wake behavior and circadian rhythms are tightly coupled to energy metabolism and food intake. Altered feeding times in mice are known to entrain clock-gene rhythms in brain and liver and sleep-deprived humans tend to eat more and gain weight. Previous observations in mice showing that sleep deprivation (SD) changes clock-gene expression might thus relate to altered food intake and not to the loss of sleep per se. Whether SD affects food intake in the mouse and how this might affect clock-gene expression is, however, unknown. We therefore quantified i) the cortical expression of the clock genes Per1, Per2, Dbp, and Cry1 in mice that had access to food or not during a 6h SD, and ii) food intake during baseline, SD, and recovery sleep. We found that food deprivation did not modify the SD-incurred clock-gene changes in the cortex. Moreover, we discovered that although food intake during SD did not differ from baseline, mice lost weight and increased food intake during subsequent recovery. We conclude that SD is associated with food deprivation and that the resulting energy deficit might contribute to the effects of SD that are commonly interpreted as a response to sleep loss.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473656" rel="alternate" title="Depriving mice of sleep also deprives of food (3 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473802</id><title>Growth kinetics and power laws indicate distinct mechanisms of cell-cell interactions in the aggregation process (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.463377+00:00</updated><author><name>Debangana Mukhopadhyay</name></author><author><name>Rumi De</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cellular aggregation is a complex process orchestrated by various kinds of interactions depending on its environments. Different interactions give rise to different pathways of cellular rearrangement and the development of specialized tissues. To distinguish the underlying mechanisms, in this theoretical work, we investigate the spontaneous emergence of tissue patterns from an ensemble of single cells on a substrate following three leading pathways of cell-cell interactions, namely, direct cell adhesion contacts, matrix mediated mechanical interaction,  and chemical signalling. Our analysis shows that the growth kinetics of the aggregation process is distinctly different for each pathway and bears the signature of the specific cell-cell interactions. Interestingly, we find that the average domain size and the mass of the clusters exhibit a power law growth in time under certain interaction mechanisms hitherto unexplored. Further, as observed in experiments, the cluster size distribution can be characterized by stretched exponential functions showing distinct cellular organization processes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473802" rel="alternate" title="Growth kinetics and power laws indicate distinct mechanisms of cell-cell interactions in the aggregation process (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>