<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.849909+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455935</id><title>FAILURE OF PANCREATIC ALPHA CELLS TO RESPOND TO HYPOGLYCEMIA IS LINKED TO IMPAIRED GLUTAMATE RECEPTOR SIGNALING IN DIABETES (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.850162+00:00</updated><author><name>Julia K. Panzer</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Tamayo</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Caicedo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glucagon secretion from the pancreatic alpha cells is crucial to prevent hypoglycemia. People with type 1 diabetes, however, lose this glucoregulatory mechanism and are susceptible to dangerous insulin treatment-induced hypoglycemia. We established that activating glutamate receptors of the AMPA/kainate type in alpha cells is needed for decreases in glucose levels to elicit full glucagon responses from mouse and human islets. We performed functional studies using living pancreas slices from donors with type 1 diabetes and found that alpha cells had normal glucagon content and responded typically to KCl depolarization, but failed to respond to decreases in glucose concentration and had severely impaired AMPA/kainate receptor signaling. Reactivating residual AMPA/kainate receptor function with the positive allosteric modulators cyclothiazide and aniracetam partially rescued glucagon secretion in response to hypoglycemia. Positive allosteric modulators of AMPA/kainate receptors already approved to treat other conditions could thus be repurposed to prevent hypoglycemia and improve management of diabetes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455935" rel="alternate" title="FAILURE OF PANCREATIC ALPHA CELLS TO RESPOND TO HYPOGLYCEMIA IS LINKED TO IMPAIRED GLUTAMATE RECEPTOR SIGNALING IN DIABETES (7 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456287</id><title>Novel murine models of post-implantation and midgestional malaria-induced preterm birth (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.850334+00:00</updated><author><name>Alicer Keendalyn Andrew</name></author><author><name>Caitlin Cooper</name></author><author><name>Julie Moore</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite major advances made in malaria treatment and control over recent decades, the development of new models for studying disease pathogenesis remains a vital part of malaria research efforts. The study of malaria infection during pregnancy is particularly reliant on mouse models, as a means of circumventing many challenges and costs associated with pregnancy studies in endemic human populations. Here, we introduce three novel murine models that will further our understanding of how post-implantation and midgestional malaria infection affects pregnancy outcomes. When C57BL/6J (B6) mice are infected with  Plasmodium chabaudi chabaudi  AS on either embryonic day (E) 6.5, 8.5, or 10.5, preterm birth occurs in all animals by E16.5, E17.5, or E18.5 respectively, with no evidence of intrauterine growth restriction. We found that the time to delivery, placental inflammatory and antioxidant transcript upregulation, and the relationships between parasitemia and transcript expression prior to preterm birth are different based on the embryonic day of infection. On the day before preterm delivery, E6.5 infected mice did not experience significant upregulation of the inflammatory or antioxidant gene transcripts examined; however, parasitemia correlated positively with  Il1β  ,  Cox1  , and  Hmox1  placental transcript abundance. E8.5 infected mice had elevated transcripts for  Ifn  g  ,  Tnf  ,  Il10  ,  Cox1  ,  Cox2  ,  Sod1  ,  Sod2  ,  Cat  , and  Nrf2  , while  Sod3  was the only transcript that correlated with parasitemia. Finally, E10.5 infected mice had elevated transcripts for  Ifn  g  only, with a tendency for  Tnf  transcripts to correlate with parasitemia. Tumor necrosis factor deficient (TNF  -/-  ) and TNF receptor 1 deficient (TNFR1  -/-  ) mice infected on E8.5 experienced preterm birth at the same time as B6 controls. Further characterization of these models is necessary to discover new and/or existing mechanism(s) or trigger(s) responsible for malaria-driven preterm birth that is determined by gestational age upon maternal infection, parasite-host dynamics, or both.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456287" rel="alternate" title="Novel murine models of post-implantation and midgestional malaria-induced preterm birth (6 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>