<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.156265+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.08.459552</id><title>MOLECULAR VIDEOGAMING: SUPER-RESOLVED TRAJECTORY-BASED NANOCLUSTERING ANALYSIS USING SPATIO-TEMPORAL INDEXING (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.157014+00:00</updated><author><name>Tristan P. Wallis</name></author><author><name>Anmin Jiang</name></author><author><name>Huiyi Hou</name></author><author><name>Rachel S. Gormal</name></author><author><name>Nela Durisic</name></author><author><name>Giuseppe Balistreri</name></author><author><name>Merja Joensuu</name></author><author><name>Frédéric A. Meunier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single-molecule localization microscopy (SMLM) techniques are emerging as vital tools to unravel the nanoscale world of living cells. However, current analysis methods primarily focus on defining spatial nanoclusters based on detection density, but neglect important temporal information such as cluster lifetime and recurrence in “hotspots” on the plasma membrane. Spatial indexing is widely used in videogames to effectively detect interactions between moving geometric objects. Here, we use the R-tree spatial indexing algorithm to perform SMLM data analysis and determine whether the bounding boxes of individual molecular trajectories overlap, as a measure of their potential membership in nanoclusters. Extending the spatial indexing into the time dimension allows unique resolution of spatial nanoclusters into multiple spatiotemporal clusters. We have validated this approach using synthetic and SMLM-derived data. Quantitative characterization of recurring nanoclusters allowed us to demonstrate that both syntaxin1a and Munc18-1 molecules transiently cluster in hotspots on the neurosecretory plasma membrane, offering unprecedented insights into the dynamics of these protein which are essential to neuronal communication. This new analytical tool, named Nanoscale Spatiotemporal Indexing Clustering (NASTIC), has been implemented as a free and open-source Python graphic user interface.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.08.459552" rel="alternate" title="MOLECULAR VIDEOGAMING: SUPER-RESOLVED TRAJECTORY-BASED NANOCLUSTERING ANALYSIS USING SPATIO-TEMPORAL INDEXING (11 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.08.459492</id><title>Combined free energy calculation and machine learning methods for understanding ligand unbinding kinetics (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.157493+00:00</updated><author><name>Magd Badaoui</name></author><author><name>Pedro J Buigues</name></author><author><name>Dénes Berta</name></author><author><name>Gaurav M. Mandana</name></author><author><name>Hankang Gu</name></author><author><name>Callum J Dickson</name></author><author><name>Viktor Hornak</name></author><author><name>Mitsunori Kato</name></author><author><name>Carla Molteni</name></author><author><name>Simon Parsons</name></author><author><name>Edina Rosta</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The determination of drug residence times, which define the time an inhibitor is in complex with its target, is a fundamental part of the drug discovery process. Synthesis and experimental pharmacokinetics measurements are, however, expensive, and time-consuming. In this work, we aimed to obtain drug residence times computationally. Furthermore, we propose a novel algorithm to identify molecular design objectives based on ligand unbinding kinetics. We designed an enhanced sampling technique to accurately predict the free energy profiles of the ligand unbinding process, focusing on the free energy barrier for unbinding. Our method first identifies unbinding paths determining a corresponding set of internal coordinates (IC) that form contacts between the protein and the ligand, then iteratively updates these interactions during a series of biased molecular-dynamics (MD) simulations to reveal the ICs important for the whole of the unbinding process. Subsequently, we performed finite temperature string simulations to obtain the free energy barrier for unbinding using the set of ICs as a complex reaction coordinate. Importantly, we also aimed to enable further design of drugs focusing on improved residence times. To this end, we developed a supervised machine learning (ML) approach that uses as input unbiased “downhill” trajectories from the transition state (TS) ensemble of the string unbinding path. We demonstrate that our ML method can identify key ligand-protein interactions driving the system through the TS. Some of the most important drugs for cancer treatment are kinase inhibitors. One of these kinase targets is Cyclin Dependent Kinase 2 (CDK2), an appealing target for anticancer drug development. Here, we tested our method using three different CDK2 inhibitors for potential further development of these compounds. We compared the free energy barriers obtained from our calculations with those observed in available experimental data. We highlighted important interactions at the distal ends of the ligands that can be targeted for improved residence times. Our method provides a new tool to determine unbinding rates, and to identify key structural features of the inhibitors that can be used as starting points for novel design strategies in drug discovery.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.08.459492" rel="alternate" title="Combined free energy calculation and machine learning methods for understanding ligand unbinding kinetics (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>