<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.197150+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470551</id><title>Skeletal muscle releases extracellular vesicles with distinct protein and miRNA signatures that accumulate and function within the muscle microenvironment (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.197901+00:00</updated><author><name>Sho Watanabe</name></author><author><name>Yuri Sudo</name></author><author><name>Satoshi Kimura</name></author><author><name>Kenji Tomita</name></author><author><name>Makoto Noguchi</name></author><author><name>Hidetoshi Sakurai</name></author><author><name>Makoto Shimizu</name></author><author><name>Yu Takahashi</name></author><author><name>Ryuichiro Sato</name></author><author><name>Yoshio Yamauchi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Extracellular vesicles (EVs) contain various regulatory molecules and mediate intercellular communications. Although EVs are secreted from various cell types, including skeletal muscle cells, and present in the blood, their identity is poorly characterized &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, limiting the identification of their origin in the blood. Since the skeletal muscle is the largest organ in the body, it could substantially contribute to circulating EVs as their source. However, due to the lack of defined markers that distinguish SkM-EVs from others, whether the skeletal muscle releases EVs &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and how much the skeletal muscle-derived EVs (SkM-EVs) account for plasma EVs remain poorly understood. In this work, we perform quantitative proteomic analyses on EVs released from C2C12 cells and human iPS cell-derived myocytes and identify potential marker proteins that mark SkM-EVs. These markers we identified apply to &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; tracking of SkM-EVs. The results show that skeletal muscle makes only a subtle contribution to plasma EVs as their source in both control and exercise conditions in mice. On the other hand, we demonstrate that SkM-EVs are concentrated in the skeletal muscle interstitium. Furthermore, we show that interstitium EVs are highly enriched with the muscle-specific miRNAs and repress the expression of the paired box transcription factor &lt;italic&gt;Pax7&lt;/italic&gt;, a master regulator for myogenesis. Taken together, our findings reveal that the skeletal muscle releases exosome-like small EVs with distinct protein and miRNA profiles &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and that SkM-EVs mainly play a role within the muscle microenvironment where they accumulate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470551" rel="alternate" title="Skeletal muscle releases extracellular vesicles with distinct protein and miRNA signatures that accumulate and function within the muscle microenvironment (12 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471046</id><title>ABC Transporters are billion-year-old Maxwell Demons (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.198337+00:00</updated><author><name>Solange Flatt</name></author><author><name>Daniel M. Busiello</name></author><author><name>Stefano Zamuner</name></author><author><name>Paolo De Los Rios</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;ABC transporters are a broad family of biological machines, found in most prokaryotic and eukaryotic cells, performing the crucial import or export of substrates through both plasma and organellar membranes, and maintaining a steady concentration gradient driven by ATP hydrolysis. Building upon the present biophysical and biochemical characterization of ABC transporters, we propose here a model whose solution reveals that these machines are an exact molecular realization of the Maxwell Demon, a century-old abstract device that uses an energy source to drive systems away from thermodynamic equilibrium. In particular, the Maxwell Demon does not perform any direct mechanical work on the system, but simply selects which spontaneous processes to allow and which ones to forbid based on information that it collects and processes. In the molecular model introduced here, the different information-processing steps that characterize Maxwell Demons (measurement, feedback and resetting) are features that emerge from the biochemical and structural properties of ABC transporters, allowing us to develop an explicit bridge between the molecular level description and the higher-level language of information theory.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471046" rel="alternate" title="ABC Transporters are billion-year-old Maxwell Demons (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470839</id><title>The SPICA Coarse-Grained Force Field for Proteins and Peptides (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.198589+00:00</updated><author><name>Shuhei Kawamoto</name></author><author><name>Huihui Liu</name></author><author><name>Sangjae Seo</name></author><author><name>Yusuke Miyazaki</name></author><author><name>Mayank Dixit</name></author><author><name>Russell DeVane</name></author><author><name>Christopher MacDermaid</name></author><author><name>Giacomo Fiorin</name></author><author><name>Michael L. Klein</name></author><author><name>Wataru Shinoda</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A coarse-grained (CG) model for peptides and proteins was developed as an extension of the SPICA (Surface Property fItting Coarse grAined) force field (FF). The model was designed to examine membrane proteins that are fully compatible with the lipid membranes of the SPICA FF. A preliminary version of this protein model was created using thermodynamic properties, including the surface tension and density in the SPICA (formerly called SDK) FF. In this study, we improved the CG protein model to facilitate molecular dynamics (MD) simulation with a reproduction of multiple properties from both experiments and all-atom (AA) simulations. The side chain analogs reproduced the transfer free energy profiles across the lipid membrane and demonstrated reasonable dimerization free energies in water compared to those from AA-MD. A series of peptides/proteins adsorbed or penetrated into the membrane simulated by the CG-MD correctly predicted the penetration depths and tilt angles of peripheral and transmembrane peptides/proteins comparable to those in the orientation of protein in membrane (OPM) database. In addition, the dimerization free energies of several transmembrane helices within a lipid bilayer were comparable to those from experimental estimation. Application studies on a series of membrane protein assemblies, scramblases, and poliovirus capsids demonstrated a good performance of the SPICA FF.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470839" rel="alternate" title="The SPICA Coarse-Grained Force Field for Proteins and Peptides (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470531</id><title>Potassium effects on NCC are attenuated during inhibition of Cullin E3-ubiquitin ligases (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.198856+00:00</updated><author><name>Sathish K Murali</name></author><author><name>Robert Little</name></author><author><name>Søren B Poulsen</name></author><author><name>Mohammed Z Ferdaus</name></author><author><name>David H Ellison</name></author><author><name>James A McCormick</name></author><author><name>Robert A Fenton</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The thiazide sensitive sodium-chloride co-transporter (NCC) plays a vital role in maintaining sodium (Na&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;) and potassium (K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;) homeostasis. NCC activity is modulated by the with-no-lysine kinases 1 and 4 (WNK1 and WNK4), the abundance of which are controlled by the RING-type E3 ligase Cullin 3 (Cul3) and its substrate adapter Kelch-like protein 3. Dietary K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; intake has an inverse correlation with NCC activity, but the mechanism underlying this phenomenon remains to be fully elucidated. Here, we investigated the involvement of other members of the Cullin family in mediating K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; effects on NCC phosphorylation (active form) and abundance. In kidneys from mice fed diets varying in K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; content, there were negative correlations between NCC (phosphorylated and total) and active (neddylated) forms of Cullins (Cul1, 3, 4 and 5). High dietary K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; effects on phosphorylated NCC were attenuated in Cul3 mutant mice (CUL3-Het/Δ9). Short-term (30 min) and long-term (24 h) alterations in the extracellular K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; concentration did not affect Cullin neddylation levels in &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; renal tubules. Short-term, the ability of high extracellular K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; to decrease NCC phosphorylation was preserved in the presence of MLN4924 (pan Cullin inhibitor), but the response to low extracellular K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; was absent. Long-term, MLN4924 attenuated the effects of high extracellular K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; on NCC phosphorylation and responses to low extracellular K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; were absent. Our data suggest that in addition to Cul3, other Cullins are involved in mediating the effects of K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; on NCC phosphorylation and abundance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470531" rel="alternate" title="Potassium effects on NCC are attenuated during inhibition of Cullin E3-ubiquitin ligases (3 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471142</id><title>An accelerometer-derived ballistocardiogram method for detecting heartrates in free-ranging marine mammals (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.199060+00:00</updated><author><name>Max F Czapanskiy</name></author><author><name>Paul J Ponganis</name></author><author><name>James A Fahlbusch</name></author><author><name>Todd L Schmitt</name></author><author><name>Jeremy A Godlbogen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Physio-logging methods, which use animal-borne devices to record physiological variables, are entering a new era driven by advances in sensor development. However, existing datasets collected with traditional bio-loggers, such as accelerometers, still contain untapped eco-physiological information. Here we present a computational method for extracting heartrate from high-resolution accelerometer data using a ballistocardiogram. We validated our method with simultaneous accelerometer-electrocardiogram tag deployments in a controlled setting on a killer whale (Orcinus orca) and demonstrate the method recovers previously observed cardiovascular patterns in a blue whale (Balaenoptera musculus), including the magnitude of apneic bradycardia and increase in heart rate prior to and during ascent. Our ballistocardiogram method may be applied to mine heart rates from previously collected accelerometery and expand our understanding of comparative cardiovascular physiology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471142" rel="alternate" title="An accelerometer-derived ballistocardiogram method for detecting heartrates in free-ranging marine mammals (3 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470798</id><title>iDEP-assisted isolation of insulin secretory vesicles (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.199237+00:00</updated><author><name>Mahta Barekatain</name></author><author><name>Yameng Liu</name></author><author><name>Zhongying Wang</name></author><author><name>Vadim Cherezov</name></author><author><name>Scott E. Fraser</name></author><author><name>Kate L White</name></author><author><name>Mark A. Hayes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Organelle heterogeneity and inter-organelle associations within a single cell contribute to the limited sensitivity of current organelle separation techniques, thus hindering organelle subpopulation characterization. Here we use direct current insulator-based dielectrophoresis (DC-iDEP) as an unbiased separation method and demonstrate its capability by identifying distinct distribution patterns of insulin vesicles from pancreatic β-cells. A multiple voltage DC-iDEP strategy with increased range and sensitivity has been applied, and a differentiation factor (ratio of electrokinetic to dielectrophoretic mobility) has been used to characterize features of insulin vesicle distribution patterns. We observed a significant difference in the distribution pattern of insulin vesicles isolated from glucose-stimulated cells relative to unstimulated cells, in accordance with functional maturation of vesicles upon glucose stimulation, and interpret this to be indicative of high-resolution separation of vesicle subpopulation. DC-iDEP provides a path for future characterization of subtle biochemical differences of organelle subpopulations within any biological system.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470798" rel="alternate" title="iDEP-assisted isolation of insulin secretory vesicles (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>