<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.819462+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.29.454302</id><title>Small extracellular vesicles from young mice prevent frailty and improve healthspan in old mice (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.819839+00:00</updated><author><name>Jorge Sanz-Ros</name></author><author><name>Cristina Mas-Bargues</name></author><author><name>Daniel Monleón</name></author><author><name>Mar Dromant</name></author><author><name>Aksinya Derevyanko</name></author><author><name>Ana Guío-Carrión</name></author><author><name>Aurora Román-Domínguez</name></author><author><name>Nekane Romero-García</name></author><author><name>Marta Inglés</name></author><author><name>María A. Blasco</name></author><author><name>Jose Viña</name></author><author><name>Consuelo Borrás</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aging is associated with an increased risk of frailty, disability, comorbidities, institutionalization, falls, fractures, hospitalization, and mortality. Searching for strategies to delay the degenerative changes associated with aging and frailty is interesting. We treated old animals intravenously with small extracellular vesicles (sEVs) derived from adipose mesenchymal stem cells (ADSCs) of young animals, and we found an improvement of several functional parameters usually altered with aging, such as motor coordination, grip strength, fatigue resistance, fur regeneration, and renal function. Frailty index analysis showed that 40% of old control mice were frail, whereas none of the old ADSCs-sEVs treated mice were. Molecular and structural benefits in muscle and kidney accompanied this functional improvement. ADSCs-sEVs induced pro-regenerative effects and a decrease in oxidative stress, inflammation, and senescence markers. The metabolome of treated mice changed to a youth-like pattern. Finally, we gained some insight into the miRNAs contained in sEVs that might be, at least in part, responsible for the effects observed. We propose that young sEVs treatment can be beneficial against frailty and therefore can promote healthy aging.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.29.454302" rel="alternate" title="Small extracellular vesicles from young mice prevent frailty and improve healthspan in old mice (9 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.29.454308</id><title>HGFAC is a ChREBP Regulated Hepatokine that Enhances Glucose and Lipid Homeostasis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.820154+00:00</updated><author><name>Ashot Sargsyan</name></author><author><name>Ludivine Doridot</name></author><author><name>Sarah A. Hannou</name></author><author><name>Wenxin Tong</name></author><author><name>Harini Srinivasan</name></author><author><name>Rachael Ivison</name></author><author><name>Ruby Monn</name></author><author><name>Henry H. Kou</name></author><author><name>Jonathan M. Haldeman</name></author><author><name>Michelle Arlotto</name></author><author><name>Phillip J. White</name></author><author><name>Paul A. Grimsrud</name></author><author><name>Inna Astapova</name></author><author><name>Linus Tsai</name></author><author><name>Mark A. Herman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Carbohydrate Responsive Element-Binding Protein (ChREBP) is a carbohydrate sensing transcription factor that regulates both adaptive and maladaptive genomic responses in coordination of systemic fuel homeostasis. Genetic variants in the ChREBP locus associate with diverse metabolic traits in humans, including circulating lipids. To identify novel ChREBP-regulated hepatokines that contribute to its systemic metabolic effects, we integrated ChREBP ChIP-seq analysis in mouse liver with human genetic and genomic data for lipid traits and identified Hepatocyte Growth Factor Activator (HGFAC) as a promising ChREBP-regulated candidate in mice and humans. HGFAC is a protease that activates the pleiotropic hormone Hepatocyte Growth Factor (HGF). We demonstrate that HGFAC KO mice have phenotypes concordant with putative loss-of-function variants in human HGFAC. Moreover, in gain- and loss-of-function genetic mouse models, we demonstrate that HGFAC enhances lipid and glucose homeostasis, in part, through actions to activate hepatic PPARγ activity. Together, our studies show that ChREBP mediates an adaptive response to overnutrition via activation of an HGFAC-HGF-PPARγ signaling axis in the liver to preserve glucose and lipid homeostasis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.29.454308" rel="alternate" title="HGFAC is a ChREBP Regulated Hepatokine that Enhances Glucose and Lipid Homeostasis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.31.454589</id><title>The human TRPA1 intrinsic cold and heat sensitivity involves separate channel structures beyond the N-ARD domain (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.820398+00:00</updated><author><name>Lavanya Moparthi</name></author><author><name>Viktor Sinica</name></author><author><name>Milos Filipovic</name></author><author><name>Viktorie Vlachova</name></author><author><name>Peter Michael Zygmunt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The human TRPA1 (hTRPA1) is an intrinsic thermosensitive ion channel responding to both cold and heat, depending on the redox environment. Here, we have studied purified hTRPA1 truncated proteins to gain further insight into the temperature gating of hTRPA1. We found in patch-clamp bilayer recordings that Δ1-688 hTRPA1, without the N-terminal ankyrin repeat domain (N-ARD), was more sensitive to cold and heat, whereas Δ1-854 hTRPA1 that is also lacking the S1-S4 voltage sensing-like domain (VSLD) gained sensitivity to cold but lost its heat sensitivity. The thiol reducing agent TCEP abolished the temperature sensitivity of both Δ1-688 hTRPA1 and Δ1-854 hTRPA1. Cold and heat activity of Δ1-688 hTRPA1 and Δ1-854 hTRPA1 were associated with different structural conformational changes as revealed by intrinsic tryptophan fluorescence measurements. Heat evoked major structural rearrangement of the VSLD as well as the C-terminus domain distal to the transmembrane pore domain S5-S6 (CTD), whereas cold only caused minor conformational changes. As shown for Δ1-854 hTRPA1, a sudden drop in tryptophan fluorescence occurred within 25-20°C indicating a transition between heat and cold conformations of the CTD, and thus it is proposed that the CTD contains a bidirectional temperature switch priming hTRPA1 for either cold or heat. In whole-cell patch clamp electrophysiology experiments, replacement of the cysteines 865, 1021 and 1025 with alanine modulated the cold sensitivity of hTRPA1 when heterologously expressed in HEK293T cells. It is proposed that the hTRPA1 CTD harbors cold and heat sensitive domains allosterically coupled to the S5-S6 pore region and the VSLD, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.31.454589" rel="alternate" title="The human TRPA1 intrinsic cold and heat sensitivity involves separate channel structures beyond the N-ARD domain (4 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453688</id><title>Overexpression of the gene encoding neurosecretory protein GL precursor prevents excessive fat accumulation in the adipose tissue of mice fed a long-term high-fat diet (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-02T05:56:32.820590+00:00</updated><author><name>Keisuke Fukumura</name></author><author><name>Yuki Narimatsu</name></author><author><name>Shogo Moriwaki</name></author><author><name>Eiko Iwakoshi-Ukena</name></author><author><name>Megumi Furumitsu</name></author><author><name>Kazuyoshi Ukena</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We previously identified a novel small hypothalamic protein, neurosecretory protein GL (NPGL), which induces feeding behavior and fat accumulation in rodents depending on their diet. In the present study, we explored the effects of NPGL on feeding behavior and energy metabolism in mice placed on a long-term high-fat diet with 60% calories from fat (HFD 60). Overexpression of the NPGL precursor gene &lt;italic&gt;(Npgl&lt;/italic&gt;) over 18 weeks increased food intake and body mass. The weekly body mass gain of &lt;italic&gt;Npgl&lt;/italic&gt;-overexpressing mice was higher than that of controls until 7 weeks from induction of overexpression, after which it ceased to be so. Oral glucose tolerance tests showed that &lt;italic&gt;Npgl&lt;/italic&gt; overexpression maintained glucose tolerance and increased blood insulin levels, and intraperitoneal insulin tolerance tests showed that it maintained insulin sensitivity. At the experimental endpoint, &lt;italic&gt;Npgl&lt;/italic&gt; overexpression was associated with increased mass of the perirenal white adipose tissue (WAT) and decreased mass of the epididymal WAT (eWAT), resulting in little effect on the total WAT mass. These results suggest that under long-term HFD 60 feeding, &lt;italic&gt;Npgl&lt;/italic&gt; overexpression may play a role in avoiding metabolic disturbance both by accelerating energy storage and by suppressing excess fat accumulation in certain tissues, such as the eWAT.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453688" rel="alternate" title="Overexpression of the gene encoding neurosecretory protein GL precursor prevents excessive fat accumulation in the adipose tissue of mice fed a long-term high-fat diet (3 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>