<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.121049+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462538</id><title>New tools for automated cryo-EM single-particle analysis in RELION-4.0 (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.121612+00:00</updated><author><name>Dari Kimanius</name></author><author><name>Liyi Dong</name></author><author><name>Grigory Sharov</name></author><author><name>Takanori Nakane</name></author><author><name>Sjors H.W. Scheres</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We describe new tools for the processing of electron cryo-microscopy (cryo-EM) images in the fourth major release of the RELION software. In particular, we introduce VDAM, a Variable-metric gradient Descent algorithm with Adaptive Moments estimation, for image refinement; a convolutional neural network for unsupervised selection of 2D classes; and a flexible framework for the design and execution of multiple jobs in pre-defined workflows. In addition, we present a stand-alone utility called MDCatch that links the execution of jobs within this framework with metadata gathering during microscope data acquisition. The new tools are aimed at providing fast and robust procedures for unsupervised cryo-EM structure determination, with potential applications for on-the-fly processing and the development of flexible, high-throughput structure determination pipelines. We illustrate their potential on twelve publicly available cryo-EM data sets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462538" rel="alternate" title="New tools for automated cryo-EM single-particle analysis in RELION-4.0 (22 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462487</id><title>Endoplasmic reticulum stress activates human IRE1α through reversible assembly of inactive dimers into small oligomers (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.121999+00:00</updated><author><name>Vladislav Belyy</name></author><author><name>Iratxe Zuazo-Gaztelu</name></author><author><name>Andrew Alamban</name></author><author><name>Avi Ashkenazi</name></author><author><name>Peter Walter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protein folding homeostasis in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) is regulated by a signaling network, termed the unfolded protein response (UPR). Inositol-requiring enzyme 1 (IRE1) is an ER membrane-resident kinase/RNase that mediates signal transmission in the most evolutionarily conserved branch of the UPR. Dimerization and/or higher-order oligomerization of IRE1 are thought to be important for its activation mechanism, yet the actual oligomeric states of inactive, active, and attenuated mammalian IRE1 complexes remained unknown. We developed an automated two-color single-molecule tracking approach to dissect the oligomerization of tagged endogenous human IRE1 in live cells. In contrast to previous models, our data indicate that IRE1 exists as a constitutive homodimer at baseline and assembles into small oligomers upon ER stress. We demonstrate that the formation of inactive dimers and stress-dependent oligomers is fully governed by IRE1’s lumenal domain. Phosphorylation of IRE1’s kinase domain occurs more slowly than oligomerization and is retained after oligomers disassemble back into dimers. Our findings suggest that assembly of IRE1 dimers into larger oligomers specifically enables &lt;italic&gt;trans-&lt;/italic&gt; autophosphorylation, which in turn drives IRE1’s RNase activity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462487" rel="alternate" title="Endoplasmic reticulum stress activates human IRE1α through reversible assembly of inactive dimers into small oligomers (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462062</id><title>Experimental Studies of Carpenter Bee (Xylocopa: Apidae) Thorax Mechanics During Defensive Buzzing (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.122326+00:00</updated><author><name>Mark Jankauski</name></author><author><name>Cailin Casey</name></author><author><name>Chelsea Heveran</name></author><author><name>Kathryn Busby</name></author><author><name>Stephen Buchmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bees and other Hymenoptera utilize thorax vibration to realize an extensive range of behaviors ranging from flight to pollination. Strong indirect flight muscles contract to deform the thoracic walls and the resulting oscillation is sustained through a mechanism called stretch activation. While the mechanics of the insect thorax and muscles have been studied extensively during flight, relatively little is known about the thorax mechanics during non-flight behaviors. In this work, we investigate the thorax mechanics of the carpenter bee &lt;italic&gt;Xylocopa californica&lt;/italic&gt; during defensive buzzing. During defensive buzzing, the insect folds its wings over its abdomen and rapidly fires it flight muscles, resulting in a loud audible buzz and large forces intended to deter predators. We devised a novel experiment to measure thorax oscillation and directional force production from a defensively buzzing carpenter bee. The largest peak forces were on average 175 mN and were oriented with the insect’s dorsal-ventral muscle group. Peak forces oriented with the insect’s dorsal-longitudinal muscle group averaged 117 mN. Thorax velocities were about 90 mm s^-1 p-p and velocity amplitude was positively correlated to peak force. Thorax oscillation frequency averaged 132 Hz but was highly variable both within individuals and across the tested population. From our measurements, we estimated the peak mechanical power required by defensive buzzing at 8.7 mW, which we hypothesize is greater than the power required during flight. Overall, this study provides insight into the function and capabilities of the Hymenopteran indirect flight muscle during non-flight behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462062" rel="alternate" title="Experimental Studies of Carpenter Bee (Xylocopa: Apidae) Thorax Mechanics During Defensive Buzzing (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462769</id><title>Mechanical loading and hyperosmolarity as a daily resetting cue for skeletal circadian clocks (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.122630+00:00</updated><author><name>Michal Dudek</name></author><author><name>Dharshika Pathiranage</name></author><author><name>Cátia F. Gonçalves</name></author><author><name>Craig Lawless</name></author><author><name>Dong Wang</name></author><author><name>Zhuojing Luo</name></author><author><name>Liu Yang</name></author><author><name>Judith Hoyland</name></author><author><name>Qing-Jun Meng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In mammals, temporally coordinated daily rhythms of behaviour and physiology are generated by a multi-oscillatory circadian system, entrained through cyclic environmental cues (e.g. light). Presence of niche-dependent physiological time cues has been proposed, which would allow local tissues flexibility of adopting a different phase relationship if circumstances require. Up till now, such tissue-unique stimuli have remained elusive. Here we show that cycles of mechanical loading and osmotic stimuli within physiological range drive rhythmic expression of clock genes and reset clock phase and amplitude in cartilage and intervertebral disc tissues. Hyperosmolarity (and not hypo-osmolarity) resets clocks in young and ageing skeletal tissues through mTORC2-AKT-GSK3β pathway, leading to genome-wide induction of rhythmic genes. These results suggest diurnal patterns of mechanical loading and consequent daily surges in extracellular osmolarity as a bona fide tissue niche-specific time cue to maintain skeletal circadian rhythms in sync.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Circadian clocks in aneural skeletal tissues sense the passage of time through rhythmic patterns of loading and osmolarity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462769" rel="alternate" title="Mechanical loading and hyperosmolarity as a daily resetting cue for skeletal circadian clocks (3 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462803</id><title>Improving the global dimensions of intrinsically disordered proteins in Martini 3 (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.123023+00:00</updated><author><name>F. Emil Thomasen</name></author><author><name>Francesco Pesce</name></author><author><name>Mette Ahrensback Roesgaard</name></author><author><name>Giulio Tesei</name></author><author><name>Kresten Lindorff-Larsen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Coarse-grained molecular dynamics simulations are a useful tool to determine conformational ensembles of intrinsically disordered proteins (IDPs). Here, we show that the coarse-grained force field Martini 3 underestimates the global dimensions of IDPs when compared with small angle X-ray scattering (SAXS) data. Increasing the strength of protein-water interactions favors more expanded conformations, improving agreement with SAXS data and alleviating problems with overestimated IDP-IDP interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462803" rel="alternate" title="Improving the global dimensions of intrinsically disordered proteins in Martini 3 (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462263</id><title>Enthalpic and Entropic Contributions to Interleaflet Coupling Drive Domain Registration and Anti-registration in Biological Membrane (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.123283+00:00</updated><author><name>Akshara Sharma</name></author><author><name>Aniruddha Seal</name></author><author><name>Sahithya S. Iyer</name></author><author><name>Anand Srivastava</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Biological membrane is a complex self-assembly of lipids, sterols and proteins organized as a fluid bilayer of two closely stacked lipid leaflets. Differential molecular interactions among its diverse constituents give rise to heterogeneities in the membrane lateral organization. Under certain conditions, heterogeneities in the two leaflets can be spatially synchronised and exist as registered domains across the bilayer. Several contrasting theories behind mechanisms that induce registration of nanoscale domains have been suggested[1–3]. Following a recent study[4] showing the effect of position of lipid tail unsaturation on domain registration behavior, we decided to develop an analytical theory to elucidate the driving forces that create and maintain domain registry across leaflets. Towards this, we formulated a Hamiltonian for a stacked lattice system where site variables encapsulate the lipid molecular properties including the position of unsaturation and various other interactions that could drive phase separation and interleaflet coupling. We solve the Hamiltonian using Monte Carlo simulations and create a complete phase diagram that reports the presence or absence of registered domains as a function of various Hamiltonian parameters. We find that the interleaflet coupling should be described as a competing enthalpic contribution due to interaction of lipid tail termini, primarily due to saturated-saturated interactions, and an interleaflet entropic contribution from overlap of unsaturated tail termini. We find that higher position of unsaturation provides weaker interleaflet coupling. We also find points in our parameter space that allow thermodynamically stable nanodomains in our bilayer model, which we have verified by carrying out extended Monte Carlo simulations. These persistent non-coalescing registered nanodomains close to the lower end of the accepted nanodomain size range also point towards a possible “nanoscale” emulsion description of lateral heterogeneities in biological membrane leaflets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462263" rel="alternate" title="Enthalpic and Entropic Contributions to Interleaflet Coupling Drive Domain Registration and Anti-registration in Biological Membrane (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>