<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.515593+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461876</id><title>A structural biology community assessment of AlphaFold 2 applications (219 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.517164+00:00</updated><author><name>Mehmet Akdel</name></author><author><name>Douglas E V Pires</name></author><author><name>Eduard Porta Pardo</name></author><author><name>Jürgen Jänes</name></author><author><name>Arthur O Zalevsky</name></author><author><name>Bálint Mészáros</name></author><author><name>Patrick Bryant</name></author><author><name>Lydia L. Good</name></author><author><name>Roman A Laskowski</name></author><author><name>Gabriele Pozzati</name></author><author><name>Aditi Shenoy</name></author><author><name>Wensi Zhu</name></author><author><name>Petras Kundrotas</name></author><author><name>Victoria Ruiz Serra</name></author><author><name>Carlos H M Rodrigues</name></author><author><name>Alistair S Dunham</name></author><author><name>David Burke</name></author><author><name>Neera Borkakoti</name></author><author><name>Sameer Velankar</name></author><author><name>Adam Frost</name></author><author><name>Kresten Lindorff-Larsen</name></author><author><name>Alfonso Valencia</name></author><author><name>Sergey Ovchinnikov</name></author><author><name>Janani Durairaj</name></author><author><name>David B Ascher</name></author><author><name>Janet M Thornton</name></author><author><name>Norman E Davey</name></author><author><name>Amelie Stein</name></author><author><name>Arne Elofsson</name></author><author><name>Tristan I Croll</name></author><author><name>Pedro Beltrao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Most proteins fold into 3D structures that determine how they function and orchestrate the biological processes of the cell. Recent developments in computational methods have led to protein structure predictions that have reached the accuracy of experimentally determined models. While this has been independently verified, the implementation of these methods across structural biology applications remains to be tested. Here, we evaluate the use of AlphaFold 2 (AF2) predictions in the study of characteristic structural elements; the impact of missense variants; function and ligand binding site predictions; modelling of interactions; and modelling of experimental structural data. For 11 proteomes, an average of 25% additional residues can be confidently modelled when compared to homology modelling, identifying structural features rarely seen in the PDB. AF2-based predictions of protein disorder and protein complexes surpass state-of-the-art tools and AF2 models can be used across diverse applications equally well compared to experimentally determined structures, when the confidence metrics are critically considered. In summary, we find that these advances are likely to have a transformative impact in structural biology and broader life science research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461876" rel="alternate" title="A structural biology community assessment of AlphaFold 2 applications (219 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461186</id><title>Probing nanomotion of single bacteria with graphene drums (45 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.518307+00:00</updated><author><name>I.E. Rosłoń</name></author><author><name>A. Japaridze</name></author><author><name>P.G. Steeneken</name></author><author><name>C. Dekker</name></author><author><name>F. Alijani</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Motion is a key characteristic of every form of life&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. Even at the microscale, it has been reported that colonies of bacteria can generate nanomotion on mechanical cantilevers&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, but the origin of these nanoscale vibrations has remained unresolved&lt;sup&gt;3,4&lt;/sup&gt;. Here, we present a novel technique using drums made of ultrathin bilayer graphene, where the nanomotion of single bacteria can be measured in its aqueous growth environment. A single &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; cell is found to generate random oscillations with amplitudes of up to 60 nm, exerting forces of up to 6 nN to its environment. Using mutant strains, we are able to pinpoint the bacterial flagella as the main source of nanomotion. By real-time tracing of changes in nanomotion upon administering antibiotics, we demonstrate that graphene drums can perform antibiotic susceptibility testing with single-cell sensitivity. These findings deepen our understanding of processes underlying cellular dynamics, and pave the way towards high throughput and parallelized rapid screening of the effectiveness of antibiotics in bacterial infections with graphene devices.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461186" rel="alternate" title="Probing nanomotion of single bacteria with graphene drums (45 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462538</id><title>New tools for automated cryo-EM single-particle analysis in RELION-4.0 (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.518614+00:00</updated><author><name>Dari Kimanius</name></author><author><name>Liyi Dong</name></author><author><name>Grigory Sharov</name></author><author><name>Takanori Nakane</name></author><author><name>Sjors H.W. Scheres</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We describe new tools for the processing of electron cryo-microscopy (cryo-EM) images in the fourth major release of the RELION software. In particular, we introduce VDAM, a Variable-metric gradient Descent algorithm with Adaptive Moments estimation, for image refinement; a convolutional neural network for unsupervised selection of 2D classes; and a flexible framework for the design and execution of multiple jobs in pre-defined workflows. In addition, we present a stand-alone utility called MDCatch that links the execution of jobs within this framework with metadata gathering during microscope data acquisition. The new tools are aimed at providing fast and robust procedures for unsupervised cryo-EM structure determination, with potential applications for on-the-fly processing and the development of flexible, high-throughput structure determination pipelines. We illustrate their potential on twelve publicly available cryo-EM data sets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462538" rel="alternate" title="New tools for automated cryo-EM single-particle analysis in RELION-4.0 (26 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461830</id><title>Atomic-Resolution Prediction of Degrader-mediated Ternary Complex Structures by Combining Molecular Simulations with Hydrogen Deuterium Exchange (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.518867+00:00</updated><author><name>Tom Dixon</name></author><author><name>Derek MacPherson</name></author><author><name>Barmak Mostofian</name></author><author><name>Taras Dauzhenka</name></author><author><name>Samuel Lotz</name></author><author><name>Dwight McGee</name></author><author><name>Sharon Shechter</name></author><author><name>Utsab R. Shrestha</name></author><author><name>Rafal Wiewiora</name></author><author><name>Zachary A. McDargh</name></author><author><name>Fen Pei</name></author><author><name>Rajat Pal</name></author><author><name>João V. Ribeiro</name></author><author><name>Tanner Wilkerson</name></author><author><name>Vipin Sachdeva</name></author><author><name>Ning Gao</name></author><author><name>Shourya Jain</name></author><author><name>Samuel Sparks</name></author><author><name>Yunxing Li</name></author><author><name>Alexander Vinitsky</name></author><author><name>Asghar M. Razavi</name></author><author><name>István Kolossváry</name></author><author><name>Jason Imbriglio</name></author><author><name>Artem Evdokimov</name></author><author><name>Louise Bergeron</name></author><author><name>Alex Dickson</name></author><author><name>Huafeng Xu</name></author><author><name>Woody Sherman</name></author><author><name>Jesus A. Izaguirre</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Targeted protein degradation (TPD) has recently emerged as a powerful approach for removing (rather than inhibiting) proteins implicated in diseases. A key step in TPD is the formation of an induced proximity complex where a degrader molecule recruits an E3 ligase to the protein of interest (POI), facilitating the transfer of ubiquitin to the POI and initiating the proteasomal degradation process. Here, we address three critical aspects of the TPD process using atomistic simulations: 1) formation of the ternary complex induced by a degrader molecule, 2) conformational heterogeneity of the ternary complex, and 3) degradation efficiency via the full Cullin Ring Ligase (CRL) macromolecular assembly. The novel approach described here combines experimental biophysical data with molecular dynamics (MD) simulations to accurately predict ternary complex structures at atomic resolution. We integrate hydrogen-deuterium exchange mass spectrometry (HDX-MS, which measures the solvent exposure of protein residues) directly into the MD simulation algorithm to improve the efficiency and accuracy of the ternary structure predictions of the bromodomain of the cancer target SMARCA2 with the E3 ligase VHL, as mediated by three different degrader molecules. The simulations accurately reproduce X-ray crystal structures–including a new structure that we determined in this work (PDB ID: 7S4E)–with root mean square deviations (RMSD) of 1.1 to 1.6 Å. The simulations also reveal a structural ensemble of low-energy conformations of the ternary complex. Snapshots from these simulations are used as seeds for additional simulations, where we perform 5.7 milliseconds of aggregate simulation time using Folding@home, the world’s largest distributed supercomputer. The detailed free energy surface captures the crystal structure conformation within the low-energy basin and is consistent with solution-phase experimental data (HDX-MS and SAXS). Finally, we graft a structural ensemble of the ternary complexes onto the full CRL and perform enhanced sampling simulations. Our results suggest that differences in degradation efficiency may be related to the proximity distribution of lysine residues on the POI relative to the E2-loaded ubiquitin. We make source code and the simulation and experimental datasets from this work publicly available for researchers to further advance the field of induced proximity modulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461830" rel="alternate" title="Atomic-Resolution Prediction of Degrader-mediated Ternary Complex Structures by Combining Molecular Simulations with Hydrogen Deuterium Exchange (15 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461298</id><title>Perilacunar bone tissue exhibits sub-micrometer modulus gradation which depends on the recency of osteocyte bone formation (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.519384+00:00</updated><author><name>Caleb J. Rux</name></author><author><name>Ghazal Vahidi</name></author><author><name>Amir Darabi</name></author><author><name>Lewis M. Cox</name></author><author><name>Chelsea M. Heveran</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Osteocytes are capable of resorbing and replacing bone local to the lacunar-canalicular system (LCS remodeling). However, the impacts of these processes on perilacunar bone quality are not understood. It is well established that aging is associated with reduced whole-bone fracture resistance, reduced osteocyte viability, and truncated LCS geometries, but it remains unclear if aging changes perilacunar bone quality. In this study, we employed atomic force microscopy (AFM) to quantify sub-micrometer gradations from 2D maps surrounding osteocyte lacunae in young (5 mo) and aged (22 mo) female mice. AFM-mapped lacunae were also imaged with confocal laser scanning microscopy to determine which osteocytes had recently deposited bone as determined by the presence of fluorochrome labels. These assays allowed us to quantify gradations in nanoscale mechanical properties of bone-forming/non-bone-forming osteocytes in young and aged mice. This study reports for the first time that there are sub-micrometer gradations in modulus surrounding lacunae and that these gradations are dependent upon recent osteocyte bone formation. Perilacunar bone adjacent to bone-forming osteocytes demonstrated lower peak and bulk modulus values when compared to bone near non-bone-forming osteocytes from the same mouse. Bone-forming osteocytes also showed increased perilacunar modulus variability. Age reduced lacunar size but did not significant effect modulus gradation or variability. In general, lacunar morphology was not a strong predictor of modulus gradation patterns. These findings support the idea that lacunar-canalicular remodeling activity changes the material properties of surrounding bone tissue on a sub-micrometer scale. Therefore, conditions that affect osteocyte health have the potential to impact bone quality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;GRAPHICAL ABSTRACT&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="461298v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461298" rel="alternate" title="Perilacunar bone tissue exhibits sub-micrometer modulus gradation which depends on the recency of osteocyte bone formation (13 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.460453</id><title>Structures of plasmepsin X from P. falciparum reveal a novel inactivation mechanism of the zymogen and molecular basis for binding of inhibitors in mature enzyme (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.519684+00:00</updated><author><name>Pooja Kesari</name></author><author><name>Anuradha Deshmukh</name></author><author><name>Nikhil Pahelkar</name></author><author><name>Abhishek B. Suryawanshi</name></author><author><name>Ishan Rathore</name></author><author><name>Vandana Mishra</name></author><author><name>John H. Dupuis</name></author><author><name>Huogen Xiao</name></author><author><name>Alla Gustchina</name></author><author><name>Jan Abendroth</name></author><author><name>Mehdi Labaied</name></author><author><name>Rickey Y. Yada</name></author><author><name>Alexander Wlodawer</name></author><author><name>Thomas E. Edwards</name></author><author><name>Donald D. Lorimer</name></author><author><name>Prasenjit Bhaumik</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Plasmodium falciparum&lt;/italic&gt; plasmepsin X (&lt;italic&gt;Pf&lt;/italic&gt;PMX), involved in the invasion and egress of this deadliest malarial parasite, is essential for its survival and hence considered as an important drug target. We report the first crystal structure of &lt;italic&gt;Pf&lt;/italic&gt;PMX zymogen containing a novel fold of its prosegment. A unique twisted loop from the prosegment and arginine 244 from the mature enzyme are involved in zymogen inactivation; such mechanism, not previously reported, might be common for apicomplexan proteases similar to &lt;italic&gt;Pf&lt;/italic&gt;PMX. The maturation of &lt;italic&gt;Pf&lt;/italic&gt;PMX zymogen occurs through cleavage of its prosegment at multiple sites. Our data provide thorough insights into the mode of binding of a substrate and a potent inhibitor 49c to &lt;italic&gt;Pf&lt;/italic&gt;PMX. We present molecular details of inactivation, maturation, and inhibition of &lt;italic&gt;Pf&lt;/italic&gt;PMX that should aid in the development of potent inhibitors against pepsin-like aspartic proteases from apicomplexan parasites.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.460453" rel="alternate" title="Structures of plasmepsin X from P. falciparum reveal a novel inactivation mechanism of the zymogen and molecular basis for binding of inhibitors in mature enzyme (12 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462207</id><title>Interrogating RNA-small molecule interactions with structure probing and AI augmented-molecular simulations (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.520068+00:00</updated><author><name>Yihang Wang</name></author><author><name>Shaifaly Parmar</name></author><author><name>John S. Schneekloth</name></author><author><name>Pratyush Tiwary</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;While there is increasing interest in the study of RNA as a therapeutic target, efforts to understand RNA-ligand recognition at the molecular level lag far behind our understanding of protein-ligand recognition. This problem is complicated due to the more than ten orders of magnitude in timescales involved in RNA dynamics and ligand binding events, making it not straightforward to design experiments or simulations. Here we make use of artificial intelligence (AI)-augmented molecular dynamics simulations to directly observe ligand dissociation for cognate and synthetic ligands from a riboswitch system. The site-specific flexibility profiles from our simulations are in excellent agreement with &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; measurements of flexibility using Selective 2’ Hydroxyl Acylation analyzed by Primer Extension and Mutational Profiling (SHAPE-MaP). Our simulations reproduce known binding affinity profiles for the cognate and synthetic ligands, and pinpoint how both ligands make use of different aspects of riboswitch flexibility. On the basis of our dissociation trajectories, we also make and validate predictions of pairs of mutations for both the ligand systems that would show differing binding affinities. These mutations are distal to the binding site and could not have been predicted solely on the basis of structure. The methodology demonstrated here shows how molecular dynamics simulations with all-atom force-fields have now come of age in making predictions that complement existing experimental techniques and illuminate aspects of systems otherwise not trivial to understand.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462207" rel="alternate" title="Interrogating RNA-small molecule interactions with structure probing and AI augmented-molecular simulations (12 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461508</id><title>Oligomerization of the FliF domains suggests a coordinated assembly of the bacterial flagellum MS ring (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.520447+00:00</updated><author><name>Giuseppina Mariano</name></author><author><name>Raquel Faba-Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Soi Bui</name></author><author><name>Weilong Zhao</name></author><author><name>James Ross</name></author><author><name>Svetomir Tsokov</name></author><author><name>Julien Bergeron</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The bacterial flagellum is a complex, self-assembling macromolecular machine that powers bacterial motility. It plays diverse roles in bacterial virulence, including aiding in colonization and dissemination during infection. The flagellum consists of a filamentous structure protruding from the cell, and the basal body, a large assembly that spans the cell envelope. The basal body is comprised of over 10 different proteins, forming several concentric ring structures, termed the M- S- L- P- and C-rings, respectively. In particular, the MS rings are formed by a single protein FliF, which consists of two trans-membrane helices anchoring it to the inner membrane and surrounding a large periplasmic domain. Assembly of the MS ring, through oligomerization of FliF, is one of the first steps of basal body assembly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previous computational analysis had shown that the periplasmic region of FliF consists of three structurally similar domains, termed Ring-Building Motif (RBM)1, RBM2 and RBM3. The structure of the MS-ring has been reported recently, and unexpectedly shown that these three domains adopt different symmetries, with RBM3 having a 34-mer stoichiometry, while RBM2 adopts two distinct positions in the complex, including a 23-mer ring. This observation raises some important question on the assembly of the MS ring, and the formation of this symmetry mis-match within a single protein. In this study, we analyze the oligomerization of the individual RBM domains in isolation, in the &lt;italic&gt;Salmonella typhimurium&lt;/italic&gt; FliF orthologue. We demonstrate that the periplasmic domain of FliF assembles into the MS ring, in the absence of the trans-membrane helices. We also report that the RBM2 and RBM3 domains oligomerize into ring structures, but not RBM1. Intriguingly, we observe that a construct encompassing RBM1 and RBM2 is monomeric, suggesting that RBM1 interacts with RBM2, and inhibits its oligomerization. However, this inhibition is lifted by the addition of RBM3. Collectively, this data suggests a mechanism for the controlled assembly of the MS ring.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461508" rel="alternate" title="Oligomerization of the FliF domains suggests a coordinated assembly of the bacterial flagellum MS ring (10 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462001</id><title>Integration of a radiofrequency coil and commercial field camera for ultra-high-field MRI (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.521035+00:00</updated><author><name>Kyle M. Gilbert</name></author><author><name>Paul Dubovan</name></author><author><name>Joseph S. Gati</name></author><author><name>Ravi S. Menon</name></author><author><name>Corey A. Baron</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Purpose&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To develop an RF coil with an integrated commercial field camera for ultra-high field (7 T) neuroimaging. The RF coil will operate within a head-only gradient coil and be subject to the corresponding design constraints. The RF coil can thereafter be used for subject-specific correction of k-space trajectories—notably in gradient-sensitive sequences such as single-shot spiral imaging.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The transmit and receive performance was evaluated before and after the integration of field probes, while field probes were evaluated when in an optimal configuration external to the coil and after their integration. Diffusion-weighted EPI and single-shot spiral acquisitions were employed to evaluate the efficacy of correcting higher order field perturbations and the consequent effect on image quality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Field probes had a negligible effect on RF-coil performance, including the transmit efficiency, transmit uniformity, and mean SNR over the brain. Modest reductions in field-probe signal lifetimes were observed, caused primarily by non-idealities in the gradient and shim fields of the head-only gradient coil at the probe positions. The field monitoring system could correct up to second-order field perturbations in single-shot spiral imaging.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The integrated RF coil and field camera was capable of concurrent field monitoring within a 7T head-only scanner and facilitated the subsequent correction of k-space trajectories during spiral imaging.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462001" rel="alternate" title="Integration of a radiofrequency coil and commercial field camera for ultra-high-field MRI (7 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462487</id><title>Endoplasmic reticulum stress activates human IRE1α through reversible assembly of inactive dimers into small oligomers (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.521369+00:00</updated><author><name>Vladislav Belyy</name></author><author><name>Iratxe Zuazo-Gaztelu</name></author><author><name>Andrew Alamban</name></author><author><name>Avi Ashkenazi</name></author><author><name>Peter Walter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protein folding homeostasis in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) is regulated by a signaling network, termed the unfolded protein response (UPR). Inositol-requiring enzyme 1 (IRE1) is an ER membrane-resident kinase/RNase that mediates signal transmission in the most evolutionarily conserved branch of the UPR. Dimerization and/or higher-order oligomerization of IRE1 are thought to be important for its activation mechanism, yet the actual oligomeric states of inactive, active, and attenuated mammalian IRE1 complexes remained unknown. We developed an automated two-color single-molecule tracking approach to dissect the oligomerization of tagged endogenous human IRE1 in live cells. In contrast to previous models, our data indicate that IRE1 exists as a constitutive homodimer at baseline and assembles into small oligomers upon ER stress. We demonstrate that the formation of inactive dimers and stress-dependent oligomers is fully governed by IRE1’s lumenal domain. Phosphorylation of IRE1’s kinase domain occurs more slowly than oligomerization and is retained after oligomers disassemble back into dimers. Our findings suggest that assembly of IRE1 dimers into larger oligomers specifically enables &lt;italic&gt;trans-&lt;/italic&gt; autophosphorylation, which in turn drives IRE1’s RNase activity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462487" rel="alternate" title="Endoplasmic reticulum stress activates human IRE1α through reversible assembly of inactive dimers into small oligomers (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462048</id><title>Characterizing SERCA function in murine skeletal muscles after 35-37 days of spaceflight (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.521678+00:00</updated><author><name>Jessica L. Braun</name></author><author><name>Mia S. Geromella</name></author><author><name>Sophie I. Hamstra</name></author><author><name>Holt N. Messner</name></author><author><name>Val A. Fajardo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It is well established that microgravity exposure causes significant muscle weakness and atrophy via muscle unloading. On Earth, muscle unloading leads to a disproportionate loss in muscle force and size with the loss in muscle force occurring at a faster rate. Though the exact mechanisms are unknown, a role for Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; dysregulation has been suggested. The sarco(endo)plasmic reticulum Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; ATPase (SERCA) pump actively brings cytosolic Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; into the SR, eliciting muscle relaxation and maintaining low intracellular Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; ([Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;]&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;). SERCA dysfunction contributes to elevations in [Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;]&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;, leading to cellular damage and thus may contribute to the muscle weakness and atrophy observed with spaceflight. Here, we investigated SERCA function, SERCA regulatory protein content (sarcolipin, phospholamban, and neuronatin), and reactive oxygen/nitrogen species (RONS) protein adduction in murine skeletal muscle after 35-37 days of spaceflight. In male and female soleus muscles, spaceflight led to drastic impairments in Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; uptake despite significant increases in SERCA1a protein content. We attribute this impairment to an increase in RONS production and elevated total protein tyrosine (T) nitration and cysteine (S) nitrosylation. Contrarily, in the tibialis anterior (TA) we observed an enhancement in Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; uptake, which we attribute to a shift towards a faster muscle fiber type (i.e., increased myosin heavy chain IIb and SERCA1a) without elevated total protein T-nitration and S-nitrosylation. Thus, spaceflight affects SERCA function differently between the soleus and TA. As the soleus is severely affected by spaceflight, future studies should determine whether improving SERCA function in this muscle can mitigate muscle atrophy and weakness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462048" rel="alternate" title="Characterizing SERCA function in murine skeletal muscles after 35-37 days of spaceflight (6 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.19.460958</id><title>Copeptin response to acute physical stress during hypohydration: An exploratory secondary analysis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.522359+00:00</updated><author><name>Harriet A. Carroll</name></author><author><name>Olle Melander</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Purpose&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plasma copeptin (a surrogate marker of arginine vasopressin) is increasingly being used as a marker of stress in several research and clinical contexts. However, the response to an acute physical stressor in healthy adults has not yet been tested meaning it is unclear whether copeptin reflects dynamic changes in stress or whether this is moderated by different basal copeptin concentrations and how this relates to other stress hormones.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secondary data analysis in a subsample of participants (n = 7; n = 1 woman) who opted-in for muscle biopsies in a randomised crossover study investigating the effects of acute hypohydration (HYPO) &lt;italic&gt;versus&lt;/italic&gt; rehydration (RE) on metabolism.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plasma copeptin responded to the muscle biopsy stress stimulus, with a similar magnitude of difference according to basal concentrations during HYPO and RE; however, the peak was higher and concentrations typically took longer to return to baseline during HYPO. Despite large differences in copeptin concentrations, adrenocorticotropin hormone (ACTH) and cortisol showed a similar trends in response to the biopsies, regardless of hydration status.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Copeptin responded dynamically to an acute physical stressor (muscle biopsy). HYPO induced higher basal copeptin concentrations compared to RE, and resulted in a higher and prolonged copeptin response. Further research should investigate the mechanisms underlying the lack of differences in ACTH and cortisol according to hydration status.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.19.460958" rel="alternate" title="Copeptin response to acute physical stress during hypohydration: An exploratory secondary analysis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-09-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461807</id><title>Practices for Measuring 3D Organelle Morphology and Generating Surfaces with Amira (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.522847+00:00</updated><author><name>Edgar Garza Lopez</name></author><author><name>Zer Vue</name></author><author><name>Prasanna Katti</name></author><author><name>Kit Neikirk</name></author><author><name>Michelle Biete</name></author><author><name>Jacob Lam</name></author><author><name>Heather K. Beasley</name></author><author><name>Andrea G. Marshall</name></author><author><name>Taylor Rodman</name></author><author><name>Trace Christensen</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey Salisbury</name></author><author><name>Larry Vang</name></author><author><name>Margaret Mungai</name></author><author><name>Salma AshShareef</name></author><author><name>Sandra Murray</name></author><author><name>Jianqiang Shao</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Streeter</name></author><author><name>Brian Glancy</name></author><author><name>Renata O. Pereira</name></author><author><name>E. Dale Abel</name></author><author><name>Antentor Hinton</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Analysis of 3D structures is of paramount importance in cellular biology. Although light microscopy and transmission electron microscopy (TEM) have remained staples for imaging cellular structures, they lack the ability to image in 3D. However, recent technological advances, such as serial block-face scanning electron microscopy (SBF-SEM) and focused ion beam scanning electron microscopy (FIB-SEM), have allowed researchers to observe cellular ultrastructure in 3D. Here, we propose a standardized protocol using the visualization software Amira to quantify organelle morphologies in 3D; this method allows researchers to produce accurate and reproducible measurements of cellular structure characteristics. We demonstrate this applicability by utilizing SBF-SEM and Amira to quantify mitochondria and endoplasmic reticulum (ER) structures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;GRAPHICAL ABSTRACT&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="461807v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461807" rel="alternate" title="Practices for Measuring 3D Organelle Morphology and Generating Surfaces with Amira (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461565</id><title>Structural basis of substrate recognition and translocation by human ABCD1 (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.523354+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhi-Peng Chen</name></author><author><name>Da Xu</name></author><author><name>Liang Wang</name></author><author><name>Cong-Zhao Zhou</name></author><author><name>Wen-Tao Hou</name></author><author><name>Yuxing Chen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human ATP-binding cassette (ABC) transporter ABCD1 transports CoA esters of saturated/monounsaturated very long chain fatty acid from cytosol to the peroxisome for β-oxidation. Dysfunction of human ABCD1 usually causes the severe progressive genetic disorder X-linked adrenoleukodystrophy, which eventually affects the adrenal glands and/or the central nervous system. Here, we report three cryo-EM structures of human ABCD1 in various states. The apo-form ABCD1 at 3.53 Å resolution adopts an inward-facing conformation, harboring a phosphatidyl ethanolamine (PE) molecule at each lateral entry of substrate cavity. In the substrate-bound ABCD1 structure at 3.59 Å resolution, two molecules of C22:0-CoA (one of the physiological substrates of ABCD1) is symmetrically bound to the transmembrane domains (TMDs). Each C22:0-CoA adopts an unpresented L-shape configuration: the CoA portion inserts into a polar pocket at the TMD at a pose parallel to the membrane plane, whereas the acyl chain portion perpendicular to membrane plane is embedded in a hydrophobic pocket at the opposite TMD. Upon binding the two C22:0-CoA molecules, which resemble a pair of hinges crossing the two TMDs, the two nucleotide-binding domains (NBDs) of ABCD1 approach towards each other. Addition ATP to the substrate-bound ABCD1 enabled us to reveal an ATP-bound structure at 2.79 Å, which shows an outward-facing conformation with the dimerized NBDs succeeding substrate release. These three structures combined with biochemical assays exhibit a snapshot of ABCD1-mediated substrate recognition, translocation and release. These findings provide the structural insights into the transport mechanism of ABC transporters that transport amphipathic molecules with long acyl chains.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461565" rel="alternate" title="Structural basis of substrate recognition and translocation by human ABCD1 (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461905</id><title>The interplay of supercoiling and thymine dimers in DNA (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.523655+00:00</updated><author><name>Wilber Lim</name></author><author><name>Ferdinando Randisi</name></author><author><name>Jonathan P. K. Doye</name></author><author><name>Ard A. Louis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Thymine dimers are a major mutagenic photoproduct induced by UV radiation. While they have been the subject of extensive theoretical and experimental investigations, questions of how DNA supercoiling affects local defect properties, or, conversely, how the presence of such defects changes global supercoiled structure, are largely unexplored. Here we introduce a model of thymine dimers in the oxDNA forcefield, and validate it by comparison to melting experiments and structural measurements of the thymine dimer induced bend angle. We performed extensive molecular dynamics simulations of double-stranded DNA as a function of external twist and force. Compared to undamaged DNA, the presence of a thymine dimer lowers the supercoiling densities at which plectonemes and bubbles occur. For biologically relevant supercoiling densities and forces, thymine dimers can preferentially segregate to the tips of the plectonemes, where they enhance the probability of a localized tip-bubble. This mechanism increases the probability of highly bent and denatured states at the thymine dimer site, which may facilitate repair enzyme binding. Thymine dimer-induced tip-bubbles also pin plectonemes, which may help repair enzymes to locate damage. We hypothesize that the interplay of supercoiling and local defects plays an important role for a wider set of DNA damage repair systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461905" rel="alternate" title="The interplay of supercoiling and thymine dimers in DNA (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462803</id><title>Improving the global dimensions of intrinsically disordered proteins in Martini 3 (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.523924+00:00</updated><author><name>F. Emil Thomasen</name></author><author><name>Francesco Pesce</name></author><author><name>Mette Ahrensback Roesgaard</name></author><author><name>Giulio Tesei</name></author><author><name>Kresten Lindorff-Larsen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Coarse-grained molecular dynamics simulations are a useful tool to determine conformational ensembles of intrinsically disordered proteins (IDPs). Here, we show that the coarse-grained force field Martini 3 underestimates the global dimensions of IDPs when compared with small angle X-ray scattering (SAXS) data. Increasing the strength of protein-water interactions favors more expanded conformations, improving agreement with SAXS data and alleviating problems with overestimated IDP-IDP interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462803" rel="alternate" title="Improving the global dimensions of intrinsically disordered proteins in Martini 3 (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461797</id><title>Single-molecule analysis of specificity and multivalency in binding of short linear substrate motifs to the APC/C (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.524370+00:00</updated><author><name>Nairi Hartooni</name></author><author><name>Jongmin Sung</name></author><author><name>Ankur Jain</name></author><author><name>David O. Morgan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Robust regulatory signals in the cell often depend on interactions between short linear motifs (SLiMs) and globular proteins. Many of these interactions are poorly characterized because the binding proteins cannot be produced in the amounts needed for traditional methods. To address this problem, we developed a single-molecule off-rate (SMOR) assay based on microscopy of fluorescent ligand binding to immobilized protein partners. We used it to characterize substrate binding to the Anaphase-Promoting Complex/Cyclosome (APC/C), a ubiquitin ligase that triggers chromosome segregation. We find that SLiMs in APC/C substrates (the D box and KEN box) display distinct affinities and specificities for the substrate-binding subunits of the APC/C, and we show that multiple SLiMs in a substrate generate a high-affinity multivalent interaction. The remarkably adaptable substrate-binding mechanisms of the APC/C have the potential to govern the order of substrate destruction in mitosis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461797" rel="alternate" title="Single-molecule analysis of specificity and multivalency in binding of short linear substrate motifs to the APC/C (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461481</id><title>Mechanical characterisation of the developing cell wall layers of tension wood fibres by Atomic Force Microscopy (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.524660+00:00</updated><author><name>O. Arnould</name></author><author><name>M. Capron</name></author><author><name>M. Ramonda</name></author><author><name>F. Laurans</name></author><author><name>T. Alméras</name></author><author><name>G. Pilate</name></author><author><name>B. Clair</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Trees can generate large mechanical stresses at the stem periphery to control the orientation of their axes. This key factor in the biomechanical design of trees, named “maturation stress”, occurs in wood fibres during cellular maturation when their secondary cell wall thickens. In this study, the spatial and temporal stiffening kinetics of the different cell wall layers were recorded during fibre maturation on a sample of poplar tension wood using atomic force microscopy. The thickening of the different layers was also recorded. The stiffening of the CML, S&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; and S&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-layers was initially synchronous with the thickening of the S&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; layer and continued a little after the S&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-layer reached its final thickness as the G-layer begins to develop. In contrast, the global stiffness of the G-layer, which initially increased with its thickening, was almost stable long before it reached its final maximum thickness. A limited radial gradient of stiffness was observed in the G-layer, but it decreased sharply on the lumen side, where the new sub-layers are deposited during cell wall thickening. Although very similar at the ultrastructural and biochemical levels, the stiffening kinetics of the poplar G-layer appears to be very different from that described in maturing bast fibres.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlight&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;New insights into the changes in mechanical properties within the cell wall of poplar tension wood fibres during maturation have been obtained using atomic force microscopy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461481" rel="alternate" title="Mechanical characterisation of the developing cell wall layers of tension wood fibres by Atomic Force Microscopy (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461199</id><title>Mitochondrial stress-induced GDF15-GFRAL axis promotes anxiety-like behavior and CRH-dependent anorexia (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.524959+00:00</updated><author><name>Carla Igual Gil</name></author><author><name>Bethany M. Coull</name></author><author><name>Wenke Jonas</name></author><author><name>Rachel Lippert</name></author><author><name>Mario Ost</name></author><author><name>Susanne Klaus</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Growth differentiation factor 15 (GDF15) is a stress-induced cytokine that modulates food intake and energy metabolism. Until now, most mechanistic studies on GDF15 rely on pharmacological interventions using exogenous GDF15, but little is known about its mode of action when induced both chronically and endogenously. Mitochondrial stress is one of the most described physiological conditions that induces GDF15&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;, and therefore an important model to study the underlying mechanisms of endogenous GDF15’s action. Here, using a mouse model of mitochondrial dysfunction via elevated respiratory uncoupling in skeletal muscle, we show a circadian oscillation of muscle-derived GDF15 to promote a daytime-restricted anorexia without signs of nausea or reduced physical activity, contrary to findings using recombinant GDF15&lt;sup&gt;2–5&lt;/sup&gt;. We find that mitochondrial stress-induced GDF15 associates with increased anxiety and hypothalamic corticotropin releasing hormone (CRH) induction, without further activation of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis and corticosterone response. Strikingly, the daytime-restricted anorexia, lean phenotype, systemic shift in substrate metabolism and anxiety-like behavior are completely abolished in conditions of mitochondrial stress coupled with genetic ablation of the GDF15 receptor GDNF receptor alpha-like (GFRAL), which is predominantly expressed in the hindbrain. Finally, we demonstrate that stress-induced GDF15-GFRAL signaling is required for hypothalamic CRH induction to control diurnal food intake in a CRH-receptor 1 (CRHR1)-dependent manner. With this, we uncover for the first time a molecular target of the GDF15-GFRAL axis that links anxiolytic and anorectic behavior as downstream effects of the chronic activation of this pathway by mitochondrial stress.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461199" rel="alternate" title="Mitochondrial stress-induced GDF15-GFRAL axis promotes anxiety-like behavior and CRH-dependent anorexia (4 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461349</id><title>Improved antibody structure prediction by deep learning of side chain conformations (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.525467+00:00</updated><author><name>Deniz Akpinaroglu</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey A. Ruffolo</name></author><author><name>Sai Pooja Mahajan</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey J. Gray</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antibody engineering is becoming increasingly popular in medicine for the development of diagnostics and immunotherapies. Antibody function relies largely on the recognition and binding of antigenic epitopes via the loops in the complementarity determining regions. Hence, accurate high-resolution modeling of these loops is essential for effective antibody engineering and design. Deep learning methods have previously been shown to effectively predict antibody backbone structures described as a set of inter-residue distances and orientations. However, antigen binding is also dependent on the specific conformations of surface side chains. To address this shortcoming, we created DeepSCAb: a deep learning method that predicts inter-residue geometries as well as side chain dihedrals of the antibody variable fragment. The network requires only sequence as input, rendering it particularly useful for antibodies without any known backbone conformations. Rotamer predictions use an interpretable self-attention layer, which learns to identify structurally conserved anchor positions across several species. We evaluate the performance of our model for discriminating near-native structures from sets of decoys and find that DeepSCAb outperforms similar methods lacking side chain context. When compared to alternative rotamer repacking methods, which require an input backbone structure, DeepSCAb predicts side chain conformations competitively. Our findings suggest that DeepSCAb improves antibody structure prediction with accurate side chain modeling and is adaptable to applications in docking of antibody-antigen complexes and design of new therapeutic antibody sequences.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461349" rel="alternate" title="Improved antibody structure prediction by deep learning of side chain conformations (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462527</id><title>Identification of CD73 as the antigen of an antigen-unknown monoclonal antibody established by exosome immunization, and its antibody-drug conjugate exerts an antitumor effect on glioblastoma cell lines (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.525755+00:00</updated><author><name>Takahiro anzai</name></author><author><name>Shinji Saijou</name></author><author><name>Hiroki Takashima</name></author><author><name>Misato Hara</name></author><author><name>Shingo Hanaoka</name></author><author><name>Yasuhiro Matsumura</name></author><author><name>Masahiro Yasunaga</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Development of antibodies against the native structure of membrane proteins with multiple transmembrane domains is challenging because it is difficult to prepare antigens with native structures. Previously, we successfully developed a monoclonal antibody against multi-pass membrane protein TMEM180 by exosome immunization in rats. This approach yielded antibod-ies that recognized cancer-specific antigens on the exosome. In this study, we performed im-munoprecipitation using magnetic beads to identify the antigen of one of the rat antibody clones, 0614, as CD73. We then converted antibody 0614 to human chimeric antibody 0614-5 and found that the humanized antibody did not inhibit CD73 enzymatic activity. Glioblastoma (GB) was the cancer type with the highest expression of CD73 in the tumor relative to healthy tissue. An antibody–drug conjugate (ADC) of 0614-5 exerted an antitumor effect on GB cell lines according to expression of CD73. The 0614-5-ADC could be used to treat cancers with high CD73 expression. In addition, our strategy could be used to determine the antigen of any antibody produced by exosome immunization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462527" rel="alternate" title="Identification of CD73 as the antigen of an antigen-unknown monoclonal antibody established by exosome immunization, and its antibody-drug conjugate exerts an antitumor effect on glioblastoma cell lines (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462062</id><title>Experimental Studies of Carpenter Bee (Xylocopa: Apidae) Thorax Mechanics During Defensive Buzzing (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.526013+00:00</updated><author><name>Mark Jankauski</name></author><author><name>Cailin Casey</name></author><author><name>Chelsea Heveran</name></author><author><name>Kathryn Busby</name></author><author><name>Stephen Buchmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bees and other Hymenoptera utilize thorax vibration to realize an extensive range of behaviors ranging from flight to pollination. Strong indirect flight muscles contract to deform the thoracic walls and the resulting oscillation is sustained through a mechanism called stretch activation. While the mechanics of the insect thorax and muscles have been studied extensively during flight, relatively little is known about the thorax mechanics during non-flight behaviors. In this work, we investigate the thorax mechanics of the carpenter bee &lt;italic&gt;Xylocopa californica&lt;/italic&gt; during defensive buzzing. During defensive buzzing, the insect folds its wings over its abdomen and rapidly fires it flight muscles, resulting in a loud audible buzz and large forces intended to deter predators. We devised a novel experiment to measure thorax oscillation and directional force production from a defensively buzzing carpenter bee. The largest peak forces were on average 175 mN and were oriented with the insect’s dorsal-ventral muscle group. Peak forces oriented with the insect’s dorsal-longitudinal muscle group averaged 117 mN. Thorax velocities were about 90 mm s^-1 p-p and velocity amplitude was positively correlated to peak force. Thorax oscillation frequency averaged 132 Hz but was highly variable both within individuals and across the tested population. From our measurements, we estimated the peak mechanical power required by defensive buzzing at 8.7 mW, which we hypothesize is greater than the power required during flight. Overall, this study provides insight into the function and capabilities of the Hymenopteran indirect flight muscle during non-flight behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462062" rel="alternate" title="Experimental Studies of Carpenter Bee (Xylocopa: Apidae) Thorax Mechanics During Defensive Buzzing (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462263</id><title>Enthalpic and Entropic Contributions to Interleaflet Coupling Drive Domain Registration and Anti-registration in Biological Membrane (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.526181+00:00</updated><author><name>Akshara Sharma</name></author><author><name>Aniruddha Seal</name></author><author><name>Sahithya S. Iyer</name></author><author><name>Anand Srivastava</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Biological membrane is a complex self-assembly of lipids, sterols and proteins organized as a fluid bilayer of two closely stacked lipid leaflets. Differential molecular interactions among its diverse constituents give rise to heterogeneities in the membrane lateral organization. Under certain conditions, heterogeneities in the two leaflets can be spatially synchronised and exist as registered domains across the bilayer. Several contrasting theories behind mechanisms that induce registration of nanoscale domains have been suggested[1–3]. Following a recent study[4] showing the effect of position of lipid tail unsaturation on domain registration behavior, we decided to develop an analytical theory to elucidate the driving forces that create and maintain domain registry across leaflets. Towards this, we formulated a Hamiltonian for a stacked lattice system where site variables encapsulate the lipid molecular properties including the position of unsaturation and various other interactions that could drive phase separation and interleaflet coupling. We solve the Hamiltonian using Monte Carlo simulations and create a complete phase diagram that reports the presence or absence of registered domains as a function of various Hamiltonian parameters. We find that the interleaflet coupling should be described as a competing enthalpic contribution due to interaction of lipid tail termini, primarily due to saturated-saturated interactions, and an interleaflet entropic contribution from overlap of unsaturated tail termini. We find that higher position of unsaturation provides weaker interleaflet coupling. We also find points in our parameter space that allow thermodynamically stable nanodomains in our bilayer model, which we have verified by carrying out extended Monte Carlo simulations. These persistent non-coalescing registered nanodomains close to the lower end of the accepted nanodomain size range also point towards a possible “nanoscale” emulsion description of lateral heterogeneities in biological membrane leaflets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462263" rel="alternate" title="Enthalpic and Entropic Contributions to Interleaflet Coupling Drive Domain Registration and Anti-registration in Biological Membrane (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461192</id><title>Efficient Flocking: Metric Versus Topological Interactions (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.526335+00:00</updated><author><name>Vijay Kumar</name></author><author><name>Rumi De</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Flocking is a fascinating phenomenon observed across a wide range of living organisms. We investigate, based on a simple self-propelled particle model, how the emergence of ordered motion in a collectively moving group is influenced by the local rules of interactions among the individuals, namely, metric versus topological interactions as debated over in the current literature. In the case of the metric ruling, the individuals interact with the neighbours within a certain metric distance; in contrast, in the topological ruling, interaction is confined within a number of fixed nearest neighbours. Here, we explore how the range of interaction versus the number of fixed interacting neighbours affects the dynamics of flocking in an unbounded space, as observed in natural scenarios. Our study reveals the existence of a certain threshold value of the interaction radius in the case of metric ruling and a threshold number of interacting neighbours for the topological ruling to reach an ordered state. Interestingly, our analysis shows that topological interaction is more effective in bringing the order in the group, as observed in field studies. We further compare how the nature of the interactions affects the dynamics for various sizes and speeds of the flock.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461192" rel="alternate" title="Efficient Flocking: Metric Versus Topological Interactions (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461545</id><title>Functional Communication between IP3R and STIM2 at sub-threshold stimuli is a critical checkpoint for initiation of SOCE (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.526475+00:00</updated><author><name>Moaz Ahmad</name></author><author><name>Hwei Ling Ong</name></author><author><name>Hassan Saadi</name></author><author><name>Ga Yeon Son</name></author><author><name>Zahra Shokatian</name></author><author><name>Lara E. Terry</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Trebak</name></author><author><name>David I. Yule</name></author><author><name>Indu Ambudkar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Stromal interaction molecules, STIM1 and STIM2, sense decreases in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) [Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;] ([Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;]&lt;sub&gt;ER&lt;/sub&gt;) and cluster in ER-plasma membrane (ER-PM) junctions where they recruit and activate Orai1. While STIM1 responds when [Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;]&lt;sub&gt;ER&lt;/sub&gt; is relatively low, STIM2 displays constitutive clustering in the junctions and is suggested to regulate basal Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; entry. The cellular cues that determine STIM2 clustering under basal conditions is not known. By using gene editing to fluorescently tag endogenous STIM2, we report that endogenous STIM2 is constitutively localized in mobile and immobile clusters. The latter associate with ER-PM junctions and recruit Orai1 under basal conditions. Agonist stimulation increases immobile STIM2 clusters which co- ordinate recruitment of Orai1 and STIM1 to the junctions. Extended synaptotagmin (E-Syt)2/3 are required for forming the ER-PM junctions, but are not sufficient for STIM2 clustering. Importantly, inositol 1,4,5-triphosphate receptor (IP&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;R) function and local [Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;]&lt;sub&gt;ER&lt;/sub&gt; are the main drivers of immobile STIM2 clusters. Enhancing, or decreasing, IP&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;R function at ambient [IP&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;] causes corresponding increase, or attenuation, of immobile STIM2 clusters. We show that immobile STIM2 clusters denote decreases in local [Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;]&lt;sub&gt;ER&lt;/sub&gt; mediated by IP&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;R that is sensed by the STIM2-N terminus. Finally, under basal conditions, ambient PIP&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-PLC activity of the cell determines IP&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;R function, immobilization of STIM2, and basal Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; entry while agonist stimulation augments these processes. Together, our findings reveal that immobilization of STIM2 clusters within ER-PM junctions, a first response to ER-Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; store depletion, is facilitated by the juxtaposition of IP&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;R and marks a checkpoint for initiation of Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; entry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;STIM proteins sense decreases in [Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;]&lt;sub&gt;ER&lt;/sub&gt; and cluster in endoplasmic reticulum (ER)-plasma membrane (PM) junctions where they recruit and activate Orai1. While STIM1 clustering requires substantial [Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;]&lt;sub&gt;ER&lt;/sub&gt; decrease, STIM2 displays pre-clustering under resting conditions and regulates basal Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; entry. The mechanism(s) underlying constitutive clustering of STIM2 is not known. We show herein that endogenous STIM2 assembles as mobile and immobile clusters and that Orai1 is recruited to the latter. Anchoring of STIM2 clusters is triggered by decreases in local [Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;]&lt;sub&gt;ER&lt;/sub&gt; that is mediated by ambient activity of IP&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;R and sensed by the STIM2 N-terminus. This functional link between IP&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;R and STIM2 governs constitutive STIM2 clustering and ensures coupling of [Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;]&lt;sub&gt;ER&lt;/sub&gt; decrease at sub-threshold stimuli with activation of Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; entry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461545" rel="alternate" title="Functional Communication between IP3R and STIM2 at sub-threshold stimuli is a critical checkpoint for initiation of SOCE (3 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461836</id><title>Spontaneous nucleation and fast aggregate-dependent proliferation of α-synuclein aggregates within liquid condensates at physiological pH (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.526657+00:00</updated><author><name>Samuel T. Dada</name></author><author><name>Maarten C. Hardenberg</name></author><author><name>Lena K. Mrugalla</name></author><author><name>Mollie O. McKeon</name></author><author><name>Ewa Klimont</name></author><author><name>Thomas C. T. Michaels</name></author><author><name>Michele Vendruscolo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It is well-established that α-synuclein aggregation may proceed through an initial lipid-dependent aggregate formation and, if at acidic pH, a subsequent aggregate-dependent proliferation. It has also been recently reported that the aggregation of α-synuclein may also take place through an alternative pathway, which takes place within dense liquid condensates produced through liquid-liquid phase separation. The microscopic mechanism of this process, however, remains to be clarified. Here, we developed a fluorescence-based assay to perform a kinetic analysis of the aggregation process of α-synuclein within liquid condensates, and applied it to determine the corresponding mechanism of aggregation. Our analysis shows that at pH 7.4 the aggregation process of α-synuclein within dense condensates starts with spontaneous primary nucleation followed by rapid aggregate-dependent proliferation. Taken together, these results reveal a highly efficient pathway for the appearance and proliferation of α-synuclein aggregates at physiological pH.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461836" rel="alternate" title="Spontaneous nucleation and fast aggregate-dependent proliferation of α-synuclein aggregates within liquid condensates at physiological pH (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461697</id><title>Myofibril orientation as a metric for characterizing heart disease (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.526829+00:00</updated><author><name>Weikang Ma</name></author><author><name>Henry Gong</name></author><author><name>Vivek Jani</name></author><author><name>Maicon Landim-Vieira</name></author><author><name>Maria Papadaki</name></author><author><name>Jose R. Pinto</name></author><author><name>M. Imran Aslam</name></author><author><name>Anthony Cammarato</name></author><author><name>Thomas Irving</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Myocyte disarray is a hallmark of many cardiac disorders. However, the relationship between alterations in the orientation of individual myofibrils and myofilaments to disease progression has been largely underexplored. This oversight has predominantly been due to a paucity of methods for objective and quantitative analysis. Here we introduce a novel, less-biased approach to quantify myofibrillar and myofilament orientation in cardiac muscle under near physiological conditions and demonstrate its superiority as compared to conventional histological assessments. Using small-angle X-ray diffraction, we first investigated changes in myofibrillar orientation at increasing sarcomere lengths in permeabilized, relaxed, wildtype mouse myocardium by assessing the angular spread of the 1,0 equatorial reflection (angle σ). At a sarcomere length (SL) of 1.9 μm, the angle σ was 0.23±0.01 rad, decreased to 0.19±0.01 rad at a SL of 2.1 μm, and further decreased to 0.15±0.01 rad at a SL of 2.3 μm (p&amp;lt;0.0001). Angle σ was significantly larger in R403Q, a MYH7 hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (HCM) model, porcine myocardium (0.24±0.01 rad) compared to WT myocardium (0.14±0.005 rad, p&amp;lt;0.0001) as well as in human heart failure tissue (0.19±0.006 rad) when compared to non-failing samples (0.17±0.007 rad, p=0.01). These data indicate that diseased myocardium suffers from greater myofibrillar disorientation compared to healthy controls. Finally, we showed that conventional, histology-based analysis of disarray can be subject to user bias and/or sampling error and lead to false positives. Our method for directly assessing myofibrillar orientation avoids the artifacts introduced by conventional histological approaches that assess myocyte orientation and only indirectly evaluate myofibrillar orientation, and provides a precise and objective metric for phenotypically characterizing myocardium. The ability to obtain excellent X-ray diffraction patterns from frozen human myocardium provides a new tool for investigating structural anomalies associated with cardiac diseases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Statement of Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We introduce a precise and quantitative approach to directly measure myofibrillar and myofilament orientation in cardiac muscle under near physiological conditions as a novel tool for phenotypically characterizing striated muscle systems. We use this technique to demonstrate that myocardium from disease model organisms and failing human myocardium suffers from greater myofibrillar disorientation compared to healthy controls. We also demonstrate that excellent diffraction patterns can be obtained from frozen and thawed human myocardium. Given the ready availability of frozen human heart tissue in tissue banks, this capability opens up a large space of potential experiments relating sarcomere structure to dysfunction in cardiac disorders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461697" rel="alternate" title="Myofibril orientation as a metric for characterizing heart disease (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462769</id><title>Mechanical loading and hyperosmolarity as a daily resetting cue for skeletal circadian clocks (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.527284+00:00</updated><author><name>Michal Dudek</name></author><author><name>Dharshika Pathiranage</name></author><author><name>Cátia F. Gonçalves</name></author><author><name>Craig Lawless</name></author><author><name>Dong Wang</name></author><author><name>Zhuojing Luo</name></author><author><name>Liu Yang</name></author><author><name>Judith Hoyland</name></author><author><name>Qing-Jun Meng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In mammals, temporally coordinated daily rhythms of behaviour and physiology are generated by a multi-oscillatory circadian system, entrained through cyclic environmental cues (e.g. light). Presence of niche-dependent physiological time cues has been proposed, which would allow local tissues flexibility of adopting a different phase relationship if circumstances require. Up till now, such tissue-unique stimuli have remained elusive. Here we show that cycles of mechanical loading and osmotic stimuli within physiological range drive rhythmic expression of clock genes and reset clock phase and amplitude in cartilage and intervertebral disc tissues. Hyperosmolarity (and not hypo-osmolarity) resets clocks in young and ageing skeletal tissues through mTORC2-AKT-GSK3β pathway, leading to genome-wide induction of rhythmic genes. These results suggest diurnal patterns of mechanical loading and consequent daily surges in extracellular osmolarity as a bona fide tissue niche-specific time cue to maintain skeletal circadian rhythms in sync.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Circadian clocks in aneural skeletal tissues sense the passage of time through rhythmic patterns of loading and osmolarity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462769" rel="alternate" title="Mechanical loading and hyperosmolarity as a daily resetting cue for skeletal circadian clocks (3 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461649</id><title>Dissection of function and recognition mechanism of M. tuberculosis ESX-1 secreted virulence factor EspC (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.527589+00:00</updated><author><name>Ruby Sharma</name></author><author><name>Vipin K. Kashyap</name></author><author><name>Manoj Kumar</name></author><author><name>Abhisheka Bansal</name></author><author><name>Ajay K. Saxena</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; uses the ESAT-6 system-1/type VII (ESX-1) system for secretion of virulence proteins into the host cell, however the mechanism of virulence proteins secretion, molecular components and regulation of ESX-1 system are only partly understood. In the current study, we have analyzed the biological function and recognition mechanism between ESX-1 virulence EspC and EccA&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; ATPase proteins. The EspC enters into A549 human lung carcinoma cells and exhibited cytotoxicity, as observed in MTT Assay. To understand the recognition mechanism between EspC and EccA&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; ATPase, the EspC and EccA&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; mutants were generated based on EspC~EccA&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; interactions, as observed in molecular modeling. Binding analysis shows that EspC export arm interacts specifically to the β-hairpin insertion motif of the TPR domain of EccA&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; ATPase. Mutations in these epitopes lead to significant decrease/or abolish the binding between EspC and EccA&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; ATPase. Our study provides insight into biological function and recognition mechanism between EspC and EccA&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; ATPase, which can be used as target to prevent EspC secretion/ or in general virulence factor secretion by mycobacterial ESX-1 system.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461649" rel="alternate" title="Dissection of function and recognition mechanism of M. tuberculosis ESX-1 secreted virulence factor EspC (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461340</id><title>Influence of high energy diet and polygenic predisposition for obesity on postpartum health in rat dams (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.527828+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrea S. Leuthardt</name></author><author><name>Julia Bayer</name></author><author><name>Josep M. Monné Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Christina N. Boyle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It is estimated that 30% of pregnant women worldwide are overweight or obese, which leads to adverse health effects for both the mother and child. Women with obesity during pregnancy are at higher risk for developing both metabolic and mental disorders, such as diabetes and depression. Numerous studies have used rodent models of maternal obesity to understand its consequences on the offspring, yet characterization of changes in the dams is rare, and most rodent models rely solely on a high fat diet to induce maternal obesity, without regarding genetic propensity for obesity. Here we present the influence of both peripartum high energy diet (HE) and obesity-proneness on maternal health using selectively-bred diet-resistant (DR) and diet-induced obese (DIO) rat dams. Outbred Sprague-Dawley rats were selected and bred according to their propensity to gain weight. From F1 onward, dams consuming a HE diet displayed higher body weight gain during pregnancy, and HE diet had a strong effect on meal patterns. Sensitivity to the hormone amylin was preserved during pregnancy, regardless of diet. After several rounds of selective breeding, dams from generation F3 were assessed for their postpartum physiology and behaviors. We observed strong diet and phenotype effects on gestational weight gain, with DIO-HE dams gaining 119% more weight than DR-chow. A high-resolution analysis of maternal behaviors on postpartum day 2 (P2) did not detect main effects of diet or phenotype, but a subset of DIO dams showed decreased pup-related behaviors. During a sucrose preference test (SPT) on P14, all DR dams consumed at least 70% sucrose, while a subset of DIO dams preferred water. In generation F6/F7 dams, effects on gestational weight gain persisted, and we observed a main effect of phenotype of SPT, with DIO-chow dams showing the lowest sucrose preference. Both DIO and DR dams consuming HE diet had severe postpartum liver lipidosis and exhibited reduced leptin sensitivity in the arcuate nucleus at the time of pup-weaning. These data demonstrate that both diet and genetic obesity-proneness have consequences on maternal health.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461340" rel="alternate" title="Influence of high energy diet and polygenic predisposition for obesity on postpartum health in rat dams (3 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461773</id><title>Control of subunit stoichiometry in single-chain MspA nanopores (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.527991+00:00</updated><author><name>Mikhail Pavlenok</name></author><author><name>Luning Yu</name></author><author><name>Dominik Herrmann</name></author><author><name>Meni Wanunu</name></author><author><name>Michael Niederweis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Transmembrane protein channels enable fast and highly sensitive electrical detection of single molecules. Nanopore sequencing of DNA was achieved using an engineered &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium smegmatis&lt;/italic&gt; porin A (MspA) in combination with a motor enzyme. Due to its favorable channel geometry, the octameric MspA pore exhibits the highest current level as compared to other pore proteins. To date, MspA is the only protein nanopore with a published record of DNA sequencing. While widely used in commercial devices, nanopore sequencing of DNA suffers from significant base-calling errors due to stochastic events of the complex DNA-motor-pore combination and the contribution of up to five nucleotides to the signal at each position. Asymmetric mutations within subunits of the channel protein offer an enormous potential to improve nucleotide resolution and sequencing accuracy. However, random subunit assembly does not allow control of the channel composition of MspA and other oligomeric protein pores. In this study, we showed that it is feasible to convert octameric MspA into a single-chain pore by connecting eight subunits using peptide linkers. We constructed single-chain MspA trimers, pentamers, hexamers and heptamers to demonstrate that it is feasible to alter the subunit stoichiometry and the MspA pore diameter. All single-chain MspA proteins formed functional channels in lipid bilayer experiments. Importantly, we demonstrated that single-chain MspA discriminated all four nucleotides identical to MspA produced from monomers. Thus, single-chain MspA constitutes a new milestone in its development and adaptation as a biosensor for DNA sequencing and many other applications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;STATEMENT OF SIGNFICANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nanopore sequencing of DNA is a fast and cheap technology that uniquely delivers multi-kilobase reads. It is currently used world-wide in many applications such as genome sequencing, epigenetics, and surveillance of viral and bacterial pathogens and has started to revolutionize human lives in medicine, agriculture and environmental studies. However, the high base-calling error rates prevent nanopore DNA sequencing from reaching its full potential. In this study, we converted octameric MspA into a single-chain pore enabling asymmetric mutations to fine-tune the pore geometry and chemistry and address the shortcomings of nanopores. Thus, single-chain MspA constitutes a new milestone in its development and adaptation as a biosensor for DNA sequencing and many other applications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461773" rel="alternate" title="Control of subunit stoichiometry in single-chain MspA nanopores (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462583</id><title>Strain and crack propagation of HIV-1 capsids during uncoating (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.528319+00:00</updated><author><name>Alvin Yu</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth M.Y. Lee</name></author><author><name>John A.G. Briggs</name></author><author><name>Barbie K. Ganser-Pornillos</name></author><author><name>Owen Pornillos</name></author><author><name>Gregory A. Voth</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Viral replication in HIV-1 relies on a fullerene-shaped capsid to transport genetic material deep into the nucleus of an infected cell. Capsid stability is linked to the presence of cofactors, including inositol hexakisphosphate (IP&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;) that bind to pores found in the capsid. Using extensive all-atom molecular dynamics simulations of HIV-1 cores imaged from cryo-electron tomography (cryo-ET) in intact virions, which contain IP&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt; and a ribonucleoprotein complex, we find markedly striated patterns of strain on capsid lattices. The presence of these cofactors also increases rigidity of the capsid. Conformational analysis of capsid (CA) proteins show CA accommodates strain by locally flexing away from structures resolved using x-ray crystallography and cryo-electron microscopy. Then, cryo-ET of HIV-1 cores undergoing endogenous reverse transcription demonstrate that lattice strain increases in the capsid prior to mechanical failure and that the capsid ruptures by crack propagation along regions of high strain. These results uncover HIV-1 capsid properties involved in their critical disassembly process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The mature capsids of HIV-1 are transiently stable complexes that self-assemble around the viral genome during maturation, and uncoat to release preintegration complexes that archive a double-stranded DNA copy of the virus in the host cell genome. However, a detailed view of how HIV cores rupture remains lacking. Here, we elucidate the physical properties involved in capsid rupture using a combination of large-scale all-atom molecular dynamics simulations and cryo-electron tomography. We find that intrinsic strain on the capsid forms highly correlated patterns along the capsid surface, along which cracks propagate. Capsid rigidity also increases with high strain. Our findings provide fundamental insight into viral capsid uncoating.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462583" rel="alternate" title="Strain and crack propagation of HIV-1 capsids during uncoating (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461618</id><title>Computational study on Strontium ion modified Fibronectin-Hydroxyapatite interaction (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.528617+00:00</updated><author><name>Subhadip Basu</name></author><author><name>Bikramjit Basu</name></author><author><name>Prabal K Maiti</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protein adsorption is the first key step in cell-material interaction. The initial phase of such adsorption process can only be probed using modelling approaches like molecular dynamics (MD) simulation. Despite a large number of studies on the adsorption behaviour of proteins on different biomaterials including hydroxyapatite (HA); little attention has been paid towards quantitative assessment of the effects of various physicochemical influencers like surface modification, pH, and ionic strength. Among these factors, surface modification through isomorphic substitution of foreign ions inside the apatite structure is of particular interest in the context of protein-HA interaction as it is widely used to tailor the biological response of HA. Given this background, we present here the molecular-level understanding of fibronectin (FN) adsorption mechanism and kinetics on Sr&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;-doped HA (001) surface, at 300K by means of all-atom molecular dynamics simulation. Electrostatic interaction involved in adsorption of FN on HA was found to be significantly modified in presence of Sr&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; doping in apatite lattice. In harmony with the published experimental observations, the Sr-doped surface was found to better support FN adhesion compared to pure HA, with 10 mol% Sr-doped HA exhibiting best FN adsorption. Sr&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; ions also influence the stability of the secondary structure of FN, as observed from the root mean square deviation (RMSD) and root mean square fluctuation (RMSF) analysis. The presence of Sr&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; enhances the flexibility of specific residues (residue no. 20-44, 74-88) of the FN module. Rupture forces to disentangle FN from the biomaterials surface, obtained from steered molecular dynamics (SMD) simulations, were found to corroborate well with the results of equilibrium MD simulations. One particular observation is that, the availability of RGD motif for the interaction with cell surface receptor integrin is not significantly influenced by Sr&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; substitution. Summarizing, the present work establishes a quantitative foundation towards the molecular basis of the earlier experimentally validated better cytocompatibility of Sr-doped HA.
&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="461618v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461618" rel="alternate" title="Computational study on Strontium ion modified Fibronectin-Hydroxyapatite interaction (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>