<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.911041+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466983</id><title>Structure Determination of Inactive-State GPCRs with a Universal Nanobody (95 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.911793+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael J. Robertson</name></author><author><name>Feng He</name></author><author><name>Justin G. Meyerowitz</name></author><author><name>Alpay B. Seven</name></author><author><name>Ouliana Panova</name></author><author><name>Maria-Claudia Peroto</name></author><author><name>Tao Che</name></author><author><name>Georgios Skiniotis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cryogenic electron microscopy (cryo-EM) has widened the field of structure-based drug discovery by allowing for routine determination of membrane protein structures previously intractable. However, despite representing one of the largest classes of therapeutic targets, most inactive-state G protein-coupled receptors (GPCRs) have remained inaccessible for cryo-EM because their small size and membrane-embedded nature impedes projection alignment for high-resolution map reconstructions. Here we demonstrate that a camelid single-chain antibody (nanobody) recognizing a grafted intracellular loop can be used to obtain cryo-EM structures of different inactive-state GPCRs at resolutions comparable or better than those obtained by X-ray crystallography. Using this approach, we obtained the structure of human neurotensin 1 receptor (NTSR1) bound to antagonist SR48692, of μ-opioid receptor (MOR) bound to the clinical antagonist alvimopan, as well as the structure of the previously uncharacterized somatostatin receptor 2 (SSTR2) in the apo state; each of these structures yields novel insights into ligand binding and specificity. We expect this rapid, straightforward approach to facilitate the broad structural exploration of GPCR inactive states without the need for extensive engineering and crystallization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466983" rel="alternate" title="Structure Determination of Inactive-State GPCRs with a Universal Nanobody (95 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467474</id><title>Aggregation controlled by condensate rheology (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.912233+00:00</updated><author><name>Wolfram Poenisch</name></author><author><name>Thomas C.T. Michaels</name></author><author><name>Christoph A. Weber</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Condensates in living cells can exhibit a complex rheology including viscoelastic and glassy behaviour. This rheological behavior of condensates was suggested to regulate polymerisation of cytoskeletal filaments and aggregation of amyloid fibrils. Here, we theoretically investigate how the rheological properties of condensates can control the formation of linear aggregates. To this end, we propose a kinetic theory for the aggregate size distribution and the exchange of aggregates between inside and outside of condensates. The rheology of condensates is accounted for by aggregate mobilities that depend on aggregate size. We show that condensate rheology can control whether either aggregates of all sizes or dominantly small aggregates are exchanged between condensate inside and outside on the time-scale of aggregation. As a result, the ratio of aggregate numbers inside to outside of condensates differs significantly. Strikingly, we also find that weak variations in the rheological properties of condensates can lead to a switch-like change of the number of aggregates. These results suggest a possible physical mechanism for how living cells could control linear aggregation in a switch-like fashion through variations in condensate rheology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467474" rel="alternate" title="Aggregation controlled by condensate rheology (23 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466478</id><title>Cooperative electrolyte-PEG interactions drive the signal amplification in a solid-state nanopore (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.912551+00:00</updated><author><name>Chalmers C. Chau</name></author><author><name>Fabio Marcuccio</name></author><author><name>Dimitrios Soulias</name></author><author><name>Martin A. Edwards</name></author><author><name>Sheena E. Radford</name></author><author><name>Eric W. Hewitt</name></author><author><name>Paolo Actis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nanopore systems have emerged as a leading platform for the analysis of biomolecular complexes with single molecule resolution. However, the analysis of several analytes like short nucleic acids or proteins with nanopores represents a sensitivity challenge, because their translocation lead to small signals difficult to distinguish from the noise. Here, we report a simple method to enhance the signal to noise ratio in nanopore experiments by a simple modification of the solution used in nanopore sensing. The addition of poly-ethylene glycol (PEG) and the careful selection of the supporting electrolyte leads to large signal enhancement. We observed that the translocation dynamics are in good agreement with an established method that uses the lattice energy of an electrolyte to approximate the affinity of an ion to PEG. We identified CsBr as the optimal supporting electrolyte to complement PEG to enable the analysis of dsDNA at 500 kHz bandwidth, and the detection of dsDNA as short as 75 bp.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466478" rel="alternate" title="Cooperative electrolyte-PEG interactions drive the signal amplification in a solid-state nanopore (19 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466666</id><title>Montage electron tomography of vitrified specimens (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.913041+00:00</updated><author><name>Ariana Peck</name></author><author><name>Stephen D. Carter</name></author><author><name>Huanghao Mai</name></author><author><name>Songye Chen</name></author><author><name>Alister Burt</name></author><author><name>Grant J. Jensen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cryo-electron tomography provides detailed views of macromolecules &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt;. However, imaging a large field of view to provide more cellular context requires reducing magnification during data collection, which in turn restricts the resolution. To circumvent this trade-off between field of view and resolution, we have developed a montage data collection scheme that uniformly distributes the dose throughout the specimen. In this approach, sets of slightly overlapping circular tiles are collected at high magnification and stitched to form a composite projection image at each tilt angle. These montage tilt-series are then reconstructed into massive tomograms with a small pixel size but a large field of view. For proof-of-principle, we applied this method to the thin edge of HeLa cells. Thon rings to better than 15 Å were observed in the montaged tilt-series, and diverse cellular features were evident in the resulting tomograms. These results indicate that the additional dose required by this technique is not prohibitive to performing structural analysis to intermediate resolution across a large field of view. We anticipate that montage tomography will prove particularly useful for lamellae, increase the likelihood of imaging rare cellular events, and facilitate visual proteomics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466666" rel="alternate" title="Montage electron tomography of vitrified specimens (15 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466988</id><title>Plasticity in Ligand Recognition at Somatostatin Receptors (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.913443+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael J. Robertson</name></author><author><name>Justin G. Meyerowitz</name></author><author><name>Ouliana Panova</name></author><author><name>Kenneth Borrelli</name></author><author><name>Georgios Skiniotis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Somatostatin is a signaling peptide that plays a pivotal and wide-ranging role in physiologic processes relating to metabolism and growth through its actions at somatostatin receptors (SSTRs). Somatostatin receptors, particularly somatostatin receptor 2, are key drug targets for neuroendocrine neoplasms, with several synthetic peptide agonists currently in use. Here, we present the cryogenic electron microscopy structures of SSTR2 in the active G-protein complex with either the endogenous ligand SST14 or the FDA-approved drug octreotide. Complemented by biochemical assays and molecular dynamics simulations, these structures reveal key details of ligand recognition, receptor activation, and subtype-selectivity at somatostatin receptors. We find that SSTR ligand recognition is highly diverse, as demonstrated by ligand-induced conformational changes in ECL2, substantial sequence divergence across subtypes in extracellular regions, and loss of ligand binding upon several structurally homologous substitutions between subtypes. Despite this complexity, were are able to rationalize several discrete sources of SSTR subtype selectivity and identify an additional key interaction for SSTR2/3/5 specific binding. These results shed light on the basis of ligand recognition by somatostatin receptors and provide valuable insights for structure-based drug discovery at these important targets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466988" rel="alternate" title="Plasticity in Ligand Recognition at Somatostatin Receptors (15 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.466690</id><title>A prior exposure to Serratia marcescens or xenobiotics primes Drosophila enterocytes against a recurring cytoplasmic purge (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.913865+00:00</updated><author><name>Simone Terreri</name></author><author><name>Bechara Sina-Rahme</name></author><author><name>Inês Pais</name></author><author><name>Catherine Socha</name></author><author><name>Matthieu Lestradet</name></author><author><name>Miriam Yamba</name></author><author><name>Stefanie Schirmeier</name></author><author><name>Kwang-Zin Lee</name></author><author><name>Dominique Ferrandon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The cytoplasmic extrusion of enterocytes is a fast response to an exposure to pore-forming toxin (PFT)-producing bacteria whereby their apical cytoplasm is extruded into the intestinal lumen. As a result of this purge, the intestinal epithelium becomes thin prior to a subsequent recovery. We report here that the ingestion of ethanol or caffeine induces a similar response, which suggests that a common purging process is triggered by bacterial toxins and abiotic toxicants. We also delineate an additional mechanism that is initiated by these stimuli that we refer to as priming. The initial exposure of the intestinal epithelium to either PFT or xenobiotics protects enterocytes against a further round of purging upon a second bacterial infection. Priming prevents the epithelium from being persistently thin in the context of chronic intestinal infections. We have identified the upper part of the p38b MAPK pathway as well as the homeobox-containing transcription factors E5/EMS as being required for priming and not for the regrowth of enterocytes after the cytoplasmic purge. Unexpectedly, the priming process appears to function cell-nonautonomously. Our findings suggest that the cytoplasmic purge extrusion has been selected because it constitutes a fast reaction to accidental exposure to bacterial toxins or toxicants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.31.466690" rel="alternate" title="A prior exposure to Serratia marcescens or xenobiotics primes Drosophila enterocytes against a recurring cytoplasmic purge (4 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466919</id><title>Annexin A4 senses membrane curvature in a density dependent manner (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.914553+00:00</updated><author><name>Christoffer D. Florentsen</name></author><author><name>Joshua A. Daniels</name></author><author><name>Guillermo Moreno-Pescador</name></author><author><name>Iliriana Qoqaj</name></author><author><name>Jesper Nylandsted</name></author><author><name>Poul Martin Bendix</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Annexins (ANXs) are a family of peripheral membrane binding proteins which play a vital role in the maintenance and function of cellular membranes. These proteins are known to be part of the plasma membrane repair machinery where they are known to bind to negatively charged lipids in the cell membrane in a calcium dependent manner. The shape of the plasma membrane is known to be a regulator of protein density and thereby affects several biological functions of the cell such as exo-and endocytosis, cell motility, immune responses and also membrane repair. Membrane deformation and curvature sensing by proteins is a well described phenomenon which can assist in recruitment of specific proteins to certain regions in the cell and facilitate membrane bending. Following ruptures in the plasma membrane, calcium influx assist in the association of ANXs with the membrane around the ruptured area. Due to the expected increase in curvature at the damaged membrane site, it has been suggested that both membrane curvature and Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; participate in the recruitment of ANXs. We have investigated the curvature sensing of ANXA4 in giant unilamellar vesicles (GUVs) by pulling high curvature membrane tethers from the vesicle surface using optical tweezers showing that ANXA4 recruitment increases with higher membrane curvature. We also describe an assay for determining protein density on the plasma membrane by utilizing ANXA4’s property as a calcium dependent membrane binding protein. This new assay allows us to investigate the effect of protein density on curvature sensing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466919" rel="alternate" title="Annexin A4 senses membrane curvature in a density dependent manner (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>